<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T13:12:20.538Z">12/2/2025 1:12:20 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T13:12:06.535793Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T13:12:06.535793Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Comparing preferences to evaluations of<lb/> barrier self-efficacy for two strength training<lb/> programs in US older adults<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jordan D. Kurth ID<lb/> 1,2<lb/> *, Christopher N. Sciamanna 1,2 , Cheyenne Herrell ID<lb/> 1,2 ,<lb/> Matthew Moeller 1,2 , Jonathan G. Stine 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Penn State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>University Park, PA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Penn State College of Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hershey, PA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Penn State Health-Milton S. Hershey Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hershey,<lb/> PA, United States of America<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>jdk5930@psu.edu</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background/Objectives<lb/> Engagement in regular physical activity is one of the best strategies for older adults to<lb/> remain healthy. Unfortunately, only 35% of older adults meet guidelines for muscle strength-<lb/>ening activities. Eliciting participant preferences is one possible way to improve physical<lb/> activity engagement. However, other sources of participant input to improve uptake and<lb/> maintenance remain uninvestigated. This study compared preferences to self-efficacy rat-<lb/>ings for two strength training programs. Methods<lb/> We conducted a national cross-sectional survey of 611 US adults over age 65. We com-<lb/>pared two participant evaluations (the preferred program and the program for which they<lb/> had higher barrier self-efficacy) of two hypothetical strength training programs (45 minutes<lb/> performed three times per week (traditional) and 5 minutes performed daily (brief)). Results<lb/> Most participants (68%) preferred the brief strength training program. The difference in self-<lb/>efficacy ratings was an average of 1.2 (SD = 0.92). One in five participants preferred a<lb/> strength training program for which they had less self-efficacy; nearly all of these partici-<lb/>pants (92%) preferred the traditional strength training program but had more self-efficacy for<lb/> the brief strength training program. Conclusion<lb/> Older adults reported preferring and having more self-efficacy for a brief compared to a tra-<lb/>ditional strength training program. Differences in self-efficacy ratings between the two<lb/> strength training programs were large. Preferences were often not congruent with ratings of<lb/> self-efficacy.<lb/></div>

	<!-- minor corrections -->
	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 9<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Kurth JD, Sciamanna CN, Herrell C,<lb/> Moeller M, Stine JG (2024) Comparing preferences<lb/> to evaluations of barrier self-efficacy for two<lb/> strength training programs in US older adults.<lb/> PLoS ONE 19(5): e0302892.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/<lb/> 10.1371/journal.pone.0302892<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Sohel Ahmed,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Ahmed Physiotherapy and<lb/> Research Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BANGLADESH<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: January 31, 2024<lb/> Accepted: April 15, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>May 9, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Kurth et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">Data associated with<lb/> this study is available via Penn State Data<lb/> Commons at https://doi.org/10.26208/Q1KB-<lb/>AW67.<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Significance/Implications<lb/> Preferences for strength training programming may not always reflect the program most<lb/> likely to be maintained. Future investigations should evaluate differences in behavioral<lb/> uptake, maintenance, and outcomes from two comparative strength training interventions<lb/> using preferences and self-efficacy.<lb/></div>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">The author(s) received no specific<lb/> funding for this work.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">I have read the journal&apos;s<lb/> policy and the authors of this manuscript have the<lb/> following competing interests: Christopher<lb/> Sciamanna has an investment, such as stock, in a<lb/> company which has begun to investigate the<lb/> possibility of creating a business that provides<lb/> exercise programs. All other authors declare that<lb/> they have no known competing financial interests<lb/> or personal relationships that could have appeared<lb/> to influence the work reported in this paper.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>