<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T10:22:40.087Z">12/2/2025 10:22:40 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T10:21:52.723876Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T10:21:52.723876Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Disentangling associations between pubertal<lb/> development, healthy activity behaviors, and<lb/> sex in adolescent social networks<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mark C. Pachucki ID<lb/> 1,2<lb/> *, Lindsay Till Hoyt 3 , Li Niu 3☯ , Richard Carbonaro ID 1☯<lb/> , Hsin<lb/> Fei Tu 1☯ , John R. Sirard 4 , Genevieve Chandler 5<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Sociology, University of Massachusetts Amherst,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of<lb/> America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 UMass Computational Social Science Institute, University of Massachusetts Amherst,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Amherst,<lb/> Massachusetts, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Applied Developmental Psychology, Fordham<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bronx, New York, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 School of Public Health &amp; Health Sciences,<lb/> University of Massachusetts Amherst,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Elaine Marieb<lb/> College of Nursing, University of Massachusetts Amherst,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>mpachucki@umass.edu</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">With the onset of puberty, youth begin to choose their social environments and develop<lb/> health-promoting habits, making it a vital period to study social and biological factors contex-<lb/>tually. An important question is how pubertal development and behaviors such as physical<lb/> activity and sleep may be differentially linked with youths&apos; friendships. Cross-sectional statis-<lb/>tical network models that account for interpersonal dependence were used to estimate<lb/> associations between three measures of pubertal development and youth friendships at two<lb/> large US schools drawn from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health.<lb/> Whole-network models suggest that friendships are more likely between youth with similar<lb/> levels of pubertal development, physical activity, and sleep. Sex-stratified models suggest<lb/> that girls&apos; friendships are more likely given a similar age at menarche. Attention to similar<lb/> pubertal timing within friendship groups may offer inclusive opportunities for tailored devel-<lb/>opmental puberty education in ways that reduce stigma and improve health behaviors.<lb/></div>

	<!-- minor changes -->
	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 25<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Pachucki MC, Hoyt LT, Niu L, Carbonaro<lb/> R, Tu HF, Sirard JR, et al. (2024) Disentangling<lb/> associations between pubertal development,<lb/> healthy activity behaviors, and sex in adolescent<lb/> social networks. PLoS ONE 19(5): e0300715.<lb/></reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Yasas Chandra Tanguturi,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of<lb/> Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: November 15, 2023<lb/> Accepted: March 3, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>May 16, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Pachucki et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">This research uses<lb/> third party data from the National Longitudinal<lb/> Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health).<lb/> Information on how to obtain the Add Health data<lb/> files is available on the Add Health website (http://<lb/> www.cpc.unc.edu/addhealth). To apply for these<lb/> data, the researcher must request access and<lb/> download a contract application from the UNC<lb/> Carolina Population Center Data Portal (https://<lb/> data.cpc.unc.edu/projects/2/view). Once<lb/> completed, researchers must submit their<lb/> application through the portal. Data used in the<lb/> current study were not collected by the study<lb/> authors and therefore we do not have the<lb/> permission to share the data. The data used are<lb/> restricted use data from the Add Health study.<lb/> Researchers who wish to gain access to this data<lb/> must apply for access using the information<lb/> specified above. The authors did not have any<lb/> special access privileges to the data and confirm<lb/> that the data was obtained in the same manner<lb/> outlined above. Relevant codes for replicating<lb/> analyses are within the Supporting information files<lb/> of this manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">Research reported in this study was<lb/> supported by the National Institute of Nursing<lb/> Research under Award Number R21NR017154 to<lb/> Co-PIs Mark C. Pachucki and Lindsay T. Hoyt. This<lb/> research uses data from the National Longitudinal<lb/> Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health).<lb/> Add Health is directed by Robert A. Hummer and<lb/> funded by the National Institute on Aging<lb/> cooperative agreements U01 AG071448 (Hummer)<lb/> and U01AG071450 (Allison E. Aiello and Hummer)<lb/> at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.<lb/> Waves I-V data are from the Add Health Program<lb/> Project, grant P01 HD319121 (Harris) was directed<lb/> by Kathleen Mullan Harris and designed by J.<lb/> Richard Udry, Peter S. Bearman, and Kathleen<lb/> Mullan Harris at the University of North Carolina at<lb/> Chapel Hill, and funded by Grant P01-HD31921<lb/> from the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute<lb/> of Child Health and Human Development, with<lb/> cooperative funding from 23 other federal agencies<lb/> and foundations. No direct support was received<lb/> from grant P01-HD31921 for this analysis. The<lb/> funders had no role in study design, data collection<lb/> and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of<lb/> the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>