<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin11891280306508741743"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Gray whale (Eschrichtius robustus) post-<lb/>mortem findings from December 2018<lb/> through 2021 during the Unusual Mortality<lb/> Event in the Eastern North Pacific<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Stephen Raverty ID 1☯¤<lb/> *, Pa ´draig Duignan 2☯ , Denise Greig 3,4☯ , Jessica L. Huggins 5 , Kathy<lb/> Burek Huntington ID 6<lb/> , Michael Garner 7 , John Calambokidis ID 5<lb/> , Paul Cottrell 8 , Kerri Danil 9 ,<lb/> Dalin D&apos;Alessandro 10 , Deborah Duffield 10 , Moe Flannery 4 , Frances MD Gulland 11 ,<lb/> Barbie Halaska 2 , Dyanna M. Lambourn 12 , Taylor Lehnhart 8 , Jorge Urba ´n R. 13 ,<lb/> Teri Rowles 14 , James Rice 15 , Kate Savage 16 , Kristin Wilkinson 17 , Justin Greenman 18 ,<lb/> Justin Viezbicke 18 , Brendan CottrellID 19 , P. Dawn Goley 20 , Maggie MartinezID 2 ,<lb/> Deborah Fauquier 14<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Animal Health Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abbotsford, BC, Canada,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 The Marine Mammal Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sausalito, CA, United<lb/> States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Ocean Associates, Inc. under contract to Office of Protected Resources, National<lb/> Marine Fisheries Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Silver Spring, MD, United States<lb/> of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 California Academy of Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>San Francisco, CA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Cascadia<lb/> Research Collective,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Olympia, WA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Alaska Veterinary Pathology Services,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Eagle<lb/> River, AK, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 Northwest ZooPath,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Monroe, WA, United States of America,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>8 Fisheries and Oceans Canada,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>9 Southwest Fisheries Science Center, National<lb/> Marine Fisheries Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>La Jolla, CA, United States of<lb/> America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>10 Portland State University, Department of Biology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Portland, OR, United States of America,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>11 Wildlife Health Center, School of Veterinary Medicine, UC Davis,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Davis, CA, United States of America,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>12 Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife, Marine Mammal Investigations,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lakewood, WA, United<lb/> States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>13 Departamento de Ciencias Marinas y Costeras, Universidad Auto ´noma de Baja<lb/> California Sur,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>La Paz, Mexico,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>14 Office of Protected Resources, National Marine Fisheries Service,<lb/> National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Silver Spring, MD, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>15 Oregon<lb/> State University Marine Mammal Institute, Hatfield Marine Science Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Newport, OR, United States of<lb/> America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>16 Alaska Biosystems under contract to Alaska Regional Office, National Marine Fisheries Service,<lb/> National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Juneau, AK, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>17 Protected<lb/> Resources Division, West Coast Region, National Marine Fisheries Service, National Oceanic and<lb/> Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seattle, WA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>18 Protected Resources Division, West<lb/> Coast Region, National Marine Fisheries Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Long<lb/> Beach, CA, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>19 Applied Remote Sensing Lab, Department of Geography, McGill<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montreal, QC, Canada,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>20 Department of Biological Sciences, Cal Poly Humboldt,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Arcata, CA,<lb/> United States of America<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> ¤ Current address:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of British Columbia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>stephen.raverty@gov.bc.ca</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Beginning in December 2018, increased numbers of gray whale (Eschrichtius robustus)<lb/> strandings were reported along the west coast of Mexico, the United States, and Canada,<lb/> prompting declaration of a gray whale Unusual Mortality Event (UME) by the United States<lb/> National Marine Fisheries Service. Although strandings declined in 2020 and 2021 from a<lb/> peak in 2019, the UME is still ongoing as of fall 2023. Between 17 December 2018 and 31<lb/> December 2021, 503 animals stranded along the west coast of North America, with 226<lb/> strandings in Mexico, 71 in California, 12 in Oregon, 56 in Washington, 21 in British<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295861 March 27, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 25<lb/></page>

	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Raverty S, Duignan P, Greig D, Huggins<lb/> JL, Huntington KB, Garner M, et al. (2024) Gray<lb/> whale (Eschrichtius robustus) post-mortem<lb/> findings from December 2018 through 2021<lb/> during the Unusual Mortality Event in the Eastern<lb/> North Pacific. PLoS ONE 19(3): e0295861.</reference>

	<idno>https://<lb/> doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295861<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Vitor Hugo Rodrigues Paiva,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>MARE -<lb/>Marine and Environmental Sciences Centre,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>PORTUGAL<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: July 18, 2023<lb/> Accepted: November 27, 2023<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>March 27, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295861<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright: This is an open access article, free of all<lb/> copyright, and may be freely reproduced,<lb/> distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or<lb/> otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.<lb/> The work is made available under the Creative<lb/> Commons CC0 public domain dedication.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">Third party data are<lb/> publicly available from NOAA (https://www.<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Columbia, and 117 in Alaska. These included 187 males, 167 females, and 149 whales of<lb/> undetermined sex; and 193 adults, 194 subadults, 40 calves, 1 fetus, and 75 whales of<lb/> undetermined age class. We report on 61 of the 503 carcasses (12%) that had external and<lb/> internal gross necropsy and/or histopathology data: of these 61 whales, findings that con-<lb/>tributed to death were identified in 33 (54%) whales. Sixteen of the 61 (26%) were severely<lb/> emaciated. Gross lesions of blunt force trauma consistent with vessel strike were identified<lb/> in 11 of the 61 animals (18%), only two of which were emaciated. Two whales (3%) were<lb/> entangled at time of death, and one died from entrapment. Signs of killer whale (Orcinus<lb/> orca) interaction were documented in 19 of the 61 animals; five were deemed from recent<lb/> interactions and three (5%) likely contributed to mortality. A specific cause of death could<lb/> not be identified in 28 of 61 whales (46%). Additionally, logistical challenges and the<lb/> advanced state of decomposition of most examined carcasses precluded detection of<lb/> potential infectious or toxic causes of morbidity or mortality. Up to 2016, the eastern North<lb/> Pacific population of gray whale population had generally been increasing since the cessa-<lb/>tion of historic whaling and a prior UME in 1999-2000. However, recent abundance and calf<lb/> production estimates have declined, a trend that overlaps the current UME. The relative<lb/> contributions of carrying capacity, environmental change, prey shifts, and infectious, toxic,<lb/> and other processes to the increased gray whale mortalities have not yet been resolved.<lb/> Nevertheless, the marked temporal increase in strandings, including findings of malnutrition<lb/> in some of the whales, along with low calf production, likely represent consequences of com-<lb/>plex and dynamic ecological interactions in the ocean impacting the population.<lb/></div>

	<note type="availability">fisheries.noaa.gov/national/marine-life-distress/<lb/> 2019-2023-gray-whale-unusual-mortality-event-<lb/>along-west-coast-and). Additional data is available<lb/> as Supporting Information.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">National Marine Fisheries Service<lb/> provided support in the form of salaries for authors<lb/> DF and PC, respectively, but did not have any<lb/> additional role in the study design, data collection<lb/> and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of<lb/> the manuscript. The specific roles of these authors<lb/> are articulated in the &apos;author contributions&apos; section.<lb/> The funders had no role in study design, data<lb/> collection and analysis, decision to publish, or<lb/> preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have no<lb/> competing interests.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
