<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin4077550627334240568"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Training for endovascular therapy of acute<lb/> arterial disease and procedure-related<lb/> complication: An extracorporeally-perfused<lb/> human cadaver model study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Viktor Hartung ID<lb/> 1 , Anne Marie Augustin 1 , Jan-Peter Grunz ID 1<lb/> , Henner Huflage ID 1<lb/> , Jan-<lb/>Lucca Hennes 1 , Florian Kleefeldt ID 2<lb/> , Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n2 , Dominik Peter 3 , Sven Lichthardt 3 ,<lb/> Thorsten Alexander Bley 1 , Philipp Gruschwitz ID 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Wu ¨rzburg, Wu ¨rzburg,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Germany,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Institute of Anatomy and Cell Biology, University of Wu ¨rzburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wu ¨rzburg, Germany,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of General, Visceral, Transplant, Vascular, and Pediatric Surgery, University Hospital of<lb/> Wu ¨rzburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wu ¨rzburg, Germany<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>Gruschwitz_P@ukw.de</email>

	Abstract Purpose<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The aim of this study was to evaluate the usability of a recently developed extracorporeally-<lb/>perfused cadaver model for training the angiographic management of acute arterial dis-<lb/>eases and periprocedural complications that may occur during endovascular therapy of the<lb/> lower extremity arterial runoff.<lb/> Materials and methods<lb/> Continuous extracorporeal perfusion was established in three fresh-frozen body donors via<lb/> inguinal and infragenicular access. Using digital subtraction angiography for guidance, both<lb/> arterial embolization (e.g., embolization using coils, vascular plugs, particles, and liquid<lb/> embolic agents) and endovascular recanalization procedures (e.g., manual aspiration or<lb/> balloon-assisted embolectomy) as well as various embolism protection devices were tested.<lb/> Furthermore, the management of complications during percutaneous transluminal angio-<lb/>plasty, such as vessel dissection and rupture, were exercised by implantation of endovascu-<lb/>lar dissection repair system or covered stents. Interventions were performed by two board-<lb/>certified interventional radiologists and one resident with only limited angiographic<lb/> experience. Results<lb/> Stable extracorporeal perfusion was successfully established on both thighs of all three<lb/> body donors. Digital subtraction angiography could be performed reliably and resulted in<lb/> realistic artery depiction. The model allowed for repeatable training of endovascular recana-<lb/>lization and arterial embolization procedures with typical tactile feedback in a controlled<lb/> environment. Furthermore, the handling of more complex angiographic devices could be<lb/></div>

	PLOS ONE<lb/>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024<lb/></reference>

	1 / 14<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Hartung V, Augustin AM, Grunz J-P,<lb/> Huflage H, Hennes J-L, Kleefeldt F, et al. (2024)<lb/> Training for endovascular therapy of acute arterial<lb/> disease and procedure-related complication: An<lb/> extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model<lb/> study. PLoS ONE 19(2): e0297800.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/<lb/> 10.1371/journal.pone.0297800<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Ezio Lanza,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Humanitas Clinical and<lb/> Research Center -IRRCS,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>ITALY<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: August 19, 2023<lb/> Accepted: January 12, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>February 8, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Hartung et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript.<lb/> exercised.
	<div type="abstract">Whereas procedural success was be ascertained for most endovascular inter-<lb/>ventions, thrombectomies procedures were not feasible in some cases due to the lack of<lb/> inherent coagulation. Conclusion<lb/> The presented perfusion model is suitable for practicing time-critical endovascular interven-<lb/>tions in the lower extremity runoff under realistic but controlled conditions.<lb/></div>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">PG; Z-02CSP/18; Interdisciplinary Center<lb/> for Clinical Research (IZKF) at the University of<lb/> Wu ¨rzburg; https://www.med.uni-wuerzburg.de/<lb/> izkf/startseite/ JPG.; Z-3BC/02; Interdisciplinary<lb/> Center for Clinical Research (IZKF) at the University<lb/> of Wu ¨rzburg; https://www.med.uni-wuerzburg.de/<lb/> izkf/startseite/ The funders had no role in study<lb/> design, data collection and analysis, decision to<lb/> publish, or preparation of the manuscript. TAB and<lb/> JPG received speaker honoraria from Siemens<lb/> Healthcare GmbH outside of the presented work.<lb/> The Department of Diagnostic and Interventional<lb/> Radiology of the University Hospital Wu ¨rzburg<lb/> receives ongoing research funding from Siemens<lb/> Healthcare GmbH; https://www.siemens-<lb/>healthineers.com/en-us The funders had no role in<lb/> study design, data collection and analysis, decision<lb/> to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.<lb/></note>
			
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
