<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-01T17:18:11.564Z">12/1/2025 5:18:11 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-01T17:17:57.679758Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-01T17:17:57.679758Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Reliability and validity of a simplified touch<lb/> experiences and attitudes questionnaire for<lb/> Chinese college students<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lei Yang 1,2 , Xuelian Li 2 , Zhijie Xie 2 , Lujun Shen ID<lb/> 2,3 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Faculty of Psychology, Tianjin Normal University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tianjin, China,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 School of Psychology, Xinxiang Medical<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Xinxiang City, Henan Province, China,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 School of Education, Hebei University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baoding City,<lb/> Hebei Province, China<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>shenlj945@163.com</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Touch cultures have both differences and commonalities in different regions. The Touch<lb/> Experiences and Attitudes Questionnaire (TEAQ) is a widely applicable self-report tool. The<lb/> purpose of our research was to examine the validity and reliability of the Chinese version of<lb/> TEAQ for Chinese college students. We translated the 57 items of the original TEAQ into<lb/> Chinese and assessed its cultural and linguistic adaptation in Chinese context. Two sam-<lb/>ples were recruited for the assessment of validity and reliability. The Social Support Rating<lb/> Scale, Index of Well-being Scale and Security Questionnaire were chosen as criterion-<lb/>related validity indicators. Item analysis, principal component analysis and confirmatory fac-<lb/>tor analysis indicated that the simplified Chinese version of TEAQ contained 18 items in<lb/> three factors: Attitude to Intimate Touch, Childhood Touch and Current Positive Touch, with<lb/> a cumulative variance contribution rate of 57.12%. The 3-factor model had good validity and<lb/> reliability. The TEAQ was positively correlated with social support, sense of security and<lb/> well-being. There were demographic differences in sex and left-behind experience. We<lb/> anticipate the simplified TEAQ will be a valuable tool for the research of touch among Chi-<lb/>nese college students.<lb/></div>

	<!-- minor corrections -->
	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295812 January 2, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 15<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Yang L, Li X, Xie Z, Shen L (2024)<lb/> Reliability and validity of a simplified touch<lb/> experiences and attitudes questionnaire for<lb/> Chinese college students. PLoS ONE 19(1):<lb/> e0295812.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.<lb/> pone.0295812<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Chongzeng Bi,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Southwest University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>CHINA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: June 27, 2023<lb/> Accepted: November 28, 2023<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>January 2, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Yang et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All data files are<lb/> available from the figshare (DOI: 10.6084/m9.<lb/> figshare.23479643).<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">This study was funded by the Tianjin<lb/> Research Innovation Project for Postgraduate<lb/> Students (2022BKYZ021): L Y; the Philosophy and<lb/> Social Sciences Planning Projects of Henan<lb/> Province (2021BSH015): L Y. This work was also<lb/> supported by Henan Province Medical Discipline-<lb/>Medical Psychology. The funders had no role in<lb/> study design, data collection and analysis, decision<lb/> to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>