<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T12:37:16.690Z">12/2/2025 12:37:16 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T12:37:05.459837Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T12:37:05.459837Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4-<lb/>coumarate: CoA ligases from Marchantia<lb/> paleacea and their roles in lignin and<lb/> flavanone biosynthesis<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Shuai Gao 1 , Xin-Yan Liu 1 , Rong Ni 1 , Jie Fu 1 , Hui Tan 1 , Ai-Xia Cheng ID 1☯<lb/> *,<lb/> Hong-Xiang Lou 1,2☯ *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Key Laboratory of Chemical Biology of Natural Products, Ministry of Education, School of Pharmaceutical<lb/> Sciences, Shandong University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jinan, Shandong, China,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Shandong Provincial Clinical Research Center<lb/> for Emergency and Critical Care Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jinan, Shan-dong, China<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>aixiacheng@sdu.edu.cn</email>

	(AXC);
	<email>louhongxiang@sdu.edu.cn</email>

	(HXL) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Phenylpropanoids play important roles in plant physiology and the enzyme 4-coumarate:<lb/> coenzyme A ligase (4CL) catalyzes the formation of thioesters. Despite extensive character-<lb/>ization in various plants, the functions of 4CLs in the liverwort Marchantia paleacea remain<lb/> unknown. Here, four 4CLs from M. paleacea were isolated and functionally analyzed. Heter-<lb/>ologous expression in Escherichia coli indicated the presence of different enzymatic activi-<lb/>ties in the four enzymes. Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 were able to convert caffeic, p-coumaric,<lb/> cinnamic, ferulic, dihydro-p-coumaric, and 5-hydroxyferulic acids to their corresponding<lb/> CoA esters, while Mp4CL3 and Mp4CL4 catalyzed none. Mp4CL1 transcription was induced<lb/> when M. paleacea thalli were treated with methyl jasmonate (MeJA). The overexpression of<lb/> Mp4CL1 increased the levels of lignin in transgenic Arabidopsis. In addition, we recon-<lb/>structed the flavanone biosynthetic pathway in E. coli. The pathway comprised Mp4CL1, co-<lb/>expressed with chalcone synthase (CHS) from different plant species, and the efficiency of<lb/> biosynthesis was optimal when both the 4CL and CHS were obtained from the same spe-<lb/>cies M. paleacea.<lb/></div>

	<!-- minor corrections -->

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 19<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Gao S, Liu X-Y, Ni R, Fu J, Tan H, Cheng<lb/> A-X, et al. (2024) Molecular cloning and functional<lb/> analysis of 4-coumarate: CoA ligases from<lb/> Marchantia paleacea and their roles in lignin and<lb/> flavanone biosynthesis. PLoS ONE 19(1):<lb/> e0296079.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.<lb/> pone.0296079<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Igor Cesarino,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>,
	</byline>

	<address>BRAZIL<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: June 23, 2023<lb/> Accepted: December 5, 2023<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>January 8, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Gao et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> information files.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">This work was supported by the National<lb/> Natural Science Foundation of China, URL: https://<lb/> www.nsfc.gov.cn/ (No. 32000228). The funders<lb/> had no role in study design, data collection and<lb/> analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the<lb/> manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>