<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-04T11:37:41.963Z">12/4/2025 11:37:41 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-04T11:37:25.157581Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-04T11:37:25.157581Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Detection of driver mutations and genomic<lb/> signatures in endometrial cancers using<lb/> artificial intelligence algorithms<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anda Stan 1☯ , Korey Bosart 1☯ , Mehak Kaur 1☯ , Martin Vo 2 , Wilber Escorcia 2 , Ryan J. Yoder 3 ,<lb/> Renee A. BouleyID 3 *, Ruben C. PetreacaID 4,5 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Biology Program, The Ohio State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Marion, Ohio, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Biology<lb/> Department, Xavier University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cincinnati, Ohio, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Chemistry and<lb/> Biochemistry, The Ohio State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Marion, Ohio, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Molecular<lb/> Genetics, The Ohio State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Marion, Ohio, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 James Comprehensive<lb/> Cancer Center, The Ohio State University Columbus,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Columbus, Ohio, United States of America<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>bouley.8@osu.edu</email>

	(RAB);
	<email>petreaca.1@osu.edu</email>

	(RCB) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Analyzed endometrial cancer (EC) genomes have allowed for the identification of molecular<lb/> signatures, which enable the classification, and sometimes prognostication, of these can-<lb/>cers. Artificial intelligence algorithms have facilitated the partitioning of mutations into driver<lb/> and passenger based on a variety of parameters, including gene function and frequency of<lb/> mutation. Here, we undertook an evaluation of EC cancer genomes deposited on the Cata-<lb/>logue of Somatic Mutations in Cancers (COSMIC), with the goal to classify all mutations as<lb/> either driver or passenger. Our analysis showed that approximately 2.5% of all mutations are<lb/> driver and cause cellular transformation and immortalization. We also characterized nucleo-<lb/>tide level mutation signatures, gross chromosomal re-arrangements, and gene expression<lb/> profiles. We observed that endometrial cancers show distinct nucleotide substitution and<lb/> chromosomal re-arrangement signatures compared to other cancers. We also identified high<lb/> expression levels of the CLDN18 claudin gene, which is involved in growth, survival, metasta-<lb/>sis and proliferation. We then used in silico protein structure analysis to examine the effect of<lb/> certain previously uncharacterized driver mutations on protein structure. We found that cer-<lb/>tain mutations in CTNNB1 and TP53 increase protein stability, which may contribute to cellu-<lb/>lar transformation. While our analysis retrieved previously classified mutations and genomic<lb/> alterations, which is to be expected, this study also identified new signatures. Additionally,<lb/> we show that artificial intelligence algorithms can be effectively leveraged to accurately pre-<lb/>dict key drivers of cancer. This analysis will expand our understanding of ECs and improve<lb/> the molecular toolbox for classification, diagnosis, or potential treatment of these cancers.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 19<lb/></page>
	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Stan A, Bosart K, Kaur M, Vo M, Escorcia<lb/> W, Yoder RJ, et al. (2024) Detection of driver<lb/> mutations and genomic signatures in endometrial<lb/> cancers using artificial intelligence algorithms.<lb/> PLoS ONE 19(2): e0299114.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/<lb/> 10.1371/journal.pone.0299114<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Nandini Dey,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Avera Research Institute,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: October 16, 2023<lb/> Accepted: February 5, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>February 26, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Stan et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All data can be found<lb/> at COSMIC: https://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cosmic<lb/> cBioPortal: https://www.cbioportal.org/.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">Ohio State University Comprehensive<lb/> Cancer Center -Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital<lb/> and Richard J. Solove Research Institute. There is<lb/> no grant number.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>