<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-01T17:14:43.747Z">12/1/2025 5:14:43 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-01T17:14:22.499079Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-01T17:14:22.499079Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Examining the influence of environmental<lb/> factors on Acanthamoeba castellanii and<lb/> Pseudomonas aeruginosa in co-culture<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rhiannon E. Cecil ID , Deborah R. Yoder-Himes ID *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Biology Department, University of Louisville,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>deborah.yoder-himes@louisville.edu</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Exploration of interspecies interactions between microorganisms can have taxonomic, eco-<lb/>logical, evolutionary, or medical applications. To better explore interactions between micro-<lb/>organisms it is important to establish the ideal conditions that ensure survival of all species<lb/> involved. In this study, we sought to identify the ideal biotic and abiotic factors that would<lb/> result in high co-culture viability of two interkingdom species, Pseudomonas aeruginosa and<lb/> Acanthamoeba castellanii, two soil dwelling microbes. There have been limited studies<lb/> showing long-term interactions between these two organisms as co-culture can result in<lb/> high mortality for one or both organisms suggesting a predator-predator interaction may<lb/> exist between them. In this study, we identified biotic and abiotic conditions that resulted in a<lb/> high viability for both organisms in long-term co-culture, including optimizing temperature,<lb/> nutrient concentration, choice of bacterial strains, and the initial ratio of interacting partners.<lb/> These two species represent ideal partners for studying microbial interactions because<lb/> amoebae act similarly to mammalian immune cells in many respects, and this can allow<lb/> researchers to study host-pathogen interactions in vitro. Therefore, long-term interaction<lb/> studies between these microbes might reveal the evolutionary steps that occur in bacteria<lb/> when subjected to intense predation, like what occurs when pathogens enter the human<lb/> body. The culture conditions characterized here resulted in high viability for both organisms<lb/> for at least 14-days in co-culture suggesting that long-term experimental studies between<lb/> these species can be achieved using these culture conditions.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024<lb/></reference>

    <!-- minor corrections -->
	<page>1 / 18<lb/></page>
          a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Cecil RE, Yoder-Himes DR (2024)<lb/> Examining the influence of environmental factors<lb/> on Acanthamoeba castellanii and Pseudomonas<lb/> aeruginosa in co-culture. PLoS ONE 19(6):<lb/> e0305973.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.<lb/> pone.0305973<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Robert P. Smith,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nova Southeastern<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: September 14, 2023<lb/> Accepted: June 7, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>June 24, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Cecil, Yoder-Himes. This is an<lb/> open access article distributed under the terms of<lb/> the Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> Information files.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">&quot;This research was supported by a grant<lb/> (YODERHIMES) from The Center for Predictive<lb/> Medicine at the University of Louisville. The<lb/> funders had no role in study design, data collection<lb/> and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of<lb/> the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>