<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T12:42:22.967Z">12/2/2025 12:42:22 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T12:42:12.852224Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T12:42:12.852224Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Overexpression of miR-200s inhibits<lb/> proliferation and invasion while increasing<lb/> apoptosis in murine ovarian cancer cells<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Resh Carter, Jim J. Petrik, Roger A. Moorehead ID *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Biomedical Sciences, Ontario Veterinary College, University of Guelph,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guelph, ON, Canada<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>rmoorehe@uoguelph.ca</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Women diagnosed with ovarian cancer frequently have a poor prognosis as their cancer is<lb/> often diagnosed at more advanced stages when the cancer has metastasized. At this point<lb/> surgery cannot remove all the tumor cells and while ovarian cancer cells often initially<lb/> respond to chemotherapeutic agents like carboplatin and paclitaxel, resistance to these<lb/> agents frequently occurs. Thus, novel therapies are required for the treatment of advanced<lb/> stage ovarian cancer. One therapeutic option being explored is the regulation of non-coding<lb/> RNAs such as microRNAs. An advantage of microRNAs is that they can regulate tens, hun-<lb/>dreds and sometimes thousands of mRNAs in cells and thus may be more effective than<lb/> chemotherapeutic agents or targeted therapies. To investigate the therapeutic potential of<lb/> miR-200s in ovarian cancer, lentiviral vectors were used to overexpress both miR-200 clus-<lb/>ters in two murine ovarian cancer cell lines, ID8 and 28-2. Overexpression of miR-200s<lb/> reduced the expression of several mesenchymal genes and proteins, significantly inhibited<lb/> proliferation as assessed by BrdU flow cytometry and significantly reduced invasion through<lb/> Matrigel coated transwell inserts in both cell lines. Overexpression of miR-200s also<lb/> increased basal apoptosis approximately 3-fold in both cell lines as determined by annexin<lb/> V flow cytometry. Pathway analysis of RNA sequencing of control and miR-200 overexpres-<lb/>sing ovarian cancer cells revealed that genes regulated by miR-200s were involved in pro-<lb/>cesses like epithelial mesenchymal transition (EMT) and cell migration. Therefore, miR-<lb/>200s can inhibit proliferation and increase apoptosis while suppressing tumor cell invasion<lb/> and thus simultaneously target three key cancer pathways.<lb/></div>

    <!-- minor changes -->
	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 17<lb/></page>
    a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Carter R, Petrik JJ, Moorehead RA (2024)<lb/> Overexpression of miR-200s inhibits proliferation<lb/> and invasion while increasing apoptosis in murine<lb/> ovarian cancer cells. PLoS ONE 19(7): e0307178.<lb/></reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Yi-Hsien Hsieh</editor>,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Chung Shan Medical<lb/> University</affiliation>,
	</byline>

	<address>TAIWAN<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: April 11, 2024<lb/> Accepted: July 1, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>July 19, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Carter et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">Our data is publicly<lb/> available at NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus as<lb/> accession number GSE250195.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">CIHR project grant PJT-162218 awarded<lb/> to Roger Moorehead. The funders had no role in<lb/> study design, data collection and analysis, decision<lb/> to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.<lb/></note>

	Abbreviations:
	<keyword>ba429, miR-200b/200a/429 cluster;<lb/> BrdU, bromodeoxyuridine; c141, miR-200c/141<lb/> cluster; CCC, clear cell carcinoma; EC,<lb/> endometrioid carcinoma; EMT, epithelial<lb/> mesenchymal transition; EV, empty vector; FDR,<lb/> false discovery rate; HGSOC, high grade serous<lb/> ovarian cancer; LGSOC, low grade serous ovarian<lb/> cancer; MC, mucinous carcinoma; miRNA,<lb/> microRNA; PARP, poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase;<lb/> PRC2, polycomb repressor complex 2; UTR,<lb/> untranslated region.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>