<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin9042278285876124342"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024<lb/> https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under<lb/> the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Greenland-wide empirical reconstruction of paleo ice sheet<lb/> retreat informed by ice extent markers: PaleoGrIS version 1.0<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tancrède P. M. Leger 1 , Christopher D. Clark 1 , Carla Huynh 2 , Sharman Jones 3 , Jeremy C. Ely 1 , Sarah L. Bradley 1 ,<lb/> Christiaan Diemont 1 , and Anna L. C. Hughes 4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Geography, University of Sheffield,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sheffield, S10 2TN, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 School of GeoSciences, University of Edinburgh,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Drummond Street, Edinburgh, EH8 9XP, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Geography and Earth Sciences, Aberystwyth University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Aberystwyth, SY23 3DB, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Geography, School of Environment, Education and Development, The University of Manchester,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Manchester, M13 9PL, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	Correspondence:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tancrède P. M. Leger</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<email>t.p.leger@sheffield.ac.uk</email>

	,
	<email>tancrede.leger@unil.ch</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received: 28 July 2023 -Discussion started: 31 July 2023<lb/> Revised: 29 November 2023 -Accepted: 12 February 2024</note>

	-Published:
	<date>28 March 2024<lb/></date>

	Abstract.
	<div type="abstract">The Greenland Ice Sheet is a large contributor to<lb/> global sea level rise, and current mass losses are projected<lb/> to accelerate. However, model projections of future ice sheet<lb/> evolution are limited by the fact that the ice sheet is not in<lb/> equilibrium with present-day climate but is still adjusting to<lb/> past changes that occurred over thousands of years. While the<lb/> influence of such committed adjustments on future ice sheet<lb/> evolution remains unquantified, it could be addressed by cal-<lb/>ibrating numerical ice sheet models over larger timescales<lb/> and, importantly, against empirical data on ice margin posi-<lb/>tions. To enable such paleo data-model interactions, we need<lb/> Greenland-wide empirical reconstructions of past ice sheet<lb/> extent that combine geomorphological and geochronological<lb/> evidence. Despite an increasing number of field studies pro-<lb/>ducing new chronologies, such a reconstruction is currently<lb/> lacking in Greenland. Furthermore, a time slice reconstruc-<lb/>tion can help to (i) answer open questions regarding the rate<lb/> and pattern of ice margin evolution in Greenland since the<lb/> glacial maximum, (ii) develop a standardised record of em-<lb/>pirical data, and (iii) identify new sites for future field cam-<lb/>paigns. Based on these motivations, we here present Pale-<lb/>oGrIS 1.0, a new Greenland-wide isochrone reconstruction<lb/> of ice sheet extent evolution through the Late Glacial and<lb/> early-to mid-Holocene informed by both geomorphological<lb/> and geochronological markers. Our isochrones have a tem-<lb/>poral resolution of 500 years and span ∼ 7.5 kyr from ap-<lb/>proximately 14 to 6.5 kyr BP. We describe the resulting re-<lb/>construction of the shrinking ice sheet and conduct a series of<lb/> ice-sheet-wide and regional analyses to quantify retreat rates,<lb/> areal extent change, and their variability across space and<lb/> time. During the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene,<lb/> we find the Greenland Ice Sheet has lost about one-third<lb/> of its areal extent (0.89 million km 2 ). Between ∼ 14 and<lb/> ∼ 8.5 kyr BP, it experienced a near-constant rate of areal ex-<lb/>tent loss of 170 ± 27 km 2 yr -1 . We find that the ice-sheet-<lb/>scale pattern of margin retreat is well correlated to atmo-<lb/>spheric and oceanic temperature variations, which implies a<lb/> high sensitivity of the ice sheet to deglacial warming. How-<lb/>ever, during the Holocene, we observe inertia in the ice sheet<lb/> system that likely caused a centennial-to millennial-scale<lb/> time lag in ice extent response. At the regional scale, we<lb/> observe highly heterogeneous deglacial responses in ice ex-<lb/>tent evident in both the magnitude and rate of retreat. We hy-<lb/>pothesise that non-climatic factors, such as the asymmetrical<lb/> nature of continental shelves and onshore bed topographies,<lb/> play important roles in determining the regional-to valley-<lb/>scale dynamics. PaleoGrIS 1.0 is an open-access database<lb/> designed to be used by both the empirical and numerical<lb/> modelling communities. It should prove a useful basis for im-<lb/>proved future versions of the reconstruction when new geo-<lb/>morphological and geochronological data become available.<lb/></div>

	Published by
	<publisher>Copernicus Publications</publisher>

	on behalf of the European Geosciences Union.<lb/> T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
