<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin171924385924389269"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024<lb/> https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under<lb/> the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>


	<title level="j">IAHS2022 -Variability and change across space, time, extremes, and interfaces<lb/></title>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Use of the HEC RAS model for the analysis of<lb/> exceptional floods in the Ouémé basin<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ernest Amoussou 1,2 , Félix Toundé Amoussou 2 , Aymar Yaovi Bossa 3 , Domiho Japhet Kodja 2 , Henri<lb/> Sourou Totin Vodounon 1,2 , Constant Houndénou 2 , Valérie Borrell Estupina 4 , Jean-Emmanuel Paturel 5 ,<lb/> Gil Mahé 5 , Christophe Cudennec 6 , and Michel Boko 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Geography and Regional Planning (DGAT), University of Parakou,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Parakou, Benin<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Laboratoire Pierre Pagney: Climate, Water, Ecosystem and Development (LACEEDE),<lb/> University of Abomey-Calavi,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abomey-Calavi, Benin<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 National Water Institute (INE), University of Abomey-Calavi,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abomey-Calavi, Benin<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 G-EAU, Univ. Montpellier, IRD, INRAE,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Montpellier HydroSciences Laboratory, University of Montpellier 2,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 The Agro Institute Agrocampus Ouest,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rennes, France<lb/></address>

	Correspondence:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ernest Amoussou</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<email>ajernest@yahoo.fr</email>

	) and

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Félix Toundé Amoussou</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<lb/> (
	<email>felixamoussou96@gmail.com</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received: 10 June 2022 -Revised: 16 November 2022 -Accepted: 14 March 202 -</note>

	Published:
	<date>18 April 2024<lb/></date>

	Abstract.
	<div type="abstract">The Ouémé River basin extends over almost half of Benin&apos;s territory, entirely located in a humid<lb/> tropical climate. This river system includes a deltaic zone (delta of the Ouémé) known for its high agricultural<lb/> potential and thus subject to a socio-economic development agenda. The Ouémé delta is facing recurrent floods<lb/> that maintain rural agricultural population into a retrograding crisis with significant damages such as losses of<lb/> properties. The objective of this study is to improve decision-making in the Ouémé basin through the simulation<lb/> of exceptional floods using the HEC-RAS model.<lb/> The HEC RAS model is a conceptual model, which works through mathematical and physical formulas to<lb/> implement environmental phenomena for forecasting, understanding and analysis purposes. The model inputs<lb/> used are basin GIS data, hydro-meteorological data, characteristics of existing hydraulic structures, etc. The<lb/> targeted outputs include 1D/2D/3D view plans with support of satellite images, tables, graphs and curves. It is<lb/> worth mentioning that the model provides outputs compatible with other tools, such as civil engineering (Civil<lb/> 3D, Revit, Infraworks, etc.) and GIS, that help to expand the valorization fields.<lb/> The implementation of the model in the Ouémé basin has made it possible to note: (i) that the recurring<lb/> effect of losses and damages is justified by the settlement of the population on the river banks; (ii) that there<lb/> is an important agricultural production in areas of high flood risk; (iii) that depending on the occurrence of<lb/> the phenomenon, the flooded extent and the height of submersion remains variable, and more important for<lb/> extreme flooding; (iv) about 12.07 % occurrence of river flood against 13.24 % for flash flood at a return period<lb/> of 30 years. Moreover, it is very relevant to note that most of flood waters converge to the western part of the basin<lb/> (an area with a low risk of flooding, stretched over 63.68 km 2 ) and to the eastern part around the Damè-Wogon<lb/> depression (an area at high risk of flooding, stretched over 10.49 km 2 ).<lb/></div>

	Keywords.
	<keyword>Flood risk; flood damage estimation; Ouémé River<lb/> Basin; HEC-RAS model; exceptional flood<lb/></keyword>

	Published by

	<publisher>Copernicus Publications</publisher>

	on behalf of the International Association of Hydrological Sciences.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
