<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-17T15:51:56.792Z">11/17/2025 3:51:56 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-17T15:50:18.315993Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-17T15:50:18.315993Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Barriers to accessibility of medicines for <lb/>hyperlipidemia in low-and middle-income <lb/>countries <lb/>Chaoyang Li 1 *, Garrison Spencer 2 , Muhammad Jami Husain 1 , Rachel Nugent 2 , <lb/>Deon Auzenne 3 , Deliana Kostova 1 , Patricia RichterID 1 <lb/>1 Division of Global Health Protection, Global Health Center, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, <lb/>Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 2 Center for Global Noncommunicable Diseases, RTI <lb/>International, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, United States of America, 3 Department of <lb/>Psychology, Howard University, Washington, District of Columbia, United States of America <lb/>* cli@cdc.gov. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Despite the high burden of hyperlipidemia and the effectiveness of treatment, evidence sug-<lb/>gests that the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines can be low in many low-and middle-<lb/>income countries (LMICs). The aim of this study was to identify common barriers to the <lb/>accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia in LMICs. A multimethod analysis and multiple <lb/>data sources were used to assess the accessibility and barriers of medicines for hyperlipid-<lb/>emia in selected LMICs. The overall median availability of statins for hyperlipidemia in public <lb/>facilities was 0% and 5.4%, for originators and generics, respectively. In private facilities, <lb/>median availability was 13.3% and 35.9%, for originators and generics, respectively. Statin <lb/>availability was lowest in Africa and South-East Asia. Private facilities generally had higher <lb/>availability than public facilities. Statins are less affordable in lower-income countries, cost-<lb/>ing around 6 days&apos; wages per month. Originator statins are less affordable than generics in <lb/>countries of all income-levels. The median cost for statin medications per month ranges <lb/>from a low of $1 in Kenya to a high of $62 in Mexico, with most countries having a median <lb/>monthly cost between $3.6 and $17.0. The key informant interviews suggested that accessi-<lb/>bility to hyperlipidemia medicines in LMICs faces barriers in multiple dimensions of health <lb/>systems. The availability and affordability of statins are generally low in LMICs. Several <lb/>steps could be implemented to improve the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines, <lb/>including private sector engagement, physician education, investment in technology, and <lb/>enhancement of health systems. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Cardiovascular diseases (CVD) are the leading cause of death worldwide, and 80% of CVD <lb/>deaths occur in low-and middle-income countries (LMICs) [1]. Hyperlipidemia (or dyslipide-<lb/>mia) is one of the important risk factors for CVD [2]. Hyperlipidemia encompasses disorders <lb/>of lipoproteins, including elevations of total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/>1 / 23 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Li C, Spencer G, Husain MJ, Nugent R, <lb/>Auzenne D, Kostova D, et al. (2024) Barriers to <lb/>accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia in <lb/>low-and middle-income countries. PLOS Glob <lb/>Public Health 4(2): e0002905. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 <lb/>Editor: Julia Robinson, PLOS: Public Library of <lb/>Science, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: March 8, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 22, 2024 <lb/>Published: February 12, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: This is an open access article, free of all <lb/>copyright, and may be freely reproduced, <lb/>distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or <lb/>otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. <lb/>The work is made available under the Creative <lb/>Commons CC0 public domain dedication. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All data and related <lb/>metadata underlying the findings reported in a <lb/>submitted manuscript are provided as part of the <lb/>submitted article. <lb/>Funding: Funding for this project was provided by <lb/>the CDC Foundation through support from Amgen. <lb/>The funders had no role in study design, data <lb/>collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>(LDL-C), non-high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (non-HDL-C), and triglycerides, as well as <lb/>low HDL cholesterol. <lb/>Based on the global estimates from the Noncommunicable Disease Risk Factor Collabora-<lb/>tion (NCD-RisC), age-standardized mean non-HDL cholesterol concentration increased in <lb/>LMICs, particularly in East and South-East Asia and sub-Saharan Africa and Melanesia, <lb/>whereas it decreased substantially in high-income western regions and central and eastern <lb/>Europe from 1980 to 2018 [3]. Data from the Global Burden of Disease (GBD) Study 2019 sug-<lb/>gest that a total of 3.78 million deaths from ischemic heart disease (IHD) worldwide could be <lb/>attributable to high LDL-C concentrations, accounting for 44.3% of IHD deaths. A total of <lb/>0.61 million deaths from ischemic stroke could be attributable to high LDL-C levels, account-<lb/>ing for 22.4% of ischemic stroke deaths [4]. The age-standardized death rates for IHD and <lb/>ischemic stroke attributable to high LDL-C levels have reduced by about 35% from 1990 to <lb/>2019 globally. These rates have decreased in most high-income countries, however, the rates <lb/>did not change in many Asian and Africa countries or even significantly increased in Central <lb/>Asia and East Asia. <lb/>Statins, inhibitors of HMG-CoA reductase, and the rate-limiting enzyme of cholesterol bio-<lb/>synthesis, have been clinically used as first line agents to reduce LDL-C [5]. Statins are the only <lb/>lipid-modifying medication on the World Health Organization (WHO) Model List of Essential <lb/>Medicines. Statins are the leading recommended treatment globally and make up most lipid-<lb/>modifying medicines currently in use [6,7]. Compared to the high-income countries [8-10], <lb/>the prevalence of statin uses among eligible people for the treatment of dyslipidemia or the sec-<lb/>ondary prevention of cardiovascular diseases in the LMICs [11,12] remains low. <lb/>The WHO defines access as &quot;having medicines continuously available and affordable at <lb/>public or private health facilities or medicine outlets that are within one hour&apos;s walk from the <lb/>homes of the population&quot; [13]. Despite the high burden of hyperlipidemia and the effective-<lb/>ness of treatment, evidence suggests that the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines can be <lb/>extremely low in many LMIC contexts [14]. In LMICs, several characteristics could impede <lb/>access to statins, including high prices, lack of coverage in health benefit packages, and low <lb/>availability in pharmacies or other healthcare facilities. The aim of this study was to identify <lb/>common barriers to the accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia in LMICs. By reviewing <lb/>international databases and peer-reviewed literature as well as conducting key informant inter-<lb/>views, this study describes conditions in a range of LMICs and the status of access to medicines <lb/>for hyperlipidemia by region and income levels. <lb/>Methods <lb/>In this study, we used a multimethod approach to review, collect and analyze data from various <lb/>sources including international databases, literature review of published articles, and key infor-<lb/>mant interviews. <lb/>International database sources <lb/>Three data sources that were reviewed and analyzed included Health Action International <lb/>(HAI), Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA), and Management Sciences for <lb/>Health (MSH). <lb/>Health Action International (HAI). The HAI Database of Medicine Prices, Availability, <lb/>Affordability, and Price Components was created in collaboration with WHO in 2001 in order <lb/>to develop a reliable methodology for collecting and analyzing medicine prices, availability, <lb/>and affordability across different sectors and regions and to publish those data in a publicly <lb/>available website to improve transparency and advocate for appropriate national policies [15]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>The database contains availability, price, and affordability data for both generic and originator <lb/>drugs, as well as for both private and public medicine outlets (i.e., pharmacy, clinic, or other <lb/>health facility). Availability of individual medicines is defined as &quot;the percentage of medicine <lb/>outlets in which the medicine was found on the day of data collection&quot;. Simvastatin is one of <lb/>14 drugs included in the HAI/WHO global list of medicines survey template, though therapeu-<lb/>tically equivalent medicines may be added if they are widely used, and other types of statins <lb/>are reported in the database. <lb/>The HAI database reports the median unit price of medicines, which represents the final <lb/>dispensed price paid for a medicine, whether it be purchased by a patient, government, or <lb/>insurance provider. This price includes any value-added tax, goods, and services tax, or dis-<lb/>pensing fees but does not include any drug registration fees, patient fees for service, co-pay-<lb/>ments, informal charges, or discounts and rebates. Affordability is defined as the number of <lb/>days&apos; wages of the lowest-paid unskilled national government employee required to purchase a <lb/>month&apos;s supply of statin therapy (30 tablets). According to HAI standards, medicines are usu-<lb/>ally considered affordable if they cost one day&apos;s wages or less for an entire course of treatment <lb/>for an acute condition or for a 30-day supply for a chronic condition. <lb/>Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA). The SARA is a health facility <lb/>survey tool created by WHO to assess and monitor the service availability and readiness of the <lb/>health sector and to create evidence to assist in the planning and management of health sys-<lb/>tems. The SARA methodology includes surveying at least 150 public and private facilities and <lb/>is designed to generate a set of tracer indicators of health system service availability and readi-<lb/>ness, including the availability of 14 medicines from the WHO Essential Medicines List (EML) <lb/>[16]. <lb/>Management Sciences for Health (MSH). The International Medical Products Price <lb/>Guide has been published by the MSH since 1986 and in collaboration with WHO since 2000 <lb/>and is meant to contribute to equitable access to health products and essential medicines by <lb/>making price information more widely available in order to improve procurement for the low-<lb/>est possible prices [17]. The guide includes prices from suppliers (including international aid <lb/>organizations and procurement agencies that maintain a warehouse and supply items directly <lb/>to customers) and buyers (usually government agencies). <lb/>The three international data sources (i.e., HAI data, SARA data, and MSH guide) are pub-<lb/>licly accessible. Country income level in 2017 was based on World Bank data [18]. Health <lb/>expenditure as a percent of GDP and health expenditure per capita data were obtained from <lb/>the WHO Global Health Expenditure Database [19]. Disease burden (all cause mortality and <lb/>DALYs) attributed to high LDL-C were obtained from the Global Burden of Disease Study <lb/>2017 [20]. <lb/>The clinical practice and experience of countries from literature reviews <lb/>To identify peer-reviewed literature assessing the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines in <lb/>LMIC contexts, a literature search of the PubMed database was conducted in January 2020 <lb/>and updated in June 2022. The search was limited to publications in English, and that had <lb/>been published from January 1, 2010, through May 31, 2022. A second search was conducted <lb/>with several countries from Latin America, Africa, South Asia, and East Asia that were selected <lb/>for their large populations and the likelihood of having data available. Google and Google <lb/>Scholar searches were conducted to identify grey literature and online databases containing <lb/>information on the availability, accessibility, or affordability of hyperlipidemia medicines. A <lb/>snowball technique of searching the reference lists of retrieved included studies was used to <lb/>identify additional relevant studies. The PubMed search strategy and terms are available in <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>S1 and S2 Tables. The Endnote 21 reference management tool (https://endnote.com/? <lb/>language=en) and Covidence systematic review management tool (https://www.covidence. <lb/>org/) were used for the title and abstract screening, full text review, and data extraction of <lb/>included studies. Each study was assessed independently by two researchers. <lb/>Key informant interviews <lb/>To supplement limited data availability and inform barriers to access in LMIC contexts, inter-<lb/>views were conducted with key stakeholders, including representatives from the pharmaceuti-<lb/>cal industry, nongovernmental organizations (NGOs), multilateral organizations, and <lb/>academia, in February and March 2020. The interview was designed by RTI, and the initial list <lb/>of experts invited for interviews was developed collaboratively by RTI, CDC, and CDC Foun-<lb/>dation. In addition, experts from the Ministries of Health or other relevant government agen-<lb/>cies from five LMICs were also invited for their specialized knowledge of accessibility issues <lb/>for hyperlipidemia medicines. <lb/>The interviewees were asked a series of standard questions on factors that impact demand <lb/>for lipid-modifying medicines from the patient perspective, features of the market that act as <lb/>barriers to access, systematic features of LMIC markets that contribute to limited accessibility, <lb/>ways to mitigate barriers to accessibility, and about initiatives that have been successful in <lb/>improving access to lipid-modifying medicines. <lb/>Data summarization and analysis <lb/>Microsoft 365 Excel (https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365) was used to summa-<lb/>rize, merge, and analyze data. Median availability and mean affordability of statins were calcu-<lb/>lated by WHO region and WB income levels. <lb/>Results <lb/>Availability of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/>The HAI database contains availability data for any statin across 46 countries representing <lb/>each WHO region and income level (Table 1). The overall median availability of statins for <lb/>hyperlipidemia among included countries was 0% and 5.4% for originators and generics in <lb/>public facilities, and 13.3% and 35.9% in private facilities, respectively. <lb/>Statin availability was lowest in Africa and South-East Asia, with no availability of statins in <lb/>public facilities (Table 1). Private facilities generally had higher availability. The lowest avail-<lb/>ability was in originator statins in public facilities, except for in Western Pacific, where the <lb/>higher availability of originator statins in public facilities may be driven by China. <lb/>There appeared to be a clear and positive relationship between country income level and <lb/>availability (Table 1). Additionally, generic statins were more available than originator statins <lb/>in both public and private facilities in countries of all income levels. The highest level of avail-<lb/>ability was found for generic statins in private facilities, with this gap being more pronounced <lb/>in upper-middle-income countries. HAI data show greater availability of statins in higher-<lb/>income countries. The detailed availability data by country from the HAI database can be <lb/>found in S3 Table. <lb/>Of the 15 countries with SARA reports available on the WHO website, 10 reported the over-<lb/>all level of availability of statins in healthcare facilities. These countries are all in sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa dated from 2010 to 2016 and ranged from 0% in Burkina Faso to 5% in Sierra Leone <lb/>and Zambia [21] (Table 2). In the MSH guide, the lowest price was reported by a buyer for 20 <lb/>mg lovastatin at less than half a cent per pill, while the most expensive price was reported by a <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>buyer for 40 mg simvastatin for $0.20 (Table 3) [17]. At least one type or up to seven types of <lb/>statins were listed in the EML among 11 out of 14 countries identified (Table 4). The most <lb/>common types of statins were atorvastatin and simvastatin, followed by fluvastatin, prava-<lb/>statin, and rosuvastatin. Other types of statins included lovastatin, ezetimibe, and ezetimibe-<lb/>simvastatin combination. <lb/>The literature search assessing the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines in LMIC con-<lb/>texts yielded 1,287 articles, of which 112 were selected for full-text review, and 22 studies that <lb/>contained accessibility data were included in the review (Fig 1). Among included studies, two <lb/>large multi-country epidemiological studies, the Africa Middle East Cardiovascular <lb/>Table 1. Median availability and mean affordability of statins by region and income levels, HAI database, 2001-2015. <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>Availability, %, median <lb/>Affordability, number of days&apos; wage*, mean <lb/>Public facility <lb/>Private facility <lb/>Public facility <lb/>Private facility <lb/>Num of Countries Originator Generic Originator Generic Num of Countries Originator Generic Originator Generic <lb/>Overall <lb/>46 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>5.4% <lb/>13.3% <lb/>35.9% <lb/>26 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>WHO Region <lb/>Africa <lb/>10 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>3.4% <lb/>11.1% <lb/>3 <lb/>- † <lb/>-<lb/>11.4 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>Americas <lb/>10 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>3.3% <lb/>20.0% <lb/>58.6% <lb/>6 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>11.2 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>East Mediterranean <lb/>11 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>45.5% <lb/>30.2% <lb/>86.1% <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>1.4 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Europe <lb/>6 <lb/>17.1% <lb/>75.2% <lb/>35.7% <lb/>88.6% <lb/>5 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>South-East Asia <lb/>3 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>1.6% <lb/>20.0% <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>Western Pacific <lb/>6 <lb/>13.4% <lb/>10.6% <lb/>10.0% <lb/>33.3% <lb/>3 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>WB Income Level <lb/>Low <lb/>9 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>15.2% <lb/>5 <lb/>-<lb/>5.8 <lb/>-<lb/>3.8 <lb/>Lower middle <lb/>17 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>22.2% <lb/>10 <lb/>5.7 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>Upper middle <lb/>16 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>11.1% <lb/>33.3% <lb/>68.8% <lb/>9 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>High <lb/>4 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>47.3% <lb/>57.2% <lb/>80.9% <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>5.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>Note <lb/>* Affordability is defined as the number of days wages of the lowest-paid unskilled national government employee required to purchase a month supply of statin therapy <lb/>(30 tablets). <lb/> †Data unavailable. <lb/>WHO = World Health Organization; WB = World Bank. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.t001 <lb/>Table 2. Statin availability in public and private health facilities, SARA reports, 2010-2016. <lb/>Country <lb/>WB income classification <lb/>Statin availability (%) <lb/>Year of SARA report <lb/>Burkina Faso <lb/>Low <lb/>0% <lb/>2014 <lb/>Dem. Rep. of Congo <lb/>Low <lb/>2% <lb/>2014 <lb/>Togo <lb/>Low <lb/>2% <lb/>2012 <lb/>Benin <lb/>Low <lb/>3% <lb/>2015 <lb/>Mauritania <lb/>Lower middle <lb/>3% <lb/>2016 <lb/>Niger <lb/>Low <lb/>3% <lb/>2015 <lb/>Tanzania <lb/>Low <lb/>3% <lb/>2012 <lb/>Uganda <lb/>Low <lb/>3% <lb/>2013 <lb/>Sierra Leone <lb/>Low <lb/>5% <lb/>2012 <lb/>Zambia <lb/>Lower middle <lb/>5% <lb/>2010 <lb/>Note: SARA = Service availability and readiness assessment; WB = World Bank. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Epidemiological (ACE) Study [22] and the Prospective Urban Rural Epidemiological (PURE) <lb/>Study [23], were reviewed. <lb/>Data from the literature review showed the limited availability of statins in clinical practice <lb/>in LMICs. In Cameroon, Atorvastatin and simvastatin were available in 50% of private com-<lb/>munity outlets and were more available at urban outlets than semi-urban outlets [24]. A survey <lb/>conducted in Ghana in 2013 showed that statins were unavailable at all nine Community-<lb/>based Health Planning Services (CHPS, lowest level of care in Ghana) or the nine health cen-<lb/>ters surveyed [25]. Statins were available in one of the three district hospitals surveyed and in <lb/>both of the two regional hospitals surveyed. In Kenya, qualitative research among providers at <lb/>the Kenyatta National Hospital in Nairobi indicated that statins were available and, that stock-<lb/>outs were rare, but that cost represents a major barrier to long term adherence [26]. A survey <lb/>conducted in Nyandarua County, Kenya, in 2018 found that simvastatin was available in only <lb/>10 out of 47 primary healthcare facilities, or 21% [27]. In Delta State of Nigeria, 150 commu-<lb/>nity pharmacists were surveyed about statin use. While the majority of pharmacists correctly <lb/>identified statins as the first line treatment for high cholesterol, less than half were able to iden-<lb/>tify the most common side effect of statin therapy [28]. A review of prescriptions in patients <lb/>admitted at a tertiary hospital in southwestern Nigeria between January 2012 and August 2013 <lb/>found that 59 patients (out of 1,280) received a total of 62 statin prescriptions-two patients <lb/>were prescribed more than one statin-and only 29.0% of these statins were prescribed by their <lb/>generic name [29]. In South Africa, although the overall percentage of facilities that had at <lb/>least one of atorvastatin, simvastatin, or rosuvastatin in stock on the day of the survey was high <lb/>(93.0%), qualitative research by the investigators revealed that there was widespread belief in <lb/>the community that stockouts were common [30]. <lb/>Bangladesh has a publicly funded healthcare system in which consultations were provided <lb/>at low cost and medicines were free of charge to patients, however, about half of the physicians <lb/>employed in the public district and local hospitals were not satisfied with the availability of <lb/>medicines at their facilities, leading to many patients purchasing medicines out-of-pocket [31]. <lb/>In India, analysis of prescription data collected by Intercontinental Medical Statistics (IMS) <lb/>Health found that, as of January 2010, there were 259 unique statin products available from 65 <lb/>manufacturers, with atorvastatin accounting for 81.1% of the products and 84.8% of statin <lb/>sales [32]. In Indonesia, only 1.47% were on statin treatment among those at high CVD risk <lb/>(2.01% in urban areas, 0.91% in semi-urban areas, and 0.94% in rural areas) [33]. <lb/>In the Philippines, statins were more available at private facilities (ranging from 23.8% to <lb/>83.3%) than at public facilities (ranging from 0.0% to 61.1%) [34]. In Vietnam, a survey done <lb/>Table 3. MSH international medical products price guide for prices (US $) on lipid-lowering agents, 2015. <lb/>Supplier <lb/>Buyer <lb/>Medicine <lb/>Defined daily dose Number of prices <lb/>High/low price <lb/>ratio <lb/>Median price, US <lb/>$ <lb/>Number of prices <lb/>High/low price <lb/>ratio <lb/>Median price, US <lb/>$ <lb/>Atorvastatin 10 mg <lb/>20 mg <lb/>2 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>4 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Atorvastatin 20 mg <lb/>20 mg <lb/>3 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>3 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>Atorvastatin 40 mg <lb/>20 mg <lb/>NA <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Gemfibrozil 600 <lb/>mg <lb/>20 mg <lb/>NA <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Lovastatin 20 mg <lb/>45 mg <lb/>NA <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.01 <lb/>Simvastatin 10 mg <lb/>30 mg <lb/>NA <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.01 <lb/>Simvastatin 20 mg <lb/>30 mg <lb/>2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.05 <lb/>Simvastatin 40 mg <lb/>30 mg <lb/>NA <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.20 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.t003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>in Phunhuan district between 2009 and 2011 found that simvastatin or lovastatin was available <lb/>in seven of 15 primary care facilities [35]. A survey conducted in 2010 in Dong Hy district <lb/>found that statins were not available at any of the 18 CHCs included in the study [36]. How-<lb/>ever, a survey of Commune Health Center (CHC) capacity conducted in 2017 in Hai Dong <lb/>province found that none of the five rural CHCs had a statin available, and only one of the five <lb/>urban CHCs had a statin available [37]. Although statins may be available at some CHCs, pub-<lb/>lic health insurance did not cover them at this level of care, so patients must travel to district-<lb/>level hospitals in order to have their insurance cover a statin prescription [38]. <lb/>Fig 1. PRISMA flow diagram. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4. Accessibility to medicines of hyperlipidemia and country profiles, 2017. <lb/>Region <lb/>Country <lb/>(Ref #) <lb/>World <lb/>Bank <lb/>income <lb/>level <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>% of GDP <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>per capita US <lb/>dollars <lb/>Death <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>death) <lb/>DALYs <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>DALYs) <lb/>Guideline for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>management <lb/>Essential <lb/>Medicines <lb/>List (EML) <lb/>Availability of <lb/>statins in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Median cost <lb/>of statins, per <lb/>month or <lb/>30-day supply, <lb/>or per unit <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>obtaining <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>medicines <lb/>Africa <lb/>Cameroon <lb/>[14] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>3.5% <lb/>$49.8 <lb/>2147 (1.0%) 61015 (0.4%) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>• Atorvastatin <lb/>available in 20% <lb/>of private <lb/>community <lb/>outlets, 5.9% of <lb/>urban outlets, <lb/>and 4% of semi-<lb/>urban outlets <lb/>• Simvastatin <lb/>available in 50% <lb/>of private <lb/>community <lb/>outlets, 17.6% of <lb/>urban outlets, <lb/>and 8% of semi-<lb/>urban outlets. <lb/>• Atorvastatin <lb/>cost $13.9 for <lb/>a 30-day <lb/>supply, equal <lb/>to 6.9 days <lb/>wage <lb/>• Simvastatin <lb/>cost $26.9 for <lb/>a 30-day <lb/>supply, equal <lb/>to 13.4 days&apos; <lb/>wage <lb/>• Statin <lb/>medications were <lb/>largely purchased <lb/>by out-of-pocket <lb/>payments due to <lb/>the absence of <lb/>universal health <lb/>coverage and few <lb/>health insurance <lb/>schemes <lb/>Ghana <lb/>[15] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>3.4% <lb/>$68.0 <lb/>7972 (3.8%) 212379 <lb/>(1.7%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Fluvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Rosuvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• Statins were <lb/>found in none of <lb/>the nine <lb/>community-<lb/>based health <lb/>planning <lb/>services surveyed <lb/>(2013) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Kenya <lb/>[16-18,38] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>4.1% <lb/>$65.1 <lb/>4473 (1.5%) 129537 <lb/>(0.7%) <lb/>• Strongly <lb/>recommends <lb/>statin treatment <lb/>for those with a <lb/>CVD risk greater <lb/>than 20% or with <lb/>known CVD <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>statin treatment <lb/>be considered for <lb/>those with <lb/>moderate risk <lb/>(between 10% and <lb/>20%) <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Simvastatin <lb/>was available in <lb/>only 10, or 21% <lb/>of the facilities <lb/>• $1 per <lb/>treatment per <lb/>month <lb/>• Cost represented <lb/>a major barrier to <lb/>long term <lb/>adherence <lb/>• County-level <lb/>variation in <lb/>medicine <lb/>procurement and <lb/>distribution <lb/>• Private facility <lb/>outlets were not <lb/>included in the <lb/>program <lb/>• Contradictions <lb/>between <lb/>treatment <lb/>guidelines and the <lb/>EML <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Region <lb/>Country <lb/>(Ref #) <lb/>World <lb/>Bank <lb/>income <lb/>level <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>% of GDP <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>per capita US <lb/>dollars <lb/>Death <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>death) <lb/>DALYs <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>DALYs) <lb/>Guideline for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>management <lb/>Essential <lb/>Medicines <lb/>List (EML) <lb/>Availability of <lb/>statins in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Median cost <lb/>of statins, per <lb/>month or <lb/>30-day supply, <lb/>or per unit <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>obtaining <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>medicines <lb/>Nigeria <lb/>[19,20] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>3.8% <lb/>$73.9 <lb/>28527 (1.7%) 732007 <lb/>(0.6%) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>• Generics <lb/>$8.90 per <lb/>month <lb/>• Originator <lb/>brands $17.00 <lb/>per month <lb/>• Under-dosing <lb/>South <lb/>Africa <lb/>[21,36,39] <lb/>Upper <lb/>middle <lb/>8.7% <lb/>$534.4 <lb/>15653 (2.8%) 374022 <lb/>(1.3%) <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>statin treatment <lb/>be considered for <lb/>patients with low <lb/>and moderate <lb/>CVD risk <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>immediately <lb/>initiated for high-<lb/>risk patients with <lb/>high cholesterol <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Pravastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Rosuvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• Overall, 93% of <lb/>facilities had a <lb/>statin in stock <lb/>• $3.6 per <lb/>month (58 <lb/>South African <lb/>Rand; 9.7% of <lb/>a household&apos;s <lb/>capacity-to-<lb/>pay) <lb/>• Long wait times <lb/>deterring patients <lb/>from returning <lb/>for cholesterol <lb/>monitoring <lb/>Eastern <lb/>Mediterranean <lb/>Iran <lb/>[22] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>8.4% <lb/>$481.6 <lb/>49741 <lb/>(13.0%) <lb/>1141211 <lb/>(5.8%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Rosuvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• Lovastatin <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>South-East <lb/>Asia <lb/>Bangladesh <lb/>[23,36] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>2.4% <lb/>$37.4 <lb/>44847 (5.4%) 1211031 <lb/>(2.8%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>■ Consultations <lb/>are provided at <lb/>low cost and <lb/>medicines are <lb/>free of charge to <lb/>patients. <lb/>■ Many patients <lb/>purchasing <lb/>medicines out-<lb/>of-pocket. <lb/>• $5.2 per <lb/>month (450 <lb/>Bangladeshi <lb/>Taka, BDT, <lb/>15.8% of a <lb/>household&apos;s <lb/>capacity-to-<lb/>pay) <lb/>India <lb/>[24,36,40] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>2.9% <lb/>$57.6 <lb/>592129 <lb/>(6.5%) <lb/>16914661 <lb/>(3.6%) <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>statins as the first <lb/>line of treatment <lb/>for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>• Add fibrates if <lb/>targeted levels are <lb/>not met on the <lb/>maximum <lb/>tolerated dose of <lb/>statins <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• $3.8 per <lb/>month (296 <lb/>Indian Rupee, <lb/>INR, 16.6% of <lb/>a household&apos;s <lb/>capacity-to-<lb/>pay <lb/>• Low per capita <lb/>prescribing rates <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Region <lb/>Country <lb/>(Ref #) <lb/>World <lb/>Bank <lb/>income <lb/>level <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>% of GDP <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>per capita US <lb/>dollars <lb/>Death <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>death) <lb/>DALYs <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>DALYs) <lb/>Guideline for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>management <lb/>Essential <lb/>Medicines <lb/>List (EML) <lb/>Availability of <lb/>statins in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Median cost <lb/>of statins, per <lb/>month or <lb/>30-day supply, <lb/>or per unit <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>obtaining <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>medicines <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>[25,41] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>2.9% <lb/>$111.4 <lb/>107383 <lb/>(6.4%) <lb/>3151277 <lb/>(4.0%) <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>statin treatment <lb/>for type 2 diabetes <lb/>patients who are <lb/>over 40 years of <lb/>age or at high <lb/>CVD risk <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Americas <lb/>Brazil <lb/>[26,36,42] <lb/>Upper <lb/>middle <lb/>9.5% <lb/>$940.4 <lb/>95510 (7.0%) 2291836 <lb/>(3.5%) <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>statin treatment as <lb/>the first line <lb/>therapy <lb/>• Add ezetimibe <lb/>when statin <lb/>therapy alone is <lb/>unable to achieve <lb/>LDL cholesterol <lb/>goals <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Fluvastatin <lb/>• Lovastatin <lb/>• Pravastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• 68.1% of statin <lb/>users reported <lb/>accessing their <lb/>medication at an <lb/>SUS pharmacy <lb/>free of charge, <lb/>16.7% from a <lb/>private <lb/>pharmacy, 13.8% <lb/>from pharmacy <lb/>with a co-<lb/>payment, and 1.5 <lb/>percent from <lb/>other sources. <lb/>• $14.2 per <lb/>month (73 <lb/>Brazilian Real, <lb/>BRL, 3.9% of a <lb/>household&apos;s <lb/>capacity-to-<lb/>pay) <lb/>• Poor adherence <lb/>Mexico <lb/>[28] <lb/>Upper <lb/>middle <lb/>5.5% <lb/>$506.9 <lb/>50027 (7.1%) 1109947 <lb/>(3.3%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Fluvastatin <lb/>• Pravastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Rosuvastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• Ezetimibe <lb/>• Ezetimibe-<lb/>simvastatin <lb/>combination <lb/>• 23.0% of <lb/>patients <lb/>diagnosed with <lb/>dyslipidemia <lb/>have initiated <lb/>treatment. <lb/>• $62.0 per <lb/>month (792 <lb/>Mexican <lb/>Pesos) <lb/>• Variability <lb/>between <lb/>healthcare <lb/>systems <lb/>• Failure to <lb/>calculate low and <lb/>high <lb/>cardiovascular <lb/>risk, patients with <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>were treated in <lb/>the same way <lb/>• Length of <lb/>treatment was <lb/>inadequate <lb/>• High-intensity <lb/>statin therapy was <lb/>unavailable <lb/>Western <lb/>Pacific <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Region <lb/>Country <lb/>(Ref <lb/>World <lb/>Bank <lb/>income <lb/>level <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>% of GDP <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>per capita US <lb/>dollars <lb/>Death <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>death) <lb/>DALYs <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>DALYs) <lb/>Guideline for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>management <lb/>Essential <lb/>Medicines <lb/>List (EML) <lb/>Availability of <lb/>statins in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Median cost <lb/>of statins, per <lb/>month or <lb/>30-day supply, <lb/>or per unit <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>obtaining <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>medicines <lb/>China <lb/>[29,36,43] <lb/>Upper <lb/>middle <lb/>5.1% <lb/>$437.3 <lb/>872065 <lb/>(8.5%) <lb/>19255113 <lb/>(5.1%) <lb/>• Recommends <lb/>medium-intensity <lb/>statins for initial <lb/>treatment, then <lb/>adjusting dose <lb/>according to <lb/>individual efficacy <lb/>and tolerance, <lb/>adding ezetimibe <lb/>if necessary <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Lovastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>NA <lb/>• $3.7 per <lb/>month (25 <lb/>Chinese Yuan, <lb/>RMB, 2.4% of <lb/>household <lb/>capacity-to-<lb/>pay) <lb/>• Low utilization <lb/>of generics <lb/>• Tendency of <lb/>prescribing <lb/>originators <lb/>Philippines <lb/>[30] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>4.0% <lb/>$123.7 <lb/>49747 (7.8%) 1445544 <lb/>(4.4%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>• Pravastatin <lb/>• <lb/>Simvastatin <lb/>• Atorvastatin <lb/>was available in <lb/>38.9% of public <lb/>facilities and <lb/>83.3% of private <lb/>facilities <lb/>• Pravastatin was <lb/>available in 0% <lb/>of public <lb/>facilities and <lb/>23.8% of private <lb/>facilities <lb/>• Rosuvastatin <lb/>was available in <lb/>27.8% of public <lb/>facilities and <lb/>64.3% of private <lb/>facilities <lb/>• Simvastatin <lb/>was available in <lb/>61.1% of public <lb/>facilities and <lb/>81% of private <lb/>facilities <lb/>• Atorvastatin <lb/>in private <lb/>facilities: <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $0.68; in <lb/>public facility <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $0.19 <lb/>• Pravastatin <lb/>in private <lb/>facility <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $0.46 <lb/>• Rosuvastatin <lb/>in private <lb/>facilities: <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $1.53; in <lb/>in public <lb/>facility <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $ 0.36 <lb/>• Simvastatin <lb/>in private <lb/>facilities: <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $0.60; in <lb/>public facility <lb/>median unit <lb/>price: $0.08 <lb/>• Low statin <lb/>medication <lb/>availability in the <lb/>public facility <lb/>• Patients <lb/>purchased their <lb/>medicines from <lb/>private <lb/>pharmacies <lb/>• Increasing the <lb/>patient&apos;s out-of-<lb/>pocket spending <lb/>on drugs <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>4. (Continued) <lb/>Region <lb/>Country <lb/>(Ref #) <lb/>World <lb/>Bank <lb/>income <lb/>level <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>% of GDP <lb/>Health <lb/>expenditure, <lb/>per capita US <lb/>dollars <lb/>Death <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>death) <lb/>DALYs <lb/>attributable <lb/>to high LDL <lb/>(% of total <lb/>DALYs) <lb/>Guideline for <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>management <lb/>Essential <lb/>Medicines <lb/>List (EML) <lb/>Availability of <lb/>statins in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Median cost <lb/>of statins, per <lb/>month or <lb/>30-day supply, <lb/>or per unit <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>obtaining <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>medicines <lb/>Vietnam <lb/>[31-34] <lb/>Lower <lb/>middle <lb/>4.7% <lb/>$140.1 <lb/>38445 (6.2%) 876615 <lb/>(3.4%) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>• None of the <lb/>five rural CHCs <lb/>surveyed had a <lb/>statin available <lb/>in 2010 <lb/>• Only one of the <lb/>five urban CHCs <lb/>had a statin <lb/>available <lb/>Simvastatin or <lb/>lovastatin was <lb/>available in <lb/>seven of 15 <lb/>primary care <lb/>facilities (46.7%) <lb/>NA <lb/>• Public health <lb/>insurance did not <lb/>cover statins at <lb/>CHCs <lb/>• Patients must <lb/>travel to district <lb/>level hospitals in <lb/>order to have <lb/>their insurance <lb/>cover a statin <lb/>prescription <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.t004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>In Brazil, 68.1% of statin users accessing their medication at an Sistema U ´nico de <lb/>Sau ´de (SUS, Brazil&apos;s publicly funded healthcare system) pharmacy free of charge, 16.7% from a <lb/>private pharmacy, 13.8% from the pharmacy in the Popular Pharmacy Program with a co-pay-<lb/>ment, and 1.5% from other sources [39]. A survey conducted between July 2014 and May 2015 <lb/>of patients aged 18 years and older from 1,305 primary healthcare centers in 272 cities found <lb/>that the prevalence of statin use was 9.3%. In Mexico, the CARMELA study, published in 2010, <lb/>showed that the prevalence of dyslipidemia in Mexico City was 50.1% among adults aged 25 to <lb/>64 years but that only 21.7% of those who were prescribed a lipid-modifying medication were <lb/>currently taking that medication [40]. <lb/>Affordability and price of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/>Where available, originator statins required at least twice as many days&apos; wages as the lowest <lb/>cost generic statins in Africa, the Americas, Eastern Mediterranean, South-East Asia, and <lb/>Western Pacific, while there is a smaller affordability gap in Europe. (Table 1). The median <lb/>cost for statin medications per month ranged from a low of $1 in Kenya to a high of $62 in <lb/>Mexico. The majority of countries had a median monthly cost between $3.6 and $17.0. On <lb/>average, statins appeared to be unaffordable by region using the HAI standard. Statins were <lb/>less affordable in lower-income countries, with both originators and generics costing around 6 <lb/>days&apos; wages on average (Table 1). The full set of price and affordability data from the HAI <lb/>database can be found in S4 Table. <lb/>The cost of statin treatment accounted for less than 10% of a household&apos;s capacity-to-pay in <lb/>China (2.4%), Brazil (3.9%), and South Africa (9.7%) [23]. In contrast, this cost accounts for <lb/>greater than 15% of a household&apos;s capacity-to-pay in Bangladesh (15.8%) and India (16.6%) <lb/>(Table 4). Originator statins were less affordable than generics in countries at any income-level. <lb/>Guidelines for hyperlipidemia management <lb/>Based on the literature review, six out of 14 countries had guidelines and recommendations on <lb/>statin treatment (Table 4). The Kenya National Guidelines for Cardiovascular Diseases Man-<lb/>agement strongly recommends statin treatment for those with a CVD risk greater than 20% or <lb/>with known CVD, and recommends statin treatment be considered for those with moderate <lb/>risk (between 10% and 20%) who do not reach treatment goals with lifestyle management [41]. <lb/>The South African dyslipidemia guideline consensus statement recommends statin therapy be <lb/>considered for patients with low and moderate cardiovascular risk when lifestyle interventions <lb/>do not control high LDL cholesterol and be immediately initiated for high-risk patients with <lb/>high cholesterol [42]. Indian guidelines recommend statins as the first line of treatment for <lb/>hyperlipidemia and recommend adding fibrates if targeted levels are not met on the maximum <lb/>tolerated dose of statins [43]. Indonesia&apos;s treatment guidelines for type 2 diabetes indicate <lb/>statin treatment for those over 40 years of age or at high CVD risk [44]. Brazil&apos;s Guidelines on <lb/>Cardiovascular Prevention recommend statin treatment as the first line of therapy and recom-<lb/>mends the addition of ezetimibe when statin therapy alone is unable to achieve LDL choles-<lb/>terol goals [45]. China&apos;s hyperlipidemia treatment guidelines recommend medium-intensity <lb/>statins for initial treatment, then adjusted according to individual efficacy and tolerance, add-<lb/>ing ezetimibe if necessary [46]. <lb/>Barriers to the accessibility of lipid-modifying medications in clinical <lb/>practice <lb/>Kenya was the first country to receive assistance through the Novartis Access program, which <lb/>made available for purchase a portfolio of NCD medicines, including simvastatin, for $1 per <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 23 <lb/></page>
	<!-- missing first -->
	<body>per month by the Mission for Essential Drugs and Supplies (MEDS)-a main distrib-<lb/>utor to Kenyan public and non-profit health facilities [47]. A cluster-randomized controlled <lb/>trial of the program that included 127 health facilities in eight counties showed that simvastatin <lb/>was found at three or fewer facilities at follow-up and was not available even at well-stocked <lb/>hospital pharmacies. In this study, barriers to the availability of simvastatin were identified, <lb/>including county-level variation in medicine procurement and distribution; $1 per treatment <lb/>per month still being above international median reference prices; many patients purchasing <lb/>medicines at private sector outlets which were not included in the program; and, contradic-<lb/>tions between treatment guidelines and the EML. In Nigeria, under-dosing (prescribed daily <lb/>dose compared to the defined daily dose) was observed in 56.0% of the statin prescriptions <lb/>[29]. <lb/>A baseline assessment of health service capacity that was conducted in South Africa in 2015 <lb/>to identify gaps in the continuum of care for cardiovascular diseases at 86 health facilities in <lb/>two districts identifies several barriers to obtaining hyperlipidemia medications. Only approxi-<lb/>mately half of health facilities had total cholesterol or LDL cholesterol tests, resulting in <lb/>patients needing to be referred to higher-level facilities for diagnosis [30]. An additional bar-<lb/>rier identified by both patients and providers was long wait times deterring patients from <lb/>returning for cholesterol monitoring. In India, per capita, prescribing rates among patients <lb/>remain 20 times lower than those in the United States and Canada [32]. <lb/>In China, despite the reduced price, there continued to be a low utilization of generics and a <lb/>tendency of prescribing originators. For example, in one of the hospital systems, prescribing <lb/>generic simvastatin-the lowest cost statin-accounted for 0.1% of statin prescriptions despite <lb/>being between 68.0% and 77.0% cheaper than the most frequently prescribed statin, originator <lb/>atorvastatin (30.7% of prescriptions), to which it was therapeutically similar [48]. In Vietnam, <lb/>public health insurance did not cover statins at the commune health centers, so patients must <lb/>travel to district-level hospitals in order to have their insurance cover a statin prescription [38]. <lb/>In Brazil, poor adherence was self-reported by 6.5% of statin users, with the most common <lb/>cause being a personal decision not to take medicine (30.7%), forgetting to take medicine <lb/>(24.1%), lack of access (23.5%), adverse events (10.6%), and other causes (11.2%) [39]. A <lb/>review of hyperlipidemia treatment in Mexico identified several barriers to better outcomes, <lb/>including the low proportion of the population who have ever had a lipid screen, variability <lb/>between healthcare systems (with many using random capillary cholesterol measurements <lb/>instead of the recommended fasting lipid profile), and a failure to calculate the cardiovascular <lb/>risk that results in low-and high-risk hyperlipidemia cases being treated in the same way [49]. <lb/>Additionally, the length of treatment is inadequate, and high-intensity statin therapy is <lb/>unavailable in most public healthcare systems. <lb/>The main barriers by domains and by the components of accessibility [14] as identified in <lb/>the key informant interviews are summarized in Table 5. Statins did not seem to be prioritized <lb/>in existing initiatives to improve access to hyperlipidemia medicines. No interviewee was able <lb/>to provide an example of an existing initiative that had a quantifiable impact specifically on the <lb/>accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia. Accessibility to hyperlipidemia medicines in <lb/>LMICs faced barriers in multiple dimensions of health systems, among providers, and among <lb/>patients. Though the barriers to accessibility provided by the interviewees were numerous and <lb/>complex, and statins had not been prioritized in past accessibility initiatives, there were ideas <lb/>on how to improve the situation moving forward. <lb/>When asked about ways to overcome these barriers and improve accessibility to medicines <lb/>for hyperlipidemia, the most frequent response related to the role of technology and digital <lb/>health applications. These tools could be used in many ways, including identifying patients at <lb/>high risk through social media using artificial intelligence and thereby reducing the need for <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 5. Key barriers to accessibility statins identified in key informant interviews. <lb/>Domain <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>component <lb/>Barrier <lb/>Leadership and <lb/>governance <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• Lipid-lowering drugs are not authorized at low levels of care or can <lb/>only be prescribed by specialists. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Newly formed national or supranational regulatory agencies in <lb/>LMICs may require dossiers for well-established drugs that increase <lb/>the cost and make economies of scale more difficult to accomplish. <lb/>Essential medicines <lb/>-<lb/>• Corruption during the medicine procurement process. <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• In many LMIC context, physicians prescribe statins at low doses to <lb/>avoid myalgia though this is not best practice. <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• Procurement patterns in LMICs often means that the medicines that <lb/>are available change frequently. This results in medicines of different <lb/>sizes, colors, doses, and side effects, which can affect adherence. <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• Issues with procurement and transportation can cause questions <lb/>about medicine reliability, due to medicines arriving without the <lb/>correct packaging or technical instructions, not having been stored <lb/>properly or for too long a time, or they may be counterfeit in the first <lb/>place. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• In remote settings, pharmacists may mark up prices knowing that <lb/>the patient does not have the opportunity to compare prices and will <lb/>not go elsewhere. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Trend of in-house physicians at pharmacies may cause conflicts of <lb/>interest. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Lipid-lowering drugs often only available in private pharmacies, <lb/>which are often more expensive. <lb/>-<lb/>• Research suggests that presence on a country&apos;s EML has an effect on <lb/>availability. Both national EMLs and treatment guidelines are often <lb/>quite outdated, and research suggests that presence on a country&apos;s <lb/>EML has an effect on availability. <lb/>Health financing <lb/>-<lb/>• Lipid profile tests needed to diagnose hyperlipidemia are often <lb/>prohibitively expensive. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Lipid-lowering drugs are unaffordable. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Factors such as being reimbursable, covered by the public facility, or <lb/>part of insurance schemes affect accessibility. If lipid-lowering <lb/>medicines are covered but the financing system is dysfunctional, that <lb/>will affect accessibility as well. <lb/>Health information <lb/>systems <lb/>-<lb/>• There is very poor data coming out of LMICs on NCDs and <lb/>hyperlipidemia medicine distribution and lipid levels are not being <lb/>input into District Health Information Software 2 (DHIS2). While <lb/>most lipid-lowering drugs utilized in LMICs are statins, which are <lb/>mostly generic, unlike the US and Europe, it is difficult to obtain <lb/>market authorization information about these drugs for LMICs. <lb/>Therefore, in LMIC contexts it is hard to know who is making statins, <lb/>where they are selling them, and what type of quality they are. <lb/>-<lb/>• There is a lack of information on how frequently statins go into <lb/>shortage. There does not seem to be evidence of a lack of access from a <lb/>manufacturing standpoint. <lb/>Human resources <lb/>-<lb/>• Lack of awareness among physicians that testing for lipid levels <lb/>should be a part of a package of services for those at risk of CVD, even <lb/>at high-level facilities. <lb/>-<lb/>• Little training in medical schools about how to communicate CVD <lb/>risk to patients <lb/>-<lb/>• Lack of lower-level healthcare workers capable of preforming the <lb/>necessary lab work to diagnose hyperlipidemia. <lb/>-<lb/>• Competition between different healthcare professions can inhibit <lb/>task sharing that might allow different cadres of health workers to <lb/>diagnose or treat hyperlipidemia. <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 23 <lb/></page>
	<!-- missing first -->
	<body>diagnostics and monitoring hyperlipidemia through wearable devices; training or <lb/>supplementing community health workers with eLearning apps; dispensing medicines <lb/>through mobile pharmacies; and providing hyperlipidemia information and referrals in local <lb/>languages. Concerns about digital technology use include the limited scope of many apps, <lb/>patient privacy, difficulty with regulation, and problems with uptake among older patients. <lb/>New lipid-modifying drugs or delivery methods, such as a drug that is injected twice a year, <lb/>could improve access and adherence. Also, strengthening the voice of patients through advo-<lb/>cacy groups that exist for other types of diseases could also increase demand. An especially <lb/>interesting proposal was to integrate solutions whereby the pharmaceutical company would <lb/>not only provide the medicine, but also support the diagnostic and treatment management <lb/>processes. An integrated provider could potentially relieve some of the burden of seeking care <lb/>from the patient. This could possibly be approached through the tendering process. <lb/>By combining the results from multiple data sources, the major barriers to accessibility of <lb/>medicines for hyperlipidemia in LMICs was summarized in Fig 2. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study examined the barriers to the accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia in <lb/>LMICs. We found some evidence of the poor accessibility of statins in selected countries based <lb/>on our literature review and cross-country analysis. The availability of medicines for hyperlip-<lb/>idemia based on the international databases including HAI data, SARA data, and MSH guide <lb/>was under 15% for originators and under 40% for generics and was predominant in private <lb/>facilities. The lowest statin availability was identified in Africa and South-East Asia. The most <lb/>common types of statins were atorvastatin and simvastatin, followed by fluvastatin, prava-<lb/>statin, and rosuvastatin. <lb/>Table 5. (Continued) <lb/>Domain <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>component <lb/>Barrier <lb/>-<lb/>• Lack of specialized physicians; patients can only see general <lb/>practitioners who do not have specialized knowledge for treating <lb/>hyperlipidemia <lb/>Service delivery <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• Hard for patients to receive adequate diagnostics, prescription, <lb/>monitoring, and follow-up due to poorly functioning health system. <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• The distance to the pharmacy is prohibitive. <lb/>Accessibility <lb/>• In remote settings, the only option for distribution is sometimes <lb/>private facilities which are difficult and more expensive to access for <lb/>multinational companies, in part due to limited infrastructure. <lb/>Availability <lb/>• Lipid-lowering drugs are not available due to stockouts or other <lb/>supply chain issues. <lb/>Patient <lb/>-<lb/>• Low demand for hyperlipidemia medicine from patients <lb/>(hyperlipidemia is asymptomatic) <lb/>-<lb/>• Side effects of hyperlipidemia medicines <lb/>-<lb/>• Poor understanding of cardiovascular risk, do not comprehend <lb/>10-year CVD risk profiles. <lb/>-<lb/>• Hyperlipidemia does not have as strong of an association with stroke <lb/>as hypertension, which incentivizes patients to adhere to hypertension <lb/>treatment <lb/>-<lb/>• Psychological aspect of having to take a drug for the rest of one&apos;s life. <lb/>-<lb/>• Difficult to monitor the progression of treatment due to requiring <lb/>blood draws. <lb/>Affordability <lb/>• Intrahousehold competition for resources <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.t005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>There was limited availability of statins clinical practice in LMICs. In Africa, statins were <lb/>unavailable at most community-based health or clinical centers and cost represents a major <lb/>barrier to long term adherence of statin use. In South-East Asia, statins were more available at <lb/>Fig 2. Major barriers to accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia in LMICs. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>private facilities than at public facilities. Statins were either unavailable or not covered by pub-<lb/>lic health insurance at community health centers so that the patients traveled to higher level <lb/>health facilities to obtain the medicines. Although statins were free of charge to patients in a <lb/>publicly funded healthcare system in some countries, however, the availability of statins at the <lb/>health facilities was unsatisfactory which resulted in many patients purchasing the medicines <lb/>out-of-pocket. In Americas, statins were also free of charge in publicly funded healthcare sys-<lb/>tem, however, the utilization of satins remained low. <lb/>High costs of originator satins were identified as a major barrier where generic statins were <lb/>unavailable. Originator statins at least doubled the price of generic statins in Africa, the Ameri-<lb/>cas, Eastern Mediterranean, South-East Asia, and Western Pacific. Statins appeared to be unaf-<lb/>fordable according to the HAI standard. The costs of statin treatment were even higher in <lb/>South-East Asia than Africa, Americas, and Western Pacific. <lb/>The main strength of this study included the use of a multimethod approach and multiple <lb/>data sources from international databases, a literature review of published country-specific <lb/>data, and key informant interviews to assess the barriers to accessibility of medicines for hyper-<lb/>lipidemia in LMICs. However, there were several limitations in this study. First, data provided <lb/>by countries that have conducted a survey using HAI methodology were not verified by HAI/ <lb/>WHO. The database provides periodic results from various countries with available data in dif-<lb/>ferent years. Second, some of the data were collected in 2001, and the conditions in those <lb/>countries may have changed substantially. Third, the number of countries reporting statin <lb/>availability and affordability in the HAI database was small, and the reporting time varied <lb/>from 2001 to 2015. The comparability of data across countries, regions, and income levels <lb/>should be interpreted with caution. Fourth, the number of countries included in the literature <lb/>review was small due to a lack of studies identified. Therefore, the generalizability of these <lb/>findings to all other LMICs could be limited. Future research is needed to assess the relation-<lb/>ships between the availability and affordability of statins as well as the impact of the accessibil-<lb/>ity of the medicines on cardiovascular disease burden (e.g., mortality, DALY, or quality of life) <lb/>in LMICs. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The findings of this study suggest that the accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia was <lb/>limited and barriers to the accessibility might exist at various levels of the health systems in <lb/>LMICs. The overall availability and affordability were low. Statins were more available in pri-<lb/>vate facilities than public facilities, and more available in urban areas than in rural areas. <lb/>Generic statins were more available than originator statins in both public and private facilities. <lb/>Statins were unaffordable to patients regardless of region and income level. <lb/>Recommendations <lb/>To tackle the barriers identified in this study, there are several steps that could be implemented <lb/>to improve the accessibility of hyperlipidemia medicines in LMICs. <lb/>First, private sector engagement could be prioritized <lb/>Pharmaceutical companies are actively engaged with access programs and play an important <lb/>role in LMIC contexts; however, statins do not seem to be prioritized in these programs. <lb/>Exploring how to emphasize the importance of hyperlipidemia treatment to these companies <lb/>and innovative ways of engaging them, such as integrated diagnosis and treatment, could <lb/>improve the prominence of hyperlipidemia medicines in these programs and increase <lb/>accessibility. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<body>Second, physician education and training could be emphasized <lb/>Hyperlipidemia is an asymptomatic chronic condition, and there is little demand for treatment <lb/>by patients. Therefore, patients rely on physicians to advocate for them and educate them on <lb/>the risks of hyperlipidemia. Unfortunately, even in many high-level facilities in LMICs, lipid <lb/>profiles are not being ordered, indicating a need for greater awareness of the impact of manag-<lb/>ing lipids in cardiovascular disease prevention. Also, prescribing practices should be reviewed, <lb/>and guidelines provided so that patients are encouraged to avail themselves of quality generic <lb/>medicines. <lb/>Third, investment in technology could be encouraged <lb/>LMICs have opportunities to adopt modern technology systems without going through inter-<lb/>mediary steps. For example, using wearable devices to diagnose and monitor hyperlipidemia, <lb/>mobile apps to encourage adherence or train community health workers, or new technologies <lb/>to distribute medicines represents some of the possibilities for technology to improve access to <lb/>hyperlipidemia medicines. <lb/>Fourth, enhancement of health systems could be implemented <lb/>Many of the barriers identified in the key informant interviews stem from weak health systems. <lb/>While not specific to hyperlipidemia medicines, investments in health financing, governance, <lb/>information systems, service delivery, and the health workforce will certainly combine to <lb/>improve NCD care and accessibility to medicines, including for hyperlipidemia. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. PubMed search results for accessibility, affordability, and availability of medi-<lb/>cines for hyperlipidemia in LMIC contexts. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. PubMed search results for accessibility, affordability, and availability of medi-<lb/>cines for hyperlipidemia in specific countries. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Table. Availability (%) of statins from Health Action International (HAI) database. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S4 Table. Price and affordability of statins from Health Action International (HAI) data-<lb/>base. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, Rachel <lb/>Nugent, Deliana Kostova, Patricia Richter. <lb/>Data curation: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, Rachel Nugent, <lb/>Deon Auzenne. <lb/>Formal analysis: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, Deon Auzenne. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Rachel Nugent, Patricia Richter. <lb/>Methodology: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Project administration: Rachel Nugent, Deliana Kostova, Patricia Richter. <lb/>Resources: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, Rachel Nugent, Deon <lb/>Auzenne, Deliana Kostova, Patricia Richter. <lb/>Supervision: Patricia Richter. <lb/>Validation: Chaoyang Li. <lb/>Visualization: Chaoyang Li. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, Rachel <lb/>Nugent, Patricia Richter. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Chaoyang Li, Garrison Spencer, Muhammad Jami Husain, <lb/>Rachel Nugent, Deon Auzenne, Deliana Kostova, Patricia Richter. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bovet P, Paccaud F. Cardiovascular Disease and the Changing Face of Global Public Health: A Focus <lb/>on Low and Middle Income Countries. Public Health Rev. 2011; 33(2):397-415. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>BF03391643 <lb/>2. Stanaway JD, Afshin A, Gakidou E, Lim SS, Abate D, Abate KH, et al. Global, regional, and national <lb/>comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks <lb/>or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the Global <lb/>Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet. 2018; 392(10159):1923-94. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S0140-6736(18)32225-6 PMID: 30496105 <lb/>3. Repositioning of the global epicentre of non-optimal cholesterol. Nature. 2020; 582(7810):73-7. Epub <lb/>20200603. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2338-1 PMID: 32494083; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC7332422. <lb/>4. Liu T, Zhao D, Qi Y. Global Trends in the Epidemiology and Management of Dyslipidemia. J Clin Med. <lb/>2022; 11(21). Epub 20221028. https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm11216377 PMID: 36362605; PubMed Cen-<lb/>tral PMCID: PMC9656679. <lb/>5. Grundy SM, Stone NJ, Bailey AL, Beam C, Birtcher KK, Blumenthal RS, et al. 2018 AHA/ACC/ <lb/>AACVPR/AAPA/ABC/ACPM/ADA/AGS/APhA/ASPC/NLA/PCNA Guideline on the Management of <lb/>Blood Cholesterol: Executive Summary: A Report of the American College of Cardiology/American <lb/>Heart Association Task Force on Clinical Practice Guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2019; 73(24):3168-<lb/>209. Epub 2018/11/14. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2018.11.002 PMID: 30423391. <lb/>6. World Health Organization. WHO Model Lists of Essential Medicines Geneva, Switzerland: World <lb/>Health Organizatoin. Available from: https://www.who.int/medicines/publications/essentialmedicines/ <lb/>en/. <lb/>7. Jeemon P, Gupta R, Onen C, Adler A, Gaziano TA, Prabhakaran D, Poulter N. Management of Hyper-<lb/>tension and Dyslipidemia for Primary Prevention of Cardiovascular Disease. In: Prabhakaran D, Anand <lb/>S, Gaziano TA, Mbanya JC, Wu Y, Nugent R, editors. Cardiovascular, Respiratory, and Related Disor-<lb/>ders. 3rd ed. Washington (DC)2017. <lb/>8. Thalmann I, Preiss D, Schlackow I, Gray A, Mihaylova B. Population-wide cohort study of statin use for <lb/>the secondary cardiovascular disease prevention in Scotland in 2009-2017. Heart. 2023; 109(5):388-<lb/>95. Epub 20230214. https://doi.org/10.1136/heartjnl-2022-321452 PMID: 36192149; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC9985707. <lb/>9. Salami JA, Warraich H, Valero-Elizondo J, Spatz ES, Desai NR, Rana JS, et al. National Trends in <lb/>Statin Use and Expenditures in the US Adult Population From 2002 to 2013: Insights From the Medical <lb/>Expenditure Panel Survey. JAMA Cardiol. 2017; 2(1):56-65. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2016. <lb/>4700 PMID: 27842171. <lb/>10. Hennessy DA, Tanuseputro P, Tuna M, Bennett C, Perez R, Shields M, et al. Population health impact <lb/>of statin treatment in Canada. Health Rep. 2016; 27(1):20-8. PMID: 26788719. <lb/>11. Marcus ME, Manne-Goehler J, Theilmann M, Farzadfar F, Moghaddam SS, Keykhaei M, et al. Use of <lb/>statins for the prevention of cardiovascular disease in 41 low-income and middle-income countries: a <lb/>cross-sectional study of nationally representative, individual-level data. Lancet Glob Health. 2022; 10 <lb/>(3):e369-e79. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00551-9 PMID: 35180420; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC8896912. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>12. Yusuf S, Islam S, Chow CK, Rangarajan S, Dagenais G, Diaz R, et al. Use of secondary prevention <lb/>drugs for cardiovascular disease in the community in high-income, middle-income, and low-income <lb/>countries (the PURE Study): a prospective epidemiological survey. Lancet. 2011; 378(9798):1231-43. <lb/>Epub 20110826. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61215-4 PMID: 21872920. <lb/>13. MDG Gap Task Force. Delivering on the Global Partnership for Achieving the Millennium Development <lb/>Goals. New York: United 2008. <lb/>14. Wirtz VJ, Kaplan WA, Kwan GF, Laing RO. Access to Medications for Cardiovascular Diseases in Low-<lb/>and Middle-Income Countries. Circulation. 2016; 133(21):2076-85. Epub 2016/05/25. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.008722 PMID: 27217433; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4880457. <lb/>15. Health Action International (HAI). Medicine Prices, Availability, Affordability &amp; Price Components Data-<lb/>base Amsterdam 2019. Available from: https://haiweb.org/what-we-do/price-availability-affordability/ <lb/>price-availability-data/. <lb/>16. World Health Organization. Service availability and readiness assessment (SARA) World Health Orga-<lb/>nization. Available from: https://www.who.int/data/data-collection-tools/service-availability-and-<lb/>readiness-assessment-(sara). <lb/>17. Management Sciences for Health (MSH). International Medical Products Price Guide. Medford, Mass.: <lb/>MSH, 2016. <lb/>18. World Bank. World Bank Country and Lending Groups 2017. Available from: https://datahelpdesk. <lb/>worldbank.org/knowledgebase/articles/906519-world-bank-country-and-lending-groups. <lb/>19. World Health Organization. Global Health Expenditure Database Geneva, Switzerland: World Health <lb/>Organization (WHO); 2017 [cited 2022]. Available from: https://apps.who.int/nha/database/ViewData/ <lb/>Indicators/en. <lb/>20. Global Burden of Disease Study 2017 (GBD 2017) Results [Internet]. Institute for Health Metrics and <lb/>Evaluation (IHME). 2018 [cited December 10, 2018]. <lb/>21. World Health Organization. SARA reports, 2010-2016 Geneva: World Health Organization; [cited 2020 <lb/>04/17/2020]. Available from: https://www.who.int/healthinfo/systems/sara_reports/en/. <lb/>22. Hamoui O, Omar MI, Raal FJ, Rashed W, Kane A, Alami M, et al. Increases in statin eligibility to reduce <lb/>cardiovascular risk according to the 2013 ACC/AHA cholesterol guidelines in the Africa Middle East <lb/>region: a sub-analysis of the Africa Middle East Cardiovascular Epidemiological (ACE) study. BMC Car-<lb/>diovasc Disord. 2019; 19(1):61. Epub 2019/03/17. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12872-019-1034-2 PMID: <lb/>30876390; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6420771. <lb/>23. Khatib R, McKee M, Shannon H, Chow C, Rangarajan S, Teo K, et al. Availability and affordability of <lb/>cardiovascular disease medicines and their effect on use in high-income, middle-income, and low-<lb/>income countries: an analysis of the PURE study data. Lancet (London, England). 2016; 387 <lb/>(10013):61-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00469-9 PMID: 26498706. <lb/>24. Dzudie A, Njume E, Abanda M, Aminde L, Hamadou B, Dzekem B, et al. Availability, cost and affordabil-<lb/>ity of essential cardiovascular disease medicines in the south west region of Cameroon: Preliminary <lb/>findings from the Cameroon science for disease study. PLoS One. 2020; 15(3):e0229307. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pone.0229307 PMID: 32130252. <lb/>25. Nyarko KM, Ameme DK, Ocansey D, Commeh E, Markwei MT, Ohene SA. Capacity assessment of <lb/>selected health care facilities for the pilot implementation of Package for Essential Non-communicable <lb/>Diseases (PEN) intervention in Ghana. Pan Afr Med J. 2016; 25(Suppl 1):16. Epub 2017/02/06. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.11604/pamj.supp.2016.25.1.6252 PMID: 28149441; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC5257011. <lb/>26. Bahiru E, Temu T, Mwanga J, Ndede K, Vusha S, Gitura B, et al. Facilitators, context of and barriers to <lb/>acute coronary syndrome care at Kenyatta National Hospital, Nairobi, Kenya: a qualitative analysis. <lb/>Cardiovasc J Afr. 2018; 29(3):177-82. Epub 2018/05/12. https://doi.org/10.5830/CVJA-2018-013 <lb/>PMID: 29750227; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6107733. <lb/>27. Njoroge HM. Determinants of Public Primary Health Facilities Preparedness for Service Delivery in <lb/>Nyandarua County, Kenya. Nairobi, Kenya: Kenya Methodist University; 2019. <lb/>28. Adje UD, Arute EJ, Adarighofua MI. Knowledge, attitude and practice of community pharmacists in rela-<lb/>tion to cholesterol screening in Delta State, Nigeria. African Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacology. <lb/>2017; 11(36):451-7. <lb/>29. Akunne O, Adedapo ADA. Quality of Statins Prescription in Patients Admitted at a Tertiary Hospital in <lb/>Southwestern Nigeria: Focus on Cost Containment. African Journal of Biomedical Research. 2018; 21 <lb/>(3):251-5. <lb/>30. Wollum A, Gabert R, McNellan CR, Daly JM, Reddy P, Bhatt P, et al. Identifying gaps in the continuum <lb/>of care for cardiovascular disease and diabetes in two communities in South Africa: Baseline findings <lb/>from the HealthRise project. PLoS One. 2018; 13(3):e0192603. Epub 2018/03/15. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0192603 PMID: 29538420; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5851537. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>31. Kasonde L, Tordrup D, Naheed A, Zeng W, Ahmed S, Babar ZU. Evaluating medicine prices, availability <lb/>and affordability in Bangladesh using World Health Organisation and Health Action International meth-<lb/>odology. BMC Health Serv Res. 2019; 19(1):383. Epub 2019/06/15. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-<lb/>019-4221-z PMID: 31196078; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6567665. <lb/>32. Choudhry NK, Dugani S, Shrank WH, Polinski JM, Stark CE, Gupta R, et al. Despite increased use and <lb/>sales of statins in India, per capita prescription rates remain far below high-income countries. Health Aff <lb/>(Millwood). 2014; 33(2):273-82. Epub 2014/02/05. https://doi.org/10.1377/hlthaff.2013.0388 PMID: <lb/>24493771. <lb/>33. Maharani A, Sujarwoto, Praveen D, Oceandy D, Tampubolon G, Patel A. Cardiovascular disease risk <lb/>factor prevalence and estimated 10-year cardiovascular risk scores in Indonesia: The SMARThealth <lb/>Extend study. PLoS One. 2019; 14(4):e0215219. Epub 2019/05/01. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0215219 PMID: 31039155; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6490907. <lb/>34. Lambojon K, Chang J, Saeed A, Hayat K, Li P, Jiang M, et al. Prices, Availability and Affordability of <lb/>Medicines with Value-Added Tax Exemption: A Cross-Sectional Survey in the Philippines. Int J Environ <lb/>Res Public Health. 2020; 17(14). https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17145242 PMID: 32708060. <lb/>35. Mendis S, Al Bashir I, Dissanayake L, Varghese C, Fadhil I, Marhe E, et al. Gaps in capacity in primary <lb/>care in low-resource settings for implementation of essential noncommunicable disease interventions. <lb/>Int J Hypertens. 2012; 2012:584041. Epub 2012/12/20. https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/584041 PMID: <lb/>23251789; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3517842. <lb/>36. Van Minh H, Do YK, Bautista MA, Tuan Anh T. Describing the primary care system capacity for the pre-<lb/>vention and management of non-communicable diseases in rural Vietnam. Int J Health Plann Manage. <lb/>2014; 29(2):e159-73. Epub 2013/04/05. https://doi.org/10.1002/hpm.2179 PMID: 23553675. <lb/>37. Tao X. Capacity of Primary Healthcare Facilities on Prevention and Management of Cardiovascular Dis-<lb/>eases in a Resource-limited Area in Vietnam: Duke Kunshan University and Duke University; 2017. <lb/>38. Meiqari L, Nguyen TP, Essink D, Zweekhorst M, Wright P, Scheele F. Access to hypertension care and <lb/>services in primary health-care settings in Vietnam: a systematic narrative review of existing literature. <lb/>Glob Health Action. 2019; 12(1):1610253. Epub 2019/05/24. https://doi.org/10.1080/16549716.2019. <lb/>1610253 PMID: 31120345; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6534204. <lb/>39. do Nascimento R, Guerra AA Jr, Alvares J, Gomes IC, Godman B, Bennie M, et al. Statin use in Brazil: <lb/>findings and implications. Curr Med Res Opin. 2018; 34(10):1809-17. Epub 2018/03/13. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1080/03007995.2018.1451312 PMID: 29528246. <lb/>40. Vinueza R, Boissonnet CP, Acevedo M, Uriza F, Benitez FJ, Silva H, et al. Dyslipidemia in seven Latin <lb/>American cities: CARMELA study. Prev Med. 2010; 50(3):106-11. Epub 2009/12/26. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ypmed.2009.12.011 PMID: 20034514. <lb/>41. Kenya DoN-CDMoHRo. Kenya National Guidelines for Cardiovascular Diseases Management. Nairobi, <lb/>Kenya: 2018. <lb/>42. Klug E, Raal FJ, Marais AD, Smuts CM, Schamroth C, Jankelow D, et al. South African dyslipidaemia <lb/>guideline consensus statement: 2018 update A joint statement from the South African Heart Association <lb/>(SA Heart) and the Lipid and Atherosclerosis Society of Southern Africa (LASSA). S Afr Med J. 2018; <lb/>108(11b):973-1000. Epub 2018/11/14. PMID: 30421699. <lb/>43. Chandra KS, Bansal M, Nair T, Iyengar SS, Gupta R, Manchanda SC, et al. Consensus statement on <lb/>management of dyslipidemia in Indian subjects. Indian Heart J. 2014; 66 Suppl 3:S1-51. Epub 2015/ <lb/>01/18. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ihj.2014.12.001 PMID: 25595144; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC4297876. <lb/>44. Widyahening IS, van der Graaf Y, Soewondo P, Glasziou P, van der Heijden GJ. Awareness, agree-<lb/>ment, adoption and adherence to type 2 diabetes mellitus guidelines: a survey of Indonesian primary <lb/>care physicians. BMC Fam Pract. 2014; 15:72. Epub 2014/04/24. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2296-<lb/>15-72 PMID: 24755412; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4000317. <lb/>45. Simao AF, Precoma DB, Andrade JP, Correa FH, Saraiva JF, Oliveira GM, et al. [I Brazilian Guidelines <lb/>for cardiovascular prevention]. Arq Bras Cardiol. 2013; 101(6 Suppl 2):1-63. Epub 2014/02/21. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.5935/abc.2013S012 PMID: 24554026. <lb/>46. Joint committee for guideline revision. 2016 Chinese guidelines for the management of dyslipidemia in <lb/>adults. J Geriatr Cardiol. 2018; 15(1):1-29. Epub 2018/02/13. https://doi.org/10.11909/j.issn.1671-<lb/>5411.2018.01.011 PMID: 29434622; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5803534. <lb/>47. Rockers PC, Laing RO, Ashigbie PG, Onyango MA, Mukiira CK, Wirtz VJ. Effect of Novartis Access on <lb/>availability and price of non-communicable disease medicines in Kenya: a cluster-randomised con-<lb/>trolled trial. Lancet Glob Health. 2019; 7(4):e492-e502. Epub 2019/02/26. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S2214-109X(18)30563-1 PMID: 30799142. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 23 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>48. Finlayson AE, Godman B, Xi H, Eng B, Malmstrom R, Zeng W. Ongoing initiatives to improve prescrib-<lb/>ing efficiency in China; statins as a case history. Generics and Biosimilars Initiative Journal. 2014; 3 <lb/>(3):122-32. Epub 09/01/2014. <lb/>49. Rivas-Gomez B, Almeda-Valdes P, Tussie-Luna MT, Aguilar-Salinas CA. Dyslipidemia in Mexico, a <lb/>Call for Action. Rev Invest Clin. 2018; 70(5):211-6. Epub 2018/10/12. https://doi.org/10.24875/RIC. <lb/>18002573 PMID: 30307444. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Accessibility of medicines for hyperlipidemia <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002905 February 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 23 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>