<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Refining flowering date enhances sesame yield independently of day-length</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Idan</forename>
          <surname>Sabag</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shaked</forename>
          <surname>Pnini</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Gota</forename>
          <surname>Morota</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Zvi</forename>
          <surname>Peleg</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T16:40:02.631Z">11/12/2025 4:40:02 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12870-024-05431-8</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Idan Sabag, Shaked Pnini, Gota Morota, Zvi Peleg. (2024). Refining flowering date enhances sesame yield independently of day-length. BMC Plant Biology, 24(1), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12870-024-05431-8</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T16:39:45.757192Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T16:39:45.757192Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Discover Education <lb/>Case Study <lb/>Assessment, credential, or both? Higher education faculty&apos;s design <lb/>principles for micro-credentials <lb/>Anne Reed 1 • Yiren Kong 2 • Samuel Abramovich 1 <lb/>Received: 26 October 2023 / Accepted: 6 February 2024 <lb/>Published online: 12 February 2024 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024, corrected publication 2024 <lb/>OPEN <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The rise of small, skills-focused credentials, also known as micro-credentials, has garnered considerable attention in <lb/>recent years. By offering micro-credentials, institutions of higher education can provide additional credential options, <lb/>thereby attracting more diverse audiences beyond degree-seekers. However, amidst their growth, fundamental ques-<lb/>tions surrounding their effective design and pedagogical implementation remain. This lack of clarity may inadvertently <lb/>hinder their effectiveness. To address this gap, there is a need for studies that examine the perspectives and practices of <lb/>faculty involved in micro-credential development and delivery. This study employed a single-embedded case design to <lb/>investigate the perceptions and practices of faculty members who implemented micro-credentials for a pilot program <lb/>at a large public research university. Specifically, this study aimed to identify faculty perceptions of the assessment <lb/>and credentialing affordances of micro-credentials, and strategies employed to integrate these affordances into the <lb/>design of micro-credentials. In-depth interviews were conducted with faculty members representing a diverse array of <lb/>academic disciplines. Findings revealed that faculty need support in recognizing and integrating certain characteristics <lb/>of quality assessments when designing micro-credentials, including aligning of assessments with a micro-credential&apos;s <lb/>delivery method, and integrating equity-oriented assessments into the design. These findings underscore the necessity <lb/>for interventions and training programs aimed at integrating quality assessment practices into micro-credential design. <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Micro-credentials are gaining widespread adoption throughout higher education [48, 51] providing learners with new <lb/>opportunities to gain knowledge, skills, and experience relevant to their professional goals. A micro-credential is defined <lb/>as &quot;a qualification that represents assessed achievement of a subset of learning within and beyond the traditional realm <lb/>of certificates, diplomas, and degrees&quot; providing &quot;recognition for what a person knows and can do at a modular level&apos; <lb/>([15], p. 5). &quot;Modular level&quot; in this definition indicates that micro-credentials are smaller than traditional credentials (e.g., <lb/>degrees) in terms of the length of time they take to earn, and the specificity of knowledge and skills they verify. Expand-<lb/>ing on this definition, micro-credentials are often issued digitally, a format that can provide more detailed evidence of <lb/>achievement than is possible with paper-based credentials [25]. The term &quot;micro-credential&quot; is used throughout this <lb/>paper to refer to digital micro-credentials specifically. <lb/>Micro-credentials are different from other, more commonly used credentials, in terms of size, digital format, and <lb/>use in verifying both technical and professional &quot;soft&quot; skills [19, 38]. Micro-credentials are emerging across all types of <lb/>higher education organizations, including community colleges, technical colleges, and universities [46]. But despite <lb/></body>

    <front>* Anne Reed, annereed@buffalo.edu | 1 Department of Learning and Instruction, University at Buffalo, 408 Capen Hall, Buffalo, NY 14260, <lb/>USA. 2 Stony Brook University, Stony Brook 11794, United States. <lb/>Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></front>

    <body>the growth of micro-credentials, it is still unclear what practices are enacted when they are designed for use in higher <lb/>education, or what qualities constitute well-designed micro-credentials. Without this information, micro-credentials <lb/>may continue to be developed, but their design may be sub-optimal, which would likely influence their effectiveness. <lb/>Research on the design of other educational technologies (e.g., online courses, MOOCs, gamified learning) shows <lb/>that design has an impact on the effectiveness of the technology and can influence factors such as student satisfac-<lb/>tion, persistence, and perceived learning [20, 21]. This point is included to reinforce the importance of examining <lb/>micro-credentials from the standpoint of design. While there is much value in researching micro-credentials in terms <lb/>of their impact on learning, this subject is beyond the scope of this study. <lb/>Because they have unique characteristics, including size and digital format, and are therefore different from other <lb/>types of credentials, micro-credential design warrants examination. Considering how many institutions are embracing <lb/>micro-credentials [7], poorly designed micro-credentials may waste students&apos; time and money, institutional resources, <lb/>and faculty time and effort. Research on the value of micro-credentials for students and employers is emerging [26, <lb/>30], but micro-credentials have rarely been examined from the perspective of the academic faculty who are primarily <lb/>responsible for their design and implementation. <lb/>1.1 Purpose of micro-credentials <lb/>The definition of a micro-credential as &quot;a qualification that represents assessed achievement&quot; ([15], p. 5) indicates that <lb/>micro-credentials serve both credentialing and assessment purposes and can achieve optimal impact when fulfilling <lb/>both objectives. However, micro-credentials are not always used for both purposes (Table 1). For example, a micro-<lb/>credential that recognizes completion, participation, attendance, or interest [10] may function as a credential but not <lb/>as an assessment in that it validates the recipients&apos; knowledge, skills or experience similar to traditional credentials. <lb/>But these types of micro-credentials are likely to have less value to stakeholders who are concerned with feedback <lb/>towards an educational objective [49]. Similarly, a micro-credential issued to provide formative and summative feed-<lb/>back or scaffold learning [11] may function as an assessment but not as a credential. This assessment-only application <lb/>of a micro-credential likely has value for learners within a learning context in that it facilitates communication around <lb/>learning, but likely would not serve as a mechanism for validating or guaranteeing learning gains across settings [36]. <lb/>Much of the literature on micro-credentials as credentials is centered on twenty-first century skills and workforce <lb/>job development. The literature on micro-credentials as assessments is centered on motivation, pedagogy, and <lb/>gamification. A critical, potential flaw with using micro-credentials as credentials is that until the micro-credential is <lb/>accepted as a valid representation of performance then it has little currency in employment or the workforce, similar <lb/>to the degree or certificate that is ignored or perceived as irrelevant. As assessments, micro-credentials can have the <lb/>critical, potential flaw of having little ongoing value to a learner or educator beyond what it means at the time it is <lb/>issued. For example, a micro-credential that is issued to provide formative feedback no longer has value if the learner <lb/>has earned a newer-micro credential or other credentials that supersedes the original. <lb/>1.2 Conceptual framework <lb/>This study approaches the subject of higher education micro-credentials from a learning design perspective. Like <lb/>any educational technology, positive outcomes are not automatic for micro-credentials; successful implementation <lb/>and outcomes of micro-credentials hinge on intentional design principles and facilitation by educators. Based on <lb/>their affordances, micro-credential design should exhibit qualities of good assessment design and good credential <lb/>design. While credentials are awards that show qualification, assessment validates the award, and serves numerous <lb/>purposes in terms of teaching, institutional quality assurance, and, most importantly, learning. If a credential earner <lb/>is not assessed then there is no proof that learning occurred, or that the earning of the credential was warranted. <lb/>Without effective assessment, a credential lacks legitimacy. <lb/>1.2.1 Micro-credentials as assessments <lb/>An assessment is an appraisal, or judgement, of student work or performance that is intended to collect information <lb/>about learning gains and guide a students&apos; learning towards an intended goal [39]. A micro-credential provides appraisal <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>Table 1 Micro-credentials whose focus is either a Credential or Assessment <lb/>Aspects of a micro-credential <lb/>Credentialing as the objective <lb/>Assessing as the objective <lb/>Application <lb/>Recognition of Completion, Participation, Attendance, or Interest <lb/>Provide Formative or Summative Feedback and Scaffold Learning <lb/>Communication <lb/>Validates the recipient&apos;s knowledge, skills, or experience <lb/>Defines what the recipient has learned during a specific learning experience <lb/>Value to Stakeholders <lb/>Guarantee <lb/>Vehicle for Communication <lb/>Similar Learning Object <lb/>Degrees, Certificates <lb/>Grades, Personal Communication <lb/>Theoretical Framing <lb/>21st Century Skills, Workforce Job Development <lb/>Gamification, Motivation, Pedagogical Practices <lb/>Potential Flaw <lb/>Unpromised value in supporting stakeholders in their information needs <lb/>Little ongoing value if not continuously useful to the learner or educator <lb/>Citations <lb/>[10, 30, 45] <lb/>[1, 11, 21, 49] <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></note>

    <body>or judgement of learning and therefore is an assessment construct. A micro-credential communicates an appraisal or <lb/>judgement in the form of feedback to the learner, gauging learning progress toward the intended goal. For example, <lb/>micro-credentials may be issued during the learning process to communicate to a student that certain competencies <lb/>have been met. Or, as a result of performance, they may be issued upon completion of a learning opportunity to indicate <lb/>to learners (and other stakeholders) that specific skills, knowledge, or abilities have been gained [31]. A micro-credential <lb/>can be added to a learning opportunity that otherwise would not have an assessment, such as co-curricular, non-credit <lb/>experience, adding an integral learning component. Additionally, faculty can add a micro-credential to a curricular <lb/>experience to provide an assessment opportunity that is &apos;above and beyond&apos; what the curriculum typically mandates. <lb/>For example, the grade in a Computer Science course is based on accredited competencies, while micro-credentials can <lb/>provide feedback to students on soft skills such as time management [1]. <lb/>1.2.2 Micro-credentials as credentials <lb/>A credential is &quot;a documented award by a responsible and authorized body that attests to the achievement of specific <lb/>learning outcomes or to a defined level of knowledge or skill relative to a given standard&quot; [28, p. 105]. A credential acts as <lb/>a communication device that translates learning gains from an educational context to other contexts and serves as &quot;proof&quot; <lb/>of those learning gains. Micro-credentials are credentials because they are documented awards, issued by institutions <lb/>of education, or other educational organizations, that attest that specific knowledge or skills have been gained. When <lb/>a micro-credential is shared (e.g., posted on social media), and then viewed by a third party (e.g., reviewed by potential <lb/>employer), the knowledge and skills that the earner gained in an educational context is communicated to other contexts, <lb/>such as the workplace, and serves as proof of learning gains. <lb/>Micro-credentials are different from other credentials (e.g., degrees, certifications), though. The &quot;micro&quot; denotes that <lb/>micro-credentials are meant to be earned in a shorter amount of time than commonly used credentials such as college <lb/>degrees and industry certifications [33] and to provide recognition of achievement on a more granular level than other <lb/>credentials [41]. Moreover, micro-credentials, as they are discussed in the context of this study, are digital, which allows <lb/>them to be easily shared in digital spaces (e.g., social media). Although other types of credentials can also be issued <lb/>digitally (e.g., digital diplomas meant to ensure security against credential fraud) [40], the digital aspect serves a unique <lb/>purpose for micro-credentials. Digital credentials are often embedded with metadata, which provides information that <lb/>helps to validate the credential, such as information regarding the issuing institution, the criteria for earning, and even <lb/>artifacts of learning (i.e., &quot;evidence&quot;). When combined with &quot;micro&quot; aspects (e.g., specificity of subject matter, short com-<lb/>pletion time), the digital format of a micro-credential allows for discrete knowledge and skills to be validated, thereby <lb/>providing more precise recognition of abilities than other (non-digital, broader) credentials offer. For example, a learner <lb/>who has earned a micro-credential in Data Visualization can share it with a potential employer to indicate their skills in <lb/>using data visualization tools. When embedded with evidence, the viewer of the micro-credential can see what the earner <lb/>is capable of producing (e.g., Tableau dashboard). Arguably, digital micro-credentials are more specific and transparent <lb/>than other credentials in terms of attesting to what the earner knows and can do [27]. <lb/>1.3 Research questions <lb/>As the number of higher education micro-credentials grows, so too does the number of faculty performing the work <lb/>required to offer them. There is now a critical mass of these professionals in higher education, but little is known about this <lb/>population in relation to micro-credentials [37, 41]. Specifically, we do not know how faculty perceive micro-credentials <lb/>or the practices they employ when designing and implementing them; without this knowledge, research cannot fully <lb/>reflect the complexities and realities of how and why micro-credentials are used in higher education. This causes a dis-<lb/>connect between research findings and the practical uses of micro-credentials in the contexts which they are developed. <lb/>This study aims to identify perceptions of faculty members, from a range of academic disciplines, concerning the <lb/>assessment and credentialing affordances of micro-credentials, and strategies employed to integrate these affordances <lb/>when designing micro-credentials. The following research questions were posed: (1) What are faculty perceptions of <lb/>micro-credentials as assessments and as credentials? and (2) How do faculty integrate qualities of assessments and <lb/>credentials when designing micro-credentials? <lb/>To answer these questions, we first examined literature on assessment design and credential design to identify key <lb/>characteristics of quality assessments and quality credentials. We based this approach on educational technology research <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>that examined the affordances of a technology to derive design principles [16, 18]. By examining micro-credentials in rela-<lb/>tion to quality design principles, and from the perspective of individuals who developed them, this study aims to locate <lb/>micro-credentials as &quot;part of a curriculum practice within a broader repertoire of pedagogic practices&quot; ([6], p. 1115). This <lb/>approach provides a more nuanced, socially situated, and therefore comprehensive understanding of micro-credentials <lb/>than would be possible otherwise. <lb/>2 Characteristics of quality assessments and credentials in the literature <lb/>This section provides an overview of key characteristics of quality assessments and credentials. These characteristics <lb/>were identified through a review of the literature on assessment design and credential design and serve as a frame of <lb/>reference for determining quality design principles for micro-credentials. We consider each of the principles individually <lb/>for their impact, and how they are analyzed in our analysis. <lb/>2.1 Quality assessment design <lb/>2.1.1 Formative and summative components <lb/>Learning opportunities should provide opportunities for both formative and summative assessment. These are often <lb/>distinguished as &quot;assessment to support learning&quot; and &quot;assessment of learning, &quot; respectively [44]. Formative assessment <lb/>guides students toward the learning objectives and provides scaffolding or correction, and helps learners determine <lb/>knowledge gaps and areas for improvement. Summative assessment is intended to determine what learning has been <lb/>achieved [14] and is useful so that the learner knows if they have gained the knowledge or skills they need, or if addi-<lb/>tional learning is needed. <lb/>Used formatively, micro-credentials can be issued to learners as they progress toward the learning objectives of <lb/>a course or program. In this way, micro-credentials may be a feedback mechanism, indicating what progress has or <lb/>has not been made, and what knowledge or skills have or have not yet been demonstrated as the learner progresses <lb/>toward meeting the intended learning objectives [27]. As a summative assessment, a micro-credential can be issued, as <lb/>a validation of achievement, when a learner successfully demonstrates the learning objectives have been met [17, 30]. <lb/>If the micro-credential is used formatively, the learning experience should also provide an opportunity for summative <lb/>assessment, and vice-versa. Assessment research underscores the significance of both components in the teaching and <lb/>learning processes [22, 23]. <lb/>2.1.2 Sustainable assessment <lb/>Education should prepare individuals to be lifelong learners. An assessment is sustainable when it not only helps stu-<lb/>dents meet the specific and immediate learning requirements and outcomes, but also establishes a basis for students to <lb/>carry out their own assessment activities in future contexts [5]. Sustainable assessment practices offer opportunities for <lb/>students to establish their own learning goals, judge their own progression towards goals, generate their own feedback, <lb/>and provide feedback to their peers [31]. <lb/>A micro-credential can serve as a sustainable assessment by providing an opportunity for learners to become asses-<lb/>sors of their own learning, a skill they can later apply in future contexts. For example, an instructor might offer a crea-<lb/>tive writing course with a standard syllabus that includes predefined learning objectives, and a set of assignments that <lb/>they assess and provide feedback on. The instructor could augment the course by adding writing prompts that are not <lb/>included in the final grade for the course but that provide additional opportunities for students to hone their skills. The <lb/>students could earn a micro-credential if they complete a writing prompt and conduct a self-assessment by reflecting <lb/>on the extent to which their writing met the criteria. This micro-credential would serve as a sustainable assessment as it <lb/>would provide an opportunity for students to practice assessing their own skills. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></note>

    <body>2.1.3 Clarity of outcomes and criteria <lb/>For assessments to be understandable to learners and other stakeholders, the learning being assessed should have well-<lb/>defined outcomes (e.g., what was supposed to be learned) and criteria (e.g., what is evidence of that learning) [2, 42]. If <lb/>the assessment lacks clarity for students, then they will be hampered in their ability to meet the criteria for the assessment <lb/>and to achieve the intended outcomes. If the assessment lacks clarity for instructors, then they will not be able to judge <lb/>whether students met the criteria and will not be able to provide feedback to help meet the intended learning outcomes. <lb/>If the assessment lacks clarity for other stakeholders, like employers, then they will not be able to make informed deci-<lb/>sions about the learner, such as how they were evaluated to prove they possess certain knowledge and skills. <lb/>For micro-credentials to be clearly understandable they also need to have well-defined outcomes and criteria; since <lb/>digital micro-credentials can be shared more widely than paper-based credentials, the clarity of criteria and outcomes <lb/>is consequential for a wider audience. For example, an earner might share their micro-credential on social media, to <lb/>showcase the skills they have recently acquired. Someone in their personal network may have interest in gaining similar <lb/>skills, but if the outcomes and criteria are not clear then a viewer would not be able to make an informed decision about <lb/>pursuing the micro-credential. <lb/>2.1.4 Optimized for the learning opportunity <lb/>The type of learning opportunity, and any unique features of the learning opportunity, should be considered when <lb/>designing an assessment. An assessment that is appropriate for one opportunity might not apply to another [8]. For exam-<lb/>ple, a cumulative exam, or a portfolio, would not be suitable assessments for a succinct learning experience. Similarly, a <lb/>multiple-choice exam would not be a suitable assessment for a performance-based learning experience. If the assess-<lb/>ment is not optimal for the specific aspects of the learning opportunity, it may reduce the validity of the assessment [35]. <lb/>Micro-credentials have unique features, such as their short length, and granularity of subject matter. Consequently, <lb/>assessment aspects of the micro-credential need to be appropriate for those fundamental &quot;micro&quot; concepts by evaluat-<lb/>ing learners&apos; competencies in a focused, concise, and pertinent manner that aligns with the nature of these targeted <lb/>learning opportunities. The design stage, then, requires the identification of concrete competencies to be assessed, and <lb/>assessment tasks that support and evaluate competency development [34]. <lb/>2.1.5 Aligned with the delivery method <lb/>An assessment should be designed to suit the context of its intended delivery method [47]. Delivery method refers spe-<lb/>cifically to modality (e.g., online, face-to-face), meaning the medium through which information is delivered to students. <lb/>This differs from the quality of being &quot;optimized for the learning opportunity&quot; which refers to designing assessments that <lb/>are appropriate to the type of learning opportunity. Delivery method does not define a type of learning opportunity but <lb/>rather a means of offering a learning opportunity. <lb/>Delivery method should be considered when determining the criteria to earn a micro-credential. In a face-to-face <lb/>context, assessment for a micro-credential could be conducted through observation of learners working collaboratively <lb/>in teams. In an online asynchronous micro-credential, the criteria could not be met through direct observation and would <lb/>need to be verified through video demonstration or other appropriate assessment that would match the online context. <lb/>2.1.6 Equity-oriented assessment <lb/>Equity is a critical issue in education that should be addressed through pedagogical practices, including assessment <lb/>design. Equity speaks to and references fairness, inclusion, and social justice. Equitable education encompasses several <lb/>aims, including eliminating disparities, providing every student with a chance to succeed academically, and preparing <lb/>them for participatory, democratic citizenship [43]. Equity-oriented assessment strategies give students some control <lb/>over how they are assessed, a role that is typically performed only by authority figures. Involving students in their own <lb/>assessment de-centers authority and provides learners with a sense of agency [50]. <lb/>Micro-credentials can empower learners to be active players in their own assessment. For instance, micro-credentials <lb/>can be awarded to show progress toward goals that are set by the learner, therefore focusing on what they deemed <lb/>important rather than on standards set by an authority. Learners can decide what evidence they want to submit to show <lb/>they have met their learning goals, and they can decide if they want that evidence to be published as viewable metadata <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>in their digital credential. This type of participation empowers learners and makes education more pluralistic, teaching <lb/>that all voices (rather than just the voices of authority) are important. <lb/>2.2 Quality credential design <lb/>2.2.1 Meets the needs of employers <lb/>Credentials should be aligned to the labor market so that they verify skills that are needed by employers and have cur-<lb/>rency in the job market [45]. Employers will then be able to look for credentials to identify preferred qualifications of <lb/>employees. If a credential earner can show that they possess the skills that employers need, they will be a strong candi-<lb/>date when seeking a job or advancing their position. <lb/>Since micro-credentials can be developed more quickly than traditional credentials, they are well-suited to meet the <lb/>ever-changing needs of employers. Input from employers and industry experts will lead to the development of micro-<lb/>credentials that verify skills that are needed [32], thereby increasing the value of the micro-credential to both employers <lb/>and learners. <lb/>2.2.2 Prepares learners to succeed in the workforce <lb/>An important aim of postsecondary credentials is to benefit earners through financial returns and upward social mobil-<lb/>ity [54]. Xu and Trimble [52] found that credentials with &quot;tight labor market alignment and clear indicators of the career <lb/>trajectory&quot; (p. 273) lead to better economic opportunities for earners than those with only a general approach to work-<lb/>force preparation. <lb/>Micro-credentials could help learners in their career trajectory by preparing them with knowledge and skills that they <lb/>will need in the workforce, and by providing opportunities to demonstrate these skills. Micro-credentials should include <lb/>&quot;hands-on&quot; learning that enables learners to gain practical experience and to demonstrate their qualifications [19]. For <lb/>example, a micro-credential can be earned for completing a project for a local business. The earner can then use that <lb/>project to demonstrate their experience and preparedness to advance toward a career in that industry. <lb/>2.2.3 Understood by stakeholders <lb/>According to credentialing theory, the meaning of an educational credential is constructed and maintained through <lb/>shared beliefs about the value of the credential [29]. &quot;Shared beliefs&quot; means that relevant stakeholders (e.g., educational <lb/>institutions, employers, professional associations, students) possess mutual understanding of the purpose of the cre-<lb/>dential and its unique qualities [24]. Shared understanding leads to increased credibility and viability of a credential. <lb/>For a micro-credential to be understood by stakeholders, the individual or entity that awards it (e.g., a university) <lb/>should clearly communicate its purpose and unique qualities. Since micro-credentials are digital credentials, the infor-<lb/>mation that stakeholders need should be embedded as metadata which allows for a level of transparency that is not <lb/>possible with non-digital credentials. <lb/>3 Methods <lb/>This study examined faculty perceptions of the assessment and credentialing affordances of micro-credentials, and <lb/>practices employed when designing micro-credentials to address these affordances. To do this, we applied a qualitative <lb/>design, specifically an embedded-single case design. This research design is appropriate when examining more than one <lb/>sub-unit of analysis within a broader organizational context, especially when an examination of those sub-units intro-<lb/>duces different perspectives [53]. In this study, a university&apos;s micro-credential pilot program constituted the main unit <lb/>of analysis. The site of the pilot program was a large public research university in the United States. The faculty members <lb/>who each designed a micro-credential for the pilot constituted the sub-units of analysis. <lb/>In-depth interviews were conducted with five faculty members, each representing distinct areas of expertise within the <lb/>university. The participants encompassed a diverse spectrum of disciplines, including Engineering, Pharmacy, University <lb/>Libraries, Dental Medicine, and Experiential Learning. The participants were assigned pseudonyms-Dr. E, Dr. P, Dr. L, Dr. D, <lb/>and Dr. EL, respectively. Before their participation in the pilot program, none of the participants had previous experience <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></note>

    <body>designing micro-credentials. However, all participants had extensive experience (i.e., five years or more) teaching and <lb/>designing learning experiences, including academic courses, programs, and co-curricular learning. The participants <lb/>designed a range of micro-credentials, including credit-bearing and non-credit micro-credentials, for undergraduate, <lb/>graduate, and professional students. <lb/>The interviews were conducted in-person in secured conference rooms and were audio-recorded. The interview pro-<lb/>tocol consisted of semi-structured, open-ended questions to elicit the faculty&apos;s responses regarding their perceptions of <lb/>micro-credentials, and their experience designing and implementing micro-credentials. The participants were asked to <lb/>explain what they knew about micro-credentials before they decided to develop one; to discuss their decision to develop <lb/>a micro-credential; and to describe their process of designing a micro-credential. Sample questions from the interview <lb/>protocol included What was your understanding for why micro-credentials are implemented? Why did you decide to offer <lb/>this micro-credential? and What were some of the design decisions that you had to make? The interviews were transcribed <lb/>verbatim. Follow-up emails were sent to participants for clarification or additional questions. Instances that necessitated <lb/>follow-up inquiry included incoherent portions of the recorded audio and ambiguous statements. For example, one <lb/>participant frequently used the term &quot;they, &quot; but it was sometimes unclear to whom &quot;they&quot; referred. <lb/>The transcripts were reviewed, and the authors coded them individually applying deductive analysis using an a priori <lb/>template [4]. Prior to collecting data, the authors developed a codebook of the design qualities identified through <lb/>the literature review. This codebook served as the a priori coding system and included a definition for each of the key <lb/>characteristics of quality assessment and credential design [12]. After individually coding each interview, the authors <lb/>met to compare codes and reason through any discrepancies in coding. Discrepancies surfaced during individual cod-<lb/>ing sessions where one researcher applied a code to a particular segment of an interview that other researchers had <lb/>not considered or where different codes were applied to the same segment by different authors. To effectively manage <lb/>these discrepancies, the research team adopted a consensus-driven approach, which involved thorough discussions <lb/>where disagreements were deliberated upon, leading to joint decisions by the team [9]. Through these discussions, <lb/>each researcher had the opportunity to present and clarify the rationale behind their application of specific codes. This <lb/>approach was instrumental in ensuring inter-coding consistency across the coding process. Upon reaching consensus, <lb/>it was established that all of the a priori codes pertained to micro-credential design. <lb/>4 Findings <lb/>Through a deductive analysis of interview data, we found that all of the participants designed micro-credentials to serve <lb/>as both assessments and as credentials. Participants&apos; application of the principles is illustrated in Table 2. No additional <lb/>design qualities were explored in this study. Each of the faculty addressed the assessment and credentialing affordances <lb/>by applying some of the characteristics of quality assessments and quality credentials, as defined in the literature. No <lb/>faculty member discussed their application of every characteristic of quality assessment when describing how they <lb/>designed a micro-credential; however, most of the participants (all but Dr. D) discussed all the characteristics of quality <lb/>credentials. This section details our findings in terms of how and why the participating faculty applied these design quali-<lb/>ties when designing micro-credentials. These findings shed light on how design principles can be applied to address the <lb/>assessment and credentialing affordances of a micro-credential. <lb/>4.1 Characteristics of quality assessments integrated into micro-credentials <lb/>The six columns under Assessment Design Principles in Table 2 show which characteristics of quality assessments were <lb/>applied by each of the participating faculty members when designing a micro-credential. <lb/>4.1.1 Formative and summative components <lb/>Four of the participants acknowledged that micro-credentials served both formative and summative assessment pur-<lb/>poses. While all of the participants discussed their micro-credentials as serving summative assessment purposes, as <lb/>indicated in Table 2, one faculty member did not perceive the purpose of her micro-credential as providing formative <lb/>feedback. Dr. P stated &quot;I view it as summative…. but, understand that I&apos;m grounded in professional education culture <lb/>and graduate education culture…. So, somebody from [another unit] may have a different perspective. &quot; While this faculty <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>Table 2 Participants&apos; Application of Assessment and Credential Design Principles <lb/>+ <lb/>Participant discussed application of the principle <lb/>-<lb/>Participant did not discuss application of the principle <lb/>Assessment design principles <lb/>Credential design principles <lb/>Participant <lb/>Formative and <lb/>summative <lb/>Aligns with <lb/>delivery method <lb/>Sustainable <lb/>Clarity of out-<lb/>comes and criteria <lb/>Optimized for the <lb/>learning opportunity <lb/>Equity-<lb/>oriented <lb/>Meets needs of <lb/>employers <lb/>Prepares Learners to Suc-<lb/>ceed in the Workforce <lb/>Understood <lb/>by Stakehold-<lb/>ers <lb/>Dr. E <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Dr. P <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Dr. L <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Dr. D <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Dr. EL <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>member acknowledged that others might view micro-credentials as having a formative use, she made an explicit design <lb/>choice to use the micro-credential as a summative assessment. <lb/>4.1.2 Sustainable assessment <lb/>Micro-credentials were described as sustainable assessments by four of the participants. For example, Dr. E described <lb/>a mock job interview that was required for his micro-credential. The students&apos; mock job interviews were recorded and <lb/>then &quot;[the students] have to go back, watch themselves and then do one final reflection where they&apos;re sort of trying to <lb/>evaluate How do you think you did on that? How did you do with answering each question in the mock interview? I&apos;m <lb/>not watching their mock interview, but I am reading their reflection on their own performance.&quot; This faculty member <lb/>designed the micro-credential so that learners were asked to reflect on their own performance to better prepare them for <lb/>a future &quot;real life&quot; interview. This is an example of a sustainable assessment in that the learners practiced self-assessment <lb/>in order to be prepared to self-assess in other, future, contexts. <lb/>4.1.3 Clarity of outcomes and criteria <lb/>Two faculty members discussed the notion that the outcomes and criteria of a micro-credential should be clearly under-<lb/>stood by stakeholders. In one example, Dr. EL discussed how she developed resources to assist the students in under-<lb/>standing the criteria for earning the micro-credential that she designed. She stated that she &quot;spent a lot of time creating <lb/>a template and giving students instructions for how to earn [the micro-credential]. &quot; She also discussed working with a <lb/>colleague to develop an instructional guide. The effort she spent was indicative of her view that it was important for <lb/>students to clearly understand the criteria for the micro-credential. <lb/>4.1.4 Optimized for the learning opportunity <lb/>Three faculty members discussed designing a micro-credential to be optimized for the unique aspects of the learning <lb/>opportunity. Dr. L designed a micro-credential for a self-paced short program to teach what she categorized as &quot;soft skills, &quot; <lb/>including critical thinking, and evaluating digital resources. She stated &quot;we had to build [quizzes] that would measure <lb/>what we had them watching or reading, so they could actually answer to those competencies. But we had to do it in <lb/>a way that inspired critical thinking. &quot; When the interviewer followed up by asking &quot;and if it weren&apos;t a micro-credential, <lb/>would you have built that?&quot; She replied, &quot;we probably wouldn&apos;t have because [we would instead] observe the student or <lb/>interview the student through the process. &quot; Her conjecture is that without the micro aspect of the credential, she could <lb/>have still assessed the soft skills but that would have required an observation protocol that would require a longer period <lb/>of time (e.g., a semester) and more resources (e.g., a librarian conducting observations). <lb/>4.1.5 Aligned with the delivery method <lb/>The importance of aligning micro-credentials with delivery method was described by two faculty members, both of <lb/>whom offered their micro-credentials fully online. Dr. EL created a micro-credential that students earned through an <lb/>online, international collaborative experience. She described the culminating assessment in which students developed <lb/>a &quot;connective narrative&quot; video, created and delivered online, that &quot;integrated their [collaborative] experience and what <lb/>they gained from it. &quot; This is an example of alignment with delivery method because the video requirement was chosen <lb/>as an activity to be compatible with the online design of the micro-credential. <lb/>4.1.6 Equity-oriented assessment <lb/>Only one of the faculty members described a micro-credential as an equitable assessment. Dr. EL explained how the <lb/>micro-credential she designed empowered students by providing them with a sense of agency. She stated, &quot;we have <lb/>three activities, the first one has three steps to the badge and requires them to look at a list of skills and pick five that they <lb/>feel are most relevant to their experience and explain why. &quot; This can be characterized as an equitable assessment since <lb/>this micro-credential was designed as an opportunity for learners to participate in their own assessment by selecting <lb/>the skills they wanted to gain, and also because their personal experiences were recognized as valuable. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>4.2 Characteristics of quality credentials integrated into micro-credentials <lb/>The three columns under Credential Design Principles in Table 2 show which characteristics of quality credentials were <lb/>applied by each of the participating faculty members when designing a micro-credential. <lb/>4.2.1 Meets needs of employers <lb/>Four of the faculty members discussed their micro-credentials in terms of meeting the needs of employers. For example, <lb/>Dr. P stated that the micro-credential she developed would &quot;help [students] verify to employers that they have the skill-<lb/>sets employers are looking for. &quot; She suggested that although students might have the skills that employers need, they <lb/>still needed additional methods for conveying those skills. The micro-credential acted as the means by which those skills <lb/>can be conveyed, such as displaying them on a CV or using them as prompts during an interview (e.g., &quot;I&apos;d like to mention <lb/>that I earned micro-credential in a relevant skill. &quot;). <lb/>4.2.2 Prepares learners to succeed in the workforce <lb/>All of the participants characterized their micro-credentials in terms of preparing learners for success in the workforce. <lb/>Dr. P described micro-credentials as a way to gain specialized skill sets that are needed in specific fields, but not currently <lb/>offered through coursework at the university. She stated &quot;I really think it should be used for a select group of students <lb/>who want to enhance their skill-set. &quot; She designed a micro-credential to assess skills in conducting original research. In <lb/>describing how she communicated this to students and stated, &quot;if you&apos;re interested in this career path [in pharmaceutical <lb/>research], you may be interested in this micro-credential. &quot; This indicated that she viewed the micro-credential as having <lb/>a role in preparing learners for a career involving research. <lb/>4.2.3 Understood by stakeholders <lb/>Each of the participants discussed the notion that a micro-credential should be understood by stakeholders, both inter-<lb/>nal (students, faculty, and an advisory council) and external (industry partners and employers). Dr. D described doubts <lb/>about his micro-credential from both faculty and students by stating &quot;The faculty, as well as students in most cases, are <lb/>not seeing the inherent value…. because it&apos;s not really mainstream at this point. &quot; He also pondered whether employers <lb/>understood micro-credentials and asked, rhetorically &quot;Is this something that employers are looking at? Are they going <lb/>to know to click on a digital icon and realize that this is going to provide information on what the student did to accom-<lb/>plish it?&quot; From his perspective, stakeholders lacked an understanding because of the newness of micro-credentials. He <lb/>did not identify ways to counter stakeholders&apos; lack of understanding but rather expressed his belief that understanding <lb/>would develop over time. <lb/>5 Discussion <lb/>The findings of this study indicated that faculty did, in fact, apply both assessment design and credential design principles <lb/>when designing micro-credentials. These principles can serve as foundational recommendations for designing micro-<lb/>credentials, particularly those meant to function as both an assessment of learning, and as a credential that validates <lb/>learning. These principles are not unique to micro-credentials, but when integrated may optimize the assessment and <lb/>credentialing affordances of micro-credentials. <lb/>These principles serve as a guide to support quality micro-credential design but is not necessarily meant to be applied <lb/>in-aggregate; a micro-credential may be well-designed without the inclusion of every one of these design principles. <lb/>Also, there may be other principles that, when integrated into the design of a micro-credential, may positively serve its <lb/>assessment and credentialing affordances. Therefore, the design principles examined in this study serve as a foundation <lb/>for optimizing micro-credential design, not as a definitive formula. Given these caveats, we found that some assessment <lb/>qualities were overlooked by most of the participating faculty. We also found that all but one of the faculty members <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></note>

    <body>addressed all of the characteristics of quality credentials when designing a micro-credential. Also in our findings, all but <lb/>one of the faculty members considered and incorporated all of the characteristics of quality credentials when designing <lb/>a micro-credential. <lb/>5.1 Assessment qualities largely overlooked by faculty-designers of micro-credentials <lb/>Three characteristics of assessment were largely unmentioned by the faculty, &quot;Aligns with the Delivery Method, &quot; &quot;Clarity <lb/>of Outcomes and Criteria&quot; and &quot;Equity-Oriented. &quot; We acknowledge that not all six characteristics of quality assessment <lb/>need to be present in the design of a micro-credential, as a micro-credential may still function as an assessment if some <lb/>characteristics are missing. For instance, during the interviews, Dr. E, Dr. P, and Dr. D did not discuss whether or how they <lb/>addressed &quot;Alignment with the Delivery Method&quot; when designing a micro-credential. The absence of this principle does <lb/>not necessarily negate the functionality of a micro-credential as an assessment tool, however, misalignment with the <lb/>delivery method could dimmish the overall quality of a micro-credential. For example, a micro-credential delivered fully <lb/>online would be misaligned with its delivery method if the learners were required to take a paper-based quizzes and email <lb/>them to the instructor. While this type of misalignment would cause unnecessary burden, the micro-credential would <lb/>still function as an assessment. Alignment with the delivery method positively impacts the design of an assessment, and <lb/>therefore faculty should be supported in designing micro-credentials that are well-suited to their chosen delivery method. <lb/>&quot;Equity-Oriented&quot; is another quality of assessment that may not be present in all micro-credentials, but, when miss-<lb/>ing, may diminish the overall quality of a micro-credential. Equitable assessment was the least mentioned assessment <lb/>characteristic, discussed only by Dr. EL. The limited discussion regarding micro-credentials as equitable assessments was <lb/>surprising because micro-credentials are often publicized as opportunities to gain skills that are relevant to an individual&apos;s <lb/>goals. Equitable assessment involves learners as active participants in their own assessment and therefore is well-aligned <lb/>with this aim of &quot;individualizing&quot; learning. The limited discussion regarding micro-credentials as equitable assessments <lb/>was concerning because inequity is a major issue in the United States, one that pervades all aspects of society, including <lb/>education. We do not claim that micro-credentials are a solution to inequality or social injustices. We do, however, believe <lb/>that it is imperative that equity-oriented processes be incorporated into pedagogical practices. Therefore, faculty should <lb/>be supported in designing micro-credentials that focus on individual progress, and that welcome the voices of all learners. <lb/>&quot;Clarity of Outcomes and Criteria&quot; was also largely unaddressed, discussed only by Dr. EL, and Dr. L, but we believe this <lb/>is an important characteristic that may lead to damaging consequences if not included in the design of a micro-credential. <lb/>For students, if this characteristic is missing, and they are unable to understand the assessment criteria and expected <lb/>outcomes, then they may not be able to meet those outcomes and earn the micro-credential. For other stakeholders such <lb/>as employers, if this characteristic is missing then they would not be able to make an informed decision about the earner <lb/>(e.g., placing them in a job where the credentialed skill would be optimal). Faculty should be supported in developing <lb/>well-defined outcomes and clear criteria for a micro-credential, and also supported in making this information readily <lb/>accessible to stakeholders. <lb/>Given the scarcity of empirical research on micro-credential design it is not clear whether the assessment design quali-<lb/>ties examined in this study commonly characterize micro-credentials across varied contexts. Several conceptual papers <lb/>advocate for the importance of high-quality curriculum design in the realm of micro-credentials [3, 32, 37]; however, <lb/>there remains a scarcity of research concerning the application of principles and strategies to ensure this quality. For <lb/>example, Desmarchelier &amp; Cary [13] argue for equitable approaches to micro-credentials but do not examine specific <lb/>strategies for assuring equity, such as equity-oriented assessments, <lb/>5.2 Credential qualities applied by faculty-designers of micro-credentials <lb/>While few characteristics of quality assessments were consistently mentioned by the faculty, they consistently discussed <lb/>the characteristics of quality credentials. This was surprising, as we had speculated that faculty would be more focused <lb/>on assessment of learning than with credentialing. Our assumption was that faculty, when teaching, are asked to engage <lb/>in curriculum design and revision. Naturally, curriculum design must include assessment since it determines if students <lb/>meet the learning outcomes of the curriculum. Engaging in the design of credentials necessitates decision-making that <lb/>transcends the context of a course (i.e., &quot;What are the needs of employers?&quot; &quot;What skills do graduates need to be successful <lb/>in the workforce?&quot;). Although it is the responsibility of all faculty to consider and ensure credential-like goals when design-<lb/>ing curriculum, it is likely that faculty members have various levels of responsibility regarding credential-like goals. Some <lb/>instructional faculty may not have as much experience or knowledge concerning those goals than others (e.g., deans, <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <body>department chairs, registrars, experienced faculty members). Our study reveals that credential design was ubiquitously <lb/>perceived as an important aspect of designing a micro-credential. This suggests an unexpected result of micro-credential <lb/>design may be an expansion of faculty responsibilities into regular consideration of credentials, or a merging of faculty <lb/>and administrative duties regarding the use of micro-credentials outside of the original learning context. <lb/>We also note that while the credential quality of being &quot;Understood by Stakeholders&quot; was discussed by each of the <lb/>faculty members, the participants largely expressed doubt in both internal and external stakeholder understanding of <lb/>micro-credentials. For example, Dr. D, Dr. L, and Dr. EL voiced uncertainty about whether students see value in earning <lb/>micro-credentials. Similarly, both Dr. P and Dr. EL expressed doubts about how well employers understand micro-cre-<lb/>dentials. Each of these participants were cognizant of the need for stakeholders to understand micro-credentials, but <lb/>they either did not know how to design to address this quality or questioned their role in addressing this quality. This <lb/>suggests that stakeholder acceptance of micro-credentials is a perceived gap by faculty designers, and an area where <lb/>additional support is needed. <lb/>6 Limitations <lb/>We acknowledge that our research findings are constrained in their generalizability due to methodological limitations, <lb/>including the study&apos;s small sample size and the inherent constraints of a single-case research design. Research that <lb/>includes a larger dataset, including a range of institutions, is needed. <lb/>The use of interviews was critical to our study as this technique provided detailed information regarding faculty <lb/>perceptions and rich descriptions of their design decisions and processes, however, we acknowledge that self-reported <lb/>data introduces potential flaws to the study. It is possible that more design principles may have been integrated but <lb/>not broached in the interviews. We acknowledge that the use of additional data sources, and the triangulation of data <lb/>would have benefited this study. <lb/>7 Conclusion <lb/>The design principles investigated here, derived from empirical research on educational design in other learning contexts, <lb/>lay the groundwork for establishing a crucial knowledge base necessary for future micro-credential design research. Fur-<lb/>ther research is needed to refine these principles and to determine their applicability across other settings of higher edu-<lb/>cation. We anticipate that additional research will build upon this work, as it is likely that there are other principles that, <lb/>when integrated into the design of a micro-credential, may positively serve its assessment and credentialing affordances. <lb/>Our findings show that some critical design principles, particularly assessment design principles, were largely not <lb/>discussed, or not applied, by the faculty in this study. While there may be higher education institutions where faculty <lb/>have mastered the merger between assessment and credential when designing a micro-credential, based upon our <lb/>study some faculty may need support in recognizing and integrating quality assessment principles. For future research <lb/>we suggest the development and testing of interventions, such as trainings that focus on applying quality assessment <lb/>principles when designing a micro-credential. <lb/>Lastly, we would like to emphasize that all of the design principles examined in this study were extracted from the <lb/>literature and are not indicative of the authors&apos; views. For example, the literature pertaining to credentials is focused on <lb/>the workforce, and &quot;consumers&quot; of credentials are largely identified as employers and other individuals involved in hiring <lb/>(e.g., recruiters, hiring managers). We believe that this is a limiting framing of the purpose of credentials. Employment-<lb/>related goals are not the only aim of learners who pursue higher education. For a critical analysis see Wheelahan and <lb/>Moodie&apos;s [51] examination of micro-credentials as a tool to re-orient higher education curriculum towards a narrow focus <lb/>on employability. More research on the use of micro-credentials by other stakeholders, besides employers (e.g., admis-<lb/>sions officers), is needed to better understand how micro-credential design can be optimized for use in other contexts. <lb/></body>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions AR served as the project lead. For the data collection AR co-wrote the interview protocol, arranged the interviews and <lb/>co-conducted interviews. AR served as data custodian by safely storing and anonymizing data. AR led the data analysis by serving as initial <lb/>coder and developing the codebook. With input from co-authors, AR conducted the literature review and served as the primary author of <lb/>the manuscript. YK supported data collection by transcribing the interviews and following up with participants when clarity was needed. <lb/>YK participated in the data analysis by serving as second coder and editing the codebook. YK also participated in writing the manuscript by <lb/></div>

    <note place="footnote">Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Case Study <lb/>Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">providing substantive revisions. SA supported the data collection by co-writing the interview protocol and co-conducting the interviews <lb/>with AR. A3 also edited the manuscript and provided substantive feedback on revisions. All authors collaborated on the design of the study. <lb/>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant No. 1936947. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Data availability The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon request. <lb/>Code availability Not applicable. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate All standard practices for minimizing risk to participants were followed, including ethical guidelines <lb/>for data collection, protecting participants by using pseudonyms, and securing storage were followed. Analyzed data came from an internal <lb/>review of the studied programs. The university does not require a statement from an institutional ethics committee for such non-invasive work. <lb/>Consent for publication Faculty participants were informed of the potential for research outcomes and gave permission to use collected data. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

    <front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adapta-<lb/>tion, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, <lb/>provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article <lb/>are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in <lb/>the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will <lb/>need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. <lb/></front>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Abramovich S. Understanding digital badges in higher education through assessment. On the Horizon. 2016;24(1):126-31. <lb/>2. Adom D, Mensah JA, Dake DA. Test, measurement, and evaluation: Understanding and use of the concepts in education. Int J Eval Res <lb/>Educ. 2020;9(1):109-19. <lb/>3. Ahsan K, Akbar S, Kam B, Abdulrahman MDA. 2023. Implementation of micro-credentials in higher education: A systematic literature <lb/>review. Educ Inf Technol, pp.1-36. <lb/>4. Bingham AJ, Witkowsky P. 2021. Deductive and inductive approaches to qualitative data analysis. Analyzing and interpreting qualitative <lb/>data: After the interview, pp.133-146. <lb/>5. Boud D, Soler R. Sustainable assessment revisited. Assess Eval High Educ. 2016;41(3):400-13. <lb/>6. Boud D, Dawson P, Bearman M, Bennett S, Joughin G, Molloy E. Reframing assessment research: Through a practice perspective. Stud <lb/>High Educ. 2018;43(7):1107-18. <lb/>7. Brown M, McGreal R, Peters M. A strategic institutional response to micro-credentials: Key questions for educational leaders. J Interact <lb/>Media Educ. 2023;2023(1):1-17. <lb/>8. Bryan C, Clegg K. Innovative assessment in higher education: A handbook for academic practitioners. Oxfordshire: Routledge; 2019. <lb/>9. Campbell JL, Quincy C, Osserman J, Pedersen OK. Coding in-depth semi-structured interviews: Problems of unitization and intercoder <lb/>reliability and agreement. Sociol Methods Res. 2013;42(3):294-320. <lb/>10. Carey K, Stefaniak J. An exploration of the utility of digital badging in higher education settings. Educ Technol Res Dev. 2018;66(5):1211-29. <lb/>11. Cook, E. 2021. Practice-based engineering: Mathematical competencies and micro-credentials. International Journal of Research in <lb/>Undergraduate Mathematics Education, pp.1-22. <lb/>12. Crabtree BF, Miller WL. Doing qualitative research. California: Sage publications; 2023. <lb/>13. Desmarchelier R, Cary LJ. Toward just and equitable micro-credentials: An Australian perspective. Int J Educ Technol High Educ. <lb/>2022;19(1):1-12. <lb/>14. Dolin J, Black P, Harlen W, Tiberghien A. Exploring relations between formative and summative assessment. In: Dolin J, Evans R, editors. <lb/>Transforming assessment: through an interplay between practice, research and policy. Springer International; 2018. p. 53-80. <lb/>15. Duklas J. 2020. Micro-Credentials: Trends in credit transfer and credentialing. British Columbia Council on Admissions and Transfer. <lb/>16. Dunleavy M. Design principles for augmented reality learning. TechTrends. 2014;58(1):28-34. <lb/>17. Elliott R, Clayton J, Iwata J. 2014. Exploring the use of micro-credentialing and digital badges in learning environments to encourage <lb/>motivation to learn and achieve. In B. Hegarty, J. McDonald, &amp; S.-K. Loke (Eds.), Rhetoric and Reality: Critical perspectives on educational <lb/>technology. Proceedings ascilite Dunedin 2014, pp. 703-707. <lb/>18. Fowler C. Virtual reality and learning: Where is the pedagogy? Br J Educ Technol. 2015;46(2):412-22. <lb/>19. Gauthier T. The value of microcredentials: The employer&apos;s perspective. J Competency-Based Educ. 2020;5(2):1-6. <lb/>20. Gray JA, DiLoreto M. The effects of student engagement, student satisfaction, and perceived learning in online learning environments. <lb/>Int J Leadersh Educ. 2016;11(1): n1. <lb/>21. Groening C, Binnewies C. &quot;Achievement unlocked!&quot;-the impact of digital achievements as a gamification element on motivation and <lb/>performance. Comput Hum Behav. 2019;97:151-66. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Discover Education (2024) 3:16 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s44217-024-00100-2 <lb/>Case Study <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>22. Harlen W, James M. Assessment and learning: Differences and relationships between formative and summative assessment. Assess Educ. <lb/>1997;4(3):365-79. <lb/>23. Houston D, Thompson JN. Blending formative and summative assessment in a capstone subject: &apos;It&apos;s not your tools, it&apos;s how you use them. &apos; <lb/>J Univ Teach Learn Pract. 2017;14(3):2. <lb/>24. Isopahkala-Bouret U. &apos;It&apos;s considered a second class thing.&apos; The differences in status between traditional and newly established higher <lb/>education credentials. Stud High Educ. 2015;40(7):1291-306. <lb/>25. De St J, Jorre T. Sharing achievement through digital credentials: Are universities ready for the transparency afforded by a digital world? <lb/>Re-imagining Univ Assess Digital World. 2020;7:277. <lb/>26. Kiiskilä P, Kukkonen A, Pirkkalainen H. Are micro-credentials valuable for students? Perspective on verifiable digital credentials. SN Comput <lb/>Sci. 2023;4(4):366. <lb/>27. Maina MF, Guàrdia Ortiz L, Mancini F, Martinez Melo M. A micro-credentialing methodology for improved recognition of HE employability <lb/>skills. Int J Educ Technol High Educ. 2022;19(1):1-22. <lb/>28. Maxwell N, Gallagher S. Building a consistent terminology in the market for new credentials. New Dir Commun Coll. 2020;189:103-7. <lb/>29 Maire Q. Credential market: Mass schooling, academic power and the international baccalaureate diploma. Cham: Springer Nature; 2021. <lb/>30. Miller KK and Jorre De St Jorre T. 2022. Digital micro-credentials in environmental science: An employer perspective on valued evidence <lb/>of skills. Teach High Educ, pp. 1-17. <lb/>31. Nguyen TT, Walker M. Sustainable assessment for lifelong learning. Assess Eval High Educ. 2016;41(1):97-111. <lb/>32. Oliver B, 2019. Making micro-credentials work for learners, employers and providers. https:// dteach. deakin. edu. au/ wp-conte nt/ uploa <lb/>ds/ sites/ 103/ 2019/ 08/ Making-micro-crede ntials-work-Oliver-Deakin-2019-full-report. pdf. <lb/>33. Perea B. Using smaller credentials to build flexible degree completion and career pathways. New Dir Commun Coll. 2020;2020(189):23-37. <lb/>34 Peisachovich EH, Dubrowski A, Da Silva C, Kapralos B, Klein JE, Rahmanov Z, Peisachovich E. Using simulation-based methods to support <lb/>demonstration of competencies required by micro-credential courses. Cureus. 2021. https:// doi. org/ 10. 7759/ cureus. 16908. <lb/>35. Pereira D, Flores MA, Niklasson L. Assessment revisited: A review of research in assessment and evaluation in higher education. Assess <lb/>Eval High Educ. 2016;41(7):1008-32. <lb/>36. Pitt CR, Bell A, Strickman R, Davis K. Supporting learners&apos; STEM-oriented career pathways with digital badges. Inf Learn Sci. <lb/>2019;120(1):87-107. <lb/>37. Pollard V, Vincent A. Micro-credentials: A postdigital counternarrative. Postdigit Sci Educ. 2022;4(3):843-59. <lb/>38. Ruddy C, Ponte F. Preparing students for university studies and beyond: A micro-credential trial that delivers academic integrity aware-<lb/>ness. J Aust Libr Inf Assoc. 2019;68(1):56-67. <lb/>39. Sadler DR. 2014. Beyond feedback: Developing student capability in complex appraisal. In Approaches to assessment that enhance learning <lb/>in higher education (pp. 45-60). Routledge. <lb/>40. Schär F, Mösli F. Blockchain diplomas: Using smart contracts to secure academic credentials. J Higher Educ. 2019;41(3):48-58. <lb/>41. Selvaratnam RM, Sankey MD. An integrative literature review of the implementation of micro-credentials in higher education: Implica-<lb/>tions for practice in Australasia. J Teach Learn Grad Employab. 2021;12(1):1-17. <lb/>42. Sewagegn AA. Learning objective and assessment linkage: Its contribution to meaningful student learning. Univers J Educ Res. <lb/>2020;8(11):5044-52. <lb/>43 Shields CM. Transformative leadership in education: Equitable and socially just change in an uncertain and complex world. Oxfordshire: <lb/>Routledge; 2017. <lb/>44. Schellekens LH, Bok HG, de Jong LH, van der Schaaf MF, Kremer WD, van der Vleuten CP. A scoping review on the notions of assessment <lb/>as learning (AaL), assessment for learning (AfL), and assessment of learning (AoL). Stud Educ Eval. 2021;71:1-15. <lb/>45. Taylor SC, Soares L. Quality assurance for the new credentialing market. New Dir Community Coll. 2020;2020(189):67-82. <lb/>46. Tinsley B, Cacicio S, Shah Z, Parker D, Younge O, Luke Luna C. 2022. Micro-credentials for social mobility in rural postsecondary communi-<lb/>ties: A landscape report. Digital Promise. <lb/>47. Tractenberg RE. The assessment evaluation rubric: Promoting learning and learner-centered teaching through assessment in face-to-face <lb/>or distanced higher education. Educ Sci. 2021;11(8):441. <lb/>48. Varadarajan S, Koh JHL, Daniel BK. A systematic review of the opportunities and challenges of micro-credentials for multiple stakeholders: <lb/>Learners, employers, higher education institutions and government. Int J Educ Technol High Educ. 2023;20(1):1-24. <lb/>49. West RE, Randall DL. The case for rigor in open badges. In: Muilenburg LY, Berge ZL (Eds). Digital badges in education: trends, issues, and <lb/>cases. Routledge; 2016. p. 21-9. <lb/>50. West-Puckett S. Making classroom writing assessment more visible, equitable, and portable through digital badging. Coll Engl. <lb/>2016;79(2):127-51. <lb/>51. Wheelahan L, Moodie G. Analysing micro-credentials in higher education: A Bernsteinian analysis. J Curric Stud. 2021;53(2):212-28. <lb/>52. Xu D, Trimble M. What about certificates? Evidence on the labor market returns to nondegree community college awards in two states. <lb/>Educ Eval Pol Anal. 2016;38(2):272-92. <lb/>53. Yin RK. Case study research: Design and methods. Thousand Oaks: Sage; 2014. <lb/>54. Zhou X. Equalization or selection? Reassessing the &quot;meritocratic power&quot; of a college degree in intergenerational income mobility. Am <lb/>Socio Rev. 2019;84(3):459-85. <lb/></listBibl>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </div>

  </text>

</TEI>