<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T11:24:24.292Z">11/14/2025 11:24:24 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T11:24:13.234126Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T11:24:13.234126Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Comparing preferences to evaluations of <lb/>barrier self-efficacy for two strength training <lb/>programs in US older adults <lb/>Jordan D. Kurth ID <lb/>1,2 <lb/>*, Christopher N. Sciamanna 1,2 , Cheyenne Herrell ID <lb/>1,2 , <lb/>Matthew Moeller 1,2 , Jonathan G. Stine 3 <lb/>1 Penn State University, University Park, PA, United States of America, 2 Penn State College of Medicine, <lb/>Hershey, PA, United States of America, 3 Penn State Health-Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, Hershey, <lb/>PA, United States of America <lb/>* jdk5930@psu.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background/Objectives <lb/>Engagement in regular physical activity is one of the best strategies for older adults to <lb/>remain healthy. Unfortunately, only 35% of older adults meet guidelines for muscle strength-<lb/>ening activities. Eliciting participant preferences is one possible way to improve physical <lb/>activity engagement. However, other sources of participant input to improve uptake and <lb/>maintenance remain uninvestigated. This study compared preferences to self-efficacy rat-<lb/>ings for two strength training programs. <lb/>Methods <lb/>We conducted a national cross-sectional survey of 611 US adults over age 65. We com-<lb/>pared two participant evaluations (the preferred program and the program for which they <lb/>had higher barrier self-efficacy) of two hypothetical strength training programs (45 minutes <lb/>performed three times per week (traditional) and 5 minutes performed daily (brief)). <lb/>Results <lb/>Most participants (68%) preferred the brief strength training program. The difference in self-<lb/>efficacy ratings was an average of 1.2 (SD = 0.92). One in five participants preferred a <lb/>strength training program for which they had less self-efficacy; nearly all of these partici-<lb/>pants (92%) preferred the traditional strength training program but had more self-efficacy for <lb/>the brief strength training program. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Older adults reported preferring and having more self-efficacy for a brief compared to a tra-<lb/>ditional strength training program. Differences in self-efficacy ratings between the two <lb/>strength training programs were large. Preferences were often not congruent with ratings of <lb/>self-efficacy. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/>1 / 9 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Kurth JD, Sciamanna CN, Herrell C, <lb/>Moeller M, Stine JG (2024) Comparing preferences <lb/>to evaluations of barrier self-efficacy for two <lb/>strength training programs in US older adults. <lb/>PLoS ONE 19(5): e0302892. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 <lb/>Editor: Sohel Ahmed, Ahmed Physiotherapy and <lb/>Research Center, BANGLADESH <lb/>Received: January 31, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: April 15, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 9, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Kurth et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data associated with <lb/>this study is available via Penn State Data <lb/>Commons at https://doi.org/10.26208/Q1KB-<lb/>AW67. <lb/>Significance/Implications <lb/>Preferences for strength training programming may not always reflect the program most <lb/>likely to be maintained. Future investigations should evaluate differences in behavioral <lb/>uptake, maintenance, and outcomes from two comparative strength training interventions <lb/>using preferences and self-efficacy. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Engagement in regular physical activity (PA) is one of the best strategies for adults over the age <lb/>of 65 to preserve mobility, reduce falls risk, and remain both physically and mentally healthy <lb/>[1-5]. Unfortunately, 31% of U.S. older adults report performing zero physical activity in their <lb/>leisure time, and only 23% report meeting both the Centers for Disease Control and Preven-<lb/>tion guidelines for aerobic activity (150 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity per <lb/>week) and the recommendations for muscle strengthening activities (two days per week) [6]. <lb/>Thus, a need exists to enhance current physical activity promotion efforts among older adults. <lb/>One possible physical activity promotion effort is to align characteristics (e.g., duration, fre-<lb/>quency, mode of physical activity, reward structure) of physical activity programs with the <lb/>preferences of the participants. There have been numerous examples of physical activity pref-<lb/>erence identification, particularly in community-dwelling older adults and clinical popula-<lb/>tions, such as those with chronic joint pain [7-10]. Despite the intuitive appeal of this <lb/>approach, there is limited evidence to support its influence on increasing regular physical <lb/>activity engagement [11-13]. Additionally, preferences are often operationally defined as &quot;a <lb/>predisposition to like a particular type of or context for physical activity more than others and <lb/>to choose it when given the opportunity [emphasis added]&quot; [14]. This definition, and much of <lb/>the evidence that does exist surrounding the influence of preference alignment in physical <lb/>activities, often evaluates self-selection [12,13] instead of preference alignment [11]. While the <lb/>connection between allowing an individual to self-select program characteristics and improved <lb/>affective response is well-established [15,16], this is of limited value when attempting to design <lb/>a large, prescribed, scalable physical activity program. What we do know about expressed pref-<lb/>erences generally suggests that they evolve across social and environmental contexts, and in <lb/>some cases may be difficult to articulate prior to a relevant experience [17]. Additionally, they <lb/>may be susceptible to repeated exposure to or familiarity with the stimuli being presented [18-<lb/>20], thereby calling into question their utility in informing program design, particularly with <lb/>relatively low-active populations that are frequently targeted. <lb/>The goal of most physical activity programming is long-term engagement in the behavior, <lb/>or maintenance, as repeated performance is required to reap the benefits associated with phys-<lb/>ical activity. Identifying factors associated with maintenance of regular physical activity-and <lb/>in fact even defining the phenomenon of &quot;maintenance&quot; itself-remains an active pursuit of <lb/>both research and clinical practice [21]. However, of what is known, self-efficacy (SE; the level <lb/>of confidence in one&apos;s capability to engage in the behavior) is to-date perhaps the single most <lb/>well-established predictor of physical activity engagement and maintenance according to sys-<lb/>tematic reviews and meta-analyses [22-25]. As such, designing programs that maximize <lb/>known predictors of long-term physical activity engagement such as self-efficacy may promote <lb/>long-term behavior performance. One novel method by which this might be accomplished is <lb/>to use the evaluation of program characteristics rated using a known predictor of physical <lb/>activity maintenance (i.e., self-efficacy) in place of the traditional rating of preference [26]. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <front>Funding: The author(s) received no specific <lb/>funding for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/>following competing interests: Christopher <lb/>Sciamanna has an investment, such as stock, in a <lb/>company which has begun to investigate the <lb/>possibility of creating a business that provides <lb/>exercise programs. All other authors declare that <lb/>they have no known competing financial interests <lb/>or personal relationships that could have appeared <lb/>to influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></front>

    <body>Therefore, this study aimed to compare two hypothetical evaluations: [1] preferred strength <lb/>training program (5-minute daily program vs. 45-minute program performed 3 times per week) <lb/>and [2] barrier self-efficacy for each respective program in a population of adults over the age of <lb/>65 years. We hypothesized that most participants would prefer the shorter, more frequent train-<lb/>ing program, and have higher self-efficacy for that same program. We also hypothesized that <lb/>most participants would report preferring a program for which they had higher self-efficacy. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>This institutional review board exempted study (Penn State University IRB# <lb/>STUDY00022306) used an anonymous online cross-sectional survey to inform the design of <lb/>strength training programs in adults over 65 years of age with varying levels of health status <lb/>and comorbidities. Throughout this manuscript, the reporting of data are in-line with the <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) guidelines <lb/>for observational cross-sectional studies [27]. The survey was conducted using a commercial <lb/>survey company (Qualtrics). Qualtrics uses a network of survey participants from many sup-<lb/>pliers with a range of recruitment methodologies from across the US. Participants are sourced <lb/>from different methods depending on the supplier, including advertisements and promotions <lb/>on smartphones, referrals from membership lists, social networks, mobile games, banner <lb/>advertisements, mail-based recruitment campaigns and others [28,29]. The survey was esti-<lb/>mated to take 5-10 minutes to complete and all participants were compensated. To ensure <lb/>data quality, surveys included [1] attention checks (i.e., factual questions with correct answers) <lb/>and [2] speeding checks (i.e., eliminating responses from those who completed the online sur-<lb/>vey in less than one-third the median duration of survey completion). <lb/>Participants <lb/>Participants were required to be at least 65 years of age, located in the United States, and fluent <lb/>in the English language. Additional target demographic quotas were placed on recruitment to <lb/>ensure a sample representative of the population over 65 years of age in the US. Target demo-<lb/>graphic quotas were placed on sex (50% male/50% female) and race/ethnicity (55% non-White <lb/>Hispanic, 15% African American, 15% Asian American, 15% Alaskan Native/Native Hawaiian; <lb/>10% Hispanic). A target minimum of 556 participants (278 per preferred program) were <lb/>planned to be enrolled in order to be able to detect a small (Cohen&apos;s d = 0.2) difference at 90% <lb/>power at an α = 0.05 within each preference group. Data collection occurred between April 3, <lb/>2023 and May 31, 2023. The need for consent was waived by the institutional review board, as <lb/>data was collected anonymously. <lb/>Instruments and measures <lb/>Demographic information. Smoking status was assessed using a single item adapted <lb/>from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS), &quot;Do you use a tobacco product <lb/>every day?&quot; [30]. Medical history was assessed using questions (also from BRFSS) assessing <lb/>presence or absence of: diabetes, high cholesterol, heart disease, osteoporosis, hypertension, <lb/>stroke, and arthritis, as well as the frequency of strength training [30]. Demographic and <lb/>anthropometric characteristics, such as age, gender, race, ethnicity, height, and weight were <lb/>assessed, and body mass index (BMI) was calculated using the standard formula. <lb/>Strength training program preference. Strength training program preference was <lb/>assessed by asking the following, &quot;We are designing a strength training program for people over <lb/>65 to use at home, to improve their physical function, ability to walk and to reduce falls. Assum-<lb/>ing that all programs include similar types of exercises, which would you prefer?&quot; Participants <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>were given two strength training program options from which to choose: &quot;5 minutes, every <lb/>day&quot; or &quot;45 minutes, 3 times per week&quot;. The order of these answer options was randomized for <lb/>each participant. <lb/>Strength training program self-efficacy. Self-efficacy for each strength training program <lb/>was assessed using a 5-item, 5-point Likert scale (Not at all confident to Extremely confident) <lb/>[31] to respond to the prompt &quot;Regardless of your previous selection, please answer the following <lb/>regarding a strength training program performed [45 minutes, 3 days per week OR 5 minutes, <lb/>every day]. How confident are you that you could complete this program under each of the fol-<lb/>lowing conditions over the next 12 months? I could exercise for [45 minutes, 3 times per week OR <lb/>5 minutes, each day. . .]&quot;. The order of the presentation of each program&apos;s scale was also ran-<lb/>domized for each participant. The five items evaluated by each participant were: &quot;when I am <lb/>tired.&quot;, &quot;when I am in a bad mood.&quot;, &quot;when I feel I do not have the time.&quot;, &quot;when I am on vaca-<lb/>tion.&quot;, and &quot;during bad weather (i.e., raining or snowing).&quot;. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Participants were grouped by their expressed strength training program preference. Addition-<lb/>ally, two mean self-efficacy scores, one for the 5-minute daily program and one for the 45-min-<lb/>ute program performed three days per week, were then calculated for each participant. These <lb/>two scores were then compared; where applicable, the program for which participants reported <lb/>higher SE was identified as the program for which the participant had the most self-efficacy. <lb/>The distribution of these two variables (program preference and higher/lower/equal self-effi-<lb/>cacy) were then cross-tabulated for comparison. <lb/>Results <lb/>Participant profile <lb/>A total of 1,162 of the participants that were screened met inclusion criteria. Data from partici-<lb/>pants that did not complete the survey (n = 438) were excluded from the final sample. Addi-<lb/>tionally, participants whose demographic quotas were filled before they completed their <lb/>survey (n = 95), that completed the survey too quickly (less than half of the median complete <lb/>time; n = 9), that failed the attention check (n = 5), or that were identified as bots using embed-<lb/>ded survey fields (n = 4) were removed. Therefore, the final sample size included 611 partici-<lb/>pants (Fig 1). A demographic summary of the 611 participants that completed the survey is <lb/>provided in Table 1. Of note, the mean participant age was 72 years. Approximately half of par-<lb/>ticipants were female. Racial and ethnic distributions were representative of the US population <lb/>over the age of 65 [32]. <lb/>Description of strength training program preference and self-efficacy <lb/>Most participants (68%) expressed preference for the 5-minute daily strength training pro-<lb/>gram over the 45-minute program completed three times per week. Even more participants <lb/>(80%) reported having more self-efficacy for the 5-minute, daily program compared to the <lb/>45-minute program completed three days per week. The mean absolute difference in program <lb/>self-efficacy rating was 1.2 (SD = 0.92; Cohen&apos;s d = 1.3). <lb/>Congruence of strength training program preference and self-efficacy <lb/>rating <lb/>Most participants&apos; (402/611; 66%) expressed strength training program preference was con-<lb/>gruent with the program for which they had the most self-efficacy. However, more than 1 in 5 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 1. Participant flow diagram. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892.g001 <lb/>Table 1. Participant characteristics. <lb/>Total (N = 611) <lb/>Mean(SD) or n(%) <lb/>Age, years <lb/>72.4 (5.1) <lb/>Sex, female, n <lb/>294 (48.1) <lb/>Race, White, n <lb/>341 (55.8) <lb/>Race, Black, n <lb/>102 (16.7) <lb/>Ethnicity, Hispanic, n <lb/>62 (10.2) <lb/>Body Mass Index, kg/m 2 <lb/>27.7 (7.0) <lb/>Strength Training, days/week <lb/>1.4 (2.1) <lb/>Daily Tobacco Use, n <lb/>64 (10.5) <lb/>Diabetes, n <lb/>152 (25.2) <lb/>High Cholesterol, n <lb/>338 (56.5) <lb/>Heart Disease, n <lb/>787 (14.6) <lb/>Osteoporosis, n <lb/>100 (17.0) <lb/>Hypertension, n <lb/>375 (62.1) <lb/>Stroke, n <lb/>40 (6.6) <lb/>Arthritis, n <lb/>295 (49.4) <lb/>Prefer 5-min, daily program, n <lb/>380 (68.4) <lb/>Higher SE for 5-min, daily program, n <lb/>490 (80.2) <lb/>Note. SE = self-efficacy. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>participants (130/611; 21.3%) expressed a strength training program preference that was <lb/>incongruent with the program for which they reported higher self-efficacy. Nearly all (370/ <lb/>418; 89%) participants who reported preferring the 5-minute daily program also had higher <lb/>self-efficacy for that same program, whereas only 17% of participants (32/193) who reported <lb/>preferring the 45-minute program completed 3 days per week also had higher self-efficacy for <lb/>the 45-minute program. Approximately 13% (79/611) participants reported the same self-effi-<lb/>cacy for both programs, reporting nearly equal preferences for each (n = 41 vs. n = 38; <lb/>Table 2). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, consistent with our hypothesis, more than 2 in 3 adults over the age of 65 <lb/>expressed a preference for a 5-minute daily strength training program compared to a 45-min-<lb/>ute program completed three times per week. Also consistent with our hypothesis, more than <lb/>80% of participants reported higher self-efficacy for the 5-minute program. Two in three par-<lb/>ticipants preferred the program for which they had higher self-efficacy. However, more than <lb/>four out of every five participants that preferred the 45-minute program had higher self-effi-<lb/>cacy for the 5-minute program. <lb/>The present study suggests that elicited preferences are often not congruent with ratings of <lb/>self-efficacy. The impact of this discrepancy between preference selection and higher self-effi-<lb/>cacy ratings on long-term behavior remains unknown. Given that most participants who pre-<lb/>ferred the 45-minute program had higher self-efficacy for the 5-minute program, and that the <lb/>45-minute program structure is the most commonly offered, the potential impact of designing <lb/>self-efficacy driven programs could be large. What is known is that the literature supporting <lb/>the positive effects of self-efficacy [22-25] is much stronger than the literature supporting the <lb/>effects of preference selection [11-13]. <lb/>Additionally, preferences are known to not necessarily arise directly from cognitions [20]. <lb/>In other words, they are rife with influence from irrelevant and/or counterproductive sources-<lb/>such as emotional states and repeated exposure to or familiarity with the stimuli being pre-<lb/>sented [18-20]. Standard physical activity programs are typically 45-60 minutes performed <lb/>three days per week. This is one possible factor that may have led some participants to report <lb/>preferring the 45-minute program despite having higher self-efficacy for the 5-minute pro-<lb/>gram. While self-efficacy is not immune to emotional influence [33], that emotional influence <lb/>is theoretically more directly relevant to the activity in question. For those reasons, soliciting <lb/>evaluations of possible program options on known predictors of the target behavior (in this <lb/>case self-efficacy for physical activity maintenance) instead of preference may lead to more <lb/>effective decision-making by intervention designers targeting physical activity maintenance. <lb/>This is a preliminary investigation into asking for program evaluations using a known pre-<lb/>dictor of the target behavior (in this case, barrier self-efficacy for physical activity) instead of <lb/>preference. This study is not intended to suggest that a 5-minute daily strength training <lb/>Table 2. Cross-tabulation of preference and higher self-efficacy rating. <lb/>Self-Efficacy Rating Higher for 45-minute, 3 <lb/>Times per Week <lb/>Self-Efficacy Rating Higher for <lb/>5-minute, Daily <lb/>Self-Efficacy Rating Equal for Both <lb/>Programs <lb/>Prefer 45-minute, 3 Times per <lb/>Week Program <lb/>32 (5.2%) <lb/>120 (19.6%) <lb/>41 (6.7%) <lb/>Prefer 5-minute, Daily Program <lb/>10 (1.6%) <lb/>370 (60.6%) <lb/>38 (6.2%) <lb/>Note. Percentages are relative to the total sample (N = 611). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892.t002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>workout is the best strength training format for older adults or that it is better than a 45-min-<lb/>ute program completed three times per week. Further exploration into alternative/additional <lb/>program details, the number of options presented, and how those programs are described is <lb/>required. Most importantly, investigation also needs to be done to evaluate differences in <lb/>actual behavioral uptake, maintenance, and outcomes that arise from two comparative inter-<lb/>ventions: one designed using participant preferences and one designed using a known predic-<lb/>tor of maintenance. <lb/>This study has several limitations. First, only two program options were evaluated; informa-<lb/>tion about any alternative program options that may be preferable or elicit higher self-efficacy <lb/>evaluations is not available. Second, the relevance of the difference in self-efficacy, though <lb/>large (Cohen&apos;s d = 1.3), is unclear. While one program was often rated higher than the other <lb/>and dichotomized as the program for which self-efficacy was higher, the magnitude of that dif-<lb/>ference varied by participant. Finally, the impact of preference and self-efficacy evaluations <lb/>was not evaluated by assessing actual behavior uptake, maintenance, or outcomes. It remains <lb/>unclear if there is a behavioral or outcome-based difference between preference and self-effi-<lb/>cacy-designed programs. <lb/>This study also has multiple strengths. Sampling quotas allowed for a demographically-rep-<lb/>resentative sample of the US population over the age of 65 years based on the characteristics of <lb/>sex, race, and ethnicity-overcoming a well-documented limitation of exercise promotion <lb/>research historically [34]. Additionally, data was collected using a digital, anonymous survey, <lb/>thereby reducing-though not eliminating-self-selection bias common in physical activity <lb/>research. Additionally the presentation of the self-efficacy questions and preference answer <lb/>options were presented randomly to eliminate order effects. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In this novel study directly comparing preferences and self-efficacy, adults over the age of 65 <lb/>years reported preferring a 5-minute daily strength training program compared to a 45-minute <lb/>program performed three times per week. Most participants also reported higher self-efficacy <lb/>for that program. However, 1 in 5 older adults preferred a program for which they had lower <lb/>self-efficacy than the alternative; nearly all of these participants preferred the 45-minute pro-<lb/>gram but had lower self-efficacy for it. This evidence suggests that expressed preferences for <lb/>physical activity programming may not always reflect the program most likely to be main-<lb/>tained. Soliciting evaluations of possible program options on known predictors of the target <lb/>behavior (in this case self-efficacy for physical activity maintenance) instead of preference may <lb/>lead to more effective decision-making by intervention designers targeting physical activity <lb/>maintenance. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. STROBE statement-checklist of items that should be included in reports of <lb/>cross-sectional studies. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna, Cheyenne Herrell, Matthew <lb/>Moeller, Jonathan G. Stine. <lb/>Formal analysis: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Methodology: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna. <lb/>Project administration: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna. <lb/>Visualization: Jordan D. Kurth. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna, Cheyenne Herrell, <lb/>Matthew Moeller, Jonathan G. Stine. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Jordan D. Kurth, Christopher N. Sciamanna, Cheyenne Herrell, <lb/>Matthew Moeller, Jonathan G. Stine. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Fishman EI, Steeves JA, Zipunnikov V, Koster A, Berrigan D, Harris TA, et al. Association between <lb/>objectively measured physical activity and mortality in nhanes. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2016 Jul; 48 <lb/>(7):1303-11. https://doi.org/10.1249/MSS.0000000000000885 PMID: 26848889 <lb/>2. Rabel M, Meisinger C, Peters A, Holle R, Laxy M. The longitudinal association between change in phys-<lb/>ical activity, weight, and health-related quality of life: Results from the population-based KORA S4/F4/ <lb/>FF4 cohort study. PLoS ONE. 2017 Sep 27; 12(9):1-13. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0185205 <lb/>PMID: 28953956 <lb/>3. Rietdyk S, Ambike S, Amireault S, Haddad JM, Lin G, Newton D, et al. Co-occurrences of fall-related <lb/>factors in adults aged 60 to 85 years in the United States National Health and Nutrition Examination Sur-<lb/>vey. PLOS ONE. 2022 Nov 8; 17(11):e0277406. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0277406 PMID: <lb/>36346815 <lb/>4. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 2018 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans, 2nd <lb/>edition. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office; 2018. 118 p. <lb/>5. White RL, Babic MJ, Parker PD, Lubans DR, Astell-Burt T, Lonsdale C. Domain-specific physical activ-<lb/>ity and mental health: A meta-analysis. Am J Prev Med. 2017 May 1; 52(5):653-66. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.amepre.2016.12.008 PMID: 28153647 <lb/>6. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and <lb/>Health Promotion, Division of Nutrition, Physical Activity, and Obesity. 2023 [cited 2023 May 25]. Data, <lb/>Trend and Maps [online]. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/dnpao/data-trends-maps/index. <lb/>html <lb/>7. Brown DS, Finkelstein EA, Brown DR, Buchner DM, Johnson FR. Estimating older adults&apos; preferences <lb/>for walking programs via conjoint analysis. Am J Prev Med. 2009 Mar 1; 36(3):201-207.e4. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.amepre.2008.10.014 PMID: 19215845 <lb/>8. de Guzman AB, Jatulan EHM, Jimenez JACA. Explicating Physical Activity Preferences of Community-<lb/>Dwelling Filipino Elderly in Urban and Rural Settings: A Conjoint Analysis. Educ Gerontol. 2015 Apr 3; <lb/>41(4):251-66. <lb/>9. Pinto D, Bockenholt U, Lee J, Chang RW, Sharma L, Finn DJ, et al. Preferences for physical activity: A <lb/>conjoint analysis involving people with chronic knee pain. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2019 Feb 1; 27 <lb/>(2):240-7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joca.2018.10.002 PMID: 30336210 <lb/>10. Wilcox S, King AC, Brassington GS, Ahn DK. Physical Activity Preferences of Middle-Aged and Older <lb/>Adults: A Community Analysis. J Aging Phys Act. 1999 Oct 1; 7(4):386-99. <lb/>11. Parfitt G, Gledhill C. The effect of choice of exercise mode on psychological responses. Psychol Sport <lb/>Exerc. 2004 Apr 1; 5(2):111-7. <lb/>12. Stewart AL, Verboncoeur CJ, McLellan BY, Gillis DE, Rush S, Mills KM, et al. Physical Activity Out-<lb/>comes of CHAMPS II: A Physical Activity Promotion Program for Older Adults. J Gerontol A Biol Sci <lb/>Med Sci. 2001 Aug; 56(8):M465-70. https://doi.org/10.1093/gerona/56.8.m465 PMID: 11487597 <lb/>13. Thompson CE, Wankel LM. The Effects of Perceived Activity Choice upon Frequency of Exercise <lb/>Behavior. J Appl Soc Psychol. 1980; 10(5):436-43. <lb/>14. Amireault S, Baier JM, Spencer JR. Physical Activity Preferences Among Older Adults: A Systematic <lb/>Review. J Aging Phys Act. 2018; 27(1):128-39. https://doi.org/10.1123/japa.2017-0234 PMID: <lb/>29283793 <lb/>15. Ekkekakis P. Let them roam free? Physiological and psychological evidence for the potential of self-<lb/>selected exercise intensity in public health. Sports Med Auckl NZ. 2009; 39(10):857-88. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.2165/11315210-000000000-00000 PMID: 19757863 <lb/>16. Ekkekakis P, Lind E. Exercise does not feel the same when you are overweight: the impact of self-<lb/>selected and imposed intensity on affect and exertion. Int J Obes. 2006 Apr; 30(4):652-60. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>17. Dhar R, Novemsky N. Beyond rationality: The content of preferences. J Consum Psychol. 2008 Jul 1; <lb/>18(3):175-8. <lb/>18. Harrison AA. Mere Exposure. In: Berkowitz L, editor. Advances in Experimental Social Psychology <lb/>[Internet]. Academic Press; 1977 [cited 2023 Aug 15]. p. 39-83. Available from: https://www. <lb/>sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0065260108603548 <lb/>19. Zajonc RB. Attitudinal effects of mere exposure. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1968; 9(2, Pt.2):1-27. <lb/>20. Zajonc RB. Feeling and thinking: Preferences need no inferences. Am Psychol. 1980; 35(2):151-75. <lb/>21. Dunton GF, Leventhal AM, Rebar AL, Gardner B, Intille SS, Rothman AJ. Towards consensus in con-<lb/>ceptualizing and operationalizing physical activity maintenance. Psychol Sport Exerc. 2022 Jul 1; <lb/>61:102214. <lb/>22. Amireault S, Godin G, Ve ´zina-Im LA. Determinants of physical activity maintenance: a systematic <lb/>review and meta-analyses. Health Psychol Rev. 2013 Mar 1; 7(1):55-91. <lb/>23. McAuley E, Jerome GJ, Elavsky S, Marquez DX, Ramsey SN. Predicting long-term maintenance of <lb/>physical activity in older adults. Prev Med. 2003 Aug 1; 37(2):110-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0091-<lb/>7435(03)00089-6 PMID: 12855210 <lb/>24. McAuley E, Blissmer B. Self-Efficacy Determinants and Consequences of Physical Activity. Exerc Sport <lb/>Sci Rev. 2000 Apr; 28(2):85. PMID: 10902091 <lb/>25. Young MD, Plotnikoff RC, Collins CE, Callister R, Morgan PJ. Social cognitive theory and physical activ-<lb/>ity: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Obes Rev Off J Int Assoc Study Obes. 2014 Dec; 15 <lb/>(12):983-95. https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.12225 PMID: 25428600 <lb/>26. Kurth JD, Klenosky DB, Kao SC, Ruiz Y. Factors impacting the anticipated pleasure of potential physi-<lb/>cal activity experiences: a conjoint investigation across involvement segments. Int J Sport Exerc Psy-<lb/>chol. 2023 Apr 13;1-16. <lb/>27. von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP, et al. The Strengthen-<lb/>ing the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for report-<lb/>ing observational studies. J Clin Epidemiol. 2008 Apr; 61(4):344-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi. <lb/>2007.11.008 PMID: 18313558 <lb/>28. Miller CA, Guidry JPD, Dahman B, Thomson MD. A Tale of Two Diverse Qualtrics Samples: Information <lb/>for Online Survey Researchers. Cancer Epidemiol Biomark Prev Publ Am Assoc Cancer Res Cospon-<lb/>sored Am Soc Prev Oncol. 2020 Apr; 29(4):731-5. https://doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-19-0846 <lb/>PMID: 32066616 <lb/>29. Peer E, Rothschild D, Gordon A, Evernden Z, Damer E. Data quality of platforms and panels for online <lb/>behavioral research. Behav Res Methods. 2022 Aug; 54(4):1643-62. https://doi.org/10.3758/s13428-<lb/>021-01694-3 PMID: 34590289 <lb/>30. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System Survey Ques-<lb/>tionnaire [Internet]. Atlanta, Georgia: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Dis-<lb/>ease Control and Prevention; 2021 [cited 2023 Aug 14]. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/brfss/ <lb/>questionnaires/index.htm <lb/>31. Marcus BH, Selby VC, Niaura RS, Rossi JS. Self-Efficacy and the Stages of Exercise Behavior Change. <lb/>Res Q Exerc Sport. 1992 Mar 1; 63(1):60-6. https://doi.org/10.1080/02701367.1992.10607557 PMID: <lb/>1574662 <lb/>32. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 2021 Profile of Older Americans [Internet]. 2022 [cited <lb/>2023 Jun 12]. Available from: https://acl.gov/aging-and-disability-in-america/data-and-research/profile-<lb/>older-americans <lb/>33. Bandura A. Health promotion from the perspective of social cognitive theory. Psychol Health. 1998 Jul <lb/>1; 13(4):623-49. <lb/>34. Dorsch TE, Blazo JA, Delli Paoli AG, Hardiman AL. We know what we know, but from whom did we <lb/>learn it? A sociodemographic history of participant characteristics and reporting practices in sport and <lb/>exercise psychology. Psychol Sport Exerc. 2023 Nov 1; 69:102504. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>psychsport.2023.102504 PMID: 37665939 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Comparing preferences to ratings of self-efficacy <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302892 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 9 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>