<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Construct prognostic models of multiple myeloma with pathway information incorporated</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shuo</forename>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>ShanJin</forename>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Wei</forename>
          <surname>Pan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>YuYang</forename>
          <surname>Yi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Junyan</forename>
          <surname>Lu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T10:20:46.548Z">11/13/2025 10:20:46 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012444</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Shuo Wang, ShanJin Wang, Wei Pan, YuYang Yi, Junyan Lu. (2024). Construct prognostic models of multiple myeloma with pathway information incorporated. PLOS Computational Biology, 20(9), e1012444. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012444</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T10:17:00.901642Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T10:17:00.901642Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Perceptuo-affective organization of touched <lb/>materials in younger and older adults <lb/>Knut DrewingID* <lb/>HapLab, Institute for Psychology, Justus-Liebig University, Giessen, Germany <lb/>* Knut.Drewing@psychol.uni-giessen.de <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In everyday interaction we touch different materials, which we experience along a limited <lb/>number of perceptual and emotional dimensions: For instances, a furry surface feels soft <lb/>and pleasant, whereas sandpaper feels rough and unpleasant. In a previous study, younger <lb/>adults manually explored a representative set of solid, fluid and granular materials. Their rat-<lb/>ings were made along six perceptual dimensions (roughness, fluidity, granularity, deform-<lb/>ability, fibrousness, heaviness) and three emotional ones (valence, arousal, dominance). <lb/>Perceptual and emotional dimensions were systematically correlated. Here, we wondered <lb/>how this perceptuo-affective organization of touched materials depends on age, given that <lb/>older adults show decline in haptic abilities, in particular detail perception. 30 younger partic-<lb/>ipants (~22 years, half females) and 15 older participants (~66 years) explored 25 materials <lb/>using 18 perceptual and 9 emotional adjectives. We extracted 6 perceptual and 2 emotional <lb/>dimensions. Older and younger adults showed similar dimensions. However, in younger <lb/>participants roughness and granularity judgments were done separately, while they were <lb/>collapsed in a single dimension in older people. Further, age groups differed in the percep-<lb/>tion of roughness, granularity and valence, and older people did not show a positive correla-<lb/>tion between valence and granularity as did younger people. As expected, control analyses <lb/>between young males and females did not reveal similar gender differences. Overall, the <lb/>results demonstrate that older people organize and experience materials partly differently <lb/>from younger people, which we lead back to sensory decline. However, other aspects of <lb/>perceptual organization that also include fine perception are preserved into older age. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>In daily life we interact with a number of different materials, such as sand, silicone or suntan <lb/>oil. In our haptic representations, we judge these materials according to a limited number of <lb/>salient perceptual dimensions, often including, e.g., roughness or deformability characteristics. <lb/>At the same time we relate the materials&apos; perceptual properties to emotional responses and <lb/>probably also behaviours. Most of us describe a baby&apos;s skin or a rabbit&apos;s fur as feeling pleasant <lb/>and aim to approach it, whereas the feel of coarse sandpaper or raw wood rather elicits nega-<lb/>tive avoidance reactions. The perceptual organization of haptic materials and its emotional <lb/>associations so far have been mainly studied in samples of younger adults [1]. However, <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/>1 / 17 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Drewing K (2024) Perceptuo-affective <lb/>organization of touched materials in younger and <lb/>older adults. PLoS ONE 19(1): e0296633. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 <lb/>Editor: Dan-Cristian Dabija, Babes-Bolyai <lb/>University, Cluj-Napoca, ROMANIA <lb/>Received: June 26, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 16, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 22, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Knut Drewing. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The datasets <lb/>generated during and/or analysed during the <lb/>current study will be available upon publication in <lb/>the Zenodo repository, https://doi.org/10.5281/ <lb/>zenodo.7944861. <lb/>Funding: The research was supported by grants to <lb/>K.D. from Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft <lb/>(DFG, German Research Foundation, https://www. <lb/>dfg.de/) -project number 222641018-SFB/ <lb/>TRR135 A5, and-project no. 502774891-ORA <lb/>project &quot;UNTOUCH&quot;. The funders had no role in <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/></front>

    <body>sensory, perceptual and cognitive abilities change over lifespan. Here, we studied how older as <lb/>compared to younger adults organize their haptic world of materials, both perceptually and <lb/>affectively. In particular, we wondered whether decline in perception of detail would come <lb/>along with a dedifferentiation of perceptual space and emotional responses or whether young <lb/>peoples&apos; complex world of touch would be preserved. <lb/>The dimensions along which humans discriminate have been investigated in several studies. <lb/>In the studies, (younger) people judged materials according to a list of perceptual adjectives, <lb/>such as &quot;smooth&quot; or &quot;hard&quot; [2] or rated perceptual similarities of different materials [3, 4]. Per-<lb/>ceptual dimensions have then been determined by factor analyses or by multidimensional scal-<lb/>ing methods. For judgments on surface materials a review on 18 studies [5] postulates five <lb/>perceptual dimensions: softness, fine and macro roughness, friction and warmness. No single <lb/>study reported all five dimensions, which can, however, be explained by differences and limita-<lb/>tions in the used set of surfaces [5]. In a more recent study [1], we varied materials in a wider <lb/>range beyond surface characteristics and did constrain exploratory movements less as com-<lb/>pared to the previous studies. There, we confirmed dimensions that have been frequently <lb/>observed before (roughness, deformability [linking to softness], fluidity [linking to friction]), <lb/>but also found dimensions (heaviness, granularity, fibrousness) that are beyond surface <lb/>characteristics. <lb/>With regard to emotional responses, participants typically judge smoother and softer mate-<lb/>rials as being more pleasant than rougher and stickier materials [6-9]. In the hairy skin, spe-<lb/>cialized mechanoreceptors respond to stimulations patterns that strongly associate with <lb/>pleasantness [10, 11]. In the glabrous skin of the hand, where pleasantness can also well be <lb/>assessed [7, 12-15], these mechanoreceptors were not observed. There, pleasantness is proba-<lb/>bly based on experience and learning stimulation patterns from the hairy skin [11, 13, 15, 16]. <lb/>Other studies suggest further dimensions of emotional responses in active touch beyond pleas-<lb/>antness [17]. In general, emotional responses have been differentiated according to the dimen-<lb/>sions valence, arousal and dominance [18-20]. Valence is pleasantness/unpleasantness; <lb/>arousal is subjective activation, ranging from a very calm state to vigilance and excitement. <lb/>Dominance can be described by the range from feeling passive/weak to feeling in control/ <lb/>strong [21]. In their studies, Ackerley and colleagues [14] and Guest and colleagues [22, 23] <lb/>observed the dimensions of valence and arousal, when participants rated touched materials <lb/>according to a number of adjectives. In our study [1] we observed all three emotional dimen-<lb/>sions valence, arousal and dominance. Emotional dimensions were partly correlated with per-<lb/>ceptual dimensions [1, 22, 23], including negative correlations between valence and roughness <lb/>or between dominance and deformability, and positive correlations between valence and gran-<lb/>ularity, between valence and fibrousness, between arousal and fluidity, or between dominance <lb/>and heaviness. <lb/>In the previous experiments mainly young adults took part, hardly older ones. Thus, previ-<lb/>ous findings might provide an appropriate picture of young adult&apos;s haptic organization of <lb/>materials, but likely fail to describe older adults&apos; world of touch. Note that there is tremendous <lb/>change across lifespan in several psychological domains. Aging comes along with deterioration <lb/>and decline of cognitive and sensory functions, but overall the picture of change is more het-<lb/>erogeneous, demonstrating also stability and even improvement besides decline [24]. The <lb/>diversity of changes is concomitant with adaptive processes that stabilize functional capacities <lb/>[25]. With respect to somatosensory processing we know about decline in skin elasticity, skin <lb/>moisture, receptor density and spatial accuracy as assessed by two-point discrimination [26-<lb/>30]. Dinse [32], e.g., gives two-point discrimination thresholds of 1.5 mm for younger adults <lb/>(20-30 years) and 3.4 mm for older adults (66-86 years). These changes come along with <lb/>reduced haptic perception of fine detail in texture, material, shape and spatial perception [30-<lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <front>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>35] and reduced abilities to detect light touch or vibration [27, 36]. The decline can well be <lb/>observed after an age of around 60 years [29]. At the same time older adults may make use of <lb/>compensatory strategies that counteract sensitivity loss, e.g. by effective multisensory integra-<lb/>tion [37-39]. <lb/>Also, emotional functions change with age. Large and by, emotional processing is preserved <lb/>into older age [40, 41], but also some reduction of behavioral and physiological emotional <lb/>responses has been reported [42, 43]. The reduction is more evident for negative emotions <lb/>such as disgust, whereas experiences of positive emotions hardly decline-including the pleas-<lb/>antness of being touched [44-46]. This positivity bias in older adults is controversially dis-<lb/>cussed with regard to scope and explanation [43, 47]: Socio-emotional selectivity theory [48] <lb/>assumes that older adults intentionally focus more on positive rather than negative experiences <lb/>as compared to younger adults [45]. In contrast deterioration-based accounts lead positivity <lb/>bias back to specific or more general neural decline [49, 50]. In any case, reduction of negative <lb/>affect might also occur for emotional responses to touched materials. <lb/>Here, we study how age change affects the organization of touched materials, i.e. the dimen-<lb/>sions along that people discriminate materials and their relation to emotional responses. In <lb/>particular, we wondered whether decline in perception of detail would come along with a <lb/>dedifferentiation of perceptual space and emotional responses. Or, would the basic organiza-<lb/>tion be preserved into older age despite of sensory loss? Such, preservation could, e.g. be sup-<lb/>ported by substitution on properties from memory [51]. To find out, we developed a shorter <lb/>variant of the task used in our previous study [1], and tested it with younger (18-29 years) and <lb/>older adults (61-77 years). In the previous study participants had manually explored a repre-<lb/>sentative set of 47 solid, fluid and granular materials and rated the materials according to a list <lb/>of perceptual and emotional adjectives. Adjectives were taken from previous studies [19, 22, <lb/>23] and from own considerations. Principal component analyses were used to extract percep-<lb/>tual and emotional dimensions. Here, we used a subset of 25 materials and 27 adjectives that <lb/>are representative for the larger original sets according to component scores and component <lb/>loads, respectively. For the younger age group we used two gender sub groups, sampling from <lb/>15 females and 15 males. We did not expect noteworthy differences between genders with <lb/>respect to haptic perceptual organization, but aimed to check this assumption. The older age <lb/>group had the sample size of 15 overall. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Participants <lb/>The sample consisted of 15 older adults (age range 61-77 years, M = 66.2; 9 females) and 30 <lb/>young adults (age range 18-29 years, M = 22.0 years). 15 of the young adults were females (19-<lb/>29 years, M = 22.0), 15 were males (18-29 years, M = 22.1). The sample size of 15 per group <lb/>was appropriate to detect small to moderate interaction effects (Cohen&apos;s f = 0.15; power of <lb/>0.95) between the judgment patterns of either two groups. <lb/>Participants were recruited in November 2017, data was collected in 2017 and beginning of <lb/>2018. Data was pseudonymized in accordance with Europe&apos;s General Data Protection Regula-<lb/>tion (GDPR). The formal level of education was higher for the younger adults (lowest level: <lb/>advanced technical college entrance qualification; 90% general qualification for university <lb/>entrance) as compared to the older group (lowest level: certificate of secondary education; 20% <lb/>general qualification for university entrance), which, however, is partly due to differences <lb/>between cohorts (overall ~21% and ~54% qualification for university entrance for the years of <lb/>birth before 1959, and 1989-1999, respectively; p. 38, [52]). Two-point discrimination thresh-<lb/>olds in the old sample were 4 mm or better (except one person with 6mm), and thus as <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>expected higher than in the younger sample (3 mm or better). In the Montreal Cognitive <lb/>Assessment test (MOCA, [53]), none of the old participants showed signs of cognitive deficits <lb/>(less than 26 of 30 points). The MOCA was not conducted with the younger sample. The youn-<lb/>ger participants conducted the experiment in a lab. The majority of old participants lived in a <lb/>village close to Giessen. Hence the old participants conducted the experiments in an experi-<lb/>mental setup that was reproduced, as similar as possible, to the lab setup, in a residential build-<lb/>ing in that village. The research was ethically approved by the local ethics committee of <lb/>Fachbereich 06 (LEK FB 06) at Giessen and was performed in accordance with the Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki from 2008. Participants provided written informed consent. Participants were <lb/>naïve to the purpose of the study, and spoke German on a native speaker level. None of them <lb/>reported cutaneous, sensory or motor impairments in the dominant hand. Participants were <lb/>paid 8€ per hour. <lb/>Setup <lb/>Participants sat in a quiet room at a table that was hidden from view by a curtain. A glass con-<lb/>tainer was placed in front of the participant at the table [1]. The glass container had a circular <lb/>opening of 8 cm diameter that was oriented towards the participant. The participant could <lb/>explore the material in the container by reaching out under the curtain. The material was <lb/>never seen, the curtain prevented the materials from view and acted as a barrier for odors; pas-<lb/>sively noise-cancelling head phones reduced auditory signals from touching the materials. <lb/>One experimenter stood to the right of the participant, presented labels with the to-be-rated <lb/>adjectives and noted the participant&apos;s verbal response on a computer. We chose this manner to <lb/>collect the participant&apos;s responses in order to keep the setup simple. The material that was cur-<lb/>rently explored by the participant was not known to this experimenter. The experimenter was <lb/>instructed to interact with the participant in an affectively neutral, standardized manner. The <lb/>other experimenter sat behind the curtain and exchanged the glass containers as required; <lb/>glass containers with all materials were hidden behind the curtain. <lb/>Materials and adjectives <lb/>We used a set of 25 solid, fluid and granular everyday materials, namely aluminium foil, bark, <lb/>cork, flour, hay, iron, jute, lace, oil, paper, pebbles, plastic, polished stone, putty, rabbit fur, <lb/>sand, sandpaper, silicone, shaving foam, soil, styrofoam, velvet, wadding, water, and wrapping <lb/>foil. This was a representative subset selected from the 47 materials used by Drewing and col-<lb/>leagues [1]: We removed materials from the original set that were haptically similar to others <lb/>(as indicated by their scores in the six perceptual dimensions extracted there; e.g. salt to sand), <lb/>and materials which did not score high (negative or positive) in any dimension (e.g., saw <lb/>dust). We kept similar numbers of high-scoring materials for each dimension. The 25 final <lb/>materials were put in different glass containers. Materials that change appearance over time or <lb/>through exploration (e.g., shaving foam, aluminium foil) were renewed for each participant. <lb/>The adjectives were selected as a subset from the 32 perceptual and 23 emotional adjectives <lb/>used by Drewing and colleagues (2018) in experiment 2. They had chosen many of their adjec-<lb/>tives from the TPT scale [22], and from [19, 21, 54]. We chose adjectives that had loaded high <lb/>on one of the six perceptual or three emotional dimensions extracted in [1], while trying to <lb/>avoid adjectives that are tightly linked to a single specific material (e.g., silky). The final percep-<lb/>tual list included 18 adjectives: elastisch (elastic), faserig (fibrous), feucht (moist), fluffig <lb/>(fluffy), glatt (smooth), glitschig (slippery), grobko ¨rnig (coarse), haarig (hairy), hart (hard), <lb/>klebrig (sticky), ko ¨rnig (grainy), leicht (light), pulverig (powdery), rau (rough), schroff (jag-<lb/>ged), schwer (heavy), verformbar (deformable), weich (soft). In the final emotional list were 9 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>adjectives: angenehm (pleasant), aufmerksamkeitserregend (attention-grabbing), aufregend <lb/>(exciting), dominant (dominant), entspannend (relaxing), erfreulich (enjoyable), langweilig <lb/>(boring), ma ¨chtig (mighty), schwach (weak). <lb/>Design and procedure <lb/>Participants rated each of the 25 materials according to each of the 9 emotional and each of the <lb/>18 perceptual adjectives. Adjectives were used as Likert items with possible ratings ranging <lb/>from 1 to 7 (&quot;The felt material is. . .?&quot;, 1: &quot;strongly disagree&quot;. . . 4: &quot;indifferent&quot;. . . 7: &quot;strongly <lb/>agree&quot;). The 25 x (9 + 18) = 675 responses from each participant were the primary data. <lb/>In each single trial, the participant explored one of the materials. They used the dominant <lb/>hand without constraints on manner of exploration and without explicit time limit. One of the <lb/>experimenters serially presented the labels on which the adjectives were printed. By saying a <lb/>whole number between 1 and 7 the participant rated in how far the felt material can be <lb/>described by the adjective. The response was noted down by the experimenter. Then, the next <lb/>label was presented, until each adjective had been shown once. The other experimenter took <lb/>care that the participant was in touch with the material during the entire trial, and changed the <lb/>material after the end of the trial. The orders of materials and adjectives were randomized. <lb/>However, all the emotional adjectives were presented before the perceptual ones, and for each <lb/>participant the same randomized order of adjectives was used for each material. Using wet <lb/>wipes, the participant cleaned the hand between trials if necessary (e.g. after oil, soil). <lb/>The experimental session started with the consent form, questions on demography and sen-<lb/>sorimotor functioning, and the measurement of the two-point discrimination threshold at the <lb/>dominant hand&apos;s index finger using a two-point discriminator. Before the experiment partici-<lb/>pants removed any rings or bracelets. The entire session took about 1 ½ hours. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>First, we analyzed how consistent responses were. We defined the three equal-sized groups of <lb/>older adults, younger females and younger males. We distinguished between the young males <lb/>and females in order to control for potential gender effects. Within each group, we calculated <lb/>pair-wise correlations of either two participants&apos; responses across all materials and all adjec-<lb/>tives, separately for perceptual and emotional adjectives, and we calculated standardized Cron-<lb/>bach&apos;s α between participants for each single adjective to estimate the consistency per adjective <lb/>(α takes values between 0 and 1; values of 0.6-0.7 are &quot;borderline&quot;; 0.7-0.8 &quot;acceptable&quot;; 0.8-<lb/>0.9 &quot;good&quot;, � 0.9 &quot;excellent&quot;; smaller values reflect poor to unacceptable consistency). We <lb/>eliminated adjectives from analyses, if Cronbach&apos;s α was &quot;unacceptable&quot;. <lb/>Individual adjective scores were submitted to covariance-based principal component analy-<lb/>ses (PCAs), which we did group-wise and overall, separately for perceptual adjectives, one for <lb/>emotional ones. We checked whether data are suitable for PCA using Bartlett&apos;s test of spheric-<lb/>ity and the Keyser-Meyer-Olkin (KMO) criterion. Bartlett&apos;s test is significant, when correla-<lb/>tions in the data are not random, and thus can be meaningfully analyzed by PCA. The KMO <lb/>score takes values between 0 and 1; higher values indicate that data are more suitable. To <lb/>extract principal components we used the Kaiser-criterion supplemented by additional consid-<lb/>erations on comparability (see Results), and rotated components using the varimax method. <lb/>For the overall analyses, we extracted 6 perceptual and 2 emotional components, and we calcu-<lb/>lated individual component scores (z-scores) per material using Bartlett&apos;s method, on which <lb/>we conducted further analyses: Separately for each component, we compared component <lb/>scores in analyses of variance (ANOVAs) with the within-participant factor Material (25 lev-<lb/>els) and the between-participant factor Group (young females vs young males, all males vs <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>females, older vs younger adults). In addition, we correlated individual component scores per <lb/>material for each pair of emotional and perceptual component, which were 12 correlations. <lb/>Individual scores were Fisher-z-transformed, and then analysed using group-wise t-tests <lb/>against zero (Bonferroni-corrected for 36 comparisons), and two-sample t-tests between <lb/>young females vs young males, all males vs females (full sample) and between old vs young par-<lb/>ticipants (each set Bonferroni-corrected for 12 comparisons). <lb/>Results <lb/>Consistency between participants and exclusion <lb/>With one exception (participant #35, young male, Median [Mdn]: .08) correlations between <lb/>the perceptual ratings of different participants in the different groups tended to be high (Mdn <lb/>of other young males: .60-.70; young females: .53-.73; older group: .54-.68). In contrast, corre-<lb/>lations between emotional ratings were low to moderate (Mdn of young males: .15-.32; young <lb/>females: .20-.40; older group: .09-.33). The single participant #35 showing small consistency in <lb/>perceptual ratings was considered an outlier and excluded from further analysis. Standardized <lb/>Cronbach&apos;s alphas demonstrate a good or excellent consistency between participants in each <lb/>group for each perceptual adjective (each α � .88; Mdn .97, .96, .97 for young females, young <lb/>males and older group, respectively). For emotional adjectives Cronbach&apos;s alpha showed more <lb/>variable consistencies, but still ranging from borderline to excellent (young females, .79 � α � <lb/>.94, Mdn. 89; young males, .62 � α � .90, Mdn. 82; old group .63 � α � .90, Mdn. 74) with <lb/>one exception: The older persons&apos; ratings on &quot;boring&quot; were not at all consistent with an alpha <lb/>of .00. This adjective was, hence, excluded from all further analyses. <lb/>PCAs on perceptual adjectives <lb/>PCAs were conducted on individual adjective scores both group-wise and over all participants. <lb/>The KMO scores for perceptual adjectives reached values of .78 (young males), .77 (young <lb/>females) and .80 (old group) and .79 overall, indicating a &quot;middling&quot; suitability for PCA [55]. <lb/>Bartlett&apos;s tests of sphericity were significant for each group, χ 2 (153) = 3154.41, p &lt; .001 (young <lb/>males), χ 2 (153) = 3658.22, p &lt; .001 (young females), χ 2 (153) = 2838.96, p &lt; .001 (old group), <lb/>and overall χ 2 (153) = 9157.71, p &lt; .001, suggesting that observed correlations are meaningful. <lb/>According to the Kaiser-criterion (= component explains &gt;5.56% variance) there were 5 <lb/>principal components for the young males and the old group and 6 for young females and the <lb/>overall analysis. However, a 6 th component in the young males (5.44%) and the old group <lb/>(5.36%) only marginally failed to reach the criterion, and in order to improve comparability <lb/>between groups we always extracted 6 components. The 6 components also explained similar <lb/>amounts of variance in all cases (young females: 77.6%, young males: 76.2%, old group: 73.5%, <lb/>overall: 74.7%), supporting our approach. Component loadings of each adjective are detailed <lb/>for the overall analysis in Table 1 and for each group in S1 Table. The most relevant adjectives <lb/>after varimax rotation per group are shown in Fig 1. <lb/>Most rotated components are quite similar in the three groups (Fig 1). For the first compo-<lb/>nent the adjectives &quot;moist&quot;, &quot;sticky&quot;, and &quot;slippery&quot; are most relevant in all three groups, so <lb/>that the component can be labelled Fluidity/ Friction. For the second component relevant <lb/>adjectives are &quot;fluffy&quot;, &quot;fibrous&quot; and &quot;hairy&quot; (even if in the old group &quot;hairy&quot; explains 26% of <lb/>variance per adjective only, and thus marginally fails the criterion of 30%), and can be labelled <lb/>Fibrousness. Also components five and six are similar in all groups: Component five covers <lb/>the adjectives &quot;heavy&quot; and &quot;light&quot;-plus &quot;soft&quot; in the older group, plus &quot;hard&quot; in the young <lb/>males and plus &quot;hard&quot;, &quot;smooth&quot; in the young females. The component might be called Heavi-<lb/>ness. Component six contains the adjectives &quot;elastic&quot; and &quot;deformable&quot; in all groups and can <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 1. Adjective loads in overall perceptual PCA. <lb/>Adjective <lb/>Fluid <lb/>Fibr <lb/>Rgh <lb/>Gran <lb/>Hvi <lb/>Def <lb/>moist <lb/>1.76 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-0.23 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>slippery <lb/>1.57 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>-0.18 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>sticky <lb/>1.14 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>hairy <lb/>-0.18 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>fibrous <lb/>-0.33 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>-0.33 <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>fluffy <lb/>0.15 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>-0.62 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>-0.37 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>rough <lb/>-0.51 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>1.63 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>jagged <lb/>-0.32 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>grainy <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>powdery <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.12 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>coarse <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>hard <lb/>-0.64 <lb/>-0.49 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>1.43 <lb/>-0.56 <lb/>light <lb/>-0.28 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-1.49 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>heavy <lb/>0.08 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>deformable <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>-0.30 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>-0.57 <lb/>2.09 <lb/>elastic <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>-0.34 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>1.70 <lb/>soft <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>-1.09 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>-0.91 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>smooth <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.23 <lb/>-1.42 <lb/>-0.46 <lb/>0.89 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>Variance explained <lb/>12.9 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>15.8 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>13.7 <lb/>13.0 <lb/>After varimax rotation. In gray are the adjectives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains more than 30% of mean variance per adjective (|1.05) <lb/>and (B) load higher on that component as compared to on any other component. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.t001 <lb/>Fig 1. Perceptual PCA-Group-wise components and relevant adjectives. After varimax rotation. Shown are the <lb/>adjectives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains more than 30% of mean variance per <lb/>adjective (|1.03| for young males/ females, |1.08| for old group) and (B) load higher on that component as compared to <lb/>on any other component. Grayed adjectives fulfill only one of the two criteria. Percentages give the variance explained <lb/>per component. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>be identified with Deformability. The third and fourth components are similar for the young <lb/>females and males, but different for the old group. Component three includes the adjectives <lb/>&quot;rough&quot; and &quot;jagged&quot; plus &quot;smooth&quot; in young males, and plus &quot;soft&quot; in young females. Rough-<lb/>ness would be a good label for this component. Component four includes the adjectives <lb/>&quot;grainy&quot;, &quot;coarse&quot; and &quot;powdery&quot; in young males and young females, and could be labelled as <lb/>Granularity. In contrast, in the old group, component four has contributions from &quot;rough&quot;, <lb/>&quot;jagged&quot;, &quot;grainy&quot;, &quot;coarse&quot; and &quot;hard&quot;, and thus seems to cover content from the young <lb/>groups&apos; Granularity and Roughness components in a single component. We call this compo-<lb/>nent Coarseness. In addition, component four in the old group only contains the adjective <lb/>&quot;smooth&quot;. Results from the overall analysis replicate the distinction in the six components <lb/>found for the young groups: Fluidity, Fibrousness, Roughness, Granularity, Heaviness, and <lb/>Deformability (for details see Table 1). <lb/>PCAs on emotional adjectives <lb/>PCAs were conducted on individual adjective scores both group-wise and over all participants. <lb/>KMO scores were .68 (young males), .75 (young females), .76 (older group), and .74 overall, <lb/>indicating a &quot;mediocre&quot; to &quot;middling&quot; suitability for PCA [55]. Bartlett&apos;s tests of sphericity <lb/>were significant for each group, χ 2 (28) = 1080.28, p &lt; .001 (young males), χ 2 (28) = 1783.17, p <lb/>&lt; .001 (young females), χ 2 (28) = 1357.80, p &lt; .001 (older group), and overall χ 2 (28) = 3944.64, <lb/>p &lt; .001 suggesting that observed correlations are meaningful. <lb/>According to the Kaiser-criterion (= component explains &gt;12.5% variance) there were 2 <lb/>principal components for each group and the overall analysis. The two-component solutions <lb/>explained 61.7% (young males), 71.2% (young females), 66.7% (older group) and 65.3% (over-<lb/>all) variance. The most relevant adjectives after varimax rotation per group are shown in Fig 2. <lb/>Component loadings of each adjective are detailed for the overall analysis in Table 2 and for <lb/>each group in S2 Table. The young females two-factor solution had one Valence/ Arousal com-<lb/>ponent (adjectives: &quot;pleasant&quot;, &quot;relaxing&quot;, &quot;enjoyable&quot;, &quot;exciting&quot; and &quot;attention-grabbing&quot;), <lb/>and a second component of Dominance (adjectives: &quot;dominant&quot;, &quot;mighty&quot;, &quot;weak&quot;). The <lb/>males solution had a Valence component (adjectives: &quot;pleasant&quot;, &quot;relaxing&quot;, &quot;enjoyable&quot;, <lb/>&quot;exciting&quot;), and a Dominance component (adjectives: &quot;dominant&quot;, &quot;mighty&quot;, &quot;weak&quot;, atten-<lb/>tion-grabbing fulfilling), and in both Arousal adjectives were intermixed. Finally, the older <lb/>Fig 2. Emotional PCA-Group-wise components and relevant adjectives. After varimax rotation. Shown are the <lb/>adjectives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains more than 30% of mean variance per <lb/>adjective (|0.99| for young males, (|0.96| for young females, |1.05| for old group) and (B) load higher on that <lb/>component as compared to on any other component. Grayed adjectives fulfill only one of the two criteria. Percentages <lb/>give the variance explained per component. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.g002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>group solutions also had a Valence component (&quot;pleasant&quot;, &quot;relaxing&quot;, &quot;enjoyable&quot;, &quot;exciting&quot;), <lb/>and a Dominance/ Arousal component (&quot;dominant&quot;, &quot;mighty&quot;, &quot;attention-grabbing&quot;, &quot;excit-<lb/>ing&quot;). Results from the overall analysis (Table 2) suggest a distinction in two components simi-<lb/>lar to that found for the old groups: Valence (&quot;pleasant&quot;, &quot;relaxing&quot;, &quot;enjoyable&quot;; 38.6% <lb/>variance explained), and Arousal/Dominance (&quot;dominant&quot;, &quot;mighty&quot;, &quot;attention-grabbing&quot;, <lb/>&quot;exciting&quot;). <lb/>Group effects on Bartlett scores <lb/>In a second step, we compared the individual Bartlett scores separately for each perceptual and <lb/>emotional component (Roughness, Fluidity/Friction, Fibrousness, Heaviness, Granularity, <lb/>Deformability &amp; Valence, Dominance/Arousal). We used ANOVAs with the within-partici-<lb/>pant variable Material (25 levels) and the between-participant variable Gender (female vs <lb/>male, 1 st set of analyses) or Age (young vs old group, 2 nd set of analyses). The statistical results <lb/>of the 16 ANOVAs are summarized in Table 3 for the gender comparisons, and in Table 4 for <lb/>the age comparisons. Average values per dimension, material and group can be found in Fig 3. <lb/>In essence, materials significantly differ in component scores for each single component, in <lb/>both types of analyses as should be the case. Further, there were no significant main effects of <lb/>gender nor of age group. There were also no significant interactions of gender with materials. <lb/>Given the power calculations above, we can thus confirm that judgment patterns across <lb/>Table 2. Adjective loads in overall emotional PCA. <lb/>Adjective <lb/>Val <lb/>ArDom <lb/>pleasant <lb/>1.70 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>relaxing <lb/>1.78 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>enjoyable <lb/>1.48 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>exciting <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>attention-grabbing <lb/>0.86 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>dominant <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>mighty <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>1.52 <lb/>weak <lb/>0.53 <lb/>-0.54 <lb/>Variance explained <lb/>38.1 <lb/>27.2 <lb/>After varimax rotation. In gray are the adjectives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains <lb/>more than 30% of mean variance per adjective (|1.00|) and (B) load higher on that component as compared to on any <lb/>other component. Light gray if only one of the two criteria is fulfilled. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.t002 <lb/>Table 3. Gender comparison: Two-way ANOVA statistics of Bartlett scores. <lb/>Material <lb/>Gender <lb/>Material X Gender <lb/>F(24, 648) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>F(1, 27) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>F(24, 648) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>Roughness <lb/>75.083 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.74 <lb/>2.946 <lb/>0.098 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>1.057 <lb/>0.397 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Fluidity/Friction <lb/>184.058 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.177 <lb/>0.677 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.967 <lb/>0.466 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Heaviness <lb/>57.690 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.68 <lb/>2.172 <lb/>0.152 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.636 <lb/>0.770 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Fibrousness <lb/>70.455 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>0.886 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.230 <lb/>0.271 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Granularity <lb/>83.433 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>0.878 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.877 <lb/>0.534 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Deformability <lb/>26.490 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.103 <lb/>0.751 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.678 <lb/>0.724 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Valence <lb/>19.581 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.943 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.175 <lb/>0.305 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Arousal/Domin. <lb/>19.173 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.017 <lb/>0.896 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.837 <lb/>0.595 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.t003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 4. Age comparison: Two-way ANOVA statistics of Bartlett scores. <lb/>Material <lb/>Age <lb/>Material X Age <lb/>F(24, 1008) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>F(1, 42) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>F(24, 1008) <lb/>p <lb/>η p <lb/>2 <lb/>Roughness <lb/>86.539 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.67 <lb/>3.596 <lb/>0.065 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>2.389 <lb/>0.005* <lb/>0.05 <lb/>Fluidity/Friction <lb/>226.670 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.965 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.954 <lb/>0.045* <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Heaviness <lb/>75.108 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.64 <lb/>1.108 <lb/>0.299 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>1.243 <lb/>0.255 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Fibrousness <lb/>81.820 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.66 <lb/>1.683 <lb/>0.202 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>1.382 <lb/>0.181 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Granularity <lb/>93.777 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.69 <lb/>0.502 <lb/>0.482 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>4.094 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.09 <lb/>Deformability <lb/>29.412 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.876 <lb/>0.552 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.748 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>Valence <lb/>24.539 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.940 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.879 <lb/>0.032* <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Arousal/Domin. <lb/>19.775 <lb/>&lt;0.001* <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.671 <lb/>0.417 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>1.221 <lb/>0.268 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.t004 <lb/>Fig 3. Bartlett scores for each component, group and material. Materials are ordered according to their average <lb/>score. In case of a significant interaction age X material, materials where old age&apos;s score exceeds the young age groups&apos; <lb/>average by more than 0.2 are placed at the left and materials where young groups&apos; average is higher by the same <lb/>amount are placed to the right. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>materials do not differ between genders to a more than small-to-moderate degree. Note that <lb/>we also did not find any significant interaction of gender with materials when analyzing the <lb/>full sample including the older adults. <lb/>However, we found several significant interactions of age group with material in the full <lb/>sample: Roughness, Fluidity/Friction and Granularity are the perceptual components that <lb/>younger and older participants judged differently for different materials, and Valence is the <lb/>emotional component. In Fig 3 one can see how judgment patterns across materials differ <lb/>between age groups. In particular, a large number of materials tend to be perceived as less <lb/>rough by older as compared to younger participants. For fluidity/friction there seem to be <lb/>mainly two materials that older people tend to perceive as more fluid than younger ones, <lb/>namely soil and putty. For granular stuff, there tend to be effects that older participants judged <lb/>stuff with larger parts (pebbles, polished stone) as more granular and stuff with smaller parti-<lb/>cles (flour, sand) as less granular than younger people, but there are additional differences. <lb/>Finally, there are also differentiated age effects for valence, both with certain materials being <lb/>more positive for older people and others feeling less positive. <lb/>Correlations of perceptual and emotional components <lb/>Finally, we calculated individual correlations for each pair of emotional and perceptual scores, <lb/>and computed further analyses on their Fisher z transforms. Average values per group and <lb/>pair of scores can be found in Fig 4. Group-wise t-tests against zero show the following associa-<lb/>tions: In all groups rougher materials were associated with lower valence (rs -.29 to -.45, corr <lb/>ps &lt; .012), more fibrous materials were associated with higher valence (rs .31 to .44, corr ps &lt; <lb/>.011), and heavier materials scored higher on the dominance/arousal component (rs .50 to .58, <lb/>corr ps &lt; .001). Further, there were associations with dominance/arousal that reached signifi-<lb/>cance in particular groups including a positive correlation with roughness in the old group (r <lb/>= .29, p = .047), a negative association with fibrousness in the young males (r = -.27, p = .002), <lb/>and a negative association with deformability in young females (r = -.24, p = .012). <lb/>Fig 4. Group-wise perceptuo-emotional correlations. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>Finally, in young females and males (rs .33 &amp; .21, corr ps &lt; .012), but not in the old group <lb/>more granular materials were associated with higher valence. In all between-group compari-<lb/>sons (young males vs. females, all males vs. females, younger vs. older), only the young-old dif-<lb/>ference in the granular-valence correlation reached significance, t(42) = 4.23, p corr = .002. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We studied how age-related change affects the organization of touched materials. Older and <lb/>younger adults-for control purpose split in younger females and younger males-rated a set <lb/>of 25 representative solid, granular and fluid materials. Significant amounts of variance in per-<lb/>ceptual ratings were explained by the 4 independent components: fluidity, deformability, <lb/>fibrousness, heaviness. In the younger adults additional components of roughness, and granu-<lb/>larity were observed (similar to previous findings, [1]). In contrast, roughness and granularity <lb/>seem to combine into a single component of coarseness in the older participants, pointing to <lb/>age-specific particularities. Variance in emotional ratings was in all three groups explained by <lb/>two independent components (rather than three as e.g. in [1]). The analyses of material-spe-<lb/>cific component scores from the overall component analysis, yielded several differences <lb/>between younger and older adults, particularly in the perception of roughness, granularity and <lb/>valence of materials and in the older people&apos;s absence of the younger people&apos;s positive correla-<lb/>tion between valence and granularity. In contrast, based on power analysis and findings we <lb/>can exclude more-than-small gender differences within the young people, as expected. Overall, <lb/>the results suggests that older people organize and experience haptic materials partly differ-<lb/>ently from younger people. Several aspects of organization are, however, also surprisingly simi-<lb/>lar in older and younger people. <lb/>There was one clear age difference in perceptuo-emotional correlations, namely a signifi-<lb/>cant difference between the old and younger group with respect to the relation between granu-<lb/>larity and valence. Else the groups showed differential absence or presence of a significant <lb/>non-zero correlation of perceptual dimensions with dominance, which, however was not cor-<lb/>roborated by significance in the direct between-group comparison. Here, we hence focus on <lb/>the granularity-valence relation and the other significant age differences, which were in the <lb/>perception of roughness, granularity and valence of materials. In particular, many materials <lb/>were perceived as less rough by older as compared to younger participants (Fig 3), older adults <lb/>tended to judge granular stuff with larger parts (pebbles, polished stone) as more granular and <lb/>stuff with smaller particles (flour, sand) as less granular than younger people, and there are dif-<lb/>ferentiated age effects for valence. It is actually, two of three dimensions on fine texture or <lb/>material detail that are differently judged by older as compared to younger people, while the <lb/>three perceptual dimensions that deal less with detail (heaviness, deformability, fluidity/fric-<lb/>tion) are unaffected. This might be explained by the observation that older people&apos;s detail per-<lb/>ception is declined. That is, finer-grained material may actually not be perceived as fine-<lb/>grained, i.e. rough or granular, by the older people. Along the same line, the collapse of rough-<lb/>ness-and granularity-related adjectives in a single &quot;coarseness&quot;-component in the older group <lb/>(and its separation into two components in the younger groups), could also be due to reduced <lb/>perceptual differentiation of fine-grained structure and detail. As well the lack of a positive <lb/>relation between granularity and valence for older people might be due to a loss of perceptual <lb/>differentiation of the granular material, and older adults might have unlearnt that association <lb/>between granular material and positive valence. One may wonder whether these changes <lb/>could, alternatively, be explained by changes in emotional responses. However, literature sug-<lb/>gests that negative, but rather not positive experiences are reduced in older adults [43-50], ren-<lb/>dering this explanation unlikely, because granular materials elicits positive feelings. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>It is surprising under the perspective of decline in detail perception that age differences <lb/>spare fibrousness, because highly fibrous stuff like wadding, fur or jute is also characterized by <lb/>a detailed fine-structure. As well it is surprising that the inverse relation between valence and <lb/>roughness is preserved into older age. Note that this is also against the typical trend of reduced <lb/>processing of negative feelings (for instance, disgust, fear) in older age [43-50]. Though, in a <lb/>previous study on relearning valences [56], we found that the valence of granular materials <lb/>could be unlearned in young adult participants but not that of rough material. This would be <lb/>in line with an interpretation that the negative relation between valence and roughness is pre-<lb/>served in old people, but not the positive one between valence and granularity. It is a highly rel-<lb/>evant point that old people did not completely preserve the perceptual organization of young <lb/>people, but that partly relearning based on changes in perceptual gathering took place. In the <lb/>previous study we interpreted the result of differential relearning in terms of different <lb/>strengths in the perceptuo-emotional connections, and led them back to the degree to which <lb/>connections are learned during lifetime vs being evolutionary prepared to serve a biological <lb/>function. In particular, we argued that rough materials could be potentially harmful to the <lb/>skin, and hence, an association of those materials with feelings of unpleasantness could be pre-<lb/>pared or even hard-wired in our nervous system. In contrast, positive valence of granular <lb/>materials is probably not evolutionary driven. Note that the positive valence of fibrous materi-<lb/>als is also preserved in old age, albeit the perception of fibrous materials should also partly be <lb/>based on the perception of fine detail. Also a relation between positive valence and fibrous <lb/>stuff, such as fur could be evolutionary prepared, given that many of our phylogenetic ances-<lb/>tors had fur. So, the valence-fibrousness connection could be another hardwired one. Given <lb/>this interpretation, old adults perceptual organization would preserve and substitute for sen-<lb/>sory loss with respect to hardwired connections but not for learnt ones. Note that aging of <lb/>emotional responses to pictures also possibly partly reflects biological factors [47]. A preserva-<lb/>tion could, e.g., be supported by substitution on properties from memory [51]. However, this <lb/>remains highly speculative and requires future research, also with respect to the actual detail <lb/>perception of more or less pleasant rough, granular and fibrous stimuli. <lb/>Besides the above age differences (and stability) in perceptuo-emotional connections, we <lb/>also observed change in the materials&apos; valence per se (cf. Fig 4). Older adults responded more <lb/>positive than younger adults to some materials (for instances, water, cork) and more negative <lb/>to others (for instances, putty and sandpaper) both with respect to materials that are rather on <lb/>the pleasant side and with respect to rather unpleasant materials. While these differences sug-<lb/>gest some change, they do not fit in the gross picture of a positivity bias in older adults emo-<lb/>tional processing [43-50]-like the findings on perceptuo-emotional connections that also do <lb/>not fit the positivity bias. Hence, results here might hint at the need for differentiating the per-<lb/>spective on aging of emotion. <lb/>Finally, it might be noteworthy that, in general, for younger people we confirmed most of <lb/>our previous findings [1]. We replicated the previously observed six perceptual dimensions, <lb/>and two of the emotional dimensions in material perception, namely valence and dominance. <lb/>Actually, the lack of replicating the previous third dimension of arousal likely leads back to an <lb/>insufficient number of related adjectives in the PCA. One adjective targeting at arousal, namely <lb/>&quot;boring&quot; was not consistently used by the older people and hence could not be considered in <lb/>the analyses. So, there were only two adjectives remaining that target at arousal (&quot;exciting&quot; and <lb/>&quot;attention-grabbing&quot;), which is a much lower number as compared to our previous studies <lb/>(with 4 and 7 adjectives). Note that also other studies had observed an arousal dimension [15, <lb/>22, 23]. Importantly, we replicated the dimension of dominance, which has been controversely <lb/>discussed with respect to non-living objects [22]. Notwithstanding the lack of an independent <lb/>arousal dimension we also confirmed many perceptual-emotional correlations from the <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <body>previous studies [1, 22]: Valence correlated negatively with Roughness [1, 22], and for the <lb/>younger people also positively with granularity [1]. In addition, valence correlated positively <lb/>with Fibrousness, which had previously been arisen as a trend [1, 22]. Further, we confirmed a <lb/>positive correlation between dominance and heaviness. We did not replicate a previous gen-<lb/>eral observation of a negative correlation between dominance and deformability. This was <lb/>only observed for younger females, whereas we observed for younger males a negative correla-<lb/>tion dominance-fibrousness, and for older participants a positive correlation dominance-<lb/>roughness. The latter two specific correlations were not found before and might require repli-<lb/>cation. So taken together, we replicated previous observations here, except for the relation <lb/>between dominance and deformability. <lb/>Overall, we replicated observations on the perceptuo-affective organization of touched <lb/>materials in younger adults, and demonstrated that there are, as expected, no gender differ-<lb/>ences. In contrast, older people organize and experience haptic materials partly differently <lb/>from younger people. While the differences can be related to older adults&apos; sensory decline and <lb/>to deficits in detail perception, several other aspects that also likely link to detail perception <lb/>are, however, preserved. It is an interesting question for future research in how far and why in <lb/>these cases sensory abilities are spared or substituted for. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. Adjective loads in perceptual PCAs. After varimax rotation. Shown are the adjec-<lb/>tives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains more than 30% of mean <lb/>variance per adjective (|1.03| for young males/ females, |1.08| for old group) and (B) load <lb/>higher on that component as compared to on any other component. Light gray adjectives fulfill <lb/>only one of the two criteria. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Table. Adjective loads in emotional PCAs. After varimax rotation. Shown are the adjec-<lb/>tives in each component that (A) have an unsigned load that explains more than 30% of mean <lb/>variance per adjective (|0.99| for young males, (|0.96| for young females, |1.05| for old group) <lb/>and (B) load higher on that component as compared to on any other component. Light gray <lb/>adjectives fulfill only one of the two criteria. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors wishes to thank Marie Neuberger, and Sarah Peichl, who set up part of the experi-<lb/>ments, and collected data within the framework of their Bachelor theses, and Jutta Billino for <lb/>advice with aging-related questions. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Data curation: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Formal analysis: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Investigation: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Methodology: Knut Drewing. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Project administration: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Resources: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Software: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Supervision: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Validation: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Visualization: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Knut Drewing. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Knut Drewing. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Drewing K, Weyel C, Celebi H, Kaya D. Systematic relations between affective and sensory material <lb/>dimensions in touch. IEEE Trans Hapt Percept. 2018. https://doi.org/10.1109/TOH.2018.2836427 <lb/>PMID: 29994318 <lb/>2. Baumgartner E, Wiebel C, Gegenfurtner K. Visual and haptic representations of material properties. <lb/>Multisens Res. 2013; 26: 429-455. https://doi.org/10.1163/22134808-00002429 PMID: 24649528 <lb/>3. Hollins M, Faldowski R, Rao S, Young F. Perceptual dimensions of tactile surface texture: A multidimen-<lb/>sional scaling analysis. Percept Psychophys 1993; 54: 697-705. https://doi.org/10.3758/bf03211795 <lb/>PMID: 8134240 <lb/>4. Yoshioka T, Bensmaia S, Craig J, Hsiao SS. Texture perception through direct and indirect touch: An <lb/>analysis of perceptual space for tactile textures in two modes of exploration. Somatosens Mot Res. <lb/>2007; 24: 53-70. https://doi.org/10.1080/08990220701318163 PMID: 17558923 <lb/>5. Okamoto S, Nagano H, Yamada Y. Psychophysical dimensions of tactile perception of textures, IEEE <lb/>Trans Hapt. 2013; 6: 81-93. https://doi.org/10.1109/TOH.2012.32 PMID: 24808270 <lb/>6. Essick GK, McGlone F, Dancer C, Fabricant D, Ragin Y, Phillips N, et al. Quantitative assessment of <lb/>pleasant touch. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2010 Feb 1; 34(2):192-203. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>neubiorev.2009.02.003 PMID: 19896001 <lb/>7. Klo ¨cker A, Arnould C, Penta M, Thonnard JL. Rasch-built measures of pleasant touch through active <lb/>fingertip exploration. Front Neurorobot. 2012; 6: article 5. <lb/>8. Klo ¨cker A, Wiertlewski M, The ´ate V, Hayward V, Thonnard JL. Physical factors influencing pleasant <lb/>touch during tactile exploration. PLoS ONE. 2013; 8: e79085. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0079085 PMID: 24244425 <lb/>9. Ripin R, Lazarsfeld PF. The tactile-kinaesthetic perception of fabrics with emphasis on their relative <lb/>pleasantness. J Appl Psychol. 1937; 21: 198-224. <lb/>10. Sailer U, Hausmann M, Croy I. Pleasantness only? How sensory and affective attributes describe touch <lb/>targeting c-tactile fibers. Exp Psychol. 2020; 67: 224-236. <lb/>11. McGlone F, Wessberg J, Olausson H. Discriminative and Affective Touch: Sensing and Feeling. Neu-<lb/>ron 2015; 82: 737-755. <lb/>12. Ackerley R, Saar K, McGlone F, Wasling HB. Quantifying the sensory and emotional perception of <lb/>touch: differences between glabrous and hairy skin. Front Behav Neurosci. 2014; 8: article 34. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00034 PMID: 24574985 <lb/>13. Lo ¨ken LS, Wessberg J, McGlone F, Olausson H. Coding of pleasant touch by unmyelinated afferents in <lb/>humans. Nat Neurosci. 2009; 12: 547-548. https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.2312 PMID: 19363489 <lb/>14. Lo ¨ken LS, Evert M, Wessberg J. Pleasantness of touch in human glabrous and hairy skin: Order effects <lb/>on affective ratings. Brain Res. 2012; 1417: 9-15. <lb/>15. McGlone F, Olausson H, Boyle JA, Jones-Gotman M, Dancer C, Guest S, et al. Touching and feeling: <lb/>differences in pleasant touch processing between glabrous and hairy skin in humans. Europ J Neurosci. <lb/>2012 Jun; 35(11):1782-8. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1460-9568.2012.08092.x PMID: 22594914 <lb/>16. Sailer U, Ackerley R. Exposure shapes the perception of affective touch. Devel Cogn Neurosci. 2019; <lb/>35: 109-114. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dcn.2017.07.008 PMID: 28818429 <lb/>17. Iosifyan M, Korolkova O. Emotions associated with different textures during touch. Consciousn Cognit <lb/>2019; 71: 79-85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.concog.2019.03.012 PMID: 30970295 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>18. Osgood CE, Suci GJ. Factor analysis of meaning. J Exp Psychol. 1955; 50: 325. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1037/h0043965 PMID: 13271697 <lb/>19. Russell JA, Mehrabian A. Evidence for a three-factor theory of emotions. J Res Personal. 1977; 11: <lb/>273-294. <lb/>20. Russell JA, Steiger J. The structure in persons&apos; implicit taxonomy of emotions. J Res Personal. 1982; <lb/>16: 447-469. <lb/>21. Mehrabian A, Russell JA. An approach to environmental psychology. Cambridge, MA; MIT Press; <lb/>1974. <lb/>22. Guest S, Dessirier JM, Mehrabyan A, McGlone F, Essick G, Gescheider G, et al. The development and <lb/>validation of sensory and emotional scales of touch perception. Attent Percept Psychophys. 2011; 73: <lb/>531-50. https://doi.org/10.3758/s13414-010-0037-y PMID: 21264727 <lb/>23. Guest S, Mehrabyan A, Essick G, Phillips N, Hopkinson A, McGlone F. Physics and tactile perception <lb/>of fluid-covered surfaces. Journal of texture studies. 2012 Feb; 43(1):77-93. <lb/>24. Hartshorne JK, Germine LT. When does cognitive functioning peak? The asynchronous rise and fall of <lb/>different cognitive abilities across the life span. Psych Sci. 2015; 26: 433-443. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>0956797614567339 PMID: 25770099 <lb/>25. Billino J, Pilz KS. Motion perception as a model for perceptual aging. J Vis. 2019; 19: 3-3. <lb/>26. Amaied E, Vargiolu R, Bergheau JM, Zahouani H. Aging effect on tactile perception: experimental and <lb/>modelling studies. Wear. 2015; 332: 715-724. <lb/>27. Bruce MF. The relation of tactile thresholds to histology in the fingers of elderly people. J Neurol Neuro-<lb/>surg Psych 1980; 43: 730-734. https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp.43.8.730 PMID: 7431035 <lb/>28. Garcı ´a-Piqueras J, Garcı ´a-Mesa Y, Ca ´rcaba L, Feito J, Torres-Parejo I, Martı ´n-Biedma B, et al. Ageing <lb/>of the somatosensory system at the periphery: Age-related changes in cutaneous mechanoreceptors. J <lb/>Anatom 2019; 234(6): 839-852. https://doi.org/10.1111/joa.12983 PMID: 30924930 <lb/>29. McIntyre S, Nagi SS, McGlone F, Olausson H. The effects of ageing on tactile function in humans. Neu-<lb/>rosci. 2021; 464: 53-58. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2021.02.015 PMID: 33607227 <lb/>30. Skedung L, El Rawadi C, Arvidsson M, Farcet C, Luengo GS, Breton L, et al. Mechanisms of tactile sen-<lb/>sory deterioration amongst the elderly. Sci Rep. 2018; 8: 5303. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-<lb/>23688-6 PMID: 29674633 <lb/>31. Dinse HR, Kleibel N, Kalisch T, Ragert P, Wilimzig C, Tegenthoff M. Tactile coactivation resets age-<lb/>related decline of human tactile discrimination. Ann Neurol. 2006; 60: 88-94. <lb/>32. Cheeseman JR, Norman JF, Kappers AML. Dynamic cutaneous information is sufficient for precise cur-<lb/>vature discrimination. Sci Rep. 2016; 6: 25473. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep25473 PMID: 27137417 <lb/>33. Lundblad LC, Olausson H, Wasling P, Jood K, Wysocka A, Hamilton JP, et al. Tactile direction discrimi-<lb/>nation in humans after stroke. Brain Communic. 2020; 2(2): fcaa088. https://doi.org/10.1093/ <lb/>braincomms/fcaa088 PMID: 32954335 <lb/>34. Norman JF, Dukes JM, Palmore TN. Aging and haptic shape discrimination: the effects of variations in <lb/>size. Sci Rep. 2020; 10(1): 1-9. <lb/>35. Sathian K, Zangaladze A, Green J, Vitek JL, DeLong MR. Tactile spatial acuity and roughness discrimi-<lb/>nation: impairments due to aging and Parkinson&apos;s disease. Neurol. 1997; 49(1): 168-177. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1212/wnl.49.1.168 PMID: 9222186 <lb/>36. Kenshalo DR Sr. Somesthetic sensitivity in young and elderly humans. J Geront. 1986; 41(6): 732-<lb/>742. https://doi.org/10.1093/geronj/41.6.732 PMID: 3772049 <lb/>37. Billino J, Drewing K. Age effects on visuo-haptic length discrimination: evidence for optimal integration <lb/>of senses in senior adults. Multisens Res. 2018; 31: 273-300. <lb/>38. Braem B, Honore ´J, Rousseaux M, Saj A, Coello Y. Integration of visual and haptic informations in the <lb/>perception of the vertical in young and old healthy adults and right brain-damaged patients. Clin Neuro-<lb/>phys. 2014; 44: 41-48. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neucli.2013.10.137 PMID: 24502904 <lb/>39. Norman JF, Crabtree CE, Norman HF, Moncrief BK, Herrmann M, Kapley N. Aging and the visual, hap-<lb/>tic, and cross-modal perception of natural object shape. Percept. 2006; 35(10): 1383-1395. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1068/p5504 PMID: 17214383 <lb/>40. Kensinger EA. Age differences in memory for arousing and nonarousing emotional words. J Gerontol <lb/>Ser B. 2008; 63: P13-P18. https://doi.org/10.1093/geronb/63.1.p13 PMID: 18332189 <lb/>41. Waring JD, Kensinger EA. Effects of emotional valence and arousal upon memory trade-offs with <lb/>aging. Psychol Aging. 2009; 24(2): 412. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0015526 PMID: 19485658 <lb/>42. Cacioppo JT, Berntson GG, Klein DJ, Poehlmann KM. Psychophysiology of emotion across the life <lb/>span. Ann Rev Gerontol Geriat. 1997; 17: 27-74. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>16 / 17 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>43. Renfroe JB, Bradley MM, Sege CT, Bowers D. Emotional modulation of the late positive potential during <lb/>picture free viewing in older and young adults PLoS ONE. 2016; 11(9): e0162323. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0162323 PMID: 27589393 <lb/>44. Sehlstedt I, Ignell H, Backlund Wasling H, Ackerley R, Olausson H, Croy I. Gentle touch perception <lb/>across the lifespan. Psychol Aging. 2016; 31(2): 176. https://doi.org/10.1037/pag0000074 PMID: <lb/>26950227 <lb/>45. Charles ST, Mather M, Carstensen LL. Aging and emotional memory: The forgettable nature of negative <lb/>images for older adults. J Exp Psychol: General. 2003; 132: 310-324. https://doi.org/10.1037/0096-<lb/>3445.132.2.310 PMID: 12825643 <lb/>46. Curtis V, Aunger R, Rabie T. Evidence that disgust evolved to protect from risk of disease. Proceed <lb/>Royal Society London. Ser B: Biol Sci. 2004; 271(suppl_4): S131-S133. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl. <lb/>2003.0144 PMID: 15252963 <lb/>47. Ferrari V, Bruno N, Chattat R, Codispoti M. Evaluative ratings and attention across the life span: emo-<lb/>tional arousal and gender. Cogn Emot. 2017; 31(3): 552-563. https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2016. <lb/>1140020 PMID: 26864052 <lb/>48. Carstensen LL, Isaacowitz DM, Charles ST. Taking time seriously: A theory of socioemotional selectiv-<lb/>ity. American Psychol; 1999: 54, 165-181. <lb/>49. Cacioppo JT, Berntson GG, Bechara A, Tranel D, Hawkley LC. Could an aging brain contribute to sub-<lb/>jective well-being? The value added by a social neuroscience perspective. In A Todorov, ST Fiske, DA <lb/>Prentice (Eds.), Social neuroscience: Toward understanding the underpinnings of the social mind, 2011 <lb/>(pp. 249-262). New York, NY: Oxford University Press. <lb/>50. Labouvie-Vief G, Gru ¨hn D, Studer J. Dynamic integration of emotion and cognition: Equilibrium regula-<lb/>tion in development and aging. In RM Lerner, ME Lamb, AM Freund (Eds.), The handbook of life-span <lb/>development, 2010 (Vol. 2, pp. 79-115). Hoboken, NJ: Wiley. <lb/>51. Cavdan M, Goktepe N, Drewing K, Doerschner K. Assessing the representational structure of softness <lb/>activated by words. Sci Rep. 2023; 13: 8974. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-35169-6 PMID: <lb/>37268674 <lb/>52. Statistisches Bundesamt (Destatis). Bildungsstand der Bevo ¨lkerung-Ergebnisse des Mikrozensus <lb/>2019, Wiesbaden: Statistisches Bundesamt (Destatis); 2020. <lb/>53. Nasreddine ZS, Phillips NA, Be ´dirian V, Charbonneau S, Whitehead V, Collin I, et al. The Montreal Cog-<lb/>nitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. J Amer Geriatr Soc. <lb/>2005; 53(4): 695-699. <lb/>54. Reik P, Skrandies W. Die affektive Bewertung von imaginierten Geru ¨chen mit dem semantischen Differ-<lb/>ential. Zeitschrift fu ¨r Psychologie. 2006; 214: 108-115. <lb/>55. Kaiser HF, Rice J. Little Jiffy, Mark IV. Educ Psych Meas. 1974; 34: 111-117. <lb/>56. Cavdan M, Freund A, Trieschmann AK, Doerschner K, Drewing K. From hate to love: How learning can <lb/>change affective responses to touched materials. In Haptics: Science, Technology, Applications: 12th <lb/>International Conference, EuroHaptics 2020, Leiden, The Netherlands, September 6-9, 2020, Pro-<lb/>ceedings 2020 Sep 5 (pp. 60-68). Cham: Springer International Publishing. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Touched materials and aging <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296633 January 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>17 / 17 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>