<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Nose to brain targeting of the donepezil nanostructured lipid carrier &lt;i&gt;in situ&lt;/i&gt; gel: formulation, &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;ex vivo&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt; pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic characterization</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Devika</forename>
          <surname>Sonawane</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Varsha</forename>
          <surname>Pokharkar</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T14:04:57.749Z">11/12/2025 2:04:57 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1039$1$d4pm00174e</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1039/d4pm00174e</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Devika Sonawane, Varsha Pokharkar. (2024). Nose to brain targeting of the donepezil nanostructured lipid carrier &lt;i&gt;in situ&lt;/i&gt; gel: formulation, &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;ex vivo&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt; pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic characterization. RSC Pharmaceutics, 1(4), 820-840. DOI: 10.1039/d4pm00174e</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T14:04:47.834923Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T14:04:47.834923Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Advanced lightweight lightning strike protection <lb/>composites based on super-aligned carbon <lb/>nanotube films and thermal-resistant zirconia <lb/>fibers † <lb/>Mingquan Zhu, ‡ ab Peng Zhang, ‡ ad Feng Gao, ‡ a Yunxiang Bai, * ab Hui Zhang, * a <lb/>Min Zu, e Luqi Liu ab and Zhong Zhang * ac <lb/>Carbon nanotube films have drawn attention in the past decade as promising substitutes for aluminum or <lb/>copper used in aircraft lightning strike protection (LSP) systems. Throughout this study, advanced <lb/>lightweight lightning strike protection (LSP) composites are based on highly conductive super-aligned <lb/>carbon nanotube films (SA-CNTFs) and a new isolation layer of zirconia fiber paper. The internal damage <lb/>level of the composite laminate was assessed using a microfocus X-ray system and non-destructive <lb/>ultrasonic techniques. Results show that the composite laminate comprising SA-CNTFs (1000-layer) and <lb/>zirconia fiber paper (1-layer) effectively shields CFRP from 100 kA lightning strikes. Furthermore, weight <lb/>reductions of approximately 44.3% and 10.4% can be achieved, respectively, relative to the isolation layer <lb/>of glass fibers and quartz fibers. Meanwhile, the lightning protection mechanism was further studied. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Non-metallic composites like carbon ber (CFRP) and glass <lb/>ber-reinforced polymers (GFRPs) blend the exibility of poly-<lb/>mer materials with the enhanced strength, stiffness, and wear <lb/>resistance of reinforced materials. These composites are widely <lb/>used in engineering practices, including the manufacturing of <lb/>advanced new generation aircra, 1 wind turbines, 2 etc., replac-<lb/>ing the metal counterparts. According to the data, the content of <lb/>composites in Airbus A350 and Boeing 787 accounts for more <lb/>than 50% of the total weight. 3,4 CFRPs boast low density, <lb/>corrosion resistance, and superior mechanical properties, but <lb/>their low electrical conductivity makes them susceptible to <lb/>lightning strikes during operating. 5,6 Statistics show that each <lb/>airplane is struck by lightning more than once yearly or during <lb/>its 2000-5000 ight hours. 7 Lightning strike is a high-energy, <lb/>complex, and instantaneous process. The lightning waveform <lb/>standard comprises multiple strokes of varying intensity and <lb/>duration with currents ranging from a few hundred amperes to <lb/>upwards of 200 kA. The transient current rise to 200 kA is <lb/>conveyed to the CFRP structures in under a few hundred <lb/>microseconds. 8 The lightning current contributes over 90% of <lb/>the total energy and will search for an optimal (least resistance) <lb/>path. 9 The remaining energy converts into light, heat, and shock <lb/>waves. 10,11 This may cause very substantial damage to the CFRP <lb/>structure via heat, pressure, acoustic shock, and electromag-<lb/>netic shock. 12-14 <lb/>Several engineering compromises have been made to <lb/>address these issues. For example, aluminum spray coating and <lb/>expanded metal foils (EMFs) have been generally applied to <lb/>CFRP surfaces to boost the electrical conductivity in Lightning <lb/>Strike Protection (LSP) systems used in current aircra. 15,16 <lb/>However, critical issues with these metallic materials include <lb/>high density, poor compatibility, inconsistent coefficients of <lb/>thermal expansion, and failure under high temperatures. 17 <lb/>Consequently, advances in conductive materials and structural <lb/>design technologies have led to the investigation of novel <lb/>lightning strike protection technologies. 18-22 Low-dimensional, <lb/>advanced carbon materials, like carbon nanotubes (CNTs) <lb/>exhibit high electrical conductivity, 13,23 are considered the ideal <lb/>alternatives for shielding CFRP from lightning strikes. Zhang <lb/>et al. integrated 12-layer CNT thin lms into CFRP laminates, <lb/>which signicantly enhanced both in-plane and through-<lb/>thickness conductivity. Additionally, this modication <lb/></body>

			<front>a CAS Key Laboratory of Nanosystem and Hierarchical Fabrication, CAS Center for <lb/>Excellence in Nanoscience, National Center for Nanoscience and Technology, <lb/>Beijing, 100190, China. E-mail: baiyunxiang0101@163.com; zhangh@nanoctr.cn <lb/>b University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100049, China <lb/>c CAS Key Laboratory Mechanical Behavior and Design of Materials, Department of <lb/>Modern Mechanics, University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei, 230027, <lb/>China. E-mail: zhongzhang@ustc.edu.cn <lb/>d <lb/>State Key Laboratory of Metastable Materials Science and Technology, College of <lb/>Materials Science and Engineering, Yanshan University, Qinhuangdao 066004, China <lb/>e CAS Key Laboratory of Standardization and Measurement for Nanotechnology, CAS <lb/>Center for Excellence in Nanoscience, National Center for Nanoscience and <lb/>Technology, 100190, Beijing, China <lb/> † Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available. See DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1039/d4na00392f <lb/> ‡ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Cite this: Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, <lb/>4858 <lb/>Received 10th May 2024 <lb/>Accepted 20th July 2024 <lb/>DOI: 10.1039/d4na00392f <lb/>rsc.li/nanoscale-advances <lb/>4858 | Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Nanoscale <lb/>Advances <lb/>PAPER <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/>View Journal | View Issue <lb/></front>

			<body>reduced the damage depth by 68.0% aer a 100 kA lightning <lb/>strike. 24 However, this method does not fully exploit the <lb/>mechanical advantages of epoxy composites, is not compatible <lb/>with conventional technology, and is not easy to repair. 20 To <lb/>address this problem, researchers have preferred applying <lb/>a highly conductive lm directly to the surface of the CFRP <lb/>laminate. CNT lms have low density, high thermostability, <lb/>good chemical/environmental stability and compatibility with <lb/>CFRP. 13,23-29 Recently, Han et al. used 70 mm thick buckypaper to <lb/>effectively withstand 40 kA lightning strikes. 27 However, the <lb/>areal density was still very high. <lb/>Glass bers are typically introduced as an isolation layer <lb/>between the CFRP and LSP layer. 17 In the laboratory, we set up <lb/>the Miniature Tip Discharge System (MTDS) and studied the <lb/>failure mechanisms of the composite system. 30 The results <lb/>indicated that the isolation layers signicantly enhance LSP <lb/>effectiveness through their thermal resistance and insulation <lb/>properties. In addition, compared with the metal mesh/foil LSP <lb/>layer, SA-CNTFs have advantages such as low density, high <lb/>thermostability, good chemical/environmental stability and <lb/>compatibility with CFRP, while compared with buckypaper <lb/>(electrical conductivity &lt; 6000 S m -1 ), SA-CNTFs have higher <lb/>purity, higher densication degree, and much better electrical <lb/>conductivity (∼6 × 10 4 S m -1 ). As a result, we then craed an <lb/>advanced composite laminate using quartz bers for the isola-<lb/>tion layers. This laminate, consisting of 1500 SA-CNTF layers <lb/>and 2 quartz ber prepreg layers, demonstrated the capacity to <lb/>withstand a 100 kA lightning strike. 31 Compared to LSP lami-<lb/>nates using glass ber isolation layers, the areal density can be <lb/>reduced by ∼38%. However, both have much room for <lb/>improvement in thermal resistance and insulating properties <lb/>compared to lightweight, high-performance ceramic bers, like <lb/>zirconia bers. 32 <lb/>In this work, advanced lightweight LSP composites are <lb/>fabricated using zirconia ber as the isolation layer. Simulated <lb/>lightning strikes were employed to explore the LSP performance <lb/>of the zirconia ber-based isolation layer and validate the <lb/>protection mechanism. Aer lightning strikes, the internal <lb/>damage level of the composite laminate was assessed using <lb/>a microfocus X-ray system and non-destructive ultrasonic <lb/>techniques, and compression tests provided additional evalua-<lb/>tion of the damage level. The composite laminate, composed of <lb/>SA-CNTFs (1000-layer) and zirconia ber (1-layer), was demon-<lb/>strated to have the capacity to withstand 100 kA lightning <lb/>strikes. Furthermore, a weight reduction of ∼44.3% and <lb/>∼10.4% was realized compared to isolation layers composed of <lb/>glass ber and quartz ber, respectively. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>Characterization of the composite laminates <lb/>SEM analysis was conducted to characterize the microscopic <lb/>morphology of composite laminates. Fig. S1a and b † reveal that <lb/>the zirconia ber paper consists of a multitude of randomly <lb/>brous networks with a diameter of approximately 4-6 mm. <lb/>Zirconia bers are composed solely of the elements oxygen and <lb/>zirconium, without any doping from additional elements <lb/>(Fig. S1c †). The zirconia ber paper was regarded as &quot;isolation <lb/>layers&quot;, and SA-CNTFs were used as &quot;conductive layers&quot; and <lb/>then embedded with the CFRP laminates by hot compression. <lb/>The structure of composite laminates is schematically depicted <lb/>in Fig. 1, and the typical microscopic morphologies of the <lb/>carbon ber, zirconia ber paper, and SA-CNTFs are illustrated <lb/>in Fig. 1b-d, respectively. The three components (SA-CNTFs, <lb/>zirconia ber, CFRP prepreg) of the composite are effectively <lb/>bonded by epoxy resin. Due to the spaces between the CNTs in <lb/>the SA-CNTFs and the loose structure of the zirconia bers, the <lb/>epoxy resin fully permeates these materials. There are no <lb/>apparent bubbles between the layers and no resin-rich layer. <lb/>Moreover, the SA-CNTFs remain super-aligned and have excel-<lb/>lent electrical conductivity aer curing. <lb/>Damage analysis of samples following LS tests <lb/>Lightning strike tests were performed with a D waveform to <lb/>directly assess the LSP properties of composite laminates. To <lb/>the best of our knowledge, carbon ber will be severely broken <lb/>inside the laminate when no conductive layer is on the CFRP <lb/>surface. The leading causes of severe damage are shockwaves <lb/>and Joule-heating induced by lightning strikes. Without the <lb/>addition of SA-CNTFs, the LSP laminate samples remain insu-<lb/>lated. Therefore, we do not design a test without a conductive <lb/>layer. 13,33 However, as the number of layers increases, the elec-<lb/>trical conductivity improves signicantly. When 1000 layers of <lb/>CNT lm are added, the sheet resistance decreases to 2.56 U <lb/>, -1 (Table S1 †). Fig. 2a1 and b1 show that the composite <lb/>laminate comprises 1000/1200 layer SA-CNTFs and one layer of <lb/>zirconia ber paper. The C-scan and B-scan images indicate that <lb/>Fig. 1 Typical morphology of the composite laminate. (a) Optical <lb/>microscopy image of the cross-section of composite laminates, <lb/>(b)-(d) are the SEM images of the red rectangular area in (d), corre-<lb/>sponding to the conductive layer, isolation layer, and CFRP laminate, <lb/>respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 | </note>
    
            <page>4859 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

            <body>the composite laminate surface is at and free of defects, <lb/>cracks, and delamination before the lightning strike tests <lb/>(Fig. S2 †). Although the existence of the conductive SA-CNTFs <lb/>prevents the composite laminates from severe damage, <lb/>damage to the surface is inevitable aer the lightning strike. As <lb/>shown in Fig. 2a2 and b2, the SA-CNTFs on the composite <lb/>laminate&apos;s surface were severely damaged and debonded from <lb/>the bottom CFRP laminate aer the lightning strike. The <lb/>damage of SA-CNTFs is observed along the radial direction of <lb/>CNTs in the middle of the specimen. <lb/>The assessment of the effectiveness of LSP involves <lb/>inspecting the internal damage within composite laminates. <lb/>Ultrasonic testing provides a non-destructive method for the <lb/>assessment of the internal damage. The C-scan image and B-<lb/>scan reveal extensive damage on the surface of the SA-CNTFs <lb/>along the CNT radial in Z1C1000, while no internal damage is <lb/>observed within the CFRP laminate (Fig. 2a3 and b3). The <lb/>specimen exhibits a maximum damaged area of approximately <lb/>3.94 × 10 4 mm 2 and reaches a depth of around 0.3 mm (Table <lb/>1). As the number of CNT layers increases to 1200, the damage is <lb/>reduced, and the B-scan demonstrates a uniform pattern in the <lb/>cross-section, verifying that the CFRP laminate remains intact <lb/>(Fig. 2a4 and b4). Furthermore, the specimen exhibits <lb/>a maximum damage area of approximately 3.75 × 10 4 mm 2 and <lb/>a depth of 0.1 mm (Table 1). Signicantly, the damage depth of <lb/>Z1C1200 is lower than that of Z1C1000. The primary reason for <lb/>this reduction is that an increase in the conductive layer aids in <lb/>transferring lightning current to the ground, effectively dissi-<lb/>pating energy and shielding the laminate from damage. <lb/>Previous results show that carbon ber breakage was observed <lb/>in the composite laminate (damage depth ∼ 1.8 mm) composed <lb/>of 1200-layer SA-CNTFs and 2-layer quartz ber when suffering <lb/>the lightning strike with a peak current I peak = 100 kA. 31 <lb/>Therefore, zirconia ber demonstrates superior LSP effective-<lb/>ness compared with quartz ber. Additionally, a comparison of <lb/>LSP effectiveness and corresponding surface areal densities <lb/>with CNT lms as conductive layers and different isolation <lb/>layers is provided in Table 1. Among the materials achieving <lb/>LSP, zirconia bers as isolation layers exhibited the lowest areal <lb/>density. Although the surface damage to these SA-CNTF-based <lb/>protective materials is very severe, the severely damaged <lb/>surfaces effectively dissipate the lightning energy, reducing the <lb/>depth of damage in the thickness direction. <lb/>A microfocus X-ray system was utilized to further investigate <lb/>internal damage in Z1C1200. 13,34 Typical X-ray images of CFRP <lb/>have a homogeneous light grey signal, suggesting that it is free of <lb/>cracks and defects. In contrast, if cracks or defects exist, black <lb/>areas will occur in X-ray images. The size of the black area deter-<lb/>mines the damage level. 34 Before lightning strikes, the cross-<lb/>section of composite laminates is divided into three layers: the <lb/>SA-CNTFs and CFRP are light grey, and the isolation layer is off-<lb/>white with some black spots. The most severely damaged area of <lb/>the specimen was selected for the test aer lightning strikes. As <lb/>shown in the vertical cross-section, the morphology of the <lb/>Fig. 2 Damage assessment of composite laminates. (a) Z1C1000. (b) Z1C1200. Images labeled with subscripts 1, 2, 3, and 4 are the digital <lb/>photographs of composite laminates before LS, after LS, C-scan image, and B-scan image. (c) X-ray image of internal damage to Z1C1200 prior <lb/>to and following the LS. <lb/></body>

			<page>4860</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>isolation layer and CFRP of the specimen aer lightning strikes <lb/>remained consistent with the original specimen, indicating an <lb/>excellent LSP effect. The disappearance of the light grey color on <lb/>the surface clearly indicates the absence or break of SA-CNTFs in <lb/>the top layer, corroborating the SEM results (Fig. 2c). <lb/>Possible mechanism of SA-CNTFs and zirconia ber for LSP <lb/>The morphologies of the damaged surface are examined <lb/>using SEM. As shown in Fig. 3a, the surface SA-CNTFs near <lb/>the arc attachment point are severely damaged with the <lb/>aligned CNT network disrupted and extensive resin ablation <lb/>observed (Fig. 3b and c). To study the LSP mechanism, Raman <lb/>spectroscopy was conducted. The observed decrease in the I G / <lb/>I D ratio indicated an increase in the prevalence of defects <lb/>(Fig. 3d). XRD further revealed the phase transitions of the <lb/>SA-CNTFs during the LS tests. The position of the peak (D 002 ) <lb/>upshis slightly, indicating a slight decrease in the interlayer <lb/>spacing of the CNTs (Fig. 3e). The XPS survey detected vari-<lb/>ations in the elemental composition of SA-CNTFs prior to and <lb/>following the LS tests. There was a signicant increase in the <lb/>nitrogen and oxygen elements, indicating the nitrogenization <lb/>and oxidation of CNTs due to the lightning strike process. As <lb/>a result, when LS occurs, the conductivity layer channels <lb/>a portion of the current away. The instantaneous Joule heat-<lb/>ing from lightning current triggers various chemical reac-<lb/>tions and physical processes, including oxidation, <lb/>nitrogenization, phase change of CNTs, and ablation of resin. <lb/>Those reactions help to dissipate a portion of the generated <lb/>heat. 35 However, such small amounts of SA-CNTFs and resin <lb/>cannot dissipate all the heat alone, 36 and the residual <lb/>temperature is then conveyed to the underlying layers. An <lb/>excellent LSP effect can be achieved if the isolation layer <lb/>effectively dissipates the residual temperature, preventing <lb/>the temperature transferred to the CFRP from reaching its <lb/>decomposition temperature. 37 <lb/>Consistent with our previous validation results, there are two <lb/>critical factors: thermal resistance and thermal insulation. 30,31 <lb/>We tested the thermal insulation performance of different <lb/>isolation layers to further elucidate the LSP effectiveness of <lb/>zirconia ber. Composite laminates consisting of different <lb/>isolation layers and the same number of layers of carbon ber <lb/>prepreg were constructed, and their thermal conductivity in the <lb/>thickness direction was tested. 38 As listed in Tables 2 and S1, † <lb/>the thermal conductivity of composite laminates composed of <lb/>zirconia ber with CFRP shows the lowest thermal conductivity, <lb/>followed by glass ber and quartz ber. It is widely recognized <lb/>that the thermal conductivity of surface SA-CNTFs, both axially <lb/>and radially, spans from tens to hundreds of W m -1 K -1 , <lb/>substantially exceeding that of the isolation layer by hundreds <lb/>of times. Consequently, heat diffusion occurs more efficiently <lb/>from the SA-CNTFs. Due to the low thermal conductivity of <lb/>zirconia bers, the majority of the heat dissipates within the <lb/>surface layer of the isolation layer and SA-CNTF layer, with only <lb/>a minimal amount transferring to the CFRP, insufficient to <lb/>cause damage. Another critical factor is thermal resistance. <lb/>Zirconia ber has superior thermal resistance (∼2700 °C), much <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>The sample composition and the damage condition after simulated lightning strikes compared with other composite laminates a <lb/>No. <lb/>Name <lb/>Composition of composite laminates <lb/>Extent of damage <lb/>Materials of <lb/>isolation layers <lb/>Layer count of <lb/>isolation layers <lb/>Thickness of CNT <lb/>lms (mm) <lb/>Total areal density of isolation <lb/>layers and conductive layers <lb/>(g m -2 <lb/>) <lb/>Damage location <lb/>Depth (mm) <lb/>Area (mm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>Whether protection <lb/>is achieved or not <lb/>1 <lb/>Z1C1000 <lb/>ZrO <lb/>2 ber <lb/>1 <lb/>30 <lb/>206 <lb/>Surface <lb/>∼0.3 <lb/>∼3.94 × 10 4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>Z1C1200 <lb/>ZrO <lb/>2 ber <lb/>1 <lb/>36 <lb/>212 <lb/>Surface <lb/>∼0.1 <lb/>∼3.75 × 10 4 <lb/>3 <lb/>(Ref. 31) 3 <lb/>Q3C500 <lb/>Quartz <lb/>ber <lb/>3 <lb/>15 <lb/>310 <lb/>Surface <lb/>∼0.1 <lb/>∼2.82 × 10 4 <lb/>3 <lb/>(Ref. 31) 4 <lb/>G3C500 <lb/>Glass <lb/>ber <lb/>3 <lb/>15 <lb/>370 <lb/>Inside <lb/>∼2.0 <lb/>∼1.68 × 10 4 <lb/>7 <lb/>(Ref. 31) 5 <lb/>Q2C1200 <lb/>Quartz <lb/>ber <lb/>2 <lb/>36 <lb/>224 <lb/>Inside <lb/>∼1.8 <lb/>∼2.55 × 10 4 <lb/>7 <lb/>(Ref. 31) 6 <lb/>Q2C1500 <lb/>Quartz <lb/>ber <lb/>2 <lb/>45 <lb/>230 <lb/>Surface <lb/>∼0.2 <lb/>∼4.07 × 10 4 <lb/>3 <lb/>(Ref. 27) 7 <lb/>P-IEP-BP-4 <lb/>Boron nitride <lb/>1 <lb/>70 <lb/>325 <lb/>Surface <lb/>∼0 <lb/>∼860 <lb/>3 <lb/>a <lb/>The <lb/>&quot;Name&quot; column in the table is dened as follows: Z: zirconia <lb/>ber paper. G: glass <lb/>ber prepreg. Q: quartz <lb/>ber prepreg. C: SA-CNTFs. The numbers indicate the layer count. The labels <lb/>&quot;Surface&quot; and <lb/>&quot;Inside&quot; refer to the location of the damaged area, either on the surface or inside. <lb/>&quot;Depth&quot; represents the maximum depth of the damaged area, while <lb/>&quot;Area&quot; refers to the <lb/>largest area of the damaged surface. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 | </note>
    
            <page>4861 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>higher than that of quartz ber (∼1700 °C). No melting was <lb/>observed aer the lightning strike, and the zirconia bers <lb/>retained their intact shape (Fig. 3c). Therefore, owing to their <lb/>superior thermal resistance and insulation properties, zirconia <lb/>bers are more effective as isolation layer materials than glass <lb/>and quartz bers. <lb/>Residual strength of the samples following the LS tests <lb/>It must be noted that the conductivity layer and isolation layer <lb/>in composite laminates act as sacricial layers. Even if the <lb/>sacricial layers are damaged or sacriced, protection is ach-<lb/>ieved as long as the mechanical properties of the bottom <lb/>material are maintained. 7,39 The damage level and actual effec-<lb/>tiveness against lightning strikes can be visualized in the <lb/>residual mechanical properties. 40 Lightning strikes can severely <lb/>damage composite laminates by shock and joule heating <lb/>induced by lightning currents. Samples in the lightning strike <lb/>zone are exposed to thermal degradation, and the most severely <lb/>damaged areas show the worst mechanical properties. The most <lb/>severely damaged area was selected for the test for the post-<lb/>strike samples. 17,40 All the laminates were cut into boards <lb/>measuring 75.0 mm in length and 12.5 mm in width, in <lb/>compliance with GB/T 3356-2014. The boards were positioned <lb/>on two supports with a span of 48 mm, with the non-struck side <lb/>facing upwards to undergo exural failure. Fig. 4a shows that <lb/>the load-displacement curves of post-strike Z1C1000 and post-<lb/>strike Z1C1200 are highly consistent with the pristine samples&apos; <lb/>curves, indicating that the mechanical properties remain intact <lb/>aer LS. Aer LS, the residual strengths of Z1C1000 and <lb/>Z1C1200 are 1222 ± 59 MPa and 1118 ± 50 MPa, respectively, <lb/>Fig. 4 Residual strength and flexural modulus of the composite laminate after LS tests. (a) Specimens load-displacement curves before and after <lb/>LS tests. (b) Residual strength of the samples before and after LS tests. (c) Flexural modulus of the samples before and after LS tests. <lb/>Table 2 The thermal resistance and thermal conductivity of zirconia fibers compared with other isolation layers used in LSP <lb/>Materials <lb/>Thermal resistance <lb/>of isolation layers (°C) <lb/>Thermal conductivity of <lb/>isolation layers with CFRP (W m -1 K -1 ) <lb/>Zirconia ber <lb/>∼2700 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>Glass ber <lb/>∼900 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>Quartz ber <lb/>∼1700 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>Fig. 3 Characterization of the specimen. (a-c) SEM images of the fracture surface of the specimen after LS tests. (d) Raman spectra of SA-CNTFs <lb/>prior to and following the LS tests. (e) XRD study of SA-CNTFs prior to and following the LS tests. (f) XPS survey scans of the SA-CNTFs prior to and <lb/>following the LS tests. <lb/></body>

			<page>4862</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>and the exural moduli of Z1C1000 and Z1C1200 are 54.55 ± <lb/>1.62 GPa and 50.13 ± 4.48 GPa, respectively. The results <lb/>demonstrate that Z1C1000 could retain residual strengths of <lb/>more than 98.0% and more than 99.0% of its residual strengths <lb/>(Fig. 4a and b). For Z1C1200, the residual strengths and <lb/>modulus remained at 91.4% and 84.0%, respectively. If more <lb/>than 80% of the composite&apos;s residual strength is retained aer <lb/>LS, the composite can be appropriately maintained and reused <lb/>in engineering applications. 41 In conclusion, the Z1C1000 and <lb/>Z1C1200 laminates combine lower surface density with excel-<lb/>lent LSP performance, making them suitable for continued use <lb/>in practical applications (Fig. 4). <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this study, we developed a lightweight, advanced LSP system <lb/>composed of conductive SA-CNTFs and zirconia bers and <lb/>further explored its reliability and mechanism for LSP. The <lb/>conductive SA-CNTFs can provide effective LSP by performing <lb/>two key functions: conducting current away and aiding in the <lb/>dissipation of heat generated by lightning currents through <lb/>processes such as gasication, oxidation, phase change, etc. <lb/>Furthermore, with the lower thermal conductivity and high <lb/>thermal resistance, the zirconia bers isolation layer can <lb/>effectively impede Joule heat transfer to CFRP and provide <lb/>a good LSP effect. The composite laminate composed of 1000 <lb/>layers of SA-CNTFs and 1 layer of zirconia ber paper can shield <lb/>the CFRP from 100 kA lightning strikes. The excellent LSP effect <lb/>was demonstrated by the microfocus X-ray system and non-<lb/>destructive ultrasonic techniques. Consequently, zirconia <lb/>bers outperform glass and quartz bers as isolation materials <lb/>due to their superior thermal resistance and insulation capa-<lb/>bilities, leading to weight reductions of ∼44.3% and ∼10.4%, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>Experimental section <lb/>Materials <lb/>SA-CNTFs (1000-layer) with an areal density and thickness of <lb/>∼20 g m -2 and 30 mm, respectively, were supplied by the <lb/>Department of Physics &amp; Tsinghua-Foxconn Nanotechnology <lb/>Research Center, Tsinghua University. The higher the number <lb/>of layers, the higher the surface density and thickness (for <lb/>a more detailed preparation process, please see Text S1 †). 29 <lb/>Epoxy adhesive lms with an areal density of ∼90 g m -2 were <lb/>used. Unidirectional carbon ber prepregs (G125000) with <lb/>a thickness of 0.1 mm were purchased from Shanghai HuanXu <lb/>Group Co., Ltd. The areal density was ∼100 g m -2 , with a ber <lb/>weight fraction of 60%. ZrO 2 ber paper with an areal density of <lb/>∼96 g m -2 and a thickness of 0.6 mm was purchased from <lb/>Foshan Inai Energy Saving Material Co., Ltd. <lb/>Preparation of composite laminates <lb/>The method for preparing composite laminates follows the <lb/>curing procedure recommended in our previous study. 31 Carbon <lb/>ber prepreg, zirconia ber paper, and SA-CNTFs were <lb/>sequentially layered and subsequently hot-pressed to obtain <lb/>composite laminates. Composite laminate compositions are <lb/>provided in Table 1. <lb/>Lightning strike test <lb/>The simulated lightning strike test is conducted at the Hefei <lb/>Hangtai Electrophysics Co., Ltd. The lightning strike tests are <lb/>guided by the SAE ARP 5416A-2013 standard lightning strike <lb/>introduction test. 8 For this research, the D waveform (I peak = <lb/>100 kA) was simulated on the composite laminates. The lami-<lb/>nate was clamped and electrically grounded by a copper plate. <lb/>And the discharged electrode was located at the center of the <lb/>laminate and linked with a copper wire. <lb/>Other characterization <lb/>The severity of damage was inspected with non-destructive <lb/>ultrasonic testing. The B-scan and C-scan images obtained by <lb/>non-destructive ultrasonic testing can be analyzed to determine <lb/>the damage depth and area of composite laminates. 42,43 (For <lb/>further details on how to analyze this, please refer to our earlier <lb/>publication.) 31 A microfocus X-ray system (Xradia 520 Versa, <lb/>Zeiss) was used to further evaluate the internal damage of <lb/>composite laminates. The scanning voltage was set at 60 kV (83 <lb/>mA), with an exposure time of 3 seconds for each radiograph. <lb/>The Scout-and-Scan Control System Reconstructor soware was <lb/>utilized for reconstructing each scan volume, with manipula-<lb/>tion and analysis conducted using XM3D Viewer soware. The <lb/>surface morphologies of composite laminates were character-<lb/>ized by scanning electron microscopy (Hitachi SU8220). The <lb/>elemental composition was analyzed by energy-dispersive X-ray <lb/>spectroscopy mapping (SEM-EDS). X-ray photoelectron spec-<lb/>troscopy was used to analyze the elemental content of SA-<lb/>CNTFs. Raman spectra for the SA-CNTFs were acquired using <lb/>a Renishaw inVia Plus Raman spectrometer, equipped with <lb/>a 514 nm laser. The overhead view of laminates was obtained by <lb/>a digital camera (Canon, ESO M50). The compressive strengths <lb/>of composite laminates were measured using an MTS C45 105 <lb/>Universal Testing Machine under the GB/T 3356-2014 standard. <lb/>Additionally, the &quot;laser ash&quot; technique (LFA467, Netzsch) <lb/>along with differential scanning calorimetry (DSC, Q2000) was <lb/>employed to evaluate the through-thickness thermal diffusivity <lb/>(a) and heat capacity (C p ), respectively. Subsequently, the <lb/>thermal conductivity (K) was subsequently calculated using the <lb/>equation K = arC p , where r represents the density of composite <lb/>laminates. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>The data supporting this article have been included as part of <lb/>the ESI. † <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: ZZ, HZ, YB, MZ. Methodology: MZ, FG, YB, <lb/>MZ. Investigation: ZZ, HZ, YB, MZ. Visualization: MZ, FG, FG. <lb/>Funding acquisition: ZZ. Project administration: ZZ, HZ, YB. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 | </note>
    
            <page>4863 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>
    
            <div type="contribution">Supervision: ZZ, HZ, YB. Writing -original dra: MZ, PZ, FG, <lb/>YB. Writing -review &amp; editing: ZZ, LL, HZ, YB, MZ, PZ, FG. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflicts of interest <lb/>The authors declare no competing nancial interest in this <lb/>work. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported by the National Key Basic Research <lb/>Program of China (grant no. 2022YFA1205400). <lb/>Notes and references <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1 B. Parveez, M. I. Kittur, I. A. Badruddin, S. Kamangar, <lb/>M. Hussien and M. A. Umarfarooq, Polymers, 2022, 14, 5007. <lb/>2 P. Veers, K. Dykes, E. Lantz, S. Barth, C. L. Bottasso, <lb/>O. Carlson, A. Clion, J. Green, P. Green and H. Holttinen, <lb/>Science, 2019, 366, eaau2027. <lb/>3 K. Lu, Science, 2010, 328, 319-320. <lb/>4 Q. Dong, Y. Guo, X. Sun and Y. Jia, Polymer, 2015, 56, 385-<lb/>394. <lb/>5 H. Kawakami, Lightning Strike Induced Damage Mechanisms of <lb/>Carbon Fiber Composites, University of Washington, 2011. <lb/>6 Y. Guo, Y. Xu, Q. Wang, Q. Dong, X. Yi and Y. Jia, Compos. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 2019, 169, 95-102. <lb/>7 V. Kumar, T. Yokozeki, C. Karch, A. A. Hassen, C. J. Hershey, <lb/>S. Kim, J. M. Lindahl, A. Barnes, Y. K. Bandari and V. Kunc, <lb/>Part B, 2020, 183, 107688. <lb/>8 A.-L. Committee, Aircra Lightning Test Method ARP5416, SAE <lb/>International, 2013. <lb/>9 V. Mazur, Principles of Lightning Physics, IOP Publishing, <lb/>2016. <lb/>10 V. Kumar, T. Yokozeki, C. Karch, A. A. Hassen, C. J. Hershey, <lb/>S. Kim, J. M. Lindahl, A. Barnes, Y. K. Bandari and V. Kunc, <lb/>Composites, Part B, 2020, 183, 107688. <lb/>11 J. Lee, T. E. Lacy, C. U. Pittman and J. N. Reddy, Compos. <lb/>Struct., 2019, 224, 111039. <lb/>12 P. Feraboli and M. Miller, Composites, Part A, 2009, 40, 954-<lb/>967. <lb/>13 B. Wang, Y. Duan, Z. Xin, X. Yao, D. Abliz and G. Ziegmann, <lb/>Compos. Sci. Technol., 2018, 158, 51-60. <lb/>14 X. Zhang, X. Tian, N. Wu, S. Zhao, Y. Qin, F. Pan, S. Yue, <lb/>X. Ma, J. Qiao, W. Xu, W. Liu, J. Liu, M. Zhao, K. Ostrikov <lb/>and Z. Zeng, Sci. Adv., 2024, 10(11), eadl6498. <lb/>15 M. Gagné and D. Therriault, Prog. Aerosp. Sci., 2014, 64, 1-16. <lb/>16 Y. Guo, Y. Xu, Q. Wang, Q. Dong, X. Yi and Y. Jia, Composites, <lb/>Part A, 2019, 117, 211-218. <lb/>17 Y. Guo, Y. Xu, L. Zhang, X. Wei, Q. Dong, X. Yi and Y. Jia, <lb/>Compos. Sci. Technol., 2019, 174, 117-124. <lb/>18 P. S. M. Rajesh, F. Sirois and D. Therriault, Mater. Des., 2018, <lb/>139, 45-55. <lb/>19 S. Yamashita, Y. Hirano, T. Sonehara, J. Takahashi, <lb/>K. Kawabe and T. Murakami, Composites, Part A, 2017, 101, <lb/>185-194. <lb/>20 Z. J. Zhao, G. J. Xian, J. G. Yu, J. Wang, J. F. Tong, J. H. Wei, <lb/>C. C. Wang, P. Moreira and X. S. Yi, Compos. Sci. Technol., <lb/>2018, 167, 555-562. <lb/>21 J. Gou, Y. Tang, F. Liang, Z. Zhao, D. Firsich and J. Fielding, <lb/>Composites, Part B, 2010, 41, 192-198. <lb/>22 J. Langot, E. Gourcerol, A. Serbescu, D. Brassard, K. Chizari, <lb/>M. Lapalme, A. Desautels, F. Sirois and D. Therriault, <lb/>Composites, Part A, 2023, 175, 107772. <lb/>23 V. Kumar, S. Sharma, A. Pathak, B. P. Singh, S. R. Dhakate, <lb/>T. Yokozeki, T. Okada and T. Ogasawara, Compos. Struct., <lb/>2019, 210, 581-589. <lb/>24 J. Zhang, X. Zhang, X. Cheng, Y. Hei, L. Xing and Z. Li, <lb/>Composites, Part B, 2019, 168, 342-352. <lb/>25 D. K. Chakravarthi, V. N. Khabashesku, R. Vaidyanathan, <lb/>J. Blaine, S. Yarlagadda, D. Roseman, Q. Zeng and <lb/>E. V. Barrera, Adv. Funct. Mater., 2011, 21, 2527-2533. <lb/>26 J. S. Bulmer, A. Kaniyoor and J. A. Elliott, Adv. Mater., 2021, <lb/>33, e2008432. <lb/>27 J.-h. Han, H. Zhang, M.-j. Chen, D. Wang, Q. Liu, Q.-l. Wu <lb/>and Z. Zhang, Carbon, 2015, 94, 101-113. <lb/>28 Q. Xia, H. Mei, Z. Zhang, Y. Liu, Y. Liu and J. Leng, <lb/>Composites, Part B, 2020, 180, 107563. <lb/>29 Y. Bai, M. Zhu, S. Wang, L. Liu and Z. Zhang, Carbon, 2023, <lb/>202, 425-431. <lb/>30 Y. Bai, M. Zhu, S. Wang, F. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Qu, X. Cui, <lb/>G. Wang, L. Liu, H. Zhang and Z. Zhang, Composites, Part <lb/>A, 2023, 167, 107394. <lb/>31 Y. Bai, M. Zhu, S. Wang, F. Gao, R. Gao, C. Wang, G. Wang, <lb/>H. Jin, L. Liu, H. Zhang and Z. Zhang, Composites, Part A, <lb/>2023, 173, 107617. <lb/>32 B. Li, H. Tian, L. Li, W. Liu, J. Liu, Z. Zeng and N. Wu, Adv. <lb/>Funct. Mater., 2024, 2314653. <lb/>33 H. Zhu, K. Fu, B. Yang and Y. Li, Compos. Sci. Technol., 2021, <lb/>207, 108675. <lb/>34 G. P. McCombe, J. Rouse, R. S. Trask, P. J. Withers and <lb/>I. P. Bond, Composites, Part A, 2012, 43, 613-620. <lb/>35 Q. Xia, H. Mei, Z. Zhang, Y. Liu, Y. Liu and J. Leng, <lb/>Composites, Part B, 2020, 180, 107563. <lb/>36 G. Abdelal and A. Murphy, Compos. Struct., 2014, 109, 268-278. <lb/>37 Y. Guo, Y. Xu, Q. Wang, Q. Dong, X. Yi and Y. Jia, Compos. <lb/>Sci. Technol., 2019, 169, 95-102. <lb/>38 S. Kamiyama, Y. Hirano, T. Okada and T. Ogasawara, <lb/>Compos. Sci. Technol., 2018, 161, 107-114. <lb/>39 X. Li, Y. Zhou, S. Kamiyama, T. Okada and T. Yokozeki, <lb/>Composites, Part A, 2024, 177, 107933. <lb/>40 V. Kumar, T. Yokozeki, T. Okada, Y. Hirano, T. Goto, <lb/>T. Takahashi and T. Ogasawara, Composites, Part A, 2018, <lb/>114, 429-438. <lb/>41 H. Chu, Q. Xia, Z. Zhang, Y. Liu and J. Leng, Carbon, 2019, <lb/>143, 204-214. <lb/>42 C. J. Norris, I. P. Bond and R. S. Trask, Composites, Part A, <lb/>2011, 42, 639-648. <lb/>43 G. J. Williams, I. P. Bond and R. S. Trask, Composites, Part A, <lb/>2009, 40, 1399-1406. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4864</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Nanoscale Adv., 2024, 6, 4858-4864 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nanoscale Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 23 July 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 5:14:14 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online </note>


	</text>


  </TEI>