<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-18T16:36:38.668Z">11/18/2025 4:36:38 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T16:36:29.081949Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-18T16:36:29.081949Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions <lb/>of internal migrants in China <lb/>Sichen LiuID 1☯ *, Quanling CaiID 2,3☯ , Mingxing Wang 4 , Kaisheng Di 2,3,5 <lb/>1 College of Economics and Management, Wuhan University, Wuhan, Hubei Province, China, 2 Department <lb/>of Management and Economics, Tianjin University, Tianjin, China, 3 College of Politics and Public <lb/>Administration, Qinghai Minzu University, Xining, Qinghai Province, China, 4 College of Finance and <lb/>Economics, Qinghai University, Xining, Qinghai Province, China, 5 Department of Party Committee, Party <lb/>School of the Qinghai Provincial Committee of CPC, Xining, Qinghai Province, China <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* sichen1103@whu.edu.cn <lb/>Abstract <lb/>As China continues to implement its progressive fertility promotion policy, there has been a <lb/>drastic decline in the fertility rate. Given that the migrant population constitutes more than a <lb/>quarter of China&apos;s total population, enhancing the willingness of this demographic to have <lb/>additional children through policy-guided urban public services is pivotal for optimizing Chi-<lb/>na&apos;s population development strategy. This study analyzes the influence of urban public ser-<lb/>vices on the reproductive intentions of the migrant population, utilizing data from 110,667 <lb/>migrant families with one child, drawn from China&apos;s Migrant Population Dynamic Monitoring <lb/>data in 2016 and 2018. The data analysis reveals several key findings: (1) Urban public ser-<lb/>vices, overall, exhibit a notable positive effect on the willingness of the migrant population to <lb/>have more children, albeit with limitations and a declining trend. (2) Among urban public ser-<lb/>vices, primary basic education significantly impacts the willingness of the migrant population <lb/>to expand their families. (3) Large cities have created a &apos;reverse screening&apos; effect on the <lb/>migrant population, leading to differential access to public services. This scenario caters <lb/>effectively to the high human capital migrant individuals while reducing accessibility to liveli-<lb/>hood public services for the low human capital migrant population. This paper critically eval-<lb/>uates China&apos;s progressively adjusted fertility policy from the perspective of the migrant <lb/>population. It underscores the necessity of establishing a comprehensive fertility support <lb/>policy system across China. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>In recent years, experts and scholars have increasingly recognized socio-economic develop-<lb/>ment as a crucial factor in reducing global fertility levels [1]. As Polanyi noted, a spontaneously <lb/>regulated market has never existed. Since the industrial era [2], developed countries have wit-<lb/>nessed concurrent advancements in medical technology [3], increased educational costs [4], <lb/>and a substantial expansion of social security coverage [5]. Changes in societal attitudes and <lb/>approaches [6], along with decreasing infant and child mortality rates and the escalating costs <lb/>of child-rearing [7], have collectively influenced a shift in attitudes towards childbearing, <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/>1 / 24 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Liu S, Cai Q, Wang M, Di K (2024) Urban <lb/>public services and fertility intentions of internal <lb/>migrants in China. PLoS ONE 19(3): e0300345. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 <lb/>Editor: Mihajlo Jakovljevic, Hosei University: Hosei <lb/>Daigaku, JAPAN <lb/>Received: May 16, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: February 22, 2024 <lb/>Published: March 28, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Liu et al. This is an open access <lb/>article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original author and <lb/>source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The China Migrants <lb/>Dynamic Survey (CMDS) is a nationwide large-<lb/>scale annual sampling survey conducted by the <lb/>National Health Commission of China since 2009. It <lb/>covers 31 provinces and autonomous regions, as <lb/>well as the Xinjiang Production and Construction <lb/>Corps, focusing on areas with a concentrated <lb/>population of migrant individuals. The survey <lb/>comprises nearly 200,000 households annually, <lb/>gathering information on basic demographics of <lb/>migrant populations and their family members, <lb/>migration patterns and trends, employment and <lb/>social security, income and expenditures, basic <lb/>public health services, marriage, childbirth, and <lb/></front>

			<body>resulting in a decline in birth rates [8]. This economic and social &quot;two-way street,&quot; signifying <lb/>the expansion of market forces [9], ultimately triggers a counter-movement to safeguard <lb/>human welfare [10]. According to United Nations statistics, the average urbanization level in <lb/>developed countries is projected to reach 81.3 percent in 2020, accompanied by an ultra-low <lb/>average total fertility rate (below 1.3). Contrarily, as per the results of the 7th China Population <lb/>Census, China&apos;s total fertility rate for women of childbearing age is expected to be 1.3 in 2020, <lb/>already at an ultra-low level, despite the degree of urbanization lagging significantly behind <lb/>that of developed countries [11, 12]. <lb/>Since the initiation of reform and opening up, China has undergone swift urbanization <lb/>[13], witnessing a rise in the urbanization rate from 17.9% in 1978 to 64.31% in 2021. The <lb/>National Development and Reform Commission (NDRC) of China highlighted that, with the <lb/>gradual stabilization of China&apos;s Migrant Population, each one percentage point increase in this <lb/>demographic implies a migration of 14 million people from rural areas to urban centers [14]. <lb/>Consequently, China&apos;s year-end resident population has surged from 1,143.33 million people <lb/>in 1990 to 1,412.6 million people by the end of 2021 [15]. The results of the 7th National Popu-<lb/>lation Census reveal that by the conclusion of 2021, China&apos;s Migrant Population has reached <lb/>385 million, constituting more than a quarter of the country&apos;s total population. As per the Sta-<lb/>tistical Bulletin of the National Economic and Social Development of the People&apos;s Republic of <lb/>China [16], as of the end of 2021, the nation had 504 million people separated from their <lb/>households, of which 385 million were mobile, making up more than a quarter of the total <lb/>population [5]. The 2020 Seventh Population Census data indicates that women of childbear-<lb/>ing age accounted for 22.86% of China&apos;s total population [17], with the proportion of women <lb/>of childbearing age among the population separated from households reaching 16.80%. Con-<lb/>currently, the proportion of women of childbearing age within the Migrant Population <lb/>amounted to 12.56% of the total population, totaling 177 million [18]. Leveraging this substan-<lb/>tial base of women of childbearing age in the Migrant Population, China conducted a nation-<lb/>wide survey on the dynamic monitoring of health and family planning within this group [19]. <lb/>The survey revealed that following the implementation of the &quot;comprehensive two-child&quot; pol-<lb/>icy, barring a minor, transient surge in the birth rate in 2016 attributed to compensatory child-<lb/>bearing, the overall fertility intention in 2018 declined by 10% compared to 2016. Increasingly, <lb/>families within the Migrant Population, adopting a cautious stance toward the fertility policy, <lb/>opted to forgo their intention of &quot;having the next child [20]&quot;. <lb/>In the context outlined above, this paper aims to address three pivotal questions. Firstly, it <lb/>seeks to assess the current state of urban public services accessible to the Migrant Population, <lb/>considering the recent improvements in these services. Secondly, the research aims to identify <lb/>the urban public service indicators that significantly influence the Migrant Population&apos;s will-<lb/>ingness to have another child. Thirdly, it aims to pinpoint the segment of the Migrant Popula-<lb/>tion most responsive to urban public services and delve into its underlying rationale. To <lb/>address these inquiries, the study leverages data from the 2016 and 2018 national mobile popu-<lb/>lation dynamics monitoring (referred to as CMDS2016 and CMDS2018) conducted by the <lb/>National Health Commission. Additionally, it utilizes data from the 2016 and 2018 China <lb/>Urban Statistical Yearbooks and data from the statistical yearbooks of various provinces and <lb/>municipalities on the resident population during the same years. The objective is to compre-<lb/>hensively examine the urban public services accessible to the mobile population at the place of <lb/>inflow. Building on this analysis, the study aims to profoundly investigate the impact and <lb/>mechanisms of urban public services on the Migrant Population&apos;s inclination to have another <lb/>child. Furthermore, the research intends to contribute insights into the development of a <lb/>birth-friendly urban public service system for the Migrant Population, offering valuable guid-<lb/>ance for advancing the establishment of a comprehensive public service system in China. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<front>family planning services, children&apos;s migration and <lb/>education, psychological and cultural aspects, <lb/>along with special surveys on social integration, <lb/>mental health, health services in places of origin, <lb/>and healthcare services for elderly migrants. On <lb/>September 25, 2023, the National Health <lb/>Commission&apos;s Center for Migrant Population <lb/>Services announced the cessation of the free <lb/>dissemination of the China Migrants Dynamic <lb/>Survey data. They had previously made this data <lb/>available for nine consecutive years since 2014 <lb/>under the auspices of the former National Health <lb/>and Family Planning Commission&apos;s Migrant <lb/>Population Division, receiving extensive support <lb/>from relevant entities. Due to a shift in the center&apos;s <lb/>functions and the inability to further update the <lb/>survey data, they decided to halt the online free <lb/>access to the China Migrants Dynamic Survey data. <lb/>The data application portal on the Migrant <lb/>Population Data Platform was closed starting from <lb/>September 25, 2023. Applications submitted <lb/>before September 24, 2023, at 24:00 will be <lb/>processed within the period from September 25, <lb/>2023, to November 10, 2023. For future users with <lb/>specific data needs, the Center will provide services <lb/>through data exchange or collaborative research <lb/>projects. Data Link: https://www.ncmi.cn/phda/ <lb/>dataDetails.do?id=CSTR:A0006.11.A000T.201906. <lb/>000225 Contact Organization: National Health <lb/>Commission&apos;s Center for Migrant Population <lb/>Services Contact Number: 010-68791297 Contact <lb/>Person: Zhou Fang Contact Person&apos;s Email: <lb/>ldrkzxsj@163.com. <lb/>Funding: 1. Achievements of the Joint Doctoral <lb/>Forum Program between Tianjin University and <lb/>Qinghai Minzu University. 2.Qinghai Minzu <lb/>University:(23XJX01) Study on the Coupling Effect <lb/>of Technology-Organization-Environmental <lb/>Condition Configuration on the Performance of <lb/>Low Carbon City Development in China. 3.Qinghai <lb/>Minzu University (39D2023005): The Impact of <lb/>Low-Carbon Urban Transformation on Regional <lb/>Employment Levels. 4.Tianjin Research Innovation <lb/>Project for Postgraduate Students:(2022BKYZ029) <lb/>The linkage of technology-organization-<lb/>environment condition Configuration on the <lb/>construction of low carbon city in China&apos;s <lb/>development performance. The above funders play <lb/>a role in data collection. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors declare that <lb/>there are no competing interests. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <body>Literature review and theoretical foundations <lb/>Literature review <lb/>According to the &quot;sequential pattern&quot; theory of reproductive intention [21], the reproductive <lb/>intentions of China&apos;s Migrant Population exhibit dynamic changes [22]. The traditional fertil-<lb/>ity notions prevalent in the place of origin [23], such as &quot;more children, more happiness&quot; [24] <lb/>and &quot;passing on the family line&quot; [25], have historically influenced the Migrant Population. <lb/>Simultaneously, they are confronted with modern fertility concepts like &quot;female independence&quot; <lb/>[26] and &quot;fewer children, better births&quot; [27] in the destination area. Consequently, some schol-<lb/>ars posit that the willingness of the Migrant Population to have children is lower than that in <lb/>the place of origin but higher than that in the destination area [28]. <lb/>While earlier studies [12] in China indicated that the reproductive intentions of the Migrant <lb/>Population were primarily shaped by fertility policies [29], recent adjustments in China&apos;s fertil-<lb/>ity policy suggest a convergence between the reproductive intentions of the Migrant Popula-<lb/>tion and the genuine intentions of their families [13]. Previous literature predominantly <lb/>focused on analyzing the impact on the fertility intentions of the Migrant Population from the <lb/>perspectives of individual and family characteristics [30]. Regarding individual characteristics, <lb/>an increase in educational attainment weakens traditional childbearing beliefs, significantly <lb/>decreasing childbearing intentions among highly educated female migrants [31]. Male <lb/>migrants, with improved education levels experience delayed childbearing intentions [32], <lb/>forming a &quot;U&quot; shaped curve [33]. The influence of economic factors, such as income levels, on <lb/>fertility intentions and behaviors is perceived as complex, with some studies suggesting that a <lb/>short-term increase in income levels can promote fertility intentions [34]. <lb/>In terms of family characteristics, analysis of &quot;single,&quot; &quot;doubly independent,&quot; and &quot;doubly <lb/>non-permanent&quot; family groups based on 2014 Migrant Population data reveals significantly <lb/>higher fertility rates compared to those in the 1980s [12]. Conversely, a more recent analysis of <lb/>these family groups based on 2014 Migrant Population data indicates uniformly low fertility <lb/>rates [35]. Scholars posit that the Migrant Population, influenced by external factors such as <lb/>traditional rural concepts and elder influence, tends to make reproductive decisions navigating <lb/>between the contrasting fertility cultures of urban and rural settings [36]. Moreover, some <lb/>scholars argue that the regional culture at the destination and the socio-economic status of the <lb/>fam region&apos;s economic development level differentially impact the Migrant Population&apos;s will-<lb/>ingness population to have more children [37]. <lb/>Aligned with the global trend of establishing a service-oriented government, the emphasis <lb/>on public service theory has gained prominence among a growing cohort of experts and schol-<lb/>ars [38]. Scholars [39], in their endeavor to dissect the fertility intentions of the Migrant Popu-<lb/>lation, delve into the lens of urban integration [40]. They posit that Migrant Populations <lb/>exhibiting stronger urban adaptation tend to manifest weaker fertility intentions [41]. The <lb/>degree of integration with the destination area [42], juxtaposed with the native ties to the <lb/>departure region [43], is perceived as exerting a direct influence on the fertility intentions of <lb/>the Migrant Population [16]. Some scholars [44] take a novel approach by scrutinizing fertility <lb/>policy support for both &quot;birth&quot; and &quot;parenting&quot; [45], advocating increased governmental sup-<lb/>port for the latter [46]. <lb/>Against the backdrop of China&apos;s recent adjustments to its progressive fertility policy [47], <lb/>evident in Table 1, the creation of fertility-friendly cities has become a focal point on the gov-<lb/>ernment&apos;s agenda [48]. Navigating from the viewpoint of policy support at the destination <lb/>[49], the challenge lies in minimizing the costs associated with childbearing and augmenting <lb/>the inclination to give birth [50]. This paradigm shift [51] underscores the pivotal role of the <lb/>fertility support policy system [52]. According to China&apos;s National New Urbanization Plan <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>[53], the essential urban public services that the Migrant Population should access include <lb/>basic education for accompanying children [54], employment and entrepreneurship services <lb/>[55], basic social security [56], basic medical care [57], and guaranteed housing [58]. To under-<lb/>stand the impact on the fertility intentions of the Migrant Population, this paper categorizes <lb/>these services into two overarching types: safeguard services (encompassing social security like <lb/>pension and medical insurance) and development services (encompassing public medical <lb/>resources, basic public education, and public infrastructure). <lb/>Theoretical foundations <lb/>Two fundamental questions precede the inquiry into whether urban public services can <lb/>enhance the fertility intentions of the Migrant Population: firstly, the accessibility of these ser-<lb/>vices for migrants [59]; secondly, whether the utility derived from urban public services can <lb/>amplify the fertility benefits for migrants [53]. <lb/>The costs associated with childbearing for the Migrant Population encompass various <lb/>aspects [60]. Primarily, there are costs unrelated to urban public services, such as the opportu-<lb/>nity costs incurred by mothers compelled to relinquish employment or career advancements <lb/>to care for their children [61]. Additionally, there are direct costs encompassing clothing, food, <lb/>housing, and transportation incurred due to the presence of children [62]. Concurrently, fertil-<lb/>ity benefits are augmented by the &quot;positive externalities&quot; arising from urban public services. <lb/>Strictly speaking, urban public services function as quasi-public goods with a certain degree <lb/>of exclusivity [63]. Consequently, the provision of these services doesn&apos;t automatically translate <lb/>into accessibility for the Migrant Population. In essence, the supply of public services is a nec-<lb/>essary but not a sufficient condition for migrants to access them. The National New Urbaniza-<lb/>tion Plan (2021-2035) and the Key Tasks of New Urbanization and Urban-Rural Integration <lb/>Development in 2022 categorize urban public services theoretically into two types: livelihood-<lb/>guaranteeing public services (e.g., children&apos;s education and healthcare) and developmental <lb/>public services (e.g., transportation, environment, and culture resulting from infrastructure <lb/>development). <lb/>Table 1. A compendium of the Chinese government&apos;s progressive fertility policy adjustments over the past decade. <lb/>Period of <lb/>time <lb/>Event <lb/>Policy <lb/>Main content <lb/>November <lb/>2013 <lb/>Having a second child on one&apos;s <lb/>own <lb/>Decision of the Central Committee of the Communist <lb/>Party of China on Several Major Issues Concerning <lb/>Comprehensively Deepening Reforms <lb/>Adhering to the basic national policy of family planning, <lb/>it has initiated the implementation of the policy that <lb/>couples in which one of the parents is an only child may <lb/>have two children. <lb/>January <lb/>2016 <lb/>Comprehensive second-child <lb/>policy <lb/>Law of the People&apos;s Republic of China on Population and <lb/>Family Planning <lb/>Article 18: &quot;The State promotes the birth of two children <lb/>per couple.&quot; <lb/>May 2021 <lb/>Comprehensive three-child <lb/>policy <lb/>Law of the People&apos;s Republic of China on Population and <lb/>Family Planning <lb/>Article 18 &quot;The State promotes marriage and parenthood <lb/>at the right age, and optimal parenthood. A couple may <lb/>have three children.&quot; <lb/>June 2021 <lb/>Top-level design of maternity <lb/>support policies <lb/>Decision of the Central Committee of the Communist <lb/>Party of China and the State Council on Optimizing <lb/>Fertility Policy and Promoting Long-term Balanced <lb/>Development of Population <lb/>Accelerating the construction of an active birth support <lb/>policy system, and deepening and refining the overall <lb/>plan and policy arrangements for more operational and <lb/>active birth support measures. <lb/>August <lb/>2022 <lb/>Constructing a fertility support <lb/>policy system for the new stage <lb/>of development <lb/>China&apos;s National Health Commission and 17 other <lb/>departments jointly issued the Guiding Opinions on <lb/>Further Improving and Implementing Positive Birth <lb/>Support Measures <lb/>Marriage, childbirth, upbringing and education are <lb/>explicitly considered as a whole, and the supporting <lb/>support measures for the three-child policy have been <lb/>refined. <lb/>Note: The table is collected and organized by the author. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Historical and institutional factors have led to a dualized development path between urban <lb/>and rural areas, causing an influx of excessive and high-quality education and healthcare <lb/>resources into large cities [64]. Better education and healthcare services are pivotal for promot-<lb/>ing the fertility of the Migrant Population [65]. However, the household registration system, <lb/>linked to high housing prices in major cities, hinders access to urban public services for the <lb/>majority of migrants [66]. China&apos;s household registration system, governing resource alloca-<lb/>tion across critical domains like education, healthcare, and employment, significantly favors <lb/>major urban centers like Beijing and Shanghai over other regions. This system intricately links <lb/>privileges such as housing, consumption patterns (e.g., vehicle ownership), education, and <lb/>social security, providing differential benefits contingent upon registered residency. At birth, <lb/>individuals in China are mandated to inherit one parent&apos;s household registration, with poten-<lb/>tial migration opportunities related to education and employment. Nevertheless, some local <lb/>governments enforce migration restrictions and levy substantial fees for urban residency <lb/>expansion. <lb/>This system obstructs access to urban public services through multifaceted mechanisms. <lb/>Primarily, educational inequalities persist, affording urban registrants superior access to <lb/>quality education, while rural or non-urban residents encounter limited resources and <lb/>restricted enrollment prospects. Secondarily, employment prospects remain constrained for <lb/>non-urban registrants due to prevailing discrimination or limited access to urban job mar-<lb/>kets. Tertiary, disparities persist in healthcare and social security services, favoring urban <lb/>registrants with more comprehensive support compared to their non-urban counterparts. <lb/>Migration restrictions and associated high costs exacerbate these disparities. Despite the <lb/>possibility of relocating household registration, migration quotas and substantial fees for <lb/>urban residency expansion curtail mobility and hinder access to urban public services. Chi-<lb/>na&apos;s household registration system perpetuates unequal access to urban public services, pos-<lb/>ing a significant impediment to urban development. The disparities in resources, education, <lb/>employment, and healthcare between urban and non-urban registrants underscore the sys-<lb/>temic inequalities arising from this system, impeding equitable access to critical urban <lb/>amenities. <lb/>The implementation of the government&apos;s household categorization policy has led to struc-<lb/>tural differentiation in public service provision between large, medium, and small cities. <lb/>Recent reports on the Migrant Population and census data reveal continued clustering in <lb/>mega and central cities, where the accessibility of livelihood-focused public services is severely <lb/>hampered by the household registration system and settling points. Conversely, medium-sized <lb/>and small cities exhibit an inefficient supply of such services despite robust provision and high <lb/>accessibility [67]. <lb/>Within this vast Migrant Population, which constitutes nearly a quarter of China&apos;s populace <lb/>[53], the ability to access public services in large cities becomes a critical consideration. The <lb/>&quot;talent introduction policy&quot; in major cities, designed to attract high human capital, initiates a <lb/>&quot;reverse screening&quot; process for migrants, elevating the threshold for low-cost migrants to <lb/>access urban public services [59]. <lb/>Built upon this foundation, the study posits the following hypotheses(As shown in Figs 1 <lb/>and 2): <lb/>H1: The comprehensive provision of urban public services can positively influence the willing-<lb/>ness of the Migrant Population to have additional children. <lb/>H2: Smaller and medium-sized cities exert a more pronounced pull on the fertility intentions <lb/>of the Migrant Population compared to larger cities. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 1. Research framework diagram. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.g001 <lb/>Fig 2. Heterogeneous effects of urban public services on the reproductive intentions of the migrant population. <lb/>Note: Given the pyramidal structure of individual strata within the Migrant Population group, such as economic <lb/>income and education level, the influence of received urban public services exhibits differentiation, manifesting a <lb/>spindle-shaped structural characteristic. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>H3: Public services falling within the livelihood protection category exert a more discernible <lb/>impact on the fertility intentions of the Migrant Population than those categorized as infra-<lb/>structure-related public services. <lb/>H4: Urban public service provision has a more significant impact on high-cost migrant popu-<lb/>lations compared to their low-cost counterparts. High-cost migrants, with their higher <lb/>incomes and financial resources, are often able to afford and access better quality housing, <lb/>education, healthcare, and other public services. <lb/>Data and variable selection <lb/>Data sources <lb/>In this study, we undertake several approaches. First, we employ CMDS data from 2016 and <lb/>2018 to assess the current status of the Migrant Population&apos;s inclination toward having another <lb/>child, focusing on a micro-individual perspective. Second, we utilize urban public services data <lb/>from the China City Statistical Yearbook to gauge the level of public services across diverse cit-<lb/>ies from a macro perspective. Third, recognizing the substantial representation of the Migrant <lb/>Population in the resident demographic of inflow areas, we collected data on the resident pop-<lb/>ulation at the end of 2015 and 2017. This data is sourced from the 2015, 1% Population Sample <lb/>Survey Data of Chinese Provinces and Regions, statistical yearbooks of Chinese provinces and <lb/>cities, and statistical bulletins on national economic and social development for each province <lb/>and city. Fourth, to mitigate endogeneity concerns arising from survey timing, we introduce a <lb/>lag of one year for the data on urban characteristics and resident population data, given that <lb/>the survey for China&apos;s mobile population health and family planning dynamic monitoring <lb/>data occurs in the first half of the survey year. Fifth, considering data timeliness and the impact <lb/>of the COVID-19 pandemic, we select survey data from 2016 and 2018 as our samples to inves-<lb/>tigate the willingness of the Migrant Population to reproduce. The survey spans 31 provinces <lb/>(municipalities and autonomous regions), 106 cities (comprising provincial capitals, planned <lb/>cities, prefecture-level cities, and county-level cities), 2,456 streets, and 4,912 neighborhood <lb/>committees or administrative villages nationwide. A total of 170,000 samples were collected, <lb/>covering respondents&apos; basic information, family details, work particulars, social security status, <lb/>and intentions regarding residency and having another child. <lb/>Sample structure <lb/>The following criteria were applied for data selection: 1. Exclusion of the Migrant Population <lb/>with Hukou statuses (The household registration status of individuals or families in a specific <lb/>area, which includes population statistics, migration records, and eligibility for access to public <lb/>services and entitlements.) categorized as agriculture-to-resident, non-agriculture-to-resident, <lb/>resident, and other samples, retaining only those with agricultural and non-agricultural <lb/>Hukou to facilitate differentiation between rural-urban and urban-urban Migrant Populations. <lb/>2. Removal of samples whose reason for mobility is military enlistment to ensure comparabil-<lb/>ity across sample types. 3. Elimination of samples involving out-of-country mobility, focusing <lb/>exclusively on inter-provincial and intra-provincial mobility cases. 4. Concentration on the <lb/>study of the Migrant Population with a spouse who has one child and is of childbearing age, <lb/>equipped to express the desire to have another child. <lb/>Consequently, only samples comprising married individuals with one child within the <lb/>childbearing age range (15-49 years old) were retained. 2016, there were 60,764 eligible survey <lb/>data samples, with 43,167 eligible survey data samples in 2018. The specifics of the sample are <lb/>shown in Figs 3 and 4. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Measurement of variables <lb/>The independent variable considered in this study is the intention to have another child. Since <lb/>fertility intentions do not entirely predict fertility behavior, there is often some degree of deviation <lb/>between the two. This phenomenon is evident in many contemporary European and American <lb/>countries, where the ideal family size is generally characterized by two children, yet fertility levels <lb/>remain well below replacement levels. Similar discrepancies exist in Japan and Korea, which <lb/>underwent demographic transitions earlier in Asia. In these countries, the reported ideal number <lb/>of children in fertility surveys has remained stable at around two. However, the number of chil-<lb/>dren born has declined, sometimes sharply, to nearly one child or even below. <lb/>Therefore, the explanatory variables in this paper include &quot;whether you plan to have chil-<lb/>dren in the next two years&quot; and &quot;whether you and your wife are currently using contraceptive <lb/>methods,&quot; considering behavioral superposition. This is done to reflect the willingness of the <lb/>Migrant Population to have children again. Social insurance, basic education, and primary <lb/>medical care are selected as explanatory variables to measure the level of urban public services <lb/>based on the first scores of principal component analysis, considering data accessibility and <lb/>the results of principal component analysis. Additionally, this paper controls for urban charac-<lb/>teristics, family characteristics, and personal characteristics to mitigate the potential impacts of <lb/>these factors on the willingness of the Migrant Population to reproduce. The specific variables <lb/>are calculated as shown in Table 2. See S1 Appendix for details of how the explanatory vari-<lb/>ables (Social security, Education, Medical Resources) were calculated. <lb/>Empirical studies <lb/>Basic regression models <lb/>This paper employs a fundamental multiple regression model, using the intention to have chil-<lb/>dren again as the dependent variable and primary education and basic medical care as the <lb/>independent variables. After accounting for individual, family, and city characteristics <lb/>Fig 3. Comparing the overall willingness to have more children among the migrant population in 2016 and 2018. <lb/>Notes: Data were from China&apos;s Migration Dynamic Surveillance (2016) and China&apos;s Migration Dynamic Surveillance <lb/>(2018). This figure indicates that the willingness of the migrant population to have a second child is declining overall. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>influencing the intention to have children again among the Migrant Population, the model is <lb/>established. <lb/>Fertility ¼ b 0 þ b 1 P j þ b 2 D j þ b 3 x j þ b 4 z j þ ε ij <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>Fig 4. Comparison of public services owned by groups with different fertility intentions, 2016 and 2018. Note: <lb/>Data from China Urban Statistical Yearbook, China Mobile Population Dynamic Monitoring Data, and China <lb/>Provincial and Municipal Statistical Yearbook data. Calculation method of growth rate = (Average value of public <lb/>services per 10,000 resident population in China in 2018-Average value of public services per 10,000 resident <lb/>population in China in 2016) / Average value of public services per 10,000 resident population in China 2016 * 100. <lb/>The table shows that (1), in general, the influx rate of the Migrant Population is much faster than the rate of the supply <lb/>of urban public services, which has led to a continuous decline in the accessibility of urban public services for the <lb/>Migrant Population. Accessibility of urban public services for the Migrant Population has been declining. (2) The <lb/>accessibility of public services for the group that has the intention to have a second child &gt; the accessibility of public <lb/>services for the group that does not consider whether to have a second child &gt; the accessibility of public services for <lb/>the group that does not have the intention to have a second child. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the equation, the variable &quot;Fertility&quot; on the left-hand side is the dependent variable, while <lb/>the variables on the right-hand side are the independent or explanatory variables. Further-<lb/>more, &quot;Fertility&quot; is a binary variable. When the migrant population in city j does not wish to <lb/>have a second child, the value of &quot;Fertility&quot; is 0. When the migrant population in city j wishes <lb/>Table 2. Calculation method of variables. <lb/>Categories <lb/>Variables <lb/>How to calculate variables <lb/>Explained variables <lb/>Willingness to have a second <lb/>child <lb/>1. Willingness to not have a second child and use of contraceptive methods; 2. Willingness to not <lb/>have a second child and no contraception; 3. Uncertain about a second child and use of <lb/>contraceptive methods; 4. Uncertain about a second child and no contraception; 5. Willingness <lb/>to have a second child and use of contraceptive methods; 6. Willingness to have a second child <lb/>and use of contraceptive methods no contraception. <lb/>Explanatory variables <lb/>Social security <lb/>The first score of public services of urban security category <lb/>fundamental education <lb/>First score value of principal component analysis of fundamental education <lb/>Medical resources <lb/>First score value of principal component analysis of medical resources <lb/>Control variables-<lb/>Factors of City Features <lb/>Level of economic <lb/>development of the Urban <lb/>Take logarithm of GDP per capita for urban <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>Take the logarithm of the average annual wage for urban workers <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>Average value of tertiary sector/average value of secondary sector in urban areas <lb/>Size of urban resident <lb/>population <lb/>Take the logarithm of the resident population of the city <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>Take the logarithm of the average sales price per square meter of commercial housing in the <lb/>urban area <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>1. Municipalities; 2. special economic zone; 3. sub-provincial city; 4. Provincial capital cities <lb/>(Except for sub-provincial and special zones); 5. Other prefecture-level cities. <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>family characteristics <lb/>Family members moving in <lb/>with the situation <lb/>1. Family members (Spouse, children, parents) moving with; 0. Family members did not move <lb/>with. <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>1. Less than 500 yuan per month; 2. Above 500 yuan-below 1500 yuan per month; 3. More than <lb/>1500 yuan per month. <lb/>Disposable income of the <lb/>household <lb/>1. Less than 3000 yuan per month; 2. Above 3000 yuan-below 6000 yuan per month; 3. More <lb/>than 6000 yuan per month. <lb/>Gender of the first child <lb/>1. boy; 0. girl. <lb/>Age of the first child <lb/>1. Age 0-3; 2. Age 4-6; 3. Age 7-10; 4. Age 11-14; 5. Age over 15. <lb/>The first child&apos;s current place <lb/>of residence <lb/>1. The city that flows with family; 0. Other locations. <lb/>Primary caregiver of the first <lb/>child <lb/>1. Both parents; 2. Mother; 3. grandfather and grandmother; 4. Others. <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>personal characteristics <lb/>Age <lb/>April 2016 (the time of the survey) minus the year of birth of the sample <lb/>Age squared <lb/>Age* Age <lb/>Gender <lb/>1. Male; 0. female. <lb/>Level of education <lb/>0. Never been to school; 6. Finished elementary school; 9. Graduated from junior high school; 12. <lb/>Graduated from high school or junior college; 14. Graduated from college; 16. Graduated from <lb/>university with a bachelor&apos;s degree; 19. Received a postgraduate bachelor&apos;s degree; 22. Received a <lb/>bachelor&apos;s degree with a PhD. <lb/>Nature of household <lb/>registration <lb/>1. Agricultural household registration; 0. Non-agricultural household registration. <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>1. Inter-provincial mobility; 0. Other types. <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>1. Lessthan1year; 2. 1-2years; 3. 3-4years;4. 4-9years; 5. 10-14years; 6. 5-19 years; 7. 20-29 years; <lb/>8. Over 30 years. <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>1. Willingness; 2. Unwilling and unthinking. <lb/>Notes: This table reports the indicators for the specific measures of the explained, explanatory, and control variables and the way the variables were explicitly calculated. <lb/>Non-agricultural household registration includes non-agricultural, agricultural to the resident, non-agricultural to the resident, and others. Other types contain inter-<lb/>city and inter-county within the province. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>to have a second child, the value of &quot;Fertility&quot; is 1. The core explanatory variable P indicates the <lb/>level of basic security in city j, D indicates the level of development in city j, and ε is the distur-<lb/>bance term. <lb/>Conditional Logit <lb/>The intention to have a second child exhibits variability across individual samples and pro-<lb/>grams. Consequently, this paper employs a Conditional Logit to analyze the heterogeneity <lb/>within the migrant population, considering differences in human capital characteristics, <lb/>employment features, and mobility traits. The constructed Conditional Logit model is pre-<lb/>sented below: <lb/>Pðy i ¼ jjx ij Þ ¼ <lb/>expðx <lb/>0 <lb/>ij bÞ <lb/>X J <lb/>K expðx <lb/>0 <lb/>ik bÞ <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>In the above equation, p indicates the probability that individual i chooses a different option <lb/>for the intention to have a second child, and the explanatory variable x ij indicates that it varies <lb/>with sample individual i and also with option j (differences in human capital characteristics, <lb/>differences in employment characteristics, and differences in mobility characteristics). The <lb/>coefficient β indicates that the random utility of p does not depend on option j. <lb/>Results <lb/>Table 3 presents the outcomes of stepwise regression analyses to have a second child as the <lb/>dependent variable. Specifically, models (1), (2), and (3) showcase the results of stepwise <lb/>regression estimation using 2016 data, while models (4), (5), and (6) illustrate the results based <lb/>on the 2018 dataset. <lb/>Through the comparison of regression results between 2016 and 2018, models (1) and (4) <lb/>highlight the significant influence of personal characteristics on the willingness to have chil-<lb/>dren among the Migrant Population. The regression outcomes indicate that, within the per-<lb/>missible age range for childbearing, the willingness to give birth to the next child increased <lb/>significantly with the parent&apos;s age in 2016; however, by 2018, older parents exhibited a declin-<lb/>ing inclination to have another child. This trend may be attributed to the release of short-term <lb/>effects from the birth buildup and the higher medical and other childbearing costs for older <lb/>parents. Men exhibit a significantly higher willingness to have more children than women. <lb/>Higher-educated migrant populations also show a greater willingness to have children. Com-<lb/>pared to non-agricultural household registration, migrant populations with agricultural house-<lb/>hold registration are more inclined to have another child. Those who do not move across <lb/>provinces show a stronger intention to have another child compared to those moving across <lb/>provinces. The duration of mobility is inversely proportional to the willingness to reproduce, <lb/>while the willingness to settle down correlates positively to having another child. <lb/>Regarding urban public services, the regression coefficient indicates a low impact of essen-<lb/>tial security category services in the inflow city on the willingness of the mobile population to <lb/>have another child. This aligns with earlier descriptive statistics illustrating the low access of <lb/>the migrant population to public services in the inflow city, particularly in the realm of social <lb/>insurance like pension and medical insurance. The preference for paying insurance in the <lb/>place of domicile over the inflow area might be attributed to the migrant population&apos;s prior <lb/>contributions to New Rural Cooperative Insurance and New Rural Insurance in the inflow <lb/>area. Women&apos;s willingness to have more children decreases with age and is potentially linked <lb/>to the physical condition of women at childbearing age. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>The persistent preference for sons over daughters in China is evident, as families with boys <lb/>exhibit a significantly lower willingness to have another child. This preference relates to the <lb/>anticipated higher future costs of marriage and home purchase for boys in China. Notably, the <lb/>caregiver&apos;s gender for the first child plays a significant role, aligning with the traditional Chi-<lb/>nese practice of females typically assuming the caregiving role. Families with a male caregiver <lb/>for the first child express a lower intention to have another child. Economic factors influencing <lb/>the willingness to have another child include employment status, with employees and self-<lb/>employed individuals who often work overtime displaying a lower intention to have children. <lb/>However, monthly household income, housing purchase, and pension insurance status do not <lb/>show significant effects. <lb/>Lastly, house prices have a stable and significant effect on the willingness to have children <lb/>among the Migrant Population. Models (3) and (6) indicate a negative correlation between <lb/>housing prices and the propensity to have another child, suggesting that an increase in <lb/>housing costs leads to a decrease in the willingness of mobile population to have another <lb/>child. This conclusion is particularly pronounced in larger cities with higher house prices, <lb/>emphasizing the substantial impact of renting costs on the fertility decisions of the migrant <lb/>population. <lb/>Table 3. Comparative analysis of basic regression results. <lb/>Categories <lb/>Variables <lb/>Willingness to have a second child (2016) <lb/>Willingness to have a second child (2018) <lb/>(1) <lb/>(2) <lb/>(3) <lb/>(4) <lb/>(5) <lb/>(6) <lb/>Explanatory <lb/>variables <lb/>Social security <lb/>0.001 (0.001) <lb/>0.001 (0.001) <lb/>-0.001 (-0.002) <lb/>0.000 (0.001) <lb/>0.000 (0.001) <lb/>0.001* (0.001) <lb/>fundamental education <lb/>-0.154*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.165*** (-0.011) <lb/>-0.140*** (-0.011) <lb/>0.004*** (0.001) <lb/>0.003*** (0.001) <lb/>-0.001*** (-0.011) <lb/>Medical resources <lb/>-0.010*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.012*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.006*** (-0.002) <lb/>0.001*** (0.001) <lb/>0.003*** (0.001) <lb/>0.001*** (0.002) <lb/>Control <lb/>variables-<lb/>Factors of City <lb/>Features <lb/>Level of economic development of the Urban <lb/>-0.047*** (-0.007) <lb/>-0.008*** (-0.001) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.014*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.004*** (-0.001) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>-0.014*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.004*** (-0.001) <lb/>Size of urban resident population <lb/>-0.013*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.010*** (-0.001) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>-0.099*** (-0.008) <lb/>-0.199*** (-0.007) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>-0.012*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.015*** (-0.003) <lb/>Control <lb/>variables-<lb/>Factors of <lb/>family <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Family members moving in with the situation <lb/>-0.025*** (-0.007) <lb/>-0.023*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.005*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.025*** (-0.000) <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>-0.132*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.152*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.231*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.253*** (-0.005) <lb/>Disposable income of the household <lb/>-0.017*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.005*** (-0.002) <lb/>0.127*** (0.004) <lb/>0.005*** (0.003) <lb/>Gender of the first child <lb/>-0.101*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.097*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.301*** (-0.000) <lb/>-0.489*** (-0.000) <lb/>Age of the first child <lb/>-0.001*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.004*** (-0.003) <lb/>0.131*** (0.008) <lb/>-0.455*** (-0.001) <lb/>The first child&apos;s current place of residence <lb/>-0.01* (-0.005) <lb/>-0.003 (-0.006) <lb/>-0.000 (-0.005) <lb/>-0.009 (-0.002) <lb/>Primary caregiver of the first child <lb/>-0.001* (-0.003) <lb/>-0.002* (-0.006) <lb/>-0.000 (-0.001) <lb/>-0.001* (-0.002) <lb/>Control <lb/>variables-<lb/>Factors of <lb/>personal <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Age <lb/>-0.005* (-0.003) <lb/>-0.012*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.007** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.041*** (-0.002) <lb/>0.092*** (0.003) <lb/>-0.003** (-0.002) <lb/>Age squared <lb/>-0.000*** (-0.000) <lb/>-0.000*** (-0.000) <lb/>-0.000*** (-0.000) <lb/>0.000*** (0.000) <lb/>0.000*** (0.000) <lb/>0.000*** (0.000) <lb/>Gender <lb/>-0.007*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.041*** (-0.000) <lb/>-0.029*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.001*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.003*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.010*** (-0.003) <lb/>Level of education <lb/>-0.002*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.010*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.001*** (-0.001) <lb/>0.011*** (0.001) <lb/>-0.100*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.161*** (-0.001) <lb/>Nature of household registration <lb/>-0.030*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.031*** (-0.006) <lb/>-0.039*** (-0.006) <lb/>-0.009** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.110*** (-0.006) <lb/>-0.109*** (-0.006) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.004*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.001*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.016*** (-0.005) <lb/>-0.013*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.022*** (-0.003) <lb/>-0.028*** (-0.005) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>-0.005*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.006*** (-0.002) <lb/>-0.005*** (-0.002) <lb/>-0.007*** (-0.001) <lb/>-0.009*** (-0.002) <lb/>-0.009*** (-0.002) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>-0.013*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.037*** (-0.004) <lb/>-0.037*** (-0.005) <lb/>0.005*** (0.005) <lb/>-0.007*** (-0.006) <lb/>-0.017*** (-0.005) <lb/>Observations <lb/>60,764 <lb/>45,371 <lb/>35760 <lb/>43167 <lb/>39823 <lb/>31678 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.084 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.092 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>F <lb/>473.21 <lb/>314.25 <lb/>183.24 <lb/>436.95 <lb/>261.75 <lb/>156.51 <lb/>Notes <lb/>***, **, * indicate significance at the 1%, 5%, and 10% levels; data in brackets are robust standard errors. This study used non-standardized regression coefficients for <lb/>estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Heterogeneity analysis <lb/>Characteristics of human capital <lb/>Does the impact of urban public services on the willingness of the migrant population to <lb/>reproduce remain significant across various education levels and age groups? In addressing <lb/>this, we categorized the migrant population according to their education levels and reproduc-<lb/>tive age in 2018. Education levels were classified into nine years and below and ten years and <lb/>above based on the nine years of compulsory education. Age groups were divided into three <lb/>categories based on ten years (as shown in Table 4). <lb/>The educational landscape has significantly improved as China&apos;s economy experiences <lb/>ongoing development and societal progress. This shift fosters independent thinking, diminish-<lb/>ing the inclination for childbearing and enhancing awareness of contraception, contributing <lb/>to a reduced desire for additional children. Furthermore, childbearing introduces a heightened <lb/>opportunity cost for women. Consequently, numerous scholars posit a strong correlation <lb/>between the contemporary decline in fertility rates and the factors above. Conversely, there is a <lb/>growing recognition among parents that investing in education represents a &quot;long-term invest-<lb/>ment&quot; characterized by steady growth. Drawing on Becker&apos;s quantity-quality substitution <lb/>model [68], parents are increasingly optimizing their choices, directing limited family <lb/>resources and energies toward enhancing their children&apos;s quality rather than quantity. <lb/>Characteristics of the labor force <lb/>This paper categorizes the Migrant Population based on household income and occupational <lb/>characteristics. Using the 25% and 75% quartiles, monthly household income is stratified into <lb/>three groups: below RMB 4,000 for low-income, RMB 4,000 to RMB 8,000 for middle-income, <lb/>and above RMB 8,000 for high-income. Occupational nature is differentiated into stable and <lb/>non-stable employment. In alignment with the provided questionnaire options, stable employ-<lb/>ment includes individuals identified as heads of state organs, party and group organizations, <lb/>enterprises and institutions, professional and technical personnel, civil servants, clerical staff, and <lb/>related personnel. Others are classified as having non-stable employment(as shown in Table 5). <lb/>The regression findings reveal a noteworthy positive correlation between urban develop-<lb/>ment public services and the inclination to have children among the migrant population, irre-<lb/>spective of their household income levels. However, the impact of urban public services on the <lb/>willingness to have children is notably weaker in the high-income group due to their ability to <lb/>choose between private and general products. <lb/>Whether the migrant population is engaged in stable or non-stable employment, primary <lb/>education, and medical services significantly and positively influence their willingness to have <lb/>children. In cases where the spouse works in a regular employment setting, such as a state-<lb/>owned enterprise with fixed working hours, there is more time to assist with household chores <lb/>and childcare. Increased spousal support positively correlates with a higher willingness of <lb/>women to have another child. This effect is particularly pronounced among those in stable <lb/>employment when a parent serves as the primary caregiver of the child (1 represents that the <lb/>primary caregiver of the child is either the father or the mother, while 0 represents that the <lb/>grandparents or other individuals serve as the primary caregiver.). Engagement in regular <lb/>units, like state-owned enterprises, fosters a favorable environment for women&apos;s fertility, rein-<lb/>forced by initiatives like maternity insurance and paid vacations. Given that stable employ-<lb/>ment migrants already benefit from social security provided by their workplaces (generally <lb/>higher than that offered by flexible employment and urban workers types), the impact of <lb/>urban universal social insurance on stable employment migrants is not statistically significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. Regression results of the difference in human capital characteristics mobile population&apos;s willingness to have another child. <lb/>Categories <lb/>Variables <lb/>Years of Education 9 <lb/>years or less <lb/>Years of Education 10 <lb/>years and above <lb/>Age group: <lb/>19-28 <lb/>Age group: <lb/>29-38 <lb/>Age group: <lb/>39-48 <lb/>Explanatory variables <lb/>Social security <lb/>0.000** (0.000) <lb/>0.000** (0.000) <lb/>0.032** <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>0.005 (0.009) <lb/>0.0711*** <lb/>(0.023) <lb/>fundamental education <lb/>0.987*** (0.1) <lb/>0.732*** (0.095) <lb/>0.795*** <lb/>(0.125) <lb/>0.786*** <lb/>(0.098) <lb/>1.113*** <lb/>(0.223) <lb/>Medical resources <lb/>0.0451** (0.018) <lb/>0.081*** (0.020) <lb/>0.003*** <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>0.063*** <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>0.129*** <lb/>(0.043) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of City <lb/>Features <lb/>Level of economic <lb/>development of the Urban <lb/>0.300*** (0.060) <lb/>0.283*** (0.061) <lb/>0.166** <lb/>(0.077) <lb/>0.378*** <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>0.415*** <lb/>(0.149) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.079** (-0.035) <lb/>-0.059 (-0.038) <lb/>-0.116*** <lb/>(-0.044) <lb/>-0.064* <lb/>(-0.038) <lb/>0.020 (-0.092) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>0.086*** (-0.031) <lb/>0.114*** (-0.033) <lb/>0.152*** <lb/>(-0.042) <lb/>0.084*** <lb/>(-0.031) <lb/>0.114 (-0.075) <lb/>Size of urban resident <lb/>population <lb/>-0.080*** (-0.029) <lb/>-0.087*** (-0.032) <lb/>-0.080** <lb/>(-0.038) <lb/>-0.049 <lb/>(-0.031) <lb/>-0.184** <lb/>(-0.076) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>-0.581*** (-0.067) <lb/>-0.579*** (-0.062) <lb/>-0.575*** <lb/>(-0.081) <lb/>-0.621*** <lb/>(-0.064) <lb/>-0.396** <lb/>(-0.17) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>-0.074** (-0.035) <lb/>-0.130*** (-0.036) <lb/>-0.098** <lb/>(-0.045) <lb/>-0.137*** <lb/>(-0.035) <lb/>-0.053 <lb/>(-0.092) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>family characteristics <lb/>Family members moving in <lb/>with the situation <lb/>-0.159*** (-0.060) <lb/>-0.039 (-0.067) <lb/>-0.012 <lb/>(-0.066) <lb/>-0.127* <lb/>(-0.070) <lb/>-0.013 <lb/>(-0.230) <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>-0.216*** (-0.048) <lb/>-0.121*** (-0.042) <lb/>-0.164*** <lb/>(-0.059) <lb/>-0.189*** <lb/>(-0.043) <lb/>-0.001 <lb/>(-0.111) <lb/>Disposable income of the <lb/>household <lb/>-0.117*** (-0.026) <lb/>-0.138*** (-0.027) <lb/>-0.121*** <lb/>(-0.033) <lb/>-0.122*** <lb/>(-0.027) <lb/>-0.068 <lb/>(-0.070) <lb/>Gender of the first child <lb/>-0.614*** (-0.038) <lb/>-0.526*** (-0.038) <lb/>-0.598*** <lb/>(-0.048) <lb/>-0.554*** <lb/>(-0.038) <lb/>-0.350*** <lb/>(-0.101) <lb/>Age of the first child <lb/>-0.094*** (-0.027) <lb/>-0.018 (-0.027) <lb/>-0.007 <lb/>(-0.037) <lb/>-0.072*** <lb/>(-0.024) <lb/>-0.571*** <lb/>(-0.055) <lb/>The first child&apos;s current place <lb/>of residence <lb/>-0.080 (-0.055) <lb/>-0.0427 (-0.048) <lb/>-0.068 <lb/>(-0.067) <lb/>-0.027 <lb/>(-0.051) <lb/>-0.036 <lb/>(-0.125) <lb/>Primary caregiver of the first <lb/>child <lb/>-0.147** (-0.059) <lb/>-0.026 (-0.053) <lb/>-0.097 <lb/>(-0.071) <lb/>-0.030 <lb/>(-0.057) <lb/>-0.454*** <lb/>(-0.139) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>personal characteristics <lb/>Gender <lb/>-0.223*** (-0.041) <lb/>-0.094** (-0.041) <lb/>-0.011 <lb/>(-0.053) <lb/>-0.169*** <lb/>(-0.040) <lb/>-0.418*** <lb/>(-0.116) <lb/>Nature of household <lb/>registration <lb/>-0.317*** (-0.089) <lb/>-0.237*** (-0.046) <lb/>-0.029** <lb/>(-0.012) <lb/>-0.018** <lb/>(-0.009) <lb/>-0.083*** <lb/>(-0.023) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.140*** (-0.042) <lb/>-0.052 (-0.044) <lb/>-0.293*** <lb/>(-0.088) <lb/>-0.297*** <lb/>(-0.054) <lb/>-0.459*** <lb/>(-0.137) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>0.025* (0.015) <lb/>0.051*** (0.016) <lb/>0.069*** <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>0.026* (0.015) <lb/>-0.108*** <lb/>(-0.032) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>-0.269*** (-0.043) <lb/>-0.196*** (-0.041) <lb/>-0.164*** <lb/>(-0.053) <lb/>-0.280*** <lb/>(-0.041) <lb/>-0.248** <lb/>(-0.109) <lb/>Observations <lb/>20,130 <lb/>15,630 <lb/>8,256 <lb/>15,196 <lb/>8,643 <lb/>Pseudo R 2 <lb/>0.1604 <lb/>0.0729 <lb/>0.0359 <lb/>0.0399 <lb/>0.131 <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>3325.4 <lb/>1328.38 <lb/>384.99 <lb/>716.76 <lb/>488.66 <lb/>Notes <lb/>***, **, * indicate significance at the 1%, 5%, and 10% levels; data in brackets are robust standard errors. The Logitech model reports Pseudo R 2 and Chi2 values. This <lb/>study used non-standardized regression coefficients for estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Characteristics of the flow <lb/>Beyond individual endowments, encompassing human capital characteristics and employment <lb/>stability, the reproductive intentions of the mobile population are also shaped by variations in <lb/>Table 5. Regression results in the willingness to have another child among the mobile population with differences in employment characteristics. <lb/>Categories <lb/>Variables <lb/>low income <lb/>level <lb/>middle income <lb/>level <lb/>high income <lb/>level <lb/>stable <lb/>employment <lb/>non-stable <lb/>employment <lb/>Explanatory variables <lb/>Social security <lb/>-0.007 (-0.016) -0.018** (-0.01) -0.005 (-0.01) <lb/>-0.001 (-0.017) <lb/>-0.000* (-0.007) <lb/>fundamental education <lb/>-0.971*** <lb/>(-0.127) <lb/>-0.918*** <lb/>(-0.109) <lb/>-0.707*** <lb/>(-0.129) <lb/>-0.802*** <lb/>(-0.236) <lb/>0.847*** (0.072) <lb/>Medical resources <lb/>0.046* (0.025) 0.076*** (0.021) 0.062** 0.024) 0.0858* (0.045) <lb/>0.061*** (0.014) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of City <lb/>Features <lb/>Level of economic development of <lb/>the Urban <lb/>-0.357*** <lb/>(-0.078) <lb/>-0.336*** <lb/>(-0.067) <lb/>-0.188** <lb/>(-0.082) <lb/>-0.187 (-0.129) <lb/>-0.307*** (-0.045) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.032 (-0.046) -0.105** (-0.042) -0.073 (-0.046) -0.038 (-0.089) <lb/>-0.073*** (-0.027) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>0.014 (0.041) <lb/>0.126*** (0.04) <lb/>-0.155*** <lb/>(-0.044) <lb/>0.114* (0.068) <lb/>0.099*** (0.024) <lb/>Size of urban resident population 0.132*** (0.04) <lb/>0.056 (0.035) <lb/>0.059 (0.039) <lb/>0.159** (0.073) <lb/>0.076*** (0.023) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>0.712*** <lb/>(0.103) <lb/>0.710*** (0.076) <lb/>0.449*** <lb/>(0.071) <lb/>0.497*** (0.147) <lb/>0.596*** (0.048) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>0.119** (0.052) 0.101** (0.034) 0.108** (0.043) <lb/>0.09 (0.082) <lb/>0.102*** (0.026) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>family Features <lb/>Family members moving in with <lb/>the situation <lb/>0.078 (0.077) <lb/>0.151** (0.071) <lb/>0.066 (0.090) <lb/>0.418 (0.257) <lb/>0.086* (0.045) <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>-0.183*** <lb/>(-0.064) <lb/>-0.168*** (-0.05) <lb/>-0.163*** <lb/>(-0.052) <lb/>-0.173* (-0.093) <lb/>-0.164*** (-0.033) <lb/>Disposable income of the <lb/>household <lb/>-0.488*** <lb/>(-0.053) <lb/>-0.585*** <lb/>(-0.043) <lb/>-0.623*** <lb/>(-0.046) <lb/>0.130** (0.066) <lb/>0.122*** (0.02) <lb/>Age of the first child <lb/>-0.065* <lb/>(-0.037) <lb/>-0.041 (-0.031) <lb/>0.023 (0.034) <lb/>-0.553*** <lb/>(-0.086) <lb/>-0.571*** (-0.028) <lb/>The first child&apos;s current place of <lb/>residence <lb/>0.089 (0.070) <lb/>-0.05** (-0.138) <lb/>-0.106* <lb/>(-0.062) <lb/>0.097 (0.062) <lb/>0.047** (0.020) <lb/>Primary caregiver of the first child 0.047 (0.084) <lb/>0.138** (0.064) <lb/>0.077 (0.063) <lb/>0.005 (0.103) <lb/>-0.008 (-0.039) <lb/>Control variables-Factors of <lb/>personal Features <lb/>Age <lb/>0.281*** <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>0.489*** (0.042) <lb/>0.368*** <lb/>(0.046) <lb/>0.041*** (0.113) <lb/>0.089* (0.042) <lb/>Age squared <lb/>-0.006*** <lb/>(-0.001) <lb/>-0.009*** <lb/>(-0.001) <lb/>-0.007*** <lb/>(-0.001) <lb/>-0.573*** <lb/>(-0.102) <lb/>-0.376*** (-0.026) <lb/>Gender <lb/>0.196*** <lb/>(0.059) <lb/>0.168*** (0.046) <lb/>0.149*** <lb/>(0.049) <lb/>0.010*** (0.002) <lb/>0.007*** (0.000) <lb/>Level of education <lb/>-0.016 (-0.012) -0.006 (-0.010) <lb/>0.016 (0.011) <lb/>0.075 (0.094) <lb/>0.187*** (0.031) <lb/>Nature of household registration 0.219** (0.089) 0.277*** (0.067) <lb/>0.208*** <lb/>(0.065) <lb/>0.148 (0.103) <lb/>0.267*** (0.046) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.148** <lb/>(-0.061) <lb/>-0.093* (-0.048) -0.063 (-0.05) <lb/>-0.019 (-0.099) <lb/>-0.102*** (-0.032) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>-0.035* <lb/>(-0.021) <lb/>-0.042** (-0.017) <lb/>-0.037** <lb/>(-0.019) <lb/>-0.029 (-0.035) <lb/>-0.039*** (-0.011) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>-0.263*** <lb/>(-0.059) <lb/>-0.244*** <lb/>(-0.046) <lb/>0.171*** <lb/>(-0.05) <lb/>-0.283*** <lb/>(-0.091) <lb/>-0.224*** (-0.031) <lb/>Observations <lb/>9,762 <lb/>15,005 <lb/>10,993 <lb/>3,178 <lb/>32,582 <lb/>Pseudo R 2 <lb/>0.1254 <lb/>0.128 <lb/>0.1053 <lb/>0.0761 <lb/>0.1259 <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>1283 <lb/>2028.38 <lb/>1359.39 <lb/>273.1 <lb/>4470.59 <lb/>Notes <lb/>***, **, * indicate significance at the 1%, 5%, and 10% levels; data in brackets are robust standard errors. The Logitech model reports Pseudo R 2 and Chi2 values. This <lb/>study used non-standardized regression coefficients for estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>mobility characteristics. In alignment with the standard procedure of the National Bureau of <lb/>Statistics (NBS), geographic regions are classified into four groups: Eastern, Central, Western, <lb/>and Northeastern regions. Additionally, the nature of household registration is stratified based <lb/>on the place of outflow, distinguishing between urban-rural migrant populations and rural-<lb/>rural migrant populations. These groupings serve as the basis for examining the influence of <lb/>urban public services on the inclination of the migrant population to have another child, tak-<lb/>ing into account disparities in mobility(as shown in Table 6). <lb/>Irrespective of the geographical area to which the mobile population has migrated, the pri-<lb/>mary education index exhibits a significant positive correlation with their willingness to have <lb/>another child. Notably, the pronounced impact of the primary education index is observed in <lb/>the eastern region, with a continuous marginal effect of 0.82 at the mean of the primary educa-<lb/>tion index. This implies that for every 1% increase in the primary education index, the proba-<lb/>bility of the mobile population&apos;s desire to have another child increases by 0.82 percentage <lb/>points. The influence of urban public services is most prominent in the West but relatively <lb/>weaker in the Northeast. This discrepancy might be attributed to the Northeast experiencing <lb/>lesser effects from social security factors due to its higher education level, substantial outflow <lb/>of individuals of childbearing age, and fewer ethnic minorities. <lb/>Additionally, it could be linked to regional marital cultures and economic conditions. <lb/>Among the influencing factors, primary education has the most substantial impact on the <lb/>migrant population in the eastern region, possibly stemming from a population concentration <lb/>that results in a relative scarcity of essential education resources. Meanwhile, the medical ser-<lb/>vice factor exerts the most decisive influence on the mobile population in the western region, <lb/>likely associated with the lagging medical infrastructure in the area, accentuating the signifi-<lb/>cance of medical service resources. <lb/>For both urban-city and rural-city mobile populations, urban development-type public ser-<lb/>vices exhibit a significant positive relationship with their willingness to have another child. <lb/>However, it is evident that urban public services more strongly influence the reproductive <lb/>intentions of the urban-city mobile population. Scholars addressing the lack of social security <lb/>for urban-city and rural-urban migrant populations highlight the double disadvantage faced <lb/>by the rural-urban migrant population, creating significant disparities in status and opportuni-<lb/>ties with the urban-rural migrant population. The latter group, being selectively mobile, bene-<lb/>fits from higher education levels and skills, which are advantageous for their entry into the <lb/>inflow area, offering advantages in employment choices, career progression, income levels, <lb/>and networking resources, thereby enhancing their social security. In contrast, the rural-urban <lb/>migrant population encounters inherent disadvantages, such as lower education levels and a <lb/>lack of skills, which prevent them from enjoying the benefits of local citizenship and participat-<lb/>ing in the household registration-based social security system. Simultaneously, their acquired <lb/>deficiencies place them at a disadvantage in choosing professions, further widening the gap <lb/>between them and developmental aspects of public services like health insurance and primary <lb/>education. <lb/>Robustness test <lb/>To enhance the reliability of the aforementioned findings, this study utilizes two distinct meth-<lb/>odologies for testing. Firstly, the urban public services indicator in the 2016 data is replaced. <lb/>Secondly, the 2018 data is subjected to a test where the sample of individuals &quot;not considering <lb/>whether to have two children&quot; is excluded. Both robustness tests consistently affirm the mod-<lb/>el&apos;s strong fit. The results indicate that, even with the transformation of relevant indicators, the <lb/>inclination of the Migrant Population to have a second child is significantly influenced by the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 6. Regression results in the willingness to have another child among the mobile population with differences in mobility characteristics. <lb/>Categories <lb/>Variables <lb/>Eastern <lb/>Region <lb/>Middle <lb/>Region <lb/>Western <lb/>Region <lb/>Northeast <lb/>Region <lb/>Mobility from <lb/>urban to urban <lb/>Mobility from rural <lb/>to urban areas <lb/>Explanatory variables <lb/>Social security <lb/>-0.011 <lb/>(-0.009) <lb/>-0.056*** <lb/>(-0.015) <lb/>-0.023* <lb/>(-0.013) <lb/>-0.055 <lb/>(-0.041) <lb/>-0.001 (-0.014) <lb/>-0.012* (-0.007) <lb/>fundamental education <lb/>0.82*** <lb/>(0.205) <lb/>0.013* <lb/>(0.131) <lb/>0.605*** <lb/>(0.137) <lb/>0.965 (3.838) <lb/>0.0919*** (0.174) <lb/>0.825*** (0.074) <lb/>Medical resources <lb/>-0.02 (-0.033) <lb/>-0.017 <lb/>(-0.021) <lb/>-0.068** <lb/>(-0.028) <lb/>-0.873* <lb/>(-0.446) <lb/>-0.080** (-0.034) <lb/>-0.057*** (-0.014) <lb/>Control variables-Factors <lb/>of City Features <lb/>Level of economic <lb/>development of the Urban <lb/>-0.312** <lb/>(-0.132) <lb/>-0.194** <lb/>(-0.089) <lb/>-0.395*** <lb/>(-0.078) <lb/>-0.044 <lb/>(-1.355) <lb/>-0.320*** (-0.106) <lb/>-0.252*** (-0.046) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.198*** <lb/>(-0.069) <lb/>-0.014 <lb/>(-0.071) <lb/>-0.001 (-0.05) <lb/>-0.282* <lb/>(-0.678) <lb/>-0.0113 (-0.064) <lb/>-0.091*** (-0.028) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>0.302*** <lb/>(0.054) <lb/>0.062 (0.068) <lb/>0.141*** <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>0.928 (1.273) <lb/>0.095* (0.054) <lb/>0.10*** (0.025) <lb/>Size of urban resident <lb/>population <lb/>-0.046 <lb/>(-0.052) <lb/>-0.234*** <lb/>(-0.053) <lb/>-0.070* <lb/>(-0.037) <lb/>-0.74 (-0.804) -0.156*** (-0.055) <lb/>-0.056** (-0.023) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>-0.176*** <lb/>(-0.068) <lb/>-0.834*** <lb/>(-0.233) <lb/>-0.827*** <lb/>(-0.183) <lb/>-1.759 <lb/>(-0.374) <lb/>-0.633*** (-0.109) <lb/>-0.607*** (-0.049) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>-0.004 <lb/>(-0.043) <lb/>0.387** <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>0.312*** <lb/>(0.086) <lb/>0.703 (0.63) <lb/>0.133** (0.065) <lb/>-0.092*** (-0.027) <lb/>Control variables-Factors <lb/>of family Features <lb/>Family members moving in <lb/>with the situation <lb/>-0.188** <lb/>(-0.079) <lb/>-0.045 <lb/>(-0.086) <lb/>-0.144* <lb/>(-0.076) <lb/>-0.085 (-0.26) <lb/>-0.088** (-0.078) <lb/>-0.085* (-0.046) <lb/>Household rental expenses -0.07 (-0.058) <lb/>-0.069 <lb/>(-0.058) <lb/>-0.082 <lb/>(-0.057) <lb/>-0.173 <lb/>(-0.164) <lb/>-0.059 (-0.061) <lb/>-0.069 (-0.058) <lb/>Gender of the first child <lb/>-0.718*** <lb/>(-0.044) <lb/>-0.532*** <lb/>(-0.053) <lb/>-0.522*** <lb/>(-0.049) <lb/>-0.324** <lb/>(-0.148) <lb/>-0.518*** (-0.044) <lb/>-0.534*** (-0.053) <lb/>Age of the first child <lb/>-0.052* <lb/>(-0.032) <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>(-0.040) <lb/>-0.052*** <lb/>(-0.035) <lb/>-0.089 <lb/>(-0.107) <lb/>-0.056* (-0.032) <lb/>-0.009 (-0.040) <lb/>The first child&apos;s current <lb/>place of residence <lb/>0.078 (0.059) <lb/>-0.051 <lb/>(-0.071) <lb/>-0.034*** <lb/>(-0.069) <lb/>-0.078 <lb/>(-0.199) <lb/>0.068 (0.059) <lb/>-0.053 (-0.074) <lb/>Primary caregiver of the first <lb/>child <lb/>0.044 (0.062) 0.138* (0.08) <lb/>0.280*** <lb/>(0.077) <lb/>0.178 (0.223) <lb/>0.056 (0.062) <lb/>0.135* (0.06) <lb/>Control variables-Factors <lb/>of personal Features <lb/>Age <lb/>0.489*** <lb/>(0.042) <lb/>0.435*** <lb/>(0.051) <lb/>0.235*** <lb/>(0.043) <lb/>0.323** <lb/>(0.151) <lb/>0.318** (0.033) <lb/>0.056** (0.038) <lb/>Gender <lb/>0.169*** <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>0.149*** <lb/>(0.057) <lb/>0.236*** <lb/>(0.054) <lb/>0.394** (0.16) <lb/>0.465*** 0.05) <lb/>0.157*** (0.069) <lb/>Level of education <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>(-0.011) <lb/>-0.027** <lb/>(-0.013) <lb/>-0.014 <lb/>(-0.011) <lb/>-0.040 <lb/>(-0.035) <lb/>-0.129** (-0.011) <lb/>-0.067** (-0.045) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.266*** <lb/>(-0.048) <lb/>-0.294*** <lb/>(-0.066) <lb/>-0.076 <lb/>(-0.057) <lb/>-0.383** <lb/>(-0.159) <lb/>-0.281*** (-0.045) <lb/>-0.294*** (-0.066) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>-0.039** <lb/>(-0.017) <lb/>-0.039* <lb/>(-0.021) <lb/>-0.027 <lb/>(-0.020) <lb/>-0.035 <lb/>(-0.063) <lb/>-0.045** (-0.015) <lb/>-0.039* (-0.021) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>-0.151*** <lb/>(-0.046) <lb/>-0.143** <lb/>(-0.061) <lb/>-0.320*** <lb/>(-0.055) <lb/>-0.047 <lb/>(-0.167) <lb/>-0.162*** (-0.046) <lb/>-0.143** (-0.061) <lb/>Observations <lb/>12,209 <lb/>9,507 <lb/>10,198 <lb/>3,846 <lb/>12,209 <lb/>9,507 <lb/>Pseudo R 2 <lb/>0.1262 <lb/>0.1025 <lb/>0.1146 <lb/>0.119 <lb/>0.1987 <lb/>0.1348 <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>1867.06 <lb/>1035.18 <lb/>1308.81 <lb/>191.9 <lb/>1968.34 <lb/>989.34 <lb/>Notes <lb/>***, **, * indicate significance at the 1%, 5%, and 10% levels; data in brackets are robust standard errors. The Logitech model reports Pseudo R 2 and Chi2 values. This <lb/>study used non-standardized regression coefficients for estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>essential public services in the city. Notably, while these results remain broadly consistent with <lb/>the overall model, there are variations in the extent of the impact. <lb/>(1) Robustness test for sample error in explanatory variables. Throughout this paper, <lb/>samples indicating no consideration for another child are treated as lacking the intention to <lb/>have one during the research process. However, it is imperative to acknowledge that not <lb/>contemplating it does not equate to a complete absence of intention; individuals may still <lb/>possess the desire to have another child. To enhance rigor, categorical variables are reset by <lb/>excluding samples falling under categories 3 (those not wanting children and using contra-<lb/>ception) and 4 (those not wanting children and not using contraception), resulting in <lb/>11,731 samples. The estimation and analysis are then conducted exclusively on samples <lb/>explicitly expressing their intention to have another child. The table below illustrates that, <lb/>regardless of the inclusion or exclusion of characteristic variables from other cities, the two-<lb/>child reproduction intention of the migrant population is significantly impacted by urban <lb/>public services. This reaffirms the robustness of the findings, indicating that higher levels of <lb/>urban public services strengthen the willingness of the migrant population to have another <lb/>child(as shown in Table 7). <lb/>(2) Robustness test for computational errors of core explanatory variables. In this study, <lb/>urban public services in the inflow area are generally classified into three evaluation modes <lb/>Table 7. Regression results after excluding some samples. <lb/>Variables <lb/>logit(1) <lb/>logit(2) <lb/>Per capita public finance expenditure <lb/>-0.013(-0.018) <lb/>0.272***(0.039) <lb/>Number of teachers per 10,000 elementary school students <lb/>0.246***(0.086) <lb/>0.162***(0.096) <lb/>Number of doctors per 10,000 resident population <lb/>0.202***(0.027) <lb/>0.391***(0.041) <lb/>Level of economic development of the Urban <lb/>-0.616***(-0.053) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.185***(-0.031) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>-0.234***(-0.028) <lb/>Size of urban resident population <lb/>-0.0455(-0.028) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>-0.564***(-0.061) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>-0.101***(-0.03) <lb/>Age <lb/>-0.331***(-0.024) <lb/>-0.341***(-0.029) <lb/>Age squared <lb/>0.008***(0.000) <lb/>0.008***(0.000) <lb/>Gender <lb/>0.434***(0.028) <lb/>0.388***(0.034) <lb/>Level of education <lb/>0.036***(0.006) <lb/>0.046***(0.007) <lb/>Nature of household registration <lb/>0.173***(0.039) <lb/>0.274***(0.048) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.060**(-0.028) <lb/>-0.134***(-0.035) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>-0.012(-0.01) <lb/>-0.013(-0.012) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>0.121***(0.028) <lb/>0.156***(0.034) <lb/>Disposable income of the household <lb/>0.055***(0.019) <lb/>0.116***(0.022) <lb/>Family members moving in with the situation <lb/>0.196***(0.044) <lb/>0.129**(0.052) <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>-0.178***(-0.03) <lb/>-0.185***(-0.036) <lb/>Observations <lb/>35,881 <lb/>24,952 <lb/>PseudoR 2 <lb/>0.2178 <lb/>0.2425 <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>9950.91 <lb/>7813.4 <lb/>Notes <lb/>*, **, *** indicate significant at the 10%, 5%, and 1% levels, respectively; data in parentheses are robust standard <lb/>errors; Logitech models report PseudoR 2 and Chi2 values. This study used non-standardized regression coefficients <lb/>for estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>per the related subject literature. These include the objective input level of public services, <lb/>primarily comprising local public service expenditures or infrastructure construction <lb/>expenditures; the objective output level of public services, encompassing qualitative changes <lb/>in the provision of public products by primary and secondary schools, public hospitals, etc. <lb/>as well as indicators measuring the quality of public services, such as the academic qualifica-<lb/>tions of full-time teachers, and the individual&apos;s subjective evaluation of the city&apos;s public ser-<lb/>vices, which involves questionnaire surveys, among other methods. This paper synthesizes <lb/>the first and second evaluation models, focusing on urban public services&apos; objective input <lb/>and output models. A single indicator is employed to replace the composite indicator, test-<lb/>ing the robustness of the basic econometric model. Per capita fiscal expenditure substitutes <lb/>for basic security public services, while the number of teachers per 10,000 elementary school <lb/>students and doctors per 10,000 resident population replaces primary education and medi-<lb/>cal services. The robustness test results are presented in the table: irrespective of whether <lb/>other city characteristic variables are included in the regression results, urban public ser-<lb/>vices consistently exhibit a significant positive effect on the two-child re-birth intention of <lb/>the migrant population. This aligns with the fundamental regression results of this paper <lb/>and further validates the robustness of the findings (as shown in Table 8). <lb/>Table 8. Robustness tests for replacing public service indicators. <lb/>Variables <lb/>logit(1) <lb/>logit(2) <lb/>Per capita public finance expenditure <lb/>-0.004(-0.012) <lb/>0.168***(0.033) <lb/>Number of teachers per 10,000 elementary school students <lb/>0.860***(0.073) <lb/>0.809***(0.081) <lb/>Number of doctors per 10,000 resident population <lb/>0.150***(0.023) <lb/>0.273***(0.034) <lb/>Level of economic development of the Urban <lb/>-0.387***(-0.043) <lb/>Urban salary level <lb/>-0.097***(-0.025) <lb/>Urban industrial structure <lb/>0.187***(0.023) <lb/>Size of urban resident population <lb/>0.0453*(0.023) <lb/>City apartment prices <lb/>0.378***(0.049) <lb/>Level of city administration <lb/>0.121***(0.025) <lb/>Age <lb/>0.363***(0.021) <lb/>0.372***(0.024) <lb/>Age squared <lb/>-0.007***(-0.000) <lb/>-0.007***(-0.000) <lb/>Gender <lb/>0.250***(0.023) <lb/>0.203***(0.028) <lb/>Level of education <lb/>0.006(0.005) <lb/>0.010*(0.006) <lb/>Nature of household registration <lb/>0.147***(0.033) <lb/>0.210***(0.04) <lb/>Flowing area <lb/>-0.040*(-0.024) <lb/>-0.106***(-0.029) <lb/>Flowing time <lb/>0.031***(0.009) <lb/>0.032***(0.01) <lb/>Willingness to settle down <lb/>0.194***(0.024) <lb/>0.222***(0.029) <lb/>Disposable income of the household <lb/>0.067***(0.012) <lb/>0.107***(0.019) <lb/>Family members moving in with the situation <lb/>0.170***(0.037) <lb/>0.111***(0.043) <lb/>Household rental expenses <lb/>-0.144***(-0.026) <lb/>-0.140***(-0.031) <lb/>Observations <lb/>52,545 <lb/>36,742 <lb/>PseudoR 2 <lb/>0.0975 <lb/>0.1073 <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>5494.8 <lb/>4303.89 <lb/>Notes <lb/>*, **, *** indicates significant at the 10%, 5%, and 1% levels, respectively; data in parentheses are robust standard <lb/>errors; Logitech models report PseudoR 2 and Chi2 values. This study used non-standardized regression coefficients <lb/>for estimation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345.t008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Conclusion and discussion <lb/>In conclusion, this study offers valuable insights into the impact of urban public services on the <lb/>willingness of the migrant population to have more children. These findings have sparked sig-<lb/>nificant discussions within the realms of urbanization, fertility behavior, and public service pro-<lb/>vision, enriching academic discourse and further exploring the implications of these results. <lb/>Firstly, the positive correlation observed between essential public services in the domain of <lb/>urban security and the increased willingness of the Migrant Population to reproduce aligns <lb/>with the views of scholars who emphasize the role of social security as a driver of population <lb/>dynamics [69]. As highlighted by Zhou [43], the evolving landscape of social security often <lb/>plays a critical role in shaping population decisions, acting as a substitute for traditional family <lb/>support structures [70]. <lb/>Secondly, the identified positive correlation between primary education and the willingness <lb/>to have children is in accordance with assertions made by scholars [71] regarding the influence <lb/>of educational investments on altering fertility preferences. This underscores the socio-eco-<lb/>nomic dimensions of fertility decision-making, where improved educational opportunities can <lb/>mitigate perceived costs and enhance the desirability of reproduction. <lb/>Thirdly, the observed positive correlation between essential medical services and the will-<lb/>ingness to have children is consistent with the framework proposed by Ji [72], emphasizing the <lb/>crucial role of health-related services in shaping fertility intentions. Comprehensive and acces-<lb/>sible medical services can address reproductive health issues and create an environment con-<lb/>ducive to family expansion. <lb/>These findings raise intriguing questions about the evolving role of urban public services in <lb/>a dynamic and ever-changing society. The counterintuitive impact of urban public services on <lb/>the willingness of the Migrant Population to reproduce challenges conventional perspectives <lb/>regarding the positive role of public services in demographic dynamics. This phenomenon can <lb/>be interpreted through the lens of Polanyi theory [73], which suggests that urbanization might <lb/>induce shifts in individual values and lifestyle choices, thus influencing fertility decisions. <lb/>The differential impact of security, medical services, and primary education on increasing <lb/>fertility intentions deserves further exploration. As proposed by scholars [74], these varying <lb/>effects may be attributed to differences in the perceived importance of these services in the <lb/>lives of the Migrant Population [75]. Future research should delve deeper into the qualitative <lb/>aspects of these services to unveil potential underlying mechanisms. <lb/>In summary, the theoretical significance of these findings extends beyond the scope of this <lb/>study, opening up new avenues for research to delve into the intricate relationship between <lb/>urban public services and fertility preferences within the context of contemporary urbaniza-<lb/>tion dynamics. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Appendix. Construction of indicators for urban basic public services. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Quanling Cai. <lb/>Data curation: Sichen Liu, Quanling Cai. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Quanling Cai. <lb/>Methodology: Mingxing Wang, Kaisheng Di. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Project administration: Kaisheng Di. <lb/>Resources: Quanling Cai, Kaisheng Di. <lb/>Supervision: Mingxing Wang. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Quanling Cai. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Sichen Liu. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bar M, Leukhina O. Demographic transition and industrial revolution: A macroeconomic investigation. <lb/>Rev Econ Dyn. 2010; 13: 424-451. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.red.2009.03.002 <lb/>2. Boca DD. The Effect of Child Care and Part Time Opportunities on Participation and Fertility Decisions <lb/>in Italy. J Popul Econ. 2002; 15: 549-573. https://doi.org/10.1007/s001480100089 <lb/>3. Bongaarts J, Watkins SC. Social Interactions and Contemporary Fertility Transitions. Popul Dev Rev. <lb/>1996; 22: 639-682. https://doi.org/10.2307/2137804 <lb/>4. Zhang J, Li X, Tang J. Effect of public expenditure on fertility intention to have a second child or more: <lb/>Evidence from China&apos;s CGSS survey data. Cities. 2022; 128: 103812. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities. <lb/>2022.103812 <lb/>5. Economic backwardness and economic growth: studies in the theory of economic development | CiNii <lb/>Research. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://cir.nii.ac.jp/crid/1130282270614710016 <lb/>6. Social insurance participation and urban settlement intentions of China&apos;s floating population-Huang-<lb/>2020-Population, Space and Place-Wiley Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https:// <lb/>onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/psp.2366 <lb/>7. Toulemon L, Testa MR. Fertility intentions and actual fertility: A complex relationship. <lb/>8. Schoen R, Astone NM, Kim YJ, Nathanson CA, Fields JM. Do Fertility Intentions Affect Fertility Behav-<lb/>ior? J Marriage Fam. 1999; 61: 790-799. https://doi.org/10.2307/353578 <lb/>9. Philipov D. Theories on fertility intentions: a demographer&apos;s perspective. Vienna Yearb Popul Res. <lb/>2011; 9: 37-45. https://doi.org/10.1553/populationyearbook2011s37 <lb/>10. Spatial pattern and determinants of migrant workers&apos; interprovincial hukou transfer intention in China: <lb/>Evidence from a National Migrant Population Dynamic Monitoring Survey in 2016-Gu-2020-Popu-<lb/>lation, Space and Place-Wiley Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary. <lb/>wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/psp.2250 <lb/>11. Puig-Barrachina: Decline in fertility induced by. . .-Google 学术搜索. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=Decline+in+fertility+induced+by+economic+recession <lb/>+in+Spain&amp;author=Puig-Barrachina,+V.&amp;author=Rodr%C3%ADguez-Sanz,+M.&amp;author=Dom%C3% <lb/>ADnguez-Berj%C3%B3n,+M.F.&amp;author=Mart%C3%ADn,+U.&amp;author=Luque,+M.%C3%81.&amp;author= <lb/>Ruiz,+M.&amp;author=Perez,+G.&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;journal=Gac.+Sanit.&amp;volume=34&amp;pages=238% <lb/>E2%80%93244&amp;doi=10.1016/j.gaceta.2019.05.011&amp;pmid=31640904 <lb/>12. Ajzen I, Klobas J. Fertility intentions: An approach based on the theory of planned behavior. Demogr <lb/>Res. 2013; 29: 203-232. https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2013.29.8 <lb/>13. Liu J, Liu T. Two-child policy, gender income and fertility choice in China. Int Rev Econ Finance. 2020; <lb/>69: 1071-1081. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.iref.2018.12.009 <lb/>14. Meng T, Lyu S. The impact of the selective two-child policy on residents&apos; fertility intentions in China. <lb/>Appl Econ Lett. 2022; 29: 1455-1459. https://doi.org/10.1080/13504851.2021.1937492 <lb/>15. Zhu Y. China&apos;s floating population and their settlement intention in the cities: Beyond the Hukou reform. <lb/>Habitat Int. 2007; 31: 65-76. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.habitatint.2006.04.002 <lb/>16. Acculturation, urban identity, and psychological well-being of rural-urban migrants in China-Li-2022 <lb/>-Applied Psychology: Health and Well-Being-Wiley Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://iaap-journals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/aphw.12327?_gl=1*a8bc6l*_gcl_ <lb/>au*MTQ2NTIxMzAzOS4xNjk1MDIzMzkw <lb/>17. The impacts of house prices on floating population&apos;s fertility intentions-evidence from China: Applied <lb/>Economics Letters: Vol 0, No 0. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10. <lb/>1080/13504851.2023.2186350 <lb/>18. Theories of International Migration: A Review and Appraisal on JSTOR. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://www.jstor.org/stable/2938462?typeAccessWorkflow=login <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. Religiosity and Trajectories of Lifetime Fertility Intentions-Evidence from a German Panel Study-<lb/>ScienceDirect. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/ <lb/>S1040260823000539 <lb/>20. Cavalli L. &apos;He wants, I don&apos;t&apos;: females&apos; contrasting attitude about fertility intentions for a second child. Int <lb/>Rev Sociol. 2012; 22: 71-93. https://doi.org/10.1080/03906701.2012.657533 <lb/>21. Does formal housing encourage settlement intention of rural migrants in Chinese cities? A structural <lb/>equation model analysis-Zhilin Liu, Yujun Wang, Shaowei Chen, 2017. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/ https://doi.org/10.1177/0042098016634979 <lb/>22. Changes in the Chinese Population&apos;s Fertility Intentions: 1980-2011: Social Sciences in China: Vol 36, <lb/>No 1. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02529203.2015. <lb/>1001482?src=recsys <lb/>23. Full article: Employment uncertainty and fertility intentions: Stability or resilience? [cited 15 Oct 2023]. <lb/>Available: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00324728.2021.1939406?src=recsys <lb/>24. Gao Y, Qu Z. &apos;More Children, More Happiness?&apos;: New Evidence from Elderly Parents in China. GLO <lb/>Discussion Paper; 2019. Report No.: 366. Available: https://www.econstor.eu/handle/10419/200243 <lb/>25. Religiosity and Fertility in the United States: The Role of Fertility Intentions | Social Forces | Oxford Aca-<lb/>demic. [cited 30 Oct 2023]. Available: https://academic.oup.com/sf/article-abstract/86/3/1163/ <lb/>2235018?login=false <lb/>26. The Poetics of Economic Independence for Female Empowerment: An Interview with Flora Nwapa on <lb/>JSTOR. [cited 30 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.jstor.org/stable/3820268 <lb/>27. Fewer and Better Children: Race, Class, Religion, and Birth Control Reform in America1 | American <lb/>Journal of Sociology: Vol 119, No 6. [cited 30 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/ <lb/>doi/abs/10.1086/674007 <lb/>28. Do Children Born Before and After Adequate Birth Intervals Do Better at School? | Journal of Tropical <lb/>Pediatrics | Oxford Academic. [cited 30 Oct 2023]. Available: https://academic.oup.com/tropej/article/ <lb/>51/5/265/1690120?login=false <lb/>29. Missing the Target? Correspondence of Fertility Intentions and Behavior in the U.S. | SpringerLink. <lb/>[cited 30 Oct 2023]. Available: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/B:POPU.0000021074.33415.c1 <lb/>30. Health status and fertility intentions among migrants-Alderotti-2022-International Migration-Wiley <lb/>Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/imig. <lb/>12921 <lb/>31. Rural migrant workers in urban China: living a marginalised life-Keung Wong-2007-International <lb/>Journal of Social Welfare-Wiley Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary. <lb/>wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1468-2397.2007.00475.x <lb/>32. Examining the psychosocial determinants of women&apos;s decisions to delay childbearing | Human Repro-<lb/>duction | Oxford Academic. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://academic.oup.com/humrep/article/31/ <lb/>8/1776/2379940?login=false <lb/>33. Sobotka T, Testa MR. Attitudes and Intentions Toward Childlessness in Europe. In: Ho ¨hn C, Avramov <lb/>D, Kotowska IE, editors. People, Population Change and Policies. Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands; <lb/>2008. pp. 177-211. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-6609-2_9 <lb/>34. ter Keurst A, Boivin J, Gameiro S. Women&apos;s intentions to use fertility preservation to prevent age-related <lb/>fertility decline. Reprod Biomed Online. 2016; 32: 121-131. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rbmo.2015.10.007 <lb/>PMID: 26611498 <lb/>35. Ben-Porath Y. Child Mortality and Fertility: Issues in the Demographic Transition of a Migrant Popula-<lb/>tion. Population and Economic Change in Developing Countries. University of Chicago Press; <lb/>1980. pp. 151-208. Available: https://www.nber.org/books-and-chapters/population-and-economic-<lb/>change-developing-countries/child-mortality-and-fertility-issues-demographic-transition-migrant-<lb/>population <lb/>36. Raybould A, Sear R. Children of the (gender) revolution: A theoretical and empirical synthesis of how <lb/>gendered division of labour influences fertility. Popul Stud. 2021; 75: 169-190. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>00324728.2020.1851748 PMID: 33321056 <lb/>37. Childbearing intention and its associated factors: A systematic review-Hashemzadeh-2021-Nurs-<lb/>ing Open-Wiley Online Library. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/ <lb/>10.1002/nop2.849 <lb/>38. The effect of stepchildren on childbearing intentions and births | SpringerLink. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Avail-<lb/>able: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1353/dem.2002.0011 <lb/>39. He: The Impact of Rural Population Mobility on Fertility. . .-Google 学术搜索. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Avail-<lb/>able: https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=The+Impact+of+Rural+Population+Mobility+on <lb/>+Fertility+Intention+under+the+Comprehensive+Two-Child+Policy:+Evidence+from+Rural <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>+China&amp;author=He,+Q.&amp;author=Deng,+X.&amp;author=Li,+C.&amp;author=Yan,+Z.&amp;author=Qi,+Y.&amp;publica-<lb/>tion_year=2022&amp;journal=Int.+J.+Environ.+Res.+Public+Health&amp;volume=19&amp;pages=7365&amp;-<lb/>doi=10.3390/ijerph19127365&amp;pmid=35742624 <lb/>40. IJERPH | Free Full-Text | Fertility Intention and Influencing Factors for Having a Second Child among <lb/>Floating Women of Childbearing Age. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/ <lb/>19/24/16531 <lb/>41. The Importance of Motherhood and Fertility Intentions among U.S. Women-Julia McQuillan, Arthur L. <lb/>Greil, Karina M. Shreffler, Andrew V. Bedrous, 2015. [cited 16 Oct 2023]. Available: https://journals. <lb/>sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0731121414534393 <lb/>42. Wang L. Fertility and unemployment in a social security system. Econ Lett. 2015; 133: 19-23. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.econlet.2015.05.014 <lb/>43. Zhou M, Guo W. Comparison of second-child fertility intentions between local and migrant women in <lb/>urban China: a Blinder-Oaxaca decomposition. J Ethn Migr Stud. 2021; 47: 2417-2438. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1080/1369183X.2020.1778456 <lb/>44. I would if I could: precarious employment and childbearing intentions in Italy | SpringerLink. [cited 31 <lb/>Oct 2023]. Available: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11150-010-9117-y <lb/>45. Zhou M, Guo W. Fertility intentions of having a second child among the floating population in China: <lb/>Effects of socioeconomic factors and home ownership. Popul Space Place. 2020; 26: e2289. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1002/psp.2289 <lb/>46. Liu J, Liu M, Zhang S, Ma Q, Wang Q. Intent to have a second child among Chinese women of child-<lb/>bearing age following China&apos;s new universal two-child policy: a cross-sectional study. BMJ Sex Reprod <lb/>Health. 2020; 46: 59-66. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjsrh-2018-200197 PMID: 31754062 <lb/>47. Women&apos;s Fertility Autonomy in Urban China: The Role of Couple Dynamics Under the Universal Two-<lb/>Child Policy: Chinese Sociological Review: Vol 50, No 3. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www. <lb/>tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/21620555.2018.1428895 <lb/>48. IJERPH | Free Full-Text | Mothers&apos; Subjective Well-Being after Having a Second Child in Current China: <lb/>A Case Study of Xi&apos;an City. Available: https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3823 <lb/>49. Options for Fertility Policy Transition in China-Yi-2007-Population and Development Review-<lb/>Wiley Online Library. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1728-4457.2007. <lb/>00168.x <lb/>50. China&apos;s Below-Replacement Fertility: Government Policy or Socioeconomic Development?-Cai-<lb/>2010-Population and Development Review-Wiley Online Library. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1728-4457.2010.00341.x <lb/>51. Hardee-Cleaveland K, Banister J. Fertility Policy and Implementation in China, 1986-88. Popul Dev <lb/>Rev. 1988; 14: 245-286. https://doi.org/10.2307/1973572 PMID: 11651940 <lb/>52. Baochang G, Feng W, Zhigang G, Erli Z. China&apos;s Local and National Fertility Policies at the End of the <lb/>Twentieth Century. Popul Dev Rev. 2007; 33: 129-147. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1728-4457.2007. <lb/>00161.x <lb/>53. Chu Y. China&apos;s new urbanization plan: Progress and structural constraints. Cities. 2020; 103: 102736. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cities.2020.102736 <lb/>54. Guo Z. The low fertility rate is the major demographic risk in China. China Econ J. 2012; 5: 65-84. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/17538963.2012.761834 <lb/>55. Homeownership and fertility intentions among migrant population in urban China: Housing Studies: Vol <lb/>0, No 0. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02673037.2022. <lb/>2108382 <lb/>56. INCOME, SOCIAL SECURITY AND CHINESE FAMILIES&apos; &quot;TWO-CHILD&quot; DECISIONS: EVIDENCE <lb/>FROM URBAN RESIDENTS&apos; FERTILITY INTENTIONS | The Singapore Economic Review. [cited 31 <lb/>Oct 2023]. Available: https://www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S0217590820500101 <lb/>57. Fertility Intentions and Reproductive Health Care Needs of People Living with HIV in Cape Town, South <lb/>Africa: Implications for Integrating Reproductive Health and HIV Care Services | SpringerLink. [cited 31 <lb/>Oct 2023]. Available: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10461-009-9550-1 <lb/>58. A Home to Plan the First Child? Fertility Intentions and Housing Conditions in Italy-Vignoli-2013-<lb/>Population, Space and Place-Wiley Online Library. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary. <lb/>wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/psp.1716 <lb/>59. Shao S, Tian Z, Zhang Y, Li B. The housing status and two-child fertility willingness of floating popula-<lb/>tion: Evidence from the Chinese General Social Survey. Econ Anal Policy. 2023; 80: 247-266. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.eap.2023.08.012 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>60. Housing, income inequality and child injury mortality in Europe: a cross-sectional study-Sengoelge-<lb/>2014-Child: Care, Health and Development-Wiley Online Library. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: <lb/>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/cch.12027 <lb/>61. Child care subsidy and child maltreatment-Yang-2019-Child &amp; Family Social Work-Wiley Online <lb/>Library. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/cfs.12635 <lb/>62. Moving up the social ladder: homeownership and expected socioeconomic status among migrant <lb/>young adults in China: International Journal of Housing Policy: Vol 0, No 0. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Avail-<lb/>able: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/19491247.2023.2178819?src=recsys <lb/>63. Paul S. Accountability in public services: Exit, voice and control. World Dev. 1992; 20: 1047-1060. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0305-750X(92)90130-N <lb/>64. Increase in Prevalence of Overweight in Dutch Children and Adolescents: A Comparison of Nationwide <lb/>Growth Studies in 1980, 1997 and 2009 | PLOS ONE. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://journals. <lb/>plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0027608 <lb/>65. Fertility, Migration and Acculturation (FEMINA): a research protocol for studying intersectional sexual <lb/>and reproductive health inequalities | Reproductive Health. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. Available: https://link. <lb/>springer.com/article/10.1186/s12978-019-0795-5 <lb/>66. Comparing the needs and utilization of health services between urban residents and rural-to-urban <lb/>migrants in China from 2012 to 2016 | BMC Health Services Research | Full Text. [cited 31 Oct 2023]. <lb/>Available: https://bmchealthservres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12913-018-3522-y <lb/>67. Declining fertility: Intentions, attitudes and aspirations-Deborah Mitchell, Edith Gray, 2007. [cited 31 <lb/>Oct 2023]. Available: https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1440783307073933 <lb/>68. Becker GS. An Economic Analysis of Fertility. Demographic and Economic Change in Developed Coun-<lb/>tries. Columbia University Press; 1960. pp. 209-240. Available: https://www.nber.org/books-and-<lb/>chapters/demographic-and-economic-change-developed-countries/economic-analysis-fertility <lb/>69. The gap between desired and expected fertility among women in Iran: A case study of Tehran city | <lb/>PLOS ONE. [cited 9 Dec 2023]. Available: https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0257128 <lb/>70. Xiong Y, Jiao G, Zheng J, Gao J, Xue Y, Tian B, et al. Fertility Intention and Influencing Factors for Hav-<lb/>ing a Second Child among Floating Women of Childbearing Age. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022; <lb/>19: 16531. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192416531 PMID: 36554418 <lb/>71. Xing Y, Tarimo CS, Ren W, Zhang L. The Impact of Health Insurance Policy on the Fertility Intention of <lb/>Rural Floating Population in China: Empirical Evidence from Cross-Sectional Data. Int J Environ Res <lb/>Public Health. 2023; 20: 175. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph20010175 PMID: 36612496 <lb/>72. Ji S. Fertility Intentions of Childbearing-Age Migrant Women With One Child and Its Influences. Atlantis <lb/>Press; 2021. pp. 1040-1047. https://doi.org/10.2991/assehr.k.210121.201 <lb/>73. The Great Transformation-Readings in Economic Sociology-Wiley Online Library. [cited 9 Dec <lb/>2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/9780470755679.ch4 <lb/>74. China&apos;s Floating Population: New Evidence from the 2000 Census-Liang-2004-Population and <lb/>Development Review-Wiley Online Library. [cited 15 Oct 2023]. Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley. <lb/>com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1728-4457.2004.00024.x <lb/>75. Gott C, Johnston K. The migrant population in the UK: fiscal effects: Citeseer; 2002. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Urban public services and fertility intentions of internal migrants in China <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300345 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 24 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>