<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T10:04:34.529Z">11/14/2025 10:04:34 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T10:04:21.546266Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T10:04:21.546266Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Lhx3/4 initiates a cardiopharyngeal-specific <lb/>transcriptional program in response to <lb/>widespread FGF signaling <lb/>C. J. Pickett ID , Hannah N. Gruner, Bradley Davidson ID * <lb/>Department of Biology, Swarthmore College, Swarthmore, Pennsylvania, United States of America <lb/>* bdavids1@swarthmore.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>AU : Pleaseconfirmthatallheadinglevelsarerepresentedcorrectly: <lb/>Individual signaling pathways, such as fibroblast growth factors (FGFs), can regulate a <lb/>plethora of inductive events. According to current paradigms, signal-dependent transcription <lb/>factors (TFs), such as FGF/MapK-activated Ets family factors, partner with lineage-deter-<lb/>mining factors to achieve regulatory specificity. However, many aspects of this model have <lb/>not been rigorously investigated. One key question relates to whether lineage-determining <lb/>factors dictate lineage-specific responses to inductive signals or facilitate these responses <lb/>in collaboration with other inputs. We utilize the chordate model Ciona robusta to investigate <lb/>mechanisms generating lineage-specific induction. Previous studies in C. robusta have <lb/>shown that cardiopharyngeal progenitor cells are specified through the combined activity of <lb/>FGF-activated Ets1/2.b and an inferred ATTA-binding transcriptional cofactor. Here, we <lb/>show that the homeobox TF Lhx3/4 serves as the lineage-determining TF that dictates car-<lb/>diopharyngeal-specific transcription in response to pleiotropic FGF signaling. Targeted <lb/>knockdown of Lhx3/4 leads to loss of cardiopharyngeal gene expression. Strikingly, ectopic <lb/>expression of Lhx3/4 in a neuroectodermal lineage subject to FGF-dependent specification <lb/>leads to ectopic cardiopharyngeal gene expression in this lineage. Furthermore, ectopic <lb/>Lhx3/4 expression disrupts neural plate morphogenesis, generating aberrant cell behaviors <lb/>associated with execution of incompatible morphogenetic programs. Based on these find-<lb/>ings, we propose that combinatorial regulation by signal-dependent and lineage-determi-<lb/>nant factors represents a generalizable, previously uncategorized regulatory subcircuit we <lb/>term &quot;cofactor-dependent induction.&quot; Integration of this subcircuit into theoretical models will <lb/>facilitate accurate predictions regarding the impact of gene regulatory network rewiring on <lb/>evolutionary diversification and disease ontogeny. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Overview of developmental gene regulatory networks <lb/>Developmental gene regulatory networks (GRNs) program spatiotemporal gene expression, <lb/>ultimately determining embryonic cell fate decisions and morphogenesis [1-4]. The <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/>1 / 33 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Pickett CJ, Gruner HN, Davidson B (2024) <lb/>Lhx3/4 initiates a cardiopharyngeal-specific <lb/>transcriptional program in response to widespread <lb/>FGF signaling. PLoS Biol 22(1): e3002169. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 <lb/>Academic Editor: Anna Kostadinova Kicheva, <lb/>Institute of Science and Technology Austria, <lb/>AUSTRIA <lb/>Received: May 4, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 21, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 25, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Pickett et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Raw and processed <lb/>RNA sequencing data available from NCBI Gene <lb/>Expression Omnibus (accession number <lb/>GSE250325). <lb/></front>

	<body>cardiogenic GRN in the invertebrate chordate Ciona robusta provides a useful overview of one <lb/>such network (Fig 1). During early stages of development, network circuits composed of genes <lb/>encoding transcription or signaling factors dictate changes in the regulatory state or signaling <lb/>status of each cell lineage (Fig 1A-1C). As development proceeds, these early circuits feed into <lb/>effector circuits driving transient changes in cell behavior or more stable changes in cell iden-<lb/>tity associated with differentiation (Fig 1D-1F). Some portions of developmental GRNs <lb/>encode cell autonomous programs in which inherited regulatory states dictate cascading shifts <lb/>in gene expression (Fig 1A). However, substantial portions of developmental GRNs encode <lb/>non-cell-autonomous programs, in which signals regulate the cell fate of neighboring lineages <lb/>through modifications of signal-dependent transcription factor (TF) activity (Fig 1B). Previous <lb/>studies have elucidated many fundamental features of GRNs, including recurrent network <lb/>motifs [5], the bistability of cell fate [6], modular subcircuits [7,8], along with linkages between <lb/>regulatory and effector circuits [3,9]. However, critical aspects of developmental GRN struc-<lb/>ture and function remain poorly described. One major gap involves integration of microenvi-<lb/>ronmental, extrinsic cues, including paracrine signals and matrix factors. How are subcircuits <lb/>structured to permit robust responses to inherently noisy extrinsic cues? How do GRNs pro-<lb/>cess a limited set of signal-dependent inputs to generate a vast array of differential transcrip-<lb/>tional outputs? Addressing these gaps is required to productively investigate GRN rewiring <lb/>associated with evolution and disease progression. <lb/>The hierarchical topology of developmental GRNs <lb/>Developmental GRNs consist of semi-independent, hierarchical modules or circuits. Distinct <lb/>populations of progenitor or precursor cells are programed by distinct territorial gene net-<lb/>works. Each territorial GRN can be divided into regulatory modules, or subcircuits, that exe-<lb/>cute discrete, cascading functions as first elucidated in reference to echinoderm skeletogenic <lb/>mesoderm specification [10]. Network motifs, such as feedback or feedforward loops, have <lb/>also been considered to act as regulatory modules [11]. It has been proposed that there may be <lb/>a limited set of recurring subcircuits or motifs that are deployed for related functions across <lb/>both developmental and physiological GRNs [8,11-14]. Because theories regarding network <lb/>motifs were derived from studies of bacterial signaling, extrinsic inputs are well integrated. In <lb/>contrast, initial theories regarding developmental subcircuits were largely derived from knock-<lb/>down of lineage-specific TFs as opposed to highly pleiotropic signal-dependent TFs. Thus <lb/>extrinsic inputs have not been fully integrated into current theoretical overviews of develop-<lb/>mental subcircuits. <lb/>The pleiotropic input of signals in developmental GRNs <lb/>Signals play an integral role in coordinating and refining the deployment of nearly all territo-<lb/>rial GRNs [15]. Remarkably, this rich array of developmental functions largely involves only <lb/>10 signaling pathway families [15-17]. Although these families have diversified to generate <lb/>numerous paralogous signaling components, each family still regulates transcription through <lb/>a limited set of signal-dependent TFs, each of which binds a similar, family-specific binding <lb/>site motif. This paradigm is well illustrated by the receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs), a signaling <lb/>pathway family that encompasses many key developmental signals, including epidermal <lb/>growth factors (EGFs), vascular/endothelial growth factors (VEGFs), and fibroblast growth <lb/>factors (FGFs). All of these signals mediate changes in transcription through a shared set of <lb/>transduction cascades that includes the Map kinase (MapK) pathway. MapKs, regardless of the <lb/>upstream signal that drives their activity, often regulate transcription through phosphorylation <lb/>of Ets family TFs [18,19] (Fig 1B). All Ets factors bind a highly stereotyped motif (GGAW) <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/>PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/>2 / 33 <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by two grants <lb/>received by BD. The American Heart Association <lb/>grant number 20AIREA35080013 (https:// <lb/>professional.heart.org/en/research-programs/aha-<lb/>funding-opportunities) along with the National <lb/>Science Foundation grant number 8077804 <lb/>(https://www.nsf.gov/). The funders had no role in <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>Abbreviations: ANP, AU : Anabbreviationlisthasbeencompiledforthoseusedthroughoutthetext:Pleaseverifythatallentriesarecorrectlyabbreviated: <lb/>anterior neural plate; ASMF, <lb/>atrial siphon muscle founder; ASV, anterior <lb/>sensory vesicle; CPF, cardiopharyngeal founder; <lb/>CPP, cardiopharyngeal progenitor; EGF, epidermal <lb/>growth factor; FFL, feed-forward loop; FGF, <lb/>fibroblast growth factor; FGFR, FGF receptor; GRN, <lb/>gene regulatory network; HP, heart precursor; HPF, <lb/>hours postfertilization; LSA, lineage-specific <lb/>coactivator; LSR, lineage-specific repressor; MapK, <lb/>Map kinase; MG, motor ganglion; NE, <lb/>neuroectodermal; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; <lb/>RTK, receptor tyrosine kinase; TF, transcription <lb/>factor; VEGF, vascular/endothelial growth factor. <lb/></front>

	<body>[20,21]. The resulting tendency for diverse, widely deployed signaling pathway families to reg-<lb/>ulate transcription through a single, shared motif represents a conundrum. How does the <lb/>genome encode such a vast array of temporally and spatially distinct transcriptional responses <lb/>Fig 1. Ciona robusta cardiopharyngeal specification and development. Panels pair regulatory circuits (A-E) or <lb/>summaries of morphogenetic events (F) with corresponding schematics. Red and orange HPs represent primary and <lb/>secondary heart precursors respectively. (G) Illustration of C. robusta regulatory networks involving FGF/Ets and <lb/>known or putative lineage-determining cofactors. Colors used in network diagrams pair with shaded territories in <lb/>cartoon tailbud C. robusta embryo. ASMF, atrial siphon muscle founder; CPP, 2˚CPP, primary and secondary <lb/>cardiopharyngeal progenitors; FGF, fibroblast growth factor; HP, heart precursor; MapK, Map kinaseAU : Abbreviationlistshavebe <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>to functionally indistinguishable inputs? Lineage-specific transcriptional responses to pleiotro-<lb/>pic signaling are thought to be driven by differential deployment of cofactors, referred to as <lb/>lineage-determining TFs [22,23]. However, despite the central role of Ets family factors and <lb/>other signal-dependent TFs in developmental patterning, the transcriptional partners that <lb/>mediate discrete transcriptional outputs remain poorly characterized [24-26]. More broadly, <lb/>the mechanisms by which these partners determine signal-dependent transcriptional outputs <lb/>have not been characterized and relevant subcircuits have not been incorporated into theoreti-<lb/>cal models [8]. We aim to address these fundamental gaps in inductive specificity through in-<lb/>depth analysis of the C. robusta cardiopharyngeal GRN. <lb/>Elucidation of gene regulatory networks in Ciona robusta <lb/>Ciona robusta (also referred to as Ciona intestinalis Type A [27,28]) provides an excellent plat-<lb/>form for investigating developmental GRN structure and function. C. robusta is a tunicate, a <lb/>clade of invertebrate chordates that are the closest sister group to the vertebrates [29]. How-<lb/>ever, tunicate genomes were not subjected to 2 rounds of duplications that occurred within the <lb/>vertebrate lineage. The resulting lack of paralogs for many key signaling and TFs leads to <lb/>greatly reduced GRN complexity. For example, there is a single gene encoding the FGF recep-<lb/>tor (FGFR) in C. robusta versus at least 4 distinct FGFR genes in most vertebrate genomes. <lb/>Additionally, the C. robusta genome is extremely compact. Relatively short intergenic regions <lb/>permit rapid identification of C. robusta regulatory elements, and the ability to easily generate <lb/>large numbers of transgenic C. robusta embryos has facilitated in-depth characterization of <lb/>these elements [30]. These advantages have been productively exploited to generate a high-res-<lb/>olution map of the C. robusta cardiopharyngeal GRN [31,32]. <lb/>The Ciona robusta cardiopharyngeal gene network <lb/>In C. robusta embryos, 2 founder cells (the cardiopharyngeal founders or CPFs) give rise to the <lb/>heart and a subset of pharyngeal muscle cells. According to current models (Fig 1), CPFs are <lb/>specified by the 110-cell stage when overlapping expression domains of Lhx3/4 and Tbx6-r.b <lb/>activate Mesp exclusively in these 2 cells [33,34] (Fig 1A). Mesp is presumed to activate expres-<lb/>sion of Ets1/2.b [35-37], making the CPF cells competent to respond to FGF signaling <lb/>(Fig 1B). During gastrulation, CPFs are exposed to uniform FGF signaling, but due to differen-<lb/>tial FGFR trafficking, only a subset of CPF daughter cells activate the MapK cascade required <lb/>to execute the downstream cardiopharyngeal progenitor (CPP) specification program (green <lb/>cells in Fig 1C) [36,38]. In these daughter cells, MapK-dependent phosphorylation of Ets1/2.b <lb/>initiates progenitor induction. Activated Ets1/2.b partners with an ATTA-binding cofactor to <lb/>drive transcription of CPP genes, including Foxf, Hand.r, and Gata.a (Fig 1C) [39]. Foxf initi-<lb/>ates a migratory program by driving transcription of effector genes, including RhoDF (Fig 1D) <lb/>[37,40]. During early tailbud stages, pairs of bilateral CPPs migrate along the ventral trunk epi-<lb/>dermis and eventually meet along the ventral midline (Fig 1D) [36,41]. These progenitors then <lb/>undergo a series of asymmetrical divisions to produce heart precursor (HP) and atrial siphon <lb/>muscle founder (ASMF) lineages (Fig 1E). Each of these lineages execute distinct GRNs even-<lb/>tually driving distinct morphogenetic programs in the juvenile (Fig 1F) [42-45]. <lb/>Pleiotropic roles for the FGF/MapK/Ets pathway in C. robusta <lb/>C. robusta&apos;s cellular simplicity has facilitated characterization of a wide array of FGF-depen-<lb/>dent inductive events [46]. Indeed, FGF plays a predominant role in C. robusta embryonic pat-<lb/>terning. During early cleavage stages, FGF secreted from the central endoderm progenitors <lb/>specifies notochord and neural plate progenitor lineages, along with a range of &quot;mesenchymal&quot; <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>lineages that give rise to postlarval mesodermal tissues. As mentioned above, FGF also specifies <lb/>the CPP lineage during this early embryonic period. In later stages, FGF subspecifies a number <lb/>of distinct lineages within the neural plate, CPPs, ectoderm, and endoderm [36,47-49]. As <lb/>with CPP induction, many of these FGF-dependent specification events have been shown to <lb/>alter transcription through the MapK/Ets pathway [47,48]. According to current models, <lb/>shared reliance on FGF is translated into differential specification through deployment of dis-<lb/>tinct, lineage-determining Ets cofactors, some of which have been identified. For example, <lb/>Gata.a and Zic-r.b serve as the Ets cofactors for neuroectodermal and primary notochord spec-<lb/>ification, respectively (Fig 1G) [18,50,51]. However, many of these presumptive partner fac-<lb/>tors, including the ATTA-binding factor driving Ets-dependent expression of CPP genes, have <lb/>not been characterized. <lb/>Here, we show that the homeobox TF Lhx3/4 serves as the Ets1/2.b partner responsible for <lb/>coactivation of the transcriptional program driving C. robusta CPP specification. Because <lb/>Lhx3/4 also participates in CPF lineage specification (Fig 1A) [34], it effectively regulates CPP <lb/>gene expression through a multistep coherent feed-forward loop. Strikingly, we find that mis-<lb/>expression of Lhx3/4 in the anterior neural plate (ANP) lineage is sufficient to suppress the <lb/>native FGF/MapK-dependent ANP program and initiate ectopic activation of the CPP specifi-<lb/>cation program [18,48,52]. However, Lhx3/4 misexpression also initiates ectopic activation of <lb/>a neuroectodermal motor ganglion (MG) program. The resulting execution of incompatible <lb/>morphogenetic programs appears to drive highly aberrant cell behaviors. Based on these find-<lb/>ings, we propose that lineage-determining cofactors play an instructive role, dictating rather <lb/>than merely facilitating lineage-specific transcriptional responses to pleiotropic signals. We <lb/>also argue that integration of subcircuits delineating the contribution of lineage-determining <lb/>factors is essential for accurate modeling of developmental GRNs and the impact of GRN <lb/>rewiring on evolutionary diversification and disease ontogeny. <lb/>Results <lb/>Lhx3/4 is required for cardiopharyngeal progenitor cell migration <lb/>Previous studies have demonstrated that phosphorylated Ets1/2.b works in conjunction with <lb/>an unknown ATTA-binding cofactor to initiate CPP gene expression (Fig 1B, 1C and 1G) <lb/>[39]. Because ATTA resembles the core homeobox TF binding motif [53,54], we hypothesized <lb/>that the CPP cofactor is a homeobox factor. The C. robusta genome contains 86 <lb/>homeobox TFs [55]. However, a previous study revealed that only a small subset of these fac-<lb/>tors are enriched in sorted CPF lineage cells that were subjected to expression analysis just <lb/>prior to CPP specification (Fig 1A and 1B) [39]. We employed CRISPR-Cas9 to separately <lb/>knock down 4 of these candidate cofactors (Lhx3/4, Lmx1, Pax3/7, and Pou2; Fig 2A). Varying <lb/>combinations of 2 single guide RNAs (sgRNAs)AU : Pleaseprovidefullspellingfor}sgRNA}atfirstmentio <lb/>targeting each of these candidates were <lb/>expressed ubiquitously using the C. robusta U6 promoter [56] (see S1 Table for details of all <lb/>sgRNAs utilized). To ensure targeted knockdown in the CPF lineage, embryos were cotrans-<lb/>fected with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls in which the Mesp enhancer is deployed to drive robust and <lb/>lineage-specific knockdown in CPF lineage cells [35]. Embryos were also cotransfected with <lb/>Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP, allowing us to determine whether knockdown of any of these candidate <lb/>genes blocks CPP specification as reflected by disrupted CPP migration from the tail into the <lb/>trunk (Figs 1C, 1D and 2C) [35]. In the negative control group (electroporated with <lb/>Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP, Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, and an empty sgRNA vector (sgControl)), an average <lb/>of 10.1% of embryos displayed abnormal migration (Fig 2B). This baseline rate accords with <lb/>other published results [37] and likely reflects generalized developmental defects resulting <lb/>from dechorionation and transgenic expression of GFP or Cas9. We also performed a positive <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. Lhx3/4 is required for CPP migration. (A) Table displaying candidate genes targeted for knockdown including names, gene IDs for KY21 <lb/>gene models [57], and DNA-binding LOGOs [58-60]. LOGOs have been loosely aligned to highlight shared ATTA (TAAT) motifs. See http:// <lb/>ghost.zool.kyoto-u.ac.jp/default_ht.html [57] for conversion of KY21 IDs into the previous generation KH2012 IDs. (B) Graph displaying the <lb/>average percent of embryos exhibiting blocked migration over 2 trials. Negative control group (10.1%, n = 78). Ets1/2.b-targeting positive control <lb/>group (26.9%, n = 63, p = .0097). Lhx3/4 knockdown group (28.1%, n = 64, p = .0061). Underlying data can be found in S1 Appendix. (C-E) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>control, using a pair of sgRNAs to knockdown Ets1/2.b. This manipulation led to a modest but <lb/>significant suppression of CPP migration (26.9% +/-6.1%) in comparison to the negative con-<lb/>trol group (Fig 2B and 2D). The limited penetrance of this phenotype aligns with previous <lb/>studies in which Mesp was deployed as the Cas9 driver and may reflect the narrow time frame <lb/>for Cas9-driven gene editing, which must occur between expression of Cas9 protein (at <lb/>approximatelyAU : PleasenotethatasperPLOSstyle; donotusethesymbol � inprosetomeanaboutorapprox <lb/>5 hours postfertilization (HPF)) and CPP specification (at 6.5 HPF). Among <lb/>the 4 homeobox candidates, targeted knockdown of Lhx3/4 using a combination of sgRNAs <lb/>(sgLhx3/4 185 and sgLhx3/4 886 , subsequently referred to as sgLhx3/4) was the only manipula-<lb/>tion that resulted in a significant suppression of CPP migration (Figs 2B, 2E and S1). The level <lb/>of suppressed migration in these samples was similar to that seen in the positive control group <lb/>(sgEts1/2.b). Although these results indicate that Lhx3/4 is required for CPP migration, we <lb/>conducted a number of follow-up experiments to buttress this interpretation. <lb/>To evaluate predicted gene editing of Lhx3/4 by the sgLhx3/4 185/886 pair of sgRNAs, we <lb/>sequenced the Lhx3/4 locus in transfected CPP cells (S2 Fig). Because the Mesp regulatory ele-<lb/>ment only drives Cas9 in a small percentage of embryonic cells, transgenic tailbud stage <lb/>embryos (Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP, Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, U6&gt;sgLhx3/4) were dissociated and GFP-<lb/>labeled CPP-lineage cells were FACS collected. These sorted cells were then used as a PCR <lb/>template to sequence the Lhx3/4 locus. Lhx3/4 sgRNAs were designed to ensure that alterna-<lb/>tively spliced forms of Lhx3/4 [61] would be silenced by deletion of an approximately 6,000-bp <lb/>region between the first and third exon of the longer isoform (S2A Fig). Sequencing of PCR <lb/>amplicons derived from sorted cell gDNA confirmed the predicted deletion in the Lhx3/4 <lb/>locus (S2B Fig). Because we did not conduct further analysis of sgRNA knockdown for the <lb/>other targets, we cannot rule out a potential role for one of these alternative candidate factors <lb/>in CPP specification. <lb/>To determine whether the observed impact of the Lhx3/4 sgRNAs on CPP migration specif-<lb/>ically reflected Lhx3/4 knockdown instead of off-target effects, we co-expressed the sgLhx3/4 <lb/>constructs along with an sgLhx3/4-protected form of Lhx3/4 in the CPPs (Mesp&gt;Lhx3/4 rescue ) <lb/>and examined the impact on CPP migration (labeled with Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP). Reflecting the <lb/>initial screen, targeted Lhx3/4 knockdown blocked migration in 29.6% of transfected embryos <lb/>(averaged across 3 trials; Fig 2F and 2G). In contrast, coexpression of Mesp&gt;Lhx3/4 rescue in <lb/>matched samples significantly reduced the incidence of blocked migration (15.1% across 3 tri-<lb/>als; Figs 2F, 2H and S3A). Notably, knockdown of Lhx3/4 did not decrease expression of the <lb/>Mesp reporter (Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP), indicating knockdown of Lhx3/4 did not interfere with ini-<lb/>tial CPF specification (S3B Fig). Taken together, these results demonstrate that Lhx3/4 is <lb/>required for CPP migration and support the hypothesis that Lhx3/4 serves as the cofactor for <lb/>CPP specification. <lb/>Lhx3/4 is required for Hand.r expression in cardiopharyngeal progenitors <lb/>To further test the hypothesized role for Lhx3/4 in CPP specification, we examined the impact <lb/>of Lhx3/4 knockdown on Hand.r expression. Hand.r is expressed in bilateral pairs of CPPs <lb/>immediately following their specification (early neurula; Fig 3A, black arrowheads). At this <lb/>stage, Hand.r is also expressed in a bilateral set of anterior cells (Fig 3A, white arrowheads; <lb/>Representative tailbud stage embryos electroporated with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP, and sgRNAs as indicated. (F) Graph displaying <lb/>the average percent of embryos exhibiting blocked migration over 3 trials. Negative control group (3.7%, n = 194). Lhx3/4-targeting positive <lb/>control group (29.6%, n = 203). Lhx3/4 rescue group (15.1%, n = 222, p &lt; .0001). Lhx3/4 rescue only control group (4.5%, n = 223). Underlying <lb/>data can be found in S1 Appendix. (G, H) Representative tailbud stage embryos electroporated with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP, <lb/>U6&gt;sgLhx3/4, and Mesp&gt;Lhx3/4 rescue as indicated. (C-E, G, H) In these panels, white arrows mark normal CPP position at this stage of <lb/>development. Green is nuclear GFP fluorescence. Numbers indicate quantity of embryos displaying phenotype depicted by each image over total. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 3. Lhx3/4 is required for Hand.r expression and heart formation. (A-C, F, G) Representative neurula stage embryos coelectroporated with Mesp&gt;nls:: <lb/>Cas9::nls and sgRNAs as indicated. (A) Control embryo displays wild-type Hand.r expression pattern in the CPPs (black arrowheads) and anterior lineages <lb/>(white arrowheads). (B, C) sgRNAs targeting Lhx3/4 (B) or Ets1/2.b (C) often resulted in embryos that are missing Hand.r expression in the CPPs on one side <lb/>of the embryo (as indicated by a white asterisk). (D) Graph showing the average percent of CPPs lacking Hand.r expression across 2 trials. Control group <lb/>n = 122 (1.8%); Ets1/2.b knockdown n = 148 (23.3%), p &lt; .00001; Lhx3/4 knockdown n = 114 (19.8%), p &lt; .00001). Underlying data can be found in S1 <lb/>Appendix. (E) GRN showing hypothesized role of Lhx3/4 (see text). (F, G) Representative embryos probed for Ets1/2.b expression. (H) Graph displaying two-<lb/>trial average percentage of CPPs expressing Ets1/2.b, for control group n = 84 (93.1%) and for Lhx3/4 knockdown group, n = 78 (97.4%), p = .17896. All <lb/>embryos positioned anterior to the left. Numbers indicate quantity of embryos displaying phenotype depicted in each image over total. Underlying data can be <lb/>found in S1 Appendix. (I, J) Representative transmitted light images taken from movies of juveniles coelectroporated with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls and sgRNAs as <lb/>indicated (3I is from S1 Movie and 3J is from S2 Movie). Black dotted circle indicates the heart. (K) Quantification of the percent of heart defects observed over <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>[62]). In approximately 98% of control embryos (Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, U6&gt;sgGFP), Hand.r <lb/>exhibited a wild-type expression pattern (Fig 3A and 3D). As predicted by our hypothesis, <lb/>knockdown of Lhx3/4 (Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, U6&gt;sgLhx3/4) led to a consistent and significant <lb/>reduction in the percentage of CPPs displaying bilateral Hand.r expression (Fig 3B and 3D). A <lb/>similar result was seen in positive controls (sgEts1/2.b; Fig 3C and 3D). In both Lhx3/4 and <lb/>Ets1/2.b knockdowns, embryos often showed unilateral loss of Hand.r expression (white aster-<lb/>isks, Fig 3B and 3C), consistent with mosaic, unilateral incorporation of transgenes often <lb/>observed in electroporated C. robusta embryos [63,64]. <lb/>Knockdown of Lhx3/4 does not impact Ets1/2.b expression in the CPPs <lb/>Based on our knockdown results, we hypothesized that Lhx3/4 has 2 critical roles in CPP speci-<lb/>fication (Fig 3E). During early cleavage stages, Lhx3/4 serves as a cofactor for cell-autonomous <lb/>specification of the CPF lineage [34]. Subsequently, during gastrulation, Lhx3/4 serves as the <lb/>Ets1/2.b cofactor mediating signal-dependent specification of the CPP lineage. Although our <lb/>results demonstrate that Lhx3/4 is required for Hand.r expression and CPP migration, it is not <lb/>clear whether this is due to the hypothesized role of Lhx3/4 in CPP specification or reflects an <lb/>earlier, previously characterized role of Lhx3/4 in CPF lineage specification (Fig 3E). In partic-<lb/>ular, if Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls-dependent knockdown of Lhx3/4 disrupted Mesp expression, this <lb/>may lead to loss of Ets1/2.b expression, indirectly blocking signal-dependent specification of <lb/>CPPs. Although it is unlikely that the Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls would knockdown Lhx3/4 early <lb/>enough to disrupt founder lineage specification, we addressed this concern by examining Ets1/ <lb/>2.b expression. In control trials (Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls and U6&gt;sgGFP), normal, bilateral Ets1/2. <lb/>b expression was consistently observed in 93.1% of transgenic embryos (Fig 3F and 3H). <lb/>Knockdown of Lhx3/4 generated a similar impact on Ets1/2.b expression (Fig 3G and 3H). <lb/>These results provide further support for the hypothesis that Lhx3/4 serves as the Ets1/2.b <lb/>cofactor during signal-dependent CPP specification. <lb/>Lhx3/4 knockdown disrupts heart formation <lb/>According to our model, knockdown of Lhx3/4 and the subsequent loss of CPP specification <lb/>should disrupt the formation of a beating heart, which is first observed after metamorphosis in <lb/>4-day old juveniles. To test this prediction, we reared Lhx3/4-knockdown and control animals <lb/>to an early juvenile stage (Stage 6: Days 7 to 9; [65]). We first examined gross heart morphol-<lb/>ogy using low-power imaging of living juveniles and then fixed them for higher-resolution <lb/>confocal analysis. At this stage of juvenile development, the heart is composed of an outer peri-<lb/>cardial sphere surrounding a single-cell layer myocardial tube that undergoes regular peristal-<lb/>tic contractions (Fig 3I and 3L and S1 Movie). In control trials, an average of 13% of animals <lb/>exhibited mildly abnormal phenotypes, largely consisting of abnormally slow peristaltic con-<lb/>traction (Fig 3K). As predicted by our model, Lhx3/4 knockdown led to a significant increase <lb/>in the percentage of juveniles displaying phenotypically abnormal hearts. In these experimen-<lb/>tal trials, 44% of Lhx3/4-knockdown animals exhibited a range of morphological defects <lb/>including frequent gross abnormalities (Fig 3J, 3K and 3M). In some of these samples, the <lb/>2 trials, for controls (n = 35, 13%) and for Lhx3/4 knockdown samples (n = 35, 44%), p = .0041). Underlying data can be found in S1 Appendix. (L, M) <lb/>Representative confocal Z-stacks of juvenile hearts electroporated with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls and sgRNAs as indicated. Nuclei stained with DAPI (white). (L) <lb/>Control hearts show stereotypical anatomical structures including a myocardial tube (Myo, outlined in blue) and pericardial sphere (Peri, outlined in red), <lb/>adjacent to the stomach (Stm). (M) Representative Lhx3/4 knockdown heart illustrating one of the observed abnormal phenotypes similar to that shown in S3 <lb/>Movie. Heart morphology is grossly abnormal and putative myocardial cells are disorganized and hard to distinguish. Note that another small, grossly <lb/>malformed heart was visible on the other side of the stomach in this sample, but this was difficult to visualize using a projected Z-stack. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>heart was composed of an empty pericardial cavity with no discernible myocardium (Fig 3J <lb/>and S2 Movie). In other samples, heart size was reduced and the myocardium was severely dis-<lb/>organized (Fig 3M and S3 Movie). These results align with defects in CPP migration and uni-<lb/>lateral loss of CPP gene expression observed in Lhx3/4-knockdown embryos (Figs 2E and 3B). <lb/>Misexpression of Lhx3/4 is sufficient for ectopic activation of CPP <lb/>enhancers in the anterior neural plate <lb/>As detailed in the introduction, shared reliance on an inductive signal, such as FGF, is thought <lb/>to drive differential specification by deployment of distinct, lineage-determining cofactors. <lb/>This model predicts that shifting the expression of an Ets cofactor from one FGF-dependent <lb/>lineage to another should drive ectopic expression of genes normally restricted to the first line-<lb/>age. Due to widespread deployment of FGF/MapK/Ets-dependent induction in early embryos <lb/>(Fig 1G), C. robusta provides a valuable experimental platform for testing this prediction. In <lb/>particular, we focused on determining whether ectopic expression of the CPP Ets cofactor <lb/>Lhx3/4 would be sufficient to drive expression of CPP genes in the ANP, which also undergoes <lb/>FGF-dependent induction. As illustrated in Fig 4A, Dlx.b serves as the presumptive cofactor <lb/>for FGF/Ets-dependent expression of ANP genes, including Zic-r.b [66]. FGF-dependent <lb/>induction of the ANP occurs during the 64-cell stage in a row of cells that express both Dmrt <lb/>and Dlx.b (Fig 4B). By the neurula stage, this row has undergone 2 divisions and 2 of the result-<lb/>ing 4 rows of ANP cells express Zic-r.b (expression of this gene is repressed in the anterior 2 <lb/>rows, which are fated to form the palps) [48]. A similar cofactor-dependent induction circuit <lb/>also drives CPP specification, except in this case Lhx3/4 serves as the cofactor (Fig 4C). Thus, <lb/>by the early neurula stage, FGF-dependent induction has resulted in differential expression of <lb/>lineage-specific TFs (including Zic-r.b or Foxf) in both ANP and CPP lineages (Fig 4B). <lb/>We used the Dmrt enhancer [48] to ectopically express the putative CPP cofactor Lhx3/4 in <lb/>ANP lineage cells at the 64-cell stage. Because the FGF/MapK/Ets1/2.b pathway induces ANP <lb/>lineage gene expression at this stage (Fig 4A), the cofactor-dependent induction model pre-<lb/>dicts that ectopic expression of Lhx3/4 will activate the cardiopharyngeal specification pro-<lb/>gram in ANP progenitors (Fig 4D). We cotransfected embryos with either a Foxf or Hand.r <lb/>reporter construct (FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ or Hand.r&gt;LacZ) to assess activation of the CPP specifica-<lb/>tion program. These constructs contain well-characterized enhancer elements with Ets1/2.b <lb/>and Lhx3/4 binding sites that are required for FGF-dependent reporter activity in the CPP <lb/>lineage (Figs 1C and 4C) [39]. In control samples (FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ or Hand.r&gt;LacZ + <lb/>Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP), reporter activity was almost entirely restricted to CPP lineage cells (Figs 4E, <lb/>4G, 4K, 4O and S4). Strikingly, in experimental samples (+Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4), ectopic reporter <lb/>activity was observed in the ANP of nearly all FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ embryos and in the majority of <lb/>Hand.r&gt;LacZ embryos (arrowheads, Figs 4F, 4G, 4L, 4O and S4). <lb/>Although these results indicate that Lhx3/4 is sufficient for FGF/MapK/Ets-dependent <lb/>induction of CPP genes in the ANP lineage, it is also possible that ectopic Lhx3/4 drives CPP <lb/>gene expression independently of FGF induction. To distinguish between these alternative <lb/>hypotheses, we expressed Lhx3/4 in the ANP lineage while blocking FGF/MapK induction <lb/>using U0126, a well-established inhibitor of the MapK pathway [67,68] As observed in previ-<lb/>ous experiments, misexpression of Lhx3/4 (Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) led to ectopic FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ or <lb/>Hand.r&gt;LacZ reporter activity in the neural plate of DMSO-treated embryos (Fig 4H, 4J, 4L <lb/>and 4O). As predicted by the cofactor-dependent induction model, disruption of the MapK <lb/>pathway completely disrupted FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ activity in both CPPs and neural plate cells <lb/>(Fig 4I and 4J). Disruption of the MapK pathway also consistently and robustly disrupted <lb/>ectopic Hand.r&gt;LacZ activity in the majority of U0126-treated embryos (Fig 4M and 4O). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 4. Misexpression of Lhx3/4 is sufficient for ectopic, FGF-dependent activation of CPP reporters in the anterior neural plate. (A) Illustration of C. <lb/>robusta regulatory circuit for ANP specification. (B) Diagram depicting induction of the ANP and CPP lineages. (C) Illustration of the regulatory circuit for <lb/>CPP specification. (D) Predicted impact of ectopic cofactor misexpression (see text). (E) Representative control embryo displaying Foxf reporter expression in <lb/>the CPP lineage (black arrows). (F) Representative embryo electroporated with FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 displaying ectopic Foxf reporter expression <lb/>in the ANP (black arrowheads). (G) Graphical representation of results from panels E and F showing average levels of Foxf reporter activity in the neural plate <lb/>over 2 trials. Control embryos (7.8%, n = 114), experimental FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 transgenic samples (91.3%, n = 162; p &lt; .0001). Underlying <lb/>data can be found in S1 Appendix. (H) Representative FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ, Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 transgenic embryo treated with DMSO displaying Foxf reporter <lb/>expression in the CPF lineage (black arrows) and neural plate (black arrowhead). (I) Representative embryo electroporated with Foxf&gt;LacZ and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 <lb/>treated with U0126. Note the absence of Foxf reporter expression in both the neural plate and CPPs. (J) Graphical representation of results from panels H and I <lb/>showing average levels of Foxf reporter activity in the neural plate and CPPs over 3 trials. Each condition n = 150. Underlying data can be found in S1 <lb/>Appendix. (K) Representative Dmrt&gt;GFP control embryo treated with DMSO displaying Hand.r reporter expression in the CPP lineage (black arrows). (L) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Intriguingly, although this treatment completely eliminated Hand.r&gt;LacZ reporter activity in <lb/>CPPs, about one-third of treated embryos retained reporter activity in ANP lineage cells <lb/>(Fig 4N and 4O). These results indicate that differences in the regulatory circuits underlying <lb/>CPP expression of Foxf and Hand.r led to differences in their reliance on the FGF/MapK/Ets <lb/>pathway. More broadly, these results indicate that lineage-determining cofactors instruct, <lb/>rather than facilitate, lineage-specific responses to shared signals (see Discussion). <lb/>Ectopic expression of Lhx3/4 disrupts anterior neural plate morphogenesis <lb/>Specification programs often activate morphogenetic modules that dictate the cell behavior of <lb/>newly specified lineages [9,69]. Thus, cofactor-dependent induction of lineage-specific specifi-<lb/>cation programs in response to a shared signal will also lead to differential execution of down-<lb/>stream morphogenetic modules. This logical corollary to the cofactor-dependent induction <lb/>model predicts that ectopic, overlapping expression of 2 cofactors would result in execution of <lb/>2 likely incompatible, morphogenetic modules. We tested this prediction by examining the <lb/>impact of ectopic Lhx3/4 expression (Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) on morphogenesis of Dmrt&gt;LacZ-<lb/>labeled ANP cells. Our model predicts that ectopic expression of Lhx3/4 will activate incom-<lb/>patible ANP and CPP morphogenetic modules and disrupt normal cell behavior (Fig 5A). As <lb/>seen in control embryos, by the mid-tailbud stage, posterior rows of ANP cells that express <lb/>both Dmrt and Zic-r.b invaginate to form the anterior sensory vesicle (ASV) of the central ner-<lb/>vous system, which lies beneath the epidermis (arrowhead, Fig 5B) while anterior rows, in <lb/>which Zic-r.b expression is repressed, form the palps (arrow, Fig 5B). Transgenically labeled <lb/>ANP cells in all control mid-tailbud stage embryos displayed these behaviors (Fig 5B and 5D). <lb/>In contrast, ectopic expression of Lhx3/4 (Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) appeared to block invagination <lb/>(Fig 5C and 5D). Transgenically labeled cells were consistently observed to lie superficial to the <lb/>epidermis, forming a cluster that protruded dorsally (Fig 5C, arrowhead). Additionally, ANP <lb/>lineage cells failed to spread anteriorly to form the palp primordia. These results align with our <lb/>model, indicating that overlapping cofactor expression leads to execution of incompatible <lb/>morphogenetic programs in response to a shared signal. In particular, disruption of ANP mor-<lb/>phogenesis could reflect Lhx3/4-dependent activation of a CPP migration module (Fig 1C). <lb/>Alternatively, overlapping activation of ANP and CPP morphogenetic modules might disrupt <lb/>ANP morphogenesis through misregulation of cell proliferation. To begin testing these <lb/>hypotheses, we examined the impact of Lhx3/4 on ANP morphogenesis in more detail. <lb/>Ectopic Lhx3/4 induces precocious migratory behavior in anterior neural <lb/>plate lineage cells <lb/>To begin assessing whether misexpression of Lhx3/4 disrupted ANP morphogenesis through <lb/>inappropriate activation of a CPP migration module (Fig 1C), we conducted live imaging of <lb/>transgenic embryos in which ANP cells were labeled with GFP (Dmrt&gt;GFP) (Fig 5E and S4 <lb/>and S5 Movies). In initial tailbud stage control embryos (stage 18), Dmrt&gt;GFP-labeled ANP <lb/>cells have formed a well-organized, dorsal neural plate. The anterior half of the ANP is broad <lb/>with a sharp, well-defined border, and it extends to the anteriormost tip of the developing <lb/>Representative Hand.r&gt;LacZ, Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 transgenic embryo treated with DMSO displaying Hand.r reporter expression in the CPP lineage (black arrow) <lb/>and neural plate (black arrowhead). (M, N) Representative embryos electroporated with Hand.r&gt;LacZ and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 after treatment with U0126. Note <lb/>that in the majority of embryos, Hand.r reporter expression is absent in both the ANP or CPP lineages (M) while some embryos retain expression in the ANP <lb/>(N, arrowhead). (O) Graphical representation of results from panels K through N showing average levels of Hand.r reporter activity in the neural plate and <lb/>CPPs over 3 trials. Each condition n = 150. Underlying data can be found in S1 Appendix. Bar and asterisks (***) in G, J, and O indicate p-values of less than <lb/>.0001. ANP, anterior neural plate; CPF, cardiopharyngeal founder; CPP, cardiopharyngeal progenitor; FGF, fibroblast growth factor. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 5. Ectopic Lhx3/4 expression causes abnormal, migratory cell behavior in the neural plate but does not alter cell numbers. (A) Predicted <lb/>activation of incompatible morphogenetic modules due to ectopic expression of the CPP lineage-determining factor Lhx3/4. (B) Representative control <lb/>embryo in which Dmrt&gt;LacZ-positive ANP cells are observed in the palps (arrow) and invaginated cells of the developing ASV. Note that ASV cells are <lb/>at this stage covered by a layer of unstained epidermis (arrowhead). (C) Representative early tailbud embryo electroporated with Dmrt&gt;LacZ and <lb/>Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4. Note that Dmrt&gt;LacZ-positive cells protrude from the anterior dorsal trunk and are not covered by epidermis (arrowhead). Staining is <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>embryo (arrow, Fig 5Ei). The posterior half of the ANP has invaginated beneath the epidermis <lb/>(Fig 5B, 5Ei and 5F) and bilateral cell columns extend from the posterior end. By the late tail-<lb/>bud stage (stage 22), the ANP has begun to narrow and distal cells begin to form dense pla-<lb/>codes that will give rise to the palps (arrow, Fig 5Eii). Labeled ANP cells are well organized in <lb/>regular rows with a sharp border and no visible protrusions. A pair of large cells that resemble <lb/>migratory Eminens-like neurons (recently described in [70]; arrowheads, Fig 5Ei) begin to <lb/>emerge from the posterior portion of the developing ASV (Fig 5Eii, arrowhead). The bilateral <lb/>posterior columns have merged to form a single, well-organized narrow band. In early larvae <lb/>(stage 25), the Dmrt&gt;GFP-labeled cells in the ANP continue to neurulate, converging to form <lb/>a narrow, medial tube. At the anterior tip, palp primordia begin to protrude and differentiate <lb/>(Fig 5Eiii, arrow). In the posterior region, presumed Eminens-like neurons complete their pre-<lb/>viously characterized migratory path to form a ring around the developing sensory vesicle <lb/>(Fig 5Eiii, arrowhead and S4 Movie). <lb/>As observed in the fixed samples, ectopic expression of Lhx3/4 (Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) severely dis-<lb/>rupts neural plate morphogenesis (Fig 5Eiv-vi). Summary illustrations comparing typical ANP <lb/>morphology in control and experimental samples are provided in Fig 5F. By the initial tailbud <lb/>stage (stage 18), Dmrt&gt;GFP-labeled ANP cells are already noticeably disorganized. The ANP <lb/>lacks discernable rows, and the border is poorly defined. Additionally, the neural plate fails to <lb/>extend to the distal palp region, and posterior bilateral columns are also not observed <lb/>(Fig 5Eiv). As embryos proceed through late tailbud and early larval stages (stages 22 and 25), <lb/>the ANP fails to invaginate and narrow (Fig 5Ev and 5Evi). There is also no sign of palp pla-<lb/>code formation or morphogenesis (arrow, Fig 5Eii). In the posterior region, presumed Emi-<lb/>nens-like neurons fail to form a ring around the developing sensory vesicle (Fig 5Eiii, <lb/>arrowhead, and S6 Movie). Notably, throughout the observed stages, ANP cells appear to be <lb/>highly dynamic, extending outside of the neural plate border and exhibiting signs of irregular <lb/>protrusive activity (arrowheads, Fig 5Ev and S6-S8 Movies). Some cells appear to exhibit aber-<lb/>rant migration, and in one instance, a cell is seen to migrate from the right to the left side of <lb/>the ANP cluster (S6 Movie). This increased protrusive activity, and aberrant migratory cell <lb/>behaviors observed in the experimental samples suggest that misexpression of Lhx3/4 drives <lb/>inappropriate activation of a CPP migration module in the ANP lineage. <lb/>Ectopic Lhx3/4 does not increase proliferation in the anterior neural plate <lb/>To determine whether ectopic Lhx3/4 might also disrupt ANP morphogenesis by altering cell <lb/>proliferation, we quantified Dmrt&gt;GFP-labeled cells in control and experimental samples <lb/>(+Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) fixed at early neurula (stage 14; Fig 5G and 5I) or at late larvae (24 HPF; <lb/>Fig 5H and 5J). Interestingly, Lhx3/4 had no discernible impact on ANP cell number or neural <lb/>plate morphology in early neurula stage embryos (Fig 5I and 5K). Similar numbers of <lb/>Dmrt&gt;GFP labeled cells were arranged in a stereotypical grid at the dorsal anterior of the <lb/>embryo across all samples. Thus, Lhx3/4-dependent disruption of ANP morphogenesis begins <lb/>also absent from the anterior tip of the embryo (arrow) where the palps normally develop. (D) Graph of average percent of early tailbud embryos <lb/>displaying neural plate defects across 2 trials; controls (n = 200, 0%) and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 samples (n = 200, 69%). Underlying data can be found in S1 <lb/>Appendix. (E, F) Effect of Lhx3/4 on neural plate morphogenesis. Stages indicated above each image or illustration column. (E) Still images taken from <lb/>representative movies of control (i-iii; S4 Movie) and experimental Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 embryos (iv-vi; S6 Movie). See text for details. (F) Schematics <lb/>illustrating phenotypes shown in the previous panel. D = dorsal view, L = lateral view. (G-K) Effect of Lhx3/4 on cell division. Representative neurulae <lb/>(G, I) and larvae (H, J) expressing transgenes as indicated on the left. Transgenic GFP expression domain shown in magenta and DAPI-labeled nuclei in <lb/>cyan. (K) Quantification of GFP-positive (GFP+) cells from experiments represented in panels G, I (left plot) and panels H, J (right plot). Two trials, <lb/>control neurulae n = 9 (avg. 27.6 GFP+ cells), Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 neurulae, n = 9 (avg. 26.8 GFP+ cells), control larvae n = 5 (avg. 170.8 GFP+ cells), <lb/>Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 larvae n = 6 (avg. 178.5 GFP+ cells). Underlying data can be found in S1 Appendix. ANP, anterior neural plate; ASV, anterior sensory <lb/>vesicle; CPP, cardiopharyngeal progenitor. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>in the 2-hour window between stage 14 and stage 18, when abnormal morphogenesis was <lb/>observed in our live imaging studies. In line with our previous results, Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 larvae <lb/>displayed severe developmental defects including an extruded dorsal ANP cluster (arrowhead, <lb/>Fig 5J, compare to Fig 5H) and lack of ANP extension into the anterior, distal palp region <lb/>(arrows, Fig 5J). Interestingly, we also observed that pigmentation associated with pigment cell <lb/>sensory structures in the cerebral vesicle [71,72] were absent in Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 larvae (Fig 5J). <lb/>Thus, Lhx3/4 expression appears to impact some aspects of ANP subspecification. However, <lb/>these defects were not accompanied by any detectable, consistent shift in cell numbers <lb/>(Fig 5K). Taken together, these results suggest that Lhx3/4-dependent impacts on cell prolifer-<lb/>ation do not contribute to abnormal ANP morphogenesis. <lb/>Evaluating the impact of ectopic Lhx3/4 on gene expression in anterior <lb/>neural plate cells <lb/>To more rigorously assess the impact of ectopic Lhx3/4 on ANP gene expression and evaluate <lb/>alternative hypotheses regarding the regulatory circuits underlying cofactor-dependent induc-<lb/>tion, we conducted comparative RNA-sequencing analysis. To accomplish this, Dmrt&gt;GFP-<lb/>labeled ANP lineage cells were collected by FACS from dissociated control embryos or experi-<lb/>mental embryos coelectroporated with Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 (Fig 6A). For each condition, triplicate <lb/>samples were used to generate mRNA libraries for sequencing. Triplicate control or experi-<lb/>mental samples clustered together, and intergroup sample similarity was greater than between <lb/>groups (Fig 6B). To begin assessing the impact of ectopic Lhx3/4 on ANP gene expression, we <lb/>first focused on genes that displayed significant (adjusted p-value of &lt; .05) and robust changes <lb/>in expression (fold change greater than or equal to 1.5, threshold log2 +/-0.58; Fig 6C). <lb/>Through this analysis, we distinguished 567 up-regulated genes and 865 down-regulated genes <lb/>relative to the control group (Fig 6C). To highlight changes in the ANP regulatory program, <lb/>we conducted a similar analysis focused solely on annotated TFs (Fig 6D) [62]. As expected, <lb/>these cells displayed robust enrichment of Lhx3/4 expression. In line with our previous data, <lb/>Lhx3/4 misexpression led to significant and robust up-regulation of some primary targets of <lb/>FGF-dependent induction in the CPP lineage including Foxf, Hand.r, and Irxb (homologs to <lb/>human FOXF2, HAND2, and IRX6, respectively) [39]. However, expression of many charac-<lb/>terized primary CPP targets were either not impacted (Irxa, Soxh, and Gsc) or down-regulated <lb/>(Elk1, Foxp, and SoxC). Foxf is considered to be a key regulator of subsequent CCP specifica-<lb/>tion and morphogenesis [37,40,73]. To investigate whether ectopic activation of Foxf was suffi-<lb/>cient for activation of downstream target genes, we examined the expression of 26 <lb/>characterized Foxf targets, as delineated through prior ATAC-seq and loss of function studies <lb/>(S2 Appendix) [74]. Strikingly, the expression of a majority of these characterized targets <lb/>(including RhoDF, Gata.a, Ddr, SLC17A5, TSPAN4/9, TMEM150A, and Fzd10/9) were not sig-<lb/>nificantly impacted by this manipulation, and only 3 were up-regulated. Thus, while ectopic <lb/>Lhx3/4 is sufficient for partial activation of the primary cardiopharyngeal program in ANP <lb/>cells, further execution of this program was severely abbreviated. Additionally, we observed <lb/>that some of the most highly up-regulated TFs are associated with MG patterning, including <lb/>Vsx, Nkx6, Islet, and Pax6 [75,76]. Previous studies have demonstrated that Lhx3/4 is expressed <lb/>in a subset of MG interneuron and motoneuron precursors in C. robusta [61,76] and contrib-<lb/>utes to MG patterning in DrosophilaAU : Pleasenotethatgenus}Drosophila}hasbeenaddedto}D:melano <lb/>melanogaster and vertebrate embryos [77-79]. Thus, it <lb/>appears that misexpression of Lhx3/4 was able to activate MG programs ectopically in the <lb/>ANP lineage, potentially disrupting execution of both ANP and CPP programs. MG and ANP <lb/>precursors originate in the neuroectoderm. Thus, MG patterning programs may be more <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 6. Comparative RNA-seq analysis delineates the impact of ectopic Lhx3/4 on ANP gene expression. (A) Diagram of the experimental setup. <lb/>(B) Sample-to-sample distance matrix. C1-C3 and X1-X3 refer to the 3 control and 3 experimental samples, respectively. (C-H) Volcano plots of <lb/>differentially expressed genes. Red indicates down-regulated genes; blue indicates up-regulated genes. Y-axes: -log10(Adjusted p-value), X-axes: Log2 <lb/>(fold change: ectopic Lhx3/4 ANP vs. control). Superimposed tables list top up-or down-regulated genes and include the reported human homologs <lb/>of each C. robusta gene [57]. Note that &quot;KY21.Chr&quot; is not included but applicable to all gene ID numbers listed in the middle columns of all tables. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>amenable to ectopic activation in the ANP in comparison to cardiopharyngeal specification <lb/>programs that are executed in mesendodermal lineage cells. <lb/>Along with assessing the potential for Lhx3/4 misexpression to ectopically activate non-<lb/>ANP regulatory circuits, we also attempted to analyze the impact on ANP specification and <lb/>morphogenetic programs. This involved plotting the top 1,000 most highly expressed genes <lb/>from the control, wild-type ANP dataset (Fig 6E and S2 Appendix). This analysis indicated <lb/>that Lhx3/4 misexpression has a largely negative impact on ANP gene expression, significantly <lb/>and robustly down-regulating 109 ANP genes versus only 10 that were up-regulated (Fig 6E). <lb/>Furthermore, several of the top 10 most down-regulated genes have characterized roles in reg-<lb/>ulating ANP specification, including Onecut (KY21.Chr6.231) and Six3/6 (KY21.Chr 10.262) <lb/>or represent key downstream target genes such as Tyrp-1 (KY21.Chr 5.389) [48,83,84]. Expres-<lb/>sion of a number of other characterized ANP transcription and signaling factors were also sig-<lb/>nificantly down-regulated including TCF/Lef (KY21.Chr6.59), Gsx (KY21.Chr2.996), <lb/>Neurogenin (KY21.Chr6.434), and Pou4f (KY21.Chr2.456) [48,62,85,86]. Thus, it appears that <lb/>Lhx3/4 misexpression suppresses execution of ANP specification and morphogenetic <lb/>programs. <lb/>To better understand how Lhx3/4 misexpression disrupted ANP morphogenesis (Fig 5), we <lb/>also analyzed the expression of genes with potential roles in neural tube closure, actin dynam-<lb/>ics, adhesion, cell polarity, and other morphogenetic processes. In line with the observed <lb/>impact of Lhx3/4 misexpression on neural tube invagination (Fig 5E and 5F), 10 of 61 genes <lb/>with characterized roles in neural tube closure [80] were robustly and significantly down-regu-<lb/>lated, while only one was up-regulated (Fig 6F). To explore other aberrant behaviors exhibited <lb/>by Lhx3/4-expressing ANP lineage cells, we also analyzed the expression of genes that might <lb/>contribute to cell adhesion or migration (Fig 6G). This included a list of 53 C. robusta ortho-<lb/>logs to genes involved in cell polarity or actin dynamics [82], as well as a comprehensive set of <lb/>57 annotated orthologs to cadherin, protocadherin, laminin, and claudin genes ([81]; S2 <lb/>Appendix). In line with the observed impact of Lhx3/4 misexpression on the organization and <lb/>coherence of the neural plate (Fig 5F), we detected down-regulation of genes that may encode <lb/>proteins that contribute to epithelial adhesion and organization, including orthologs to Cad-<lb/>herin18, a protocadherin, a laminin, and Prickle2, a key planar cell polarity protein (Fig 6G). <lb/>As mentioned above, it does not appear that Lhx3/4 misexpression was sufficient to drive <lb/>full execution of the CPP specification program and downstream expression of Foxf target <lb/>genes involved in CPP migration, such as RhoD/F. To further explore ectopic CPP gene <lb/>expression, we extracted the gene expression profile of mid-tailbud stage CPPs from a single-<lb/>cell embryonic database of C. robusta gene expression [70]. We chose this stage because it rep-<lb/>resents CPP gene expression 4 hours after the initial FGF-dependent induction, mirroring the <lb/>4-hour interval between Lhx3/4 misexpression/FGF induction in the ANP and the RNA <lb/>sequencing time point in our comparative analysis. Additionally, we reasoned that CPPs have <lb/>begun their ventral migration at this time point (Fig 1D) and likely express genes involved in <lb/>this behavior. We calculated the average normalized read count (0.44) for genes expressed in <lb/>Shaded-out hits indicate ambiguous representation. Underlying data can be found in S2 Appendix. (C) Plot of all genes. The top 10 up-and down-<lb/>regulated genes are highlighted. (D) Plot of annotated C. robusta TF genes [57,62]. The top 10 up-and down-regulated genes are highlighted. Bolded <lb/>text highlights genes with characterized roles in cardiopharyngeal development. (E) Plot of the top 1,000 highest-expressed control sample (ANP-<lb/>lineage) genes. (F) Plot of neural tube closure genes (as characterized in [80]). Table lists all up-and down-regulated genes. (G) Plotted collection of <lb/>putative migration and cellular adhesion genes [81,82]. Table lists all up-and down-regulated genes. Genes with potential roles in cellular adhesion <lb/>displayed in blue, actin dynamics in red, cell polarity in yellow, and extracellular matrix in black. (H) Plot of genes expressed at above average levels <lb/>in the CPP lineage at stage 21 (mid-tailbud), as characterized through extensive, stage-specific single-cell RNA-sequencing [70]. The top 10 down-<lb/>regulated genes and the top 30 up-regulated genes are highlighted. Bolded text highlights genes with characterized roles in migratory behavior. ANP, <lb/>anterior neural plate; CPP, cardiopharyngeal progenitor; TF, transcription factor. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>the CPP lineage during the mid-tailbud stage (stage 21; [70]) and evaluated the impact of <lb/>ectopic Lhx3/4 on their expression levels in the ANP (Fig 6H and S2 Appendix). Strikingly, the <lb/>majority of impacted CPP genes, 83 in total, were down-regulated, further supporting abbrevi-<lb/>ated execution of the CPP program. However, this analysis did reveal 53 up-regulated CPP <lb/>genes including several orthologs to genes that have characterized roles in migratory behavior, <lb/>including FHOD3 [87], GLIPR2 [88], PLEC [89], and CTNNAL1 [90] (bold lettering, Fig 6H). <lb/>Additionally, orthologs to some of the genes that were most highly up-regulated by Lhx3/4 <lb/>misexpression are also involved in cell migration (Fig 6C). For instance, the most highly up-<lb/>regulated gene in this dataset is orthologous to EPHA3, an Ephrin receptor with documented <lb/>roles in cardiac cell migration and in the de-adhesion of epithelial cells [91,92]. Furthermore, <lb/>the second most highly up-regulated gene, THSD7A, has a role in actin cytoskeleton rearrange-<lb/>ment and can induce filopodial extensions [93,94]. Thus, up-regulation of these CPP and non-<lb/>CPP genes might contribute to the aberrant migratory behaviors observed in Lhx3/4-express-<lb/>ing ANP cells. <lb/>Collectively, comparative RNA sequencing analysis of Lhx3/4-expressing ANP cells <lb/>revealed severe disruption of the native ANP program along with partial, highly abbreviated <lb/>execution of the CPP specification program. While these results support the cofactor-depen-<lb/>dent induction model, they do not indicate that lineage-determining factors function as &quot;mas-<lb/>ter-regulators&quot; of differential induction downstream of a shared signal. Instead, these factors <lb/>appear to participate as key players in complex, cascading circuits that dictate lineage-specific <lb/>responses. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>A dual role for Lhx3/4 in cardiopharyngeal progenitor specification <lb/>Previous studies have shown that CPP cells are specified through the combined activity of <lb/>FGF-activated Ets1/2.b and an inferred ATTA-binding transcriptional cofactor. Here, our loss <lb/>and gain of function data strongly support the hypothesis that Lhx3/4 serves as this cofactor. <lb/>Interestingly, this represents a second role for Lhx3/4 in CPP specification, as it also contrib-<lb/>utes to founder cell specification earlier in development (Fig 1A). The resulting CPP specifica-<lb/>tion circuit (Fig 3E) resembles an extended coherent feed-forward loop (FFL) [5]. In a typical <lb/>FFL, a primary TF (A) participates in direct regulation of a target gene (C) while also partici-<lb/>pating in indirect regulation through a transcriptional cascade whereby (A) also activates a sec-<lb/>ondary TF (B), which coactivates the target gene (C). If all of the interactions are positive, then <lb/>the FFL is considered to be a Type 1 Coherent FFL (C1-FFL) and serves to generate a &quot;sign-<lb/>sensitive delay.&quot; During CPP specification, Lhx3/4 acts in a similar manner to the primary TF <lb/>in a coherent type 1 FFL, activating target genes directly and indirectly through a transcrip-<lb/>tional cascade (Fig 3E). However, in this case, the transcriptional cascade is more complex, as <lb/>it involves 2 separated cascading steps (A activates B1, B1 activates B2, then A and B2 activates <lb/>C). Network motifs are largely derived from studies of single-celled organisms, and it was pre-<lb/>dicted that these motifs would be more complicated and extended in developmental GRNs for <lb/>multicellular organisms [5]. Studies of these more elaborate extended or interlinked motifs <lb/>remain limited, and the functions of such motifs have not been well characterized [95]. This <lb/>extended FFL may generate a sign-sensitive delay, but further testing will be required to exam-<lb/>ine potential impacts of this motif on regulatory dynamics. Functionally, this extended cascade <lb/>links autonomous specification (Fig 1A) to non-autonomous, signal-dependent subspecifica-<lb/>tion (Fig 1C). It will be interesting to investigate how often similar motifs are deployed in <lb/>developmental GRNs and whether this represents a recurring topological feature, leveraging <lb/>persistent expression of a lineage-determining TF to drive initial signal-independent <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>specification along with subsequent signal-dependent subspecification. It will also be critical to <lb/>further assess the exact contributions of Ets1/2.b and Lhx3/4 in cardiopharyngeal specification <lb/>and to determine whether these 2 factors directly interact or function in a cooperative or semi-<lb/>independent manner. Additionally, it will be interesting to examine whether Lhx3/4 (or other <lb/>members of this gene family) play similar roles during vertebrate cardiopharyngeal specifica-<lb/>tion. Although previous studies suggest that Lhx2 participates in cardiac and craniofacial <lb/>development in mouse embryos [96], further studies will be needed to assess potential evolu-<lb/>tionary implications regarding cardiopharyngeal development within the shared tunicate/ver-<lb/>tebrate ancestor. <lb/>Cofactor-dependent induction as a novel gene regulatory network <lb/>subcircuit <lb/>Current reviews propose that a limited suite of subcircuit topologies capture the key regulatory <lb/>logic of cascading gene regulation during development [8,13,14,20,21]. However, the existing <lb/>slate of theoretical GRN subcircuits do not encompass the regulatory logic entailed by cofac-<lb/>tor-dependent inductive signaling. To illustrate this, we have adopted diagrams previously <lb/>deployed to depict the range of subcircuits observed in the well-characterized sea urchin devel-<lb/>opmental GRN [22]. According to these diagrams, inductive signaling entails a subcircuit in <lb/>which gene expression is activated when both a signal Z (FGF), and the associated signal-<lb/>dependent TF Y (Ets) are present (Fig 7A). However, according to this subcircuit, the same sig-<lb/>nal would always lead to the same transcriptional response. In order to explain signal specific-<lb/>ity, we have combined this inductive signaling subcircuit with the previously posited &quot;AND <lb/>logic&quot; subcircuit in which 2 TFs (W and X) coregulate gene expression (Fig 7B; [22]). The <lb/>resulting &quot;cofactor-dependent induction&quot; subcircuit (Fig 7C) illustrates the key role of lineage-<lb/>determining cofactors (X) in spatially restricting gene activation in response to widespread <lb/>expression of signals and associated signal-dependent TFs (Y+Z). This model also illustrates <lb/>how expression of multiple, spatially distinct cofactors (X 1 -X 4 ) mediates differential, lineage-<lb/>specific expression (colored boxes) in response to a shared signal (Fig 7D). As highlighted in <lb/>this study, C. robusta provides a valuable experimental platform for investigating how wide-<lb/>spread use of a shared signaling pathway (FGF/MapK/Ets) is translated into lineage-specific <lb/>gene expression through the deployment of spatially restricted cofactors (Figs 1G and 7D). <lb/>Inclusion of the cofactor-dependent induction subcircuit will be essential for productive <lb/>integration of many key signaling pathways into theoretical models of regulatory networks. In <lb/>recent overviews, 2 subcircuit categories center on signaling, community effect, and toggle <lb/>switch subcircuits [13,14]. Community effect subcircuits involve signal-dependent feedback <lb/>loops that can generate a broad, regional transcriptional response to a spatially or temporally <lb/>restricted initiating signal. Toggle switches serve to explain the regulatory logic underlying a <lb/>subset of widely deployed developmental signaling pathways including Wnt, Notch, and <lb/>Hedgehog. In these 3 signaling pathways, signal-dependent TFs act as repressors until they are <lb/>converted to activators by receipt of the appropriate signal. Neither of these categories encom-<lb/>pass the logic underlying differential, lineage-specific responses to the other 7 major families <lb/>of highly pleiotropic developmental signals (TGF-ß, RTK, JAK-STAT, Hippo, Nuclear Recep-<lb/>tor, NFK-ß, and JNK). In these 7 pathways, signal-dependent TFs do not function as default <lb/>repressors. Rather, signal-dependent alteration of the localization or function of corresponding <lb/>TFs can either promote or suppress gene expression in a context-dependent manner. The logic <lb/>underlying transcriptional regulation by these 7 major signaling pathways is captured by cofac-<lb/>tor-dependent induction subcircuit (Fig 7C). Thus, integration of this subcircuit category will <lb/>help to rectify inaccurate representation of signal-dependent regulatory logic in current <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 7. Theoretical implications of cofactor-dependent induction. (A-C) Subcircuit diagrams in which left hand boxes represent spatial domains for each <lb/>contributing factor along with conditions that allow activation of each circuit, right hand boxes portray regulatory states, while gray lines and arrows <lb/>indicate absence or inactivity of a particular factor. (D) Illustrations of spatially distinct outputs (color scheme from Fig 1G) due to differential expression <lb/>of LD factors in accordance with the cofactor-dependent induction subcircuit (C). (E, F) Circuit diagrams illustrating 2 different models for the role of LD <lb/>cofactors in signal-dependent transcription (see text). (G) Schematic illustrating the potential impact of LD factor binding site mutations on signal-<lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>theoretical models. For example, signal-dependent TFs, including Ets family members, are <lb/>often included in regulatory circuits without inclusion of the upstream signal mediating their <lb/>activity or consideration of the logic mediating lineage-specific outputs [1,10,13,14,97-102]. <lb/>Potential roles for lineage-specific cofactors in signal-dependent <lb/>transcription <lb/>Our identification of Lhx3/4 as the lineage-determining factor for CPP specification extends <lb/>the list of characterized partners mediating lineage-specific response to FGF, as illustrated in <lb/>Fig 1G. In looking over this list, it becomes apparent that a simple model in which a single line-<lb/>age-determining partner dictates differential, signal-dependent transcription is incomplete. In <lb/>particular, some of these partners are in the same gene family. For example, the presumptive <lb/>lineage-determining partners for CPP and ANP progenitors, Lhx3/4 and Dlx.b, are both <lb/>homeobox-family factors and would thus bind the same core nucleotides (ATTA). Therefore, <lb/>it is not clear how enhancers would encode differential transcriptional responses to Ets1/2.b <lb/>and Lhx3/4 in versus Ets1/2.b and Dlx.b. One straightforward way to bypass this issue is to <lb/>invoke the role of lineage-specific cofactors that also bind to signal-dependent regulatory ele-<lb/>ments (Fig 7E and 7F). These could either be lineage-specific repressors (Fig 7E, LSR) or line-<lb/>age-specific coactivators (Fig 7F, LSA). Future studies will focus on characterizing these <lb/>presumptive lineage-specific cofactors and their respective binding sites through informatic <lb/>and wet-bench analysis of FGF-dependent regulatory elements in C. robusta. <lb/>A primary, instructive role for lineage-determining factors in signal-<lb/>dependent transcription <lb/>Current models of signal-dependent transcription do not indicate whether lineage-determin-<lb/>ing factors instruct or facilitate lineage-specific responses to pleiotropic signals <lb/>[22,23,103,104]. The precise contribution of lineage-determining factors may be determined <lb/>by their interactions with additional cofactors. For example, lineage-determining factors could <lb/>instruct signal-dependent transcription by blocking a lineage-specific repressor (Fig 7E). Alter-<lb/>natively, lineage-determining factors could form a complex with one or more lineage-specific <lb/>co-activators, facilitating signal-dependent transcription only when other members of the <lb/>complex were available (Fig 7F). Based on this hypothetical framework, our results strongly <lb/>suggest that lineage-determining factors play a primary, instructive role in signal-dependent <lb/>transcription by blocking repressor activity (Fig 7E). In particular, we have shown that ectopic <lb/>expression of Lhx3/4 is sufficient for activation of CPP gene expression in the ANP (Figs 4E-<lb/>4O, 6D and S4) as predicted by the &quot;lineage-specific repressor&quot; model (Fig 7E). The contribu-<lb/>tion of lineage specific repressors also serves to explain why ectopic CPP reporter expression <lb/>extends into all 4 rows of the ANP including the anterior rows in which FGF-dependent <lb/>expression of non-palp ANP genes are usually suppressed (Fig 4F and 4L). In particular, these <lb/>dependent expression of a hypothetical cardiopharyngeal progenitor lineage gene (CPP1, green) and neuroectodermal gene (NE1, blue). (H) Schematic <lb/>illustrating the role of LD factors (X 1 , X 2 ) in spatially restricted activation of specification modules (S 1 , S 2 ) along with downstream morphogenetic <lb/>modules (C 1 , C 2 ) and differentiation gene batteries (D 1 , D 2 ). Colors in accordance with Fig 1G. Note that these cartoons include 2 characterized, distinct <lb/>notochord domains, primary notochord (orange) and secondary distal notochord (dark orange). (I) Schematic illustrating the hypothesized impact that <lb/>overlapping expression of LD factors would have on morphogenetic programs. Cartoon tailbud depicts resulting nonviable phenotype. (J) Schematic <lb/>illustrating hypothetical scenarios by which misexpression of LD factors might lead to selectively advantageous phenotypes. Top: primary notochord <lb/>cofactor domain expansion generates more notochord cells or CPP cofactor domain restriction generates reduced cardiopharyngeal cells; center: the loss <lb/>of a primary notochord cofactor results in a shortened tail, note that the distal secondary notochord (dark orange) is known to be independently specified; <lb/>bottom: extended expression of the CPP cofactor in place of the primary notochord cofactor reallocates primary notochord lineage cells to increase the <lb/>numbers of CPPs. CPP, cardiopharyngeal progenitor; LD, lineage-determining; LSA, lineage-specific coactivator; LSR, lineage-specific repressor; TF, <lb/>transcription factor. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169.g007 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>results suggest that CPP regulatory elements do not contain binding sites for repressors that <lb/>modulate ANP expression in the palps. Further studies will be required to explore the role of <lb/>presumptive lineage-specific repressors or cofactors and generate a precise model for the geno-<lb/>mic encoding of signal-dependent transcription. <lb/>Capabilities and limitations of lineage-determining transcription factors <lb/>Our data indicate that the roles of lineage-determining cofactors in inductive circuits may vary <lb/>for different target genes. In particular, we found that misexpression of the CPP lineage-deter-<lb/>mining factor (Lhx3/4) drove ectopic expression of one CPP target gene (Foxf) in a purely <lb/>FGF/MapK-dependent fashion while another target gene (Hand.r) displayed ectopic expres-<lb/>sion independent of FGF/MapK signaling (Fig 4). While the response of to this manipula-<lb/>tion can be explained by invoking lineage-specific repressors (Fig 7E), the response of Hand.r <lb/>appears to reflect an alternative regulatory logic in which high levels of cofactor expression <lb/>(transgene-driven Lhx3/4) may overcome the need for a signal-dependent input. <lb/>Our data also highlight a key role for the regulatory landscape in modulating the impact of <lb/>cofactor-dependent inductive circuits on downstream specification and morphogenetic pro-<lb/>grams. Based on our model, we predicted that ectopic expression of the CPP lineage-determin-<lb/>ing factor (Lhx3/4) would be sufficient to launch the CPP specification program along with <lb/>downstream morphogenetic modules. We assumed that simultaneous execution of the native <lb/>ANP program led to incompatible gene expression patterns that drove observed aberrations in <lb/>ANP cell behaviors. However, our RNA-sequencing results did not align with this interpreta-<lb/>tion. Instead, these results indicated that ectopic execution of the CPP regulatory cascade was <lb/>highly abbreviated, failing to fully extend beyond the expression of a subset of primary target <lb/>genes (Fig 6H). These data also indicated that the native ANP regulatory cascade was severely <lb/>disrupted leading to down-regulated expression of many key ANP TFs and downstream mor-<lb/>phogenetic genes (Fig 6E and 6F). Intriguingly, it also appears that Lhx3/4 misexpression <lb/>drove ectopic activation of a MG patterning program, as reflected by robust up-regulation for <lb/>a subset of TFs associated with this lineage. Thus, it appears that the capacity for lineage-deter-<lb/>mining factors to dictate lineage-specific inductive cascades is limited and context dependent. <lb/>Although misexpression of a cofactor can launch an ectopic inductive program, further execu-<lb/>tion is likely constrained by the preexisting regulatory state of the target lineage. Further stud-<lb/>ies will be required to delineate how execution of conflicting inductive programs play out in <lb/>different linages and at different time points in development. <lb/>Implications of cofactor-dependent induction for disease states and <lb/>evolution <lb/>Fully characterizing the regulatory logic underlying signal-dependent transcription will be <lb/>critical for understanding and predicting the roles of nucleotide polymorphisms in disease <lb/>ontogeny and evolutionary diversification. The regulatory elements encoding differential <lb/>responses to highly pleiotropic signals may be particularly vulnerable to erroneous execution <lb/>of specification or morphogenetic programs. This hypothesis is supported by previous studies <lb/>regarding the use of suboptimal Ets binding sites in C. robusta regulatory elements encoding <lb/>responses to FGF-dependent induction [105-107]. In these studies, optimization of Ets bind-<lb/>ing sites in anterior neural or cardiopharyngeal lineage enhancers was sufficient for wide-<lb/>spread misexpression in other lineages undergoing FGF-dependent specification. Thus, it is <lb/>likely that single nucleotide polymorphisms in other signal-dependent TF binding sites or in <lb/>binding sites for lineage-determining cofactors could alter gene expression, thereby <lb/>compromising developmental or physiological genetic programs. For example, 2 base pair <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>mutations could convert core binding motifs for the characterized neuroectodermal (NE) line-<lb/>age-determining factor (GATA) in a C. robusta NE enhancer into core binding motifs for the <lb/>cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant Lhx3/4 (ATTA; Fig 7G). According to our current <lb/>model (Fig 7E), this change would be sufficient to drive ectopic cardiopharyngeal expression <lb/>(as illustrated in Fig 7G) assuming that NE enhancers lack binding sites for cardiopharyngeal <lb/>lineage repressors (Fig 7E). A similar logic applies to potential misexpression of lineage-deter-<lb/>mining factors. As mentioned above, our Lhx3/4 misexpression results (Figs 4 and 6) indicate <lb/>that lineage-determining factors play a primary, instructive role in differential execution of <lb/>specification programs in response to widespread signals. According to current models, the <lb/>resulting execution of lineage-specific specification programs lead to downstream execution of <lb/>lineage-specific morphogenetic and differentiation modules (Fig 7E and 7H). Thus, polymor-<lb/>phisms that result in overlapping expression of lineage-determining factors (Fig 7G) may <lb/>result in execution of incompatible morphogenetic programs and contribute to the onset of <lb/>inappropriate cell behaviors associated with congenital defects or disease (Fig 7I). From an <lb/>evolutionary perspective, cofactor-dependent induction may represent a highly versatile GRN <lb/>subcircuit subject to modifications that could result in selectively advantageous phenotypic <lb/>changes. For instance, shifts in the expression domain of a lineage-determining factor could <lb/>drive trait diversification through reduction, loss, or reallocation of a cell lineage (Fig 7J). <lb/>Comparative analysis between the developmental GRNs in C. robusta and other diverse tuni-<lb/>cates represent a potent framework for investigating whether these hypothesized regulatory <lb/>shifts in cofactor-dependent induction subcircuits have contributed to trait loss, such as the <lb/>loss of cardiopharyngeal structures in larvaceans [108-110] or trait diversification, as exhibited <lb/>within highly divergent pelagic tunicate taxa [111]. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Molecular cloning <lb/>Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP was previously described in [35]. U6&gt;sgRNA(F+E) and Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls <lb/>were generously provided by Lionel Christiaen [56]. Targeting U6&gt;sgRNA plasmids were cre-<lb/>ated by ligating annealed, phosphorylated oligo pairs into a BsaI-digested, empty U6&gt;sgRNA <lb/>(F+E) vector (S1 Table). FoxfΔepi&gt;LacZ was created by fusing together 2 sections of DNA <lb/>upstream of the Foxf gene. This approximately 200 bp deletion eliminates expression in the <lb/>epidermis [39]. The first fragment spanned from 1,238 bp to 857 bp upstream of the Foxf TSS <lb/>and was amplified using the 5 0 oligo GAATGTGGTGTTATACTT and 3 0 oligo <lb/>CTCTCCAACGCGATCCAT. The second fragment spanned from 648 bp upstream of the <lb/>TSS to 360 bp downstream of the TSS using the 5 0 oligo CGAGTCGTAAAGCTTGCCG and <lb/>3 0 oligo GCCTGATGTAATCTGTCTGC. This second fragment includes the Foxf 5 0 UTR and <lb/>the first 99 amino acids of the Foxf coding sequence, which was fused in frame with LacZ. <lb/>Hand.r&gt;LacZ was described in [39] (Hand-like -1972-1793:296:lacZ). Dmrt&gt;LacZ and <lb/>Dmrt&gt;GFP were generated as in [48]. Dmrt cis-regulatory DNA was amplified with the 5 0 <lb/>oligo TCAGAACGAGGCGCTACATG and 3 0 oligo TCACTGTTCTAAGCAAGGTATC <lb/>AAGG [48]. Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 was generated by amplifying full length Lhx3/4 (KY21.Chr13.457. <lb/>v1.ND1-1) from mixed stage embryo cDNA using the 5 0 oligo ATGATTCTCGATACTAAG <lb/>GCGC and 3 0 oligo CCACGTGACACATTTCCAA. This fragment was subcloned into the <lb/>Dmrt&gt;GFP vector after restriction digest removal of the GFP sequence. The sgLhx3/4-pro-<lb/>tected rescue construct (Mesp&gt;Lhx3/4 rescue ) was created by removing H2B::GFP from our <lb/>Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP construct and inserting the full length Lhx3/4 (KY21.Chr13.457.v1.ND1-1) <lb/>sequence. This construct (Mesp&gt;Lhx3/4) was then amplified with the oligos agcagttag-<lb/>gaactggggacgtaggtCAATTCTATTTGCTGGATG and <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>cactacaatcgtcatctacatattgCATGAAACATCTGAAGCATTC (bold underlined nucleotides <lb/>highlight induced mutations that do not affect translated amino acid sequence). AboutAU : Pleasenoteth <lb/>1.0 μL <lb/>of PCR product was used with the NEB Kinase-Ligase-DpnI enzyme mix (M0554S) per manu-<lb/>facturer&apos;s instructions. The resulting clones were screened via Sanger sequencing for presence <lb/>of desired mutations. <lb/>Electroporations <lb/>Gravid C. robusta were provided by MREP, collected from various locations near San Diego, <lb/>CA, and kept under constant illumination in a recirculating refrigerated tank to promote the <lb/>accumulation of gametes. Transgene DNAs in water used for electroporations were pooled <lb/>together and mixed to a final concentration 0.77 M D-Mannitol. Specific amounts of transgene <lb/>DNAs used per experiment were listed in S1 Table. Electroporations were carried out essen-<lb/>tially as in [64], and electroporated embryos were left to develop at 18˚C in 0.22 μm-filtered <lb/>artificial seawater supplemented with penicillin/streptomycin (10 U/mL and 10 μg/mL, respec-<lb/>tively). An individual trial refers to an independent electroporation on a different day using <lb/>different parent animals. <lb/>Sequencing of CRISPR-Cas9-induced indels <lb/>Lhx3/4 CRISPR-Cas morphants coexpressing a Mesp&gt;H2B::GFP reporter were developed <lb/>until the early tailbud stage. Embryos were dissociated in magnesium and calcium-free seawa-<lb/>ter in 0.2% trypsin (Sigma Aldrich) on ice as in [36]. Trypsin was quenched using 1% BSA <lb/>(Sigma Aldrich) and placed in calcium and magnesium-free seawater on ice. Dissociated GFP-<lb/>positive cells were FACS collected using a BD Influx cell sorter (Penn Genomic and Sequenc-<lb/>ing Core, University of Pennsylvania). Captured cells were utilized directly as PCR template <lb/>and amplicons containing the target sequences were generated using the 5 0 oligo GTAGAC <lb/>AATGCAGACCGGA and the 3 0 oligo CGTCACAATACCTTGTATTCGTTGATCG. Ampli-<lb/>cons were cloned into an empty vector and submitted for Sanger sequencing. <lb/>Juveniles <lb/>After coelectroporation with Mesp&gt;nls::Cas9::nls, PC2&gt;Kaede (CITRES, https://marinebio. <lb/>nbrp.jp/ciona/), and sgRNA plasmids targeting GFP or Lhx3/4, animals were kept on gelatin <lb/>coated dishes for 20 to 22 hours at 18˚C until reaching the swimming larval stage. Larva were <lb/>transferred to gelatin-coated dishes with scratch marks that facilitate adhesion of the papillae <lb/>to the dish necessary for metamorphosis. Animals were reared until reaching the end of the <lb/>first ascidian stage (Stage 6: Days 7 to 9 postfertilization). Animals were first sorted based on <lb/>the presence of the coelectroporation fluorescent marker (PC2&gt;Kaede) and then heart mor-<lb/>phology and peristalsis were assessed under transmitted light. Animals were scored as either <lb/>normal or abnormal. Representative transmitted light videos were taken with a Zeiss LSM 980 <lb/>confocal microscope. Those specimens were then relaxed using a menthol crystal placed in <lb/>seawater until animals were unresponsive (approximately 15 minutes). Animals were fixed in <lb/>4% paraformaldehyde for 15 minutes at room temperature and stored at 4˚C overnight. Ani-<lb/>mals were washed 3 times in 1X phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 5 minutes. Animals were <lb/>then stained with 1:1,000 DAPI (Thermo Fisher Scientific) for 30 minutes at room tempera-<lb/>ture and washed in 1X PBS. Animals were placed in an optical dish and imaged using a Zeiss <lb/>LSM 980 confocal microscope at 40× magnification in 1X PBS. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>24 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>LacZ staining <lb/>Embryos were fixed in MEM-GA (0.1 M MOPS (pH 7.4), 0.5 M NaCl, 2.0 mM MgSO4, 1.0 <lb/>mM EGTA (pH 8.0), 0.2% glutaraldehyde, 0.05% Tween 20) for 30 minutes at room tempera-<lb/>ture, then washed 4X in 1X PBS plus 0.2% Tween 20 (PBST). Embryos were stained in a solu-<lb/>tion of 1% X-gal, 100 mM MgCl, 0.75 M Na2HPO4, 1.0 M NaH2PO4, 100 mM potassium <lb/>ferrocyanide, 100 mM potassium ferricyanide, and 0.10% Tween 80, at room temperature for <lb/>2 to 4 hours, then washed 2X in PBST before transfer into 70% glycerol for imaging. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry <lb/>Immunohistochemistry was executed as in [112]. Briefly, embryos were fixed in 2% parafor-<lb/>maldehyde, washed in PBST, and briefly permeabilized in ice-cold 100% methanol. Embryos <lb/>were incubated at room temperature for 1 to 2 hours or 4˚C overnight with primary antibody <lb/>(rabbit-anti-GFP, Thermo Fisher Scientific, A11122) at 1:1,000, washed 3 times in PBST, and <lb/>incubated at room temperature for 1 to 2 hours or 4˚C overnight in secondary antibody <lb/>(Alexa Fluor 488, A-11001, Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 1:500. Embryos were washed twice in <lb/>PBST, incubated for 10 minutes in 50% glycerol/PBST and 1:1,000 DAPI, and then transferred <lb/>to 80% glycerol/PBST for imaging. <lb/>In situ hybridization <lb/>Whole mount in situ hybridization was performed essentially as in [113] with slight modifica-<lb/>tions. After several hours of staining, embryos were transferred out of staining buffer into 1X <lb/>Tris-buffered saline and rocked at 4˚C overnight. The next day, embryos were transferred <lb/>back into staining buffer for further colorimetric development. Upon completion, embryos <lb/>were washed in PBST, fixed briefly in 4% paraformaldehyde, washed 2X in PBST, and trans-<lb/>ferred to 70% glycerol for imaging. Embryos probed for Ets1/2.b expression were transferred <lb/>into 100% EtOH for approximately 5 minutes, then washed twice in PBST, prior to transfer <lb/>into 70% glycerol. <lb/>Imaging <lb/>Images of LacZ-stained and in situ hybridized embryos were captured through a 10X objective <lb/>using a Nikon Alphaphot with an AmScope 10MP USB 2.0 Color CMOS Camera. Images and <lb/>time-lapse movies of embryonic and larval fluorescence were captured on a Zeiss LSM 980 <lb/>confocal microscope at 20× magnification. Fixed samples were imaged in 1X PBS, and live <lb/>embryos were imaged in artificial seawater. S4-S8 Movies were generated by assembling time-<lb/>lapse series of Z-stacks of live embryos from Stage 16 through Stage 25 using ImageJ software <lb/>[114]. <lb/>mRNA sequencing and analysis <lb/>PolyA+ RNA was isolated from GFP+ cells (dissociated and FACS-collected as above; Penn <lb/>Genomic and Sequencing Core, University of Pennsylvania). Paired-end libraries were pre-<lb/>pared from &gt;10 ng RNA (Takara SMART-Seq HT). Libraries were pooled and then sequenced <lb/>on a lane of a NovaSeq 6000 S4 (Illumina) at Azenta Life Sciences, generating maximum reads <lb/>of 150 nucleotides and a read depth of 45 to 62 million reads/sample (assessed using FastQC). <lb/>Reads were then aligned by HiSat2 [115] to the ci3 assembly (UCSC Genome Browser). The C. <lb/>robusta KH2012 gene models were used [116]. Referenced KY21 genes were manually con-<lb/>verted using the KY genome browser [57]. KH IDs were input into the genome browser search <lb/>bar. Results on the genome browser contained the KY IDs and homolog information. HTSeq <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 acts as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>25 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<body>was used to perform gene counts [117]. DESeq2 was used to normalize gene count and calcu-<lb/>late Log2 Fold Change and p-adjusted statistical significance [118]. A minimum of 100 reads <lb/>was the threshold required for gene expression. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. (Top) Mass of transgene DNA used in each experiment. (Bottom) Sense strand <lb/>sequences of sgRNAs used in this study. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Fig. Full homeobox screen data. (Left) Average percent of embryos displaying perturbed <lb/>migration covering 2 trials for all of the sgRNAs tested in this study (* = p &lt; .05). (Right) <lb/>Table of p-values comparing sgRNA effects on migration. Column 1) p-values for negative <lb/>controls vs. other sgRNAs; column 2) Ets1/2.b sgRNAs vs. other sgRNAs; and column 3) the <lb/>185/886 pair of Lhx3/4 sgRNAs vs. other sgRNAs. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Detailed Lhx3/4 targeting strategy. (A) Diagram of Lhx3/4 locus depicting the 2 iso-<lb/>forms of Lhx3/4 and the locations targeted by Lhx3/4 sgRNAs. (B) Sequencing results. WT <lb/>spans upstream of the sgLhx3/4 185 position to downstream of the sgLhx3/4 886 position, (6,221 <lb/>bp) indicates the nucleotides in the intervening wild-type sequence, underlining marks sgRNA <lb/>NGGs. C06, C08, C14: sequenced clones of CRISPR morphant amplicons. Dashes indicate <lb/>missing nucleotides in the sgRNA-targeted sequences. Two clones (C06/C14) had deletions, <lb/>while one clone (C08) had a deletion and an addition of TATA (nonbolded). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Complete representation of the Lhx3/4 rescue experiment. (A) Left: representative <lb/>embryos, inset numbers refer to quantity of embryos displaying the phenotype presented by <lb/>each image over total GFP+ embryos for each group. Arrows point to normal CPP position at <lb/>this time point. Green, GFP fluorescence. Right: graph of percent migration phenotype for <lb/>each group for GFP+ embryos. Blocked migration refers to CPPs in the tail; excess migration <lb/>refers to CPF-lineage anterior tail muscle cells in the trunk. n = 300 per condition. **** indi-<lb/>cates t test p-value of &lt; .0001. (B) Graph of overall percent GFP-negative embryos per condi-<lb/>tion. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S4 Fig. Confocal imaging of Lhx3/4-activated Hand.r&gt;LacZ in the ANP lineage. (Top) Rep-<lb/>resentative control embryo electroporated with Hand.r&gt;LacZ and Dmrt&gt;GFP. (Bottom) Rep-<lb/>resentative embryo electroporated with Hand.r&gt;LacZ, Dmrt&gt;GFP, and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 <lb/>displaying Hand.r&gt;LacZ reporter expression in the ANP lineage (white arrowheads). Confocal <lb/>max projected Z-stacks were scored over 2 trials. InAU : PleasenotethatasperPLOSstyle; numeralsareno <lb/>the Dmrt lineage, 13/13 (100%) of control <lb/>embryos exhibited no LacZ staining, whereas 15/16 (93.7%) of experimental Hand.r&gt;LacZ <lb/>and Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4 transgenic embryos were positive for LacZ staining in the Dmrt lineage. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Movie. Control juvenile showing peristalsis normally observed in the range of control <lb/>animals (corresponds to Fig 3I). <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S2 Movie. Experimental juvenile with sgRNAs targeting Lhx3/4 that has no discernable <lb/>myocardial cells (corresponds to Fig 3J). <lb/>(MOV) <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>26 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">S3 Movie. Experimental juvenile with sgRNAs targeting Lhx3/4 that exhibits abnormal <lb/>peristalsis due to severe disruption of myocardial tube morphogenesis. Note that the heart <lb/>appears to be compressed against the stomach. All videos contain juveniles that are in the first <lb/>ascidian stage (Stage 6: Days 7-9). <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S4 Movie. Representative control embryo (Dmrt&gt;GFP) displaying normal development <lb/>and GFP expression in the anterior neural plate lineage. S4-S8 MoviesAU : Pleasenotethat}Suppleme <lb/>are constructed from <lb/>confocal Z-stacks starting at Stages 15-16 (approximately 7 hours postfertilization) through <lb/>Stage 25 at 20-minute intervals. Developing embryos are dorsal side up and anterior to the left. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S5 Movie. A second representative control embryo displaying normal development of <lb/>GFP-labeled cells. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S6 Movie. Representative experimental embryo (Dmrt&gt;Lhx3/4) displaying aberrant <lb/>behavior of GFP-labeled cells (described in text). <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S7 Movie. A second representative experimental embryo displaying aberrant behavior of <lb/>GFP-labeled cells. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S8 Movie. A third representative experimental embryo displaying aberrant behavior of <lb/>GFP-labeled cells. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S1 Appendix. Raw data for Figs 2-5. Raw counts for all of the experiments conducted in Figs <lb/>2-5. Tab labels refer to data presented in particular graphs. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S2 Appendix. RNA-sequencing data. (Tab 1) DESeq2 statistics for all genes. (Tab 2-6) Lists <lb/>of up-and down-regulated genes from Fig 6. First column lists the KH gene IDs for all genes <lb/>that were selected for a particular analysis shown in each figure panel. The KH gene IDs for all <lb/>relevant genes that were significantly up-or down-regulated are shown in blue or red font. <lb/>Boxes indicate the most highly impact subset of genes as shown in the Fig 6 tables. For these <lb/>genes KH IDs were paired with KY IDs and human homologs. (Tab 7) Referenced Foxf target <lb/>genes. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: C. J. Pickett, Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Data curation: C. J. Pickett. <lb/>Formal analysis: C. J. Pickett, Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Investigation: C. J. Pickett, Hannah N. Gruner. <lb/>Methodology: C. J. Pickett, Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Project administration: Bradley Davidson. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>27 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Supervision: Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Visualization: C. J. Pickett. <lb/>Writing -original draft: C. J. Pickett, Hannah N. Gruner, Bradley Davidson. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: C. J. Pickett, Hannah N. Gruner, Bradley Davidson. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Levine M, Davidson EH. Gene regulatory networks for development. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005; <lb/>102(14):4936-4942. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0408031102 PMID: 15788537 <lb/>2. Davidson EH, McClay DR, Hood L. Regulatory gene networks and the properties of the developmental <lb/>process. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003; 100(4):1475-1480. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>0437746100 PMID: 12578984 <lb/>3. Bernadskaya Y, Christiaen L. Transcriptional Control of Developmental Cell Behaviors. Annu Rev Cell <lb/>Dev Biol. 2016; 32:77-101. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-cellbio-111315-125218 PMID: 27501446 <lb/>4. Walhout AJ. Gene-centered regulatory network mapping. Methods Cell Biol. 2011; 106:271-288. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-544172-8.00010-4 PMID: 22118281 <lb/>5. Alon U. Network motifs: theory and experimental approaches. Nat Rev Genet. 2007; 8(6):450-461. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nrg2102 PMID: 17510665 <lb/>6. Mojtahedi M, Skupin A, Zhou J, Castano IG, Leong-Quong RY, Chang H, et al. Cell Fate Decision as <lb/>High-Dimensional Critical State Transition. PLoS Biol. 2016; 14(12):e2000640. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pbio.2000640 PMID: 28027308 <lb/>7. Peter IS, Davidson EH. Modularity and design principles in the sea urchin embryo gene regulatory net-<lb/>work. FEBS Lett. 2009; 583(24):3948-3958. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2009.11.060 PMID: <lb/>19932099 <lb/>8. Davidson EH. Emerging properties of animal gene regulatory networks. Nature. 2010; 468 <lb/>(7326):911-920. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature09645 PMID: 21164479 <lb/>9. Smith SJ, Rebeiz M, Davidson L. From pattern to process: studies at the interface of gene regulatory <lb/>networks, morphogenesis, and evolution. Curr Opin Genet Dev. 2018; 51:103-110. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.gde.2018.08.004 PMID: 30278289 <lb/>10. Oliveri P, Tu Q, Davidson EH. Global regulatory logic for specification of an embryonic cell lineage. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008; 105(16):5955-5962. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0711220105 <lb/>PMID: 18413610 <lb/>11. Mangan S, Alon U. Structure and function of the feed-forward loop network motif. Proc Natl Acad Sci U <lb/>S A. 2003; 100(21):11980-11985. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2133841100 PMID: 14530388 <lb/>12. Peter IS, Davidson EH. Genomic control of patterning. Int J Dev Biol. 2009; 53(5-6):707-716. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1387/ijdb.072495ip PMID: 19378258 <lb/>13. Peter IS, Davidson EH. Assessing regulatory information in developmental gene regulatory networks. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017; 114(23):5862-5869. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1610616114 <lb/>PMID: 28584110 <lb/>14. Peter IS, Davidson EH, ProQuest. Genomic control process: development and evolution. London, <lb/>England: Elsevier: AP; 2015. <lb/>15. Basson MA. Signaling in cell differentiation and morphogenesis. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol. <lb/>2012; 4(6). https://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a008151 PMID: 22570373 <lb/>16. Perrimon N, Pitsouli C, Shilo BZ. Signaling mechanisms controlling cell fate and embryonic patterning. <lb/>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol. 2012; 4(8):a005975. https://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a005975 <lb/>PMID: 22855721 <lb/>17. Sanz-Ezquerro JJ, Munsterberg AE, Stricker S. Editorial: Signaling Pathways in Embryonic Develop-<lb/>ment. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2017; 5:76. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcell.2017.00076 PMID: 28913334 <lb/>18. Bertrand V, Hudson C, Caillol D, Popovici C, Lemaire P. Neural tissue in ascidian embryos is induced <lb/>by FGF9/16/20, acting via a combination of maternal GATA and Ets transcription factors. Cell. 2003; <lb/>115(5):615-627. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0092-8674(03)00928-0 PMID: 14651852 <lb/>19. Miya T, Nishida H. An Ets transcription factor, HrEts, is target of FGF signaling and involved in induc-<lb/>tion of notochord, mesenchyme, and brain in ascidian embryos. Dev Biol. 2003; 261(1):25-38. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/s0012-1606(03)00246-x PMID: 12941619 <lb/>20. Sharrocks AD, Brown AL, Ling Y, Yates PR. The ETS-domain transcription factor family. Int J Biochem <lb/>Cell Biol. 1997; 29(12):1371-1387. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1357-2725(97)00086-1 PMID: 9570133 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>28 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>21. Hollenhorst PC, McIntosh LP, Graves BJ. Genomic and biochemical insights into the specificity of <lb/>ETS transcription factors. Annu Rev Biochem. 2011; 80:437-471. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev. <lb/>biochem.79.081507.103945 PMID: 21548782 <lb/>22. Trompouki E, Bowman TV, Lawton LN, Fan ZP, Wu D-C, DiBiase A, et al. Lineage regulators direct <lb/>BMP and Wnt pathways to cell-specific programs during differentiation and regeneration. Cell. 2011; <lb/>147(3):577-589. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2011.09.044 PMID: 22036566 <lb/>23. Zhang DX, Glass CK. Towards an understanding of cell-specific functions of signal-dependent tran-<lb/>scription factors. J Mol Endocrinol. 2013; 51(3):T37-T50. https://doi.org/10.1530/JME-13-0216 PMID: <lb/>24130129 <lb/>24. Crepieux P, Coll J, Stehelin D. The Ets family of proteins: weak modulators of gene expression in <lb/>quest for transcriptional partners. Crit Rev Oncog. 1994; 5(6):615-638. PMID: 8519813 <lb/>25. Li R, Pei H, Watson DK. Regulation of Ets function by protein-protein interactions. Oncogene. 2000; <lb/>19(55):6514-6523. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc.1204035 PMID: 11175367 <lb/>26. Verger A, Duterque-Coquillaud M. When Ets transcription factors meet their partners. Bioessays. <lb/>2002; 24(4):362-370. https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.10068 PMID: 11948622 <lb/>27. Sato A, Satoh N, Bishop JDD. Field identification of &apos;types&apos; A and B of the ascidian in a region of sym-<lb/>patry. Mar Biol. 2012; 159(7):1611-1619. <lb/>28. Brunetti R, Gissi C, Pennati R, Caicci F, Gasparini F, Manni L. Morphological evidence that the molec-<lb/>ularly determined type A and type B are different species: and. J Zool Syst Evol Res. 2015; 53(3):186-<lb/>193. <lb/>29. Delsuc F, Brinkmann H, Chourrout D, Philippe H. Tunicates and not cephalochordates are the closest <lb/>living relatives of vertebrates. Nature. 2006; 439(7079):965-968. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04336 <lb/>PMID: 16495997 <lb/>30. Dehal P, Satou Y, Campbell RK, Chapman J, Degnan B, De Tomaso A, et al. The draft genome of <lb/>Ciona intestinalis: insights into chordate and vertebrate origins. Science. 2002; 298(5601):2157-2167. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1080049 PMID: 12481130 <lb/>31. Cota CD, Segade F, Davidson B. Heart genetics in a small package, exploiting the condensed genome <lb/>of Ciona intestinalis. Brief Funct Genomics. 2014; 13(1):3-14. https://doi.org/10.1093/bfgp/elt034 <lb/>PMID: 24005910 <lb/>32. Anderson HE, Christiaen L. Ciona as a Simple Chordate Model for Heart Development and Regenera-<lb/>tion. J Cardiovasc Dev Dis. 2016; 3(3). https://doi.org/10.3390/jcdd3030025 PMID: 27642586 <lb/>33. Satou Y, Imai KS, Satoh N. The ascidian Mesp gene specifies heart precursor cells. Development. <lb/>2004; 131(11):2533-2541. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.01145 PMID: 15115756 <lb/>34. Christiaen L, Stolfi A, Davidson B, Levine M. Spatio-temporal intersection of Lhx3 and Tbx6 defines <lb/>the cardiac field through synergistic activation of Mesp. Dev Biol. 2009; 328(2):552-560. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.01.033 PMID: 19389354 <lb/>35. Davidson B, Shi W, Levine M. Uncoupling heart cell specification and migration in the simple chordate <lb/>Ciona intestinalis. Development. 2005; 132(21):4811-4818. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.02051 PMID: <lb/>16207759 <lb/>36. Davidson B, Shi W, Beh J, Christiaen L, Levine M. FGF signaling delineates the cardiac progenitor <lb/>field in the simple chordate, Ciona intestinalis. Genes Dev. 2006; 20(19):2728-2738. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1101/gad.1467706 PMID: 17015434 <lb/>37. Christiaen L, Davidson B, Kawashima T, Powell W, Nolla H, Vranizan K, et al. The transcription/migra-<lb/>tion interface in heart precursors of Ciona intestinalis. Science. 2008; 320(5881):1349-1352. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1126/science.1158170 PMID: 18535245 <lb/>38. Cooley J, Whitaker S, Sweeney S, Fraser S, Davidson B. Cytoskeletal polarity mediates localized <lb/>induction of the heart progenitor lineage. Nat Cell Biol. 2011; 13(8):952-957. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>ncb2291 PMID: 21785423 <lb/>39. Woznica A, Haeussler M, Starobinska E, Jemmett J, Li Y, Mount D, et al. Initial deployment of the car-<lb/>diogenic gene regulatory network in the basal chordate, Ciona intestinalis. Dev Biol. 2012; 368 <lb/>(1):127-139. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2012.05.002 PMID: 22595514 <lb/>40. Beh J, Shi W, Levine M, Davidson B, Christiaen L. FoxF is essential for FGF-induced migration of <lb/>heart progenitor cells in the ascidian Ciona intestinalis. Development. 2007; 134(18):3297-3305. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.010140 PMID: 17720694 <lb/>41. Gline S, Kaplan N, Bernadskaya Y, Abdu Y, Christiaen L. Surrounding tissues canalize motile cardio-<lb/>pharyngeal progenitors towards collective polarity and directed migration. Development. 2015; 142 <lb/>(3):544-554. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.115444 PMID: 25564651 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>29 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>42. Davidson B, Levine M. Evolutionary origins of the vertebrate heart: Specification of the cardiac lineage <lb/>in Ciona intestinalis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003; 100(20):11469-11473. https://doi.org/10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.1634991100 PMID: 14500781 <lb/>43. Razy-Krajka F, Lam K, Wang W, Stolfi A, Joly M, Bonneau R, et al. Collier/OLF/EBF-dependent tran-<lb/>scriptional dynamics control pharyngeal muscle specification from primed cardiopharyngeal progeni-<lb/>tors. Dev Cell. 2014; 29(3):263-276. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2014.04.001 PMID: 24794633 <lb/>44. Kaplan N, Razy-Krajka F, Christiaen L. Regulation and evolution of cardiopharyngeal cell identity and <lb/>behavior: insights from simple chordates. Curr Opin Genet Dev. 2015; 32:119-128. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.gde.2015.02.008 PMID: 25819888 <lb/>45. Stolfi A, Gainous TB, Young JJ, Mori A, Levine M, Christiaen L. Early chordate origins of the vertebrate <lb/>second heart field. Science. 2010; 329(5991):565-568. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1190181 <lb/>PMID: 20671188 <lb/>46. Lemaire P, Smith WC, Nishida H. Ascidians and the plasticity of the chordate developmental program. <lb/>Curr Biol. 2008; 18(14):R620-R631. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2008.05.039 PMID: 18644342 <lb/>47. Hudson C, Lotito S, Yasuo H. Sequential and combinatorial inputs from Nodal, Delta2/Notch and FGF/ <lb/>MEK/ERK signalling pathways establish a grid-like organisation of distinct cell identities in the ascidian <lb/>neural plate. Development. 2007; 134(19):3527-3537. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.002352 PMID: <lb/>17728350 <lb/>48. Gainous TB, Wagner E, Levine M. Diverse ETS transcription factors mediate FGF signaling in the <lb/>Ciona anterior neural plate. Dev Biol. 2015; 399(2):218-225. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2014.12. <lb/>032 PMID: 25576927 <lb/>49. Razy-Krajka F, Gravez B, Kaplan N, Racioppi C, Wang W, Christiaen L. An FGF-driven feed-forward <lb/>circuit patterns the cardiopharyngeal mesoderm in space and time. Elife. 2018: 7. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>7554/eLife.29656 PMID: 29431097 <lb/>50. Matsumoto J, Kumano G, Nishida H. Direct activation by Ets and Zic is required for initial expression of <lb/>the Brachyury gene in the ascidian notochord. Dev Biol. 2007; 306(2):870-882. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ydbio.2007.03.034 PMID: 17459364 <lb/>51. Rothba ¨cher U, Bertrand V, Lamy C, Lemaire P. A combinatorial code of maternal GATA, Ets and β-<lb/>catenin-TCF transcription factors specifies and patterns the early ascidian ectoderm. Development. <lb/>2007; 134(22):4023-4032. <lb/>52. Hudson C, Lemaire P. Induction of anterior neural fates in the ascidian Ciona intestinalis. Mech Dev. <lb/>2001; 100(2):189-203. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0925-4773(00)00528-1 PMID: 11165477 <lb/>53. Desplan C, Theis J, Ofarrell PH. The Sequence Specificity of Homeodomain-DNA Interaction. Cell. <lb/>1988; 54(7):1081-1090. https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(88)90123-7 PMID: 3046753 <lb/>54. Hoey T, Levine M. Divergent homeo box proteins recognize similar DNA sequences in Drosophila. <lb/>Nature. 1988; 332(6167):858-861. https://doi.org/10.1038/332858a0 PMID: 2895896 <lb/>55. Wada S, Tokuoka M, Shoguchi E, Kobayashi K, Di Gregorio A, Spagnuolo A, et al. A genomewide sur-<lb/>vey of developmentally relevant genes in Ciona intestinalis. II. Genes for homeobox transcription fac-<lb/>tors. Dev Genes Evol. 2003; 213(5-6):222-234. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00427-003-0321-0 PMID: <lb/>12736825 <lb/>56. Stolfi A, Gandhi S, Salek F, Christiaen L. Tissue-specific genome editing in Ciona embryos by <lb/>CRISPR/Cas9. Development. 2014; 141(21):4115-4120. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.114488 PMID: <lb/>25336740 <lb/>57. Satou Y, Tokuoka M, Oda-Ishii I, Tokuhiro S, Ishida T, Liu B, et al. A Manually Curated Gene Model <lb/>Set for an Ascidian, Ciona robusta (Ciona intestinalis Type A). Zoolog Sci. 2022; 39(3):253-260. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2108/zs210102 PMID: 35699928 <lb/>58. Berger MF, Badis G, Gehrke AR, Talukder S, Philippakis AA, Pena-Castillo L, et al. Variation in home-<lb/>odomain DNA binding revealed by high-resolution analysis of sequence preferences. Cell. 2008; 133 <lb/>(7):1266-1276. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2008.05.024 PMID: 18585359 <lb/>59. Jolma A, Yan J, Whitington T, Toivonen J, Nitta KR, Rastas P, et al. DNA-binding specificities of <lb/>human transcription factors. Cell. 2013; 152(1-2):327-339. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.12.009 <lb/>PMID: 23332764 <lb/>60. Nitta KR, Vincentelli R, Jacox E, Cimino A, Ohtsuka Y, Sobral D, et al. High-Throughput Protein Pro-<lb/>duction Combined with High-Throughput SELEX Identifies an Extensive Atlas of Ciona robusta Tran-<lb/>scription Factor DNA-Binding Specificities. Methods Mol Biol. 2019; 2025:487-517. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/978-1-4939-9624-7_23 PMID: 31267468 <lb/>61. Kobayashi M, Takatori N, Nakajima Y, Kumano G, Nishida H, Saiga H. Spatial and temporal expres-<lb/>sion of two transcriptional isoforms of Lhx3, a LIM class homeobox gene, during embryogenesis of two <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>30 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>phylogenetically remote ascidians, Halocynthia roretzi and Ciona intestinalis. Gene Expr Patterns. <lb/>2010; 10(2-3):98-104. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gep.2010.01.004 PMID: 20123132 <lb/>62. Imai KS, Hino K, Yagi K, Satoh N, Satou Y. Gene expression profiles of transcription factors and sig-<lb/>naling molecules in the ascidian embryo: towards a comprehensive understanding of gene networks. <lb/>Development. 2004; 131(16):4047-4058. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.01270 PMID: 15269171 <lb/>63. Corbo JC, Levine M, Zeller RW. Characterization of a notochord-specific enhancer from the Brachyury <lb/>promoter region of the ascidian, Ciona intestinalis. Development. 1997; 124(3):589-602. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1242/dev.124.3.589 PMID: 9043074 <lb/>64. Zeller RW, Virata MJ, Cone AC. Predictable mosaic transgene expression in ascidian embryos pro-<lb/>duced with a simple electroporation device. Dev Dynam. 2006; 235(7):1921-1932. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1002/dvdy.20815 PMID: 16607640 <lb/>65. Chiba S, Sasaki A, Nakayama A, Takamura K, Satoh N. Development of Ciona intestinalis juveniles <lb/>(through 2nd ascidian stage). Zoolog Sci. 2004; 21(3):285-298. https://doi.org/10.2108/zsj.21.285 <lb/>PMID: 15056923 <lb/>66. Imai KS, Hikawa H, Kobayashi K, Satou Y. Tfap2 and Sox1/2/3 cooperatively specify ectodermal fates <lb/>in ascidian embryos. Development. 2017; 144(1):33-37. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.142109 PMID: <lb/>27888190 <lb/>67. Favata MF, Horiuchi KY, Manos EJ, Daulerio AJ, Stradley DA, Feeser WS, et al. Identification of a <lb/>novel inhibitor of mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase. J Biol Chem. 1998; 273(29):18623-18632. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.273.29.18623 PMID: 9660836 <lb/>68. Kim GJ, Nishida H. Role of the FGF and MEK signaling pathway in the ascidian embryo. Dev Growth <lb/>Differ. 2001; 43(5):521-533. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1440-169x.2001.00594.x PMID: 11576169 <lb/>69. Pegoraro C, Monsoro-Burq AH. Signaling and transcriptional regulation in neural crest specification <lb/>and migration: lessons from xenopus embryos. Wiley Interdiscip Rev Dev Biol. 2013; 2(2):247-259. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/wdev.76 PMID: 24009035 <lb/>70. Cao C, Lemaire LA, Wang W, Yoon PH, Choi YA, Parsons LR, et al. Comprehensive single-cell tran-<lb/>scriptome lineages of a proto-vertebrate. Nature. 2019; 571(7765):349-354. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41586-019-1385-y PMID: 31292549 <lb/>71. Nishida H. Cell lineage analysis in ascidian embryos by intracellular injection of a tracer enzyme. III. <lb/>Up to the tissue restricted stage. Dev Biol. 1987; 121(2):526-541. https://doi.org/10.1016/0012-1606 <lb/>(87)90188-6 PMID: 3582738 <lb/>72. Sakurai D, Goda M, Kohmura Y, Horie T, Iwamoto H, Ohtsuki H, et al. The role of pigment cells in the <lb/>brain of ascidian larva. J Comp Neurol. 2004; 475(1):70-82. https://doi.org/10.1002/cne.20142 PMID: <lb/>15176085 <lb/>73. Colgan W, Leanza A, Hwang A, DeBiasse MB, Llosa I, Rodrigues D, et al. Variable levels of drift in <lb/>tunicate cardiopharyngeal gene regulatory elements. EvoDevo. 2019; 10(1):1-17. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1186/s13227-019-0137-2 PMID: 31632631 <lb/>74. Racioppi C, Wiechecki KA, Christiaen L. Combinatorial chromatin dynamics foster accurate cardio-<lb/>pharyngeal fate choices. Elife. 2019; 8:e49921. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.49921 PMID: 31746740 <lb/>75. Stolfi A, Levine M. Neuronal subtype specification in the spinal cord of a protovertebrate. Develop-<lb/>ment. 2011; 138(5):995-1004. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.061507 PMID: 21303852 <lb/>76. Stolfi A, Wagner E, Taliaferro JM, Chou S, Levine M. Neural tube patterning by Ephrin, FGF and <lb/>Notch signaling relays. Development. 2011; 138(24):5429-5439. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.072108 <lb/>PMID: 22110057 <lb/>77. Thor S, Andersson SG, Tomlinson A, Thomas JB. A LIM-homeodomain combinatorial code for motor-<lb/>neuron pathway selection. Nature. 1999; 397(6714):76-80. https://doi.org/10.1038/16275 PMID: <lb/>9892357 <lb/>78. Thaler JP, Lee SK, Jurata LW, Gill GN, Pfaff SL. LIM factor Lhx3 contributes to the specification of <lb/>motor neuron and interneuron identity through cell-type-specific protein-protein interactions. Cell. <lb/>2002; 110(2):237-249. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0092-8674(02)00823-1 PMID: 12150931 <lb/>79. Lee S, Lee B, Joshi K, Pfaff SL, Lee JW, Lee SK. A regulatory network to segregate the identity of neu-<lb/>ronal subtypes. Dev Cell. 2008; 14(6):877-889. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2008.03.021 PMID: <lb/>18539116 <lb/>80. Smith HM, Khairallah SM, Nguyen AH, Newman-Smith E, Smith WC. Misregulation of cell adhesion <lb/>molecules in the Ciona neural tube closure mutant bugeye. Dev Biol. 2021; 480:14-24. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.ydbio.2021.08.006 PMID: 34407458 <lb/>81. Brozovic M, Dantec C, Dardaillon J, Dauga D, Faure E, Gineste M, et al. ANISEED 2017: extending <lb/>the integrated ascidian database to the exploration and evolutionary comparison of genome-scale <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>31 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>datasets. Nucleic Acids Res. 2018; 46(D1):D718-D725. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkx1108 PMID: <lb/>29149270 <lb/>82. Sasakura Y, Yamada L, Takatori N, Satou Y, Satoh N. A genomewide survey of developmentally rele-<lb/>vant genes in Ciona intestinalis. VII. Molecules involved in the regulation of cell polarity and actin <lb/>dynamics. Dev Genes Evol. 2003; 213(5-6):273-283. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00427-003-0325-9 <lb/>PMID: 12740699 <lb/>83. D&apos;Aniello E, Pezzotti MR, Locascio A, Branno M. Onecut is a direct neural-specific transcriptional acti-<lb/>vator of Rx in Ciona intestinalis. Dev Biol. 2011; 355(2):358-371. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2011. <lb/>05.584 PMID: 21600895 <lb/>84. Squarzoni P, Parveen F, Zanetti L, Ristoratore F, Spagnuolo A. FGF/MAPK/Ets signaling renders pig-<lb/>ment cell precursors competent to respond to Wnt signal by directly controlling Ci-Tcf transcription. <lb/>Development. 2011; 138(7):1421-1432. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.057323 PMID: 21385767 <lb/>85. Hudson C, Esposito R, Palladino A, Staiano L, Ferrier D, Faure E, et al. Transcriptional regulation of <lb/>the Ciona Gsx gene in the neural plate. Dev Biol. 2019; 448(2):88-100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio. <lb/>2018.12.013 PMID: 30583796 <lb/>86. Candiani S, Pennati R, Oliveri D, Locascio A, Branno M, Castagnola P, et al. Ci-POU-IV expression <lb/>identifies PNS neurons in embryos and larvae of the ascidian Ciona intestinalis. Dev Genes Evol. <lb/>2005; 215(1):41-45. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00427-004-0444-y PMID: 15526215 <lb/>87. Iskratsch T, Lange S, Dwyer J, Kho AL, dos Remedios C, Ehler E. Formin follows function: a muscle-<lb/>specific isoform of FHOD3 is regulated by CK2 phosphorylation and promotes myofibril maintenance. <lb/>J Cell Biol. 2010; 191(6):1159-1172. https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201005060 PMID: 21149568 <lb/>88. Huang S, Liu F, Niu Q, Li Y, Liu C, Zhang L, et al. GLIPR-2 overexpression in HK-2 cells promotes cell <lb/>EMT and migration through ERK1/2 activation. PLoS ONE. 2013; 8(3):e58574. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0058574 PMID: 23516513 <lb/>89. Koster J, Geerts D, Favre B, Borradori L, Sonnenberg A. Analysis of the interactions between BP180, <lb/>BP230, plectin and the integrin alpha6beta4 important for hemidesmosome assembly. J Cell Sci. <lb/>2003; 116(Pt 2):387-399. https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.00241 PMID: 12482924 <lb/>90. Park B, Nguyen NT, Dutt P, Merdek KD, Bashar M, Sterpetti P, et al. Association of Lbc Rho guanine <lb/>nucleotide exchange factor with alpha-catenin-related protein, alpha-catulin/CTNNAL1, supports <lb/>serum response factor activation. J Biol Chem. 2002; 277(47):45361-45370. https://doi.org/10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M202447200 PMID: 12270917 <lb/>91. Lawrenson ID, Wimmer-Kleikamp SH, Lock P, Schoenwaelder SM, Down M, Boyd AW, et al. Ephrin-<lb/>A5 induces rounding, blebbing and de-adhesion of EphA3-expressing 293T and melanoma cells by <lb/>CrkII and Rho-mediated signalling. J Cell Sci. 2002; 115(Pt 5):1059-1072. https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs. <lb/>115.5.1059 PMID: 11870224 <lb/>92. Stephen LJ, Fawkes AL, Verhoeve A, Lemke G, Brown A. A critical role for the EphA3 receptor tyro-<lb/>sine kinase in heart development. Dev Biol. 2007; 302(1):66-79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2006. <lb/>08.058 PMID: 17046737 <lb/>93. Kuo MW, Wang CH, Wu HC, Chang SJ, Chuang YJ. Soluble THSD7A is an N-glycoprotein that pro-<lb/>motes endothelial cell migration and tube formation in angiogenesis. PLoS ONE. 2011; 6(12):e29000. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0029000 PMID: 22194972 <lb/>94. Tomas NM, Hoxha E, Reinicke AT, Fester L, Helmchen U, Gerth J, et al. Autoantibodies against <lb/>thrombospondin type 1 domain-containing 7A induce membranous nephropathy. J Clin Invest. 2016; <lb/>126(7):2519-2532. https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI85265 PMID: 27214550 <lb/>95. Chepyala SR, Chen YC, Yan CC, Lu CY, Wu YC, Hsu CP. Noise propagation with interlinked feed-for-<lb/>ward pathways. Sci Rep. 2016; 6:23607. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep23607 PMID: 27029397 <lb/>96. Harel I, Maezawa Y, Avraham R, Rinon A, Ma HY, Cross JW, et al. Pharyngeal mesoderm regulatory <lb/>network controls cardiac and head muscle morphogenesis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012; 109 <lb/>(46):18839-18844. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1208690109 PMID: 23112163 <lb/>97. Beccari L, Marco-Ferreres R, Bovolenta P. The logic of gene regulatory networks in early vertebrate <lb/>forebrain patterning. Mech Dev. 2013; 130(2-3):95-111. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mod.2012.10.004 <lb/>PMID: 23111324 <lb/>98. Olson EN. Gene regulatory networks in the evolution and development of the heart. Science. 2006; <lb/>313(5795):1922-1927. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1132292 PMID: 17008524 <lb/>99. Sinigaglia C, Busengdal H, Leclere L, Technau U, Rentzsch F. The bilaterian head patterning gene <lb/>six3/6 controls aboral domain development in a cnidarian. PLoS Biol. 2013; 11(2):e1001488. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001488 PMID: 23483856 <lb/>100. Goto H, Kimmey SC, Row RH, Matus DQ, Martin BL. FGF and canonical Wnt signaling cooperate to <lb/>induce paraxial mesoderm from tailbud neuromesodermal progenitors through regulation of a two-<lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>32 / 33 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>step epithelial to mesenchymal transition. Development. 2017; 144(8):1412-1424. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1242/dev.143578 PMID: 28242612 <lb/>101. Willaredt MA, Schluter T, Nothwang HG. The gene regulatory networks underlying formation of the <lb/>auditory hindbrain. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2015; 72(3):519-535. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-014-1759-<lb/>0 PMID: 25332098 <lb/>102. Rafiq K, Cheers MS, Ettensohn CA. The genomic regulatory control of skeletal morphogenesis in the <lb/>sea urchin. Development. 2012; 139(3):579-590. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.073049 PMID: <lb/>22190640 <lb/>103. Yadav Y, Subbaroyan A, Martin OC, Samal A. Relative importance of composition structures and bio-<lb/>logically meaningful logics in bipartite Boolean models of gene regulation. Sci Rep. 2022; 12(1):18156. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-22654-7 PMID: 36307465 <lb/>104. Edginton-White B, Maytum A, Kellaway SG, Goode DK, Keane P, Pagnuco I, et al. A genome-wide <lb/>relay of signalling-responsive enhancers drives hematopoietic specification. Nat Commun. 2023; 14 <lb/>(1):267. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-35910-9 PMID: 36650172 <lb/>105. Farley EK, Olson KM, Zhang W, Brandt AJ, Rokhsar DS, Levine MS. Suboptimization of developmen-<lb/>tal enhancers. Science. 2015; 350(6258):325-328. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aac6948 PMID: <lb/>26472909 <lb/>106. Song BP, Ragsac MF, Tellez K, Jindal GA, Grudzien JL, Le SH, et al. Diverse logics and grammar <lb/>encode notochord enhancers. Cell Rep. 2023; 42(2):112052. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2023. <lb/>112052 PMID: 36729834 <lb/>107. Jindal GA, Bantle AT, Solvason JJ, Grudzien JL, D&apos;Antonio-Chronowska A, Lim F, et al. Single-nucleo-<lb/>tide variants within heart enhancers increase binding affinity and disrupt heart development. Dev Cell. <lb/>2023. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2023.09.005 PMID: 37848026 <lb/>108. Brena C, Cima F, Burighel P. Alimentary tract of Kowalevskiidae (Appendicularia, Tunicata) and evolu-<lb/>tionary implications. J Morphol. 2003; 258(2):225-238. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmor.10145 PMID: <lb/>14518015 <lb/>109. Marti-Solans J, Godoy-Marin H, Diaz-Gracia M, Onuma TA, Nishida H, Albalat R, et al. Massive Gene <lb/>Loss and Function Shuffling in Appendicularians Stretch the Boundaries of Chordate Wnt Family Evo-<lb/>lution. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2021; 9:700827. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcell.2021.700827 PMID: <lb/>34179025 <lb/>110. Ferrandez-Roldan A, Fabrega-Torrus M, Sanchez-Serna G, Duran-Bello E, Joaquin-Lluis M, Bujosa <lb/>P, et al. Cardiopharyngeal deconstruction and ancestral tunicate sessility. Nature. 2021; 599 <lb/>(7885):431-435. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-04041-w PMID: 34789899 <lb/>111. Piette J, Lemaire P. Thaliaceans, the neglected pelagic relatives of Ascidians: a developmental and <lb/>evolutionary enigma. Q Rev Biol. 2015; 90(2):117-145. https://doi.org/10.1086/681440 PMID: <lb/>26285352 <lb/>112. Joyce Tang W, Chen JS, Zeller RW. Transcriptional regulation of the peripheral nervous system in <lb/>Ciona intestinalis. Dev Biol. 2013; 378(2):183-193. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.03.016 PMID: <lb/>23545329 <lb/>113. Satou Y, Takatori N, Yamada L, Mochizuki Y, Hamaguchi M, Ishikawa H, et al. Gene expression pro-<lb/>files in Ciona intestinalis tailbud embryos. Development. 2001; 128(15):2893-2904. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1242/dev.128.15.2893 PMID: 11532913 <lb/>114. Schneider CA, Rasband WS, Eliceiri KW. NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis. Nat Meth-<lb/>ods. 2012; 9(7):671-675. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2089 PMID: 22930834 <lb/>115. Pertea M, Kim D, Pertea GM, Leek JT, Salzberg SL. Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq <lb/>experiments with HISAT, StringTie and Ballgown. Nat Protoc. 2016; 11(9):1650-1667. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1038/nprot.2016.095 PMID: 27560171 <lb/>116. Satou Y, Kawashima T, Shoguchi E, Nakayama A, Satoh N. An integrated database of the ascidian, <lb/>Ciona intestinalis: towards functional genomics. Zoolog Sci. 2005; 22(8):837-843. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>2108/zsj.22.837 PMID: 16141696 <lb/>117. Anders S, Pyl PT, Huber W. HTSeq-a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing <lb/>data. Bioinformatics. 2015; 31(2):166-169. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638 PMID: <lb/>25260700 <lb/>118. Love MI, Huber W, Anders S. Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data <lb/>with DESeq2. Genome Biol. 2014; 15(12):550. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8 PMID: <lb/>25516281 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Lhx3/4 as a cardiopharyngeal lineage determinant <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002169 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>33 / 33 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>