<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-19T17:02:48.272Z">11/19/2025 5:02:48 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-19T17:02:37.843726Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-19T17:02:37.843726Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>STUDY PROTOCOL <lb/>Researching COVID to enhance recovery <lb/>(RECOVER) pediatric study protocol: Rationale, <lb/>objectives and design <lb/>Rachel S. Gross 1☯ *, Tanayott Thaweethai 2☯ , Erika B. Rosenzweig 3 , James Chan 2 , Lori <lb/>B. Chibnik 2 , Mine S. Cicek 4 , Amy J. Elliott 5 , Valerie J. FlahermanID 6 , Andrea S. Foulkes 2 , <lb/>Margot Gage Witvliet 7 , Richard Gallagher 8 , Maria Laura Gennaro 9 , Terry L. Jernigan 10,11 , <lb/>Elizabeth W. Karlson 12 , Stuart D. Katz 13 , Patricia A. KinserID 14 , Lawrence C. Kleinman 15 , <lb/>Michelle F. Lamendola-Essel 13 , Joshua D. Milner 16 , Sindhu Mohandas 17 , Praveen <lb/>C. Mudumbi 18 , Jane W. Newburger 19 , Kyung E. Rhee 20 , Amy L. Salisbury 14 , Jessica <lb/>N. Snowden 21 , Cheryl R. SteinID 8 , Melissa S. Stockwell 22,23 , Kelan G. Tantisira 24 , Moriah <lb/>E. ThomasonID 8 , Dongngan T. Truong 25 , David Warburton 26 , John C. Wood 27 , <lb/>Shifa Ahmed 2 , Almary AkerlundhID 28 , Akram N. Alshawabkeh 29 , Brett R. Anderson 3 , Judy <lb/>L. Aschner 30 , Andrew M. Atz 31 , Robin L. Aupperle 32 , Fiona C. Baker 33 , <lb/>Venkataraman Balaraman 34 , Dithi Banerjee 35 , Deanna M. Barch 36 , Arielle Baskin-<lb/>Sommers 37 , Sultana Bhuiyan 13 , Marie-Abele C. Bind 2 , Amanda L. Bogie 38 , <lb/>Tamara Bradford 39 , Natalie C. BuchbinderID 40 , Elliott Bueler 13 , Hu ¨lya Bu ¨ku ¨lmez 41 , B. <lb/>J. Casey 42 , Linda Chang 43 , Maryanne Chrisant ID <lb/>44 , Duncan B. Clark 45 , Rebecca <lb/>G. Clifton 46 , Katharine N. Clouser 30 , Lesley Cottrell 47 , Kelly Cowan 48 , Viren D&apos;Sa 49 , <lb/>Mirella Dapretto 50 , Soham Dasgupta 51 , Walter Dehority ID <lb/>52 , Audrey Dionne 19 , Kirsten <lb/>B. Dummer ID <lb/>53 , Matthew D. Elias 54 , Shari Esquenazi-Karonika 13 , Danielle N. Evans ID <lb/>55 , E. <lb/>Vincent S. Faustino 56 , Alexander G. Fiks 57 , Daniel Forsha 58 , John J. Foxe 59 , Naomi <lb/>P. Friedman 60 , Greta Fry 61 , Sunanda Gaur 15 , Dylan G. Gee 37 , Kevin M. Gray 62 , <lb/>Stephanie Handler 63 , Ashraf S. Harahsheh ID <lb/>64 <lb/>, Keren Hasbani 65 , Andrew C. Heath 66 , <lb/>Camden Hebson 67 , Mary M. Heitzeg 68 , Christina M. Hester ID <lb/>69 <lb/>, Sophia Hill 13 , Laura Hobart-<lb/>Porter 70 , Travis K. F. Hong 34 , Carol R. Horowitz 71 , Daniel S. Hsia ID <lb/>72 , <lb/>Matthew Huentelman 73 , Kathy D. Hummel 74 , Katherine Irby 74 , Joanna Jacobus 75 , Vanessa <lb/>L. Jacoby 76 , Pei-Ni Jone ID <lb/>77 , David C. Kaelber 78,79 , Tyler J. Kasmarcak 80 , Matthew <lb/>J. Kluko ID <lb/>56 <lb/>, Jessica S. Kosut 34 , Angela R. Laird 81 , Jeremy Landeo-Gutierrez 82 , Sean <lb/>M. Lang 83 , Christine L. Larson 84 , Peter Paul C. Lim ID <lb/>85 , Krista M. Lisdahl 84 , Brian <lb/>W. McCrindle 86 , Russell J. McCulloh 87 , Kimberly McHugh 80 , Alan L. Mendelsohn 88 , Torri <lb/>D. Metz 89 , Julie Miller 90 , Elizabeth C. Mitchell 91 , Lerraughn M. Morgan 92 , Eva M. Mu ¨ller-<lb/>Oehring ID <lb/>33 <lb/>, Erica R. Nahin 13 , Michael C. Neale 93 , Manette Ness-Cochinwala 15 , Sheila <lb/>M. Nolan 94 , Carlos R. Oliveira ID <lb/>56 , Onyekachukwu Osakwe 95 , Matthew E. Oster 96 , R. <lb/>Mark Payne ID <lb/>97 , Michael A. Portman 98 , Hengameh Raissy 99 , Isabelle G. Randall 13 , <lb/>Suchitra Rao 100 , Harrison T. Reeder 2 , Johana M. Rosas 13 , Mark W. Russell 101 , Arash <lb/>A. Sabati ID <lb/>102 <lb/>, Yamuna Sanil 103 , Alice I. Sato 104 , Michael S. Schechter 105 , <lb/>Rangaraj Selvarangan 35 , S. Kristen Sexson Tejtel 106 , Divya Shakti 95 , Kavita Sharma 107 , <lb/>Lindsay M. Squeglia 62 , Shubika Srivastava 108 , Michelle D. Stevenson 109 , <lb/>Jacqueline Szmuszkovicz 110 , Maria M. Talavera-BarberID 111 , Ronald J. Teufel, II 31 , <lb/>Deepika Thacker 108 , Felicia Trachtenberg 90 , Mmekom M. Udosen 18 , Megan R. Warner 28 , <lb/>Sara E. Watson 109 , Alan Werzberger 112 , Jordan C. Weyer 113 , Marion J. Wood 18 , H. <lb/>Shonna Yin 114 , William T. Zempsky 115 , Emily Zimmerman 116 , Benard P. Dreyer 1 , on behalf <lb/>of the RECOVER-Pediatric Consortium ¶ <lb/>1 Department of Pediatrics, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New York, United <lb/>States of America, 2 Department of Biostatistics, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts, <lb/>United States of America, 3 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Columbia University <lb/>Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons and NewYork-Presbyterian, New York, New York, United <lb/>States of America, 4 Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, Mayo Clinic Hospital, Rochester, <lb/>Minnesota, United States of America, 5 Avera Research Institute, Avera Health, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, <lb/>United States of America, 6 Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/>1 / 29 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Gross RS, Thaweethai T, Rosenzweig EB, <lb/>Chan J, Chibnik LB, Cicek MS, et al. (2024) <lb/>Researching COVID to enhance recovery <lb/>(RECOVER) pediatric study protocol: Rationale, <lb/>objectives and design. PLoS ONE 19(5): e0285635. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 <lb/>Editor: Seyed Aria Nejadghaderi, Shahid Beheshti <lb/>University of Medical Sciences School of Medicine, <lb/>ISLAMIC REPUBLIC OF IRAN <lb/>Received: April 25, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: November 14, 2023 <lb/>Published: May 7, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Gross et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: No datasets were <lb/>generated or analysed during the current study. All <lb/>California, United States of America, 7 Department of Sociology, Lamar University, Beaumont, Texas, United <lb/>States of America, 8 Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, New York University Grossman School <lb/>of Medicine, New York, New York, United States of America, 9 Public Health Research Institute and <lb/>Department of Medicine, Rutgers New Jersey Medical School, Newark, New Jersey, United States of <lb/>America, 10 Center for Human Development, Department of Cognitive Science, University of California San <lb/>Diego, San Diego, California, United States of America, 11 Departments of Psychiatry and Radiology, <lb/>University of California San Diego School of Medicine, San Diego, California, United States of America, <lb/>12 Department of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America, <lb/>13 Department of Medicine, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New York, <lb/>United States of America, 14 School of Nursing, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, <lb/>United States of America, 15 Department of Pediatrics, Rutgers Robert Wood Johnson Medical School, New <lb/>Brunswick, New Jersey, United States of America, 16 Division of Pediatric Allergy, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Immunology and Rheumatology, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons and <lb/>NewYork-Presbyterian, New York, New York, United States of America, 17 Department of Infectious <lb/>Diseases, Children&apos;s Hospital Los Angeles, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California, Los <lb/>Angeles, California, United States of America, 18 Department of Population Health, New York University <lb/>Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New York, United States of America, 19 Department of Cardiology, <lb/>Boston Children&apos;s Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America, 20 Division of Child and <lb/>Community Health, Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Diego School of Medicine, San <lb/>Diego, California, United States of America, 21 Departments of Pediatrics and Biostatistics, University of <lb/>Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, Arkansas, United States of America, 22 Division of Child and <lb/>Adolescent Health, Department of Pediatrics, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and <lb/>Surgeons and NewYork-Presbyterian, New York, New York, United States of America, 23 Department of <lb/>Population and Family Health, Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health, New York, New York, <lb/>United States of America, 24 Division of Pediatric Respiratory Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, University <lb/>of California San Diego School of Medicine, San Diego, California, United States of America, 25 Division of <lb/>Pediatric Cardiology, University of Utah and Primary Children&apos;s Hospital, Salt Lake City, Utah, United States <lb/>of America, 26 Division of Neonatology, Department of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital Los Angeles, Keck <lb/>School of Medicine, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California, United States of America, <lb/>27 Department of Pediatrics and Radiology, Children&apos;s Hospital Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United <lb/>States of America, 28 Department of Pulmonary Research, Rady Children&apos;s Hospital-San Diego, San Diego, <lb/>California, United States of America, 29 College of Engineering, Northeastern University, Boston, <lb/>Massachusetts, United States of America, 30 Department of Pediatrics, Hackensack Meridian School of <lb/>Medicine, Nutley, New Jersey, United States of America, 31 Department of Pediatrics, Medical University of <lb/>South Carolina, Charleston, South Carolina, United States of America, 32 Oxley College of Health Sciences, <lb/>Laureate Institute for Brain Research, Tulsa, Oklahoma, United States of America, 33 Department of <lb/>Biosciences, SRI International, Menlo Park, California, United States of America, 34 Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Kapiolani Medical Center for Women and Children, Honolulu, Hawaii, United States of America, <lb/>35 Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, Children&apos;s Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, Missouri, <lb/>United States of America, 36 Department of Psychiatry, Washington University in St. Louis, Saint Louis, <lb/>Missouri, United States of America, 37 Department of Psychology, Yale University School of Medicine, New <lb/>Haven, Connecticut, United States of America, 38 Department of Pediatrics, University of Oklahoma Health <lb/>Science Center, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, United States of America, 39 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, <lb/>Department of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital of New Orleans and LSU Health Sciences Center, New <lb/>Orleans, United States of America, 40 Center for Human Development, University of California San Diego, <lb/>San Diego, California, United States of America, 41 Division of Rheumatology, Department of Pediatrics, The <lb/>MetroHealth System, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America, <lb/>42 Department of Neuroscience and Behavior, Barnard College-Columbia University, New York, New York, <lb/>United States of America, 43 Departments of Diagnostic Radiology &amp; Nuclear Medicine and Neurology, <lb/>University of Maryland Baltimore, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America, 44 Department of Women&apos;s <lb/>and Children&apos;s Health, Charles E. Schmidt College of Medicine at Florida Atlantic University, Hollywood, <lb/>Florida, United States of America, 45 Department of Psychiatry, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, <lb/>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America, 46 Biostatistics Center, George Washington University, <lb/>Washington, DC, United States of America, 47 Department of Pediatrics, West Virginia University, <lb/>Morgantown, West Virginia, United States of America, 48 Department of Pediatrics, Robert Larner M.D. <lb/>College of Medicine at the University of Vermont, Burlington, Vermont, United States of America, <lb/>49 Department of Pediatrics, Rhode Island Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island, United States of America, <lb/>50 Department of Psychiatry and Biobehavioral Sciences, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, <lb/>California, United States of America, 51 Department of Pediatrics, Norton Children&apos;s Hospital, University of <lb/>Louisville, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America, 52 Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, New Mexico, United States of America, 53 Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, University of California San Diego, San Diego, California, United States of America, 54 Division of <lb/>Cardiology, Children&apos;s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America, <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<front>relevant data from this study will be made available <lb/>upon study completion. <lb/>Funding: National Institutes of Health (NIH) <lb/>Agreement OTA OT2HL161847 (SDK, RG), <lb/>OT2HL161841 (ASF). https://www.nih.gov/ The <lb/>funders did not and will not have a role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to <lb/>publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/>following competing interests: Brett Anderson <lb/>reported receiving direct support for work not <lb/>related to RECOVER work/publications from <lb/>Genentech and the National Institute of Allergy and <lb/>Immunology. Walter Dehority reported receiving <lb/>grant support from Merck and participating in <lb/>research for the Moderna COVID-19 pediatric <lb/>vaccine trial and the Pfizer Paxlovid trial. Alex Fiks <lb/>reported receiving support from NJM insurance <lb/>and personal consulting fees not related to this <lb/>paper from Rutgers University and the American <lb/>Academy of Pediatrics. Ashraf Harahsheh reported <lb/>serving as a scientific advisory board member <lb/>unrelated to this paper for OP2 DRUGS. Lawrence <lb/>Kleinman reported serving as an unpaid member of <lb/>the Board of Directors for the DARTNet Institute, as <lb/>a principle investigator at Quality Matters, Inc., and <lb/>as the Vice Chair for the Borough of Metuchen <lb/>Board of Health. Dr. Kleinman also reported grant <lb/>support for work not related to RECOVER work/ <lb/>publications from NIH, HRSA, and the Robert <lb/>Wood Johnson Foundation. Dr. Kleinman also <lb/>reported minority individual stock ownership in <lb/>Apple Computer, Sanofi SA, Experion, <lb/>GlaxoSmithKline, Magyar Bank, Regeneron <lb/>Pharmaceuticals, JP Morgan Chase, and Amgen <lb/>Inc. Torri Metz reported participating as a Principle <lb/>Investigator in the medical advisory board for the <lb/>planning of a Pfizer clinical trial of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>vaccination in pregnancy. She is also a principle <lb/>investigator for a Pfizer study evaluating the <lb/>pharmacokinetics of Paxlovid in pregnant people <lb/>with COVID-19. Joshua Milner reported serving as <lb/>a member of the Scientific Advisory Board for <lb/>Blueprint Medicines, in a capacity unrelated to <lb/>RECOVER work/publications. This does not alter <lb/>our adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing <lb/>data and materials. <lb/>55 Arkansas Children&apos;s Research Institute, Arkansas Children&apos;s Hospital, Little Rock, Arkansas, United <lb/>States of America, 56 Department of Pediatrics, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, <lb/>Connecticut, United States of America, 57 Department of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital of Philadelphia, <lb/>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America, 58 Department of Cardiology, Children&apos;s Mercy <lb/>Kansas City, Ward Family Heart Center, Kansas City, Missouri, United States of America, 59 Department of <lb/>Neuroscience, University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, Rochester, New York, United States <lb/>of America, 60 Institute for Behavioral Genetics and Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, University <lb/>of Colorado Boulder, Bolder, Colorado, United States of America, 61 Pennington Biomedical Research <lb/>Center Clinic, Pennington Biomedical Research Center, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, United States of America, <lb/>62 Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston, <lb/>South Carolina, United States of America, 63 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, United States of America, 64 Division of Cardiology, <lb/>Department of Pediatrics, George Washington University School of Medicine &amp; Health Sciences, Washington, <lb/>DC, United States of America, 65 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Dell Children&apos;s <lb/>Medical Center, Dell Medical School, Austin, Texas, United States of America, 66 Department of Psychiatry, <lb/>Washington University School of Medicine, St Louis, Missouri, United States of America, 67 Division of <lb/>Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, <lb/>United States of America, 68 Department of Psychiatry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United <lb/>States of America, 69 Division of Practice-Based Research, Innovation, &amp; Evaluation, American Academy of <lb/>Family Physicians, Leawood, Kansas, United States of America, 70 Departments of Pediatrics and Physical <lb/>Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation, Section of Pediatric Rehabilitation, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, <lb/>Little Rock, Arkansas, United States of America, 71 Center for Health Equity and Community Engaged <lb/>Research and Department of Population Health Science and Policy, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, <lb/>New York, New York, United States of America, 72 Clinical Trials Unit, Pennington Biomedical Research <lb/>Center, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, United States of America, 73 Division of Neurogenomics, Translational <lb/>Genomics Research Institute, Phoenix, Arizona, United States of America, 74 Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Arkansas Children&apos;s Hospital, University of Arkansas Medical School, Little Rock, Arkansas, United States of <lb/>America, 75 Department of Psychiatry, University of California San Diego, San Diego, California, United <lb/>States of America, 76 Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology, and Reproductive Sciences, University of <lb/>California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America, 77 Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Pediatric Cardiology, Lurie Children&apos;s Hospital, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, <lb/>Chicago, Illinois, United States of America, 78 The Center for Clinical Informatics Research and Education, <lb/>The MetroHealth System and the Departments of Pediatrics, Internal Medicine, and Population and <lb/>Quantitative Health Sciences, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America, <lb/>79 Departments of Pediatrics, Internal Medicine, and Population &amp; Quantitative Health Sciences, Case <lb/>Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America, 80 Department of Pediatric Clinical <lb/>Research, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston, South Carolina, United States of America, <lb/>81 Department of Physics, Florida International University, Miami, Florida, United States of America, <lb/>82 Respiratory Medicine Division, Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Diego, San Diego, <lb/>California, United States of America, 83 Heart Institute, Cincinnati Children&apos;s Hospital Medical Center, <lb/>Cincinnati, Ohio, United States of America, 84 Department of Psychology, University of Wisconsin-<lb/>Milwaukee, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, United States of America, 85 Department of Pediatric Infectious Disease, <lb/>Avera McKennan University Health Center, University of South Dakota, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, United <lb/>States of America, 86 Department of Pediatrics, University of Toronto, Labatt Family Heart Center, The <lb/>Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 87 Department of Pediatrics, University of Nebraska <lb/>Medical Center, Omaha, Nebraska, United States of America, 88 Division of Developmental-Behavioral <lb/>Pediatrics, Department of Pediatrics, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New <lb/>York, United States of America, 89 Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Utah Health, Salt <lb/>Lake City, Utah, United States of America, 90 Carelon Research, Newton, Massachusetts, United States of <lb/>America, 91 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Cohen Children&apos;s Medical Center <lb/>(Northwell Health), New Hyde Park, New York, United States of America, 92 Department of Pediatrics, Valley <lb/>Children&apos;s Healthcare, Madera, California, United States of America, 93 Virginia Institute for Psychiatric and <lb/>Behavioral Genetics, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, United States of America, <lb/>94 Department of Pediatrics, New York Medical College, Valhalla, New York, United States of America, <lb/>95 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, University of Mississippi Medical Center, <lb/>Jackson, Mississippi, United States of America, 96 Department of Pediatric Cardiology, Children&apos;s <lb/>Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 97 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, <lb/>Department of Pediatrics, Riley Hospital for Children, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, <lb/>Indiana, United States of America, 98 Division of Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Seattle Children&apos;s <lb/>and University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, United States of America, 99 Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>University of New Mexico, Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque, New Mexico, United States of America, <lb/>100 Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Epidemiology and Hospital Medicine, <lb/>University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, Colorado, United States of America, <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<front>101 Department of Pediatrics, University of Michigan Health System, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United States of <lb/>America, 102 Department of Pediatric Cardiology, Phoenix Children&apos;s Hospital, Phoenix, Arizona, United <lb/>States of America, 103 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital of <lb/>Michigan, Detroit, Michigan, United States of America, 104 Department of Pediatric Infectious Disease, <lb/>University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, Nebraska, United States of America, 105 Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital of Richmond at Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, United <lb/>States of America, 106 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of Pediatrics, Texas Children&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, United States of America, 107 Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas, United States of America, 108 Division of <lb/>Cardiovascular Medicine, Department of Pediatric Cardiology, Nemours Children&apos;s Health, Wilmington, <lb/>Delaware, United States of America, 109 Department of Pediatrics, University of Louisville School of <lb/>Medicine, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America, 110 Division of Cardiology, Children&apos;s Hospital Los <lb/>Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United States of America, 111 Department of Pediatrics, Avera McKennan <lb/>Hospital and University Health Center, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, United States of America, 112 Department <lb/>of Pediatrics, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, New York, United <lb/>States of America, 113 Center for Individualized Medicine, Mayo Clinic Hospital, Rochester, Minnesota, <lb/>United States of America, 114 Departments of Pediatrics and Population Health, New York University <lb/>Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New York, United States of America, 115 Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Connecticut Children&apos;s Medical Center, University of Connecticut School of Medicine, Hartford, <lb/>Connecticut, United States of America, 116 Department of Communication Sciences &amp; Disorders, <lb/>Northeastern University, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> ¶ Membership of the RECOVER-Pediatrics Consortium is provided in the Supplement S1 Appendix. <lb/>* Rachel.Gross@nyulangone.org <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Importance <lb/>The prevalence, pathophysiology, and long-term outcomes of COVID-19 (post-acute <lb/>sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 [PASC] or &quot;Long COVID&quot;) in children and young adults remain <lb/>unknown. Studies must address the urgent need to define PASC, its mechanisms, and <lb/>potential treatment targets in children and young adults. <lb/></front>

			<body>Observations <lb/>We describe the protocol for the Pediatric Observational Cohort Study of the NIH&apos;s <lb/>REsearching COVID to Enhance Recovery (RECOVER) Initiative. RECOVER-Pediatrics is <lb/>an observational meta-cohort study of caregiver-child pairs (birth through 17 years) and <lb/>young adults (18 through 25 years), recruited from more than 100 sites across the US. This <lb/>report focuses on two of four cohorts that comprise RECOVER-Pediatrics: 1) a de novo <lb/>RECOVER prospective cohort of children and young adults with and without previous or cur-<lb/>rent infection; and 2) an extant cohort derived from the Adolescent Brain Cognitive Develop-<lb/>ment (ABCD) study (n = 10,000). The de novo cohort incorporates three tiers of data <lb/>collection: 1) remote baseline assessments (Tier 1, n = 6000); 2) longitudinal follow-up for <lb/>up to 4 years (Tier 2, n = 6000); and 3) a subset of participants, primarily the most severely <lb/>affected by PASC, who will undergo deep phenotyping to explore PASC pathophysiology <lb/>(Tier 3, n = 600). Youth enrolled in the ABCD study participate in Tier 1. The pediatric proto-<lb/>col was developed as a collaborative partnership of investigators, patients, researchers, cli-<lb/>nicians, community partners, and federal partners, intentionally promoting inclusivity and <lb/>diversity. The protocol is adaptive to facilitate responses to emerging science. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<front>Conclusions and relevance <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics seeks to characterize the clinical course, underlying mechanisms, <lb/>and long-term effects of PASC from birth through 25 years old. RECOVER-Pediatrics is <lb/>designed to elucidate the epidemiology, four-year clinical course, and sociodemographic <lb/>correlates of pediatric PASC. The data and biosamples will allow examination of mechanis-<lb/>tic hypotheses and biomarkers, thus providing insights into potential therapeutic <lb/>interventions. <lb/>Clinical trials.gov identifier <lb/>Clinical Trial Registration: http://www.clinicaltrials.gov. Unique identifier: NCT05172011. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Long COVID, or the post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 (PASC), has been defined as symp-<lb/>toms, signs and conditions that continue or develop after a SARS-CoV-2 infection. These <lb/>symptoms can affect people for weeks, months or even years after getting coronavirus disease <lb/>2019 (COVID-19) [1, 2]. Symptoms can develop shortly after the initial recovery from an <lb/>acute COVID-19 episode or persist from the initial illness. Symptoms may also emerge later or <lb/>fluctuate or relapse over time. These symptoms can have debilitating effects on the daily health <lb/>and quality of life of those affected. <lb/>The COVID-19 pandemic has significantly impacted child health. Nearly 100 million peo-<lb/>ple have been diagnosed with COVID-19 in the United States (US), with nearly 16 million <lb/>children [3]. Although it is estimated that between 10% and 30% of adults experience persis-<lb/>tent symptoms from COVID-19 [4], the prevalence in children is less well-established [5, 6]. <lb/>As an emerging illness, the absence of universally-accepted PASC definitions in children chal-<lb/>lenge the elucidation of its epidemiology. <lb/>Unique challenges in understanding PASC symptoms in children have likely contributed to <lb/>the limited evidence. For example, young children might not be able to articulate their symp-<lb/>toms. This has required studies to rely on caregiver interpretation of their young child&apos;s symp-<lb/>toms. In addition, manifestation of symptoms may vary substantively across stages of <lb/>physiological, emotional, and cognitive development [7]. As the medical community shifts <lb/>from managing serious acute disease to addressing long-term consequences, large scale studies <lb/>are needed to define PASC in children across the life course, to understand its natural history, <lb/>and to develop evidence to guide successful treatment. <lb/>The pandemic began with a misconception that children were spared [8]. We now recog-<lb/>nize that children and families are greatly impacted during both acute and chronic phases [9-<lb/>12]. One distinct manifestation in children was recognized in April 2020; now called Multisys-<lb/>tem Inflammatory Syndrome in Children (MIS-C) [13]. This debilitating hyperinflammatory <lb/>syndrome has impacted over 9,000 children and young adults in the US [14], and represents a <lb/>distinct post-acute syndrome that is typically recognizable in clinical practice. Other more <lb/>chronic manifestations of PASC are challenging to characterize and identify. Furthermore, <lb/>children with PASC may present with different symptoms and greater mental health concerns <lb/>than adults [3, 15-21]. Additional phenotypes of childhood PASC are being reported, includ-<lb/>ing phenotypes similar to postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS), myalgic enceph-<lb/>alomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome (ME/CFS), postintensive care unit syndrome, and <lb/>potentially many others [22-24]. Therefore, a compelling rationale exists to invest resources <lb/>and effort to study PASC in children. The NIH&apos;s REsearching COVID to Enhance Recovery <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>(RECOVER) Initiative responded by bringing together researchers, communities, and families <lb/>in a systematic study of PASC in children [25]. Evidence that leads to improved health trajecto-<lb/>ries of children with PASC, could have population-level health impacts for decades to come. <lb/>Study rationale <lb/>RECOVER has established the Pediatric Observational Cohort Study (RECOVER-Pediatrics), <lb/>which is a combined retrospective and prospective longitudinal study, including four distinct <lb/>cohorts, integrated together as a meta-cohort [25]. The overall goal is to characterize the clini-<lb/>cal course, underlying mechanisms and long-term health effects of PASC on children and <lb/>young adults from birth through 25 years old, to inform future pediatric preventive and treat-<lb/>ment measures. <lb/>Study aims <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics scientific aims are to: <lb/>1. Characterize the prevalence and incidence of new onset or worsening symptoms related to <lb/>PASC <lb/>2. Characterize the spectrum of clinical symptoms of PASC, including distinct phenotypes, <lb/>and describe the clinical course and recovery. <lb/>3. Identify risk and resiliency factors for developing PASC and recovering from PASC. <lb/>4. Define the pathophysiology of PASC, including subclinical organ dysfunction, and identify <lb/>biological mechanisms underlying the pathogenesis of PASC. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Overview of study design <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics is a longitudinal, observational meta-cohort study of children and <lb/>young adults (ages birth through 25 years) and their caregivers, recruited from healthcare-and <lb/>community-based settings in more than 100 sites throughout the US, including Puerto Rico. <lb/>Those with and without a history of a SAR-CoV-2 infection are included. For those 17 years or <lb/>younger, data are collected by caregiver report and child direct assessments, and for those 18 <lb/>through 25 years old by self-report. The study is being conducted from March 2022 to March <lb/>2026. <lb/>The pediatric meta-cohort is comprised of four distinct cohorts: 1) de novo RECOVER pro-<lb/>spective cohort including children and young adults ages birth through 25 years, with or with-<lb/>out a known history of infection, and their caregivers; 2) Adolescent Brain Cognitive <lb/>Development (ABCD) extant cohort, the largest long-term US study of brain development in <lb/>adolescence [26, 27]; 3) In utero exposure cohort, including children less than 3 years old born <lb/>to individuals with and without a SAR-CoV-2 infection during pregnancy [28, 29]; and 4) <lb/>COVID MUSIC Study extant cohort (Long-Term Outcomes after the Multisystem Inflammatory <lb/>Syndrome In Children), including children and young adults with history of MIS-C [30]. This <lb/>report focuses on the de novo cohort and ABCD (Fig 1). <lb/>Fig 1 shows a tiered overview of 2 of the 4 cohorts included in the meta-cohort (de novo <lb/>RECOVER prospective cohort and ABCD), their participation in the three study tiers, and <lb/>their targeted sample sizes (see Study Participants). Children and young adults ages newborn <lb/>through 25 years old will be enrolled in the meta-cohort at Tier 1 for the de novo RECOVER <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>prospective cohort (more than 6,000 from birth through 25 years old, including those with and <lb/>without history of infection), and from ABCD (up to 10,000 adolescents with and without his-<lb/>tory of infection). All children and young adults enrolled in the study complete a baseline <lb/>assessment (Tier 1). Percentages shown indicate random sampling proportions. Children and <lb/>young adults without history of infection are assigned at random with prespecified propor-<lb/>tions to the acute and post-acute arms. All children and young adults with history of infection <lb/>who enroll into the acute arm and those without a history of infection who are randomized to <lb/>the acute arm are asked to complete assessments at 2, 4, and 8 weeks. Following a promotion <lb/>algorithm, children and young adults in Tier 1 will be selected to be promoted to Tier 2, which <lb/>includes assessments at 2-6, 12, 24, 36, and 48 months after enrollment. 600 children and <lb/>young adults with history of infection, selected from Tier 2, will complete more intensive Tier <lb/>3 assessments at 12 and 24 months after enrollment. <lb/>*Children and young adults with history of infection who enroll in the post-acute arm <lb/>(&quot;post-acute infected&quot;, n = 4,000) are stratified into High, Medium, and Low probability of <lb/>Fig 1. Overview of RECOVER-Pediatrics (de novo and ABCD cohorts). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>PASC groups based on a combination of past Long COVID diagnoses, Tier 1 Global PROMIS <lb/>health measures, and symptom survey screener responses. Then, 100% of the high probability <lb/>group, 50% of the medium probability group, and 20% of the low probability group are pro-<lb/>moted at random to Tier 2. In June 2023, the promotion rate for the medium probability <lb/>group was increased to 100% to enhance promotion rates and include the wider spectrum of <lb/>symptom severity within our longitudinal cohort. Since the distribution of these probability <lb/>groups is unknown a priori, sample sizes are not specified for each category. Overall, the num-<lb/>ber of children and young adults who progress to Tier 2 will be less than the initial post-acute <lb/>infected sample size, but the total target sample size for infected children and young adults in <lb/>Tier 2 is 5,400. <lb/>** In order to achieve a sample of 5,400 children and young adults with history of infection <lb/>in Tier 2 that is skewed towards those with greater likelihood of having PASC, additional chil-<lb/>dren and young adults will be recruited from Long COVID clinics and subspecialty services to <lb/>complete both Tier 1 and Tier 2 assessments. <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics is structured in a sequential fashion with three Tiers of data collec-<lb/>tion. Participants are enrolled initially into Tier 1, which consists of a broad screening of health <lb/>using remote surveys and biospecimen collection. Participants may subsequently progress to <lb/>Tier 2, which includes a detailed review of health collected longitudinally for up to four years, <lb/>using a combination of remote surveys and in-person assessments of biological and psychoso-<lb/>cial data. In order to achieve the sample size required for Tier 2 assessments, other study par-<lb/>ticipants will be recruited who present with a high probability of having PASC, such as those <lb/>directly recruited from a clinic that focuses on Long COVID or presenting with a physician <lb/>diagnosis of PASC. These participants will receive Tier 1 assessments and progress directly to <lb/>Tier 2. Finally, in Tier 3, a subset of children and young adults most severely affected by PASC <lb/>will undergo deep phenotyping with more intensive assessments to study PASC <lb/>pathophysiology. <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics Tier 1 assessments aim to characterize the prevalence and incidence <lb/>of new onset or worsening of sustained COVID-related symptoms (aim 1) and to gain a com-<lb/>prehensive understanding of the impact of exposure to a SARS-CoV-2 infection on broad <lb/>physical, behavioral and mental health (aim 2). Tier 2 facilitates studying the natural history of <lb/>PASC symptoms and potential recovery over time (aim 2). Child, household, and caregiver <lb/>factors gathered in Tier 1, such as social determinants of health and prior health conditions, <lb/>will be assessed to determine how they increase the risk of or protect against specific clinical <lb/>outcomes (aim 3). Finally, Tier 3 data investigates long-term effects on multiple organ systems <lb/>and child development (aim 4). Additionally, integration of Tier 1 and Tier 2 data will allow <lb/>investigation of COVID-disease exposures and experiences which may be responsible for the <lb/>clinical patterns observed in Tier 3. <lb/>The pediatric protocol was designed through collaboration across key stakeholders, includ-<lb/>ing patients, caregivers, researchers, clinicians, community partners, and federal partners, fos-<lb/>tering a patient-centered approach and promoting inclusivity and diversity. The pediatric <lb/>protocol is adaptive to facilitate the changes needed in light of emerging science and the evolv-<lb/>ing pandemic. <lb/>Study organizational structure and management <lb/>Study infrastructure includes four cores: 1) Clinical Science Core (CSC) at the NYU Grossman <lb/>School of Medicine, which oversees study sites and provides scientific leadership in collabora-<lb/>tion with hub and site Principal Investigators; 2) Data Resource Core (DRC) at Massachusetts <lb/>General Hospital and Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital, which provides scientific and statistical <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>leadership, and handles data management and storage; 3) PASC Biorepository Core (PBC) at <lb/>Mayo Clinic, which manages biospecimens obtained; and 4) Administrative Coordinating <lb/>Center (ACC) at RTI International, which provides operational and administrative support; <lb/>collectively these form the Core Operations Group. The four cores are supported by oversight <lb/>committees and pathobiology task forces provide content-specific input. RECOVER cohort <lb/>studies are overseen by the National Community Engagement Group (NCEG) composed of <lb/>patient and community representatives, a Steering Committee composed of site Principal <lb/>Investigators and NIH program leadership, an Executive Committee composed of NIH Insti-<lb/>tute leadership, and an Observational Safety Monitoring Board composed of experts in longi-<lb/>tudinal observational studies, epidemiology, bioethics, and biostatistics. RECOVER-Pediatrics <lb/>includes 10 hubs that manage ~100 sites (S1 Table), located in more than 39 states, Washing-<lb/>ton DC and Puerto Rico. Awardees were selected through a process that included independent <lb/>peer review in response to OTA-21-015B. <lb/>Ethics <lb/>The study was approved by the NYU Grossman School of Medicine Institutional Review <lb/>Board (IRB), which serves as the single IRB for the majority of the study sites. A few pre-exist-<lb/>ing networks use their own central IRBs through an exemption granted by the NIH (e.g., <lb/>ABCD, MUSIC). Caregivers, for children 17 years old or younger, and young adult partici-<lb/>pants provide signed informed consent to participate. <lb/>Recruitment, consent, and screening strategies <lb/>The de novo RECOVER prospective cohort study is recruiting participants from healthcare-and <lb/>community-based settings. Healthcare-based recruitment involves local media, text messaging, <lb/>hospital websites, COVID registries, and partnerships with pediatric practices, nurse hotlines, <lb/>or emergency departments. Community-based recruitment includes partnering with commu-<lb/>nity health workers, school nurses, sports coaches, health fairs, and a mobile van to access <lb/>rural communities. Participants can also join by self-referral through the RECOVER website, <lb/>or in response to plain language and picture-based recruitment materials in both English and <lb/>Spanish, which were developed with community input and using health literacy principles <lb/>[31]. <lb/>Eligible dyads complete an informed written consent process at enrollment for Tiers 1 and <lb/>2. The consent process may be conducted using telephone, a secure video conference platform <lb/>approved for exchange of PHI, or in person (using either a signed written consent form or via <lb/>electronic informed consent [e-consenting]). An assent process is being conducted for chil-<lb/>dren between 7 years and 17 years old. The study team explains the assent document to the <lb/>child and parent/legal guardian and answers all questions. Child understanding of the key ele-<lb/>ments of the assent document is assessed by the study team and parent/legal guardian. The <lb/>child either signs the age-appropriate assent document or provides verbal assent (with docu-<lb/>mentation in the local records and the central REDcap). Young adults, aged 18 through 25 <lb/>years old, sign their own informed consent. Tier 3 consent forms will only be completed when <lb/>testing is offered. A standardized teach back method is implemented as needed to ensure <lb/>understanding of the key aspects of participation before enrollment. Participants are recon-<lb/>sented if there are major changes to the study design or to anticipated risks. <lb/>In ABCD, 11,880 children aged 9-10 years old were recruited from community and school <lb/>sites to participate in a 10-year study with the goal of understanding neurocognitive develop-<lb/>ment during adolescence [26, 27, 32]. All ABCD participants are being contacted and offered <lb/>enrollment into RECOVER-Pediatrics. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Eligibility criteria <lb/>Children and young adults from birth through 25 years old are eligible to be enrolled in the de <lb/>novo cohort, regardless of history of SARS CoV-2 infection. Enrolled participants are then cate-<lb/>gorized as either &quot;infected&quot; or &quot;uninfected&quot;: Infected participants have history of suspected, <lb/>probable, or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, defined by the World Health Organization <lb/>(WHO) criteria [33], evidence of infection by serum antibody profile, or a history of MIS-C. <lb/>Uninfected participants are those who self-report as having no history of a SARS-CoV-2 infec-<lb/>tion and who have never met WHO criteria; they have no evidence of a past asymptomatic <lb/>infection in their medical history or evidence of past infection by serum antibody profile. <lb/>A primary caregiver, defined as an individual responsible for the enrolled child or young <lb/>adult who resides in the same household, such as biological or nonbiological family member, <lb/>is invited to enroll. <lb/>The primary exclusion criterion is any child or young adult with co-morbid illness with <lb/>expected survival of less than 2 years. There is no limit to the number of children or young <lb/>adults who can be enrolled from a single household. See supplemental tables for detailed eligi-<lb/>bility criteria, definitions of analytic groups, and the World Health Organization Criteria (S2-<lb/>S4 Tables). <lb/>Study participants <lb/>Recruitment is striving for a diverse sample that generally represents the US population, and <lb/>encourages participation from rural or medically underserved communities, non-English <lb/>speaking participants, and non-hospitalized participants with an acute COVID-19 infection. <lb/>Participants are compensated for completing assessments and reimbursed for excess travel. <lb/>At least 6,000 participants will be recruited into the de novo cohort (Fig 1). Children and <lb/>young adults with history of infection are classified into one of two study arms (acute arm vs. <lb/>post-acute arm), based on their history of SARS-CoV-2 infection and infection dates. The <lb/>acute arm includes 800 children and young adults whose most recent SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>was 30 days or less prior to enrollment. The post-acute arm includes 4,000 children and young <lb/>adults whose most recent SARS-CoV-2 infection was greater than 30 days prior to enrollment. <lb/>In the group without a history of infection, 1,200 children and young adults will be randomly <lb/>assigned to follow either the acute (200, or 17%) or post-acute (1,000 or 83%) arm of the proto-<lb/>col. Additional children and young adults will be recruited from Long COVID clinics and <lb/>other subspecialty services in order to achieve Tier 2 sample size targets (see Timing of Study <lb/>Assessments). <lb/>Up to 10,000 participants will also be recruited from the ABCD cohort. <lb/>Timing of study assessments <lb/>The assessments for the de novo cohort consists of three tiers, which vary in timing, collection <lb/>methods and intensity. <lb/>Tier 1 (baseline visit for all participants) includes a single visit that is completed either via <lb/>self-administration (remote and electronic) or research staff-assisted collection (e.g., tele-<lb/>phone, videoconference, or in-person). <lb/>Tier 2 (follow-up visits) includes five longitudinal in-person visits at 2 to 6-, 12-, 24-, 36-<lb/>and 48-months post-enrollment. The children and young adults followed longitudinally in <lb/>Tier 2 are selected based on a sampling scheme that prioritizes the acute arm as well as children <lb/>and youth in the post-acute arm with a greater likelihood of having PASC. Promotion to Tier <lb/>2 occurs as follows: 1) All children/young adults in the acute arm with or without history of <lb/>infection will be promoted; 2) children/young adults in the post-acute arm with a history of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>infection will be promoted at a rate dependent on their likelihood of PASC based on prior <lb/>Long COVID diagnoses, Tier 1 PROMIS global health measure responses [34-36], and symp-<lb/>toms screener survey responses [18, 37] (Table 1); and 3) 40% of children/young adults with-<lb/>out known infection in the post-acute arm, selected at random, will be promoted. In addition <lb/>to promoting children and young adults from Tier 1, children and young adults will also be <lb/>recruited from Long COVID clinics and subspecialty services to achieve the target sample size <lb/>in Tier 2 of 6,000. These children and young adults will complete both Tier 1 and Tier 2 assess-<lb/>ments. See Table 2 for a full description of the promotion algorithm. <lb/>Children and young adults in the acute arm with a history of infection will also complete <lb/>remote assessments at 2, 4, and 8 weeks after their infection onset, with additional in-person <lb/>assessments at 8 weeks. Children and young adults in the acute arm without history of infec-<lb/>tion will complete the same assessments, timed relative to their enrollment date. All ABCD <lb/>youth are eligible to participate in RECOVER Tier 1, and can be referred to a de novo cohort <lb/>site to participate in Tiers 2 and 3, if geographically feasible. <lb/>Tier 3 has the most clinically intensive assessments with longitudinal in-person visits for a <lb/>subset at 12 and 24 months post-enrollment. Tier 3 will include 600 children and young adults <lb/>with history of infection from Tier 2. <lb/>Main categories of data <lb/>Data collected for the de novo and ABCD cohorts are described below (Table 3). <lb/>Surveys include validated surveys with NIH common data elements, as available, informed <lb/>by expert opinion (S5 Table). All are completed using Research Electronic Data Capture <lb/>(REDCap), with the child&apos;s first name coded within surveys to personalize the experience and <lb/>to clarify which child the questions refer to given caregivers can have multiple children <lb/>enrolled. For youth 17 years or younger, the caregiver is the primary respondent. Participants <lb/>18 through 25 years old are the primary respondent. Surveys assess sociodemographic infor-<lb/>mation [38], child birth history [39], special health care needs [39-41], SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>history, related conditions (e.g., MIS-C, POTS or other form of dysautonomia, and Long <lb/>COVID diagnoses), COVID testing and vaccine history, COVID-related symptoms (both <lb/>acute and long-term), COVID health consequences (e.g., diet [42], physical activity [42], sleep <lb/>[42], screen time [42], schooling, parenting [43]) and social determinants of health (e.g., food <lb/>insecurity [44], social support [45]). A list of potential Long COVID symptoms are assessed <lb/>[18, 37] (Table 1), with respondents asked whether a specific problem or symptom is/was pres-<lb/>ent for at least 4 weeks since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic and, for respondents <lb/>with a history of infection, if the symptoms started before or after their infection. <lb/>Clinical assessments are completed at in-person Tier 2 visits across overarching domains of <lb/>physical growth, physical health, neurocognition, and neurobehavioral function (S6 Table). <lb/>Physical health domains include anthropometrics, vital signs, an active standing test measur-<lb/>ing orthostatic blood pressures [46, 47], joint flexibility tests [48], electrocardiograms, and spi-<lb/>rometry. Neurocognitive and neurobehavioral assessments vary by age (Table 4). <lb/>Neurocognitive domains include broad and specific measures of attention, memory, receptive <lb/>and expressive language skills, reading, and sensory function [49-53]. Neurobehavioral <lb/>domains include a broad assessment of behavioral function including anxiety, mood, social <lb/>interactions, aggression, sleep, self-regulatory behaviors, somatic complaints and attention <lb/>concerns [54-61]. Tier 3 assessments follow the same domains, but provide more in-depth <lb/>measurements. The promotion algorithm for Tier 3 is still under development. Physical health <lb/>domains of cardio-pulmonary function are assessed by echocardiogram, cardiopulmonary <lb/>exercise testing, cardiac MRI, pulmonary function tests, and sputum induction. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Potential post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 (PASC) symptoms being Assessed in <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics*. <lb/>Major or Minor <lb/>Classification** <lb/>Symptoms being Assessed <lb/>General symptoms or problems <lb/>Major <lb/>Fever <lb/>Feeling sleepy during the day a <lb/>Fussy or cranky (crying a lot) b <lb/>Low energy or not feeling strong enough to do things a <lb/>Feeling very tired all day long a <lb/>Feeling very tired after walking a <lb/>Not wanting to eat (poor appetite) <lb/>Lost weight or gained less than expected <lb/>Lost height or grew less than expected <lb/>Minor <lb/>Trouble sleeping <lb/>Hot and cold spells (feeling hot or cold for no reason) a <lb/>Sweating more than normal <lb/>Wanting to eat more than normal (increased appetite) <lb/>Wanting to drink liquids more than normal (increased thirst) <lb/>Gained weight more than expected <lb/>Symptoms or problems in the eyes, ears, nose, and throat <lb/>Major <lb/>Light hurts your eyes a <lb/>Change in hearing a <lb/>Ringing in the ears a <lb/>Change in smell a <lb/>Loss of smell a <lb/>Throat hurts (sore throat) a <lb/>Loss of voice (sounding hoarse) <lb/>Problems swallowing <lb/>Change in how things taste c <lb/>Minor <lb/>Eyes look red <lb/>Eyes are watery <lb/>Eyes are dry <lb/>Dark circles or color under the eyes <lb/>Trouble seeing or blurry vision a <lb/>Stuffy nose or runny nose <lb/>Very dry mouth a <lb/>Problems with teeth or gums <lb/>Chapped lips <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving the heart and lungs <lb/>Major <lb/>Dry cough <lb/>Wet cough (brings up mucus) <lb/>Barking cough <lb/>Trouble breathing (breathing too fast) <lb/>Pain when breathing a <lb/>Pain in the chest c <lb/>Feeling like your heart is beating really fast, racing, or pounding (called palpitations) <lb/>when not doing exercise c <lb/>Feeling like your heart is beating really fast when doing exercise c <lb/>Fainting or feeling like you are going to faint (lightheaded) c <lb/>Trouble walking a <lb/>Trouble climbing stairs a <lb/>Trouble running a <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Major or Minor <lb/>Classification** <lb/>Symptoms being Assessed <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving the belly <lb/>Major <lb/>Nausea (feeling like you are going to throw up) <lb/>Throwing up (vomiting) <lb/>Loose stool (diarrhea) <lb/>Pain with peeing (urination) a <lb/>Peeing more than normal (urination more than normal) a <lb/>Minor <lb/>Stomach pains/cramps a <lb/>Trouble pooping/stooling (constipation) <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving the skin, hair, and nails <lb/>Major <lb/>Skin rash <lb/>Changes or problems with nails <lb/>Changes or problems with hair <lb/>Color changes in your skin, such as red, white or purple <lb/>Color changes on the fingers or toes <lb/>Minor <lb/>Itchiness of the skin a <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving the bones and muscles <lb/>Major <lb/>Muscle weakness <lb/>Pains in the joints (like the elbows, knees, ankles) a <lb/>Pain in the back a <lb/>Pain in the neck a <lb/>Minor <lb/>Sore muscles or pain in the muscles a <lb/>Body aches or pains <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving the brain and nerves <lb/>Major <lb/>Headache c <lb/>Feeling dizzy (feeling like the room is spinning) c <lb/>Shakiness or tremors c <lb/>Feeling tingling or &apos;pin-and-needles&apos; in the hands and feet c <lb/>Unable to move part of the body <lb/>Problems with remembering things (memory) a <lb/>Problems with focusing on things (concentration), sometimes called &quot;brain fog&quot; a <lb/>Problems with talking a <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving feelings or behavior <lb/>Major <lb/>Feeling sad or depressed c <lb/>Feeling anxious or on edge c <lb/>Feeling a lot of fear when being away from parent or caregiver b <lb/>Feeling a lot of fear of specific things like spiders or being up high d <lb/>Feeling a lot of fear about being with other children or adults d <lb/>Feeling fear of crowds or being in closed-in spaces c <lb/>Having a sudden intense feeling of fear, like a panic attack e <lb/>Refusing to go to school c <lb/>Seeing, hearing, or feeling that something is there when it is not (hallucinations) c <lb/>Being hyperactive or much more active than other children a <lb/>Refusing to follow rules or doing what they are asked to do a <lb/>Serious breaking of rules like lying, stealing, starting fights, or bullying a <lb/>Having repeating memories, dreams, thoughts, or worries after a traumatic event a <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Gastrointestinal function is assessed using abdominal ultrasound, and neurological function is <lb/>assessed using brain MRI, electroencephalogram, and measures of neurocognitive function <lb/>and psychiatric symptoms. These assessments include higher level measurement of all cogni-<lb/>tive domains (thinking, language processing, memory, attention, and executive functioning) <lb/>[62], visual motor integration and speed [63-65], and a psychiatric symptom battery [66]. <lb/>Biospecimens are collected across all Tiers using kits designed specifically for each visit, <lb/>timepoint, and participant age (Table 5; S6 Table). Tier 1 biospecimens consist of saliva and <lb/>whole blood. Kits are shipped to homes for remote collection. Child and primary caregivers <lb/>provide both saliva and blood; the other biological parent when available provides only saliva. <lb/>Saliva is collected using Oragene devices (OGR-600) and banked for future DNA analysis. <lb/>Whole blood is collected using a TASSO M20 device [67], which collects capillary blood using <lb/>4 volumetric sponges that each hold 17.5μL of blood (70 μL total). One sponge is used for <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 spike and nucleocapsid antibody testing and remaining sponges are banked for <lb/>future use. <lb/>Tier 2 acute biospecimens include saliva (Oragene OGR-600) and whole blood collections. <lb/>All post-acute Tier 2 biospecimens consist of whole blood. The maximum amount of blood <lb/>drawn at a single visit is age dependent. Whole blood is collected using serum separator tube <lb/>(SST) and Ethylenediaminetetraacetic tube acid (EDTA) across all ages above 24 months and <lb/>an additional cell preparation tube (CPT) is included for participants 6 years of age and older. <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Major or Minor <lb/>Classification** <lb/>Symptoms being Assessed <lb/>Minor <lb/>Having a lot of tantrums b <lb/>Holding their breath for a long time when they are afraid or angry b <lb/>Having nightmares <lb/>Screaming in fear while asleep, sometimes called night terrors b <lb/>Aggressive behavior like hitting, biting or kicking b <lb/>Rocking the body back and forth or head banging <lb/>Symptoms or problems involving periods <lb/>Minor <lb/>Getting periods less often f <lb/>Getting periods more often f <lb/>Heavier periods f <lb/>Lighter periods f <lb/>* The following question is used to assess potential PASC symptoms in RECOVER-Pediatrics: &quot;Did your child have <lb/>any of these problems or symptoms lasting for more than 4 weeks that started or got worse since the COVID <lb/>pandemic began in March 2020? These are problems or symptoms that kept happening without stopping or kept <lb/>happening again and again for longer than 4 weeks.&quot; <lb/>** Symptoms were classified as major or minor depending on their severity and presumed likelihood of being <lb/>associated with a COVID-19 infection. <lb/>a Symptoms included for children 3 years or older. <lb/>b Symptom included for children 5 years or younger. <lb/>c Symptom included for children 6 years or older. <lb/>d Symptoms included for children 2 years or older. <lb/>e Symptoms included for children 12 years or older. <lb/>f Symptoms included for those who report having menses. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tier 3 biospecimens consist of whole blood, sputum, swabs (e.g., skin, nasal, oral), urine <lb/>and stool. Collection of Tier 3 biospecimens is limited to children ages 3 years and older (max-<lb/>imum allowable volume is age dependent). <lb/>Statistical methods <lb/>We will estimate the proportion of children and young adults experiencing new onset or wors-<lb/>ening of each symptom (incidence), stratified by age (0-5, 6-12, 13-17, 18-25 years), over <lb/>time. Age stratifications were based on child developmental stages, including early childhood <lb/>(birth to 5 years), school-age (6 to 11 years), adolescence (12 to 17 years) and young adulthood <lb/>(18 to 25 years) [39]. Prevalence within the recruited population will be estimated by calculat-<lb/>ing the point prevalence of each symptom by calculating the proportion of children and young <lb/>adults who are currently experiencing each symptom at each study visit. The excess burden of <lb/>Table 2. Promotion algorithm used in the de novo RECOVER-Pediatrics cohort for selecting children and young adults for the longitudinal follow-up (Tier 2). <lb/>Type of participant <lb/>Subgroup <lb/>Subgroup criteria <lb/>Promotion rate <lb/>to Tier 2 <lb/>&quot;Acute infected&quot;: Children and young adults who <lb/>reported having a COVID infection �30 days prior <lb/>to enrollment <lb/>All <lb/>None <lb/>100% <lb/>&quot;Post-acute infected&quot;: Children and young adults <lb/>who reported having a COVID infection <lb/>&gt;30 days prior to enrollment <lb/>High probability <lb/>of PASC a <lb/>Any of the following: <lb/>1. Prior diagnosis of Long COVID or MIS-C based on study site medical <lb/>record review or referral by a health care provider <lb/>2. Recruitment from a Long COVID clinic <lb/>3. �1 fair/poor responses on the global health PROMIS scale b and �1 <lb/>major or minor symptom reported c <lb/>4. �1 good/fair/poor responses on the global health PROMIS scale b <lb/>and � 1 major symptom reported c <lb/>5. �1 good/fair/poor responses on the global health PROMIS scale b and <lb/>�2 minor symptoms reported c <lb/>100% <lb/>Medium <lb/>probability of <lb/>PASC a <lb/>Any of the following: <lb/>1. �1 good responses on the global health PROMIS scale b and �1 major <lb/>or minor symptom reported c <lb/>2. �1 very good/good/fair/poor responses on the global health PROMIS <lb/>scale b and �1 major symptom reported c <lb/>3. �1 very good/good/fair/poor responses on the global health PROMIS <lb/>scale b and �2 minor symptoms reported c <lb/>50% <lb/>Low probability of <lb/>PASC a <lb/>Does not meet high or medium probability of PASC criteria <lb/>20% <lb/>&quot;Uninfected&quot;: Children or Young adults without a <lb/>known history of a COVID infection <lb/>Acute arm <lb/>At enrollment, 17% of the &quot;uninfected&quot; group were randomly assigned <lb/>to participate in the acute arm of the study. <lb/>100% <lb/>Post-acute arm <lb/>At enrollment, 83% of the &quot;uninfected&quot; group were randomly assigned <lb/>to participare in the post-acute arm of the study. 40% of this group will <lb/>be randomly assigned to participate in Tier 2 <lb/>40% <lb/>a Responses to the PROMIS Global Health Scales and the presence of major and minor symptoms are used to categorize participants who are post-acute infected as high, <lb/>medium, or low probability of PASC. <lb/>b The PROMIS Global Health Scales are self-reported or caregiver-reported measures of overall, physical, and mental health for young adults and children, respectively <lb/>[34-36]. The three questions from the caregiver-reported version that are used in the algorithm, include: 1) &quot;In general, would you say your child&apos;s health is?; 2) &quot;In <lb/>general, how would you rate your child&apos;s physical health?&quot;; and 3) &quot;In general, how would you rate your child&apos;s mental health, including mood and ability to think?&quot; <lb/>Responses include: Excellent, Very Good, Good, Fair, or Poor. <lb/>c <lb/>A list of all major and minor symptoms, reported at the enrollment visit as part of the symptom screener, is provided in the Table 1 [18, 37]. Not all symptoms are <lb/>asked of all participants, as many are age-specific (e.g., fewer symptoms assessed for younger children) and sex-specific (e.g., menses related symptoms). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. Summary of study assessments in the de novo RECOVER-Pediatrics cohort a . <lb/>BL <lb/>. . . <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>. . . <lb/>2 to 6 <lb/>12 <lb/>24 <lb/>36 <lb/>48 <lb/>(weeks) <lb/>(months) <lb/>Tier 1 and Tier 2 Assessments <lb/>BL <lb/>Acute phase <lb/>Post-acute phase <lb/>Identity <lb/>Demographics <lb/>Child Birth History <lb/>Child Current Health Status <lb/>Special Health Care Needs Screener <lb/>PROMIS Global Health <lb/>First COVID Infection History <lb/>Current COVID Infection History <lb/>Weekly COVID Infection History <lb/>COVID Infection History (Follow-up) <lb/>Related Conditions (MIS-C, POTS) <lb/>COVID Testing History <lb/>COVID Family Infection <lb/>COVID Symptoms <lb/>COMPASS-31 <lb/>COVID Vaccine History <lb/>COVID Health Consequences <lb/>Social Determinants of Health <lb/>Child Wellbeing <lb/>Tier 1 Biospecimen <lb/>Anthropometry &amp; Vital Signs <lb/>Electrocardiogram <lb/>Spirometry <lb/>Pulse Oximetry <lb/>Tier 2 Acute Biospecimens <lb/>10 Minute Active Standing Test (Orthostatic BP) <lb/>Joint Flexibility (Beighton Scale) <lb/>Neurocognitive Development (e.g., NIH Toolbox) <lb/>Emotional/Mental Health <lb/>Post-Acute Tier 2 Biospecimens <lb/>Tier 3 Assessments <lb/>Echocardiogram <lb/>Cardiac MRI <lb/>Pulmonary Function Tests (PFTs) <lb/>Lung Microbiome (Sputum Induction) <lb/>Cardiopulmonary Exercise Testing <lb/>Abdominal Ultrasound <lb/>Brain MRI <lb/>Brain EEG <lb/>Neurocognitive Testing <lb/>Tier 3 Biospecimens <lb/>a <lb/>Blue = Questionnaires; Red = Clinical Assessments; Yellow = Biospecimen Collection <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>each symptom due to infection will be assessed by calculating differences in incidence and <lb/>prevalence between children and young adults with and without an infection history. Odds <lb/>ratios and relative risks for the association between infection and onset of each symptom will <lb/>also be calculated, adjusting for sex in each age strata. Logistic regression and poisson regres-<lb/>sion with robust standard errors will be used in these analyses [68]. <lb/>Table 4. Neurocognitive, Neurobehavioral, Well-Being and mental health measures by age in Tiers 2 and 3 for the de novo RECOVER-Pediatrics cohort. <lb/>Study <lb/>Tier <lb/>Neurocognitive and Developmental Assessments <lb/>Neurobehavioral, Well-Being and Mental Health Assessments <lb/>Infancy and Toddlerhood: Birth through 2 years old <lb/>Tier 2 <lb/>Ages and Stages Questionnaire-3rd Edition (ASQ-3) [49-51] <lb/>Modified Checklist for Autism in Toddlers Revised with Follow up <lb/>(MCHAT-RF) [52] <lb/>Ages and Stages Questionnaires: Social-Emotional, 2nd Edition (ASQ:SE-2) [54] <lb/>Child Behavior Checklist [55] <lb/>Tier 3 <lb/>N/A <lb/>N/A <lb/>Preschool-Age: 3 years old through 5 years old <lb/>Tier 2 <lb/>Ages and Stages Questionnaire-3rd Edition (ASQ-3) [49-51] <lb/>NIH Toolbox Cognitive Measures [53] <lb/>Ages and Stages Questionnaires: Social-Emotional, 2nd Edition (ASQ:SE-2) [54] <lb/>Child Behavior Checklist [55] <lb/>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS 1 ) Parent <lb/>Proxy Anger Scale [56] <lb/>PROMIS 1 Parent Proxy Psychological Stress Experiences Scale [57] <lb/>PROMIS 1 Parent Proxy Positive Affect Scale [58] <lb/>Tier 3 <lb/>Cognitive: Woodcock Johnson Cognitive Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Language: Woodcock-Johnson Oral Language Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Verbal Memory: Woodcock Johnson subtests [62] <lb/>Visual Memory: Wide Range Assessment of Memory and Learning <lb/>[63] <lb/>Visual-Motor Drawing: Beery Buktenica [64] <lb/>Visual Motor Speed: Purdue Pegboard [65] <lb/>Pre-Academics: Woodcock-Johnson Achievement Battery subtests <lb/>[62] <lb/>Kiddie SADS computer completed by caregiver [66] <lb/>School-age and Adolescence: 6 years old through 17 years old <lb/>Tier 2 <lb/>NIH Toolbox Cognitive Measures [53] <lb/>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS 1 ) Parent <lb/>Proxy Anger Scale [56] <lb/>PROMIS 1 Parent Proxy Psychological Stress Experiences Scale [57] <lb/>PROMIS 1 Parent Proxy Positive Affect Scale [58] <lb/>Revised Children&apos;s Anxiety and Depression Scale (RCADS-25) [59] <lb/>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (Hyperactivity/Inattention and Conduct <lb/>Problems Subscales) [60] <lb/>Tier 3 <lb/>Cognitive: Woodcock Johnson Cognitive Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Language: Woodcock-Johnson Oral Language Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Verbal Memory: Woodcock Johnson subtests [62] <lb/>Visual Memory: Wide Range Assessment of Memory and Learning <lb/>[63] <lb/>Visual-Motor Drawing: Beery Buktenica [64] <lb/>Visual Motor Speed: Purdue Pegboard [65] <lb/>Pre-Academics: Woodcock-Johnson Achievement Battery subtests <lb/>[62] <lb/>Kiddie SADS computer completed by caregiver [66] <lb/>Young Adults: 18 years through 25 years old <lb/>Tier 2 <lb/>NIH Toolbox Cognitive Measures [53] <lb/>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS 1 ) Parent <lb/>Proxy Anger Scale [56] <lb/>PROMIS 1 Parent Proxy Psychological Stress Experiences Scale [57] <lb/>Achenbach Adult Self Report [61] <lb/>Tier 3 <lb/>Cognitive: Woodcock Johnson Cognitive Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Language: Woodcock-Johnson Oral Language Battery subtests [62] <lb/>Verbal Memory: Woodcock Johnson subtests [62] <lb/>Visual Memory: Wide Range Assessment of Memory and Learning <lb/>[63] <lb/>Visual-Motor Drawing: Beery Buktenica [64] <lb/>Visual Motor Speed: Purdue Pegboard [65] <lb/>SADS Structured Psychiatric Interview [66] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 5. Biospecimen collection and processing summary. <lb/>Participant Samples <lb/>Collected For <lb/>Collected Specimen <lb/>Quantity a Biobanked Specimen Type <lb/>Number of Aliquots <lb/>Aliquot <lb/>Volume <lb/>Tier 1 <lb/>Pediatric Participant; <lb/>Primary Caregiver; <lb/>Additional Biologic <lb/>Parent <lb/>OGR-600 -Saliva <lb/>1 x 2mL <lb/>Saliva <lb/>NA <lb/>2 mL <lb/>Pediatric Participant; <lb/>Primary Caregiver <lb/>TASSO M20 -Capillary Blood <lb/>1 x 70 μL <lb/>Blood <lb/>4 x volumetric sponges <lb/>17.5 μL <lb/>Tier 2 Acute <lb/>All Age Groups over 24 <lb/>months <lb/>Oragene 600 -Saliva <lb/>1 x 2mL <lb/>Saliva <lb/>N/A <lb/>2 mL <lb/>All Age Groups over 24 <lb/>months <lb/>Serum Separator Tube (SST)-Whole Blood b <lb/>1 x 5mL <lb/>Serum <lb/>5 <lb/>500 μL <lb/>All Age Groups over 24 <lb/>months <lb/>EDTA-Whole Blood c <lb/>1 x 10mL • Plasma <lb/>• White Blood Cells <lb/>(WBCs) <lb/>• Red Blood Cells (RBCs) <lb/>• 13 x Plasma <lb/>• 1 x WBC <lb/>• 3 x RBCs <lb/>• 5 x 200 μL <lb/>Plasma <lb/>(Rutgers) <lb/>• 8 x 500 μL <lb/>Plasma (PBC) <lb/>• WBC-1 mL <lb/>• RBCs-1 mL <lb/>Ages 6-25 yrs. <lb/>Sodium Citrate Cell Preservation Tube <lb/>(CPT)-Whole Blood d <lb/>2 x 4 mL • Peripheral Blood <lb/>Mononuclear Cells <lb/>(PBMCs) <lb/>~3 x PBMCs (target cell <lb/>count minimum 5 million <lb/>cells/mL) <lb/>1 mL <lb/>Tier 2 Post Acute <lb/>Ages 24mo -under 6 <lb/>years (all post-acute visits) <lb/>Serum Separator Tube (SST)-Whole Blood b <lb/>1 x 5mL <lb/>Serum <lb/>5 <lb/>• 500 μL <lb/>Ages 6-25 yrs <lb/>(6 month visit only) <lb/>Serum Separator Tube (SST)-Whole Blood b <lb/>2 x 5mL <lb/>Serum <lb/>3 <lb/>• 1 x 1 mL-<lb/>ARUP <lb/>• 1 x 2 mL-<lb/>ARUP <lb/>• 1 x 1.5 mL-<lb/>PBC <lb/>• 6 x 200 μL for <lb/>Rutgers and/or <lb/>• 3 x 500 μL for <lb/>PBC <lb/>Ages 6-9 yrs. <lb/>Sodium Citrate Cell Preservation Tube <lb/>(CPT)-Whole Blood d <lb/>2 x 4 mL Peripheral Blood <lb/>Mononuclear Cells <lb/>(PBMCs) <lb/>8 x PBMCs (target cell count <lb/>minimum 5 million cells/mL) <lb/>1 mL <lb/>Ages 10-25 yrs. <lb/>Sodium Citrate Cell Preservation Tube <lb/>(CPT)-Whole Blood d <lb/>4 x 4 mL Peripheral Blood <lb/>Mononuclear Cells <lb/>(PBMCs) <lb/>16 x PBMCs (target cell <lb/>count minimum 5 million <lb/>cells/mL) <lb/>1 mL <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>EXCEPT <lb/>6-month Post Acute visit <lb/>for age 6-9 yrs <lb/>EDTA-Whole Blood c <lb/>1 x 10mL • Plasma <lb/>• White Blood Cells <lb/>(WBCs) <lb/>• Red Blood Cells (RBCs) <lb/>• 13 x Plasma <lb/>• 1 x WBC <lb/>• 3 x RBCs <lb/>• 5 x 200μL <lb/>Plasma <lb/>(Rutgers) <lb/>• 8 x 500μL <lb/>Plasma (PBC) <lb/>• WBC-1mL <lb/>• RBCs-1 mL <lb/>Tier 3 e <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>Serum Separator Tube (SST)-Whole Blood b <lb/>TBD <lb/>• Serum <lb/>• TBD <lb/>• TBD <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>A preliminary working definition of PASC will be informed by using variable selection <lb/>methods to identify which symptoms best differentiate children and young adults with and <lb/>without an infection, following the methodology previously applied to develop a working defi-<lb/>nition of PASC in the RECOVER adult cohort [69]. Data from the Tier 1 visit will primarily be <lb/>used. The estimated associations obtained from regression models will be used to define a <lb/>PASC score, with a cutoff for PASC defined based on clinical expertise while ensuring that the <lb/>rate of those with no history of infection who are diagnosed as having PASC is reasonably low. <lb/>This preliminary symptom-based working definition is intended for research purposes and <lb/>not clinical diagnosis. It will be modified and augmented by clinical and subclinical findings as <lb/>they become available. The working definition of PASC that is developed will also be validated <lb/>in RECOVER participants who have linked EHR data against other definitions derived from <lb/>EHR-based cohorts [70]. While the working definition of PASC will be initially developed <lb/>within each age strata, depending on the overlap of key symptoms that are identified that <lb/>define PASC, some age groups may be aggregated in the interest of developing a more unified <lb/>definition of PASC. To identify PASC phenotypes among children and young adults who are <lb/>classified as having PASC defined by symptom patterns, we will use unsupervised learning <lb/>methods to discover symptom clusters within each age strata (e.g., agglomerative hierarchical <lb/>clustering [71] and consensus clustering [72]) to define PASC sub-phenotypes. <lb/>With this definition of PASC, we will conduct regression analyses to evaluate whether the <lb/>risk of PASC and PASC sub-types differs by multiple factors, including demographic, clinical, <lb/>and caregiver characteristics, social determinants of health, SARS-CoV-2 infection and immu-<lb/>nization history, symptom severity during the acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection, and <lb/>Table 5. (Continued) <lb/>Participant Samples <lb/>Collected For <lb/>Collected Specimen <lb/>Quantity a Biobanked Specimen Type <lb/>Number of Aliquots <lb/>Aliquot <lb/>Volume <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>EDTA-Whole Blood c <lb/>TBD <lb/>• Plasma <lb/>• White Blood Cells <lb/>(WBCs) <lb/>• Red Blood Cells (RBCs) <lb/>• TBD <lb/>• TBD <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>Lithium Heparin-Whole Blood <lb/>TBD <lb/>• Plasma <lb/>• TBD <lb/>• TBD <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>Red Top (No Additive)-Whole Blood <lb/>TBD <lb/>• Serum <lb/>• TBD <lb/>• TBD <lb/>All Age Groups <lb/>Other Biospecimens for Microbiome <lb/>Analysis (e.g. sputum, swaps (skin, nasal, <lb/>oral), urine, stool) <lb/>TBD <lb/>• Sputum <lb/>• Swabs <lb/>• Urine <lb/>• Stool <lb/>• TBD <lb/>• TBD <lb/>a <lb/>Sample volumes are age dependent: (newborn to under 6 years: maximum draw of 2 mL per kg of body weight; 6 to under 10 years: 25 mL; greater than 10 years old: 38 <lb/>mL) <lb/>b SST tube is collected and within 4 hours of collection the SST tube is centrifuged, serum is aliquoted and frozen locally at collection sites. Serum aliquots are batch <lb/>shipped frozen on dry ice in monthly intervals and are banked for future research. <lb/>c <lb/>The EDTA tube is collected for all age groups and is processed for plasma, WBC, and RBC aliquots. A plasma aliquot is sent out for central testing. The other EDTA <lb/>aliquot derivatives are frozen and banked for future research. <lb/>d <lb/>The CPT tubes are only collected for age groups 6-25 years. The CPT tubes are centrifuged at collection sites and sent on ice packs day of collection to the PBC. Once <lb/>arrived at the PBC, the CPT tubes are processed. A maximum of 8 x 1 mL PBMC aliquots (minimum of 5 million cells/mL) are derived. PBMC aliquots are stored in <lb/>liquid nitrogen and banked for future research. <lb/>e <lb/>Tier 3 biospecimen parameters are currently under development, but will involve collection of whole blood for clinical chemistry and biobanking and the collection <lb/>and banking of biospecimens for microbiome analysis. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>therapeutic exposures. Logistic and Poisson regression will be used to evaluate the association <lb/>(i.e., odds ratios and risk ratios) between pre-infection factors and PASC as a binary outcome, <lb/>and multinomial regression will be used when PASC sub-types are used as categorical out-<lb/>comes. Among participants in Tier 2 who develop PASC, we will use time-to-event analyses <lb/>(i.e., Cox proportional hazards regression) to identify factors that influence time to recovery <lb/>from PASC. To investigate biomarkers related to PASC, clinical laboratory assessments will be <lb/>compared between children and young adults who do and do not develop PASC. Mediation <lb/>analyses will also be used to study the pathways by which SARS-CoV-2 infection leads to the <lb/>development of PASC. Since the trajectory of how PASC manifests may be affected by the <lb/>presence of pre-existing conditions, we will study separately the pathophysiology of PASC in <lb/>children and young adults with and without such conditions, when appropriate. <lb/>The study aims cover a wide range of scientific questions, but not all analyses will involve <lb/>hypothesis testing. For instance, defining PASC does not require hypothesis testing, but evalu-<lb/>ating whether the definition of or rates of PASC differ between age groups does. When multi-<lb/>ple comparisons are made across age groups or other defined strata, or when different <lb/>exposures and outcomes are assessed within the same subgroups, multiplicity adjustments for <lb/>testing of non-exploratory hypotheses will be performed using the Hochberg procedure, in <lb/>which tests of significance are performed in order of decreasing p-value with increasingly <lb/>stringent thresholds [73]. This approach has been found to sacrifice less power in observational <lb/>studies with correlated outcomes compared to the Bonferroni and other standard approaches <lb/>for addressing multiplicity [74]. <lb/>Potential sources of missing data include item nonresponse and attrition. Multiple imputation <lb/>by chained equations will be the primary approach used to handle item nonresponse [75]. Sensi-<lb/>tivity analyses will include adjustments for potentially missing not at random data (i.e., informa-<lb/>tive missingness) using pattern mixture models, which permit the distribution of missing <lb/>variables to differ between observed and unobserved values. Attrition, or missed visits, in the lon-<lb/>gitudinal phase of the study (Tier 2) will be addressed depending on the affected analysis. For <lb/>time-to-event modeling, attrition induces censoring, which may not be independent if partici-<lb/>pants drop out of the study in a systematic fashion (i.e., participants with worse symptom trajecto-<lb/>ries may be less likely to continue to participate in the study). Inverse probability of censoring <lb/>weights will be used to address dependent censoring in this context [76]. For analyses with <lb/>repeated measures, multiple imputation alongside likelihood-based methods, which are robust to <lb/>the missing at random assumption, [77] will be used to handle missing data, with pattern mixture <lb/>models used to perform sensitivity analyses for informatively missing data as appropriate [78]. <lb/>Statistical analyses will primarily be conducted in R and SAS, though the statistical packages <lb/>used by individual investigators for future analyses beyond those described in this manuscript <lb/>will vary. <lb/>Power calculations <lb/>Power calculations for the de novo cohort were performed prior to recruitment using a type 1 <lb/>error rate of 0.01 as a preliminary multiplicity adjustment. The actual statistical approach for <lb/>addressing multiplicity will differ depending on the analysis and will involve more sophisti-<lb/>cated methods (see Statistical methods), but these are not amenable to most power calcula-<lb/>tions. With 4,800 infected and 1,200 uninfected children and young adults from both acute <lb/>and post-acute arms in Tier 1, as well as 10,000 children ages 12-17 from the ABCD cohort <lb/>(assuming 3,500 are infected and 6,500 are uninfected), assuming the risk of a given symptom <lb/>in the uninfected group is 10%, we have 90% power to detect a difference as small as 1.9% in <lb/>the frequency of that symptom between groups. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<body>In Tier 2, given the sampling and promotion framework described in Timing of Study <lb/>Assessments, our sample with longitudinal follow-up will be skewed towards those who are <lb/>more likely to have PASC. Following development of a definition of PASC, we consider the <lb/>scenario in which we assume that of the 5,400 children and young adults with a history of <lb/>infection in Tier 2, 3,600 meet PASC criteria and 1,800 do not. For a hypothetical risk factor <lb/>with 50% prevalence in the PASC-group, we have 90% power to detect an odds ratio as small <lb/>as 1.25 for the odds of PASC for those with the risk factor versus those without. For a factor <lb/>with 25% prevalence in the PASC-negative group, the minimum detectable odds ratio is 1.28. <lb/>In our Tier 3 sample of 600 children and young adults with history of infection (which includes <lb/>additional data on biomarkers), assuming the sample has 400 with PASC and 200 without <lb/>PASC, for a marker with 10% prevalence in the PASC-group, we have 90% power to detect an <lb/>odds ratio as small as 2.60 for PASC. <lb/>Given that many analyses will be stratified by age group, we calculate minimum detectable <lb/>effect sizes overall and within each age stratum in S7 Table. Estimates of the distribution of <lb/>ages are based on early enrollment data, with 26% of main cohort participants in the age 0-5 <lb/>years category, 28% in ages 6-11 years, 26% in ages 12-17 years, and 20% in ages 18-25 years. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The overall goal of RECOVER-Pediatrics is to improve our understanding of recovery after <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 infection, with a focus on the prevalence, natural history, and pathogenesis of <lb/>PASC in children and young adults. Successful completion should lead to formal characteriza-<lb/>tion of pediatric PASC as its own syndrome. This is essential to develop diagnostic, treatment, <lb/>and preventive strategies tailored to children&apos;s unique physiology. <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics is well positioned to ascertain the epidemiology, four-year clinical <lb/>course, and sociodemographic contributions to pediatric PASC, with rich data and biosamples <lb/>available to readily test further mechanistic hypotheses, establish biomarkers, and provide <lb/>insights into potential therapies. The meta-cohort is designed to provide details that are not <lb/>available in other large epidemiologic or electronic health records queries, including a <lb/>dynamic study design that can be flexible and responsive as new variants arise, and as our <lb/>understanding of the long-term effects of SARS-CoV-2 evolves. RECOVER-Pediatrics was <lb/>designed to include a wide range of ages, and diverse socioeconomic, racial, ethnic and geo-<lb/>graphic populations to ensure that findings are generalizable, and provide equitable benefit for <lb/>all. <lb/>The generation-defining nature of the COVID-19 pandemic will impact the life course of <lb/>children in ways that we have yet to fully understand. The unprecedented scope of RECO-<lb/>VER-Pediatrics sets the stage for not only characterizing a new disorder that will impact chil-<lb/>dren for years to come, but also for identifying and deploying solutions through its <lb/>collaborations with investigators and communities across the country. <lb/>RECOVER-Pediatrics is expected to gather a rich data set that can be used to develop treat-<lb/>ments for persons with Long COVID and provide guidelines for how to respond more quickly <lb/>to prevent, reduce the consequences, and treat complications of future coronavirus outbreaks <lb/>which are likely to emerge. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. SPIRIT clinical trials checklist. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S1 Table. Hubs and enrolling sites. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. Inclusion and exclusion criteria. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Table. Inclusion into analytic groups. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S4 Table. World Health Organization (WHO) criteria. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S5 Table. Survey topics in tiers 1 and 2 questionnaires. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Table. Clinical and laboratory assessments across the tiers in the de novo RECOVER-<lb/>Pediatrics cohort. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S7 Table. Power calculations to determine minimum detectable effect sizes, stratified by <lb/>age group. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Appendix. RECOVER-Pediatrics consortium members. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Protocol. RECOVER-Pediatrics protocol. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S6 Text. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S5 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S6 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S7 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Data. <lb/>(ZIP) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We would like to thank the National Community Engagement Group (NCEG), all patient, <lb/>caregiver and community representatives, and all the participants enrolled in the RECOVER <lb/>initiative. <lb/>Disclaimer: Authorship has been determined according to ICMJE recommendations. The <lb/>content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official <lb/>views of the RECOVER program, the NIH or other funders. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Erika B. Rosenzweig, Lori B. Chib-<lb/>nik, Valerie J. Flaherman, Andrea S. Foulkes, Richard Gallagher, Terry L. Jernigan, Eliza-<lb/>beth W. Karlson, Stuart D. Katz, Patricia A. Kinser, Lawrence C. Kleinman, Michelle F. <lb/>Lamendola-Essel, Joshua D. Milner, Sindhu Mohandas, Jane W. Newburger, Kyung E. <lb/>Rhee, Melissa S. Stockwell, Kelan G. Tantisira, Moriah E. Thomason, David Warburton, <lb/>John C. Wood, Andrew M. Atz, Robin L. Aupperle, Fiona C. Baker, Deanna M. Barch, <lb/>Hu ¨lya Bu ¨ku ¨lmez, Rebecca G. Clifton, Viren D&apos;Sa, E. Vincent S. Faustino, Laura Hobart-<lb/>Porter, Matthew Huentelman, Vanessa L. Jacoby, David C. Kaelber, Alan L. Mendelsohn, <lb/>Torri D. Metz, Michael C. Neale, Matthew E. Oster, Hengameh Raissy, Jacqueline Szmusz-<lb/>kovicz, William T. Zempsky. <lb/>Data curation: Tanayott Thaweethai, James Chan, Andrea S. Foulkes, Stuart D. Katz, Shifa <lb/>Ahmed, Arielle Baskin-Sommers, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Walter Dehority, John J. Foxe, <lb/>Kevin M. Gray, Ashraf S. Harahsheh, Daniel S. Hsia, Joanna Jacobus, Tyler J. Kasmarcak, <lb/>Angela R. Laird, Peter Paul C. Lim, Brian W. McCrindle, Sheila M. Nolan, Harrison T. <lb/>Reeder, Mark W. Russell, Alice I. Sato, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Maria M. Talavera-Barber, <lb/>Ronald J. Teufel, II, Emily Zimmerman. <lb/>Formal analysis: James Chan, Lori B. Chibnik, David Warburton, Mark W. Russell. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Amy J. Elliott, Andrea S. Foulkes, <lb/>Terry L. Jernigan, Stuart D. Katz, Lawrence C. Kleinman, Kyung E. Rhee, Melissa S. Stock-<lb/>well, David Warburton, John C. Wood, Robin L. Aupperle, Fiona C. Baker, Duncan B. <lb/>Clark, Alexander G. Fiks, John J. Foxe, Dylan G. Gee, Christina M. Hester, Matthew Huen-<lb/>telman, Krista M. Lisdahl, Russell J. McCulloh, Torri D. Metz, Eva M. Mu ¨ller-Oehring, <lb/>Michael C. Neale, Alice I. Sato, Rangaraj Selvarangan, Emily Zimmerman. <lb/>Investigation: Rachel S. Gross, Erika B. Rosenzweig, Valerie J. Flaherman, Lawrence C. Klein-<lb/>man, Sindhu Mohandas, Kyung E. Rhee, Melissa S. Stockwell, Kelan G. Tantisira, Dongn-<lb/>gan T. Truong, David Warburton, John C. Wood, Judy L. Aschner, Andrew M. Atz, <lb/>Venkataraman Balaraman, Dithi Banerjee, Deanna M. Barch, Amanda L. Bogie, Elliott <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Bueler, Hu ¨lya Bu ¨ku ¨lmez, B. J. Casey, Linda Chang, Lesley Cottrell, Viren D&apos;Sa, Walter <lb/>Dehority, Kirsten B. Dummer, Matthew D. Elias, E. Vincent S. Faustino, Alexander G. Fiks, <lb/>Daniel Forsha, John J. Foxe, Sunanda Gaur, Dylan G. Gee, Kevin M. Gray, Mary M. Heit-<lb/>zeg, Christina M. Hester, Sophia Hill, Travis K. F. Hong, Carol R. Horowitz, Daniel S. Hsia, <lb/>Katherine Irby, Joanna Jacobus, Vanessa L. Jacoby, David C. Kaelber, Matthew J. Kluko, <lb/>Jessica S. Kosut, Jeremy Landeo-Gutierrez, Sean M. Lang, Peter Paul C. Lim, Krista M. Lis-<lb/>dahl, Russell J. McCulloh, Torri D. Metz, Manette Ness-Cochinwala, Matthew E. Oster, R. <lb/>Mark Payne, Hengameh Raissy, Suchitra Rao, Mark W. Russell, Arash A. Sabati, Alice I. <lb/>Sato, Rangaraj Selvarangan, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Jacqueline Szmuszkovicz, Maria M. Tala-<lb/>vera-Barber, Deepika Thacker, Alan Werzberger, H. Shonna Yin, William T. Zempsky, <lb/>Emily Zimmerman. <lb/>Methodology: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Erika B. Rosenzweig, Lori B. Chibnik, <lb/>Amy J. Elliott, Valerie J. Flaherman, Andrea S. Foulkes, Richard Gallagher, Elizabeth W. <lb/>Karlson, Stuart D. Katz, Patricia A. Kinser, Lawrence C. Kleinman, Michelle F. Lamendola-<lb/>Essel, Joshua D. Milner, Sindhu Mohandas, Jane W. Newburger, Kyung E. Rhee, Amy L. <lb/>Salisbury, Cheryl R. Stein, Melissa S. Stockwell, Moriah E. Thomason, David Warburton, <lb/>Shifa Ahmed, Robin L. Aupperle, Venkataraman Balaraman, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Andrew <lb/>C. Heath, Carol R. Horowitz, Matthew Huentelman, Joanna Jacobus, Vanessa L. Jacoby, <lb/>Krista M. Lisdahl, Alan L. Mendelsohn, Torri D. Metz, Erica R. Nahin, Michael C. Neale, <lb/>Carlos R. Oliveira, Hengameh Raissy, Isabelle G. Randall, Harrison T. Reeder, Johana M. <lb/>Rosas, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Michelle D. Stevenson, Maria M. Talavera-Barber, Ronald J. <lb/>Teufel, II, Megan R. Warner, Jordan C. Weyer, H. Shonna Yin, William T. Zempsky. <lb/>Project administration: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Erika B. Rosenzweig, James <lb/>Chan, Mine S. Cicek, Andrea S. Foulkes, Terry L. Jernigan, Stuart D. Katz, Lawrence C. <lb/>Kleinman, Michelle F. Lamendola-Essel, Praveen C. Mudumbi, Kyung E. Rhee, Melissa S. <lb/>Stockwell, David Warburton, John C. Wood, Shifa Ahmed, Akram N. Alshawabkeh, Brett <lb/>R. Anderson, Andrew M. Atz, Robin L. Aupperle, Fiona C. Baker, Dithi Banerjee, Arielle <lb/>Baskin-Sommers, Sultana Bhuiyan, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Amanda L. Bogie, Natalie C. <lb/>Buchbinder, Elliott Bueler, Hu ¨lya Bu ¨ku ¨lmez, Linda Chang, Duncan B. Clark, Rebecca G. <lb/>Clifton, Katharine N. Clouser, Walter Dehority, Shari Esquenazi-Karonika, Danielle N. <lb/>Evans, John J. Foxe, Naomi P. Friedman, Dylan G. Gee, Kevin M. Gray, Andrew C. Heath, <lb/>Christina M. Hester, Sophia Hill, Daniel S. Hsia, Kathy D. Hummel, Katherine Irby, Joanna <lb/>Jacobus, David C. Kaelber, Christine L. Larson, Krista M. Lisdahl, Russell J. McCulloh, <lb/>Torri D. Metz, Eva M. Mu ¨ller-Oehring, R. Mark Payne, Hengameh Raissy, Harrison T. <lb/>Reeder, Alice I. Sato, Divya Shakti, Kavita Sharma, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Michelle D. Ste-<lb/>venson, Ronald J. Teufel, II, Mmekom M. Udosen, Megan R. Warner, Sara E. Watson, Jor-<lb/>dan C. Weyer, Marion J. Wood, H. Shonna Yin. <lb/>Resources: Tanayott Thaweethai, Mine S. Cicek, Andrea S. Foulkes, Stuart D. Katz, Sindhu <lb/>Mohandas, Shifa Ahmed, Akram N. Alshawabkeh, Judy L. Aschner, Arielle Baskin-Som-<lb/>mers, Sultana Bhuiyan, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Mirella Dapretto, Walter Dehority, Danielle <lb/>N. Evans, Andrew C. Heath, Mary M. Heitzeg, Matthew Huentelman, Joanna Jacobus, <lb/>David C. Kaelber, Russell J. McCulloh, Manette Ness-Cochinwala, Harrison T. Reeder, <lb/>Mark W. Russell, Michael S. Schechter, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Mmekom M. Udosen, H. <lb/>Shonna Yin, Emily Zimmerman. <lb/>Software: Tanayott Thaweethai, James Chan, Andrea S. Foulkes, Shifa Ahmed, Marie-Abele <lb/>C. Bind, Harrison T. Reeder. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Supervision: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Valerie J. Flaherman, Andrea S. Foulkes, <lb/>Terry L. Jernigan, Stuart D. Katz, Michelle F. Lamendola-Essel, Kyung E. Rhee, Melissa S. <lb/>Stockwell, Kelan G. Tantisira, David Warburton, Brett R. Anderson, Andrew M. Atz, Robin <lb/>L. Aupperle, Dithi Banerjee, Arielle Baskin-Sommers, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Amanda L. <lb/>Bogie, Elliott Bueler, Hu ¨lya Bu ¨ku ¨lmez, Linda Chang, Duncan B. Clark, Lesley Cottrell, Mir-<lb/>ella Dapretto, Walter Dehority, Danielle N. Evans, John J. Foxe, Dylan G. Gee, Ashraf S. <lb/>Harahsheh, Mary M. Heitzeg, Christina M. Hester, Sophia Hill, Daniel S. Hsia, Kathy D. <lb/>Hummel, Katherine Irby, Joanna Jacobus, Vanessa L. Jacoby, David C. Kaelber, Krista M. <lb/>Lisdahl, Russell J. McCulloh, Eva M. Mu ¨ller-Oehring, Manette Ness-Cochinwala, Suchitra <lb/>Rao, Harrison T. Reeder, Mark W. Russell, Yamuna Sanil, Michael S. Schechter, Rangaraj <lb/>Selvarangan, Divya Shakti, Lindsay M. Squeglia, Michelle D. Stevenson, Maria M. Talavera-<lb/>Barber, Ronald J. Teufel, II, Mmekom M. Udosen, Megan R. Warner, Sara E. Watson, Alan <lb/>Werzberger, Jordan C. Weyer, H. Shonna Yin. <lb/>Validation: James Chan, Walter Dehority, Ashraf S. Harahsheh, Suchitra Rao, Alice I. Sato. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Erika B. Rosenzweig, Lori B. <lb/>Chibnik, Mine S. Cicek, Richard Gallagher, Patricia A. Kinser, Lawrence C. Kleinman, <lb/>Michelle F. Lamendola-Essel, Sindhu Mohandas, Praveen C. Mudumbi, Kyung E. Rhee, <lb/>Cheryl R. Stein, Melissa S. Stockwell, Kelan G. Tantisira, Moriah E. Thomason, David War-<lb/>burton, Torri D. Metz, Hengameh Raissy, Benard P. Dreyer. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Rachel S. Gross, Tanayott Thaweethai, Erika B. Rosenzweig, <lb/>James Chan, Lori B. Chibnik, Mine S. Cicek, Amy J. Elliott, Valerie J. Flaherman, Andrea S. <lb/>Foulkes, Margot Gage Witvliet, Richard Gallagher, Maria Laura Gennaro, Terry L. Jerni-<lb/>gan, Elizabeth W. Karlson, Stuart D. Katz, Patricia A. Kinser, Lawrence C. Kleinman, <lb/>Michelle F. Lamendola-Essel, Sindhu Mohandas, Praveen C. Mudumbi, Jane W. Newbur-<lb/>ger, Kyung E. Rhee, Amy L. Salisbury, Jessica N. Snowden, Cheryl R. Stein, Melissa S. <lb/>Stockwell, Kelan G. Tantisira, Moriah E. Thomason, David Warburton, John C. Wood, <lb/>Shifa Ahmed, Almary Akerlundh, Akram N. Alshawabkeh, Brett R. Anderson, Judy L. <lb/>Aschner, Andrew M. Atz, Robin L. Aupperle, Fiona C. Baker, Dithi Banerjee, Deanna M. <lb/>Barch, Marie-Abele C. Bind, Tamara Bradford, Linda Chang, Maryanne Chrisant, Rebecca <lb/>G. Clifton, Katharine N. Clouser, Lesley Cottrell, Kelly Cowan, Viren D&apos;Sa, Soham Das-<lb/>gupta, Walter Dehority, Audrey Dionne, Matthew D. Elias, Shari Esquenazi-Karonika, E. <lb/>Vincent S. Faustino, Alexander G. Fiks, Daniel Forsha, John J. Foxe, Greta Fry, Sunanda <lb/>Gaur, Dylan G. Gee, Kevin M. Gray, Stephanie Handler, Keren Hasbani, Camden Hebson, <lb/>Mary M. Heitzeg, Christina M. Hester, Laura Hobart-Porter, Carol R. Horowitz, Daniel S. <lb/>Hsia, Kathy D. Hummel, Katherine Irby, Vanessa L. Jacoby, Pei-Ni Jone, David C. Kaelber, <lb/>Peter Paul C. Lim, Krista M. Lisdahl, Brian W. McCrindle, Russell J. McCulloh, Kimberly <lb/>McHugh, Torri D. Metz, Julie Miller, Elizabeth C. Mitchell, Lerraughn M. Morgan, Eva M. <lb/>Mu ¨ller-Oehring, Erica R. Nahin, Michael C. Neale, Sheila M. Nolan, Carlos R. Oliveira, <lb/>Onyekachukwu Osakwe, Matthew E. Oster, Michael A. Portman, Hengameh Raissy, Suchi-<lb/>tra Rao, Harrison T. Reeder, Johana M. Rosas, Mark W. Russell, Arash A. Sabati, Yamuna <lb/>Sanil, Alice I. Sato, Rangaraj Selvarangan, S. Kristen Sexson Tejtel, Divya Shakti, Lindsay <lb/>M. Squeglia, Shubika Srivastava, Michelle D. Stevenson, Jacqueline Szmuszkovicz, Maria <lb/>M. Talavera-Barber, Ronald J. Teufel, II, Felicia Trachtenberg, Sara E. Watson, Jordan C. <lb/>Weyer, Marion J. Wood, H. Shonna Yin, William T. Zempsky, Emily Zimmerman, Benard <lb/>P. Dreyer. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Long COVID or Post-COVID Conditions 2023 [cited <lb/>2023 September 28, 2023]. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html. <lb/>2. Soriano JB, Murthy S, Marshall JC, Relan P, Diaz JV. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condi-<lb/>tion by a Delphi consensus. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022; 22(4):e102-e7. Epub 20211221. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/S1473-3099(21)00703-9 PMID: 34951953. <lb/>3. Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommen-<lb/>dations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023; 21(3):133-46. Epub 20230113. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-022-<lb/>00846-2 PMID: 36639608. <lb/>4. World Health Organization. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) dashboard 2023 2023. https://covid19.who. <lb/>int/. <lb/>5. Zimmermann P, Pittet LF, Curtis N. How common is Long COVID in children and adolescents? Pediatr <lb/>Infect Dis J. 2021; 40(12):e482-e7. https://doi.org/10.1097/INF.0000000000003328 PMID: 34870392. <lb/>6. Kompaniyets L, Bull-Otterson L, Boehmer TK, Baca S, Alvarez P, Hong K, et al. Post-COVID-19 symp-<lb/>toms and conditions among children and adolescents-United States, March 1, 2020-January 31, <lb/>2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022; 71(31):993-9. Epub 20220805. https://doi.org/10.15585/ <lb/>mmwr.mm7131a3 PMID: 35925799. <lb/>7. Borch L, Holm M, Knudsen M, Ellermann-Eriksen S, Hagstroem S. Long COVID symptoms and dura-<lb/>tion in SARS-CoV-2 positive children-a nationwide cohort study. Eur J Pediatr. 2022; 181(4):1597-<lb/>607. Epub 20220109. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00431-021-04345-z PMID: 35000003. <lb/>8. Forrest CB, Burrows EK, Mejias A, Razzaghi H, Christakis D, Jhaveri R, et al. Severity of acute COVID-<lb/>19 in children &lt;18 years old March 2020 to December 2021. Pediatrics. 2022; 149(4). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1542/peds.2021-055765 PMID: 35322270. <lb/>9. Lopez-Leon S, Wegman-Ostrosky T, Ayuzo Del Valle NC, Perelman C, Sepulveda R, Rebolledo PA, <lb/>et al. Long-COVID in children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analyses. Sci Rep. 2022; <lb/>12(1):9950. Epub 20220623. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-13495-5 PMID: 35739136. <lb/>10. Chua PEY, Shah SU, Gui H, Koh J, Somani J, Pang J. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of <lb/>non-severe and severe pediatric and adult COVID-19 patients across different geographical regions in <lb/>the early phase of pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. J Investig <lb/>Med. 2021; 69(7):1287-96. Epub 20210616. https://doi.org/10.1136/jim-2021-001858 PMID: <lb/>34135068. <lb/>11. Funk AL, Kuppermann N, Florin TA, Tancredi DJ, Xie J, Kim K, et al. Post-COVID-19 conditions among <lb/>children 90 days after SARS-CoV-2 infection. JAMA Netw Open. 2022; 5(7):e2223253. Epub <lb/>20220701. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.23253 PMID: 35867061. <lb/>12. Groff D, Sun A, Ssentongo AE, Ba DM, Parsons N, Poudel GR, et al. Short-term and long-term rates of <lb/>Postacute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 Infection: A systematic review. JAMA Netw Open. 2021; 4(10): <lb/>e2128568. Epub 20211001. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.28568 PMID: 34643720. <lb/>13. Dufort EM, Koumans EH, Chow EJ, Rosenthal EM, Muse A, Rowlands J, et al. Multisystem Inflamma-<lb/>tory Syndrome in Children in New York State. N Engl J Med. 2020; 383(4):347-58. Epub 20200629. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa2021756 PMID: 32598830. <lb/>14. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). COVID data tracker 2023 [cited 2023 March 9]. <lb/>https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#mis-national-surveillance. <lb/>15. Stephenson T, Pinto Pereira SM, Shafran R, de Stavola BL, Rojas N, McOwat K, et al. Physical and <lb/>mental health 3 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection (long COVID) among adolescents in England <lb/>(CLoCk): a national matched cohort study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2022; 6(4):230-9. Epub <lb/>20220208. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-4642(22)00022-0 PMID: 35143770. <lb/>16. Hernandez-Romieu AC, Carton TW, Saydah S, Azziz-Baumgartner E, Boehmer TK, Garret NY, et al. <lb/>Prevalence of select new symptoms and conditions among persons aged younger than 20 years and <lb/>20 years or older at 31 to 150 days after testing positive or negative for SARS-CoV-2. JAMA Netw <lb/>Open. 2022; 5(2):e2147053. Epub 20220201. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.47053 <lb/>PMID: 35119459. <lb/>17. Buonsenso D, E Pujol F, Munblit D, Pata D, McFarland S, Simpson FK. Clinical characteristics, activity <lb/>levels and mental health problems in children with long coronavirus disease: a survey of 510 children. <lb/>Future Microbiol. 2022; 17(8):577-88. Epub 20220401. https://doi.org/10.2217/fmb-2021-0285 PMID: <lb/>35360923. <lb/>18. Kikkenborg Berg S, Dam Nielsen S, Nygaard U, Bundgaard H, Palm P, Rotvig C, et al. Long COVID <lb/>symptoms in SARS-CoV-2-positive adolescents and matched controls (LongCOVIDKidsDK): a <lb/>national, cross-sectional study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2022; 6(4):240-8. Epub 20220208. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-4642(22)00004-9 PMID: 35143771. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. Wulf Hanson S, Abbafati C, Aerts JG, Al-Aly Z, Ashbaugh C, Ballouz T, et al. Estimated global propor-<lb/>tions of individuals with persistent fatigue, cognitive, and respiratory symptom clusters following symp-<lb/>tomatic COVID-19 in 2020 and 2021. Jama. 2022; 328(16):1604-15. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama. <lb/>2022.18931 PMID: 36215063. <lb/>20. Haddad A, Janda A, Renk H, Stich M, Frieh P, Kaier K, et al. Long COVID symptoms in exposed and <lb/>infected children, adolescents and their parents one year after SARS-CoV-2 infection: A prospective <lb/>observational cohort study. EBioMedicine. 2022; 84:104245. Epub 20220922. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>ebiom.2022.104245 PMID: 36155957. <lb/>21. Roessler M, Tesch F, Batram M, Jacob J, Loser F, Weidinger O, et al. Post-COVID-19-associated mor-<lb/>bidity in children, adolescents, and adults: A matched cohort study including more than 157,000 individ-<lb/>uals with COVID-19 in Germany. PLoS Med. 2022; 19(11):e1004122. Epub 20221110. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pmed.1004122 PMID: 36355754. <lb/>22. Brugler Yonts A. Pediatric Long-COVID: A review of the definition, epidemiology, presentation, and <lb/>pathophysiology. Pediatr Ann. 2022; 51(11):e416-e20. Epub 20221101. https://doi.org/10.3928/ <lb/>19382359-20220913-06 PMID: 36343180. <lb/>23. Rao S, Lee GM, Razzaghi H, Lorman V, Mejias A, Pajor NM, et al. Clinical features and burden of Post-<lb/>acute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 Infection in children and adolescents. JAMA Pediatr. 2022; 176 <lb/>(10):1000-9. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.2800 PMID: 35994282. <lb/>24. Morrow AK, Malone LA, Kokorelis C, Petracek LS, Eastin EF, Lobner KL, et al. Long-term COVID 19 <lb/>sequelae in adolescents: the overlap with orthostatic intolerance and ME/CFS. Curr Pediatr Rep. 2022; <lb/>10(2):31-44. Epub 20220309. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40124-022-00261-4 PMID: 35287333. <lb/>25. National Institutes of Health. RECOVER: Researching COVID to Enhance Recovery 2023 [cited 2023 <lb/>March 12]. https://recovercovid.org/. <lb/>26. Barch DM, Albaugh MD, Avenevoli S, Chang L, Clark DB, Glantz MD, et al. Demographic, physical and <lb/>mental health assessments in the adolescent brain and cognitive development study: Rationale and <lb/>description. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2018; 32:55-66. Epub 20171103. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dcn.2017. <lb/>10.010 PMID: 29113758. <lb/>27. Volkow ND, Koob GF, Croyle RT, Bianchi DW, Gordon JA, Koroshetz WJ, et al. The conception of the <lb/>ABCD study: From substance use to a broad NIH collaboration. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2018; 32:4-7. <lb/>Epub 20171010. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dcn.2017.10.002 PMID: 29051027. <lb/>28. Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Maternal-Fetal <lb/>Medicine Units Network 2023. https://www.nichd.nih.gov/research/supported/mfmu. <lb/>29. The Regents of the University of California. PRIORITY: Pregnancy Coronavirus Outcomes Registry <lb/>University of California, San Francisco2023. https://priority.ucsf.edu/. <lb/>30. Truong DT, Trachtenberg FL, Pearson GD, Dionne A, Elias MD, Friedman K, et al. The NHLBI Study on <lb/>Long-terM OUtcomes after the Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome In Children (MUSIC): Design and <lb/>objectives. Am Heart J. 2022; 243:43-53. Epub 20210819. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ahj.2021.08.003 <lb/>PMID: 34418362. <lb/>31. Davis TC, Gazmararian J, Kennen EM. Approaches to improving health literacy: lessons from the <lb/>field. J Health Commun. 2006; 11(6):551-4. https://doi.org/10.1080/10810730600835517 PMID: <lb/>16950727. <lb/>32. Garavan H, Bartsch H, Conway K, Decastro A, Goldstein RZ, Heeringa S, et al. Recruiting the ABCD <lb/>sample: Design considerations and procedures. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2018; 32:16-22. Epub 20180416. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dcn.2018.04.004 PMID: 29703560. <lb/>33. World Health Organization. Public health surveillance for COVID-19: interim guidance, 2022 [updated <lb/>July 22]. No. WHO/2019-nCoV/SurveillanceGuidance/2022.2. World Health Organization, 2022. <lb/>34. Kallen MA, Lai JS, Blackwell CK, Schuchard JR, Forrest CB, Wakschlag LS, et al. Measuring PROMIS ® <lb/>Global Health in Early Childhood. J Pediatr Psychol. 2022; 47(5):523-33. https://doi.org/10.1093/ <lb/>jpepsy/jsac026 PMID: 35552435. <lb/>35. Forrest CB, Bevans KB, Pratiwadi R, Moon J, Teneralli RE, Minton JM, et al. Development of the PRO-<lb/>MIS ® pediatric global health (PGH-7) measure. Qual Life Res. 2014; 23(4):1221-31. Epub 20131122. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11136-013-0581-8 PMID: 24264804. <lb/>36. Hays RD, Bjorner JB, Revicki DA, Spritzer KL, Cella D. Development of physical and mental health <lb/>summary scores from the patient-reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS) <lb/>global items. Qual Life Res. 2009; 18(7):873-80. Epub 20090619. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11136-009-<lb/>9496-9 PMID: 19543809. <lb/>37. Walker LS, Beck JE, Garber J, Lambert W. Children&apos;s Somatization Inventory: psychometric properties <lb/>of the revised form (CSI-24). J Pediatr Psychol. 2009; 34(4):430-40. Epub 20080909. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1093/jpepsy/jsn093 PMID: 18782857. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>38. Denny JC, Rutter JL, Goldstein DB, Philippakis A, Smoller JW, Jenkins G, et al. The &quot;All of Us&quot; <lb/>Research Program. N Engl J Med. 2019; 381(7):668-76. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsr1809937 <lb/>PMID: 31412182. <lb/>39. Data Resourse Center for Child and Adolescent Health. The National Survey of Children&apos;s Health 2021 <lb/>[March 12, 2023]. https://www.childhealthdata.org/learn-about-the-nsch/NSCH. <lb/>40. Bethell CD, Read D, Stein RE, Blumberg SJ, Wells N, Newacheck PW. Identifying children with special <lb/>health care needs: development and evaluation of a short screening instrument. Ambul Pediatr. 2002; 2 <lb/>(1):38-48. https://doi.org/10.1367/1539-4409(2002)002&lt;0038:icwshc&gt;2.0.co;2 PMID: 11888437. <lb/>41. Read D, Bethell C, Blumberg SJ, Abreu M, Molina C. An evaluation of the linguistic and cultural validity <lb/>of the Spanish language version of the children with special health care needs screener. Matern Child <lb/>Health J. 2007; 11(6):568-85. Epub 20070612. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10995-007-0207-2 PMID: <lb/>17562154. <lb/>42. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Behavioral risk factor surveillance system 2023 <lb/>[cited 2023 March 12]. https://www.cdc.gov/brfss/index.html. <lb/>43. Sausen KA, Randolph JW, Casciato AN, Dietrich MS, Scholer SJ. The development, preliminary valida-<lb/>tion, and clinical application of the quick parenting assessment. Prev Sci. 2022; 23(2):306-20. Epub <lb/>20211115. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-021-01320-w PMID: 34780005. <lb/>44. Economic Research Service USDoA. U.S. Household Food Security Survey Module 2022 [updated <lb/>October 17; cited 2023 March 12]. https://www.ers.usda.gov/topics/food-nutrition-assistance/food-<lb/>security-in-the-u-s/survey-tools/. <lb/>45. RAND Corporation. Social Support Survey Instrument [cited 2023 March 12]. https://www.rand.org/ <lb/>health-care/surveys_tools/mos/social-support/survey-instrument.html. <lb/>46. Freeman R, Wieling W, Axelrod FB, Benditt DG, Benarroch E, Biaggioni I, et al. Consensus statement <lb/>on the definition of orthostatic hypotension, neurally mediated syncope and the postural tachycardia <lb/>syndrome. Auton Neurosci. 2011; 161(1-2):46-8. Epub 20110309. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.autneu. <lb/>2011.02.004 PMID: 21393070. <lb/>47. Singer W, Sletten DM, Opfer-Gehrking TL, Brands CK, Fischer PR, Low PA. Postural tachycardia in <lb/>children and adolescents: what is abnormal? J Pediatr. 2012; 160(2):222-6. Epub 20111011. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.08.054 PMID: 21996154. <lb/>48. Malek S, Reinhold EJ, Pearce GS. The Beighton Score as a measure of generalised joint hypermobility. <lb/>Rheumatol Int. 2021; 41(10):1707-16. Epub 20210318. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00296-021-04832-4 <lb/>PMID: 33738549. <lb/>49. Squires J, Bricker D, Potter L. Revision of a parent-completed development screening tool: Ages and <lb/>Stages Questionnaires. J Pediatr Psychol. 1997; 22(3):313-28. https://doi.org/10.1093/jpepsy/22.3. <lb/>313 PMID: 9212550. <lb/>50. Squires J B D. Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaires ® , Third Edition (ASQ ® -3): A Parent-Completed Child <lb/>Monitoring System. Baltimore: Paul H. Brookes Publishing Co., Inc.; 2009. <lb/>51. Squires J, Potter L, Bricker D. The ASQ user&apos;s guide for the Ages and Stages Questionnaires: A parent-<lb/>completed, child-monitoring system Baltimore, MD: Paul H Brookes Publishing Company; 1995. <lb/>52. Robins DL, Casagrande K, Barton M, Chen CM, Dumont-Mathieu T, Fein D. Validation of the modified <lb/>checklist for Autism in toddlers, revised with follow-up (M-CHAT-R/F). Pediatrics. 2014; 133(1):37-45. <lb/>Epub 20131223. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2013-1813 PMID: 24366990. <lb/>53. Weintraub S, Dikmen SS, Heaton RK, Tulsky DS, Zelazo PD, Bauer PJ, et al. Cognition assessment <lb/>using the NIH Toolbox. Neurology. 2013; 80(11 Suppl 3):S54-64. https://doi.org/10.1212/WNL. <lb/>0b013e3182872ded PMID: 23479546. <lb/>54. Squires J B D, Twombly E. Ages and Stages Questionnaire: Social-Emotional (ASQ:SE). Baltimore, <lb/>MD: Paul H. Brookes Publishing Co; 2002. <lb/>55. Achenbach TM. Child behavior checklist. Burlington, VT: University of Vermont, Department of Psychi-<lb/>atry; 1991. <lb/>56. Irwin DE, Gross HE, Stucky BD, Thissen D, DeWitt EM, Lai JS, et al. Development of six PROMIS pedi-<lb/>atrics proxy-report item banks. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2012; 10:22. Epub 20120222. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1186/1477-7525-10-22 PMID: 22357192. <lb/>57. Bevans KB, Gardner W, Pajer KA, Becker B, Carle A, Tucker CA, et al. Psychometric Evaluation of the <lb/>PROMIS ® Pediatric Psychological and Physical Stress Experiences Measures. J Pediatr Psychol. <lb/>2018; 43(6):678-92. https://doi.org/10.1093/jpepsy/jsy010 PMID: 29490050. <lb/>58. Forrest CB, Ravens-Sieberer U, Devine J, Becker BD, Teneralli R, Moon J, et al. Development and <lb/>Evaluation of the PROMIS( ® ) Pediatric Positive Affect Item Bank, Child-Report and Parent-Proxy Edi-<lb/>tions. J Happiness Stud. 2018; 19(3):699-718. Epub 20170121. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10902-016-<lb/>9843-9 PMID: 29760578. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 / 29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>59. Chorpita BF, Yim L, Moffitt C, Umemoto LA, Francis SE. Assessment of symptoms of DSM-IV anxiety <lb/>and depression in children: a revised child anxiety and depression scale. Behav Res Ther. 2000; 38 <lb/>(8):835-55. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0005-7967(99)00130-8 PMID: 10937431. <lb/>60. Goodman R. The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: a research note. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. <lb/>1997; 38(5):581-6. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x PMID: 9255702. <lb/>61. Achenbach T, Rescorla L. Manual for the ASEBA adult forms &amp; profiles. Burlington, VT: University of <lb/>Vermont, Research Center for Children, Youth, &amp; Families; 2003. <lb/>62. Schrank FA, McGrew KS, Mather N. Woodcock-Johnson IV. Rolling Meadows, IL: Riverside; 2014. <lb/>63. Adams W, Sheslow D. Wide-Range Assessment of Memory and Learning-3rd Edition. Bloomington, <lb/>MN: Pearson; 2021. <lb/>64. Beery K, Beery N. Beery VMI: The Beery-Buktenica Developmental test of visual-motor integration with <lb/>supplemental developmental tests of visual perception and motor coordination: Stepping stones age <lb/>norms from birth to age six. administration, scoring, and teaching manual: PsychCorp; 2010. <lb/>65. Science Research Associates. SRA examiner&apos;s manual for the Purdue Pegboard. Chicago, IL: Sci-<lb/>ence Research Associates; 1948. <lb/>66. Townsend L, Kobak K, Kearney C, Milham M, Andreotti C, Escalera J, et al. Development of three web-<lb/>based computerized versions of the Kiddie Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia Child <lb/>Psychiatric Diagnostic Interview: Preliminary Validity Data Journal of American Academy of Child &amp; <lb/>Adolescent Psychiatry. 2020; 59(2):309-25. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2019.05.009 PMID: <lb/>31108163 <lb/>67. Tasso Inc. Tasso-M20 2023 [cited 2023 March 12]. https://www.tassoinc.com/tasso-m20. <lb/>68. Zou G. A modified poisson regression approach to prospective studies with binary data. Am J Epide-<lb/>miol. 2004; 159(7):702-6. https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwh090 PMID: 15033648. <lb/>69. Thaweethai T, Jolley SE, Karlson EW, Levitan EB, Levy B, McComsey GA, et al. Development of a Def-<lb/>inition of Postacute Sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 Infection. Jama. 2023; 329(22):1934-46. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1001/jama.2023.8823 PMID: 37278994. <lb/>70. Lorman V, Rao S, Jhaveri R, Case A, Mejias A, Pajor NM, et al. Understanding pediatric long COVID <lb/>using a tree-based scan statistic approach: an EHR-based cohort study from the RECOVER Program. <lb/>JAMIA Open. 2023; 6(1):ooad016. Epub 20230314. https://doi.org/10.1093/jamiaopen/ooad016 PMID: <lb/>36926600. <lb/>71. Murtagh F C P. Algorithms for hierarchical clustering: an overview. WIREs Data Mining Knowl Discov. <lb/>2011. https://doi.org/10.1002/widm.53 <lb/>72. Monti S TP, Mesirov J, Golub T. Consensus clustering: a resampling-based method for class discovery <lb/>and visualization of gene expression microarray data. Machine Learning. 2003; 52(1):91-118. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1023/A:1023949509487 <lb/>73. Hochberg Y. A sharper Bonferroni procedure for multiple tests of significance. Biometrika. 1998; 75 <lb/>800-3. <lb/>74. Leon AC, Heo M, Teres JJ, Morikawa T. Statistical power of multiplicity adjustment strategies for corre-<lb/>lated binary endpoints. Stat Med. 2007; 26(8):1712-23. https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.2795 PMID: <lb/>17252534. <lb/>75. White IR, Royston P, Wood AM. Multiple imputation using chained equations: Issues and guidance for <lb/>practice. Stat Med. 2011; 30(4):377-99. Epub 20101130. https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.4067 PMID: <lb/>21225900. <lb/>76. Robins JM, Finkelstein DM. Correcting for noncompliance and dependent censoring in an AIDS Clinical <lb/>Trial with inverse probability of censoring weighted (IPCW) log-rank tests. Biometrics. 2000; 56(3):779-<lb/>88. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0006-341x.2000.00779.x PMID: 10985216. <lb/>77. Daniels MJ H J. Missing data in longitudinal studies: Strategies for Bayesian Modeling and Sensitivity <lb/>Analysis. 1st Edition ed. New York: Chapman and Hall/CRC; 2008 March 10, 2008. <lb/>78. Little RJ, Wang Y. Pattern-mixture models for multivariate incomplete data with covariates. Biometrics. <lb/>1996; 52(1):98-111. PMID: 8934587. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>RECOVER pediatric cohort protocol <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0285635 May 7, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 / 29 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>