<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T15:19:05.078Z">11/14/2025 3:19:05 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T15:18:53.796572Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T15:18:53.796572Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Dopamine and acetylcholine have distinct <lb/>roles in delay-and effort-based decision-<lb/>making in humans <lb/>Mani Erfanian Abdoust ID <lb/>1 *, Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se 1 , Alfons Schnitzler 2 , <lb/>Elisabeth Schreivogel 2 , Gerhard Jocham 1 <lb/>1 Biological Psychology of Decision Making, Institute of Experimental Psychology, Heinrich Heine University <lb/>Du ¨sseldorf, Du ¨sseldorf, Germany, 2 Institute of Clinical Neuroscience and Medical Psychology, Medical <lb/>Faculty, Heinrich Heine University Du ¨sseldorf, Germany <lb/>* erfanian@hhu.de <lb/>Abstract <lb/>AU : Pleaseconfirmthatallheadinglevelsarerepresentedcorrectly: <lb/>In everyday life, we encounter situations that require tradeoffs between potential rewards <lb/>and associated costs, such as time and (physical) effort. The literature indicates a prominent <lb/>role for dopamine in discounting of both delay and effort, with mixed findings for delay dis-<lb/>counting in humans. Moreover, the reciprocal antagonistic interaction between dopaminer-<lb/>gic and cholinergic transmission in the striatum suggests a potential opponent role of <lb/>acetylcholine in these processes. We found opposing effects of dopamine D2 (haloperidol) <lb/>and acetylcholine M1 receptor (biperiden) antagonism on specific components of effort-<lb/>based decision-making in healthy humans: haloperidol decreased, whereas biperiden <lb/>increased the willingness to exert physical effort. In contrast, delay discounting was reduced <lb/>under haloperidol, but not affected by biperiden. Together, our data suggest that dopamine, <lb/>acting at D2 receptors, modulates both effort and delay discounting, while acetylcholine, act-<lb/>ing at M1 receptors, appears to exert a more specific influence on effort discounting only. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Consider the following scenarios: Would you prefer to order an average pizza that can be <lb/>delivered within minutes or rather wait an extra hour for your most favourite pizza? Similarly, <lb/>would you visit a highly rated pizza place that requires climbing up a steep hill or opting for a <lb/>conveniently accessible pizza place right in front of the next bus stop? In scenarios like this, <lb/>decision-making involves the balancing of potential rewards against distinct costs required to <lb/>obtain them. The tendency to devalue rewards as a function of effort or delay costs are com-<lb/>monly described as effort and delay discounting, respectively [1,2]. <lb/>Striatal dopamine has been suggested to play a central role in both effort and delay dis-<lb/>counting. For effort-based decision-making, studies in both humans and rodents indicate that <lb/>diminished dopamine transmission makes individuals less willing to exert physical effort in <lb/>exchange for larger rewards [3-9]. Pharmacological studies consistently demonstrate that <lb/>agents that enhance dopaminergic transmission in humans increase reward sensitivity and <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/>1 / 29 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Erfanian Abdoust M, Frobo ¨se MI, <lb/>Schnitzler A, Schreivogel E, Jocham G (2024) <lb/>Dopamine and acetylcholine have distinct roles in <lb/>delay-and effort-based decision-making in <lb/>humans. PLoS Biol 22(7): e3002714. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 <lb/>Academic Editor: Raphael Samuel Matthew <lb/>Kaplan, Universitat Jaume 1, SPAIN <lb/>Received: December 14, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: June 14, 2024 <lb/>Published: July 12, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Erfanian Abdoust et al. This is <lb/>an open access article distributed under the terms <lb/>of the Creative Commons Attribution License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Anonymized and <lb/>preprocessed datasets, along with the regression <lb/>and computational modelling analysis codes, are <lb/>available at https://osf.io/gx76t/. <lb/></front>

    <body>decrease effort sensitivity, while studies directly investigating the effects of selective D2-recep-<lb/>tor antagonism in healthy humans are rare [10-12]. For delay discounting, the existing litera-<lb/>ture is somewhat more mixed. Some studies suggest that increased dopamine transmission <lb/>decreases delay discounting [13-15], whereas others have found either no effect [16,17] or an <lb/>increase in delay discounting [18]. Notably, more recent evidence in humans indicates <lb/>decreased delay discounting after blockade of D2 receptors [19,20]. While dopamine has <lb/>received much attention in cost-benefit decision-making, other neuromodulators may also <lb/>play an important role [21-23]. One modulator that has not received much attention in this <lb/>regard is acetylcholine, which is surprising given the literature on reciprocal antagonistic inter-<lb/>actions between acetylcholine and dopamine signalling in the striatum [24-28]. This suggests <lb/>that pharmacological blockade of M1 receptors will have effects on cost-benefit decision-mak-<lb/>ing that are opposite to those of blocking dopamine D2 receptors. In line with this, animal <lb/>studies indicate that muscarinic agonists induce behavioural changes in effort-based choices <lb/>that are similar to those produced by dopamine antagonists [23,29], underscoring the potential <lb/>interplay between dopamine and acetylcholine in modulating cost-benefit decision-making. <lb/>Furthermore, research in animal models points to a role for acetylcholine in modulating <lb/>delay-based choices through both muscarinic and nicotinic receptors, albeit with inconsistent <lb/>findings [30-33]. Importantly, studies directly investigating these effects in human decision-<lb/>making are lacking. <lb/>To our knowledge, there has been no study so far that tested the impact of dopaminergic <lb/>and cholinergic manipulations on both aspects of cost-benefit decision-making in 1 single <lb/>experiment. To fill this gap, we investigated the effects of 2 drugs, haloperidol and biperiden, <lb/>that selectively block either dopamine D2-like or muscarinic M1 acetylcholine receptors in <lb/>human participants performing 2 decision-making tasks involving effort-and delay-based <lb/>decisions. The goal of our study was 3-fold. First, we aimed to conceptually replicate the find-<lb/>ing that dopamine D2 antagonists increase discounting of physical effort. Second, we aimed to <lb/>assess the contribution of acetylcholine to cost-benefit decision-making and conceptually con-<lb/>trast it with the effects of dopamine. In doing so, we investigated whether any effects of musca-<lb/>rinic or dopaminergic receptor antagonism would modulate the computation of both time <lb/>and effort costs or have a more specific effect on one cost dimension. Third, we sought to con-<lb/>tribute new evidence to the thus far conflicting literature on the role of dopamine in delay-<lb/>based decision-making using a large sample size and a within-subjects design. Based on previ-<lb/>ous findings, we hypothesised that the administration of haloperidol will (1) increase effort dis-<lb/>counting; and (2) reduce delay discounting. In contrast, we expected opposite effects of <lb/>biperiden, in particular (3) a decrease in effort discounting; and (4) an increase in delay dis-<lb/>counting. In brief, we found opposing effects of haloperidol and biperiden only on specific <lb/>components of effort-based choices. Specifically, haloperidol reduced the willingness to invest <lb/>physical effort, whereas biperiden increased it. Results for delay discounting were less consis-<lb/>tent. While haloperidol decreased delay discounting, there was no credible modulation by <lb/>biperiden. <lb/>Results <lb/>The 62 healthy participants performed 2 cost-benefit decision-making tasks aimed to quantify <lb/>the extent to which the subjective value (SV) of a monetary reward is discounted as a function <lb/>of either effort or delay costs. Participants completed both tasks during 3 sessions under the <lb/>influence of either the D2 receptor antagonist haloperidol (2 mg), the M1 acetylcholine recep-<lb/>tor antagonist biperiden (4 mg), or a placebo in a within-subjects design (Fig 1A). The effort-<lb/>based decision-making task (effort discounting task, Fig 1B) involved choices between options <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <front>Funding: This work was supported by a grant (DFG <lb/>JO-787/5-1 to GJ) from the Deutsche <lb/>Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG; https://www.dfg. <lb/>de/). The funders had no role in study design, data <lb/>collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>Abbreviations: AES, AU : Anabbreviationlisthasbeencompiledforthoseusedinthetext:Pleaseverifythatallentriesarecorrect: <lb/>Apathy Evaluation Scale; BDI, <lb/>Beck&apos;s Depression Inventory; BIP, biperiden; BIS, <lb/>Barratt Impulsiveness Scale; GLMM, generalized <lb/>linear mixed model; HAL, haloperidol; HDI, highest <lb/>density interval; LOOIC, leave-one-out information <lb/>criterion; MVC, maximum voluntary contraction; <lb/>PLC, placebo; SD, standard deviation; SV, <lb/>subjective value. <lb/></front>

    <body>varying in reward magnitude and effort requirement (using handgrip force), while the delay-<lb/>based decision-making task (delay discounting task, Fig 1C) involved choices between one <lb/>option varying in reward magnitude and delay versus a fixed one. Thus, both tasks required <lb/>participants to choose between a high-reward/high-cost (high-cost option) and a low-reward/ <lb/>low-cost (low-cost option) alternative. <lb/>Drug effects on choice behaviour <lb/>Participants consistently exhibited a preference for the high-cost option over the low-cost <lb/>alternative in both tasks (effort discounting task: 78.50% ± 1.03; delay discounting task: <lb/>71.31% ± 1.12; Fig 2A). For each of the 2 tasks, we used a logistic Bayesian generalized linear <lb/>mixed model (GLMM) to investigate the impact of drug manipulation, changes in task param-<lb/>eters, and the interaction between both, on choosing the high-cost option. Specifically, to <lb/>Fig 1. Study procedure and experimental tasks. (a) The experimental sessions were standardised across all sessions <lb/>except for the drug treatment, which was counterbalanced. To account for the different times of haloperidol and <lb/>biperiden to reach peak plasma levels, a dummy drug application was introduced, ensuring that the maximum <lb/>concentration of both drugs was aligned to task execution. Approximately 180 min after the first capsule and <lb/>approximately 60 min after the second capsule, participants engaged in the effort discounting task (b), followed by the <lb/>delay discounting task (c). Physiological measures (including heart rate and blood pressure) and mood ratings (using <lb/>the Bond and Lader Visual Analogue Scales) were collected at 3 distinct time points. Additionally, participants <lb/>completed the trail-making test part A before task execution (see Materials and methods for more details). In both <lb/>tasks, participants were presented with 2 alternative options, each providing information about a monetary reward in <lb/>return for specific costs. (b) Effort discounting task. One option required less effort (indicated by the horizontal yellow <lb/>line) and provided a smaller reward (indicated by the number of apples, low-cost option), while the other option <lb/>required more effort and provided a higher reward (high-cost option). Participants then chose 1 option and exerted <lb/>the required effort (adjusted to the MVC) for at least 1 s. (c) Delay discounting task. Similarly, participants were <lb/>presented with 2 offers: a smaller but immediately available reward (low-cost option) or a larger reward available after <lb/>the delay indicated (high-cost option). BIP, biperiden; HAL, haloperidol; MVC, maximum voluntary contraction; <lb/>PLC, placebo. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 2. Behavioural performance in the effort (left panel) and delay (right panel) discounting task. (a) The overall <lb/>proportions of high-cost choices were modulated by drug administration in the effort (left), but not in the delay <lb/>discounting task (right). Biperiden increased and haloperidol decreased the willingness to invest physical effort in <lb/>return for reward. (b) The probability of choosing the high-cost option increased as a function of increasing reward <lb/>magnitude for both the effort and delay discounting tasks. In the effort discounting task (left), biperiden increased the <lb/>impact of the reward level on choice. (c) Similarly, the tendency to choose the high-cost option decreased as a function <lb/>of increasing levels of effort and delay. This effect is reduced by haloperidol in the delay discounting task (right). <lb/>Values in (a) show group-level (single-subject) means represented by bold (light) dots. Values in (b) and (c) display <lb/>averaged group-level means per reward and cost level, with error bars representing the standard error of the mean. In <lb/>(b), reward levels are presented as the difference in magnitude between the high-and low-cost option in the effort <lb/>discontinuing task and as the absolute reward value of the high-cost option in the delay discounting task. Likewise in <lb/>(c), the effort level represents the difference between the proportions of the individually calibrated MVC of the high-<lb/>versus low-cost option, while the delay levels indicate the delay of the high-cost option. The data underlying the effort <lb/>discounting task (left panel) can be found in S1 Data, and the data underlying the delay discounting task (right panel) <lb/>can be found in S2 Data. MVC, maximum voluntary contraction. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.g002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>regress participants&apos; choices, we included the following fixed-effect predictors: drug condition, <lb/>reward magnitude, cost level (i.e., effort or delay), and all possible interactions. In the effort <lb/>discounting task, we used the difference terms (high-cost option minus low-cost option) for <lb/>both reward and effort. For the delay discounting task, we used the absolute reward and delay <lb/>levels of the varying high-cost option. To account for within-subject variability, we included <lb/>random intercepts for each subject along with random slopes for all fixed-effect predictors (see <lb/>Materials and methods). We first confirmed that participants effectively discounted rewards <lb/>based on costs and thereby adhered to the task requirements: As expected, in both discounting <lb/>tasks higher reward magnitudes increased, while higher cost levels (effort or delay) decreased <lb/>participants&apos; likelihood to select the high-cost option (reward effect on effort discounting: <lb/>HDI Mean = 3.44, HDI 95% = [2.96; 3.95]; reward effect on delay discounting: HDI Mean = 55.64, <lb/>HDI 95% = [41.76; 69.38], effort effect on effort discounting: HDI Mean = -1.64, HDI 95% = <lb/>[-1.87; -1.40]; delay effect on delay discounting: HDI Mean = -2.29, HDI 95% = [-3.30; -1.25], <lb/>Fig 2B and 2C). <lb/>Notably, and in line with our predictions, we found that the 2 drugs had opposite effects on <lb/>the tendency to choose high-effort options in the effort discounting task relative to placebo. <lb/>Haloperidol reduced the willingness to invest higher effort for greater reward, while biperiden <lb/>increased this willingness (placebo: 79.17% ± 1.76; haloperidol: 74.34% ± 1.85; biperiden: <lb/>81.99% ± 1.64; Fig 2A (left panel)). These effects were confirmed by credible main effects of <lb/>both haloperidol (HDI Mean = -0.532, HDI 95% = [-0.943; -0.136]) and biperiden (HDI Mean = <lb/>0.620, HDI 95% = [0.230; 1.048]; Fig 3A) on choosing the high-cost option relative to placebo. <lb/>Moreover, this analysis revealed that biperiden increased reward sensitivity, as evidenced by a <lb/>credible interaction effect between biperiden and reward (HDI Mean = 0.802, HDI 95% = [0.256; <lb/>1.409]; Fig 3B). See S1 Table for the full results. <lb/>In contrast, in the delay discounting task, both drugs had no effect on the average rate of <lb/>choosing the high-cost option (placebo: 71.59% ± 2.25; haloperidol: 71.55% ± 1.73; biperiden: <lb/>70.79% ± 1.82; Fig 2A (right panel)), as indicated by the absence of credible main effects for <lb/>haloperidol (HDI Mean = -0.046, HDI 95% = [-2.648; 1.884]) and biperiden (HDI Mean = -1.315, <lb/>HDI 95% = [-4.147; 0.655]; Fig 3D). Importantly, however, the analysis revealed a reduced sen-<lb/>sitivity to delays under haloperidol, evidenced by a credible interaction effect between haloper-<lb/>idol and delay (HDI Mean = 1.332, HDI 95% = [0.328; 2.440]; Fig 3F), while the other drug <lb/>interactions did not reach credibility (Fig 3 and S2 Table). This indicates that diminished <lb/>dopaminergic activity attenuates the impact of time costs on decision-making. <lb/>Having established distinct task-specific drug effects on participants&apos; choice behaviour, we <lb/>next investigated potential confounding order and fatigue effects using separate GLMMs for <lb/>effort-and delay-based decision-making. These models mirrored the previously described <lb/>GLMMs but included additional predictors to test for fatigue and session effects and their <lb/>modulation by drugs. <lb/>To test for possible fatigue effects, we added trial number as well as the two-way interaction <lb/>with drug as additional predictors. This analysis revealed a credible main effect of trial number <lb/>for both the effort and delay discounting task (trial number effect on effort discounting: HDI-<lb/>Mean = -0.60, HDI 95% = [-0.75; -0.46]; trial number effect on delay discounting: HDI Mean = <lb/>-0.20, HDI 95% = [-0.33; -0.08]), suggesting that the tendency to choose high-cost options, <lb/>irrespective of cost type, decreased over the course of the experiment. Notably, we found a <lb/>credible interaction effect between trial number and haloperidol in the effort discounting task <lb/>(HDI Mean = -0.43, HDI 95% = [-0.63; -0.23]), indicating that the fatigue effect was more pro-<lb/>nounced under haloperidol compared to placebo. Importantly, even after accounting for these <lb/>fatigue-related effects, the main effect of haloperidol on effort discounting remained credible <lb/>(HDI Mean = -0.48, HDI 95% = [-0.90; -0.05]) (S12 and S13 Tables). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 3. Drug effects on choice behaviour. Posterior distributions and 95% HDI of the logistic Bayesian GLMMs depict <lb/>the estimate of each effect on choosing the high-cost option. (a) Biperiden credibly increased the overall willingness to <lb/>invest physical effort for a corresponding reward, while haloperidol had the opposite effect. (b) Biperiden increased <lb/>reward sensitivity in the effort discounting task, as indicated by a biperiden-by-reward interaction, without a credible <lb/>effect of haloperidol. (c) In contrast, neither drug affected effort sensitivity. (d) In the delay discounting task, the <lb/>willingness to tolerate delays for rewards was not affected by either drug. (e) Likewise, neither drug modulated reward <lb/>sensitivity in the delay discounting task. (f) However, haloperidol decreased delay sensitivity, with no credible effect of <lb/>biperiden. Here, a positive estimate of the interaction effect between haloperidol and delay indicates a reduction of the <lb/>negative parameter estimate associated with delay, suggesting an attenuation of the impact of delay on choice <lb/>behaviour. Bold dots represent the mean group-level estimate of the posterior distribution. The horizontal bars <lb/>represent the group-level 95% HDI. GLMM, generalized linear mixed model; HDI, highest density interval. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>Next, to investigate session and drug-order effects, we included session and the two-way <lb/>interaction between session and drug as additional predictors. These analyses confirmed a <lb/>main effect of session only for effort-based choices (HDI Mean = 0.49, HDI 95% = [0.13; 0.85]), <lb/>suggesting increased preference for high-effort options in later sessions, likely reflecting task <lb/>familiarity. Crucially, the interaction effects between either drug and session were not credible <lb/>in both tasks (S14 and S15 Tables). This indicates that neither dopaminergic nor cholinergic <lb/>manipulations modulated learning effects across sessions. Moreover, this finding underscores <lb/>that the observed drug-induced effects cannot be explained by drug order effects. <lb/>To summarise, regression-based results show that haloperidol reduced the overall propen-<lb/>sity to choose the high-cost options in the effort domain. While haloperidol had no effect on <lb/>the average rate of selecting the high-cost option in delay-based choices, it attenuated partici-<lb/>pants&apos; sensitivity to delay costs. In contrast, biperiden increased the overall propensity of <lb/>selecting the high-cost option in the effort discounting task, opposite to the effect of haloperi-<lb/>dol. Consistent with this, biperiden also increased sensitivity to reward magnitudes during <lb/>effort-based choices. <lb/>Drug effects on computational parameters <lb/>To obtain a more detailed understanding of the mechanism underlying the drug effects on <lb/>behaviour described above, we used hierarchical Bayesian modelling. To begin with, we deter-<lb/>mined the best-fitting discounting models for both effort and delay, comparing 4 commonly <lb/>used models (linear, parabolic, hyperbolic, and exponential). In line with previous findings <lb/>[2,34-37], model comparisons revealed that effort discounting was best described by a para-<lb/>bolic model, suggesting a greater impact of changes in high rather than low-effort levels. In <lb/>contrast, delay discounting was best described by a hyperbolic model, indicating a greater <lb/>impact of changes in low rather than high-delay levels (S3 Table). For each model, we first cal-<lb/>culated the SVs of all choice options, based on participant-specific weighing of reward magni-<lb/>tude and associated costs (i.e., effort and delay levels). By introducing condition-specific shift <lb/>parameters, we captured potential drug effects on the effort and delay discounting parameter κ <lb/>(denoted as s κ HAL for haloperidol and s κ BIP for biperiden), with positive/negative shift <lb/>parameter values indicating increased/decreased effort and delay discounting, respectively. <lb/>We then used a softmax function to transform the option values into choice probabilities, with <lb/>choice stochasticity being modelled by an inverse temperature parameter β. Again, condition-<lb/>specific shift parameters for haloperidol and biperiden captured potential drug effects on <lb/>choice stochasticity (s β HAL for haloperidol and s β BIP for biperiden), with positive/negative <lb/>shift parameters indicating more deterministic/more stochastic decision-making (see Materi-<lb/>als and methods, and Supporting Materials and Methods in S1 Text). Model validation and <lb/>parameter recovery confirmed that both models accurately captured key features of the choice <lb/>data (see Supporting Results in S1 Text). <lb/>The results from the computational model of the effort discounting task align with and <lb/>extend the regression-based results presented above. Specifically, again biperiden and haloper-<lb/>idol exerted opposing effects on both the discounting and inverse temperature parameter. Hal-<lb/>operidol increased effort discounting, while biperiden diminished it. Similarly, haloperidol <lb/>induced more stochastic choices, while biperiden led to more deterministic decisions <lb/>(Table 1). For both drug-specific effects on the effort discounting parameter κ, we acknowl-<lb/>edge that, strictly speaking, the 95% HDI of s κ BIP (HDI Mean = -0.012, HDI 95% = [-0.000; <lb/>0.027]) and s κ HAL (HDI Mean = 0.013, HDI 95% = [-0.025; 0.000]) did overlap with zero, albeit <lb/>to a very small extent (Fig 4A). Notably, the density that did not overlap with zero still <lb/>accounted for more than 94% of the posterior distribution (94.8% HDI &gt; 0 for haloperidol <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>and 94.4% HDI &gt; 0 for biperiden). This provides strong evidence for a credible modulation of <lb/>effort discounting by cholinergic M1 and dopaminergic D2 receptor manipulation, despite the <lb/>slight overlap. <lb/>A similar pattern emerged in the analysis of the inverse temperature parameter, further sup-<lb/>porting the partly opposing effects of these neurotransmitters. The HDIs for s β HAL (HDI Mean <lb/>= -0.089, HDI 95% = [-0.164; -0.010]) and s β BIP (HDI Mean = 0.127, HDI 95% = [0.048; 0.219]) <lb/>did not overlap with zero, supporting the modulatory effects of these drugs on choice stochas-<lb/>ticity. Specifically, haloperidol increased choice stochasticity, while biperiden exhibited the <lb/>opposite effect (Fig 4B). <lb/>For the delay discounting task, computational modelling revealed credible evidence only <lb/>for a dopaminergic, but not cholinergic modulation of delay discounting (Fig 4D and Table 2). <lb/>In line with the diminished delay sensitivity reported above, haloperidol reduced delay dis-<lb/>counting, making participants more willing to wait for greater financial rewards with increas-<lb/>ing levels of delay (s κ HAL : HDI Mean = -0.630, HDI 95% = [-1.083; -0.237]). For biperiden, we <lb/>did not observe any shift of the discounting parameter (s κ BIP : HDI Mean = -0.125, HDI 95% = <lb/>[-0.410; 0.148]). Next, we examined the effects of dopaminergic and muscarinic antagonism <lb/>on choice stochasticity (Fig 4E). Biperiden credibly increased the choice stochasticity (s β BIP : <lb/>HDI Mean = -0.043, HDI 95% = [-0.085; -0.000]), while we did not find credible evidence for a <lb/>modulatory effect of haloperidol, as the 95% HDI overlapped with zero (s β HAL : HDI Mean = <lb/>-0.055, HDI 95% = [-0.114; 0.006]). <lb/>Lastly, to test whether putatively confounding side effects of the pharmacological treatment <lb/>account for our main effects of interest, we tested medication effects on several control mea-<lb/>sures, including mood (alertness, calmness, and contentedness) and basic physiological <lb/>parameters (heart rate, systolic, and diastolic blood pressure), using Bayesian linear mixed <lb/>models. In short, biperiden administration induced reductions in systolic blood pressure and <lb/>heart rate at T 1 and at T 2 . Moreover, relative to placebo, both biperiden and haloperidol caused <lb/>decreases in subjective alertness ratings at T 2 (all HDI 95% &lt; 0). T 1 represents the measurement <lb/>taken before participants began the effort discounting task, and T 2 represents the measure-<lb/>ment taken after they completed the delay discounting task. Importantly, neither the changes <lb/>in blood pressure or heart rate, nor reductions in alertness showed credible correlations with <lb/>any shift parameter that was credibly modulated by haloperidol or biperiden in both tasks. <lb/>This implies that the drug-induced changes in behaviour were not linked to drug effects on <lb/>alertness, heart rate, or blood pressure. More detailed information can be found in the Sup-<lb/>porting Results in S1 Text. <lb/>Taken together, the results derived from hierarchical Bayesian modelling are consistent <lb/>with findings obtained from the GLMMs. Diminishing dopaminergic D2 receptor activity <lb/>Table 1. Summary of the group-level parameter estimates for the effort discounting task, including the mean, SD, <lb/>and the lower and upper bounds of the 95% HDI interval. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>2.5% <lb/>97.5% <lb/>κ <lb/>0.102 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.086 <lb/>0.118 <lb/>β <lb/>0.667 <lb/>0.032 <lb/>0.605 <lb/>0.732 <lb/>s κ HAL <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>-0.000 <lb/>0.027 <lb/>s κ BIP <lb/>-0.012 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>-0.025 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>s β HAL <lb/>-0.089 <lb/>0.038 <lb/>-0.164 <lb/>-0.010 <lb/>s β BIP <lb/>0.127 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>0.048 <lb/>0.219 <lb/>HDI, highest density interval; SD, standard deviation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 4. Drug effect on computational parameters. Posterior distributions and changes in the SV from the hierarchical <lb/>Bayesian models. (a) In the effort discounting task, the discounting parameter κ is modulated in opposite directions by <lb/>the drugs, with haloperidol increasing and biperiden decreasing effort discounting. (b) Similarly, these opposite effects <lb/>are also present in the modulation of the softmax inverse temperature β, reflecting choice stochasticity. Biperiden <lb/>administration led to more deterministic choices, while haloperidol induced more stochastic choices. (c) Modelled <lb/>discounting functions show steeper discounting under haloperidol and flatter discounting under biperiden. (d) In the <lb/>delay discounting task, the discounting parameter κ is reduced by haloperidol, with no credible modulatory effect of <lb/>biperiden. (e) In contrast, the softmax inverse temperature β is reduced by biperiden, indicating more stochastic <lb/>choices. (f) Overall, participants showed flatter discounting of future rewards under haloperidol compared to placebo. <lb/>In (a), (b), (d), and (e), bold (light) dots represent the group-level (participant-level) mean estimate. The horizontal <lb/>bars represent the group-level 95% HDI. In (c) and (f), the SVs are displayed as a discount function of effort and delay. <lb/>Parabolic (effort discounting task) and hyperbolic (delay discounting task) functions are fitted on group-level mean <lb/>estimates for each drug (see Materials and methods). HDI, highest density interval; SV, subjective value. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>decreases the willingness to invest effort for rewards, possibly by amplifying effort discounting. <lb/>Conversely, the administration of a cholinergic M1 receptor antagonist produces opposite <lb/>effects. However, this pattern of opponent dopaminergic and cholinergic effects on specific <lb/>components of effort discounting was not present in the delay discounting task. Instead, the <lb/>findings suggest a reduced impact of delay on decision-making under haloperidol, while biper-<lb/>iden affected only the choice stochasticity. This implies that contrasting effects of dopaminer-<lb/>gic and cholinergic manipulations may reflect computationally specific, rather than universal <lb/>effects. <lb/>Across-task relationship of discounting behaviour <lb/>Lastly, as an exploratory analysis, we asked whether there was a relationship between discount-<lb/>ing of delays versus efforts across individuals. In other words, we tested whether people show-<lb/>ing steep discounting of physical efforts would also show steep delay-based discounting. In <lb/>line with previous findings [36,38], we found no relationship between individuals&apos; tendency to <lb/>discount rewards based on efforts compared to delays (no credible correlation between the <lb/>effort and delay discounting parameters κ under placebo; r = -0.17, HDI 95% = [-0.06; 0.39]). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we investigated the effects of pharmacologically manipulating dopaminergic and <lb/>cholinergic neurotransmission on cost-benefit decision-making in healthy young adults. Spe-<lb/>cifically, we administered haloperidol or biperiden, 2 drugs that selectively block either dopa-<lb/>mine D2-like or muscarinic M1 acetylcholine receptors, respectively, and tested the effects on <lb/>discounting a monetary reward as a function of either effort or delay. In short, we found that <lb/>reducing dopaminergic transmission at D2-like receptors decreased participants&apos; willingness <lb/>to invest physical effort for monetary rewards and attenuated the impact of delay on decision-<lb/>making. In contrast, cholinergic M1 receptor manipulations promoted the preference for <lb/>high-effort options, without affecting delay-based choices. <lb/>The goal of our study was 3-fold. First, we sought to conceptually replicate the boosting <lb/>effects of dopamine on motivation. Second, we examined the contribution of acetylcholine, <lb/>acting at M1 receptors, on cost-benefit decision-making, as the influence of muscarinic acetyl-<lb/>choline receptors on human (value-based) decision-making has rarely been reported. Third, <lb/>we aimed to address the conflicting literature on dopamine&apos;s role in delay-based decision-<lb/>making by providing data from a large sample using a within-subjects design. <lb/>Dopamine has been widely suggested to play a key role in various aspects of reward process-<lb/>ing and cost-benefit decision-making [39-41]. It modulates choices based on expected rewards <lb/>and costs associated with different options [42-44]. However, the direction of dopaminergic <lb/>Table 2. Summary of the group-level parameter estimates for the delay discounting task, including the mean, SD, <lb/>and the lower and upper bounds of the 95% HDI interval. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>2.5% <lb/>97.5% <lb/>κ <lb/>-4.621 <lb/>0.271 <lb/>-5.176 <lb/>-4.107 <lb/>β <lb/>0.356 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.272 <lb/>0.449 <lb/>s κ HAL <lb/>-0.630 <lb/>0.214 <lb/>-1.083 <lb/>-0.237 <lb/>s κ BIP <lb/>-0.125 <lb/>0.142 <lb/>-0.410 <lb/>0.148 <lb/>s β HAL <lb/>-0.055 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>-0.114 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>s β BIP <lb/>-0.043 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>-0.085 <lb/>-0.000 <lb/>HDI, highest density interval; SD, standard deviation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714.t002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>manipulations on different aspects of costs remains ambiguous. Traditionally, dopamine has <lb/>been implicated in promoting behaviour that maximises reward outcomes, suggesting that <lb/>increased dopaminergic activity energises behaviour to approach high-reward options despite <lb/>associated costs [7,45-47]. According to this view, increasing dopaminergic transmission <lb/>should bias decision-making toward high-reward options, even when they involve higher costs <lb/>such as effort, delay, and risk. Conversely, decreasing dopaminergic transmission should have <lb/>the opposite effect. <lb/>In line with this view, in our study, the administration of a D2-like receptor antagonist did <lb/>in fact reduce the willingness to invest physical effort for reward. However, contrary to the <lb/>notion that dopamine supports reward-maximising behaviour, our findings in the delay dis-<lb/>counting task did not confirm the expected pattern. We observed a decrease in delay discount-<lb/>ing under haloperidol, rather than an increase. While there is indeed a substantial body of <lb/>evidence suggesting enhancing effects of dopamine on motivation, as demonstrated by studies <lb/>highlighting its involvement in promoting reward-seeking behaviour [8,9,48,49], the impact of <lb/>pharmacological manipulations targeting other cost-related factors, such as delay [13,15,17,50] <lb/>and risk [51-53], has produced rather inconsistent findings. These studies showed either con-<lb/>tradicting results regarding dopaminergic manipulations or no effect at all. These inconsisten-<lb/>cies challenge traditional views of dopamine and raise questions about the specific <lb/>mechanisms through which dopamine modulates choices that incorporate time-dependent <lb/>costs. A more recent theory proposes that dopamine, acting at D2-like receptors, biases action <lb/>selection by increasing the preference for options with a proximity advantage over more dis-<lb/>tant alternatives [54,55]. This theory is based on studies in rodents, where firing rates of neu-<lb/>rons in the nucleus accumbens are increased by spatially proximal rewards, promoting a <lb/>decision bias towards nearby low-reward options [56]. This notion of proximity, originally <lb/>referring to spatial proximity, has been extended to the context of psychological proximity <lb/>[55]. According to this view, dopamine not only favours options that are physically closer in <lb/>space, but also options that are psychologically closer, as in our case, rewards that are available <lb/>sooner in time. Consequently, the administration of D2 receptor antagonists, which, according <lb/>to this theory, are believed to reduce the proximity bias, have been shown in some studies to <lb/>increase the preference for delayed and risky reward options, which lack the proximity advan-<lb/>tage [19,20,51,57]. In other words, this theoretical framework proposes that dopamine may <lb/>play a dual role in (1) promoting choices towards options with a psychological proximity <lb/>advantage; and (2) weighing reward magnitudes against associated costs. Our findings of <lb/>decreased delay discounting under haloperidol align with this theory, potentially suggesting a <lb/>diminished preference for more proximal options when D2-receptor activity is reduced, <lb/>resulting in increased endurance for higher (time) costs. On the other hand, the reduction of <lb/>dopaminergic neurotransmission had the opposite effect on effort discounting, leading to a <lb/>diminished willingness to bear higher (effort) costs. This apparently conflicting finding <lb/>between effort and time costs may be explained by the fact that neither the low-effort nor the <lb/>high-effort option had a pronounced psychological proximity advantage. Thus, in this specific <lb/>context of cost-benefit decision-making, the proximity factor appears to be less relevant, and <lb/>dopamine instead may promote behaviour aimed at maximising rewards simply by weighing <lb/>rewards against associated costs. Importantly, our experimental paradigm did not directly <lb/>manipulate psychological proximity, nor did it distinguish between proximity effects and the <lb/>impact of delay. Therefore, specific effects of dopamine on psychological proximity in human <lb/>delay discounting remain highly speculative and warrant further investigation with experi-<lb/>mental paradigms specifically tailored to this question. <lb/>Low doses of dopamine receptor antagonists may facilitate dopaminergic transmission by <lb/>primarily blocking presynaptic autoreceptors, which may increase rather than decrease <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>dopamine release [58,59]. We would however argue that such a presynaptic mechanism of <lb/>action is unlikely to explain our findings. First, a positron emission tomography study found <lb/>that the same dose of haloperidol as used here led to high levels of D2 receptor occupancy in <lb/>the striatum [60]. Second, our pattern of results aligns with studies in rodents showing motiva-<lb/>tional deficits following ventral striatal dopamine depletion [61-63]. Third, high doses of halo-<lb/>peridol have been shown to reduce alertness [64], whereas drugs like methylphenidate that <lb/>increase synaptic dopamine levels, enhance subjective ratings of alertness [65,66]. Consistent <lb/>with this, we observed a reduction in alertness ratings following haloperidol administration. <lb/>Together, this suggests that our results are best explained by a blockade of postsynaptic D2 <lb/>receptors by haloperidol. <lb/>Notably, prior research has highlighted the contribution of other neurotransmitters such as <lb/>serotonin [22,67], adenosine [68,69], and acetylcholine [23,29,70], in the weighing of costs and <lb/>rewards. However, the exact role of these neurotransmitters in reward processing and cost-ben-<lb/>efit decision-making in humans has been rarely investigated. Understanding the involvement of <lb/>acetylcholine, due to its reciprocal activity with dopamine in the striatum, is of particular inter-<lb/>est [24,26,27,71]. At the functional level, these mutual interactions are evident from the fact that <lb/>muscarinic receptor antagonists diminish the extrapyramidal side effects of dopamine antago-<lb/>nists, and, vice versa, muscarinic agonists display antipsychotic properties, resembling the <lb/>action of D2 antagonists [72,73]. Additionally, blocking M1 receptors has been shown to reverse <lb/>motivational impairments induced by dopaminergic antagonism, further emphasising its <lb/>potential role in modulating dopamine-related processes [29]. At the cellular level, it has been <lb/>shown that M1 receptor activation inhibits D2-receptor-mediated effects in the striatum [74]. <lb/>These observations highlight an interplay between acetylcholine and dopamine signalling. <lb/>Therefore, in addition to testing dopaminergic D2-like receptor manipulations, we also investi-<lb/>gated the role of cholinergic M1 receptor neurotransmission on decision-making. <lb/>Indeed, we observed opposing effects of dopaminergic and cholinergic manipulations <lb/>within specific components of effort-, but not delay-based decision-making. Specifically, we <lb/>found evidence for biperiden increasing the willingness to invest effort for rewards and, in line <lb/>with this, decreasing effort discounting. In contrast, haloperidol reduced the general willing-<lb/>ness to invest effort and increased effort discounting. However, we also observed drug effects <lb/>that were not in opposite directions between biperiden and haloperidol. For example, biperi-<lb/>den increased reward sensitivity, while haloperidol had no credible effect on the impact of <lb/>rewards on effort-based choices. Furthermore, haloperidol modulated decision times in both <lb/>experimental tasks, whereas biperiden did not affect them. These findings suggest partially <lb/>opposing effects between both neurotransmitters, mostly evident within specific components <lb/>of effort-based choices. <lb/>This partially opposing mechanistic relationship between dopaminergic and cholinergic <lb/>neurotransmission during the effort discounting task is further reflected in changes in choice <lb/>stochasticity. Previous studies have linked D2 receptor antagonism with increased choice sto-<lb/>chasticity [75,76]. Consistent with these findings, our results revealed that haloperidol admin-<lb/>istration increased stochasticity and thereby reduced value dependency on choices, while <lb/>biperiden had the opposite effect. After lowering cholinergic M1 receptor activity, participants <lb/>were more likely to choose the option with the highest expected value compared to placebo. <lb/>However, it is important to note that biperiden had the opposite effect in the delay discounting <lb/>task, increasing, rather than reducing choice stochasticity. This discrepancy indicates that the <lb/>role of cholinergic neurotransmission in balancing deterministic versus stochastic behaviour is <lb/>more complex and needs further investigation. <lb/>Some limitations should be noted. First, our focus was primarily on striatal D2 receptor <lb/>activity, as haloperidol predominantly targets D2 receptors in the striatum [77]. However, it is <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>important to note that in the context of cost-benefit decision-making, dissociable roles of D1 <lb/>versus D2 receptor activity have been reported [41,54,78], and thus the general role of dopa-<lb/>mine beyond its selective activity on striatal D2 receptors remains unclear. Conversely, biperi-<lb/>den primarily targets M1 receptors in the cortex and striatum [79], making it challenging to <lb/>determine the precise mechanisms underlying cortical and striatal cholinergic modulation and <lb/>the reciprocal effects on dopaminergic activity. Second, previous research has suggested a U-<lb/>shaped dose-response function for dopamine, indicating deleterious effects of both extremely <lb/>high and extremely low levels of dopamine [80,81]. According to this idea, the same dopamine <lb/>agent can produce opposing effects in different individuals. Therefore, it may be insightful to <lb/>consider individual differences in baseline dopamine levels when studying the effects of dopa-<lb/>minergic manipulations. A recent study found evidence for the absence of a correlation <lb/>between dopamine synthesis capacity and putative behavioural proxies of dopamine, such as <lb/>working memory or trait impulsivity [82]. Consequently, investigating baseline dopamine lev-<lb/>els require more costly and invasive techniques, such as positron emission tomography. Third, <lb/>as participants were required to exert physical effort on each trial, fatigue effects could have <lb/>developed in the effort discounting task. While our additional analysis confirmed a general <lb/>fatigue effect and a dual role of haloperidol in both reducing the overall propensity to invest <lb/>effort and in exacerbating the fatigue effect throughout the task, we acknowledge that recent <lb/>studies revealed the existence of distinct states of fatigue [83,84]. Importantly, this was discov-<lb/>ered by using task paradigms and computational models that were designed to distinguish <lb/>between these different types of fatigue. Additionally, it is important to consider that potential <lb/>motor effects, particularly in the context of dopaminergic manipulations, could also affect <lb/>effort discounting behaviour. Future studies could extend our approach by incorporating mea-<lb/>surements of force pulses to investigate potential motor-related effects and apply task designs <lb/>and computational models specifically tailored to capture how drug manipulations might <lb/>affect different forms of fatigue. Lastly, it is important to note that several factors preclude a <lb/>direct quantitative comparison between the delay and effort discounting tasks. These include <lb/>the distinct nature of rewards and costs (hypothetical versus real), varying reward magnitudes <lb/>in both tasks (large versus small), and differences in task structure (fixed versus variable alter-<lb/>native option). Additionally, both tasks were consistently performed in a fixed order within <lb/>and between participants (effort followed by delay). While this ensured consistent drug levels <lb/>within each task, it is potentially introducing task order effects and possibly leading to differen-<lb/>tial drug concentrations between tasks. These methodological differences limit our ability to <lb/>directly compare drug effects across the 2 cost domains. Future research would benefit from <lb/>applying experimental paradigms that manipulate both delay and effort costs within the same <lb/>task, allowing a more controlled and direct comparison of how pharmacological manipula-<lb/>tions differentially influence sensitivity to these distinct cost types. <lb/>In conclusion, our findings support prior research indicating an invigorating effect of dopa-<lb/>mine on motivation in an effort-based decision-making task. Moreover, our study contributed <lb/>to understanding dopamine&apos;s involvement in temporal cost-benefit tradeoffs by revealing <lb/>decreased delay discounting following dopaminergic D2-like receptor antagonism. Further, <lb/>we demonstrate that the administration of biperiden, a muscarinic M1 receptor antagonist, <lb/>had contrasting effects to those of dopaminergic D2 receptor antagonism in the general will-<lb/>ingness to choose high-cost options and the effort discounting parameter. This suggests that in <lb/>the context of human cost-benefit decision-making, the previously reported reciprocal rela-<lb/>tionship between both neurotransmitters may be limited only to specific components of <lb/>behaviour. Our findings indicate that, while D2 receptor activity plays a role in integrating <lb/>both delay and effort costs, acetylcholine, acting at M1 receptors, may have a more specific <lb/>role in effort processing. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>Materials and methods <lb/>Ethics <lb/>Ethical approval for the study (2021-1549) was obtained from the Ethics Committee of the <lb/>Medical Faculty of the University of Du ¨sseldorf, Germany. The study was conducted in accor-<lb/>dance with the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki. Prior to participating, all <lb/>volunteers provided informed written consent. <lb/>Participants <lb/>Participants were recruited for the study via online advertisements and university postings. <lb/>They were initially screened via email interviews to verify compliance with the inclusion and <lb/>exclusion criteria. Inclusion criteria included an age range of 18 to 35 years, a body weight <lb/>ranging from 60 to 90 kg, and a body mass index equal to or greater than 18 and less than 28. <lb/>Exclusion criteria included a history of psychiatric or neurological illnesses, current intake of <lb/>prescription medication (excluding oral contraceptives), current pregnancy or breastfeeding, <lb/>and the presence of any medical conditions contraindicated for the drugs used in the study. <lb/>Additionally, participants with a history of drug use were excluded, with exceptions for alco-<lb/>hol, nicotine, and cannabis, which were limited to consumption of less than 14 units of alcohol <lb/>per week, less than 5 cigarettes per day, and no cannabis consumption within the past month. <lb/>From an initial group of 96 individuals attending the medical screening on site, 33 candi-<lb/>dates decided not to proceed, or they were excluded due to not meeting the participation crite-<lb/>ria (despite otherwise indicated in the prior interview). Eventually, a total of 63 volunteers <lb/>were enrolled in the study. One participant had to be excluded due to experiencing side effects <lb/>following the biperiden testing session, resulting in a final sample size of 62 participants (32 <lb/>female; mean age (standard deviation, SD): 22.79 (3.20); age range: 18 to 35). The sample did <lb/>not include any nonbinary participants. All participants received a fixed reimbursement of 240 <lb/>€ for their participation in all testing sessions and were provided with a flexible payment based <lb/>on their performance in the tasks. <lb/>Procedure <lb/>A double-blind, randomised, within-subject design was employed. Participation involved 3 <lb/>testing sessions, each separated by a minimum of 1 week to ensure complete drug washout. <lb/>Prior to participation, on a separate day, participants underwent a medical screening session <lb/>to determine their eligibility. This screening session consisted of a clinical interview, medical <lb/>assessment, practice trials of both tasks, and completion of several questionnaires assessing <lb/>personality traits, including Apathy Evaluation Scale (AES) [85,86], Beck&apos;s Depression Inven-<lb/>tory (BDI) [87,88], and Barratt Impulsiveness Scale (BIS-15) [89,90]. The final decision regard-<lb/>ing participant suitability for the study was made by a physician at the end of the screening <lb/>session. <lb/>Each testing day followed the same procedure, with the only difference being the adminis-<lb/>tration of a placebo, biperiden (4 mg), or haloperidol (2 mg) in separate sessions. Testing ses-<lb/>sions were scheduled between 9 AM and 12 PM, with efforts made to assign participants to the <lb/>same time slot consistently. Participants were instructed to fast overnight and consume only <lb/>water before the testing session. Additionally, female participants completed a pregnancy test <lb/>before the start of each testing day. Upon arrival, participants underwent a screening con-<lb/>ducted by a physician, who restated the potential effects of the drug and provided a recap of <lb/>the testing day&apos;s procedures. Subsequently, participants received the assigned drug treatment <lb/>along with a standardised breakfast. Orally administered biperiden reaches its peak <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>concentration between 1 and 1.5 h after administration [72,91], while haloperidol reaches its <lb/>peak concentration only between 2 and 6 h after administration [92]. In order to follow a dou-<lb/>ble-blind procedure while also accounting for variations in the drugs&apos; peak times, a dummy <lb/>drug application was included. Thus, on each testing day, a second capsule was administered <lb/>120 min after the first drug application, resulting in the planned delay between drug and effort <lb/>discounting task of approximately 180 min for haloperidol (179.57 ± 2.61) and, on a separate <lb/>day, approximately 60 min (59.65 ± 1.30) for biperiden. The second task was performed <lb/>205.59 min (± 3.12) after haloperidol and 86.24 min (± 6.09) after biperiden administration. <lb/>Shortly before starting the experimental task, participants further completed the trail-making <lb/>test A [93]. Blood pressure and heart rate were measured 3 times throughout the testing day: at <lb/>T 0 (before drug administration), T 1 (before starting the effort discounting task), and T 2 (after <lb/>finishing the delay discounting task). These measurements coincided with mood assessments <lb/>using Visual Analogue Scales [94]. Please refer to Fig 1A for a detailed explanation of the pro-<lb/>cedure. The tasks were presented in a fixed order during each session, starting with the effort <lb/>discounting task (Fig 1B) and concluding with the delay discounting task (Fig 1C). These dis-<lb/>counting paradigms were implemented using Visual Basic software and displayed on a 15.6&quot; <lb/>laptop screen (Dell Latitude E5550). Participants used an external keypad to indicate their <lb/>choices, arranging the laptop and keypad in a manner that was most comfortable for them. <lb/>Experimental tasks <lb/>Effort discounting task. Participants engaged in a modified version of the Apple Tree <lb/>Task, which has been previously utilised with both healthy volunteers and patients with neuro-<lb/>logical diseases [5,95,96]. Unlike the original task where participants accepted or rejected <lb/>offers, in this modified task, they were presented with 2 alternative options on each trial. Prior <lb/>to each experimental session, the participants&apos; maximum voluntary contraction (MVC) was <lb/>assessed by having them grip a handheld dynamometer (Vernier, Orlando, United States of <lb/>America) with their dominant hand as forcefully as possible. The MVC was determined imme-<lb/>diately before starting the task by measuring the highest force exerted over 3 contractions. <lb/>During each trial, they had to choose between a high-reward/high-effort (high-cost) and a <lb/>low-reward/low-effort (low-cost) offer. Participants had unlimited time for their decision. <lb/>Notably, both the reward levels and effort levels of each option were varied among 5 possible <lb/>levels. The reward levels ranged from 2 to 16 (2, 4, 8, 12, and 16), and the effort levels ranged <lb/>from no effort to 80% (0%, 20%, 40%, 60%, and 80%) of the individually determined MVC. <lb/>After making a choice, participants were given a 5-s window to squeeze the handheld dyna-<lb/>mometer and reach the required effort level. They had to maintain the required force for at <lb/>least 1 s. Throughout this effort production period, a bar visually represented the force exerted, <lb/>providing real-time feedback. Following successful trials, participants received feedback on the <lb/>reward earned during the trial. If participants failed to reach the designated effort level, no <lb/>apples were gathered. In cases where participants chose an offer that required no effort, they <lb/>had to wait for the same duration without engaging in squeezing. At the end of the experiment, <lb/>we asked participants to rate the perceived level of demand for each effort level using a Likert <lb/>scale ranging from 0 (&quot;not demanding at all&quot;) to 20 (&quot;extremely demanding&quot;). This subjective <lb/>rating allowed us to examine whether the administration of the drugs had any effects on partic-<lb/>ipants&apos; perception of the demand associated with each effort level. <lb/>Each participant completed a total of 125 trials, divided into 5 blocks. The trial structure <lb/>was full randomised for each participant and experimental session. To prevent strategic behav-<lb/>iour and mitigate delay discounting effects, all blocks and trials were the same length, regard-<lb/>less of previous choices made. Importantly, patients were required to squeeze the handheld <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>dynamometer after every trial (if effort production was chosen), meaning that no hypothetical <lb/>choices were made. Based on their task performance, participants received a flexible payment <lb/>consisting of 1 cent for each apple they collected. <lb/>Delay discounting task. After completing the effort discounting task, participants pro-<lb/>ceeded to the delay-based decision-making task. In this task, they were presented with a similar <lb/>choice paradigm, but this time between a high-reward/high-delay (high-cost) and a low-<lb/>reward/low-delay (low-cost) option on each trial, again without any time limit. The tasks <lb/>shared a common structure, with participants consistently facing decisions involving a tradeoff <lb/>between a more favourable outcome with higher associated costs and a less favourable out-<lb/>come with fewer costs. In contrast to the previous task, the low-cost option was fixed at 20 € <lb/>and available immediately across all trials. The high-cost option varied between 20.20 € and <lb/>260 € (20.20, 20.40, 21, 22, 24, 30, 36, 40, 50, 60, 80, 100, 140, 200, and 260 €), with associated <lb/>delays ranging from 1 day to 60 days (1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 30, and 60). This resulted in a total of 105 <lb/>unique high-cost combinations. <lb/>Participants completed 2 blocks, with each block containing all unique combinations, <lb/>resulting in a total of 210 trials. We used a pseudorandomised trial order, counterbalanced <lb/>across experimental sessions but not across participants. Consistent with previous studies, all <lb/>choices in this task were hypothetical [97,98]. However, participants were instructed to imag-<lb/>ine that one of their choices would be randomly selected and paid out. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Regression-based analysis. To investigate the influence of drug administration (com-<lb/>pared to placebo) and experimental manipulations (i.e., reward magnitude, delay, and/or <lb/>effort) on choice behaviour, we employed logistic Bayesian GLMMs, using the brms package <lb/>[99] in R (Version 4.1.3). In these models, we regressed choices (choosing the high-cost option <lb/>versus choosing the low-cost option) on fixed-effect predictors including drug, reward, cost <lb/>(i.e., delay or effort), and all possible interaction terms. Importantly, to test drug-specific <lb/>effects on behaviour, we included the drug condition (placebo, haloperidol, biperiden) as a <lb/>3-level categorical predictor with placebo set as the reference. Thus, all drug-related main and <lb/>interaction effects are estimated in reference to the placebo. For the effort discounting task, as <lb/>predictors we used the difference term between both the reward magnitude and effort levels of <lb/>the 2 presented options (high-cost option-low-cost option). In the delay discounting task, the <lb/>reward and delay levels of the varying high-cost option were included as regressors. To <lb/>account for individual differences, all fixed-effect predictors were also modelled as random <lb/>slopes in addition to subject-specific random intercepts. To ensure robust and informative <lb/>analyses, we followed the approach suggested by Gelman and colleagues [100]. Weakly infor-<lb/>mative priors were employed, with nonbinary variables scaled to have a mean of 0 and a stan-<lb/>dard deviation of 0.5. Posterior distributions of the parameter estimates were obtained by <lb/>running 4 chains with 3,000 samples (1,000 samples for warmup). We present the 95% highest <lb/>density intervals (HDIs) of the estimates to capture the uncertainty in the parameter estimates. <lb/>The 95% HDI indicates that there is a 95% probability that the true parameter value falls within <lb/>this interval. If the 95% HDI does not overlap with zero, it provides credible evidence that the <lb/>respective model parameter is meaningful [101,102]. For detailed information on the models <lb/>employed in this analysis, please refer to the Supporting Materials and Methods in S1 Text. <lb/>Order and fatigue control analysis. To further test for potential confounding effects on <lb/>choice behaviour, we ran separate control regression analyses. For these models, we used the <lb/>structure of the original GLMMs but included additional fixed-effect predictors to control for <lb/>session and fatigue effects. Specifically, we included trial number as a predictor to account for <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>16 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>potential systematic changes in choice behaviour throughout the task progress. In separate <lb/>models, session was included as a fixed effect to control for potential learning or drug order <lb/>effects across different experimental sessions. Importantly, to capture potential interactions <lb/>between these control variables and the drug manipulations, we included the two-way interac-<lb/>tion terms in the fixed-effects structure. This allows to investigate whether the effects of the <lb/>drug manipulation on choice behaviour differed as a function of the task progress or experi-<lb/>mental session. All other aspects of the model specification, including random-effects struc-<lb/>ture, priors, and estimation procedures, remained identical to the original regression models <lb/>described above. <lb/>Hierarchical Bayesian modelling. Next, to investigate the impact of dopaminergic and <lb/>cholinergic manipulations on underlying cognitive processes, specifically how individuals inte-<lb/>grate rewards and costs to discount subjective reward values, we employed hierarchical Bayes-<lb/>ian modelling. This approach allowed us to estimate both group-level hyperparameters and <lb/>individual subject-level estimates, leveraging the hierarchical structure of the experimental <lb/>design. By incorporating information from each individual&apos;s estimates into the group esti-<lb/>mates and vice versa, we obtained more robust and reliable parameter estimates compared to <lb/>conventional methods like maximum likelihood estimation [101]. <lb/>To capture how changes in the SVs are influenced by reward, effort, and delay, we <lb/>employed a single-parameter discounting model to determine which discounting function <lb/>best describes the observed behaviour. Initially, participants&apos; responses from the placebo con-<lb/>dition were fitted to 4 commonly used models for discounting: linear, parabolic, hyperbolic, <lb/>and exponential [2,36,103,104]. Model fits were compared using the trial-based leave-one-out <lb/>information criterion (LOOIC) from the loo package [105]. <lb/>Consistent with previous findings, delay discounting was best described by a hyperbolic <lb/>model [34,35], whereas effort discounting showed the best fit with a parabolic model [2,36,37]. <lb/>See Supporting Materials and Methods in S1 Text for more details. The discounting parameter <lb/>in the delay discounting model was modelled in log space due to the skewed distribution of the <lb/>values towards zero. <lb/>SV HC ðtÞ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>¼ <lb/>R ðtÞ <lb/>1 þ expðkÞ * D ðtÞ <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>SVðHC ðtÞ Þ ¼ R HC ðtÞ À k * E HC ðtÞ <lb/>2 <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>SVðLC ðtÞ Þ ¼ R LC ðtÞ À k * E LC ðtÞ <lb/>2 <lb/>ð3Þ <lb/>In the delay discounting model (Eq 1), R t represents the reward magnitude and D t repre-<lb/>sents the delay in days of the high-cost option (HC) on trial t, while the SV of the low-cost <lb/>option (LC) was fixed at 20 for each trial. In contrast, the effort discounting models (Eqs 2 and <lb/>3) involve varying levels of both options. In this model, the SV of the HC option and the SV of <lb/>the LC option are calculated separately. Once again, R t denotes the corresponding reward <lb/>magnitude, and E t represents the associated effort in percentage on trial t. <lb/>k ¼ k PLC þ I HAL ðtÞ * s k HAL þ I BIP ðtÞ * s k BIP <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>Consistent with previous studies that examined drug effects on changes in discounting <lb/>[20,106,107], we extended the original single-parameter model by incorporating 2 additional <lb/>free parameters (Eq 4). In both cases, κ is the discounting parameter, either reflecting delay <lb/>discounting or effort discounting. A higher κ value indicates a greater degree of discounting, <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>17 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>whereas a lower κ value suggests less discounting. To capture potential drug effects (compared <lb/>to placebo), 2 separate shift parameters (s κ HAL for haloperidol and s κ BIP for biperiden) were <lb/>included to model changes in the discounting rate. A positive shift parameter indicates that <lb/>the corresponding drug increases discounting, while a negative shift parameter suggests that <lb/>the drug decreases discounting. The condition for each trial is indicated by the dummy-coded <lb/>variable Ι, which indicates the drug condition of the current trial. <lb/>P HC ðtÞ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>¼ <lb/>expðSVðHC ðtÞ Þ * bÞ <lb/>expðSVðHC ðtÞ Þ * bÞ þ expðSVðLC ðtÞ Þ * bÞ <lb/>ð5Þ <lb/>b ¼ b PLC þ I HAL ðtÞ * s b HAL þ I BIP ðtÞ * s b BIP <lb/>ð6Þ <lb/>We then used a softmax function to transform the option values to choice probabilities <lb/>(Eq 5). The choice stochasticity was modelled using the inverse temperature parameter β. A <lb/>lower β value indicates more stochastic behaviour. Conversely, a higher β value suggests more <lb/>deterministic choices. <lb/>Similar to the previous analysis, 2 additional shift parameters (s β HAL for haloperidol and s <lb/>β BIP for biperiden) were introduced to capture potential drug effects on choice stochasticity <lb/>(Eq 6). A positive s β parameter indicates that the corresponding drug decreases the level of <lb/>stochasticity in choices, while a negative s β parameter suggests that the drug increases <lb/>stochasticity. <lb/>Model estimation was performed using MCMC sampling as implemented in STAN [108] <lb/>via R and the rSTAN package (Version 2.21.0). We utilised separate group-level distributions <lb/>for all parameters in the placebo condition (i.e., κ and β), as well as for the shift parameters <lb/>(i.e., s κ HAL , s κ BIP , s β HAL , and s β BIP ), which capture potential modulatory effects of the drugs. <lb/>Prior distributions for the parameter means and standard deviations were chosen within plau-<lb/>sible ranges based on previous findings [20,106,109-111]. The sampling process involved run-<lb/>ning 4 chains with 4,000 iterations after a warmup period of 3,000 iterations. Chain <lb/>convergence was assessed using the Gelman-Rubinstein convergence diagnostic r-hat, with <lb/>values less than 1.01 considered acceptable [112]. We report the mean of the posterior group <lb/>distribution for all parameters, along with the associated 95% HDI. <lb/>Please refer to the Supporting Materials and Methods in S1 Text for details of the prior dis-<lb/>tributions, model comparison, and model estimation procedure. <lb/>Model validation and parameter recovery. To assess the model&apos;s ability to capture and <lb/>recover important characteristics of the data, we conducted a model validation and parameter <lb/>recovery analysis. This involved generating 500 synthetic datasets per participant using the <lb/>posterior distributions of subject-level parameters obtained from the winning models. From <lb/>these 500 datasets, we randomly selected 10 datasets for each participant and conducted the <lb/>same analysis as described above, using the synthetic datasets instead of the actual data. <lb/>First, to validate that the simulated data accurately captures the key features of the partici-<lb/>pants&apos; behaviour, we simulated the relative choice rates and visualised how behavioural pat-<lb/>terns changed as a function of varying levels of costs and rewards. Next, to evaluate the <lb/>recovery of group-level parameters, we examined whether the simulated group-level parame-<lb/>ters fell within the 95% HDI of the actual group-level parameter distribution. For the subject-<lb/>level parameter estimates, we calculated the correlation between the simulated (averaged <lb/>across all 10 simulated datasets) and true estimated subject-level parameters. The results of the <lb/>model validation and parameter recovery are presented in the Supporting Results in S1 Text. <lb/>Drug effects on vital signs, mood, trail-making performance, MVC, and effort rating. <lb/>The effects of the drugs on mood (alertness, calmness, and contentedness) and physiological <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>18 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <body>measures (heart rate, systolic, and diastolic blood pressure) were analysed using Bayesian lin-<lb/>ear mixed models. If credible drug interactions were found, we further explored the relation-<lb/>ship between drug-induced alterations in behaviour and potential explanatory factors, <lb/>including changes in subjective mood ratings and/or physiological responses. Specifically, we <lb/>calculated the absolute differences in mood ratings and physiological parameters between T 0 <lb/>(before drug administration) and the time point where a credible drug effect was observed <lb/>(either T 1 or T 2 ). These difference values were then correlated with the shift parameters that <lb/>capture drug-induced changes in performance. The purpose of this Bayesian correlation analy-<lb/>sis was to exclude that drug-induced changes in mood ratings or physiological measures could <lb/>account for the observed drug-induced changes in behaviour. We further investigated poten-<lb/>tial confounding drug effects on trail-making response times, MVC, and subjective effort per-<lb/>ception. These analyses did not reveal significant effects of drug manipulation on any of these <lb/>measures (see Supporting Results in S1 Text). More detailed descriptions of these analysis are <lb/>presented in the Supporting Materials and Methods in S1 Text. <lb/>Association between task-and drug-specific computational parameter estimates. We <lb/>investigated the association between discounting tendencies across different cost domains, <lb/>specifically exploring whether participants who exhibit stronger effort discounting also dis-<lb/>played stronger delay discounting. To examine this, we performed a Bayesian correlation anal-<lb/>ysis using the mean estimates of the κ parameters from the placebo conditions in both the <lb/>effort and delay discounting task. <lb/>Computational parameter estimates, self-ratings scores, and demographics. In a sup-<lb/>plementary analysis, we investigated potential associations between self-reported question-<lb/>naire scores, demographic data (including age and sex of the participants), and the estimated <lb/>discounting parameters κ from the baseline (placebo) condition of both tasks. To this end, we <lb/>performed robust linear regressions with the respective discounting parameter as the outcome <lb/>variable (see Supporting Materials and Methods and Supporting Results in S1 Text). <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Text. Supporting Results; Supporting Materials and Methods. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Data. Excel file containing the underlying numerical data for the effort discounting <lb/>task in Figs 2 and S8. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S2 Data. Excel file containing the underlying numerical data for the delay discounting task <lb/>in Figs 2 and S8. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Fig. Choice behaviour in the placebo (baseline) condition. Posterior distributions and <lb/>95% HDI of the logistic Bayesian generalized linear mixed models depict the estimate of each <lb/>task parameter on choosing the high-cost option. (a) Higher reward magnitudes increased the <lb/>overall willingness to invest physical effort for a corresponding reward in the effort discount-<lb/>ing task. (b) Higher levels of effort had the opposite effect. (c) Similarly, higher reward magni-<lb/>tudes increased the likelihood to choose the high-cost option in the delay discounting task. (d) <lb/>In contrast, higher levels of delay decreased the willingness to choose the high-reward/high-<lb/>delay option. Bold dots represent the mean group-level estimate of the posterior distribution. <lb/>The horizontal bars represent the group-level 95% highest density interval. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>19 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">S2 Fig. Model validation for the effort (a-c) and delay discounting task (d-f). Plots depict <lb/>the averaged overall proportion of choosing the high-cost option as a function of reward and <lb/>cost for both the effort (a-c) and the delay (d-f) discounting task. The upper panels display the <lb/>actual data and the lower panels present the simulated data for comparison. Group-level <lb/>means are indicated by dots, with error bars representing the standard error of the mean. In <lb/>the effort discounting task, reward levels are presented as the difference in magnitude between <lb/>the high-and low-cost option, and in the delay discounting task, reward levels are shown as <lb/>the reward value of the high-cost option. Likewise, the effort level corresponds to the difference <lb/>between the proportions of the individually calibrated MVC of the high-and low-cost option, <lb/>while the delay levels indicate the delay of the high-cost option. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Parameter recovery of the group-level posterior distributions for the effort (a-f) <lb/>and delay discounting task (g-l). We tested the ability of our models to recover parameters <lb/>using simulated datasets. Each panel displays the actual distribution (red) of each parameter of <lb/>interest alongside 10 corresponding simulated datasets (blue). Horizontal bars, depicted in red, <lb/>represent the group-level 95% HDI of the actual parameter estimate, with dots indicating the <lb/>mean of the distribution. The shaded area in blue depicts the 95% HDI of the simulated param-<lb/>eter estimates. We evaluated whether the mean estimates of the simulated group-level parame-<lb/>ter values fell within the 95% HDI of the true parameter distribution. The parameter recovery <lb/>analysis of the group-level distribution demonstrated positive results, as all mean parameter <lb/>estimates of the simulated data are located within the 95% HDI of the actual dataset. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S4 Fig. Parameter recovery of the subject-level parameters for the effort (a-f) and delay <lb/>discounting task (g-l). We calculated the Pearson correlation coefficients between the mean <lb/>subject-level posterior distribution of the simulated and actual data. For the simulated data, <lb/>subject-level means were averaged across each dataset. The correlation coefficients demon-<lb/>strate strong to excellent correlations (all r &gt; 0.8), further confirming that the models are able <lb/>to accurately to recover the actual task parameter values. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S5 Fig. Physiological effects of drug administration. Plots depict the change in each physio-<lb/>logical parameter following drug administration. (a) Diastolic BP decreased at T1 (HDI Mean = <lb/>-3.75, HDI 95% = [-5.71; -1.85]) and T2 (HDI Mean = -2.99, HDI 95% = [-4.96; -1.07]) com-<lb/>pared to T0. However, we did not find a credible main or interaction effect of drug, implying <lb/>that diastolic BP decreases as the task progresses irrespective of drug administration. (b) Sys-<lb/>tolic BP reflected notable two-way biperiden interactions at T1 and T2 (Biperiden x T1: HDI-<lb/>Mean = -3.91, HDI 95% = [-7.74; -1.07]; Biperiden x T2: HDI Mean = -4.80, HDI 95% = [-8.74; <lb/>-0.95]), suggesting a more pronounced decrease in systolic BP following Biperiden applica-<lb/>tion. (c) Heart rate was reduced at T1 (HDI Mean = -6.82, HDI 95% = [-10.74; -2.97]) and T2 <lb/>(HDI Mean = -7.88, HDI 95% = [-11.83; -3.89]) relative to T0. A credible two-way interaction <lb/>was found between Biperiden at T1 and T2 (Biperiden x T1: HDI Mean = -6.82, HDI 95% = <lb/>[-10.74; -2.97]; Biperiden x T2: HDI Mean = -7.88, HDI 95% = [-11.83; -3.89]), indicating that, <lb/>analogously to the drop in systolic BP, the drop in heart rate at T1 and T2 is more pronounced <lb/>following biperiden administration compared to placebo. Dots represent the group-level <lb/>mean, error bars depict the standard error of the mean. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S6 Fig. Subjective mood rating effects of drug administration. Plots show alterations in sub-<lb/>jective mood ratings following drug administration. No credible effects of time or drug were <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>20 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">found for (a) contentedness and (b) calmness ratings. However, (c) alertness ratings notably <lb/>decreased over time, exhibiting a credible drop at both T1 (HDI Mean = -0.08, HDI 95% = <lb/>[-0.16; -0.01]) and T2 (HDI Mean = -0.23, HDI 95% = [-0.30; -0.15]) compared to T0. Impor-<lb/>tantly, at T2, credible two-way interaction effects were found for biperiden and haloperidol <lb/>(Biperiden x T2: HDI Mean = -0.15, HDI 95% = [-0.26; -0.05]; Haloperidol x T2: HDI Mean = <lb/>-0.15, HDI 95% = [-0.25; -0.04]), suggesting that both drugs led to more pronounced reduc-<lb/>tions in alertness ratings towards the end of the experiment, compared to placebo. Dots repre-<lb/>sent the group-level mean, error bars depict the standard error of the mean. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S7 Fig. Drug effects on trail-making test performance, subjective effort ratings, and MVC. <lb/>(a) No credible drug effects were observed for response times during trail-making test A. How-<lb/>ever, credible main effects of session were found (Session 2: HDI Mean = -4.77, HDI 95% = <lb/>[-8.41; -1.17]; Session 3: HDI Mean = -6.40, HDI 95% = [-10.14; -2.66]), suggesting that partici-<lb/>pants became faster after the first session, possibly due to familiarity with the task. (b) Effort <lb/>ratings were modulated only by increasing effort levels (HDI Mean = 5.15, HDI 95% = [4.81; <lb/>5.49]), suggesting no drug effects on the subjective experience of effort demand. (c) MVC was <lb/>not credibly modulated by drug administration, indicating that participant&apos;s ability to exert <lb/>effort was not modulated by drug either. Dots represent the group-level mean and error bars <lb/>represent standard error of the mean. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S8 Fig. Decision times in milliseconds (ms) in the effort (left panel) and delay (right <lb/>panel) discounting tasks. (a) Overall decision times in the effort discounting task (left) were <lb/>not affected by haloperidol or biperiden. However, in the delay discounting task (right), halo-<lb/>peridol reduced the decision times. (b) Decision times decreased with larger rewards. Haloper-<lb/>idol reduced this speed-up effect in both the effort (left) and delay discounting task (right <lb/>panel). (c) Conversely, decision times increased with higher cost levels. This effect was not <lb/>modulated by any drug in the effort discounting task (left). However, in the delay discounting <lb/>task (right), haloperidol diminished the decelerating effect of increasing delay levels. (a) Shows <lb/>group-level (single-subject) means represented by bold (light) dots. (b and c) Display averaged <lb/>group-level means per reward and cost level, with error bars representing the standard error of <lb/>the mean. Reward levels are presented as the difference in magnitude between the high-and <lb/>low-cost option in the effort discontinuing task and as the absolute reward value of the high-<lb/>cost option in the delay discounting task. Likewise, the effort level represents the difference <lb/>between the proportions of the individually calibrated MVC of the high-and low-cost option, <lb/>while the delay level indicates the delay of the high-cost option. The data underlying the effort <lb/>discounting task (left panel) can be found in S1 Data, and the data underlying the delay dis-<lb/>counting task (right panel) can be found in S2 Data. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S9 Fig. Drug effects on decision times. Posterior distributions and 95% HDI of the Bayesian <lb/>linear mixed models depict the estimate of each effect on decision times. (a) In the effort dis-<lb/>counting task, overall decision times were not credibly influenced by either haloperidol or <lb/>biperiden. (b) Notably, a haloperidol-by-reward interaction revealed a reduced reward sensi-<lb/>tivity after haloperidol administration. (c) On the other hand, sensitivity towards increasing <lb/>levels of effort is not affected by either drug. (d) In the delay discounting task, haloperidol <lb/>credibly reduced overall decision times, while biperiden did not show any credible effect. (e) <lb/>Analogous to the effort discounting task, a credible haloperidol-by-reward interaction demon-<lb/>strate reduced reward sensitivity following haloperidol administration. (f) Furthermore, <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>21 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">haloperidol administration credibly reduced delay sensitivity, while biperiden had no effect on <lb/>the impact of delay on decision times. Bold dots represent the mean group-level estimate of <lb/>the posterior distribution. The horizontal bars represent the group-level 95% HDI. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the effort discounting task, regress-<lb/>ing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward (difference <lb/>between high-cost vs. low-cost reward level), effort (difference between high-cost vs. low-<lb/>cost effort level), and their interaction terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the delay discounting task, regress-<lb/>ing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward (high-cost option <lb/>reward), delay (high-cost option delay), and their interaction terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Table. Model comparison for the effort and delay discounting task. To compare the <lb/>validity of each model, we used the leave-one-out cross-validation information criterion <lb/>(LOOIC) procedure. A lower LOOIC score indicates a better-fitting model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S4 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the effort discounting task-baseline <lb/>session; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for reward (differ-<lb/>ence between high-cost vs. low-cost reward level), effort (difference between high-cost vs. <lb/>low-cost effort level), and their interaction terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S5 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the delay discounting task-baseline <lb/>session; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for reward (high-<lb/>cost option reward), delay (high-cost option delay), and their interaction terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Table. Bayesian linear mixed models of the effort discounting task, regressing decision <lb/>times on predictors for drug, reward (difference between high-cost vs. low-cost reward <lb/>level), effort (difference between high-cost vs. low-cost effort level), and their interaction <lb/>terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S7 Table. Bayesian linear mixed models of the delay discounting task, regressing decision <lb/>times on predictors for drug, reward (high-cost option reward), delay (high-cost option <lb/>delay), and their interaction terms. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S8 Table. Fixed effects from robust linear regression model with κ as dependent variable <lb/>and questionnaire total scores, sex, and age as independent variable for the effort discount-<lb/>ing task. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S9 Table. Fixed effects from robust linear regression model with κ as dependent variable <lb/>and questionnaire total scores, sex, and age as independent variable for the delay discount-<lb/>ing task. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>22 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">S10 Table. Fixed effects from robust linear regression model with κ as dependent variable <lb/>and questionnaire subscales as independent variable for the effort discounting task. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S11 Table. Fixed effects from robust linear regression model with κ as dependent variable <lb/>and questionnaire subscales as independent variable for the delay discounting task. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S12 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the effort discounting task-fatigue <lb/>effects; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward <lb/>(difference between high-cost vs. low-cost reward level), effort (difference between high-<lb/>cost vs. low-cost effort level), and their interaction terms, as well as trial number and two-<lb/>way trial number × drug interactions. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S13 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the delay discounting task-fatigue <lb/>effects; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward <lb/>(high-cost option reward), delay (high-cost option delay), and their interaction terms, as <lb/>well as trial number and two-way trial number × drug interactions. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S14 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the effort discounting task-session <lb/>effects; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward <lb/>(difference between high-cost vs. low-cost reward level), effort (difference between high-<lb/>cost vs. low-cost effort level), and their interaction terms, as well as session and two-way <lb/>session × drug interactions. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S15 Table. Bayesian generalized linear mixed models of the delay discounting task-session <lb/>effects; regressing choices (high-cost vs. low-cost option) on predictors for drug, reward <lb/>(high-cost option reward), delay (high-cost option delay), and their interaction terms, as <lb/>well as session and two-way session × drug interactions. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We express our gratitude to the students who conducted and supported the data collection: <lb/>Bibiana Ackers, Evelina Andronova, Alina Hansen, and Maria Angelina Morales Diaz. <lb/>Computational infrastructure and support were provided by the Centre for Information and <lb/>Media Technology at Heinrich Heine University Du ¨sseldorf. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Data curation: Mani Erfanian Abdoust. <lb/>Formal analysis: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Investigation: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Elisabeth Schreivogel. <lb/>Methodology: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>23 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Project administration: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Alfons Schnitzler, <lb/>Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Resources: Alfons Schnitzler, Elisabeth Schreivogel, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Software: Mani Erfanian Abdoust. <lb/>Supervision: Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Alfons Schnitzler, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Validation: Mani Erfanian Abdoust, Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Gerhard Jocham. <lb/>Visualization: Mani Erfanian Abdoust. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Mani Erfanian Abdoust. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Monja Isabel Frobo ¨se, Alfons Schnitzler, Elisabeth Schreivogel, <lb/>Gerhard Jocham. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bickel WK, Marsch LA. Toward a behavioral economic understanding of drug dependence: delay dis-<lb/>counting processes. Addiction. 2001; 96:73-86. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1360-0443.2001.961736.x <lb/>PMID: 11177521 <lb/>2. Hartmann MN, Hager OM, Tobler PN, Kaiser S. Parabolic discounting of monetary rewards by physi-<lb/>cal effort. Behav Processes. 2013; 100:192-196. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.beproc.2013.09.014 PMID: <lb/>24140077 <lb/>3. Denk F, Walton ME, Jennings KA, Sharp T, Rushworth MFS, Bannerman DM. Differential involvement <lb/>of serotonin and dopamine systems in cost-benefit decisions about delay or effort. Psychopharmacol-<lb/>ogy. 2005; 179:587-596. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-004-2059-4 PMID: 15864561 <lb/>4. Farrar AM, Segovia KN, Randall PA, Nunes EJ, Collins LE, Stopper CM, et al. Nucleus accumbens <lb/>and effort-related functions: behavioral and neural markers of the interactions between adenosine <lb/>A2A and dopamine D2 receptors. Neuroscience. 2010; 166:1056-1067. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>neuroscience.2009.12.056 PMID: 20096336 <lb/>5. Le Heron C, Plant O, Manohar S, Ang Y-S, Jackson M, Lennox G, et al. Distinct effects of apathy and <lb/>dopamine on effort-based decision-making in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Brain. 2018; 141:1455-1469. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awy110 PMID: 29672668 <lb/>6. McGuigan S, Zhou S-H, Brosnan MB, Thyagarajan D, Bellgrove MA, Chong TT-J. Dopamine restores <lb/>cognitive motivation in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Brain. 2019; 142:719-732. https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/ <lb/>awy341 PMID: 30689734 <lb/>7. Salamone JD, Correa M. The mysterious motivational functions of mesolimbic dopamine. Neuron. <lb/>2012; 76:470-485. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2012.10.021 PMID: 23141060 <lb/>8. Soder HE, Cooper JA, Lopez-Gamundi P, Hoots JK, Nunez C, Lawlor VM, et al. Dose-response <lb/>effects of d-amphetamine on effort-based decision-making and reinforcement learning. Neuropsycho-<lb/>pharmacology. 2020. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-020-0779-8 PMID: 32722661 <lb/>9. Wardle MC, Treadway MT, Mayo LM, Zald DH, de Wit H. Amping up effort: effects of d-amphetamine <lb/>on human effort-based decision-making. J Neurosci. 2011; 31:16597-16602. https://doi.org/10.1523/ <lb/>JNEUROSCI.4387-11.2011 PMID: 22090487 <lb/>10. Bogdanov M, LoParco S, Otto AR, Sharp M. Dopaminergic medication increases motivation to exert <lb/>cognitive control by reducing subjective effort costs in Parkinson&apos;s patients. Neurobiol Learn Mem. <lb/>2022; 193:107652. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nlm.2022.107652 PMID: 35724812 <lb/>11. Chong TT-J, Fortunato E, Bellgrove MA. Amphetamines improve the motivation to invest effort in <lb/>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder. J Neurosci. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0982-<lb/>23.2023 PMID: 37666665 <lb/>12. Le Bouc R, Rigoux L, Schmidt L, Degos B, Welter M-L, Vidailhet M, et al. Computational Dissection of <lb/>Dopamine Motor and Motivational Functions in Humans. J Neurosci. 2016; 36:6623-6633. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3078-15.2016 PMID: 27335396 <lb/>13. de Wit H, Enggasser JL, Richards JB. Acute administration of d-amphetamine decreases impulsivity <lb/>in healthy volunteers. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2002; 27:813-825. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0893-<lb/>133X(02)00343-3 PMID: 12431855 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>24 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>14. Floresco SB, Tse MTL, Ghods-Sharifi S. Dopaminergic and glutamatergic regulation of effort-and <lb/>delay-based decision making. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2008; 33:1966-1979. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/sj.npp.1301565 PMID: 17805307 <lb/>15. Kayser AS, Allen DC, Navarro-Cebrian A, Mitchell JM, Fields HL. Dopamine, corticostriatal connectiv-<lb/>ity, and intertemporal choice. J Neurosci. 2012; 32:9402-9409. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI. <lb/>1180-12.2012 PMID: 22764248 <lb/>16. Acheson A, de Wit H. Bupropion improves attention but does not affect impulsive behavior in healthy <lb/>young adults. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 2008; 16:113-123. https://doi.org/10.1037/1064-1297.16.2. <lb/>113 PMID: 18489015 <lb/>17. Hamidovic A, Kang UJ, de Wit H. Effects of low to moderate acute doses of pramipexole on impulsivity <lb/>and cognition in healthy volunteers. J Clin Psychopharmacol. 2008; 28:45-51. https://doi.org/10.1097/ <lb/>jcp.0b013e3181602fab PMID: 18204340 <lb/>18. Pine A, Shiner T, Seymour B, Dolan RJ. Dopamine, time, and impulsivity in humans. J Neurosci. 2010; <lb/>30:8888-8896. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6028-09.2010 PMID: 20592211 <lb/>19. Soutschek A, Tobler PN. A process model account of the role of dopamine in intertemporal choice. <lb/>Elife. 2023:12. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.83734 PMID: 36884013 <lb/>20. Wagner B, Clos M, Sommer T, Peters J. Dopaminergic Modulation of Human Intertemporal Choice: A <lb/>Diffusion Model Analysis Using the D2-Receptor Antagonist Haloperidol. J Neurosci. 2020; 40:7936-<lb/>7948. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0592-20.2020 PMID: 32948675 <lb/>21. Borderies N, Bornert P, Gilardeau S, Bouret S. Pharmacological evidence for the implication of nor-<lb/>adrenaline in effort. PLoS Biol. 2020; 18:e3000793. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3000793 <lb/>PMID: 33044952 <lb/>22. Meyniel F, Goodwin GM, Deakin JW, Klinge C, MacFadyen C, Milligan H, et al. A specific role for sero-<lb/>tonin in overcoming effort cost. Elife. 2016:5. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.17282 PMID: 27824554 <lb/>23. Nunes EJ, Randall PA, Podurgiel S, Correa M, Salamone JD. Nucleus accumbens neurotransmission <lb/>and effort-related choice behavior in food motivation: effects of drugs acting on dopamine, adenosine, <lb/>and muscarinic acetylcholine receptors. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2013; 37:2015-2025. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.neubiorev.2013.04.002 PMID: 23583616 <lb/>24. Chantranupong L, Beron CC, Zimmer JA, Wen MJ, Wang W, Sabatini BL. Dopamine and glutamate <lb/>regulate striatal acetylcholine in decision-making. Nature. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-<lb/>06492-9 PMID: 37557915 <lb/>25. Foster DJ, Wilson JM, Remke DH, Mahmood MS, Uddin MJ, Wess J, et al. Antipsychotic-like Effects <lb/>of M4 Positive Allosteric Modulators Are Mediated by CB2 Receptor-Dependent Inhibition of Dopa-<lb/>mine Release. Neuron. 2016; 91:1244-1252. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2016.08.017 PMID: <lb/>27618677 <lb/>26. Gerber DJ, Sotnikova TD, Gainetdinov RR, Huang SY, Caron MG, Tonegawa S. Hyperactivity, ele-<lb/>vated dopaminergic transmission, and response to amphetamine in M1 muscarinic acetylcholine <lb/>receptor-deficient mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2001; 98:15312-15317. https://doi.org/10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.261583798 PMID: 11752469 <lb/>27. Myslivecek J. Two Players in the Field: Hierarchical Model of Interaction between the Dopamine and <lb/>Acetylcholine Signaling Systems in the Striatum. Biomedicine. 2021:9. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>biomedicines9010025 PMID: 33401461 <lb/>28. Threlfell S, Clements MA, Khodai T, Pienaar IS, Exley R, Wess J, et al. Striatal muscarinic receptors <lb/>promote activity dependence of dopamine transmission via distinct receptor subtypes on cholinergic <lb/>interneurons in ventral versus dorsal striatum. J Neurosci. 2010; 30:3398-3408. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1523/JNEUROSCI.5620-09.2010 PMID: 20203199 <lb/>29. Hailwood JM, Heath CJ, Phillips BU, Robbins TW, Saksida LM, Bussey TJ. Blockade of muscarinic <lb/>acetylcholine receptors facilitates motivated behaviour and rescues a model of antipsychotic-induced <lb/>amotivation. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2019; 44:1068-1075. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-018-<lb/>0281-8 PMID: 30478410 <lb/>30. Dallery J, Locey ML. Effects of acute and chronic nicotine on impulsive choice in rats. Behav Pharma-<lb/>col. 2005; 16:15-23. https://doi.org/10.1097/00008877-200502000-00002 PMID: 15706134 <lb/>31. Kolokotroni KZ, Rodgers RJ, Harrison AA. Acute nicotine increases both impulsive choice and beha-<lb/>vioural disinhibition in rats. Psychopharmacology. 2011; 217:455-473. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00213-011-2296-2 PMID: 21503608 <lb/>32. Mendez IA, Gilbert RJ, Bizon JL, Setlow B. Effects of acute administration of nicotinic and muscarinic <lb/>cholinergic agonists and antagonists on performance in different cost-benefit decision making tasks in <lb/>rats. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2012; 224:489-499. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-012-2777-y <lb/>PMID: 22760484 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>25 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>33. Ozga JE, Anderson KG. Reduction in delay discounting due to nicotine and its attenuation by choliner-<lb/>gic antagonists in Lewis and Fischer 344 rats. Psychopharmacology. 2018; 235:155-168. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/s00213-017-4752-0 PMID: 28971227 <lb/>34. Green L, Myerson J. A discounting framework for choice with delayed and probabilistic rewards. Psy-<lb/>chol Bull. 2004; 130:769-792. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.130.5.769 PMID: 15367080 <lb/>35. Kirby KN, Maraković NN. Modeling myopic decisions: Evidence for hyperbolic delay-discounting within <lb/>subjects and amounts. Organ Behav Hum Decis Process. 1995; 64:22-30. https://doi.org/10.1006/ <lb/>obhd.1995.1086 <lb/>36. Klein-Flu ¨gge MC, Kennerley SW, Saraiva AC, Penny WD, Bestmann S. Behavioral modeling of <lb/>human choices reveals dissociable effects of physical effort and temporal delay on reward devalua-<lb/>tion. PLoS Comput Biol. 2015; 11:e1004116. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004116 PMID: <lb/>25816114 <lb/>37. Lockwood PL, Hamonet M, Zhang SH, Ratnavel A, Salmony FU, Husain M, et al. Prosocial apathy for <lb/>helping others when effort is required. Nat Hum Behav. 2017; 1:0131. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-<lb/>017-0131 PMID: 28819649 <lb/>38. Seaman KL, Brooks N, Karrer TM, Castrellon JJ, Perkins SF, Dang LC, et al. Subjective value repre-<lb/>sentations during effort, probability and time discounting across adulthood. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci. <lb/>2018; 13:449-459. https://doi.org/10.1093/scan/nsy021 PMID: 29618082 <lb/>39. Jocham G, Klein TA, Ullsperger M. Dopamine-mediated reinforcement learning signals in the striatum <lb/>and ventromedial prefrontal cortex underlie value-based choices. J Neurosci. 2011; 31:1606-1613. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3904-10.2011 PMID: 21289169 <lb/>40. Jocham G, Klein TA, Ullsperger M. Differential modulation of reinforcement learning by D2 dopamine <lb/>and NMDA glutamate receptor antagonism. J Neurosci. 2014; 34:13151-13162. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1523/JNEUROSCI.0757-14.2014 PMID: 25253860 <lb/>41. Webber HE, Lopez-Gamundi P, Stamatovich SN, de Wit H, Wardle MC. Using pharmacological <lb/>manipulations to study the role of dopamine in human reward functioning: A review of studies in <lb/>healthy adults. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2020. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2020.11.004 PMID: <lb/>33202256 <lb/>42. Schultz W. Dopamine reward prediction-error signalling: a two-component response. Nat Rev Neu-<lb/>rosci. 2016; 17:183-195. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn.2015.26 PMID: 26865020 <lb/>43. Schultz W. Dopamine reward prediction error coding. Dialogues Clin Neurosci. 2016; 18:23-32. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.31887/DCNS.2016.18.1/wschultz PMID: 27069377 <lb/>44. Tanaka SO&apos;Doherty JP, Sakagami M. The cost of obtaining rewards enhances the reward prediction <lb/>error signal of midbrain dopamine neurons. Nat Commun. 2019; 10:3674. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41467-019-11334-2 PMID: 31417077 <lb/>45. Bailey MR, Simpson EH, Balsam PD. Neural substrates underlying effort, time, and risk-based deci-<lb/>sion making in motivated behavior. Neurobiol Learn Mem. 2016; 133:233-256. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.nlm.2016.07.015 PMID: 27427327 <lb/>46. Berke JD. What does dopamine mean? Nat Neurosci. 2018; 21:787-793. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41593-018-0152-y PMID: 29760524 <lb/>47. Phillips PEM, Walton ME, Jhou TC. Calculating utility: preclinical evidence for cost-benefit analysis by <lb/>mesolimbic dopamine. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2007; 191:483-495. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00213-006-0626-6 PMID: 17119929 <lb/>48. Michely J, Viswanathan S, Hauser TU, Delker L, Dolan RJ, Grefkes C. The role of dopamine in <lb/>dynamic effort-reward integration. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2020; 45:1448-1453. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1038/s41386-020-0669-0 PMID: 32268344 <lb/>49. Soutschek A, Gvozdanovic G, Kozak R, Duvvuri S, de Martinis N, Harel B, et al. Dopaminergic D1 <lb/>Receptor Stimulation Affects Effort and Risk Preferences. Biol Psychiatry. 2020; 87:678-685. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.09.002 PMID: 31668477 <lb/>50. Petzold J, Kienast A, Lee Y, Pooseh S, London ED, Goschke T, et al. Baseline impulsivity may moder-<lb/>ate L-DOPA effects on value-based decision-making. Sci Rep. 2019; 9:5652. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41598-019-42124-x PMID: 30948756 <lb/>51. Burke CJ, Soutschek A, Weber S, Raja Beharelle A, Fehr E, Haker H, et al. Dopamine Receptor-Spe-<lb/>cific Contributions to the Computation of Value. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2018; 43:1415-1424. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/npp.2017.302 PMID: 29251282 <lb/>52. Rutledge RB, Skandali N, Dayan P, Dolan RJ. Dopaminergic Modulation of Decision Making and Sub-<lb/>jective Well-Being. J Neurosci. 2015; 35:9811-9822. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0702-15. <lb/>2015 PMID: 26156984 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>26 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>53. Zack M, Poulos CX. A D2 antagonist enhances the rewarding and priming effects of a gambling epi-<lb/>sode in pathological gamblers. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2007; 32:1678-1686. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/sj.npp.1301295 PMID: 17203013 <lb/>54. Soutschek A, Jetter A, Tobler PN. Toward a Unifying Account of Dopamine&apos;s Role in Cost-Benefit <lb/>Decision Making. Biol Psychiatry Glob Open Sci. 2023; 3:179-186. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpsgos. <lb/>2022.02.010 PMID: 37124350 <lb/>55. Westbrook A, Frank MJ. Dopamine and Proximity in Motivation and Cognitive Control. Curr Opin <lb/>Behav Sci. 2018; 22:28-34. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cobeha.2017.12.011 PMID: 29713659 <lb/>56. Morrison SE, Nicola SM. Neurons in the nucleus accumbens promote selection bias for nearer objects. <lb/>J Neurosci. 2014; 34:14147-14162. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2197-14.2014 PMID: <lb/>25319709 <lb/>57. Ojala KE, Janssen LK, Hashemi MM, Timmer MHM, Geurts DEM, Ter Huurne NP, et al. Dopaminergic <lb/>Drug Effects on Probability Weighting during Risky Decision Making. eNeuro. 2018:5. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1523/ENEURO.0330-18.2018 PMID: 29632870 <lb/>58. Frank MJO&apos;Reilly RC. A mechanistic account of striatal dopamine function in human cognition: <lb/>psychopharmacological studies with cabergoline and haloperidol. Behav Neurosci. 2006; 120:497-<lb/>517. https://doi.org/10.1037/0735-7044.120.3.497 PMID: 16768602 <lb/>59. Schoemaker H, Claustre Y, Fage D, Rouquier L, Chergui K, Curet O, et al. Neurochemical characteris-<lb/>tics of amisulpride, an atypical dopamine D2/D3 receptor antagonist with both presynaptic and limbic <lb/>selectivity. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1997; 280:83-97. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/ <lb/>pubmed/8996185. PMID: 8996185 <lb/>60. Kapur S, Remington G, Jones C, Wilson A, DaSilva J, Houle S, et al. High levels of dopamine D2 <lb/>receptor occupancy with low-dose haloperidol treatment: a PET study. Am J Psychiatry. 1996; <lb/>153:948-950. https://doi.org/10.1176/ajp.153.7.948 PMID: 8659621 <lb/>61. Cousins MS, Atherton A, Turner L, Salamone JD. Nucleus accumbens dopamine depletions alter rela-<lb/>tive response allocation in a T-maze cost/benefit task. Behav Brain Res. 1996; 74:189-197. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/0166-4328(95)00151-4 PMID: 8851929 <lb/>62. Mai B, Sommer S, Hauber W. Motivational states influence effort-based decision making in rats: the <lb/>role of dopamine in the nucleus accumbens. Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci. 2012; 12:74-84. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3758/s13415-011-0068-4 PMID: 22012275 <lb/>63. Salamone JD, Cousins MS, Bucher S. Anhedonia or anergia? Effects of haloperidol and nucleus <lb/>accumbens dopamine depletion on instrumental response selection in a T-maze cost/benefit proce-<lb/>dure. Behav Brain Res. 1994; 65:221-229. https://doi.org/10.1016/0166-4328(94)90108-2 PMID: <lb/>7718155 <lb/>64. Liem-Moolenaar M, Gray FA, de Visser SJ, Franson KL, Schoemaker RC, Schmitt JAJ, et al. Psycho-<lb/>motor and cognitive effects of a single oral dose of talnetant (SB223412) in healthy volunteers com-<lb/>pared with placebo or haloperidol. J Psychopharmacol. 2010; 24:73-82. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>0269881108094524 PMID: 18755817 <lb/>65. Linssen AMW, Vuurman EFPM, Sambeth A, Nave S, Spooren W, Vargas G, et al. Contingent nega-<lb/>tive variation as a dopaminergic biomarker: evidence from dose-related effects of methylphenidate. <lb/>Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2011; 218:533-542. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-011-2345-x PMID: <lb/>21597989 <lb/>66. Swart JC, Frobo ¨se MI, Cook JL, Geurts DE, Frank MJ, Cools R, et al. Catecholaminergic challenge <lb/>uncovers distinct Pavlovian and instrumental mechanisms of motivated (in)action. Elife. 2017:6. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.22169 PMID: 28504638 <lb/>67. Miyazaki K, Miyazaki KW, Sivori G, Yamanaka A, Tanaka KF, Doya K. Serotonergic projections to the <lb/>orbitofrontal and medial prefrontal cortices differentially modulate waiting for future rewards. Sci Adv. <lb/>2020:6. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abc7246 PMID: 33246957 <lb/>68. Randall PA, Nunes EJ, Janniere SL, Stopper CM, Farrar AM, Sager TN, et al. Stimulant effects of <lb/>adenosine antagonists on operant behavior: differential actions of selective A2A and A1 antagonists. <lb/>Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2011; 216:173-186. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00213-011-2198-3 PMID: <lb/>21347642 <lb/>69. Salamone JD, Correa M, Ferrigno S, Yang J-H, Rotolo RA, Presby RE. The Psychopharmacology of <lb/>Effort-Related Decision Making: Dopamine, Adenosine, and Insights into the Neurochemistry of Moti-<lb/>vation. Pharmacol Rev. 2018; 70:747-762. https://doi.org/10.1124/pr.117.015107 PMID: 30209181 <lb/>70. Betts GD, Hynes TJ, Winstanley CA. Pharmacological evidence of a cholinergic contribution to ele-<lb/>vated impulsivity and risky decision-making caused by adding win-paired cues to a rat gambling task. <lb/>J Psychopharmacol. 2021:269881120972421. https://doi.org/10.1177/0269881120972421 PMID: <lb/>33573446 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>27 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>71. Moehle MS, Conn PJ. Roles of the M4 acetylcholine receptor in the basal ganglia and the treatment of <lb/>movement disorders. Mov Disord. 2019; 34:1089-1099. https://doi.org/10.1002/mds.27740 PMID: <lb/>31211471 <lb/>72. Brocks DR. Anticholinergic drugs used in Parkinson&apos;s disease: An overlooked class of drugs from a <lb/>pharmacokinetic perspective. J Pharm Pharm Sci. 1999; 2:39-46. Available from: https://www.ncbi. <lb/>nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10952768. PMID: 10952768 <lb/>73. Stanhope KJ, Mirza NR, Bickerdike MJ, Bright JL, Harrington NR, Hesselink MB, et al. The muscarinic <lb/>receptor agonist xanomeline has an antipsychotic-like profile in the rat. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2001; <lb/>299:782-792. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11602695. PMID: 11602695 <lb/>74. Di Chiara G, Morelli M, Consolo S. Modulatory functions of neurotransmitters in the striatum: ACh/ <lb/>dopamine/NMDA interactions. Trends Neurosci. 1994; 17:228-233. https://doi.org/10.1016/0166-<lb/>2236(94)90005-1 PMID: 7521083 <lb/>75. Eisenegger C, Naef M, Linssen A, Clark L, Gandamaneni PK, Mu ¨ller U, et al. Role of dopamine D2 <lb/>receptors in human reinforcement learning. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2014; 39:2366-2375. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1038/npp.2014.84 PMID: 24713613 <lb/>76. Mikus N, Korb S, Massaccesi C, Gausterer C, Graf I, Willeit M, et al. Effects of dopamine D2/3 and opi-<lb/>oid receptor antagonism on the trade-off between model-based and model-free behaviour in healthy <lb/>volunteers. Elife. 2022:11. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.79661 PMID: 36468832 <lb/>77. Nordstro ¨m AL, Farde L, Halldin C. Time course of D2-dopamine receptor occupancy examined by <lb/>PET after single oral doses of haloperidol. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 1992; 106:433-438. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/BF02244811 PMID: 1533719 <lb/>78. Collins AGE, Frank MJ. Opponent actor learning (OpAL): modeling interactive effects of striatal dopa-<lb/>mine on reinforcement learning and choice incentive. Psychol Rev. 2014; 121:337-366. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1037/a0037015 PMID: 25090423 <lb/>79. Sudo Y, Suhara T, Suzuki K, Okubo Y, Yoshikawa K, Uchida S, et al. Muscarinic receptor occupancy <lb/>by biperiden in living human brain. Life Sci. 1999; 64:PL99-104. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0024-3205 <lb/>(98)00613-4 PMID: 10069534 <lb/>80. Cools RD&apos;Esposito MInverted-U-shaped dopamine actions on human working memory and cognitive <lb/>control. Biol Psychiatry. 2011; 69:e113-e125. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2011.03.028 PMID: <lb/>21531388 <lb/>81. Goldman-Rakic PS, Muly EC III, Williams GV. D1 receptors in prefrontal cells and circuits. Brain Res <lb/>Rev. 2000; 31:295-301. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0165-0173(99)00045-4 PMID: 10719156 <lb/>82. van den Bosch R, Lambregts B, Ma ¨a ¨tta ¨J, Hofmans L, Papadopetraki D, Westbrook A, et al. Striatal <lb/>dopamine dissociates methylphenidate effects on value-based versus surprise-based reversal learn-<lb/>ing. Nat Commun. 2022; 13:4962. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-32679-1 PMID: 36002446 <lb/>83. Matthews J, Pisauro MA, Jurgelis M, Mu ¨ller T, Vassena E, Chong TT-J, et al. Computational mecha-<lb/>nisms underlying the dynamics of physical and cognitive fatigue. Cognition. 2023; 240:105603. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2023.105603 PMID: 37647742 <lb/>84. Mu ¨ller T, Klein-Flu ¨gge MC, Manohar S, Husain M, Apps MAJ. Neural and computational mechanisms <lb/>of momentary fatigue and persistence in effort-based choice. Nat Commun. 2021; 12:4593. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41467-021-24927-7 PMID: 34321478 <lb/>85. Lueken U, Seidl U, Schwarz M, Vo ¨lker L, Naumann D, Mattes K, et al. Psychometric properties of a <lb/>German version of the Apathy Evaluation Scale. Fortschr Neurol Psychiatr. 2006; 74:714-722. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1055/s-2006-932164 PMID: 17167730 <lb/>86. Marin RS, Biedrzycki RC, Firinciogullari S. Reliability and validity of the Apathy Evaluation Scale. Psy-<lb/>chiatry Res. 1991; 38:143-162. https://doi.org/10.1016/0165-1781(91)90040-v PMID: 1754629 <lb/>87. Beck AT, Steer RA, Brown G. Beck Depression Inventory-II. Psychol Assess. 1996. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1037/t00742-000 <lb/>88. Ku ¨hner C, Bu ¨rger C, Keller F, Hautzinger M. [Reliability and validity of the Revised Beck Depression <lb/>Inventory (BDI-II). Results from German samples]. Nervenarzt. 2007; 78:651-656. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s00115-006-2098-7 PMID: 16832698 <lb/>89. Meule A, Vo ¨gele C, Ku ¨bler A. Psychometrische Evaluation der deutschen Barratt Impulsiveness <lb/>Scale-Kurzversion (BIS-15). Diagnostica. 2011; 57:126-133. https://doi.org/10.1026/0012-1924/ <lb/>a000042 <lb/>90. Spinella M. Normative data and a short form of the Barratt Impulsiveness Scale. Int J Neurosci. 2007; <lb/>117:359-368. https://doi.org/10.1080/00207450600588881 PMID: 17365120 <lb/>91. Grimaldi R, Perucca E, Ruberto G, Gelmi C, Trimarchi F, Hollmann M, et al. Pharmacokinetic and <lb/>pharmacodynamic studies following the intravenous and oral administration of the antiparkinsonian <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>28 / 29 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>drug biperiden to normal subjects. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 1986; 29:735-737. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>BF00615970 PMID: 3709619 <lb/>92. Kudo S, Ishizaki T. Pharmacokinetics of haloperidol: an update. Clin Pharmacokinet. 1999; 37:435-<lb/>456. https://doi.org/10.2165/00003088-199937060-00001 PMID: 10628896 <lb/>93. Tombaugh TN. Trail Making Test A and B: normative data stratified by age and education. Arch Clin <lb/>Neuropsychol. 2004; 19:203-214. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0887-6177(03)00039-8 PMID: 15010086 <lb/>94. Bond A, Lader M. The use of analogue scales in rating subjective feelings. Br J Med Psychol. 1974; <lb/>47:211-218. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.2044-8341.1974.tb02285.x <lb/>95. Bonnelle V, Veromann K-R, Burnett Heyes S, Lo Sterzo E, Manohar S, Husain M. Characterization of <lb/>reward and effort mechanisms in apathy. J Physiol Paris. 2015; 109:16-26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jphysparis.2014.04.002 PMID: 24747776 <lb/>96. Chong TT-J, Apps MAJ, Giehl K, Hall S, Clifton CH, Husain M. Computational modelling reveals dis-<lb/>tinct patterns of cognitive and physical motivation in elite athletes. Sci Rep. 2018; 8:11888. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41598-018-30220-3 PMID: 30089782 <lb/>97. Bickel WK, Pitcock JA, Yi R, Angtuaco EJC. Congruence of BOLD response across intertemporal <lb/>choice conditions: fictive and real money gains and losses. J Neurosci. 2009; 29:8839-8846. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5319-08.2009 PMID: 19587291 <lb/>98. Madden GJ, Begotka AM, Raiff BR, Kastern LL. Delay discounting of real and hypothetical rewards. <lb/>Exp Clin Psychopharmacol. 2003; 11:139-145. https://doi.org/10.1037/1064-1297.11.2.139 PMID: <lb/>12755458 <lb/>99. Bu ¨rkner P-C. brms: An R Package for Bayesian Multilevel Models Using Stan. J Stat Softw. 2017; <lb/>80:1-28. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v080.i01 <lb/>100. Gelman A, Jakulin A, Pittau MG, Su Y-S. A weakly informative default prior distribution for logistic and <lb/>other regression models. Ann Appl Stat. 2008; 2:1360-1383. https://doi.org/10.1214/08-AOAS191 <lb/>101. Ahn W-Y, Haines N, Zhang L. Revealing Neurocomputational Mechanisms of Reinforcement Learning <lb/>and Decision-Making With the hBayesDM Package. Comput Psychiatr. 2017; 1:24-57. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1162/CPSY_a_00002 PMID: 29601060 <lb/>102. Kruschke JK. Doing Bayesian Data Analysis: A Tutorial with R, JAGS, and Stan. Academic Press; <lb/>2014. <lb/>103. Białaszek W, Marcowski P, Ostaszewski P. Physical and cognitive effort discounting across different <lb/>reward magnitudes: Tests of discounting models. PLoS ONE. 2017; 12:e0182353. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0182353 PMID: 28759631 <lb/>104. Chong TT-J, Apps M, Giehl K, Sillence A, Grima LL, Husain M. Neurocomputational mechanisms <lb/>underlying subjective valuation of effort costs. PLoS Biol. 2017; 15:e1002598. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pbio.1002598 PMID: 28234892 <lb/>105. Vehtari A, Gelman A, Gabry J. Practical Bayesian model evaluation using leave-one-out cross-valida-<lb/>tion and WAIC. Stat Comput. 2017; 27:1413-1432. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11222-016-9696-4 <lb/>106. Mathar D, Erfanian Abdoust M, Marrenbach T, Tuzsus D, Peters J. The catecholamine precursor Tyro-<lb/>sine reduces autonomic arousal and decreases decision thresholds in reinforcement learning and tem-<lb/>poral discounting. PLoS Comput Biol. 2022; 18:e1010785. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi. <lb/>1010785 PMID: 36548401 <lb/>107. Peters JD&apos;Esposito M. The drift diffusion model as the choice rule in inter-temporal and risky choice: A <lb/>case study in medial orbitofrontal cortex lesion patients and controls. PLoS Comput Biol. 2020; 16: <lb/>e1007615. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007615 PMID: 32310962 <lb/>108. Stan Development Team. Stan Modeling Language Users Guide and Reference Manual. 2021. <lb/>109. Knauth K, Peters J. Trial-wise exposure to visual emotional cues increases physiological arousal but <lb/>not temporal discounting. Psychophysiology. 2022; 59:e13996. https://doi.org/10.1111/psyp.13996 <lb/>PMID: 35037293 <lb/>110. Lockwood PL, Abdurahman A, Gabay AS, Drew D, Tamm M, Husain M, et al. Aging Increases Proso-<lb/>cial Motivation for Effort. Psychol Sci. 2021:956797620975781. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>0956797620975781 PMID: 33860711 <lb/>111. Lockwood PL, Wittmann MK, Nili H, Matsumoto-Ryan M, Abdurahman A, Cutler J, et al. Distinct neural <lb/>representations for prosocial and self-benefiting effort. Curr Biol. 2022. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub. <lb/>2022.08.010 PMID: 36029773 <lb/>112. Gelman A, Rubin DB. Inference from Iterative Simulation Using Multiple Sequences. Stat Sci. 1992; <lb/>7:457-472. https://doi.org/10.1214/ss/1177011136 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Dopaminergic and cholinergic modulation of cost-benefit decision making <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002714 July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>29 / 29 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>