<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-19T14:46:10.543Z">11/19/2025 2:46:10 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-19T14:46:01.356625Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-19T14:46:01.356625Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Beyond active learning: Using 3-Dimensional <lb/>learning to create scientifically authentic, <lb/>student-centered classrooms <lb/>Melanie M. Cooper ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Marcos D. Caballero ID <lb/>2,3,4 <lb/>, Justin H. Carmel ID <lb/>5 <lb/>, Erin M. Duffy 6 , <lb/>Diane Ebert-May 7 , Cori L. Fata-Hartley 8 , Deborah G. HerringtonID 9 , James T. Laverty 10 , <lb/>Paul C. NelsonID 8 , Lynmarie A. PoseyID 1 , Jon R. StoltzfusID 11 , Ryan L. StoweID 12 , Ryan <lb/>D. SweederID 13 , Stuart Tessmer 2 , Sonia M. UnderwoodID 5 <lb/>1 Department of Chemistry, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America, <lb/>2 Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of <lb/>America, 3 Department of Computational Science, Mathematics and Engineering, Michigan State University, <lb/>East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America, 4 Department of Physics and Center for Computing in <lb/>Science Education, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway, 5 Department of Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry and STEM <lb/>Transformation Institute, Florida International University, Miami, Florida, United States of America, 6 Science <lb/>Department, Solebury School, New Hope, Pennsylvania, United States of America, 7 Department of Plant <lb/>Biology, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America, 8 Human Biology <lb/>Program, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America, 9 Department of <lb/>Chemistry, Grand Valley State University, Allendale, Michigan, United States of America, 10 Department of <lb/>Physics, Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kansas, United States of America, 11 Department of <lb/>Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America, 12 Department of <lb/>Chemistry, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, United States of America, 13 Lyman <lb/>Briggs College, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America <lb/>* mmc@msu.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In recent years, much of the emphasis for transformation of introductory STEM courses has <lb/>focused on &quot;active learning&quot;, and while this approach has been shown to produce more equi-<lb/>table outcomes for students, the construct of &quot;active learning&quot; is somewhat ill-defined and is <lb/>often used as a &quot;catch-all&quot; that can encompass a wide range of pedagogical techniques. <lb/>Here we present an alternative approach for how to think about the transformation of STEM <lb/>courses that focuses instead on what students should know and what they can do with that <lb/>knowledge. This approach, known as three-dimensional learning (3DL), emerged from the <lb/>National Academy&apos;s &quot;A Framework for K-12 Science Education&quot;, which describes a vision <lb/>for science education that centers the role of constructing productive causal accounts for <lb/>phenomena. Over the past 10 years, we have collected data from introductory biology, <lb/>chemistry, and physics courses to assess the impact of such a transformation on higher <lb/>education courses. Here we report on an analysis of video data of class sessions that allows <lb/>us to characterize these sessions as active, 3D, neither, or both 3D and active. We find that <lb/>3D classes are likely to also involve student engagement (i.e. be active), but the reverse is <lb/>not necessarily true. That is, focusing on transformations involving 3DL also tends to <lb/>increase student engagement, whereas focusing solely on student engagement might result <lb/>in courses where students are engaged in activities that do not involve meaningful engage-<lb/>ment with core ideas of the discipline. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/>1 / 17 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Cooper MM, Caballero MD, Carmel JH, <lb/>Duffy EM, Ebert-May D, Fata-Hartley CL, et al. <lb/>(2024) Beyond active learning: Using 3-<lb/>Dimensional learning to create scientifically <lb/>authentic, student-centered classrooms. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(5): e0295887. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0295887 <lb/>Editor: Shailender Kumar Verma, University of <lb/>Delhi, INDIA <lb/>Received: December 2, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: April 22, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 31, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Cooper et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Over the past twenty years, the wide array of pedagogical techniques that have come to be col-<lb/>lectively known as active learning [1,2] have been the predominant focus for transformation <lb/>efforts in higher education STEM teaching and learning. A meta-analysis across a wide range <lb/>of STEM disciplines found that the use of active learning techniques tends to increase average <lb/>course grades, particularly by decreasing the DFW (D&apos;s, F&apos;s and withdrawals) rate [3]. In addi-<lb/>tion, active learning appears particularly helpful in promoting more equitable outcomes for <lb/>students [4,5]. Thus, many faculty development efforts focus on instructional practices that <lb/>increase student engagement in the classroom [6-8], although studies have also shown that <lb/>their uptake is somewhat disappointing [9]. <lb/>However, as discussed in &quot;The Curious Construct of Active Learning&quot;, an extensive over-<lb/>view and synthesis of the literature on active learning across STEM disciplines [1], the con-<lb/>struct of active learning is amorphous; it can refer to minor adaptations to lecture-based <lb/>courses, such as the use of student response systems, or to flipped classrooms, or to completely <lb/>re-envisioned curricula taught in studio classrooms. It has become the catch-all description for <lb/>a wide range of instructional practices. Freeman et al., in their highly cited meta-analysis on <lb/>the impact of active learning [3] do not disaggregate findings by instructional strategy and use <lb/>the following definition to determine which courses engaged students in active learning: <lb/>&quot;Active learning engages students in the process of learning through activities and/or discussion <lb/>in class, as opposed to passively listening to an expert. It emphasizes higher-order thinking and <lb/>often involves group work.&quot; It is notable that these authors do not say more about what students <lb/>are learning, other than a reference to higher-order thinking or critical thinking; constructs <lb/>that are also subject to multiple definitions [10-12]. Thus, the often ill-defined construct of <lb/>active learning is characterized by other ill-defined constructs. For example, Bailin noted that <lb/>&apos;&apos;the field lacks a coherent and defensible conception of critical thinking,&quot;[13]. As noted in the <lb/>National Academies report on 21 st Century thinking skills, there is considerable evidence that <lb/>&quot;higher order thinking&quot; or &quot;critical thinking skills&quot; are domain specific, rather than domain <lb/>general-that is teaching such skills should be connected to domain knowledge [14]. <lb/>Certainly, the evidence is clear that student engagement is a necessary, but perhaps not suffi-<lb/>cient, component of learning for most students [15]. Evidence for the use of active learning strate-<lb/>gies typically does not include discussions of what is being learned during the instruction, or how <lb/>students are able to use that knowledge. The most highly cited study on the impact of active learn-<lb/>ing on student outcomes relies on scores on conceptual multiple-choice exams and/or course <lb/>grades as evidence of improvement [3]. While there are certainly studies where what students <lb/>must know and do are carefully described and measured, for example in reports of the impact of <lb/>transformation projects such as Process Oriented Guided Inquiry Learning (POGIL) [16-18], or <lb/>those that incorporate simulations that allow students to explore phenomena [19,20], it appears <lb/>that active learning has often been conflated with having students engage with some classroom <lb/>activity, regardless of what that activity involves. In many cases, little information is provided <lb/>about what students are doing or what the subsequent assessments are based on [5]. We have pre-<lb/>viously argued that it is not sufficient to know facts (or even concepts) or to solve rote mathemati-<lb/>cal exercises; students should be able to use their knowledge to explain, model, and predict <lb/>phenomena by engaging in Three-Dimensional Learning (3DL) [21]. <lb/>3DL was originally developed in the National Academies consensus report &quot;A Framework <lb/>for K-12 Science Education&quot; which lays out a vision for science education that centers the role <lb/>of constructing productive causal accounts for phenomena [22]. The &quot;Framework&quot; proposes <lb/>that three interconnected dimensions of science learning are central to the vision: Scientific and <lb/>Engineering Practices, Disciplinary Core Ideas, and Crosscutting Concepts, as shown in Fig 1. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<front>Funding: Our funding acknowledgement National <lb/>Science Foundation [EHR DUE 1725520], should <lb/>be changed to National Science Foundation <lb/>[Education and Human Resources, Division of <lb/>Undergraduate Education 1725520]. The funders <lb/>had no role in study design, data collection and <lb/>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>The Scientific and Engineering Practices are the ways that scientists use and engage with <lb/>their knowledge-for example, asking questions or defining problems, developing and using <lb/>models, and evaluating and communicating information. The Core Ideas of a discipline are <lb/>the underlying ideas that have broad applicability and can be used to predict and explain phe-<lb/>nomena at different levels of depth and complexity. For example, in biology the core idea of <lb/>evolution underlies a vast range of phenomena; atomic and molecular interactions and bond-<lb/>ing play a similar role in chemistry, as do fields as the mediators of interactions in physics. The <lb/>Crosscutting Concepts can be thought of as lenses that transcend disciplines and allow scien-<lb/>tists to focus their investigation of a phenomenon on specific aspects-for example, cause and <lb/>effect, structure and function, and stability and change [23]. The Framework emphasizes that, <lb/>for meaningful learning, the three dimensions must be inextricably intertwined. For example, <lb/>if we want our students to be able to model (a Scientific Practice) how energy (a Core Idea) is <lb/>transferred within or between systems (a Crosscutting Concept), all three dimensions must be <lb/>combined during instructional and assessment activities. A focus on content without consider-<lb/>ing how students should use that knowledge can lead to fragmented, disconnected under-<lb/>standing and inert knowledge that is not useful in new contexts [22]. Consequently, it is <lb/>important to intentionally build all three dimensions into learning objectives, assessments, <lb/>and classroom activities. <lb/>There are several other approaches to transformation of STEM education that, while not <lb/>explicitly developed using a 3D framework, also have the potential to engage students in the <lb/>use of scientific practices. For example, POGIL activities often begin with experimental data <lb/>that students may analyze and interpret to make an argument about the phenomenon under <lb/>study [17]. Similarly, Course Based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CURES), may ask <lb/>students to design and carry out experiments, analyze and interpret data and so on [24,25]. <lb/>3DL is a unifying framework that can tie all these approaches together. <lb/>The 3DL approach has been the focus of a multidisciplinary project to transform the STEM <lb/>gateway (introductory biology, chemistry and physics) courses at Michigan State University <lb/>(MSU) by adapting the Framework for use in higher education [21]. In our work, we adopted <lb/>the Scientific Practices and Crosscutting Concepts as presented in the Framework with minor <lb/>modifications. However, the Core Ideas presented in the Framework were originally developed <lb/>for a more interdisciplinary approach to K-12 science teaching and learning (for example, <lb/>Core Ideas are presented for physical science), which does not align with how introductory sci-<lb/>ence courses are organized at the college level. Furthermore, the Core Ideas were not intended <lb/>for the depth of college science courses. We worked collaboratively with disciplinary experts <lb/>and introductory course instructors from chemistry, biology, and physics to define more <lb/>appropriate Core Ideas for those disciplines [26,27]. <lb/>Fig 1. 3D-Learning. The three dimensions, Scientific and Engineering Practices, Disciplinary Core Ideas, and <lb/>Crosscutting Concepts, are intertwined to form 3D-Learning. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>To evaluate the extent of the transformation, we developed two protocols, the Three-<lb/>Dimensional Learning Assessment Protocol (3D-LAP) [27] and the Three-Dimensional <lb/>Learning Observation Protocol (3D-LOP) [28], that are intended to characterize the extent to <lb/>which assessments and instruction incorporate 3D learning. The 3D-LAP allows us to deter-<lb/>mine whether an assessment task has the potential to elicit a 3D response from students. We <lb/>have previously reported on the use of the 3D-LAP as a tool to evaluate the change in 3D <lb/>assessment over time [29] by coding over 4,000 examination questions from midterm and <lb/>final exams that were used in the introductory courses. These earlier findings show that the <lb/>3D-LAP is a useful tool for characterizing the extent of transformation which focuses on stu-<lb/>dent use of knowledge in the context of Core Ideas. Our findings showed that for a large gen-<lb/>eral chemistry course that was completely transformed using the 3DL approach [30], with <lb/>around 50% of exam points associated with 3D tasks on course exams, the average grades in <lb/>the course increased, and the percentage of students who received a D, F or W in the course <lb/>decreased [29]. That is, we saw similar overall outcomes to those reported for courses that <lb/>employ active learning. Another study showed that 3DL assessment tasks focusing on mecha-<lb/>nistic reasoning about a chemical phenomenon are more equitable than typical general chem-<lb/>istry tasks involving calculations that are more traditionally featured on such exams [31]. <lb/>We note that the 3D-LAP can only give us a measure of the potential of an assessment item <lb/>to elicit 3DL. To determine whether students are actually engaging in 3DL requires that we <lb/>analyze student responses to such assessment tasks, and study how students construct these <lb/>responses. There are now a number of studies in which responses from matched cohorts of <lb/>students, from both traditional and transformed sections of a course, were analyzed [32-37]. <lb/>In general, these studies show that students in 3DL courses are significantly more likely to <lb/>engage in construction of mechanistic explanations and construction and use of models in the <lb/>context of 3D tasks. Another study asked students &quot;what kind of thinking&quot; they were expected <lb/>to engage in for a given course, and what kinds of thinking course assessments tested [38]. Stu-<lb/>dents in a 3DL-transformed organic chemistry course were most likely to respond that they <lb/>were expected to use their knowledge (apply and reason), whereas students in a traditional sec-<lb/>tion were more likely to perceive that they were expected to memorize information. In a study <lb/>that followed students through four semesters of chemistry, (the first two semester were 3D <lb/>and the last two were traditional) we found that students from the very large enrollment 3D <lb/>general chemistry course performed as well or better than students from more selective <lb/>courses (honors or majors) in the next two organic courses in the sequence [32]. <lb/>One intriguing study compared three student cohorts from different institutions on a task <lb/>that asked students to explain how and why a substance dissolved in water [39]. All instructors <lb/>agreed that students would have learned about this phenomenon and should be able to com-<lb/>plete the task. The three different institutions employed three different instructional <lb/>approaches: 1) a traditional lecture (didactic) course with a traditional curriculum, 2) an active <lb/>learning approach with a traditional curriculum, and 3) a 3DL approach with transformed cur-<lb/>riculum and assessments that included 3D tasks. Students in the didactic and active learning <lb/>courses provided similar responses, while the 3DL students were far more likely to construct a <lb/>full explanation for the phenomenon, invoking ideas about both interactions and bonding, <lb/>and energy changes. Although we should not be surprised that students who were enrolled in <lb/>traditional courses were less able to provide appropriate responses to a 3DL task (students <lb/>tend to learn what is emphasized in a course), we also note that the active learning students <lb/>performed similarly to those who listened to lectures. This indicates that active learning alone <lb/>does not support students&apos; understanding of mechanistic reasoning and chemical phenomena <lb/>if the curriculum does not intentionally include activities that require students to use knowl-<lb/>edge in this way. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>3DL can also support the integration of important and overlooked scientific practices. <lb/>Using a computer to model scientific phenomenon and data is central to the enterprise of sci-<lb/>ence, and yet, computational modeling is absent from most introductory science instruction. <lb/>Some introductory physics courses use computational modeling activities to support students <lb/>as they make predictions or construct explanations [40]. Instructional strategies used in com-<lb/>puter science education, such as pair programming [41,42] and live-coding [31], have been <lb/>used in disciplinary courses to ensure students are active in their learning of computational <lb/>modeling. Research conducted in our introductory physics courses has demonstrated that <lb/>such active learning strategies alone are not sufficient to promote 3DL. However, newer com-<lb/>putationally enabled physics courses at MSU that are characterized as 3D and are designed <lb/>around a communities of practice framework [32,33] have been shown to support the ways in <lb/>which students work in their groups as they develop computational models for real-world phe-<lb/>nomena [42-47]. <lb/>While analyzing the types of assessment tasks and concomitant student responses has pro-<lb/>vided us with compelling evidence for the efficacy of 3DL, it does not provide information <lb/>about the instructional practices employed during instructional activities. To address this <lb/>need, we developed the 3D-LOP, which can be used to characterize instruction by coding <lb/>classroom video recordings. The 3D-LOP is, in some ways, similar to other classroom observa-<lb/>tion protocols, such as the COPUS or RTOP [48,49], because it provides a way to characterize <lb/>the instructional methods used in a classroom. What sets the 3D-LOP apart from other such <lb/>observation protocols is that it also allows the user to characterize what is being taught as well <lb/>as the way that it is taught. Thus, the 3D-LOP provides a way to characterize a class period by <lb/>the topic covered, instructional activities, whether the instruction is aligned with 3DL, and <lb/>whether that instruction is student-or instructor-centered. Full details of the development and <lb/>coding protocols for the 3D-LOP have been published previously [28]. <lb/>Using class video recordings, we are now able to investigate the enactment of 3DL in these <lb/>introductory biology, chemistry, and physics classes and to determine whether there is a con-<lb/>nection between 3DL and the more common approach to reform that typically focuses on <lb/>instructional practices and student engagement (i.e., active learning). We have evidence that <lb/>transformation efforts using different approaches (e.g., 3DL or active learning) do tend to <lb/>result in some of the same outcomes (for example, improved average grades, retention rates, <lb/>and more equitable outcomes). However, as noted earlier, there are aspects of 3DL that go <lb/>beyond active learning. For example, students who are enrolled in courses where active <lb/>engagement, but not where 3DL is prevalent, are unlikely to provide causal explanations for <lb/>phenomena [39]. Additionally, 3DL supports inclusion of scientific practices that are often <lb/>neglected, such as computational modelling [40]. It also explicitly defines what is expected as <lb/>outcomes for a course; rather than &quot;knowing&quot; or &quot;understanding,&quot; students perceive that they <lb/>are going to apply and reason with their knowledge [38]. <lb/>Now that we have the methodology to characterize whether 3DL and/or active learning <lb/>take place during class instruction, the current study uses evidence from class session video <lb/>recordings to address the following research questions: <lb/>1. In what ways can 3DL and/or active learning occur within a STEM course? <lb/>2. How are 3DL and active learning related? <lb/>Experimental methods <lb/>The data corpus explored in this report is composed of video recordings of in-class instruction <lb/>collected over 4 sequential years from introductory biology, chemistry, and physics courses at <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Michigan State University. As discussed in our earlier paper [28] the camera was mounted at <lb/>the back of the classroom to record the instructor activities and interactions between instruc-<lb/>tor and students. All the instructors in our data set gave permission for their classes to be video <lb/>recorded and for their course exams to be analyzed. All identifying information, such as <lb/>instructor name, course ID, semester, etc. were removed before coding, and randomly gener-<lb/>ated identifiers were applied to the video files, in accordance with the Michigan State Univer-<lb/>sity approved IRB protocols (IRB# x13-1110e Category: Exempt 1, IRB# x17-1053e Category: <lb/>Exempt 1). <lb/>3D-LOP analysis of classroom videos <lb/>The 3D-LOP was used to code video recordings, as discussed in our prior work [28]. For the <lb/>present study, videos of 82 class meeting sessions across the gateway courses in biology, chem-<lb/>istry, and physics were recorded. Each video was segmented into blocks of contiguous time <lb/>devoted to a particular topic of instruction. These segments (N = 417) were then coded by two <lb/>researchers from the team for alignment with the three dimensions and whether instruction <lb/>was instructor-or student-centered. By instructor-centered, we mean the instructional activi-<lb/>ties were lecture-based, perhaps with call-and-response questioning. By student-centered, we <lb/>mean more extensive instructor-student interactions, group or individual tasks, clicker ques-<lb/>tions and so on. This process allowed us to create parallel sets of timelines that provide infor-<lb/>mation about the topic being taught, the classroom activities, whether the instruction was 3D, <lb/>and whether the topic segment was &quot;student-centered&quot; or &quot;instructor-centered&quot;. Here we <lb/>define &quot;active&quot; segments as those with more than 50% of the time dedicated to teaching activi-<lb/>ties that directly engaged students (interactions, tasks, clicker questions), and 3D segments as <lb/>those that spend more than 50% of the time on 3DL. We chose these criteria for simplicity and <lb/>because other researchers have also used this cut off to determine whether active learning is <lb/>present [5]. Thus, a segment may be characterized as 3D and active, active only, 3D only, or <lb/>neither 3D nor active. The data reported here do not include those used in our development of <lb/>the 3D-LOP and were recorded over several years before the COVID pandemic. <lb/>Each video was coded by at least two disciplinary experts, and if the IRR fell below 70% a <lb/>third disciplinary expert also coded the videos. Eventually all videos were coded until all the <lb/>coders agreed. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>RQ 1: In what ways can 3DL and/or active learning occur within a STEM <lb/>course? <lb/>As discussed above, the data from coding class videos with the 3D-LOP allow us to develop <lb/>visualizations of class timelines as shown in Fig 2. Each timeline shows the types of instruc-<lb/>tional activities (teaching activities) and the segments of class (or topics) that are three dimen-<lb/>sional. Each 3DL segment is coded as instructor-centered (l) or student-centered (S), which <lb/>allows us to determine: 1) the class time that is devoted to student engagement (active learn-<lb/>ing), 2) the class time that is devoted to 3DL, and 3) the class time that is devoted to both 3DL <lb/>and active learning. Fig 2 provides representative examples of such timelines, which can be <lb/>characterized as (a) active but not 3D, (b) active and 3D, (c) 3D but not active, and (d) neither <lb/>active nor 3D. <lb/>Active but not 3D. Instructional segments that employ active learning techniques at least <lb/>50% of the time but are not 3D are quite common in our data set (95 of 417 segments, see Fig <lb/>3); the timeline in Fig 2A exemplifies one such class session. In this introductory biology class <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. Representative timelines highlighting examples of each of the four possible combinations of active and 3D class segments. (a) A <lb/>73-minute biology class session that is active but not 3D. (b) A 77-min long chemistry class session that is both active and aligned with 3DL. (c) A <lb/>47-min long chemistry class session that is not active but contains a 3DL-aligned segment. (d) A 52-min physics class that is neither active nor 3D. <lb/>The leftmost column provides a label for each row, with the beginning of class starting at the right edge of the label column and the end of the class <lb/>session at the right edge of the timeline; the width of each segment (labelled here as Topic) is directly proportional to the time spent on that topic <lb/>during the class session. Admin refers to announcements by instructor; Task refers to students engaging in a task as described in the 3D-LOP paper. <lb/>Checkmarks and filled color denote the presence of a given dimension with &quot;(I)&quot; and &quot;(S)&quot; denoting Instructor or Student-centered engagement with <lb/>a Scientific Practice, if present. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>session, students worked in groups on several activities, which we label as &quot;Tasks&quot;. These tasks <lb/>included discussions on identifying the correct number of chromosomes for a given set of <lb/>cells, drawing cells in different stages of cell division as the discussion of meiosis progressed, <lb/>and identifying the genotype and phenotype of common traits (e.g., mid-digital hair). Punctu-<lb/>ating these task segments were periods of lecturing in which the task is concluded or new top-<lb/>ics are introduced. The tasks were focused on observation of elements of biological systems <lb/>and building foundational skills. Although these tasks potentially build important foundational <lb/>knowledge for biology and prepare students for future topics in the class, they do not engage <lb/>students with any of the Scientific Practices. While most of the class period is devoted to stu-<lb/>dent activities and is engaging students in a range of tasks, it is not asking students to use their <lb/>knowledge in sensemaking activities, but rather the students are re-representing ideas in the <lb/>form of pictures and diagrams. <lb/>Active and 3D. The data set contains 58 segments that are both active and 3D. An exam-<lb/>ple of a class with 3 such segments is provided by the timeline in Fig 2B from a general chemis-<lb/>try course, in which the topic of solutions is discussed over several segments. Here, we see <lb/>instructional approaches that included instructor-student interactions that go beyond lecture <lb/>interactions, multiple tasks that engage students, and a series of clicker questions followed by <lb/>group discussions. Aside from the segment designated as &quot;Homework Review&quot;, all topics were <lb/>explored by means of at least one of the Scientific Practices, and 3 out of 4 of these segments in <lb/>the class are three-dimensional. All the occurrences of Scientific Practices are characterized as <lb/>student-centered. Students constructed explanations and models for themselves, rather than <lb/>watching the instructor work through the reasoning. For instance, the activities focused on <lb/>students engaging with a hands-on activity (observing the dissolution of a salt and the accom-<lb/>panying temperature change). After scaffolded group discussions facilitated by the instructor, <lb/>Graduate Teaching Assistants and Undergraduate Learning Assistants supported groups of <lb/>Fig 3. Contingency table displaying the number of segments observed to be 3D or not, versus active or not. A <lb/>segment is defined as active when 50% or more of the segment time is devoted to non-lecture teaching activities, and as <lb/>3D when 50% of more or the segment time involves 3D instruction. Expected counts and the chi-square residuals for <lb/>each cell are given above the observed counts. Cell color indicates the magnitude of the contribution of the residual to <lb/>the chi-square value for the table as shown in the color bar below the table: Blue indicates more than expected by <lb/>chance and red less than expected. The chi-square value for the table is 33.9, with the Fisher&apos;s p-value of less than 0.001 <lb/>and an effect size (phi) of 0.285 (small to medium). The critical Bonferroni-corrected chi-square value is 9.14 for an <lb/>alpha of o,01. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

   	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

  	<page>/ 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>students working to create an explanation for their observations and answer a series of clicker <lb/>questions. By incorporating the Core Ideas of Energy and Electrostatic and Bonding Interac-<lb/>tions and the Crosscutting Concept of Systems and System Models, students constructed a <lb/>model that explained the observed temperature change, by relating it to the energy changes as <lb/>various interactions are either broken or formed. While not all class sessions that are 3DL-<lb/>aligned are as active, the co-occurrence of 3DL and active learning appears to be common in <lb/>3D class sessions as will be discussed later. <lb/>3D but not active. Not all classes that focus on 3DL are also student-centered (35 of 417 <lb/>segments), as illustrated by the timeline shown in Fig 2C, which depicts a traditional lecture in <lb/>a large-enrollment general chemistry course. The class consisted of three different topic seg-<lb/>ments. Instruction began with a lecture review of Valence-Shell Electron-Pair Repulsion <lb/>(VSEPR) Theory, followed by using that theory to understand how molecular dipoles can arise <lb/>and how they can be used to predict molecular properties. Finally, hybrid orbital formation in <lb/>bonding was described. After the VSEPR review, the instructor engaged students with the con-<lb/>tent by combining use of VSEPR as a model that predicts molecular shape and knowledge of <lb/>bond polarities to predict the distribution of electron densities in a molecule. Molecular polar-<lb/>ity was then used to predict and explain molecular properties. Although some student engage-<lb/>ment occurred during this class session, it was either via call-and-response questioning or by <lb/>the instructor addressing student questions during the lecture; therefore, we do not character-<lb/>ize the instruction in this class as active learning, since it did not incorporate activities usually <lb/>designated as active learning, such as clicker questions, peer discussion, or group activities <lb/>[1,3]. <lb/>The non-active module on the use of molecular dipoles has been characterized as three-<lb/>dimensional. However, in this case, the instructor was doing the work of demonstrating how <lb/>to explore a phenomenon (why different molecular substances have different melting and boil-<lb/>ing points), while employing the Scientific Practice of Developing and Using Models for their <lb/>students (as indicated by the &quot;(I)&quot; on the diagram meaning an &quot;instructor-centered segment&quot;). <lb/>By discussing the molecular shape and electron distribution, the instructor showed how the <lb/>molecular structure can be used to predict molecular properties (a Core Idea), by using <lb/>VSEPR as a model and the Crosscutting Concept of cause and effect (strong attractive interac-<lb/>tions between polar molecules cause the macroscopic substance to exhibit predictable proper-<lb/>ties such as a high boiling point). <lb/>Neither active nor 3D. We have numerous examples of classroom recordings that are nei-<lb/>ther active, nor 3D (229 of 417 segments). Fig 2D provides an example of a physics class that <lb/>meets this criterion. In this traditional-lecture, large-enrollment introductory electromagne-<lb/>tism course, the lecture focused on introducing the fundamental connections between electric <lb/>fields and charges. These ideas are certainly important and foundational to much of the future <lb/>curriculum. However, the instructor did not present the phenomena and key connections in a <lb/>way that employed any Scientific Practices; hence, the class was not 3D. Although some stu-<lb/>dent engagement occurred, it was either call-and-response questioning or the instructor <lb/>addressed student questions during the lecture. Whereas many of the traditional-format phys-<lb/>ics courses in our database employed clicker questions and peer discussion, in this case the <lb/>instructor did not engage students in this way. Hence, this class was not designated as includ-<lb/>ing any active learning (Freeman et al., 2014; Lombardi et al., 2021). <lb/>The four examples of class timelines in Fig 2 show that active learning and 3DL are in fact <lb/>different, and that these differences can be detected using the 3D-LOP. It is possible to have <lb/>one without the other; a class session may be highly active and yet not involve students&apos; use of <lb/>knowledge to make sense of phenomena. For example, the class in which students draw the <lb/>stages of meiosis (shown in Fig 2A) has students engaged in tasks most of the time, but they <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>/ 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>are not engaged in reasoning about Core Ideas. Rather, they are drawing diagrams of a process, <lb/>and those diagrams are not used to predict or explain anything further. On the other hand, Fig <lb/>2B represents a class which is both active and involves 3DL where students are engaged in sen-<lb/>semaking activities that are 3D. Students feel the temperature change when a salt dissolves in <lb/>water and use the core ideas of interactions and energy to predict and explain this phenome-<lb/>non. Fig 2C represents a class where there is a 3DL segment in which the instructor is doing <lb/>the work by modelling for the class how VSEPR can be used to predict and explain molecular <lb/>properties, but there is little meaningful input or activity from most of the students. Finally Fig <lb/>2D represents a class where there are no student-instructor interactions, the material is being <lb/>delivered by a lecture, and does not include any 3D segments. <lb/>RQ 2: How are 3DL and active learning related? <lb/>As shown in the examples above, active learning and 3DL are different, and it is entirely possi-<lb/>ble to have one without the other. An important next question, then, is: how are active learning <lb/>and 3DL related? To address whether there is a relationship between active learning and 3DL <lb/>in our data set, we designated the 417 video segments as active or not active, and 3D or not-<lb/>3D, using the criterion that 50% of the instructional time in the segment should be active and/ <lb/>or 3D, respectively, to qualify for that designation. Using this characterization, we were able to <lb/>determine whether there is a relationship between active learning and 3D learning using a chi-<lb/>square analysis. This type of analysis can determine whether co-occurrences of the two are <lb/>greater than one would expect by chance. Out of the 417 video segments in our data set, more <lb/>than half of them are neither 3D nor active. This is not surprising, as traditional instruction is <lb/>common, particularly in large-enrollment introductory courses that make up the majority of <lb/>our data set, and studies have shown that the transformation of instruction is slow [9]. 93 of <lb/>the 417 segments were characterized as 3D, while 153 were active. 58 of these active sections <lb/>were also 3D and the rest (95) were not 3D. Using these data, we find a significant association <lb/>between 3D and active segments with a small-to-medium effect size (chi-square, 33.9, p_fisher <lb/>&lt;0.001, phi = 0.285), as shown in Fig 3. <lb/>This chi-square test tells us that 3D and active instructional segments tend to co-occur, but <lb/>it does not tell us what is driving this relationship. A post-hoc analysis using the contributions <lb/>to the chi-square allowed us to calculate the standardized residual for each of the cells in the <lb/>contingency table (Fig 3). This provides a measure for how different the observed count is <lb/>from the expected count, and thus shows which combinations are driving the associations in <lb/>the table. For this table, the critical value is 9.14, and therefore, as shown in Fig 3, the major <lb/>driver of significance is the higher-than-expected number of segments in which 3D &amp; active <lb/>learning co-occur. <lb/>Our findings indicate that 3D instruction is moderately associated with active learning, but <lb/>that the reverse is not true. In our sample, we observed that about 1/3 of the 3D segments were <lb/>not active (35/93), whereas nearly 2/3 of the active learning segments were not 3D (95/153). <lb/>That is, a focus on 3DL is also likely to involve active learning, whereas a focus on active learn-<lb/>ing practices is not as likely to incorporate 3DL. <lb/>Discussion and implications <lb/>Our analysis of the video recordings from 82 classes (and 417 total instructional segments), <lb/>using the 3D-LOP shows that: 1) 3D instruction and active learning are different, and it is pos-<lb/>sible to have one without the other, and 2) 3D instruction is likely to include active student <lb/>engagement, whereas active learning does not necessarily include 3DL. Although we do not <lb/>know how this association arises, there are several potential explanations. For example, it may <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>be that because the Scientific and Engineering Practices are inherently active, when instructors <lb/>focus on 3DL and incorporating these practices into their instruction and assessment, they are <lb/>also more likely to actively engage their students. Alternatively, perhaps instructors who <lb/>become aware of 3DL strategies are already cognizant of the advantages of active learning and <lb/>thus incorporate them along with 3DL. It is also possible that because engaging students in Sci-<lb/>entific Practices is at the heart of 3DL, instructors who understand 3DL and are intentional in <lb/>their instructional design also incorporate active learning to engage the students. The mecha-<lb/>nism by which an instructor comes to use 3DL almost certainly depends on the instructor and <lb/>the constraints and affordances of their environment, but what seems clear is that while 3DL <lb/>and active learning could both be considered evidence-based approaches to teaching and <lb/>learning, only one of them provides a well described framework and mechanism to support <lb/>students&apos; use of knowledge in scientifically authentic ways. <lb/>We will illustrate this difference using the topic of meiosis in an introductory biology course <lb/>as an example, and as shown in Table 1. A traditional lecture on meiosis may involve discuss-<lb/>ing the structures seen in diagrams or micrographs illustrating the stages of meiosis and <lb/>describing the importance of meiosis in generating gametes. Having students work in groups <lb/>making diagrams or manipulating pipe cleaners or yarn to illustrate the stages of meiosis con-<lb/>verts this lecture into an active learning experience that is not necessarily three-dimensional, <lb/>as illustrated in Fig 2A. While this type of activity may enhance student performance on assess-<lb/>ments that ask them to match images to the stages of meiosis or describe what happens at each <lb/>stage, it is unclear, or even unlikely, that this engaged learning would enhance their ability to <lb/>explain how and why meiosis produces gametes with one allele of each gene (assuming a <lb/>Table 1. Distinguishing features of four hypothetical biology class meetings. <lb/>Biology <lb/>Example <lb/>Not Active (Instructor-centered) <lb/>Active (Student-centered) <lb/>Not 3D <lb/>• traditional lecture <lb/>• instructor discusses structures associated <lb/>with stages of meiosis <lb/>• instructor describes importance of meiosis in <lb/>generating gametes <lb/>• call-and-response questioning or the <lb/>instructor addresses student questions during the <lb/>lecture <lb/>• multiple tasks that engage students <lb/>• students identify the correct number of <lb/>chromosomes for a given set of cells <lb/>• students draw cells in different stages of cell <lb/>division <lb/>• students manipulate pipe cleaners or yarn to <lb/>illustrate stages <lb/>• students identify the genotype and phenotype <lb/>of common traits <lb/>Instructor presents content without SPs or CIs or <lb/>CCCs (content agnostic; didactic) <lb/>Students re-represent and identify (content <lb/>agnostic; interactive) <lb/>3D <lb/>• traditional lecture <lb/>• instructor constructs models that explain <lb/>how the molecular machinery in the cell <lb/>replicates and sorts information <lb/>• instructor makes predictions of what <lb/>happens to that information when the <lb/>mechanism fails or changes <lb/>• multiple tasks that engage students <lb/>• students construct models and use them to <lb/>explain how the molecular machinery in the cell <lb/>replicates and sorts information <lb/>• students make predictions of what happens <lb/>to that information when the mechanism fails or <lb/>changes using the model <lb/>Instructor demonstrates how to explore a <lb/>phenomenon with 3DL (CI-focused content with <lb/>SPs &amp; CCCs; didactic) <lb/>Students explore a phenomenon with 3DL (CI-<lb/>focused content with SPs &amp; CCCs; interactive) <lb/>Distinguishing features of four hypothetical biology class meetings focused on the topic of meiosis, representing each <lb/>of the four possible combinations of Active and 3D. The class depicted by the timeline in Fig 2A falls into the Active / <lb/>Not 3D cell here. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>diploid organism) while contributing to genetic diversity; or to predict how changes in the <lb/>components or process would change the outcome, without explicitly asking students to use <lb/>the model to explain or predict. Helping students achieve these goals requires engagement in <lb/>constructing and using models to explain how the molecular machinery in the cell replicates <lb/>and sorts information and how this causes appropriate mixing and distribution of this infor-<lb/>mation. Making a lesson on meiosis three-dimensional accomplishes this. The instructor <lb/>would focus on the core idea of information flow and include a scientific practice, for example <lb/>by using a model to make predictions, using the cross-cutting concept cause and effect. The <lb/>purpose of the lesson is now helping students develop a mechanistic understanding of how the <lb/>cell sorts genetic information, which enables predictions of what happens to that information <lb/>when the mechanism fails or changes. As we have shown earlier, engaging students in making <lb/>predictions will most likely result in active learning, but what the students are doing and why <lb/>they are doing it will be quite different than in the original active learning scenario. It is cer-<lb/>tainly possible that active learning can result in high-quality instructional activities that pro-<lb/>mote knowledge in use or activities that mirror authentic scientific activities, however, three-<lb/>dimensional learning, by design, intentionally accomplishes this, and in many cases results in <lb/>active learning as well. <lb/>The key difference between engaging students in active learning and engaging students in <lb/>3DL is that 3DL requires students to gain experience with the components of the Scientific <lb/>Practices. For many students, this requires a shift-from restating ideas that they have learned, <lb/>or learning skills that are never used to predict or explain, or performing calculations without <lb/>understanding what the result implies-to understanding and articulating why a phenomenon <lb/>occurs, or using data or calculations to support a claim, or constructing and using models to <lb/>predict and explain what happens when the system is changed. 3DL provides both instructors <lb/>and students with explicit guidelines for what it means to engage in Scientific Practices. Rather <lb/>than the nebulous goals of &quot;critical thinking&quot; or &quot;higher order thinking&quot;, 3DL makes it possible <lb/>to construct both formative and summative assessments that require engagement in 3DL in all <lb/>its forms. There are a number of resources available for faculty who are interested in adopting <lb/>the 3DL approach, from the original National Academies report [22], to how to adapt assess-<lb/>ments to make them 3D [50], the design of 3D curricula [30,51,52], and approaches to faculty <lb/>development [53,54]. As noted we have also developed protocols that can be used both to mea-<lb/>sure change in assessments and instruction, and to support faculty development by highlight-<lb/>ing important pedagogical changes and instructional designs that tend to support 3DL, <lb/>including courses that go beyond the introductory level (since the underlying theory behind <lb/>the use of 3DL can be (and has been) applied to the design of course sequences and learning <lb/>tasks). Finally, we acknowledge that there are facts, skills and procedures that students have to <lb/>learn in order to use them in the context of Scientific Practices. In general, we have found that <lb/>around 50% of both course time and assessment tasks are an accessible goal that appears to <lb/>lead to improved and long-term use of knowledge [29]. <lb/>Because most faculty development is focused on incorporating student-centered pedago-<lb/>gies, such as those discussed in Freeman et. al. [3], this presents us with a dilemma. Should fac-<lb/>ulty development focus on active engagement, as is currently the case, or should it focus on <lb/>3DL, assuming that student engagement will follow? We caution that characterizing transfor-<lb/>mation efforts by focusing solely on active learning, without also investigating what is expected <lb/>of students in terms of sensemaking and reasoning may result in the illusion of transformation, <lb/>or what Wiggins and McTighe describe as &quot;hands on without being minds on&quot; [55] while at the <lb/>same time maintaining the status quo. <lb/>We propose that it is time to move beyond &quot;active learning&quot; and refocus attention on what <lb/>it is that we want students to know and do. There are many potential ways to approach <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>redesigning teaching and learning, for example: a focus on modelling phenomena [56,57], or <lb/>systems thinking [58-60], the well-established POGIL learning cycle [17], Course based <lb/>research experiences (CURES) [61], or the use of interactive simulations to model predict and <lb/>explain data arising from a specific phenomenon [19]. However, 3DL is a unifying framework <lb/>that can tie all of these approached together. POGIL and the use of interactive simulations to <lb/>model and predict can be understood as incorporating the Scientific Practices of constructing <lb/>and using models and analyzing and interpreting data., and Systems Thinking is a cross-cut-<lb/>ting concept. It is also important to recognize that none of these approaches are meaningful <lb/>without connections to disciplinary Core Ideas. 3DL provides an evidence-based framework <lb/>for designing instructional materials that center around student sensemaking of phenomena, <lb/>and, as we have shown, tends to include student engagement, even in large lecture sections <lb/>that traditionally are far more passive. We propose that focusing on creating 3DL aligned <lb/>learning objectives, assessments, and instructional materials is a more fruitful approach to <lb/>transforming a learning environment than the more common approach which focuses on <lb/>instructional methods such as incorporating clickers, or group activities alone. This approach <lb/>recognizes that it is what students are doing, across a wide range of activities both inside and <lb/>outside of the class, rather than the mere fact that they are doing something, that ultimately <lb/>can result in students having more coherent, connected, and useful disciplinary knowledge. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Data. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the faculty who provided observational access, engaged in discussions of core ideas, <lb/>and have taken steps to incorporate three-dimensional learning into their courses. We also <lb/>thank our advisory board members for their helpful feedback: Stacey Lowery Bretz, Charles <lb/>Henderson, Joseph Krajcik, Michelle Smith, and Marilyne Stains. Finally, our team of under-<lb/>graduate research assistants (S. Luba, S. Ly, C. Morrison, K. Noyes, Z. Nusbaum, R.Thornburg, <lb/>and Q. Babcock) helped code the videos for teaching activities and create 3D-LOP timelines. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Diane Ebert-May, Cori L. Fata-<lb/>Hartley, Deborah G. Herrington, Lynmarie A. Posey, Sonia M. Underwood. <lb/>Data curation: Melanie M. Cooper, Cori L. Fata-Hartley, James T. Laverty, Paul C. Nelson. <lb/>Formal analysis: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Justin H. Carmel, Erin M. Duffy, <lb/>Diane Ebert-May, Cori L. Fata-Hartley, Deborah G. Herrington, James T. Laverty, Paul C. <lb/>Nelson, Lynmarie A. Posey, Jon R. Stoltzfus, Ryan L. Stowe, Ryan D. Sweeder, Stuart Tess-<lb/>mer, Sonia M. Underwood. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Justin H. Carmel, Diane <lb/>Ebert-May, Cori L. Fata-Hartley, Deborah G. Herrington, James T. Laverty, Lynmarie A. <lb/>Posey, Ryan D. Sweeder, Sonia M. Underwood. <lb/>Investigation: Melanie M. Cooper, Diane Ebert-May, Paul C. Nelson. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Methodology: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Deborah G. Herrington, Paul C. Nel-<lb/>son, Lynmarie A. Posey, Jon R. Stoltzfus. <lb/>Project administration: Melanie M. Cooper, Deborah G. Herrington, Paul C. Nelson. <lb/>Resources: Melanie M. Cooper. <lb/>Supervision: Melanie M. Cooper. <lb/>Validation: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Justin H. Carmel, Erin M. Duffy, Diane <lb/>Ebert-May, Paul C. Nelson, Lynmarie A. Posey, Jon R. Stoltzfus, Ryan L. Stowe, Ryan D. <lb/>Sweeder, Stuart Tessmer, Sonia M. Underwood. <lb/>Visualization: Paul C. Nelson, Ryan L. Stowe. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Melanie M. Cooper. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Melanie M. Cooper, Marcos D. Caballero, Justin H. Carmel, Erin <lb/>M. Duffy, Diane Ebert-May, Cori L. Fata-Hartley, Deborah G. Herrington, James T. Lav-<lb/>erty, Paul C. Nelson, Lynmarie A. Posey, Jon R. Stoltzfus, Ryan L. Stowe, Ryan D. Sweeder, <lb/>Stuart Tessmer, Sonia M. Underwood. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Lombardi D, Shipley TF, Bailey JM, Bretones PS, Prather EE, Ballen CJ, et al. The Curious Construct <lb/>of Active Learning. Psychol Sci Public Interest. 2021; 22: 8-43. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>1529100620973974 <lb/>2. Rahman T, Lewis SE. Evaluating the evidence base for evidence-based instructional practices in chem-<lb/>istry through meta-analysis. Journal of Research in Science Teaching. 2020; 57: 765-793. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1002/tea.21610 <lb/>3. Freeman S, Eddy SL, McDonough M, Smith MK, Okoroafor N, Jordt H, et al. Active learning increases <lb/>student performance in science, engineering, and mathematics. PNAS. 2014; 111: 8410-8415. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1319030111 PMID: 24821756 <lb/>4. Ballen CJ, Wieman C, Salehi S, Searle JB, Zamudio KR. Enhancing Diversity in Undergraduate Sci-<lb/>ence: Self-Efficacy Drives Performance Gains with Active Learning. LSE. 2017; 16: ar56. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1187/cbe.16-12-0344 PMID: 29054921 <lb/>5. Theobald EJ, Hill MJ, Tran E, Agrawal S, Arroyo EN, Behling S, et al. Active learning narrows achieve-<lb/>ment gaps for underrepresented students in undergraduate science, technology, engineering, and <lb/>math. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2020; 117: 6476-6483. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1073/pnas.1916903117 PMID: 32152114 <lb/>6. Chasteen SV, Chattergoon R, Prather EE, Hilborn R. Evaluation methodology and results for the new <lb/>faculty workshops. AMER ASSOC PHYSICS TEACHERS; 2016. <lb/>7. Chasteen SV, Chattergoon R. Insights from the Physics and Astronomy New Faculty Workshop: How <lb/>do new physics faculty teach? Physical Review Physics Education Research. 2020; 16: 020164. <lb/>8. Stains M, Pilarz M, Chakraverty D. Short and Long-Term Impacts of the Cottrell Scholars Collaborative <lb/>New Faculty Workshop. J Chem Educ. 2015; 92: 1466-1476. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed. <lb/>5b00324 <lb/>9. Stains M, Harshman J, Barker MK, Chasteen SV, Cole RS, DeChenne-Peters SE, et al. Anatomy of <lb/>STEM teaching in North American universities. Science. 2018; 359: 1468-1470. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1126/science.aap8892 PMID: 29599232 <lb/>10. Schulz HW, FitzPatrick B. Teachers&apos; understandings of critical and higher order thinking and what this <lb/>means for their teaching and assessments. Alberta Journal of Educational Research. 2016; 62: 61-86. <lb/>11. Lewis A, Smith D. Defining higher order thinking. Theory Into Practice. 1993; 32: 131-137. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1080/00405849309543588 <lb/>12. Bowen RS. Student perceptions of &quot;critical thinking&quot;: insights into clarifying an amorphous construct. <lb/>Chem Educ Res Pract. 2022; 23: 725-741. https://doi.org/10.1039/D2RP00097K <lb/>13. Bailin S. Critical Thinking and Science Education. Science &amp; Education. 2002; 11: 361-375. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1023/A:1016042608621. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>14. National Research Council. Education for life and work: Developing transferable knowledge and skills in <lb/>the 21st century. Washington, DC: National Academies Press; 2012. <lb/>15. National Research Council. Discipline-based education research: Understanding and improving learn-<lb/>ing in undergraduate science and engineering. Singer S. R, Nielson N. R, Schweingruber H. A, editors. <lb/>Washington, DC: National Academies Press; 2012. <lb/>16. Walker L, Warfa A-RM. Process oriented guided inquiry learning (POGIL®) marginally effects student <lb/>achievement measures but substantially increases the odds of passing a course. PLOS ONE. 2017; 12: <lb/>e0186203. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0186203 PMID: 29023502 <lb/>17. Moog RS, Spencer JN, editors. Process Oriented Guided Inquiry Learning (POGIL). Washington, DC: <lb/>American Chemical Society; 2008. <lb/>18. Rodriguez J-MG, Hunter KH, Scharlott LJ, Becker NM. A Review of Research on Process Oriented <lb/>Guided Inquiry Learning: Implications for Research and Practice. J Chem Educ. 2020; 97: 3506-3520. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.0c00355 <lb/>19. Moore EB, Chamberlain JM, Parson R, Perkins KK. PhET Interactive Simulations: Transformative <lb/>Tools for Teaching Chemistry. J Chem Educ. 2014; 91: 1191-1197. https://doi.org/10.1021/ed4005084 <lb/>20. VandenPlas JR, Herrington DG, Shrode AD, Sweeder RD. Use of Simulations and Screencasts to <lb/>Increase Student Understanding of Energy Concepts in Bonding. J Chem Educ. 2021; 98: 730-744. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.0c00470 <lb/>21. Cooper MM, Caballero MD, Ebert-May D, Fata-Hartley CL, Jardeleza SE, Krajcik JS, et al. Challenge <lb/>faculty to transform STEM learning. Science. 2015; 350: 281-282. https://doi.org/10.1126/science. <lb/>aab0933 PMID: 26472897 <lb/>22. National Research Council. A Framework for K-12 Science Education: Practices, Crosscutting Con-<lb/>cepts, and Core Ideas. Washington, DC: The National Academies Press; 2012. <lb/>23. Cooper MM. The Crosscutting Concepts: Critical Component or &quot;Third Wheel&quot; of Three-Dimensional <lb/>Learning? J Chem Educ. 2020; 97: 903-909. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.9b01134 <lb/>24. Linn MC, Palmer E, Baranger A, Gerard E, Stone E. Undergraduate research experiences: Impacts and <lb/>opportunities. Science. 2015; 347: 1261757. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1261757 PMID: 25657254 <lb/>25. Gentile J, Brenner K, Stephens A, editors. Undergraduate Research Experiences for STEM Students: <lb/>Successes, Challenges, and Opportunities. Washington, D.C.: National Academies Press; 2017. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.17226/24622 <lb/>26. Cooper MM, Posey LA, Underwood SM. Core ideas and topics: Building up or drilling down? J Chem <lb/>Educ. 2017; 94: 541-548. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.6b00900 <lb/>27. Laverty JT, Underwood SM, Matz RL, Posey LA, Carmel JH, Caballero MD, et al. Characterizing col-<lb/>lege science assessments: The Three-Dimensional Learning Assessment Protocol. PLoS ONE. 2016; <lb/>11: e0162333. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0162333 PMID: 27606671 <lb/>28. Bain K, Bender L, Bergeron P, Caballero MD, Carmel JH, Duffy EM, et al. Characterizing college sci-<lb/>ence instruction: The Three-Dimensional Learning Observation Protocol. PLOS ONE. 2020; 15: <lb/>e0234640. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0234640 PMID: 32544166 <lb/>29. Matz RL, Fata-Hartley CL, Posey LA, Laverty JT, Underwood SM, Carmel JH, et al. Evaluating the <lb/>extent of a large-scale transformation in gateway science courses. Science Advances. 2018; 4: <lb/>eaau0554. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aau0554 PMID: 30397646 <lb/>30. Cooper MM, Klymkowsky MW. Chemistry, Life, the Universe and Everything: A new approach to gen-<lb/>eral chemistry, and a model for curriculum reform. J Chem Educ. 2013; 90: 1116-1122. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1020/ed300456y <lb/>31. Ralph VR, Scharlott LJ, Schafer AG, Deshaye MY, Becker NM, Stowe RL. Advancing Equity in STEM: <lb/>The Impact Assessment Design Has on Who Succeeds in Undergraduate Introductory Chemistry. <lb/>JACS Au. 2022; 2: 1869-1880. https://doi.org/10.1021/jacsau.2c00221 PMID: 36032534 <lb/>32. Crandell OM, Kouyoumdjian H, Underwood SM, Cooper MM. Reasoning about Reactions in Organic <lb/>Chemistry: Starting It in General Chemistry. J Chem Educ. 2019; 96: 213-226. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>acs.jchemed.8b00784 <lb/>33. Crandell OM, Lockhart MA, Cooper MM. Arrows on the Page Are Not a Good Gauge: Evidence for the <lb/>Importance of Causal Mechanistic Explanations about Nucleophilic Substitution in Organic Chemistry. J <lb/>Chem Educ. 2020; 97: 313-327. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.9b00815 <lb/>34. Noyes K, McKay RL, Neumann M, Haudek KC, Cooper MM. Developing Computer Resources to Auto-<lb/>mate Analysis of Students&apos; Explanations of London Dispersion Forces. J Chem Educ. 2020; 97: 3923-<lb/>3936. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.0c00445 <lb/>35. Underwood SM, Reyes-Gastelum D, Cooper MM. Answering the questions of whether and when stu-<lb/>dent learning occurs: Using discrete-time survival analysis to investigate how college chemistry <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>students&apos; understanding of structure-property relationships evolves. Sci Educ. 2015; 99: 1055-1072. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/sce.21183 <lb/>36. Underwood SM, Kararo AT, Gadia G. Investigating the impact of three-dimensional learning interven-<lb/>tions on student understanding of structure-property relationships. Chem Educ Res Pract. 2021; 22: <lb/>247-262. https://doi.org/10.1039/D0RP00216J <lb/>37. Houchlei SK, Bloch RR, Cooper MM. Mechanisms, Models, and Explanations: Analyzing the Mechanis-<lb/>tic Paths Students Take to Reach a Product for Familiar and Unfamiliar Organic Reactions. J Chem <lb/>Educ. 2021; 98: 2751-2764. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.1c00099 <lb/>38. Bowen RS, Flaherty AA, Cooper MM. Investigating student perceptions of transformational intent and <lb/>classroom culture in organic chemistry courses. Chemistry Education Research and Practice. 2022; 23: <lb/>560-581. <lb/>39. Ralph VR, Scharlott LJ, Schwarz CE, Becker NM, Stowe RL. Beyond instructional practices: Character-<lb/>izing learning environments that support students in explaining chemical phenomena. Journal of <lb/>Research in Science Teaching. 2022; 59: 841-875. <lb/>40. Irving PW, Obsniuk MJ, Caballero MD. P3: a practice focused learning environment. Eur J Phys. 2017; <lb/>38: 055701. https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6404/aa7529 <lb/>41. Williams L, Upchurch RL. In support of student pair-programming. SIGCSE Bull. 2001; 33: 327-331. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1145/366413.364614 <lb/>42. Braught G, Wahls T, Eby LM. The Case for Pair Programming in the Computer Science Classroom. <lb/>ACM Trans Comput Educ. 2011; 11: 1-21. https://doi.org/10.1145/1921607.1921609 <lb/>43. Paxton J. Live programming as a lecture technique. Journal of Computing Sciences in Colleges. 2002; <lb/>18: 51-56. <lb/>44. Hamerski PC, Irving PW, McPadden D. Learning assistants as student partners in introductory physics. <lb/>Phys Rev Phys Educ Res. 2021; 17: 020107. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevPhysEducRes.17. <lb/>020107 <lb/>45. Irving PW, McPadden D, Caballero MD. Communities of practice as a curriculum design theory in an <lb/>introductory physics class for engineers. Phys Rev Phys Educ Res. 2020; 16: 020143. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevPhysEducRes.16.020143 <lb/>46. Griswold K, McPadden DR, Caballero MD, Irving PW. Denoting and Comparing Leadership Attributes <lb/>and Behaviors in Group Work. 2018. Available: https://www.per-central.org/items/detail.cfm?ID=14790. <lb/>47. Hamerski PC, McPadden D, Caballero MD, Irving PW. Students&apos; perspectives on computational chal-<lb/>lenges in physics class. Phys Rev Phys Educ Res. 2022; 18: 020109. https://doi.org/10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevPhysEducRes.18.020109 <lb/>48. Lund TJ, Pilarz M, Velasco JB, Chakraverty D, Rosploch K, Undersander M, et al. The best of both <lb/>worlds: building on the COPUS and RTOP observation protocols to easily and reliably measure various <lb/>levels of reformed instructional practice. CBE Life Sci Educ. 2015; 14: ar18. https://doi.org/10.1187/ <lb/>cbe.14-10-0168 PMID: 25976654 <lb/>49. Smith MK, Jones FHM, Gilbert SL, Wieman CE. The classroom observation protocol for undergraduate <lb/>STEM (COPUS): A new instrument to characterize university STEM classroom practices. CBE Life Sci <lb/>Educ. 2013; 12: 618-627. https://doi.org/10.1187/cbe.13-08-0154 PMID: 24297289 <lb/>50. Underwood SM, Posey LA, Herrington DG, Carmel JH, Cooper MM. Adapting Assessment Tasks To <lb/>Support Three-Dimensional Learning. J Chem Educ. 2018; 95: 207-217. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. <lb/>jchemed.7b00645 <lb/>51. Underwood SM, Kararo AT, Posey LA, Pollock AM, Herrington DG, Stowe RL, et al. Components Criti-<lb/>cal to Successful Adoption and Adaptation of CLUE, a Transformed General Chemistry Curriculum. J <lb/>Chem Educ. 2023; 100: 3374-3385. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.3c00190 <lb/>52. Cooper MM, Stowe RL, Crandell OM, Klymkowsky MW. Organic Chemistry, Life, the Universe and <lb/>Everything (OCLUE): A Transformed Organic Chemistry Curriculum. J Chem Educ. 2019; 96: 1858-<lb/>1872. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.9b00401 <lb/>53. Fata-Hartley CL, Nelson PC, Matz RL, Cooper MM. CHANGING HOW STEM FACULTY TEACH BY <lb/>CHANGING WHAT THEY TEACH. Handbook of STEM Faculty Development. 2022; 181. <lb/>54. Nelson PC, Matz RL, Bain K, Fata-Hartley CL, Cooper MM. Characterizing faculty motivation to imple-<lb/>ment three-dimensional learning. Disciplinary and Interdisciplinary Science Education Research. 2023; <lb/>5: 11. https://doi.org/10.1186/s43031-023-00079-0 <lb/>55. Wiggins GP, McTighe J. Understanding by Design. 2nd ed. Alexandria, VA: Association for Supervision <lb/>and Curriculum Development; 2005. <lb/>56. Brewe E, Sawtelle V, Kramer LH, O&apos;Brien GE, Rodriguez I, Pamela ´P. Toward equity through participa-<lb/>tion in Modeling Instruction in introductory university physics. Phys Rev ST Phys Educ Res. 2010; 6: <lb/>010106. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevSTPER.6.010106 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>57. Posthuma-Adams E. How the Chemistry Modeling Curriculum Engages Students in Seven Science <lb/>Practices Outlined by the College Board. Journal of Chemical Education. 2014; 91: 1284-1290. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1021/ed400911a <lb/>58. Momsen J, Speth EB, Wyse S, Long T. Using systems and systems thinking to unify biology education. <lb/>CBE-Life Sciences Education. 2022; 21: es3. https://doi.org/10.1187/cbe.21-05-0118 PMID: <lb/>35499820 <lb/>59. Verhoeff RP, Knippels M-CP, Gilissen MG, Boersma KT. The theoretical nature of systems thinking. <lb/>Perspectives on systems thinking in biology education. Frontiers in Education. Frontiers Media SA; <lb/>2018. p. 40. <lb/>60. Orgill M, York S, MacKellar J. Introduction to Systems Thinking for the Chemistry Education Commu-<lb/>nity. J Chem Educ. 2019; 96: 2720-2729. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jchemed.9b00169 <lb/>61. Dolan EL. Course-based undergraduate research experiences: Current knowledge and future direc-<lb/>tions. Natl Res Counc Comm Pap. 2016; 1: 1-34. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Beyond active learning <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295887 May 31, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 17 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>