<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T15:01:48.285Z">11/13/2025 3:01:48 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T15:01:37.021611Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T15:01:37.021611Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Entomological assessment of hessian fabric <lb/>transfluthrin vapour emanators as a means to <lb/>protect against outdoor-biting Aedes after <lb/>providing them to households for routine use <lb/>in Port-au-Prince, Haiti <lb/>Chicoye Supreme 1 , Obrillant Damus 1 , Joseph Frederick 2 † , Jean-Frantz Lemoine 2 , <lb/>Christian Raccurt 1 , Justin McBeath 3¤ , Nosrat Mirzai 4 , Sheila B. Ogoma 5 , Vincent Corbel 6,7 , <lb/>Daniel Impoinvil 8 , Gerry F. Killeen ID <lb/>9,10,11 *, Cyrille Czeher 6,12 <lb/>1 Universite ´Quisqueya, Port-au-Prince, Republic of Haiti, 2 Programme National de Contro ˆle de la Malaria, <lb/>Ministère de la Sante ´Publique et de la Population, Port-au-Prince, Republic of Haiti, 3 Envu UK Ltd, <lb/>Cambridge, Milton, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 4 Institute of Biodiversity, Animal Health and Comparative <lb/>Medicine, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, United Kingdom, 5 Abt Associates, Nairobi, Kenya, 6 Institut de <lb/>Recherche pour le Developpement, University of Montpellier, Montpellier, France, 7 Laborato ´rio de Fisiologia <lb/>e Controle de Artro ´podes Vetores (Laficave), Instituto Oswaldo Cruz (IOC), Fundac ¸ão Oswaldo Cruz <lb/>(FIOCRUZ), Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 8 Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, <lb/>United States of America, 9 Ifakara Health Institute, Ifakara, Morogoro, United Republic of Tanzania, <lb/>10 Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, Department of Vector Biology, Liverpool, United Kingdom, <lb/>11 School of Biological Earth &amp; Environmental Sciences, Environmental Research Institute, University <lb/>College Cork, Cork, Republic of Ireland, 12 Entente Interde ´partementale pour la De ´moustication du Littoral <lb/>Me ´diterrane ´en (EID Me ´diterrane ´e), Montpellier, France <lb/> † Deceased. <lb/>¤ Current address: Innovative Vector Control Consortium, Pembroke Place, Liverpool, United Kingdom <lb/>* gerard.killeen@ucc.ie <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background <lb/>A simple treated fabric device for passively emanating the volatile pyrethroid transfluthrin <lb/>was recently developed in Tanzania that protected against nocturnal Anopheles and Culex <lb/>mosquitoes for several months. Here these transfluthrin emanators were assessed in Port-<lb/>au-Prince, Haiti against outdoor-biting Aedes. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Transfluthrin emanators were distributed to participating households in poor-to-middle class <lb/>urban neighbourhoods and evaluated once every two months in terms of their effects on <lb/>human landing rates of wild Aedes populations. A series of three such entomological <lb/>assessment experiments were conducted, to examine the influence of changing weather <lb/>conditions, various transfluthrin formulations and emanator placement on protective efficacy <lb/>measurements. Laboratory experiments assessed resistance of local Aedes aegypti to <lb/>transfluthrin and deltamethrin, and the irritancy and repellency of the transfluthrin-treated <lb/>fabric used in the field. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/>1 / 27 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Supreme C, Damus O, Frederick J, <lb/>Lemoine J-F, Raccurt C, McBeath J, et al. (2024) <lb/>Entomological assessment of hessian fabric <lb/>transfluthrin vapour emanators as a means to <lb/>protect against outdoor-biting Aedes after <lb/>providing them to households for routine use in <lb/>Port-au-Prince, Haiti. PLoS ONE 19(5): e0298919. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 <lb/>Editor: Luca Nelli, University of Glasgow College of <lb/>Medical Veterinary and Life Sciences, UNITED <lb/>KINGDOM <lb/>Received: May 16, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 31, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 28, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: This is an open access article, free of all <lb/>copyright, and may be freely reproduced, <lb/>distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or <lb/>otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. <lb/>The work is made available under the Creative <lb/>Commons CC0 public domain dedication. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. The data and material availability <lb/>statement now reads as follows: The data for all <lb/>three rounds of field assessments of transfluthrin <lb/>emanator efficacy are available as S1 Data and the <lb/>R script used to process the data for all three <lb/>rounds of field assessments of transfluthrin <lb/>emanator efficacy and optimize the model <lb/>Results <lb/>Across all three entomological field assessments, little evidence of protection against wild <lb/>Ae. aegypti was observed, regardless of weather conditions, transfluthrin formulation or <lb/>emanator placement: A generalized linear mixed model fitted to the pooled data from all <lb/>three assessment rounds (921 females caught over 5129 hours) estimated a relative land-<lb/>ing rate [95% Confidence interval] of 0.87 [0.73, 1.04] for users of treated versus untreated <lb/>emanators (P = 0.1241). Wild Ae. aegypti in this setting were clearly resistant to transfluthrin <lb/>when compared to a fully susceptible colony. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Transfluthrin emanators had little if any apparent effect upon Aedes landing rates by wild <lb/>Ae. aegypti in urban Haiti, and similar results have been obtained by comparable studies in <lb/>Tanzania, Brazil and Peru. In stark contrast, however, parallel sociological assessments of <lb/>perspectives among these same end-users in urban Haitian communities indicate strong <lb/>satisfaction in terms of perceived protection against mosquitoes. It remains unclear why the <lb/>results obtained from these complementary entomological and sociological assessments in <lb/>Haiti differ so much, as do those from a similar set of studies in Brazil. It is encouraging, how-<lb/>ever, that similar contrasts between the entomological and epidemiological results of a <lb/>recent large-scale assessment of another transfluthrin emanator product in Peru, which indi-<lb/>cate they provide useful protection against Aedes-borne arboviral infections, despite appar-<lb/>ently providing only modest protection against Aedes mosquito bites. <lb/></front>

    <body>Background <lb/>The Aedes (Stegomia) mosquitoes that mediate most transmission of Dengue, Chikungunya, <lb/>Yellow Fever and Zika viruses often attack people during daylight hours when they are awake <lb/>and active, often outdoors, so there are limits to how much protection may be reasonably <lb/>expected from indoor interventions [1, 2] like insecticidal bed nets that protect sleeping spaces <lb/>[3] or even insecticidal screens that protect entire houses [4]. However, a recent large-scale <lb/>trial of a spatial repellent product that emanates vapour of the volatile pyrethroid transfluthrin <lb/>to designed to protect users in outdoor spaces and open structures successfully demonstrated <lb/>that such devices may reduce incidence of arboviral infections [5]. Unfortunately, these devices <lb/>and other existing repellent products currently available on the market only protect against <lb/>mosquitoes for hours, days or weeks per application or dispensing dose, so they may be too <lb/>expensive and impractical for continuous, indefinite use in low-income countries like Haiti <lb/>[1, 6], and some formulations may even be hazardous [7, 8]. <lb/>However, a low-technology transfluthrin emanator, which slowly and passively releases <lb/>vapour of this volatile pyrethroid under ambient temperature conditions without any electric-<lb/>ity or other power source, was recently developed in Tanzania [9] that provided &gt;90% protec-<lb/>tion for &gt;4 months against nocturnal Anopheles and Culex spp. vectors of malaria, filariasis <lb/>and several arboviruses in urban Dar es Salaam [10]. In a subsequent study in rural Tanzania, <lb/>&gt;75% protection was sustained over 6 months and at least some degree of protection persisted <lb/>over 2.5 years without any evidence of diversion to non-users [11]. Also, equivalent efficacy <lb/>was achieved over 6 months with a 10-fold lower transfluthrin dosage, which costs only €0.10 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <front>presented in table 1 is available as S2 Analytical <lb/>Script. Access to the transfluthrin formulations <lb/>used for this study may be requested from Envu <lb/>AG though the most relevant national contact <lb/>person at https://www.envu.com/. <lb/>Funding: This research was primarily funded by <lb/>the United States Agency for International <lb/>Development through its Combating Zika and <lb/>Future Threats: A Grand Challenge for <lb/>Development scheme (Award number AID-OAA-F-<lb/>16-00095). GFK was partially supported by an AXA <lb/>Research Chair award, jointly funded by the AXA <lb/>Research Fund and the College of Science, <lb/>Engineering and Food Sciences at University <lb/>College Cork. The funders had no role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to <lb/>publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Open <lb/>access publication was funded and facilitated <lb/>through the ongoing agreement between PLoS and <lb/>the IReL consortium of Irish research libraries. <lb/>Competing interests: JM was employed by Bayer/ <lb/>Envu AG at the time of the study, which <lb/>manufactured all the transfluthrin formulations that <lb/>were used in this study. Otherwise, all the other <lb/>authors declare that they have no competing <lb/>interests. This does not alter our adherence to <lb/>PLoS One policies on sharing data and materials. <lb/>Abbreviations: CI, Confidence interval; EC, <lb/>Emulsifiable Concentrate; GLMM, Generalized <lb/>Linear Mixed Model; HITSS, High-Throughput <lb/>Screening System; NA, Not applicable because this <lb/>was the reference value specified in the model; RR, <lb/>Relative Rate; σ, Variance; SD, Standard Deviation; <lb/>TC, Technical Concentrate; WHO, World Health <lb/>Organization. <lb/></front>

    <body>and releases vapour concentrations of only 0.00013 mg/m 3 [11], comparing well with its regis-<lb/>tered acceptable exposure concentration of 0.5 mg/m 3 [12]. While the initial prototype was <lb/>suspended on four poles placed around the user a more practical format has now been devel-<lb/>oped that is completely mobile and can be conveniently placed anywhere the user chooses to <lb/>[9, 10]. <lb/>If these transfluthrin emanator devices were to prove as effective against day-biting Aedes <lb/>as they are against night-biting Culex and Anopheles, they could offer simultaneous, broad-<lb/>spectrum daytime protection against Dengue, Chikungunya, Yellow Fever and Zika. The fol-<lb/>lowing series of studies was therefore carried out in Port-au-Prince, Haiti, to measure the <lb/>extent and duration of entomologically measured protective efficacy of transfluthrin emana-<lb/>tors against outdoor-biting Aedes under normal conditions of routine community use, as well <lb/>as Culex quinquefasciatus feeding outdoors and indoors. Parallel social science studies to eval-<lb/>uate the perceived effectiveness and user acceptability of transfluthrin emanators are reported <lb/>elsewhere in a complementary manuscript [13]. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Field site and study design <lb/>All procedures for this study, together with the complementary social science assessments of <lb/>end user perceptions in these same Haitian communities [13], and a similar entomological <lb/>assessment of transfluthrin emanator efficacy in Tanzania [14], both of which were carried out <lb/>in parallel with this study, are provided as supporting information in S1-S3 Protocols. These <lb/>simple transfluthrin emanators were distributed to participating households in poor-to-middle <lb/>class urban neighbourhoods of Haut-Turgeau in the city of Port-au-Prince, Haiti (Fig 1) and <lb/>evaluated as described herein, in terms their effects on landing rates of mosquitoes upon <lb/>human users under experimentally controlled conditions. In addition to the quantitative ento-<lb/>mological assessments reported herein, parallel qualitative social science surveys were con-<lb/>ducted among community end-users to gather complementary data. The details of these <lb/>surveys are reported elsewhere [13], revealing generally encouraging perceptions among com-<lb/>munity end-users with respect to the efficacy, safety and utility of these transfluthrin emanator <lb/>devices. <lb/>Each of the household clusters illustrated in Fig 1 consisted of the first four consenting <lb/>households (See Ethical considerations) that could be identified by door-to-door convenience <lb/>sampling, starting from a central point within that neighbourhood. All engagements with <lb/>community members in these neighbourhoods of Port-au-Prince, including the formal social <lb/>science surveys reported elsewhere [13], were carried out in fluent Haitian Creole by resident <lb/>team members for whom this was their first language. While some trivial deviations from the <lb/>following experimental procedures occurred in practice during implementation for practical <lb/>reasons (eg. households withdrawing from the study or some household clusters omitted for <lb/>safety reasons during periods of civil unrest), these slight variations in procedures were all <lb/>minor and had no obvious implications for the interpretation of the results. <lb/>The original intention had been to carry out these quantitative entomological assessments, <lb/>and the complementary qualitative assessments of community end-user perceptions [13], only <lb/>once. As detailed below, however, the former entomological assessments yielded no evidence <lb/>of significant protection in terms of reduced human landing rates at the first attempt. Both <lb/>types of assessment were therefore repeated twice, with minor procedural variations to deter-<lb/>mine whether changing the transfluthrin formulation used or the position of the emanator rel-<lb/>ative to the user improved the levels of efficacy observed based on quantitative entomological <lb/>indicators (Figs 2 and 3). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 1. A map of the study site in the Haut-Turgeau neighbourhood in the city of Port-au-Prince, Haiti, illustrating the <lb/>four clusters of three households where the three rounds of quantitative entomological assessments for transfluthrin <lb/>emanators reported herein were carried out. Note that the three different assessment rounds otherwise differed only in that <lb/>the emanators were treated with different formulations of transfluthrin and slightly different experimental procedures were <lb/>used to assess their efficacy in entomological terms (Figs 2 and 3). The parallel qualitative social science assessments of user-<lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Formulation of transfluthrin treated strips <lb/>Panels of hessian fabric, each measuring 70 × 40 cm, were made from jute rolls bought locally <lb/>and then washed, dried and treated with 99% technical grade transfluthrin (Bayer AG, Envi-<lb/>ronmental Sciences at the time, now trading as Envu AG, Germany) as follows. For each hes-<lb/>sian panel, either a mixture of 3g of transfluthrin technical concentrate (TC) and 90ml of <lb/>locally available liquid dish washing detergent (Apta Vaisselle, Intermarche ´), or the equivalent <lb/>amount of active ingredient in emulsifiable concentrate (EC) form, were mixed with 400ml of <lb/>perceived efficacy reported elsewhere [13] were conducted in the same four clusters as the entomological assessments reported <lb/>herein for the first two assessment rounds. Note, however, that they were carried out in two geographically separate clusters of <lb/>four households for the third assessment round. This separation of the entomological and social science assessments was <lb/>intended to minimize risk of community perspectives being unduly influenced by competing financial interests (See Ethical <lb/>Considerations) or by discussions with the entomological research team during the regular monitoring visits necessitated by <lb/>those procedures [13]. This map was produced with QGIS1 version 3.28.9 open source software, using a base map obtained <lb/>from OpenStreetMap1 under the Open Database License. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g001 <lb/>Fig 2. The experimental setup used to assess transfluthrin emanator effects on landing rates of outdoor-biting mosquitoes using Mosquito Electrocuting <lb/>Traps (METs) [15-19]. This schematic illustrates how the arrangements of the emanator devices varied in terms placement of the emanators relative to the <lb/>human user (Fig 2), as well as the choice of transfluthrin formulation (Emulsifiable concentrate (EC) versus technical concentrate (TC)) used to treat them. The <lb/>Tanzanian studies referred herein to are described in detail in reference [14]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>water and then soaked into a the panel as evenly as possible, as previously described [11]. Each <lb/>panel was then left to dry at room temperature indoors, for between two days and a week, <lb/>before being distributed. Control panels were also soaked into similar mixtures of water and <lb/>detergent but without transfluthrin, to create a suitable set of control devices with which the <lb/>transfluthrin-treated panels could be compared. Before being distributed, the dried strips were <lb/>each wrapped within a wire-mesh to form a folded, zig-zag-shaped, self-supporting emanator <lb/>(Fig 2), essential identical to that similarly evaluated against Ae. aegypti in Tanzania [14]. The <lb/>plastic-coated wire-mesh cover was designed to prevent dermal contact of participants and <lb/>researchers with the treated hessian panels. It was also designed to provide enough rigidity, <lb/>but also enough flexibility, to allow the devices to be folded into self-standing shapes like the <lb/>cylindrical and zig-zag prototypes (Fig 2). <lb/>Provision of transfluthrin emanators and usage guidance to households <lb/>Each participating household was provided with 2 freshly prepared transfluthrin emanators at <lb/>the outset of an experiment, to be used freely by the householders following advisory <lb/>Fig 3. A schematic outline of how the three entomological efficacy assessment experiments described herein fitted into typical seasonal temperature <lb/>trends in Port-au-Prince, Haiti. This schematic also illustrates how these three experiments differed from each other in terms of placement of the emanators <lb/>relative to the human user (Fig 2), as well as the choice of transfluthrin formulation (Emulsifiable concentrate (EC) versus technical concentrate (TC)) used to <lb/>treat them. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>discussions with the research team on how to safely and effectively deploy them. Specifically, <lb/>they were advised that they were free to use the emanators in whatever way they perceive to be <lb/>the most convenient and effective, so long as they did not open the protective holder or use it <lb/>in any other way that would allow direct physical contact with the treated fabric inside. All <lb/>treated emanators provided to households were taken back from them for entomological eval-<lb/>uations of their efficacy for only 8 days (Fig 4) every two months. During brief periods of <lb/>transport between the residences of the community end-users and the test sites where they <lb/>were evaluated under controlled conditions in entomological terms, the devices were fully <lb/>shaded inside black plastic bags to protect them against the sun. Note that the two untreated <lb/>emanators used to complete the experimentally controlled component of the assessment study <lb/>design (Fig 4) were never provided to community members and were instead stored separately <lb/>from any treated emanators when they were not in use. <lb/>For the remainder of each 2-month evaluation cycle, when they were not being assessed <lb/>through controlled entomological experiments, the emanators were used freely within the <lb/>bounds of the safety instructions provided. Participants were actively encouraged to use them <lb/>creatively, in whatever way they perceived to be optimal in terms of convenience and protec-<lb/>tion against mosquito bites, so long as they did not open the protective holder or use them in <lb/>any way that would allow direct physical contact with the treated fabric inside it. As an illustra-<lb/>tive example, the research team explained how one investigator placed such a device beside the <lb/>front door of his house at night to prevent house entry by Culex mosquitoes [11]. <lb/>Initial protocol for measuring the effects of transfluthrin emanators on <lb/>outdoor landing rates of mosquitoes <lb/>The effects of transfluthrin-treated emanators upon human landing rates were measured with <lb/>recently developed Mosquito Electrocuting Traps (METs), which were originally developed <lb/>for night-biting Anopheles and Culex in East Africa [15, 16, 18] but have also proven useful for <lb/>Fig 4. A schematic illustration of the experimental design used for entomological assessment of transfluthrin emanators using Mosquito Electrocuting <lb/>Traps (METs) [15-19] (Fig 2) as a means of protection against Aedes aegypti, Ae. albopictus and other human biting mosquitoes. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>day-biting Aedes in both East Africa [19] and Latin America [17]. METs were placed around <lb/>the feet of volunteers who were fully protected against mosquito bites with protective clothing <lb/>and headgear (Fig 2), similarly to a parallel study in Tanzania where these traps were designed <lb/>[14]. Only adult males (�18 years) and adult females of non-child-bearing age (�50 years) <lb/>were recruited as volunteers, to comprehensively avoid any risks associated with infection with <lb/>Zika or any other vector borne pathogen to which pregnant women are particularly vulnerable. <lb/>All mosquitoes captured by each volunteer over each hour spent sitting in a MET were placed <lb/>in a separate labelled paper cups which were coved on top by a piece of nets to prevent mos-<lb/>quito from escaping. After the morning shift of experiments, mosquitoes in each paper cups <lb/>were first killed by using ethanol, and then sorted, counted and morphologically identified to <lb/>genus level and classified by sex and abdominal status (Unfed, part fed, fully fed or gravid). For <lb/>reasons explained in the Results and Discussion section, the third entomological assessment <lb/>experiment supplemented these MET measurements of landing (presumably host-seeking) <lb/>mosquitoes with prokopak aspirator collections of resting mosquitoes [20]. <lb/>Eight catching stations 15 to 50 meters apart from each other were identified within each <lb/>replicate block, each of which was located in a different part of the study area (Fig 1) to capture <lb/>a diversity of environmental conditions. Catching stations were established in peri-domestic <lb/>areas amongst houses, to maximize mosquito density because, in our experience and consis-<lb/>tent with reports from Brazil [21, 22], Aedes aegypti thrive in these micro-environments and <lb/>don&apos;t fly far from them. Note also, however, that locations of these catching stations were cho-<lb/>sen to minimize disturbance of the residents or accidental contact with the METs, particularly <lb/>children and livestock. <lb/>In the first and second entomological assessment experiments, each day of work comprised <lb/>the same sequence of 6 one-hour collection periods, with 3 being in the morning (6:00 to 7:00, <lb/>7:00 to 08:00 and 08:00 to 09:00) and 3 in the evening (16:00 to 17:00, 17:00 to 18:00 and 18:00 <lb/>to 19:00), to match the known diurnal but crepuscular activity patterns of Ae. aegypti [17]. In <lb/>order to average out potential biases arising from the prevailing directions of wind and sun-<lb/>shine, each of these one-hour periods for a given day was randomly allocated without replace-<lb/>ment to one of 6 angles (0˚, 60˚, 120˚, 180˚, 240˚and 300˚, relative to North), which was the <lb/>same for all 8 catching stations for that day and hour-long period. Each hour, the chair of the <lb/>catcher and the MET [15-19] he or she used was rotated together around the centre of the <lb/>catching station to face in that particular direction, so that all possible orientations relative to <lb/>wind direction (measured with a miniature weather station placed nearby) were represented. <lb/>A replicated Latin square design was used for the entomological efficacy evaluation of the 3 <lb/>pairs of treated emanators distributed to each of the 3 participating households (2 per house-<lb/>hold, 6 in total) in each experimental block. In each experimental block, each of which was <lb/>matched to a specific housing cluster where 6 emanators were distributed to 3 households in <lb/>the community, mosquito collections were conducted over a series of 8 continuous days once <lb/>every 2 months. One complete replicate of the experimental design was completed in each <lb/>block of 8 catching stations by rotating all 8 emanators (the 6 treated emanators used by the <lb/>householders plus 2 negative controls treated with detergent and water only) through all 8 sta-<lb/>tions in a random order over the course of 8 days (Fig 4). Eight human volunteers assigned <lb/>one of the 8 treated or untreated emanators and collected mosquitoes with METs [15-19] <lb/>while using the emanator (Fig 2) assigned to them for that day (Fig 4). Each volunteer was allo-<lb/>cated to a single, fixed catching station within the block for the duration of each replicate, so <lb/>that the two sources of variation in capture rate associated with station and volunteer could be <lb/>combined into a single source of variance captured with a single random effect and maximum <lb/>statistical power in the analysis. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>The 8×8 Latin square design described above was repeated 6 times for a single replicate in a <lb/>single block of 8 catching stations, by repeating it in 6 distinct blocks in different parts of the <lb/>field site, where all 18 participating households were each provided with 2 freshly prepared <lb/>transfluthrin emanators at the outset of the experiment. Overall, one full round of this experi-<lb/>mental design took 48 days of field work (8 days per block and rotation replicate × 6 blocks and <lb/>replicates) that was distributed across a working period of 2 months, to allow personnel time to <lb/>rest and attend to other commitments. These two-month rounds of evaluation were repeated <lb/>up to three times over experimental periods of up to six months. Note that the 6 treated emana-<lb/>tors distributed to household in each block were used for only 8 days of every two-month <lb/>round of experimental entomological assessment. For the remainder of each 2-month evalua-<lb/>tion cycle, the emanators were used freely by the households to whom they were given. <lb/>Subsequent repetition and readjustment of the emanator evaluation <lb/>protocol <lb/>The first attempt to evaluate the transfluthrin emanators (Experimental assessment round 1) <lb/>yielded no evidence of significant protection against outdoor-biting Ae. aegypti (See Results), <lb/>contrasting starkly with the encouraging perspectives shared by community end-users during <lb/>parallel sociological assessments of their perceived effectiveness [13]. This evaluation proce-<lb/>dure was therefore repeated from scratch twice thereafter, with changes made to the transflu-<lb/>thrin formulation used, the positioning of the emanator and the time of year over which each <lb/>round of experimental assessment was carried out (Figs 2 and 3). <lb/>A particularly notable limitation of entomological experiment 2, and one which motivated <lb/>one more repetition of the overall assessment protocol from scratch, was that it was conducted <lb/>in the relatively cool months of the winter. Even though temperatures were nevertheless remark-<lb/>ably warm in the Caribbean at that time (Fig 3), and comparable with those at which transflu-<lb/>thrin had previously proven efficacious in Tanzania [9-11, 23, 24], it was considered prudent to <lb/>repeat the assessment of this new emulsifiable concentrate (EC) formulation with the emanator <lb/>device placed under the chair (Fig 2) during the warmer months of summer (Fig 3). <lb/>This third entomological assessment of efficacy (Experiment 3) was also complemented by <lb/>a parallel repetition of the sociological assessments of perceived effectiveness [13]. However, <lb/>this third set of social science investigations were conducted in separate housing clusters from <lb/>the third set of entomological assessments (Fig 1), to reduce risk of bias arising from compet-<lb/>ing interests amongst participants caused by the generous renumeration associated with the <lb/>latter (See Ethical Considerations and reference [13]). <lb/>Also, the complementary sociological investigations of community end-user perspectives <lb/>indicated that the emanators were perceived to be most effective indoors at night by several <lb/>participants [13], which suggested to the investigators that they might be more effective against <lb/>nocturnal, endophilic Culex quinquefasciatus than against Aedes aegypti. Some informal dis-<lb/>cussions with participants outside these formal sociological studies also suggested some users <lb/>were actually targeting mosquitoes while they rest indoors, rather than when they attempt to <lb/>land and bite [13]. Consequently, the third round of entomological assessments (Experiment <lb/>3) collected human landing mosquitoes indoors as well as outdoors and shifted the the 6-hour <lb/>time window for mosquito collection to either side of dusk (16:00 to 17:00, 17:00 to 18:00, <lb/>18:00 to 19:00, 19:00 to 20:00, 20:00 to 21:00 and 21:00 to 22:00). <lb/>Protective efficacy field data management and analysis <lb/>All the data obtained from the field efficacy assessments (S1 Data) were entered into a pre-<lb/>designed paper-based data collection form, and then entered, cleaned and linked using a <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>standardized entomological data informatics system as previously described [25]. Generalized <lb/>linear mixed models (GLMMs) were initially fitted to each subset of data comprising the first <lb/>full two-month experimental replicate of the study design, before additional GLMMs were fit-<lb/>ted to the full longitudinal datasets, with and without a term for time since treatment to allow <lb/>for any longitudinal trends in protective efficacy. Models assuming simple Poisson distribu-<lb/>tions for the mosquito count outcomes were initially assessed with and without observation <lb/>effects. However, the final reported models giving the best fit to the combined data from all 3 <lb/>rounds of experimental assessment assumed negative binomial distributions for this depen-<lb/>dent variable (AIC = 4887 versus 5018 for the equivalent Poisson model with an observation <lb/>random effect and 5094 without it (P &lt;&lt; 0.0001 in both cases), as per S1 File). All final <lb/>reported models, fitted to either each separate round of experimental assessment, or to the <lb/>pooled data from all three, accounted for the effects of spatiotemporal variations in mosquito <lb/>density by including date, time of day and station within block as separate random effects <lb/>(S1 File). <lb/>Surveying resistance of the field population of Aedes aegypti to <lb/>transfluthrin and deltamethrin <lb/>Resistance status of mosquitoes to transfluthrin was assessed using the CDC bottle bioassay <lb/>[26] and a diagnostic dosage of 3μg of transfluthrin per bottle for Aedes aegypti [27]. Dose-<lb/>response curves were also established in Haiti using wild specimens collected as larvae from <lb/>the study blocks of Debussy (Block 1) and Pedant (Block 4) and compared to results obtained <lb/>at the laboratories of the Institut de Recherche pour le Developpement (IRD) in Montpellier <lb/>using a fully insecticide susceptible Ae. aegypti laboratory colony originating from French <lb/>Polynesia (Bora Bora strain), in order to evaluate their level of resistance. Bottle tests from Feb-<lb/>ruary were done on mixed specimens from both blocks due to low numbers, while tests from <lb/>June were done on specimens from Debussy only. Even when collections were made in sepa-<lb/>rate blocks, these were considered to represent a single population because the distance <lb/>between breeding sites in the two blocks did not exceed 750m. Deltamethrin resistance pheno-<lb/>types for the same mosquito batches were determined using standard World Health Organiza-<lb/>tion (WHO) tube assays [26] and diagnostic concentration of 0.05% deltamethrin on <lb/>impregnated papers, so that their responses to transfluthrin could be interpreted in the context <lb/>of their observed resistance to more conventional solid-phased pyrethroids. <lb/>Assays for the contact irritancy and spatial repellency of transfluthrin-<lb/>treated hessian <lb/>The insecticide susceptible Ae. aegypti Bora Bora colony maintained at IRD Montpellier was <lb/>also used for laboratory assessment of the contact irritancy and spatial repellency effects of the <lb/>transfluthrin-treated hessian used in Haiti, using the high-throughput screening system <lb/>(HITSS) developed by Grieco et al. [28, 29]. Only one concentration of transfluthrin per square <lb/>meter of hessian was used (5.14 g/m 2 , i.e. same application rate used for the field evaluation), <lb/>and two different fabric sizes were tested in order to study how both irritancy and spatial repel-<lb/>lency are affected by varying quantities of transfluthrin vapor within the HITSS. The hessian <lb/>samples were treated in Haiti at the end of February 2019 in the same way as for all emanators <lb/>used in the field study. They were stored in sealed plastic bags at 4˚C in the dark between <lb/>experiments, so that they could be considered freshly treated and with maximum efficacy <lb/>throughout the tests carried out in March and May 2019. All results were expressed as the <lb/>mean proportion that were knocked down or died. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>In the contact irritancy assay, female mosquitoes were introduced at the end of the treated <lb/>chamber (holding the treated hessian on the inner side) and given 10 minutes in the dark to <lb/>escape and rest inside the untreated chamber. The HITSS apparatus was fitted either with a <lb/>full-size rectangle of hessian (10 × 29 cm) covering the whole internal surface of the chamber, <lb/>or a strip of 1 × 29cm (1/10 th of the size of a full panel) fixed at the side of the treated chamber. <lb/>The same tests (at least 8 replicates per condition) were repeated at two different temperatures <lb/>to evaluate whether 2 to 3˚C differences could modify the contact irritancy and spatial repel-<lb/>lency observed using the HITSS experimental set up. <lb/>The spatial repellency assays used the same modular HITSS system but with a third com-<lb/>partment: clear untreated cylinder in the middle where females are introduced, control cham-<lb/>ber on one side, treated chamber on the other side. This test allows to determine if a particular <lb/>substance / concentration act from a distance as spatial repellent or attractant, and to estimate <lb/>the resulting spatial activity index. All mortality, contact irritancy and spatial activity outcomes <lb/>were calculated from the number of mosquitoes found in the different chambers at the end of <lb/>each exposure period, as detailed by Grieco et al. [28, 29]. <lb/>Ethical considerations <lb/>The procedures for this study were reviewed and approved by the Comite ´Nationale de <lb/>Bioe ´thique of the Ministère de la Sante ´Publique et de la Population of the Republic of Haiti <lb/>(Ref. 1718-42) and the Research Ethics Committee of the Liverpool School of Tropical Medi-<lb/>cine in the United Kingdom (Ref. 16-037). <lb/>At the outset of the study, the concentrations of tranfluthrin vapour released by these ema-<lb/>nator devices had previously been measured as only 0.00013 mg/m 3 [11], which compares very <lb/>well (&lt;1/1000th) with its registered acceptable exposure concentration of 0.5 mg/m 3 for the <lb/>European Union [12]. Inhalation exposure to transfluthrin was therefore considered to present <lb/>negligible risk to participants at the outset of this study. <lb/>The MET device is designed to kill mosquitoes before they can bite, so human volunteers sit-<lb/>ting within it are not exposed to increased risk of mosquito-borne infections [15-19]. Each partic-<lb/>ipant in mosquito landing catches sat on a chair with his or her legs protected within the square <lb/>plastic frame of the MET, while the rest of body was protected from mosquito bites by a wearing <lb/>hat with a netting curtain, a long sleeve shirt and gloves (Right hand panel of Fig 2). From within <lb/>the square PVC/wooden frame is lined up with insulating plastic fiber mesh which serves not only <lb/>for protection of mosquito entry, but also prevent volunteer&apos;s limbs from making contact with the <lb/>exterior electrified wires of the MET device [15-19]. Furthermore, only adult males (�18 years) <lb/>and adult females of non-child-bearing age (�50 years) were recruited as participants in mosquito <lb/>landing catches, to comprehensively avoid any risk of infection with Zika, malaria or any other <lb/>vector borne pathogen to which pregnant women are particularly vulnerable. <lb/>Participants in the study were recruited between May 2018 and February 2019. All partici-<lb/>pants in this study were fully informed of these potential risks and benefits of participation in <lb/>the study, as well as their freedom to withdraw at any stage, and were given every opportunity <lb/>to ask any questions they had before informed consent was documented in writing. No per-<lb/>sonal information was collected from any participants, other than their names as recorded on <lb/>the informed consent forms, all of which were stored in locked filing cabinets. Although sev-<lb/>eral of the investigator knew the participants by name and could therefore identify them as <lb/>individuals in the datasets based on their recorded initials, none of the data provided in <lb/>S1 Data can be linked to any individual by any other person. Overall, no personally identifiable <lb/>data or images are presented in this publication and written consent has been obtained from <lb/>both individuals depicted in Fig 2. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>The remuneration rate of $15 per day offered to participants in mosquito landing catches <lb/>with METs [15-19] had been standardized across all PNCM activities at the time, to strike a <lb/>balance between being enough to provide fair compensation for time and discomfort, without <lb/>inducing volunteers to participate despite any reservations they may have. Nevertheless, this <lb/>represented a significant amount of money in this low-income context, raising the possibility <lb/>that community perspectives might be unduly influenced by competing financial interests <lb/>and/or discussions with the entomological research team during the regular visits necessitated <lb/>by those procedures [13]. For the third and final round assessments, the entomological assess-<lb/>ments reported herein and the social science investigations reported elsewhere [13] were <lb/>completely separated and carried out in distinct housing clusters (Fig 1). <lb/>Results <lb/>As illustrated in Fig 5, the first round of entomological evaluations carried out in the middle of <lb/>the Haitian summer yielded little evidence of protection against Aedes aegypti. Based on 437 <lb/>females caught over a total of 985 hours of collection, the best fit GLMM indicated no statisti-<lb/>cally significant reduction in mosquito landing rates (Relative rate (RR) of mosquito landing <lb/>upon users of treated versus untreated emanators [95% confidence intervals (CI)] = 0.85 [0.63, <lb/>1.14], z = -1.092, P = 0.275). Graphical inspection of the distribution of the pooled data reveals <lb/>no obvious difference between landing rates on volunteers using emanators treated with 3g of <lb/>transfluthrin TC and those using untreated devices within 6 weeks of treatment (Fig 5A). <lb/>Examining these same data as a function of time (Fig 5B) or ambient temperature (Fig 5C) <lb/>also indicates negligible differences between treated and untreated emanators and suggests no <lb/>confounders or other obvious alternative explanation for the apparent lack of protective effi-<lb/>cacy observed. Fig 5C is particularly informative because it reveals no treatment-dependent <lb/>effect of temperature on mosquito catches. <lb/>In this first entomological experiment to assess transfluthrin emanators (Fig 5), the devices <lb/>were treated with the TC formulation emulsified with liquid dishwashing detergent [9, 10, 23] <lb/>and placed in front of the legs of the user, so the two subsequent experiments instead used an <lb/>EC formulation and placed the device under the chair of the users (Figs 2 and 3). They were <lb/>also carried out at different times of the year, with experimental assessment 2 being conducted <lb/>in the Haitian winter while experiment 3 extended from late spring to early summer (Fig 3). <lb/>The second entomological assessment of transfluthrin efficacy against Ae. aegypti also <lb/>yielded no evidence of protection against mosquito bites (Fig 6), with GLMM analysis indicat-<lb/>ing only a very modest and non-significant difference between Ae. aegypti landing rates on <lb/>users of treated versus untreated emanators (RR [95% CI] = 0.84 [0.66, 1.07], z = -1.386, <lb/>P = 0.166, from 449 females caught over 2644 hours). Graphical inspection of the explicit data <lb/>for human landing rates of Aedes aegypti reveals no obvious reduction of landing rates by <lb/>treated emanators (Fig 6A), regardless of time since treatment (Fig 6B) or temperature <lb/>(Fig 6C). Indeed, even the trivial differences that are seen in the temperature dependence <lb/>trends for treated and untreated emanators are the opposite of what would be expected if the <lb/>former provided any protection that relied on high temperatures to facilitate evaporation of <lb/>the active ingredient: Mosquito landing rates on users of treated emanators actually increased <lb/>slightly with temperature and crossed over the flatter trend line for users of placebo devices. <lb/>As illustrated in Fig 7, the third round of experimental entomological evaluation yielded no <lb/>evidence of protection against Ae. aegypti, although the sparse mosquito densities during this <lb/>period badly constrained statistical power: GLMM analyses indicate negligible reductions of <lb/>landing rates, albeit with very wide confidence intervals, both indoors (RR [95% confidence <lb/>intervals (CI)] = 1.05 [0.57, 1.94], z = 0.167, P = 0.868 from 63 females caught over 900 hours) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 5. Daily Aedes aegypti landing catches from the first entomological experiment to compare transfluthrin-treated emanators with untreated <lb/>negative control (placebo) emanators, carried out in in Port-au-Prince from July to September 2018. In this first experiment, emanators were <lb/>treated with 3g of the technical concentrate (TC) formulation emulsified with liquid dishwashing detergent [9-11] and placed in front of the chairs of <lb/>users (Left-hand panel of Fig 2) sitting outdoors. A: Outdoor catches with treated and untreated emanators presented as separate violin plots of <lb/>density distribution with the first quartile, median and third quartile indicated by three horizontal lines and overlain by a dot plot of the individual <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>and outdoors (RR [95% CI] = 0.89 [0.44, 1.78], z = -0.329, P = 0.742, from 43 females caught, <lb/>also over 900 hours). No hint of reduced landing rates on users of treated emanators were <lb/>obvious indoors (Fig 7A and 7B) or outdoors (Fig 7A and 7C), regardless of time since treat-<lb/>ment (Fig 7A and 7B) or mean daily temperature (Fig 7D). Again, what little evidence of tem-<lb/>perature dependence could be seen was negligible and with an opposite trend to that expected <lb/>for temperature-dependent evaporation of a repellent active ingredient: The trend line for <lb/>treated emanators has a slight upward slope and crosses over that for untreated emanators <lb/>(Fig 7D). <lb/>Similar to the results from separate analysis of individual rounds of experimental assess-<lb/>ment, pooled analysis of all the data to obtain improved statistical power yielded no evidence <lb/>of significant protection against Ae. aegypti (Table 1). While landing rates were somewhat <lb/>lower outdoors than indoors, and assessment rounds two and especially three were carried out <lb/>at much lower densities of Ae. aegypti mosquitoes, what little protection transfluthrin emana-<lb/>tors appeared to provide only distantly approached significance (Table 1). <lb/>Insufficient numbers of Aedes albopictus (37 females across all three assessment rounds) <lb/>were caught to allow similar assessment of transfluthrin emanator efficacy against this mos-<lb/>quito species. Although far too few Culex spp. mosquitoes were caught to allow rigorous com-<lb/>parison (67, 34 and 23 females in assessment rounds one, two and three, respectively), the <lb/>frequency distributions of landing rates appeared similar indoors and outdoors for users of <lb/>treated and untreated emanators, regardless of temperature or time since treatment (Fig 8). <lb/>Correspondingly, GLMM analysis of the pooled Culex spp. data from all three assessment <lb/>rounds, similar to that described for Ae. aegypti in Table 1, indicated little if any protective <lb/>effect (RR [95%CI] = 0.96 [0.63, 1.46], z = -0.203, P = 0.807) against this genus. <lb/>All pyrethroid resistance assays were carried out in February and June 2019, before and <lb/>immediately after the third field evaluation (Figs 7 and 8). At the transfluthrin diagnostic con-<lb/>centration of 3 μg/bottle, an average of 65% of females tested were knocked down at 1h and <lb/>29% were dead at 24h using field specimens collected in February 2019 (n = 143), while speci-<lb/>mens collected in June 2019 showed 46% of knockdown at 1h and only 10% mortality after the <lb/>usual 24h recovery period (n = 68). Those results indicate a high phenotypic resistance level <lb/>among wild Ae. aegypti in the study area of Port-au-Prince following WHO criteria. More bot-<lb/>tle tests were then conducted with various transfluthrin concentrations between 1.5 and 30 μg/ <lb/>bottle to establish a concentration-response curve, revealing a high phenotypic resistance ratio <lb/>for transfluthrin among wild Ae. aegypti in Port-au-Prince when compared to the susceptible <lb/>colony (Fig 9). Notably, 100% of knockdown and 97% of mortality were reached with bottles <lb/>coated with the 15μg dose, which is 5 times higher than the diagnostic concentration. <lb/>Results from the contact irritancy assessments for the transfluthrin-treated hessian panels <lb/>used in Haiti with the HITSS experimental system [28, 29] are summarized in Table 2. The <lb/>first tests were carried out in a manner that allowed the test mosquitoes could touch and land <lb/>on the treated hessian panel surface. Most females were knocked down after few seconds and <lb/>only 5% were able to escape. The HITSS was then modified using fine mesh mosquito proofing <lb/>sheets to avoid direct contact with the treated material for all subsequent tests, so as to expose <lb/>daily total catch observations. Note that three times as many landing catches were carried out on users of treated emanators than untreated <lb/>emanators (Fig 4), so the width of the probability density violin graphs may be directly compared in absolute terms but not those of the dot plots. B: <lb/>Presented as a longitudinal time course, with separate longitudinal trends for the treated and untreated emanators over time estimated and plotted <lb/>using the geom_smooth function of the ggplot2 package in R, specifying the general linear model (glm) method with time as the independent variable <lb/>and mosquito catch as the dependent variable with a Poisson distribution. C: Presented as a function of daily mean temperature, with separate trends <lb/>for the treated and untreated emanators with temperature variations estimated and plotted using the geom_smooth function of the ggplot2 package in <lb/>R, specifying the glm method with temperature as the independent variable and mosquito catch as the dependent variable with a Poisson distribution. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g005 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 6. Daily Aedes aegypti catches from the second entomological experiment to evaluate transfluthrin emanators in Port-au-Prince, carried <lb/>out from October 2018 to January 2019. In this experiment, emanators were treated with the emulsifiable concentrate (EC) formulation and placed <lb/>under the chairs of users (Right-hand panel of Fig 2) sitting outdoors. A: Outdoor catches with treated and untreated emanators presented as <lb/>separate violin plots of density distribution with the first quartile, median and third quartile indicated by three horizontal lines and overlain by a dot <lb/>plot of the individual daily total catch observations. Note that three times as many landing catches were carried out on users of treated emanators <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>mosquitoes to transfluthrin vapour only. When the larger treated hessian panels were used, <lb/>with mosquitoes allowed no direct contact, between 48 and 61% of females escaped from the <lb/>treated chamber while 92 to 97% of those recovered from the chambers with treated and <lb/>untreated hessian panels were knocked down after 10 minutes of exposure. Treated hessian <lb/>panels that were 10 times smaller nevertheless yielded a similar proportion of females escaping <lb/>the treated chamber (44 to 48%), although less were knocked down by the transfluthrin vapor <lb/>(47 to 60%). <lb/>Results from the spatial repellency assessments for the transfluthrin-treated hessian panels <lb/>used in Haiti with the HITSS experimental system [28, 29] are summarized in Table 3. In all <lb/>test conditions of hessian surface and temperature, most females did not leave the central <lb/>chamber where they were introduced, even though the doors between compartments were <lb/>open for 10 minutes (61 to 92%). Some modest spatial repellency was observed across all tests, <lb/>except for one assessment of the full-size treated hessian panel under the warmer of the two <lb/>conditions that yielded a null spatial activity index. Spatial activity index varied between 0.00 <lb/>and only 0.12 overall and the strongest repellency was observed with the smaller hessian piece <lb/>at lower temperature. Overall, between 58 and 91% of female mosquitoes that entered the <lb/>treated chamber were knocked down, while only 0 to 5% females recovered from the untreated <lb/>central cylinder and the control chamber were knocked down. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Taken at face value, these results consistently indicate that the emanator prototypes and trans-<lb/>fluthrin formulations evaluated here provided negligible protection against wild, free-flying <lb/>populations of Ae. aegypti in Port-au-Prince, Haiti. Over the course of three separate and care-<lb/>fully controlled experimental evaluations, no statistically significant protective effect could be <lb/>demonstrated (Figs 5-7 plus Table 1), regardless of the transfluthrin formulation used, posi-<lb/>tioning of the emanator or weather conditions at the time (Figs 2 and 3). <lb/>Although the wild field populations of Aedes aegypti in Haiti appear strongly resistant to <lb/>the lethal effects of contact exposure to transfluthrin (Fig 9) and pyrethroid resistance is <lb/>known to be associated with reduced behavioural responsiveness to the spatial repellency of <lb/>this active ingredient [30], it remains unclear whether such physiological resistance could have <lb/>contributed to the apparent lack of protection against Ae. aegypti reported here from Haiti. <lb/>Indeed, dose-response experiments with the same prototype inside large cage semi-field sys-<lb/>tems in Tanzania indicated no substantial difference in behavioural response profiles between <lb/>modestly resistant wild populations of Ae. aegypti and a fully susceptible colony of the same <lb/>species originating from the same setting or a fully susceptible colony of Anopheles gambiae <lb/>[14] thus confirming that physiological resistance is unlikely to have played a major role in the <lb/>generally disappointing entomological results against this species. Furthermore, similar large-<lb/>cage assessments of a sandal format emanator against Ae. aegypti from a fully susceptible col-<lb/>ony indicate that this prototype prevented only a third of bites [31], suggesting that mecha-<lb/>nisms other than physiological resistance may be responsible for their apparently limited <lb/>efficacy as spatial repellents against Aedes when used to treat hessian strips in this manner. <lb/>than untreated emanators (Fig 4), so the width of the probability density violin graphs may be directly compared in absolute terms but not those of <lb/>the dot plots. B: Presented as a longitudinal time course, with separate longitudinal trends for the treated and untreated emanators over time <lb/>estimated and plotted using the geom_smooth function of the ggplot2 package in R, specifying the general linear model (glm) method with time as the <lb/>independent variable and mosquito catch as the dependent variable with a Poisson distribution. C: Presented as a function of daily mean <lb/>temperature, with separate trends for the treated and untreated emanators with temperature variations estimated and plotted using the geom_smooth <lb/>function of the ggplot2 package in R, specifying the glm method with temperature as the independent variable and mosquito catch as the dependent <lb/>variable with a Poisson distribution. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g006 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>16 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 7. Daily Aedes aegypti catches from the third entomological experiment to evaluate transfluthrin emanators in Port-au-Prince, carried out from <lb/>March to May 2019. In this experiment, emanators were treated with the emulsifiable concentrate (EC) formulation and placed under the chairs of users <lb/>(Right-hand panel of Fig 2) sitting either indoors or outdoors. A: Indoor and outdoor catches with treated and untreated emanators presented as separate <lb/>violin plots of density distribution with the first quartile, median and third quartile indicated by three horizontal lines and overlain by a dot plot of the <lb/>individual daily total catch observations. Note that three times as many landing catches were carried out on users of treated emanators than untreated <lb/>emanators (Fig 4), so the width of the probability density violin graphs may be directly compared in absolute terms but not those of the dot plots. B: Indoor <lb/>catches presented as a longitudinal time course, with separate longitudinal trends for the treated and untreated emanators over time estimated and plotted <lb/>using the geom_smooth function of the ggplot2 package in R, specifying the general linear model (glm) method with time as the independent variable and <lb/>mosquito catch as the dependent variable with a Poisson distribution. C: Outdoor catches presented as a longitudinal time course in exactly the same way as <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>17 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Regarding the counterintuitive laboratory results obtained using the HITSS system [28, 29] <lb/>(Table 2), it is known that different concentrations of transfluthrin vapor can lead to varying <lb/>repellency levels, sometimes even attracting mosquitoes [30, 32], so this could explain why the <lb/>smaller piece of treated hessian seemed to have a stronger apparent repellent effect. While it is <lb/>also possible that the higher concentration of vapor produced by the full-size hessian panel <lb/>could quickly saturate the whole system and confound the intended function of the test, the <lb/>low knockdown rates in the central and control chambers suggest this was probably not a <lb/>major issue in this case. A more direct and parsimonious interpretation of these results is that <lb/>non-lethal repellency per se may play a relatively minor role in the overall mode of action of <lb/>transfluthrin when deployed through this hessian emanator format. <lb/>The prototype emanator design evaluated here differs substantively from the suspended rib-<lb/>bon prototypes that have proven successful against night biting Anopheles and Culex in Africa <lb/>[9-11, 33]. However, it is notable that several other studies in rural Tanzania confirm satisfac-<lb/>tory efficacy against Anopheles and Culex for similar portable designs [23, 24] to that used in <lb/>panel B. D: Combined indoor and outdoor catches presented as a function of daily mean temperature, with separate trends for the treated and untreated <lb/>emanators with temperature variations estimated and plotted using the geom_smooth function of the ggplot2 package in R, specifying the glm method with <lb/>temperature as the independent variable and mosquito catch as the dependent variable with a Poisson distribution. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g007 <lb/>Table 1. Statistical estimates for the protective efficacy of transfluthrin-treated emanator devices and other vari-<lb/>ables influencing the densities of female Aedes aegypti mosquitoes, based on the best fit generalized linear mixed <lb/>model (GLMM) of the pooled data from all three rounds of experimental assessment (921 females caught over <lb/>5129 hours, as illustrated in Figs 5-7 and shared in S1 Data), assuming a negative binomial distribution for this <lb/>positive integer dependent variable to account for overdispersion (S1 File). <lb/>Variable <lb/>Statistical parameter estimates <lb/>Fixed Effects <lb/>Mean [95%CI] <lb/>z <lb/>P <lb/>Intercept <lb/>Mosquito density under reference conditions <lb/>0.52 [0.24, 1.10] <lb/>-1.717 <lb/>0.0896 <lb/>RR [95%CI] <lb/>z <lb/>P <lb/>Emanator device treatment status <lb/>Untreated <lb/>1.0 [NA] <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Transfluthrin treated <lb/>0.87 [0.73, 1.04] <lb/>-1.538 <lb/>0.1241 <lb/>Experimental assessment <lb/>Round one <lb/>1.0 [NA] <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Round two <lb/>0.34 [0.22, 0.53] <lb/>-0.472 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Round three <lb/>0.09 [0.04, 0.18] <lb/>-6.655 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Location <lb/>Indoors (Assessment round 3 only) <lb/>1.0 [NA] <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Outdoors <lb/>0.59 [0.35, 0.99] <lb/>-1.972 <lb/>0.0486 <lb/>Random effects <lb/>σ <lb/>SD <lb/>Date <lb/>0.5643 <lb/>0.7512 <lb/>Block and station <lb/>0.5616 <lb/>0.7494 <lb/>Time of day <lb/>0.1035 <lb/>0.3217 <lb/>CI: Confidence interval <lb/>NA: Not applicable because this was the reference value specified in the model <lb/>RR: Relative Rate <lb/>σ: Variance <lb/>SD: Standard Deviation <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>18 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>this evaluation against Aedes in urban Haiti. Also, a quite similar entomological evaluation in <lb/>urban Dar es Salaam in Tanzania, involving minor variations on the same emanator design <lb/>and transfluthrin formulations from the same manufacturer, also indicated little if any reduc-<lb/>tion of human landing rates [14]. Semi-field evaluations in Tanzania using large cages and <lb/>insectary-reared mosquitoes, even including those derived from recently wild-caught stock, <lb/>confirmed that neither replacing the METs [15-19] used here with human landing catches <lb/>(HLCs) [14, 19, 34, 35] nor changing the position of the emanator [14] led to any apparent <lb/>improvements in protective efficacy. Also, entomological field evaluations of a quite different <lb/>sandal format of emanator [31, 36] in Brazil, which also used the gold standard HLC method, <lb/>yielded no consistent evidence of satisfactory protection against Ae. aegypti (Alvaro Eiras, Per-<lb/>sonal communication). Furthermore, a recent large-scale field trial of a different transfluthrin <lb/>emanator device in urban Iquitos, Peru, which surveyed human exposure levels based on the <lb/>number of blood fed Aedes inside the houses of end users [5], yielded statistically significant <lb/>but otherwise identical results to those reported here. <lb/>On the other hand, however, these consistently outcomes from entomological assessments <lb/>in Haiti, together with similar results from Tanzania [14] and Brazil (Alvaro Eiras, Personal <lb/>communication) contrast starkly with the observations of complementary social science inves-<lb/>tigations [13] that engaged with the Haitian households whose same treated emanators were <lb/>intermittently borrowed for the entomological evaluations reported herein. These carefully tri-<lb/>angulated sociological investigations, using several complementary survey methods, consis-<lb/>tently indicate moderate-to-high levels of user satisfaction, even in their third iteration when <lb/>they were redesigned to minimize biases introduced by the investigators and by competing <lb/>interests among the end users (See Methods, Ethical Considerations and reference [13]). Simi-<lb/>larly, in Brazil, end users of a sandal format of transfluthrin emanator [31, 36] also expressed <lb/>Table 2. Results of laboratory contact irritancy assays in the high-throughput screening system (HITSS) developed by Grieco et al. [28, 29]. Each value was calcu-<lb/>lated from a minimum of 8 replicates, using either large (290 cm 2 ) or small (29 cm 2 ) hessian panels treated with 5.14 g/m 2 transfluthrin. <lb/>Date <lb/>Conditions <lb/>Total Mosquitoes (n) <lb/>Escape (%) <lb/>Knock Down (%) <lb/>Temperature (˚C) <lb/>Relative Humidity (%) <lb/>March 2019 <lb/>Untreated controls <lb/>255 <lb/>16.5% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>24.5-25.8 <lb/>24-32 <lb/>Treated-large-with contact <lb/>40 <lb/>5.0% <lb/>100.0% <lb/>24.5-25.8 <lb/>24-32 <lb/>Treated-large-no contact <lb/>106 <lb/>61.3% <lb/>92.5% <lb/>24.5-25.8 <lb/>24-32 <lb/>Treated-small-no contact <lb/>142 <lb/>44.4% <lb/>59.9% <lb/>24.5-25.8 <lb/>24-32 <lb/>May 2019 <lb/>Untreated controls <lb/>318 <lb/>22.0% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>27.1-28.0 <lb/>29-35 <lb/>Untreated controls <lb/>60 <lb/>33.3% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>27.5-28.1 <lb/>21-23 <lb/>Treated-large-no contact <lb/>122 <lb/>48.4% <lb/>97.5% <lb/>27.5-28.1 <lb/>21-23 <lb/>Untreated controls <lb/>70 <lb/>4.3% <lb/>0.0% <lb/>27.8-28.1 <lb/>39-42 <lb/>Treated-small-no contact <lb/>80 <lb/>47.5% <lb/>47.5% <lb/>27.8-28.1 <lb/>39-42 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.t002 <lb/>Table 3. Results of spatial repellency assays carried out in the laboratory using the high-throughput screening system (HITSS) developed by Grieco et al. [28, 29]. <lb/>Each value was calculated from a minimum of 8 replicates, using either large (290 cm 2 ) or small (29 cm 2 ) hessian panels treated with 5.14 g/m 2 transfluthrin. <lb/>Period <lb/>(Temperature) <lb/>Size <lb/>Treated chamber <lb/>Central Chamber <lb/>Control chamber <lb/>Spatial activity <lb/>Index <lb/>Recovered <lb/>(%) <lb/>Knocked Down <lb/>(%) <lb/>Recovered (%) Knocked Down <lb/>(%) <lb/>Recovered (%) Knocked Down <lb/>(%) <lb/>March 2019 <lb/>Large <lb/>9.6 <lb/>85.7 <lb/>76.3 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>14.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>(24.5-25.4˚C) <lb/>Small <lb/>13.1 <lb/>57.9 <lb/>61.4 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>25.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>May 2019 <lb/>Large <lb/>13.9 <lb/>90.9 <lb/>72.2 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>13.9 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>(27.7-27.9˚C) <lb/>Small <lb/>2.5 <lb/>75.0 <lb/>92.4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.t003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>19 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 8. Daily catches of Culex spp. mosquitoes from the third entomological experiment to evaluate transfluthrin emanators in Port-au-Prince, carried <lb/>out from March to May 2019. In this experiment, emanators were treated with the emulsifiable concentrate (EC) formulation and placed under the chairs of <lb/>users (Right-hand panel of Fig 1) sitting either indoors or outdoors. A: Presented as a violin plot of density distribution with the first quartile, median and third <lb/>quartile indicated by three horizontal lines and overlain by a dot plot of the individual daily total catch observations. Note that three times as many landing <lb/>catches were carried out on users of treated emanators than untreated emanators (Fig 4), so the width of the probability density violin graphs may be directly <lb/>compared in absolute terms but not those of the dot plots. B, C and D: Presented as a longitudinal time course for either the indoor (B) or outdoor (C) <lb/>observations presented separately or pooled together and presented as a function of daily mean temperature (D), with separate Poisson-distributed smoothed <lb/>averages for the treated and untreated emanators. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g008 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>20 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>surprizing levels of satisfaction with the protection provided against mosquito bites, despite <lb/>yielding generally unsatisfactory results against Aedes in open field assessments (Alvaro Eiras, <lb/>personal communication). Furthermore, all rounds of social science assessment in this Haitian <lb/>setting [13] used exactly the same individual emanator devices as the entomological evalua-<lb/>tions reported herein, so this clear contrast cannot be explained in terms of differing prototype <lb/>designs, transfluthrin formulations or treatment procedures. <lb/>It may therefore be useful to consider the potential influence of emanator deployment prac-<lb/>tices upon objective and subjective measures of protective efficacy. For example, some of the <lb/>Haitian community participants who routinely used the same individual emanator devices <lb/>[13] suggest that use of a single emanator device, rather than two, might explain the apparently <lb/>minimal protective efficacy observed here under similar full field conditions: <lb/>&quot;I had given an emanator [away]. I still have one left. When I had two, it was more efficient. <lb/>Now I only have one. It lacks efficiency.&quot; Community end user, Haiti (Obrilliant, <lb/>Unpublished) <lb/>Thus, it seems that using two or more emanators might be more effective, creating a protective <lb/>&quot;bubble&quot; [32, 37] even in windy open outdoor spaces, where mosquitoes could otherwise safely <lb/>attack users of a single emanator by flying with or across the wind on their approach. On the other <lb/>hand, recent semi-field assessments of sitting in between two similar self-standing emanators in <lb/>Tanzania yielded modest estimates of protective efficacy against Ae. aegypti [19, 34, 35], similar to <lb/>those reported for a single device under similar conditions in the same country [14]. It therefore <lb/>seems unlikely that the discouraging results against wild, free-flying populations of the same spe-<lb/>cies in the same African setting arose from using only one emanator rather than two or more. <lb/>Interestingly, community users in both Haiti and Brazil described household deployment <lb/>practices that seemed to target indoor resting mosquitoes rather than host-seeking mosquitoes <lb/>(Reference [13] and Alvaro Eiras, personal communication), so this may be a potential applica-<lb/>tion worth investigating in the future. Given that we rarely observed Ae. aegypti resting <lb/>Fig 9. Results of transfluthrin resistance tests. Dose-response curves established using wild females collected as larvae in February and June 2019. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919.g009 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>21 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <body>indoors in Port-au-Prince, it seemed reasonable at the time to speculate that community end <lb/>users were instead targeting the Culex quinquefasciatus that can be so abundant indoors in <lb/>such urban tropical settings, so our third entomological evaluation extended collections into <lb/>the hours of darkness to target this nocturnal species. Although no evidence of efficacy against <lb/>Culex spp. was obvious from those data (Fig 8), insufficient numbers of Culex spp. mosquitoes <lb/>were captured to reach any firm conclusion. <lb/>Although questions have been raised about the validity of the MET method [15-19] for col-<lb/>lecting human-biting mosquitoes [19], the traditional and reliable HLC method has repeatedly <lb/>yielded essentially identical results under semi-field conditions in Tanzania [14, 19, 34, 35]. <lb/>However, both approaches actually record the rates at which mosquitoes land rather than bite <lb/>per se, but transfluthrin and other pyrethroids are known to incapacitate mosquitoes so that <lb/>they cannot feed again for up to a day [32, 38]. Furthermore, the investigators have sometimes <lb/>observed mosquitoes landing on them but not biting them while using such emanators during <lb/>previous studies [11]. It may therefore be worth considering non-entomological indicators of <lb/>exposure to biting Aedes mosquitoes [39-45] and the arboviruses they carry [5] as alternative <lb/>methods for assessing the efficacy of such spatial repellent products. <lb/>Having said all that, the low and non-significant levels of apparent efficacy estimated here <lb/>using entomological methods are remarkably similar to those recently estimated for a quite <lb/>different transfluthrin emanator device in Iquitos, Peru [5], based more reliably upon direct <lb/>surveys of the numbers of blood-fed Ae. aegypti inside the homes of end-users (13% versus <lb/>12% reductions, respectively). Interestingly, the carefully controlled large scale trial of Morri-<lb/>son et al. in Peru [5] also demonstrated a larger effect size for protection against arboviral <lb/>infections (34% reduction), similar to the contrasting entomological observations reported <lb/>herein and the more encouraging perspectives shared by end-users in the same neighbour-<lb/>hoods of Port-au-Prince [13]. Nevertheless, it remains unclear how the very different results of <lb/>these two distinct assessments in Haiti may be reconciled with each other and with comple-<lb/>mentary assessments in Tanzania and Brazil. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The underlying reasons for the apparent contradiction between the lack of entomological evi-<lb/>dence for protection against host-seeking Aedes and more encouraging results from social sci-<lb/>ence and epidemiological assessments, collectively spanning studies from Tanzania [14, 31], <lb/>Haiti [13], Brazil (Alvaro Eiras et al., Personal communication) and Peru [5], therefore remains <lb/>unresolved. While it may be useful to explore whether serological indicators of infection [5] and <lb/>of exposure to mosquitoes [39-45] can resolve this dilemma in the future, for now it remains <lb/>unclear whether these particular long-lasting transfluthrin emanator devices are effective <lb/>against the Aedes species responsible for most of the world&apos;s arbovirus transmission. It also <lb/>remains to be determined whether they may have useful alternative applications against Culex <lb/>mosquitoes indoors, as suggested by some of the shared perspectives of end users from both <lb/>Haiti [13] and Brazil (Alvaro Eiras, Personal communication). More encouragingly, similar <lb/>contrasts between the entomological and epidemiological results from a recent large scale trial <lb/>of a different transfluthrin emanator product in Peru suggest that, for reasons that remain to be <lb/>understood, such devices may provide useful protection against Aedes-borne arboviral infec-<lb/>tions despite apparently providing only modest protection against biting Aedes mosquitoes [5]. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Data. All the entomological data used to generate Figs 5 to 9 and Tables 1-3. <lb/>(CSV) <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>22 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">S1 Protocol. Full approved English language version of the protocol for this study, together <lb/>with the complementary social science assessments of end user perceptions in these same <lb/>Haitian communities [13] and a similar entomological assessment of transfluthrin emana-<lb/>tor efficacy in Tanzania [14], both of which were carried out in parallel with this study. See <lb/>also S2 Protocol for all relevant annexes in English and S3 Protocol for the approved protocol <lb/>and annexes as translated into French and Haitian Creole. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Protocol. English language versions of all annexes to the approved protocol for this <lb/>study, together with the complementary social science assessments of end-user perceptions <lb/>in these same Haitian communities [13] and a similar entomological assessment of trans-<lb/>fluthrin emanator efficacy in Tanzania [14], both of which were carried out in parallel <lb/>with this study. See also S1 Protocol for the main protocol document itself in English and <lb/>S3 Protocol for the approved protocol and annexes as translated into French and Haitian Cre-<lb/>ole. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Protocol. Full approved protocol (French only) and all relevant annexes (French and <lb/>Haitian Creole) for this study, together with the complementary social science assessments <lb/>of end-user perceptions that were carried out in parallel in these same Haitian communi-<lb/>ties [13] (Figs 1 and 2), as translated, reviewed, approved and used in Port-au-Prince, <lb/>Haiti. See also S1 and S2 Protocols for the approved protocol and annexes in English, respec-<lb/>tively. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 File. The R script used to generate Table 1. <lb/>(R) <lb/>S2 File. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank Joseph Frederic, who kindly assisted in planning this study but sadly passed away in <lb/>2020. We thank the communities of Haut-Turgeau in Port-au-Prince for kindly collaborating <lb/>with us throughout this study. We thank Julia Samedi, Joane Laine ´, Milot Valeus and Wesly <lb/>Saint-Hilaire for technical assistance during the field work. We also thank Bernard Okech, <lb/>Thom Eisele and Joe Keating for their helpful advice while planning this study, as well as <lb/>Alvaro Eiras for sharing his observations from similar studies in Brazil and for his helpful com-<lb/>ments upon the manuscript. <lb/>Disclaimer: The opinions or assertions contained in this manuscript are the private ones of <lb/>the authors and are not to be construed as official or reflecting the views of the U.S. Public <lb/>Health Service or Department of Health and Human Services. Use of trade names is for identi-<lb/>fication only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Public Health Service or Depart-<lb/>ment of Health and Human Services. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Justin McBeath, Sheila B. Ogoma, Vincent Corbel, Gerry F. Killeen. <lb/>Data curation: Chicoye Supreme, Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>23 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Formal analysis: Chicoye Supreme, Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Gerry F. Killeen. <lb/>Investigation: Chicoye Supreme, Obrillant Damus, Joseph Frederick, Christian Raccurt, Nos-<lb/>rat Mirzai, Sheila B. Ogoma, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil, Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille <lb/>Czeher. <lb/>Methodology: Nosrat Mirzai, Sheila B. Ogoma, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil, Gerry F. <lb/>Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Project administration: Chicoye Supreme, Obrillant Damus, Jean-Frantz Lemoine, Christian <lb/>Raccurt, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil, Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Resources: Justin McBeath, Nosrat Mirzai, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil. <lb/>Supervision: Chicoye Supreme, Obrillant Damus, Joseph Frederick, Jean-Frantz Lemoine, <lb/>Christian Raccurt, Nosrat Mirzai, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil, Gerry F. Killeen, <lb/>Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Validation: Vincent Corbel, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Visualization: Chicoye Supreme, Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Gerry F. Killeen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Chicoye Supreme, Obrillant Damus, Christian Raccurt, Justin <lb/>McBeath, Nosrat Mirzai, Sheila B. Ogoma, Vincent Corbel, Daniel Impoinvil, Gerry F. Kil-<lb/>leen, Cyrille Czeher. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Achee NL, Bangs MJ, Farlow R, Killeen GF, Lindsay S, Logan JG, et al. Spatial repellents: From discov-<lb/>ery and development to evidence-based validation. Malar J. 2012; 11:164. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>1475-2875-11-164 PMID: 22583679 <lb/>2. Achee NL, Perkins TA, Moore SM, Liu F, Sagara I, Van Hulle S, et al. Spatial repellents: The current <lb/>roadmap to global recommendation of spatial repellents for public health use. Curr Res Parasitol Vector <lb/>Borne Dis. 2023; 3:100107. Epub 20221209. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crpvbd.2022.100107 PMID: <lb/>36590345; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9801085. <lb/>3. Lenhart A, Orelus N, Maskill R, Alexander N, Streit T, McCall PJ. Insecticide-treated bednets to control <lb/>dengue vectors: preliminary evidence from a controlled trial in Haiti. Trop Med Int Health. 2008; 13 <lb/>(1):56-67. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3156.2007.01966.x PMID: 18291003. <lb/>4. Manrique-Saide P, Herrera-Bojo ´rquez J, Medina-Barreiro A, Trujillo-Peña E, Villegas-Chim J, Valadez-<lb/>Gonza ´lez N, et al. Insecticide-treated house screening protects against Zika-infected Aedes aegypti in <lb/>Merida, Mexico. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2021; 15(1):e0009005. Epub 20210119. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pntd.0009005 PMID: 33465098; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7853519. <lb/>5. Morrison AC, Reiner RC, Elson WH, Astete H, Guevara C, Del Aguila C, et al. Efficacy of a spatial repel-<lb/>lent for control of Aedes-borne virus transmission: A cluster-randomized trial in Iquitos, Peru. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A. 2022; 119(26):e2118283119. Epub 20220623. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>2118283119 PMID: 35737833; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9245620. <lb/>6. Killeen GF, Tatarsky A, Diabate A, Chaccour CJ, Marshall JM, Okumu FO, et al. Developing an <lb/>expanded vector control toolbox for malaria elimination. BMJ Global Health. 2017; 2(2):e000211. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2016-000211 PMID: 28589022 <lb/>7. Hogarh JN, Antwi-Agyei P, Obiri-Danso K. Application of mosquito repellent coils and associated self-<lb/>reported health issues in Ghana. Malar J. 2016; 15:61. Epub 20160204. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s12936-016-1126-8 PMID: 26847206; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4743129. <lb/>8. Hogarh JN, Agyekum TP, Bempah CK, Owusu-Ansah EDJ, Avicor SW, Awandare GA, et al. Environ-<lb/>mental health risks and benefits of the use of mosquito coils as malaria prevention and control strategy. <lb/>Malar J. 2018; 17(1):265. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-018-2412-4 PMID: 30012143; PubMed Cen-<lb/>tral PMCID: PMC6048806. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>24 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>9. Ogoma SB, Ngonyani H, Simfukwe ET, Mseka A, Moore J, Killeen GF. Spatial repellency of transflu-<lb/>thrin-treated hessian strips against laboratory-reared Anopheles arabiensis mosquitoes in a semi-field <lb/>tunnel cage. Parasit Vectors. 2012; 5(1):54. https://doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-5-54 PMID: 22433128 <lb/>10. Govella NJ, Ogoma SB, Paliga J, Chaki PP, Killeen G. Impregnating hessian strips with the volatile <lb/>pyrethroid transfluthrin prevents outdoor exposure to vectors of malaria and lymphatic filariasis in urban <lb/>Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. Parasit Vectors. 2015; 8(1):322. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-015-0937-8 <lb/>PMID: 26063216 <lb/>11. Ogoma SB, Mmando AS, Swai JK, Horstmann S, Malone D, Killeen GF. A low technology emanator <lb/>treated with the volatile pyrethroid transfluthrin confers long term protection against outdoor biting vec-<lb/>tors of lymphatic filariasis, arboviruses and malaria. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2017; 11(4): <lb/>e0005455. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005455 PMID: 28388682 <lb/>12. EU Standing Committee on Biocidal Products. Evaluation of active substances assessment report: <lb/>Transfluthrin (insecticides, acaricides and products to control other arthropods). 2014. <lb/>13. Damus O, Supreme C, Lemoine J-F, Raccurt C, McBeath J, Ogoma SB, et al. Community end user per-<lb/>ceptions of hessian fabric transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against mosquitoes under con-<lb/>ditions of routine use in Port-au-Prince, Haiti. PLoS One. 2023;In Press. <lb/>14. Govella NJ, Assenga A, Mlwale AT, Mirzai N, Heffernan E, Moriarty J, et al. Entomological assessment <lb/>of hessian fabric transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against outdoor-biting Aedes aegypti in <lb/>coastal Tanzania. PLoS One. 2023;In press. <lb/>15. Govella NJ, Maliti DF, Mlwale AT, Masallu JP, Mirzai N, Johnson PCD, et al. An improved mosquito <lb/>electrocuting trap that safely reproduces epidemiologically relevant metrics of mosquito human-feeding <lb/>behaviours as determined by human landing catch. Malaria Journal. 2016; 15(1):465. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1186/s12936-016-1513-1 PMID: 27618941 <lb/>16. Meza FC, Kreppel KS, Maliti DF, Mlwale AT, Mirzai N, Killeen GF, et al. Mosquito electrocuting traps for <lb/>directly measuring biting rates and host-preferences of Anopheles arabiensis and Anopheles funestus <lb/>outdoors. Malaria Journal. 2019; 18(1):83. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-019-2726-x PMID: 30885205 <lb/>17. Ortega-Lo ´pez LD, Pondeville E, Kohl A, Leo ´n R, Betancourth MP, Almire F, et al. The mosquito electro-<lb/>cuting trap as an exposure-free method for measuring human-biting rates by Aedes mosquito vectors. <lb/>Parasit Vectors. 2020; 13(1):31. Epub 20200115. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-020-3887-8 PMID: <lb/>31941536; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6961254. <lb/>18. Maliti DV, Govella NJ, Killeen GF, Mirzai N, Johnson PCD, Kreppel K, et al. Development and evalua-<lb/>tion of mosquito-electrocuting traps as alternatives to the human landing catch technique for sampling <lb/>host-seeking malaria vectors. Malar J. 2015; 14(1). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-015-1025-4 PMID: <lb/>26670881 <lb/>19. Tambwe MM, Saddler A, Kibondo UA, Mashauri R, Kreppel KS, Govella NJ, et al. Semi-field evaluation <lb/>of the exposure-free mosquito electrocuting trap and BG-Sentinel trap as an alternative to the human <lb/>landing catch for measuring the efficacy of transfluthrin emanators against Aedes aegypti. Parasit Vec-<lb/>tors. 2021; 14(1):265. Epub 20210520. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-021-04754-x PMID: 34016149; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8138975. <lb/>20. Maia MF, Robinson A, John AN, Mgando J, Simfukwe E, Moore SJ. Comparison of the CDC Backpack <lb/>aspirator and the Prokopack aspirator for sampling indoor-and outdoor-resting mosquitoes in southern <lb/>Tanzania. Parasit Vectors. 2011; 4:124. https://doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-4-124 PMID: 21718464 <lb/>21. Prado GP, Maciel JS, Leite GR, Souza MAA. Influence of shading and pedestrian traffic on the prefer-<lb/>ence of Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae) for oviposition microenvironments. J Vector <lb/>Ecol. 2017; 42(1):155-60. https://doi.org/10.1111/jvec.12250 PMID: 28504433. <lb/>22. Arduino MB, Mucci LF, Santos LMD, Soares MFS. Importance of microenvironment to arbovirus vector <lb/>distribution in an urban area, São Paulo, Brazil. Rev Soc Bras Med Trop. 2020; 53:e20190504. Epub <lb/>20200403. https://doi.org/10.1590/0037-8682-0504-2019 PMID: 32267458; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC7156254. <lb/>23. Masalu JP, Finda M, Okumu FO, Minja EG, Mmbando AS, Sikulu-Lord MT, et al. Efficacy and user <lb/>acceptability of transfluthrin-treated sisal and hessian decorations for protecting against mosquito bites <lb/>in outdoor bars. Parasit Vectors. 2017; 10(1):197. Epub 20170420. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-<lb/>017-2132-6 PMID: 28427437; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5397833. <lb/>24. Masalu JP, Okumu FO, Mmbando AS, Sikulu-Lord MT, Ogoma SB. Potential benefits of combining <lb/>transfluthrin-treated sisal products and long-lasting insecticidal nets for controlling indoor-biting malaria <lb/>vectors. Parasit Vectors. 2018; 11(1):231. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-018-2811-y PMID: <lb/>29631633; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5891933. <lb/>25. Kiware SS, Russell TL, Mtema ZJ, Malishee AD, Chaki P, Lwetoijera D, et al. A generic schema and <lb/>data collection forms applicable to diverse entomological studies of mosquitoes. Source Code for Biol-<lb/>ogy and Medicine. 2016; 11(1):4. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13029-016-0050-1 PMID: 27022408 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>25 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>26. World Health Organization. Test procedures for insecticide resistance monitoring in malaria vector mos-<lb/>quitoes. 2nd ed. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2016. 48 p. <lb/>27. World Health Organization. Determining discriminating concentrations of insecticides for monitoring <lb/>resistance in mosquitoes: Report of a multi-centre laboratory study and WHO expert consultations. <lb/>Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. <lb/>28. Grieco JP, Achee NL, Sardelis MR, Chauhan KR, Roberts DR. A novel high-throughput screening sys-<lb/>tem to evaluate the behavioral response of adult mosquitoes to chemicals. J Am Mosq Control Assoc. <lb/>2005; 21(4):404-11. https://doi.org/10.2987/8756-971X(2006)21[404:ANHSST]2.0.CO;2[404: <lb/>ANHSST]2.0.CO;2. PMID: 16506566. <lb/>29. Grieco JP, Achee NL, Chareonviriyaphap T, Suwonkerd W, Chauhan K, Sardelis MR, et al. A new clas-<lb/>sification system for the actions of IRS chemicals traditionally used for malaria control. PLoS One. <lb/>2007; 2(8):e716. Epub 20070808. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000716 PMID: 17684562; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1934935. <lb/>30. Wagman JM, Achee NL, Grieco JP. Insensitivity to the spatial repellent action of transfluthrin in Aedes <lb/>aegypti: a heritable trait associated with decreased insecticide susceptibility. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2015; <lb/>9(4):e0003726. Epub 20150416. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0003726 PMID: 25879206; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4400042. <lb/>31. Mponzi WP, Swai JK, Kaindoa EW, Kifungo K, Eiras AE, Batista EPA, et al. Observing the distribution <lb/>of mosquito bites on humans to inform personal protection measures against malaria and dengue vec-<lb/>tors. PLoS One. 2022; 17(7):e0271833. Epub 20220725. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0271833 <lb/>PMID: 35877666; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9312397. <lb/>32. Ogoma SB, Ngonyani H, Simfukwe ET, Mseka A, Moore J, Maia MF, et al. The mode of action of spatial <lb/>repellents and their impact on vectorial capacity of Anopheles gambiae sensu stricto. PLoS One. 2014; <lb/>9(12):e110433. Epub 20141208. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0110433 PMID: 25485850; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4259296. <lb/>33. Swai JK, Mmbando AS, Ngowo HS, Odufuwa OG, Finda MF, Mponzi W, et al. Protecting migratory <lb/>farmers in rural Tanzania using eave ribbons treated with the spatial mosquito repellent, transfluthrin. <lb/>Malar J. 2019; 18(1):414. Epub 20191210. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-019-3048-8 PMID: <lb/>31823783; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6905030. <lb/>34. Tambwe MM, Moore SJ, Chilumba H, Swai JK, Moore JD, Stica C, et al. Semi-field evaluation of free-<lb/>standing transfluthrin passive emanators and the BG sentinel trap as a &quot;push-pull control strategy&quot; <lb/>against Aedes aegypti mosquitoes. Parasit Vectors. 2020; 13(1):392. Epub 20200731. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1186/s13071-020-04263-3 PMID: 32736580; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7395400. <lb/>35. Tambwe MM, Kibondo UA, Odufuwa OG, Moore J, Mpelepele A, Mashauri R, et al. Human landing <lb/>catches provide a useful measure of protective efficacy for the evaluation of volatile pyrethroid spatial <lb/>repellents. Parasit Vectors. 2023; 16(1):90. Epub 20230307. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-023-<lb/>05685-5 PMID: 36882842; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9993701. <lb/>36. Sangoro OP, Gavana T, Finda M, Mponzi W, Hape E, Limwagu A, et al. Evaluation of personal protec-<lb/>tion afforded by repellent-treated sandals against mosquito bites in south-eastern Tanzania. Malar J. <lb/>2020; 19(1):148. Epub 20200408. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-020-03215-7 PMID: 32268907; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7140554. <lb/>37. Andre ´s M, Lorenz LM, Mbeleya E, Moore SJ. Modified mosquito landing boxes dispensing transfluthrin <lb/>provide effective protection against Anopheles arabiensis mosquitoes under simulated outdoor condi-<lb/>tions in a semi-field system. Malar J. 2015; 14:255. Epub 20150624. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-<lb/>015-0762-8 PMID: 26104719; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4477292. <lb/>38. Cohnstaedt LW, Allan SA. Effects of sublethal pyrethroid exposure on the host-seeking behavior of <lb/>female mosquitoes. J Vector Ecol. 2011; 36(2):395-403. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1948-7134.2011. <lb/>00180.x PMID: 22129411. <lb/>39. Drame PM, Poinsignon A, Besnard P, Cornelie S, Le Mire J, Toto JC, et al. Human antibody responses <lb/>to the Anopheles salivary gSG6-P1 peptide: a novel tool for evaluating the efficacy of ITNs in malaria <lb/>vector control. PLoS One. 2010; 5(12):e15596. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0015596 PMID: <lb/>21179476; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3001874. <lb/>40. Drame PM, Diallo A, Poinsignon A, Boussari O, Dos Santos S, Machault V, et al. Evaluation of the effec-<lb/>tiveness of malaria vector control measures in urban settings of Dakar by a specific Anopheles salivary <lb/>biomarker. PLoS One. 2013; 8(6):e66354. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0066354 PMID: <lb/>23840448; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3688790. <lb/>41. Doucoure S, Mouchet F, Cornelie S, Drame PM, D&apos;Ortenzio E, DeHecq JS, et al. Human antibody <lb/>response to Aedes albopictus salivary proteins: a potential biomarker to evaluate the efficacy of vector <lb/>control in an area of Chikungunya and Dengue Virus transmission. Biomed Res Int. 2014; <lb/>2014:746509. https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/746509 PMID: 24822216; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC4005104. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>26 / 27 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>42. Doucoure S, Drame PM. Salivary biomarkers in the control of mosquito-borne diseases. Insects. 2015; <lb/>6(4):961-76. https://doi.org/10.3390/insects6040961 PMID: 26593952; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC4693181. <lb/>43. Elanga Ndille E, Doucoure S, Poinsignon A, Mouchet F, Cornelie S, D&apos;Ortenzio E, et al. Human IgG <lb/>antibody response to Aedes Nterm-34kDa Salivary Peptide, an epidemiological tool to assess vector <lb/>control in Chikungunya and Dengue transmission. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2016; 10(12):e0005109. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005109 PMID: 27906987; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5131890. <lb/>44. Sagna AB, Yobo MC, Elanga Ndille E, Remoue F. New immuno-epidemiological biomarker of human <lb/>exposure to Aedes vector bites: From concept to applications. Trop Med Infect Dis. 2018; 3(3). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3390/tropicalmed3030080 PMID: 30274476; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6161005. <lb/>45. Yobo CM, Sadia-Kacou CAM, Adja MA, Elanga-Ndille E, Sagna AB, Guindo-Coulibaly N, et al. Evalua-<lb/>tion of human exposure to Aedes bites in rubber and palm cultivations using an immunoepidemiological <lb/>biomarker. Biomed Res Int. 2018; 2018:3572696. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/3572696 PMID: <lb/>30175128; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6106716. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Entomological assessment of transfluthrin vapour emanators for protecting against Aedes mosquitoes <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0298919 May 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>27 / 27 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>