<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T09:59:13.145Z">11/14/2025 9:59:13 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T09:58:59.987662Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T09:58:59.987662Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4-<lb/>coumarate: CoA ligases from Marchantia <lb/>paleacea and their roles in lignin and <lb/>flavanone biosynthesis <lb/>Shuai Gao 1 , Xin-Yan Liu 1 , Rong Ni 1 , Jie Fu 1 , Hui Tan 1 , Ai-Xia Cheng ID <lb/>1☯ <lb/>*, <lb/>Hong-Xiang Lou 1,2☯ * <lb/>1 Key Laboratory of Chemical Biology of Natural Products, Ministry of Education, School of Pharmaceutical <lb/>Sciences, Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China, 2 Shandong Provincial Clinical Research Center <lb/>for Emergency and Critical Care Medicine, Jinan, Shan-dong, China <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* aixiacheng@sdu.edu.cn (AXC); louhongxiang@sdu.edu.cn (HXL) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Phenylpropanoids play important roles in plant physiology and the enzyme 4-coumarate: <lb/>coenzyme A ligase (4CL) catalyzes the formation of thioesters. Despite extensive character-<lb/>ization in various plants, the functions of 4CLs in the liverwort Marchantia paleacea remain <lb/>unknown. Here, four 4CLs from M. paleacea were isolated and functionally analyzed. Heter-<lb/>ologous expression in Escherichia coli indicated the presence of different enzymatic activi-<lb/>ties in the four enzymes. Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 were able to convert caffeic, p-coumaric, <lb/>cinnamic, ferulic, dihydro-p-coumaric, and 5-hydroxyferulic acids to their corresponding <lb/>CoA esters, while Mp4CL3 and Mp4CL4 catalyzed none. Mp4CL1 transcription was induced <lb/>when M. paleacea thalli were treated with methyl jasmonate (MeJA). The overexpression of <lb/>Mp4CL1 increased the levels of lignin in transgenic Arabidopsis. In addition, we recon-<lb/>structed the flavanone biosynthetic pathway in E. coli. The pathway comprised Mp4CL1, co-<lb/>expressed with chalcone synthase (CHS) from different plant species, and the efficiency of <lb/>biosynthesis was optimal when both the 4CL and CHS were obtained from the same spe-<lb/>cies M. paleacea. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Phenylpropanoids, an important class of plant secondary metabolites, are widely present in <lb/>terrestrial plants. Lignins, flavonoids, coumarins, suberins, and bibenzyls are all phenylpropa-<lb/>noid derivatives synthesized via the phenylpropanoid pathway [1]. Phenylpropanoids play <lb/>vital roles in plants where they protect against various biotic and abiotic stress, such as drought <lb/>and UV-B radiation [2]. Furthermore, phenylpropanoids possess a variety of pharmacological <lb/>activities. For example, bibenzyls have decent anti-cancer, anti-fungal, and anti-proliferative <lb/>activity [3], and flavonoids have anti-cholinesterase and anti-inflammatory [4]. Because of the <lb/>wide range of biological activities and physiological significance, phenylpropanoids and the <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/>1 / 19 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Gao S, Liu X-Y, Ni R, Fu J, Tan H, Cheng <lb/>A-X, et al. (2024) Molecular cloning and functional <lb/>analysis of 4-coumarate: CoA ligases from <lb/>Marchantia paleacea and their roles in lignin and <lb/>flavanone biosynthesis. PLoS ONE 19(1): <lb/>e0296079. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0296079 <lb/>Editor: Igor Cesarino, University of Sao Paulo, <lb/>BRAZIL <lb/>Received: June 23, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 5, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 8, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Gao et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>information files. <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by the National <lb/>Natural Science Foundation of China, URL: https:// <lb/>www.nsfc.gov.cn/ (No. 32000228). The funders <lb/>had no role in study design, data collection and <lb/>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></front>

	<body>phenylpropanoid biosynthetic pathway have attracted increasing attention. During phenylpro-<lb/>panoid synthesis, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase and tyrosine ammonia-lyase non-oxidatively <lb/>deaminate phenylalanine and tyrosine, respectively, to form cinnamic and p-coumaric acids, <lb/>respectively. 4CL uses p-coumaric, cinnamic, caffeic, ferulic and sinapic acids as substrates for <lb/>the formation of their corresponding CoA thioesters [5, 6]. The corresponding CoA thioesters <lb/>act as substrates for the synthesis of essential downstream compounds, such as flavonoids, lig-<lb/>nins, and bibenzyls [1] (Fig 1). 4CL is a member of the adenylate-forming enzyme family [7] <lb/>and 4CL genes have been identified in numerous plant species, including Arabidopsis thaliana <lb/>[8], rice [9], and Populus trichocarpa [10]. The main branch point enzyme channels the precur-<lb/>sors for different phenylpropanoid-derived end products. Members of the 4CL gene family <lb/>can be classified into four groups: type I, II, III, and IV. Dicot plants&apos; 4CL genes are grouped <lb/>into types I and II, and monocot 4CLs are categorized into types III and IV. Type I and III <lb/>clusters are mainly involved in monolignol biosynthesis, whereas types II and IV are involved <lb/>in the biosynthesis of phenylpropanoids other than lignins [9]. The 4CL enzyme has multiple <lb/>isoforms, each of which has a different substrate affinity. The amino acid residues important <lb/>for recognizing and accommodating substrates at the active sites of enzymes have been identi-<lb/>fied and characterized [11]. The 4CL enzymes are critically involved in plant growth, develop-<lb/>ment, and responses to stress, both biotic and abiotic. Upregulation of 4CL has been <lb/>demonstrated during plant development and in response to exogenous stimuli, such as <lb/>Fig 1. The proposed synthesis pathway of polyphenol compounds in liverworts. PAL, phenylalanine ammonia-<lb/>lyase; C4H, cinnamate 4-hydroxylase; 4CL, 4-coumarate CoA ligase; C3H, 4-coumarate 3-hydroxylase; COMT, caffeic <lb/>acid O-methyl transferase; F5H, ferulate 5-hydroxylase; HCT, p-hydroxy cinnamoyl transferase; CCoAOMT, caffeoyl-<lb/>CoA O-methyltransferase; CHS, chalcone synthase; STCS, stilbenecarboxylate synthase; DBR, double bond reductase. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<front>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>wounding, pathogen infection, UV radiation, and exposure to methyl jasmonate [9]. The acti-<lb/>vation of 4CL upon elicitor treatment or UV irradiation is coordinated with the activation of <lb/>phenylalanine ammonia-lyase [12, 13], the first enzyme in the general phenylpropanoid path-<lb/>way. Apart from participating in lignin biosynthesis, 4CL upregulation in tobacco has been <lb/>found to increase drought tolerance [14]. <lb/>4CL products can enter the flavonoid biosynthesis pathway through chalcone synthase <lb/>(CHS) [15]. Flavonoids such as naringenin, homoeriodictyol, pinocembrin, and eriodictyol <lb/>are present in numerous edible plants and fruits. They also have a variety of useful biological <lb/>properties, including antioxidation, anticancer, and anti-inflammatory activities [16]. How-<lb/>ever, their relatively low concentrations, fluctuations according to season and region, and <lb/>structural diversity present problems for their supply [16]. Hence, the development of syn-<lb/>thetic and molecular engineering techniques for the improvement of flavonoid production is <lb/>an important consideration. <lb/>Bryophytes are small multicellular green plants. They represent an important evolutionary <lb/>lineage between algae and vascular plants. Bryophytes can be divided into liverworts, mosses, <lb/>and hornworts. As medicinal plants, liverworts are useful in the treatment of hepatitis and <lb/>burn infections [17]. These plants are rich in some valuable secondary metabolites, among <lb/>which phenylpropanoids are a major class [18, 19]. With the continuous discovery of phenyl-<lb/>propanes from liverworts, the exploration of the enzymes involved in their biosynthesis is <lb/>important. 4CL, as major enzyme in phenylpropanoid synthesis, has only been investigated in <lb/>three bryophyte species-Anthoceros agrestis, Plagiochasma appendiculatum, and Physcomi-<lb/>trium patens [20-22]. Therefore, identifying more 4CL genes in liverworts is important to <lb/>explain the distribution and accumulation of different phenylpropanes in liverworts and may <lb/>assist in the understanding of the phylogeny and origin of plant 4CLs. Here, we first cloned <lb/>four 4CL genes from the liverwort Marchantia paleacea and found that two distinct 4CL <lb/>enzymes (Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2) had different substrate specificity. The transient expression <lb/>of GFP-Mp4CL1 and GFP-Mp4CL2 in Nicotiana benthamiana leaves demonstrated that both <lb/>Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 are located in the cytoplasm and nucleus. In particular, Mp4CL1 was <lb/>found to increase lignin content after heterologous overexpression in Arabidopsis and was <lb/>induced when an M. paleacea thallus was subjected to abiotic stress. Furthermore, Mp4CL1 <lb/>combined with the CHS from Stenoloma chusanum, A. thaliana, or M. paleacea can produce <lb/>the naringenin product, which further proves the function of Mp4CL1. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Tissues and reagents <lb/>M. paleacea was cultivated in a greenhouse at 25˚C with a 12 h light/12 h dark cycle. Two-<lb/>month-old thalli were harvested, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at -80˚C until use. All <lb/>reagents and chemicals were from Alfa Aesar (Heysham, UK) or Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, <lb/>USA), unless otherwise specified. <lb/>Sequence analysis <lb/>Four putative 4CLs were identified in the M. paleacea transcriptome sequencing database <lb/>(SRP078650). The predicted sequences were aligned with those of 4CLs from other plant spe-<lb/>cies using DNAMAN v.7.0.2 software. A neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree was created with <lb/>MEGA v5.1 [23], and its robustness was confirmed with 1000 bootstrap replications. The tree <lb/>was based on 4CL polypeptide sequences (S1 Table). <lb/>SWISS-MODEL [24] was used for homology modeling of Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 using <lb/>chain A of Populus tomentosa 4CL (PDB accession code: 3NI2) [25] bound to adenosine 5&apos;-(3-<lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>(4-hydroxyphenyl) propyl) phosphate (APP), an adenosine 5&apos;-coumaroyl phosphate mimic, as <lb/>the template. The structures were visualized with PyMol [26]. <lb/>DNA isolation, recombinant protein expression, and purification <lb/>Total RNA was extracted using the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) method and <lb/>reverse-transcribed to cDNA [27]. Amplification of the full-length open reading frames <lb/>(ORFs) of Mp4CL1-4 was performed using the primer pairs Mp4CL1-Sense/Anti-Sense, <lb/>Mp4CL2-Sense/Anti-Sense, Mp4CL3-Sense/Anti-Sense, and Mp4CL4-Sense/Anti-Sense (S2 <lb/>Table). The purified amplicons were inserted into pMD19-T (TaKaRa, Shiga, Japan) cloning <lb/>vector, then the positive clones were selected and sequenced at Sangon Biotech (Shanghai). <lb/>The ORFs of Mp4CLs were PCR amplified using PrimeSTAR 1 Max DNA Polymerase <lb/>(TaKaRa) from pMD19-T-Mp4CLs plasmids, using the primer pairs Mp4CL1-primer1/2, <lb/>Mp4CL2-primer1/2, Mp4CL3-primer1/2, and Mp4CL4-primer1/2 (S2 Table). The restriction <lb/>enzymes Kpn I and Sal I were used for the digestion of Mp4CL1 PCR product, BamH I and <lb/>EcoR I for Mp4CL2 PCR product, Kpn I and Sac I for Mp4CL3 PCR product, and BamH I and <lb/>Sal I for Mp4CL4 PCR product. The PCR products of Mp4CLs and pET32a plasmids were <lb/>digested with the same restriction enzymes at 37˚C for 3 h. After double-digestion with restric-<lb/>tion enzymes, the restriction fragments and pET32a plasmids were extracted using a Gel <lb/>Extraction Kit (Omega Bio-Tek, America). The extracted products were ligated using T4 DNA <lb/>Ligase at 16˚C for 12 h and then transfected into E. coli strain DH5α. Then the positive clones <lb/>were selected and sequenced at Sangon Biotech (Shanghai). The resultant plasmids were <lb/>extracted from the positive clones using a Plasmid Mini Kit (Omega Bio-Tek, America) and <lb/>transfected into E. coli strain BL21 (DE3) and selected on LB ampicillin plates. The empty <lb/>pET32a was also transfected into BL21 (DE3) as a control. Following expression induction <lb/>with 0.5 mM isopropyl β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) for 20 h at 16˚C, the proteins <lb/>were purified as previously described [22], separated on 12% SDS-PAGE, and the band visual-<lb/>ized with Coomassie Blue R250 [28]. Molecular weights were estimated in comparison with <lb/>standards (10-170 kDa) (Fermentas, USA). <lb/>Enzyme assays <lb/>The enzyme activities of Mp4CLs were assessed by CoA esters formation from various deriva-<lb/>tives of cinnamic acid. Assays were conducted for 20 min at 30˚C with a reaction volume of <lb/>200 μL containing 10 μg of purified protein, 200 μM of substrate (p-coumaric, caffeic, ferulic, <lb/>5-OH ferulic, cinnamic, or dihydro-p-coumaric acids), 5 mM ATP, 300 μM CoA, and 5 mM <lb/>MgCl 2 , in 200 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5). Extracts of E. coli cells with empty pET32a plasmids <lb/>were used to replace the protein in the controls. The reaction products were analyzed on the <lb/>Agilent 1260 HPLC system equipped with a DAD detector (190-950 nm) using a reverse-<lb/>phase C18 column (XDB-C18, 5 μm; Agilent, USA). The mobile phase A was 1% (v/v) phos-<lb/>phoric acid water and phase B was acetonitrile. The gradient was 0-5 min, 5% B; 5-35 min, <lb/>5-25% B; 35-36 min, 25-100% B; 36-45 min, 100% B; and 45-55 min, 5% B. The flow rate <lb/>was 1 mL/min. <lb/>Enzyme activities were detected under different temperatures, pH, and metal cations. In <lb/>addition, the effect of Mg 2+ was also assessed at concentrations of 1, 2.5, 5, 10, 20, 100, and 200 <lb/>mM. Michaelis-Menten kinetics were assessed using GraphPad Prism 6. Varying concentra-<lb/>tions of the substrate in 200 mM Tris-HCl buffer were evaluated, with monitoring of UV <lb/>absorption at one-minute intervals. The wavelengths used for the specific CoA esters were 311 <lb/>nm (cinnamoyl), 333 nm (p-coumaroyl), 346 nm (caffeoyl), 346 nm (feruloyl), and 350 nm <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>(5-hydroxyferuloyl) [29-31]. The kinetics of dihydro-p-coumaric acid were determined and <lb/>the product concentrations were calculated from a standard calibration curve using HPLC. <lb/>Treatment with plant growth regulator and gene expression <lb/>Two-month-old M. paleacea thalli were treated with 1 mM MeJA for 0, 6, 12, 24, 36, or 48 h. <lb/>Samples were initially placed in liquid nitrogen after collection and RNA extraction and <lb/>cDNA synthesis was performed as described above. Gene expression was assessed by real-time <lb/>quantitative PCR using the appropriate primers (S2 Table), using an Eppendorf realplex2 sys-<lb/>tem (Eppendorf, Germany). The 20 μL reaction volume included 1 μg cDNA, 0.5 μM of each <lb/>primer, and 1×SYBR Green PCR Master mix. M. paleacea elongation factor 1 alpha (accession <lb/>number: OR881401) was used as a reference gene which was amplified using the primer pair <lb/>Mpelongation-F/R. <lb/>Subcellular localization <lb/>To investigate the subcellular localization of Mp4CLs, full-length cDNAs of Mp4CL1 and <lb/>Mp4CL2 were amplified with the gene-specific primers listed in S2 Table (attB1-Mp4CL1/ <lb/>attB2-Mp4CL1-GFP, attB1-Mp4CL2/attB2-Mp4CL2-GFP). The PCR products were subcloned <lb/>into plasmid pDONR207 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, USA) using the Gateway BP Clonase II <lb/>enzyme mix (ThermoFisher Scientific) according to the protocol offered and verified by com-<lb/>plete gene sequencing. Then, two plasmids were transferred into binary vector pGWB5 (Invi-<lb/>trogen, Carlsbad, USA) using the Gateway LR Clonase II enzyme mix (ThermoFisher <lb/>Scientific) according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocols. These expression vectors bearing the <lb/>GFP-Mp4CL1 and GFP-Mp4CL2 constructs were transferred into Agrobacterium tumefaciens <lb/>strain EHA105 using the freeze-thaw method [32]. Transient expression in N. benthamiana <lb/>leaves was conducted as described with minor modifications [33, 34]. Specifically, positive <lb/>transformants were cultured at 28˚C overnight, rinsed, and resuspended to an optical density <lb/>of 1 at 600 nm in transformation buffer [33]. The efficiency of transformation was increased <lb/>by using a helper A. tumefaciens strain with a p19 construct [35] with a similar concentration. <lb/>The two suspensions were mixed and incubated at 25˚C for 2 h before syringe infiltration into <lb/>N. benthamiana leaves. After two days, the leaves were assessed under confocal microscopy <lb/>(Zeiss LSM 700 laser confocal microscope, Germany). An argon laser (488 nm for GFP, 550 <lb/>nm for autofluorescence of chlorophyll) and primary beam-splitting mirrors (458/514 or 488 <lb/>nm) were used. Processing of images was performed with Zeiss ZEN 2009 software. <lb/>Heterologous expression of Mp4CL1 in Arabidopsis <lb/>The Mp4CL1 ORF was amplified by PCR using the attB1-Mp4CL1/attB2-Mp4CL1-OE primer <lb/>pairs (S2 Table). After construction of the pGWB5-Mp4CL1 vector, it was transferred into A. <lb/>tumefaciens strain EHA105 [32]. The wild-type (WT) Arabidopsis thaliana plants were then <lb/>transformed by the floral dip method [36]. Positive transformants were obtained after cultiva-<lb/>tion of the seeds on 1/2 Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium containing 50 mg/L kanamycin. <lb/>The positive transformants of Mp4CL1 were confirmed by Reverse transcription-polymerase <lb/>chain reaction (RT-PCR) using Mp4CL1-At-F1/Mp4CL1-At-R1 primer pairs and the AtActin <lb/>gene (NM_001338359.1) was used as a reference with the AtActin-F2/AtActin-R2 primer <lb/>pairs (S2 Table). Homozygous transgenic lines (i.e., Mp4CL1-OE1) from the T3 generation <lb/>were selected for further analyses. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Lignin concentrations and histochemistry <lb/>Lignin concentrations were assessed using an acetyl bromide (AcBr) based method [37, 38] <lb/>and lignin staining was performed using phloroglucinol-HCl color development [39]. Frozen <lb/>sections with the thickness of 20 μm were cut from the base of the two-month-old A. thaliana <lb/>stems using MICROM HM550 temperature frozen section machine under -35˚C and incu-<lb/>bated in 1 mL of 1% phloroglucinol ethanol HCl solution for 2 min. The sections were then <lb/>washed, stained in 20% HCl, and evaluated and imaged using an inverted optical microscope <lb/>(IX71, Olympus) equipped with a 4× objective. <lb/>Synthetic production of flavanones <lb/>The CHSs sequences were obtained from pET32a-MpCHS, AtCHS, and ScCHS1 by PCR and <lb/>ligated into pCDFDuet-1 between the BamH I/Hind III, BamH I/Not I, and Hind III/Not I <lb/>sites to yield pCDFDuet-1-MpCHS, pCDFDuet-1-AtCHS, and pCDFDuet-1-ScCHS1, respec-<lb/>tively. Subsequently, Mp4CL1 was cloned into pCDFDuet-1-MpCHS, pCDFDuet-1-AtCHS, <lb/>and pCDFDuet-1-ScCHS1 through the Bgl II and Kpn I sites to generate plasmids p1 <lb/>(pCDFDuet-1-MpCHS-Mp4CL1), p2 (pCDFDuet-1-AtCHS-Mp4CL1), and p3 (pCDFDuet-<lb/>1-ScCHS1-Mp4CL1). Then, plasmids p1, p2, and p3 were introduced into E. coli BL21 (DE3) <lb/>to obtain strains E1, E2, and E3, respectively. All constructs were confirmed using Sanger <lb/>sequencing and colony PCR. The primers and plasmids used are shown in S2 and S3 Tables, <lb/>respectively. The engineered strains (E1, E2, and E3) were grown in 10 mL of LB (or TB) <lb/>medium at 37˚C with shaking at 120 rpm. When the OD600 reached 0.4-0.6, the temperature <lb/>was equilibrated to 16˚C, and IPTG was added to the final concentration of 0.5 mM. To pro-<lb/>duce naringenin, varying concentrations of p-coumaric acid (100, 300, 500, and 700 μM) were <lb/>added, followed by incubation at 16˚C for 96 h. One milliliter of the samples was collected at <lb/>regular intervals (every 12 hours) from the media. After two extractions in equal volume of <lb/>ethyl acetate, the organic layer was collected and evaporated. The product was then resus-<lb/>pended in 100 μL of 80% (v/v) methanol and analyzed by HPLC. The HPLC parameters were <lb/>as described by Ni et al. [40]. Briefly, samples were analyzed with the Agilent 1260 HPLC sys-<lb/>tem equipped with a reverse-phase XDB-C18 column (4.6 mm × 150 mm, 5 μm, Agilent) <lb/>under the gradient elution mode at a flow rate of 0.8 mL/min. Mobile phases A and B were <lb/>water (containing 0.1% glacial acetic acid) and methanol, respectively. A linear gradient of <lb/>70% A and 30% B to 20% A and 80% B was supplied over 30 min. When the product was pino-<lb/>cembrin, eriodictyol, or homoeriodictyol, the fermentation conditions and detection method <lb/>were carried out, as mentioned above. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>Isolation of genes, sequencing, and homology modeling <lb/>Four putative 4CL genes were identified through mining of the transcriptomic data of M. <lb/>paleacea and were designated Mp4CL1-4. The open reading frames (ORFs) of the sequences <lb/>were 1650 (Mp4CL1), 1641 (Mp4CL2), 1683 (Mp4CL3), and 1578 bp (Mp4CL4) in length, <lb/>encoding proteins of 549 (59.21 kDa), 546 (59.60 kDa), 560 (61.57 kDa), and 525 (56.43 kDa) <lb/>residues, respectively. The protein sequences shared 24.0-59.4% similarity with At4CL2 <lb/>(accession number: NP_188761) and Pt4CL (accession number: AAL02144). Specifically, <lb/>Mp4CL1 shared 58.7% identity with At4CL2 and 59.4% identity with Pt4CL, while Mp4CL4 <lb/>shared 24.0% and 27.3% identity, respectively. All Mp4CLs contained two highly conserved <lb/>domains, namely, a putative AMP-binding domain (Box I) and the conserved GEICIRG <lb/>domain (Box II) (Fig 2). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Three-dimensional structures of the Mp4CL1-APP and Mp4CL2-APP complexes were <lb/>modeled using the 4CL chain A from P. tomentosa 4CL as the template (S1 Fig). Both struc-<lb/>tures resembled that of the P. tomentosa protein in having two globular domains, a larger <lb/>domain in the N-terminal region and a smaller domain in the C-terminal region [25]. In <lb/>Mp4CL1, the lengths of the N-terminal and C-terminal domains were 450 (residues 1-450) <lb/>and 100 residues (residues 450-549), respectively, and 441 (residues 1-441) and 105 residues <lb/>Fig 2. Alignment of the deduced amino acid sequence of Marchantia paleacea 4CLs with other plant 4CLs. Residues involved in <lb/>hydroxycinnamate binding are marked by triangles, while those involved in enzymatic function are marked by diamonds. The putative AMP-binding <lb/>domain is indicated within Box I, and the conserved &quot;GEICIRG&quot; putative catalytic site is represented in Box II. The abbreviations for species and <lb/>accession numbers are Arabidopsis thaliana 4CL2 (AAD47192.1) and Populus tomentosa 4CL (AAL02144.1). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>(residues 442-546) in Mp4CL2, respectively. The overall sequence similarities of Mp4CL1 and <lb/>Mp4CL2 with the template were 62.8% and 40.4%. Furthermore, the value of Global Model <lb/>Quality Estimate (GMQE) of the modeled Mp4CL1 was 0.83, and the value of Mp4CL2 was <lb/>0.73. The APP-binding site was visible as a cavity in the N-terminal domain (S1 Fig). Residues <lb/>A322 and G321 in Mp4CL1 and A316 and G315 in Mp4CL2 formed hydrogen bonds with the <lb/>coumaroyl-AMP conjugate, while K454 and Q459 in Mp4CL1 and K445 and Q450 in <lb/>Mp4CL2 bound the phosphate group using hydrogen bonds (S1B and S1D Fig). <lb/>Phylogenetic analysis of 4CL homologs <lb/>The neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree was constructed from the protein sequences of M. <lb/>paleacea, alfalfa (Medicago truncatula), A. thaliana, soybean (Glycine max), Physcomitrella pat-<lb/>ens, and other plant species (GenBank accession numbers listed in S1 Table). After bootstrap-<lb/>ping, it could be seen that the 4CL proteins were divided into four subgroups (Fig 3): one clade <lb/>consisting of Mp4CL2, Mp4CL3, and Pa4CL1 from liverworts; and three clades (classes I, II, <lb/>and III) of 4CLs that are present in angiosperms, gymnosperms, pteridophytes, and bryophytes <lb/>(including Mp4CL1) (Fig 3). Class I 4CLs were associated with growth and development, <lb/>mainly through phenol formation via the lignin pathway, while Class II proteins were linked <lb/>to abiotic stress responses [41]. Class III 4CLs were predominantly associated with monocoty-<lb/>ledonous plants while Class II were found mostly in dicotyledonous species. The tree was <lb/>rooted with Mp4CL4, indicating that Mp4CL4 might not the real 4CL. <lb/>Fig 3. Phylogeny of Mp4CLS and other plant 4CLs. Accession numbers of the sequences are listed in S1 Table. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Enzyme activities HPLC analysis <lb/>The in vitro enzymatic activities of the expressed Mp4CLs were examined. As shown by <lb/>SDS-PAGE analysis of the purified recombinant proteins, their molecular weights ranged <lb/>between 70 and 100 kDa (S2 Fig). The proteins were expressed as fusion proteins with the N-<lb/>terminal tags, which has a molecular weight of 20.4 kDa. Their activities were assessed using <lb/>various substrates, including p-coumaric, cinnamic, caffeic, ferulic, 5-hydroxy ferulic, and <lb/>dihydro-p-coumaric acids. As shown by HPLC, Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 converted all these <lb/>substrates to their corresponding CoA esters (Fig 4). In contrast, neither Mp4CL3 nor <lb/>Fig 4. Functional characterization of Mp4CLs. HPLC chromatograms of the reactions of Mp4CLs with p-coumaric acid (A), caffeic acid (B), <lb/>ferulic acid (C), 5-OH ferulic acid (D), cinnamic acid (E), and dihydro-p-coumaric acid (F) as substrates. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Mp4CL4 displayed any activity with the provided substrates (Table 1). The mechanisms <lb/>underlying these affinities were explored using modeled structures of Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 <lb/>in complex with APP (S1 Fig). This showed that Y252 and S256 in Mp4CL1, which are neces-<lb/>sary for hydroxycinnamate binding and tend to be strongly conserved in 4CL enzymes [25], <lb/>were replaced by M246 and V250 in Mp4CL2 (S1 Fig). The residues were replaced by H221 <lb/>and A225 in Mp4CL4, and Y256 and T260 in Mp4CL3, which might explain why Mp4CL3 <lb/>and Mp4CL4 displayed no activity with the provided substrates. The enzymatic activity of <lb/>Mp4CL1 for all substrates was higher than that of Mp4CL2 (Table 2). This was likely due to <lb/>the formation of van der Waals interactions between the respective 4-hydroxyphenyl groups <lb/>on Y252 and APP in Mp4CL1 as well as the formation of hydrogen bonds between S256 and <lb/>the hydroxyphenyl group of APP, enhancing the effectiveness of substrate binding. <lb/>Furthermore, it was observed that Mp4CL1 activity was sensitive to both pH and tempera-<lb/>ture. Mp4CL1 was most active at pH 7.0 and 30˚C (S3A and S3B Fig). In addition, it is widely <lb/>known that metal cations also affect enzymatic activity. In our experiment, Mg 2+ at 10 Mm <lb/>resulted in the optimum performance (S3C and S3D Fig). We next chose p-coumaric, caffeic, <lb/>cinnamic, ferulic, and dihydro-p-coumaric acids for comparison of the kinetic parameters of <lb/>the enzyme with different substrates. The V max , K m , k cat , and k enz (k cat /K m ) values of Mp4CL1 <lb/>for the different substrates are shown in Table 2. Mp4CL1 showed the strongest affinity for p-<lb/>coumaric acid (K m = 93.99 μM), followed by caffeic (K m = 113.30 μM), cinnamic (K m = <lb/>115.10 μM), dihydro-p-coumaric (K m = 289.20 μM), and ferulic (K m = 414.10 μM) acids. Addi-<lb/>tionally, the catalytic efficiency of Mp4CL1 toward p-coumaric acid (k enz = 9.20×10 4 M -1 min -<lb/>1 <lb/>) was higher than others. These findings indicated that p-coumaric acid was the preferred sub-<lb/>strate for Mp4CL1 (Table 2). <lb/>Table 1. The substrate specificity of Mp4CLs. <lb/>Substrate <lb/>Specific activity (nmol mg -1 min -1 ) <lb/>Mp4CL1 <lb/>Mp4CL2 <lb/>Mp4CL3 <lb/>Mp4CL4 <lb/>p-coumaric acid <lb/>124.52±8.76 <lb/>35.04±0.82 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>caffeic acid <lb/>93.39±10.19 <lb/>14.29±0.58 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>ferulic acid <lb/>77.44±6.93 <lb/>12.35±1.15 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>5-hydroxy ferulic acid <lb/>86.69±3.28 <lb/>4.81±0.19 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>cinnamic acid <lb/>73.32±1.76 <lb/>26.91±1.22 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>dihydro-p-coumaric acid <lb/>176.07±2.12 <lb/>10.12±0.10 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>ND, No detectable activity. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.t001 <lb/>Table 2. Kinetic parameters of recombinant Mp4CL1. <lb/>Substrate <lb/>K m (μM) <lb/>V max (nmol mg -1 min -1 ) <lb/>k cat (min -1 ) <lb/>k enz (M -1 min -1 ) <lb/>p-coumaric acid <lb/>93.99±30.94 <lb/>146.10±17.04 <lb/>8.65±1.01 <lb/>9.20×10 4 <lb/>caffeic acid <lb/>113.30±24.27 <lb/>165.20±11.00 <lb/>9.78±0.65 <lb/>8.63×10 4 <lb/>cinnamic acid <lb/>115.10±16.56 <lb/>124.70±5.17 <lb/>7.39±0.31 <lb/>6.42×10 4 <lb/>ferulic acid <lb/>414.10±95.69 <lb/>364.00±38.71 <lb/>21.55±2.29 <lb/>5.20×10 4 <lb/>dihydro-p-coumaric acid <lb/>289.20±36.50 <lb/>430.1±26.00 <lb/>25.47±1.54 <lb/>8.81×10 4 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Elicitor-induced Mp4CL1 transcription <lb/>It is documented that 4CL enzymes are associated with responses to exogenous signals, such as <lb/>methyl jasmonate (MeJA), Abscisic acid (ABA) and salicylic acid (SA) [42]. In this research, we <lb/>measured the expression pattern of Mp4CL1 under exogenous MeJA treatment using real-time <lb/>quantitative PCR. As shown in Fig 5, upon MeJA induction, the transcript abundance of <lb/>Mp4CL1 in the thallus peaked after 24 h before declining to the levels of the control after 48 h <lb/>(Fig 5). Similarly, exposure to MeJA upregulated the transcript levels of 4CLs in Capparis spinosa, <lb/>meanwhile, MeJA treatment significantly increased the rutin content of C. spinose [43]. In the <lb/>other case, ABA treatment strongly induced the expression of Cf4CL of Coleus forskohlii, and <lb/>increased the lignin content [43]. Thus, the present findings indicate the significance of 4CLs, not <lb/>only in terms of secondary metabolite synthesis, but also in responses to abiotic stressors [44]. <lb/>Subcellular localization <lb/>As predicted by SignalP (https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/SignalP-6.0/), the signal <lb/>peptides of Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 are located at the N-terminal of proteins, which was the <lb/>same with some genes the literatures reported [45, 46], the subcellular localization of Mp4CL1 <lb/>and Mp4CL2 was determined in vivo. To evaluate the subcellular localization of the Mp4CL1 <lb/>and Mp4CL2 proteins, two C-terminal GFP-fusion plasmids (GFP-Mp4CL1 and <lb/>GFP-Mp4CL2) were constructed and transiently expressed in tobacco leaves. GFP signals <lb/>were detected in both the nucleus and cytoplasm for the GFP control, GFP-Mp4CL1, and <lb/>GFP-Mp4CL2 (Fig 6). This result indicates that both Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 are localized to <lb/>the cytoplasm and nucleus, as reported for Cs4CLs [47]. <lb/>Mp4CL1 overexpression in arabidopsis <lb/>To further functionally characterize Mp4CLs, we overexpressed Mp4CL1 in Arabidopsis. After <lb/>insertion of the full-length Mp4CL1 coding sequence into the pGWB5 vector to generate an <lb/>overexpression construct and transformation with A. tumefaciens, lines stably overexpressing <lb/>Mp4CL1 were generated in the Columbia-0 background. The presence of Mp4CL1 transcripts <lb/>in the T3 plants but not in the WT was confirmed by RT-PCR (Fig 7A). The lignin contents of <lb/>the two lines (22.86 and 23.49 mg AcBr lignin/mg dry weight) were measured and compared <lb/>Fig 5. Mp4CL1 transcript abundance in thalli exposed to MeJA. The reference gene was the Marchantia paleacea <lb/>Elongation Factor. The data represent the mean of three biological replicates. Error bars indicate the standard <lb/>deviation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>with the wild-type control (16.12 mg AcBr lignin/mg dry weight) using the AcBr based <lb/>method [37, 38]. The result showed that the presence of the two transgenes increased the depo-<lb/>sition of lignin by 41.8% and 45.7%, respectively (Fig 7B). As 4CLs are closely involved in lig-<lb/>nin biosynthesis [48, 49], lignin deposition was examined in the stems of Mp4CL1-OE and <lb/>WT plants using histochemistry. This showed elevated lignin contents in the stem vascular tis-<lb/>sues (Fig 7C and 7D) in the transgenic plants but not the WT. This demonstrates that Mp4CL1 <lb/>overexpression enhanced lignin deposition and may thus increase lodging resistance, an <lb/>important agronomic characteristic. <lb/>Flavanone production in E. coli from supplementation with different <lb/>hydroxycinnamic acids using 4CL and CHS enzymes <lb/>During flavonoid biosynthesis, both 4CL and chalcone synthase (CHS) are necessary for pro-<lb/>ducing flavanone from various hydroxycinnamic acids. Previous studies have suggested that <lb/>naringenin biosynthesis from p-coumaroyl CoA, which is catalyzed by CHS, is the limiting <lb/>step for flavonoid production [50]. To date, many CHSs have been characterized in plant spe-<lb/>cies spanning Bryophyta [51], Pteridophyta [40, 52], Gymnospermae, and Angiospermae [53, <lb/>54]. In this study, we selected the chalcone synthases MpCHS (AUG98250.1) [55], Stenoloma <lb/>chusanaum chalcone synthase (ScCHS1, ON462260) [40], and AtCHS (NP_196897.1) [56] for <lb/>investigation by constructing three engineered strains, E1 (harboring MpCHS and Mp4CL1), <lb/>E2 (harboring AtCHS and Mp4CL1), and E3 (harboring ScCHS1 and Mp4CL1) (Fig 8A). Thus, <lb/>Fig 6. Subcellular localization of Mp4CLs. The expression cassettes Mp4CL1-or Mp4CL2-GFP chimeric gene, driven by 35S promoter, transiently <lb/>transformed tobacco leaf discs. The GFP signal appears green, and the chlorophyll signal is red. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Mp4CL1, which displayed high enzyme activity in vitro (Fig 4), was used to convert p-couma-<lb/>ric acid to p-coumaroyl CoA. As shown in Fig 8, after 84 h of fermentation, strain E1 produced <lb/>naringenin at a concentration of 21 mg/L (supplemented with 500 μM of p-coumaric acid) at a <lb/>rate of 15.4% in LB media (Fig 8B and 8D). For optimization, strain E1 was supplemented with <lb/>substrate at different concentrations. Via HPLC analysis, the optimal substrate concentration <lb/>was determined to be 300 μM (Fig 8B); at this concentration, the maximum conversion rate <lb/>was as high as 24.9% (Fig 8C and 8D). Under optimized conditions, strains E1, E2, and E3 <lb/>were suspended in the TB medium with 300 μM of p-coumaric acid, cinnamic acid, caffeic <lb/>acid, and ferulic acid for 84 h to produce naringenin, pinocembrin, eriodictyol, and homoerio-<lb/>dictyol respectively. Strain E1 produced approximately 49 mg/L naringenin (conversion yield, <lb/>60.8%), 4 mg/L pinocembrin (conversion yield, 5.6%), and 2 mg/L homoeriodictyol (conver-<lb/>sion yield, 2.6%), with no eriodictyol being detected in the extract (Fig 8E and 8F; S4 Table). <lb/>For E2, 18 mg/L of naringenin (conversion yield, 23.1%), 3.5 mg/L of pinocembrin (conver-<lb/>sion yield, 4.6%), and no homoeriodictyol and eriodictyol were detected in the extract (Fig 8F; <lb/>S4 Table). No production was detected in strain E3. As AtCHS and ScCHS1 are from species <lb/>other than M. paleacea, there results suggest that flavanone production is likely to be more effi-<lb/>cient when 4CL and CHS from the same species are present. Similarly, co-expression of the <lb/>upstream OsF2H with OsCGT from Oryza sativa in yeast was found to maximize the flavone <lb/>C-glucoside yield [57]. <lb/>Fig 7. Heterologous expression of Mp4CL1 genes in A. thaliana and its effect on lignin content. A. RT-PCR profiling <lb/>shows that Mp4CL1 was transcribed in the selected transgenic lines; AtActin was used as the reference sequence. B. Lignin <lb/>content of Mp4CL1 transgenic A. thaliana. The results were shown as the means of three biological replicate reactions with <lb/>standard deviations, significant differences were determined by Student&apos;s t-test, *p &lt; 0.05 and **p &lt; 0.01. Phloroglucinol-<lb/>HCl stained stem sections with the thickness of 20 μm sampled from (C) wild type A. thaliana plant and (D) transgenic <lb/>plant expressing 35S::Mp4CL1. Lignin was stained violet-red. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g007 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Conclusions <lb/>Here, two 4CL genes Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 were functionally characterized from the liverwort <lb/>M. paleacea. They could catalyze p-coumaric, caffeic, ferulic, cinnamic, 5-hydroxy ferulic, and <lb/>dihydro-p-coumaric acids to the corresponding hydroxycinnamoyl CoA thioesters. In addition, <lb/>Fig 8. Synthetic production of various flavanones by recombinant Escherichia coli strains. A. Engineered pathway for naringenin biosynthesis <lb/>from p-coumaric acid using 4-Coumarate: coenzyme A ligase (4CL) and chalcone synthases (CHS) in E. coli. B. The effect of fermentation time on the <lb/>production of naringenin using strain E1. C. Effect of varying concentrations of p-coumaric acid on the production of naringenin using strain E1. D. <lb/>Maximizing the conversion rate of naringenin by optimizing the substrate concentration and time course. E. Effect of optimized (LB and TB) media <lb/>on naringenin production using strain E1. F. Biosynthesis of naringenin (NAR), pinocembrin (PIN), eriodictyol (ERI), and homoeriodictyol (HOM) <lb/>in different E. coli strains. Three biological replicates were performed for each analysis; the error bars indicate the SD. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079.g008 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>we investigated the subcellular localization and expression pattern of Mp4CL1 and Mp4CL2 in <lb/>plants treated with MeJA. Mp4CL1 can be used to produce various flavanones in E. coli. Our <lb/>research will contribute to the understanding of the functional diversity of 4CL in liverworts. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Dataset. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Fig. Homology modeling and docking of Mp4CLs with APP. A. Three-dimensional <lb/>structural model of the Mp4CL1-APP complex. The structure was obtained by homology <lb/>modeling using P. tomentosa 4CL-3NI2 as a template. The N-domain is colored green, and the <lb/>C-domain is cyan. APP is indicated by a sphere, with its C, O, and N atoms colored in yellow, <lb/>pink, and blue, respectively. B. Stereoview of the Mp4CL1-APP interaction. The APP C, O, <lb/>and N atoms are colored in green, pink, and blue, respectively. Hydrogen bonds between APP <lb/>and Mp4CL1 are shown as red dashed lines. C. Three-dimensional structural model of the <lb/>Mp4CL2-APP complex. D. Stereoview of the Mp4CL2-APP interaction. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. SDS-PAGE analysis of recombinant proteins. M: Weight marker, Lane 1: Mp4CL1, <lb/>Lane 2: Mp4CL2, Lane 3: Mp4CL3, and Lane 4: Mp4CL4. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Enzymatic characteristics of purified recombinant Mp4CL1. Effect of various pH <lb/>(A), temperature (B), mental cations (C), and the Mg 2+ concentration (D) on the enzyme <lb/>activities of Mp4CL1 using p-coumaric acid as the substrate. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Accession numbers of amino acid sequences used for phylogenetic reconstruc-<lb/>tion. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S2 Table. Primers were used in this research. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S3 Table. Plasmids and strains were used in this study. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S4 Table. The conversion rate generated by the four hydroxycinnamic acids to produce <lb/>naringenin, pinocembrin, eriodictyol, and homoeriodictyol at the 300 μM substrate con-<lb/>centration in the TB medium. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S1 Raw images. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Shuai Gao. <lb/>Data curation: Shuai Gao, Xin-Yan Liu, Rong Ni, Jie Fu, Hui Tan. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Shuai Gao. <lb/>Investigation: Shuai Gao. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Methodology: Shuai Gao, Ai-Xia Cheng. <lb/>Project administration: Ai-Xia Cheng, Hong-Xiang Lou. <lb/>Resources: Ai-Xia Cheng, Hong-Xiang Lou. <lb/>Supervision: Hong-Xiang Lou. <lb/>Validation: Shuai Gao, Xin-Yan Liu, Rong Ni, Jie Fu, Hui Tan. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Shuai Gao, Ai-Xia Cheng. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Vogt T., 2010. Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis. Mol. Plant 3(1), 2-20. https://doi.org/10.1093/mp/ <lb/>ssp106 PMID: 20035037 <lb/>2. Lavhale S.G., Kalunke R.M., Giri A.P., 2018. Structural, functional and evolutionary diversity of 4-cou-<lb/>marate-CoA ligase in plants. Planta 248(5), 1063-1078. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00425-018-2965-z <lb/>PMID: 30078075 <lb/>3. Nandy S., Dey A., 2020. Bibenzyls and bisbybenzyls of bryophytic origin as promising source of novel <lb/>therapeutics: pharmacology, synthesis and structure-activity. Daru. 28(2), 701-734. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s40199-020-00341-0 PMID: 32803687 <lb/>4. Panche A.N., Diwan A.D., Chandra S.R., 2016. Flavonoids: an overview. J. Nutr. Sci. 5, e47. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1017/jns.2016.41 PMID: 28620474 <lb/>5. Fraser C.M., Chapple C., 2011. The phenylpropanoid pathway in Arabidopsis. The Arabidopsis Book. <lb/>9, e0152. https://doi.org/10.1199/tab.0152 PMID: 22303276 <lb/>6. Hamberger B., Hahlbrock K., 2004. The 4-coumarate:CoA ligase gene family in Arabidopsis thaliana <lb/>comprises one rare, sinapate-activating and three commonly occurring isoenzymes. Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. U. S. A., 101(7), 2209-2214. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0307307101 PMID: 14769935 <lb/>7. Shockey J., Browse J., 2011. Genome-level and biochemical diversity of the acyl-activating enzyme <lb/>superfamily in plants. Plant J. 66(1), 143-160. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04512.x <lb/>PMID: 21443629 <lb/>8. Ehlting J., Bu ¨ttner D., Wang Q., Douglas C.J., Somssich I.E., Kombrink E., 1999. Three 4-coumarate: <lb/>coenzyme A ligases in Arabidopsis thaliana represent two evolutionarily divergent classes in angio-<lb/>sperms. Plant J. 19(1), 9-20. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-313x.1999.00491.x PMID: 10417722 <lb/>9. Sun H., Li Y., Feng S., Zou W., Guo K., et al. 2013a. Analysis of five rice 4-coumarate: coenzyme A <lb/>ligase enzyme activity and stress response for potential roles in lignin and flavonoid biosynthesis in rice. <lb/>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 430(3), 1151-1156. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2012.12.019 <lb/>PMID: 23246835 <lb/>10. Lin C.Y., Sun Y., Song J., Chen H.C., Shi R., Yang C., et al. 2021. Enzyme complexes of Ptr4CL and <lb/>PtrHCT modulate co-enzyme a ligation of hydroxycinnamic acids for monolignol biosynthesis in Popu-<lb/>lus trichocarpa. Front. Plant Sci. 12, 727932. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2021.727932 PMID: <lb/>34691108 <lb/>11. Stuible H. P., Kombrink E., 2001. Identification of the substrate specificity-conferring amino acid resi-<lb/>dues of 4-coumarate: coenzyme A ligase allows the rational design of mutant enzymes with new cata-<lb/>lytic properties. J. Biol. Chem. 276(29), 26893-26897. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M100355200 PMID: <lb/>11323416 <lb/>12. Kanazawa K., Hashimoto T., Yoshida S., Sungwon P., Fukuda S., 2012. Short photoirradiation induces <lb/>flavonoid synthesis and increases its production in postharvest vegetables. J. Agric. Food Chem. 60 <lb/>(17), 4359-4368. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf300107s PMID: 22506664 <lb/>13. Hao J., Lou P., Han Y., Zheng L., Lu J., Chen Z., et al. 2022. Ultraviolet-B Irradiation Increases Antioxi-<lb/>dant Capacity of Pakchoi (Brassica rapa L.) by Inducing Flavonoid Biosynthesis. Plants (Basel) 11(6), <lb/>766. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11060766 PMID: 35336648 <lb/>14. Chen X., Wang H., Li X., Ma K., Zhan Y., Zeng F., 2019. Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4-<lb/>Coumarate: CoA ligase 4 (4CL-like 1) from Fraxinus mandshurica and its role in abiotic stress tolerance <lb/>and cell wall synthesis. BMC Plant Biol. 19(1), 231. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12870-019-1812-0 PMID: <lb/>31159735 <lb/>15. Harding S.A., Leshkevich J., Chiang V.L., Tsai C.J., 2002. Differential substrate inhibition couples kinet-<lb/>ically distinct 4-coumarate: coenzyme A ligases with spatially distinct metabolic roles in quaking aspen. <lb/>Plant Physiol. 128(2), 428-438. https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.010603 PMID: 11842147 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>16. Liga S., Paul C., Pe ´ter F., 2023. Flavonoids: Overview of Biosynthesis, Biological Activity, and Current <lb/>Extraction Techniques. Plants (Basel) 12(14), 2732. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants12142732 PMID: <lb/>37514347 <lb/>17. Singh M., Singh S., Nath V., Sahu V., Rawat A. K., 2011. Antibacterial activity of some bryophytes used <lb/>traditionally for the treatment of burn infections. Pharm. Biol. 49(5), 526-530. https://doi.org/10.3109/ <lb/>13880209.2010.523007 PMID: 21391844 <lb/>18. Asakawa Y., 2008. Liverworts-potential source of medicinal compounds. Curr. Pharm. Des. 14(29), <lb/>3067-3088. https://doi.org/10.2174/138161208786404272 PMID: 19075692 <lb/>19. Kim J.W., Seo J.Y., Oh W.K., Sung S.H., 2016. Anti-neuroinflammatory ent-kaurane diterpenoids from <lb/>Pteris multifida roots. Molecules 22(1), 27. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules22010027 PMID: <lb/>28035965 <lb/>20. Wohl J., Petersen M., 2020. Phenolic metabolism in the hornwort Anthoceros agrestis: 4-coumarate <lb/>CoA ligase and 4-hydroxybenzoate CoA ligase. Plant Cell Rep. 39(9), 1129-1141. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s00299-020-02552-w PMID: 32405654 <lb/>21. Silber M.V., Meimberg H., Ebel J., 2008. Identification of a 4-coumarate: CoA ligase gene family in the <lb/>moss, Physcomitrella patens. Phytochemistry 69(13), 2449-2456. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>phytochem.2008.06.014 PMID: 18722632 <lb/>22. Gao S., Yu H.N., Xu R.X., Cheng A.X., Lou H.X., 2015. Cloning and functional characterization of a 4-<lb/>coumarate CoA ligase from liverwort Plagiochasma appendiculatum. Phytochemistry 111, 48-58. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2014.12.017 PMID: 25593011 <lb/>23. Tamura K., Dudley J., Nei M., Kumar S., 2007. MEGA4: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis <lb/>(MEGA) software version 4.0. Mol. Biol. Evol. 24(8), 1596-1599. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/ <lb/>msm092 PMID: 17488738 <lb/>24. Arnold K., Bordoli L., Kopp J., Schwede T., 2006. The SWISS-MODEL workspace: a web-based envi-<lb/>ronment for protein structure homology modeling. Bioinformatics 22(2), 195-201. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1093/bioinformatics/bti770 PMID: 16301204 <lb/>25. Hu Y., Gai Y., Yin L., Wang X., Feng C., Feng L., et al. 2010. Crystal structures of a Populus tomentosa <lb/>4-coumarate: CoA ligase shed light on its enzymatic mechanisms. Plant Cell 22(9), 3093-3104. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1105/tpc.109.072652 PMID: 20841425 <lb/>26. Bramucci E., Paiardini A., Bossa F., Pascarella S., 2012. PyMod: sequence similarity searches, multiple <lb/>sequence-structure alignments, and homology modeling within PyMOL. BMC Bioinformatics 13, 1-6. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-13-S4-S2 PMID: 22536966 <lb/>27. Gambino G., Perrone I., Gribaudo I., 2008. A rapid and effective method for RNA extraction from differ-<lb/>ent tissues of grapevine and other woody plants. Phytochem. Anal. 19(6), 520-525. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1002/pca.1078 PMID: 18618437 <lb/>28. Sun Y., Wu Y., Zhao Y., Han X., Lou H., Cheng A., 2013b. Molecular cloning and biochemical char-<lb/>acterization of two cinnamyl alcohol dehydrogenases from a liverwort Plagiochasma appendicula-<lb/>tum. Plant Physiol. Biochem. 70, 133-141. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2013.05.027 PMID: <lb/>23774375 <lb/>29. LU ¨DERITZ T., SCHATZ G., GRISEBACH H., 1982. Enzymic synthesis of lignin precursors: purification <lb/>and properties of 4-coumarate: CoA ligase from cambial sap of spruce (Picea abies L.). Eur. J. Bio-<lb/>chem. 123(3), 583-586. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1432-1033.1982.tb06572.x <lb/>30. Meng H., Campbell W.H., 1997. Facile enzymic synthesis of caffeoyl CoA. Phytochemistry 44(4), 605-<lb/>608. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(96)00594-8 <lb/>31. Sto ¨ekigt J., Zenk M.H., 1975. Chemical syntheses and properties of hydroxycinnamoyl-coenzyme A <lb/>derivatives. Z. Naturforsch. C. Biosci. 30(3), 352-358. https://doi.org/10.1515/znc-1975-5-609 PMID: <lb/>126581 <lb/>32. Milani V.J., Heberlein G.T., 1972. Transfection in Agrobacterium tumefaciens. J. Virol. 10(1), 17-22. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.10.1.17-22.1972 <lb/>33. Xu R.X., Gao S., Zhao Y., Lou H.X., Cheng A.X., 2016. Functional characterization of a Mg 2+ -depen-<lb/>dent O-methyltransferase with coumarin as preferred substrate from the liverwort Plagiochasma appen-<lb/>diculatum. Plant Physiol. Biochem. 106, 269-277. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2016.05.018 PMID: <lb/>27213954 <lb/>34. Bendahmane A., Kanyuka K., Baulcombe D.C., 1999. The Rx gene from potato controls separate virus <lb/>resistance and cell death responses. Plant Cell 11(5), 781-792. https://doi.org/10.1105/tpc.11.5.781 <lb/>PMID: 10330465 <lb/>35. Ahn J., Lee J.S., Davarpanah S.J., Jeon J., Park Y., Liu J.R., et al. 2011. Host-dependent suppression <lb/>of RNA silencing mediated by the viral suppressor p19 in potato. Planta 234, 1065-1072. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/s00425-011-1465-1 PMID: 21717188 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>36. Clough S. J., Bent A. F., 1998. Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transforma-<lb/>tion of Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant J. 16(6), 735-743. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-313x.1998.00343.x <lb/>PMID: 10069079 <lb/>37. Van Acker R., Vanholme R., Storme V., Mortimer J. C., Dupree P., Boerjan W., 2013. Lignin biosynthe-<lb/>sis perturbations affect secondary cell wall composition and saccharification yield in Arabidopsis thali-<lb/>ana. Biotechnol. Biofuels 6(1), 46. https://doi.org/10.1186/1754-6834-6-46 PMID: 23622268 <lb/>38. Chang X. F., Chandra R., Berleth T., Beatson R. P., 2008. Rapid, microscale, acetyl bromide-based <lb/>method for high-throughput determination of lignin content in Arabidopsis thaliana. J. Agric. Food <lb/>Chem. 56(16), 6825-6834. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf800775f PMID: 18666780 <lb/>39. Zhao S., Wen J., Wang H., Zhang Z., Li X., 2016. Changes in lignin content and activity of related <lb/>enzymes in the endocarp during the walnut shell development period. Horticultural Plant Journal 2(3), <lb/>141-146. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.hpj.2016.08.003 <lb/>40. Ni R., Niu M., Fu J., Tan H., Zhu T.T., Zhang J., et al. 2022. Molecular and structural characterization of <lb/>a promiscuous chalcone synthase from the fern species Stenoloma chusanum. J. Integr. Plant Biol. 64 <lb/>(10), 1935-1951. https://doi.org/10.1111/jipb.13335 PMID: 35920566 <lb/>41. Gaid M.M., Sircar D., Mu ¨ller A., Beuerle T., Liu B., Ernst L., et al. 2012. Cinnamate: CoA ligase initiates <lb/>the biosynthesis of a benzoate-derived xanthone phytoalexin in Hypericum calycinum cell cultures. <lb/>Plant Physiol. 160(3), 1267-1280. https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.112.204180 PMID: 22992510 <lb/>42. Kianersi F., Abdollahi M.R., Mirzaie-Asl A., Dastan D., Rasheed F., 2020. Identification and tissue-spe-<lb/>cific expression of rutin biosynthetic pathway genes in Capparis spinosa elicited with salicylic acid and <lb/>methyl jasmonate. Sci. Rep. 10(1), 8884. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-65815-2 PMID: 32483287 <lb/>43. Awasthi P., Mahajan V., Jamwal V.L., Chouhan R., Kapoor N., Bedi Y.S., et al. 2019. Characterization <lb/>of the gene encoding 4-coumarate: CoA ligase in Coleus forskohlii. J. Plant Biochem. Biot. 28, 203-<lb/>210. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13562-018-0468-4 <lb/>44. Sharma A., Shahzad B., Rehman A., Bhardwaj R., Landi M., Zheng B., 2019. Response of phenylpro-<lb/>panoid pathway and the role of polyphenols in plants under abiotic stress. Molecules 24(13), 2452. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules24132452 PMID: 31277395 <lb/>45. Ziegler J., Stenzel I., Hause B., Maucher H., Hamberg M., Grimm R., et al. 2000. Molecular cloning of <lb/>allene oxide cyclase: the enzyme establishing the stereochemistry of octadecanoids and jasmonates. J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 275(25), 19132-19138. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M002133200 PMID: 10764787 <lb/>46. Widiez T., Hartman T.G., Dudai N., Yan Q., Lawton M., Havkin-Frenkel D., et al. 2011. Functional char-<lb/>acterization of two new members of the caffeoyl CoA O-methyltransferase-like gene family from Vanilla <lb/>planifolia reveals a new class of plastid-localized O-methyltransferases. Plant Mol. Biol. 76(6), 475-<lb/>488. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11103-011-9772-2 PMID: 21629984 <lb/>47. Li M., Guo L., Wang Y., Li Y., Jiang X., Liu Y., et al. 2022. Molecular and biochemical characterization of <lb/>two 4-coumarate: CoA ligase genes in tea plant (Camellia sinensis). Plant Mol. Biol. 109(4-5), 579-<lb/>593. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11103-022-01269-6 PMID: 35553312 <lb/>48. Li Y., Kim J.I., Pysh L., Chapple C., 2015. Four isoforms of Arabidopsis 4-coumarate: CoA ligase have <lb/>overlapping yet distinct roles in phenylpropanoid metabolism. Plant Physiol. 169(4), 2409-2421. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.15.00838 PMID: 26491147 <lb/>49. Sun H., Li Y., Feng S., Zou W., Guo K., Fan C., et al. 2013a. Analysis of five rice 4-coumarate: coen-<lb/>zyme A ligase enzyme activity and stress response for potential roles in lignin and flavonoid biosynthe-<lb/>sis in rice. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 430(3), 1151-1156. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2012. <lb/>12.019 PMID: 23246835 <lb/>50. Cui H., Song M.C., Lee J.Y., Yoon Y.J., 2019. Microbial production of O-methylated flavanones from <lb/>methylated phenylpropanoic acids in engineered Escherichia coli. J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 46(12), <lb/>1707-1713. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10295-019-02239-6 PMID: 31595455 <lb/>51. Yu H.N., Wang L., Sun B., Gao S., Cheng A.X., Lou H.X., 2015. Functional characterization of a chal-<lb/>cone synthase from the liverwort Plagiochasma appendiculatum. Plant Cell Rep. 34(2), 233-245. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00299-014-1702-8 PMID: 25404490 <lb/>52. Niu M., Fu J., Ni R., Xiong R.L., Zhu T.T., Lou H. X., et al. 2021. Functional and structural investigation <lb/>of chalcone synthases based on integrated metabolomics and transcriptome analysis on flavonoids and <lb/>anthocyanins biosynthesis of the fern Cyclosorus parasiticus. Front. Plant Sci. 12, 757516. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3389/fpls.2021.757516 PMID: 34777436 <lb/>53. Li L.L., Cheng H., Yuan H.H., Xu F., Cheng S.Y., Cao F.L., 2014. Functional characterization of the <lb/>Ginkgo biloba chalcone synthase gene promoter in transgenic tobacco. Genet. Mol. Res. 13(2), 3446-<lb/>3460. https://doi.org/10.4238/2014.April.30.6 PMID: 24841790 <lb/>54. Liou G., Chiang Y.C., Wang Y., Weng J. K., 2018. Mechanistic basis for the evolution of chalcone <lb/>synthase catalytic cysteine reactivity in land plants. J. Biol. Chem. 293(48), 18601-18612. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1074/jbc.RA118.005695 PMID: 30291143 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>55. Yu H. N., Liu X. Y., Gao S., Sun B., Zheng H. B., Ji M., et al. 2018. Structural and biochemical character-<lb/>ization of the plant type III polyketide synthases of the liverwort Marchantia paleacea. Plant Physiol. Bio-<lb/>chem. 125, 95-105. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2018.01.030 PMID: 29428820 <lb/>56. Liou G., Chiang Y. C., Wang Y., Weng J. K., 2018. Mechanistic basis for the evolution of chalcone <lb/>synthase catalytic cysteine reactivity in land plants. J. Biol. Chem. 293(48), 18601-18612. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1074/jbc.RA118.005695 PMID: 30291143 <lb/>57. Brazier-Hicks M., Edwards R., 2013. Metabolic engineering of the flavone-C-glycoside pathway using <lb/>polyprotein technology. Metab. Eng. 16, 11-20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymben.2012.11.004 PMID: <lb/>23246521 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Molecular cloning and functional analysis of 4CLs from Marchantia paleacea <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296079 January 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 19 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>