<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-17T17:05:40.454Z">11/17/2025 5:05:40 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-17T17:05:30.557866Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-17T17:05:30.557866Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Pharmacological induction of autophagy <lb/>reduces inflammation in macrophages by <lb/>degrading immunoproteasome subunits <lb/>Jiao Zhou ID <lb/>1,2☯ <lb/>, Chunxia Li 1☯ , Meng Lu 1 , Gaoyue Jiang 1 , Shanze Chen 3 , Huihui Li 4 , <lb/>Kefeng LuID 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Neurosurgery, State Key Laboratory of Biotherapy, West China Hospital, Sichuan University <lb/>and the Research Units of West China, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Chengdu, China, 2 National <lb/>Clinical Research Center for Geriatrics, West China Hospital, Sichuan University and Collaborative Innovation <lb/>Center of Biotherapy, Chengdu, China, 3 Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, First <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Southern University of Science and Technology, Second Clinical Medical College of <lb/>Jinan University, Shenzhen People&apos;s Hospital, Shenzhen Institute of Respiratory Diseases, Shenzhen, China, <lb/>4 West China Second University Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* lukf@scu.edu.cn <lb/>Abstract <lb/>AU : Pleaseconfirmthatallheadinglevelsarerepresentedcorrectly: <lb/>Defective autophagy is linked to proinflammatory diseases. However, the mechanisms by <lb/>which autophagy limits inflammation remain elusive. Here, we found that the pan-FGFR <lb/>inhibitor LY2874455 efficiently activated autophagy and suppressed expression of proin-<lb/>flammatory factors in macrophages stimulated by lipopolysaccharide (LPS). Multiplex prote-<lb/>omic profiling identified the immunoproteasome, which is a specific isoform of the 20s <lb/>constitutive proteasome, as a substrate that is degraded by selective autophagy. SQSTM1/ <lb/>p62 was found to be a selective autophagy-related receptor that mediated this degradation. <lb/>Autophagy deficiency or p62 knockdown blocked the effects of LY2874455, leading to the <lb/>accumulation of immunoproteasomes and increases in inflammatory reactions. Expression <lb/>of proinflammatory factors in autophagy-deficient macrophages could be reversed by immu-<lb/>noproteasome inhibitors, confirming the pivotal role of immunoproteasome turnover in the <lb/>autophagy-mediated suppression on the expression of proinflammatory factors. In mice, <lb/>LY2874455 protected against LPS-induced acute lung injury and dextran sulfate sodium <lb/>(DSS)-induced colitis and caused low levels of proinflammatory cytokines and immunopro-<lb/>teasomes. These findings suggested that selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/>was a key regulator of signaling via the innate immune system. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Inflammation is an essential immune response that enables survival during pathogenic micro-<lb/>organism infection or tissue injury [1,2]. Various extrinsic and intrinsic inflammatory stimuli <lb/>include infectious microorganisms (such as viruses and bacteria), cancer cells, or dead cells <lb/>[3-6]. Although inflammation is a vital component of a healthy immune response in the host, <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/>1 / 34 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Zhou J, Li C, Lu M, Jiang G, Chen S, Li H, <lb/>et al. (2024) Pharmacological induction of <lb/>autophagy reduces inflammation in macrophages <lb/>by degrading immunoproteasome subunits. PLoS <lb/>Biol 22(3): e3002537. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pbio.3002537 <lb/>Academic Editor: Hans-Uwe Simon, University of <lb/>Bern, SWITZERLAND <lb/>Received: February 5, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: February 5, 2024 <lb/>Published: March 6, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Zhou et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its Supporting Information <lb/>files. <lb/></front>

	<body>rampant inflammation results in various pathologies such as sepsis, rheumatoid arthritis, acute <lb/>lung injury, chronic respiratory diseases, inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), cancer, aging, <lb/>and even death [7-16]. One very recent example of inflammation-related disease is Coronavi-<lb/>rus Disease 2019 (COVID-19), which is caused by Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coro-<lb/>navirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Serious COVID-19 is associated with inflammation, and there is an <lb/>emphasis on cytokine storm syndrome [17-25]. Uncontrolled macrophage and monocyte acti-<lb/>vation in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection causes a rampant subsequent inflammatory <lb/>response that result in acute respiratory distress syndrome and end-organ injury, including <lb/>lung fibrosis [20,26,27]. Anti-inflammatory factor therapies have been used to inhibit the <lb/>development of cytokine storms in COVID-19 patients [28-32]. In addition to viruses, patho-<lb/>genic bacterial infection is also a robust cause of inflammation and death. Approximately 50% <lb/>of patients in intensive care units (ICUs) develop severe sepsis caused by bacterial infection, <lb/>and a 29% mortality rate has been shown in sepsis patients [33-35]. Mortality is mostly attrib-<lb/>uted to the cytotoxic effects of lipopolysaccharide (LPS) (endotoxin), a component of the outer <lb/>membrane of gram-negative bacteria [36-39]. Various and large numbers of inflammatory <lb/>factors, such as tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleukin-1β (IL-1β), and interleukin-6 <lb/>(IL-6), and high levels of intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS), are substantially induced <lb/>in LPS-stimulated macrophages both ex vivo and in vitro [40-44]. <lb/>The immunoproteasome is an important mediator of inflammation in immune cells such <lb/>as macrophages and nonimmune cells, and its expression is triggered by inflammatory signals <lb/>[45-57]. The immunoproteasome is a specific isoform of the 20s constitutive proteasome that <lb/>is quickly formed (in about 20 min) by replacing the β1, β2, and β5 subunits of the 20s protea-<lb/>some with different counterparts known as β1i (low molecular mass polypeptide 2, LMP2), β2i <lb/>(multi-catalytic endopeptidase complexlike-1, MECL-1, also known as LMP10), and β5i (low <lb/>molecular mass polypeptide 2, LMP7), while mixed proteasomes consisting of both, classical <lb/>and immunoproteasome subunits, can be formed [45,46,50,58]. Originally, the immunopro-<lb/>teasome was found to hydrolyse proteins into peptides loaded into the MHC-I complex as <lb/>antigens [47,59,60]. Apart from antigen processing, the immunoproteasome has been found to <lb/>promote macrophage polarization [61], brain inflammation [62-64], diabetic nephropathy <lb/>[65], the production of inflammatory cytokines [66-70], myometrium inflammation associ-<lb/>ated with preterm labor [71], diet-induced atherosclerosis [72], various inflammatory and <lb/>autoimmune diseases [66,68,73-78], colitis and colitis-associated cancers [79-82], viral infec-<lb/>tion [83-90], the activation of lymphocytes [91,92], and cardiac hypertrophy [93,94]. The <lb/>necessity of reducing excessive immunoproteasomes has been highlighted, and immunopro-<lb/>teasome inhibitors have become promising drug candidates for various diseases, such as hema-<lb/>tologic malignancies, autoimmune, and inflammatory diseases [95-102]. However, it is <lb/>unknown whether and how degradation of the immunoproteasome is achieved. <lb/>Macroautophagy (abbreviated as autophagy) is a catabolic pathway for bulk transport <lb/>through double-layered membrane vesicles (autophagosomes) and the eventual degradation of <lb/>intracellular components in lysosomes [103-106]. The autophagy pathway is highly conserved <lb/>among eukaryotic organisms and plays a fundamental role in various physiological and patho-<lb/>logical conditions [107-109]. The autophagy pathway is a dynamic process that functions to <lb/>maintain cellular homeostasis through the selective and bulk degradation of cytoplastic car-<lb/>goes such as toxic protein aggregates, unnecessary or damaged organelles, and intracellular <lb/>pathogens [110-113]. Autophagy dysfunction has been linked to several proinflammatory dis-<lb/>eases [114-118], such as rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, and IBD [119-122]. Variations in the <lb/>human autophagy genes ATG16L1, NOD2, IRGM, ATG5, and ATG7 is associated with <lb/>chronic inflammatory diseases including Crohn&apos;s disease [123-127]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<front>Funding: This work was supported by the National <lb/>Key R&amp;D Program of China under grant <lb/>2017YFA0506300 (to K.L.) and the National <lb/>Natural Science Foundation under grant 32022020 <lb/>(to K.L.) and 81902997 (to H.L.). The funders had <lb/>no role in study design, data collection and <lb/>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>Abbreviations: AU : Anabbreviationlisthasbeencompiledforthoseusedinthetext:Pleaseverifythatallentriesarecorrect: <lb/>BMDM, bone marrow-derived <lb/>macrophage; COVID-19, Coronavirus Disease <lb/>2019; DSS, dextran sulfate sodium; gRNA, guide <lb/>RNA; HE, hematoxylineosin; IBD, inflammatory <lb/>bowel disease; ICU, intensive care unit; iNOS, <lb/>inducible nitric oxide synthase; LMP2, low <lb/>molecular mass polypeptide; LPS, <lb/>lipopolysaccharide; NO, nitric oxide; PAMP, <lb/>pathogen-associated molecular pattern; PASEF, <lb/>parallel accumulation serial fragmentatio; PBS, <lb/>phosphate-buffered saline; PM, peritoneal <lb/>macrophage; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time <lb/>polymerase chain reaction; ROS, reactive oxygen <lb/>species; SARS-CoV-2, Severe Acute Respiratory <lb/>Syndrome Coronavirus 2; TNF-α, tumor necrosis <lb/>factor-α. <lb/></front>

	<body>Thus, it is important to clarify whether and how autophagy targets the immunoproteasome <lb/>for degradation and the involvement of this degradation in limiting inflammation. In the pres-<lb/>ent study, we identified the pan-FGFR inhibitor LY2874455 as an effective anti-inflammatory <lb/>treatment acting through the activation of autophagy. We utilized LPS-induced inflammatory <lb/>responses in murine macrophages as a functional screen and identified the pan-FGFR inhibi-<lb/>tor LY2874455 as an effective inhibitor of inflammation. We found that the stimulation of <lb/>autophagy by LY2874455 promoted the autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasomes <lb/>in LPS-induced macrophages. LY2874455 inhibited the AKT-mTOR axis to activate autop-<lb/>hagy, and autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome was mediated by the receptor <lb/>SQSTM1/p62. LY2874455-activated autophagy dramatically inhibited the production of <lb/>inflammatory cytokines, and blocking autophagy with inhibitors, ATG7 knockout, or knock-<lb/>down of the receptor p62 reversed this inhibition. The protective role of LY2874455-induced <lb/>autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome was verified by in vivo mouse models with <lb/>acute lung injury induced by LPS or with IBD induced by dextran sulfate sodium (DSS). These <lb/>findings suggested that selective autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome was a piv-<lb/>otal regulator of innate inflammatory signaling. <lb/>Results <lb/>The pan-FGFR inhibitor LY2874455 effectively suppressed expression of <lb/>proinflammatory factors in LPS-stimulated macrophages <lb/>Because numerous diseases are caused by rampant inflammation, we screened for chemicals <lb/>with potential suppressive effects on inflammation in the LPS-treated macrophage cell line <lb/>RAW264.7. Nitrous oxide (NO) levels were measured because NO is generated at increased <lb/>levels during inflammation [128]. RAW264.7 cells were cultured in 96-well plates and treated <lb/>with LPS and in total 5,618 compounds including the FDA-approved drug library (MedChem-<lb/>Express, Cat. HY-L022, 2669 compounds), PI3K/Akt/mTOR compound library (MedChem-<lb/>Express, Cat. HY-L015, 456 compounds), and kinase inhibitor library (MedChemExpress, Cat. <lb/>HY-L009, 2493 compounds). The NO concentration in the culture supernatant was measured <lb/>in a high-throughput manner with 3 replicate wells for each compound. We found that <lb/>LY2874455 was the most effective anti-inflammatory chemical by measuring NO levels (only <lb/>27 chemicals, including LY2874455, are shown and several other chemicals showed less effects) <lb/>(S1A and S1B Fig). LY2874455 ((R)-(E)-2-(4-(2-(5-(1-(3,5-dichloropyridin-4-yl) ethoxy)-1H-<lb/>indazol-3yl) vinyl)-1H-pyrazol-1-yl) ethanol) (Fig 1A) is a novel pan-FGFR inhibitor that <lb/>shows good tolerability and activity in solid organ cancer patients [129,130]. In addition to <lb/>suppressing NO generation in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophages without affecting cell <lb/>viabilities (Figs 1B, S1C and S1D), LY2874455 also reduced the levels of ROS (shown by <lb/>DCFH-DA staining) in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells (Fig 1C and 1D). The levels of proin-<lb/>flammatory cytokines, such as tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) and interleukin-6 (IL-6), and <lb/>inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) were dramatically induced by LPS in RAW264.7 mac-<lb/>rophages, and LY2874455 completely reversed this effect (Figs 1E-1H and S1E-S1H). Sup-<lb/>pression on the expression of proinflammatory factors by LY2874455 was repeatedly observed <lb/>in peritoneal macrophages (PMs) (S1I-S1M Fig) and bone marrow-derived macrophages <lb/>(BMDMs) (S1N-S1R Fig) obtained from mice [131,132] and in human THP-1 monocytes <lb/>(S1S and S1T Fig). Beside the mRNA levels, the protein levels of inflammatory factors induced <lb/>by LPS treatment were also reduced by LY2874455 treatment (S1U and S1V Fig). NF-κB sig-<lb/>naling is a classic proinflammatory regulator that mediates the induction of various inflamma-<lb/>tory cytokines [133-136]. The IκB kinase (IKK) complex, which contains IKK-α, IKK-β, and <lb/>IKK-γ, activates the inflammatory transcription factor NF-κB. IKK-β phosphorylates <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 1. AU : AbbreviationlistshavebeencompiledforthoseusedinFigs1to6:Pleaseverifythatallentriesarecorrect: <lb/>LY2874455 attenuated the inflammatory reactions in LPS-stimulated macrophages. (A) The chemical structure of LY2874455. <lb/>(B-K) Macrophage RAW264.7 cells were stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h together with or without LY2874455 (2 μm). (B) <lb/>LY2874455 abolished the release of NO from LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. NO concentration in culture supernatant was measured <lb/>and shown as fold change compared to the control group. Similar results were obtained from 3 independent replicated experiments. <lb/>**P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001. (C) LY2874455 abolished the generation of ROS in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. After treatment with LPS <lb/>or/and LY2874455, RAW264.7 cells were washed and labeled with DCFH-DA, a ROS probe. Quantitative measurement of cellular <lb/>DCFH-DA staining was performed by flow cytometry. Similar results were obtained from 3 independent experiments. (D) A set of <lb/>representative images showing fluorescent staining of ROS by DCFH-DA probe were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. (E-G) LY2874455 <lb/>suppressed the expression of proinflammatory cytokines and NO synthetase in macrophages stimulated with LPS. The expression of <lb/>proinflammatory cytokine genes (IL-6, TNF-α) and NO synthetase (iNOS) was checked by qRT-PCR. (H-J) Total proteins were <lb/>extracted from RAW264.7 cells and used for western blot analysis of protein levels of IL6, TNF-α, iNOS, IKK-β, p65, and phosphorylated <lb/>p65 (p-p65). For the similar experiments shown by immunoblots, 3 independent experiments were conducted and representative images <lb/>were shown. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed (S1W-S1AE Fig). (K) <lb/>LY2874455 suppressed the nucleus translocation of phosphorylated p65 in macrophages stimulated with LPS. RAW264.7 cells were <lb/>stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) for 2 h with or without LY2874455 (2 μm). Representative images of double immunostaining for p65 and <lb/>nucleus (DAPI) were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. <lb/>The data underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase; LPS, <lb/>lipopolysaccharide; NO, nitric oxide; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; ROS, reactive oxygen species. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>inhibitory IκBα to promote its polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation, and then the <lb/>classic p65/p50 heterodimer is freed to translocate to the nucleus and mediate the transcription <lb/>of NF-κB target genes, including various cytokines. The LPS-induced protein levels of IKK-β <lb/>in RAW264.7 cells were reduced by LY2874455 (Fig 1I). The activated form of p65 (phosphor-<lb/>ylated) and its translocation into the nucleus were also reversed by LY2874455 in LPS-stimu-<lb/>lated RAW264.7 cells (Fig 1J and 1K). <lb/>Taken together, these results demonstrated that the pan-FGFR inhibitor LY2874455 effec-<lb/>tively suppressed the inflammatory responses in LPS-stimulated macrophages. <lb/>LY2874455 suppressed lung and intestinal inflammation in mouse models <lb/>After demonstrating the suppressive effect of LY2874455 on production of proinflammatory <lb/>factors at the cellular level, we then analyzed whether LY2874455 could affect inflammatory <lb/>mouse models with acute lung injury and septicopyemia induced by LPS [137,138] or with <lb/>IBD induced by DSS. Histological examination of the lungs of mice stimulated with LPS <lb/>revealed considerable inflammatory cell infiltration, which is a typical symptom of lung <lb/>inflammation (Fig 2A). Notably, inflammatory cell infiltration was reduced by LY2874455 <lb/>(Fig 2A). The LPS-induced high levels of the proinflammatory cytokine IL-6 in the lung tissues <lb/>of mice were also significantly reduced by LY2874455 (Fig 2B). In addition, survival analysis <lb/>of LPS-stimulated mice with or without LY2874455 treatment was measured. The survival rate <lb/>was 100% in the control group but dropped notably in the LPS-treated group, while the sur-<lb/>vival rate was dramatically increased in mice treated with LY2874455 (Fig 2C). These results <lb/>indicated that LY2874455 suppressed inflammation in mice with acute lung injury and septic <lb/>pyemia induced by LPS and promoted survival in LPS-treated mice. <lb/>Furthermore, DSS-induced colitis model mice were used to analyze the potential gastroin-<lb/>testinal protective effects of LY2874455 (Fig 2D and 2E). The results showed that LY2874455 <lb/>notably ameliorated the reduction in colon length in DSS-treated mice (Fig 2F). To confirm <lb/>the effect of LY2874455 on bowel inflammation and tissue injury, colonic sections of mice <lb/>were subjected to histological examination. DSS caused severe damage to the mucosa of intes-<lb/>tinal villi, and LY2874455 treatment efficiently reduced tissue damage (Fig 2G and 2H). The <lb/>expression levels of the proinflammatory cytokines were reduced in colonic tissues from <lb/>LY2874455-treated mice (Fig 2I-2L), which indicated the suppressive effect of LY2874455 on <lb/>inflammation in colitis model mice. The suppression effects on expression of inflammatory <lb/>factors by LY2874455 were in a wide-range manner, as it also showed suppressive effects upon <lb/>polyI:C treatment (S2A-S2C Fig), bacteria treatment (S2D-S2F Fig), and H 2 O 2 treatment <lb/>(S2G-S2K Fig). LY2874455 also inhibited inflammasome-mediated cytokine (IL18) induction <lb/>(Fig 2L), which was in line with previous studies on Inflammasome regulation by autophagy. <lb/>LY2874455 reduced the protein levels of immunoproteasomes in LPS-<lb/>stimulated macrophages <lb/>To determine the mechanism by which LY2874455 suppresses inflammatory responses, mass <lb/>spectrometry-based proteomics analysis was performed on RAW264.7 macrophages treated <lb/>with LPS and LY2874455 (S2 Table and Fig 3A, upper panel). Clustering of the altered pro-<lb/>teins suggested that the immunoproteasome-specific subunits were down-regulated by <lb/>LY2874455 treatment (arrow pointed out in Fig 3A, lower panel). Under inflammatory condi-<lb/>tions such as LPS stimulation, the immunoproteasome-specific subunits β1i/LMP2, β2i/ <lb/>MECL-1/LMP10, and β5i/LMP7 replaced the original β1, β2, and β5 subunits of the 20s pro-<lb/>teasome, leading to the formation of immunoproteasomes (schemed in Fig 3B and 3C). The <lb/>function of the immunoproteasome in NF-κB pathway was confirmed by the observation that <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. LY2874455 suppressed lung and intestine inflammation in mouse models. (A) LY2874455 reduced immune cell <lb/>infiltration in lung tissues from acute lung injury mouse models induced by LPS. Two-month-old male C57BL/6J mice <lb/>were subject to intragastric administration with LY2874455 (1 mg/kg) and/or intraperitoneal injection with LPS (10 mg/ <lb/>kg) for 6 h (n = 6). Afterwards, upper lobe of right lungs was collected for HE staining and representative images were <lb/>displayed. Scale bar: 100 μm. (B) LY2874455 suppressed the expression of inflammatory cytokine IL-6 in acute lung <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914 efficiently blocked the nucleus translocation of p65 <lb/>(S3A Fig). The function of immunoproteasome in NF-κB pathway was suggested to be not <lb/>through degrading p-IκB-α (S3B Fig). Instead, immunoproteasome may function in NF-κB <lb/>pathway through regulating the upstream signaling steps that promotes the phosphorylation <lb/>of IκB-α (S3C Fig). The exact mechanism of immunoproteasome in regulating the NF-κB <lb/>pathway has been elusive. We analyzed the NF-κB pathway in the presence of LY2874455 or <lb/>ONX-0914 by analyzing the components function in NF-κB pathway. LY2874455 or ONX-<lb/>0914 caused the reduction of protein levels of TRAF6 and TAK1 (S3D and S3E Fig). These <lb/>results suggested that immunoproteasome may regulate the TRAF6-TAK1 phase in NF-κB <lb/>pathway. Further, the same effects of LY2874455 and ONX-0914 suggested that LY2874455 <lb/>suppressed the inflammation pathway through immunoproteasome. <lb/>We confirmed the proteomics results and found that LY2874455 indeed reduced the pro-<lb/>tein levels of the immunoproteasome subunits LMP2, LMP7, and LMP10 in LPS-stimulated <lb/>RAW264.7 macrophages (Fig 3D). In contrast, the protein levels of constitutive proteasome <lb/>subunits (PSMB1, PSMB5, PSMB6, and PSMB7) in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophages <lb/>were not affected by LY2874455 (Figs 3E and S3G). Similar results were also obtained in PMs <lb/>isolated from mice (Fig 3F and 3G). Moreover, the catalytic activities of immunoproteasome <lb/>subunits (LMP2, LMP7, and LMP10) in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophages were also <lb/>reduced by LY2874455 (Figs 3H and S3F). ONX-0914 has been reported as the specific inhibi-<lb/>tor of the immunoproteasome [71]. We confirmed that ONX-0914 effectively suppressed the <lb/>inflammatory responses in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophages by measuring the expres-<lb/>sion of the proinflammatory cytokines TNF-α and IL-6 (Fig 3I and 3J). More importantly, <lb/>additional treatment with LY2874455 did not further repress expression of proinflammatory <lb/>factors in ONX-0914-treated macrophages (Fig 3I and 3J). This result indicated that <lb/>LY2874455 repressed expression of proinflammatory factors, which was speculated to be <lb/>mediated by lowering the protein levels of immunoproteasomes. <lb/>LY2874455 activated autophagy <lb/>We then tried to determine the mechanism by which LY2874455 reduces the protein levels of <lb/>immunoproteasome subunits (equivalent to immunoproteasomes). The ubiquitin-protea-<lb/>some and autophagy-lysosome systems have been reported to be the 2 main mechanisms of <lb/>cytoplastic degradation [139]. In the 2 intracellular degradation pathways (the proteasome <lb/>pathway and the autophagy pathway), large substrates are generally targeted for autophagic <lb/>degradation. We blocked these 2 degradation pathways using proteasome inhibitor MG132 <lb/>and autophagy inhibitors chloroquine (CQ) and wortmannin (targeting Class III PI3K, VPS34 <lb/>injury mouse models induced by LPS. Two-month-old male C57BL/6J mice were treated as in (A), and relative mRNA <lb/>levels of IL-6 in lung tissues (lower lobe of right lungs) were analyzed by qRT-PCR (n = 6). (C) Two-month-old male <lb/>C57BL/6J mice were subject to intragastric administration with LY2874455 (1 mg/kg) and/or intraperitoneal injection <lb/>with LPS (35 mg/kg) (n = 8). The survival test results were presented as Kaplan-Meier survival curves. LY2874455 <lb/>reduced inflammatory injury in intestine tissues from DSS salt-induced inflammatory bowel mouse models. (D) Two-<lb/>month-old male C57BL/6J mice were subject to intragastric administration with 3% DSS for 7 days and with LY2874455 <lb/>(1 mg/kg) from the third day (n = 8). (E) The body weight was recorded and quantified. (F) The length of the colons was <lb/>shown by representative pictures and quantification data. (G) LY2874455 reduced intestine injury caused by DSS-<lb/>induced colitis. Colonic tissues from indicated mice were subject to HE staining. Representative images were shown <lb/>(n = 8). Scale bar: 100 μm. (H) The histological score was evaluated. (I-L) LY2874455 reduced the levels of inflammatory <lb/>cytokine genes induced in DSS-induced mouse models. The expression of inflammatory cytokine genes IL-17 and TNF-α <lb/>was checked by qRT-PCR in colons from indicated mice (n = 8). *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: <lb/>P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>DSS, dextran sulfate sodium; HE, hematoxylineosin; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time <lb/>polymerase chain reaction. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 3. LY2874455 reduced the protein levels of immunoproteasome-specific subunits in LPS-stimulated macrophages. (A) Above, <lb/>method diagram of mass spectrometry-based proteomics analysis of RAW264.7 cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) or/and LY2874455. The <lb/>original mass spectrometry proteomics data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository <lb/>with the dataset identifier PXD038747. Bottom, heat map of protein levels of proteasome subunits. The protein levels of <lb/>immunoproteasome-specific subunits (arrow pointed) were specifically reduced by LY2874455 treatment. (B, C) The diagram and names of <lb/>the specific subunit of 20s constitutive proteasome and immunoproteasome. (D) LY2874455 reduced the protein levels of <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>that uses PtdIns as a substrate to produce PtdIns3P, a lipid material for autophagosome forma-<lb/>tion [140,141]), and then analyzed the protein levels of immunoproteasome subunits. Protea-<lb/>some inhibitor MG132 and autophagy inhibitors CQ and wortmannin were checked for their <lb/>effects on cell viability and the concentrations without affecting cell viability were used (S4A <lb/>Fig). Western blot analysis showed that MG132 cannot inhibit the LY2874455-induced reduc-<lb/>tions in LMP2 and LMP7 expression in PM or in RAW264.7 (Figs 4A and S4B), whereas the <lb/>decrease induced by LY2874455 was markedly reversed by CQ or wortmannin (Figs 4B, 4C <lb/>and S4C). This result thus suggested that immunoproteasome degradation induced by <lb/>LY2874455 was more dependent on autophagy than the ubiquitin-proteasome system. <lb/>These findings also suggested that LY2874455 can induce autophagy. Autophagic flux <lb/>assays were conducted by measuring the dot signal of the fusion protein mCherry-EGFP-LC3 <lb/>[142]. GFP signal is quenched upon autophagosome-lysosome fusion, but the mCherry signal <lb/>is not affected, therefore the red signal indicates autophagy activation. The high intensity of <lb/>the mCherry signal and low GFP signal induced by LY2874455 indicated that LY2874455 acti-<lb/>vated autophagy (Fig 4D). Transmission electron microscopy showed many more autophago-<lb/>somes in RAW264.7 macrophages treated with LY2874455 than in control cells (Fig 4E). p62/ <lb/>SQSTM1 is an autophagic receptor that recruits substrates (usually ubiquitinated substrates) <lb/>into autophagosomes, and it is degraded together with the substrates after the autophagosome <lb/>fuses with the lysosome [143]. The protein levels of autophagy substrate p62 were reduced <lb/>with the addition of LY2874455, while the levels of the autophagosome marker LC3-II were <lb/>increased by LY2874455 treatment (Fig 4F). Autophagy inhibitor Bafilomycin A1 reversed the <lb/>effects of LY2874455 (Fig 4F). These results suggested the activation of autophagy by <lb/>LY2874455. LPS stimulation caused the accumulation of p62 (Fig 4G), indicating that LPS <lb/>blocked autophagy, which was consistent with the observation that LPS reduced autophagic <lb/>flux (Fig 4D, yellow signal in LPS cells). LY2874455 effectively reduced the protein levels of <lb/>p62 in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophages (Fig 4G). In PMs and BMDMs isolated from <lb/>mice, LY2874455 also reduced the protein levels of p62 (Fig 4H and 4I). These results con-<lb/>firmed the role of LY2874455 in activating autophagy. <lb/>FGFRs are transmembrane RTKs and activated by FGF to form dimers, leading to the acti-<lb/>vation of downstream FRS2 complex and subsequent activation of PI3K/AKT/mTOR signal-<lb/>ing pathway [144-147]. mTOR targets ULK1 but inhibits the activation of the complex <lb/>through inhibitory phosphorylation [141,148]. We found that LY2874455 reduced the levels of <lb/>AKT-mTOR signaling, as shown by the low levels of mTOR and AKT phosphorylation upon <lb/>LPS-induced activation (Fig 4J). This LY2874455-mediated inhibition of the AKT-mTOR sig-<lb/>naling pathway further indicated its ability to support activation through inhibition of AKT-<lb/>immunoproteasome specific subunits. Protein levels of immunoproteasome subunits LMP2, LMP7, LMP10, and control GAPDH were <lb/>analyzed in RAW264.7 cells treated with LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. The blots were quantified with densitometric <lb/>values and statistical significance was analyzed in S3 Fig. (E) LY2874455 had no effect on the protein levels of constitutive proteasome-<lb/>specific subunits. Protein levels of constitutive proteasome subunits PSMB5, PSMB6, PSMB7, and control GAPDH were analyzed. The blots <lb/>were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (F) PMs from C57BL/6J mice were obtained and treated <lb/>with LPS (20 ng/ml) and/or LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. The total proteins were extracted to detect the protein levels of immunoproteasome <lb/>subunits LMP2, LMP7, LMP10, and GAPDH. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. <lb/>(G) Protein levels of constitutive proteasome subunits PSMB5, PSMB6, PSMB7, and GAPDH were detected. The blots were quantified with <lb/>densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (H) The enzymatic activities of immunoproteasome subunits LMP2 and <lb/>LMP7 were measured in RAW264.7 cells. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001. (I, J) LY2874455 could not cause further repression on <lb/>inflammation in macrophages with inhibited immunoproteasome. The specific inhibitor of immunoproteasome, ONX-0914, suppressed <lb/>expression of inflammatory cytokines in macrophages stimulated with LPS. Additional treatment with LY2874455 could not cause further <lb/>inflammation-repression. The expression of inflammatory cytokine genes (TNF-α and IL-6) was checked by qRT-PCR in RAW264.7 cells <lb/>treated with LPS, the immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914(1 μm) and LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. ***: P &lt; 0.001. NS: no statistical <lb/>difference. The data underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. LPS, lipopolysaccharide; PM, peritoneal <lb/>macrophage; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 4. LY2874455 activated the autophagy process. (A) Proteasome inhibitor MG132 cannot block the reduction of <lb/>immunoproteasome subunits induced by LY2874455. Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were analyzed in RAW264.7 <lb/>cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and MG132 (5 μm). The blots were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (B, C) Autophagy inhibitors blocked the reduction of immunoproteasome subunits <lb/>induced by LY2874455. Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were analyzed in RAW264.7 cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ <lb/>ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and autophagy inhibitors chloroquine (CQ, 20 μm) or wortmannin (100 nM). The blots were <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>mTOR signaling. LY2874455 suppresses the FGFR activities and the downstream PI3K/AKT/ <lb/>mTOR signaling pathway, leading to the release and activation of autophagy (schemed in S4D <lb/>Fig). In fibroblast cells, LY2874455 also reduced the protein levels of the autophagic substrate <lb/>p62 while increased the protein levels of the autophagosome marker LC3-II (S4E Fig). <lb/>Another FGFR inhibitor ADZ4547 also reduced the protein levels of p62, LMP2, and LMP7 <lb/>and inhibited the expression of inflammatory factors (S4F-S4I Fig). Other chemicals in our <lb/>screen that inhibited the expression of proinflammatory factors induced by LPS (S1B Fig) <lb/>showed either promotion or inhibition on the autophagic degradation of p62 (S4J Fig), sug-<lb/>gesting the effects of LY2874455 on suppression of expression of proinflammatory factors and <lb/>autophagy induction were specific. <lb/>LY2874455 promoted the degradation of immunoproteasomes through <lb/>autophagy and the selective receptor p62 <lb/>For further validation of the effect of LY2874455 on promoting the degradation of immuno-<lb/>proteasomes through autophagy, ATG7, an essential gene in autophagy, was knocked out in <lb/>RAW264.7 cells, which resulted in blocked autophagy, an increase in p62 and deficiency in the <lb/>activated form of LC3 (LC3-II) (S5A Fig). Then, the protein levels of the immunoproteasome <lb/>subunits LMP2 and LMP7 were analyzed. In ATG7-knockout (ATG7-KO) RAW264.7 cells, <lb/>the protein levels of LMP2 and LMP7 were increased compared to those in WT cells (Fig 5A). <lb/>While the protein levels of LMP2 and LMP7 were reduced by LY2874455 in WT cells, this <lb/>effect was abolished in ATG7-KO cells (Fig 5B and 5C). We examined the localization of <lb/>autophagosomes and the immunoproteasome. The results showed that an autophagosome <lb/>marker (LC3 dots) colocalized with LMP2 and LMP7 (Fig 5D). Collectively, these results dem-<lb/>onstrated that LY2874455 induced the selective capture and degradation of immunoprotea-<lb/>somes via autophagy. <lb/>Generally, selective targeting of substrates into autophagosomes is mediated by receptors <lb/>that link cargos to autophagosomes and are degraded together with the substrates after autop-<lb/>hagic transfer into lysosomes. We then analyzed 3 previously reported receptors and found <lb/>that p62 behaved similarly to LMP2 and LMP7 in RAW264.7 cells, was increased by LPS treat-<lb/>ment and decreased by further LY2874455 treatment (Fig 5E). Knockdown of p62 in <lb/>RAW264.7 cells led to increased protein levels of LMP2 and LMP7 (Figs 5F and S5B Fig). <lb/>quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (D) LY2874455 enhanced autophagy flux. <lb/>RAW264.7 cells transfected with mCherry-EGFP-LC3 were stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) or/and LY2874455 for another 24 h, <lb/>and the puncta of LC3 in cells was monitored after fixation under a confocal fluorescent microscope. Higher level of mCherry-<lb/>LC3 signal and lower level of EGFP-LC3 signal (showing red in merge) indicated the stimulated autophagy flux, while the <lb/>similar signal levels of mCherry-LC3 and GFP-L3 (showing yellow in merge) indicated the blocked autophagy flux. <lb/>Representative images from 3 replicated experiments were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. (E) LY2874455 promoted the formation of <lb/>autophagosomes. RAW264.7 cells treated with control or LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h were analyzed by transmission electron <lb/>microscopy. Autophagosomes were pointed by arrows and representative images from 3 replicated experiments were shown. <lb/>Scale bars: 1 μm. (F) LY2874455 promoted the autophagic degradation of substrate receptor p62. RAW264.7 cells were treated <lb/>with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 (0.5, 2, 4 μm) with or without Bafilomycin A1 (20 nM) for 24 h and protein levels of p62, <lb/>LC3, and GAPDH were analyzed by western blot. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical <lb/>significance was analyzed. (G) Protein levels of p62 and GAPDH were detected by western blot in RAW264.7 cells treated with <lb/>LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) and for 24 h. The blot was quantified with densitometric values and statistical <lb/>significance was analyzed. (H) Protein levels of p62 and GAPDH were detected by western blot in PMs from C57BL/6J mice <lb/>treated as in (G). The blot was quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (I) Protein levels of <lb/>p62 and GAPDH were detected by western blot in BMDMs from C57BL/6J mice treated as in (G). The blot was quantified with <lb/>densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (J) LY2874455 inhibited the AKT-mTOR signaling. Protein levels <lb/>of p-mTOR (Ser248), mTOR, p-AKT (Ser473), AKT, and GAPDH were detected by western blot in RAW264.7 cells treated as <lb/>in (G). The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, <lb/>***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. BMDM, bone marrow-derived macrophage; LPS, <lb/>lipopolysaccharide; PM, peritoneal macrophage. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 5. LY2874455 promoted the degradation of immunoproteasomes through autophagy and selective receptor p62. (A) Autophagy <lb/>deficiency caused increased levels of immunoproteasome subunits. Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were detected by western blot <lb/>in WT or ATG7 knock out (ATG7-KO, through CRISPR-CAS9 method) RAW264.7 cells. The blots were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (B, C) LY2874455 could not reduce the protein levels of immunoproteasome subunits in autophagy-<lb/>deficient macrophages. WT or ATG7-KO RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) alone or together with LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. <lb/>Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, p62, and GAPDH were analyzed by western blot. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and <lb/>statistical significance was analyzed. (D) Immunoproteasome subunits colocalized with autophagosome marker LC3. RAW264.7 cells <lb/>expressing mCherry-tagged LC3 and GFP-tagged LMP2 or LMP7 were stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. The <lb/>colocalization of GFP-LMP2/GFP-LMP7 with mCherry-LC3 was observed by confocal fluorescent microscope. Scale bars: 10 μm. (E) <lb/>LY2874455 reduced the protein levels of selective autophagy receptor p62. RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 <lb/>(2 μm) for 24 h, and then the protein levels of NBR1, Tollip, p62, and GAPDH were detected by western blot. The blots were quantified with <lb/>densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (F) Knockdown of p62 caused increase of protein levels of immunoproteasome <lb/>subunits. The protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were detected by western blot in control shRNA or p62-targeting shRNA <lb/>transfected RAW264.7 cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. The blots were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (G) Immunoproteasome subunits were ubiquitinated. RAW264.7 cells expressing GFP-LMP2 or <lb/>GFP-LMP7 were treated with LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. Then, equal amounts of protein lysates were subject to immunoprecipitation with <lb/>anti-GFP affinity beads and analyzed by western blot with anti-GFP and anti-ubiquitin antibodies. (H, I) p62 interacted with <lb/>immunoproteasome subunits through its ubiquitin-binding UBA domain. RAW264.7 cells expressing GFP-LMP2, GFP-LMP7, and Flag-<lb/>tagged full-length p62 or truncated p62 (ubiquitin-binding domain UBA deleted) were subject to immunoprecipitation with anti-GFP affinity <lb/>beads and then analyzed by western blot with anti-GFP and anti-Flag antibodies. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: <lb/>no statistical difference. LPS, lipopolysaccharide; WT, wild type. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>These results indicated p62 was the receptor protein for the autophagic degradation of immu-<lb/>noproteasomes. Substrate ubiquitination is necessary for selective targeting by the autophagy <lb/>receptor p62. Indeed, LMP2 and LMP7 were ubiquitinated (Fig 5G). Furthermore, LMP2 and <lb/>LMP7 could interact with p62, and this interaction was shown to be dependent on the UBA <lb/>domain (ubiquitin-associated domain for ubiquitin binding) of p62 (Fig 5H and 5I). Thus, <lb/>these results indicated p62 was the receptor that mediated the autophagic degradation of <lb/>immunoproteasomes. <lb/>LY2874455 suppressed expression of proinflammatory factors though the <lb/>autophagy pathway <lb/>Now that we have shown that LY2874455 induced the autophagic degradation of immunopro-<lb/>teasomes, we then examined whether the suppressive effect of LY2874455 on expression of <lb/>proinflammatory factors occurred through the autophagy pathway. The LPS-induced increase <lb/>in ROS levels (shown by the DCFH-DA probe) in RAW264.7 cells was abolished by <lb/>LY2874455; however, this abolishment was blocked by the autophagy inhibitor wortmannin <lb/>(Fig 6A). Moreover, increased mRNA levels of iNOS and IL-6 were observed in wortmannin-<lb/>treated RAW264.7 cells compared to LY2874455-treated RAW264.7 cells (Fig 6B and 6C), <lb/>mouse-isolated primary macrophages (Fig 6D and 6E), and BMDMs (S6A and S6B Fig). <lb/>These results suggested that LY2874455 suppressed expression of proinflammatory factors <lb/>through induction of autophagy. This finding was further confirmed by the observation that <lb/>ATG7 knockout or p62 knockdown led to increased levels of iNOS and IL-6 in the presence of <lb/>LPS and LY2874455 (Fig 6F and 6G). The effects of LY2874455 suppression on NF-κB path-<lb/>way was also shown to be dependent on autophagy and receptor p62, as in autophagy-(S6C-<lb/>S6F Fig) or p62-deficient (S6G and S6H Fig) macrophages, LY2874455 cannot suppress NF-<lb/>κB pathway. Autophagy inhibitors reversed the effects of LY2874455 (S6J and S6K Fig), fur-<lb/>ther indicating that LY2874455 suppressed expression of proinflammatory factors through <lb/>autophagy. <lb/>Together with the data showing that LY2874455 induced the autophagic degradation of <lb/>immunoproteasomes, these results indicated the possibility that the increased expression of <lb/>proinflammatory factors in autophagy-deficient cells may be caused by the accumulation of <lb/>autophagic substrate immunoproteasomes. The immunoproteasome-specific inhibitor ONX-<lb/>0914 was then used to treat ATG7-KO RAW264.7 cells, and the expression levels of iNOS and <lb/>the proinflammatory cytokines IL-6 and TNF-α were analyzed. The results showed that the <lb/>immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914 dramatically reduced expression of proinflamma-<lb/>tory factors in autophagy-deficient cells (Figs 6H-6J and S6I Fig), indicating that the activated <lb/>immunoproteasome in autophagy-deficient cells induced expression of proinflammatory fac-<lb/>tors. In LMP7 knockdown cells, ONX-0914 did not inhibit the expression levels of inflamma-<lb/>tory factor (S6L and S6M Fig), indicating the specific effects of ONX-0914 on <lb/>immunoproteasome. <lb/>Hence, these results indicated that the suppressive effect of LY2874455 on expression of <lb/>proinflammatory factors was dependent on the induction of the autophagic degradation of <lb/>immunoproteasomes. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>It has been found that disruption of autophagy leads to diseases with inflammatory compo-<lb/>nents, including infections, autoimmunity and metabolic disorders [149-153]. Autophagy <lb/>restricts inflammation through various mechanisms by targeting inflammatory mediators <lb/>including inflammasomes, STING and MAVS for cytosolic pathogen-associated molecular <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 6. LY2874455 suppressed inflammation though autophagy pathway. (A) Autophagy inhibitor reversed the effect of <lb/>LY2874455 on ROS-reduction in LPS-stimulated macrophages. RAW264.7 cells were stained with ROS-probe DCFH-DA <lb/>after treatment with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and wortmannin (100 nM) as indicated for 24 h. Quantitative <lb/>measurement of cellular ROS was performed by flow cytometry. (B, C) Autophagy inhibitor reversed the effect of <lb/>LY2874455 in LPS-stimulated macrophages. The expression of inflammatory cytokine genes (iNOS and IL-6) was checked <lb/>by qRT-PCR in RAW264.7 cells treated as (A). (D, E) The expression of inflammatory cytokine IL-6 and iNOS was checked <lb/>by qRT-PCR in PMs as treated as in (A). (F) Autophagy deficiency reversed the effect of LY2874455 in inflammatory <lb/>macrophages. WT or ATG7 knock out (ATG7-KO) RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 <lb/>(2 μm) for 24 h. The expression of iNOS and IL-6 was checked by qRT-PCR and expressed as fold changes compared to <lb/>values in WT cells. (G) p62 knock down reversed the effect of LY2874455 in inflammatory macrophages. Control (sh-CTL, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>pattern (PAMP) recognition [154-162]. In the present study, we uncovered the role and mech-<lb/>anism of the pan-FGFR inhibitor LY2874455 in suppression of production of proinflamma-<lb/>tory factors. In macrophages stimulated with LPS, immunoproteasomes were induced and <lb/>then triggered NF-κB-mediated inflammatory responses, leading to robust expression and <lb/>generation of proinflammatory cytokines, ROS, and NO. In the presence of LY2874455, the <lb/>autophagy pathway was activated and captured immunoproteasomes, and this effect was <lb/>mediated by the selective receptor p62 recognizing ubiquitin signals on immunoproteasomes. <lb/>This autophagic degradation reduced the abundance of immunoproteasomes and thus blocked <lb/>the activity of NF-κB and eventually suppressed inflammation. Our work here reveals a novel <lb/>mechanism by which autophagy suppresses inflammation, which may substantially contribute <lb/>to the development of new therapeutic approaches for inflammatory diseases. <lb/>Currently, it is unclear how the induction and autophagic degradation of immunoprotea-<lb/>somes are coordinated. We hypothesize that inflammatory stimuli such as LPS may induce the <lb/>expression, assembly, and increased abundance of immunoproteasomes, while LPS inhibits <lb/>the autophagy pathway, as shown by the increased protein levels of the receptor p62 (Fig 4F-<lb/>4I). This result suggests that LPS not only induces the production of the immunoproteasome <lb/>but also prohibits its autophagic degradation, which consequently causes the accumulation of <lb/>the immunoproteasome and eventual rampant inflammation. The high level of immunopro-<lb/>teasome-induced inflammation provides efficacious signals to remind the host of toxic stimuli <lb/>and thus activate host responses [57]. However, the host benefits from intense inflammation-<lb/>induced signals and simultaneously suffers from inflammation-induced damage, especially <lb/>under severe/acute or chronic inflammatory conditions. Thus, the balance between moderate <lb/>and controllable inflammation is essential in maintaining host health. Here, we propose a <lb/>mechanism to explain how autophagy functions to break rampant inflammation. The selective <lb/>autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome in macrophages suppressed the production <lb/>of proinflammatory factors (S6R Fig). <lb/>LY2874455, a novel pan-FGFR inhibitor, was shown to have good tolerability, absorbance, <lb/>and activity in solid organ cancer patients in a Phase I clinical study [130]. Thus, LY2874455 <lb/>could be a good therapeutic candidate for inflammation-related diseases such as sepsis and <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease. <lb/>In addition to the regulation of acute inflammation, autophagy has been shown to positively <lb/>alleviate chronic inflammation-related neurodegenerative disorders such as Alzheimer&apos;s dis-<lb/>ease, Parkinson&apos;s disease, and depression [163,164]. An overwhelming number of studies have <lb/>connected autophagy in neurons to degenerative diseases; however, there are only sporadic <lb/>hints of inflammatory connections via autophagy. Recently, it was shown that LPS could <lb/>impair autophagy and relieve autophagic inhibition of the inflammatory machinery in micro-<lb/>glia, a specific type of macrophage in the central nervous system [165-167]. Autophagy-defi-<lb/>cient microglia show impaired phagocytic capacities and the overproduction of <lb/>proinflammatory cytokines, which can lead to synaptic dysfunction, neuronal death, and the <lb/>inhibition of neurogenesis [168]. It will be interesting to examine whether autophagic <lb/>control shRNA) or p62 knockdown (sh-p62, p62-targeting shRNA) RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and <lb/>LY2874455 (2 μm) for 24 h. The expression of iNOS and IL-6 was checked by qRT-PCR and expressed as fold changes <lb/>compared to values in control cells. (H-J) The enhanced production of proinflammatory factors in autophagy-deficient <lb/>macrophages was suppressed by immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914. WT or ATG7 knockout (ATG7-KO) RAW264.7 <lb/>cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and ONX-0914 (1 μm). The expression of iNOS and inflammatory cytokine genes (IL-6 <lb/>and TNF-α) was checked by qRT-PCR. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical <lb/>difference. The data underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. iNOS, inducible nitric oxide <lb/>synthase; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; PM, peritoneal macrophage; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; <lb/>ROS, reactive oxygen species; WT, wild type. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>degradation of the immunoproteasome shows anti-inflammatory effect in microglia and <lb/>whether and how much this dysregulation contributes to neurodegenerative diseases. <lb/>Cautiously, while in some cases defective autophagy causes excessive inflammation that <lb/>leads to disease pathology, there are certain situations in which elevated inflammation pro-<lb/>motes survival of model animals. For example, myeloid-specific knockout of autophagy genes <lb/>(RB1CC1, ATG5, ATG7, or ATG14) caused increased inflammation in the lungs and facili-<lb/>tated resistance to influenza virus infection in animals [169]. Additionally, myeloid-specific <lb/>knockout of several autophagy genes (RB1CC1, Beclin1, ATG3, ATG5, ATG7, ATG14, or <lb/>ATG16L) in animals subjected to herpesvirus infection results in elevated inflammation and <lb/>prevented viral reactivation from latency [170]. We hypothesize that for pathogens that induce <lb/>normal (slight increase above baseline) inflammation, autophagy deficiency results in elevated <lb/>inflammation that is beneficial for host recognition and reaction to invaded pathogens, while <lb/>for pathogens that induce high levels of inflammation, autophagy deficiency further increases <lb/>inflammation, and this inflammation leads to damage to the host. That is, although we showed <lb/>that the autophagy-mediated reduction in the immunoproteasome is beneficial for animals <lb/>with LPS-induced lung damage and DSS-induced inflammatory bowel damage, it is possible <lb/>that in certain situations, autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome may weaken <lb/>proper host responses to pathogens. Therefore, whether and how autophagic degradation of <lb/>the immunoproteasome functions in inflammation-related diseases such as aging, cancer, car-<lb/>diovascular disease, neurodegeneration, and infections needs to be specifically examined. <lb/>The functions of selective autophagy in various conditions occur through receptors that <lb/>specifically recognize certain types of substrates and concomitantly interact with lipidated <lb/>LC3/Atg8 residing in the autophagosome membrane [171,172]. The degradation of substrates <lb/>mostly indicates specific roles of autophagy [173]. The nature of autophagic substrates varies <lb/>according to cell type and stimulating signals [110,174]. In our case, selective targeting of the <lb/>immunoproteasome by autophagy explains the suppressive effect of autophagy on inflamma-<lb/>tion in macrophages. This conclusion was strengthened by the observation that autophagy <lb/>blockade induced the accumulation of immunoproteasomes accompanied by intense inflam-<lb/>matory reactions that could be completely reversed by the immunoproteasome inhibitor (Fig <lb/>6H-6J). This finding suggests that, at least in the contexts examined in this work, autophagic <lb/>degradation of immunoproteasomes is mainly responsible for the role of autophagy in inflam-<lb/>mation repression. <lb/>The receptor mediating autophagic degradation of the immunoproteasome is p62 but not <lb/>NBR1 or Tollip, as shown in this study. One interesting question regarding receptor function <lb/>in autophagy is why so many receptors exist. For example, p62, NBR1, Tollip, and OPTN func-<lb/>tion in aggrephagy (autophagy of protein aggregates); BNIP3L, FUNDC1, BNIP3, AMBRA1, <lb/>BCL2LI3, FKBP8, CHDH, DISC1, PHB2, and cardiolipin function in mitophagy (autophagy <lb/>of mitochondria); FAM134B, Sec62, RTN3, CCPG1 ATL3, and TEX264 function in ERphagy <lb/>(autophagy of ER); and p62, NBR1, and PEX3 function in pexophagy (autophagy of peroxi-<lb/>somes) [110,143,174,175]. The redundancy of receptors may reflect the specific and meticulous <lb/>regulation and function of autophagy in multicellular organisms. In other words, certain <lb/>receptors functions in specifically defined types of cells. The clarification of where (cell types), <lb/>when (activation or inhibition), and how (substrate targeting) autophagy functions may <lb/>improve our knowledge of the intrinsic nature of autophagy as a dynamic and multifunctional <lb/>process. The observation that immunoproteasome subunits are polyubiquitinated and their <lb/>binding with p62 relies on the ubiquitin-binding domain of 62 indicates ubiquitin chains as <lb/>the signal for immunoproteasome targeting by autophagosomes. Identifying the ubiquitin <lb/>ligase(s) responsible for ubiquitination of the immunoproteasome may help to determine how <lb/>ubiquitin ligase(s) directly or indirectly facilitate the specific recognition of the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>immunoproteasome by p62. Interestingly, p62 and other receptor-mediated autophagy has <lb/>been found to be responsible for autophagic degradation of constitute proteasome [176-178]. <lb/>Autophagy not only functions as a degradation pathway, but also functions to facilitate <lb/>extracellular secretion [179]. In the study on chondrocytes [180], the authors found that autop-<lb/>hagy is induced in growth-plate chondrocytes and regulates the secretion of type II collagen <lb/>(Col2). We speculate that in chondrocytes at growth conditions, autophagy is activated and <lb/>necessary for cell secretion of certain factor. <lb/>Hence, autophagy functions differently in different types of cells. It is interesting that FGF <lb/>signaling (FGF18 and FGFR4) activates autophagy in chondrocytes while in our case FGF sig-<lb/>naling inhibition (FGFR inhibitor LY2874455 treatment) activates autophagy. It is possible <lb/>that the main functional downstream kinases of FGF signaling may be different in different <lb/>types of cells, for example, JNK in chondrocytes while AKT and mTOR in macrophages (Figs <lb/>4J and S4D). <lb/>In conclusion, our findings described the selective autophagic degradation of the immuno-<lb/>proteasome in the context of aberrant inflammation in macrophages and supported a novel <lb/>mechanism of the regulation of inflammation by selective autophagy (S6R Fig). This study <lb/>explored the crosstalk between selective autophagy and inflammation, which should be mean-<lb/>ingful in establishing effective therapies for inflammatory diseases. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Antibodies and reagents <lb/>The following antibodies were purchased from Abcam: anti-SQSTM-1/p62 (ab109012), anti-<lb/>LMP2 (ab3328), anti-LMP7 (ab3329), anti-Ubiquitin (ab7780), anti-NBR1 (ab55474), anti-<lb/>ATG7 (ab133528), anti-Mtor (ab87540), anti-LMP10 (ab183506), anti-PSMB5 (ab90867), <lb/>anti-GAPDH (60004-1-Ig), anti-p65 (10745-1-AP). Anti-PSMB1 (11749-1-AP) and anti-<lb/>PSMB2 (15154-1-AP) were purchased from Proteintech. Those antibodies anti-LC3 (2775S), <lb/>anti-phospho-AktSer473 (4060S), anti-phospho-mTORSer2448 (2971S), anti-p70S6K (9202S), <lb/>anti-phospho-p70S6KThr421/Ser424 (9204S), anti-Akt (4685S), and anti-TNF-α (11948S) <lb/>were from Cell Signaling Technology. The phospho-NF-kB p65 (Ser536) (bs-0982R) antibody <lb/>and anti-IL6 (bs-0782R) was purchased from Bioss. Anti-phospho-IκB-α (Ser32) (AP0707), <lb/>anti-TRIF (A1155), anti-MYD88 (A0980), anti-TRAF6 (A16991), anti-TAK1 (A19077), anti-<lb/>TAB2 (A9867) antibodies were from ABclonal Technology. Anti-IL1β (ab216995) and anti-<lb/>IL18 (ab207323) antibodies were from Abcam. The secondary antibodies HRP-conjugated <lb/>anti-rabbit (D-110058) and HRP-conjugated anti-mouse (D-110087) were from BBI Life Sci-<lb/>ences. Fluor-conjugated (488 and 594) secondary antibodies were purchased from Invitrogen. <lb/>LY2874455, Domiphen (bromide), Cetylpyridinium (chloride monohydrate), Fenticonazole <lb/>(Nitrate), AZD4547, and ULK1-IN-2 were from MCE and dissolved in phosphate-buffered <lb/>saline (PBS). LPS (E. coli, serotype 055:B5) was purchased from Sigma. The H 2 -2 0 ,7 0 -dichloro-<lb/>dihydrofluorescein diacetate (DCFH-DA) (S0033S) and NO detection Kit(S0021S) were pur-<lb/>chased from Beyotime. Protease inhibitor cocktail was purchased from Sigma (Roche <lb/>11697498001). Polyinosinic-polycytidylic acid (Poly(I:C)) (HY-107202) was purchased from <lb/>MCE. <lb/>Macrophage culture and isolation <lb/>RAW264.7 macrophages were cultured in RPMI-1640 (Sigma) with 10% fetal bovine serum <lb/>(Gibco) and maintained in humidified 5% CO 2 atmosphere at 37˚C. PM and BMDMs were <lb/>isolated from C57BL/6J mice, and 6 to 8 weeks aged mice were injected with 3% thioglycolate <lb/>prior to the sacrifice of the mice and the isolation of BMDM. Cells separated from ascites were <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>seeded in cell plates with RPMI-1640 medium and were allowed to adhere for 4 to 6 h. Adher-<lb/>ent cells were considered as PM. Cells from bone marrow were seeded in cell plates incubated <lb/>with RPMI1640 complete medium with M-CSF (10 ng/ml, Sigma) and were allowed to adhere <lb/>for 7 days. Adherent cells were considered as BMDM. <lb/>Plasmid construction and DNA transfection <lb/>The target gene p62, LMP2, LMP7 were cloned into the pEGFP-C1 vector, respectively. The <lb/>target gene p62 and p624UBA were cloned into the pFlag-CMV2 vector, respectively. The tar-<lb/>get gene LC3 was cloned into the pLVX-mCherry-C1 vector. The sh-RNA targeting p62 <lb/>sequence (CCGGGTCTCTACAGATGCCAGAATCCTCGAGGATTCTGGCATCTGTAGAGACTT <lb/>TTTG) was cloned into the PLKO.1 vector. The guide RNA (gRNA) sequence (TCTGCCC <lb/>ACCCGCTTGACGT) of the target gene ATG7 was cloned into the PX330 vector. Upstream <lb/>(800 bp) and downstream (800 bp) sequences from the knockout site of the target gene and <lb/>selection marker (puro) were cloned into the pUC19 vector. Endoxin-free plasmids were <lb/>transfected into cells using jetprime reagent according to the protocol recommended by the <lb/>manufacturer (Polyplus). <lb/>ROS detection <lb/>For intracellular ROS measurement, the cells treated with LY2874455 and/or LPS for 24 h <lb/>were washed with PBS 3 times and incubated with 10 μm H2-DCFH-DA for 30 min at 37˚C in <lb/>the dark. Then, cells were washed 3 times and collected by scraping. Collected cells were resus-<lb/>pended in PBS and their fluorescence intensity corresponding to intracellular DCFH-DA lev-<lb/>els was immediately read on a Becton Dickinson FACS. DCFH-DA signals were also <lb/>visualized using fluorescence microscope (Zeiss Apotome) and quantified with Image J. <lb/>Nitric oxide (NO) concentration measurements <lb/>The level of NO derivative nitrite in culture medium was determined by Griess reaction as per <lb/>the kit&apos;s manual (Beyotime). After the reaction, the signal in the supernatant is measured at <lb/>540 nm with a multifunctional microplate reader (Biotek). <lb/>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction analysis (qRT-PCR) <lb/>Total RNA was extracted from cells lines, primary cells, or tissues by using Fast Pure cell/Tis-<lb/>sue Total RNA Isolation Kit (Nanjing Vazyme Biotek). cDNAs were reverse transcribed from <lb/>1 μg of RNA using the Superscript II Reverse Transcriptase kit (Nanjing Vazyme). The pro-<lb/>duction was used as templates in quantitative real-time polymerase chain reactions (PCRs) by <lb/>using SYBR Green reagent (Nanjing Vazyme) according to the protocol recommended by the <lb/>manufacturer. The sequences of primers used for PCR amplification are shown in S1 Table. <lb/>GAPDH served as internal normalization control. <lb/>Proteasome activity profiling <lb/>Subunit-selective fluorogenic peptide substrates were used to measure the catalytic activities of <lb/>individual catalytic subunits by monitoring the rate of substrate hydrolysis over time. Briefly, <lb/>protein lysates were prepared using passive lysis buffer (25 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 100 mM Nacl, 5 <lb/>mM ATP, 0.2% NP40, 20% Glycerol) and diluted in 20S proteasome assay buffer (20 mM Tris-<lb/>HCl, 0.5 mM EDTA, 0.035% SDS (pH 8.0)). Enzyme reactions were initiated by the addition <lb/>of proteasome substrates. Substrates and concentrations were used as following: Ac-<lb/>ANW-AMC (β5i, 100 μm), Ac-PAL-AMC (β1i activity, 100 μm), and Ac-Arg-Leu-Arg-AMC <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>(β2i activity, 100 μm). The mixture was incubated at 37˚C for 2 h. Fluorescence signals were <lb/>measured using a multifunctional microplate reader (Biotek) at the excitation and emission <lb/>wavelengths of 345 and 445 nm, respectively. <lb/>Immunoblotting <lb/>Cells or tissues were lysed with RIPA buffer with protease inhibitors (Roche 11697498001). <lb/>The protein was quantified by BCA Protein Assay Kit (Sigma) according to the protocol rec-<lb/>ommended by the manufacturer. After quantified, protein precipitates were subjected to <lb/>SDS-PAGE. Protein was transferred to PVDF membranes and blocked in 5% non-fat milk in <lb/>Tris-HCl-buffered saline (TBS) with 0.1% Tween-20 (TBST) for 1 h at room temperature, after <lb/>which primary antibody (S1 Table) was incubated overnight at 4˚C. Then, the membranes <lb/>were incubated with the secondary antibody (S1 Table) at room temperature for 1 h. Signals <lb/>were acquired with a Chemidoc MP Imaging System (Bio-Rad). <lb/>Immunoprecipitation <lb/>Cells were lysed in a buffer containing 0.25% TX-100, 1% NP-40, 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8), 150 <lb/>mM NaCl, and 1 mM EDTA. Lysates were adjusted for concentration at 1 to 2 mg/ml and vol-<lb/>ume and incubated with GFP-Beads (Shenzhen Sports Life Technology Company) at 4˚C <lb/>overnight. Then, the samples were centrifuged at 2,000 rpm at 4˚C for 3 min. The pellet was <lb/>washed 5 times with wash buffer A (50 mM tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 100 mM sodium chloride, and 2 <lb/>mM EDTA). Bound proteins were collected in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris (pH 7.4), 150 mM <lb/>NaCl, 0.1% SDS, 1% TritonX-100, and 0.5% sodium deoxycholate), and the precipitated pro-<lb/>teins were subjected to SDS-PAGE. <lb/>Immunofluorescence <lb/>Cells grown on cover slips were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS for 10 min followed <lb/>by permeabilization with 0.1% TritonX100 for 10 min and incubation with 3% BSA for 1 h at <lb/>room temperature. Cells were then incubated with primary antibody followed by a PBS wash <lb/>and incubated with secondary antibody (donkey anti-mouse and anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 488 <lb/>or 594). DAPI was used to stain the DNA. Images were captured using the Zeiss LSM 880. <lb/>Mass spectrometry-based proteomics analysis <lb/>The original mass spectrometry proteomics data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange <lb/>Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository with the dataset identifier PXD038747 and are <lb/>publicly available as of the date of publication. <lb/>Protein extraction. Sample was sonicated 3 times on ice using a high-intensity ultrasonic <lb/>processor (Scientz) in lysis buffer (8 M urea, 1% Protease Inhibitor Cocktail). The remaining <lb/>debris was removed by centrifugation at 12,000 g at 4˚C for 10 min. Finally, the supernatant <lb/>was collected and the protein concentration was determined with BCA kit according to the <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Trypsin digestion. For digestion, the protein solution was reduced with 5 mM dithiothreitol <lb/>for 30 min at 56˚C and alkylated with 11 mM iodoacetamide for 15 min at room temperature <lb/>in darkness. The protein sample was then diluted by adding 100 mM TEAB to urea concentra-<lb/>tion less than 2 M. Finally, trypsin was added at 1:50 trypsin-to-protein mass ratio for the first <lb/>digestion overnight and 1:100 trypsin-to-protein mass ratio for a second 4-h digestion. <lb/>LC-MS/MS analysis. The tryptic peptides were dissolved in solvent A (0.1% formic acid, <lb/>0.1% acetonitrile/in water), directly loaded onto a homemade reversed-phase analytical <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>column (25 cm length, 75/100 μm i.d.). Peptides were separated with a gradient from 6% to <lb/>24% solvent B (0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile) over 70 min, 24% to 35% in 14 min and climb-<lb/>ing to 80% in 3 min then holding at 80% for the last 3 min, all at a constant flow rate of 450 <lb/>nL/min on a nanoElute UHPLC system (Bruker Daltonics). The peptides were subjected to <lb/>capillary source followed by the timsTOF Pro (Bruker Daltonics) mass spectrometry. The elec-<lb/>trospray voltage applied was 1.75 kV. Precursors and fragments were analyzed at the TOF <lb/>detector, with an MS/MS scan range from 100 to 1,700 m/z. The timsTOF Pro was operated in <lb/>parallel accumulation serial fragmentation (PASEF) mode. Precursors with charge states 0 to 5 <lb/>were selected for fragmentation, and 10 PASEF-MS/MS scans were acquired per cycle. The <lb/>dynamic exclusion was set to 30 s. <lb/>Data processing protocol. The resulting MS/MS data were processed using MaxQuant <lb/>search engine (v1.6.6.0). Tandem mass spectra were searched against the Mus_muscu-<lb/>lus_10090_SP_20191115 (17,032 entries) concatenated with reverse decoy database. Trypsin/P <lb/>was specified as cleavage enzyme allowing up to 2 missing cleavages. The mass tolerance for <lb/>precursor ions was set as 20 ppm in first search and 20 ppm in main search, and the mass toler-<lb/>ance for fragment ions was set as 0.02 Da. Carbamidomethyl on Cys was specified as fixed <lb/>modification, and acetylation on protein N-terminal and oxidation on Met were specified as <lb/>variable modifications. FDR was adjusted to &lt;1%. <lb/>Cell aging induction <lb/>NIH3T3 cells were cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS. NIH3T3 cells were trypsi-<lb/>nized and suspended in phosphate buffer solution (PBS) with H 2 O 2 (400 μm in PBS) at 37˚C <lb/>for 45 min. H 2 O 2 treatment was terminated by 3 times of washing with PBS. Then, the <lb/>NIH3T3 cells were cultured with complete medium for 3 days. <lb/>Animal experiments <lb/>All procedures involve animals were performed in conformity with relevant guidelines and <lb/>regulations and approved by the Ethics Committee of Sichuan University West China hospital <lb/>(approval number 20220406005). <lb/>Induction of ALI (acute lung injury) <lb/>Male mice aged 8 weeks were randomly divided into 3 groups (control group, LPS (10 mg/kg) <lb/>group, LPS (10 mg/kg) + LY2874455 (1 mg/kg) group, 6 mice in each group). Mice were sub-<lb/>ject to intragastric administration with either saline or LY2874455 (1 mg/kg) at the same time <lb/>as LPS injection (10 mg/kg). Six hours after LPS injection, mice were killed and the lungs were <lb/>removed. Lung tissues were subsequently used for quantitative real-time PCR assay and hema-<lb/>toxylineosin (HE) staining. <lb/>Induction of sepsis <lb/>Male mice aged 8 weeks were randomly divided into 3 groups, 8 mice in each group. To evalu-<lb/>ate the effect of LY2874455 on the survival of mice, endotoxemia was induced by a single i.p. <lb/>injection of bacterial endotoxin (LPS, 35 mg/kg), with i.g. administration of LY2874455 (1 mg/ <lb/>kg), at 2 h before the injection of LPS. The mice not receiving LY2874455 received a mock <lb/>injection with saline as controls. Survival rates of animals were monitored up to 96 h after LPS <lb/>challenge. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<body>Induction of colitis <lb/>Colitis was induced in 8-week-old male mice by adding 3% DSS (m.w. 36,000 to 50,000; MP <lb/>Biomedicals, Solon, Ohio, United States of America) to the drinking water, beginning on day <lb/>0. On the third day of DSS treatment, mice were subject to intragastric administration with <lb/>either saline or LY2874455 (1 mg/kg) for 5 days. Thereafter, mice were given regular drinking <lb/>water. The body weight was measured daily throughout the experiment. At day 9, the mice <lb/>were killed and the intestines were removed. Intestine tissues were subsequently used for <lb/>quantitative real-time PCR assay, western blot assay, and HE staining. <lb/>Poly (IC) model <lb/>Polyinosinic-polycytidylic acid (poly(I:C)) (50 μg/ml) and LY2874455 (2 μm) were applied to <lb/>BMDM for 24 h and expression levels of inflammatory cytokines were analyzed qRT-PCR. <lb/>Transmission electron microscopy <lb/>Macrophages were washed 3 times for 15 min with 0.1 M phosphate buffer, and then fixed in <lb/>2% aqueous osmium tetraoxide for 1 h followed by washing 3 times each for 15 min with <lb/>deionized water. Samples were then dyed with 2% uranyl acetate for 30 min and dehydrated <lb/>through graded alcohols (50% to 100%) and 100% acetone each for 15 min. After that, samples <lb/>were embedded in EPON 812 resin and cured for 24 h at 37˚C, 45˚C, 60˚C, respectively. Ultra-<lb/>thin (70 nm) sections were obtained by ultrathin slicer machine (Leica) and stained with 2% <lb/>uranyl acetate and 0.3% lead citrate. Electron microscopy images of the samples were taken <lb/>using Tecnai G2 Spirit transmission electron microscope (FEI Company). Representative <lb/>images of at least 3 independent replicated experiments are shown. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>All data shown in this study are representative results from at least 3 independent replicated <lb/>experiments. The data were check by Shapiro-Wilk for analysis of normal distribution. Quan-<lb/>tification data are expressed as means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. Statistical anal-<lb/>yses were conducted using Prism5. Ordinary one-way or two-way ANOVA with Turkey&apos;s <lb/>multiple comparisons test, or a two-tailed paired or unpaired Student&apos;s t test, or the Dunn&apos;s <lb/>nonparametric test (for multiple group comparisons) and the Mann-Whitney test (2 group <lb/>comparisons) were used to determine statistical significance (*: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: <lb/>P &lt; 0.001, NS: no statistical difference). <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. LY2874455 suppressed inflammation in LPS-stimulated macrophages. (A) <lb/>RAW264.7 cells were incubated with 27 chemicals and stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 <lb/>h. NO concentration in culture supernatant was measured and shown as fold change. (B) The <lb/>names of the 27 chemicals. (C, D) Different concentrations of LY2874455 were applied to LPS <lb/>(20 ng/ml)-treated RAW264.7 cells and cell viabilities and levels of NO were measured. (E-G) <lb/>The expression of proinflammatory genes (IL-6, TNF-α) and iNOS was checked by qRT-PCR <lb/>treated with LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. (H) Protein levels of IL-6, TNF-<lb/>α, iNOS, and β-actin were detected by western blot in RAW264.7 cells. The blot was quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (I-K) The expression of <lb/>proinflammatory genes (IL-6, TNF-α) and iNOS was checked by qRT-PCR in PMs treated <lb/>with LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. (L) Protein levels of iNOS and GAPDH <lb/>were detected by western blot in PM. (M) The blot was quantified with densitometric values <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">and statistical significance was analyzed. (N-P) The expression of proinflammatory genes (IL-<lb/>6, TNF-α) and iNOS was checked by qRT-PCR in BMDMs treated with LY2874455 (2 μm) <lb/>and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. (Q, R) Expression levels of iNOS were detected by in BMDM. <lb/>The blot was quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (S, <lb/>T) The expression of proinflammatory genes (IL-6 and TNF-α) was checked by qRT-PCR in <lb/>human THP-1 monocytes treated with LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. Phor-<lb/>bol12-myristate13-acetate (PMA) was used to induce THP-1 monocyte to macrophages. (U, <lb/>V) The cytokine of IL-6 and TNF-α was detected by elisa in in RAW264.7 cells treated with <lb/>LY2874455 (2 μm) and LPS (20 ng/ml) for 24 h. (W-Y) The protein expression of IL-6, TNF-<lb/>α, and iNOS in Fig 1H were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance <lb/>was analyzed. (Z-AB) The protein expression of IL-6, TNF-α, and iNOS in S1H Fig were <lb/>quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (AC) The pro-<lb/>tein expression of IKK-β in Fig 1I was quantified with densitometric values and statistical sig-<lb/>nificance was analyzed. (AD-AE) The protein expression of p65 and p-p65 in Fig 1J were <lb/>quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (AF) The <lb/>immune fluorescence micrographs of p65 were quantified in Fig 1K. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, <lb/>***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data underlying the graphs <lb/>shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Fig. LY287445 suppressed viral infection-and aging-induced inflammation. (A-C) <lb/>LY2874455 inhibited viral infection-induced inflammation. Polyinosinic-polycytidylic acid <lb/>(poly(I:C)) (50 μg/ml) and LY2874455 (2 μm) were applied to BMDM for 24 h and expression <lb/>levels of inflammatory cytokines were analyzed qRT-PCR. (D-F) LY2874455 inhibited the <lb/>bacteria (E. coli) infection-induced inflammation. E. coli and LY2874455 (2 μm) were applied <lb/>to BMDM for 24 h and expression levels of inflammatory cytokines were analyzed qRT-PCR. <lb/>(G-K) LY2874455 inhibited H 2 O 2 -induced cell aging. NIH3T3 cells were treated with H 2 O 2 <lb/>(400 μm for 2 h) for induction of cell aging followed by LY2874455 (2 μm) treatment. Repre-<lb/>sentative images of β-GAL staining of the cells were shown (G) and the expression levels of <lb/>p16 (H) and inflammatory cytokines (I-K) were analyzed by qRT-PCR. (L) The protein <lb/>expression of IL1β, IL18, and GAPDH were detected by western blot. And the protein expres-<lb/>sion was quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. *: <lb/>P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data <lb/>underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Immunoproteasome functions in LPS-induced inflammation at upstream of NF-<lb/>κB factors. (A) Immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914 suppressed the nucleartranslocation <lb/>of NF-κB factor p65 in macrophages stimulated with LPS. RAW264.7 cells were stimulated <lb/>with LPS (20 ng/ml) for 2 h with or without ONX-0914 (1 μm). Representative images of 3 <lb/>independent replicates were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. (B) Schematic diagram of NF-κB <lb/>inflammation signaling pathway. (C) Total proteins were extracted from RAW264.7 macro-<lb/>phage cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) together with ONX-0914 (1 μm) and used for western <lb/>blot analysis of protein levels of phosphorylated IκB-α (p-IκB-α). The blot was quantified with <lb/>densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (D, E) Total proteins were <lb/>extracted from RAW264.7 macrophage cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) together with ONX-<lb/>0914 (1 μm) or LY2874455 (2 μm) and used for western blot analysis of protein levels of indi-<lb/>cated factors function upstream of the NF-κB signaling pathway. The blots were quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (F) The enzymatic activities <lb/>of immunoproteasome subunits LMP10 were measured in RAW264.7 cells. ***: P &lt; 0.001. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">(G) Total proteins were extracted from RAW264.7 macrophage cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ <lb/>ml) together with LY2874455 (2 μm) and used for western blot analysis of protein levels of <lb/>PSMB1 and GAPDH. (H) The protein expression of PSMB1 in was quantified with densito-<lb/>metric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (I) The protein expression of LMP2, <lb/>LMP7, and LMP10 wereAU : PleasecheckwhetherthechangesmadeinthesentenceTheproteinexpressionof <lb/>quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was <lb/>analyzed. (J) The protein expression of PSMB6, PSMB7, and PSMB5 in Fig 3E were quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (K) The protein expression <lb/>of LMP2, LMP7, and LMP10 in Fig 3F was quantified with densitometric values and statistical <lb/>significance was analyzed. (L) The protein expression of PSMB6, PSMB7, and PSMB5 in Fig <lb/>3G were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (M) <lb/>The immune fluorescence micrographs of p65 in S3A Fig were quantified. (N-S) The protein <lb/>expression of p-IκB-α, TAK1, MyD88, TAB2, TRIF, and TRAF6 in S3D Fig were quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (T-X) The protein expres-<lb/>sion of p-IκB-α, TAK1, MyD88, TAB2, TRIF, and TRAF6 in S3E Fig were quantified with den-<lb/>sitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: <lb/>P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data underlying the graphs <lb/>shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Fig. LY2874455 induced autophagy in macrophages. (A) Inhibitors MG132, chloroquine, <lb/>or wortmannin were used at different concentrations to analyze their effects on macrophage <lb/>viabilities in the dose-and time-dependent cell death assays. (B) Inhibitor of constitutive pro-<lb/>teasome, MG132, could not block the reduction of immunoproteasome subunits induced by <lb/>LY2874455. RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and protea-<lb/>some inhibitor MG132 (5 μm). Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were detected by <lb/>western blot. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance <lb/>was analyzed. (C) Autophagy inhibitor wortmannin blocked the reduction of immunoprotea-<lb/>some subunits induced by LY2874455. Protein levels of LMP2, LMP7, and GAPDH were ana-<lb/>lyzed in RAW264.7 cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and autophagy <lb/>inhibitor wortmannin (100 nM). The blots were quantified with densitometric values and sta-<lb/>tistical significance was analyzed. (D) Model scheme of LY2874455 effect on activation of <lb/>autophagy. FGFRs are transmembrane RTKs and activated by FGF to form dimers, leading to <lb/>the activation of downstream FRS2 complex and subsequent activation of PI3K/AKT/mTOR <lb/>signaling pathway. Activated mTOR then phosphorylates and inhibits autophagy initiating <lb/>ULK1 kinase complex, leading to suppression of autophagy. LY2874455 suppresses the FGFR <lb/>activities and the downstream PI3K/AKT/mTOR signaling pathway, leading to the release and <lb/>activation of autophagy. (E) NIH3T3 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and LY2874455 <lb/>(0.2, 0.5, 1, 2, 5 μm) for 24 h and protein levels of p62, LC3, and GAPDH were analyzed by <lb/>western blot. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance <lb/>was analyzed. (F) AZD4547, an inhibitor of FGFR, was used to detect the effect on autophagy <lb/>and immunoproteasome. RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and ADZ4547 <lb/>(10, 50, 100 nM) for 24 h and protein levels of p62, LC3, and GAPDH were analyzed by west-<lb/>ern blot. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was <lb/>analyzed. (G-I) AZD4547 also has effects on inflammation suppression in RAW264.7 cells. <lb/>RAW264.7 cells were treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and ADZ4547 (100 nM) for 24 h, and the <lb/>expression of IL-6, TNF-α, IL1β, and iNOS was checked by qRT-PCR. (J) Chemicals (Fentico-<lb/>nazole, Domiphen, and Cetylpyridinium) were used to detect their effects on autophagy acti-<lb/>vation. RAW264.7 cells were treated with Fenticonazole, Domiphen, and Cetylpyridinium <lb/>(0.5, 1, 15 μm) for 24 h and protein levels of p62 and GAPDH were analyzed by western blot. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. <lb/>(K-M) The protein expression of LMP2 and LMP7 in Fig 4A-4C were quantified with densi-<lb/>tometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (N) The number of LC3 puncta were <lb/>quantified in Fig 4D. (O) Quantification of autophagosomes in macrophages treated with <lb/>LY2874455 for results in Fig 4E. (P) The protein expression of p62 and the ratio of LC3II/LC3I <lb/>in Fig 4F were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. <lb/>(Q-S) The protein expression of p62 in Fig 4G-4I were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (T-W) The protein expression of p-mTOR (Ser248), <lb/>mTOR, p-AKT(Ser473), AKT in Fig 4J were quantified with densitometric values and statisti-<lb/>cal significance was analyzed. (X-AA) The protein expression of LMP2 and LMP7 in S4B and <lb/>S4C Fig were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. <lb/>(AB-AC) The protein expression of p62 and the ratio of LC3II/LC3I in S4E Fig were quanti-<lb/>fied with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (AD-AF) The protein <lb/>expression of LMP2, LMP7, and p62 in S4F Fig were quantified with densitometric values and <lb/>statistical significance was analyzed. (AG-AI) The protein expression of p62 in S4J Fig was <lb/>quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: <lb/>P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data underlying <lb/>the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Fig. LY287445 induced the degradation of immunoproteasome subunits through <lb/>autophagy. (A) Confirmation of ATG7 gene knock out in macrophages. ATG7 gene was <lb/>deleted through CRISPR-CAS9 assay in RAW264.7 cells. Clones of gene deletion cells were <lb/>cultured and detected for protein levels of p62, LC3, ATG7, and intrinsic control GAPDH. <lb/>The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. <lb/>(B) Confirmation of the decrease of p62 protein levels in p62 knock down RAW264.7 cells. <lb/>The blot was quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (C) <lb/>The protein expression of LMP2 and LMP7 in Fig 5A were quantified with densitometric val-<lb/>ues and statistical significance was analyzed. (D) The protein expression of LMP2, LMP7, and <lb/>p62 in Fig 5B were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was ana-<lb/>lyzed. (E) The protein expression of LMP2, LMP7, and p62 in Fig 5C were quantified with <lb/>densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (F) The immune fluorescence <lb/>micrographs in Fig 5D was quantified by ImageJ. (G) The protein expression of NRB1, Tollip, <lb/>and p62 in Fig 5E were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was <lb/>analyzed. (H) The protein expression of LMP2 and LMP7 in Fig 5F were quantified with den-<lb/>sitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: <lb/>P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data underlying the graphs <lb/>shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S6 Fig. LY287445 suppressed inflammation through autophagy. (A, B) Autophagy inhibitor <lb/>wortmannin reversed the effect of LY2874455 in LPS-stimulated macrophages. BMDMs were <lb/>treated with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm), and wortmannin (100 nM) as indicated for <lb/>24 h. The expression of iNOS and inflammatory cytokine genes IL-6 was checked by <lb/>qRT-PCR. (C) RAW264.7 cells and used for western blot analysis of protein levels of p65, <lb/>phosphorylated p65 (p-p65), and IKK-β. The blots were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (D) RAW264.7 cells were stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ <lb/>ml) for 2 h with or without LY2874455 (2 μm). Representative images of double immunostain-<lb/>ing for p65 and nucleus (DAPI) were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. (D, F) Deficiency of autophagy <lb/>factor ATG7 or receptor p62 caused blockage of LY2874455 function in suppression of NF-κB <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>24 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">factor p65 (phosphorylation and nucleus translocation). (E, G) Total proteins were extracted <lb/>from ATG7 knockout or p62 knockdown RAW264.7 cells and used for western blot analysis <lb/>of protein levels of p65, phosphorylated p65 (p-p65), and IKK-β. The blots were quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (F, H) ATG7 knockout or <lb/>p62 knockdown RAW264.7 cells were stimulated with LPS (20 ng/ml) for 2 h with or without <lb/>LY2874455 (2 μm). Representative images of double immunostaining for p65 and nucleus <lb/>(DAPI) were shown. Scale bars: 10 μm. (I) The enhanced inflammatory capacity in autophagy-<lb/>deficient macrophages was suppressed by immunoproteasome inhibitor ONX-0914. Wild-<lb/>type (WT) or ATG7 knockout (ATG7-KO) RAW264.7 cells treated with LPS (20 ng/ml) and <lb/>ONX-0914 (1 μm). The protein levels of iNOS and inflammatory cytokine genes (IL-6 and <lb/>TNF-α) were checked. The blots were quantified with densitometric values and statistical sig-<lb/>nificance was analyzed. (J, K) Autophagy inhibitors (ULK1-IN-2 and chloroquine (CQ)) <lb/>reversed the effect of LY2874455 in LPS-stimulated macrophages. RAW264.7 cells were har-<lb/>vest after treatment with LPS (20 ng/ml), LY2874455 (2 μm) and ULK1-IN-2 (5 μm) or chloro-<lb/>quine (20 μm) as indicated for 24 h. The expression of inflammatory cytokine genes (iNOS <lb/>and IL-6) was checked by qRT-PCR in RAW264.7 cells. (L) siRNA was used to knock down <lb/>the expression of lmp7. The gene expression of lmp7 was detected by qRT-PCR. (M) <lb/>RAW264.7 cells were transfected with siRNA for 48 h and then treated with ONX-0914 for 24 <lb/>h. The gene expression of IL6 was detected by qRT-PCR. (N) The protein expression of p65, <lb/>phosphorylated p65 (p-p65), and IKK-β in S6C Fig were quantified with densitometric values <lb/>and statistical significance was analyzed. (O) The protein expression of p65, phosphorylated <lb/>p65 (p-p65), and IKK-β in S6D Fig were quantified with densitometric values and statistical <lb/>significance was analyzed. (P) The protein expression of p65, phosphorylated p65 (p-p65), and <lb/>IKK-β in S6G Fig were quantified with densitometric values and statistical significance was <lb/>analyzed. (Q) The protein expression of iNOS, TNF-α, and IL-6 in S6I Fig were quantified <lb/>with densitometric values and statistical significance was analyzed. (R) Diagrammatic sketch <lb/>of selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome suppresses inflammation regulation. *: <lb/>P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001, ****: P &lt; 0.0001, NS: no statistical difference. The data <lb/>underlying the graphs shown in the figure can be found in S1 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Table. Primers and dilutions for antibodies used in this study. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Table. Proteins analyzed by mass spectrometry in RAW264.7 macrophages treated with <lb/>LPS and LY2874455. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Data. Data that underlies all figures. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Raw Images. Uncropped images for all relevant figures in this article. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the Imaging Center of Sichuan University for imaging. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Jiao Zhou, Gaoyue Jiang, Shanze Chen, Huihui Li, Kefeng Lu. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>25 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Data curation: Chunxia Li. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Huihui Li, Kefeng Lu. <lb/>Investigation: Jiao Zhou. <lb/>Methodology: Jiao Zhou, Chunxia Li, Meng Lu, Gaoyue Jiang. <lb/>Project administration: Jiao Zhou. <lb/>Resources: Gaoyue Jiang, Shanze Chen. <lb/>Supervision: Huihui Li, Kefeng Lu. <lb/>Validation: Jiao Zhou, Kefeng Lu. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Jiao Zhou. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kefeng Lu. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Luo A, Leach ST, Barres R, Hesson LB, Grimm MC, Simar D. The Microbiota and epigenetic Regula-<lb/>tion of T Helper 17/Regulatory T Cells: in Search of a Balanced immune System. Front Immunol. <lb/>2017. 8(00417). https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2017.00417 PMID: 28443096 <lb/>2. Hawiger J. Innate immunity and inflammation: A transcriptional paradigm. Immunol Res. 2001; 23(2-<lb/>3):99-109. https://doi.org/10.1385/IR:23:2-3:099 PMID: 11444396 <lb/>3. Artis D, Spits H. The biology of innate lymphoid cells. Nature. 2015; 517(7534):293-301. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/nature14189 PMID: 25592534 <lb/>4. Isailovic N, Daigo K, Mantovani A, Selmi C. Interleukin-17 and innate immunity in infections and <lb/>chronic inflammation. J Autoimmun. 2015; 60:1-11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaut.2015.04.006 PMID: <lb/>25998834 <lb/>5. Rock KL, Lai J, Kono H. Innate and adaptive immune responses to cell death. Immunol Rev. 2011; <lb/>243(SI):191-205. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-065X.2011.01040.x PMID: 21884177 <lb/>6. Waisman A, Liblau RS, Becher B. Innate and adaptive immune responses in the CNS. Lancet Neurol. <lb/>2015; 14(9):945-955. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(15)00141-6 PMID: 26293566 <lb/>7. Bektas A, Schurman SH, Gonzalez-Freire M, Dunn CA, Singh AK, Macian F, et al. Age-associated <lb/>changes in human CD4(+) T cells point to mitochondrial dysfunction consequent to impaired autop-<lb/>hagy. Aging. 2019; 11(21):9234-9263. https://doi.org/10.18632/aging.102438 PMID: 31707363 <lb/>8. Franceschi C, Garagnani P, Parini P, Giuliani C, Santoro A. Inflammaging: a new immune-metabolic <lb/>viewpoint for age-related diseases. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2018; 14(10):576-590. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/s41574-018-0059-4 PMID: 30046148 <lb/>9. Ferrucci L, Fabbri E. Inflammageing: chronic inflammation in ageing, cardiovascular disease, and <lb/>frailty. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2018; 15(9):505-522. <lb/>10. Xavier RJ, Podolsky DK. Unravelling the pathogenesis of inflammatory bowel disease. Nature. 2007; <lb/>448(7152):427-434. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature06005 PMID: 17653185 <lb/>11. Sands BE, Sandborn WJ, Panaccione R, O&apos;Brien CD, Zhang H, Jewel J, et al. Ustekinumab as Induc-<lb/>tion and Maintenance Therapy for Ulcerative Colitis. N Engl J Med. 2019; 381(13):1201-1214. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1900750 PMID: 31553833 <lb/>12. Olivera P, Danese S, Jay N, Natoli G, Peyrin-Biroulet L. Big data in IBD: a look into the future. Nat Rev <lb/>Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2019; 16(5):312-321. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41575-019-0102-5 PMID: <lb/>30659247 <lb/>13. Andersson U. Hyperinflammation: On the pathogenesis and treatment of macrophage activation syn-<lb/>drome. Acta Paediatr. 2021; 110(10):2717-2722. https://doi.org/10.1111/apa.15900 PMID: 33934408 <lb/>14. Brands X, Haak BW, Klarenbeek AM, Otto NA, Faber DR, Lutter R, et al. Concurrent Immune Sup-<lb/>pression and Hyperinflammation in Patients With Community-Acquired Pneumonia. Front Immunol. <lb/>2020; 11:796. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2020.00796 PMID: 32477337 <lb/>15. Dickson K, Lehmann C. Inflammatory Response to Different Toxins in Experimental Sepsis Models. <lb/>Int J Mol Sci. 2019; 20(18). https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms20184341 PMID: 31491842 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>26 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>16. Schuller SS, Wisgrill L, Herndl E, Spittler A, Forster-Waldl E, Sadeghi K, et al. Pentoxifylline modulates <lb/>LPS-induced hyperinflammation in monocytes of preterm infants in vitro. Pediatr Res. 2017; 82 <lb/>(2):215-225. https://doi.org/10.1038/pr.2017.41 PMID: 28288151 <lb/>17. England JT, Abdulla A, Biggs CM, Lee AYY, Hay KA, Hoiland RL, et al. Weathering the COVID-19 <lb/>storm: Lessons from hematologic cytokine syndromes. Blood Rev. 2020:100707-100707. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.blre.2020.100707 PMID: 32425294 <lb/>18. Mehta P, McAuley DF, Brown M, Sanchez E, Tattersall RS, Manson JJ, et al. COVID-19: consider <lb/>cytokine storm syndromes and immunosuppression. Lancet. 2020; 395(10229):1033-1034. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30628-0 PMID: 32192578 <lb/>19. Sinha P, Matthay MA, Calfee CS. Is a &quot;Cytokine Storm&quot; Relevant to COVID-19? JAMA Intern Med. <lb/>2020; 180(9):1152-1154. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.3313 PMID: 32602883 <lb/>20. Moore JB, June CH. Cytokine release syndrome in severe COVID-19. Science. 2020; 368(6490):473-<lb/>474. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abb8925 PMID: 32303591 <lb/>21. Webb BJ, Peltan ID, Jensen P, Hoda D, Hunter B, Silver A, et al. Clinical criteria for COVID-19-associ-<lb/>ated hyperinflammatory syndrome: a cohort study. Lancet Rheumatol. 2020; 2(12):e754-e763. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S2665-9913(20)30343-X PMID: 33015645 <lb/>22. Liuzzo G, Patrono C. COVID 19: in the eye of the cytokine storm. Eur Heart J. 2021; 42(2):150-151. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/eurheartj/ehaa1005 PMID: 33462598 <lb/>23. Ritchie AI, Singanayagam A. Immunosuppression for hyperinflammation in COVID-19: a double-<lb/>edged sword? Lancet. 2020; 395(10230):1111. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30691-7 <lb/>PMID: 32220278 <lb/>24. Ho J, Mok BW, Campisi L, Jordan T, Yildiz S, Parameswaran S, et al. TOP1 inhibition therapy protects <lb/>against SARS-CoV-2-induced lethal inflammation. Cell. 2021; 184(10):2618-2632.e17. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.051 PMID: 33836156 <lb/>25. Hasan D, Shono A, van Kalken CK, van der Spek PJ, Krenning EP, Kotani T. A novel definition and <lb/>treatment of hyperinflammation in COVID-19 based on purinergic signalling. Purinergic Signal. 2022; <lb/>18(1):13-59. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11302-021-09814-6 PMID: 34757513 <lb/>26. McGonagle D, Sharif K, O&apos;Regan A, Bridgewood C. The Role of Cytokines including Interleukin-6 in <lb/>COVID-19 induced Pneumonia and Macrophage Activation Syndrome-Like Disease. Autoimmun Rev. <lb/>2020; 19(1025376). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.autrev.2020.102537 PMID: 32251717 <lb/>27. Merad M, Martin JC. Pathological inflammation in patients with COVID-19: a key role for monocytes <lb/>and macrophages. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020; 20(6):355-362. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41577-020-<lb/>0331-4 PMID: 32376901 <lb/>28. Feldmann M, Maini RN, Woody JN, Holgate ST, Winter G, Rowland M, et al. Trials of anti-tumour <lb/>necrosis factor therapy for COVID-19 are urgently needed. Lancet. 2020; 395(10234):1407-1409. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30858-8 PMID: 32278362 <lb/>29. Huang Q, Wu X, Zheng X, Luo S, Xu S, Weng J. Targeting inflammation and cytokine storm in COVID-<lb/>19. Pharmacol Res. 2020; 159(105051). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2020.105051 PMID: 32603772 <lb/>30. Safavi F, Nath A. Silencing of immune activation with methotrexate in patients with COVID-19. J Neu-<lb/>rol Sci. 2020; 415(116942). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jns.2020.116942 PMID: 32471659 <lb/>31. Wright DJM. Prevention of the cytokine storm in COVID-19. Lancet Infect Dis. 2021; 21(1):25-26. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30376-5 PMID: 32386610 <lb/>32. Schulert GS. Can tocilizumab calm the cytokine storm of COVID-19? Lancet Rheumatol. 2020; 2(8): <lb/>E449-E451. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2665-9913(20)30210-1 PMID: 32835248 <lb/>33. Timsit J, Bassetti M, Cremer O, Daikos G, de Waele J, Kallil A, et al. Rationalizing antimicrobial ther-<lb/>apy in the ICU: a narrative review. Intensive Care Med. 2019; 45(2):172-189. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00134-019-05520-5 PMID: 30659311 <lb/>34. Bergsbaken T, Fink SL, Cookson BT. Pyroptosis: host cell death and inflammation. Nat Rev Microbiol. <lb/>2009; 7(2):99-109. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro2070 PMID: 19148178 <lb/>35. Ramachandran G. Gram-positive and gram-negative bacterial toxins in sepsis: A brief review. Viru-<lb/>lence. 2014; 5(1):213-218. https://doi.org/10.4161/viru.27024 PMID: 24193365 <lb/>36. Munford RS, Weiss JP, Lu M. Biochemical transformation of bacterial lipopolysaccharides by acylox-<lb/>yacyl hydrolase reduces host injury and promotes recovery. J Biol Chem. 2020; 295(51):17842-<lb/>17851. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.REV120.015254 PMID: 33454018 <lb/>37. Jing W, Lo Pilato J, Kay C, Man SM. Activation mechanisms of inflammasomes by bacterial toxins. <lb/>Cell Microbiol. 2021:e13309-e13309. https://doi.org/10.1111/cmi.13309 PMID: 33426791 <lb/>38. Rathinam VAK, Zhao Y, Shao F. Innate immunity to intracellular LPS. Nat Immunol. 2019; 20(5):527-<lb/>533. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590-019-0368-3 PMID: 30962589 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>27 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>39. Pfalzgraff A, Weindl G. Intracellular Lipopolysaccharide Sensing as a Potential Therapeutic Target for <lb/>Sepsis. Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2019; 40(3):187-197. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2019.01.001 <lb/>PMID: 30691865 <lb/>40. Kim J, Kwak HJ, Cha J, Jeong Y, Rhee SD, Kim KR, et al. Metformin Suppresses Lipopolysaccharide <lb/>(LPS)-induced Inflammatory Response in Murine Macrophages via Activating Transcription Factor-3 <lb/>(ATF-3) Induction. J Biol Chem. 2014; 289(33):23246-23255. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M114. <lb/>577908 PMID: 24973221 <lb/>41. Arikawa M, Kakinuma Y, Noguchi T, Todaka H, Sato T. Donepezil, an acetylcholinesterase inhibitor, <lb/>attenuates LPS-induced inflammatory response in murine macrophage cell line RAW 264.7 through <lb/>inhibition of nuclear factor kappa B translocation. Eur J Pharmacol. 2016; 789:17-26. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.ejphar.2016.06.053 PMID: 27373848 <lb/>42. Naruishi K, Nagata T. Biological effects of interleukin-6 on Gingival Fibroblasts: Cytokine regulation in <lb/>periodontitis. J Cell Physiol. 2018; 233(9):6393-6400. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.26521 PMID: <lb/>29574949 <lb/>43. Zhang G, Meredith TC, Kahne D. On the essentiality of lipopolysaccharide to Gram-negative bacteria. <lb/>Curr Opin Microbiol. 2013; 16(6):779-785. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mib.2013.09.007 PMID: <lb/>24148302 <lb/>44. Zamyatina A, Heine H. Lipopolysaccharide Recognition in the Crossroads of TLR4 and Caspase-4/11 <lb/>Mediated Inflammatory Pathways. Front Immunol. 2020; 11(585146). https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu. <lb/>2020.585146 PMID: 33329561 <lb/>45. Murata S, Takahama Y, Kasahara M, Tanaka K. The immunoproteasome and thymoproteasome: <lb/>functions, evolution and human disease. Nat Immunol. 2018; 19(9):923-931. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41590-018-0186-z PMID: 30104634 <lb/>46. McCarthy MK, Weinberg JB. The immunoproteasome and viral infection: a complex regulator of <lb/>inflammation. Front Microbiol. 2015; 6(21). https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2015.00021 PMID: <lb/>25688236 <lb/>47. Kimura H, Caturegli P, Takahashi M, Suzuki K. New Insights into the Function of the Immunoprotea-<lb/>some in Immune and Nonimmune Cells. J Immunol Res. 2015; 2015(541984). https://doi.org/10.1155/ <lb/>2015/541984 PMID: 26636107 <lb/>48. Ferrington DA, Gregerson DS. Immunoproteasomes: Structure, Function, and Antigen Presentation. <lb/>Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci. 2012;75-112. <lb/>49. Groettrup M, Kirk CJ, Basler M. Proteasomes in immune cells: more than peptide producers? Nat Rev <lb/>Immunol. 2010; 10(1):72-77. https://doi.org/10.1038/nri2687 PMID: 20010787 <lb/>50. Griffin TA, Nandi D, Cruz M, Fehling HJ, Van Kaer L, Monaco JJ, et al. Immunoproteasome assembly: <lb/>Cooperative incorporation of interferon gamma (IFN-gamma)-inducible subunits. J Exp Med. 1998; <lb/>187(1):97-104. https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.187.1.97 PMID: 9419215 <lb/>51. Arellano-Garcia ME, Misuno K, Tran SD, Hu S. Interferon-gamma induces immunoproteasomes and <lb/>the presentation of MHC I-associated peptides on human salivary gland cells. PLoS ONE. 2014; 9(8): <lb/>e102878. <lb/>52. Macagno A, Gilliet M, Sallusto F, Lanzavecchia A, Nestle FO, Groettrup M. Dendritic cells up-regulate <lb/>immunoproteasomes and the proteasome regulator PA28 during maturation. Eur J Immunol. 1999; 29 <lb/>(12):4037-4042. https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1521-4141(199912)29:12&lt;4037::AID-IMMU4037&gt;3.0. <lb/>CO;2-T PMID: 10602014 <lb/>53. Cui Z, Hwang SM, Gomes AV. Identification of the immunoproteasome as a novel regulator of skeletal <lb/>muscle differentiation. Mol Cell Biol. 2014; 34(1):96-109. https://doi.org/10.1128/MCB.00622-13 <lb/>PMID: 24164898 <lb/>54. Xie X, Bi HL, Lai S, Zhang YL, Li N, Cao HJ, et al. The immunoproteasome catalytic beta5i subunit reg-<lb/>ulates cardiac hypertrophy by targeting the autophagy protein ATG5 for degradation. Sci Adv. 2019; 5 <lb/>(5):p.eaau0495. <lb/>55. Keller IE, Vosyka O, Takenaka S, Kloss A, Dahlmann B, Willems LI, et al. Regulation of immunopro-<lb/>teasome function in the lung. Sci Rep. 2015; 5:10230. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep10230 PMID: <lb/>25989070 <lb/>56. Chen S, Kammerl IE, Vosyka O, Baumann T, Yu Y, Wu Y, et al. Immunoproteasome dysfunction aug-<lb/>ments alternative polarization of alveolar macrophages. Cell Death Differ. 2016; 23(6):1026-1037. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2016.3 PMID: 26990663 <lb/>57. Eskandari SK, Seelen M, Lin G, Azzi JR. The immunoproteasome: An old player with a novel and <lb/>emerging role in alloimmunity. Am J Transplant. 2017; 17(12):3033-3039. https://doi.org/10.1111/ajt. <lb/>14435 PMID: 28719024 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>28 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>58. Herrmann J, Willuweit K, Loeffler D, Peterson K, Lerman L, Lerman A, et al. The Immunoproteasome <lb/>-a new characteristic of symptomatic carotid artery plaques. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012; 59S(13): <lb/>E2054-E2054. <lb/>59. Seliger B, Maeurer MJ, Ferrone S. Antigen-processing machinery breakdown and tumor growth. <lb/>Immunol Today. 2000; 21(9):455-464. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0167-5699(00)01692-3 PMID: <lb/>10953098 <lb/>60. Ebstein F, Kloetzel P, Krueger E, Seifert U. Emerging roles of immunoproteasomes beyond MHC <lb/>class I antigen processing. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2012; 69(15):2543-2558. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00018-012-0938-0 PMID: 22382925 <lb/>61. Chen S, Kammerl IE, Vosyka O, Baumann T, Yu Y, Wu Y, et al. Immunoproteasome dysfunction aug-<lb/>ments alternative polarization of alveolar macrophages. Cell Death Differ. 2016; 23(6SI):1026-1037. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2016.3 PMID: 26990663 <lb/>62. Kremer M, Henn A, Kolb C, Basler M, Moebius J, Guillaume B, et al. Reduced Immunoproteasome <lb/>Formation and Accumulation of Immunoproteasomal Precursors in the Brains of Lymphocytic Chorio-<lb/>meningitis Virus-Infected Mice. J Immunol. 2010; 185(9):5549-5560. https://doi.org/10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.1001517 PMID: 20881186 <lb/>63. Mundt S, Basler M, Buerger S, Engler H, Groettrup M. Inhibiting the immunoproteasome exacerbates <lb/>the pathogenesis of systemic Candida albicans infection in mice. Sci Rep. 2016; 6(19434). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/srep19434 PMID: 26776888 <lb/>64. Chen X, Zhang X, Wang Y, Lei H, Su H, Zeng J, et al. Inhibition of immunoproteasome reduces infarc-<lb/>tion volume and attenuates inflammatory reaction in a rat model of ischemic stroke. Cell Death Dis. <lb/>2015:6. <lb/>65. Sun Y, Peng R, Peng H, Liu H, Wen L, Wu T, et al. miR-451 suppresses the NF-kappaB-mediated <lb/>proinflammatory molecules expression through inhibiting LMP7 in diabetic nephropathy. Mol Cell <lb/>Endocrinol. 2016; 433:75-86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mce.2016.06.004 PMID: 27264074 <lb/>66. Basler M, Dajee M, Moll C, Groettrup M, Kirk CJ. Prevention of Experimental Colitis by a Selective <lb/>Inhibitor of the Immunoproteasome. J Immunol. 2010; 185(1):634-641. https://doi.org/10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.0903182 PMID: 20525886 <lb/>67. Basler M, Kirk CJ, Groettrup M. The immunoproteasome in antigen processing and other immunologi-<lb/>cal functions. Curr Opin Immunol. 2013; 25(1):74-80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coi.2012.11.004 PMID: <lb/>23219269 <lb/>68. Basler M, Mundt S, Muchamuel T, Moll C, Jiang J, Groettrup M, et al. Inhibition of the immunoprotea-<lb/>some ameliorates experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. EMBO Mol Med. 2014; 6(2):226-<lb/>238. https://doi.org/10.1002/emmm.201303543 PMID: 24399752 <lb/>69. Farini A, Sitzia C, Cassani B, Cassinelli L, Rigoni R, Colleoni F, et al. Therapeutic Potential of Immuno-<lb/>proteasome Inhibition in Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy. Mol Ther. 2016; 24(11):1898-1912. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1038/mt.2016.162 PMID: 27506451 <lb/>70. Yan W, Bi HL, Liu LX, Li NN, Liu Y, Du J, et al. Knockout of immunoproteasome subunit beta2i amelio-<lb/>rates cardiac fibrosis and inflammation in DOCA/Salt hypertensive mice. Biochem Biophys Res Com-<lb/>mun. 2017; 490(2):84-90. <lb/>71. Liong S, Lim R, Nguyen-Ngo C, Barker G, Parkington HC, Lappas M. The immunoproteasome inhibi-<lb/>tor ONX-0914 regulates inflammation and expression of contraction associated proteins in myome-<lb/>trium. Eur J Immunol. 2018; 48(8):1350-1363. https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.201747458 PMID: <lb/>29883518 <lb/>72. Liao J, An X, Yang X, Lin QY, Liu S, Xie Y, et al. Deficiency of LMP10 Attenuates Diet-Induced Athero-<lb/>sclerosis by Inhibiting Macrophage Polarization and Inflammation in Apolipoprotein E Deficient Mice. <lb/>Front Cell Dev Biol. 2020; 8:592048. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcell.2020.592048 PMID: 33195259 <lb/>73. Basler M, Mundt S, Groettrup M. The immunoproteasome subunit LMP7 is required in the murine thy-<lb/>mus for filling up a hole in the Tcell repertoire. Eur J Immunol. 2018; 48(3):419-429. <lb/>74. Basler M, Lindstrom MM, LaStant JJ, Bradshaw JM, Owens TD, Schmidt C, et al. Co-inhibition of <lb/>immunoproteasome subunits LMP2 and LMP7 is required to block autoimmunity. EMBO Rep. 2018; <lb/>19(12). https://doi.org/10.15252/embr.201846512 PMID: 30279279 <lb/>75. Mundt S, Engelhardt B, Kirk CJ, Groettrup M, Basler M. Inhibition and deficiency of the immunoprotea-<lb/>some subunit LMP7 attenuates LCMV-induced meningitis. Eur J Immunol. 2016; 46(1):104-113. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.201545578 PMID: 26464284 <lb/>76. Zaiss DM, Bekker CP, Grone A, Lie BA, Sijts AJ. Proteasome immunosubunits protect against the <lb/>development of CD8 T cell-mediated autoimmune diseases. J Immunol. 2011; 187(5):2302-2309. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1101003 PMID: 21804012 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>29 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>77. Ichikawa HT, Conley T, Muchamuel T, Jiang J, Lee S, Owen T, et al. Beneficial effect of novel protea-<lb/>some inhibitors in murine lupus via dual inhibition of type I interferon and autoantibody-secreting cells. <lb/>Arthritis Rheum. 2012; 64(2):493-503. https://doi.org/10.1002/art.33333 PMID: 21905015 <lb/>78. Basler M, Mundt S, Bitzer A, Schmidt C, Groettrup M. The immunoproteasome: a novel drug target for <lb/>autoimmune diseases. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2015; 33(4 Suppl 92):S74-S79. PMID: 26458097 <lb/>79. Koerner J, Brunner T, Groettrup M. Inhibition and deficiency of the immunoproteasome subunit LMP7 <lb/>suppress the development and progression of colorectal carcinoma in mice. Oncotarget. 2017; 8 <lb/>(31):50873-50888. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.15141 PMID: 28881611 <lb/>80. Vachharajani N, Joeris T, Luu M, Hartmann S, Pautz S, Jenike E, et al. Prevention of colitis-associated <lb/>cancer by selective targeting of immunoproteasome subunit LMP7. Oncotarget. 2017; 8(31):50447-<lb/>50459. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.14579 PMID: 28881574 <lb/>81. Moallemian R, Rehman AU, Zhao N, Wang H, Chen H, Lin G, et al. Immunoproteasome inhibitor <lb/>DPLG3 attenuates experimental colitis by restraining NF-kappaB activation. Biochem Pharmacol. <lb/>2020; 177:113964. <lb/>82. Schmidt N, Gonzalez E, Visekruna A, Kuhl AA, Loddenkemper C, Mollenkopf H, et al. Targeting the <lb/>proteasome: partial inhibition of the proteasome by bortezomib or deletion of the immunosubunit <lb/>LMP7 attenuates experimental colitis. Gut. 2010; 59(7):896-906. https://doi.org/10.1136/gut.2009. <lb/>203554 PMID: 20581238 <lb/>83. Althof N, Goetzke CC, Kespohl M, Voss K, Heuser A, Pinkert S, et al. The immunoproteasome-specific <lb/>inhibitor ONX 0914 reverses susceptibility to acute viral myocarditis. EMBO Mol Med. 2018; 10 <lb/>(2):200-218. https://doi.org/10.15252/emmm.201708089 PMID: 29295868 <lb/>84. Liu Q, Hu W, Zhang YL, Hu SP, Zhang Z, He XJ, et al. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2018; 502 <lb/>(4):472-478. <lb/>85. Oh IS, Textoris-Taube K, Sung PS, Kang W, Gorny X, Ka ¨hne T, et al. Immunoproteasome induction is <lb/>suppressed in hepatitis C virus-infected cells in a protein kinase R-dependent manner. Exp Mol Med. <lb/>2016; 48(11):e270. https://doi.org/10.1038/emm.2016.98 PMID: 27833096 <lb/>86. Moebius J, van den Broek M, Groettrup M, Basler M. Immunoproteasomes are essential for survival <lb/>and expansion of T cells in virus-infected mice. Eur J Immunol. 2010; 40(12):3439-3449. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1002/eji.201040620 PMID: 21108466 <lb/>87. Robek MD, Garcia ML, Boyd BS, Chisari FV. Role of immunoproteasome catalytic subunits in the <lb/>immune response to hepatitis B virus. J Virol. 2007; 81(2):483-491. https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI. <lb/>01779-06 PMID: 17079320 <lb/>88. Desterke C, Turhan AG, Bennaceur-Griscelli A, Griscelli F. HLA-dependent heterogeneity and macro-<lb/>phage immunoproteasome activation during lung COVID-19 disease. J Transl Med. 2021; 19(1):290. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12967-021-02965-5 PMID: 34225749 <lb/>89. Pang KC, Sanders MT, Monaco JJ, Doherty PC, Turner SJ, Chen W. Immunoproteasome subunit <lb/>deficiencies impact differentially on two immunodominant influenza virus-specific CD8+ T cell <lb/>responses. J Immunol. 2006; 177(11):7680-7688. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.177.11.7680 <lb/>PMID: 17114438 <lb/>90. Gan CS, Lim PJ, Razif MF, Yusof R, Othman S. Subversion of immunoproteasome subunit expression <lb/>in dengue virus serotype 2-infected HepG2 cells. Rev Soc Bras Med Trop. 2017; 50(1):99-103. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1590/0037-8682-0207-2016 PMID: 28327809 <lb/>91. Santos RDLA, Bai L, Singh PK, Murakami N, Fan H, Zhan W, et al. Structure of human immunoprotea-<lb/>some with a reversible and noncompetitive inhibitor that selectively inhibits activated lymphocytes. Nat <lb/>Commun. 2017; 8(1692). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-017-01760-5 PMID: 29167449 <lb/>92. Karreci ES, Fan H, Uehara M, Mihali AB, Singh PK, Kurdi AT, et al. Brief treatment with a highly selec-<lb/>tive immunoproteasome inhibitor promotes long-term cardiac allograft acceptance in mice. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A. 2016; 113(52):E8425-E8432. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1618548114 PMID: <lb/>27956634 <lb/>93. Xie X, Bi H, Lai S, Zhang Y, Li N, Cao HJ, et al. The immunoproteasome catalytic beta 5i subunit regu-<lb/>lates cardiac hypertrophy by targeting the autophagy protein ATG5 for degradation. Sci Adv. 2019: 5 <lb/>(eaau04955). <lb/>94. Wang S, Li J, Wang T, Bai J, Zhang Y, Lin QY, et al. Ablation of Immunoproteasome beta 5i Subunit <lb/>Suppresses Hypertensive Retinopathy by Blocking ATRAP Degradation in Mice. Mol Ther. 2020; 28 <lb/>(1):279-292. <lb/>95. Liu H, Wan C, Ding Y, Han R, He Y, Xiao J, et al. PR-957, a selective inhibitor of immunoproteasome <lb/>subunit low-MW polypeptide 7, attenuates experimental autoimmune neuritis by suppressing T(h)17-<lb/>cell differentiation and regulating cytokine production. FASEB J. 2017; 31(4):1756-1766. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1096/fj.201601147R PMID: 28096232 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>30 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>96. Liu R, Zhang P, Yang C, Pang Y, Zhang M, Zhang N, et al. ONX-0914, a selective inhibitor of immuno-<lb/>proteasome, ameliorates experimental autoimmune myasthenia gravis by modulating humoral <lb/>response. J Neuroimmunol. 2017; 311:71-78. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2017.08.005 PMID: <lb/>28844501 <lb/>97. Guo Y, Chen X, Li D, Liu H, Ding Y, Han R, et al. PR-957 mediates neuroprotection by inhibiting Th17 <lb/>differentiation and modulating cytokine production in a mouse model of ischaemic stroke. Clin Exp <lb/>Immunol. 2018; 193(2):194-206. https://doi.org/10.1111/cei.13132 PMID: 29603201 <lb/>98. Muchamuel T, Basler M, Aujay MA, Suzuki E, Kalim KW, Sylvain C, et al. A selective inhibitor of the <lb/>immunoproteasome subunit LMP7 blocks cytokine production and attenuates progression of experi-<lb/>mental arthritis. Nat Med. 2009; 15(7):781-U12. https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.1978 PMID: 19525961 <lb/>99. Nagayama Y, Nakahara M, Shimamura M, Horie I, Arima K, Abiru N. Prophylactic and therapeutic effi-<lb/>cacies of a selective inhibitor of the immunoproteasome for Hashimoto&apos;s thyroiditis, but not for Graves&apos; <lb/>hyperthyroidism, in mice. Clin Exp Immunol. 2012; 168(3):268-273. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-<lb/>2249.2012.04578.x PMID: 22519588 <lb/>100. Xiao F, Lin X, Tian J, Wang X, Chen Q, Rui K, et al. Proteasome inhibition suppresses Th17 cell gener-<lb/>ation and ameliorates autoimmune development in experimental Sjogren&apos;s syndrome. Cell Mol Immu-<lb/>nol. 2017; 14(11):924-934. <lb/>101. Huber EM, Basler M, Schwab R, Heinemeyer W, Kirk CJ, Kirk CJ, et al. Immuno-and Constitutive Pro-<lb/>teasome Crystal Structures Reveal Differences in Substrate and Inhibitor Specificity. Cell. 2012; 148 <lb/>(4):727-738. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2011.12.030 PMID: 22341445 <lb/>102. Ettari R, Zappala M, Grasso S, Musolino C, Innao V, Allegra A. Immunoproteasome-selective and <lb/>non-selective inhibitors: A promising approach for the treatment of multiple myeloma. Pharmacol <lb/>Ther. 2018; 182:176-192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pharmthera.2017.09.001 PMID: 28911826 <lb/>103. Ohsumi Y. Molecular dissection of autophagy: Two ubiquitin-like systems. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. <lb/>2001; 2(3):211-216. https://doi.org/10.1038/35056522 PMID: 11265251 <lb/>104. Kraft C, Martens S. Mechanisms and regulation of autophagosome formation. Curr Opin Cell Biol. <lb/>2012; 24(4):496-501. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ceb.2012.05.001 PMID: 22664348 <lb/>105. Hollenstein DM, Kraft C. Autophagosomes are formed at a distinct cellular structure. Curr Opin Cell <lb/>Biol. 2020; 65:50-57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ceb.2020.02.012 PMID: 32203894 <lb/>106. Xie Z, Klionsky DJ. Autophagosome formation: core machinery and adaptations. Nat Cell Biol. 2007; 9 <lb/>(10):1102-1109. https://doi.org/10.1038/ncb1007-1102 PMID: 17909521 <lb/>107. Levine B, Kroemer G. Biological Functions of Autophagy Genes: A Disease Perspective. Cell. 2019; <lb/>176(1-2):11-42. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2018.09.048 PMID: 30633901 <lb/>108. Ma X, McKeen T, Zhang J, Ding WX. Role and Mechanisms of Mitophagy in Liver Diseases. Cells. <lb/>2020; 9(4). https://doi.org/10.3390/cells9040837 PMID: 32244304 <lb/>109. Dikic I, Elazar Z. Mechanism and medical implications of mammalian autophagy. Nat Rev Mol Cell <lb/>Biol. 2018; 19(6):349-364. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41580-018-0003-4 PMID: 29618831 <lb/>110. Gatica D, Lahiri V, Klionsky DJ. Cargo recognition and degradation by selective autophagy. Nat Cell <lb/>Biol. 2018; 20(3):233-242. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41556-018-0037-z PMID: 29476151 <lb/>111. Wen X, Klionsky DJ. An overview of macroautophagy in yeast. J Mol Biol. 2016; 428(9 Pt A):1681-<lb/>1699. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2016.02.021 PMID: 26908221 <lb/>112. Liu XM, Sun LL, Hu W, Ding YH, Dong MQ, Du LL. ESCRTs Cooperate with a Selective Autophagy <lb/>Receptor to Mediate Vacuolar Targeting of Soluble Cargos. Mol Cell. 2015; 59(6):1035-1042. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2015.07.034 PMID: 26365378 <lb/>113. Xu Y, Zhou P, Cheng S, Lu Q, Nowak K, Hopp AK, et al. A Bacterial Effector Reveals the V-ATPase-<lb/>ATG16L1 Axis that Initiates Xenophagy. Cell. 2019; 178(3):552-566.e20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>cell.2019.06.007 PMID: 31327526 <lb/>114. Chen C, Xu P. Cellular functions of cGAS-STING signaling. Trends Cell Biol. 2023; 33(8):630-648. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcb.2022.11.001 PMID: 36437149 <lb/>115. Matsuzawa-Ishimoto Y, Hwang S, Cadwell K. Autophagy and Inflammation. Annu Rev Immunol. <lb/>2018; 36:73-101. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-immunol-042617-053253 PMID: 29144836 <lb/>116. Randow F, Munz C. Autophagy in the regulation of pathogen replication and adaptive immunity. <lb/>Trends Immunol. 2012; 33(10):475-487. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.it.2012.06.003 PMID: 22796170 <lb/>117. Munz C. Autophagy in immunity. Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci. 2020; 172:67-85. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>bs.pmbts.2020.03.005 PMID: 32620251 <lb/>118. Deretic V. Autophagy in inflammation, infection, and immunometabolism. Immunity. 2021; 54(3):437-<lb/>453. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2021.01.018 PMID: 33691134 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>31 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>119. Cuda CM, Pope RM, Perlman H. The inflammatory role of phagocyte apoptotic pathways in rheumatic <lb/>diseases. Nat Rev Rheumatol. 2016; 12(9):543-558. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrrheum.2016.132 <lb/>PMID: 27549026 <lb/>120. Vomero M, Barbati C, Colasanti T, Perricone C, Novelli L, Ceccarelli F, et al. Autophagy and Rheuma-<lb/>toid Arthritis: Current Knowledges and Future Perspectives. Front Immunol. 2018; 9(1577). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.01577 PMID: 30072986 <lb/>121. Karami J, Masoumi M, Khorramdelazad H, Bashiri H, Darvishi P, Sereshki HA, et al. Role of autophagy <lb/>in the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis: Latest evidence and therapeutic approaches. Life Sci. <lb/>2020; 254(117734). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117734 PMID: 32380080 <lb/>122. Retnakumar SV, Muller S. Pharmacological Autophagy Regulators as Therapeutic Agents for Inflam-<lb/>matory Bowel Diseases. Trends Mol Med. 2019; 25(6):516-537. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molmed. <lb/>2019.03.002 PMID: 30952481 <lb/>123. Jostins L, Ripke S, Weersma RK, Duerr RH, McGovern DP, Hui KY, et al. Host-microbe interactions <lb/>have shaped the genetic architecture of inflammatory bowel disease. Nature. 2012; 491(7422):119-<lb/>124. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11582 PMID: 23128233 <lb/>124. Harley JB, Alarcon-Riquelme ME, Criswell LA, Jacob CO, Kimberly RP, Moser KL, et al. Genome-<lb/>wide association scan in women with systemic lupus erythematosus identifies susceptibility variants in <lb/>ITGAM, PXK, KIAA1542 and other loci. Nat Genet. 2008; 40(2):204-210. https://doi.org/10.1038/ng. <lb/>81 PMID: 18204446 <lb/>125. Salem M, Ammitzboell M, Nys K, Seidelin JB, Nielsen OH. ATG16L1: A multifunctional susceptibility <lb/>factor in Crohn disease. Autophagy. 2015; 11(4):585-594. https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2015. <lb/>1017187 PMID: 25906181 <lb/>126. Cadwell K, Patel KK, Komatsu M, Virgin HW, Stappenbeck TS. A common role for Atg16L1, Atg5 and <lb/>Atg7 in small intestinal Paneth cells and Crohn disease. Autophagy. 2009; 5(2):250-252. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.4161/auto.5.2.7560 PMID: 19139628 <lb/>127. Ardali R, Kazemipour N, Nazifi S, Lankarani KB, Jahromi IR, Sepehrimanesh M. Pathophysiological <lb/>role of Atg5 in human ulcerative colitis. Intest Res. 2020; 18(4):421-429. https://doi.org/10.5217/ir. <lb/>2019.00120 PMID: 32380583 <lb/>128. Lo Faro ML, Fox B, Whatmore JL, Winyard PG, Whiteman M. Hydrogen sulfide and nitric oxide inter-<lb/>actions in inflammation. Nitric Oxide. 2014; 41(SI):38-47. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.niox.2014.05.014 <lb/>PMID: 24929214 <lb/>129. Zhao G, Li W, Chen D, Henry JR, Li H, Chen Z, et al. A Novel, Selective Inhibitor of Fibroblast Growth <lb/>Factor Receptors That Shows a Potent Broad Spectrum of Antitumor Activity in Several Tumor Xeno-<lb/>graft Models. Mol Cancer Ther. 2011; 10(11):2200-2210. https://doi.org/10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-11-<lb/>0306 PMID: 21900693 <lb/>130. Michael M, Bang Y, Park YS, Kang Y, Kim TM, Hamid O, et al. A Phase 1 Study of LY2874455, an <lb/>Oral Selective pan-FGFR Inhibitor, in Patients with Advanced Cancer. Target Oncol. 2017; 12(4):463-<lb/>474. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11523-017-0502-9 PMID: 28589492 <lb/>131. He C, Hu X, Weston TA, Jung RS, Sandhu J, Huang S, et al. Macrophages release plasma mem-<lb/>brane-derived particles rich in accessible cholesterol. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2018; 115(36): <lb/>E8499-E8508. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1810724115 PMID: 30127022 <lb/>132. He C, Jiang H, Song W, Riezman H, Tontonoz P, Weston TA, et al. Cultured macrophages transfer <lb/>surplus cholesterol into adjacent cells in the absence of serum or high-density lipoproteins. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A. 2020; 117(19):10476-10483. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1922879117 PMID: <lb/>32354992 <lb/>133. Zhang Q, Lenardo MJ, Baltimore D. 30 Years of NF-kappa B: A Blossoming of Relevance to Human <lb/>Pathobiology. Cell. 2017; 168(1-2):37-57. <lb/>134. Catrysse L, van Loo G. Inflammation and the Metabolic Syndrome: The Tissue-Specific Functions of <lb/>NF-kappa B. Trends Cell Biol. 2017; 27(6):417-429. <lb/>135. He G, Karin M. NF-kappa B and STAT3-key players in liver inflammation and cancer. Cell Res. <lb/>2011; 21(1):159-168. <lb/>136. Taniguchi K, Karin M. NF-kappa B, inflammation, immunity and cancer: coming of age. Nat Rev Immu-<lb/>nol. 2018; 18(5):309-324. <lb/>137. Li N, Liu XX, Hong M, Huang XZ, Chen H, Xu JH, et al. Sodium butyrate alleviates LPS-induced acute <lb/>lung injury in mice via inhibiting HMGB1 release. Int Immunopharmacol. 2018; 56:242-248. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.intimp.2018.01.017 PMID: 29414658 <lb/>138. He R, Liu B, Xiong R, Geng B, Meng H, Lin W, et al. Itaconate inhibits ferroptosis of macrophage via <lb/>Nrf2 pathways against sepsis-induced acute lung injury. Cell Death Dis. 2022; 8(1):43. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1038/s41420-021-00807-3 PMID: 35110526 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>32 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>139. Kats I, Khmelinskii A, Kschonsak M, Huber F, Kniess RA, Bartosik A, et al. Mapping Degradation Sig-<lb/>nals and Pathways in a Eukaryotic N-terminome. Mol Cell. 2018; 70(3):p. 488. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>j.molcel.2018.03.033 PMID: 29727619 <lb/>140. Blommaart EF, Krause U, Schellens JP, Vreeling-Sindelarova H, Meijer AJ. The phosphatidylinositol <lb/>3-kinase inhibitors wortmannin and LY294002 inhibit autophagy in isolated rat hepatocytes. Eur J Bio-<lb/>chem. 1997; 243(1-2):240-246. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1432-1033.1997.0240a.x PMID: 9030745 <lb/>141. Klionsky DJ, Abdel-Aziz AK, Abdelfatah S, Abdellatif M, Abdoli A, Abel S, et al. Guidelines for the use <lb/>and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy (4th ed). Autophagy. 2021; 17(1):1-382. <lb/>142. Klionsky D, Abdelmohsen AK, Abe A, Abedin MJ, Abeliovich H, Arozena AA, et al. Guidelines for the <lb/>use and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy (3rd ed). Autophagy. 2016; 12(1):1-222. <lb/>143. Kirkin V, Rogov VV. A Diversity of Selective Autophagy Receptors Determines the Specificity of the <lb/>Autophagy Pathway. Mol Cell. 2019; 76(2):268-285. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2019.09.005 <lb/>PMID: 31585693 <lb/>144. Zhang J, Tang PMK, Zhou Y, Cheng ASL, Yu J, Kang W, et al. Targeting the Oncogenic FGF-FGFR <lb/>Axis in Gastric Carcinogenesis. Cells. 2019; 8(6). https://doi.org/10.3390/cells8060637 PMID: <lb/>31242658 <lb/>145. Wheler JJ, Atkins JT, Janku F, Moulder SL, Stephens PJ, Yelensky R, et al. Presence of both alter-<lb/>ations in FGFR/FGF and PI3K/AKT/mTOR confer improved outcomes for patients with metastatic <lb/>breast cancer treated with PI3K/AKT/mTOR inhibitors. Onco Targets Ther. 2016; 3(5-6):164-172. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.18632/oncoscience.307 PMID: 27489863 <lb/>146. Lin X, Zhang Y, Liu L, McKeehan WL, Shen Y, Song S, et al. FRS2 alpha is Essential for the Fibroblast <lb/>Growth Factor to Regulate the mTOR Pathway and Autophagy in Mouse Embryonic Fibroblasts. Int J <lb/>Biol Sci. 2011; 7(8):1114-1121. <lb/>147. Wang Y, Pan X, Liu G, Liu Z, Zhang C, Chen T, et al. FGF-2 suppresses neuronal autophagy by regu-<lb/>lating the PI3K/Akt pathway in subarachnoid hemorrhage. Brain Res Bull. 2021; 173:132-140. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.brainresbull.2021.05.017 PMID: 34023434 <lb/>148. Heras-Sandoval D, Perez-Rojas JM, Hernandez-Damian J, Pedraza-Chaverri J. The role of PI3K/ <lb/>AKT/mTOR pathway in the modulation of autophagy and the clearance of protein aggregates in neuro-<lb/>degeneration. Cell Signal. 2014; 26(12):2694-2701. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cellsig.2014.08.019 <lb/>PMID: 25173700 <lb/>149. Zhu Y, Deng J, Nan ML, Zhang J, Okekunle A, Li JY, et al. The Interplay Between Pattern Recognition <lb/>Receptors and Autophagy in Inflammation. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2019; 1209:79-108. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/978-981-15-0606-2_6 PMID: 31728866 <lb/>150. Deretic V, Levine B. Autophagy balances inflammation in innate immunity. Autophagy. 2018; 14 <lb/>(2):243-251. https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2017.1402992 PMID: 29165043 <lb/>151. Shibutani ST, Saitoh T, Nowag H, Munz C, Yoshimori T. Autophagy and autophagy-related proteins in <lb/>the immune system. Nat Immunol. 2015; 16(10):1014-1024. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.3273 PMID: <lb/>26382870 <lb/>152. Grosjean I, Romeo B, Domdom MA, Belaid A, D&apos;Andrea G, Guillot N, et al. Autophagopathies: from <lb/>autophagy gene polymorphisms to precision medicine for human diseases. Autophagy. 2022; 18 <lb/>(11):2519-2536. https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2022.2039994 PMID: 35383530 <lb/>153. Nanayakkara R, Gurung R, Rodgers SJ, Eramo MJ, Ramm G, Mitchell CA, et al. Autophagic lysosome <lb/>reformation in health and disease. Autophagy. 2023; 19(5):1378-1395. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>15548627.2022.2128019 PMID: 36409033 <lb/>154. Shi CS, Shenderov K, Huang NN, Kabat J, Abu-Asab M, Fitzgerald KA, et al. Activation of autophagy <lb/>by inflammatory signals limits IL-1beta production by targeting ubiquitinated inflammasomes for <lb/>destruction. Nat Immunol. 2012; 13(3):255-263. <lb/>155. Chen M, Meng Q, Qin Y, Liang P, Tan P, He L, et al. TRIM14 Inhibits cGAS Degradation Mediated by <lb/>Selective Autophagy Receptor p62 to Promote Innate Immune Responses. Mol Cell. 2016; 64(1):105-<lb/>119. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2016.08.025 PMID: 27666593 <lb/>156. Zhang Y, Guo X, Yan W, Chen Y, Ke M, Cheng C, et al. ANGPTL8 negatively regulates NF-kappaB <lb/>activation by facilitating selective autophagic degradation of IKKgamma. Nat Commun. 2017; 8 <lb/>(1):2164. <lb/>157. Samie M, Lim J, Verschueren E, Baughman JM, Peng I, Wong A, et al. Selective autophagy of the <lb/>adaptor TRIF regulates innate inflammatory signaling. Nat Immunol. 2018; 19(3):246-254. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41590-017-0042-6 PMID: 29358708 <lb/>158. Prabakaran T, Bodda C, Krapp C, Zhang BC, Christensen MH, Sun C, et al. Attenuation of cGAS-<lb/>STING signaling is mediated by a p62/SQSTM1-dependent autophagy pathway activated by TBK1. <lb/>EMBO J. 2018; 37(8). https://doi.org/10.15252/embj.201797858 PMID: 29496741 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>33 / 34 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>159. Lee NR, Ban J, Lee NJ, Yi CM, Choi JY, Kim H, et al. Activation of RIG-I-Mediated Antiviral Signaling <lb/>Triggers Autophagy Through the MAVS-TRAF6-Beclin-1 Signaling Axis. Front Immunol. 2018; <lb/>9:2096. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.02096 PMID: 30258449 <lb/>160. Pena-Francesch M, Vanoaica LD, Zhu GF, Stumpe M, Sankar DS, Nowag H, et al. The autophagy <lb/>machinery interacts with EBV capsids during viral envelope release. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2023; <lb/>120(34):e2211281120. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2211281120 PMID: 37579175 <lb/>161. Liu T, Wang L, Liang P, Wang X, Liu Y, Cai J, et al. USP19 suppresses inflammation and promotes <lb/>M2-like macrophage polarization by manipulating NLRP3 function via autophagy. Cell Mol Immunol. <lb/>2021; 18(10):2431-2442. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41423-020-00567-7 PMID: 33097834 <lb/>162. Wang L, Cai J, Zhao X, Ma L, Zeng P, Zhou L, et al. Palmitoylation prevents sustained inflammation <lb/>by limiting NLRP3 inflammasome activation through chaperone-mediated autophagy. Mol Cell. 2023; <lb/>83(2):281-297.e10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2022.12.002 PMID: 36586411 <lb/>163. Bar-Yosef T, Damri O, Agam G. Dual Role of Autophagy in Diseases of the Central Nervous System. <lb/>Front Cell Neurosci. 2019; 13(196). https://doi.org/10.3389/fncel.2019.00196 PMID: 31191249 <lb/>164. Rahman MA, Rhim H. Therapeutic implication of autophagy in neurodegenerative diseases. BMB <lb/>Rep. 2017; 50(7):345-354. https://doi.org/10.5483/bmbrep.2017.50.7.069 PMID: 28454606 <lb/>165. Lee J, Nam H, Kim LE, Jeon Y, Min H, Ha S, et al. TLR4 (toll-like receptor 4) activation suppresses <lb/>autophagy through inhibition of FOXO3 and impairs phagocytic capacity of microglia. Autophagy. <lb/>2019; 15(5):753-770. https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2018.1556946 PMID: 30523761 <lb/>166. He Y, She H, Zhang T, Xu H, Cheng L, Yepes M, et al. p38 MAPK inhibits autophagy and promotes <lb/>microglial inflammatory responses by phosphorylating ULK1. J Cell Biol. 2018; 217(1):315-328. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201701049 PMID: 29196462 <lb/>167. Wang H, Guo Y, Qiao Y, Zhang J, Jiang P. Nobiletin Ameliorates NLRP3 Inflammasome-Mediated <lb/>Inflammation Through Promoting Autophagy via the AMPK Pathway. Mol Neurobiol. 2020; 57 <lb/>(12):5056-5068. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12035-020-02071-5 PMID: 32833187 <lb/>168. Lyman M, Lloyd DG, Ji X, Vizcaychipi MP, Ma D. Neuroinflammation: The role and consequences. <lb/>Neurosci Res. 2014; 79:1-12. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neures.2013.10.004 PMID: 24144733 <lb/>169. Lu Q, Yokoyama CC, Williams JW, Baldridge MT, Jin X, DesRochers B, et al. Homeostatic Control of <lb/>Innate Lung Inflammation by Vici Syndrome Gene Epg5 and Additional Autophagy Genes Promotes <lb/>Influenza Pathogenesis. Cell Host Microbe. 2016; 19(1):102-113. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom. <lb/>2015.12.011 PMID: 26764600 <lb/>170. Park S, Buck MD, Desai C, Zhang X, Loginicheva E, Martinez J, et al. Autophagy Genes Enhance <lb/>Murine Gammaherpesvirus 68 Reactivation from Latency by Preventing Virus-Induced Systemic <lb/>Inflammation. Cell Host Microbe. 2016; 19(1):91-101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2015.12.010 <lb/>PMID: 26764599 <lb/>171. Yu L, Chen Y, Tooze SA. Autophagy pathway: Cellular and molecular mechanisms. Autophagy. 2018; <lb/>14(2):207-215. https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2017.1378838 PMID: 28933638 <lb/>172. Nishimura T, Tooze SA. Emerging roles of ATG proteins and membrane lipids in autophagosome for-<lb/>mation. Cell Discov. 2020; 6(321). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41421-020-0161-3 PMID: 32509328 <lb/>173. Yim WW, Mizushima N. Lysosome biology in autophagy. Cell Discov. 2020; 6:61. <lb/>174. Johansen T, Lamark T. Selective Autophagy: ATG8 Family Proteins, LIR Motifs and Cargo Receptors. <lb/>J Mol Biol. 2020; 432(1SI):80-103. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2019.07.016 PMID: 31310766 <lb/>175. Yao R, Ren C, Xia Z, Yao Y. Organelle-specific autophagy in inflammatory diseases: a potential thera-<lb/>peutic target underlying the quality control of multiple organelles. Autophagy. <lb/>176. Sengupta D, Graham M, Liu X, Cresswell P. Proteasomal degradation within endocytic organelles <lb/>mediates antigen cross-presentation. EMBO J. 2019; 38(16):e99266. https://doi.org/10.15252/embj. <lb/>201899266 PMID: 31271236 <lb/>177. Dengjel J, Hoyer-Hansen M, Nielsen MO, Eisenberg T, Harder LM, Schandorff S, et al. Identification <lb/>of autophagosome-associated proteins and regulators by quantitative proteomic analysis and genetic <lb/>screens. Mol Cell Proteomics. 2012; 11(3):M111.014035. https://doi.org/10.1074/mcp.M111.014035 <lb/>PMID: 22311637 <lb/>178. Cohen-Kaplan V, Livneh I, Avni N, Fabre B, Ziv T, Kwon YT, et al. p62-and ubiquitin-dependent <lb/>stress-induced autophagy of the mammalian 26S proteasome. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016; 113 <lb/>(47):E7490-E7499. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1615455113 PMID: 27791183 <lb/>179. Munz C. Non-canonical roles of autophagy proteins in endocytosis and exocytosis. Biochem Soc <lb/>Trans. 2021; 49(6):2841-2851. https://doi.org/10.1042/BST20210811 PMID: 34783341 <lb/>180. Cinque L, Forrester A, Bartolomeo R, Svelto M, Venditti R, Montefusco S, et al. FGF signalling regu-<lb/>lates bone growth through autophagy. Nature. 2015; 528(7581):272-275. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nature16063 PMID: 26595272 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>A novel mechanism of inflammation-suppression by selective autophagy of the immunoproteasome <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002537 March 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>34 / 34 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>