<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Rural-Urban Disparities in Hospital Services and Outcomes for Children With Medical Complexity</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>JoAnna K.</forename>
          <surname>Leyenaar</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Seneca D.</forename>
          <surname>Freyleue</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mary</forename>
          <surname>Arakelyan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Andrew P.</forename>
          <surname>Schaefer</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Erika L.</forename>
          <surname>Moen</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Andrea M.</forename>
          <surname>Austin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>David C.</forename>
          <surname>Goodman</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>A. James</forename>
          <surname>O’Malley</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:49:12.448Z">11/12/2025 10:49:12 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1001$1$jamanetworkopen.2024.35187</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.35187</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>JoAnna K. Leyenaar, Seneca D. Freyleue, Mary Arakelyan, Andrew P. Schaefer, Erika L. Moen, Andrea M. Austin, David C. Goodman, A. James O’Malley. (2024). Rural-Urban Disparities in Hospital Services and Outcomes for Children With Medical Complexity. JAMA Network Open, 7(9), e2435187. DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.35187</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T10:49:04.423592Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T10:49:04.423592Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Original Investigation | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/>A Randomized Clinical Trial <lb/>Pamela Seron, PhD; Maria Jose Oliveros, MSc; Gabriel Nasri Marzuca-Nassr, PhD; Gladys Morales, PhD; Claudia Román, MSc; Sergio Raúl Muñoz, PhD; Manuel Gálvez, PT; <lb/>Gonzalo Latin, MSc; Tania Marileo, PT; Juan Pablo Molina, PT; Rocío Navarro, PT; Pablo Sepúlveda, PT; Fernando Lanas, PhD, MSc; Nicolás Saavedra, PhD; <lb/>Constanza Ulloa, MSc; Sherry L. Grace, PhD; for the HYCARET Investigators <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IMPORTANCE While effective, cardiovascular rehabilitation (CR) as traditionally delivered is not well <lb/>implemented in lower-resource settings. <lb/>OBJECTIVE To test the noninferiority of hybrid CR compared with traditional CR in terms of <lb/>cardiovascular events. <lb/>DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS This pragmatic, multicenter, parallel arm, open-label <lb/>randomized clinical trial (the Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Trial [HYCARET]) with blinded outcome <lb/>assessment was conducted at 6 referral centers in Chile. Adults aged 18 years or older who had a <lb/>cardiovascular event or procedure, no contraindications to exercise, and access to a mobile <lb/>telephone were eligible and recruited between April 1, 2019, and March 15, 2020, with follow-up until <lb/>July 29, 2021. <lb/>INTERVENTIONS Participants were randomized 1:1 in permuted blocks to the experimental arm, <lb/>which received 10 center-based supervised exercise sessions plus counseling in 4 to 6 weeks and <lb/>then were supported at home via telephone calls and text messages through weeks 8 to 12, or the <lb/>control arm, which received the standard CR of 18 to 22 sessions with exercises and education in 8 to <lb/>12 weeks. <lb/>MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES The primary outcome was cardiovascular events or mortality. <lb/>Secondary outcomes were quality of life, return to work, and lifestyle behaviors measured with <lb/>validated questionnaires; muscle strength and functional capacity, measured through physical tests; <lb/>and program adherence and exercise-related adverse events, assessed using checklists. <lb/>RESULTS A total of 191 participants were included (mean [SD] age, 58.74 [9.80] years; 145 [75.92%] <lb/>male); 93 were assigned to hybrid CR and 98 to standard CR. At 1 year, events had occurred in 5 <lb/>unique participants in the hybrid CR group (5.38%) and 9 in the standard CR group (9.18%). In the <lb/>intention-to-treat analysis, the hybrid CR group had 3.80% (95% CI, -11.13% to 3.52%) fewer <lb/>cardiovascular events than the standard CR group, and relative risk was 0.59 (95% CI, 0.20-1.68) for <lb/>the primary outcome. In the per-protocol analysis at different levels of adherence to the intervention, <lb/>all 95% CIs crossed the noninferiority boundary (eg, 20% adherence: absolute risk difference, <lb/>-0.35% [95% CI, -7.56% to 6.85%]; 80% adherence: absolute risk difference, 3.30% [95% CI, <lb/>-3.70% to 10.31%]). No between-group differences were found for secondary outcomes except <lb/>adherence to supervised CR sessions (79.14% [736 of 930 supervised sessions] in the hybrid CR <lb/>group vs 61.46% [1201 of 1954 sessions] in the standard CR group). <lb/>(continued) <lb/>Key Points <lb/>Question Is a hybrid model of cardiac <lb/>rehabilitation (CR) noninferior to the <lb/>traditional center-based model in terms <lb/>of the occurrence of <lb/>cardiovascular events? <lb/>Findings In this randomized clinical trial <lb/>involving 191 patients with coronary <lb/>artery disease, hybrid CR was not <lb/>inferior to standard CR. Participants in <lb/>the hybrid CR group had fewer <lb/>cardiovascular events than participants <lb/>in the standard CR group. <lb/>Meaning In low-resource settings, <lb/>considering resource availability and <lb/>patient preferences, a hybrid CR model <lb/>may serve as an alternative intervention <lb/>to a standard center-based program. <lb/>+ Visual Abstract <lb/>+ Supplemental content <lb/>Author affiliations and article information are <lb/>listed at the end of this article. <lb/>Open Access. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/>1/14 <lb/>Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/>Abstract (continued) <lb/>CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE The results suggest that a hybrid CR program is noninferior to <lb/>standard center-based CR in a low-resource setting, primarily in terms of recurrent cardiovascular <lb/>events and potentially in terms of intermediate outcomes. Hybrid CR may induce superior adherence <lb/>to supervised exercise. Clinical factors and patient preferences should inform CR model allocation. <lb/>TRIAL REGISTRATION ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT03881150 <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Coronary heart disease remains highly prevalent worldwide, with 197.2 million cases annually and <lb/>182.0 million disability-adjusted life years. 1 In southern Latin America, the prevalence is 1152.3 per <lb/>100 000 population, presenting a persistent concern. 1 <lb/>Individuals with coronary heart disease face a heightened risk of experiencing new <lb/>cardiovascular events. This affects their daily functioning and societal participation and thus warrants <lb/>rehabilitation. Cardiac rehabilitation (CR) is a recommended intervention to enhance prognosis. 2,3 A <lb/>Cochrane review indicated that CR was associated with reduced likelihood of a second heart attack <lb/>by 7% and hospitalization risk by 23% compared with standard care and with significant <lb/>improvements in health-related quality of life (HRQOL). 4 Despite advancements in medical care, CR&apos;s <lb/>benefits, including cost-effectiveness, persist. 5,6 <lb/>Despite this evidence, CR remains underused globally, with only 55% of countries offering a CR <lb/>program. 7 Also, access to CR varies widely, with lower-resource regions, such as Latin America, <lb/>experiencing lower rates. 8,9 <lb/>In situations in which CR is not widely implemented despite the proven efficacy and cost-<lb/>effectiveness, such that the benefits are only reaped by a fraction of indicated patients, it is <lb/>necessary to design alternative models or approaches to lowering the cost and increasing the <lb/>coverage of CR. Studied approaches include unsupervised or home-based delivery, use of <lb/>information and communication technology, delegation of tasks to lower-wage health care workers, <lb/>and reduction of face-to-face sessions. 10 Additionally, proposed strategies involve using more <lb/>affordable exercise equipment and monitoring without telemetry. 10,11 <lb/>Cardiac rehabilitation is a complex intervention affording the opportunity to design models <lb/>adapted to different contexts and, with the advent of the COVID-19 pandemic, to hybrid models in <lb/>particular. In hybrid models, patients transition from a supervised, center-based phase as soon as it is <lb/>appropriate to an unsupervised phase. Hybrid CR has been widely implemented and advocated. 12,13 <lb/>Thus, combining the International Council of Cardiovascular Prevention and Rehabilitation consensus <lb/>recommendations for CR in low-resource settings 3 with studies of alternative CR models (ie, home-<lb/>based or technology-mediated CR, which to date has largely been applied in high-resource <lb/>settings 14-19 ), we developed a hybrid CR model. <lb/>The main objective of this randomized clinical trial was to evaluate whether the reduction in <lb/>cardiovascular events (fatal and nonfatal) in patients receiving hybrid CR is not inferior to reductions <lb/>in patients receiving standard supervised CR. A secondary aim was to compare hybrid CR with <lb/>traditional supervised CR in terms of HRQOL, exercise capacity, muscle strength, heart-healthy <lb/>behavior, return to work, cardiovascular risk factor control, adherence to CR, and exercise-related <lb/>adverse events. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>The Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Trial (HYCARET) (NCT03881150) was a noninferiority, pragmatic <lb/>(ie, in a real-life context), multicenter, open-label, randomized clinical trial with 2 parallel arms and <lb/>blinded end point assessment. This report has been prepared in accordance with the Consolidated <lb/>Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) Statement 20 including extensions. 21-23 In addition, mainly <lb/>as a result of COVID-19 but also because of the political situation in Chile, we adhered to the <lb/>CONSORT and SPIRIT Extension for RCTs Revised in Extenuating Circumstances (CONSERVE) <lb/>Statement. 24 The original study protocol (Supplement 1) and its subsequent amendments were <lb/>approved by the corresponding scientific ethics committees at the participating centers (eTable 1 in <lb/>Supplement 2) and have been described elsewhere. 25 Written informed consent was obtained from <lb/>all participants. <lb/>Eligibility Criteria, Recruitment, and Assignment <lb/>Recruitment began April 1, 2019, and patients were approached consecutively until March 15, 2020, <lb/>when accrual had to be stopped due to prevention and control measures related to COVID-19. <lb/>Participants were included if they were aged 18 years or older; had coronary artery disease, including <lb/>acute coronary syndrome or stable coronary vessel disease diagnosed by angiography or a stress <lb/>test; had access to a mobile telephone; and provided written informed consent. The specific <lb/>inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in eMethods 1 in Supplement 2. Participants were <lb/>consecutively recruited from 6 hospitals in Chile (eTable 1 in Supplement 2). Allocation to the hybrid <lb/>CR or standard CR arm was stratified by center, with 1:1 permuted blocked randomization, and the <lb/>concealment of the assignment was preserved through features available in REDCap. <lb/>Interventions <lb/>Patients in the experimental arm participated in a hybrid CR program. It comprised 2 stages. Initially, <lb/>supervised sessions were led by a physiotherapist at a center; after 10 sessions in 4 to 6 weeks, the <lb/>program transitioned to a self-managed, home-based phase through weeks 8 to 12. The supervised <lb/>exercise sessions involved aerobic exercise, muscular fitness, and flexibility exercise. Each session <lb/>started with 5 to 10 minutes of warm-up, followed by 20 to 60 minutes of conditioning (in exercise <lb/>bouts of at least 10 minutes) and finishing with 8 to 10 minutes of cooldown. Intensity was moderate <lb/>(perceived exertion rated 12-13 on the Borg 6-20 scale 26 and heart rate not higher than 60% of the <lb/>heart rate reserve). Sessions were 2 to 3 times per week. In addition, the first stage included <lb/>individual counseling delivered as a progressive dialogue between the physiotherapist and patient <lb/>during face-to-face exercise sessions. This counseling was based on the theory of self-efficacy and <lb/>supported by an accompanying manual titled How Can I Live Better? 27 <lb/>The second stage in the experimental arm was home based, and it consisted of telephone <lb/>support through text messages twice a week and a total of 3 voice calls through weeks 8 to 12. The <lb/>content of the text messages and voice calls was delivered by a trained health professional, adapted <lb/>from a bank of suggestions, 28 and focused on the benefits of physical activity and a healthy diet, <lb/>recommended behaviors and strategies to achieve these, and medication adherence (eMethods 2 in <lb/>Supplement 2). <lb/>The control group followed the standard face-to-face CR program, which included supervised <lb/>aerobic and resistance training similar to that received by the experimental group. The program <lb/>spanned 8 to 12 weeks with 18 to 22 sessions, based on patient needs and center availability. <lb/>Additionally, there was 1 group education session covering various topics like physical activity, diet, <lb/>tobacco use, and medication adherence that involved a multidisciplinary team. <lb/>Outcomes and Measures <lb/>The primary outcome for which noninferiority was evaluated was cardiovascular events, defined as a <lb/>composite of cardiovascular mortality (death by stroke, myocardial infarction, or heart failure) or new <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>cardiovascular events (heart failure or hospitalization due to nonfatal stroke, nonfatal myocardial <lb/>infarction, and need for revascularization surgery). To fully capture probable events, every 2 months, <lb/>a research assistant contacted the participants to complete a brief health event survey. When <lb/>applicable, for death adjudication including cause, the death certificate with associated medical <lb/>documentation was collected. For probable hospitalization, a research assistant reviewed the clinical <lb/>record with all associated tests and examination reports in each participating center. For all <lb/>supporting documentation, an independent central adjudication committee (with 1 member being a <lb/>cardiology specialist) blinded to participant allocation reviewed all information to make the final <lb/>decision as to whether the event was definitive or rejected, specifying the final death cause or <lb/>hospitalization diagnosis. <lb/>Secondary outcomes were assessed through questionnaires or physical measures by trained <lb/>personnel blinded to participant allocation. Health-related quality of life was measured with the <lb/>disease-specific HeartQoL instrument 29 comprising 14 items covering 2 dimensions (physical and <lb/>emotional). Total scores range from 0 to 3, where 0 is the best and 3 is the worst quality of life. In <lb/>addition, the visual analog scale (0 to 100, with higher scores indicating better quality of life) of the <lb/>EuroQol 5-dimension, 3-level measure was also administered. 30 Functional exercise capacity was <lb/>evaluated through the 6-minute walk test. 31 Results were expressed in total distance walked in <lb/>meters during the test. Muscle strength was evaluated through grip strength (kg) using a Jamar <lb/>dynamometer (Patterson Medical) according to a standardized method. 32,33 The International <lb/>Physical Activity Questionnaire 34 was administered to determine adherence to physical activity <lb/>recommendations as defined by the World Health Organization. 35 The Mediterranean Dietary Index <lb/>for the Chilean population was used to assess adherence to diet recommendations; those who <lb/>scored 5 or more points on a scale from 0 to 14 were considered adherent. 36,37 For return to work, <lb/>work status was queried at baseline and each point of follow-up; if the participants were paid workers <lb/>at the time of the event that made them eligible for inclusion in CR, the date of their return to work <lb/>was recorded, from which the time to return to work was calculated in days from baseline. <lb/>Attendance at each supervised exercise session was recorded to calculate the adherence to CR in <lb/>both arms as a percentage of the total sessions prescribed. 38 Finally, exercise-related adverse events <lb/>were recorded. <lb/>All outcomes were measured at baseline, at the end of the intervention, and at 6 months and 12 <lb/>months of follow-up, with the last time of measurement being used as the primary one. Results for <lb/>the main outcome were analyzed at 12 months but were recorded until a maximum of 30 months <lb/>(July 29, 2021), when the trial ended. <lb/>Sample Size Calculation <lb/>The sample size was calculated using the Sealed Envelope platform, 39 considering a success rate of <lb/>88% in the control group receiving standard CR. Thus, if there were a true difference of 7% in favor of <lb/>the experimental arm with hybrid CR, 84 patients per arm were required for us to be 80% sure that <lb/>the upper limit of a 1-sided 97.5% CI excluded a difference of more than 5% in favor of the standard <lb/>group. The noninferiority margin of 5% was set at 62% of the difference between the standard or <lb/>current intervention and usual care (8%), obtained from a systematic review by Anderson et al 40 <lb/>balancing study feasibility with an acceptable loss of therapeutic efficacy. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>To test the primary hypothesis, differences in proportions of recurrent cardiovascular events were <lb/>estimated as absolute risk difference (ARD) with 5% of the noninferiority margin. Intention-to-treat <lb/>(ITT) and per-protocol (PP) analyses were performed; noninferiority was established if both ITT and <lb/>PP analyses supported it. 41 For the PP analysis, 4 levels of adherence to the intervention were <lb/>compared: 80%, 60%, 40%, and 20% of attendance at supervised CR sessions. The two 1-sided test <lb/>procedure (TOST) was used to test the noninferiority of hybrid CR compared with standard CR. 41 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Additionally, relative risk (RR) was calculated, and survival analysis was performed to estimate the <lb/>hazard ratio (HR). <lb/>To test the secondary outcomes, both the ARD and RR were estimated for binary outcomes, <lb/>and mean differences were calculated for continuous outcomes. Data were analyzed using Stata, <lb/>version 18.0 (StataCorp LLC). For secondary outcomes, significance was set at 2-sided P &lt; .05. <lb/>Results <lb/>A total of 191 participants were included from 283 potential participants, with a mean (SD) age of <lb/>58.74 (9.80) years; 46 (24.08%) were female, and 145 (75.92%) were male. These 191 participants <lb/>were randomly assigned to hybrid CR (n = 93) or standard CR (n = 98), with 89 (95.70%) and 92 <lb/>(93.88%) in each respective group actually receiving the intervention. In Table 1, the baseline <lb/>characteristics of the participants by arm are shown, with no important differences between groups, <lb/>and Figure 1 shows the CONSORT flowchart detailing the reasons for not receiving the assigned <lb/>intervention and loss to follow-up, with details of the data available for analysis at each follow-up <lb/>point by outcome group in accordance with the CONSERVE guidelines. 24 Reasons for the loss of data <lb/>for physical measurements or questionnaires are reported separately, since from the beginning of <lb/>the COVID-19 pandemic, the participants could not be on site for the physical measurements but it <lb/>was possible to administer the questionnaires by telephone when participants agreed. <lb/>Results for each outcome of interest at each follow-up point in both arms are displayed in <lb/>eTable 2 in Supplement 2. By the end of follow-up, 14 participants (7.33%) had experienced a <lb/>cardiovascular event: 5 in the hybrid CR group (5.38%) and 9 in the standard CR group (9.18%). <lb/>Specifically, 4 of the 5 participants with a cardiovascular event in the hybrid CR group (80.00%) had <lb/>a myocardial infarction, of which 2 (50.00%) were fatal and 2 (50.00%) required hospitalization; <lb/>the fifth participant (20.00%) was diagnosed with heart failure. Of the 9 participants who had an <lb/>event in the standard CR group, 4 (44.44%) experienced myocardial infarction requiring <lb/>hospitalization, another 4 (44.44%) experienced heart failure (2 [50.00%] on an outpatient basis <lb/>and the other 2 [50.00%] due to decompensation requiring hospitalization), and the ninth <lb/>participant (11.11%) died of pulmonary-related sepsis. <lb/>In terms of adherence to supervised CR sessions, the hybrid CR group had 79.14% adherence <lb/>(736 of 930 supervised CR sessions), which was significantly higher than in the standard CR group, <lb/>which had 61.46% adherence (1201 of 1954 sessions) (P &lt; .001). In the standard CR group, of the 9 <lb/>participants with reported cardiovascular events, only 1 (11.11%) adhered to more than or equal to <lb/>80% of the supervised exercise program, 1 (11.11%) adhered to 60%, 2 (22.22%) adhered to 45%, 1 <lb/>(11.11%) adhered to 30%, and 4 (44.44%) adhered to less than 20%. In contrast, in the hybrid CR <lb/>group, of the 5 participants who reported cardiovascular events, 4 (80.00%) adhered to 100% of <lb/>the supervised exercise program and 1 (20.00%) adhered to 40%. <lb/>For the main outcome of recurrent cardiovascular events, noninferiority was detected in the ITT <lb/>analysis, where the upper limit of the 95% CI was 3.52%, not exceeding the noninferiority limit of <lb/>5%. This was not the case in the PP analysis, in which the greater the adherence to the intervention, <lb/>the further away from the no-effect threshold the point estimate of the ARD was found and the <lb/>further away from the noninferiority threshold of the upper limit of the 95% CI was found (eg, 20% <lb/>adherence: ARD, -0.35% [95% CI, -7.56% to 6.85%]; 80% adherence: ARD, 3.30% [95% CI, -3.70% <lb/>to 10.31%]). Figure 2 shows the findings derived from the TOST procedure for both ITT and PP <lb/>analyses at different levels of adherence to attending supervised CR sessions. Participants in the <lb/>hybrid CR group had 3.80% (95% CI, -11.13% to 3.52%) fewer cardiovascular events than participants <lb/>in the standard CR group, and relative risk was 0.59 (95% CI, 0.20-1.68) for the primary outcome. In <lb/>the worst scenario (upper limit of the 95% CI), participants receiving hybrid CR had a 3.52% higher <lb/>likelihood of experiencing an event, but this was lower than the 5% established as the noninferiority <lb/>threshold, indicating that hybrid CR was not inferior to standard CR according to the ITT analysis. <lb/>The PP analysis showed that all point estimates did not exceed the noninferiority threshold but the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>upper limits of the 95% CIs exceeded the threshold, indicating that in some patients, the hybrid CR <lb/>was inferior to the standard CR. Finally, the HR for the ITT analysis was 0.67 (95% CI, 0.22-2.06), with <lb/>censoring of 5.38% for the hybrid CR arm vs 9.18% for the standard CR arm (P = .31). <lb/>Table 2 shows the findings derived from the ITT analysis and the PP analysis at 80% adherence <lb/>to the intervention for all outcomes at each follow-up point. eTables 3 and 4 in Supplement 2 show <lb/>the results for the PP analyses at the 60%, 40%, and 20% adherence levels. <lb/>Finally, 3 participants in the hybrid CR group (3.22%) reported exercise-related adverse events <lb/>(1 [33.33%], angina without need for emergency care; 2 [66.67%], nonspecific symptoms). Thirteen <lb/>participants in the standard CR group (13.27%) experienced adverse events (5 [38.46%], dizziness; <lb/>Table 1. Baseline Characteristics by Arm in the HYCARET <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>Participants a <lb/>All (N = 191) <lb/>Hybrid CR (n = 93) <lb/>Standard CR (n = 98) <lb/>Demographic <lb/>Age, mean (SD) <lb/>58.74 (9.80) <lb/>58.83 (9.54) <lb/>58.65 (10.10) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>46 (24.08) <lb/>22 (23.66) <lb/>24 (23.71) <lb/>Male <lb/>145 (75.92) <lb/>71 (76.34) <lb/>74 (76.32) <lb/>Marital status <lb/>Married or unmarried partner <lb/>124 (64.40) <lb/>61 (65.59) <lb/>63 (64.29) <lb/>Single <lb/>32 (16.75) <lb/>12 (12.90) <lb/>20 (20.40) <lb/>Divorced, separated, or widowed <lb/>35 (18.32) <lb/>20 (21.51) <lb/>15 (15.30) <lb/>Highest level of education completed <lb/>Primary or lower <lb/>73 (38.22) <lb/>36 (38.71) <lb/>37 (37.76) <lb/>Secondary <lb/>63 (32.98) <lb/>29 (31.18) <lb/>34 (34.69) <lb/>Postsecondary <lb/>55 (28.80) <lb/>28 (30.11) <lb/>27 (27.55) <lb/>Cardiovascular risk factors <lb/>Tobacco use <lb/>Former <lb/>28 (14.66) <lb/>13 (13.98) <lb/>15 (15.31) <lb/>Never <lb/>147 (76.96) <lb/>70 (75.27) <lb/>77 (78.57) <lb/>Current <lb/>16 (8.38) <lb/>10 (10.75) <lb/>6 (6.12) <lb/>Adherence to PA recommendations <lb/>127 (66.84) <lb/>66 (70.97) <lb/>61 (62.89) <lb/>Adherence to diet recommendations <lb/>155 (82.45) <lb/>79 (84.95) <lb/>76 (80.00) <lb/>BMI, mean (SD) <lb/>28.82 (4.10) <lb/>28.93 (4.20) <lb/>28.71 (4.10) <lb/>Waist circumference, mean (SD), cm <lb/>99.54 (9.92) <lb/>100.13 (10.02) <lb/>98.98 (9.85) <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>130 (68.42) <lb/>65 (69.89) <lb/>65 (67.01) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>61 (32.11) <lb/>28 (30.11) <lb/>33 (34.02) <lb/>Dyslipidemia <lb/>79 (41.58) <lb/>41 (44.09) <lb/>38 (39.18) <lb/>Other clinical characteristics <lb/>Diagnosis <lb/>Unstable Angina <lb/>12 (6.28) <lb/>7 (7.53) <lb/>5 (5.10) <lb/>AMI <lb/>154 (80.63) <lb/>71 (76.34) <lb/>83 (84.69) <lb/>Coronary artery disease <lb/>25 (13.09) <lb/>15 (16.13) <lb/>10 (10.20) <lb/>Time between event or diagnosis and baseline <lb/>assessment, mean (SD), d <lb/>49.33 (51.82) <lb/>49.26 (51.88) <lb/>49.5 (52.03) <lb/>Treatment b <lb/>Only medication <lb/>34 (17.89) <lb/>18 (19.35) <lb/>16 (16.49) <lb/>Thrombolysis <lb/>10 (5.26) <lb/>5 (5.38) <lb/>5 (5.15) <lb/>Angioplasty <lb/>132 (69.47) <lb/>63 (67.74) <lb/>69 (71.13) <lb/>Revascularization surgery <lb/>54 (28.42) <lb/>29 (31.18) <lb/>25 (25.77) <lb/>AACVPR cardiovascular risk c <lb/>Low <lb/>95 (63.33) <lb/>45 (61.64) <lb/>50 (64.94) <lb/>Moderate <lb/>33 (22.00) <lb/>15 (20.55) <lb/>18 (23.38) <lb/>High <lb/>22 (14.67) <lb/>13 (17.81) <lb/>9 (11.69) <lb/>Abbreviations: AACVPR, American Association of <lb/>Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation; AMI, <lb/>acute myocardial infarction; BMI, body mass index <lb/>(calculated as weight in kilograms divided by height in <lb/>meters squared); CR, cardiac rehabilitation; HYCARET, <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Trial; PA, physical <lb/>activity. <lb/>a Data are presented as number (percentage) of <lb/>patients unless otherwise indicated. <lb/>b Participants had more than 1 treatment. <lb/>c For 40 participants, not all data were obtained to <lb/>estimate cardiovascular risk. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. CONSORT Flowchart With CONSERVE Considerations <lb/>283 Patients assessed for eligibility <lb/>92 Excluded <lb/>69 Did not meet inclusion criteria <lb/>6 Did not attend baseline evaluations <lb/>2 Social crisis <lb/>1 Cardiovascular event before randomization <lb/>1 Declined to participate <lb/>22 Other reasons <lb/>13 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>191 Randomized <lb/>92 Received allocated intervention <lb/>98 Allocated to standard CR <lb/>6 Did not receive allocated intervention <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>89 Received allocated intervention <lb/>93 Allocated to hybrid CR <lb/>4 Did not receive allocated intervention <lb/>3 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>1 Social crisis <lb/>0 Lost to follow-up for primary outcome <lb/>12 Lost to follow-up for secondary outcomes <lb/>92 Analyzed for primary outcome <lb/>Baseline <lb/>90 Analyzed <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>6 mo <lb/>21 Analyzed <lb/>71 Missing <lb/>62 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Did not attend <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 Died <lb/>12 mo <lb/>12 Analyzed <lb/>80 Missing <lb/>70 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>3 Did not attend <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 Died <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>48 Analyzed <lb/>44 Missing <lb/>31 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>6 Did not attend <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 Died <lb/>Physical measures <lb/>Baseline <lb/>90 Analyzed <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>6 mo <lb/>55 Analyzed <lb/>37 Missing <lb/>24 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>6 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 Died <lb/>12 mo <lb/>78 Analyzed <lb/>14 Missing <lb/>6 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>1 Died <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>63 Analyzed <lb/>29 Missing <lb/>16 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>6 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>4 Dropped out <lb/>2 Lost to follow-up <lb/>1 Died <lb/>Questionnaires <lb/>0 Lost to follow-up for primary outcome <lb/>16 Lost to follow-up for secondary outcomes <lb/>89 Analyzed for primary outcome <lb/>Baseline <lb/>89 Analyzed <lb/>0 Lost to follow-up <lb/>6 mo <lb/>25 Analyzed <lb/>64 Missing <lb/>57 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>4 Did not attend <lb/>3 Died <lb/>12 mo <lb/>11 Analyzed <lb/>78 Missing <lb/>72 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>3 Did not attend <lb/>3 Died <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>50 Analyzed <lb/>39 Missing <lb/>32 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>4 Did not attend <lb/>3 Died <lb/>Physical measures <lb/>6 mo <lb/>63 Analyzed <lb/>26 Missing <lb/>16 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>7 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>3 Died <lb/>12 mo <lb/>80 Analyzed <lb/>9 Missing <lb/>4 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>3 Died <lb/>2 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>66 Analyzed <lb/>23 Missing <lb/>12 Did not attend or answer telephone <lb/>8 COVID-19 lockdown <lb/>3 Died <lb/>Baseline <lb/>89 Analyzed <lb/>0 Lost to follow-up <lb/>Questionnaires <lb/>CR indicates cardiac rehabilitation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>2 [15.38%], substantial palpitations; 1 [7.69%], syncope; 1 [7.69%], hypertensive crisis; 1 [7.69%], <lb/>hypotension; 1 [7.69%], angina without the need for emergency care; 2 [15.38%], nonspecific <lb/>symptoms). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This randomized clinical trial tested a CR model incorporating low-tech delivery modes, which was <lb/>well suited for infection prevention and control, consistent with models widely implemented <lb/>worldwide during the pandemic. 42 However, this trial, like many others, was hampered by COVID-19. <lb/>The findings indicate that hybrid CR was noninferior to standard CR in ITT analysis but not in PP <lb/>analysis. While it is suggested that noninferiority should be demonstrated in both analyses, 2 <lb/>Figure 2. Absolute Risk Differences for the Main Outcome of Recurrent Cardiovascular Events <lb/>by Intention-to-Treat and Per-Protocol Analyses <lb/>-12 <lb/>11 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>Risk difference, % (95% CI) <lb/>Favors hybrid cardiac rehabilitation Favors standard cardiac rehabilitation <lb/>Risk difference, <lb/>% (95% CI) <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Intention to treat <lb/>Per protocol <lb/>-3.8 (-11.1 to 3.5) <lb/>20% Adherence -0.4 (-7.6 to 6.8) <lb/>40% Adherence 0.5 (-7.2 to 8.2) <lb/>60% Adherence 1.3 (-5.9 to 8.7) <lb/>80% Adherence 3.3 (-3.7 to 10.0) <lb/>The no difference threshold corresponds to 0% and <lb/>the noninferiority limit (orange dashed line) to 5%. <lb/>Table 2. Between-Group Effects by Assessment Point in ITT and PP Analyses at Adherence of 80% or Greater to Supervised Sessions <lb/>Outcome <lb/>ITT analysis a <lb/>PP analysis at ≥80% adherence to supervised sessions b <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>6 mo <lb/>12 mo <lb/>End of intervention <lb/>6 mo <lb/>12 mo <lb/>ARD (95% CI) <lb/>Recurrent <lb/>cardiovascular events <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>-0.04 (-0.11 to 0.04) <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>0.03 (-0.04 to 0.10) <lb/>Adherence to physical <lb/>activity <lb/>recommendations <lb/>0.07 (-0.03 to 0.17) <lb/>0.11 (0.01 to 0.22) <lb/>0.04 (-0.06 to 0.14) <lb/>0.05 (-0.06 to 0.16) 0.02 (-0.09 to 0.13) <lb/>0.01 (-0.13 to 0.11) <lb/>Adherence to diet <lb/>recommendations <lb/>0.04 (-0.14 to 0.06) <lb/>0.08 (-0.18 to 0.02) <lb/>0.02 (-0.11 to 0.08) <lb/>0.01 (-0.10 to 0.12) 0.09 (-0.22 to 0.04) <lb/>0.05 (-0.16 to 0.07) <lb/>RR (95% CI) <lb/>Recurrent <lb/>cardiovascular events <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>0.59 (0.20 to 1.68) <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>2.42 (0.28 to 20.97) <lb/>Adherence to physical <lb/>activity <lb/>recommendations <lb/>1.07 (0.96 to 1.20) <lb/>1.14 (1.01 to 1.30) <lb/>1.05 (0.94 to 1.17) <lb/>1.05 (0.93 to 1.19) <lb/>1.02 (0.90 to 1.16) <lb/>0.98 (0.87 to 1.11) <lb/>Adherence to diet <lb/>recommendations <lb/>0.67 (0.22 to 2.00) <lb/>0.37 (0.10 to 1.35) <lb/>0.85 (0.35 to 2.10) <lb/>1.19 (0.30 to 4.70) <lb/>0.30 (0.06 to 1.56) <lb/>0.58 (0.15 to 2.18) <lb/>Difference, mean (95% CI) <lb/>Heart QOL <lb/>Global <lb/>-0.06 (-0.22 to 0.11) <lb/>0.06 (-0.09 to 0.20) <lb/>-0.04 (-0.22 to 0.13) <lb/>0.01 (-0.20 to 0.22) 0.09 (-0.09 to 0.27) <lb/>0.06 (-0.13 to 0.24) <lb/>Physical function <lb/>-0.07 (-0.22 to 0.08) <lb/>-0.00 (-0.16 to 0.16) -0.11 (-0.29 to 0.60) <lb/>-0.04 (-0.23 to 0.16) -0.00 (-0.20 to 0.19) -0.07 (-0.27 to 0.13) <lb/>Emotional function <lb/>-0.05 (-0.24 to 0.14) <lb/>0.09 (-0.07 to 0.25) <lb/>-0.01 (-0.20 to 0.19) <lb/>0.04 (-0.20 to 0.28) 0.14 (-0.05 to 0.33) <lb/>0.12 (-0.08 to 0.34) <lb/>EQ-5D, VAS <lb/>-2.22 (-8.12 to 3.69) <lb/>-0.45 (-7.76 to 6.86) -0.08 (-5.79 to 5.63) <lb/>ISS <lb/>1.26 (-0.98 to 2.31) <lb/>-0.84 (-1.22 to 1.01) <lb/>Exercise capacity, m <lb/>26.12 (-26.34 to <lb/>78.59) <lb/>40.58 (-13.63 to <lb/>94.78) <lb/>ISS <lb/>-16.77 (-74.37 to <lb/>40.83) <lb/>ISS <lb/>ISS <lb/>Muscle strength, kg <lb/>-1.02 (-2.95 to 0.91) <lb/>1.07 (-2.19 to 4.33) <lb/>ISS <lb/>ISS <lb/>ISS <lb/>ISS <lb/>Return to work <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>5.25 (-45.48 to 55.99) NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>NAT <lb/>Abbreviations: ARD, absolute risk difference; CR, cardiac rehabilitation; EQ-5D, EuroQol <lb/>5-dimension measure; ISS, insufficient sample size; ITT, intention-to-treat; NAT, not <lb/>assessed at this time point; PP, per-protocol; QOL quality of life; RR, relative risk; VAS, <lb/>visual analog scale. <lb/>a The hybrid CR arm included 93 participants, and the standard CR arm, 98 participants. <lb/>b The hybrid CR arm included 71 participants, and the standard CR arm, 43 participants. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>important considerations arose. First, due to the COVID-19 pandemic, recruitment of new <lb/>participants was suspended, leading to a revised sample size based on different assumptions and <lb/>potentially affecting statistical power. Second, PP analyses exclude participants who do not adhere <lb/>to treatment; in our trial, adherence differed significantly by trial arm, raising the possibility of <lb/>exclusion bias. 41 As previously stated, in the standard CR group, of the participants with reported <lb/>cardiovascular events, only 1 adhered to more than or equal to 80% of the supervised exercise <lb/>program, and of the 5 participants in the hybrid CR group who reported cardiovascular events, 4 <lb/>adhered to 100% of the supervised exercise program. This diluted the event differences in favor of <lb/>the hybrid CR group, as suggested by the ITT analysis. <lb/>Other trials of hybrid CR are limited, particularly in low-income settings for patients with <lb/>coronary conditions. Additionally, interventions vary widely and often cannot be directly compared <lb/>with our study&apos;s approach given the inherently complex nature of CR. 43 One of the first such studies <lb/>in the US examined hybrid CR in 80 patients with low to moderate cardiac risk. 44 The study&apos;s <lb/>intervention, similar to ours but extended by 3 months (totaling 6 months), found that the low-cost <lb/>hybrid model was as effective as a traditional CR protocol in physiological outcomes, exercise <lb/>adherence, and program participation. <lb/>Two recent studies 45,46 also found similar conclusions regarding comparable effects including <lb/>feasibility, safety, and effectiveness outcomes, such as quality of life, mental health, and functional <lb/>capacity. Pakrad et al, 45 in a study involving 107 patients with coronary artery bypass graft in Iran, <lb/>compared a 12-session supervised CR program over 1 month with the same program supplemented <lb/>by 3 months of smartphone-delivered care involving 24 contacts through a mobile app. While the <lb/>intervention was hybrid and implemented in a middle-income setting, it had a longer duration <lb/>compared with the control group. A strength of HYCARET is that although we integrated technology <lb/>in a more basic yet arguably feasible and adoptable manner through telephone calls and text <lb/>messages, we also ensured an equivalent 3-month follow-up period for both groups to eliminate <lb/>alternative explanations for our findings. A study by Meslet et al 46 in France involved 60 patients <lb/>recovering from an acute coronary syndrome within the past 3 months. Unlike HYCARET, that study <lb/>compared a fully center-based CR control group with a partially center-based CR group. The <lb/>experimental group initially had only 5 sessions of supervised CR followed by the remainder at an <lb/>equipped sport and community center. In addition, 2 systematic reviews 47,48 involving other patients <lb/>showed comparable effectiveness between hybrid and standard CR in terms of functional capacity <lb/>but contradictory results in relation to quality of life, without considering the occurrence of <lb/>cardiovascular events as an outcome of interest. <lb/>The current trial contributes to the literature in several ways. It was designed with a <lb/>noninferiority hypothesis, which distinguishes it from the previously mentioned trials, 45,46 in which <lb/>a superiority hypothesis was assumed and, in most cases, equivalence conclusions were reached. <lb/>Also, from a more clinical point of view, fatal and nonfatal cardiovascular events served as the main <lb/>outcome, and there was a long, 1-year follow-up; these are unique strengths in the cardiac <lb/>rehabilitation and exercise field. Despite the need for CR being greater and resources being fewer (so <lb/>that leveraging technology in CR may be more cost-effective) in low-resource settings, 49 this is 1 of <lb/>few hybrid CR trials conducted in a low-resource setting; CR interventions designed in higher-<lb/>resource settings are generally not transferable for multilevel reasons. 50 In the HYCARET model, the <lb/>supervised phase minimized resource requirements (eg, professionals and equipment), and the <lb/>latter, unsupervised phase was mobile telephone supported, which is potentially a more accessible, <lb/>efficient, and feasible intervention for settings such as in Latin American countries. 50 <lb/>Limitations <lb/>This study has limitations, and caution is warranted when interpreting these results. First, the <lb/>adjustment to sample size and the substantial loss to follow-up for secondary outcome measures due <lb/>to extenuating circumstances limited power and precision in effect estimates. Second, the feasibility <lb/>rationale for setting a noninferiority limit may be questionable, but setting a limit considering all <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>clinical factors and patient perspectives would make this and almost all noninferiority trials <lb/>unfeasible. 51 These 2 limitations may be overcome as more interventions like this one are studied and <lb/>results are aggregated in future meta-analyses. 51 Third, while the trial was conducted in a Latin <lb/>American country, generalizability to other low-resource settings and other regions of the world <lb/>cannot be known. Fourth, the fact that there was no concordance between the findings of the ITT <lb/>and PP analysis weakens confidence in the noninferiority findings despite the aforementioned <lb/>justification about the participants eliminated in the PP analysis. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The results of this trial showed that a hybrid CR model that aims to enable patients to achieve <lb/>cardiovascular disease self-management, first through a supervised, center-based phase and then <lb/>through a second phase of follow-up via mobile telephone, may be noninferior to a standard, center-<lb/>based CR model, primarily in terms of the recurrence of cardiovascular events and potentially in <lb/>terms of intermediate outcomes such as HRQOL, functional capacity, cardiovascular risk factors, <lb/>muscle strength, heart-healthy behavior, return to work, and exercise-related adverse events. In <lb/>terms of adherence to supervised sessions, the hybrid CR model may be superior to the standard <lb/>model of CR. With regard to broad implications, considering the currently available evidence as well <lb/>as the findings of the current study, where resources permit and where supervised CR and <lb/>unsupervised CR are reimbursed, 42 clinical factors and patient preferences should be considered <lb/>when determining the best model of CR for patients, as supervised and hybrid CR are likely also <lb/>equivalent in terms of patient outcomes in low-resource settings. Moreover, the lower cost of hybrid <lb/>CR may enable greater capacity to treat the many patients in need in these settings. <lb/></body>

			<front>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Accepted for Publication: November 16, 2023. <lb/>Published: January 9, 2024. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 <lb/>Open Access: This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2024 Seron P <lb/>et al. JAMA Network Open. <lb/>Corresponding Author: Pamela Seron, PhD, Facultad de Medicina, Departamento de Ciencias de la Rehabilitación, <lb/>Universidad de La Frontera, Claro Solar 115, Temuco 4781176, Chile (pamela.seron@ufrontera.cl). <lb/>Author Affiliations: Facultad de Medicina, Departamento de Ciencias de la Rehabilitación, Universidad de La <lb/>Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Seron, Oliveros); Centro de Excelencia CIGES, Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile <lb/>(Seron, Oliveros); Facultad de Medicina, Departamento de Ciencias de la Rehabilitación, Universidad de La <lb/>Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Marzuca-Nassr, Sepúlveda, Ulloa); Facultad de Medicina, Departamento de Salud Pública, <lb/>Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Morales, Muñoz); Facultad de Medicina, Escuela de Kinesiología, <lb/>Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, Santiago, Chile (Román); Unidad de Kinesiología, Complejo Hospitalario <lb/>San José, Santiago, Chile (Gálvez); Servicio de Medicina Física y Rehabilitación, Hospital Clínico, Hospital San Borja <lb/>Arriarán, Santiago, Chile (Latin); Unidad de Rehabilitación Cardiaca, Hospital Regional de Antofagasta, Antofagasta, <lb/>Chile (Marileo); Servicio de Medicina Física y Rehabilitación, Hospital San Juan de Dios, Santiago, Chile (Molina); <lb/>Servicio de Medicina Física y Rehabilitación, Hospital Clínico Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile (Navarro); <lb/>Facultad de Medicina, Departamento de Medicina Interna, Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Lanas); <lb/>Centro de Excelencia CIGES, Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Lanas); Facultad de Medicina, <lb/>Departamento de Ciencias Básicas, Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile (Saavedra); York University &amp; <lb/>University Health Network, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada (Grace). <lb/></front>

            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Dr Seron had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the <lb/>integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. <lb/>Concept and design: Seron, Oliveros, Morales, Muñoz, Lanas, Saavedra, Grace. <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Seron, Oliveros, Marzuca-Nassr, Román, Muñoz, Gálvez, Latin, <lb/>Marileo, Molina, Navarro, Sepúlveda, Lanas, Ulloa. <lb/>Drafting of the manuscript: Seron, Muñoz, Ulloa. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Oliveros, Marzuca-Nassr, Morales, Román, <lb/>Muñoz, Gálvez, Latin, Marileo, Molina, Navarro, Sepúlveda, Lanas, Saavedra, Ulloa, Grace. <lb/>Statistical analysis: Muñoz, Ulloa. <lb/>Obtained funding: Seron, Sepúlveda, Lanas, Saavedra. <lb/>Administrative, technical, or material support: Seron, Oliveros, Marzuca-Nassr, Morales, Román, Gálvez, Latin, <lb/>Marileo, Molina, Navarro, Sepúlveda, Lanas, Saavedra, Grace. <lb/>Supervision: Seron, Oliveros, Marzuca-Nassr, Román, Muñoz, Gálvez, Latin, Marileo, Molina, Navarro, Saavedra. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: Drs Seron and Marzuca-Nassr and Mr Sepúlveda reported receiving grants from <lb/>the Agencia Nacional de Investigación y Desarrollo (ANID), Chile, during the conduct of the study. No other <lb/>disclosures were reported. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding/Support: This work was supported by grant 1181734 from the Fondo Nacional de Desarrollo Científico y <lb/>Tecnológico program of the ANID, Chile (Dr Seron, Prof Oliveros, and Dr Marzuca-Nassr). <lb/>Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, <lb/>management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and <lb/>decision to submit the manuscript for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Group Information: The HYCARET Investigators appear in Supplement 3. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Sharing Statement: See Supplement 4. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Safiri S, Karamzad N, Singh K, et al. Burden of ischemic heart disease and its attributable risk factors in 204 <lb/>countries and territories, 1990-2019. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2022;29(2):420-431. doi:10.1093/eurjpc/zwab213 <lb/>2. Smith SC Jr, Benjamin EJ, Bonow RO, et al; World Heart Federation and the Preventive Cardiovascular Nurses <lb/>Association. AHA/ACCF secondary prevention and risk reduction therapy for patients with coronary and other <lb/>atherosclerotic vascular disease: 2011 update: a guideline from the American Heart Association and American <lb/>College of Cardiology Foundation. Circulation. 2011;124(22):2458-2473. doi:10.1161/CIR.0b013e318235eb4d <lb/>3. Grace SL, Turk-Adawi KI, Contractor A, et al. Cardiac rehabilitation delivery model for low-resource settings: an <lb/>international council of cardiovascular prevention and rehabilitation consensus statement. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. <lb/>2016;59(3):303-322. doi:10.1016/j.pcad.2016.08.004 <lb/>4. Dibben G, Faulkner J, Oldridge N, et al. Exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation for coronary heart disease. <lb/>Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2021;11(11):CD001800. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD001800. <lb/>5. Oliveros MJ, Serón P, Buitrago-García D, Grace SL. Cardiac rehabilitation effectiveness for coronary artery <lb/>disease by clinical era: trial sequential analysis. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2022;29(1):e18-e21. doi:10.1093/eurjpc/zwaa110 <lb/>6. Shields GE, Rowlandson A, Dalal G, et al. Cost-effectiveness of home-based cardiac rehabilitation: a systematic <lb/>review. Heart. 2023;109(12):913-920. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2021-320459 <lb/>7. Turk-Adawi K, Supervia M, Lopez-Jimenez F, et al. Cardiac rehabilitation availability and density around the <lb/>globe. EClinicalMedicine. 2019;13:31-45. doi:10.1016/j.eclinm.2019.06.007 <lb/>8. Korenfeld Y, Mendoza-Bastidas C, Saavedra L, et al. Current status of cardiac rehabilitation in Latin America and <lb/>the Caribbean. Am Heart J. 2009;158(3):480-487. doi:10.1016/j.ahj.2009.06.020 <lb/>9. Grace SL, Kotseva K, Whooley MA. Cardiac rehabilitation: under-utilized globally. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2021;23 <lb/>(9):118. doi:10.1007/s11886-021-01543-x <lb/>10. Grace SL, Turk-Adawi KI, Contractor A, et al. Cardiac rehabilitation delivery model for low-resource settings. <lb/>Heart. 2016;102(18):1449-1455. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2015-309209 <lb/>11. Moghei M, Turk-Adawi K, Isaranuwatchai W, et al. Cardiac rehabilitation costs. Int J Cardiol. 2017;244:322-328. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.ijcard.2017.06.030 <lb/>12. Keteyian SJ, Ades PA, Beatty AL, et al. A review of the design and implementation of a hybrid cardiac <lb/>rehabilitation program: an expanding opportunity for optimizing cardiovascular care. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. <lb/>2022;42(1):1-9. doi:10.1097/HCR.0000000000000634 <lb/>13. Heindl B, Ramirez L, Joseph L, Clarkson S, Thomas R, Bittner V. Hybrid cardiac rehabilitation-the state of the <lb/>science and the way forward. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. 2022;70:175-182. doi:10.1016/j.pcad.2021.12.004 <lb/>14. Clark RA, Conway A, Poulsen V, Keech W, Tirimacco R, Tideman P. Alternative models of cardiac rehabilitation: <lb/>a systematic review. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2015;22(1):35-74. doi:10.1177/2047487313501093 <lb/>15. Thomas RJ, Beatty AL, Beckie TM, et al. Home-based cardiac rehabilitation: a scientific statement from the <lb/>American Association of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation, the American Heart Association, and the <lb/>American College of Cardiology. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2019;74(1):133-153. doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2019.03.008 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>16. Huang K, Liu W, He D, et al. Telehealth interventions versus center-based cardiac rehabilitation of coronary <lb/>artery disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2015;22(8):959-971. doi:10.1177/ <lb/>2047487314561168 <lb/>17. Rawstorn JC, Gant N, Direito A, Beckmann C, Maddison R. Telehealth exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation: <lb/>a systematic review and meta-analysis. Heart. 2016;102(15):1183-1192. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2015-308966 <lb/>18. Wu C, Li Y, Chen J. Hybrid versus traditional cardiac rehabilitation models: a systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. Kardiol Pol. 2018;76(12):1717-1724. doi:10.5603/KP.a2018.0175 <lb/>19. Jin K, Khonsari S, Gallagher R, et al. Telehealth interventions for the secondary prevention of coronary heart <lb/>disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs. 2019;18(4):260-271. doi:10.1177/ <lb/>1474515119826510 <lb/>20. Schulz KF, Altman DG, Moher D; CONSORT Group. CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for <lb/>reporting parallel group randomised trials. BMJ. 2010;340:c332. doi:10.1136/bmj.c332 <lb/>21. Boutron I, Altman DG, Moher D, Schulz KF, Ravaud P; CONSORT NPT Group. CONSORT statement for <lb/>randomized trials of nonpharmacologic treatments: a 2017 update and a CONSORT extension for <lb/>nonpharmacologic trial abstracts. Ann Intern Med. 2017;167(1):40-47. doi:10.7326/M17-0046 <lb/>22. Piaggio G, Elbourne DR, Pocock SJ, Evans SJW, Altman DG; CONSORT Group. Reporting of noninferiority and <lb/>equivalence randomized trials: extension of the CONSORT 2010 statement. JAMA. 2012;308(24):2594-2604. <lb/>doi:10.1001/jama.2012.87802 <lb/>23. Zwarenstein M, Treweek S, Gagnier JJ, et al; CONSORT group; Pragmatic Trials in Healthcare (Practihc) group. <lb/>Improving the reporting of pragmatic trials: an extension of the CONSORT statement. BMJ. 2008;337:a2390. <lb/>doi:10.1136/bmj.a2390 <lb/>24. Orkin AM, Gill PJ, Ghersi D, et al; CONSERVE Group. Guidelines for reporting trial protocols and completed <lb/>trials modified due to the COVID-19 pandemic and other extenuating circumstances: the CONSERVE 2021 <lb/>Statement. JAMA. 2021;326(3):257-265. doi:10.1001/jama.2021.9941 <lb/>25. Serón P, Oliveros MJ, Marzuca-Nassr GN, et al. Hybrid cardiac rehabilitation trial (HYCARET): protocol of a <lb/>randomised, multicentre, non-inferiority trial in South America. BMJ Open. 2019;9(10):e031213. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2019-031213 <lb/>26. Borg GAV. Borg&apos;s Perceived Exertion and Pain Scales. Human Kinetics; 1998. <lb/>27. Gómez-Pérez D, Seron P, Oliveros MJ, Morales Illanes G, Arancibia MJ, Grace SL. Evaluation of counselling <lb/>materials for hybrid cardiac rehabilitation in a low-resource setting: perceptions of patients and providers. Patient <lb/>Educ Couns. 2023;113:107772. doi:10.1016/j.pec.2023.107772 <lb/>28. Redfern J, Thiagalingam A, Jan S, et al. Development of a set of mobile phone text messages designed for <lb/>prevention of recurrent cardiovascular events. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2014;21(4):492-499. doi:10.1177/ <lb/>2047487312449416 <lb/>29. Oldridge N, Höfer S, McGee H, Conroy R, Doyle F, Saner H; for the HeartQoL Project Investigators. The <lb/>HeartQoL: part II: validation of a new core health-related quality of life questionnaire for patients with ischemic <lb/>heart disease. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2014;21(1):98-106. doi:10.1177/2047487312450545 <lb/>30. Zarate V, Kind P, Valenzuela P, Vignau A, Olivares-Tirado P, Munoz A. Social valuation of EQ-5D health states: <lb/>the Chilean case. Value Health. 2011;14(8):1135-1141. doi:10.1016/j.jval.2011.09.002 <lb/>31. Crapo RO, Casaburi R, Coates AL, et al; ATS Committee on Proficiency Standards for Clinical Pulmonary <lb/>Function Laboratories. ATS statement: guidelines for the six-minute walk test. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002; <lb/>166(1):111-117. doi:10.1164/ajrccm.166.1.at1102 <lb/>32. Roberts HC, Denison HJ, Martin HJ, et al. A review of the measurement of grip strength in clinical and <lb/>epidemiological studies: towards a standardised approach. Age Ageing. 2011;40(4):423-429. doi:10.1093/ageing/ <lb/>afr051 <lb/>33. Leong DP, Teo KK, Rangarajan S, et al; Prospective Urban Rural Epidemiology (PURE) Study investigators. <lb/>Prognostic value of grip strength: findings from the Prospective Urban Rural Epidemiology (PURE) study. Lancet. <lb/>2015;386(9990):266-273. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(14)62000-6 <lb/>34. Craig CL, Marshall AL, Sjöström M, et al. International Physical Activity Questionnaire: 12-country reliability <lb/>and validity. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2003;35(8):1381-1395. doi:10.1249/01.MSS.0000078924.61453.FB <lb/>35. World Health Organization. Guidelines on physical activity and sedentary behaviour. November 25, 2020. <lb/>Accessed June 12, 2022. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240015128 <lb/>36. Urquiaga I, Echeverría G, Dussaillant C, Rigotti A. Origen, componentes y posibles mecanismos de acción de la <lb/>dieta mediterránea. Rev Med Chil. 2017;145(1):85-95. doi:10.4067/S0034-98872017000100012 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>37. Echeverría G, Urquiaga I, Concha MJ, et al. Validación de cuestionario autoaplicable para un índice de <lb/>alimentación mediterránea en Chile. Rev Med Chil. 2016;144(12):1531-1543. doi:10.4067/S0034-<lb/>98872016001200004 <lb/>38. Grace SL, Poirier P, Norris CM, Oakes GH, Somanader DS, Suskin N; Canadian Association of Cardiac <lb/>Rehabilitation. Pan-Canadian development of cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention quality indicators. <lb/>Can J Cardiol. 2014;30(8):945-948. doi:10.1016/j.cjca.2014.04.003 <lb/>39. Sealed Envelope Ltd. Power (sample size) calculators. Accessed August 10, 2019. https://www.sealedenvelope. <lb/>com/power/binary-noninferior/ <lb/>40. Anderson L, Thompson DR, Oldridge N, et al. Exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation for coronary heart disease. <lb/>Taylor RS, ed. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews. 2016;(1):CD001800. <lb/>41. Walker E, Nowacki AS. Understanding equivalence and noninferiority testing. J Gen Intern Med. 2011;26(2): <lb/>192-196. doi:10.1007/s11606-010-1513-8 <lb/>42. Ghisi GLM, Xu Z, Liu X, et al. Impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on cardiac rehabilitation delivery around the <lb/>world. Glob Heart. 2021;16(1):43. doi:10.5334/gh.939 <lb/>43. Taylor RS, Dalal HM, McDonagh STJ. The role of cardiac rehabilitation in improving cardiovascular outcomes. <lb/>Nat Rev Cardiol. 2022;19(3):180-194. doi:10.1038/s41569-021-00611-7 <lb/>44. Carlson JJ, Johnson JA, Franklin BA, VanderLaan RL. Program participation, exercise adherence, <lb/>cardiovascular outcomes, and program cost of traditional versus modified cardiac rehabilitation. Am J Cardiol. <lb/>2000;86(1):17-23. doi:10.1016/S0002-9149(00)00822-5 <lb/>45. Pakrad F, Ahmadi F, Grace SL, Oshvandi K, Kazemnejad A. Traditional vs extended hybrid cardiac rehabilitation <lb/>based on the continuous care model for patients who have undergone coronary artery bypass surgery in a <lb/>middle-income country: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2021;102(11):2091-2101.e3. doi:10. <lb/>1016/j.apmr.2021.04.026 <lb/>46. Meslet JB, Dugué B, Brisset U, Pianeta A, Kubas S. Evaluation of a hybrid cardiovascular rehabilitation program <lb/>in acute coronary syndrome low-risk patients organised in both cardiac rehabilitation and sport centres: a model <lb/>feasibility study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(15):9455. doi:10.3390/ijerph19159455 <lb/>47. Imran HM, Baig M, Erqou S, et al. Home-based cardiac rehabilitation alone and hybrid with center-based <lb/>cardiac rehabilitation in heart failure: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Am Heart Assoc. 2019;8(16): <lb/>e012779. doi:10.1161/JAHA.119.012779 <lb/>48. Tegegne TK, Rawstorn JC, Nourse RA, Kibret KT, Ahmed KY, Maddison R. Effects of exercise-based cardiac <lb/>rehabilitation delivery modes on exercise capacity and health-related quality of life in heart failure: a systematic <lb/>review and network meta-analysis. Open Heart. 2022;9(1):1-13. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2021-001949 <lb/>49. Scherrenberg M, Falter M, Dendale P. Cost-effectiveness of cardiac telerehabilitation in coronary artery <lb/>disease and heart failure patients: systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Eur Heart J Digit Health. <lb/>2020;1(1):20-29. doi:10.1093/ehjdh/ztaa005 <lb/>50. Ghisi GLM, Taylor RS, Seron P, Grace SL. Factors hindering cardiac rehabilitation in low-and middle-income <lb/>countries, by level and setting. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2023;43(2):143-144. doi:10.1097/HCR. <lb/>0000000000000774 <lb/>51. Ofori S, Cafaro T, Devereaux PJ, et al. Noninferiority margins exceed superiority effect estimates for mortality <lb/>in cardiovascular trials in high-impact journals. J Clin Epidemiol. 2023;161:20-27. doi:10.1016/j.jclinepi.2023. <lb/>06.022 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 1. <lb/>Trial Protocol <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 2. <lb/>eMethods 1. Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria <lb/>eTable 1. Study Centers, Location, Ethics Committee Approvals, and Amendments <lb/>eMethods 2. Text Message and Phone Call Content in HYCARET <lb/>eTable 2. Measurements for Each Outcome at Each Follow-Up Point According to the Assigned Group <lb/>eTable 3. Between-Group Effects by Assessment Point in PP Analysis by the Level of Adherence (60%, 40%, <lb/>20%) to the Intervention (Binary Outcomes) <lb/>eTable 4. Between-Group Effects by Assessment Point in PP Analysis by the Level of Adherence (60%, 40%, <lb/>20%) to the Intervention (Continuous Outcomes) <lb/>eReference <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 3. <lb/>HYCARET Investigators <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 4. <lb/>Data Sharing Statement <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation Program in a Low-Resource Setting <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(1):e2350301. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.50301 (Reprinted) <lb/>January 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14/14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 </note>


	</text>
</TEI>