<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T13:16:33.780Z">11/13/2025 1:16:33 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T13:16:26.131001Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T13:16:26.131001Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Examining the influence of environmental <lb/>factors on Acanthamoeba castellanii and <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa in co-culture <lb/>Rhiannon E. Cecil ID , Deborah R. Yoder-Himes ID * <lb/>Biology Department, University of Louisville, Louisville, Kentucky, United States of America <lb/>* deborah.yoder-himes@louisville.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Exploration of interspecies interactions between microorganisms can have taxonomic, eco-<lb/>logical, evolutionary, or medical applications. To better explore interactions between micro-<lb/>organisms it is important to establish the ideal conditions that ensure survival of all species <lb/>involved. In this study, we sought to identify the ideal biotic and abiotic factors that would <lb/>result in high co-culture viability of two interkingdom species, Pseudomonas aeruginosa and <lb/>Acanthamoeba castellanii, two soil dwelling microbes. There have been limited studies <lb/>showing long-term interactions between these two organisms as co-culture can result in <lb/>high mortality for one or both organisms suggesting a predator-predator interaction may <lb/>exist between them. In this study, we identified biotic and abiotic conditions that resulted in a <lb/>high viability for both organisms in long-term co-culture, including optimizing temperature, <lb/>nutrient concentration, choice of bacterial strains, and the initial ratio of interacting partners. <lb/>These two species represent ideal partners for studying microbial interactions because <lb/>amoebae act similarly to mammalian immune cells in many respects, and this can allow <lb/>researchers to study host-pathogen interactions in vitro. Therefore, long-term interaction <lb/>studies between these microbes might reveal the evolutionary steps that occur in bacteria <lb/>when subjected to intense predation, like what occurs when pathogens enter the human <lb/>body. The culture conditions characterized here resulted in high viability for both organisms <lb/>for at least 14-days in co-culture suggesting that long-term experimental studies between <lb/>these species can be achieved using these culture conditions. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa is an opportunistic human pathogen that is commonly isolated from <lb/>other natural environments such as soil or freshwater bodies of water. It is a leading cause for <lb/>nosocomial infections in the U.S. and can infect nearly every organ system in the mammalian <lb/>body including the skeletal system, cardiovascular system, digestive system, integumentary <lb/>system, reproductive system, and respiratory system [1-6]. Its ability to survive in such a wide <lb/>range of habitats is largely due to its large, plastic genome leading to wide metabolic capabili-<lb/>ties [7, 8]. P. aeruginosa is also known to reduce the size of its genome via gene deletions to <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/>1 / 18 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Cecil RE, Yoder-Himes DR (2024) <lb/>Examining the influence of environmental factors <lb/>on Acanthamoeba castellanii and Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa in co-culture. PLoS ONE 19(6): <lb/>e0305973. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0305973 <lb/>Editor: Robert P. Smith, Nova Southeastern <lb/>University, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: September 14, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: June 7, 2024 <lb/>Published: June 24, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Cecil, Yoder-Himes. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/>Funding: &quot;This research was supported by a grant <lb/>(YODERHIMES) from The Center for Predictive <lb/>Medicine at the University of Louisville. The <lb/>funders had no role in study design, data collection <lb/>and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>become highly adapted to a specific niche within a human host [9, 10]. P. aeruginosa has a <lb/>wide arsenal of virulence factors which gives it a competitive edge over both prokaryotic and <lb/>eukaryotic competitors within natural and anthropogenic environments [11-24]. <lb/>Acanthamoeba castellanii is a natural predator of P. aeruginosA. A. castellanii is a free-liv-<lb/>ing, single-celled, lobose amoeba species and is a model organism to study phagocytosis [25, <lb/>26]. Amoebae and phagocytic human immune cells, such as macrophage, share many con-<lb/>served proteins and traits such as P 21 -activated kinase, Ras and Rab proteins, PI phosphatases <lb/>and P1 kinases, mannose binding proteins, and phagocytosis [27-30]. Due to these similarities, <lb/>it has been proposed that adaptations acquired by previously innocuous bacteria to escape/kill <lb/>amoebae can, incidentally, result in virulence factors effective against human immune cells. <lb/>One example organism for studying host-pathogen interactions between eukaryotes and facul-<lb/>tative bacterial pathogens is Legionella pneumophila, which is an aquatic bacterium that sur-<lb/>vives and replicates intracellularly in eukaryotic cells. Amoebae are its natural host but, upon <lb/>infecting humans, this organism is able to survive inside monocytes and macrophages using <lb/>the same mechanisms of entry and intracellular survival strategies employed for their intracel-<lb/>lular lifestyle within amoebae [31-33]. A. castellanii itself is also an opportunistic human path-<lb/>ogen with infections resulting in ocular keratitis and can also cause a rare form of encephalitis <lb/>called Acanthamoeba granulomatous encephalitis [30]. These amoebae are found in both natu-<lb/>ral and anthropogenic water sources such as ponds or sink drains respectively. A. castellanii <lb/>exists in two forms: a metabolically active, phagotrophic trophozoite form and a cryptobiotic <lb/>cyst form. Its lifecycle involves a growth phase and two cellular differentiation stages: encyst-<lb/>ment and excystment [34]. In the metabolically active stage of the amoeba&apos;s life cycle, the cell <lb/>is referred to as a trophozoite. Trophozoites are motile, reproduce mitotically, and can phago-<lb/>cytose prey [35, 36]. Because A. castellanii is a proven predator of P. aeruginosa [37, 38] and <lb/>can be found in the same types of environmental and man-made reservoirs, it would make for <lb/>an ideal natural host to examine host-pathogen interactions. <lb/>One limitation to studying host-pathogen interactions using bacteria and amoeba is that <lb/>often the interacting partners kill each other quite readily under certain abiotic and biotic con-<lb/>ditions [37, 39-41]. This suggests that predator-predator interactions may also occur between <lb/>these species rather than a strictly predator-prey interaction. Therefore, identifying conditions <lb/>that maximize both the survival and the interaction between the partners is critical for under-<lb/>standing the molecular changes that are involved in the host-pathogen interactions and that <lb/>may change over time. <lb/>In this study, we sought to optimize conditions to allow survival of P. aeruginosa and A. cas-<lb/>tellanii in co-culture for short-or long-term interaction experiments. We examined the effect <lb/>of abiotic factors (temperature and concentration of nutrients) and biotic factors (bacterial iso-<lb/>late life history and concentration of interacting organisms) to maximize survival of both <lb/>organisms in long-term co-culture. With the proper conditions identified, ecological and evo-<lb/>lutionary interactions between these microorganisms can be further explored at the molecular <lb/>and organismal level. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Strains used in this study, culturing, and cell maintenance <lb/>Strains used in this study are described in Table 1. A. castellanii strain 30010 was obtained <lb/>from the ATCC. Clinical P. aeruginosa strains were obtained from Norton&apos;s Children&apos;s Hospi-<lb/>tal microbiology lab (strains B84725, B80398, B80427, B80422, B80425, B84723, and PA3) <lb/>from cystic fibrosis sputum. Environmental P. aeruginosa strains were isolated from household <lb/>sink drains in Louisville, Kentucky, U.S.A. (SRP3151, SRP 17-047, and SRP 17-055) [42]. A. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>castellanii cells were maintained routinely in 15 mL of HL5 (per L: 0.5 g KH 4 PO 4 ; 0.5 g <lb/>Na 4 HPO 4 ; 7 g yeast extract; 14 g proteose peptone; purchased premixed from Formedium, <lb/>Catalog #HLG0102) [25] in T-75 tissue culture flasks at room temperature (22˚C) until they <lb/>had reached confluence (* 5 days). The cells were passaged by using a cell scraper to dislodge <lb/>the trophozoites, then a sterile Pasteur pipet with suction was used to remove the culture from <lb/>the flask. One mL of the culture was added back to the flask along with 14 mL of fresh HL5. P. <lb/>aeruginosa cells were maintained in LB Lennox broth (per L: 10 g tryptone, 5 g yeast extract, 5 <lb/>g NaCl; premixed from Hardy Diagnostics, Catalog #C7653) with aeration or on LB Lennox <lb/>agar plates (IBI Scientific, Catalog #IB49121) prepared according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions and incubated at 37˚C unless otherwise noted. <lb/>General method for co-culture experiments <lb/>A. castellanii was cultured in 100% HL5 at room temperature in T-75 tissue culture flasks until <lb/>confluent. Cells were scraped with a tissue culture scraper to dislodge cells from the surface <lb/>and counted on a hemocytometer. Approximately 6x10 3 cells of A. castellanii based on hemo-<lb/>cytometer estimates, were added to 4 mL of fresh 100% HL5 in 6-well tissue culture-treated <lb/>polystyrene plates. The cells were allowed to incubate in the HL5 for 30 minutes at room tem-<lb/>perature to allow the cells to anneal to the well bottom. The HL5 was removed via a Pasteur <lb/>pipet with vacuum suction and the cells were washed 2 times with 4 mL sterile PBS. Then 8 <lb/>mL of fresh sterile indicated medium was added to each well. A. castellanii cells were cultured <lb/>in monoculture or in co-culture with P. aeruginosa strains, grown to mid-log phase in 5 mL <lb/>LB Lennox broth, under the conditions listed below. A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa cells were <lb/>enumerated on the indicated days as described below. <lb/>Co-Culture variable optimization <lb/>Strain optimization: Ten total P. aeruginosa strains were selected and are listed in Table 1. <lb/>Each was cultured in LB Lennox broth and added to A. castellanii as indicated above. Co-cul-<lb/>tures and mono-cultures were diluted into 8 mL sterile PBS in 6-well tissue culture plates for <lb/>the duration of the interaction study to force bacterial-amoeabal interaction. Quantitatively, <lb/>the ratios were set-up to reflect a 1:1 ratio of bacteria:amoeba for each strain combination. Cul-<lb/>tures were allowed to incubate over 7 days at 22˚C and were enumerated at 3, 5, and 7 days <lb/>post-inoculation. <lb/>Impact of growth medium concentration: A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa strains were cul-<lb/>tured in monoculture or in co-culture in 6-well tissue culture plates containing 8 mL of 0.1% <lb/>Table 1. Pseudomonas aeruginosa strains used in this experiment and their respective phenotypes. <lb/>Strain <lb/>Origin <lb/>Colony Phenotype <lb/>References <lb/>PA B80398 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Normal <lb/>This study <lb/>PA B80427 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Small colony <lb/>This study <lb/>PA B84725 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Mucoid <lb/>This study <lb/>PA B84723 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Normal <lb/>This study <lb/>PA B80422 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Small colony <lb/>This study <lb/>PA B80425 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Small colony <lb/>This study <lb/>PA 3 <lb/>Clinical-CF sputum sample <lb/>Normal <lb/>This study <lb/>SRP 3151 <lb/>Environmental-bathroom sink drain <lb/>Normal <lb/>[42, 43, 44] <lb/>SRP 17-047 <lb/>Environmental-bathroom sink drain <lb/>Normal <lb/>[42, 43, 44] <lb/>SRP 17-055 <lb/>Environmental-kitchen sink drain <lb/>Normal <lb/>[42, 43, 44] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>HL5, 1% HL5, 10% HL5, or 100% HL5 at 22˚C for 14 days. Each strain was tested with biologi-<lb/>cal triplicates. The cells were cultured in a 10 A. castellanii to 1 P. aeruginosa ratio. Every two <lb/>days the supernatant was removed and replaced with 8 mL of the respective medium. A. castel-<lb/>lanii and P. aeruginosa cells were enumerated on days 1, 7, and 14. <lb/>Impact of temperature: A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa strains were cultured in a 10 A. cas-<lb/>tellanii to 1 P. aeruginosa ratio in 8 mL of 1% HL5 in 6-well tissue culture plates as described <lb/>for the medium concentration experiment above except the cultures were incubated at either <lb/>22˚C, 30˚C, or 37˚C in 1% HL5 medium for 14 days. <lb/>Impact of starting ratio of A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa: A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa <lb/>were cultured in a 10 A. castellanii to 1 P. aeruginosa ratio as described for the medium con-<lb/>centration experiment above except the cultures were mixed at MOIs of 100:1, 10:1, 1:1, 1:10, <lb/>or 1:100 amoebae:bacteria and cultures were grown at 22˚C in 1% HL5 medium for 14 days. &apos; <lb/>Enumeration of A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa <lb/>A. castellanii cells were enumerated via hemocytometer prior to the initiation of each experi-<lb/>ment. A. castellanii was also subsequently enumerated via bright field microscopy at 400X <lb/>magnification by examining three replicate images within each well to assess the number of <lb/>surviving trophozoites and cysts present during and at the end of each experiment. P. aerugi-<lb/>nosa cells were enumerated via serial dilution and plating on Lennox agar. Cysts were distin-<lb/>guished from trophozoites based on cellular morphology. Trophozoite appear as lobose <lb/>amoebe cells with visible pseudopodia [45]. Cysts, on the other hand, appear as smooth circu-<lb/>lar cells with two distinct visible layers referred to as the endocyst and the exocyst [30, 46]. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>GraphPad Prism v5.04 was used for data analysis. Data were analyzed with either t-tests, one-<lb/>way ANOVAs with either Dunnett&apos;s or Tukey&apos;s post-test, or two-way ANOVAs as indicated in <lb/>each analysis. The effects of life history could not be directly analyzed in Figs 3-5 due to lack of <lb/>statistical power as only one environmental strain was tested in those experiments. When <lb/>required, values of -1, +0, or +1 of the limits of detection (either above or below) were substi-<lb/>tuted for statistical purposes only. <lb/>Results <lb/>To better understand the relational dynamics between P. aeruginosa and A. castellanii in co-<lb/>culture, we optimized several variables to ensure long-term survival of both partners. We also <lb/>sought to understand how life history (clinical versus environmental) of the bacterial strains <lb/>impacted the relationship with the amoebae. Further, we sought to optimize abiotic factors <lb/>(medium and temperature) of the cultures, and biotic factors (ratio of bacteria to amoebae) in <lb/>order to extend co-culture survival of both organisms. The contribution of each partner to sur-<lb/>vival was also explored as P. aeruginosa might serve as a food source for the amoebae [47, 48] <lb/>though at least some strains of P. aeruginosa may have adaptations that allow it to survive pha-<lb/>golysosome-mediated destruction following engulfment [49-51] In contrast, amoebae excre-<lb/>tions/secretions or the amoebae themselves can serve as a food source for P. aeruginosa in co-<lb/>culture [39, 41, 52-54]. <lb/>Impact of P. aeruginosa strain on A. castellanii survival <lb/>The ecological niche from which the P. aeruginosa strains originated may play a strong role in <lb/>their interaction with A. castellanii as different phenotypes of P. aeruginosa display different <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>virulence characteristics. For example, mucoid colony phenotypes or small colony variants of <lb/>P. aeruginosa are associated with chronic infections and lower virulence factor expression <lb/>while normal phenotypes are associated with acute infections and higher virulence <lb/>factor expression [55-57]. Ten different P. aeruginosa strains (Table 1) were tested for their <lb/>effects on co-culture survival dynamics with A. castellanii over 7 days to determine if any of <lb/>the P. aeruginosa strains were either killed by A. castellanii or conversely killed A. castellanii. <lb/>Further, we determined whether A. castellanii cells remained in their actively growing state <lb/>(trophozoite) or encysted in the presence of these strains. <lb/>All P. aeruginosa strains were able to survive in the presence of A. castellanii over the course <lb/>of the experiment (Fig 1A). After only 24 hours, several of the clinical strains, including <lb/>B80427, B80425, and PA3, showed a relatively small reduction in survival compared to all of <lb/>the strains grown in the absence of amoebae; however, all of them rebounded by day 3 or 5. <lb/>Interestingly, PA B80425 did not remain at elevated levels on day 7 and instead showed reduc-<lb/>tion in growth compared to mono-culture suggesting that it is less robust than the other strains <lb/>when in the presence of amoebae. The environmental isolates all survived at a greater concen-<lb/>trations in co-culture than in mono-culture over all 4 time points suggesting that these particu-<lb/>lar strains, at least, were well-prepared for co-culture with amoebae, which is not surprising as <lb/>both P. aeruginosa and A. castellanii are likely to share environmental niches and A. castellanii <lb/>has been shown to aid in the extracellular survival of other bacterial species [58, 59]. An analy-<lb/>sis of the P. aeruginosa concentrations in monoculture and co-culture showed that bacterial <lb/>concentrations typically peaked after day 3 and remained high out to 7 days but were only gen-<lb/>erally increase 1-2 logs (S1 Fig). For two of the strains, the bacterial conditions decreased <lb/>slightly (&lt;1-log) after 7 days but most strains retained their peak values at this time point. Bac-<lb/>terial concentrations were typically higher in the co-culture conditions compared to the mono-<lb/>culture conditions as well. <lb/>A. castellanii survived and stayed in trophozoite form when in co-culture with all 10 P. aer-<lb/>uginosa strains at days 1, 3, 5, and 7 compared to monoculture (Fig 1B), perhaps owing to the <lb/>food source of P. aeruginosa in these cultures. A. castellanii trophozoite numbers were gener-<lb/>ally highest when co-cultured with PA B80389 (normal colony, clinical isolate), PA B80427 <lb/>(small colony, clinical isolate), PA B80425 (normal colony, clinical isolate), and SRP 17-047 <lb/>(normal colony, environmental isolate) (Fig 1B). Raw A. castellanii trophozoite and cyst <lb/>counts are provided in S2 Fig. Data tables for 2-way ANOVA results are available in S1 Table. <lb/>Encystment generally decreased over the course of the experiment in co-culture compared <lb/>to monoculture though this effect was variable depending on the P. aeruginosa strain with <lb/>which A. castellanii was co-cultured (Fig 1C). This variability is most likely due to the low <lb/>numbers of cysts overall in most conditions except in the monoculture in which encystment <lb/>occurred to a much higher concentration than any of the co-culture conditions (S2 Fig). We <lb/>expect that the decrease in encystment specifically in co-culture over time comes from compe-<lb/>tition with P. aeruginosa for nutrients as the overall trophozoite and cyst concentrations in co-<lb/>culture remain steady after *1-5 days. <lb/>From these experiments, it appears that A. castellanii was able to survive with all 10 P. aeru-<lb/>ginosa strains tested, at least for the 7-day duration of the experiment. Trophozoite survival <lb/>was greater in co-culture with P. aeruginosa than in monoculture indicating that A. castellanii <lb/>is able to readily predate on all of these P. aeruginosa isolates. We also concluded that P. aerugi-<lb/>nosa grew more robustly in co-culture with A. castellanii than in monoculture, which suggests <lb/>that the amoebae are either serving as a food source themselves or are producing products that <lb/>can be metabolized by P. aeruginosa. <lb/>To assess whether life history of the bacterial isolates is important for amoebae survival, we <lb/>grouped the strains, those from humans and those from sink drains, and tested for significant <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>differences in the number of surviving trophozoites. On average, A. castellanii trophozoites <lb/>were more abundant when co-cultured with clinical P. aeruginosa strains than when cultured <lb/>with environmental strains (S3 Fig). These results were not significantly different, suggesting <lb/>Fig 1. A. castellanii exhibits increased trophozoite survival and decreased encystment in co-culture with P. <lb/>aeruginosa compared to monoculture. In all panels, 10 0 represents the number of cells or CFUs present in <lb/>monoculture at each time point. (A) Ratio of P. aeruginosa concentrations in co-culture with A. castellanii to P. <lb/>aeruginosa survival in monoculture. (B) Ratio of the number of A. castellanii trophozoites present in co-culture with <lb/>each P. aeruginosa strain compared to monoculture. (C) Number of A. castellanii cysts present in co-culture with P. <lb/>aeruginosa compared to monoculture. Data analyzed with two-way ANOVA (S1 Table). Error bars represent standard <lb/>deviations of the mean. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>that origin of isolation does not appear to influence these interactions. However, we should <lb/>note that these drain isolates may have recently been associated with human hosts as they were <lb/>isolated from households, and this could mean that they are more human-adapted rather than <lb/>true environmental (i.e. non-human associated). <lb/>Four of the ten P. aeruginosa strains tested were chosen for further testing. Three strains <lb/>were of clinical origin (B80398, B84725, and B80427) and represent three major colony pheno-<lb/>types (normal, mucoid, and small colony variant respectively). The other strain was of envi-<lb/>ronmental origin, SRP3151 (normal phenotype). The three clinical isolates were chosen based <lb/>on their colony phenotypes and the environmental isolate. SRP 3151 was chosen due to its use <lb/>in other studies [42, 43, 44] and because its genome has been sequenced and in case further <lb/>transcriptional or metabolic exploration is required in the future. <lb/>Influence of nutrient concentration <lb/>Nutrient levels could strongly influence the interactions between amoebae and bacteria. A. cas-<lb/>tellanii grows axenically in nutrient rich media, such as HL5, but can also grow in nutrient <lb/>poor media using bacteria as a food source. To elucidate the trophozoite growth patterns and <lb/>encystment rates of A. castellanii in different nutrient concentrations in the absence of bacte-<lb/>ria, A. castellannii was cultured in either 1X PBS, 100% HL5 or two intermediate media (80%/ <lb/>20% of each media) over the course of 6 days. Trophozoite levels remained high over the <lb/>course of the 6 days in media with 80% or 100% HL5 but decreased steadily over the 6 days in <lb/>20% HL5 or 1X PBS (S4 Fig). In contrast, encystment levels rose initially for all media condi-<lb/>tions for the first two days and then held steady at low nutrient concentrations (20% HL5 and <lb/>1X PBS) but continued to rise in higher nutrient concentrations. Trophozoite and cyst patterns <lb/>were further explored in mono-culture at a finer scale of different concentrations of HL5 with <lb/>the general trend that the higher the medium concentration, the greater the trophozoite levels <lb/>and the greater the encystment levels, presumably because there just more trophozoites in the <lb/>culture that encysted. The concentration of trophozoites tended to peak at days 0-2 and <lb/>remained steady thereafter. <lb/>To better understand how nutrient levels influenced co-culture survival for P. aeruginosa <lb/>and A. castellanii, A. castellanii cells were cultured in monoculture or in co-culture with P. aer-<lb/>uginosa in 0.1% HL5, 1% HL5, 10% HL5, and 100% HL5 for up to 14 days. We hypothesized <lb/>that the low nutrient conditions (0.1% or 1% HL5) would promote survival of A. castellanii in <lb/>co-culture with P. aeruginosa as co-culturing these organisms in high nutrient medium results <lb/>in high A. castellanii mortality based on pilot experiments. <lb/>In general, A. castellanii trophozoites in monoculture were significantly more abundant <lb/>when cultured in 100% HL5 compared to the all of the lower concentrations of HL5 tested <lb/>(Fig 2A-2C) at most time points. However, amoebae trophozoite numbers co-cultured with 3 <lb/>of the 4 P. aeruginosa strains were not significantly different between the nutrient concentra-<lb/>tion groups after one day (Fig 2A). In contrast, A. castellanii trophozoites were significantly <lb/>more abundant when co-cultured in 1% HL5 than in 0.1%, 10%, or 100% HL5 at days 7 and 14 <lb/>(Fig 2B and 2C). A. castellanii cyst concentrations had a trend of being higher in at 1-and <lb/>7-days post-inoculation in mono-and co-culture but by day 14, A. castellanii cysts were not <lb/>found in 10% and 100% HL5 (S5 Fig). Tied together with the trophozoite data, it appears that <lb/>in higher concentrations of nutrients, A. castellanii tends to die between 7-and 14-days post-<lb/>inoculation as there are few trophozoites and few cysts. <lb/>In contrast, P. aeruginosa survived at high concentrations (*&gt;10 5 CFU/mL) in monocul-<lb/>ture and in co-culture with A. castellanii in all nutrient concentrations tested (Fig 2D-2F). <lb/>However, P. aeruginosa CFU/mL tended to be highest when cultured in 100% HL5 compared <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>to the other concentrations tested particularly at days 7 and 14 (Fig 2E-2F). Taken together, <lb/>we can conclude that 1% HL5 supports the co-culture of A. castellanii with P. aeruginosa and <lb/>while higher nutrients concentrations support P. aeruginosa for long-duration experiments; <lb/>Fig 2. A. castellanii trophozoite survival in co-culture with P. aeruginosa is maximized when cultured in 1% HL5. A. castellanii was <lb/>cultured in monoculture or in co-culture with four P. aeruginosa strains in 0.1% HL5, 1% HL5, 10% HL5 and 100% HL5 at 22˚C. P. <lb/>aeruginosa cells and A. castellanii trophozoites were enumerated after (A &amp; D) 1 day, (B &amp; E) 7 days, and (C &amp; F) 14 days. For all panels, <lb/>solid bars indicate concentrations in monoculture and checked bars indicate concentrations in co-culture. Error bars represent standard <lb/>deviation of the mean. Data were analyzed with one-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s post-test (n = 3 biological replicates). Lowercase letters <lb/>indicate individual comparisons within each strain (but not between strains) and overall p-values for each group are indicated for each <lb/>independent group comparison. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973.g002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>however, this concentration of HL5 does not support the growth/survival of A. castellanii in <lb/>monoculture. Therefore, we chose to use 1% HL5 for the remaining experiments as it most <lb/>robustly supported A. castellanii, which was much more sensitive to nutrient concentrations <lb/>than P. aeruginosa. <lb/>Effect of temperature on co-culture population dynamics <lb/>Temperature is another abiotic factor that could have an immense effect on the co-culture sur-<lb/>vival of one or both of the studies organisms. It has been shown that P. aeruginosa alters its vir-<lb/>ulence factor expression depending on culture temperatures [60, 61]; therefore, it is imperative <lb/>to determine how temperature influences the interactions between these pathogens. We <lb/>hypothesized that, of the temperatures tested, room temperature (22˚C) would be the best <lb/>growth temperature for survival of both partners when co-culturing these two organisms as <lb/>22˚C is roughly the temperature these organisms would experience in sink drains. The optimal <lb/>growth temperature for A. castellanii ranges from 22˚C to 32˚C in vitro [62]. P. aeruginosa is <lb/>able to survive/grow at a temperature range from 4˚C to 42˚C, with 37˚C being its optimal <lb/>growth temperature [60]. <lb/>A. castellanii was cultured in monoculture and in co-culture with P. aeruginosa for 14 days <lb/>in 1% HL5 at 22˚C, 30˚C, and 37˚C. Cultures were examined at three time points: 1-, 7-, and <lb/>14-days post-inoculation. For A. castellanii, the number of trophozoites in monoculture was <lb/>small but detectable at day 1 but virtually all cells had encysted or died 7-and 14-days post-<lb/>inoculation (Figs 3A-3C and S5). This was expected as 1% HL5 is nutrient poor and does not <lb/>support metabolically active trophozoites resulting in the conversion to metabolically dormant <lb/>cysts in monoculture. In fact, cyst levels were generally higher in co-culture compared to <lb/>mono-culture in higher temperatures, particular at later time points (S5 Fig). In co-culture, <lb/>there were usually more A. castellanii trophozoites present in the 22˚C condition than were <lb/>present in the 30˚C or 37˚C conditions at all three time points (Fig 3A-3C). One exception to <lb/>this is the high abundance of A. castellanii observed when co-cultured with SRP 3151 at day 7 <lb/>at 37˚C (Fig 3B). However, because this trend was not observed at day 14, this is likely due to <lb/>biological variability. <lb/>In general, P. aeruginosa grew to higher concentrations at 37˚C compared to 30˚C or 22˚C <lb/>as expected, though growth was robust 7-and 14-days post-inoculation at all temperatures for <lb/>all strains (Fig 3D-3F). This could be due to the exhaustion of all available nutrients in the <lb/>media (except for dead cell turnover) after a few days. Taken together, these results indicate <lb/>that 22˚C is a suitable temperature to maintain the survival of P. aeruginosa with the vegetative <lb/>form of A. castellanii in co-culture over a long period of time. <lb/>The influence of inoculation ratios on co-culture dynamics <lb/>Since A. castellanii is an avid predator of P. aeruginosa, it is possible that a high amoebae:bacte-<lb/>rium inoculation ratio will result in the eradication of the bacteria. It has also been previously <lb/>shown that at low amoebae:bacterium ratios, P. aeruginosa rapidly kills A. castellanii [37]. <lb/>Therefore, we asked whether there is a middle ground that allows for the survival of both part-<lb/>ners. We hypothesized that a starting concentration of fewer P. aeruginosa compared to A. cas-<lb/>tellanii would result in higher A. castellanii trophozoite viability in co-culture long term while <lb/>not having a large impact on P. aeruginosa survival as P. aeruginosa has a much shorter dou-<lb/>bling time than the amoebae. <lb/>To test this hypothesis, A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa were co-cultured with different start-<lb/>ing ratios of A. castellanii to P. aeruginosa to identify which inoculation ratio resulted in the <lb/>highest viability of A. castellanii trophozoites and P. aeruginosa cells over time. The cells were <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>combined in ratios of 100:1, 10:1, 1:1, 1:10, or 1:100 amoebae:bacteria. Monocultures of A. cas-<lb/>tellanii and P. aeruginosa were not assessed in this experiment as they would not further our <lb/>understanding of co-culture dynamics; furthermore, we have already established the growth <lb/>Fig 3. 22˚C supports A. castellanii co-cultured with P. aeruginosa over long periods of time. A. castellanii was cultured in monoculture and in co-<lb/>culture with 4 P. aeruginosa strains in 1% HL5 at 22˚C, 30˚C, or 37˚C. A. castellanii trophozoites and P. aeruginosa were enumerated via direct cell <lb/>count at 400X magnification at (A and D) 1 day, (B and E) 7 days, and (C and F) 14 days. Panels A, B, and C represent A. castellanii trophozoites <lb/>levels while panels D, E, and F represent P. aeruginosa survival. Data were analyzed with one-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s post-test (n = 3 biological <lb/>replicates). Lowercase letters indicate individual comparisons within each strain (but not between strains) and overall p-values for each group are <lb/>indicated for each independent group comparison. N.D. indicates values beneath the limit of detection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>patterns of each of these species in 1% HL5 at room temperature in the previous experiments <lb/>mentioned in this study. In addition, because P. aeruginosa exhibits robust growth in the abi-<lb/>otic conditions described for this experiment, P. aeruginosa cells were not quantitated in this <lb/>experiment. <lb/>The different ratios of cells were incubated in 1% HL5 at 22˚C (based on our previous <lb/>results) and enumerated at 1, 7, and 14 days. We observed that amoebae survival and prolifera-<lb/>tion in co-culture at these different ratios varied strongly depending on P. aeruginosa strain. <lb/>On days 1 and 7, P. aeruginosa SRP 3151 allowed for *3 times the levels of amoebae retention <lb/>compared to the other P. aeruginosa strains on days 1 and 7. This effect was not observed on <lb/>day 14 when survival of co-cultures A. castellanii with P. aeruginosa SRP 3151 was much lower <lb/>in most conditions and P. aeruginosa strains B80398, B84725, and SRP 3151 all had similar lev-<lb/>els of trophozoites (Fig 4). In contrast, P. aeruginosa B80427, the small colony variant, sup-<lb/>ported the least amount of trophozoites at day 14 overall. In general, the ratios of 1:1 and 1:10 <lb/>amoeba:bacteria tended to support the highest trophozoite levels across the time points though <lb/>there was a great deal of variability in these data, and it may just be dependent on the strain <lb/>used. However, the 1:100, 1:10, and 1:1 ratios resulted in reductions of trophozoites to levels <lb/>below the limit of detection on days 7 and/or 14 for some strains. This could be inhibitory for <lb/>long term studies and may result in bottlenecks in the population. Therefore, the ratio of <lb/>amoebae to bacteria that supported the most consistent survival of both partners was 100:1 or <lb/>10:1 amoeba:bacterium for the strains tested. <lb/>Cyst formation was high for all starting ratios after 1 day of incubation and mostly <lb/>remained steady over 7 and 14 days (S5 Fig). Notable exceptions include a very high level of <lb/>cysts when A. castellanii was co-cultured with SRP 3151, the environmental isolate, at a start-<lb/>ing ratio of 1 amoeba:100 bacteria after 1 day and levels over the limit of detection after 7-and <lb/>14-days post-inoculation. Taken together, these results suggest that ratios with levels of A. cas-<lb/>tellanii equal or greater to the levels of P. aeruginosa will most consistently result in the reten-<lb/>tion of A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa together over the long term. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa can be cultured together with high viability of both partners if <lb/>the correct abiotic conditions are utilized. Low nutrient culture medium (1% HL5) is impera-<lb/>tive to the co-culture survival of both organisms as high concentrations of nutrients resulted in <lb/>the death of A. castellanii in co-culture with P. aeruginosa. Similarly, temperature is also an <lb/>important abiotic factor as 22˚C resulted in the most robust survival of A. castellanii when co-<lb/>cultured with multiple P. aeruginosa strains while 37˚C resulted in a significant reduction in <lb/>viable A. castellanii cells in co-culture. Biotic factors such as life history of P. aeruginosa and <lb/>the initial inoculum dose of each organism proved to have strain-dependent impacts on A. cas-<lb/>tellanii survival in co-culture. We concluded from these studies that the conditions that <lb/>ensured the robust survival of both amoebae and multiple bacterial strains were growth in 1% <lb/>HL5 medium, incubation at 22˚C, and a starting inoculum ratio of 10 to 100 amoebae: 1 bacte-<lb/>rium. We note here, however, that we did not recursively test all these conditions for all strains. <lb/>Therefore, there could be more &quot;optimal&quot; conditions, depending on the strain itself. Further, <lb/>we only tested a single strain of amoeba and other strains of A. castellanii may have different <lb/>co-culture dynamics with P. aeruginosa or other metabolic differences compared to the strain <lb/>used in this study. <lb/>Our results with respect to nutrient requirements are consistent with other bacteria-A. cas-<lb/>tellanii co-culture systems and demonstrate that A. castellanii is better equipped to tolerate co-<lb/>culture with many bacterial species, including P. aeruginosa, under low nutrient conditions <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 4. Higher initial doses of A. castellanii to P. aeruginosa cells resulted in consistent survival of both partners <lb/>overall. A. castellanii (AC) was cultured in co-culture with 4 P. aeruginosa (PA) strains at ratios of 100 AC to 1 PA, 10 <lb/>AC to 1 PA, 1 AC to 1 PA, 1 AC to 10 PA, and 1 AC to 100 PA in 1% HL5 at 22˚C for 14 days. A. castellanii <lb/>trophozoites were enumerated via direct cell count at 400X magnification at (A) 1 day, (B) 7 days, and (C) 14 days. <lb/>Data analyzed with one-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s post-test (n = 3 biological replicates). Lowercase letters indicate <lb/>individual comparisons within each strain (but not between strains) and overall p-values for each group are indicated <lb/>for each independent group comparison. N.D. (not detected) indicates values less than the lower limit of detection. <lb/>TMTC (too many to count) indicates levels higher than the upper limit of detection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <body>compared to high nutrient conditions as well as below a 100:1 bacteria to amoebae ratio [37]. <lb/>Our experiments revealed that 22˚C is a good co-culture temperature for these two species <lb/>while 37˚C resulted in high morbidity for A. castellanii when co-cultured with most of our P. <lb/>aeruginosa strains tested. This result is similar to previously published literature that described <lb/>experiments between A. castellanii and Yersinia enterocolitica where A. castellanii viability was <lb/>reduced in both monoculture and co-culture at 37˚C but both Y. enterocolitica and A. castella-<lb/>nii remained viable in the lower temperatures tested (7˚C and 25˚C) [63]. Similar results were <lb/>also observed between A. castellanii and Campylobacter jejuni where A. castellanii viability was <lb/>inhibited by the C. jejuni at 37˚C but not at 25˚C [64]. <lb/>Increased survival of A. castellanii co-cultured with P. aeruginosa in lower-nutrient culture <lb/>media and at temperatures below 37˚C could be due to the fact that expression of virulence <lb/>factors by P. aeruginosa is metabolically costly and some virulence factors have been shown to <lb/>only be expressed at 37˚C in clinical isolates [61, 65]. Though it could be argued that long-<lb/>term experimental evolution systems utilizing P. aeruginosa should be conducted at 37˚C <lb/>because it is the temperature at which P. aeruginosa is able to express many of its virulence fac-<lb/>tors and is also the temperature these organisms would experience inside a human host. It can <lb/>also be argued that 22˚C is the temperature these organisms would experience in their natural, <lb/>non-mammalian habitat and thus would be the better temperature to assess co-culture survival <lb/>and co-evolution between them. <lb/>Life history and colony phenotype did not have a substantial impact on A. castellanii sur-<lb/>vival in co-culture at an initial dose of 1 amoeba to 1 bacterial cell; however, there is a marked <lb/>impact on A. castellanii survival when the initial dose of amoebae to bacteria is altered. P. aeru-<lb/>ginosa strains from clinical origin proved to be more deadly overall to the amoebae than the <lb/>environmental isolate tested by 14-days of co-culture in most of the ratios tested. Interestingly, <lb/>this result is opposite to results observed when A. castellanii is co-cultured with clinical and <lb/>environmental strains of L. pneumophila, though the only dose tested in that study was 1 <lb/>amoebae to 10 bacteria cells [66]. Our results could be due to the fact that some of these clinical <lb/>isolates could have been recently acquired by the host and thus their life history would be <lb/>more liken to the environmental isolates tested; however, this is unlikely, particularly with <lb/>respect to the small colony and mucoid isolates as these phenotypes (P. aeruginosa B84725 and <lb/>B80427 respectively) are associated with chronic infection and heretofore are rarely if at all iso-<lb/>lated from non-host-associated systems. Conversely, it is also possible that the environmental <lb/>isolates could have recently been excreted from a human host into the bathroom/kitchen sink <lb/>drains from which they were isolated, and we have no means to rule out this possibility. <lb/>The results of these experiments give insights into the complicated dynamics of polymicro-<lb/>bial communities when multiple species can act as predators of other community members, <lb/>which is a common trope in the microbial world but less so in the animal kingdom where the <lb/>trophic levels are more defined. Researchers can also use this information to look further into <lb/>these specific interactions. For example, with the co-culture variables identified, it is possible <lb/>to increase the duration of co-culture of A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa without needing to <lb/>replenish the amoebae or bacteria for long-term experimental evolution experiments as seen <lb/>in the research conducted by Leong et al. [67]. This might be useful for studies that seek to test <lb/>broad fundamental evolutionary or ecological hypotheses in addition to further understanding <lb/>other polymicrobial, interkingdom interactions. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. P. aeruginosa viable cell count in monoculture and in co-culture with A. castellanii <lb/>in PBS for 1-, 3-, 5-, or 7-days. Viable cell counts of P. aeruginosa strains are provided for <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">monoculture (solid bars) and co-culture with A. castellanii (patterned bars). Each P. aerugi-<lb/>nosa strain is shown in its own panel with (A) B80398, (B) B80427, (C) B84725, (D) B80422, <lb/>(E) PA B80425, (F) PA B84723, (G) PA3, (H) SRP3151, (I) SRP 17-047, and (J) SRP 17-055. <lb/>Data analyzed with t-tests comparing monoculture to co-culture at each time point (asterisks <lb/>directly above bars) or with one-way ANOVAs for relevant grouped data (bracketed asterisks) <lb/>Asterisks indicate p-values (* p&lt;0.05, ** p&lt;0.01, *** p&lt;0.001, **** p&lt;0.0001). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Acanthamoeba castellanii cell count in monoculture and in co-culture with Pseudo-<lb/>monas aeruginosa in PBS for 7-days. Direct cell counts of A. castellanii (A) trophozoites and <lb/>(B) cysts in monoculture and in co-culture with P. aeruginosa are provided. Data analyzed <lb/>with 1-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s post-test comparing each co-culture condition to mono-<lb/>culture at each time point. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. A. castellanii survival in co-culture with clinical versus environmental P. aeruginosa <lb/>strains. The mean survival of A. castellanii trophozoites cultured with the 7 clinical isolates or <lb/>3 environmental isolates grouped data are shown. Data analyzed with t-test between groups at <lb/>each time point. There were no significant differences between the two groups at any time <lb/>point. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S4 Fig. Growth patterns of A. castellanii in mono-culture in different levels of HL5 <lb/>medium. Trophozoites (A, C) or cysts (B, D) were enumerated over the course of 6 days. Pan-<lb/>els A and B show data when comparing A. castellanii incubated in 1X PBS (no carbon sources <lb/>in theory) to 100% HL5 (rich medium). Panels C and D show data collected from A. castellan-<lb/>nii cultured in a 10-fold dilution of HL5 to further define its growth dynamics over the course <lb/>of 6 days. Triplicate biological replicates were quantitated by microscopy from multiple <lb/>images. Error bars represent the standard deviation of the mean. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S5 Fig. Cyst concentration in mono and co-culture based on (A-C) nutrient concentration, <lb/>(D-F) temperature, or (G-I) amoeba:bacteria starting ratio. Legends for each condition are <lb/>shown only on the rightmost panel. Panels A, D, and G represent data at 1 day after inocula-<lb/>tion, panels B, E, and H represent data after 7 days post-inoculation, and panels C, F, and I rep-<lb/>resent data after 14 days post-inoculation. Error bars represent standard deviation of the <lb/>mean. N.D. indicates cyst levels were not above the limit of detection. TMTC indicates too <lb/>many to count in a frame. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Two-way ANOVA on the effects of P. aeruginosa strain and time on the survival <lb/>of P. aeruginosa and A. castellanii in PBS. Table summarizes the 2-way ANOVA analysis <lb/>output for Fig 1. *DF (degrees of freedom), SS (summary of squares), MS (mean of squares). <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Formal analysis: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Investigation: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Methodology: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Resources: Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Software: Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Supervision: Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Visualization: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Rhiannon E. Cecil. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Rhiannon E. Cecil, Deborah R. Yoder-Himes. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Cerioli M, Batailler C, Conrad A, Roux S, Perpoint T, Becker A, et al. Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>implant-associated bone and joint infections: Experience in a regional reference center in France. Fron-<lb/>tiers in Medicine. 2020; 7:513242. <lb/>2. Bouchart F, Dubar A, Bessou JP, Redonnet M, Berland J, Mouton-Schleifer D, et al. Pseudomonas aer-<lb/>uginosa coronary stent infection. The Annals of thoracic surgery. 1997; 64(6):1810-3. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/s0003-4975(97)01151-x PMID: 9436580 <lb/>3. Markou P, Apidianakis Y. Pathogenesis of intestinal Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection in patients with <lb/>cancer. Frontiers in cellular and infection microbiology. 2014; 3:115. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcimb. <lb/>2013.00115 PMID: 24432250 <lb/>4. Spernovasilis N, Psichogiou M, Poulakou G. Skin manifestations of Pseudomonas aeruginosa infec-<lb/>tions. Current Opinion in Infectious Diseases. 2021; 34(2):72-9. https://doi.org/10.1097/QCO. <lb/>0000000000000717 PMID: 33492004 <lb/>5. Rana K, Thaper D, Vander H, Prabha V. Pseudomonas aeruginosa: A risk factor for fertility in male <lb/>mice. Reproductive Biology. 2018; 18(4):450-5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.repbio.2018.08.002 PMID: <lb/>30181055 <lb/>6. Mendes OR. The challenge of pulmonary Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection: How to bridge research <lb/>and clinical pathology. Viral, Parasitic, Bacterial, and Fungal Infections: Elsevier; 2023. p. 591-608. <lb/>7. Stover CK, Pham XQ, Erwin A, Mizoguchi S, Warrener P, Hickey M, et al. Complete genome sequence <lb/>of Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1, an opportunistic pathogen. Nature. 2000; 406(6799):959-64. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/35023079 PMID: 10984043 <lb/>8. Winsor GL, Griffiths EJ, Lo R, Dhillon BK, Shay JA, Brinkman FS. Enhanced annotations and features <lb/>for comparing thousands of Pseudomonas genomes in the Pseudomonas genome database. Nucleic <lb/>acids research. 2016; 44(D1):D646-D53. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkv1227 PMID: 26578582 <lb/>9. Smith EE, Buckley DG, Wu Z, Saenphimmachak C, Hoffman LR, D&apos;Argenio DA, et al. Genetic adapta-<lb/>tion by Pseudomonas aeruginosa to the airways of cystic fibrosis patients. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>2006; 103(22):8487-92. Epub 2006/05/12. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0602138103 PMID: <lb/>16687478; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1482519. <lb/>10. Lucchetti-Miganeh C, Redelberger D, Chambonnier G, Rechenmann F, Elsen S, Bordi C, et al. Pseudo-<lb/>monas aeruginosa Genome Evolution in Patients and under the Hospital Environment. Pathogens. <lb/>2014; 3(2):309-40. Epub 2014/12/02. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens3020309 PMID: 25437802; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4243448. <lb/>11. Hauser AR. The type III secretion system of Pseudomonas aeruginosa: infection by injection. Nature <lb/>Reviews Microbiology. 2009; 7(9):654-65. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro2199 PMID: 19680249 <lb/>12. Horna G, Ruiz J. Type 3 secretion system of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Microbiological Research. <lb/>2021; 246:126719. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2021.126719 PMID: 33582609 <lb/>13. Britigan BE, Roeder TL, Rasmussen GT, Shasby DM, McCormick ML, Cox CD. Interaction of the Pseu-<lb/>domonas aeruginosa secretory products pyocyanin and pyochelin generates hydroxyl radical and <lb/>causes synergistic damage to endothelial cells. Implications for Pseudomonas-associated tissue injury. <lb/>J Clin Invest. 1992; 90(6):2187-96. Epub 1992/12/01. https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI116104 PMID: <lb/>1469082; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC443369. <lb/>14. Sorensen RU, Klinger JD. Biological effects of Pseudomonas aeruginosa phenazine pigments. Basic <lb/>Research and Clinical Aspects of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. 1987; 39:113-24. https://doi.org/10.1159/ <lb/>000414339 PMID: 3118778 <lb/>15. Denning GM, Railsback MA, Rasmussen GT, Cox CD, Britigan BE. Pseudomonas pyocyanine alters <lb/>calcium signaling in human airway epithelial cells. American Journal of Physiology-Lung Cellular and <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>Molecular Physiology. 1998; 274(6):L893-L900. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajplung.1998.274.6.L893 <lb/>PMID: 9609727 <lb/>16. Lau GW, Hassett DJ, Ran H, Kong F. The role of pyocyanin in Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection. <lb/>Trends in molecular medicine. 2004; 10(12):599-606. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molmed.2004.10.002 <lb/>PMID: 15567330 <lb/>17. Hassan HM, Fridovich I. Mechanism of the antibiotic action pyocyanine. J Bacteriol. 1980; 141(1):156-<lb/>63. Epub 1980/01/01. https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.141.1.156-163.1980 PMID: 6243619; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC293551. <lb/>18. Yang J, Zhao H-L, Ran L-Y, Li C-Y, Zhang X-Y, Su H-N, et al. Mechanistic insights into elastin degrada-<lb/>tion by pseudolysin, the major virulence factor of the opportunistic pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa. <lb/>Scientific reports. 2015; 5(1):1-7. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep09936 PMID: 25905792 <lb/>19. Heck L, Morihara K, Abrahamson D. Degradation of soluble laminin and depletion of tissue-associated <lb/>basement membrane laminin by Pseudomonas aeruginosa elastase and alkaline protease. Infection <lb/>and immunity. 1986; 54(1):149-53. https://doi.org/10.1128/iai.54.1.149-153.1986 PMID: 3093382 <lb/>20. Wilson MJ, McMorran BJ, Lamont IL. Analysis of promoters recognized by PvdS, an extracytoplasmic-<lb/>function sigma factor protein from Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Journal of bacteriology. 2001; 183 <lb/>(6):2151-5. https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.183.6.2151-2155.2001 PMID: 11222621 <lb/>21. Rybtke M, Hultqvist LD, Givskov M, Tolker-Nielsen T. Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm infections: <lb/>community structure, antimicrobial tolerance and immune response. Journal of molecular biology. <lb/>2015; 427(23):3628-45. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2015.08.016 PMID: 26319792 <lb/>22. Olivares E, Badel-Berchoux S, Provot C, Pre ´vost G, Bernardi T, Jehl F. Clinical impact of antibiotics for <lb/>the treatment of Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm infections. Frontiers in microbiology. 2020:2894. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.02894 PMID: 31998248 <lb/>23. Moser C, Jensen PØ, Thomsen K, Kolpen M, Rybtke M, Lauland AS, et al. Immune responses to Pseu-<lb/>domonas aeruginosa biofilm infections. Frontiers in Immunology. 2021; 12:625597. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3389/fimmu.2021.625597 PMID: 33692800 <lb/>24. Hassett DJ, Korfhagen TR, Irvin RT, Schurr MJ, Sauer K, Lau GW, et al. Pseudomonas aeruginosa bio-<lb/>film infections in cystic fibrosis: insights into pathogenic processes and treatment strategies. Expert <lb/>opinion on therapeutic targets. 2010; 14(2):117-30. https://doi.org/10.1517/14728220903454988 <lb/>PMID: 20055712 <lb/>25. Kuburich NA, Adhikari N, Hadwiger JA. Acanthamoeba and Dictyostelium Use Different Foraging Strat-<lb/>egies. Protist. 2016; 167(6):511-25. Epub 2016/10/04. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.protis.2016.08.006 <lb/>PMID: 27693864; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5154823. <lb/>26. Erken M, Lutz C, McDougald D. The rise of pathogens: predation as a factor driving the evolution of <lb/>human pathogens in the environment. Microb Ecol. 2013; 65(4):860-8. Epub 2013/01/29. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/s00248-013-0189-0 PMID: 23354181; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3637895. <lb/>27. Rayamajhee B, Willcox MD, Henriquez FL, Petsoglou C, Subedi D, Carnt N. Acanthamoeba, an envi-<lb/>ronmental phagocyte enhancing survival and transmission of human pathogens. Trends in Parasitol-<lb/>ogy. 2022. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pt.2022.08.007 PMID: 36109313 <lb/>28. Al-Quadan T, Price CT, Abu Kwaik Y. Exploitation of evolutionarily conserved amoeba and mammalian <lb/>processes by Legionella. Trends Microbiol. 2012; 20(6):299-306. Epub 2012/04/13. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.tim.2012.03.005 PMID: 22494803; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3603140. <lb/>29. Kumar A, Molli PR, Pakala SB, Nguyen TMB, Rayala SK, Kumar R. PAK thread from amoeba to mam-<lb/>mals. Journal of cellular biochemistry. 2009; 107(4):579-85. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcb.22159 PMID: <lb/>19350548 <lb/>30. Siddiqui R, Khan NA. Biology and pathogenesis of Acanthamoeba. Parasit Vectors. 2012; 5:6. Epub <lb/>2012/01/11. https://doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-5-6 PMID: 22229971; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC3284432. <lb/>31. Segal G, Shuman HA. Legionella pneumophila utilizes the same genes to multiply within Acantha-<lb/>moeba castellanii and human macrophages. Infection and immunity. 1999; 67(5):2117-24. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1128/IAI.67.5.2117-2124.1999 PMID: 10225863 <lb/>32. Cirillo JD, Cirillo SL, Yan L, Bermudez LE, Falkow S, Tompkins LS. Intracellular growth in Acantha-<lb/>moeba castellanii affects monocyte entry mechanisms and enhances virulence of Legionella pneumo-<lb/>phila. Infection and immunity. 1999; 67(9):4427-34. https://doi.org/10.1128/IAI.67.9.4427-4434.1999 <lb/>PMID: 10456883 <lb/>33. Moffat JF, Tompkins L. A quantitative model of intracellular growth of Legionella pneumophila in <lb/>Acanthamoeba castellanii. Infection and immunity. 1992; 60(1):296-301. https://doi.org/10.1128/iai.60. <lb/>1.296-301.1992 PMID: 1729191 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>16 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>34. Khunkitti W, Lloyd D, Furr JR, Russell AD. Acanthamoeba castellanii: growth, encystment, excystment <lb/>and biocide susceptibility. J Infect. 1998; 36(1):43-8. Epub 1998/11/20. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0163-<lb/>4453(98)93054-7 PMID: 9515667. <lb/>35. Kim J-H, Matin A, Shin H-J, Park H, Yoo K-T, Yuan X-Z, et al. Functional roles of mannose-binding pro-<lb/>tein in the adhesion, cytotoxicity and phagocytosis of Acanthamoeba castellanii. Experimental parasitol-<lb/>ogy. 2012; 132(2):287-92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.exppara.2012.08.007 PMID: 22940016 <lb/>36. Alsam S, Sissons J, Dudley R, Khan NA. Mechanisms associated with Acanthamoeba castellanii (T4) <lb/>phagocytosis. Parasitology research. 2005; 96:402-9. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-005-1401-z <lb/>PMID: 15940518 <lb/>37. Wang X, Ahearn DG. Effect of bacteria on survival and growth of Acanthamoeba castellanii. Current <lb/>microbiology. 1997; 34:212-5. https://doi.org/10.1007/s002849900170 PMID: 9058539 <lb/>38. Siddiqui R, Lakhundi S, Khan NA. Interactions of Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Corynebacterium spp. <lb/>with non-phagocytic brain microvascular endothelial cells and phagocytic Acanthamoeba castellanii. <lb/>Parasitology Research. 2015; 114(6):2349-56. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-015-4432-0 PMID: <lb/>25792227 <lb/>39. Abd H, Wretlind B, Saeed A, Idsund E, Hultenby K, Sandstro ¨m G. Pseudomonas aeruginosa utilises its <lb/>type III secretion system to kill the free-living amoeba Acanthamoeba castellanii. Journal of eukaryotic <lb/>microbiology. 2008; 55(3):235-43. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1550-7408.2008.00311.x PMID: 18460161 <lb/>40. Matz C, Kjelleberg S. Off the hook-how bacteria survive protozoan grazing. Trends in microbiology. <lb/>2005; 13(7):302-7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tim.2005.05.009 PMID: 15935676 <lb/>41. Shteindel N, Gerchman Y. Pseudomonas aeruginosa mobbing-like behavior against Acanthamoeba <lb/>castellanii bacterivore and its rapid control by quorum sensing and environmental cues. Microbiology <lb/>Spectrum. 2021; 9(3):e00642-21. https://doi.org/10.1128/Spectrum.00642-21 PMID: 34851177 <lb/>42. Purdy-Gibson ME, France M, Hundley TC, Eid N, Remold SK. Pseudomonas aeruginosa in CF and <lb/>non-CF homes is found predominantly in drains. J Cyst Fibros. 2015; 14(3):341-6. Epub 2014/12/03. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcf.2014.10.008 PMID: 25443472. <lb/>43. Remold SK, Brown CK, Farris JE, Hundley TC, Perpich JA, Purdy ME. Differential habitat use and <lb/>niche partitioning by Pseudomonas species in human homes. Microbial ecology. 2011; 62:505-17. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00248-011-9844-5 PMID: 21503776 <lb/>44. Mojesky AA, Remold SK. Spatial structure maintains diversity of pyocin inhibition in household Pseudo-<lb/>monas aeruginosa. Proceedings of the Royal Society B. 2020; 287(1938):20201706. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1098/rspb.2020.1706 PMID: 33143580 <lb/>45. Wang Y, Jiang L, Zhao Y, Li M. Biological characteristics and pathogenicity of Acanthamoeba. Frontiers <lb/>in Microbiology. 2023; 14:1147077. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1147077 PMID: 37089530 <lb/>46. Bowers B, Korn ED. The fine structure of Acanthamoeba castellanii (Neff strain) II. Encystment. The <lb/>Journal of cell biology. 1969; 41(3):786-805. <lb/>47. Rayamajhee B, Willcox M, Henriquez FL, Vijay AK, Petsoglou C, Shrestha GS, et al. The role of natu-<lb/>rally acquired intracellular Pseudomonas aeruginosa in the development of Acanthamoeba keratitis in <lb/>an animal model. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2024; 18(1):e0011878. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pntd.0011878 PMID: 38166139 <lb/>48. Dey R, Rieger AM, Stephens C, Ashbolt NJ. Interactions of Pseudomonas aeruginosa with Acantha-<lb/>moeba polyphaga observed by imaging flow cytometry. Cytometry Part A. 2019; 95(5):555-64. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1002/cyto.a.23768 PMID: 30985067 <lb/>49. Niyyati M, Mahyar M, Haghighi A, Vala MH. Occurrence of potentially pathogenic bacterial-endosymbi-<lb/>onts in Acanthamoeba spp. Iranian journal of parasitology. 2015; 10(2):181. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>1746-1596 PMID: 26246815 <lb/>50. Iovieno A, Ledee DR, Miller D, Alfonso EC. Detection of bacterial endosymbionts in clinical Acantha-<lb/>moeba isolates. Ophthalmology. 2010; 117(3):445-52. e3. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ophtha.2009.08. <lb/>033 PMID: 20031220 <lb/>51. Steele MI, Peiser JM, Shreenidhi P, Strassmann JE, Queller DC. Predation-resistant Pseudomonas <lb/>bacteria engage in symbiont-like behavior with the social amoeba Dictyostelium discoideum. The ISME <lb/>Journal. 2023; 17(12):2352-61. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41396-023-01535-5 PMID: 37884792 <lb/>52. Matz C, Bergfeld T, Rice SA, Kjelleberg S. Microcolonies, quorum sensing and cytotoxicity determine <lb/>the survival of Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms exposed to protozoan grazing. Environmental micro-<lb/>biology. 2004; 6(3):218-26. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2004.00556.x PMID: 14871206 <lb/>53. Weitere M, Bergfeld T, Rice SA, Matz C, Kjelleberg S. Grazing resistance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>biofilms depends on type of protective mechanism, developmental stage and protozoan feeding mode. <lb/>Environmental microbiology. 2005; 7(10):1593-601. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00851.x <lb/>PMID: 16156732 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>17 / 18 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>54. Pukatzki S, Kessin RH, Mekalanos JJ. The human pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa utilizes con-<lb/>served virulence pathways to infect the social amoeba Dictyostelium discoideum. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences. 2002; 99(5):3159-64. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.052704399 PMID: <lb/>11867744 <lb/>55. Jurado-Martı ´n I, Sainz-Mejı ´as M, McClean S. Pseudomonas aeruginosa: An audacious pathogen with <lb/>an adaptable arsenal of virulence factors. International journal of molecular sciences. 2021; 22(6):3128. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22063128 PMID: 33803907 <lb/>56. Malone JG. Role of small colony variants in persistence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa infections in cystic <lb/>fibrosis lungs. Infection and drug resistance. 2015:237-47. https://doi.org/10.2147/IDR.S68214 PMID: <lb/>26251621 <lb/>57. Hogardt M, Heesemann J. Adaptation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa during persistence in the cystic <lb/>fibrosis lung. International Journal of Medical Microbiology. 2010; 300(8):557-62. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ijmm.2010.08.008 PMID: 20943439 <lb/>58. Sarink M, Pirzadian J, van Cappellen W, Tielens A, Verbon A, Severin J, et al. Acanthamoeba castellanii <lb/>interferes with adequate chlorine disinfection of multidrug-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Journal <lb/>of Hospital Infection. 2020; 106(3):490-4. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhin.2020.09.019 PMID: 32976863 <lb/>59. Hojo F, Osaki T, Yonezawa H, Hanawa T, Kurata S, Kamiya S. Acanthamoeba castellanii supports <lb/>extracellular survival of Helicobacter pylori in co-culture. Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy. 2020; <lb/>26(9):946-54. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiac.2020.04.016 PMID: 32448734 <lb/>60. LaBauve AE, Wargo MJ. Growth and laboratory maintenance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Current <lb/>protocols in microbiology. 2012; 25(1):6E. 1.-6E. 1.8. https://doi.org/10.1002/9780471729259. <lb/>mc06e01s25 PMID: 22549165 <lb/>61. Wurtzel O, Yoder-Himes DR, Han K, Dandekar AA, Edelheit S, Greenberg EP, et al. The single-nucleo-<lb/>tide resolution transcriptome of Pseudomonas aeruginosa grown in body temperature. 2012. <lb/>62. Nielsen MK, Nielsen K, Hjortdal J, Sørensen UBS. Temperature limitation may explain the containment <lb/>of the trophozoites in the cornea during Acanthamoeba castellanii keratitis. Parasitology research. <lb/>2014; 113:4349-53. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-014-4109-0 PMID: 25204727 <lb/>63. Lambrecht E, Bare ´J, Van Damme I, Bert W, Sabbe K, Houf K. Behavior of Yersinia enterocolitica in the <lb/>presence of the bacterivorous Acanthamoeba castellanii. Applied and environmental microbiology. <lb/>2013; 79(20):6407-13. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01915-13 PMID: 23934496 <lb/>64. Bare ´J, Sabbe K, Huws S, Vercauteren D, Braeckmans K, Van Gremberghe I, et al. Influence of temper-<lb/>ature, oxygen and bacterial strain identity on the association of Campylobacter jejuni with Acantha-<lb/>moeba castellanii. FEMS microbiology ecology. 2010; 74(2):371-81. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-<lb/>6941.2010.00955.x PMID: 20722733 <lb/>65. Matz C, Moreno AM, Alhede M, Manefield M, Hauser AR, Givskov M, et al. Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>uses type III secretion system to kill biofilm-associated amoebae. The ISME journal. 2008; 2(8):843-52. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2008.47 PMID: 18480848 <lb/>66. Sharaby Y, Rodrı ´guez-Martı ´nez S, Pecellin M, Sela R, Peretz A, Ho ¨fle MG, et al. Virulence traits of envi-<lb/>ronmental and clinical Legionella pneumophila multilocus variable-number tandem-repeat analysis <lb/>(MLVA) genotypes. Applied and Environmental Microbiology. 2018; 84(10):e00429-18. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1128/AEM.00429-18 PMID: 29523542 <lb/>67. Leong W, Lutz C, Williams J, Poh YH, Yee BYK, Chua C, et al. Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolates co-<lb/>incubated with Acanthamoeba castellanii exhibit phenotypes similar to chronic cystic fibrosis isolates. <lb/>bioRxiv. 2020: 2020.02. 25.964320. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Environmental factors contributing to A. castellanii and P. aeruginosa interactions <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0305973 June 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>18 / 18 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>