<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-18T15:20:30.226Z">11/18/2025 3:20:30 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T15:20:17.286789Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-18T15:20:17.286789Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Revealing the diversity of Parasmittina <lb/>Osburn, 1952 (Bryozoa, Cheilostomatida) <lb/>from the Southwest Atlantic: Species <lb/>complexes, non-native and new species <lb/>Jamile Farias ID <lb/>1,2,3☯ *, Leandro M. Vieira ID <lb/>3,4☯ <lb/>, Ana C. S. Almeida ID <lb/>1,2,3☯ * <lb/>1 Programa de Po ´s-Graduac ¸ão em Biodiversidade e Evoluc ¸ão, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal <lb/>da Bahia, Salvador, BA, Brazil, 2 Museu de Histo ´ria Natural da Bahia, Setor da Zoologia, Instituto de <lb/>Biologia, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Salvador, BA, Brazil, 3 Laborato ´rio de Estudos de Bryozoa-<lb/>LAEBry, Departamento de Zoologia, Centro de Biociências, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, Recife, <lb/>PE, Brazil, 4 Scientific Associate of the Department of Life Sciences, Natural History Museum, London, <lb/>United Kingdom <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* jamile.farias04@gmail.commailto: (JF); carol.salmeida@gmail.com (ACSA) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Parasmittina is the most representative cheilostome genus of the family Smittinidae, often <lb/>reported in the fouling non-indigenous marine community. Here, we present a review of Para-<lb/>smittina species reported in the Southwestern Atlantic including the characterization of one <lb/>species from Argentina (P. dubitata) and ten from the Brazilian coast: P. abrolhosensis, P. <lb/>alba, P. bimucronata, P. ligulata comb. nov., P. longirostrata, P. pinctatae, P. serrula, P. sim-<lb/>pulata, P. winstonae and the new species Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. The new species <lb/>is characterized by a smooth distally primary orifice with 1-2 oral spines, large lyrula, serrated <lb/>condyles with hooked tips, and two types of avicularia-small and subtriangular and large sub-<lb/>lanceolate. This study does not recognize four species previous recorded in Brazil: reports of <lb/>P. betamorphaea and P. trispinosa are now assigned to P. pinctatae; records of P. munita <lb/>belong to P. falciformis sp. nov.; and reports of P. spathulata encompass at least two taxa, <lb/>including P. abrolhosensis and P. simpulata. In this study, five species complexes (P. alba, <lb/>P. longirostrata, P. serrula, P. simpulata and P. winstonae) were identified and require further <lb/>investigations. While six species characterized here were first described based on speci-<lb/>mens from the Southwestern Atlantic (P. abrolhosensis, P. alba, P. dubitata, P. ligulata <lb/>comb. nov., P. simpulata and P. falciformis sp. nov.), the remaining species are mainly <lb/>known from the Indo-Pacific. These taxa are here recognized as exotic (P. longirostrata) and <lb/>cryptogenic (P. bimucronata, P. pinctatae, P. serrula and P. winstonae) in the studied area. <lb/>Most of the non-native taxa are widespread along the Brazilian coast, growing on both artifi-<lb/>cial and natural surfaces, indicating that they are well-established in the area. As non-native <lb/>bryozoans can negatively influence the environment, affecting human economic activities <lb/>and beach usage, further studies on the fauna presented here are suggested to determine <lb/>the origin of these taxa and help prevent bioinvasion events along the SW Atlantic. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/>1 / 49 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Farias J, Vieira LM, Almeida ACS (2024) <lb/>Revealing the diversity of Parasmittina Osburn, <lb/>1952 (Bryozoa, Cheilostomatida) from the <lb/>Southwest Atlantic: Species complexes, non-native <lb/>and new species. PLoS ONE 19(8): e0304347. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 <lb/>Editor: Karolina Goździewska-Harłajczuk, Wrocław <lb/>University of Environmental and Life Sciences: <lb/>Uniwersytet Przyrodniczy we Wroclawiu, POLAND <lb/>Received: February 3, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: May 9, 2024 <lb/>Published: August 8, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Farias et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/>Funding: The author(s) received no specific <lb/>funding for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Smittinidae Levinsen, 1909 is among the most diverse families of cheilostome bryozoans, cur-<lb/>rently comprising 20 genera distributed worldwide, six of them reported from the Southwest-<lb/>ern (SW) Atlantic: Amynaskolia Figuerola, Gordon &amp; Cristobo, 2018; Hemismittoidea Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 1973; Parasmittina Osburn, 1952; Pleurocodonellina Soule &amp; Soule, 1973; Smittina Nor-<lb/>man, 1903 and Smittoidea Osburn, 1952 [1]. Among these genera, Parasmittina stands out for <lb/>being the richest one, with more than 150 living species [1], representing a highly successful <lb/>group in reefs habitats across all oceans (e.g., [2-4]). Most Parasmittina species have been <lb/>reported from the Pacific, with more than 50 living species [2, 5, 6]. More recently, new species <lb/>from other area, including the SW Atlantic, have been described (e.g., [7-13]). <lb/>Like most cheilostome bryozoans, smittinids have short-living, non-planktotrophic larvae <lb/>with limited active dispersal over long distances (e.g., [14, 15]). However, certain taxa, including <lb/>Parasmittina species, have been reported far from their expected natural geographic distribu-<lb/>tion, indicating association with bioinvasion events (e.g., [4, 9, 16, 17]). Therefore, the accurate <lb/>taxonomic identification of these taxa represents the first step in detecting and tracking poten-<lb/>tial invasions (e.g., [14, 15]). However, the taxonomy of several Smittinidae taxa may be puz-<lb/>zling, sometimes leading to generic misassignments, notably in the case of Parasmittina (e.g., <lb/>[4, 18-20]). Studies on smittinids from Brazil, in the SW Atlantic, have resulted in morphologi-<lb/>cal redefinitions of Hemismittoidea, Smittoidea, and Parasmittina [4]. These redifinitions facili-<lb/>tate the differentiation between these genera, indicating that Parasmittina comprises smittinids <lb/>with an imperforate frontal shield, none to many spines, and avicularia with variable morphol-<lb/>ogy and sizes placed proximolateral or distolateral to the orifice [4]. Similar to genus delimita-<lb/>tion, species distinctions can be also problematic, particularly when only colonial fragments are <lb/>available. These specimens may obscure variations related to colonial development in different <lb/>ontogenetic stages, making it challenging to differentiate distinct morphospecies [4, 9, 21]. <lb/>Eleven species of Parasmittina have been reported from the SW Atlantic: P. abrolhosensis <lb/>Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018, P. alba Ramalho, Muricy &amp; Taylor, 2011, P. <lb/>amazonensis Ramalho &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al. 2021, P. betamorphaea Winston, 2005, P. dis-<lb/>tincta Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018, P. dubitata Hayward, 1980, P. lox-<lb/>oides Winston, Vieira &amp; Woollacott, 2014, P. munita (Hincks, 1884), P. simpulata Winston, <lb/>Vieira &amp; Woollacott, 2014, P. spathulata (Smitt, 1873) and P. trispinosa (Johnston, 1838) [22]. <lb/>Among these, P. munita, P. spathulata and P. trispinosa have been assigned to be part of the P. <lb/>trispinosa complex [5, 23, 24]. Although first described based on specimens from the Northeast-<lb/>ern Atlantic, P. trispinosa has been historically reported in different oceans with different mor-<lb/>phologies attributed to intraspecific variations (e.g., P. trispinosa var. loxa and P. trispinosa var. <lb/>spathulata). However, Soule &amp; Soule [5] reviewed historical records of P. trispinosa using scan-<lb/>ning electron microscopy (SEM), assigning them to 14 species, eight of which were described as <lb/>new species. The need for taxonomic reviews in some of these taxa was previously indicated by <lb/>Vieira et al. [25], Almeida et al. [26] and Farias et al. [4]. In this context, here we reexamined <lb/>SW Atlantic specimens assigned to the genus Parasmittina, providing morphological character-<lb/>ization and assessing the exotic status of 12 species, including the description of a new species. <lb/>Additionally, a tabular identification key with almost all species of the genus is provided. <lb/>Material and methods <lb/>All necessary permits for the new samples were obtained for the described field studies in Bra-<lb/>zil (collecting permit number 47108 SISBIO/Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservac ¸ão da Biodi-<lb/>versidade). The new samples in reported localities do not include protected areas and did not <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>involve endangered or protected species. Permissions from all museums were obtained to <lb/>access and study their collections. <lb/>Type and non-type specimens studied here are deposited in the Bryozoa collections of the <lb/>Setor de Zoologia do Museu de Histo ´ria Natural da Bahia, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Sal-<lb/>vador, Brazil (UFBA); Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, <lb/>Recife, Brazil (UFPE); Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo (MZUSP); Smithsonian <lb/>Institution National Museum of Natural History, Washington D.C., USA (USNM); Natural <lb/>History Museum, London, United Kingdom (NHMUK); and Museum fu ¨r Naturkunde, Ber-<lb/>lin, Germany (MFN). The specimen from Argentina was analyzed based on scanning electron <lb/>microscope (SEM) micrographs provided by Juan Lo ´pez Gappa. <lb/>Non-type specimens were first washed in sodium hypochlorite and then immersed in water <lb/>for surface cleaning using a thin brush. These specimens were air-dried before examination <lb/>under a stereoscopic microscope for the description of external morphology and delimitation <lb/>of morphotypes. Selected specimens of each morphotype were mounted on stubs, coated with <lb/>gold, and analyzed with a SEM JEOL JSM-6390LV at the Centro de Pesquisa Gonc ¸alo Moniz, <lb/>FIOCRUZ, Bahia, Brazil. Some unbleached specimens deposited at the NHMUK and USNM <lb/>were examined using a SEM equipped with a low-vacuum chamber and back-scattered elec-<lb/>tron detector, using a SEM LEO 1455-VP and PhilipsXL30, respectively. <lb/>Measurements were obtained from digital SEM images using ImageJ 1 software [27]. They <lb/>are presented based on the following characters: autozooid length (ZL), autozooid width <lb/>(ZW), primary orifice length (OL), primary orifice width (OW), avicularia length (AvL), avicu-<lb/>laria width (AvW), ovicell length (OvL), and ovicell width (OvW) (S1 Table). The measure-<lb/>ments are represented in the descriptions as minimum-median-maximum, long with the <lb/>number of measurements (n) and standard deviation (SD), all in millimeters (mm). The tax-<lb/>onomy follows Martha et al. [28]. <lb/>The determination of the native/exotic status of the studied species was conducted follow-<lb/>ing the criteria described by Chapman &amp; Carlton [29, 30] and adapted for Bryozoa by Miranda <lb/>et al. [15] and Xavier et al. [31]. <lb/>Fig 19 was created in Adobe Photoshop (https://photoshop.adobe.com/) using a basemap <lb/>available in Canva (https://www.canva.com/) under CC BY 4.0 license. <lb/>Nomenclatural acts <lb/>The electronic edition of this article conforms to the requirements of the amended Interna-<lb/>tional Code of Zoological Nomenclature, and hence the new names contained herein are avail-<lb/>able under that Code from the electronic edition of this article. This published work and the <lb/>nomenclatural acts it contains have been registered in ZooBank, the online registration system <lb/>for the ICZN. The ZooBank LSIDs (Life Science Identifiers) can be resolved, and the associated <lb/>information viewed through any standard web browser by appending the LSID to the prefix <lb/>&quot;http://zoobank.org/&quot;. The LSID for this publication is: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:FEC88DB2-<lb/>877B-46E4-94C0-DEF4C8F449BD. The electronic edition of this work was published in a <lb/>journal with an ISSN, and has been archived and is available from the following digital reposi-<lb/>tories: LOCKSS (added: Sep 10 2012 6:55PM UTC) [http://www.lockss.org]; PubMed Central <lb/>(added: Sep 10 2012 6:55PM UTC) [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc]. <lb/>Results <lb/>Order Cheilostomatida Busk, 1852 <lb/>Family Smittinidae Levinsen, 1909. Type genus. Smittina Norman, 1903 (type species <lb/>Lepralia landsborovii Johnston, 1847, by original designation). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<front>Remarks. Characteristics of the primary orifice, presence of lyrula, avicularium, and pres-<lb/>ence of pseudopores on the frontal wall and ectooecium, serve as the main taxonomic criteria <lb/>to distinguishing Smittinidae genera [2, 5, 9, 24, 32]. While most genera encompass fewer than <lb/>ten species, Parasmittina, Smittina, and Smittoidea are considered highly diverse, with Para-<lb/>smittina and Smittina comprising more than 100 known species each [1]. Parasmittina and <lb/>Smittoidea share morphological similarities, leading to misinterpretations regarding diagnostic <lb/>features and the generic placement of several taxa [4, 18, 19, 20, 21]. Therefore, a taxonomic <lb/>review of both Parasmittina and Smittoidea is strongly recommended [4, 9, 17]. <lb/>Genus Parasmittina Osburn, 1952 <lb/>Type species. Lepralia jeffreysi Norman, 1876, by original designation. <lb/>Diagnosis. Autozooids with imperforate frontal wall, except for marginal pores. Primary <lb/>orifice with smooth or beaded distal margin, oral spines usually present, lyrula of variable size <lb/>and condyles with distinct profiles. Secondary orifice with variable development, sometimes <lb/>with a proximal pseudosinus. Adventitious avicularia formed from a marginal pore [for exam-<lb/>ple, as in P. jeffreysi (acc. Winston &amp; Hayward [33]), P. nitida and P. winstonae], or sometimes, <lb/>from a latero-oral pore (for example, as in P. pinctatae, P. simpulata and P. falciformis sp. <lb/>nov.); adventitious avicularia with diverse shapes and positions (frontal, latero-oral or mar-<lb/>ginal), but never suboral, unless if displaced by the secondary calcification. Vicarious avicularia <lb/>may also be present. Ovicells hyperstomial, initially prominent and becoming immersed with <lb/>secondary calcification; ectooecium with pseudopores (modified from Osburn [24]). <lb/>Remarks. Historically, the taxonomic identification of Parasmittina was primarily based <lb/>on the morphology and position of the adventitious avicularia [3, 7, 23, 24, 34-37]. Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule [2, 5] made extensive taxonomic studies on smitinids, particularly Parasmittina, reveal-<lb/>ing that a combination of morphological characters is necessary for confident identification. <lb/>However, new species of Parasmittina have been distinguished from congeners primarily <lb/>based on avicularia morphology (e.g., [7, 10]) or were described based on colonies fragments <lb/>(i.e., [11, 12, 38]) that may not encompass intraspecific variations of these taxa, especially <lb/>regarding avicularia development [2, 4, 5, 9, 17, 21, 39]. <lb/>Thus, in this study, we attempt to analyze colonies at various astogenetic stages, comparing <lb/>them with all congeners reported worldwide and using both morphological and morphometric <lb/>data. Diagnostic features were based mainly on the primary orifice (distal margin ornamenta-<lb/>tion, number of spines, lyrula width, and condyles morphology), avicularia (if adventitious <lb/>and/or interzooidal, placement, orientation, size, and morphologies), and ooecia (number of <lb/>pseudopores, and secondary calcification). <lb/>Parasmittina abrolhosensis Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018. (Figs <lb/>1, 2; Tables 1, 10) <lb/>Smittina areolata: Canu &amp; Bassler 1928: 30, plate 6 Fig 4 [40]. Non Smittina areolata Canu <lb/>&amp; Bassler, 1927: 23 [41]. <lb/>Smittina trispinosa spathulata: Canu &amp; Bassler 1928: 29, plate 6, Fig 3 [40]; Parasmittina <lb/>spathulata: Vieira et al. 2008: 27 (in part) [25], Almeida et al. 2015: 4 (in part) [26]. Non <lb/>Escharella jacotini var. spathulata Smitt, 1873: 60 [42]. <lb/>Material examined. UFPE 813-815; UFBA 2414-2416, 2855-2859, 2861-2862, 2879-<lb/>2880, 2882-2884, 2886-2888, 3128, 5004-5007, Recife dos Cascos, Baia de Todos os Santos, <lb/>Bahia, Brazil, 13-21 m, coll. 2016-2017; UFBA 696, 3120, Costa do Dendê, Bahia, Brazil, coll. <lb/>2002; UFBA 5008, Camac ¸ari, Bahia, Brazil, 50 m, coll. 07/2004; UFPE 652-661, 2788-2797, <lb/>Bacia Potiguar, Rio Grande do Norte, coll. 2009-2010; USNM 8558, 8559, Smittina trispinosa <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>spathulata and Smittina areolata, respectively, F. Canu &amp; R. Bassler det., Bahia, Brazil, 49 m, <lb/>coll. 1876. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting. Autozooids (Fig 1A) polygonal, almost rhombic, limited <lb/>by slightly raised lateral walls, surrounded by a single row of 19-23 marginal pores (0.009-<lb/>0.025-0.042 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.008 mm). Frontal wall initially smooth in very <lb/>Fig 1. Parasmittina abrolhosensis Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018. (A, C-D) UFBA 5004, (B) UFBA 2416, (E) <lb/>UFBA 696, (F) UFBA 5008, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) growing edge of the colony with small avicularia, (B) detail of <lb/>primary orifice and small elongate avicularia, (C) autozooids with secondary calcification and small avicularia, (D) group of ovicelled <lb/>zooids with small avicularia, (E) old autozooids with large spatulate avicularia, (F) ovicelled zooids with secondary calcification and large <lb/>spatulate avicularia. Scale bars: A, C-F = 400 μm; B = 100 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>young zooids (Fig 1A, top; 1B), becoming rough, rugose, and with nodular calcification in <lb/>older zooids (Fig 1C and 1D). Primary orifice (Fig 1B) elliptical, distal margin smooth, with <lb/>1-3 oral spines, lyrula narrow (0.012-0.021-0025 mm wide; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm); a pair of <lb/>robust and down-curved hooked condyles with serrated margins. Secondary orifice (Fig 1B <lb/>and 1C) pear-shaped, forming 2-4 lateral flaps in autozooids, often with in a shallow U-shaped <lb/>pseudosinus, more pronounced in older or ovicelled zooids (Fig 1D and 1E). Adventitious <lb/>Fig 2. Parasmittina abrolhosensis Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018. (A-D) USNM 8558, (E-F) USNM 8559, <lb/>Bahia, Brazil. (A) group of autozooids, (B) detail of an autozooid showing small elongate and subtriangular and large spatulate avicularia, <lb/>(C) detail of primary orifice, (D) detail of vicarious avicularia, (E) group of young autozooids with small and large avicularia, (F) group <lb/>of ovicelled zooids. Scale bars: A, E = 500 μm; B, D, F = 200 μm; C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>avicularia variable in shapes and sizes (Fig 1A and 1D), with four morphologies: (1) small, nar-<lb/>row and elongate avicularia (Figs 1C and 1E, 2B and 2E) present at one or both side of the ori-<lb/>fice, unequal in size if paired, placed below to the secondary orifice, proximally oriented, <lb/>rostrum narrow and slightly curved, smooth to slightly corrugated at its lateral margins, <lb/>rounded tip, palate occupying about half of the rostrum length and oblong foramen; (2) small, <lb/>subtriangular, bulbous avicularia (Fig 1A and 1D), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, <lb/>proximally oriented, rostrum subtriangular, pointed tip, palate narrow, reaching twice its ini-<lb/>tial size with colonial development, leaving a sublanceolate profile; (3) small, narrow and sub-<lb/>triangular to elliptic avicularia (Figs 1C and 1E, 1F, 2B and 2E), placed in zooidal margins and/ <lb/>or in the frontal wall, with smooth lateral margins, rounded tip, palate narrow and elliptical <lb/>foramen; (4) large spatulate avicularia, more common in older zooids, placed proximolaterally <lb/>below the orifice, oriented proximally, with rounded distal edge, palate broad, foramen sub-<lb/>triangular, elongate rostrum, with smooth margins and crossbar complete, with 3-4 pseudo-<lb/>pores adjacent to the avicularia. (Figs 1F and 2A, 2E); vicarious avicularia (Fig 2D) with the <lb/>same morphology as the large spatulate avicularia occasionally present. Ovicells (Figs 1D and <lb/>2E) globose, initially prominent (Fig 1D) and densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall in <lb/>older colonies (Figs 1F and 2F); ectooecium with 18-25 small pseudopores (0.003-0.005-0.008 <lb/>mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.001 mm), mainly placed at the distal region of the ectooecium <lb/>surface. <lb/>Remarks. Canu &amp; Bassler [40] studied specimens from northeastern Brazil (Bahia) and <lb/>attributed them to two species, P. areolata (Canu &amp; Bassler, 1927) [41] and P. spathulata <lb/>(Smitt, 1873). Following Canu &amp; Bassler [40], Vieira et al. [25] and Almeida et al. [26] attrib-<lb/>uted other Brazilian specimens to P. spathulata (Smitt, 1873). These P. areolata and P. spatul-<lb/>hata records, as well as new studied specimens from the same region, are here attributed to P. <lb/>abrolhosensis. <lb/>Table 1. Morphometric data of P. abrolhosensis. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum (number of zooidal measures). Avicu-<lb/>laria abbreviations: Av1 = small elongate; Av2 = small subtriangular bulbous; Av3 = small subtriangular; Av4 = large spatulate; Av5 = vicarious spatulate. <lb/>Character <lb/>Ramalho et al. (2018) / MNRJ-Bry1359 Canu &amp; Bassler (1928) / USNM 8558 Canu &amp; Bassler (1928) / USNM 8559 Present study / UFBA 2877 <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.312-0.396-0.471 (?) <lb/>0.369-0.513-0.582 (12) <lb/>0.398-0.568-0.749 (13) <lb/>0.338-0.418-0.606 (15) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.280-0.308-0.360 (?) <lb/>0.276-0.370-0.463 (12) <lb/>0.273-0.416-0.538 (13) <lb/>0.237-0.318-0.411 (15) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.093-0.106-0.113 (?) <lb/>0.092-0.107-0.123 (6) <lb/>0.104-0.119-0.139 (7) <lb/>0.078-0.095-0.107 (12) <lb/>OW <lb/>0.075-0.084-0.099 (?) <lb/>0.082-0.094-0.107 (6) <lb/>0.093-0.104-0.125 (7) <lb/>0.084-0.096-0.109 (12) <lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.121-0.142-0.178 (?) <lb/>0.102-0.135-0.159 (7) <lb/>0.118-0.168-0.250 (15) <lb/>0.093-0.118-0.146 (15) <lb/>Av1W <lb/>-<lb/>0.006-0.009-0.013 (8) <lb/>0.009-0.019-0.029 (15) <lb/>0.011-0.017-0.022 (15) <lb/>Av2L <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.083-0.104-0.123 (10) <lb/>Av2W <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.042-0.051-0.056 (10) <lb/>Av3L <lb/>0.079-0.090-0.106 (?) <lb/>0.073-0.096-0.112 (15) <lb/>0.073-0.101-0.113 (10) <lb/>0.073-0.090-0.102 (15) <lb/>Av3W <lb/>-<lb/>0.008-0.014-0.019 (15) <lb/>0.011-0.015-0.024 (10) <lb/>0.024-0.029-0.033 (15) <lb/>Av4L <lb/>-<lb/>0.365-0.373-0.381 (2) <lb/>0.400 (1) <lb/>0.201 (1) <lb/>Av4W <lb/>-<lb/>0.073-0.075-0.077 (2) <lb/>0.073 (1) <lb/>0.048 (1) <lb/>Av5L <lb/>-<lb/>0.521 (1) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av5W <lb/>-<lb/>0.141 (1) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>OvL <lb/>0.170-0.183-0.204 (?) <lb/>0.157-0.174-0.200 (3) <lb/>0.172-0.185-0.209 (4) <lb/>0.148-0.161-0.193 (15) <lb/>OvW <lb/>0.219-0.236-253 (?) <lb/>0.167-0.192-0.230 (3) <lb/>0.218-0.244-0.273 (4) <lb/>0.203-0.214-0.229 (15) <lb/>Parasmittina abrolhosensis Ramalho, Taylor, &amp; Moraes in Ramalho et al., 2018: 165, Figs 3H, 5A-D [11]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Parasmittina areolata was originally described by Canu &amp; Bassler [41] based on specimens <lb/>from Hawaii, Pacific Ocean. However, it has been reported in Brazilian coast and in the Carib-<lb/>bean [3, 37, 40]. Here we analyzed the type of P. areolata (USNM 8443), Smittina areolata, <lb/>holotype, F. Canu &amp; R. Bassler det., Molokai, Hawaii, 142-406 m, coll. 1902, Fig 3A-3D), <lb/>revealing that this species is not conspecific with the Brazilian material. Parasmittina areolata <lb/>has a double row of areolar pores (single in specimens from Brazil), low secondary orifice <lb/>(with lateral flaps in Brazilian material) and ectooecium centrally perforated (distally perfo-<lb/>rated in specimens from Brazil). The morphologically related species P. spathulata is distinct <lb/>from the Brazilian material in having a broader lyrula (acc. Winston [7]). Specimens from the <lb/>Caribbean previously attributed to P. areolata by Winston [37] were reassigned to P. luteoser-<lb/>rula Winston &amp; Jackson, 2021 (see Winston &amp; Jackson [13]), distinct from Brazilian specimens <lb/>by having an orifice with a serrated distal margin, and a large avicularium with a coarsely ser-<lb/>rated margin. <lb/>Specimens studied here shares most of the diagnostic characters provided by Ramalho et al. <lb/>[11] in the description of P. abrolhosensis, including a primary orifice with distal margin <lb/>smooth, lyrula narrow and robust and down-curved hooked condyles with serrated margins; <lb/>secondary orifice with a U-shaped pseudosinus; avicularia with four morphologies: (1) small, <lb/>narrow and elongate, (2) small, subtriangular and bulbous [not described by Ramalho et al. <lb/>[11], but figured in 3H], (3) small, narrow and subtriangular to elliptic, and (4) large spatulate; <lb/>Fig 3. Parasmittina areolata (Canu &amp; Bassler, 1927) (A-D) USNM 8443, holotype, Hawaii, USA. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) <lb/>group of autozooids and ovicelled zooids, (B) detail of autozooid with small avicularia, (C) detail of primary orifice, (D) detail of <lb/>ovicelled zooids with small and large avicularia. Scale bars: A = 400 μm; B = 100 μm; C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>and ovicells densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall in older colonies, and with small <lb/>pseudopores. However, specimens from Ramalho et al. [11] have 3-4 oral spines (1-3 in colo-<lb/>nies studied here) and the large avicularium was not found as vicarious. Interestingly, the orig-<lb/>inal description of P. abrolhosensis was based on three small colonial fragments inhabiting <lb/>corals (acc. Ramalho et al. [11], Figs 3H, 4A-4D) whereas several colonies studied here are <lb/>Fig 4. Parasmittina alba Ramalho, Muricy &amp; Taylor, 2011. (A-B) UFBA 5059, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) <lb/>ancestrula and first zooids of the colony, (B) young autozooids showing small avicularium. (C-D) UFBA 5009, Bahia, Brazil. (C) detail of <lb/>primary orifice, (D) group of young autozooids showing large avicularium, (E) UFBA 5010, Bahia, Brazil, colony with secondary <lb/>calcification showing autozooids and ovicelled zooids, (F) UFPE 785, Espı ´rito Santo, Brazil, detail of ovicelled zooids with small <lb/>avicularia. Scale bars: A, B, D, E, F = 200 μm; C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>from artificial substrata and material from Canu &amp; Bassler [40] are colonies with rough sec-<lb/>ondary calcification. Since the number of oral spines and occurrence of avicularia in Parasmit-<lb/>tina are very variable in relation to colony development and habitat (e.g., [2, 4, 5, 9, 21, 39]), <lb/>these differences are likely to be intraspecific variations of P. abrolhosensis rather than a differ-<lb/>ent species. <lb/>Distribution. SW Atlantic: Brazil (Canu &amp; Bassler [32]; Vieira et al. [25]; Almeida et al. <lb/>[26]; Ramalho et al. [11]; present study). <lb/>Parasmittina alba Ramalho, Muricy &amp; Taylor, 2011 <lb/>(Fig 4; Tables 2, 10) <lb/>Parasmittina alba Ramalho et al., 2011: 769, figures 2A-H [10]; Souto et al. 2016: 3, figures <lb/>3A-H [17]. <lb/>? Smittia trispinosa var. protecta Thornely, 1905: 123 [43];? Parasmittina lavela Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 2002: 36 [5];? Parasmittina betamorphaea Winston, 2005: 58 [7] <lb/>? Parasmittina protecta: Harmelin et al. 2009: 169 (cum. syn.) [9]. <lb/>Material examined. UFPE 785, Ilhas Rasas, Guarapari, Espı ´rito Santo, Brazil, 11-15 m, <lb/>coll. 27/03/2017; UFPE 786-795; UFBA 5009-5010, 5013, 5016, 5027, 5033, 5036, 5041, 5045, <lb/>5047, 5054, 5058, 5062, 5065, 5069, 5074, 5079, 5084, 5088, 5098-5099, 5103, 5108-5109, <lb/>5120-5121, 5123, 5141-5142, 5148, 5156, 5165-5166, 5172, 5175, 5178, 5189, 5194, 5202-<lb/>5203, 5207, 5210, 5215, 5221, 5228, 5235, 5240, 5246, 5251, 5257, 5263-5264, 5273-5274, <lb/>5281-5182, 5285, 5290, 5303, 5355, 5425, 5448, Baia de Todos os Santos, Salvador, Bahia, Bra-<lb/>zil, 3-5 m, coll. 2012, MZUSP 2937, Alcatrazes, São Sebastião, São Paulo, Brazil, coll, 06/10/ <lb/>2011. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting. Ancestrula (Fig 4A) tatiform, with narrow marginal <lb/>cryptocyst, 8 marginal spines; 4-5 orificial spines in first daughter zooid; second and third <lb/>daughter zooids with 3-4 orifical spines. Autozooids (Fig 4B) subrectangular, limited by <lb/>slightly raised lateral walls, surrounded by a single row of 20-27 marginal pores (0.010-0.019-<lb/>0.032 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.005 mm). Frontal wall rugose, with small, rounded <lb/>tubercles. Primary orifice (Fig 4C) elliptical, distal margin smooth, with 1-3 oral spines; lyrula <lb/>broad (0.038-0.046-0.058 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.005 mm), but shallow and often with a <lb/>median keel; condyles paired, thin, with smooth margins and down-curved hooked tips. Sec-<lb/>ondary orifice (Fig 4E and 4F) raised around the proximal margin of the primary orifice, <lb/>formed from lateral flaps, resulting in a shallow V-shaped pseudosinus. Adventitious avicularia <lb/>variable in shape and size (Fig 4B, 4D and 4F), with three morphologies: (1) small, narrow, and <lb/>subtriangular avicularia (Fig 4B and 4F), rare in very young zooids, placed laterally at one side <lb/>of the orifice, commonly proximally oriented, rostrum subtriangular, finely serrated at its lat-<lb/>eral margins, pointed tip, palate narrow and subtriangular foramen; (2) small and spatulate <lb/>avicularia with broad rostrum (Fig 4F), rare in young zooids, placed laterally at one side of the <lb/>orifice, proximally oriented, rostrum subspatulate, a rounded distal edge, palate narrow and <lb/>elliptical foramen; (3) large spatulate avicularia (Fig 4D), more common in older zooids, <lb/>placed laterally at one side of the orifice, oriented proximally, with a rounded distal edge, pal-<lb/>ate broad, foramen elliptical, with smooth margins and a complete crossbar, with 2-3 pseudo-<lb/>pores adjacent to the avicularia. Ovicells (Fig 4E and 4F) surrounded by the frontal wall of <lb/>adjacent zooids, becoming immersed in older colonies; ooecium almost globular with a flat-<lb/>tened frontal surface (0.007-0.018-0.045 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.007 mm), ectooe-<lb/>cium with 18-26 funnel-shaped pseudopores that become merged and polygonal with <lb/>increasing calcification. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Remarks. Parasmittina alba was described based on specimens from Rio de Janeiro, SE <lb/>Brazil; it was characterized by having a granular frontal wall, condyles with hooked tips, large <lb/>lyrula, 1-2 oral spines, secondary orifice with lateral projections and pseudosinus, avicularia <lb/>latero-oral (small subtriangular or rounded), large (spatulate) and interzooidal (subtriangular), <lb/>with only one avicularium occurring per zooid, and ectooecium with pseudopores [10]. Most <lb/>of these morphological characters are also seen in colonies from SE and NE Brazil examined <lb/>here, despite the presence of 1-3 orificial spines and the rare presence of interzooidal avicu-<lb/>laria. Most of our examined material form small patches growing on ceramic experimental tile <lb/>plates (specimens from northeastern Brazil; Fig 4A), but the larger specimens have been only <lb/>observed growing on rhodoliths (specimens from southeastern Brazil; Fig 4F). The avicularia <lb/>were often found in older part of the colonies (Fig 4F) when comparing with the growing zone <lb/>with the new zooids (Fig 4B), suggesting the formation of the avicularia in later colony asto-<lb/>geny. Moreover, we found no morphometric differences in colonies studied here assigned and <lb/>other records of P. alba (Table 2). <lb/>Parasmittina alba was reported as a non-indigenous species in Portugal, Northeastern <lb/>Atlantic [17]. Souto et al. [17] noted slight variations between specimens from Rio de Janeiro <lb/>(acc. Ramalho et al. [10]) and those from Portugal, including smaller ectooecial pseudopores <lb/>related with more significant calcification, the occurrence of two avicularia in ovicelled zooids <lb/>and absence of interzooidal avicularia. Additionally, Souto et al. [17] suggested that P. alba <lb/>could be assigned as a junior synonym of P. betamorphaea Winston, 2005 [7] described from <lb/>the United States (Northwestern Atlantic) since characters used to distinguish these taxa are <lb/>very variable among colonies and zooids (i.e., number of avicularia, calcification of margins <lb/>and rostrum of the avicularia). The Caribbean P. lavela Soule &amp; Soule [5] also shares most <lb/>morphological diagnostic features of P. alba. These taxa have a granular frontal calcification, <lb/>primary orifice without distal denticles, with large lyrula and thin down-curved hooked con-<lb/>dyles, secondary orifice with a short pseudosinus, and ooecium with merged pseudopores [5]. <lb/>The only difference between P. alba and P. lavela is the presence of a single morphotype of avi-<lb/>cularia in P. lavela (i.e., small subtriangular latero-oral avicularia), lacking all other types <lb/>described to P. alba. Soule &amp; Soule [9] stated that avicularia are not common in P. lavela, but <lb/>only a tiny single specimen growing on algae on an anchor chain was examined [5], somewhat <lb/>Table 2. Morphometric data of P. alba, P. lavela and P. betamorphea. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum (number of zooi-<lb/>dal measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small subtriangular; Av2 = small spatulate; Av3 = large spatulate. <lb/>Character <lb/>P. alba / Ramalho et al. <lb/>(2011) <lb/>P. alba / Souto et al. <lb/>(2016) <lb/>P. alba / UFBA 5010 (present <lb/>study) <lb/>P. lavela / Soule &amp; Soule <lb/>(2002) <lb/>P. betamorphea / Winston <lb/>(2005) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.392-0.451-0.490 (?) <lb/>0.390-0.488-0.670 (24) 0.341-0.442-0.583 (15) <lb/>0.350-0.400 (?) <lb/>0.378-0.470-0.576 (6) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.265-0.305-0.383 (?) <lb/>0.240-0.340-0.460 (24) 0.225-0.297-0.415 (15) <lb/>0.243-0.320 (?) <lb/>0.252-0.290-0.324 (6) <lb/>OL <lb/>-<lb/>0.076-0.082-0.101 (20) 0.074-0.085-0.098 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.072-0.080-0.090 (?) <lb/>OW <lb/>-<lb/>0.103-0.125-0.143 (20) 0.078-0.091-0.107 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.090-0.100-0.108 (?) <lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.098-0.109-0.118 (?) <lb/>0.068-0.078-0.089 (10) 0.093 (1) <lb/>0.120-0.150 (?) <lb/>0.072-0.090-0.162 (6) <lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.069-0.083-0.098 (?) <lb/>0.037-0.047-0.054 (10) 0.041 (1) <lb/>-<lb/>0.045-0.050-0.054 (6) <lb/>Av2L <lb/>-<lb/>0.074-0.092-0.104 (9) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av2W <lb/>-<lb/>0.051-0.056-0.063 (9) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av3L <lb/>0.353 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.304-0.329-0.355 (2) <lb/>-<lb/>0.324-0.360-0.396 (6) <lb/>Av3W <lb/>0.137 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.074-0.080-0.085 (2) <lb/>-<lb/>0.180-0.190-0.198 (6) <lb/>OvL <lb/>0.274 (?) <lb/>0.235-0.265-0.297 (20) 0.228-0.245-0.276 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.180-0.200-0.216 (2) <lb/>OvW <lb/>0.323 (?) <lb/>0.233-0.267-0.300 (20) 0.260-0.275-0.296 (15) <lb/>0.225-0.260 (?) <lb/>0.180-0.200-0.216 (2) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>corroborating morphological variation and biological associations already reported [10, 17] <lb/>and assigned here to P. alba. Avicularia are known to be very variable in Smittinidae according <lb/>to colony development and habitat (e.g., [2, 4, 5, 9, 21, 39]). Avicularia morphology is quite <lb/>variable in specimens of P. alba here examined. We suspect that P. alba and P. betamorphea <lb/>may represent different astogenetic variations of P. lavela-specimens of P. alba comprising a <lb/>stage with all types of avicularia, ovicells, and secondary calcification [10], whereas P. betamor-<lb/>phea could represent young colony that lacks ovicells and have few avicularia [7]. <lb/>Zooidal measurements of specimens attributed to P. alba and P. betamorphea are like those <lb/>of P. lavela (Table 2). In addition, a peculiar feature of the species (as already mentioned by <lb/>Souto et al. [17]) is a notch on the distal margin of the primary orifice of ovicellate zooids-this <lb/>notch is formed in the place where the oral spines were inserted (Fig 4E) [see Ramalho et al. <lb/>[10] (Fig 2G) and Souto et al. [17] (Fig 3B)]. However, observing this notch in colonies of P. <lb/>lavela and P. betamorphea was impossible. Ovicelled zooids of P. lavela had the distal margin <lb/>of the primary orifice occluded by secondary calcification [5] and P. betamorphea lacks ovicells <lb/>[7]. Thus, at least one species complex involving P. alba, P. betamorphea, and P. lavela can be <lb/>recognized (Table 2). <lb/>Finally, another congener may be involved in this complex. Specimens from the Southeast <lb/>and Northeast Atlantic, as well as from the Mediterranean attributed to Parasmittina protecta <lb/>(Thornely, 1905) (acc. Harmelin et al. [9]) also share most morphological diagnostic features <lb/>of P. alba, being only variable in avicularia morphotypes occurrence. However, P. protecta was <lb/>first described with colonies from the Indian Ocean and the original description is brief, not <lb/>including diagnostic features of the primary orifice (distal margin ornamentation, condyles, <lb/>lyrula) and detailed characterization of avicularia (acc. Thornely [43]). Also, there is no rede-<lb/>scription of type or topotype specimens, preventing us from reliably characterizing P. protecta <lb/>from Thornely (1905). Additional studies including more specimens are required to identify <lb/>whether P. protecta and P. alba belong to the same species. <lb/>Distribution. Northeastern Atlantic: Portugal [17]; SW Atlantic: Brazil [10] present <lb/>study). <lb/>Parasmittina bimucronata (Hincks, 1884) <lb/>(Fig 5; Tables 3, 10) <lb/>Smittia trispinosa form bimucronata Hincks, 1884a: 118, plate 13, figure 6 [44]. <lb/>Parasmittina bimucronata: Hayward &amp; Parker 1994: 70 [under remarks of P. pectinata] <lb/>[43]. <lb/>Parasmittina glomerata: Liu 2001: 618, plate 56, figures 5-6 [45]. Non Smittia glomerata <lb/>Thornely, 1912: 152 [46]. <lb/>Material examined. UFBA 946, Baı ´a de Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, coll. 1997; UFBA <lb/>3113, Costa do Dendê, Bahia, Brazil, coll. 2002. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting. Autozooids (Fig 5A) subrectangular to polygonal, lim-<lb/>ited by slightly raised lateral walls, with a single row of 18-24 marginal pores (0.009-0.019-<lb/>0.033 mm wide; n = 30; SD = 0.005 mm). Frontal wall rugose, with large, rounded tubercles. <lb/>Primary orifice (Fig 5C) transversely elliptical, distal margin smooth, with 1-2 oral spines; lyr-<lb/>ula narrow (0.019-0.025-0.032 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.004 mm), latero-proximal condyles <lb/>triangular and thin. Secondary orifice initially low, becoming raised and forming lateral flap-<lb/>shaped projections with increasing calcification, often with a shallow U-shaped pseudosinus <lb/>(Fig 5D), partially obscuring primary orifice in latter astogeny, especially in ovicelled zooids, <lb/>resulting in a deep U-shaped pseudosinus, but often not obscuring the lyrula (Fig 5E). Adven-<lb/>titious avicularia variable in shape and size (Fig 5A-5E), with three morphologies: (1) small, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>subtriangular, bulbous avicularia (Fig 5A and 5B), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, <lb/>proximally oriented, rostrum subtriangular, corrugated at its lateral margins, pointed tip, pal-<lb/>ate narrow and subtriangular foramen; (2) small, oblong to spatulate avicularia (Fig 5A and <lb/>5B) single, common in younger zooids, placed below the secondary orifice, proximally ori-<lb/>ented, rostrum subspatulate and straight, smooth at its lateral margins, rounded tip, palate <lb/>occupying about half of the rostrum length and elliptical foramen; (3) large, sublanceolate <lb/>Fig 5. Parasmittina bimucronata (Hincks 1884a). (A-F) UFBA 946, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) group of young <lb/>autozooids with small and large latero-oral and large frontal avicularia, (B) detail of autozooids showing small latero-oral and large <lb/>frontal avicularia, (C) detail of primary orifice, (D) autozooids with secondary calcification, (E) ovicelled zooids with secondary <lb/>calcification, (F) detail of ovicells. Scale bars: A = 500 μm; B, D, E, F = 200 μm; C = 200 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>avicularia (Fig 5A), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, oriented proximally, with acute <lb/>rostrum, palate broad, foramen subtriangular, with finely serrated margins and crossbar com-<lb/>plete, with 2-3 pseudopores adjacent to the avicularia. Large frontal avicularia (Fig 5A and 5B) <lb/>occasionally present, with the same morphology as the latero-oral. Ovicells (Fig 5E-5F) wider <lb/>than long, ooecium globular, becoming immersed in the frontal calcification with increasing <lb/>calcification (Fig 5F); ectooecium with 20-27 pseudopores with slightly raised rim (0.004-<lb/>0.011-0.020 mm wide; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm). <lb/>Remarks. Parasmittina bimucronata is characterized by having the primary orifice <lb/>smooth distally, 1-2 oral spines, thin and smooth condyles and lyrula occupying one-quarter <lb/>of the orificial width; adventitious latero-oral avicularia with two sizes and three morphologies: <lb/>small (with subtriangular or oblong profile) and large (with sublanceolate profile); and ovicells <lb/>with more than 18 pseudopores (description based on lectotype, BMNH 1899.5.1.920; see Hay-<lb/>ward &amp; Parker [45], Fig 6D-6E). There are no morphological differences between Brazilian <lb/>specimens studied here and the lectotype of P. bimucronata (see comparison in Table 3). <lb/>Parasmittina bimucronata was originally described based on specimens from the Indian <lb/>Ocean as a variation of P. trispinosa [44], and the lectotype of that species was selected by Hay-<lb/>ward &amp; Parker [47]. Morphological differences can be observed between these two species, <lb/>including: number of oral spines (1-2 in P. bimucronata and 2-3 in P. trispinosa), orientation <lb/>of the large avicularium (proximolateral in P. bimucronata and distolateral in P. trispinosa), <lb/>and number of ectooecial pseudopores (20-37 in P. bimucronata and 2-4 in P. trispinosa) [5, <lb/>47]. Hincks [48] referred to specimens from the Pacific Ocean as belonging to P. bimucronata. <lb/>However, later, Harmer [36] relocated specimens from Indian and Pacific Oceans studied by <lb/>Hincks [44, 48] to P. raigii (Audouin, 1826), originally described from the Red Sea (Gulf of <lb/>Suez as the type locality). Hayward &amp; Parker [47] reexamined Hincks&apos; [47, 49] original speci-<lb/>mens and stated that none of them belonged to P. raigii-specimens from the Indian Ocean <lb/>belong to P. bimucronata and those from the Pacific were renamed as a new species, P. pecti-<lb/>nata Hayward &amp; Parker, 1994 [47]. Although P. bimucronata, P. raigii and P. pectinata have <lb/>adventitious avicularia placed laterally to the orifice with similar morphologies, these species <lb/>can be distinguished mainly by features of the primary orifice, including the distal margin <lb/>(smooth in P. bimucronata; beaded in P. raigii and P. pectinata), oral spines (1-2 in P. <lb/>Table 3. Morphometric data of P. bimucronata. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-<lb/>maximum (number of zooidal measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small subtriangular; Av2 = small oblong; <lb/>Av3 = large sublanceolate. <lb/>Character <lb/>Reference / Specimen <lb/>Hayward &amp; Parker (1994) / BMNH 1899.5.1.920 1 <lb/>Present study / UFBA 946 <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.360 ± 004 (20) <lb/>0.224-0.398-0.695 (15) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.230 ± 0.03 (20) <lb/>0.143-0.243-0.314 (15) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.080 ± 0.004 (20) <lb/>0.076-0.087-0.099 (15) <lb/>OW <lb/>0.090 ± 0.004 (20) <lb/>0.086-0.100-0.125 (15) <lb/>AvZ1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.089-0.117-0.144 (15) <lb/>AvW1 <lb/>-<lb/>0.033-0.052-0.069 (15) <lb/>AvZ2 <lb/>-<lb/>0.100-0.105-0.111 (6) <lb/>AvW2 <lb/>-<lb/>0.037-0.047-0.053 (6) <lb/>AvZ3 <lb/>-<lb/>0.217-0.363-0.472 (15) <lb/>AvW3 <lb/>-<lb/>0.034-0.054-0.073 (15) <lb/>OvL <lb/>-<lb/>0.150-0.194-0.210 (15) <lb/>OvW <lb/>-<lb/>0.216-0.255-0.293 (15) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>bimucronata and P. raigii; 2-3 in P. pectinata), condyles (thin and smooth in P. bimucronata <lb/>and P. raigii; robust and serrated in P. pectinata) and lyrula size (narrow in P. bimucronata; <lb/>broad in P. raigii and P. pectinata). Liu [45] also assigned specimens from China to P. glomer-<lb/>ata due to avicularia with similar morphologies. However, these specimens are here attributed <lb/>to P. bimucronata, since it differs from P. glomerata by having a primary orifice with smooth <lb/>distal margin (beaded in P. glomerata) and narrow lyrula (medium-sized in P. glomerata). <lb/>Distribution. Indo-Pacific: Myanmar and China [44, 45]; SW Atlantic: Brazil (present <lb/>study). <lb/>Parasmittina dubitata Hayward, 1980. (Fig 6; Table 10) <lb/>Parasmittina dubitata Hayward, 1980: 701, figures 2A-B [49]. <lb/>Material examined. Uncatalogued, Tierra del Fuego, Argentina, 90 m. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting. Autozooids (Fig 6A), (0.305-0.403-0.545 mm length; <lb/>n = 8; SD = 0.096 mm; 0.215-0.267-0.382 mm wide; n = 8; SD = 0.049 mm), subrectangular to <lb/>polygonal, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, with a single row of 11-16 marginal pores <lb/>(0.013-0.029-0.059 mm wide; n = 30; SD = 0.010 mm). Frontal wall rugose, with large, <lb/>rounded tubercles. Primary orifice (Fig 6C), (0.093-0.103-0.120 mm length; n = 7; <lb/>SD = 0.008mm; 0.086-0.108-0.123 mm wide; n = 7; SD = 0.011mm), subcircular, distal margin <lb/>smooth, with single oral spine; lyrula large, varying in size, occupy about half width of the <lb/>Fig 6. Parasmittina dubitata Hayward, 1980. (A-D) Uncatalogued specimen, Tierra del Fuego, Argentina. Arrows indicating <lb/>avicularia. (A) group of autozooids showing small and large avicularia, (B) detail of autozooids with small oblong and large subtriangular <lb/>avicularia, (C) detail of primary orifice, (D) detail of vicarious and small spatulate avicularia. Scale bars: A = 200 μm; B, D = 100 μm; <lb/>C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>orifice (0.034-0.041-0.049 mm wide; n = 7; SD = 0.005 mm), robust, with concave distal mar-<lb/>gin; a pair of prominent condyles with rounded and coarsely serrated margins. Secondary ori-<lb/>fice cormidial, low, forming slightly raised side flaps and a hood distal to the orifice (Fig 6B). <lb/>Adventitious avicularia variable in shape and size (Fig 6B and 6D), with three morphologies: <lb/>(1) small (0.059-0.099-0.131 mm length; n = 15; SD = 0.022; 0.017-0.031-0.046 mm wide; <lb/>n = 15; SD = 0.008 mm), oblong to spatulate avicularia (Fig 6A and 7B) single or paired, lat-<lb/>erally at one side of the orifice and oriented proximally or placed near zooidal margins, smooth <lb/>at its lateral margins, rounded tip, palate occupying one quarter of the rostrum length and <lb/>elliptical foramen; (2) (0.056-0.066-0.073 mm mm length; n = 4; SD = 0.007; 0.026-0.029-<lb/>0.033 mm wide; n = 4; SD = 0.003 mm), small, spatulate avicularia (Fig 6A and 6D), placed in <lb/>zooidal margins, commonly replacing a marginal pore; (3) large (0.241mm in length; n = 1; <lb/>0.123 mm in wide; n = 1), subtriangular to sublanceolate avicularia (Fig 6B) (0.425 mm in <lb/>length; 0.025 mm in wide; n = 1), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, oriented proximally, <lb/>with acute rostrum, palate broad, foramen elliptical, with smooth margins and crossbar com-<lb/>plete. Vicarious avicularia (Fig 6D) with rostrum shorter than autozooids (0.266 mm in length; <lb/>n = 1; 0.110 mm in wide; n = 1), with the same morphology as the large adventitious avicular-<lb/>ium, randomly oriented. Ovicells not observed. <lb/>Remarks. Parasmittina dubitata was first described based on specimens from Burdwood <lb/>Bank, Argentina, growing on organic carbonates [49]. Here, we provide characterization of a <lb/>single specimen from Tierra del Fuego, Argentina, kindly sent by Juan Lopez Gappa (pers. <lb/>comm. 2021), that exhibts the diagnostic characters of the original description of P. dubitata. <lb/>This species is readily distinguished from other congeners by the primary orifice morphology, <lb/>including a lyrula with a concave distal margin and rounded condyles, unlike the straight lyr-<lb/>ula and triangular to hooked condyles of most Parasmittina species. <lb/>Distribution. SW Atlantic: Argentina (Burdwood Bank and Tierra del Fuego) [49] pres-<lb/>ent study). <lb/>Parasmittina ligulata (Ridley, 1881) comb. nov. <lb/>(Fig 7, Table 10) <lb/>Smittia trispinosa var. ligulata Ridley, 1881: 53, plate 6, figure 9 [50]. <lb/>Material examined. Holotype: NHMUK 2023.9.22.1, Smittia trispinosa var. ligulata, S.O. <lb/>Ridley det., Alert Circumnavigation 1878-1882, HMS Alert, Victoria Bank, Espı ´rito Santo, <lb/>Brazil, 60 m. <lb/>Redescription. Colony encrusting. Autozooids (0.324-0.458-0.603 mm length; n = 15; <lb/>SD = 0.073 mm; 0.209-0.324-0.462 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.072 mm), (Fig 7A) polygonal, <lb/>almost rhombic, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, surrounded by a single row of 19-27 <lb/>marginal pores (0.010-0.019-0.032 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm). Frontal wall <lb/>with rugose and nodular calcification (Fig 7A). Primary orifice (0.063-0.093-0.112 mm length; <lb/>n = 4; SD = 0.023 mm; 0.074-0.087-0.096 mm wide; n = 4; SD = 0.009 mm) (Fig 7C) elliptical, <lb/>distal margin smooth, oral spines not observed, lyrula narrow (0.015-0.021-0027 mm wide; <lb/>n = 4; SD = 0.005 mm); a pair of robust and down-curved hooked condyles with coarsely ser-<lb/>rated margins (Fig 7B). Secondary orifice (Fig 7B and 7F) pear-shaped, forming lateral flaps, <lb/>resulting in a shallow U-shaped pseudosinus (Fig 7E and 7F). Adventitious avicularia variable <lb/>in shapes and sizes (Figs 7B, 7D and 7F), with three morphologies: (1) small, narrow, and elon-<lb/>gated avicularia (Fig 7B, 7D and 7F) (0.108-0.163-0.210 mm in length; n = 10; SD = 0.034 <lb/>mm; 0.015-0.022-0.032 mm in wide; n = 10; SD = 0.005 mm), present at one or both side of <lb/>the orifice, unequal in size if paired, placed below the secondary orifice, proximally oriented, <lb/>rostrum narrow and slightly curved, smooth to slightly corrugated at its lateral margins, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>rounded tip, palate occupying about half of the rostrum length and oblong foramen; (2) small, <lb/>narrow and elliptic avicularia (Fig 7B and 7F) (0.060-0.083-0.116 mm in length; n = 10; <lb/>SD = 0.014 mm; 0.013-0.017-0.025 mm in wide; n = 10; SD = 0.003 mm), placed o zooidal <lb/>margins and/or o the frontal wall, with smooth lateral margins, rounded tip, palate narrow <lb/>and elliptical foramen; (3) large, sub-lanceolate avicularia (Fig 7D), placed laterally at one side <lb/>of the orifice, oriented proximally, rostrum slightly curved with rounded distal edge, palate <lb/>narrow and calcified, occupying more than half of avicularium chamber, foramen elliptical, <lb/>Fig 7. Parasmittina ligulata comb. nov. (Ridley, 1881). (A-D) NHMUK 2023.9.22.1, holotype, Espı ´rito Santo, Brazil. Arrows <lb/>indicating avicularia. (A) group of autozooids showing small avicularia, (B) detail of autozooid showing small avicularia, (C) detail of <lb/>primary orifice, (D) detail of ovicelled zooids and small avicularia. Scale bars: A = 400 μm; B, D = 200 μm; C = 80 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>crossbar complete, without columella, Ovicells (0.171-0.185-0.211mm length; n = 5; <lb/>SD = 0.017 mm; 0.163-0.188-0.212 mm wide; n = 5; SD = 0.022 mm) globose, densely sur-<lb/>rounded by adjacent frontal wall, ectooecium with 6-10 medium-sized pores (Fig 7F). <lb/>Remarks. Parasmittina ligulata comb. nov. belongs to the complex P. spathulata-P. areo-<lb/>lata, that comprise taxa from the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans with single or paired adventitious <lb/>latero-oral avicularia with narrow and elongated profile (e.g., [3, 7, 21]). <lb/>Parasmittina ligulata comb. nov. was originally described based on specimens from south-<lb/>eastern Brazil, but later synonymized under P. spathulata by Vieira et al. [25], who also include <lb/>in the same synonym list Brazilian specimen attributed to Smittina trispinosa spathulata <lb/>(USNM 8558). As stated above, the specimen studied by Canu &amp; Bassler [40] belongs to P. <lb/>abrolhosensis. Also, the analysis of the syntype showed that P. ligulata comb. nov. can be read-<lb/>ily differentiated from P. spathulata and P. abrolhosensis by showing large, avicularia elongate <lb/>to sublanceolate avicularia (spatulate in the other species). Other differences between P. ligu-<lb/>lata comb. nov. and P. spathulata is lyrula size (occupying one-quarter of the orifice in P. ligu-<lb/>lata comb. nov. and half of the orifice in P. spathulata), and between P. ligulata comb. nov. <lb/>and P. abrolhosensis is the occurrence of small latero-oral subtriangular avicularia in P. abrol-<lb/>hosensis (absent in P. ligulata comb. nov.). <lb/>Among all congeners, P. ligulata comb. nov. most resembles Parasmittina longirostrata Liu <lb/>in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001 [45] mainly because of small proximolateral, elongate and large sublan-<lb/>ceolate avicularia. However, these species are distinguished by lyrula size (occupying about <lb/>one-quarter of the orifice in P. ligulata comb. nov. and half of the orifice in P. longirostrata) <lb/>and small oblong avicularia (absent in P. ligulata comb. nov. and very common in P. <lb/>longirostrata). <lb/>Distribution. SW Atlantic: Brazil [50]. <lb/>Parasmitina longirostrata Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001 <lb/>(Fig 8; Tables 4, 10) <lb/>Parasmittina longirostrata Liu et al. 2001: 800, plate 53, figures 4-6 [45]. <lb/>?Parasmittina serruloides Harmelin et al. 2009: 174, figure 6A-D [9]. <lb/>Material examined. UFPE 816-821, UFBA 5030, 5097, 5198, 5213, 5248, 5297, 5343, <lb/>5349, 5354, 5360, 5365-5366, 5370-5372, 5374, 5389, 5396, 5400, 5407, 5409, 5414, 5416, 5422, <lb/>5427, 5430, 5431, 5436, 5438, 5444, 5453, 5465, Baia de Todos os Santos, Salvador, Bahia, Bra-<lb/>zil, 3-5 m, coll. 2012. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting (Fig 8A). Autozooids (Fig 8B) subrectangular to polygo-<lb/>nal, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, surrounded by a single row of 12-18 small marginal <lb/>pores (0.004-0.013-0.025 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm). Frontal wall rugose and <lb/>nodular. Primary orifice elliptical (Fig 8C), wider than long, distal margin smooth, with 3-4 <lb/>oral spines, lyrula median-sized (0.025-0.030-0.036 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.003 mm), a pair <lb/>of robust, hooked, condyles with serrated margins (up to seven teeth). Secondary orifice (Fig <lb/>8D and 8F) moderate to well-developed, pear-shaped, forming 2-4 lateral flaps commonly <lb/>resulting in a shallow U-shaped pseudosinus in autozooids, only partly obscuring the lyrula, <lb/>with a hood-shaped distal calcification in ovicelled zooids. Adventitious avicularia variable in <lb/>shapes and sizes (Fig 8B-8D), with two morphologies: (1) small, narrow and elongate avicu-<lb/>laria (Fig 8B and 8D) present at one side below to the secondary orifice, proximally oriented, <lb/>rostrum narrow and slightly curved, slightly corrugated at its lateral margins, rounded tip, pal-<lb/>ate occupying about half of the rostrum length, oblong foramen and crossbar complete; (2) <lb/>large, sub-lanceolate avicularia (Fig 8C and 8E), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, ori-<lb/>ented proximally, rostrum slightly curved with coarsely serrated margins and rounded distal <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>edge, palate narrow, occupying about half the rostrum length, foramen subtriangular with 2-3 <lb/>pseudopores adjacent to the avicularia. Ovicells globose, initially prominent (Fig 8D, and 8F) <lb/>and densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall (Fig 8F) in older zooids; ectooecium with 18-<lb/>24 medium-sized pseudopores (0.003-0.006-0.009 in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.001 mm), regu-<lb/>larly distributed through the ectooecial surface. <lb/>Remarks. Parasmittina longirostrata is characterized by the combination of a primary ori-<lb/>fice with smooth distal margin, with 3-4 oral spines, lyrula median-sized, secondary orifice <lb/>Fig 8. P. longirostrata Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. (A-F) UFBA 5444, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) general view of a <lb/>colony, (B) autozooids at the growing edge of the colony, (C) autozooids with large and small latero-oral avicularia, (D) detail of primary <lb/>orifice, (E) detail of zooids with large and small avicularia, (F) group of ovicelled zooids. Scale bars: A, B, C, E = 200 μm; F, D = 100 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>forming a U-shaped pseudosinus, and two types of proximolateral avicularia: small, elongate <lb/>and thin, and large, sub-lanceolate with crenulated margins [45]. <lb/>Liu et al. [45] considered that P. serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973 [2] was the most similar conge-<lb/>ner to P. longirostrata probably because of having two types of avicularia with the smaller and <lb/>proximolateral being thin and narrow. However, several differences are observed between <lb/>these species, including the primary orifice (with smooth distal margin and lyrula occupying <lb/>half of the orificial width in P. longirostrata and with distal denticles and lyrula occupying one-<lb/>quarter of the orificial width in P. serrula), placement of the smaller avicularia (typically <lb/>straightly placed proximolateral to the orifice in P. longirostrata and transversally below the <lb/>orifice in P. serrula) and profile of the large avicularium (sublanceolate in P. longirostrata and <lb/>lanceolate with lobate edge at half distal part in P. serrula). A congener very similar to P. longir-<lb/>ostrata, however, is P. serruloides Harmelin et al. 2009 [9], described based on specimens from <lb/>the Mediterranean. These species are only distinguished by the profile of the condyles (robust <lb/>and with 4-7 teeth in P. longirostrata, but thin and with 2-5 teeth in P. serruloides). However, <lb/>the profile of the condyles can be variable within a colony, as already seen in other Parasmit-<lb/>tina (e.g., P. onychorrhyncha Ryland &amp; Hayward, 1992 and P. aleutensis Soule &amp; Soule, 2002). <lb/>Thus, despite the type locality of P. longirostrata being in the North Pacific. The morphology <lb/>and morphometry of the specimens from Brazil resemble those of specimens of P. longirostrata <lb/>from China [45], but the autozooids of P. serruloides appear to be smaller zooids when com-<lb/>pared with P. longirostrata (Table 4). However, further studies are needed with specimens <lb/>from the Mediterranean, to determine if there are intraspecific differences that justify the <lb/>synonymization of P. serruloides with P. longirostrata <lb/>Distribution. Northeastern Pacific: China [45]; SW Atlantic: Brazil (present study). Speci-<lb/>mens from Lebanon [9] need to be compared to ascertain the synonym with P. longisrostrata. <lb/>Parasmittina pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. (Figs 9, 10; Tables 5, 10) <lb/>Parasmittina pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001: 805, plate 58, figures 3-6 [45]. <lb/>Smittina trispinosa: Luederwaldt 1929: 65 [49]. Non Discopora trispinosa Johnston, 1838: <lb/>280 [51]. <lb/>Smittina trispinosa var. nitida: Marcus 1937: 104, plate 21, figure 56 [23]. Non Discopora <lb/>nitida Verril, 1875: 415 [51]. <lb/>Parasmittina betamorphaea: Vieira et al. 2008: 27 [25]. Non Parasmittina betamorphaea <lb/>Winston, 2005: 58 [7]. <lb/>Table 4. Morphometric data of P. longirostrata and P. serruloides. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum (number of zooidal <lb/>measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small elongate; Av2 = large sublanceolate. <lb/>Character <lb/>Taxa / Reference <lb/>P. longirostrata / Liu et al. (2001) <lb/>P. longirostrata / UFBA 5444 (present study) <lb/>P. serruloides / Harmelin et al. (2009) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.480-0.600-0.744 (10) <lb/>0.316-0.449-0.634 (15) <lb/>0.270-0.375-0.460 (29) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.314-0.342-0.358 (10) <lb/>0.205-0.294-0.410 (15) <lb/>0.180-0.242-0.300 (29) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.098-0.100-0.106 (10) <lb/>0.073-0.084-0.096 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>OW <lb/>-<lb/>0.084-0.092-0.104 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.072-0.120-0.144 (10) <lb/>0.074-0.128-0.164 (7) <lb/>0.90-0.115-0.145 (29) <lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.028-0.042-0.056 (10) <lb/>0.012-0.018-0.025 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>Av2L <lb/>0.330-0.369-0.414 (10) <lb/>0.257-0.298-0.327 (8) <lb/>0.195-241.5-0.330 (26) <lb/>Av2W <lb/>0.174-0.218-0.258 (10) <lb/>0.031-0.039-0.048 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>OvL <lb/>0.142-0.158-0.172 (10) <lb/>0.136-0.153-0.169 (15) <lb/>0.125-0.149.2-0.160 (23) <lb/>OvW <lb/>0.186-0.204-0.214 (10) <lb/>0.167-0.184-0.202 (15) <lb/>0.60-0.184-0.205 (23) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Parasmittina parsevalii: Liu et al. 2001: 621, plate 54, figures 5-7 [46]. Non Cellepora parse-<lb/>valii Audouin, 1826: 238 [5]. <lb/>Parasmittina egyptiaca: Harmelin et al. 2009: 166, fig 2A-2E [9]; Baradari et al. 2019: 474, <lb/>figures 54-57 [18]. Non Smittia egyptiaca Waters, 1909: 157 [52]. <lb/>Material examined. UFBA 301, 644, 1112, 5466, Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, 37 m, <lb/>coll. 17/04/1997; UFBA 5317, Praia do Francês, Marechal Deodoro, Alagoas, Brazil, coll. 03/ <lb/>Fig 9. Parasmittina pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. (A-C) UFBA 5447, (D-F) UFBA 5453, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating <lb/>avicularia. (A) ancestrula and first zooids of the colony, (B) young autozooids showing small and large avicularia, (C) detail of primary <lb/>orifice and small avicularium, (D) group of autozooids showing small avicularia, (E) detail of autozooids and large avicularium, (F) <lb/>autozooids and ovicelled zooids. Scale bars: A, B, D-F = 250 μm; C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g009 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>02/2003; UFPE 2787, Porto do Cabedelo, Cabedelo, Paraı ´ba, Brazil, intertidal, coll. 27/09/2009; <lb/>UFPE 2582-2583, Praia Arac ¸a ´, São Sebastião, São Paulo, Brazil, coll. 07/07/2009; USNM Unca-<lb/>talogued, H. Luederwaldt det. 1926, Ilha de São Sebastião, São Paulo, Brazil; UFPE 822-830, <lb/>UFBA 5011, 5022, 5025, 5031, 5039, 5050, 5055, 5059, 5066, 5070, 5075, 5080, 5085, 5089, <lb/>5094, 5100, 5104, 5110, 5116, 5127, 5130, 5136, 5144, 5151, 5157, 5168, 5177, 5193, 5195, 5204, <lb/>5216, 5223, 5230, 5236, 5241, 5245, 5252, 5259, 5260, 5265, 5270, 5278-5279, 5287, 5291, 5298, <lb/>Fig 10. Parasmittina pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. (A-D, F) UFBA 5204, (C, E) UFBA 5466, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating <lb/>avicularia. (A) general view of a colony, (B) autozooids at the growing edge of the colony showing small avicularia, (C) detail of primary <lb/>orifices, (D) detail of primary orifice with small avicularia, (E) group of autozooids with small and large avicularia, (F) group of ovicelled <lb/>zooids with secondary calcification. Scale bars: A, F = 500 μm; B, D = 200 μm; C = 100 μm; E = 400 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g010 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>5345, 5351, 5358, 5363, 5373, 5384, 5386, 5397, 5417, 5424, 5428, 5451, 5454, 5457, 5461, 5466, <lb/>5497, 5503, 5506-5507, Baia de Todos os Santos, Salvador, Bahia, Brazil, 3-5 m, coll. 2012; <lb/>MZUSP 921, Smittina trispinosa var. nitida, det. Marcus, 1937, no locality [supposedly Santos, <lb/>São Paulo, Brazil]; MZUSP 1160, Iate Clube Ilhabela, Ilhabela, São Paulo, Brazil, 2 m, coll. 05/ <lb/>03/2010; MZUSP 2430.3, CE59, Porto do Mucuripe, Fortaleza, Ceara ´, Brazil, coll. 27/08/2009; <lb/>MZUSP 2952, CE65, Porto do Mucuripe, Fortaleza, Ceara ´, Brazil, 3˚32&apos;S, 38˚48&apos;W, coll. 27/08/ <lb/>2009; MZUSP 2420, 2431.1, CE67, Porto do Mucuripe, Fortaleza, Ceara ´, Brazil, coll. 27/08/ <lb/>2009; MZUSP 2953, CE69, Porto do Mucuripe, Fortaleza, Ceara ´, Brazil, coll. 27/08/2009; <lb/>MZUSP 2515, Ubatubinha, Ilha Grande, Angra dos Reis, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil,. . . . coll, 15/ <lb/>10/2012; MZUSP 1015, Smittina trispinosa var. nitida, det. Marcus, 1937, no locality [suppos-<lb/>edly Santos, São Paulo, Brazil]; USNM Uncatalogued, Smittina trispinosa, det. H. Luederwaldt, <lb/>São Sebastião, São Paulo, Brazil, coll. Jul 1925. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting, uni to multilaminar (Fig 9A). Ancestrula (Fig 9A) tati-<lb/>form, without marginal cryptocyst, 1 marginal spine; 3 orificial spines in first daughter zooid. <lb/>Autozooids (Figs 9B, 10B) subquadrangular to polygonal, limited by slightly raised lateral <lb/>walls, surrounded by a single row of 16-22 marginal pores (0.011-0.022-0.032 mm in diame-<lb/>ter; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm). Frontal wall rugose and nodular. Primary orifice (Figs 9C and <lb/>10C) subcircular, as long as wide, smooth distally, 1-2 oral spines, lyrula relatively wide but <lb/>low, occupying about half of the orifice length (0.025-0.038-0.047 mm wide; n = 15; <lb/>SD = 0.006 mm), a pair of almost straight and robust condyles with fine serrated margins. Sec-<lb/>ondary orifice low, forming short lateral flaps (Figs 9D, 10C), larger in ovicelled zooids (Figs <lb/>9F, 10F). Adventitious avicularia variable in shape and size (Fig 9B-9D), with three morpholo-<lb/>gies: (1) small subtriangular avicularia (Figs 9B and 10B, 10E), placed distolaterally to the ori-<lb/>fice in younger zooids and randomly scattered on the frontal wall (i.e., around the orifice, and <lb/>on the ovicell) in older zooids (Fig 10F); (2) small, profile elongate, sublanceolate (Figs 9C, 9E <lb/>and 10C), to spatulate (Fig 10C), narrow and with pointed rostrum, placed o zooidal margins, <lb/>more common in older zooids; (3) large, profile spatulate (Figs 9B, 9E and 10E), placed disto-<lb/>laterally to the orifice, oriented proximolaterally, palate narrow, occupying about three-quar-<lb/>ters of the rostrum length, with smooth margins and crossbar complete; 3-5 pseudopores <lb/>Table 5. Morphometric data of P. pinctatae, P. parsevalii and P. egyptiaca. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum (number of <lb/>zooidal measures), (*) = In Liu et al. (2001) there is an error in the median value, which is why it was adopted this way Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small subtriangular; <lb/>Av2 = small elongate; Av3 = large spatulate. <lb/>Character Taxa / Reference <lb/>P. pinctatae / Liu et al. <lb/>(2001) <lb/>P. pinctatae / UFBA 5204 <lb/>(present study) <lb/>P. parsevalii / Liu et al. <lb/>(2001) <lb/>P. egyptiaca / Harmelin et al. <lb/>(2009) <lb/>P. egyptiaca / Baradari et al. <lb/>(2019) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.483-0.522-0.655 (10) <lb/>0.380-0.467-0.672 (15) <lb/>0.366-0.498-0.670 (10) <lb/>0.365-0.492-0.730 (33) <lb/>0.270-0.397-0.531 (13) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.277-0.320-0.350 (10) <lb/>0.223-0.270-0.351 (15) <lb/>0.280-0.302-0.340 (10) <lb/>0.265-0.338-0.605 (33) <lb/>0.230-0.266-0.320 (13) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.112-0.122-0.135 (10) <lb/>0.091-0.104-0.114 (15) <lb/>0.098-0.106-0.110 (10) <lb/>0.085-0.107-0.130 (28) <lb/>-<lb/>OW <lb/>0.088-0.098-0.102 (10) <lb/>0.088-0.099-0.114 (15) <lb/>0.084-0.092-0.098 (10) <lb/>0.105-0.113-0.135 (28) <lb/>-<lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.064-0.084-0.098 (10) <lb/>0.035-0.053-0.090 (10) <lb/>*0.084-0.090 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.036-0.040-0.064 (10) <lb/>0.023-0.032-0.044 (3) <lb/>0.050-0.062-0.072 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av2L <lb/>0.088-0.102-0.110 (10) <lb/>0.137 (1) <lb/>0.072-0.080-0.086 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av2W <lb/>0.038-0.048-0.056 (10) <lb/>0.015 (1) <lb/>0.048-0.054-0.072 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Av3L <lb/>0.292-0.304-0.316 (10) <lb/>0.290-0.319-0.337 (3) <lb/>0.240-0.254-0.268 (10) <lb/>0.315-0.371-0.435 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>Av3W <lb/>0.074-0.080-0.088 (10) <lb/>0.057-0.061-0.066 (3) <lb/>0.098-0.098-0.114 (10) <lb/>0.085-0.108-0.120 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>OvL <lb/>0.180-0.200-0.216 (10) <lb/>0.129-0.173-0.192 (15) <lb/>0.184-0.198-0.220 (10) <lb/>0.195-0.205-0.230 (16) <lb/>-<lb/>OvW <lb/>0.208-0.240-0.245 (10) <lb/>0.163-0.221-0.243 (15) <lb/>0.224-0.236-0.256 (10) <lb/>0.205-0.236-0.265 (16) <lb/>-<lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>adjacet to the avicularia, foramen elliptical. Ovicells globose (Figs 9F and 10F), densely sur-<lb/>rounded by adjacent frontal wall (Fig 10F); ectooecium with more than 20 small to medium-<lb/>sized pseudopores (0.002-0.007-0.011 in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.002 mm) distributed <lb/>through the entire ovicell surface. <lb/>Remarks. Although P. pinctatae occurs in Brazil since at least 1929, due to misleading <lb/>identifications [23, 26, 53], we present the first formal record of this species to the Western <lb/>Atlantic. In Brazil, this species was previously attributed to P. trispinosa [32, 53], and P. nitida <lb/>(Verrill, 1875) but Vieira et al. [25] misassigned Marcus&apos;s P. nitida to P. betamorphaea. Here <lb/>we examined specimens studied by several authors (Luederwaldt [53], USNM Uncatalogued; <lb/>Marcus [23], MZUSP 921; Almeida et al. [26], UFBA 301 and UFBA 644), and all share with P. <lb/>pinctatae the subcircular primary orifice, secondary orifice with lateral flaps, short lyrula, nod-<lb/>ular frontal calcification and three types of avicularia. Additionally, specimens recently <lb/>assigned to P. egyptiaca by Orr et al. [54] from Brazil (Bahia) and Spain belong to P. pinctatae <lb/>(Table S2 of supplementary material from [54]). <lb/>Parasmittina pinctatae differs from P. trispinosa in the profile of the primary orifice (as <lb/>long as wide in P. pinctatae and longer than wide in P. trispinosa), number of oral spines (1-2 <lb/>in Parasmittina pinctatae and 2-3 in P. trispinosa), profile of avicularia (the proximolateral is <lb/>subtriangular in P. pinctatae and oblong in P. trispinosa; the large is spatulate in P. pinctatae <lb/>and subtriangular in P. trispinosa), and number of ovicell pseudopores (more than 20 in P. <lb/>pinctatae and 2-4 in P. trispinosa) [5]. Differences between P. pinctatae and P. nitida include <lb/>the profile of the primary orifice (subcircular in P. pinctatae and rounded in P. nitida), lyrula <lb/>(median in P. pinctatae and narrow in P. nitida), types of avicularia (three types in P. pinctatae: <lb/>proximolateral, marginal and large; two types in P. nitida: proximolateral and marginal) and <lb/>orientation of the proximolateral avicularia (distolateral in P. pinctatae and proximolateral in <lb/>P. nitida) [55]. Finally, P. pinctatae is distinguished from P. betamorphea in having a narrower <lb/>lyrula (the lyrula of P. betamorphaea is twice the length of that from of P. pinctatae) and con-<lb/>dyles thin and almost straight (robust and curved in P. betamorphaea) [7]. <lb/>The taxonomic history of P. pinctatae needs to be explained. Liu et al. [45] attributed other <lb/>specimens from China to P. parsevalii (Audouin, 1826) due to these having avicularia placed at <lb/>the frontal wall and laterally to the orifice (not associated with the peristome like in P. pincta-<lb/>tae) and differences in ooecia surface. However, P. parsevalii sensu Liu et al. [45] differs from <lb/>P. parsevalii (acc. Hayward &amp; Parker [47]) by having a primary orifice with smooth distal mar-<lb/>gin (beaded in P. parsevalii), relatively wide and low lyrula (narrow and high in P. parsevalii), <lb/>almost straight and thin condyles (robust and hooked in P. parsevalii) and large spatulate avi-<lb/>cularia (subtriangular in P. parsevalii). Thus, here we reassign the Chinese specimens of P. par-<lb/>sevalii to P. pinctatae. <lb/>Some records of P. egyptiaca made by Harmelin et al. [9, 56] and Baradari et al. [18] also <lb/>belong to P. pinctatae. The type specimen of P. egyptiaca (MFN Uncatalogued; Fig 11) is dis-<lb/>tinct from specimens characterized by these authors by having a raised secondary orifice, large <lb/>avicularia with subtriangular profile and serrated margins and latero-oral avicularia oriented <lb/>proximally. Thus, a review of specimens previously attributed to both P. parsevalii and P. egyp-<lb/>tiaca and morphologically related is strongly recommended. <lb/>Distribution. Central Pacific: China [45]; Red Sea [52]; Mediterranean: Lebanon [9, 56]; <lb/>Persian Gulf: Iran [18]; SW Atlantic: Brazil [26, 23, 53] present study). <lb/>Parasmittina serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973 <lb/>(Fig 12; Tables 6, 7, 10) <lb/>Parasmittina serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973: 386, fig 3D-F [2]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>? Parasmittina luteoserrula Winston &amp; Jackson, 2021: 141 [13]. <lb/>Material examined. UFBA 2850, Guarajuba, Camac ¸ari, Bahia, Brazil, 25-27 m, coll. 1997; <lb/>UFBA 2859, Recife dos Cascos, Baia de Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, 13-21 m, coll. 2016-<lb/>2017; MZUSP 2944, CE24, Canal das Arabaianas, Ceara ´, Brazil. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting, uni to multilaminar (Fig 12A). Autozooids (Fig 12B) <lb/>rhombic-polygonal, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, surrounded by a single row of 14-<lb/>Fig 11. Parasmittina egyptiaca (Waters, 1909). (A-F) MFN 1143, type. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) colony fragment showing <lb/>small and large avicularia, (B) detail of autozooid showing oral spines and small avicularia, (C) detail of autozooid showing large <lb/>avicularia, (D) detail of primary orifice showing condyles and lyrula, (E) detail of primary orifice showing oral spines and slightly <lb/>denticulate distal margin, (F) detail of ovicell. Scale bars: A = 300 μm; B, C, F = 100 μm; D, E = 20 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g011 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>22 marginal pores (0.009-0.019-0.036 mm wide; n = 30; SD = 0.005 mm). Frontal wall rugose <lb/>and nodular. Primary orifice (Fig 12C) elliptical, wider than long, beaded distal margin with <lb/>several well-spaced minute denticles, 3-5 oral spines, lyrula narrow, occupying about half of <lb/>Fig 12. Parasmittina serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973. (A-D) UFBA 2850, Bahia Brazil. Arrows indicating avicularia. (A) general view of a <lb/>colony, (B) autozooids at the growing edge of the colony showing small and large avicularia, (C) detail of primary orifice, (D) group of <lb/>ovicelled zooids showing large avicularia. Scale bars: A = 500 μm; B, D = 200 μm; C = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g012 <lb/>Table 6. Morphometric data of P. serrula and P. luteoserrula. Values given in millimeters and represented as mini-<lb/>mum-median-maximum (number of zooidal measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small elongate; Av2 = large <lb/>spatulate. <lb/>Character Taxa / Reference <lb/>P. serrula / Soule &amp; Soule <lb/>(1973) <lb/>P. serrula / UFBA 2850 (present <lb/>study) <lb/>P. luteoserrula / Winston &amp; Jackson <lb/>(2021) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.320-0.368-0.400 (10) <lb/>0.309-0.440-0.637 (15) <lb/>0.486-0.593-0.738 (18) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.260-0.284-0.310 (10) <lb/>0.190-0.257-0.310 (15) <lb/>0.288-0.363-0.450 (18) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.080-0.084-0.090 (10) <lb/>0.065-0.084-0.120 (10) <lb/>0.072-0.085-0.108 (18) <lb/>OW <lb/>0.060-0.066-0.075 (10) <lb/>0.074-0.087 0.102 (10) <lb/>0.090-0.105-0.126 (18) <lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.075-0.079-0.080 (6) <lb/>0.083-0.099-0.127 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.030-0.031-0.035 (6) <lb/>0.004-0.015-0.026 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>Av2L <lb/>0.240-0.252-0.260 (5) <lb/>0.255-0.309-0.359 (6) <lb/>0.252-0.323-0.378 (18) <lb/>Av2W <lb/>0.060-0.063-0.065 (5) <lb/>0.051-0.057-0.066 (6) <lb/>0.072-0.091-0.126 (18) <lb/>OvL <lb/>0.220 (1) <lb/>0.118-0.152-0.170 (15) <lb/>0.162-0.185-0.216 (18) <lb/>OvW <lb/>0.240 (1) <lb/>0.180-0.195-0.220 (15) <lb/>0.180-0.199-0.360 (18) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>the orifice length (0.020-0.023-0.028 mm wide; n = 10; SD = 0.002 mm), a pair of hooked con-<lb/>dyles with coarsely serrated margins. Secondary orifice pear-shaped, forming 2 proximolateral <lb/>flaps and resulting in a pseudosinus (Fig 12B and 12D), larger in ovicelled zooids (Fig 12D). <lb/>Adventitious avicularia variable in shapes and sizes (Fig 12A, 12B and 12D), with two mor-<lb/>phologies: (1) initially small, narrow and elliptical (Fig 12A), becoming elongate with develop-<lb/>ment (Fig 12B), present at one or both sides below the secondary orifice, proximally oriented, <lb/>rostrum narrow and slightly curved, slightly corrugated at its lateral margins, rounded tip, pal-<lb/>ate occupying about half of the rostrum length, oblong foramen and crossbar complete; (2) <lb/>large lanceolate avicularia with lobate edge at half distal part (Fig 12B and 12D), placed disto-<lb/>laterally to the orifice and oriented proximally, palate broad, occupying about three-quarters <lb/>of the rostrum length, foramen oval, crossbar complete; 1-2 pseudopores adjacent to the avi-<lb/>cularia, rostrum spatulate, with crenulated margins (Fig 12A) in younger and strongly serrated <lb/>margins (Fig 12B) in older zooids. Ovicells globose (Fig 12D), surrounded by an adjacent fron-<lb/>tal wall; ectooecium with 12-27 medium-sized pseudopores (0.005-0.007-0.0013 mm wide; <lb/>n = 30; SD = 0.001 mm) distributed through the entire ovicell surface. Secondary calcification <lb/>around the primary orifice in ovicelled zooids forms a hood in the distal margin of the ovicell <lb/>(Fig 12D). <lb/>Remarks. As like P. ligulata comb. nov., P. serrula belongs to the P. spathulata-P. areolata <lb/>complex, thus having avicularia with two morphologies: narrow-elongated and large-spatu-<lb/>lated. Species of this complex, however, can be distinguished by features of the primary orifice, <lb/>avicularia ornamentation, and ovicells. Parasmittina serrula differs from P. ligulata comb. <lb/>nov., P. spathulata, and P. areolata by having up to 6 oral spines (up to 4 in all other species), <lb/>and large spatulate avicularium with strongly serrated margins (with smoother margins in all <lb/>other species). <lb/>First described based on specimens from Hawaii, in the Central Pacific [2], P. serrula was <lb/>already recorded from coral reefs of Belize, and experimental panels from Jamaica [3, 37] in <lb/>the Caribbean and several localities from the Western and Central Pacific [2]. Although most <lb/>reports of P. serrula from the Western and Central Pacific differ from the type specimens in <lb/>characters of the primary orifice (Table 7), specimens from SW Atlantic studied here showed <lb/>all morphological and morphometric characters provided by Soule &amp; Soule [2] (Tables 6 and <lb/>7) to P. serrula. Its unusual geographical distribution was already related to hull shipping <lb/>through the Panama Canal [16] and to an opportunistic behavior of the species [37]. <lb/>Table 7. Morphological variations in specimens from different localities assigned to P. serrula and P. luteoserrula. Unknown states are assigned as (?). <lb/>Taxa / Localities <lb/>Reference <lb/>Oral spines <lb/>Condyles profile <lb/>Lyrula and orifice width ratio <lb/>P. serrula <lb/>Hawaii (EUA), Central Pacific <lb/>Soule &amp; Soule (1973) <lb/>3-6 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Hawaii (EUA), Central Pacific <lb/>Gordon (1984) <lb/>4 <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Heron Island (Australia), Coral Sea <lb/>Ryland &amp; Hayward (1992) <lb/>2-4 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.50 <lb/>Philippines, Southwest Pacific <lb/>Gordon &amp; D&apos;Hondt (1997) <lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Vanuatu, Southwest Pacific <lb/>Tilbrook et al. (2001) <lb/>2-4 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.50 <lb/>Vanuatu, Southwest Pacific <lb/>Tilbrook et al. (2006) <lb/>3-4 <lb/>thin <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Hawaii (EUA), Central Pacific <lb/>Dick et al. (2006) <lb/>2-4 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.33 <lb/>Okinawa (Japan), Central Pacific <lb/>Dick &amp; Grischenko (2017) <lb/>3-4 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.50 <lb/>Brazil, Southwestern Atlantic <lb/>Present study <lb/>3-5 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.25 <lb/>P. luteoserrula <lb/>Kingston (Jamaica), Caribbeann <lb/>Winston &amp; Jackson (2021) <lb/>3-4 <lb/>strong <lb/>0.25-0.33 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Among congeners, P. serrula is very similar to Parasmittina luteoserrula, recently described <lb/>by Winston &amp; Jackson [13] based on specimens from the Caribbean. Winston &amp; Jackson [17] <lb/>compared P. luteoserrula with P. serrula and indicated differences in the zooid sizes (indicated <lb/>incorrectly as smaller in P. luteoserrula than in P. serrula, but zooids in the former species are <lb/>actually larger, as shown in Table 6), large avicularia with a more fluted rostrum, and pores <lb/>occupying more than half of the frontal surface of the ovicell. However, as previously discussed <lb/>(see remarks of P. alba, for example), much of these variations may be related to different colo-<lb/>nial and zooidal stages of development rather than different species. Thus, we consider a spe-<lb/>cies complex involving P. serrula and P. luteoserrula, but additional studies including <lb/>specimens from the current distributional range of P. serrula are needed. <lb/>Distribution. Central Pacific: Hawaii [3]; SW Atlantic: Brazil (present study). <lb/>Parasmittina simpulata Winston, Vieira &amp; Woollacott, 2014 <lb/>(Fig 13; Tables 8, 10) <lb/>Parasmittina simpulata Winston et al. 2014: 200, fig 39A-F [12]. <lb/>Parasmittina spathulata: Almeida et al. 2015: 4 (in part) [26]. Non Escharella jacotini var. <lb/>spathulata Smitt, 1873: 60 [42]. <lb/>? Parasmittina parsevaliformis Soule &amp; Soule 1973: 412 [2]. <lb/>? Parasmittina barbadensis Winston &amp; Woollacott 2009: 262 [38]. <lb/>Material examined. UFBA 209, 716, 5304, 5313-5315, 5324, 5445, UFPE 831-832, Costa <lb/>dos Coqueiros, Camac ¸ari, Bahia, Brazil, 25-30 m, coll. 1993-2004; UFBA 365, Salvador, Bahia, <lb/>Brazil, 0-25 m, coll. 05/04/2012; UFBA 952, 959, 2268, Baia de Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, <lb/>0-48 m, coll. 1997-2006; UFBA 3110, 3112, 3116, Costa do Dendê, Bahia, Brazil, coll. 2012; <lb/>UFBA 5325, Banco Charlotte, Bahia, Brazil, 35 m, coll. 03/1996. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting, primarily unilaminar (Fig 13A). Autozooids (Fig 13A) <lb/>initially subrectangular to subquadrangular, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, with a single <lb/>row of 20-31 marginal pores (0.007-0.019-0.0040 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.007 mm). <lb/>Frontal wall rugose and nodular (Fig 13B, 13C). Primary orifice (Fig 13D) elliptical, slightly <lb/>longer than wide, distal with 4-6 well-spaced minute denticles, up to 3 oral spines, lyrula nar-<lb/>row (0.017-0.031-0.038 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.005 mm), a pair of hooked condyles with <lb/>coarsely serrated margins. Secondary orifice initially developed as two short lateral projections <lb/>(Fig 13C), sometimes forming a broad U-shaped pseudosinus (Fig 13F). Adventitious avicu-<lb/>laria variable in shape and size (Fig 12B-12F), with three morphologies: (1) small, subtriangu-<lb/>lar, avicularia (Fig 13D), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, distally oriented, rostrum <lb/>subtriangular, smooth at its lateral margins, pointed tip, palate narrow, subtriangular foramen, <lb/>and crossbar complete; (2) small, oblong to spatulate avicularia (Fig 13D) single or paired, <lb/>placed below the secondary orifice, proximally oriented, smooth at its lateral margins, rounded <lb/>tip, palate occupying about three-quarters of the rostrum length, oval foramen and crossbar <lb/>complete; (3) large, spatulate avicularia (Fig 13B and 13C), placed laterally at one side of the <lb/>orifice, oriented proximally, with rostrum oblong to spoon-shaped arched upwards, palate <lb/>broad occupying three-quarters of the rostrum length, foramen subtriangular to elliptical, with <lb/>smooth margins and crossbar complete, with 2-3 pseudopores adjacent to the avicularia. Sec-<lb/>ondary calcification of the frontal wall can place avicularia randomly scattered on the frontal <lb/>wall (i.e., around the orifice, in a suboral position, and on the ovicell, Fig 13E-13F). Ovicells <lb/>globose, densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall (Fig 13E); ectooecium with 8-10 large <lb/>pseudopores (0.007-0.013-0.026 in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.004 mm). Secondary calcification <lb/>around the primary orifice in ovicelled zooids forms a hood in the distal margin of the ovicell <lb/>(Fig 13F). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Remarks. Parasmittina simpulata was originally described based on a single infertile col-<lb/>ony from southeastern Brazil, being diagnosed by having a primary orifice with distal denti-<lb/>cles, serrated condyles, proximolateral small avicularia oval and subtriangular and large <lb/>avicularia spatulate [12]. All these characters are observed in specimens from coral reefs and <lb/>experimental plates of tiles from northeastern Brazil analyzed in this study, adding that our <lb/>Fig 13. Parasmittina simpulata Winston, Vieira &amp; Woollacott, 2014. (A) UFBA 365, (B-F) UFBA 5324, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows <lb/>indicating avicularia. (A) autozooids at the growing edge of the colony showing the origin of the small avicularia, (B) group of <lb/>autozooids with small and large avicularia, (C) detail of autozooid showing small and large avicularia, (D) detail of primary orifice <lb/>showing small avicularia. (E) group of ovicelled zooids. (F) detail of ovicelled zooids showing secondary calcification around the ovicells. <lb/>Scale bars: A, E = 500 μm; D = 100 μm; B = 200 μm; C, F = 400 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g013 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>colonies have ovicell with large pseudopores (Fig 13E and 13F). Also, we observed that avicu-<lb/>laria development and ovicell calcification vary between younger (Fig 13A and 13B) and older <lb/>(Fig 13C and 13E) colonies. <lb/>Parasmittina simpulata is considered very similar to the Caribbean P. barbadensis Winston <lb/>&amp; Woollacott, 2009 [38], differing only in the large avicularia (absent in P. barbadensis) and <lb/>larger zooids of P. barbadensis [12]. Unfortunately, P. barbadensis was also described based on <lb/>a single colony fragment, preventing more comparisons. Parasmittina simpulata and P. barba-<lb/>densis also share similarities in the frontal calcification, primary and secondary orifices, and <lb/>avicularia with P. parsevaliformis Soule &amp; Soule, 1973 [2] described based on specimens from <lb/>Hawaii, except for the large avicularium (absent in P. barbadensis) (Table 8). Soule &amp; Soule [2] <lb/>described differences in avicularia morphology and secondary calcification in the orifice and <lb/>ovicell pending the colonial development of P. parsevaliformis. We also found morphological <lb/>variations in the avicularia development and ovicell calcification when compared younger (Fig <lb/>13A and 13B) and older (Fig 13E and 13F) colonies. Also, our values comprise morphometric <lb/>variations seen in the three taxa-P. simpulata, P. barbadensis and P. parsevaliformis (Table 8). <lb/>Thus, we have some evidence that the absence of avicularia in specimens originally attributed <lb/>to P. simpulata and P. barbadensis, respectively, as well as the morphometric variations, can be <lb/>related to the ontogenetic stage of the studied specimens. <lb/>Biogeographically, it is unlikely that P. simpulata (SW Atlantic), P. barbadensis (Caribbean), <lb/>and P. parsevaliformis (Central Pacific) may represent a single species. On the other hand, P. <lb/>parsevaliformis was described based on specimens that were encrusting a variety of substrata <lb/>including rocks, corals, shells and cement [2] and material studied here include colonies from <lb/>coral reefs and artificial substrata (experimental plates of tiles). Thus, the association with arti-<lb/>ficial substrata could suggest that a single species of Parasmittina may be dispersing world-<lb/>wide, resulting in isolated geographical records. However, until more data on these taxa are <lb/>known, we choose to keep them as distinct species. <lb/>Distribution. SW Atlantic: Brazil [12]; present study). <lb/>Parasmittina winstonae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001 <lb/>(Fig 14; Tables 9, 10) <lb/>Table 8. Morphometric data of P. simpulata, P. parsevaliformis and P. barbadensis. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum <lb/>(number of zooidal measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small subtriangular; Av2 = small oblong; Av3 = large spatulate. <lb/>Character Taxa / Reference / Specimen <lb/>P. simpulata / Winston et al. <lb/>(2014) <lb/>P. simpulata / Present study / UFBA <lb/>5324 <lb/>P. parsevaliformis / Soule &amp; Soule <lb/>(1973) <lb/>P. barbadensis / Winston &amp; Woollacatt <lb/>(2009) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.450-0.585-0.684 (6) <lb/>0.332-0.544 0.818 (15) <lb/>0.500-0.600-0.700 (10) <lb/>0.655-0.804-0.892 (6) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.324-0.360-0.396 (6) <lb/>0.255-0.396-0.634 (15) <lb/>0.320-0.385-0.480 (10) <lb/>0.400-0.510-0.637 (6) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.090-0.111-0.126 (6) <lb/>0.081-0.0.097-0.127 (15) <lb/>0.110-0.127-0.160 (10) <lb/>0.127-0.141-0.155 (6) <lb/>OW <lb/>0.090-0.099-0.108 (6) <lb/>0.084-0.100-0.110 (15) <lb/>0.100-0.106-0.110 (10) <lb/>0.127-0.133-0.146 (6) <lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.162-0.447-0.612 (6) <lb/>0.086-0.131-0.188 (15) <lb/>0.140-0.168-0.200 (10) <lb/>0.127-0.133-0.146 (6) <lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.108-0.129-0.144 (6) <lb/>0.033-0.057-0.069 (15) <lb/>0.080-0.092-0.100 (10) <lb/>0.055-0.074-0.091 (6) <lb/>Av2L <lb/>0.126-0.180-0.270 (6) <lb/>0.097-0.124-0.160 (15 <lb/>0.080-0.111-0.140 (10) <lb/>0.127-0.176-328 (6) <lb/>Av2W <lb/>0.054-0.081-0.144 (6) <lb/>0.039-0.046-0.056 (15) <lb/>0.040-0.053-0.060 (10) <lb/>0.055-0.086-0.200 (6) <lb/>Av3L <lb/>-<lb/>0.302-0.451-0.553 (8) <lb/>0.310-0.360-0.390 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>Av3W <lb/>-<lb/>0.100-0.126-0.156 (8) <lb/>0.120-0.174-0.200 (10) <lb/>-<lb/>OvL <lb/>-<lb/>0.199-0.226-0.254 (14) <lb/>0.200-0.215-0.240 (4) <lb/>0.237-0.267-0.291 (6) <lb/>OvW <lb/>-<lb/>0.225-0.270-0.346 (14) <lb/>0.240-0.245-0.260 (4) <lb/>0.291-0.340-0.382 (6) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Parasmittina winstonae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001: 801, pl 55, fig 1-7 [45]. <lb/>Parasmittina winstonae: Tilbrook 2006: 156, pl 29K, fig 35A-C [8]; Taylor &amp; Tan 2015: 19, <lb/>fig 11A-L [57]. <lb/>Parasmittina loxoides Winston et al., 2014: 202, fig 40A-D [12]; Almeida et al. 2018: 409, fig <lb/>5A-F [58]. <lb/>Fig 14. Parasmittina winstonae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. (A) UFBA 5321, (B) UFBA 5320, (C-F) UFBA 5316, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows <lb/>indicating avicularia. (A) group of young autozooids, (B) detail of autozooid showing small and large avicularia, (C) group of autozooids <lb/>with small and large avicularia, (D) detail of orifice, (E) group of ovicelled zooids, (F) detail of ovicelled zooids with showing secondary <lb/>calcification. Scale bars: A, E = 500 μm; B, F = 200 μm; C = 250 μm; D = 100 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g014 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>31 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Material examined. UFPE 545-554, UFBA 1619, 1621, 1622, 1627, 1628, 1652, 1661, <lb/>5319-5322, 5467-5495, Baia de Todos os Santos, Ilha de Itaparica, Itaparica, Bahia, Brazil, <lb/>intertidal, coll. 2012-2015; UFBA 2852, Baı ´a Todos os Santos, Porto da Barra, Salvador, Bahia, <lb/>Brazil, 24 m, coll. 07/2017, UFBA 575, 2847-2849, Costa dos Coqueiros, Camac ¸ari, Bahia, Bra-<lb/>zil, 22-27 m, coll. 1997-2002, UFBA 697, 5003, Costa do Dendê, Bahia, Brazil, 30 m, coll. <lb/>2002; UFPE 641-644, UFBA 5316, Praia do Francês, Marechal Deodoro, Alagoas, Brazil, coll. <lb/>03/02/2003; UFPE 651, Jatiuca, Maceio, Alagoas, Brazil, coll. 15/10/2005; MZUSP Uncatalo-<lb/>gued PE26, UFPE 579, Porto de Suape, Cabo de Santo Agostinho, Pernambuco, Brazil, coll. <lb/>01/08/2020; UFPE 621, 649 Barra de Catuama, Goiana, Pernambuco, Brazil; UFBA 5323, Pon-<lb/>tas de Pedra, Goiana, Pernambuco, Brazil, intertidal, coll. 20/02/2015, UFPE 343, 645-646, <lb/>Porto do Cabedelo, Cabedelo, Paraı ´ba, Brazil, intertidal, coll. 27/09/2009; UFPE 274, Saco da <lb/>Pedra, coll. 16/09/2004; UFPE 340, Amores, 22/09/2006; UFBA 5017, 5160, 5167, 5212, 5262, <lb/>5276, 5293, 5405, 5421, 5459, 5496, 5499, 5511, 5513, Baia de Todos os Santos, Salvador, Bahia, <lb/>Brazil, 3-5 m, coll. 2012, MZUSP 887, Santos, São Paulo, Brazil. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting, unilaminar. Autozooids (Fig 14A) subrectangular to <lb/>polygonal, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, with a single row of 25-30 large marginal <lb/>pores (0.009-0.025-0.042 mm in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.008 mm). Frontal wall slightly <lb/>rugose and nodular. Primary orifice (Fig 14B) elliptical, slightly longer than wide, anter <lb/>smooth, 1-2 oral spines, lyrula narrow (0.020-0.041 mm wide), and a pair of hook-shaped <lb/>condyles with coarsely serrated tips. Secondary orifice low (Fig 14D), forming two lateral short <lb/>projections. Adventitious avicularia variable in shapes and sizes (Fig 14B and 14F), with three <lb/>morphologies: (1) small, subtriangular avicularia (Fig 14C and 14D), placed laterally to the ori-<lb/>fice and distally oriented in autozooids, with a suboral or randomly arranged in ovicelled and <lb/>adjacent zooids (Fig 14E-14F), rostrum subtriangular, smooth at its lateral margins, pointed <lb/>tip, palate narrow, elliptical foramen and crossbar complete; (2) small, spatulate avicularia (Fig <lb/>14B and 14C), placed o zooidal margins, commonly replacing a marginal pore; (3) large, spatu-<lb/>late avicularia (Fig 14B and 14C), placed laterally at one side of the orifice, oriented distally, <lb/>palate broad occupying half of the rostrum length, foramen subtriangular to elliptical, with <lb/>smooth margins and crossbar complete, with 2-3 pseudopores adjacent to the avicularia. Ovi-<lb/>cell (Fig 14E-14F) densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall, soon becoming immersed in <lb/>Table 9. Morphometric data of specimens here assigned to P. winstonae. Values given in millimeters and represented as minimum-median-maximum (number of <lb/>zooidal measures). Avicularia abbreviations: Av1 = small subtriangular; Av2 = small spatulate; Av3 = large spatulate. <lb/>Character Reference <lb/>Liu et al. (2001) <lb/>Present study / UFBA 5316 Tilbrook (2006) Taylor &amp; Tan (2015) Winston et al. (2014) Almeida et al. (2018) <lb/>ZL <lb/>0.440-0.574-0.660 (10) 0.337-0.412-0.514 (10) <lb/>0.450 (?) <lb/>0.320-0.450 (?) <lb/>0.306-0.360-0.396 (6) 0.344-0.396-0.561 (15) <lb/>ZW <lb/>0.280-0.327-0.420 (10) 0.196-0.307-0.367 (10) <lb/>0.300 (?) <lb/>0.220-0.330 (?) <lb/>0.216-0.240-0.270 (6) 0.160-0.278-0.358 (15) <lb/>OL <lb/>0.140-0.150-0.160 (10) 0.087-0.102-0.115 (8) <lb/>0.110 (?) <lb/>0.100-0.110 (?) <lb/>0.081-0.090-0.099 (6) 0.113-0.117-0.134 (15) <lb/>OW <lb/>0.100-0.104-0.110 (10) 0.085-0.100-0.119 (8) <lb/>0.110 (?) <lb/>0.100 (?) <lb/>0.090-0.096-0.108 (6) 0.084-0.115-0.126 (15) <lb/>Av1L <lb/>0.102-0.120-0.144 (10) 0.069-0.093-0.132 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.090-0.120 (?) <lb/>0.108-0.113-0.126 (4) 0.090-0.093-0.116 (15) <lb/>Av1W <lb/>0.058-0.100-0.124 (10) 0.032-0.042-0.058 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.050-0.060 (?) <lb/>0.054-0.054-0.054 (4) 0.051-0.058-0.061 (15) <lb/>Av2L <lb/>0.062-0.0.98-124 (10) <lb/>0.041-0.054-0.076 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.050-0.060 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.051-0.068-0.083 (15) <lb/>Av2W <lb/>0.042-0.064-0.082 (10) 0.032-0.043-0.058 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.050-0.080 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.035-0.045-0.052 (15) <lb/>Av3L <lb/>0.270-0.280-300 (10) <lb/>0.386-0.415-0.444 (2) <lb/>-<lb/>0.350-0.400 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.237-0.312-0.360 (15) <lb/>Av3W <lb/>0.130-0.140-0.150 (10) 0.055-0.064-0.074 (2) <lb/>-<lb/>0.110-0.130 (?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.069-0.084-0.097 (15) <lb/>OvL <lb/>0.205-0.214-0.225 (10) 0.172-0.190-0.208 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.130-0.160 (?) <lb/>0.162-0.180-0.198 (6) 0.131-0.164-0.200 (15) <lb/>OvW <lb/>0.212-0.250-0.292 (10) 0.205-0.227-0.273 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>0.180 (?) <lb/>0.234-0.246-0.270 (6) 0.154-0.205-0.237 (15) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t009 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>32 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 10. Diagnostic characters of Parasmittina species, with respective type localities, and based on features of the primary orifice (distal margin ornamentation, <lb/>number of spines, condyles profile/condyles margin ornamentation, and lyrula size), small avicularia morphologies, large avicularia morphologies, and number of <lb/>ovicell pores. Symbols and abbreviations: (Isl.) = Island, (*) = type specimen lost, (**) = species only with vicarious avicularia, (?) = unknown states, (-) = absent, (S) = <lb/>spines, (L) = lyrula and orifice width ratio. <lb/>Species <lb/>Type locality <lb/>Primary orifice <lb/>Small avicularia <lb/>Large avicularia Ovicell <lb/>pores <lb/>Distal <lb/>margin <lb/>S Condyles L <lb/>Distolateral Proximolateral <lb/>Marginal <lb/>P. abrolhosensis Ramalho <lb/>et al., 2018 <lb/>Bahia, Brazil <lb/>smooth 3-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptical <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. aculeata Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 sublanceolate <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. acuta (Canu &amp; Bassler, <lb/>1929) <lb/>Philippines <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>thin/? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>P. alanbanneri Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 3-<lb/>6 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. alaskensis Osburn, 1952 <lb/>Alaska, USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. alba Ramalho, Muricy &amp; <lb/>Taylor, 2011 <lb/>Rio de Janeiro, <lb/>Brazil <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>&gt; 10 <lb/>P. aleutensis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>2002 <lb/>Alaska, USA <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>2-3 <lb/>P. alitis Winston &amp; Jackson, <lb/>2021 <lb/>Jamaica, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>beaded 3-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>25-29 <lb/>P. amazonensis Ramalho &amp; <lb/>Moraes in Ramalho et al. <lb/>2021 <lb/>Maranhão, Brazil smooth 5-<lb/>6 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>elliptical <lb/>elliptic <lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. aotea (Brown, 1952) <lb/>New Zealand <lb/>? <lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. areolata (Canu &amp; Bassler, <lb/>1927) <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.12 subtriangular <lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>32 <lb/>P. atypica (Powell, 1967) <lb/>New Zealand <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>5 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. aviculifera Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>2002 <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>18 or &gt; <lb/>P. baccula Hayward &amp; <lb/>Winston, 2011 <lb/>Antarctic, USA <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>24-27 <lb/>P. barbadensis Winston &amp; <lb/>Woollacott, 2009 <lb/>Barbados, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>8-10 <lb/>P. betamorphaea Winston, <lb/>2005 <lb/>Florida, Atlantic <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>elliptic/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. bimucronata (Hincks, <lb/>1884a) <lb/>Myanmar, <lb/>Andaman Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20-37 <lb/>*P. californica (Robertson, <lb/>1908) <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 &gt; <lb/>P. californiensis (Robertson, <lb/>1908) <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>4 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>P. circinanata Liu in Liu et al., <lb/>2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. circularis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 robust/? 0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>*P. collifera (Robertson, 1908) California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>8-14 <lb/>P. crosslandi (Hastings, 1930) Taboga Isl., <lb/>Pacific Panama <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. cyclops Winston &amp; Jackson, <lb/>2021 <lb/>Jamaica, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>10 or &gt; <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>33 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 10. (Continued) <lb/>Species <lb/>Type locality <lb/>Primary orifice <lb/>Small avicularia <lb/>Large avicularia Ovicell <lb/>pores <lb/>Distal <lb/>margin <lb/>S Condyles L <lb/>Distolateral Proximolateral <lb/>Marginal <lb/>P. delicatula (Busk, 1884) <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>P. dentigera (Harmer, 1957) <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>beaded 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>P. dependeo Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. distincta Ramalho et al., <lb/>2018 <lb/>Bahia, Brazil <lb/>beaded 2-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/? 0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. dolabrata Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Gala ´pagos Isl. <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>hatchet-shaped <lb/>? <lb/>P. dubitata Hayward, 1980 <lb/>Argentina <lb/>? <lb/>1-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/? 0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>12 <lb/>P. eccentrica Winston &amp; <lb/>Jackson, 2021 <lb/>Jamaica, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>hatchet-shaped/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. echinata (Canu &amp; Bassler, <lb/>1928b) <lb/>Gulf of Mexico <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. egyptiaca (Waters, 1909) <lb/>Egypt, Red Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. emersoni Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 robust/? 0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. erecta Gordon &amp; d&apos;Hondt, <lb/>1997 <lb/>New Caledonia <lb/>smooth 6 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>44 <lb/>P. exasperatrix d&apos;Hondt, 1986 New Caledonia <lb/>smooth 3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>elongate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. exiguiuncinata Tilbrook, <lb/>2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. fistulata (Harmer, 1957) <lb/>Makassar Strait, <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>smooth 1 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. floridana Winston, 2005 <lb/>Florida, Atlantic <lb/>USA <lb/>beaded 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>16 <lb/>P. fraseri Osburn, 1952 <lb/>Clarion Isl., <lb/>Mexican Pacific <lb/>smooth 3-<lb/>5 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>30 <lb/>P. galerita Ryland &amp; <lb/>Hayward, 1992 <lb/>Heron Isl., <lb/>Australia <lb/>smooth ? <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>20 <lb/>P. glabra Gordon &amp; d&apos;Hondt, <lb/>1997 <lb/>New Caledonia <lb/>smooth 7-<lb/>8 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>40 <lb/>P. glomerata (Thornely, 1912) Mascarene Isl., <lb/>Mauritius <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. hanzawae Kataoka, 1960 <lb/>Japan Sea <lb/>? <lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. hastingsae Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. ilioensis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. inalienata Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>15 <lb/>P. indiginella Winston, 2016 <lb/>Florida, Atlantic <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 5-<lb/>6 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>-<lb/>elliptical <lb/>elliptical <lb/>-<lb/>22-25 <lb/>P. kauaiensis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>thin <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>34 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 10. (Continued) <lb/>Species <lb/>Type locality <lb/>Primary orifice <lb/>Small avicularia <lb/>Large avicularia Ovicell <lb/>pores <lb/>Distal <lb/>margin <lb/>S Condyles L <lb/>Distolateral Proximolateral <lb/>Marginal <lb/>P. labellum (Canu &amp; Bassler, <lb/>1928b) <lb/>Gulf of Mexico <lb/>? <lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. latiavicularia (Kirkpatrick, <lb/>1888) <lb/>Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>10 or &gt; <lb/>P. lavela Soule &amp; Soule, 2002 Peninsula de La <lb/>Guajira, <lb/>Colombia <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>12 &gt; <lb/>P. leviavicularia Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 subtriangular/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>14-24 <lb/>P. livingstonei (Powell, 1967) New Zealand <lb/>? <lb/>5-<lb/>7 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. ligulata comb. nov. (Ridley, <lb/>1881) <lb/>Espı ´rito Santo, <lb/>Brazil <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>elliptic <lb/>elongate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20-26 <lb/>P. longirostrata Liu in Liu <lb/>et al., 2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/elongate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20-26 <lb/>P. loxoides Winston et al., <lb/>2014 <lb/>Rio de Janeiro, <lb/>Brazil <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>25 or &gt; <lb/>P. luteoserrula Winston &amp; <lb/>Jackson, 2021 <lb/>Jamaica, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>beaded 3-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrate <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>noodle tong/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>19-28 <lb/>P. macginitiei Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>2002 <lb/>Alaska, USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>P. margaritata Hayward, 1988 Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>smooth 3-<lb/>4 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>-<lb/>P. marsupialis (Busk, 1884) <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. mauritiana Hayward, 1988 Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>4 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. mexicana Pouyet &amp; <lb/>Herrera-Anduaga, 1986 <lb/>Gulf of Mexico <lb/>? <lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>15 or &gt; <lb/>P. multiaviculata Souto et al., <lb/>2016 <lb/>Madeira Isl. <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>34 <lb/>P. munita (Hincks, 1884b) <lb/>Australia <lb/>? <lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate** <lb/>? <lb/>P. murarmata (Kirkpatrick, <lb/>1888) <lb/>Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 sublanceolate <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. nasuta (Harmer, 1957) <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>? <lb/>3-<lb/>6 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. natalensis O&apos;Donoghue, <lb/>1957 <lb/>Umhlanga Rocks, <lb/>Southern Africa-<lb/>Indian <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>smooth 0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. nitida (Verrill, 1875) <lb/>Vineyard Sound, <lb/>Atlantic USA <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/? <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>10 or &gt; <lb/>P. novella Hayward &amp; Cook, <lb/>1983 <lb/>South Africa, <lb/>Southern Africa-<lb/>Indian <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>4 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>elliptic/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate/ <lb/>noodle tong <lb/>? <lb/>P. obstructa (Waters, 1889) <lb/>Australia <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 sublanceolate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate** <lb/>? <lb/>P. oculinae Winston, 2016 <lb/>Florida, Atlantic <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>elliptic/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>34-44 <lb/>P. onychorrhyncha Ryland &amp; <lb/>Hayward, 1992 <lb/>Heron Isl., <lb/>Australia <lb/>smooth 1 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>34 <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>35 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 10. (Continued) <lb/>Species <lb/>Type locality <lb/>Primary orifice <lb/>Small avicularia <lb/>Large avicularia Ovicell <lb/>pores <lb/>Distal <lb/>margin <lb/>S Condyles L <lb/>Distolateral Proximolateral <lb/>Marginal <lb/>P. ornata (Thornely, 1912) <lb/>Mesh Skirt Bank, <lb/>Indian Ocean <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. ovilirata Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>30 or &gt; <lb/>P. papulata (Harmer, 1957) <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>smooth ? <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>? <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. paradicei (Livingstone, <lb/>1926) <lb/>Great Barrier <lb/>Reef, Australia <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>10 or &gt; <lb/>P. parsevaliformis Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>beaded 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>10 or &gt; <lb/>P. parsevalii (Audouin, 1826) Gulf of Suez, Red <lb/>Sea <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular** <lb/>? <lb/>P. parsevalioidea Liu in Liu <lb/>et al., 2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>15 or &gt; <lb/>P. parsloeparsloei Hayward &amp; <lb/>Parker, 1994 <lb/>Australia <lb/>beaded 1 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 <lb/>P. parvitatis Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. parviuncinata Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>25 or &gt; <lb/>P. pectinata Hayward &amp; <lb/>Parker, 1994 <lb/>Victoria, <lb/>Australia <lb/>beaded 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. pinctatae Liu in Liu et al., <lb/>2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. proximoproducta Moyano, <lb/>1983 <lb/>Chile <lb/>? <lb/>4 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. pugetensis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>2002 <lb/>Puget Sound, <lb/>Pacific USA <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>spatulate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>8 or &gt; <lb/>P. pyriformis Seo, 2002 <lb/>Ulsan, South <lb/>Korea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>? <lb/>P. raigiformis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2 robust/? 0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. raigii (Audouin, 1826) <lb/>Gulf of Suez, Red <lb/>Sea <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate** <lb/>-<lb/>P. raigioidea Liu in Liu et al., <lb/>2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>18 or &gt; <lb/>P. recidiva Hayward, 1988 <lb/>Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>smooth 3 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. regularis Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>2002 <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. rimula Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. rostriformis (Kirkpatrick, <lb/>1888) <lb/>Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>beaded 4 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>elongate/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. santacruzana Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 2002 <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth ? <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>sublanceolate** <lb/>7-9 <lb/>P. serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973 Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>beaded 3-<lb/>6 <lb/>robust/? 0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>noodle tongs <lb/>12 or &gt; <lb/>P. serruloides Harmelin et al., <lb/>2009 <lb/>Lebanon, <lb/>Mediterranean <lb/>Sea <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>36 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>the frontal calcification; ectooecium with 20-32 medium-sized pseudopores (0.004-0.016 mm <lb/>in diameter). <lb/>Remarks. Almeida et al. [58] redescribed P. loxoides based on specimens from Brazil. <lb/>They characterized it by having subrectangular to polygonal autozooids with large marginal <lb/>pores (Fig 14A), 1-2 oral spines (Fig 14B and 14D), narrow and short lyrula, condyles with ser-<lb/>rated margins, and large avicularia distally directed. However, all these characteristics are also <lb/>Table 10. (Continued) <lb/>Species <lb/>Type locality <lb/>Primary orifice <lb/>Small avicularia <lb/>Large avicularia Ovicell <lb/>pores <lb/>Distal <lb/>margin <lb/>S Condyles L <lb/>Distolateral Proximolateral <lb/>Marginal <lb/>P. simpulata Winston et al., <lb/>2014 <lb/>Rio de Janeiro, <lb/>Brazil <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>P. solenosmilioides Hayward <lb/>&amp; Parker, 1994 <lb/>Investigator <lb/>Strait, Australia <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/? 0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong <lb/>spatulate <lb/>15 or &gt; <lb/>P. spathulata (Smitt, 1873) <lb/>Florida, Atlantic <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>2-<lb/>4 <lb/>? <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. spiculata Gluhak et al., <lb/>2007 <lb/>Taiwan, China <lb/>Sea <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>24 <lb/>P. spondylicola Harmelin <lb/>et al., 2009 <lb/>Lebanon, <lb/>Mediterranean <lb/>Sea <lb/>smooth 1 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.75 subtriangular <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>15-20 <lb/>P. subtubulata (Harmer, <lb/>1957) <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>? <lb/>P. talismani (Calvet, 1907) <lb/>Cape Verde, <lb/>Africa <lb/>smooth 4-<lb/>5 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.75 <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>oblong/elliptic <lb/>oblong/elliptic <lb/>-<lb/>20-35 <lb/>P. tatianae Denisenko, 2015 <lb/>Chukchi Sea, <lb/>Arctic <lb/>smooth 3-<lb/>4 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. triangularis (Mawatari, <lb/>1952) <lb/>Kii Peninsula, <lb/>Japan Sea <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>? <lb/>P. trianguliforma Soule &amp; <lb/>Soule, 2002 <lb/>Gulf of <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>0.75 <lb/>-<lb/>subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. trispinosa (Johnston, 1838) Berwick Bay, Gulf <lb/>of Mexico <lb/>smoot 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>thin/ <lb/>smooth <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong/ <lb/>spatulate <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>2-4 <lb/>P. tropica (Waters, 1909) <lb/>Egypt, Red Sea <lb/>? <lb/>2 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 <lb/>P. trunculata Tilbrook, 2006 <lb/>Solomon Isl., <lb/>Oceania <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>3 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.12 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. tubula (Kirkpatrick, 1888) Mauritius, Indian <lb/>Ocean <lb/>? <lb/>6 <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>P. tubulata Osburn, 1952 <lb/>California, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate <lb/>25-30 <lb/>P. turbula Ryland &amp; Hayward, <lb/>1992 <lb/>Great Barrier <lb/>Reef, Australia <lb/>? <lb/>1 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 subtriangular <lb/>elongate <lb/>subtriangular/ <lb/>elliptic <lb/>spatulate/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>25 or &gt; <lb/>P. uncinata Soule &amp; Soule, <lb/>1973 <lb/>Hawaii, Pacific <lb/>USA <lb/>smooth 2-<lb/>3 <lb/>? <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>elongate <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>spatulate/ <lb/>elongate <lb/>? <lb/>P. variabilis Liu in Liu et al., <lb/>2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/? 0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. veniliae Winston &amp; <lb/>Jackson, 2021 <lb/>Jamaica, <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>beaded 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.33 <lb/>-<lb/>oblong <lb/>oblong/ <lb/>subtriangular <lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>22-30 <lb/>P. winstonae Liu in Liu et al., <lb/>2001 <lb/>China Sea <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.25 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>spatulate <lb/>spatulate <lb/>20 or &gt; <lb/>P. falciformis sp. nov. <lb/>Bahia, Brazil <lb/>smooth 1-<lb/>2 <lb/>robust/ <lb/>serrated <lb/>0.50 subtriangular <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>sublanceolate <lb/>20-32 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t010 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>37 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>seen in P. winstonae, first described based on specimens from China by Liu et al. [45]. More-<lb/>over, no morphometric differences were seen among specimens from Brazil and China <lb/>(Table 9) (see also Tilbrook [8, 57]. Thus, here we consider P. winstonae as the senior synonym <lb/>of P. loxoides. <lb/>Among all congeners, P. winstonae most resembles P. californica (Robertson, 1908), P. colli-<lb/>fera (Robertson, 1908) and P. regularis Soule &amp; Soule, 2002 in having three types of avicularia-<lb/>lateral, marginal, and large distally directed. However, whereas the large avicularium of P. win-<lb/>stonae is spatulate with a rounded tip, that of P. californica, P. collifera and P. regularis is sub-<lb/>triangular with an acute rostrum. <lb/>Like other species described here, P. winstonae haves an unusual geographic distribution in <lb/>the Western and Central Pacific and SW Atlantic [8, 12, 45, 57, 58]. Interestingly, Chinese and <lb/>Brazilian specimens of P. winstonae showed a common association with bivalve shells of the <lb/>genus Pinctada Ro ¨ding, 1798 [45, 58]. Colonies from Brazil studied here are also from artificial <lb/>substrata, and specimens from Malaysia studied by Taylor &amp; Tan [57] were encrusting shells <lb/>on a rope hanging from a jetty. Therefore, passive dispersal may be related to the current <lb/>distributional range of P. winstonae. <lb/>Distribution. Western and Central Pacific: China, Islands Solomon and Malaysia [8, 45, <lb/>57]; SW Atlantic: Brazil [12, 58] present study. <lb/>Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. <lb/>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:82A01897-244E-4B06-8A18-600FA9E6F9C9 <lb/>(Fig 15, Table 10) <lb/>Parasmittina munita: Almeida et al. 2015: 4 [26]. <lb/>Non Smittia trispinosa var. munita Hincks, 1884b: 284 [48]; Non Smittina trispinosa var. <lb/>munita: Marcus, 1937: 108 [23]; Non Smittina trispinosa var. munita: Marcus, 1938: 44 [34]; <lb/>Non Parasmittina munita: Vieira et al. 2008: 26 [25]. <lb/>Material examined. Holotype: UFBA 714, Camac ¸ari, Bahia, Brazil, 50 m, coll. 07/2004. <lb/>Paratypes: UFBA 314, Costa do Descobrimento, Banco Charlotte, Bahia, Brazil, 35 m coll. 03/ <lb/>1996; UFBA 953, Baı ´a de Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, coll. 27/05/1997; UFBA 948, Baı ´a de <lb/>Todos os Santos, Bahia, Brazil, coll. 29/05/1997. Additional specimens: UFBA 5000, Banco Bes-<lb/>nard, Espı ´rito Santo, Brazil, coll. 04/1996; UFPE 3100-3101, Ilhas Rasas, Guarapari, Espı ´rito <lb/>Santo, Brazil, 11-15 m, coll. 27/03/2017; UFPE 3102-3105, Ilha Escalvada, Guarapari, Espı ´rito <lb/>Santo, Brazil, 15m, coll. 29/03/2017. UFPE 2599.1, Fortaleza, Ceara, Brazil, 24-27m. Coll. <lb/>1965-1966. <lb/>Etymology. Alluding to the profile of the large avicularium, subspatulate to sublanceolate, <lb/>that leaves a falciform (hooked) outline. <lb/>Diagnosis. Parasmittina with elliptical orifice, smooth distal margin, lyrula occupying <lb/>three quarters of the orifice width, and robust downward-facing condyles with serrated mar-<lb/>gin. Secondary orifice low, forming side flaps without hiding the lyrula. Adventitious avicularia <lb/>subtriangular smaller and large subspatulate to sublanceolate, with hooked tip, placed distolat-<lb/>erally to the orifice and with rostrum oriented proximolaterally. Ovicell globose with 20-32 <lb/>medium-sized pseudopores distributed through the entire ovicell surface. <lb/>Description. Colony encrusting, uni to multilaminar. Autozooids (0.322-0.432-0.584 <lb/>mm length; n = 15; SD = 0.075 mm; 0.270-0.369-0.460 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.063 mm), <lb/>(Fig 15A and 15B) subrectangular to subquadrangular, limited by slightly raised lateral walls, <lb/>surrounded by a single row of 14-24 marginal pores (0.011-0.025-0.052 mm in diameter; <lb/>n = 30; SD = 0.010 mm). Frontal wall with several rounded nodules (Fig 15A and 15B). Pri-<lb/>mary orifice (0.062-0.081-0.0.94 mm length; n = 15; SD = 0.009 mm; 0.087-0.098-0.105 mm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>38 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>wide; n = 15; SD = 0.004), (Fig 15D) elliptical, longer than wide, distal margin smooth, 1-2 <lb/>oral spines, lyrula large (0.049-0.058-0.076 mm wide; n = 15; SD = 0.006 mm), comprising <lb/>half of the orificial width, a pair of hooked condyles with serrated margins. Secondary orifice <lb/>forming 2 proximolateral flaps resulting in a pseudosinus (Fig 15B and 15D), larger in ovi-<lb/>celled zooids (Fig 15E). Adventitious avicularia variable in shape and size (Fig 15B), with two <lb/>morphologies: (1) small to moderate in size (0.154-0.169-0.184 mm in length; n = 3; <lb/>Fig 15. Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. (A-B, D-F) UFBA 714, holotype, (C) UFBA 953, paratype, Bahia, Brazil. Arrows indicating <lb/>avicularia. (A) group of young autozooids, (B) detail of autozooid showing small and large avicularia, (C) group of autozooids showing <lb/>large avicularia, (D) detail of primary orifice, (E) group of ovicelled zooids, (F) detail of ovicells. Scale bars: A = 250 μm; B, E, <lb/>F = 200 μm; C = 500 μm; D = 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g015 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>39 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>SD = 0.014 mm; 0.052-0.064-0.078 mm in wide; n = 3; SD = 0.013 mm), subtriangular avicu-<lb/>laria (Fig 15B), with a hooked tip and large foramen, placed distolaterally to the orifice, with <lb/>rostrum oriented proximolaterally; (2) large avicularia (Fig 15B and 15C) (0.336-0.384-0.457 <lb/>mm in length; n = 9; SD = 0.039mm; 0.077-0.083-0.088 mm in wide; n = 9; SD = 0.004 mm), <lb/>reaching almost the entire zooidal length, profile subspatulate to sublanceolate, broad palate, <lb/>occupying about half rostrum, foramen elliptical, rostrum subtriangular, with smooth mar-<lb/>gins, hooked tip and crossbar complete; 3-6 pseudopores adjacent to the avicularia, placed dis-<lb/>tolaterally to the orifice with rostrum oriented proximally. Ovicells (Fig 15E and 15F) (0.156-<lb/>0.176-0.212 mm in length; n = 15; SD = 0.016mm; 0.153-0.198-0.240 mm in wide; n = 15; <lb/>SD = 0.021 mm) globose, densely surrounded by adjacent frontal wall (Fig 15F); ectooecium <lb/>with 25-30 medium-sized pseudopores (0.003-0.007-0.012 in diameter; n = 30; SD = 0.002 <lb/>mm) distributed through the entire ovicell surface. <lb/>Remarks. Specimens of P. falciformis sp. nov. were previously attributed to P. munita by <lb/>Almeida et al. [26] that is known from Australia [48]. However, it is distinguished from P. fal-<lb/>ciformis sp. nov. by the number of spines (3 in P. munita and up to 2 in P. falciformis sp. nov.) <lb/>shape of pseudosinus (deep in P. munita and shallow in P. falciformis sp. nov.) and profile of <lb/>the small adventitious avicularia (oblong in P. munita and subtriangular in P. falciformis sp. <lb/>nov.). <lb/>Other specimens of Parasmittina from Brazil were also attributed to Smittina trispinosa var. <lb/>munita [23, 33]. Although these specimens have avicularia similar to that of P. falciformis sp. <lb/>nov., differences among these taxa include the number of oral spines (3 in specimens from <lb/>Marcus and 2 in P. falciformis sp. nov.), secondary orifice (shorter in P. falciformis sp. nov.), <lb/>pseudosinus (shallower in P. falciformis), and rostrum of the small adventitious avicularia <lb/>(straight in specimens from Marcus and curved in P. falciformis sp. nov.). Moreover, speci-<lb/>mens studied by Marcus [23, 34] have also a large interzooidal avicularia, not observed in P. <lb/>falciformis sp. nov. Thus, here we consider that Smittina trispinosa var. munita described by <lb/>Marcus [23, 34] represent a distinct taxon than P. munita and P. facilformis sp. nov. <lb/>The combination of primary orifice with large lyrula, smooth distally, 1-2 oral spines, ser-<lb/>rated condyles with hooked tips, and two types of avicularia distinguishes P. falciformis sp. <lb/>nov. from all congeners. <lb/>Distribution. SW Atlantic: Brazil (present study). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Although new species of Parasmittina from SW Atlantic have been described in the last years <lb/>[10, 11, 12, 13, 59], we present the first review of historical records of the genus in the area. <lb/>Additionally, to summarize the taxonomic knowledge regarding Parasmittina species world-<lb/>wide, we compiled information on morphological features from the literature, mainly based <lb/>on the original or subsequent descriptions of type specimens. This information is provided <lb/>table with diagnostic characters of the Parasmittina species, including almost all living species. <lb/>Thirteen taxa were not included as their original descriptions lack detailed morphological <lb/>characterization and figures, type specimens were not found, and there is no characterization <lb/>based on topotype specimens-P. avicularissima Gontar, 1982; P. breli d&apos;Hondt &amp; Mascarell, <lb/>2010; P. cheilodon (MacGillivray, 1869) P. contraria Seo, 1992; P. jeffreysi (Norman, 1876); P. <lb/>geometrica (Kirkpatrick, 1890); P. japonica (Ortmann, 1890); P. loxa (Marcus, 1937); P. pro-<lb/>jecta (Okada &amp; Mawatari, 1937); P. protecta (Thornely, 1905); P. rouvillei (Calvet, 1902); P. <lb/>soulesi Scholz &amp; Cusi, 1993 and P. vacuramosa Lu, Nie &amp; Zhong in Lu, 1991. Thus, we present <lb/>diagnostic features of the primary orifice (distal margin ornamentation, number of spines, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>40 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>condyles profile and ornamentation, and lyrula and orifice width ratio), avicularia morpholo-<lb/>gies, ovicell size, and number of ovicell pores of 120 Parasmittina species (Table 10). <lb/>Features of the primary orifice provided the most reliable taxonomic characters to distin-<lb/>guish Parasmittina species, as previously pointed out to the Indo-Pacific fauna by Tilbrook <lb/>[8]. The combination of distal margin and condyle ornamentations, number and profile of <lb/>spines, and lyrula and orifice width ratio is unique to each species, including in the studied <lb/>SW Atlantic taxa (Fig 16). Generally, most Parasmittina species have a smooth distal mar-<lb/>gin, 1-4 oral spines, robust and serrated condyles, and a lyrula occupying less than half of <lb/>the orifice width. <lb/>Regarding avicularia, the small ones originated from latero-oral pores can be placed disto-<lb/>and/or proximolaterally to the orifice (Fig 17A-17D), and the small avicularia originated from <lb/>marginal pores can be placed near zooidal margins and/or proximally in o the frontal wall (Fig <lb/>17E-17H). The large avicularium originated from a latero-oral pore and is typically placed <lb/>proximolaterally to the orifice (Fig 18A-18H). <lb/>Avicularia of Parasmittina can be characterized in eight main types based on its morpholo-<lb/>gies: elongate (profile linear and narrow, with parallel margins, Fig 17A); subtriangular (profile <lb/>Fig 16. Primary orifices of the studied species. (A) P. abrolhosensis, (B) P. alba, (C) P. bimucronata, (D) P. distincta, (E) P. dubitata, (F) P. <lb/>longirostrata, (G) P. pinctatae, (H) P. egyptiaca, (I) P. serrula, (J) P. simpulata, (K) P. winstonae, (L) Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. Scale bars: 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g016 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>41 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>subtriangular, with a pointed tip, Fig 17B, 17C, 18D); oblong (profile rectangular, with <lb/>rounded margins, Fig 17D); sublanceolate (profile spear-shaped, with a slightly curved tip, Fig <lb/>17F, 18F, 18I); spatulate (profile spoon-shaped, with distal constriction, Figs 17G, 18B, 18C); <lb/>elliptical (profile oval-shaped, with no constriction, Fig 17H); noodle tong (profile broadly <lb/>spatulate, with coarsely serrated margins, Fig 17H), and hatchet-shaped (profile subtriangular, <lb/>with convex proximal margin, not seen in the studied species). <lb/>Most species of Parasmittina have one or two morphologies of small avicularia and only <lb/>one morphology of large avicularia. However, several combinations of avicularia placements <lb/>and morphologies are seen among taxa, with no apparent pattern correlating these features. <lb/>For instance, based on the morphology of the small latero-oral avicularia, most Parasmittina <lb/>species can be assigned in two groups-with oblong and/or subtriangular avicularia (as P. <lb/>bimucronata, P. egyptiaca and P. simpulata) or with elongate avicularia (as P. abrolhosensis, P. <lb/>areolata and P. spathulata). Only P. longirostrata and P. nasuta have small latero-oral avicu-<lb/>laria oblong and/or elongate among all species. Also, the small elongate avicularia are always <lb/>placed proximolaterally to the orifice, and most taxa with these avicularia lack a distolateral <lb/>avicularium. <lb/>Interestingly, some nominal species can only be distinguished from congeners by characters <lb/>that are known to differ pending on habitat and colonial development (i.e., [2, 4, 5, 21]), <lb/>mainly the number of oral spines or absence of avicularia-(P. alba, P. betamorphaea and P. <lb/>lavela), (P. areolata and P. trunculata), (P. amazonensis, P. fraseri, P. indiginella and P. talis-<lb/>mani), (P. barbadensis, P. parsevaliformis and P. simpulata), (P. longirostrata and P. serru-<lb/>loides), (P. serrula and P. luteoserrula). Thus, these little differences among taxa may represent <lb/>intraspecific variations rather than different species. Currently, there are no integrative studies <lb/>(combining morphology and moleculear analysis) to investigate species delimitation within <lb/>the genus Parasmittina. Therefore, further studies including more colonies and other biologi-<lb/>cal data, particularly molecular analysis, are needed to help clarify its taxonomic identity. <lb/>Fig 17. Small avicularia of the studied species. (A-D) latero-oral avicularia, (E-H) marginal/frontal avicularia. (A) elongate as in P. <lb/>areolata, (B) subtriangular bulbous as in P. abrolhosensis, (C) subtriangular as in P. simpulata, (D) oblong as in P. simpulata, (E) <lb/>subtriangular as in P. abrolhosensis, (F) sublanceolate as in P. pinctatae, (G) spatulate as in P. winstonae, (H) elliptical as in P. <lb/>abrolhosensis. Scale bars: 50 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g017 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>42 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Thus, to prevent to erect of new names and new synonymies based on characters that can be <lb/>considered as intraspecific variations, here we choose to discuss and indicate the probable <lb/>occurrence of species complex in Parasmittina, attributing the most appropriate available <lb/>name to the studied SW Atlantic specimens and attempting to maintain some taxonomic <lb/>Fig 18. Large avicularia of the studies species. (A) spatulate of P. abrolhosensis, (B) spatulate of P. winstonae, (C) spatulate of P. <lb/>simpulata, (D) subtriangular of P. dubitada, (E) subtriangular of P. egyptiaca, (F) sublanceolate of P. bimucronata, (G) sublanceolate of <lb/>P. longirostrata, (H) noodle tong of P. serrula, (I) sublanceolate of Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. Scale bars: 100 μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g018 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>43 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>stability in the genus. Analysis including colonies in different astogenetic stages, added with a <lb/>precise characterization of the primary orifice, avicularia, and ovicells, are strongly required <lb/>for a reliable taxonomic assignment (i.e., [2, 4, 5, 9, 17, 21, 38]). <lb/>Fig 19. Distribution of Parasmittina species studied along the Southwestern Atlantic Ocean. Symbols: black circle, <lb/>P. abrolhosensis Ramalho et al., 2018; white circle, P. alba Ramalho, Muricy &amp; Taylor, 2011 [14]; white square, P. <lb/>bimucronata (Hincks, 1884b); black square, P. dubitata Hayward, 1980; black triangle, P. ligulata comb. nov. (Ridley, <lb/>1881); white triangle, P. longirostrata Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001; black lozenge, P. pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, <lb/>2001; white lozenge, P. serrula Soule &amp; Soule, 1973; black star, P. simpulata Winston, Vieira &amp; Woollacott, 2014; grey <lb/>circle, P. winstonae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001; grey triangle, Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g019 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>44 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Among the eleven species of Parasmittina reported so far from the SW Atlantic, four spe-<lb/>cies-P. betamorphaea, P. munita, P. spathulata and P. trispinosa-were not recognized in this <lb/>study (Fig 19). <lb/>Reports of P. betamorphaea [25], as well as reports of Luederwaldt [53] and Marcus [23] of <lb/>P. trispinosa, are here assigned to P. pinctatae. Part of the records of P. munita [26] are <lb/>assigned to P. falciformis sp. nov., and other records still need review [23, 34] (Fig 20). Finally, <lb/>reports of P. spathulata comprise at least two taxa, including P. abrolhosensis [25, 26, 34] and <lb/>P. simpulata [26]. <lb/>Among species here recognized to occur in Brazil, five were originally described based on <lb/>specimens from the area (P. abrolhosensis, P. alba, P. ligulata comb. nov., P. simpulata and P. <lb/>falciformis sp. nov.). As mentioned previously, P. alba and P. simpulata are part of species <lb/>complexes that need further investigation. The remaining species described here are mainly <lb/>known from the Pacific. Due to the unexpected natural occurrence of P. bimucronata, P. long-<lb/>irostrata, P. pinctatae, P. serrula and P. winstonae in the SW Atlantic, we evaluated the exotic <lb/>status of these species in the area (acc. [31]) (Table 11). <lb/>Fig 20. Parasmittina. species from Brazil studied by Marcus (1937, 1938, 1939). (A) Smittina trispinosa, Marcus, E. det. <lb/>(1937), (B) Smittina trispinosa var. munita, Marcus, E. det. (1937) = P. bimucronata (Hincks, 1884b), (C) Smittina trispinosa <lb/>var. nitida, Marcus, E. det. (1937) = P. pinctatae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001, (D) Smittina trispinosa var. munita Marcus, E. <lb/>det. (1937) = P. sp., (E) Smittina trispinosa var. loxa Marcus, E. det. (1939) = P. winstonae Liu in Liu, Yin &amp; Ma, 2001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.g020 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>45 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<body>One species was assigned as to be exotic (P. longirostrata), and the others were considered <lb/>cryptogenic, including some (P. bimucronata, P. pinctatae and P. winstonae) previously misas-<lb/>signed to distinct species [10, 11, 12, 26, 53, 58, 60, 61]. These species are widespread along the <lb/>Brazilian coast, growing on artificial and natural surfaces, indicating that these taxa are well-<lb/>established in the studied area. Cryptogenic bryozoans must be treated as a cause of concern <lb/>since, as exotic taxa, they can grow into dense colonies that can influence the associated and <lb/>native fauna and have economic effects on human activities, including beaches usage, aquacul-<lb/>ture, shipping, and fishing (acc. [15, 31, 62]). Thus, more studies with the species complexes <lb/>recognized here are suggested to determine these taxa origin and help prevent bioinvasion <lb/>events along the SW Atlantic. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We are grateful to Centro de Pesquisa Gonc ¸alo Moniz (FIOCRUZ/BA); Marcelo Fukuda from <lb/>the Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo (MZUSP); JoAnn Sanner from the <lb/>Smithsonian Institution&apos;s National Museum of Natural History (USNM); Mary Spencer-Jones <lb/>from the Natural History Museum, London (NHMUK); Bjo ¨rn Berning, Joachin Scholz, Ju ¨rgen <lb/>Kaselowsky and Carsten Lu ¨ter from the Museum fu ¨r Naturkunde, Berlin (MFN), for provid-<lb/>ing SEM images. We also thank Programa de Po ´s-Graduac ¸ão em Biologia Animal of the Uni-<lb/>versidade Federal de Pernambuco (PPGBA/UFPE) for logistical support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira. <lb/>Data curation: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Formal analysis: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Investigation: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Methodology: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/></div>

			<body>Table 11. Correspondence of criteria to classify Parasmittina species as exotic in the SW Atlantic (acc. Chapman &amp; Carlton, 19991, 1994; Miranda et al. 2008; Xavier <lb/>et al. 2021), with the respective number of positive/negative criteria used. 0, criterion not applicable due to lacking data; +, criterion applied positively to exotic status; <lb/>-, criterion applied negatively to exotic status. N = number of attributes applied positively/negatively. Local criteria: 1 = local appearance where not found previously, <lb/>2 = local dispersal after introduction, 3 = association with human mechanisms of dispersal, 4 = prevalence or restriction to new or artificial environment, 5 = restricted dis-<lb/>tribution when compared to ecologically similar native species. Global criteria: 6 = widespread geographic distribution with isolated populations, 7 = active and passive dis-<lb/>persal mechanisms incapable of achieving the current distribution, 8 = exotic evolutionary origin. Status: E = exotic, C = cryptogenic. <lb/>Species <lb/>Local criteria <lb/>Global criteria <lb/>N <lb/>Status <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>P. bimucronata <lb/>-<lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>3/2 <lb/>C <lb/>P. longirostrata <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>6/0 <lb/>E <lb/>P. pinctatae <lb/>-<lb/>0 <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>3/3 <lb/>C <lb/>P. serrula <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>5/0 <lb/>C <lb/>P. winstonae <lb/>-<lb/>0 <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>3/3 <lb/>C <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347.t011 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>46 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Project administration: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Resources: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Software: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Supervision: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Validation: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Visualization: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Jamile Farias, Leandro M. Vieira, Ana C. S. Almeida. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bock P. World List of Bryozoa. Smittinidae Levinsen, 1909. Accessed through: World Register of Marine <lb/>Species at: https://www.marinespecies.org/aphia.php?p=taxdetails&amp;id=110775https://www. <lb/>marinespecies.org/aphia.php?p=taxdetails&amp;id=110775 in 2024-02-01. <lb/>2. Soule DF, Soule JD. Morphology and speciation of Hawaiian and eastern Pacific Smittinidae (Bryozoa, <lb/>Ectoprocta). Bull Am Mus Nat Hist. 1973; 152(6): 365-440. <lb/>3. Winston JE. An annotated check-list of coral-associated bryozoans. Am Mus Novit. 1986; 2859: 1-39. <lb/>4. Farias J, Souza FBC, Vieira LM, Almeida ACS. On some Smittinidae (Bryozoa, Cheilostomata) from <lb/>Bahia, northeastern Brazil, with the description of a new species. Mar Biodivers. 2020; 50(5) 1-17. <lb/>5. Soule DF, Soule JD. The Eastern Pacific Parasmittina trispinosa Complex (Bryozoa, Cheilostomatida): <lb/>New and Previously Described Species. Irene McCulloch Foundation Monograph series. 2002; 5: 1-<lb/>40. <lb/>6. Denisenko NV. New species of the genus Parasmittina (Bryozoa: Cheilostomata: Smittinidae) from the <lb/>Chukchi Sea. Zoosyst Ross. 2015; 24(2): 300-306. <lb/>7. Winston JE. Redescription and revision of Smitt&apos;s &quot;Floridan Bryozoa&apos; in the Collection of the Museum of <lb/>Comparative Zoology, Harvard University. Virginia Mus Nat Hist Mem. 2005; 7: 1-150. <lb/>8. Tilbrook KJ. Cheilostomatous Bryozoa from the Solomon Islands. Santa Barbara Museum of Natural <lb/>History Monographs 4 (Studies in Biodiversity Number 3). 2006; 1-386. <lb/>9. Harmelin J-G, Bitar G, Zibrowius H. Smittinidae (Bryozoa, Cheilostomata) from coastal habitats of Leb-<lb/>anon (Mediterranean Sea), including new and non-indigenous species. Zoosystema. 2009; 31(1): <lb/>163-187. <lb/>10. Ramalho L V, Muricy G, Taylor PD. Taxonomic revision of some lepraliomorph cheilostome bryozoans <lb/>(Bryozoa: Lepraliomorpha) from Rio de Janeiro State, Brazil. J Nat Hist. 2011; 45(13-14): 767-798. <lb/>11. Ramalho LV, Taylor PD, Moraes FC, Moura R, Amado-Filho GM, Bastos AC. Bryozoan framework <lb/>composition in the oddly shaped reefs from Abrolhos Bank, Brazil, southwestern Atlantic: taxonomy <lb/>and ecology. Zootaxa. 2018; 4483(1): 155-186. https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4483.1.6 PMID: <lb/>30313802 <lb/>12. Winston JE, Vieira LM, Woollacott RM. Scientific results of the Hassler expedition. Bryozoa. No. 2. Bra-<lb/>zil. Bull Mus Comp Zool. 2014; 161: 139-239. <lb/>13. Winston JE, Jackson JBC. Coral reef-associated bryozoans of Jamaica. Zootaxa. 2021; 4988 (1): 1-<lb/>281. https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4988.1.1 PMID: 34186778 <lb/>14. Almeida ACS, Souza FBC, Vieira LM. Malacostegine bryozoans (Bryozoa: Cheilostomata) from Bahia <lb/>State, northeast Brazil: taxonomy and non-indigenous species. Mar Biodiv. 2017; 1-26. <lb/>15. Miranda A, Almeida ACS, Vieira LM. Non-native marine bryozoans (Bryozoa: Gymnolaemata) in Brazil-<lb/>ian waters: Assessment, dispersal and impacts. Mar Pollut Bull. 2018; 130: 184-191. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.marpolbul.2018.03.023 PMID: 29866545 <lb/>16. Dick MH, Grichensko AV. Rocky-intertidal cheilostome bryozoans from the vicinity of the Sesoko Bio-<lb/>logical Station, west-central Okinawa, Japan. J Nat Hist. 2017; 51: 3-4. <lb/>17. Souto J, Ramalhosa P, Canning-Clode, J. Three non-indigenous species from Madeira harbors, <lb/>including a new species of Parasmittina (Bryozoa). Mar Biodiv. 2016; 1-10. <lb/>18. Baradari H, Nasrolahi A, Taylor PD. Cheilostome Bryozoa of the northern Persian Gulf, Iran. Zootaxa. <lb/>2019; 4619 (3): 459-486. https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4619.3.3 PMID: 31716289 <lb/>19. Hayward PJ. Mauritian Cheilostome Bryozoa. J Zoo London. 1988; 215: 269-356. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>47 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>20. Moyano HI. Magellanic Bryozoa: some egical and zoogeographical aspects. Marine Biology. 1982; 67: <lb/>81-96. <lb/>21. Gordon DP. The marine fauna of New Zealand: Bryozoa: Gymnolaemata from the Kermadec Ridge. <lb/>New Zealand Oceanographic Institute Memoir. 1984; 91, 1-198. <lb/>22. Vieira LM, Almeida ACS 2024. Smittinidae in Cata ´logo Taxono ˆmico da Fauna do Brasil. PNUD. Avail-<lb/>able: http://fauna.jbrj.gov.br/fauna/faunadobrasil/157991. Accessed 2024: 01 feb 2. <lb/>23. Marcus E. Bryozoarios marinhos brasileiros I. Bol Fac Fil Ci Letras Univ São Paulo. 1937 1: 5-224 <lb/>24. Osburn RC. Bryozoa of the Pacific coast of America, Part 2. Cheilostomata, Ascophora. R Allan Han-<lb/>cock Pac Exp. 1952; 14: 271-611. <lb/>25. Vieira LM, Migotto AE, Winston JE. Synopsis and annotated checklist of recent marine Bryozoa from <lb/>Brazil. Zootaxa. 2008; 1810: 1-39. <lb/>26. Almeida ACS, Alves O, Peso-Aguiar M, Dominguez J, Souza FBC. Gymnolaemata bryozoans of Bahia <lb/>State, Brazil. Mar Biodiv Records. 2015; 8(120): 1-7. <lb/>27. Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, et al. A. Fiji: an open-source <lb/>platform for biological-image analysis. Nat. Methods. 2012; 9, 676-682. <lb/>28. Martha SO, Vieira LM, Souto JD, Grischenko AV, Gordon DP, Ostrovsky AN. Gymnolaemata, Cheilos-<lb/>tomata. In: Schwaha T, editor. Phylum Bryozoa. Berlin: de Gruyter. 2020; 317-423. <lb/>29. Chapman JW, Carlton JT. A test of criteria for introduced species: the global invasion by the isopod <lb/>Synidotea laevidorsalis (Miers, 1881). J. Crustac. Biol. 1991; 11 (3), 386-400. <lb/>30. Chapman JW, Carlton JT. Predicted discoveries of the introduced isopod Synidotea laevidorsalis <lb/>(Miers, 1881). J. Crustac. Biol. 1994; 14 (4), 700-71. <lb/>31. Xavier EA, Almeida ACS, Vieira LM. The role of artificial habitats on fouling bryozoan fauna in the south-<lb/>western Atlantic. Mar. Pollut. Bull.2021; 167, 112310. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2021.112310 <lb/>PMID: 33831702 <lb/>32. Hayward PJ, Ryland JS. British Ascophoran Bryozoans. In: Kermack DM, Barnes RSK. Synopses of <lb/>the British Fauna 14). London: Academic Press for the Linnaean Society. 1979; 1-312. <lb/>33. Winston JE, Hayward PJ. The Marine Bryozoans of the Northeast Coast of the United States: Maine to <lb/>Virginia. Virginia Museum of Natural History Memoir. 2012, 11: i-xii, 1-180. <lb/>34. Marcus E. Bryozoarios marinhos brasileiros II. Bol Fac Fil Ci Letras Univ São Paulo. 1938; 2: 1-137. <lb/>35. Canu F, Bassler RS. Fossil and Recent Bryozoa of the Gulf of Mexico region. Proceedings of the U.S. <lb/>national museum. 1928; 72: 1-199. <lb/>36. Harmer SF. The Polyzoa of the Siboga Expedition, Part 4. Cheilostomata Ascophora II. Siboga Expedi-<lb/>tion Reports. 1957; 28d: 641-1147. <lb/>37. Winston JE. Shallow-water Bryozoans of Carrie Bow Cay, Belize. Am Mus Novit. 1984; 2799: 1-38. <lb/>38. Winston JE, Woollacott RM. Scientific results of the Hassler Expedition. Bryozoa. No. 1. Barbados. Bull <lb/>Mus Comp Zoo1. 2009; 59: 239-300. <lb/>39. Pouyet S, Herrera-Anduaga Y. Systematics and palaeogeographical studies of some species of Bryo-<lb/>zoa (Cheilostomata) from the Gulf of Mexico. Universidad Nacional Auto ´noma de Me ´xico, Inst Geolo-<lb/>gia. 1986; 6: 204-221. <lb/>40. Canu F, Bassler RS. Bryozoaires du Bre ´sil. Bulletin de la Socie ´te ´des Sciences de Seine-et-Oise. <lb/>1928; 9: 58-110. <lb/>41. Canu F, Bassler RS. Bryozoaires des iles Hawaï. Bulletin de la Socie ´te ´des Sciences de Seine-et-<lb/>Oise. 1927; 8: 1-67. <lb/>42. Smitt FA. Floridan Bryozoa collected by Count L.F. de Pourtalès, Part 2. Kongliga Svenska Vetens-<lb/>kaps-Akademiens Handlingar. 1873; 11: 1-83. <lb/>43. Thornely LR. Report on the Polyzoa collected by Professor Herdmann, at Ceylon, in 1902. Report to the <lb/>Government of Ceylon on the Pearl Oyster Fisheries of the Gulf of Manar. 1905; 4: 107-130. <lb/>44. Hincks T. Contributions towards a General History of the Marine Polyzoa. XII. Polyzoa from India (coast <lb/>of Burmah). Ann and Mag Nat Hist. 1884a; 5(13): 356-362. <lb/>45. Liu X, Yin X, Ma J. Biology of Marine-Fouling Bryozoans in the Coastal Waters of China. Science <lb/>Press, Beijing. 2001; 1-860. <lb/>46. Thornely LR. Marine Polyzoa of the Indian Ocean. Trans Linn Soc London. 1912; 15: 137-157. <lb/>47. Hayward PJ, Parker SA. Notes on some species of Parasmittina Osburn, 1952 (Bryozoa: Cheilostoma-<lb/>tida). Zool J Linn Soc. 1994; 110: 53-75. <lb/>48. Hincks T. Contributions towards a General History of the Marine Polyzoa. XIII. Polyzoa from Victoria <lb/>and Western Australia. Ann and Mag Nat Hist. 1884b; 5(13): 363-369. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>48 / 49 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>49. Hayward PJ. Cheilostomata (Bryozoa) from the South Atlantic. J Nat Hist. 1980; 14: 701-722. <lb/>50. Ridley S O. Polyzoa, in Account of the zoological collections made during the survey of H.M. &quot;Alert&quot; in <lb/>the Straits of Magellan and on the coast of Patagonia. Proc Zool Soc Lond. 1881; 1881: 44-61. <lb/>51. Verrill AE. Brief contributions to zoology from the Museum of Yale College. No.33. Results of dredging <lb/>expeditions off the New England coast in 1874. Am J Sci Arts. 1875; 10: 36-44. <lb/>52. Waters AW. Reports on the Marine Biology of the Sudanese Red Sea. . . 12. The Bryozoa, Part 1, Chei-<lb/>lostomata. Journ Linn Soc Zool London. 1909; 31: 123-181. <lb/>53. Luederwaldt H. Resultados de uma excursão cientı ´fica à Ilha de São Sebastião no litoral do Estado de <lb/>São Paulo em 1925. Rev Mus Paul. 1929; 16: 1-79. <lb/>54. Orr RJS, Di Martino E, Ramsfjell M, Gordon DP, Berning B, Chowdhury I, et al. Paleozoic origins of <lb/>cheilostome bryozoans and their parental care inferred by a new genome-skimmed phylogeny. Science <lb/>Advances. 2022; 8 (13) eabm7452:1-11. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abm7452 PMID: 35353568 <lb/>55. Maturo FJS, Schopf TJM. Ectoproct and entoproct type material: re-examination of species from Ber-<lb/>muda and New England collected by A.E. Verrill, J.W. Dawson and E. Desor. Postilla. 1968; 120: 1-95. <lb/>56. Harmelin JG, Bitar G, Zibrowius H. High xenodiversity versus low native diversity in the south-eastern <lb/>Mediterranean: bryozoans from the coastal zone of Lebanon. Mediterranean Mar Sci. 2016; 17, 417-<lb/>439. <lb/>57. Taylor PD, Tan, SHA. Cheilostome Bryozoa from Penang and Langkawi, Malaysia. European Journal <lb/>of Taxonomy. 2015; 149: 1-34. <lb/>58. Almeida ACS, Souza FBC, Farias J, Alves OFS, Vieira LM. Bryozoa on disarticulated bivalve shells <lb/>from Todos os Santos Bay, northeastern Brazil, with the description of two new species. Zootaxa. 2018; <lb/>4434 (3): 401-428. https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4434.3.1 PMID: 30313171 <lb/>59. Ramalho LV, Moraes FC, Salgado, LT, Bastos, AC, Moura, RM. Bryozoa from the reefs off the Amazon <lb/>River mouth: checklist, thirteen new species, and notes on their ecology and distribution. Zootaxa. <lb/>2021; 4950 (1). <lb/>60. Johnston G. A history of British Zoophytes. W.H. Lizars, Edinburgh, London &amp; Dublin. 1838; 1-341. <lb/>61. Marcus E. Bryozoarios marinhos brasileiros III. Bol Fac Fil Ci Letras Univ São Paulo. 1939; 3: 111-<lb/>353. <lb/>62. Nascimento KB, Migotto AE, Vaga CF, Vieira LM. Occurrence of the bryozoan Amathia alternata <lb/>Lamouroux, 1816 in the SW Atlantic: a new invasive species with potential impact on human livelihoods. <lb/>Mar Biodivers. 2022; 52:19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Diversity of Parasmittina (Bryozoa) from the SW Atlantic <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>49 / 49 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>