<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T10:19:35.040Z">11/14/2025 10:19:35 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T10:19:19.273664Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T10:19:19.273664Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>A new oviraptorosaur (Dinosauria: <lb/>Theropoda) from the end-Maastrichtian Hell <lb/>Creek Formation of North America <lb/>Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, D. Jade Simon 2 , Holly N. Woodward 1 , Gregory <lb/>F. FunstonID 3 *, Eric SnivelyID 1 * <lb/>1 Oklahoma State University, Tahlequah, OK, United States of America, 2 Department of Ecology and <lb/>Evolutionary Biology, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 3 Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto, <lb/>Ontario, Canada <lb/>* kyle.l.atkins-weltman@okstate.edu (KLA-W); Greg.Funston@rom.on.ca (GFF); eric.snively@okstate.edu <lb/>(ES) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Caenagnathidae is a clade of derived, Late Cretaceous oviraptorosaurian theropods from <lb/>Asia and North America. Because their remains are rare and often fragmentary, caenag-<lb/>nathid diversity is poorly understood. Anzu wyliei is the only caenagnathid species currently <lb/>described from the late Maastrichtian Hell Creek Formation of the USA and is also among <lb/>the largest and most completely preserved North American caenagnathids. Smaller, less <lb/>complete caenagnathid material has long been known from the Hell Creek Formation, but it <lb/>is unclear whether these are juvenile representatives of Anzu or if they represent distinct, <lb/>unnamed taxa. Here, we describe a relatively small caenagnathid hindlimb from the Hell <lb/>Creek Formation, and conduct osteohistological analysis to assess its maturity. Histological <lb/>data and morphological differences from Anzu wyliei and other caenagnathids allow us to <lb/>conclude that this specimen represents a new species of caenagnathid from the Hell Creek <lb/>Formation, with a smaller adult body size than Anzu. This new taxon is also distinct from <lb/>other small caenagnathid material previously described from the area, potentially indicating <lb/>the coexistence of three distinct caenagnathid species in the Hell Creek Formation. These <lb/>results show that caenagnathid diversity in the Hell Creek ecosystem has been <lb/>underestimated. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Oviraptorosauria was a clade of maniraptoran theropods characterized by a foreshortened ros-<lb/>trum, often bearing an edentulous beak, and highly pneumatic skeletons, a combination that <lb/>easily distinguishes them from other theropod groups [1]. Oviraptorosaurs are known from <lb/>well-preserved fossils, primarily from Asia, that have yielded insight into the biology, morphol-<lb/>ogy, diversity, and evolutionary history of this peculiar group of theropods [1-19]. The earliest <lb/>certain oviraptorosaurs are known from the Barremian stage of the Early Cretaceous, between <lb/>125-129 million years ago [20,21], although links have recently been drawn with the unusual <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/>1 / 27 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Atkins-Weltman KL, Simon DJ, <lb/>Woodward HN, Funston GF, Snively E (2024) A <lb/>new oviraptorosaur (Dinosauria: Theropoda) from <lb/>the end-Maastrichtian Hell Creek Formation of <lb/>North America. PLoS ONE 19(1): e0294901. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 <lb/>Editor: Max Cardoso Langer, Universidade de Sao <lb/>Paulo, BRAZIL <lb/>Received: July 5, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: November 8, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 24, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Atkins-Weltman et al. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All available locality <lb/>data is reposited at Carnegie Museum of Natural <lb/>History and is available upon request by contacting <lb/>Amy Henrici at henricia@carnegiemnh.org. All <lb/>character and phylogenetic data are included within <lb/>the Supplementary Files. <lb/>Funding: Funding for histology processing <lb/>provided to HNW by Oklahoma State University for <lb/>Health Sciences. Funding to GFF provided by the <lb/>Royal Society (Grant NIF\R1\191527) and a <lb/>Banting Fellowship (NSERC). The funders had no <lb/></front>

	<body>scansoriopterygids [13] and Ornitholestes [13], potentially reconciling a gap that extends into <lb/>the Jurassic between their presumed divergence from other coelurosaurs and their earliest <lb/>appearances. The Late Cretaceous record of oviraptorosaurs is excellent, and it is clear that <lb/>they persisted until the K-Pg extinction event in Laurasia [12]. <lb/>Oviraptorosaurs ranged from chicken-or turkey-sized [3,4], to species which likely weighed <lb/>more than a tonne [5]. Based on their cranial morphology, this diverse clade contained both <lb/>omnivorous and herbivorous members [12,21-23]. Although the earliest members of this <lb/>group retained teeth [3], they were entirely lost in Late Cretaceous forms. Well-preserved fos-<lb/>sils preserve the feathery integument [3,6-8], quill knobs on the ulna [9], and specialized verte-<lb/>brae that form a pygostyle structure [10-14], showing that oviraptorosaurs had complex, <lb/>feathery integument. Other exquisite specimens have shown that these dinosaurs were social <lb/>[2,24,25], actively brooded over their nests [15,19,26-31], employed a reproductive strategy <lb/>intermediate between those used by crocodilians and extant birds [32], and had avian-like <lb/>brain organization [33,34] (see [20] for a more detailed examination of this topic). <lb/>The excellent oviraptorosaur record is overwhelmingly known from the Late Cretaceous of <lb/>Asia, and thus the true diversity across their entire range is incomplete. Throughout the past <lb/>two decades, multiple new species have been discovered in North America, leading to a better <lb/>understanding of their morphology and interrelationships [12,35-42]. All North American <lb/>oviraptorosaurs fall within the monophyletic family Caenagnathidae [8,12,35,38,42-45], which <lb/>was also present but less diverse in Asia [5,39] during the Late Cretaceous. Caenagnathids can <lb/>be easily characterized by their slender manus, gracile, long hindlimbs, and distinctive mandi-<lb/>bles with complexly-textured edentulous beaks in place of the toothed jaws seen in other thero-<lb/>pods [35,40]. North American caenagnathid fossils are often found as isolated elements or are <lb/>poorly preserved, and thus they have historically been misidentified as members of other <lb/>clades [46], or subject to taxonomic issues where isolated specimens cannot be associated due <lb/>to a lack of overlapping material [see [41] for a review]. However, a number of discoveries <lb/>have led to an improved resolution of caenagnathid relationships and their links to other <lb/>members of Oviraptorosauria [12,35-37,45,47]. <lb/>Nevertheless, our understanding of caenagnathid diversity remains plagued by the relative <lb/>incompleteness of most specimens, with most taxa known from very sparse material <lb/>[35,37,41,43-45]. Thus, caenagnathid taxonomy and variation is debated and unstable. Two <lb/>major advances in recent years have improved the situation. The first was the discoveries of <lb/>three exceptionally complete caenagnathid skeletons and their description as Anzu wyliei [12], <lb/>which remains one of the most completely known caenagnathids. This discovery drastically <lb/>improved the phylogenetic representation of caenagnathids, and helped clarify different <lb/>aspects of caenagnathid evolution [41,47-49]. Anzu wyliei specimens further elucidated the <lb/>unusual skulls and skeletal proportions of caenagnathids, and expanded the skeletal represen-<lb/>tation of large-bodied North American caenagnathids, which had previously only been repre-<lb/>sented by eggshell [50]. The second major advance is the leverage of histological data by <lb/>multiple research groups, to assess the relative maturity of specimens, so that ontogeny can be <lb/>addressed in taxonomic hypotheses [51,52]. Together, these two advances have resulted in <lb/>improved taxonomic frameworks with falsifiable hypotheses and provide a robust strategy for <lb/>unravelling the broader diversity of caenagnathids. <lb/>However, some discrepancies in caenagnathid diversity remain. Differences in species rich-<lb/>ness between Asia and North America were recently addressed [53], but differences within <lb/>North American ecosystems are less clear [41,44]. Whereas caenagnathids were highly diverse <lb/>in the Campanian [37,41,45,47], they appear to be less diverse in the Maastrichtian, with Anzu <lb/>wyliei as the only named taxon [12]. Nonetheless, some small caenagnathid material from the <lb/>Hell Creek Formation exists, and has previously been referred to what is now Citipes elegans <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<front>role in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>(= Elmisaurus elegans) [32,34,38,42], although this has not been reevaluated since that species <lb/>was transferred to a new genus. Currently unpublished descriptive and histological work [52] <lb/>suggests that multiple taxa may exist in the Hell Creek Formation, but the ontogenetic status <lb/>of the smaller material is unknown, and the caenagnathid diversity of this formation requires <lb/>reevaluation. <lb/>Here we describe the morphology and osteohistology of a new, partial caenagnathid hin-<lb/>dlimb intermediate in size between known specimens from the Hell Creek Formation. Build-<lb/>ing on recent work [46,51,52], we anticipated that this specimen might provide an opportunity <lb/>to assess growth across ontogeny in Anzu wyliei. Surprisingly, our morphological and histolog-<lb/>ical results indicate that the specimen does not represent a juvenile Anzu wyliei, but a morpho-<lb/>logically-distinct adult individual approaching asymptotic body size, representing a new <lb/>taxon. This prompted a reevaluation of the diversity of caenagnathids in the Hell Creek For-<lb/>mation, which has ramifications for the diversity of oviraptorosaurs prior to the end-Creta-<lb/>ceous extinction. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>CM 96523 comprises a partial right hindlimb including femur, tibia, astragalocalcaneum, and <lb/>metatarsals III and IV. All bones were prepared prior to acquisition. The femur was received <lb/>with the femoral head attached incorrectly, and this error was rectified by preparators at the <lb/>Carnegie Museum of Natural History (CM), Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of Amer-<lb/>ica. Likewise, some remaining matrix was removed from the tibia. The femur and tibia were <lb/>measured using ImageJ, while the metatarsals were measured using a flexible tape measure <lb/>(Table 1). Measurements were taken from the proximal end to the distal end of the element, to <lb/>the nearest millimeter. Other measurements such as proximodistal width at the proximal and <lb/>distal ends were taken digitally using prepared figures (specifically Fig 1A and 1B in case of the <lb/>femur) and ImageJ. The cnemial crest of the tibia was distorted, and a tibia proximal width <lb/>measurement would be unreliable and thus was not taken. <lb/>Paleontological ethics statements <lb/>CM 96523 is permanently reposited in the collections of the Section of Vertebrate Paleontol-<lb/>ogy at CM, where the locality information for this specimen is on file. No permits were <lb/>required for the described study, which complied with all relevant regulations. All specimens <lb/>were collected from privately-owned land in the United States of America with the written <lb/>consent of the respective landowners and were purchased by the primary author for donation <lb/>to the Carnegie Museum. <lb/></body>

	<front>Institutional abbreviations <lb/>BHM, Black Hills Institute of Geological Research, Hill City, South Dakota, United States of <lb/>America; CM, Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States <lb/>of America; FMNH, Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois, United States of <lb/>America; MPC, Mongolian Paleontological Center, Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia; MRF, Marmarth <lb/>Research Foundation, Marmarth, North Dakota, United States of America; OMNH, Sam <lb/>Noble Oklahoma Museum of Natural History, Norman, Oklahoma, United States of America; <lb/>ROM, Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; TMP, Royal Tyrrell Museum of <lb/>Palaeontology, Drumheller, Alberta, Canada; UALVP, University of Alberta Laboratory for <lb/>Vertebrate Palaeontology, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada. <lb/></front>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Nomenclatural acts <lb/>The electronic edition of this article conforms to the requirements of the amended Interna-<lb/>tional Code of Zoological Nomenclature, and hence the new names contained herein are avail-<lb/>able under that Code from the electronic edition of this article. This published work and the <lb/>nomenclatural acts it contains have been registered in ZooBank, the online registration system <lb/>for the ICZN. The ZooBank LSIDs (Life Science Identifiers) can be resolved and the associated <lb/>information viewed through any standard web browser by appending the LSID to the prefix <lb/>&quot;http://zoobank.org/&quot;. The LSID for this publication is: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: XXXXXXX. <lb/>The electronic edition of this work was published in a journal with an ISSN, and has been <lb/>Table 1. Measured length of preserved elements of Eoneophron infernalis. All measurements are in mm. <lb/>Bone <lb/>Femur <lb/>Tibia +Astragalocalcaneum <lb/>Mt III <lb/>Mt IV <lb/>Length <lb/>390 <lb/>499 <lb/>247 <lb/>233 <lb/>Circumference [est] <lb/>105.8 <lb/>106.8 <lb/>-<lb/>64.2 <lb/>Proximal width <lb/>100 <lb/>-<lb/>15 <lb/>21 <lb/>Distal width <lb/>78 <lb/>70 <lb/>21 <lb/>15 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.t001 <lb/>Fig 1. Left femur of CM 96523. A) Anterior view, showing connections between the three fragments as presently preserved. The distal two fragments were initially united <lb/>before palaeohistological sampling. B) interpretive illustration of femur; C) lateral view, D) posterior view, E) medial view, F) proximal view, and G) distal view. <lb/>Abbreviations: af, adductor fossa; at, anterior trochanter; atr, accessory trochanteric ridge; ctf, crista tibiofibularis; ect, ectocondylar tuber; fc, fovea capitis, gt, greater <lb/>trochanter; mc, medial condyle; pf, popliteal fossa; tc, tibial condyle. Scale bar = 2 cm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>archived and is available from the following digital repositories: LOCKSS [author to insert any <lb/>additional repositories]. <lb/>Histological sectioning <lb/>The region containing the minimum circumference within the mid-diaphyses of the femur, <lb/>tibia, and metatarsal IV were selected for removal and thin section processing, following pro-<lb/>cedures outlined in [54]. Lines of minimum circumference were marked with red wax pencil. <lb/>Prior to sample removal, each bone was photographed in anterior, posterior, lateral, and <lb/>medial orientations; bone shape was outlined on paper; and each bone was 3D laser scanned <lb/>using a NextEngine Ultra HD scanner. Finally, plaster cradles were made for each specimen. <lb/>Transverse samples that included the minimum diaphysis circumference were removed <lb/>using a wet tile saw fitted with a continuous rim diamond blade. On either side of the sample <lb/>removed, the specimen suffered a small amount of kerf loss from the blade. A small break was <lb/>forced upon nearly completing each transverse cut through the shafts, to ensure one area on <lb/>each side of the sample matched up to the rest of the diaphysis, to preserve the original length <lb/>of the bone once the cast was produced. Each sample removed was then molded using Douglas <lb/>and Sturgess 2-part Silputty, and cast using Smooth-On Smooth-Cast 321 two-part resin. <lb/>Casts were primed and painted to resemble the appearance of the removed samples. The cast <lb/>replicas were not restored to the bone shafts, but placed in the specimen cradles where the <lb/>original pieces were removed. The portion of the cast representing the forced break in the sam-<lb/>ples contacted with the remainder of the specimen, ensuring no loss in length in each case <lb/>with inclusion of the replica. <lb/>The sample removed was indicated on each drawn specimen outline, and the samples were <lb/>then embedded in Silmar two-part polyester resin (Sil95BA-41). After the resin cured, the sam-<lb/>ples were processed using a Buehler Isomet 1000 precision saw, with a diamond wafering <lb/>blade, to obtain two, 2 millimetre-thick transverse wafers on either side of the minimum <lb/>diaphysis. For each sample one surface of each wafer was then polished on a Buehler Ecomet 4 <lb/>variable speed polisher/grinder with 600 grit, then 800 grit silicon carbide paper to remove <lb/>marks left by the wafering blade. The polished side of the wafers were then glued to frosted <lb/>plastic slides using cyanoacrylate glue (Starbond, medium viscosity) and left to cure for 48 <lb/>hours. Each slide was then polished on the Ecomet 4 using silicon carbide papers of progres-<lb/>sively finer grit (60 to 1200), and hand polished using a 1 micron cloth with 5 micron slurry <lb/>and finally with 1 micron aluminum oxide gel. <lb/>Each completed thin section was analyzed using a Nikon Eclipse polarizing microscope <lb/>under plane, circular, and full wave-plate polarization. Whole thin section photomontages <lb/>were produced using an ASI motorized stage and Nikon DS-Ri2 camera affixed to the micro-<lb/>scope at 50X total magnification, and with the software package Nikon Elements: Documenta-<lb/>tion. The femur and tibia diaphyses suffered post-burial crushing, so the resulting digital <lb/>images of the femur and tibia were digitally restored to their original shape using Adobe Pho-<lb/>toshop CC. Digital Line of Arrested Growth (LAG) and surface tracing was also performed in <lb/>Photoshop for all three bones (which included the digitally reconstructed femur and tibia). <lb/>Each LAG, where visible, was digitally traced on a Photoshop layer using a blue line, and a red <lb/>line was used to indicate a region where LAG tracings and surface tracings had to be estimated <lb/>due to cortical drift, crushing, or missing cortex. Diaphyseal circumferences were quantified <lb/>using Fiji [55]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Mass estimation <lb/>In order to estimate the body mass of CM 96523, it was necessary to first estimate the circum-<lb/>ference of the femur, accounting for the taphonomic distortion. This was done by digitally ret-<lb/>rodeforming the cross section of the femur based on femoral cross sections generated by <lb/>computed tomography scans of other oviraptorosaurs like Oksoko [2] and Apatoraptor [47]. <lb/>This estimate was then plotted against regressions of body mass versus stylopodial circumfer-<lb/>ence made by Campione and others [56] to obtain a range of plausible body masses for this <lb/>specimen. We did the same for Anzu, using the femoral circumference of CM 78000 provided <lb/>by Lamanna et al. [12] to compare their masses using the same method of estimation. <lb/>Phylogenetic methods <lb/>To determine the phylogenetic position of the specimen, it was included as an operational tax-<lb/>onomic unit in the oviraptorosaur phylogenetic matrix of Funston et al. 2020 [2]. CM 96523 <lb/>could be scored for 23 characters (9.4%) in the dataset, which comprised 42 taxa and 246 char-<lb/>acters. A cladistic analysis was run in TNT using 10,000 replications of Wagner Trees and a <lb/>subsequent round of Tree Bisection Reconnection to find the shortest trees. Time calibration <lb/>of the phylogeny was done using the strap package in R and the age of the Hell Creek Forma-<lb/>tion [12] for CM 96523. <lb/>Results <lb/>Systematic paleontology <lb/>Theropoda Marsh 1878 [57] <lb/>Oviraptorosauria Barsbold 1976 [58] <lb/>Caenagnathidae Sternberg 1940 [59] <lb/>Eoneophron gen. nov. <lb/>[LSID from ZooBank] <lb/>Eoneophron infernalis sp. nov. <lb/>[LSID from ZooBank] <lb/>Holotype. CM 96523, partial hindlimb including right femur, right tibia and astragalocal-<lb/>caneum, a right metatarsal III, and a right metatarsal IV. <lb/>Etymology. Genus name derived from the Ancient Greek &quot;eo&quot;-meaning &quot;dawn,&quot; and <lb/>from the genus name of the Egyptian vulture, Neophron, sometimes referred to as the &quot;pha-<lb/>raoh&apos;s chicken.&quot; The species name derives from Latin for Hell, in reference to the Hell Creek <lb/>Formation. Together the taxon name equates to &quot;Pharaoh&apos;s dawn chicken from Hell.&quot; <lb/>Locality and horizon. Collected from exposures of the upper Maastrichtian [60] Hell <lb/>Creek Formation, Meade County, South Dakota, United States of America. The specimen was <lb/>prepared prior to acquisition, but matrix remains adhered to some areas, such as the proximal <lb/>portion of the tibia and anterodistal region of the femur. These sediments resemble those of <lb/>typical floodplain deposits such as siltstones with organic material as seen elsewhere in the <lb/>Hell Creek Formation (KLAW, pers. obs.). <lb/>Diagnosis. Caenagnathid oviraptorosaur diagnosed by the following combination of traits <lb/>(autapomorphies are denoted with an asterisk): femoral head directed dorsomedially, rather <lb/>than perpendicular to the shaft; astragalocalcaneum fused to tibia*, metatarsal III with well-<lb/>developed posterior cruciate ridges continuous with the distal condyle; distal condyle of meta-<lb/>tarsal III transversely wider than anteroposteriorly deep, with medial portion of condyle larger <lb/>than lateral portion; proximal end of metatarsals III and IV project posteriorly to form proxi-<lb/>mal protuberance; distal tarsal IV coossified with the proximal end of metatarsal IV at <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>maturity; shaft of metatarsal IV with well-developed oblique longitudinal ridge on anterior <lb/>surface extending along the distal three-quarters of the shaft*. <lb/>Taxonomic comments. In order to assess the taxonomic identification of the specimen, <lb/>we followed the approach used by Cullen et al. 2020 on specimen ROM VP 65884, and scored <lb/>Eoneophron infernalis for the data matrix of Funston et al. (2020). We then compared charac-<lb/>ter states and morphological characters to other oviraptorosaurs, particularly focusing on the <lb/>coeval Anzu wyliei and other Late Cretaceous caenagnathids of North America. E. infernalis <lb/>exhibits several characters of the metatarsus noted to be diagnostic of the clade Caenagnathi-<lb/>dae [46]. Specifically, the semi-arctometatarsalian relationship of the proximal ends of meta-<lb/>tarsals III and IV, the anteroposteriorly flattened metatarsal III, the prominent and deep <lb/>concavity on the posterior surface of the tarsometatarsus, and the cruciate ridges on the poste-<lb/>rior side of metatarsal III are diagnostic of caenagnathids [2,12,41,42,45,53]. While the speci-<lb/>men&apos;s incompleteness makes it difficult to place within Caenagnathidae with any great <lb/>precision, it does share some affinities with Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus rarus in the pro-<lb/>nounced development of the cruciate ridges on metatarsal III, the development of a proximal <lb/>posterior protuberance on metatarsals III and IV, and the fusion of distal tarsal IV to metatar-<lb/>sal IV. This affinity is supported by its position recovered in the phylogenetic analysis. <lb/>Description and comparisons <lb/>CM 96523 consists of the right femur, right tibia and astragalocalcaneum, right metatarsal III, <lb/>and right metatarsal IV. Both the femur and tibia are dorsoventrally crushed along their shafts, <lb/>however, proximal and distal ends of these two bones remain relatively unaltered. The bone <lb/>surface is fragmented, likely due to pressure undergone during the fossilization process. In <lb/>contrast, the two preserved metatarsals show no signs of crushing, and are entirely unbroken <lb/>aside from a few small cracks. All bones have laminated, smooth surface textures, although <lb/>there are clear changes in surface texture on articular surfaces and areas of muscle or ligament <lb/>attachment. <lb/>Femur. The femur of Eoneophron infernalis is shorter than any complete femora assigned <lb/>to Anzu wyliei [12] (Table 1), but is similar in length to known specimens of cf. Caenagnathus <lb/>collinsi and Chirostenotes pergracilis [41]. The distal and proximal ends are preserved well <lb/>enough to determine several anatomical features (Fig 1), but the shaft is crushed. The femoral <lb/>head has a series of distinct furrows, indicating a prominent cartilaginous epiphysis; these fur-<lb/>rows are not quite as prominent in CM 78000 or CM 78001 (Anzu wyliei). The head of the <lb/>femur is dorsomedially directed, so that it meets the long axis of the shaft at an obtuse angle of <lb/>approximately 100˚, which is similar to TMP 1986.036.0323 (cf. Caenagnathus collinsi) [42] <lb/>and some oviraptorids like Oksoko avarsan [2] and Rinchenia mongoliensis [61]. In contrast, in <lb/>other caenagnathids like Chirostenotes pergracilis [35], Elmisaurus rarus [62], Nomingia <lb/>gobiensis [11], and Anzu wyliei, the femoral head is directed medially and meets the shaft at <lb/>roughly a 90˚angle [12]. As in Anzu and other caenagnathids, there is a shallow groove sepa-<lb/>rating the greater trochanter and femoral head, and it appears that the anterior and greater tro-<lb/>chanters are equally tall and form a trochanteric crest, although the anterior trochanter is <lb/>damaged and its morphology is difficult to discern. There is a small accessory trochanteric <lb/>crest distal to the anterior trochanter, but its size is exaggerated by the crushing of the bone. <lb/>This crest is more poorly developed than in Chirostenotes pergracilis [35], Elmisaurus rarus <lb/>[62], or Nomingia gobiensis [11]. <lb/>There is no fourth trochanter in Eoneophron infernalis, as is the case in most oviraptoro-<lb/>saurs. The adductor fossa and the associated anteromedial crest on the distal femur are well-<lb/>developed, as seen in Anzu, but not quite to the same degree. The distal condyles of CM 96523 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>are relatively smaller than those of Anzu, but this may be allometrically related to the smaller <lb/>size of the element. There is a small ectocondylar tuber on the lateral side of the fibular con-<lb/>dyle; this is comparable in size to those of other caenagnathids, but distinctly smaller than <lb/>those of avimimids [24] or oviraptorids [2,61]. As in all oviraptorosaurs, the lateral condyle <lb/>projects distally slightly beyond the medial condyle and has a well-developed notch separating <lb/>the condyles of the crista tibiofibularis. <lb/>Tibia and astragalocalcaneum. The tibia is long and slender: the ratio of the distal con-<lb/>dyle width to the proximodistal length is less than 0.20. The tibia is approximately 128% of the <lb/>length of the femur, differing slightly from the proportions seen in CM 78000 and CM 78001, <lb/>where the tibia is between 1.25 and 1.17 times longer than the femur respectively [12]. The <lb/>cnemial crest of the tibia protrudes far anteriorly, and has a rounded anterior outline in medial <lb/>or lateral view. It is restricted to the proximal part of the shaft, not extending more than 15% <lb/>the length of the tibiotarsus, on par with those of other caenagnathids [35,47,62]. The apex of <lb/>the cnemial crest is at the ventral edge of its extent, similar to other oviraptorosaurs but differ-<lb/>ing from other families of theropods like ornithomimids, alvarezsaurs, and dromaeosaurs [47]. <lb/>The edge of the cnemial crest is tranversely thickened into a knob, which is widest dorsally and <lb/>tapers ventrally. The cnemial crest is separated from the fibular condyle by a deep incisura <lb/>tibialis. The fibular condyle is relatively large and bulbous, and it appears to be separated from <lb/>the posterior edge of the proximal end by a shallow notch. The fibular crest is ridge-like and <lb/>grades into the lateral edge of the shaft at either end. It ends 33% of the length of the tibia from <lb/>the proximal end, as in Chirostenotes pergracilis [35]. A shallow concavity on the distal end of <lb/>the shaft marks the area where the ascending process of the astragalus would have attached; <lb/>only the base of the ascending process is preserved. From this impression, it appears that the <lb/>ascending process of the astragalus was taller than its width at the base, which is the case in all <lb/>oviraptorosaurs [1]. The postfibular flange is less well developed than that of Elmisaurus rarus <lb/>[62], TMP 1994.012.0880 (cf. Citipes elegans) or RSM P2600.1 (Caenagnathidae indet. from <lb/>the Frenchman Formation of Saskatchewan, Canada) [39]. <lb/>The astragalus and calcaneum are fused into a single element without a suture (Fig 2), as is <lb/>seen in Anzu wyliei [12] but not all other caenagnathids, including Maastrichtian examples <lb/>(RSM P2600.1) [39,53,62]. Surprisingly, the astragalocalcaneum itself appears to be coossified <lb/>with the end of the tibia (Fig 3), a trait that is so far unknown in caenagnathids, but has been <lb/>described in Avimimus [24] and observed in an undescribed partial tibiotarsus, possibly also <lb/>from a caenagnathid, from the Dinosaur Park Formation of Alberta (TMP 1985.065.0001; GFF <lb/>pers. obs.). The latter specimen (TMP 1985.065.0001) is catalogued as an ornithomimid, but <lb/>shares several features with caenagnathids, including a semi-circular cross-section of the shaft <lb/>and the absence of a groove or ridge for the fibula (which sits lateral to the tibia throughout its <lb/>length in oviraptorosaurs, as opposed to other theropods including ornithomimids). The con-<lb/>dyles of the astragalocalcaneum in Eoneophron infernalis are uneven in size, and the medial <lb/>condyle is larger and extends further distally. In RSM P2600.1, the condyles are more similar <lb/>in size and extend equally far distally [39]. The medial condyle is fused to the medial malleolus <lb/>of the tibia, whereas a suture can still be discerned between the postfibular flange and the lat-<lb/>eral edge of the tibia. Due to surface crushing, it is difficult to determine with certainty whether <lb/>or not there is a tubercle on the astragalocalcaneum, but if so, it is not nearly as well developed <lb/>as is in Anzu [12]. <lb/>Metatarsals. The two metatarsals found in Eoneophron infernalis cannot be compared to <lb/>the type series of Anzu wyliei, as no weight-bearing metatarsals were preserved in the latter <lb/>specimens. While a partial set of weight-bearing metatarsals were associated with ROM VP <lb/>65884, referred by Cullen et al. to cf. Anzu wyliei [46], none of the three were complete and <lb/>each was missing the proximal ends and distal condyles. However, more complete metatarsals <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>III and IV, probably pertaining to Anzu wyliei, were described by Tsujimura et al. (2021), and <lb/>metatarsals are also known for the indeterminate Maastrichtian caenagnathids from the <lb/>Frenchman Formation (RSM P2600.1) [39]. Both provide valuable comparisons for CM 96523 <lb/>(Eoneophron infernalis) [63]. <lb/>The two metatarsals preserved in Eoneophron are complete, with both proximal and distal <lb/>ends intact and uncrushed shafts. The two metatarsals included with this specimen correspond <lb/>to metatarsals III (Fig 4) and IV (Fig 5) from the right hindlimb. These metatarsals are shorter <lb/>than those of NSM PV 21086; by 47% and 40%, respectively. Neither bones show any sign of <lb/>proximal coossification, as seen in some other caenagnathids such as Citipes elegans and <lb/>Fig 2. Right tibia and astragalocalcaneum of Eoneophron infernalis. In A) Anterior, B) Posterior, C) Lateral, D) Medial, E) Proximal, and F) Distal views. Abbreviations: <lb/>ap, ascending process; cal, calcaneum; cc, cnemial crest; fc, fibular crest; tu?, tubercle? Scale bar = 10cm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Elmisaurus rarus [41,43,62]. However, a small wafer of distal tarsal IV is adhered to the proxi-<lb/>mal surface of metatarsal IV, to which it has begun coossifying. The metatarsus would have <lb/>been elongate, more than 300% as long as its proximal width, even when accounting for the <lb/>missing metatarsal II estimated from the proportions of other caenagnathids. The metatarsus <lb/>is also long relative to the proximal elements of the hindlimb, measuring 63% the length of the <lb/>femur, and slightly less than half (49%) the length of the tibia. Elmisaurus rarus has a similarly <lb/>elongate tarsometatarsus, but the proportions of the hindlimb are slightly different: in MPC-D <lb/>102/007 the tarsometatarsus is estimated at 176 mm (note there is a transcription error in <lb/>Table 1 of Currie et al. 2016), roughly 72% of the femur and 51% of the tibia. <lb/>The proximal end of metatarsal III in Eoneophron infernalis is triangular in proximal view, <lb/>with a narrow anterior wedge that would have separated metatarsals II and IV in articulation. <lb/>The posterior margin of the proximal end is raised into a roughly rectangular mound, similar <lb/>to, but less pronounced than the posterior protuberance in Elmisaurus rarus and Citipes ele-<lb/>gans (but lacking in the Frenchman caenagnathid), which is formed by similar protrusions on <lb/>each of the three weight-bearing metatarsals [62,64]. It is unclear whether the third distal tarsal <lb/>is fused to the proximal end of metatarsal III, but there is a proximally-protruding posterior lip <lb/>(Fig 4E) that may either be a portion of distal tarsal III, or posteriorly delimits the concavity <lb/>Fig 3. Coossification of hindlimb elements in Eoneophron infernalis. A) Tibiotarsus in medial view, showing coossification of the astragalocalcaneum and <lb/>tibia (arrow). B) Interpretive illustration of (A). C) Distal tarsal IV and proximal end of Metatarsal IV in anterior view, showing fusion of the distal tarsal to the <lb/>proximal metatarsal (arrow). D) interpretive illustration of (C). E) Distal tarsal IV and Metatarsal IV in proximal view, showing fusion of the elements (arrow). <lb/>F) Interpretive illustration of (E). Abbreviations: ast, astragalus; dt IV, distal tarsal IV; mt IV, Metatarsal IV; tib, tibia. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>into which distal tarsal III would insert. The shaft of metatarsal III is highly constricted proxi-<lb/>mally, reaching its mediolaterally narrowest point approximately a quarter of the way from the <lb/>proximal articular surface. Distally along its length, it widens transversely, but it is constricted <lb/>just proximal to the distal condyle (Fig 4). This is indicative of an arctometatarsalian condition, <lb/>but based on its morphology, only the proximal-most portion of metatarsal III would be <lb/>obscured, as is the case in Citipes elegans, Chirostenotes pergracilis, and Elmisaurus rarus <lb/>[39,41,62]. This results in the semi-arctometatarsalian condition unique to caenagnathids <lb/>among theropods. A similar condition is exhibited by the third metatarsal described by Tsuji-<lb/>mura et al. (2021) [63], but that specimen is relatively broader transversely, whereas metatarsal <lb/>III of Eoneophron infernalis is more gracile throughout its length. A longitudinal ridge extends <lb/>distally from the wedge-like anterior edge of the proximal end, grading into the extensor sur-<lb/>face of the metatarsal about halfway down its length. Distal to this, two longitudinal grooves <lb/>on either side of the ridge merge to create a shallow concavity on the extensor surface of the <lb/>metatarsal. The same is true of cf. Anzu wyliei (NSM PV 21086; [63]), but this ridge and the <lb/>Fig 4. Right Metatarsal III of CM 96523. In A) Anterior, B) Posterior, C) Posterior (cruciate ridges highlighted), D) Lateral, E) Medial, F) Proximal, and G) Distal views. <lb/>Cruciate ridges highlighted in white where visible. Abbreviations: clp, collateral ligament pit; cps, concave posterior surface; cr, cruciate ridges; mtII, articular surface for <lb/>Metatarsal II; mt IV, articular surface for Metatarsal IV. Scale bar = 5cm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>accompanying concavity are less pronounced. The shaft of the metatarsal flares transversely <lb/>about 30% of the way from the distal end, which is similar to other caenagnathids. However, in <lb/>Eoneophron, this flared portion is equal in width to the distal condyle, whereas it is distinctly <lb/>narrower in Citipes elegans, Elmisaurus rarus, and RSM P2600.1. The distal condyle is large <lb/>and slightly asymmetrical, such that the medial portion of the condyle is larger than the lateral <lb/>portion, like in RSM P2600.1. The condyle is transversely wider than anteroposteriorly deep, <lb/>which contrasts with Citipes elegans but is similar to Chirostenotes pergracilis and Elmisaurus <lb/>rarus [35]. In RSM P2600.1, the distal condyle is nearly equal in transverse and anteroposterior <lb/>dimensions. In metatarsal III of Eoneophron, as like other theropods, the medial collateral liga-<lb/>ment pit is deeper than the lateral one. Towards the posterior (flexor) part of the condyle, the <lb/>edges of the articular surface become attenuated into sharp ridges that extend and merge prox-<lb/>imally. These are continuous with the prominent longitudinal ridges on the shaft of the meta-<lb/>tarsal, and together they form the distinctive cross that is characteristic of most caenagnathids <lb/>[39,62]. Similar ridges are present on the metatarsal III of cf. Anzu wyliei, suggesting they are <lb/>not restricted to &apos;elmisaurine&apos; caenagnathids (contra Funston et al. 2016), but in NSM PV <lb/>21086, they are more narrowly spaced, whereas in Eoneophron infernalis, they are separated by <lb/>a wider sulcus and are closer to the medial and lateral edges of the metatarsal. Variation <lb/>Fig 5. Right Metatarsal IV of Eoneophron infernalis. In A) Anterior, B) Posterior, C) Lateral, D) Medial, E) Proximal, and F) Distal views. Abbreviations: clp, collateral <lb/>ligament pit; dtIV, distal tarsal IV; gls, M. gastrocnemius pars lateralis insertion scar; lr, longitudinal ridge; mtIII, articular surface for Metatarsal III; pmdp, broken base <lb/>of proximodistal process; su, suture between distal tarsal IV and mt IV; tas, M tibialis anterior insertion scar. Scale bar = 5cm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>among caenagnathids also exists in the continuity of the cruciate ridges with the ridges of the <lb/>distal condyles. In Eoneophron infernalis, like Citipes elegans, Elmisaurus rarus and RSM <lb/>P2600.1, they are distinctly continuous, forming a pronounced X-shaped feature, whereas in <lb/>TMP 1979.020.0001, the ridges are not continuous, resulting in a smooth region between these <lb/>sets of ridges [41]. Overall, the third metatarsal compares well with the morphology seen in <lb/>other caenagnathids and the less complete metatarsals of ROM VP 65884 [46]. Metatarsal III <lb/>of Eoneophron shares with all other caenagnathids an anteroposteriorly flattened cross-section <lb/>with a concave posterior surface, although this feature is better developed in North American <lb/>caenagnathids than in Elmisaurus rarus. Furthermore, this posterior surface has sharp medial <lb/>and lateral longitudinal ridges, continuous with lateral and medial postcondylar ridges respec-<lb/>tively; together, these form a cross, as seen in Anzu wyliei, Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus <lb/>rarus, but not Chirostenotes pergracilis [39]. <lb/>Metatarsal IV is similar to those of other caenagnathids, especially Citipes elegans and Elmi-<lb/>saurus rarus [41,43,62]. In particular, distal tarsal IV is fused to the proximal end of the bone, <lb/>as is seen in these two species [41,43,62], but the proximodorsal process of distal tarsal IV is <lb/>broken (Fig 5). This contrasts with the condition in NSM PV 21055 (cf. Anzu wyliei; Tsujimura <lb/>et al. 2021) [63], where the distal tarsal is not fused to the proximal end of metatarsal IV. The <lb/>proximal end is the widest part of the bone, and would have contributed posteriorly to a protu-<lb/>berance as in Elmisaurus rarus [62]. In proximal view, the proximal end is roughly semicircu-<lb/>lar, with a flattened medial edge and a rounded lateral edge. The lateral edge has a slightly <lb/>flattened facet that tapers distally, which marks the contact with the missing metatarsal V. In <lb/>medial view, the proximal end of the metatarsal is incised by a triangular facet towards the pos-<lb/>terior side, for articulation with metatarsal III. Anterior to this is a smaller facet that protrudes <lb/>further medially. This facet would have contacted metatarsal II, obscuring the proximal end of <lb/>metatarsal III in anterior view as in Elmisaurus rarus [62]. The facet for metatarsal II is contin-<lb/>uous distally with a small ridge that outlines a proximal slit for Arteria tarsalis plantaris [62] <lb/>when reunited with metatarsal III. A small rugose area is present on the anterior surface of the <lb/>metatarsal just distal to the proximal expansion. Comparison with other theropods suggests <lb/>that this is an insertion for the Musculus tibialis anterior [65,66]. The shaft of the metatarsal is <lb/>anteroposteriorly compressed, not exceeding the thickness of the distal condyle in lateral and <lb/>medial views. This contrasts with Elmisaurus rarus and Citipes elegans, where a posterolateral <lb/>ridge is well developed. In Eoneophron infernalis, the posterolateral ridge does not protrude as <lb/>far posteriorly, but it runs from the medial edge of the proximal articular surface, continuing <lb/>distally to form the ridge ventral to the lateral ligament pit. However, this ridge does not form <lb/>a pointed process on the proximal articular surface. This posterolateral ridge appears rugose <lb/>and is likely the insertion scar for the M. gastrocnemius pars lateralis [66]. A second, prominent <lb/>longitudinal anterior ridge twists along the shaft from the medial edge proximally towards the <lb/>lateral edge distally. This second ridge is better developed than in Citipes elegans and Elmi-<lb/>saurus rarus, and it extends for a greater length of the shaft (three-quarters) than in the former <lb/>taxa (roughly two thirds). The roughened facet for metatarsal III on the medial surface extends <lb/>just over two thirds (70%) of the length of the bone, expanding distally to a point just above <lb/>the distal condyle. From here, it tapers distally, and a small posteroventral extension of the <lb/>facet contacts the roughened area surrounding the medial collateral ligament pit. The shaft of <lb/>the metatarsal is slightly deflected laterally at the distal end, as observed in the left metatarsal <lb/>IV of ROM VP 65884 [46]. The distal condyle is bulbous and nearly spherical. Both the lateral <lb/>and medial collateral ligament pits are shallow, but the medial one is slightly deeper than the <lb/>lateral one, which is flanked posteriorly by a wing-like ridge. The metatarsal IV of Eoneophron <lb/>infernalis is remarkably similar to that of NSM PV 21055 (cf. Anzu wyliei; Tsujimura et al. <lb/>2021), albeit much smaller and with a relatively larger proximal end because of the posterior <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>protuberance, and with a less bulbous distal condyle. In these features, it is more similar to the <lb/>smaller-bodied Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus rarus [41,43,62]. <lb/>Histology <lb/>Femur. The diaphysis was craniocaudally crushed post-burial, but cortical microstruc-<lb/>tural preservation is such that histological descriptions can still be made. There is a well-devel-<lb/>oped and complete lamellar endosteal layer, with frequent simple radial vascular canals <lb/>passing between the medullary cavity and inner cortex (Fig 6). The primary cortex is fibrola-<lb/>mellar and vascular canals are reticular and sub-laminar. Osteocyte lacunae density is high <lb/>throughout the cortex. Anterolaterally from inner to outer cortex there is a localized column <lb/>of secondary osteons, likely related to a tendon enthesis. No secondary osteons are present out-<lb/>side of this column of remodeled bone. Six LAGs are visible. The innermost LAG is only par-<lb/>tially present, having been resorbed by medullary expansion. Otherwise, there is no <lb/>remarkable evidence of cortical drift. The zone of primary tissue between the innermost LAG <lb/>and the next comprises the majority of the cortex. Thereafter, the zones between LAGs 2-6 are <lb/>more closely-spaced (Table 2 and Fig 6). After the fifth LAG, vascular density is greatly <lb/>decreased (Fig 6B), although osteocyte lacunae density remains high. After the fifth LAG, bone <lb/>tissue is also loosely parallel-fibered. From the retrodeformed transverse thin section image, <lb/>femoral shaft circumference is 105.8 mm. <lb/>Tibia. As with the femur, the tibia diaphysis was anteroposteriorly crushed post-burial, but <lb/>a histological description is still possible. The lamellar endosteal layer is well-developed, with <lb/>frequent simple radial vascular canals passing between the medullary cavity and inner cortex <lb/>(Fig 7). The primary cortex is fibrolamellar and vascular canals within the inner and mid-cortex <lb/>are a combination of reticular and longitudinal (Fig 7B), with frequent short radial anastomoses. <lb/>Longitudinal vascularity dominates within the outer cortex. No secondary osteons are observed. <lb/>The first visible LAG is located within the mid-cortex, and the tissue from the endosteal surface <lb/>to the second LAG comprises the majority of the cortex (Table 2). The first LAG is only partially <lb/>visible, having been largely eroded by medullary cavity expansion. Cortical drift, however, is <lb/>negligible. The zones between LAGs 2-6 towards the periosteal surface are markedly thinner <lb/>(Fig 7). Vascular density is also reduced in these last four zones, but only slightly. The sixth <lb/>LAG is so close to the periosteal surface that it often merges with it. From the retrodeformed <lb/>thin section image, transverse section tibia circumference is 106.8 mm. <lb/>Metatarsal IV. There is a well-developed lamellar endosteal layer, and occasional simple <lb/>radial vascular canals pass between the medullary cavity and primary cortex (Fig 8). Primary <lb/>tissue from inner to outer cortex is fibrolamellar with a high density of osteocyte lacunae. Vas-<lb/>cular canal density is somewhat higher in the innermost cortex compared with the mid-and <lb/>outer cortex. Anteromedially, canals are primarily a combination of longitudinal and reticular, <lb/>and are largely sub-laminar elsewhere. Posteriorly within the innermost cortex there is a cres-<lb/>cent of compact coarse cancellous bone (CCCB) [67] between the lamellar endosteal layer and <lb/>the periosteally-derived mid-cortex. The CCCB grades into a thin annulus of well-organized <lb/>avascular tissue, consisting of numerous flattened osteocyte lacunae. This annulus is truncated <lb/>posteromedially and posterolaterally by medullary cavity resorption. Beyond the annulus, cor-<lb/>tical tissue is fibrolamellar, and vascular density is high. CCCB results when spaces between <lb/>spongy trabecular bone are infilled by additional bone to result in compact tissue [67]. This <lb/>process occurs at the metaphyseal regions of long bones during endochondral ossification <lb/>[67]. Embryonic CCCB is sometimes found within the shaft of a long bone resulting from sub-<lb/>sequent diaphyseal lengthening [68]. A change in vascular density beyond the annulus [69-72] <lb/>and the close proximity of a periosteally-derived annulus to the CCCB are morphologically <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>consistent with a neonatal line (Fig 8B). The neonatal line, found in the bones and teeth of <lb/>amniote tetrapods, results from a brief pause in growth occurring around the time of hatching <lb/>or birth [72]. The neonatal line provides an estimate of perinatal bone circumference [72], <lb/>which for metatarsal IV is 26.1 mm. <lb/>On the anteromedial and anterolateral sides, a localized column of secondary osteons spans <lb/>from inner to outer cortex, likely related to ligamentous entheses. Beyond these columns, no <lb/>secondary osteons are present within the cortex. A nutrient foramen is present near the perios-<lb/>teal surface on the medial side. <lb/>Within the outer cortex, vascular density is decreased, consisting of scattered longitudinal <lb/>and reticular vascular canals (Fig 8B). Osteocyte lacunae density remains high in the outermost <lb/>cortex on the anterior side, and is less dense with more flattened lacunae on the posterior side. <lb/>Beyond the annulus bounding the inner-cortical CCCB, six LAGs are present. Three widely-<lb/>spaced LAGs are visible within the cortex, with the innermost only partially visible due to ero-<lb/>sion from medullary cavity expansion. LAG spacing is then abruptly decreased between the <lb/>final three LAGs nearest the periosteal surface. LAGs 4-6 are traceable, but merge with the <lb/>periosteal surface in places (Table 2 and Fig 8). Although the primary tissue within these outer <lb/>three zones is fibrolamellar on the anterior side, the tissue is parallel-fibered to lamellar on the <lb/>posterior side. An overlay of LAG tracings reveals very little cortical drift over ontogeny after <lb/>the first year of life. Transverse thin section circumference is 64.2 mm. <lb/>Mass estimation <lb/>The reconstructed femoral circumference of 105.8mm for Eoneophron infernalis predicts a <lb/>body mass of 78 kg based on the equation of Campione et al. [56], with a range from 58.9-98.1 <lb/>Fig 6. Osteological thin-section of the femur of Eoneophron infernalis in plain polarized light. A) Reconstructed cross section of femur with lines of arrested growth <lb/>[LAGs] traced in light blue; B) Close up of cross section with black arrows denoting lines of arrested growth [LAGs]. Note the change in vascularity from the inner to outer <lb/>cortex. Scale bar = 1000μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2. Comparison of relative growth for histologically sampled elements of Eoneophron infernalis. MC: Med-<lb/>ullary cavity. <lb/>Element <lb/>Growth Zone <lb/>Relative % of cortex <lb/>Femur (undeformed) <lb/>Medullary cavity to LAG 1 <lb/>Lost to MC expansion <lb/>LAG 1 to LAG 2 <lb/>6.17 <lb/>LAG 2 to LAG 3 <lb/>14.20 <lb/>LAG 3 to LAG 4 <lb/>3.09 <lb/>LAG 4 to LAG 5 <lb/>2.47 <lb/>LAG 5 to LAG 6 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>LAG 6 to outer surface <lb/>1.23 <lb/>Tibia <lb/>Medullary cavity to LAG 1 <lb/>6.40 <lb/>LAG 1 to LAG 2 <lb/>11.63 <lb/>LAG 2 to LAG 3 <lb/>2.33 <lb/>LAG 3 to LAG 4 <lb/>2.91 <lb/>LAG 4 to LAG 5 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>LAG 5 to LAG 6 (not traceable) <lb/>0.58 <lb/>LAG 6 to outer surface <lb/>0.58 <lb/>Metatarsal IV <lb/>Medullary cavity to LAG 1 <lb/>4.91 <lb/>LAG 1 to LAG 2 <lb/>31.89 <lb/>LAG 2 to LAG 3 <lb/>13.54 <lb/>* <lb/>LAG 3 to LAG 4 <lb/>2.06 <lb/>* <lb/>LAG 4 to LAG 5 <lb/>2.55 <lb/>* <lb/>LAG 5 to LAG 6 <lb/>2.16 <lb/>LAG 6 to outer surface <lb/>1.57 <lb/>*Some estimation required to trace LAG. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.t002 <lb/>Fig 7. Osteological thin section of right tibia of Eoneophron infernalis in plain polarized light. A) Reconstructed cross section of tibia with lines of arrested growth <lb/>[LAGs] traced in light blue; B) Close up of cross section with black arrows denoting lines of arrested growth [LAGs]. Note the change in vascularity from the inner to outer <lb/>cortex. Scale bar = 1000μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g007 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>kg. This is far less than predicted for the much larger CM 78000, which, using the same meth-<lb/>ods, weighed between 202 and 342 kg. However, the body mass estimate for CM 96523 is only <lb/>slightly larger than those of other mid-sized caenagnathids like Anomalipes (67 kg), Apatorap-<lb/>tor (63 kg), Chirostenotes (67 kg), and Elmisaurus (65 kg) [59]. <lb/>Phylogeny <lb/>Our phylogenetic analysis returned 504 most parsimonious trees with a tree length of 648 <lb/>steps (Fig 9). The topology of the strict consensus is similar to previous analyses of oviraptoro-<lb/>saur phylogeny, in dividing oviraptorids into two main subfamilies (although with a large <lb/>basal polytomy), and recovering Eoneophron among derived caenagnathids within a large <lb/>polytomy. Bremer support for the major nodes in Oviraptorosauria is strong, but internal sup-<lb/>port is weaker, as expected for a dataset with a high proportion of missing data. In the major-<lb/>ity-rules consensus, Eoneophron infernalis is recovered as a sister to the clade of Elmisaurus <lb/>and Citipes, which is reasonable because of the interpretation of the fusion of distal tarsal IV to <lb/>metatarsal IV. In any case, phylogenetic analysis strongly supports the identification of Eoneo-<lb/>phron as a caenagnathid, although with expectedly low resolution considering the fragmentary <lb/>preservation of the holotype specimen and most other known caenagnathid material. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Morphology <lb/>The morphology of Eoneophron infernalis is broadly consistent with that of other caenag-<lb/>nathids, but it provides additional information on their proportions and variation. There is a <lb/>negative allometric relationship between tibia and femur length in Oviraptorosauria [73]; E. <lb/>infernalis proportions are scaled similarly to those of Anzu wyliei, Chirostenotes pergracilis, <lb/>Elmisaurus rarus, and Gigantoraptor [5,8,12,62], suggesting that this negative allometry is con-<lb/>served across caenagnathids. <lb/>Fig 8. Osteological thin section of right Metatarsal IV of Eoneophron infernalis in plain polarized light. A) Cross section of Metatarsal IV with lines of arrested growth <lb/>[LAGs] traced in light blue, with area missing due to modeling or medullary cavity expansion in red, and putative neonatal line in purple B) Close up of posterior side <lb/>where CCCB, a possible neonatal line (purple arrows), and six LAGs are observed (blue arrows). Imaged in plane polarized light on the left, circularly polarized light on the <lb/>right. Note the change in vascularity from the inner to outer cortex. Scale bar = 1000μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g008 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Several discrete morphological features indicate that Eoneophron infernalis is distinct from <lb/>Anzu wyliei and other caenagnathids. Histological data also supports this separation (see <lb/>below), which indicate a smaller adult body size than Anzu wyliei. The head of the femur of E. <lb/>infernalis meets the shaft at an oblique angle, rather than extending perpendicular, as is the <lb/>case in Anzu wyliei [12] and most other caenagnathids. Furthermore, the femoral condyles <lb/>appear to be relatively smaller in E. infernalis, but it is unclear whether this is attributable to <lb/>allometry. The accessory trochanteric crest of Eoneophron infernalis is much smaller than that <lb/>of Anzu wyliei, Elmisaurus rarus, and Nomingia gobiensis. The tibia has a more proximally <lb/>restricted cnemial crest than in Anzu wyliei, but it is otherwise similar in morphology to most <lb/>oviraptorosaurs [73], although it has a less well-developed post-fibular flange than most cae-<lb/>nagnathids. Eoneophron infernalis differs from Anzu wyliei in the extension of the astragalus to <lb/>reach the lateral margin of the tarsus, a feature that has sometimes been used to distinguish <lb/>caenagnathids from oviraptorids [61], but is likewise present in RSM P2600.1. Although the <lb/>referral of metatarsals to Anzu wyliei remains equivocal, E. infernalis differs in several respects <lb/>from the larger metatarsals from the Hell Creek Formation. In particular, the presence of <lb/>Fig 9. Time-calibrated majority-rules consensus tree showing the position of Eoneophron infernalis. Tree is trimmed to Oviraptorosauria. Numbers next to <lb/>nodes indicate Bremer support values in the strict consensus tree; nodes without numbers were not recovered in the strict consensus. * indicates a node that <lb/>never collapsed under the Bremer analysis (i.e., it is exceedingly well-supported). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g009 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>posterior protuberances on metatarsals III and IV is reminiscent of the tripartite protuberance <lb/>that characterizes Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus rarus, and it is likely that Eoneophron inferna-<lb/>lis shared this feature. These protuberances are absent on the proximal ends of the metatarsals <lb/>referred to cf. Anzu wyliei. Similarly, metatarsals referred to cf. Anzu wyliei lack evidence of <lb/>fusion between distal tarsal IV and metatarsal IV, or a pointed process on the proximolateral <lb/>edge of metatarsal IV. <lb/>While the gross morphology of Eoneophron infernalis elements is generally similar to other <lb/>caenagnathids, its hindlimb is remarkable for the extensive fusion of the bones. Fusion of the <lb/>astragalus with the calcaneum and fusion of the distal tarsals with the proximal metatarsals <lb/>have been described previously in caenagnathids, but fusion between the astragalocalcaneum <lb/>and the tibia has not. Within Oviraptorosauria, only avimimids are known to exhibit fused <lb/>tibiotarsi [24], and they also exhibit extensive fusion elsewhere in the skeleton, including the <lb/>braincase, manus, and pelvis. It is noteworthy that in several specimens of Elmisaurus rarus, <lb/>the tarsometatarsi are coossified, but the associated tibiotarsi are not: in each the tibiae show <lb/>no signs of fusion to the astragalocalcanea, which are missing. Thus, although there is clearly <lb/>an ontogenetic aspect to fusion of the tibiotarsus, it appears that the fusion of the tibiotarsus in <lb/>Eoneophron infernalis is unique to this taxon within Caenagnathoidea, because other speci-<lb/>mens at presumably equivalent ontogenetic stages do not show this feature [3,32]. <lb/>Together, these morphological features distinguish CM 96523 from Anzu wyliei and other <lb/>caenagnathids known from the Late Cretaceous of North America. Considering that histologi-<lb/>cal data show that this specimen was approaching adult body size and may have already <lb/>reached sexual maturity (see below), the data support the establishment of a new taxon for this <lb/>material, Eoneophron infernalis. This taxon can be distinguished by a unique combination of <lb/>features of the hindlimb, as well as two autapomorphies: fusion of the astragalocalcaneum and <lb/>tibiotarsus at maturity and a long, sharp longitudinal ridge on the anterior surface of metatar-<lb/>sal IV. <lb/>Histology <lb/>CM 96523 contributes to a growing body of caenagnathid long bone histoanalyses <lb/>[39,41,46,51,73,74], but is the first published assessment of caenagnathid femoral histology. <lb/>The histology of the femur, tibia, and metatarsal IV are congruent, suggesting that the ontoge-<lb/>netic signal they provide is reliable. The femur, tibia, and metatarsal IV of Eoneophron inferna-<lb/>lis each record six LAGs. Although the large medullary cavities of each bone leave the <lb/>possibility that one or more LAGs from earlier ontogeny were obliterated by medullary cavity <lb/>expansion, the presence of a putative neonatal line followed by six LAGs in metatarsal IV sug-<lb/>gests the death of this individual occurred during its sixth year of life. Because the sixth LAG is <lb/>so close to the periosteal surface and often merges with the surface in each bone examined, <lb/>death probably occurred shortly after this individual emerged from its annual growth hiatus. <lb/>LAG spacing reveals that the majority of bone apposition and body size increase happened <lb/>during the first two years of age, based on femur and tibia histology. After the second LAG, <lb/>there is a marked shift to closely spaced LAGs, comprising the remainder of the outer cortex. <lb/>This inflection in apposition rate may correspond to sexual maturity, as hypothesized for other <lb/>dinosaur groups including oviraptorosaurs [75-77]. Interestingly, apposition rate inflection <lb/>occurred after the third year within metatarsal IV, rather than in the second year as observed <lb/>in the femur and tibia. The cortex of the femur and tibia is thinner than that of metatarsal IV, <lb/>which does indicate differing rates of medullary cavity enlargement. Indeed, that the putative <lb/>neonatal line is recorded in metatarsal IV and not in the femur or tibia is strong evidence that <lb/>medullary expansion rate was lower in the former. However, because the cortex of metatarsal <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>IV is thicker and still records only six LAGs, differences in apposition rate inflection reflect <lb/>individual bone growth trajectories rather than mismatched LAG counts due to medullary <lb/>resorption. <lb/>The tibia histology of Eoneophron infernalis differs from that of a previously described inde-<lb/>terminate caenagnathid (UALVP 57349) from the Campanian-early Maastrichtian Horseshoe <lb/>Canyon Formation in Alberta, Canada [73]. The histology of UALVP 57349 suggests this <lb/>small individual (tibia length of 210 mm) was a young juvenile. Its bone tissue is entirely retic-<lb/>ular and plexiform fibrolamellar, with open vascular canals at the periosteal surface, no sec-<lb/>ondary osteons, and an avascular endosteal lamellar layer. A band of parallel-fibered tissue <lb/>within the cortex may be an annulus, suggesting it was at least one year of age [73]. The larger <lb/>tibia of E. infernalis (480mm) described here is also entirely fibrolamellar, but vascular orienta-<lb/>tion is reticular to sub-laminar, has a vascularized lamellar endosteal layer, and there are six <lb/>well-defined LAGs within the cortex. Beginning with the fourth LAG, zonal spacing between <lb/>LAGs is markedly decreased towards the periosteal surface, and the vascular canals are not <lb/>open at the bone surface. The histology of UALVP 57349 and E. infernalis show that the tibia <lb/>of each was still growing when the individuals died. However, the histology of E. infernalis sug-<lb/>gests it was relatively older (six LAGs compared to a single annulus) and growth was approach-<lb/>ing an asymptote, whereas UALVP 57349 shows no indication of decreasing annual <lb/>apposition rate. <lb/>The histology of Eoneophron infernalis also differs from the fragmentary tibia of ROM VP <lb/>65884, referred to Anzu wyliei [46], from the Maastrichtian Hell Creek Formation of Montana. <lb/>Although the primary tissue in both tibiae is fibrolamellar, the vascularity in ROM VP 65884 <lb/>ranges from reticular within the inner cortex to plexiform in the outer cortex, while that of E. <lb/>infernalis is a combination of reticular and longitudinal for most of the cortex to predomi-<lb/>nantly longitudinal in the outermost cortex. ROM VP 65884 preserves seven LAGs, with a <lb/>noticeable decrease in zonal spacing occurring after the third LAG. The tibia of E. infernalis <lb/>preserves only six LAGs, with a pronounced decrease in zonal thickness occurring after the <lb/>second LAG. Finally, although zonal spacing is decreased within the outer zones of the larger <lb/>tibia of ROM VP 65884, tissue remains well-vascularized to the periosteal surface and there is <lb/>no indication an EFS is present. This differs from E. infernalis, which exhibits reduced, longi-<lb/>tudinal vascularity within the outermost cortical zones. <lb/>Vascular orientation can be compared to determine relative growth rates [78]. Longitudinal <lb/>vascular canals within the outermost zones of the tibia in Eoneophron infernalis indicate a <lb/>slower annual growth rate than the plexiform vascularity observed in tibia ROM VP 65884, <lb/>referred to A. wyliei. Although individual variation in growth cannot be discounted (e.g., <lb/>Woodward et al. 2015 [79]), it appears that E. infernalis would have attained a smaller asymp-<lb/>totic body size than reported for specimens of A. wyliei [12,46]. <lb/>The metatarsal IV histology of CM 96523 resembles that of the Campanian-aged Dinosaur <lb/>Park Formation Citipes elegans metatarsal IV (UALVP 59606) described previously by Fun-<lb/>ston et al. (2020) [74]. In both, the bone tissue is reticular to longitudinal fibrolamellar, the <lb/>lamellar endosteal layer is pierced by vascular canals, and the cortex preserves six LAGs. The <lb/>two metatarsals differ in that the LAG spacing in C. elegans metatarsal IV becomes reduced <lb/>after the second LAG, while this occurs after the third LAG in CM 96523. Also, the metatarsal <lb/>IV of C. elegans (total length of 146 mm) contained secondary osteons, and the closely spaced <lb/>LAGs within avascular outermost cortex was interpreted as an EFS and signaling skeletal <lb/>maturity [74]. In contrast, the zones between the closely spaced outermost LAGs in metatarsal <lb/>IV of E. infernalis (total length of 233mm) remain vascularized with high osteocyte lacuna den-<lb/>sity, suggesting that this larger metatarsal was approaching asymptotic size but was still grow-<lb/>ing in length at death. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Paleoecological and diagnostic implications <lb/>The number of caenagnathid taxa in the Hell Creek Formation is uncertain. Varricchio (2001) <lb/>described a partial pes of a small caenagnathid (MOR 752) he referred to &quot;Elmisaurus&apos;&apos; elegans <lb/>(now Citipes elegans) on the basis of an anterolateral process proximal to the distal condyle of <lb/>metatarsal IV, for Musculus tibialis cranialis [39,43]. At the time, the presence of a larger cae-<lb/>nagnathid in the Hell Creek Formation was known [38,80], but it was not formally described <lb/>until 2014, as Anzu wyliei [12]. There is, however, the lack of overlap of the elements described <lb/>by Varricchio (2001) and Lamanna et al. (2014), and thus it is unclear whether they could rep-<lb/>resent ontogimorphs of the same taxon. Eoneophron infernalis complicates this issue some-<lb/>what, as it is nearly double the size of MOR 752 but shows clear signs of skeletal maturity. It is <lb/>thus unclear whether these specimens indicate the presence of two taxa-in which case MOR <lb/>752 is a juvenile of either Anzu wyliei or Eoneophron-or three taxa, in which case each repre-<lb/>sents a distinct taxon. However, some evidence suggests that the latter situation may be more <lb/>likely. For example, the metatarsal II referred to cf. Anzu wyliei by Cullen et al. (2020) lacks the <lb/>anterolateral process proximal to the distal condyle described for MOR 752, which also distin-<lb/>guishes it from Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus rarus. As described by Currie et al. (2016) and <lb/>Funston et al. (2016), the prominent attachment sites for M. tibialis cranialis in Citipes elegans <lb/>and Elmisaurus rarus consistently manifest as both the anterolateral process on metatarsal II <lb/>and an anteromedial process on metatarsal IV. This suggests that, were it preserved, metatarsal <lb/>IV of the taxon represented by MOR 752 could be expected to have a prominent anteromedial <lb/>process proximal to the distal condyle. However, this is not the case in Eoneophron infernalis, <lb/>despite nearing skeletal maturity, tentatively suggesting that it is distinct from MOR 752. As <lb/>muscular insertions might be expected to become better developed allometrically and ontoge-<lb/>netically, this casts doubt on the idea that MOR 752 is a juvenile individual of either E. inferna-<lb/>lis or Anzu wyliei. Nonetheless, as MOR 752 is fragmentary, its ontogenetic status is unknown, <lb/>and the ontogeny of muscle attachments in caenagnathids is poorly understood, caution is <lb/>warranted in ascribing the remains to different taxa. <lb/>The presence of either two or three caenagnathid taxa in the Hell Creek Formation indi-<lb/>cates nevertheless that multiple species of caenagnathid coexisted during the end-Maastrich-<lb/>tian (Fig 10), and highlights palaeohistology as a key source of information on the diversity of <lb/>caenagnathids across North America [35,41,46,51,52,74]. Coexistence of multiple caenag-<lb/>nathids in the Hell Creek Formation is not unexpected, given that the Campanian Dinosaur <lb/>Park Formation also preserves three caenagnathid taxa within the same ecosystem, each of a <lb/>different adult size [41], and the Horseshoe Canyon Formation likewise preserves two differ-<lb/>ently-sized taxa [36,47]. Although tentative, two sizes of caenagnathid also appear to be present <lb/>in the Maastrichtian Frenchman Formation of Saskatchewan, Canada [39,81]. In the Dinosaur <lb/>Park and Frenchman formations, the largest species approached Anzu wyliei in size [40,41,81]. <lb/>However, there were also smaller taxa like Citipes elegans, and in the Dinosaur Park Forma-<lb/>tion, an intermediately-sized species is present: Chirostenotes pergracilis. Eoneophron infernalis <lb/>appears closest to Chirostenotes in size, whereas MOR 752 is similar in size to Citipes elegans <lb/>[43]. Tibiae and femora have not yet been unambiguously referred to Citipes, so its propor-<lb/>tions are difficult to estimate, but it was clearly the smallest caenagnathid within the Dinosaur <lb/>Park Formation [41]. Despite being similar in body mass to Chirostenotes pergracilis, in many <lb/>features E. infernalis is more similar to the smaller Citipes elegans and Elmisaurus rarus, an <lb/>affinity borne out by the phylogenetic analysis conducted here. Like in the Dinosaur Park For-<lb/>mation [41], the differing adult body masses of caenagnathid taxa in the Hell Creek Formation <lb/>suggests that size was an important factor in the coexistence of multiple caenagnathids in the <lb/>same ecosystems. However, it is interesting to note that the intermediately-sized taxa, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>Chirostenotes pergracilis and Eoneophron infernalis, differed considerably in metatarsal mor-<lb/>phology. Thus, it tentatively appears that body size niches were not necessarily restricted to <lb/>taxa with a particular set of adaptations. Unfortunately, little is known about the ecology of <lb/>caenagnathids, so it is difficult to speculate on the impacts of the fused limb elements of E. <lb/>infernalis on its behavior. Whereas it is possible that the fusion of proximal tarsals to metatar-<lb/>sus better allowed E. infernalis to handle stresses associated with cursorial locomotion, evi-<lb/>dence from the pelvic regions suggests that caenagnathids of similar proportions may have <lb/>had divergent locomotory behaviors [82]. Similarly, the grasping adaptations of the caenag-<lb/>nathid pes [80] may have served a role in locomotion, prey capture, or both, and thus the mor-<lb/>phology of the metatarsus may reflect a mosaic of selective pressures. <lb/>The unexpected histological results further highlight the importance of taking histological <lb/>data into account when assigning taxonomic identities to incomplete theropod remains, rein-<lb/>forcing the point originally made by Cullen et al. 2020 [46]. Likewise, Cullen et al. 2020 raise <lb/>concerns regarding the sampling and taxonomic stability of even well-sampled geological for-<lb/>mations. The presence of cryptic diversity, like that revealed here, may have important <lb/>Fig 10. Artist&apos;s depiction of Eoneophron infernalis (top left), MOR 752 (bottom left), and Anzu wyliei (right) in the Hell Creek Formation. Illustration by Zubin Erik <lb/>Dutta. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901.g010 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<body>ramifications for estimations of dinosaur diversity, environmental sensitivity, community <lb/>structure, and ecosystem vulnerability in Late Cretaceous ecosystems, especially those leading <lb/>up to the end-Cretaceous extinction. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>CM 96523 represents one of the few instances of associated caenagnathid hindlimbs, and <lb/>exhibits unique proportions, combinations of features, and coossifications between elements. <lb/>In tandem with histological data indicating that this animal was of subadult or adult status at <lb/>the time of its death, this suggests that it represent a new taxon, Eoneophron infernalis. This <lb/>smaller caenagnathid from the Hell Creek Formation has implications for the ecology and <lb/>diversity of caenagnathids in the end-Maastrichtian. As many as three taxa of varying body <lb/>size may have inhabited the Maastrichtian ecosystems of the Hell Creek Formation, but like in <lb/>other regions, a poor fossil record makes untangling the taxonomy of these species problem-<lb/>atic. The ecology of caenagnathids likewise remains poorly understood, but E. infernalis <lb/>expands the range of morphological variation within the family and suggests that caenagnathid <lb/>diversity in Laurasia remained largely stable through the Campanian-Maastrichtian, and these <lb/>dinosaurs remained successful components of Laurasian ecosystems until the K-Pg extinction. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 File. NEXUS phylogenetic data used in the study. <lb/>(NEX) <lb/>S2 File. TNT phylogenetic data used in the study. <lb/>(TNT) <lb/>S3 File. PHYLIP phylogenetic data used in the study. <lb/>(PHY) <lb/>S4 File. Phylogenetic tree generated from data used in the study. <lb/>(TRE) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the staff at the Carnegie Museum for facilitating study of the specimen, specifically <lb/>M. Lamanna and A. Henrici for assisting in specimen access and bone transport, D. Pickering <lb/>for repreparation and reconstruction of the femur. Nicola ´s Campione deserves recognition for <lb/>providing information and code for R-generated regressions of body mass from femoral cir-<lb/>cumference. For comments and revisions on this manuscript, we thank N. Van Vranken, R. J. <lb/>Gay, H. Mallison, and B. Lieberman. We thank D.J. Pugh for assistance with photography of <lb/>metatarsals and J. Leibach for assistance with making the plates. For the photography and <lb/>plate construction of the femur and tibia, we thank A. McAfee, H. Jones, and T. Mastalski. <lb/>Funding for histology processing provided to HNW by Oklahoma State University Center <lb/>for Health Sciences. Funding to GFF provided by the Royal Society (Grant NIF\R1\191527) <lb/>and a Banting Fellowship (NSERC). <lb/>Finally, we would like to acknowledge the Nile monitor named Pharaoh, who held great sig-<lb/>nificance in the heart of the lead author and all those who met him. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, Gregory F. Funston. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Data curation: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, Holly N. Woodward. <lb/>Formal analysis: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, D. Jade Simon, Holly N. Woodward, <lb/>Gregory F. Funston. <lb/>Investigation: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman. <lb/>Methodology: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, Holly N. Woodward, Gregory F. Funston. <lb/>Project administration: Eric Snively. <lb/>Resources: Eric Snively. <lb/>Visualization: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, Holly N. Woodward, Gregory F. Funston. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, Holly N. Woodward, Gregory F. Funston. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kyle L. Atkins-Weltman, D. Jade Simon, Holly N. Woodward, <lb/>Gregory F. Funston. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Osmo ´lska H. Oviraptorosauria. In: Weishampel D, Dodson P, Osmo ´lska H, editors. The dinosauria. <lb/>Berkeley, CA: University of California Press; 2004. pp. 165-183. <lb/>2. Funston GF, Chinzorig T, Tsogtbaatar K, Kobayashi Y, Sullivan C, Currie PJ. A new two-fingered dino-<lb/>saur sheds light on the radiation of Oviraptorosauria. R Soc Open Sci. 2020; 7: 201184. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1098/rsos.201184 PMID: 33204472 <lb/>3. Qiang J, Currie PJ, Norell MA, Shu-An J. Two feathered dinosaurs from northeastern China. Nature. <lb/>1998; 393: 753-761. https://doi.org/10.1038/31635 <lb/>4. Lu ¨J, Currie PJ, Xu L, Zhang X, Pu H, Jia S. Chicken-sized oviraptorid dinosaurs from central China and <lb/>their ontogenetic implications. Naturwissenschaften. 2013; 100: 165-175. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00114-012-1007-0 PMID: 23314810 <lb/>5. Xu X, Tan Q, Wang J, Zhao X, Tan L. A gigantic bird-like dinosaur from the Late Cretaceous of China. <lb/>Nature. 2007 [cited 28 Feb 2017]. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05849 PMID: 17565365 <lb/>6. Zhou Z-H, Wang X-L, Zhang F-C, Xu X. Important features of Caudipteryx -evidence from two nearly <lb/>complete new specimens. Vertebr Palasiat. 2000; 38: 242-254. <lb/>7. Xu X, Zheng X, You H. Exceptional dinosaur fossils show ontogenetic development of early feathers. <lb/>Nature. 2010; 464: 1338-1341. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature08965 PMID: 20428169 <lb/>8. Funston GF, Currie PJ. New material of Chirostenotes pergracilis (Theropoda, Oviraptorosauria) from <lb/>the Campanian Dinosaur Park Formation of Alberta, Canada. Hist Biol. 2020; 1-15. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1080/08912963.2020.1726908 <lb/>9. Kurzanov S. Structural characteristics of the fore limbs of Avimimus. Paleontol J. 1982; 1982: 108-112. <lb/>10. Barsbold R, Currie PJ, Myhrvold NP, Osmo ´lska H, Tsogtbaatar K, Watabe M. A pygostyle from a non-<lb/>avian theropod. Nature. 2000; 403: 155-156. https://doi.org/10.1038/35003103 PMID: 10646588 <lb/>11. Barsbold R, Osmo ´lska H, Watabe M, Currie PJ, Tsogtbaatar K. A new oviraptorosaur (Dinosauria, <lb/>Theropoda) from Mongolia: the first dinosaur with a pygostyle. Acta Palaeontol Pol. 2000; 45: 97-106. <lb/>12. Lamanna MC, Sues H-D, Schachner ER, Lyson TR. A new large-bodied oviraptorosaurian theropod <lb/>dinosaur from the latest Cretaceous of western North America. PLoS One. 2014; 9: e92022. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pone.0092022 PMID: 24647078 <lb/>13. Pittman M, O&apos;Connor J, Field D, Turner A, Ma W, Makovicky P, et al. Chapter 1: Pennaraptoran Sys-<lb/>tematics. 2020. pp. 7-36. <lb/>14. Pittman M, O&apos;Connor J, Tse E, Makovicky P, Field D, Ma W, et al. The Fossil Record of Mesozoic and <lb/>Paleocene Pennaraptorans. Bull Am Mus Nat Hist. 2020; 440: 37-96. <lb/>15. Norell MA, Clark JM, Chiappe LM, Dashzeveg D. A nesting dinosaur. Nature. 1995; 378: 774-776. <lb/>16. Yang Tzu-Ruei Sander P. Martin. The reproductive biology of oviraptorosaurs: a synthesis. Geol Soc <lb/>Lond Spec Publ. 2022; 521: 19-34. https://doi.org/10.1144/SP521-2021-181 <lb/>17. Maryańska T, Osmo ´lska H, Wolsan M. Avialan status for Oviraptorosauria. Acta Palaeontol Pol. 2002; <lb/>47: 97-116. <lb/>18. Bi S, Amiot R, Peyre de Fabrègues C, Pittman M, Lamanna MC, Yu Y, et al. An oviraptorid preserved <lb/>atop an embryo-bearing egg clutch sheds light on the reproductive biology of non-avialan theropod <lb/>dinosaurs. Sci Bull. 2021; 66: 947-954. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scib.2020.12.018 PMID: 36654242 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>24 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>19. Norell MA, Balanoff AM, Barta DE, Erickson GM. A second specimen of Citipati osmolskae associated <lb/>with a nest of eggs from Ukhaa Tolgod, Omnogov Aimag, Mongolia. Am Mus Novit. 2018; 3899: 44. <lb/>20. Balanoff AM, Bever GS, Rowe TB, Norell MA. Evolutionary origins of the avian brain. Nature. 2013; <lb/>501: 93-96. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12424 PMID: 23903660 <lb/>21. Xu X, Cheng Y-N, Wang X-L, Chang C-H. An unusual oviraptorosaurian dinosaur from China. Nature. <lb/>2002; 419: 291-293. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature00966 PMID: 12239565 <lb/>22. Smith D. Neues Jahrb Fu ¨r Geol Paläontologie Abh. 1992; 186: 365-388. <lb/>23. Zhou Z-H, Wang X-L. A new species of Caudipteryx from the Yixian Formation of Liaoning, Northeast <lb/>China. Vertebr Palasiat. 2000;38. <lb/>24. Funston GF, Currie PJ, Ryan MJ, Dong Z-M. Birdlike growth and mixed-age flocks in avimimids (Thero-<lb/>poda, Oviraptorosauria). Sci Rep. 2019; 9: 18816. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-55038-5 PMID: <lb/>31827127 <lb/>25. Funston G, Currie P, Eberth D, Ryan M, Chinzorig T, Badamgarav D, et al. The first oviraptorosaur <lb/>(Dinosauria: Theropoda) bonebed: Evidence of gregarious behaviour in a maniraptoran theropod. Sci <lb/>Rep. 2016; 6: 35782. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep35782 PMID: 27767062 <lb/>26. Osborn H. Three new Theropoda, Protoceratops zone, central Mongolia. Am Mus Novit. 1924; 144: 1-12. <lb/>27. Dong Z-M, Currie PJ. On the discovery of an oviraptorid skeleton on a nest of eggs at Bayan Mandahu, <lb/>Inner Mongolia, People&apos;s Republic of China. Can J Earth Sci. 1996; 33: 631-636. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1139/e96-046 <lb/>28. Clark JM, Norell M, Chiappe LM, Project M-AMP, Akademi MSU. An oviraptorid skeleton from the late <lb/>Cretaceous of Ukhaa Tolgod, Mongolia, preserved in an avianlike brooding position over an oviraptorid <lb/>nest. American Museum novitates; no. 3265. 1999 [cited 18 Nov 2020]. Available: http://digitallibrary. <lb/>amnh.org/handle/2246/3102. <lb/>29. Varricchio DJ, Moore JR, Erickson GM, Norell MA, Jackson FD, Borkowski JJ. Avian paternal care had <lb/>dinosaur origin. Science. 2008; 322: 1826-1828. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1163245 PMID: <lb/>19095938 <lb/>30. Fanti F, Currie PJ, Badamgarav D. New Specimens of Nemegtomaia from the Baruungoyot and <lb/>Nemegt Formations (Late Cretaceous) of Mongolia. PLOS ONE. 2012; 7: e31330. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0031330 PMID: 22347465 <lb/>31. Simon DJ, Varricchio DJ, Jackson FD, Robison S. Giant theropod eggs from the Aptian-Cenomanian <lb/>Wayan Formation of Idaho: Taxonomic, paleogeographic and reproductive implications. J Vertebr <lb/>Paleontol Programs Abstr. 2012; 32: 172. <lb/>32. Sato T, Cheng Y-N, Wu X, Zelenitsky DK, Hsiao Y. A pair of shelled eggs inside a female dinosaur. Sci-<lb/>ence. 2005; 308: 375-375. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1110578 PMID: 15831749 <lb/>33. Osmo ´lska H. Evidence on relation of brain to endocranial cavity in oviraptorid dinosaurs. Acta Palaeon-<lb/>tol Pol. 2004; 49: 321-324. <lb/>34. Kundra ´t M. Avian-like attributes of a virtual brain model of the oviraptorid theropod Conchoraptor gracilis. <lb/>Naturwissenschaften. 2007; 94: 499-504. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00114-007-0219-1 PMID: 17277940 <lb/>35. Currie PJ, Russell DA. Osteology and relationships of Chirostenotes pergracilis (Saurischia, Thero-<lb/>poda) from the Judith River (Oldman) Formation of Alberta, Canada. Can J Earth Sci. 1988; 25: 972-<lb/>986. https://doi.org/10.1139/e88-097 <lb/>36. Sues H-D. On Chirostenotes, a Late Cretaceous Oviraptorosaur (Dinosauria: Theropoda) from Western <lb/>North America. J Vertebr Paleontol. 1997; 17: 698-716. <lb/>37. Zanno LE, Sampson SD. A new oviraptorosaur (Theropoda, Maniraptora) from the Late Cretaceous <lb/>(Campanian) of Utah. J Vertebr Paleontol. 2005; 25: 897-904. <lb/>38. Currie PJ, Godfrey SJ, Nessov L. New caenagnathid (Dinosauria: Theropoda) specimens from the <lb/>Upper Cretaceous of North America and Asia. Can J Earth Sci. 1993; 30: 2255-2272. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1139/e93-196 <lb/>39. Funston GF, Currie PJ, Burns ME. New elmisaurine specimens from North America and their relation-<lb/>ship to the Mongolian Elmisaurus rarus. Acta Palaeontol Pol. 2016; 61: 159-173. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>4202/app.00129.2014 <lb/>40. Funston GF, Currie PJ. A previously undescribed caenagnathid mandible from the late Campanian of <lb/>Alberta, and insights into the diet of Chirostenotes pergracilis (Dinosauria: Oviraptorosauria). Sues H, <lb/>editor. Can J Earth Sci. 2014; 51: 156-165. https://doi.org/10.1139/cjes-2013-0186 <lb/>41. Funston G. Caenagnathids of the Dinosaur Park Formation (Campanian) of Alberta, Canada: anatomy, <lb/>osteohistology, taxonomy, and evolution. Vertebr Anat Morphol Palaeontol. 2020; 8: 105-153. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.18435/vamp29362 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>25 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>42. Funston GF, Persons IV S, Bradley GJ, Currie PJ. New material of the large-bodied caenagnathid Cae-<lb/>nagnathus collinsi from the Dinosaur Park Formation of Alberta, Canada. Cretac Res. 2015; 54: 179-<lb/>187. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cretres.2014.12.002 <lb/>43. Currie PJ. The first records of Elmisaurus (Saurischia, Theropoda) from North America. Can J Earth <lb/>Sci. 1989; 26: 1319-1324. https://doi.org/10.1139/e89-111 <lb/>44. Sullivan RM, Jasinski SE. A new caenagnathid Ojoraptorsaurus boerei, N. Gen., N. Sp. (Dinosauria, <lb/>Oviraptorosauria), from the Upper Cretaceous Ojo Alamo Formation (Naashoibito member), San Juan <lb/>basin, New Mexico. Foss Rec. 2011; 3: 418-428. <lb/>45. Longrich NR, Barnes K, Clark S, Millar L. Caenagnathidae from the Upper Campanian Aguja Formation <lb/>of West Texas, and a Revision of the Caenagnathinae. Bull Peabody Mus Nat Hist. 2013; 54: 23-49. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3374/014.054.0102 <lb/>46. Cullen TM, Simon DJ, Benner EKC, Evans DC. Morphology and osteohistology of a large-bodied cae-<lb/>nagnathid (Theropoda, Oviraptorosauria) from the Hell Creek Formation (Montana): implications for <lb/>size-based classifications and growth reconstruction in theropods. Pap Palaeontol. 2020; 1-17. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1002/spp2.1302. <lb/>47. Funston GF, Currie PJ. A new caenagnathid (Dinosauria: Oviraptorosauria) from the Horseshoe Can-<lb/>yon Formation of Alberta, Canada, and a reevaluation of the relationships of Caenagnathidae. J Vertebr <lb/>Paleontol. 2016; 36: e1160910. https://doi.org/10.1080/02724634.2016.1160910 <lb/>48. Ma W, Wang J, Pittman M, Tan Q, Tan L, Guo B, et al. Functional anatomy of a giant toothless mandible <lb/>from a bird-like dinosaur: Gigantoraptor and the evolution of the oviraptorosaurian jaw. Sci Rep. 2017; <lb/>7: 16247. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-15709-7 PMID: 29176627 <lb/>49. Yu Y, Wang K, Chen S, Sullivan C, Wang S, Wang P, et al. A new caenagnathid dinosaur from the <lb/>Upper Cretaceous Wangshi Group of Shandong, China, with comments on size variation among ovirap-<lb/>torosaurs. Sci Rep. 2018; 8: 5030. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-23252-2 PMID: 29567954 <lb/>50. Simon DJ, Varricchio DJ, Jin X, Robison SF. Microstructural overlap of Macroelongatoolithus eggs from <lb/>Asia and North America expands the occurrence of colossal oviraptorosaurs. J Vertebr Paleontol. <lb/>2018; 38: e1553046. https://doi.org/10.1080/02724634.2018.1553046 <lb/>51. Simon DJ, Evans D. Osteohistology supports immature ontogenetic status of North American oviraptor-<lb/>osaurs Apatoraptor pennatus and Chirostenotes pergracilis. J Vertebr Paleontol Programs Abstr. 2021; <lb/>41: 237-238. <lb/>52. Simon DJ, Evans DC. Histological analysis of Anzu wyliei (Dinosauria, Oviraptorosauria) reveals varia-<lb/>tion in adult body size through time. J Vertebr Paleontol Programs Abstr. 2022; 42: 306-307. <lb/>53. Funston GF, Currie PJ, Tsogtbaatar C, Khishigjav T. A partial oviraptorosaur skeleton suggests low <lb/>caenagnathid diversity in the Late Cretaceous Nemegt Formation of Mongolia. PLoS ONE. 2021; 16: <lb/>e0254564. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0254564 PMID: 34252154 <lb/>54. Lamm E-T. Preparation and Sectioning of Specimens. In: Padian K, Lamm E-T, editors. Bone histology <lb/>of fossil tetrapods: advancing methods, analysis, and interpretation. Berkeley, CA: University of Cali-<lb/>fornia Press; 2013. pp. 55-160. Available: https://california.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10. <lb/>1525/california/9780520273528.001.0001/upso-9780520273528-chapter-4 <lb/>55. Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, et al. Fiji: an open-source <lb/>platform for biological-image analysis. Nat Methods. 2012; 9: 676-682. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth. <lb/>2019 PMID: 22743772 <lb/>56. Campione NE, Evans DC, Brown CM, Carrano MT. Body mass estimation in non-avian bipeds using a <lb/>theoretical conversion to quadruped stylopodial proportions. Methods Ecol Evol. 2014; 5: 913-923. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.12226 <lb/>57. Marsh OC. Principal characters of American Jurassic dinosaurs. Am J Sci. 1878;Series 3 Vol. 16: 411-<lb/>416. https://doi.org/10.2475/ajs.s3-16.95.411 <lb/>58. Barsbold R. A new Late Cretaceous family of small theropods (Oviraptoridae n. fam.) in Mongolia. Dokl <lb/>Akad Nauk SSSR. 1976; 226: 221-223. <lb/>59. Sternberg RM. A toothless bird from the Cretaceous of Alberta. J Paleontol. 1940; 14: 81-85. <lb/>60. Johnson KR, Nichols DJ, Hartman JH. Hell Creek Formation: a 2001 synthesis. The Hell Creek Forma-<lb/>tion and the Cretaceous-Tertiary Boundary in the Northern Great Plains: An Integrated Continental <lb/>Record of the End of the Cretaceous. Geological Society of America; 2002. pp. 503-510. <lb/>61. Funston GF, Mendonca SE, Currie PJ, Barsbold R. Oviraptorosaur anatomy, diversity and ecology in <lb/>the Nemegt Basin. Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol. 2018; 494: 101-120. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.palaeo.2017.10.023 <lb/>62. Currie P, Funston G, Osmolska H. New specimens of the crested theropod dinosaur Elmisaurus rarus <lb/>from Mongolia. Acta Palaeontol Pol. 2016 [cited 9 Dec 2020]. https://doi.org/10.4202/app.00130.2014 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>26 / 27 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>63. Tsujimura K, Manabe M, Chiba Y, Tsuihiji T. Metatarsals of a large caenagnathid cf. Anzu wyliei (Thero-<lb/>poda: Oviraptorosauria) from the Hell Creek Formation in South Dakota, U.S.A. Can J Earth Sci. 2021 <lb/>[cited 10 Apr 2021]. https://doi.org/10.1139/cjes-2020-0171 <lb/>64. Osmo ´lska H. Coossified tarsometatarsi in theropod dinosaurs and their bearing on the problem of bird <lb/>origins. Palaeontol Pol. 1981; 42: 79-95. <lb/>65. Hutchinson JR. The evolution of hindlimb tendons and muscles on the line to crown-group birds. Comp <lb/>Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol. 2002; 133: 1051-1086. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1095-6433(02) <lb/>00158-7 PMID: 12485692 <lb/>66. Carrano MT, Hutchinson JR. Pelvic and hindlimb musculature of Tyrannosaurus rex (Dinosauria: Ther-<lb/>opoda). J Morphol. 2002; 253: 207-228. <lb/>67. Enlow DH. Principles of Bone Remodeling: An Account of Post-Natal Growth and Remodeling Pro-<lb/>cesses in Long Bones and the Mandible. Thomas; 1963. <lb/>68. Heck CT, Varricchio DJ, Gaudin TJ, Woodward HN, Horner JR. Ontogenetic changes in the long bone <lb/>microstructure in the nine-banded armadillo (Dasypus novemcinctus). PLOS ONE. 2019; 14: <lb/>e0215655. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215655 PMID: 31022247 <lb/>69. Curtin AJ, Macdowell AA, Schaible EG, Roth VL. Noninvasive histological comparison of bone growth <lb/>patterns among fossil and extant neonatal elephantids using synchrotron radiation X-ray microtomogra-<lb/>phy. J Vertebr Paleontol. 2012; 32: 939-955. https://doi.org/10.1080/02724634.2012.672388 <lb/>70. Curry Rogers K, Whitney M, D&apos;Emic M, Bagley B. Precocity in a tiny titanosaur from the Cretaceous of <lb/>Madagascar. Science. 2016; 352: 450-453. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aaf1509 PMID: 27102482 <lb/>71. Jasmina Hugi, Marcelo R. Sa ´nchez-Villagra. Life History and Skeletal Adaptations in the Galapagos <lb/>Marine Iguana (Amblyrhynchus cristatus) as Reconstructed with Bone Histological Data-A Compara-<lb/>tive Study of Iguanines. J Herpetol. 2012; 46: 312-324. https://doi.org/10.1670/11-071 <lb/>72. Nacarino-Meneses C, Ko ¨hler M. Limb bone histology records birth in mammals. PLOS ONE. 2018; 13: <lb/>e0198511. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0198511 PMID: 29924818 <lb/>73. Funston GF, Currie PJ. A small caenagnathid tibia from the Horseshoe Canyon Formation (Maastrich-<lb/>tian): Implications for growth and lifestyle in oviraptorosaurs. Cretac Res. 2018; 92: 220-230. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.cretres.2018.08.020 <lb/>74. Funston GF, Wilkinson RD, Simon DJ, Leblanc AH, Wosik M, Currie PJ. Histology of Caenagnathid <lb/>(Theropoda, Oviraptorosauria) dentaries and implications for development, ontogenetic edentulism, <lb/>and taxonomy. Anat Rec. 2020; 303: 918-934. https://doi.org/10.1002/ar.24205 PMID: 31270950 <lb/>75. Sander PM. Longbone histology of the Tendaguru sauropods: implications for growth and biology. Paleo-<lb/>biology. 2000; 26: 466-488. https://doi.org/10.1666/0094-8373(2000)026&lt;0466:LHOTTS&gt;2.0.CO;2 <lb/>76. Erickson GM, Curry Rogers K, Varricchio DJ, Norell MA, Xu X. Growth patterns in brooding dinosaurs <lb/>reveals the timing of sexual maturity in non-avian dinosaurs and genesis of the avian condition. Biol <lb/>Lett. 2007; 3: 558-561. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2007.0254 PMID: 17638674 <lb/>77. Lee AH, Werning S. Sexual maturity in growing dinosaurs does not fit reptilian growth models. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci. 2008; 105: 582-587. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0708903105 PMID: 18195356 <lb/>78. Francillon-Vieillot H, Buffre ´nil V de, Castanet J, Ge ´raudie J, Meunier FJ, Sire JY, et al. Microstructure <lb/>and Mineralization of Vertebrate Skeletal Tissues. Skeletal Biomineralization: Patterns, Processes and <lb/>Evolutionary Trends. American Geophysical Union (AGU); 1990. pp. 175-234. https://doi.org/10.1029/ <lb/>SC005p0175 <lb/>79. Woodward HN, Fowler EAF, Farlow JO, Horner JR. Maiasaura, a model organism for extinct vertebrate <lb/>population biology: a large sample statistical assessment of growth dynamics and survivorship. Paleobi-<lb/>ology. 2015; 41: 503-527. https://doi.org/10.1017/pab.2015.19 <lb/>80. Varricchio DJ. Late Cretaceous oviraptorosaur (Theropoda) dinosaurs from Montana. In: Tanke DH, Car-<lb/>penter K, editors. Mesozoic Vertebrate Life. Bloomington: Indiana University Press; 2001. pp. 42-57. <lb/>81. Bell PR, Currie PJ, Russell DA. Large caenagnathids (Dinosauria, Oviraptorosauria) from the upper-<lb/>most Cretaceous of western Canada. Cretac Res. 2015; 52: 101-107. <lb/>82. Rhodes MM, Henderson DM, Currie PJ. Maniraptoran pelvic musculature highlights evolutionary pat-<lb/>terns in theropod locomotion on the line to birds. Hedrick B, editor. PeerJ. 2021; 9: e10855. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.7717/peerj.10855 PMID: 33717681 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New Maastrichtian caenagnathid <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0294901 January 24, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>27 / 27 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>