<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-16T10:57:53.668Z">11/16/2025 10:57:53 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-16T10:57:33.826161Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-16T10:57:33.826161Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
	  <!-- exclude -->
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Investigation on damage evolution <lb/>mechanism of various FRP strengthened <lb/>concrete subjected to chemical-freeze-thaw <lb/>coupling erosion <lb/>Wei Li, Dayang Wang, Wenyuan Xu*, Yongcheng Ji ID * <lb/>School of Civil Engineering and Transportation, Northeast Forestry University, Harbin, 150040, China <lb/>* wenyuanxu@nefu.edu.cn (WX); yongchengji@126.com (YJ) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The corrosion resistance of FRP-reinforced ordinary concrete members under the combined <lb/>action of harsh environments (i.e., alkaline or acidic solutions, salt solutions) and freeze-thaw <lb/>cycles is still unclear. To study the mechanical and apparent deterioration of carbon/basalt/ <lb/>glass/aramid fiber cloth reinforced concrete under chemical and freeze-thaw coupling. Plain <lb/>concrete blocks and FRP-bonded concrete blocks were fabricated. The tensile properties of <lb/>the FRP sheet and epoxy resin sheet before and after chemical freezing, the compressive <lb/>strength of the FRP reinforced test block, and the bending capacity of the prismatic test block <lb/>pasted with FRP on the prefabricated crack side were tested. The deterioration mechanism of <lb/>the test block was analyzed through the change of surface photos. Based on the experimental <lb/>data, the Lam-Teng constitutive model of concrete reinforced by alkali-freeze coupling FRP is <lb/>modified. The results indicate that, in terms of apparent properties, with the increase in the <lb/>duration of chemical freeze-thaw erosion, the surface of epoxy resin sheets exhibits an <lb/>increase in pores, along with the emergence of small cracks and wrinkles. The texture of FRP <lb/>sheets becomes blurred, and cracks and wrinkles appear on the surface. In terms of failure <lb/>modes, as the number of chemical coupling erosion cycles increases, the location of failure in <lb/>epoxy resin sheets becomes uncertain, and the failure plane tilts towards the direction of the <lb/>applied load. The failure mode of FRP sheets remains unchanged. However, the bonding <lb/>strength between FRP sheets and concrete decreases, resulting in a weakened reinforcement <lb/>effect. In terms of mechanical properties, FRP sheets undergo the most severe degradation in <lb/>the coupled environment of acid freeze-thaw cycles. Among them, GFRP experiences the <lb/>largest degradation in tensile strength, reaching up to 30.17%. In terms of tensile performance, <lb/>the sheets rank from highest to lowest as follows: CFRP, BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP.As the <lb/>duration of chemical freeze-coupled erosion increases, the loss rate of compressive strength <lb/>for specimens bonded with CFRP is the smallest (9.62% in salt freeze-thaw environment), <lb/>while the loss rate of bearing capacity is higher for specimens reinforced with GFRP (33.8% in <lb/>acid freeze-thaw environment). In contrast, the loss rate of bearing capacity is lower for speci-<lb/>mens reinforced with CFRP (13.6% in salt freeze-thaw environment), but still higher for speci-<lb/>mens reinforced with GFRP (25.8% in acid freeze-thaw environment). <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/>1 / 41 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Li W, Wang D, Xu W, Ji Y (2024) <lb/>Investigation on damage evolution mechanism of <lb/>various FRP strengthened concrete subjected to <lb/>chemical-freeze-thaw coupling erosion. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(5): e0303645. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0303645 <lb/>Editor: Mohammadreza Vafaei, Universiti Teknologi <lb/>Malaysia, MALAYSIA <lb/>Received: February 14, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: April 29, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 21, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Li et al. This is an open access <lb/>article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original author and <lb/>source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript. <lb/>Funding: the Science and Technology Project of <lb/>Heilongjiang Provincial Department of <lb/>Transportation (2021-HLJ-0021). <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>In 1981, the Swedish engineer Meier proposed the concept of fiber-reinforced materials (FRP) <lb/>and reinforced it with adhesive CFRP for the first time on Ebach Bridge. Since then, fiber-rein-<lb/>forced materials have been developed with many different types of FRP materials and have <lb/>been widely used in other fields [1]. It can be roughly divided into three categories: carbon <lb/>fiber CFRP, polymer fiber including aramid fiber (AFRP), and inorganic fiber including glass <lb/>fiber (GFRP) [2,3], which has a good repair and protection effect on concrete structures [4]. <lb/>Many existing buildings in the construction industry are faced with the dilemma of mainte-<lb/>nance and reconstruction [5]. Compared with other repair methods, FRP materials have been <lb/>widely studied because of their characteristics, such as corrosion resistance, high strength, and <lb/>light unit weight [6], especially their corrosion resistance in harsh environments. At the same <lb/>time, compared with other materials, FRP materials require less material for the substructure <lb/>with the same strength due to their lightweight, which can effectively reduce carbon emissions <lb/>[7]. Although FRP materials have been studied for decades, from birth to now, and much <lb/>progress has been made, many problems still need to be solved. For example, corrosion in <lb/>harsh environments (i.e., water, alkaline or acidic solutions, salt solutions) results in severe <lb/>damage to degradation. The relative slip of concrete and FRP fiber cloth leads to problems <lb/>such as interface debonding, which leads to the failure of the whole structure [8-14]. After ero-<lb/>sion, the strength, stiffness, and other properties of the concrete structure reinforced with FRP <lb/>fiber cloth will decrease [15]. Zhou et al. studied the bonding ability of concrete bond samples <lb/>strengthened by CFRP after a sulfate attack. The experiment showed that sulfate attack seri-<lb/>ously eroded the bonding property of the interface between CFRP and concrete, and the bond-<lb/>ing property decreased under the circulation of high temperature and high humidity of sulfate <lb/>solution [16]. In winter, civil structures exposed to Marine environments or deicing salts are <lb/>usually affected by the saline-alkali environment, and salt erosion causes the intermolecular <lb/>chemical bonds within the matrix and fiber-matrix interface to break or generate strain [17]. <lb/>At the same time, the mechanical degradation of polymer resins commonly used to bond FRP <lb/>materials will produce undesirable effects, such as plasticization and hydrolysis under humid-<lb/>ity conditions [18]. The freeze-thaw cycle and its related coupling effects will deteriorate FRP <lb/>composites [19]. FRP materials will become brittle under freezing conditions, absorb water, <lb/>and expand during freezing, resulting in micro-cracks, which are especially prone to occur at <lb/>the interface between FRP materials and substrates [20]. In addition, the high pressure in con-<lb/>crete leads to the growth of ice crystals that would be generated during repeated freeze-thaw <lb/>cycles and produce micro-cracks, thus reducing the bond strength between FRP and concrete <lb/>[21]. Therefore, the increase in the bearing capacity of FRP-reinforced specimens after the <lb/>freeze-thaw cycle is lower than that of FRP-reinforced specimens at room temperature [22]. <lb/>FRP generally exhibits high specific strength, light weight, and high modulus, making it suit-<lb/>able for concrete reinforcement. Additionally, CFRP boasts excellent corrosion resistance. <lb/>GFRP offers good design flexibility and has a linear expansion coefficient close to that of con-<lb/>crete. AFRP, on the other hand, exhibits superior fatigue resistance. BFRP falls between CFRP <lb/>and GFRP in terms of strength, but it outperforms CFRP in ductility and significantly exceeds <lb/>the other three reinforcement materials in high-temperature resistance. Therefore, selecting <lb/>the appropriate type of FRP for a specific environment can maximize its characteristics and <lb/>performance. <lb/>In addition, the failure mode of the specimen will also change after the freeze-thaw cycle. <lb/>The cohesive fracture of concrete without environmental action changes to the cohesive inter-<lb/>face failure after multiple cycles, and the deterioration of FRP and coagulation interface is rela-<lb/>tively more severe under the freeze-thaw cycle [23]. The salt-freeze-thaw coupling test shows <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>that the strength and ductility of specimens restrained by CFRP and GFRP significantly <lb/>decrease, but the stiffness is unaffected. Compared with specimens subjected to room tempera-<lb/>ture and dry and wet cycling, the failure mode of specimens subjected to freeze-thaw action is <lb/>more disastrous [24]. Masmoudi et al. [25] studied the freeze-thaw cycling effects of concrete <lb/>reinforced with glass fiber reinforced pipes and mixed with decommissioned wind turbine <lb/>fiber materials. The confinement provided by the glass fiber reinforced pipes significantly <lb/>improved the compressive strength of all samples and had a positive impact on the freeze-thaw <lb/>durability of enclosed samples. Zou et al. [26] studied the durability of CFRP and GFRP <lb/>bonded pre-cracked concrete beams under three unfavorable conditions: freeze-thaw cycling, <lb/>sulfate attack, and coupled salt-freeze erosion. After 400 hours of exposure to these three <lb/>adverse conditions, the strength loss of CFRP-bonded concrete flexural specimens was 42.0%, <lb/>14.6%, and 66.3%, respectively. Similarly, the strength loss of GFRP-bonded concrete flexural <lb/>specimens was 52.3%, 21.9%, and 67%, respectively. Maras et al. [27] studied the performance <lb/>of reinforced concrete beam column connections reinforced with CFRP, GFRP, and AFRP <lb/>under load. Compared with the control specimens, the ultimate load increased by a maximum <lb/>of 12.5% after CFRP reinforcement. CFRP composite materials can be a suitable alternative to <lb/>significantly improve structural performance. A study was conducted on the axial compression <lb/>test of a new type of FRP made outer tube, steel made inner tube composition, and a space <lb/>filled concrete mixed column. It was found that GFRP tubes enhance structural behavior by <lb/>providing constraints on concrete and additional shear resistance [28].Yan et al. [29]studied <lb/>the compressive performance of FRP wrapped 3D printed ultra-high performance concrete <lb/>components, and the reinforcement of FRP significantly improved the strength and deforma-<lb/>tion capacity of ultra-high performance concrete components. Kantarci et al. [30] studied the <lb/>bending behavior of reinforced concrete beams reinforced with aluminum honeycomb sand-<lb/>wich panels and CFRP with different cross-sectional configurations (i.e. supports and interme-<lb/>diate parts). The reinforced concrete beams reinforced with 15 mm thick aluminum <lb/>honeycomb sandwich panels and CFRP showed higher bending resistance and stronger ductil-<lb/>ity than similar products. <lb/>In an acidic environment and seawater environment, it is found that the bond durability of <lb/>FRP and concrete and steel structure shows a downward trend, and the alkaline environment <lb/>with a pH value of 12 has the most significant influence on the bond of FRP and steel structure. <lb/>Although the steel structure will not suffer more corrosion damage in the alkaline environ-<lb/>ment, the alkaline environment dramatically affects the interface between FRP and steel struc-<lb/>ture, resulting in a considerable decline in bond strength [31]. In addition, the corrosive <lb/>environment not only reduces the ultimate bearing capacity of the beam but also changes the <lb/>failure form of the beam, and the bond between concrete and FRP materials will degrade in <lb/>the corrosive environment [32]. Moreover, the stripping of the loading end will change the <lb/>tensile force distribution along the bonding interface into an uneven nonlinear distribution, <lb/>which significantly increases the length of the tensile force transferred from the plate to the <lb/>concrete specimen [33]. <lb/>In summary, there is still a lack of research on the performance of FRP-reinforced concrete <lb/>members under the coupled effects of harsh chemical environments and freeze-thaw cycles. <lb/>The durability performance is still unclear and further exploration is urgently needed. <lb/>Although efforts have been made to improve the effectiveness of glass fiber-reinforced materi-<lb/>als, their applications still need to be expanded to solve simple structural problems. This may <lb/>be related to the need for design specifications, the wide variation in material properties of <lb/>FRP materials, and the limited knowledge of engineers about the application and structure of <lb/>FRP materials [34]. From the perspective of chemical-freeze-thaw coupling erosion, this paper <lb/>tries to analyze the durability influencing factors of concrete reinforced with fiber cloth in <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>practical engineering and study the mechanical and apparent deterioration laws of concrete <lb/>reinforced with carbon/basalt/glass/aramid fiber cloth under chemical and freeze-thaw <lb/>coupling. <lb/>Experimental programs <lb/>Specimen and erosion environment <lb/>This experiment used concrete with a design strength of 30 MPa. Its composition materials <lb/>were water, cement, fine aggregate, and coarse aggregate, with a ratio of 0.54:1:1.64:3.02. The <lb/>cement is Swan P.O42.5 ordinary Portland cement produced by Jilin Yatai Cement Co., LTD. <lb/>The fine aggregate is medium sand with a fineness modulus 2.4, taken from local river sand. <lb/>The coarse aggregate is gravel. The 5-10mm particle size accounted for 30%, and 10-20mm <lb/>accounted for 70%. <lb/>Four representative fiber-reinforced composites (FRP) were selected for concrete reinforce-<lb/>ment, namely carbon fiber composite (CFRP), basalt fiber composite (BFRP), glass fiber com-<lb/>posite (GFRP), and aramid fiber composite (AFRP), as shown in Fig 1. Fiber composite <lb/>material is bonded to concrete by epoxy resin adhesive. The adhesive is divided into A and B <lb/>components, including curing agent and epoxy resin (Fig 2). After seven days, the curing <lb/>Fig 1. Four kinds of fiber composites:(a) CFRP, (b) GFRP, (c) BFRP, (d) AFRP. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g001 <lb/>Fig 2. Epoxy resin glue. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>degree of epoxy resin is 95%. The epoxy resin and CFRP manufacturer is Shanghai Jingdong <lb/>Construction Technology Co., LTD. (Shanghai, China). The primary mechanical indexes of <lb/>the four fiber composite materials and epoxy resin adhesive are shown in Table 1. <lb/>Preparation of fiber cloth sheet and reinforced concrete <lb/>In order to test the effect of chemical-freeze-thaw cycle erosion from the material point of <lb/>view, epoxy resin adhesive and fiber sheet samples were prepared. Epoxy resin adhesive sam-<lb/>ple, as shown in Fig 3), epoxy resin adhesive is composed of curing agent and resin and mixed <lb/>with a mass ratio of 1:2. A fiber cloth (standard thickness of 0.165 mm) was coated with epoxy <lb/>resin adhesive on both sides to make a fiber composite specimen as shown in Fig 4. <lb/>FRP materials possess high elastic modulus and tensile strength. When wrapped around <lb/>concrete, they can increase the compressive resistance of concrete columns due to the confin-<lb/>ing pressure effect. Additionally, attaching FRP materials to the underside of beams can <lb/>enhance the bearing capacity and ductility of concrete beams. Furthermore, for damaged con-<lb/>crete structures exhibiting issues such as cracks and peeling, FRP reinforcement technology <lb/>can effectively repair and strengthen them, restoring their original bearing capacity and func-<lb/>tionality. Cylindrical specimens with a diameter of 100mm and a height of 200mm were made, <lb/>as well as prismatic specimens with a length of 100mm, a width of 100mm, and a height of <lb/>400mm. After mold removal, the specimens were cured for 24 hours under natural conditions <lb/>and put at room temperature (20±2)˚C, relative humidity 95%, and curing room for 28 days. <lb/>Table 1. Properties of fiber composites and epoxy resin adhesives. <lb/>Material <lb/>Strength/MPa <lb/>Elasticity modulus/GPa <lb/>Elongation at break/% <lb/>CFRP <lb/>3520 <lb/>267 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>BFRP <lb/>3000 <lb/>120 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>GFRP <lb/>2500 <lb/>80 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>AFRP <lb/>2106 <lb/>117.8 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>Epoxy resin <lb/>54.3 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.t001 <lb/>Fig 3. Epoxy resin: (a) Epoxy resin specimen, (b)Specimen size diagram (unit: mm). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g003 <lb/>Fig 4. Fiber composite material specimen: (a) Fiber composite specimen, (b) FRP sheet size (unit: mm). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>The concrete cylindrical specimen is pasted with fiber cloth using the wet adhesion method. <lb/>First, the outer surface of the specimen is polished and smooth, and the surface of each speci-<lb/>men is cleaned with a brush to remove unnecessary dust and cement particles. The selected <lb/>cylinder is wrapped in a single fiber cloth (200 mm wide, 340mm long, 0.165mm thick) and <lb/>bonded with epoxy resin. The outer wrapping circumference of the fiber cloth is 25mm so that <lb/>the CFRP material is not wasted but also to prevent the interface from sticking. The top and <lb/>bottom of the FRP-wrapped cylinders are covered with epoxy resin (approximately 5mm <lb/>thick) to avoid direct contact with the concrete surface with the chemical environment <lb/>through unwrapped areas. According to the manufacturer&apos;s technical data, the concrete speci-<lb/>men reinforced with fiber cloth must be cured for seven days at room temperature. The con-<lb/>crete compression specimen reinforced with fiber cloth is shown in Fig 5. <lb/>The bending specimens of concrete prisms are manufactured according to the bonding test <lb/>method in the specification (as shown in Fig 6). In order to study the influence of FRP <lb/>strengthening on the bending properties and durability of the bending specimens, the bending <lb/>specimens of unreinforced concrete (6(a)~(b)) and the bending specimens of FRP reinforced <lb/>concrete (6(c)~(f)) are designed. Cracks with a height of 40mm are prefabricated on the mid-<lb/>span tension side of the unreinforced concrete bending specimen, as shown in Fig 6(A) and 6 <lb/>(B). Visually verify that there are no microcracks near the cut tip, then clean the specimen with <lb/>a spray gun and rinse with water to remove concrete residue. The fibers are surface-polished <lb/>before being attached to them. Epoxy adhesive is applied evenly to the jagged concrete surface. <lb/>One layer of unidirectional drying fiber cloth (100 mm wide x 300 mm long) is coated with <lb/>epoxy resin glue to form a fiber cloth composite system, followed by another layer of epoxy <lb/>resin on the other side and cured at room temperature for 7 days. <lb/>Specimen exposure environment <lb/>In order to simulate the coupled environment of chemical and freeze-thaw cyclic erosion of <lb/>FRP reinforced concrete deterioration, the tests were conducted according to GB/T 50082-<lb/>2009 &quot;Standard for Experimental Methods of Long-term Performance and Durability of ordi-<lb/>nary Concrete&quot; and freeze-thaw cyclic experiments were conducted by using the quick-<lb/>Fig 5. Fiber cloth reinforced concrete compression specimen: (a) CFRP, (b) BFRP, (c) GFRP, (d) AFRP. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>freezing method. The test equipment is shown in Fig 7. During the freeze-thaw cycle, the <lb/>freeze-thaw cycle temperature was set as 5±2˚C at high temperature and -17±2˚C at low tem-<lb/>perature. The freeze-thaw cycle medium was 5% H2SO4 solution with mass concentration, <lb/>2mol/L NaOH solution, or 3.5% NaCl solution with mass fraction, which were acid-freeze <lb/>environment, alkali-freeze environment, salt-freeze environment coupled with thaw cycle. <lb/>Epoxy resin adhesive, FRP sheet, and concrete specimen are put into a freeze-thaw circulation <lb/>box. The time to complete a freeze-thaw cycle test was 4 hours, and the surface observation <lb/>and mechanical test were carried out after 0, 50, and 100 freeze-thaw cycles, respectively. <lb/>Microscopic observation <lb/>In civil engineering, digital microscopes can study the microstructure and properties of concrete, <lb/>steel, and wood. The cracks and damage inside concrete can be observed by digital microscope, <lb/>the microstructure and mechanical properties of FRP sheets can be analyzed, and the fiber struc-<lb/>ture and durability of FRP sheets can be studied. This information is essential for evaluating the <lb/>properties of materials and designing civil engineering structures. In order to study the degree of <lb/>damage to the concrete specimen, epoxy resin adhesive, and four kinds of FRP sheet in a coupled <lb/>erosion environment, the surface of the specimen was observed using a BKM-X500 digital micro-<lb/>scope. Samples of acid-freeze-thaw, alkali-freeze-thaw, and salt-freeze-thaw cycles were selected <lb/>for 50 and 100 freeze-thaw cycles. At the same time, the non-deteriorated sheet was observed for <lb/>comparison, and the observation ratio was 100 times, as shown in Fig 8. <lb/>Mechanical test <lb/>Tensile test. According to the difference of environment and cycle, the epoxy resin adhesive <lb/>and CFRP, BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP sheets are grouped and numbered, with five sheets in each <lb/>group, a total of 225 sheets, as shown in Fig 2 below. EPN represents epoxy resin film without <lb/>Fig 6. FRP reinforced bending specimen:(a) Unreinforced bending specimen, (b) Slotted bending specimen, (c) CFRP <lb/>reinforced bending specimen, (d) BFRP reinforced bending specimen, (e) GFRP reinforced bending specimen, (f) <lb/>AFRP reinforced bending specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 7. Chemistry-freeze-thaw cycle coupled immersion environment. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g007 <lb/>Fig 8. Specimen microscopic observation: (a) Epoxy resin, (b) FRP sheet, (c) FRP reinforced concrete, (d) FRP <lb/>reinforced concrete cross section resin. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g008 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>coupling erosion, EPAC-F50 represents epoxy resin film that has experienced 50 times acid-freeze <lb/>coupling erosion, and EPAC-F100 represents epoxy resin film that has experienced 100 times <lb/>acid-freeze coupling erosion. For the fiber sheet number: CSAC-F0 represents the carbon fiber <lb/>sheet without coupling erosion; CSAC-F50 represents the carbon fiber sheet that has experienced <lb/>50 times acid-freeze coupling erosion; CFA-F100 represents the carbon fiber sheet that has experi-<lb/>enced 100 times acid-freeze coupling erosion. Other fiber sheets are numbered in Table 2 below. <lb/>In order to investigate the influence of an acid-freeze-thaw coupled erosion environment <lb/>on the mechanical properties of epoxy resin adhesive and FRP sheet, the tensile tests of epoxy <lb/>resin adhesive and FRP sheet were conducted. The tensile test is a loading process that com-<lb/>prises a mechanical control system and a data acquisition system. The former is responsible <lb/>for controlling the loading rate and collecting load data, and the sheet is stretched by control-<lb/>ling the mechanical testing machine; the latter is responsible for collecting strain gauge data. <lb/>In order to obtain the strain in the tensile direction of the sheet, the strain gauge is pasted in <lb/>the middle of the standard distance segment of the sheet, and the loading rate is 2mm/min. <lb/>The loading and collection process is shown in Fig 9. <lb/>Compression test. According to the difference in environment and period, the unrein-<lb/>forced specimens and FRP-reinforced specimens were grouped and numbered, with six speci-<lb/>mens (three cylindrical test blocks and 3 prismatic test blocks) in each group, as shown in <lb/>Table 3. <lb/>The compressive strength of cylindrical specimens was determined according to the com-<lb/>pressive strength test method of the standard for Testing methods of mechanical properties of <lb/>Table 2. Numbers of epoxy resin and fiber sheets. <lb/>Sheet type Freeze-thaw cycle Acid-freeze coupling erosion specimen <lb/>No. <lb/>Alkali-freeze coupling erosion specimen <lb/>No. <lb/>Salt-freeze coupling erosion specimen <lb/>No. <lb/>Epoxy <lb/>resin <lb/>0 <lb/>EPN-F0 <lb/>EPN-F0 <lb/>EPN-F0 <lb/>CFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>0 <lb/>CSN-F0 <lb/>CSN-F0 <lb/>CSN-F0 <lb/>BFRP sheet <lb/>0 <lb/>BSN-F0 <lb/>BSN-F0 <lb/>BSN-F0 <lb/>GFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>0 <lb/>GSN-F0 <lb/>GSN-F0 <lb/>GSN-F0 <lb/>AFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>0 <lb/>ASN-F0 <lb/>ASN-F0 <lb/>ASN-F0 <lb/>Epoxy <lb/>resin <lb/>50 <lb/>EPAC-F50 <lb/>EPAL-F50 <lb/>EPSA-F50 <lb/>CFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>50 <lb/>CSAC-F50 <lb/>CSAL-F50 <lb/>CSSA-F50 <lb/>BFRP sheet <lb/>50 <lb/>BSAC-F50 <lb/>BSAL-F50 <lb/>BSSA-F50 <lb/>GFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>50 <lb/>GSAC-F50 <lb/>GSAL-F50 <lb/>GSSA-F50 <lb/>AFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>50 <lb/>ASAC-F50 <lb/>ASAL-F50 <lb/>ASSA-F50 <lb/>Epoxy <lb/>resin <lb/>100 <lb/>EPAC-F100 <lb/>EPAL-F100 <lb/>EPSA-F100 <lb/>CFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>100 <lb/>CSAC-F100 <lb/>CSAL-F100 <lb/>CSSA-F100 <lb/>BFRP sheet <lb/>100 <lb/>BSAC-F100 <lb/>BSAL-F100 <lb/>BSSA-F100 <lb/>GFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>100 <lb/>GSAC-F100 <lb/>GSAL-F100 <lb/>GSSA-F100 <lb/>AFRP <lb/>sheet <lb/>100 <lb/>ASAC-F100 <lb/>ASAL-F100 <lb/>ASSA-F100 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>ordinary Concrete (GB/T 50081-2016). The cylindrical specimen is placed between the upper <lb/>and lower pressure plates, and the center of the specimen is aligned with the center of the pres-<lb/>sure plate. In the compression test, the loading speed is 0.3MPa/s. The compression test and <lb/>bending test are shown in Fig 10. <lb/>FRP Reinforced concrete prism. The flexural load of prisms and fiber-reinforced prisms <lb/>was tested according to the flexural test method of Standard for Test Methods of Mechanical <lb/>Properties of Ordinary Concrete (GB/T 50081-2016). The flexure specimens&apos; mid-span deflec-<lb/>tion and prisms&apos; flexure strength were tested by displacement meter. The four-point loading <lb/>test method was adopted. A steel stirrup was fixed on one side of the specimen, and the other <lb/>side was pasted with a strain gauge of 2cm length at the midline of the bottom surface of the <lb/>specimen (FRP surface) to measure the strain change during loading. The loading speed is set <lb/>to 0.03MPa/s. In order to discuss the bonding performance between FRP and concrete, strain <lb/>gauges are pasted on the surface of FRP. The dimensions, loading points, and strain gauge dis-<lb/>tribution points of FRP-reinforced specimens are shown in Fig 11. <lb/>Microscopic analysis <lb/>Microscopic observation of epoxy resin <lb/>Fig 12(A) shows an electron microscope image of an epoxy resin specimen subjected to sulfu-<lb/>ric acid-freeze-thaw cycle erosion. At 100 magnification factor, the epoxy resin specimen <lb/>(EPAC-F50) showed small holes and irregular white spots on its surface after 50 cycles of cou-<lb/>pling erosion. The color changes dramatically, from yellow to yellow-green. This bleaching <lb/>effect is characteristic of materials typically eroded by sulfuric acid. After 100 cycles of acid-<lb/>freeze-thaw coupled erosion, the surface holes of the epoxy sheet (EPAC-F100) were increas-<lb/>ingly damaged, and ample area folds appeared. The discontinuous white spots on the surface <lb/>Fig 9. Tensile mechanical test. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g009 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 3. Summary of the number of acid-freeze-thaw coupled erosion specimens. <lb/>Specimen type <lb/>Freeze-thaw <lb/>cycle <lb/>Acid-freeze coupling erosion <lb/>specimen No. <lb/>Alkali-freeze coupling erosion <lb/>specimen No. <lb/>Salt-freeze coupling erosion <lb/>specimen No. <lb/>Unreinforced specimen <lb/>0 <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>CFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>0 <lb/>CCAC-F0 <lb/>CCAL-F0 <lb/>CCSA-F0 <lb/>BFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>0 <lb/>BCAC-F0 <lb/>BCAL-F0 <lb/>BCSA-F0 <lb/>GFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>0 <lb/>GCAC-F0 <lb/>GCAL-F0 <lb/>GCSA-F0 <lb/>AFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>0 <lb/>ACAC-F0 <lb/>ACAL-F0 <lb/>ACSA-F0 <lb/>Unreinforced specimen <lb/>50 <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>CFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>50 <lb/>CCAC-F50 <lb/>CCAL-F50 <lb/>CCSA-F50 <lb/>BFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>50 <lb/>BCAC-F50 <lb/>BCAL-F50 <lb/>BCSA-F50 <lb/>GFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>50 <lb/>GCAC-F50 <lb/>GCAL-F50 <lb/>GCSA-F50 <lb/>AFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>50 <lb/>ACAC-F50 <lb/>ACAL-F50 <lb/>ACSA-F50 <lb/>Unreinforced specimen <lb/>100 <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>Control group <lb/>CFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>100 <lb/>CCAC-F100 <lb/>CCAL-F100 <lb/>CCSA-F100 <lb/>BFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>100 <lb/>BCAC-F100 <lb/>BCAL-F100 <lb/>BCSA-F100 <lb/>GFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>100 <lb/>GCAC-F100 <lb/>GCAL-F100 <lb/>GCSA-F100 <lb/>AFRP reinforced <lb/>concrete <lb/>100 <lb/>ACAC-F100 <lb/>ACAL-F100 <lb/>ACSA-F100 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.t003 <lb/>Fig 10. Mechanical test device. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g010 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>spread randomly due to the chemical reaction of calcium ions in epoxy resin with sulfate ions <lb/>in sulfuric acid solution to produce white calcium sulfate. These observations show that the <lb/>epoxy initially reacts with sulfuric acid on its surface and that, over time, the sulfuric acid pene-<lb/>trates the inside of the epoxy, causing the overall performance of the epoxy to decline. <lb/>Fig 11. Bending specimen size and strain gauge layout (unit: mm). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g011 <lb/>Fig 12. Microscopic imaging of epoxy resin: (a) acid-freeze cycle erosion, (b) alkali-freeze cycle erosion, (c) salt-freeze <lb/>cycle erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g012 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 12(B) shows an electron microscope image of an epoxy resin specimen subjected to <lb/>alkali-freeze-thaw cycle erosion. Under the magnification factor of 100 times, the surface color <lb/>of the epoxy resin specimen changed obviously after 50 freeze-thaw cycles. Some white spots <lb/>were observed attached to its surface, and tiny holes appeared on the surface of the epoxy <lb/>resin. As the freeze-thaw cycle increases to 100 times, due to the continuous development and <lb/>formation of these substances, the white adhesion expands into random shapes; tiny cracks <lb/>appear, holes expand, and the surface of the epoxy resin wrinkles. Fig 12(C) shows an electron <lb/>microscope image of an epoxy resin specimen subjected to salt-freeze-thaw cycle erosion. <lb/>Under the amplification factor of 100 times, the surface color of the epoxy resin specimen <lb/>EPS-F50 changed obviously after 50 freeze-thaw cycles. Some white sodium chloride crystals <lb/>were observed attached to its surface, and tiny holes appeared on the surface of the epoxy <lb/>resin. When the freeze-thaw cycle was increased to 100 times, the substances attached to the <lb/>specimen EPS-F100 continued to develop and form, and the sodium chloride crystal attach-<lb/>ments expanded and formed into random shapes, with tiny cracks and enlarged holes, and the <lb/>surface of the epoxy resin showed folds. In summary, the deterioration of epoxy resin sheets <lb/>increases with the increase of the chemical-freeze erosion cycle. The surface holes increase and <lb/>the surface cracks and folds appear. <lb/>Microscopic observation of FRP sheet <lb/>Fig 13(A)-13(D) show the electron microscope imaging of the FRP sheet at 100 times magnifi-<lb/>cation. The fiber sheets (CSAC-F0, BSAC-F0, GSAC-F0, ASAC-F0), which have not been sub-<lb/>jected to coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycles, are bright and shiny in color, and the texture of their <lb/>internal fiber cloth is visible. After 50 times of acid-freeze-thaw coupling erosion (CSAC-F50-<lb/>100, BSAC-F50-100, GSAC-F50-100, ASAC-F50-100), the color changes of four kinds of fiber <lb/>sheets were noticeable. Due to the corrosive effect of external sulfuric acid on the epoxy resin, <lb/>the internal texture of the fiber sheet has become blurred, and there are holes. White calcium <lb/>sulfate is attached to the surface of basalt fiber and glass fiber sheet. The fiber sheets <lb/>(CSAC-F100-100, BSAC-F100-100, GSAC-F100-100, ASAC-F100-100) experienced 100 times <lb/>coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycle erosion, similar to the surface of the epoxy resin specimen; the <lb/>white adhesion expanded, the surface cracks and folds appeared. <lb/>Fig 14(A)-14(D) show the electron microscope imaging of the FRP sheet at 100 times mag-<lb/>nification. The fiber sheets (CSN-F0-100, BSN-F0-100, GSN-F0-100, ASN-F0-100) that have <lb/>not been subjected to alkalinity-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion have bright and shiny col-<lb/>ors, and the texture of their internal fiber cloth is visible. After 50 times of acid-freeze-thaw <lb/>coupling erosion (CSAL-F50, BSAL-F50, GSAL-F50, ASAL-F50), the color changes of four <lb/>kinds of fiber sheets were noticeable. Due to the corrosive effect of the external sodium <lb/>hydroxide solution on the epoxy resin, the internal texture of the fiber sheet has become <lb/>blurred, and there are holes. There is white adhesion on the surface of the basalt fiber and glass <lb/>fiber sheet. The fiber sheets (CSAL-F100, BSAL-F100, GSAL-F100, ASAL-F100), which had <lb/>undergone 100 times coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycles, were similar to the surface of the epoxy <lb/>resin specimens, and the white adhesion expanded, and cracks and folds appeared on the <lb/>surface. <lb/>Fig 15(A)-15(D) show the electron microscope imaging of the FRP sheet at 100 times <lb/>magnification. The fiber sheets (CSN-F0, BSN-F0, GSN-F0, ASN-F0) that have not been <lb/>subjected to the coupled salt-freeze-thaw cycle erosion are bright and shiny, and the texture <lb/>of the fiber fabric inside is visible. After 50 times of acid-freeze-thaw coupling erosion <lb/>(CSS-F50, BSS-F50, GSS-F50, ASS-F50), the color changes of four kinds of fiber sheets were <lb/>noticeable. Due to the corrosive effect of the external sodium hydroxide solution on the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>epoxy resin, the internal texture of the fiber sheet has become blurred, and there are holes. <lb/>There is white adhesion on the surface of the basalt fiber and glass fiber sheet. After 100 <lb/>cycles of coupled salt-freeze-thaw erosion (CSS-F100, BSS-F100, GSS-F100, ASS-F100), <lb/>similar to the surface of the epoxy resin specimen, the white adhesion expanded, and the <lb/>surface showed cracks and folds. <lb/>In summary, the surface of the FRP sheet is smooth, and the texture is clear without chemi-<lb/>cal-frost coupling erosion. After freezing and thawing in different chemical environments, the <lb/>texture of FRP sheets is blurred, holes appear, and cracks and folds appear on the surface. <lb/>Digital microscopic observation of specimen cross section <lb/>In order to investigate the damage to the concrete specimen caused by the coupled chemical <lb/>freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment, the specimen was cut at 1/2 height. The surface of the <lb/>Fig 13. Microscopic imaging of acid-frost erosion FRP sheets: (a) CFRP, (b) BFRP, (c) GFRP, (d) AFRP. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g013 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>specimen was washed and dried, and the specimen&apos;s cross-section was observed by a digital <lb/>microscope with an observation factor of 100. Fig 8(D) shows the specimen&apos;s sampling point. <lb/>Fiber cloth-reinforced specimens with 50 and 100 coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycles and axial <lb/>compression specimens not reinforced with fiber cloth were selected for observation and com-<lb/>parative analysis, and the micromorphologies of the specimens were shown in Figs 16 and 17. <lb/>Under the coupling erosion of 50 and 100 times acid-freeze-thaw cycles, the cross-section <lb/>microstructure of the unreinforced specimen is shown in Fig 16. PAC1-F100 and PAC1-F50 <lb/>are the positions near the outer edge point 1 on the cross-section, and the coupling erosion is <lb/>the most serious. A large amount of white calcium sulfate is generated inside the specimen. <lb/>PAC2-F50 and PAC2-F100 are the locations of observation points 2, where cracks are <lb/>observed in the cross-section, and a small amount of calcium sulfate is observed at <lb/>PAC2-F100. The locations of observation point 3 are shown in Fig 8(D). PAC3-F50 and <lb/>Fig 14. Microscopic imaging of alkali-freeze erosion FRP sheets: (a) CFRP, (b) BFRP, (c) GFRP, (d) AFRP. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g014 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>PAC3-F100. The internal microstructure of specimens can be seen through observation. After <lb/>100 freeze-thaw cycles, cracks appear in ITZ, the interface transition zone between aggregate <lb/>and cement slurry in the cross-section of specimens PAC3-F100, the weakest concrete area. <lb/>Fig 17(A)-17(H) show the microstructure of FRP-reinforced specimens under acid-freeze-<lb/>thaw cyclic erosion. Fig 17(A), 17(B), 17(F) and 17(H), respectively, show the microscopic <lb/>morphology of the cross-section of the reinforced specimens with carbon fiber and aramid <lb/>fiber. No apparent damage was observed under the microscope, and no micro-cracks appeared <lb/>in the cross-section of the reinforced specimens. Fig 17(C) and 17(E) show basalt and glass <lb/>fiber&apos;s microscopic morphology under 50 cycles of acid-freeze-thaw erosion, respectively. It <lb/>can be seen from the microscopic imaging at 1 point of cross section that there are holes and <lb/>damage in the epoxy resin adhesive matrix in the FRP strip area. With the increase of the cou-<lb/>pling erosion period, the damage became more serious, but no apparent damage, such as frac-<lb/>ture and wire drawing, was found. The freeze-thaw cycle hurts the bond interface between <lb/>Fig 15. Microscopic imaging of salt-freeze erosion FRP sheets: (a) CFRP, (b) BFRP, (c) GFRP, (d) AFRP. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g015 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>composite materials and concrete. After all, when pasting FRP or resin curing process, the <lb/>bond interface between FRP and concrete will inevitably have pores, cracks, and impurities. In <lb/>the melting state, water is immersed in these gaps, and when the temperature is lower than <lb/>0˚C, the water icing volume expansion generates pressure. Cracks occur when the pressure <lb/>exceeds the strength of the material. Cracks appeared on the surfaces of BAC2-F100 and <lb/>GAC2-F100, and the crack propagation was evident with the increase of the coupling erosion <lb/>Fig 16. Microstructure of cross section of unreinforced specimen(a) Under 50 cycles of acid freeze-thaw erosion <lb/>conditions, (b) Under 100 cycles of acid freeze-thaw erosion conditions. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g016 <lb/>Fig 17. Microstructure of FRP reinforced specimens: (a) CFRP reinforced specimens subjected to 50 cycles of acid <lb/>freeze cycles, (b) CFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of acid freeze cycles; (c) BFRP specimens subjected to 50 <lb/>cycles of acid freeze cycles, (d) BFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of acid freeze cycles, (e) GFRP specimens <lb/>subjected to 50 cycles of acid freeze cycles, (f) GFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of acid freeze cycles, (g) AFRP <lb/>specimens subjected to 50 cycles of acid freeze cycles, (h) AFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of acid freeze cycles. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g017 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>period, as shown in Fig 17(D) and 17(F). Compared with the unreinforced specimens, due to <lb/>the encapsulation of epoxy resin and fiber cloth, no apparent cracks, holes, or other deteriora-<lb/>tion damage were found at cross-section point 3. <lb/>From the appearance and development of microcracks, the damage degree of the specimens <lb/>is the most serious from the largest to the smallest, followed by the glass fiber and basalt fiber <lb/>reinforced specimens and the carbon fiber and aramid fiber reinforced specimens. These <lb/>cracks expand and extend with the increase of the freeze-thaw cycle. The above microscopic <lb/>analysis shows that FRP reinforcement can effectively improve the durability of concrete in the <lb/>coupled environment of the acid-freeze-thaw cycle, and carbon fiber and aramid fiber have the <lb/>best protection effect on concrete, followed by basalt fiber and glass fiber. In the coupled envi-<lb/>ronment of the acid-freeze-thaw cycle combined with the macroscopic and microscopic obser-<lb/>vation results, the specimen&apos;s concrete surface matrix falls off, exposing coarse aggregate, and <lb/>the micro-cracks appear earlier and develop more rapidly. The damage to the specimen comes <lb/>from two aspects: the extrusion pressure of calcium sulfate, the product generated by the reac-<lb/>tion of sulfuric acid and concrete, and the frost swelling force generated by the freeze-thaw <lb/>cycle. <lb/>In order to investigate the degree of damage to the cylindrical specimen caused by the cou-<lb/>pled alkali-freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment, the specimen&apos;s cross-section was observed <lb/>by a digital microscope with an observation factor of 100. Fig 8(D) shows the specimen&apos;s sam-<lb/>pling points. The fiber cloth reinforced specimen with 50 and 100 times alkali-freeze-thaw <lb/>cyclic coupled erosion and the cylinder specimen without fiber cloth reinforced were selected <lb/>for observation and comparative analysis, and the specimen&apos;s microstructure was shown in <lb/>Figs 18 and 19. Under 100 times of alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion, the cross-section <lb/>microstructure of the unreinforced specimen is shown in Fig 18. PAL1-F100 and PAL1-F50 <lb/>are the positions near the outer edge point 1 on the cross-section, and the coupling erosion is <lb/>the most serious. The specimen is attached with a large amount of white material (alkali-silica <lb/>gel). Obvious cracks were observed in PAL2-F50 and PAL2-F100. PAL3-F50 and PAL3-F100 <lb/>are the central areas of the specimens where micro-cracks can be observed. <lb/>Fig 18. Microstructure of cross section of unreinforced specimen:(a) Under 50 cycles of alkaline freeze-thaw erosion <lb/>conditions, (b) Under 100 cycles of alkaline freeze-thaw erosion conditions. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g018 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 19(A)-19(H) show the microstructure of FRP-reinforced specimens under alkali-<lb/>freeze-thaw cyclic erosion. Fig 19(a), 19(B), 19(G) and 19(H) show the microscopic morphol-<lb/>ogy of the cross-section of the reinforced specimens with carbon fiber and aramid fiber, <lb/>respectively. No apparent damage was observed under the microscope, and no micro-cracks <lb/>and white alkali-silica gel were found in the cross-section of the reinforced specimens. Fig 19 <lb/>(C) and 19(E) show the microscopic morphology of basalt fiber and glass fiber under 50 cycles <lb/>of acid-freeze-thaw erosion, respectively. It can be seen from the microscopic imaging at 1 <lb/>point of cross section that the coupling erosion results in the separation of epoxy resin adhe-<lb/>sive in the FRP strip area from the concrete matrix and the appearance of holes, thus opening <lb/>a channel for the intrusion of sodium hydroxide solution and resulting in internal deteriora-<lb/>tion of concrete damage. The fiber cloth did not have apparent damage, such as breakage and <lb/>wire drawing. Cracks were observed in BCAL2-F100, while GCAL2-F100 showed cracks in <lb/>ITZ, the interface transition zone between aggregate and cement, the weakest concrete area. <lb/>Compared with the unreinforced specimens, due to the encapsulation of epoxy resin and fiber <lb/>cloth, no apparent cracks, holes, or other deterioration damage were found at cross-section <lb/>point 3. From the appearance and development of microcracks, the degree of damage to the <lb/>specimen is consistent with the law of acid-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion. The damage of <lb/>unreinforced specimens was the most serious, followed by glass fiber and basalt fiber rein-<lb/>forced specimens, and the damage of carbon fiber and aramid fiber reinforced specimens was <lb/>the least. <lb/>In order to investigate the damage to the concrete specimen caused by the coupled salt-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment, the specimen was cut at 1/2 height. The surface of the <lb/>specimen was washed and dried, and the specimen&apos;s cross-section was observed by a digital <lb/>microscope with an observation factor of 100. Fig 8(D) shows the specimen&apos;s sampling point. <lb/>The fiber cloth reinforced specimens with 50 and 100 times acid-freeze coupling erosion and <lb/>the axial compression specimen without fiber cloth reinforcement were selected for <lb/>Fig 19. Microstructure of the FRP reinforced specimen: (a) CFRP reinforced specimens subjected to 50 cycles of alkali <lb/>freeze cycles, (b) CFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of alkali freeze cycles; (c) BFRP specimens subjected to 50 <lb/>cycles of alkali freeze cycles, (d) BFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of alkali freeze cycles, (e) GFRP specimens <lb/>subjected to 50 cycles of alkali freeze cycles, (f) GFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of alkali freeze cycles, (g) AFRP <lb/>specimens subjected to 50 cycles of alkali freeze cycles, (h) AFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of alkali freeze <lb/>cycles. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g019 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>observation and comparative analysis, and the micromorphology of the specimens is shown in <lb/>Figs 20 and 21. Under the action of 100 coupled salt-freeze-thaw cycles, the cross-section <lb/>microstructure of the unreinforced specimen is shown in Fig 20. The position of P1S-F100 <lb/>near the outer edge point 1 on the cross-section suffers the most severe coupling erosion, and <lb/>the specimen is attached with many white sodium chloride crystals. P2S-F100 is the location of <lb/>observation point 2, and the cross-section of P2S-F100 shows that deep cracks are generated <lb/>and appear in the ITZ region of the interface between aggregate and cement paste. The posi-<lb/>tion of observation point 3 is shown in figure P3S-F100, and a small crack is generated under <lb/>coupling erosion. <lb/>Fig 21(A)-21(H) show the microstructure of FRP-reinforced specimens under salt-freeze-<lb/>thaw cyclic erosion. Fig 21(A), 21(B), 21(G) and 21(H) show the microscopic morphology of <lb/>the cross-section of the reinforced specimens of carbon fiber and aramid fiber, respectively. <lb/>No apparent damage was observed under the microscope, and no micro-cracks and holes were <lb/>found in the cross-section of the reinforced specimens. Figure A1S-F100 shows a small gap <lb/>between the aramid fiber and the concrete matrix. Fig 21(C) and 21(E) show the microscopic <lb/>morphology of basalt fiber and glass fiber under 50 cycles of salt-freeze-thaw erosion. It can be <lb/>seen from the microscopic imaging at 1 point of cross section that the epoxy resin is detached <lb/>Fig 20. Microstructure of cross section of unreinforced specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g020 <lb/>Fig 21. Microstructure of the FRP reinforced specimen: (a) CFRP reinforced specimens subjected to 50 cycles of salt <lb/>freeze cycles, (b) CFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of salt freeze cycles; (c) BFRP specimens subjected to 50 <lb/>cycles of salt freeze cycles, (d) BFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of salt freeze cycles, (e) GFRP specimens <lb/>subjected to 50 cycles of salt freeze cycles, (f) GFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of salt freeze cycles, (g) AFRP <lb/>specimens subjected to 50 cycles of salt freeze cycles, (h) AFRP specimens subjected to 100 cycles of salt freeze cycles. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g021 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>from the concrete matrix, resulting in holes and damage. With the increase of coupling erosion <lb/>period, the damage was more serious, but no apparent damage such as fracture and wire draw-<lb/>ing was found. Cracks appeared in B2-F100 and G2-F100, and the crack propagation was evi-<lb/>dent with the increase of the coupling erosion period, as shown in Fig 21(D) and 21(F). <lb/>Compared with the unreinforced specimens, due to the encapsulation of epoxy resin and fiber <lb/>cloth, no apparent cracks, holes, or other deterioration damage were found at cross-section <lb/>point 3. <lb/>The damage degree of the specimens is from large to small, and the unreinforced specimens <lb/>have the most severe damage, and cracks have appeared in the central area of concrete. Glass <lb/>fiber, basalt fiber, and aramid fiber reinforced specimens were the second carbon fiber and <lb/>reinforced specimens had the minor damage degree. FRP reinforcement can effectively <lb/>improve the durability of concrete in a salt-freeze-thaw coupling environment, and carbon <lb/>fiber has the best protection effect on concrete, followed by aramid fiber, basalt fiber, and glass <lb/>fiber. In summary, FRP reinforcement can effectively improve concrete&apos;s durability in the cou-<lb/>pled chemical-freeze-thaw cycle environment. Carbon fiber and aramid fiber have the best <lb/>protection effect on concrete, followed by basalt fiber and glass fiber. <lb/>Failure modes of epoxy and FRP sheets <lb/>Fig 22(A)-22(D) show the failure modes of epoxy resin sheet EPN, EPAC-F100, EPAL-100, <lb/>and EPS-F100, respectively, under the coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycles. There was no apparent <lb/>damage to the sheet at the initial loading stage. When the loading strength reached the ultimate <lb/>load, the specimen was broken and made a &quot;crack&quot; sound. The fracture position of the epoxy <lb/>resin film appears in the middle zone fracture (EPN-F0), and the failure plane is perpendicular <lb/>to the direction of the load. With the increase of the chemical coupling erosion period, the fail-<lb/>ure location becomes uncertain, and the failure surface tilts with the load direction. <lb/>CSAC-F100, BSAC-F100, GSAC-F100, and ASAC-F100 are the same failure patterns. <lb/>There was no apparent damage to the sheet at the initial loading stage. The epoxy resin matrix <lb/>broke as the loading continued, and the sheet made a slight and continuous &quot;snap&quot; sound. <lb/>When the ultimate load is reached, the sheet makes a vast &quot;snap&quot; sound, and the sheet breaks <lb/>instantaneously, as shown in Fig 23. Carbon fiber and basalt fiber sheets start to fracture from <lb/>the corner of the standard distance segment, which is because the fixture obstructs the trans-<lb/>verse deformation at the corner of the sheet, the stress concentration at the corner leads to the <lb/>sheet fracture, and the coupled erosion environment does not affect the failure form of the <lb/>sheet. The aramid fiber and the glass fiber sheet are broken in the middle. It can be seen from <lb/>the failure morphology of these specimens that the interface properties between fiber and <lb/>Fig 22. Damage pattern of epoxy resin:(a) EPN-F0, (b) EPAC-F100, (c)EPAL-F100, (d) EPSA-F100. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g022 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>epoxy resin are affected by coupling erosion, and the failure location is always in the weakened <lb/>region of the fracture interface. <lb/>As shown in Fig 24, the failure pattern of the sheet without alkali-freeze coupling erosion is <lb/>the same as that after 100 freeze-thaw cycles. Carbon fiber (CSAL-F100) and basalt fiber sheet <lb/>(BSAL-F100) start to fracture from the corner of the standard distance segment, which is <lb/>because the fixture obstructs the transverse deformation at the corner of the sheet, and the <lb/>stress concentration at the corner leads to the sheet fracture. The coupled erosion environment <lb/>does not affect the failure form of the sheet. The aramid fiber and the glass fiber sheet are bro-<lb/>ken in the middle. It can be seen from the failure morphology of these specimens that the <lb/>interface properties between fiber and epoxy resin are affected by coupling erosion, and the <lb/>failure location is always in the weakened region of the fracture interface. <lb/>As shown in Fig 25, the failure pattern of the sheet without salt-freeze coupling erosion is <lb/>the same as that after 100 freeze-thaw cycles. The carbon fiber (CSS-F100) starts to break from <lb/>the corner of the standard distance segment because the fixture obstructs the transverse defor-<lb/>mation at the corner of the sheet, and the stress concentration at the corner leads to the sheet <lb/>fracture. The coupled erosion environment does not affect the failure form of the sheet. The <lb/>aramid fiber (ASS-F100) and glass fiber (GSS-F100) sheets are broken in the middle. It can be <lb/>Fig 23. Damage patterns of FRP sheets under acid-freeze coupling erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g023 <lb/>Fig 24. Damage patterns of FRP sheets under alkali-freeze coupling erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g024 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>seen from the failure patterns of these specimens that the interface properties between fiber <lb/>and epoxy resin are affected by coupling erosion, and the failure location occurs in the weak-<lb/>ened region of the fracture interface. To sum up. The failure pattern of the FRP sheet without <lb/>chemical-freeze coupling erosion is the same as that after 100 chemical-freeze thaw cycles. <lb/>Failure pattern analysis of cylindrical specimen <lb/>Fig 26 shows the typical compressive failure patterns of FRP-reinforced and unreinforced <lb/>specimens. It can be seen that the carbon fiber and basalt fiber reinforced specimens show <lb/>annular cracking in the middle. At the initial loading stage, the specimen had no noticeable <lb/>change. When the load gradually increased, the specimen made a continuous and slight <lb/>&quot;crackling&quot; sound, and part of the epoxy resin matrix cracked. When the load reached the ulti-<lb/>mate bearing capacity of the specimen, the specimen made a vast &quot;crackling&quot; sound, and the <lb/>middle part of the FRP strip broke instantaneously, accompanied by concrete splashes. The <lb/>specimen showed apparent brittle failure, and the morphology of the damaged specimen is <lb/>shown in Fig 26(A) and 26(B). With the increase of pressure, the friction at both ends <lb/>increases, the swelling in the middle will become larger and larger, and the final specimen will <lb/>be destroyed first from the middle part. <lb/>In the three chemical erosion environments, the failure of AFRP reinforced specimens <lb/>showed strong conductivity, and the fiber cloth at the failure site gradually cracked, which was <lb/>different from the brittle failure of other FRP and was related to the densification of the fiber <lb/>cloth itself, as shown in ACC-F100, ACAL-F100, and ACSA-F100. For glass fiber reinforced <lb/>cylindrical specimens, the degradation phenomenon in chemical solution is evident; the color <lb/>becomes bright, and the damage diagram confirms this view. The failure of the control group <lb/>was manifested as concrete fragmentation because there was no strengthening of FRP itself, <lb/>and it was affected by the coupling effect of the acid-freeze-thaw cycle. <lb/>Failure pattern analysis of prismatic specimen <lb/>For unreinforced prismatic specimens with different coupled erosion cycles of chemical-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycles, their failure patterns are the same, and there is no noticeable change in the <lb/>specimens at the initial loading stage. With the progress of loading, tiny cracks appear at the <lb/>Fig 25. Damage patterns of FRP sheets under salt-freeze coupling erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g025 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>prefabricated cracks of the specimens, and then the cracks rapidly expand upward to the top of <lb/>the specimens. The failure pattern is the bending failure of the regular section. The typical fail-<lb/>ure for FRP-reinforced concrete bending specimens is that the FRP strip is spalling from the <lb/>surface of the concrete, and the regular section of the concrete is bending. <lb/>Fig 27 shows the failure morphology of the acid-freeze coupling erosion prismatic speci-<lb/>men. The failure forms are basically the same for different kinds of reinforced bending speci-<lb/>mens. FRP fracture of specimen GPAC-F100. After 100 times of acid-freeze coupling erosion, <lb/>GFRP is aged so that its tensile strength is lower than the bond tension between the concrete <lb/>Fig 26. Compressive failure modes of FRP reinforced specimens and unreinforced specimens: (a) Under acid freezing <lb/>coupled erosion conditions, (b) Under alkaline freezing coupled erosion conditions, (c) Under salt freezing coupled <lb/>erosion conditions. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g026 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>24 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>and FRP interface. A large surface concrete of the GPAC-F100 specimen spalled off, and the <lb/>bond between FRP and concrete decreased. For unreinforced flexural specimens, the concrete <lb/>on the upper side was compressed, while the concrete on the lower side was strained. As the <lb/>tensile strength of concrete was far less than the compressive strength, cracks appeared at the <lb/>precast cracks and extended. <lb/>Fig 28 shows the failure morphology of the alkali-freeze coupling erosion prism specimen. <lb/>For specimens BPAL-F100 and GPAL-F100, the FRP of the specimens was broken. After 100 <lb/>times of alkali-freeze coupling erosion, BFRP and GFRP are fractured and destroyed, and their <lb/>failure patterns are shown in Fig 28(C). Fig 29 shows the failure morphology of the salt-freeze <lb/>coupling erosion prismatic specimen. With the progress of loading, a small crack appeared at <lb/>the prefabricated crack of the specimen, and then the crack rapidly expanded upward and <lb/>extended to the top of the specimen. The damage mode was bending failure of the standard <lb/>section, as shown in Fig 29. The failure forms are different for different kinds of reinforced <lb/>bending specimens. For specimens BPSA-F100 and GPSA-F100, the failure mode of <lb/>Fig 27. Failure modes of prismatic specimen under acid-freeze coupling erosion: (a) Failure modes of Carbon fiber <lb/>reinforced prismatic specimen; (b) Failure modes of basalt fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (c) Failure modes of <lb/>glass fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (d) Failure modes of aramid fiber reinforced prismatic specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g027 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>25 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>specimens is the concrete oblique section failure, and the upper and lower ends of the oblique <lb/>crack are near the loading point and the support, respectively. The bonding surface between <lb/>the BFRP strip and the GFRP strip and concrete is not damaged, as shown in Fig 29(B) and 29 <lb/>(C). <lb/>In summary, in different chemical and frost-coupled erosion environments, FRP-rein-<lb/>forced concrete mainly presents typical FRP strips peeling off the concrete surface and bending <lb/>damage to the standard concrete section. After the chemical-freeze-thaw cycle coupling, the <lb/>bonding force between FRP and concrete is reduced, the strengthening effect is weakened, and <lb/>the FRP of GPAC-F100, BPAL-F100, and GPAL-F100 are fractured. <lb/>Mechanical test result <lb/>FRP sheet and epoxy resin <lb/>Figs 30(A), 31(A) and 32(A plot the stress-strain curves of each sheet under the coupled chem-<lb/>istry-freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment. In the acid-freeze environment, the ultimate <lb/>Fig 28. Flexural failure patterns of FRP reinforced specimens and unreinforced specimens under alkali-freeze <lb/>coupling erosion (a) Failure modes of Carbon fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (b) Failure modes of basalt fiber <lb/>reinforced prismatic specimen; (c) Failure modes of glass fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (d) Failure modes of <lb/>aramid fiber reinforced prismatic specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g028 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>26 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>tensile strength of epoxy resin adhesive was measured to decrease by 9.02% when the acid-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycle was 50 times and 13.57% when the acid-freeze-thaw cycle was 100 times. The <lb/>ultimate tensile strength of epoxy resin adhesive was measured by coupling erosion of 50 times <lb/>and 100 times in alkali-freeze-thaw cycles, and the tensile strength decreased by 7.01% and <lb/>11.79%, respectively. The tensile strength decreased by 6.42% and 11.12% under 50 and 100 <lb/>cycles of coupled salt-freeze-thaw erosion, respectively. In the coupled erosion environment, <lb/>the tensile strength of epoxy resin film decreases, the ultimate tensile strain increases, the elas-<lb/>tic modulus decreases, and the second half of the stress-strain curve shows nonlinearity, which <lb/>indicates that the mechanical properties of epoxy resin film are seriously degraded. This is <lb/>because the epoxy resin film, due to the hydrolysis of groups, chloride ions, and freeze-thaw <lb/>cycle damage caused by surface and internal damage (micro-cracks), is the main factor of the <lb/>degradation of the mechanical properties of the sheet. <lb/>Fig 29. Flexural failure patterns of FRP reinforced specimens and unreinforced specimens under salt-freeze coupling <lb/>erosion (a) Failure modes of Carbon fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (b) Failure modes of basalt fiber reinforced <lb/>prismatic specimen; (c) Failure modes of glass fiber reinforced prismatic specimen; (d) Failure modes of aramid fiber <lb/>reinforced prismatic specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g029 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, <lb/></note>

	<page>27 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 30(B)-30(E) show each FRP sheet&apos;s stress-strain curves under the coupled acid-freeze-<lb/>thaw cycle erosion environment. It can be observed that the stress-strain curves of various FRP <lb/>sheets are highly similar, exhibiting linear elasticity. After reaching the maximum tensile <lb/>strength, their strength rapidly decreases, demonstrating a distinct brittleness. The stress-strain <lb/>curve of FRP sheets differs slightly from that of epoxy resin adhesive, which exhibits a nonlin-<lb/>ear behavior. The same research conclusion has also been reached in the literature [35]. <lb/>Although FRP materials exhibit brittleness, the overall structure reinforced with FRP through <lb/>wrapping around concrete demonstrates superior ductility. This enhanced ductility is achieved <lb/>through various mechanisms, including restraint effects, improved stress distribution, <lb/>enhanced crack control, and increased bending resistance. The ultimate tensile strength of the <lb/>CFRP sheet under the coupled erosion condition is 3508.86MPa, the erosion cycles of the <lb/>acid-freeze-thaw cycle are 50 and 100 times, and the tensile strength is reduced by 14.87% and <lb/>27.08%, respectively. The ultimate tensile strength of the BFRP sheet is 3497.98MPa without <lb/>coupling erosion. After 50 and 100 cycles of acid-freeze-thaw erosion, the tensile strength <lb/>decreases by 15.02% and 28.32%, respectively. AFRP sheets were reduced by 15.64% and <lb/>30.17%, respectively. GFRP decreased by 15.64% and 30.17%, respectively. For FRP sheets, the <lb/>tensile strength of epoxy resin adhesive is much smaller than that of the fiber cloth. Hence, the <lb/>fiber cloth mainly determines the mechanical properties of the sheet, and the damage to the <lb/>epoxy resin adhesive matrix has little effect on the mechanical properties of the sheet. The <lb/>interface damage between fiber filament and epoxy resin matrix is the main factor leading to <lb/>the degradation of the mechanical properties of FRP sheets. On the one hand, the hydrolysis <lb/>reaction leads to the gap between the fiber filament and the epoxy resin matrix [14]. On the <lb/>other hand, the temperature expansion coefficient of fiber silk and epoxy resin adhesive is dif-<lb/>ferent, and the interface stress between fiber silk and epoxy resin adhesive occurs during the <lb/>freeze-thaw cycle, resulting in interface damage. <lb/>Fig 30. Stress-strain curve of fiber sheet in coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycle environment: (a) epoxy resin, (b) CFRP <lb/>sheet, (c)BFRP sheet, (d) AFRP sheet, (e) GFRP sheet. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g030 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>28 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 31(B)-31(E) Plot the stress-strain curves of each FRP sheet under the coupled alkaline <lb/>freeze-freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment. The ultimate tensile strength of the CFRP sheet <lb/>is 3508.86MPa without erosion. The tensile strength decays by 9.32% and 17.12%, respectively, <lb/>after 50 and 100 times of coupling erosion. The ultimate tensile strength of the BFRP sheet <lb/>under non-erosion conditions is 3497.98MPa. The coupling erosion of alkali-freeze-thaw <lb/>cycles occurred 50 times and 100 times, and the tensile strength attenuated at 9.57% and <lb/>18.26%, respectively. AFRP sheet decreases by 10.66% and 20.12%, respectively. The tensile <lb/>strength of GFRP sheets decreases by 12.16% and 23.17%, respectively. It shows that the <lb/>mechanical properties are seriously degraded under the alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling ero-<lb/>sion environment. The coupling erosion resistance is CFRP&gt; from high to low. BFRP&gt; <lb/>AFRP&gt; GFRP. <lb/>Fig 32(B)-32(E) plots the stress-strain curves of each FRP sheet under the coupled salt-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment. The tensile strength of the four kinds of sheets is good. <lb/>They are CFRP, BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP from high to low. The curves drawn by the tensile <lb/>test data show that the early stage is elastic, the later stage is elastic-plastic, and the sudden frac-<lb/>ture occurs when the ultimate load is reached after the continuous increase. The ultimate ten-<lb/>sile strength of the CFRP sheet without erosion is 3508.86MPa, according to the data obtained <lb/>from the tensile test of the fiber sheet. The coupling erosion of salt-freeze-thaw cycles 50 times <lb/>and 100 times reduces the tensile strength by 6.87% and 13.52%, respectively. The ultimate ten-<lb/>sile strength of the BFRP sheet is 3497.98MPa without erosion, and the tensile strength <lb/>decreases by 7.47% and 14.28% after 50 and 100 salt-freeze-thaw cycles. AFRP intensity decays <lb/>7.98% and 14.41%; The ultimate tensile strength of the GFRP sheet under non-erosion condi-<lb/>tions is 3201.41MPa, and the salt-freeze-thaw cycles of 50 and 100 times are reduced by 9.34% <lb/>and 18.02%, respectively. In the coupled erosion environment, the tensile strength of FRP <lb/>sheets decreases slightly, and the ultimate tensile strain increases slightly, indicating that FRP <lb/>sheets&apos; mechanical properties are degraded. The tensile strength degradation rate of the CFRP <lb/>sheet is lower than that of epoxy resin adhesive and BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP sheet, indicating <lb/>Fig 31. Stress-strain curve of sheet under alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling environment: (a) epoxy resin, (b) CFRP <lb/>sheet, (c)BFRP sheet, (d) AFRP sheet, (e) GFRP sheet. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g031 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, <lb/></note>

	<page>29 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>that the durability of the CFRP sheet is better than that of the other four sheets under the cou-<lb/>pled salt-freeze-thaw cycle environment. <lb/>Compared with the salt-freeze-thaw cycle and alkali-freeze-thaw cycle, the mechanical <lb/>properties of the four FRP sheets are degraded most seriously under the coupled acid-freeze-<lb/>thaw cycle. At the same time, the properties of the acid-freeze-thaw cycle from high to low are <lb/>CFRP, BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP. The curves drawn by the tensile test data all show that the <lb/>early stage is elastic, and after the strain reaches a particular stage, it presents elastic-plastic <lb/>and then suddenly breaks when the limit load is reached. By comparing the stress-strain curves <lb/>of each sheet under the coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycle environment, it is evident that the ten-<lb/>sile strength loss of the CFRP sheet is smaller than that of BFRP, AFRP, and GFRP sheet, indi-<lb/>cating that the durability of CFRP sheet under the coupled acid-freeze-thaw cycle erosion <lb/>environment is better than that of the other three sheets. For the most seriously degraded <lb/>GFRP sheet, the tensile degradation strength exceeds 30% after 100 acid-freeze-thaw cycles. Its <lb/>strength can not meet the actual requirements of the paste. CFRP showed good durability in <lb/>the three erosion environments compared with the other three fiber fabrics. <lb/>Cylindrical specimen reinforced with FRP <lb/>Fig 33(A) shows FRP-reinforced specimens&apos; compressive strength and strength loss rate under <lb/>different acid-freeze-thaw cycles. With the increase of the acid-freeze-thaw cycle, the compres-<lb/>sive strength of each group was reduced to a certain extent. When the acid-freeze-thaw cycle <lb/>was 100 times, the strength of the CFRP-reinforced specimens was the highest, 33.8kN, 4.225 <lb/>times that of the control specimens. Compared with the initial strength without coupled acid-<lb/>freeze-thaw cyclic erosion, the strength loss rates of CFRP reinforced specimens&lt;BFRP rein-<lb/>forced specimen&lt;AFRP Reinforced specimen&lt;GFRP reinforced specimen&lt;The control <lb/>group are small to large. The strength loss of the reinforced and reinforced specimens after 100 <lb/>Fig 32. Stress-strain curves of epoxy resin and FRP sheet in coupled salt-freeze-thaw cycle environment: (a) epoxy <lb/>resin, (b) CFRP sheet, (c)BFRP sheet, (d) AFRP sheet, (e) GFRP sheet. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g032 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>30 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>acid-freeze-thaw cycles is similar, and the strength loss rate of the reinforced specimen is the <lb/>lowest at 27.8%. The acid-freeze-thaw cycle of GFRP-reinforced specimens is poor, and the <lb/>strength loss is 33.8%. <lb/>Fig 33(B) shows FRP-reinforced specimens&apos; compressive strength and strength loss rate <lb/>under different alkali-freeze-thaw cycles. It can be seen that with the increase of the freeze-<lb/>thaw cycle and alkali corrosion time, the compressive strength of each group is reduced to a <lb/>certain extent. Compared with the initial strength of 0 freeze-thaw cycles, the strength loss rate <lb/>of the CFRP reinforced specimens&lt;AFRP Reinforced specimen&lt; GFRP reinforced speci-<lb/>men&lt;BFRP reinforced specimen&lt;The control group from small to large. The minimum loss <lb/>of 100 times of freeze-thaw cyclic corrosion of CFRP-reinforced specimens is only 7.1%, and <lb/>the loss of 100 times of freeze-thaw cyclic corrosion of GFRP-reinforced specimens is very <lb/>close to that of BFRP-reinforced specimens. The initial strength of AFRP-reinforced speci-<lb/>mens is lower than that of GFRP-reinforced specimens and BFRP-reinforced specimens dur-<lb/>ing freeze-thaw cyclic corrosion. However, the strength values of the three specimens are very <lb/>similar after 100 times of freeze-thaw cyclic corrosion. <lb/>Fig 33(C) shows FRP-reinforced specimens&apos; compressive strength and strength loss rate under <lb/>different salt-freeze-thaw cycles. It can be seen that the changes in compressive strength of con-<lb/>crete reinforced by four different fiber materials are similar. After 100 freeze-thaw cycles, the com-<lb/>pressive strength of the concrete cylindrical specimens reinforced by CFRP,GFRP, BFRP, and <lb/>AFRP decreased by 8.3%, 19.2%, 27.2%, and 15.3%, respectively. The compressive strength of the <lb/>Fig 33. Compressive strength and strength loss rate of cylindrical specimens under different freeze-thaw cycles:(a) <lb/>acid-freeze cycle erosion, (b) alkali-freeze cycle erosion, (c) salt-freeze cycle erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g033 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>31 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>specimens strengthened with CFRP has the slightest change. Adhesive FRP significantly improves <lb/>the compressive strength of specimens under chemical erosion, and the compressive strength of <lb/>specimens of different groups in different environments also has the same rule, that is, CFRP rein-<lb/>forced specimens&gt;BFRP reinforced specimen&gt;GFRP Reinforced specimen&gt;AFRP strengthens <lb/>the specimen, which is related to the high strength of FRP itself. Regarding the strength loss rate <lb/>of FRP-reinforced specimens, the strength loss rate of CFRP-reinforced specimens in a chemical <lb/>environment is the smallest. The durability is the best, followed by the strength and durability of <lb/>BFRP and AFRP specimens. The strength loss rate of GFRP-reinforced specimens is the largest, <lb/>and the chemical durability is the worst. <lb/>Fig 34 shows each group of specimens&apos; uniaxial compressive stress-strain curves under the <lb/>action of acid-freeze coupling erosion. With the progress of coupling erosion, the ultimate <lb/>bearing capacity of the specimen decreases gradually. The specimens in the control group have <lb/>typical concrete stress-strain curves, but the FRP-reinforced specimens&apos; stress-strain curves <lb/>change obviously. The curves of the specimens strengthened by CFRP and BFRP are similar. <lb/>When the specimens reach the maximum compressive strength, their strength decreases rap-<lb/>idly, showing brittle failure. The constitutive curves of GFRP-reinforced specimens are similar <lb/>to those of the control group and have a certain plasticity. However, in AFRP-reinforced speci-<lb/>mens, when the compressive strength of specimens is close to the compressive strength, the <lb/>deformation is large, the strength is slow, and the plasticity is good. The order of plasticity is <lb/>AFRP&gt;GFRP&gt;Control group&gt;BFRP&gt;CFRP. <lb/>In addition, the flexural properties of the CFRP-reinforced specimens at 0, 50, and 100 <lb/>freeze-thaw cycles increased by 244.1%, 320.8%, and 450.1% compared with those of the unre-<lb/>inforced specimens, respectively, under the action of alkali-freeze coupling erosion, as shown <lb/>in Fig 35(A). The flexural characteristics of BFRP-reinforced specimens at 0, 50, and 100 <lb/>freeze-thaw cycles increased by 194.1%, 246.8%, and 290.6% compared with plain concrete <lb/>specimens, respectively, as shown in Fig 35(B). The bearing capacity curves of AFRP and <lb/>Fig 34. Uniaxial compressive stress-strain curve of cylindrical specimen under coupled acid-freeze erosion: (a)CFRP <lb/>reinforced specimen, (b) BFRP reinforced specimen, (c) GFRP reinforced specimen, (d) AFRP reinforced specimen, <lb/>(e)Control group specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g034 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>32 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>GFRP reinforced specimens show good plasticity. Meanwhile, the flexural characteristics of <lb/>GFRP-reinforced specimens at 0, 50, and 100 freeze-thaw cycles increased by 195.6%, 236.4%, <lb/>and 249.4%, respectively, compared with plain concrete specimens, as shown in Fig 35(C). The <lb/>flexural characteristics of BFRP-reinforced specimens during 0, 50, and 100 freeze-thaw cycles <lb/>increased by 160.3%, 226.0%, and 249.3%, respectively, compared with those of unreinforced <lb/>specimens, as shown in Fig 35(D). Compared with the control group, the bearing capacity of <lb/>each group is increased, which shows that FRP plays a good role in protecting concrete in the <lb/>process of alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion. Compared with unreinforced specimens, <lb/>each group&apos;s ultimate bearing capacity is increased because FRP limits the transverse deforma-<lb/>tion of concrete and plays a strengthening role. <lb/>The variation of compressive strength of concrete cylindrical specimens reinforced with <lb/>four kinds of fiber materials under the coupled salt-freeze-thaw cycle erosion environment is <lb/>shown in Fig 36. It can be seen that the changes in compressive strength of concrete reinforced <lb/>by four different fiber materials are similar. After 100 freeze-thaw cycles, the compressive <lb/>strength of the concrete cylindrical specimens reinforced by CFRP, glass fiber cloth, basalt <lb/>fiber cloth, and AFRP decreased by 8.3%, 19.2%, 27.2%, and 15.3%, respectively. The compres-<lb/>sive strength of the specimens strengthened with carbon fiber has the slightest change. In addi-<lb/>tion, in chemical erosion environments, the unreinforced concrete prism specimen curve <lb/>slowly rises and then suddenly drops. The curve of CFRP-reinforced concrete and BFRP-rein-<lb/>forced concrete specimens is similar to that of unreinforced concrete prismatic specimens. <lb/>Also, it consists of a rising section and a rapidly falling section. The bearing capacity curves of <lb/>AFRP and GFRP reinforced specimens show good plasticity. <lb/>FRP reinforced prisms <lb/>Fig 37(A) shows prismatic specimens&apos; flexural capacity, strength, and loss rate under coupled <lb/>acid-freeze-thaw cyclic erosion. The bending capacity of the specimens in each group has a <lb/>Fig 35. Uniaxial compressive stress-strain curve of cylindrical specimen under coupled alkali-freeze erosion: (a)CFRP <lb/>reinforced specimen, (b) BFRP reinforced specimen, (c) GFRP reinforced specimen, (d) AFRP reinforced specimen, <lb/>(e)Control group specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g035 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>33 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>similar change rule, and the bending capacity of the specimens decreases with the increase of <lb/>the acid-freeze-thaw coupling erosion cycle. Taking CFRP-reinforced specimens as an exam-<lb/>ple, after 50 and 100 cycles of acid-freeze-thaw coupled erosion, the loss rates of bending <lb/>capacity are 14.4% and 20.2%, respectively. The bending capacity of each group of specimens <lb/>under different acid-freeze-thaw cycles also has the same rule: CFRP reinforced speci-<lb/>mens&gt;BFRP reinforced specimen&gt;GFRP Reinforced specimen&gt;AFRP reinforced specimen. <lb/>In addition, the flexural capacity of prismatic specimens can be significantly improved by past-<lb/>ing FRP. Compared with the unreinforced specimens, the reinforced specimens of carbon <lb/>fiber, basalt fiber, glass fiber, and aramid fiber increased by 412.5%, 308.8%, 243.0%, and <lb/>195.3%, respectively, after 100 times acid-freeze-thaw coupling erosion cycles. Relative to the <lb/>initial bearing capacity, the bearing capacity loss rate of each group of specimens under 100 <lb/>times of coupled erosion is in descending order of CFRP reinforced specimens (20.23%)&lt; <lb/>BFRP reinforced specimen (20.3%)&lt;AFRP reinforced specimens (25.7%)&lt;BFRP reinforced <lb/>specimens (25.8%)&lt;Unreinforced specimens (36.5%). <lb/>Fig 37(B) shows the column diagram of the flexural capacity of FRP-reinforced specimens <lb/>and unreinforced specimens under alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion. It can be seen <lb/>that the bending capacity of each group of specimens has the same rule under different alkali-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycle coupling erosion cycles, and CFRP reinforced specimens&gt;BFRP reinforced <lb/>specimen&gt;GFRP Reinforced specimen&gt;AFRP Reinforced specimen&gt;Unreinforced speci-<lb/>men. It is obvious that pasted fiber cloth greatly improves the bending capacity of concrete. <lb/>Compared with the control group, CPAL-F100, BPAL-F100, GPAL-F100 and APAL-F100 <lb/>increased by 384.1%, 279.5%, 225% and 195%, respectively. With the increase of the coupling <lb/>erosion period, the bending capacity of all specimens decreased. Each group&apos;s bearing capacity <lb/>loss rate is CFRP&lt;AFRP&lt;BFRP&lt;GFRP&lt; Unreinforced specimen from small to large when <lb/>the cyclic corrosion is 100 times. <lb/>Fig 36. Uniaxial compressive stress-strain curve of cylindrical specimen under coupled salt-freeze erosion: (a)CFRP <lb/>reinforced specimen, (b) BFRP reinforced specimen, (c) GFRP reinforced specimen, (d) AFRP reinforced specimen, <lb/>(e)Control group specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g036 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>34 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>The flexural strength and strength loss rate of prismatic specimens under coupled salt-<lb/>freeze-thaw cyclic erosion are shown in Fig 37(C). The flexural strength of the reinforced pris-<lb/>matic specimen is higher than that of the unreinforced prismatic specimen, indicating that <lb/>FRP can effectively improve the flexural strength of the specimen. After coupled salt-freeze-<lb/>thaw cyclic erosion, the bending strength of unreinforced specimens and FRP-reinforced spec-<lb/>imens decreased, and these changes became more evident with the increase of the coupled ero-<lb/>sion period. The load-bearing capacity loss rate of specimens bonded with CFRP (acid freeze <lb/>20.23%, alkali freeze 17.12%, salt freeze 13.6%) is relatively the lowest compared to the initial <lb/>state, while the load-bearing capacity loss rate of unreinforced specimens is the highest (acid <lb/>freeze 36.5%, alkali freeze 30.16%, salt freeze 26.98%). After reaching the maximum tensile <lb/>strength, their strength rapidly decreases, demonstrating a distinct brittleness. The stress-strain <lb/>curve of FRP sheets differs slightly from that of epoxy resin adhesive, which exhibits a nonlin-<lb/>ear behavior. The same research conclusion has also been reached in the literature [26]. <lb/>In summary, with the increase of the coupled environmental period of the chemical-freeze-<lb/>thaw cycle, the bond between concrete and FRP deteriorates, and the bearing capacity of the <lb/>flexural specimens decreases. The bending capacity of CFRP reinforced specimens&gt;BFRP <lb/>reinforced specimen&gt;GFRP Reinforced specimen&gt;AFRP Reinforced speci-<lb/>men&gt;Unreinforced specimen from small to large. The bearing capacity loss rates of CFRP, <lb/>AFRP, and BFRP are smaller, while the bearing capacity loss rates of GFRP and unreinforced <lb/>specimens are significant. CFRP, AFRP, and BFRP improve the durability of concrete wells. <lb/>Fig 37. Flexural strength and loss rate: (a) coupled acid-freeze-thaw cyclic erosion; (b) coupled alkali-freeze-thaw <lb/>cyclic erosion; (c) coupled salt-freeze-thaw cyclic erosion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g037 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>35 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>Constitutive model of concrete reinforced by alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic <lb/>coupled FRP based on Lam-Teng <lb/>Mechanical properties are the most critical macroscopic properties of concrete materials, and <lb/>the study of constitutive relations is a deep understanding of the mechanical properties of con-<lb/>crete. It is necessary to master the constitutive relation of materials for numerical simulation. <lb/>According to the deformation characteristics of FRP-confined concrete, the Lam-Teng model <lb/>holds that the deformation curve is composed of a parabolic section and a linear section, and <lb/>the two sections are smoothly connected. Based on the Lam-Teng model, this paper studies <lb/>the constitutive relationship of concrete reinforced by FRP under alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic cou-<lb/>pling. The Lam-Teng model is as follows: <lb/>s c ¼ E c ε c À <lb/>ðE c À E 2 Þ <lb/>2 <lb/>4f 0 <lb/>ε 2 <lb/>c ; 0 � ε c � ε t <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>s c ¼ f 0 þ ε c E 2 ; ε t � ε c � ε cc <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>Where, σ c and ε c are the compressive stress and compressive strain of FRP confined con-<lb/>crete, respectively; E c is the elastic modulus of unconstrained concrete; E 2 is the slope of the <lb/>enhanced line segment; f 0 is the intercept of the reverse extension line on the stress axis; ε t is <lb/>the strain at the connection of the parabola and the line, which is obtained from the condition <lb/>that the slope of the parabola and the line is equal. From the condition that the slope at the <lb/>connection of the parabola and the line is equal: <lb/>ε t ¼ <lb/>2f 0 <lb/>E c À E 2 <lb/>ð3Þ <lb/>Enhanced line segment slope: <lb/>E 2 ¼ <lb/>f cc À f 0 <lb/>ε cc <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>The relationship between chemical-freeze-thaw coupling erosion on compressive strength <lb/>and the ultimate strain of FRP-reinforced concrete is explored. According to the test data, the <lb/>formula of compressive strength and ultimate strain of FRP reinforced concrete induced by <lb/>acid-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion was fitted, and the relationship between compressive <lb/>strength, ultimate strain, and coupled erosion period of different FRP reinforced concrete was <lb/>obtained, as shown in Fig 38. <lb/>Similarly, Figs 39 and 40 show the calculation results of alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupled <lb/>erosion and salt-freeze-thaw cyclic coupled erosion 40, respectively. <lb/>According to the stress-strain curve of FRP-reinforced concrete shown in Fig 34, the char-<lb/>acteristic parameters of the stress-strain curve without alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling and <lb/>acid-freeze-thaw cyclic coupling erosion were extracted. Table 4 lists some of the stress-strain <lb/>curve parameters. <lb/>Put the parameters in Table 4 into Formula 1-Formula 4 and compare the experimental <lb/>and calculation curves, as shown in Fig 41(A). The experimental results agree with the calcu-<lb/>lated results. Fig 41(B) compares the maximum stress values obtained from experiments and <lb/>model calculated.An absolute average margin (M) is defined to quantify the error. It can be <lb/>observed that the maximum M value for CFRP is 2.3%, while the maximum M value for GFRP <lb/>is 1.0%. This indicates that there is a relatively small error between the maximum stress values <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>36 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>obtained from the model calculations and the experimental results. So, the Lam-Teng model <lb/>can simulate the constitutive relationship of FRP-reinforced concrete well. <lb/>The Lam-Teng model was modified to study the constitutive model of concrete reinforced <lb/>by FRP under the coupling of the alkali-freeze-thaw cycle. Based on the relationship between <lb/>the compressive strength and ultimate strain of FRP-reinforced concrete and the number of <lb/>freeze-thaw cycles and combined with the above formula, the Lam-Teng model equation is <lb/>modified for the stress-strain curve of FRP-reinforced concrete under the coupling of different <lb/>alkali-freeze-thaw cycles, as shown in Table 5. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The mechanical and apparent deterioration laws of carbon/basalt/glass/aramid fiber cloth <lb/>reinforced concrete under chemistry-freeze-thaw coupling were studied. The tensile strength <lb/>of the FRP sheet and epoxy resin sheet before and after chemistry freeze, the compressive <lb/>strength of the fully wrapped FRP cylindrical test block, and the bending capacity of the pris-<lb/>matic test block pasted with FRP on the precast crack side were tested. Based on the Lam-Teng <lb/>model, the constitutive model of concrete reinforced by chemically frozen FRP was modified. <lb/>The conclusion is as follows: <lb/>Fig 38. The fitting formula of compressive strength and ultimate strain of acid-freeze-thaw cyclic coupled erosion <lb/>group:(a) compressive strength, (b) ultimate strain. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g038 <lb/>Fig 39. The fitting formula of compressive strength and ultimate strain of alkali-freeze-thaw cyclic coupled erosion <lb/>specimen:(a) compressive strength, (b) ultimate strain. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g039 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, <lb/></note>

	<page>37 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>1. In terms of epigenetic observation, with the chemical-freeze erosion cycle increases, the sur-<lb/>face holes of epoxy resin sheets increase, and there are tiny cracks and folds. The texture of <lb/>FRP sheets is blurred, and there are cracks and folds on the surface. FRP reinforcement can <lb/>effectively improve the durability of concrete in the coupled environment of the acid-<lb/>freeze-thaw cycle, and carbon fiber and aramid fiber have the best protection effect on con-<lb/>crete, followed by basalt fiber and glass fiber. <lb/>2. In terms of the failure state of the specimen, as the chemical coupling erosion cycle <lb/>increases, the failure position of the epoxy resin sheet becomes uncertain, and the failure <lb/>direction tilts towards the load direction. The failure mode of FRP sheets has not changed. <lb/>For compressive specimens, the failure of AFRP reinforced specimens showed strong duc-<lb/>tility in three chemical erosion environments, while other FRP reinforced specimens exhib-<lb/>ited brittle failure. For flexural specimens, after chemical freeze-thaw cycle coupling, the <lb/>bonding strength between FRP and concrete decreases, the reinforcement effect weakens, <lb/>and FRP peels off from the surface of concrete. <lb/>3. In terms of mechanical properties, the mechanical degradation of FRP sheets is most severe <lb/>in acid freezing environments, and the tensile properties from high to low are CFRP, BFRP, <lb/>AFRP, and GFRP. The curves drawn from the tensile test data indicate that the early stage <lb/>is linear elastic, and the strain suddenly decreases when it reaches the maximum stress. <lb/>4. In terms of mechanical properties, for cylindrical specimens, the compressive strength loss <lb/>rates of specimens bonded with CFRP (acid freeze minimum loss rate (27.8%), salt freeze <lb/>minimum loss rate (9.61%)), BFRP (alkali freeze minimum loss rate (11.5%), and AFRP are <lb/>relatively small compared to the initial state, while GFRP has a larger strength loss rate (acid <lb/>Fig 40. The fitting formula of compressive strength and ultimate strain of salt-freeze-thaw cyclic coupled erosion <lb/>specimen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g040 <lb/>Table 4. Stress-strain curve parameters. <lb/>E c <lb/>f 0 <lb/>εt <lb/>f cc (MPa) <lb/>ε cc <lb/>CFRP reinforced specimen without corrosion <lb/>13000 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>0.0032 <lb/>46.8 <lb/>0.00536 <lb/>GFRP reinforced specimen without corrosion <lb/>14800 <lb/>15.0 <lb/>0.0024 <lb/>40.2 <lb/>0.00416 <lb/>BFRP reinforced specimen without corrosion <lb/>11500 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>0.0028 <lb/>40.0 <lb/>0.00446 <lb/>AFRP reinforced specimen without corrosion <lb/>18200 <lb/>32.2 <lb/>0.0021 <lb/>35.4 <lb/>0.00351 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.t004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>38 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<body>freeze (33.8%), salt freeze (25.37%)). The stress-strain curve of the unreinforced specimen <lb/>slowly rises and suddenly decreases after reaching the maximum stress. The curve changes of <lb/>CFRP reinforced and BFRP reinforced concrete specimens are similar to those of unrein-<lb/>forced specimens. The curves of AFRP reinforced and GFRP reinforced specimens showed <lb/>good plasticity. For prismatic specimens, the load-bearing capacity loss rate of specimens <lb/>bonded with CFRP (acid frost 20.23%, alkali frost 17.12%, salt frost 13.6%) is relatively the <lb/>lowest compared to the initial state, while the load-bearing capacity loss rate of unreinforced <lb/>specimens is the highest (acid frost 36.5%, alkali frost 30.16%, salt frost 26.98%). <lb/>5. Calculate the Lam Teng stress-strain curve of the unreinforced specimen, and the experi-<lb/>mental curve matches well with the model calculation curve. For the absolute average mar-<lb/>gin of maximum stress calculated from experiments and models, CFRP reinforced <lb/>specimens have a maximum value of 2.3%, while GFRP reinforced specimens have a mini-<lb/>mum value of 1.0%, which is verified by the experimental curve. Analyzed the relationship <lb/>between peak stress-strain and coupled freeze-thaw cycles, and established a Lam Teng con-<lb/>stitutive model for chemical freeze coupling FRP reinforced concrete. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Raw images. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Wei Li. <lb/></div>

	<body>Fig 41. Comparison of calculated and experimental, (a) stress-strain curves, (b)maximum stress. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.g041 <lb/>Table 5. Modified Lam-Teng model equation. <lb/>Number <lb/>Proposed stress-strain curve <lb/>CFRP reinforced specimen <lb/>s c ¼ E c ε c À ðE c ε cc À f C þf 0 Þ 2 <lb/>4f 0 <lb/>ε c <lb/>2 , 0�ε c &lt;ε t ; s c ¼ f 0 þ ε c <lb/>f C À f 0 <lb/>ε cc1 , ε t �ε c �ε cc1 <lb/>BFRP reinforced specimen <lb/>s c ¼ E c ε c À ðE c ε cc À f B þf 0 Þ 2 <lb/>4f 0 <lb/>ε c <lb/>2 , 0�ε c &lt;ε t ; s c ¼ f 0 þ ε c <lb/>f B À f 0 <lb/>ε cc2 , ε t �ε c �ε cc2 <lb/>GFRP reinforced specimen <lb/>s c ¼ E c ε c À ðE c ε cc À f G þf 0 Þ 2 <lb/>4f 0 <lb/>ε c <lb/>2 , 0�ε c &lt;ε t ; s c ¼ f 0 þ ε c <lb/>f G À f 0 <lb/>ε cc3 , ε t �ε c �ε cc3 <lb/>AFRP reinforced specimen <lb/>s c ¼ E c ε c À ðE c ε cc À f A þf 0 Þ 2 <lb/>4f 0 <lb/>ε c <lb/>2 , 0�ε c &lt;ε t ; s c ¼ f 0 þ ε c <lb/>f A À f 0 <lb/>ε cc4 , ε t �ε c �ε cc4 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645.t005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>39 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Project administration: Wenyuan Xu. <lb/>Software: Dayang Wang. <lb/>Supervision: Wenyuan Xu. <lb/>Validation: Yongcheng Ji. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Wei Li, Dayang Wang. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Yongcheng Ji. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Guler S., &amp; Akbulut Z. F. Workability, physical &amp; mechanical properties of the cement mortars strength-<lb/>ened with metakaolin and steel/basalt fibers exposed to freezing-thawing periods. Construction and <lb/>Building Materials.2023; 394, 132100. <lb/>2. Lewin M., Preston J. Handbook of Fiber Science and Technology Volume 2: High Technology Fibers: <lb/>Part B. Routledge 2017. <lb/>3. Donnet J. B., Bansal R. C. Carbon fibers. Crc Press 1998. <lb/>4. Alsayed S H., Al-Salloum Y A., Almusallam T H. Performance of glass fiber reinforced plastic bars as a <lb/>reinforcing material for concrete structures. Composites Part B: Engineering. 2000; 31(6): 555-567. <lb/>5. Cigna R.; Andrade C.; Nu ¨rnberger U. COST Action 521, Corrosion of steel in reinforced concrete struc-<lb/>tures, Final report. European Communities EUR.2003 20599. <lb/>6. Gudonis E., Timinskas E., Gribniak V., Kaklauskas G., Arnautov A. K., Tamulėnas V. FRP reinforce-<lb/>ment for concrete structures: state-of-the-art review of application and design. Engineering Structures <lb/>and Technologies. 2013; 5(4), 147-158. https://doi.org/10.3846/2029882X.2014.889274 <lb/>7. Tanaka H., Tazawa H., Kurita M., &amp; Shimomura T. A case study on life-cycle assessment of environ-<lb/>mental aspect of FRP structures. In Third international conference on FRP composites in civil engineer-<lb/>ing (CICE 2006). 2006, December. <lb/>8. Lu X Z., Teng J G., Ye L P., Jiang J J. Bond-slip models for FRP sheets/plates bonded to concrete. <lb/>Engineering Structures. 2005; 27(6): 920-937. <lb/>9. Xie J, Li J, Lu Z, Zhang H. Experimental study on fatigue behaviour of BFRP concrete bond interfaces <lb/>under bending load. Shock and Vibration. 2018; 2018:1-11. <lb/>10. Al Azzawi M, Hopkins P, Mullins G, Sen R. FRP-concrete bond after 12-year exposure in Tidal waters. <lb/>Journal of Composites for Construction. 2018; 22(5): 04018031. <lb/>11. Wang JL. Cohesive-bridging zone model of FRP-concrete interface debonding. Engineering fracture <lb/>mechanics. 2007; 74(17): 2643-2658. <lb/>12. Guler S., &amp; Akbulut Z. F. (2023). The coupling effect of silica fume and basalt fibers on workability and <lb/>residual strength capacities of traditional concrete before and after freeze-thaw cycles. Archives of Civil <lb/>and Mechanical Engineering. 23(3), 173. https://doi.org/10.1007/s43452-023-00719-2 <lb/>13. Wu Y, Zhou Z, Yang Q, et al. On shear bond strength of FRP-concrete structures. Engineering Struc-<lb/>tures. 2010, 32(3): 897-905. <lb/>14. Zou X, Lin H, Feng P, et al. A review on FRP-concrete hybrid sections for bridge applications. Compos-<lb/>ite Structures. 2021, 262: 113336. <lb/>15. Duo Y., Liu X., Liu Y., Tafsirojjaman T., Sabbrojjaman M. Environmental Impact on the Durability of <lb/>FRP Reinforcing Bars. Journal of Building Engineering. 2021; 43: 102909. <lb/>16. zhou Y., Fan Z., Du J., Sui L., &amp; Xing F. Bond behavior of FRP-to-concrete interface under sulfate <lb/>attack: An experimental study and modeling of bond degradation. Construction and Building Materials. <lb/>2015; 85: 9-21. <lb/>17. Rege S K., Lakkad S C. Effect of salt water on mechanical properties of fibre reinforced plastics. Fibre <lb/>Science and Technology. 1983; 19(4): 317-324. <lb/>18. Ghabezi P., Harrison N.M. Hygrothermal Deterioration in Carbon/Epoxy and Glass/Epoxy Composite <lb/>Laminates Aged in Marine-Based Environment (Degradation Mechanism, Mechanical and Physico-<lb/>chemical Properties). Journal of Materials Science. 2022; 57(6), 4239-4254. <lb/>19. Homam S M., Sheikh S A., Pernica G, Mukherjee P K. Durability of fibre-reinforced polymers (FRP) <lb/>used in concrete structures. University of Toronto. 2000; 1651-1651. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>40 / 41 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>20. Cromwell J R., Harries K A., Shahrooz B M. Environmental durability of externally bonded FRP materi-<lb/>als intended for repair of concrete structures. Construction and Building Materials. 2011; 25(5): 2528-<lb/>2539. <lb/>21. Bellakehal H., Zaidi A., Masmoudi R., Bouhicha M. Combined effect of sustained load and freeze-thaw <lb/>cycles on one-way concrete slabs reinforced with glass fibre-reinforced polymer. Canadian Journal of <lb/>Civil Engineering. 2013; 40(11): 1060-1067. <lb/>22. Toutanji H A, Goinez W. Durability characteristics of concrete beams externally bonded with FRP com-<lb/>posite sheets. Cement and Concrete Composite. 1997; (19):351-358. <lb/>23. Qiao P, Xu Y. Effects of freeze-thaw and dry-wet conditionings on themode-I fracture of FRP-concrete <lb/>interface bonds. Earth &amp; Space. 2004; 601-608. <lb/>24. Toutanji H A., Balaguru P. Durability characteristics of concrete columns wrapped with FRP tow sheets. <lb/>Journal of Materials in Civil Engineering. 1998; 52-57. <lb/>25. Masmoudi R, Baturkin D, Tagnit-Hamou A, et al. Freeze/Thaw Cycling Effects on Concrete-Filled-FRP <lb/>Tubes with Valorized FRP Materials from Decommissioned Wind Turbine Blades//International Sympo-<lb/>sium of the International Federation for Structural Concrete. Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland. <lb/>2023; 1137-1145. <lb/>26. Zou Y., Ji Y., &amp; Li W. Research on the durability of FRP-bonded concrete beams subjected to a perfor-<lb/>mance probabilistic design method. Materials and Structures. 2024; 57(2), 30. <lb/>27. Maras M M, Kantarcı F. Structural performance of reinforced concrete (RC) moment frame connections <lb/>strengthened using FRP composite jackets. Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering. 2021; 46 <lb/>(11): 10975-10992. <lb/>28. Teng J G, Yu T, Wong Y L, et al. Hybrid FRP-concrete-steel tubular columns: concept and behavior. <lb/>Construction and building materials. 2007; 21(4): 846-854. <lb/>29. Yan Z, Zeng J J, Zhuge Y, et al. Compressive behavior of FRP-confined 3D printed ultra-high perfor-<lb/>mance concrete cylinders. Journal of Building Engineering. 2024; 83: 108304. <lb/>30. Kantarci M, Maras M M, Ayaz Y. Experimental performance of RC beams strengthened with aluminum <lb/>honeycomb sandwich composites and CFRP U-jackets. Experimental Techniques. 2023; 47(4): 767-<lb/>786. <lb/>31. Woods J M. Accelerated testing for bond reliability of fiber-reinforced polymers (FRP) to concrete and <lb/>steel in aggressive environments (Doctoral dissertation, The University of Arizona) 2003. <lb/>32. Chajes M J, Thomson T A. Durability of concrete beams externally reinforced withcomposite fabrics. <lb/>Construction and Building Materials. 1995; 9(3):141-148. <lb/>33. Mukhopadhyaya P, Swamy R M, Lynsdale C J. Durability of adhesive bonded concrete-CFRP joints. <lb/>Durability of fiber reinforced polymer (FRP) composites for construction. Canada University of Sher-<lb/>brooke. 1998; 373-389. <lb/>34. Gudonis E., Timinskas E., Gribniak V., Kaklauskas G., Arnautov A. K., &amp; Tamulėnas V. FRP reinforce-<lb/>ment for concrete structures: state-of-the-art review of application and design. Engineering Structures <lb/>and Technologies. 2013; 5(4): 147-158. <lb/>35. Al-Zubaidy H, Zhao X L, Al-Mahaidi R. Mechanical characterisation of the dynamic tensile properties of <lb/>CFRP sheet and adhesive at medium strain rates. Composite Structures. 2013; 96: 153-164. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>FRP strengthened concrete <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303645 May 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>41 / 41 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>