<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T09:45:21.176Z">11/14/2025 9:45:21 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T09:45:04.192731Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T09:45:04.192731Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Full genome sequence analysis of African <lb/>swine fever virus isolates from Cameroon <lb/>Lynnette C. Goatley 1☯ , Graham Freimanis 1☯ , Chandana Tennakoon 1☯ , Thomas J. Foster 1 , <lb/>Mehnaz Quershi 1 , Linda K. Dixon 1 , Carrie Batten 1 , Jan Hendrik Forth 2 , Abel Wade 3 , <lb/>Christopher NethertonID 1 * <lb/>1 The Pirbright Institute, Ash Road, Pirbright, Woking, Surrey, United Kingdom, 2 Institute of Diagnostic <lb/>Virology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald, Insel Riems, Germany, 3 National Veterinary Laboratory <lb/>(LANAVET), Garoua, Cameroon <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* Chris.netherton@pirbright.ac.uk <lb/>Abstract <lb/>African swine fever (ASF) is a devastating disease of domestic pigs that has spread across <lb/>the globe since its introduction into Georgia in 2007. The etiological agent is a large double-<lb/>stranded DNA virus with a genome of 170 to 180 kb in length depending on the isolate. <lb/>Much of the differences in genome length between isolates are due to variations in the copy <lb/>number of five different multigene families that are encoded in repetitive regions that are <lb/>towards the termini of the covalently closed ends of the genome. Molecular epidemiology of <lb/>African swine fever virus (ASFV) is primarily based on Sanger sequencing of a few con-<lb/>served and variable regions, but due to the stability of the dsDNA genome changes in the <lb/>variable regions occur relatively slowly. Observations in Europe and Asia have shown that <lb/>changes in other genetic loci can occur and that this could be useful in molecular tracking. <lb/>ASFV has been circulating in Western Africa for at least forty years. It is therefore reason-<lb/>able to assume that changes may have accumulated in regions of the genome other than <lb/>the standard targets over the years. At present only one full genome sequence is available <lb/>for an isolate from Western Africa, that of a highly virulent isolate collected from Benin during <lb/>an outbreak in 1997. In Cameroon, ASFV was first reported in 1981 and outbreaks have <lb/>been reported to the present day and is considered endemic. Here we report three full <lb/>genome sequences from Cameroon isolates of 1982, 1994 and 2018 outbreaks and identify <lb/>novel single nucleotide polymorphisms and insertion-deletions that may prove useful for <lb/>molecular epidemiology studies in Western Africa and beyond. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>African swine fever virus (ASFV) is a large double-stranded DNA virus that causes significant <lb/>disease burden on domestic pigs and wildlife across the globe. Depending on the isolate the <lb/>virus manifests an acute febrile illness that is invariably fatal, subacute disease in which a pro-<lb/>portion of animals recover, or in some cases a chronic disease. Both domestic and wild pigs <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/>1 / 9 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Goatley LC, Freimanis G, Tennakoon C, <lb/>Foster TJ, Quershi M, Dixon LK, et al. (2024) Full <lb/>genome sequence analysis of African swine fever <lb/>virus isolates from Cameroon. PLoS ONE 19(3): <lb/>e0293049. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0293049 <lb/>Editor: Douglas Gladue, Plum Island Animal <lb/>Disease Center, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: October 3, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: March 6, 2024 <lb/>Published: March 21, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Goatley et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The assembled <lb/>genomes generated in this study have been <lb/>deposited in the NCBI GenBank database (www. <lb/>ncbi.nlm.nih.gov) as OR387519, OR387520 and <lb/></front>

    <body>(Sus spp.) are fully susceptible. However, warthogs (Phacochoerus africanus) together with <lb/>African soft ticks of the genus Ornithodoros represent a sylvatic cycle which acts as reservoirs <lb/>for the virus in sub-Saharan Africa. Full genome sequencing of ASFV remains non-trivial due <lb/>to difficulties in separating viral from host sequence and the presence of extensive homopoly-<lb/>mers and repetitive regions that make de novo assembly problematic [1, 2]. Currently ASFV <lb/>isolates are genetically typed based on a number of conserved and variable regions within the <lb/>genome, with the genotype classified by 400 base pairs (bp) in the 3&apos; end of the B646L gene <lb/>that encodes for the major capsid protein p72 [3]. Genotypes can be further subdivided by dif-<lb/>ferences in the E183L (p54 protein), CP204L (p30 phosphoprotein), [4, 5] as well as the inter-<lb/>genic sequence between the I73R and I329L genes [6]. The B602L gene (also referred to as the <lb/>9RL gene) encodes for a chaperone required for the correct folding of p72 and contains a vari-<lb/>able number of tetra amino acid repeats, referred to as the central variable region (CVR), that <lb/>have proven useful in subtyping ASFV genomes in a number of studies [7, 8]. In addition, <lb/>ASFV isolates can be categorised into serogroups based on cross-protection studies in pigs [9] <lb/>and these serogroups map closely to the sequence of the EP153R (C-type lectin) and EP402R <lb/>(CD2v protein) genes [10]. <lb/>ASFV isolates from Western Africa are predominately B646L genotype I [11-14] with a sin-<lb/>gle outbreak of genotype II in Nigeria in 2020 [15]. With the exception of some isolates from <lb/>Senegal which are CD2v serogroup 1, these viruses are all CD2v serogroup 4 [12]. ASFV was <lb/>first reported in Cameroon in 1981, with further outbreaks reported endemically in 1985 up to <lb/>2010 [13, 16], with the most recent in 2020 [17]. Isolates obtained from Cameroon can be sub-<lb/>classified from B646L genotype I and CD2v serotype 4 into E183L genotype Ia and Ib and vari-<lb/>ants containing 6, 19, 20, 21 and 23 tetra amino acid repeats in the pB602L protein [13, 17]. <lb/>Temporal analysis suggests evolution of ASFV from strains containing 19 tetra amino acid <lb/>repeats to 20 and then most recently 21 in the Far-North region of Cameroon. Virus contain-<lb/>ing 23 amino acid repeats were only reported in the initial outbreak in 1982 and have not been <lb/>reported since then, while viruses containing 6 amino acid repeats have only been recently <lb/>reported and appear to represent a new mutation [17]. <lb/>Analysis of genotype II isolates obtained from Europe and Asia has identified additional <lb/>single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and insertion-deletions (indels) which suggests that <lb/>over time mutations can occur in regions of the genomes other than those typically analysed <lb/>[6, 18-20]. The observed differences in the B602L and E183L genes could be due to the evolu-<lb/>tion of the virus in Cameroon over time [13, 17] or repeated reintroductions from neighbour-<lb/>ing countries. Changes over time in positions other than those typically characterised by <lb/>Sanger based sequencing have been observed in Sardinia [21], where genotype I ASFV has per-<lb/>sisted in the field since 1980. In this study, we generated full genome sequences of three Cam-<lb/>eroon isolates obtained in 1982, 1994 and 2018 as a starting point to understand the genetic <lb/>diversity of ASFV in this country. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Viruses <lb/>Cameroon 1982 isolate (CAM1982) has been described previously [22]. In brief it was pas-<lb/>saged through a domestic pig, then through primary bone marrow culture and back through a <lb/>domestic pig and bone marrow culture. Cameroon 1994/1 (CAM1994) was collected from a <lb/>domestic pig in Tamrngang Puiying, Bamenda, in September 1994. CMR/lab1/2018 isolate <lb/>(CMR2018) was collected from a domestic pig in 2018. All virus samples were passaged twice <lb/>through porcine bone marrow cultures before sequencing. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <front>OR387521 and the raw data are available in <lb/>BioProject PRJNA943480. <lb/>Funding: ASFV full genome sequencing at Pirbright <lb/>has been supported by UKRI grants BBS/E/I/ <lb/>00007037, BBS/E/I/00007039, BBS/OS/GC/200015 <lb/>and BBS/OS/GC/200015A and DEFRA grant <lb/>SE1517. This project has received funding from the <lb/>European Union&apos;s Horizon 2020 research and <lb/>innovation programme under grant agreement No <lb/>773701. The funders had no role in study design, <lb/>data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>Sample preparation <lb/>Viruses were cultured on mononuclear bone marrow cells that were collected from the long <lb/>bones of pigs four to six weeks old [23]. Mononuclear cells were purified from crude bone <lb/>marrow cell preparations by density gradient centrifugation (1000 × g, 20 min, RT). Cells were <lb/>cultured in RPMI, GlutaMAX, HEPES supplemented with 10% foetal calf serum, 1 mM <lb/>sodium pyruvate, 100 IU/mL penicillin, 100 μg/mL streptomycin and 100 ng/mL porcine col-<lb/>ony-stimulating factor for 3-5 days before virus was added. <lb/>Viruses were cultured until 90 to 100% cytopathic effect was observed (typically 3 to 4 <lb/>days), supernatants were clarified of cells and debris by low speed centrifugation (1000 × g, 5 <lb/>min, 4˚C) and virions were then concentrated by ultracentrifugation (13600 × g, 90 min, 4˚C). <lb/>The virus was treated with turbo DNase for 30 minutes at 37˚C and the enzyme was removed <lb/>using DNase Inactivation reagent. <lb/>DNA extractions were carried out using MagAttract HMW DNA kit (Qiagen) and the <lb/>resulting genomic DNA isothermally amplified using a REPLI-g kit (Qiagen). The average size <lb/>and quality of the amplified DNA was checked using a genomic screentape on a TapeStation <lb/>(Agilent). The DNA was quantified using the Qubit dsDNA BR assay kit (ThermoFisher) and <lb/>the ASFV genomes in the samples were quantified by qPCR using primers for B646L [24], <lb/>only samples with greater than or equal to 5.0 × 10 6 genome copies in 2 μl were taken forward <lb/>for full genome sequencing. <lb/>Genome sequencing <lb/>Illumina library preparation was performed using the DNA Prep kit (Illumina), with an input <lb/>of approximately 500ng of DNA. The resulting libraries were quality checked using a Tapesta-<lb/>tion 4220 (Agilent) and quantified with Qubit prior to dilution and pooling. Samples were <lb/>multiplexed and run on a MiSeq (Illumina) using a 600 cycle v3 reagent kit and flow cell. <lb/>To obtain longer reads, genomic DNA samples (between 2-4μg) were individually bar-<lb/>coded using the Nanopore Native barcoding genomic DNA kit (NBD104) and Genome by <lb/>ligation kit (LSK109) as per manufacturers protocols. Samples were grouped in to 6-8 <lb/>genomes and each group was run on a MinION (MIN-101b) using a 9.4.1 MinION flow cell <lb/>for 16 hours. After this period, the flow cell was flushed out using the flow cell wash kit <lb/>(EXP-WSH004), before additional groups were added for further 24-hour period. Raw reads <lb/>are available in BioProject PRJNA943480. <lb/>Assembly <lb/>The assembly was performed using an in-house pipeline. The sequencing data was first <lb/>trimmed and adaptors removed using Trim Galore as a quality control step to reduce noise. <lb/>The reads were then sub-sampled so that there is an even coverage of k-mers across the reads <lb/>in the sample. These reads were assembled using SPADes 13.3.1 [25]. The reads were then <lb/>mapped to the contigs produced in the assembly. The unmapped reads in this step were again <lb/>sub-sampled to have an even k-mer coverage, and the contigs produced by the assembly were <lb/>designated as trusted contigs. SPADes was run again using these reads and trusted contigs as <lb/>the input. This iterative process of sub-sampling and assembly was carried out until the per-<lb/>centage of unmapped reads drops below 5% or the set of unmapped reads did not change from <lb/>the previous iteration. The nanopore reads were passed as input data at each stage of the itera-<lb/>tion. Illumina reads were mapped back to the final assembled genomes to identify SNPs and <lb/>correct assembly errors using Geneious Prime (Biomatters, Inc.). <lb/>Assemblies were annotated using Genome Automated Transfer Utility [26] with Benin <lb/>1997/1 (AM712239) as a reference strain and other open reading frames (ORFs) identified <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>manually using the transcription map of the Badajoz 1971 Vero adapted strain (ASU18466) <lb/>[27]. Annotations were edited and processed with Geneious Prime and GB2Sequin [28]. <lb/>Sanger sequencing <lb/>The central variable region (CVR) within the B602L gene was amplified by PCR and <lb/>sequenced on an ABI-3730 using primers 9RL-F (5&apos;-AATGCGCTCAGGATCTGTTAAATCGG) <lb/>and 9RL-R (5&apos;-TCTTCATGCTCAAAGTGCGTATACCT). The B407L locus was amplified <lb/>using B407L-F (5&apos;-GAGATGCCTCAGACTCTGCATATT) and B407L-R (5&apos;-ATGACCCTGA <lb/>ATTTTCGCTTGACT) and E199L with E199L-F (5&apos;-CCACTGGAAGGCATCAAACGGTA) and <lb/>E199L-R (5&apos;-ATGTCTTGCATGCCAGTTTCCAC). <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>Two viruses isolated in Cameroon in 1982 and 1994 were selected from the Pirbright Institute <lb/>ASFV reference collection for genome sequencing as well as a third isolate obtained from a <lb/>recent outbreak in 2018. Samples from the three isolates were subject to both nanopore and <lb/>Illumina sequencing. The final de novo assembled genomes were 182,927 bp for Cameroon <lb/>1982 (CAM1982) strain, 183,179 bp for Cameroon 1994/1 (CAM1994) and 181,952 bp for <lb/>Cameroon 2018/lab1 (CMR2018) with minimum Illumina read depth of 44, 237 and 97 <lb/>respectively (Table 1 and S1 Fig). <lb/>The sequences of the three isolates shared a similar genome structure to that of the Benin <lb/>1997/1 isolate, the only currently available genome sequence of a field isolate from West Africa. <lb/>CAM1982, CAM1994 and CMR2018 were 98.81%, 99.90% and 99.78% identical to the Benin <lb/>nucleotide sequence respectively. Comparison to the Badajoz 1971 Vero adapted strain <lb/>(Ba71v), the only currently available full genome sequence that includes the complete sequence <lb/>of the terminal inverted repeats (TIRs), suggested that approximately 2,000 base pairs are miss-<lb/>ing from the left end of all three of the assembled genomes. The differences in length of the <lb/>Cameroon genomes were primarily due to assembly of TIR sequence at the right end of the <lb/>genome, with CAM1982 having an additional 800 bp compared to the Benin 1997/1 sequence <lb/>and CAM1994 having an additional 1600 bp. The open reading frames (ORFs) identified were <lb/>practically identical to those seen in the Benin 1997/1 isolate, with 164 ORFs present in <lb/>CAM1982 and CAM1994 and 162 in CMR2018. The extended assembly of the right-hand TIR <lb/>in the CAM1982 and CAM1994 genomes allowed detection of orthologues of the DP83L and <lb/>DP93R genes that are present in the Ba71v genome [29]. The Benin 97/1 genome was originally <lb/>annotated with 156 ORFs, however orthologues of the DP42R, C44L and J64R genes as well as <lb/>the novel genes NG2, NG5 and NG6 [27] are present in Benin 1997/1 as well all three Camer-<lb/>oon isolates. <lb/>Many of the differences among the three Cameroon isolates and Benin 1997/1 were single <lb/>base pair insertions or deletions within intergenic homopolymers (S1 Table), however there <lb/>Table 1. Assembly details for CAM1982, CAM1994/1 and CMR2018. <lb/>Samples (ASFV isolates) <lb/>Genome length (bp) Proportion GC (%) Nanopore depth (Min to Max) Illumina depth (Min to Max) Accession numbers <lb/>Cameroon 1982 (CAM1982) <lb/>182,927 <lb/>38.6 <lb/>1-93 <lb/>44-8,181 <lb/>OR387519 <lb/>Cameroon 1994/1 (CAM1994) <lb/>183,179 <lb/>38.5 <lb/>3-184 <lb/>237-9,854 <lb/>OR387520 <lb/>Cameroon 2018/lab1 (CMR2018) 181,952 <lb/>38.6 <lb/>10-183 <lb/>97-10,264 <lb/>OR387521 <lb/>Final assembled genome length, the percentage of GC residues, the Nanopore and Illumina coverage across each assembled genome and the NCBI accession number are <lb/>indicated. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>are many homopolymers within genes and changes with some of these led to changes in the <lb/>amino acid sequences. The I196L, MGF360-16R and MGF360-18R (DP148R) genes were trun-<lb/>cated by 19, 48 and 59 aa respectively in the CMR2018 isolate, but these genes were not trun-<lb/>cated in the CAM1982, or CAM1994 sequences when compared to Benin 1997/1. All three <lb/>Cameroon isolates had an insertion at position 181868 that reconstituted the DP60R gene that <lb/>was truncated in Benin 1997/1. <lb/>Differences in ASFV genome length are often due to variations in copy numbers of the five <lb/>different multigene families (MGF) encoded by the virus, however with the exception of <lb/>MGF360-16R and -18R the majority of the genes were no different to those seen in Benin. A <lb/>number of SNPs were observed in different MGF360 and -505 genes and MGF360-2L in <lb/>CMR2018 was truncated by 8 amino acids at the C-terminus. Changes in the predicted N-ter-<lb/>minus of MGF110-11L in all three Cameroon genomes relative to Benin and in the N-termi-<lb/>nus of MGF110-13L were detected, but these changes are not predicted to affect the presence <lb/>of signal peptides or transmembrane domains. <lb/>The CMR2018/lab1 isolate contained 19 copies of the tetra amino acid repeats in the CVR <lb/>(Table 2) and these were identical to isolates obtained from across Cameroon between 2010 to <lb/>2020, corresponding to Variant A in a previous study [13]. CAM1994/1 contained 28 tetra <lb/>amino acid repeats that was mostly closely related to sequences obtained from Nigeria with 27 <lb/>tetra amino acid repeats in 2003, 2004, 2015 and 2018 and with 29 repeats that was obtained in <lb/>2006 [11, 14, 30]. The assembled sequence of the CAM1982 CVR was identical to sequence <lb/>AAQ08102 submitted to NCBI in 2003, but different to CAJ90777 [7] and inspection of the <lb/>reads aligned to the final assembled 1982 genome suggested a mixed population in the sample. <lb/>Inspection of the rest of the CAM1982 reads suggested two variants with the E199L gene (S1 <lb/>Table). Therefore, individual clones of CAM1982 were generated by limit dilution and the <lb/>sequence of the CVR, E199L and B407L loci determined by Sanger sequencing. As expected, <lb/>all clones of CAM1982 had the novel deletion in B407L as predicted by the reads, however all <lb/>eight possible versions of the B602L and the two E199L variants were present in the original <lb/>sample. These differences have been annotated as polymorphisms in the final assembled <lb/>CAM1982 sequence. <lb/>Indels of repetitive sequences that are present throughout the ASFV genome led to other <lb/>differences between the Cameroon isolates and Benin 1997/1. CAM1982 has a single copy of <lb/>ATGTTATAACC within the MGF360-9L/MGF360-10L intergenic region, whereas the other <lb/>viruses have two. Differences in repetitive sequences within the C44L gene lead to 3 additional <lb/>copies of ASTC within the protein sequence of the CMR2018/lab1 and one copy within the <lb/>CAM1994/1 protein. An additional copy of a TCTTCACATTCA sequence within the I215L <lb/>Table 2. B602L/CVR sequences from selected ASFV isolates. Each letter in the CVR sequence represents a tetra amino acid repeat where A = CAST, B = CADT, <lb/>C = GAST, D = CASM, F = CANT, N = NVDT, T = NVNT. <lb/>Sample <lb/>CVR Code <lb/>Accession Number <lb/>Reference <lb/>Benin 1997/1 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNAAAAACBNAAAAACBNAAAACBNAFA <lb/>AM712239 <lb/>[31] <lb/>Cameroon 1982 <lb/>ABNAAAA(A)CBNABTDBNAFA <lb/>OR387519 <lb/>This study <lb/>Cameroon 1982 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNABTDBNAFA <lb/>AAQ08102 <lb/>Cameroon 1982 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNABTDBNAAAAANA <lb/>CAJ90777 <lb/>[7] <lb/>Cameroon 1994/1 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNAAAAACBNAAAACBNAFA <lb/>OR387520 <lb/>This study <lb/>Cameroon 2018/lab1 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNABTDBNAFA <lb/>OR387521 <lb/>This study <lb/>Nig27-LGTT3_15 (Nigeria-Tet-27) <lb/>ABNAAAACBNAAAACBNAAAACBNAFA <lb/>KT961373 <lb/>[11] <lb/>CVR-Tet-27 <lb/>ABNAAAACBNAAAACBNAAAACBNAFA <lb/>GQ427187 <lb/>[30] <lb/>CVR-Tet-29 <lb/>ABNAAAAACBNAAAACBNAAAAACBNAFA <lb/>GQ427188 <lb/>[30] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049.t002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>gene that encodes for the E2 ubiquitin ligase is present in the CMR2018/lab1 genome which <lb/>leads to an additional DECE repeat in the amino acid sequence of the protein. All three viruses <lb/>have a GCTTTGGACCGGCCG deletion within the B169L gene that leads to the deletion of one <lb/>copy of three PAGPK repeats within the protein. There are also deletions within the B407L <lb/>gene which lead to the deletion of one of the three copies of an NGSIR repeat from the <lb/>CMR2018/lab1 protein and the deletion of two of three copies of NGSIR repeat and one of two <lb/>copies of a SGSIR repeat in the CAM1982 protein, the CAM1994/1 B407L gene is identical to <lb/>that of Benin 1997/1. Until full genome sequencing becomes routine a wider analysis of the <lb/>copy number of these short repetitive sequences within ASFV isolated from Cameroon and <lb/>West Africa could aid molecular epidemiological studies in the region. <lb/>Experimental studies with CAM1982 demonstrated a high virulence in pigs directly <lb/>infected with high doses, but a lower virulence after transmission to contact pigs where a case <lb/>fatality rate of 33% was observed [22]. Lower virulence was also reported after oral-nasal chal-<lb/>lenge with isolates obtained from Brazil and the Dominican Republic in 1978 [32, 33], <lb/>although experiments with the genotype I of OUR T88/1 isolate demonstrated a high virulence <lb/>in both directly infected and in contact pigs [34]. The principal differences between the <lb/>CAM1982 genome and those of other highly virulent genotype I viruses such as Benin 1997/1 <lb/>are the differences in the CVR and B407L. The influence of the CVR on the role of B602L in <lb/>the correct assembly of p72 and viral virulence in swine is unknown, however the 26544/OG10 <lb/>isolate of ASFV from Sardinia has a shorter CVRs than the Cameroon isolates and 26544/ <lb/>OG10 is virulent and replicates efficiently in macrophages [35]. B407L encodes for a late gene <lb/>with unknown function that is expressed in infected macrophages [36, 37], but are not incor-<lb/>porated into virions [38]. All three of the Cameroon viruses have a small deletion in the B169L <lb/>gene compared to Benin 97/1, however this deletion is present in a number of other genotype I <lb/>viruses obtained in Portugal, Spain, Sardinia and the Dominican Republic [1, 39-41]. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Full genome sequencing of three isolates obtained across a nearly forty-year period did not <lb/>identify major changes in the genome, however differences in the copy number of repetitive <lb/>sequences were identified suggesting that ASFV is evolving in the field in Cameroon. A num-<lb/>ber of these changes were in regions in which variation has not been previously reported and <lb/>therefore could represent novel targets for characterizing ASFV within Cameroon. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Coverage plots. Raw reads from Illumina and Nanopore sequencing runs were <lb/>mapped back against the assembled genomes of CAM1982 (A), CAM1994/1 (B) and <lb/>CAM2018/lab1 (C) using Geneious Prime. Plots were displayed using the Integrative Genome <lb/>Viewer. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Table. Differences between CAM1982, CAM1994/1 and CMR2018/lab1 genomes and <lb/>the Benin 1997/1 reference. The positions of substitutions (&gt;), insertions (^) and deletions <lb/>(v) relative to the Benin 1997/1 sequence (AM712239) are indicated along with the gene within <lb/>which the substitution is found, as well as any potential functional consequences. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Linda K. Dixon, Carrie Batten, Abel Wade, Christopher Netherton. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Data curation: Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Formal analysis: Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Linda K. Dixon, Carrie Batten, Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Investigation: Lynnette C. Goatley, Graham Freimanis, Chandana Tennakoon, Mehnaz <lb/>Quershi. <lb/>Methodology: Lynnette C. Goatley, Graham Freimanis, Chandana Tennakoon, Thomas J. <lb/>Foster, Mehnaz Quershi, Jan Hendrik Forth. <lb/>Supervision: Lynnette C. Goatley, Carrie Batten, Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Validation: Thomas J. Foster, Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Lynnette C. Goatley, Graham Freimanis, Chandana Tennakoon, <lb/>Christopher Netherton. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Linda K. Dixon, Abel Wade, Christopher Netherton. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Granberg F, Torresi C, Oggiano A, Malmberg M, Iscaro C, De Mia GM, et al. Complete Genome <lb/>Sequence of an African Swine Fever Virus Isolate from Sardinia, Italy. Genome Announc. 2016; 4(6): <lb/>e01220-16. Epub 20161117. https://doi.org/10.1128/genomeA.01220-16 PMID: 27856577; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMC5114369. <lb/>2. Forth JH, Forth LF, Blome S, Ho ¨per D, Beer M. African swine fever whole-genome sequencing-Quantity <lb/>wanted but quality needed. PLoS pathogens. 2020; 16(8):e1008779. Epub 2020/08/28. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.ppat.1008779 PMID: 32853289; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7451517. <lb/>3. Bastos AD, Penrith ML, Cruciere C, Edrich JL, Hutchings G, Roger F, et al. Genotyping field strains of <lb/>African swine fever virus by partial p72 gene characterisation. Arch Virol. 2003; 148(4):693-706. Epub <lb/>2003/03/29. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-002-0946-8 PMID: 12664294. <lb/>4. Gallardo C, Mwaengo DM, Macharia JM, Arias M, Taracha EA, Soler A, et al. Enhanced discrimination <lb/>of African swine fever virus isolates through nucleotide sequencing of the p54, p72, and pB602L (CVR) <lb/>genes. Virus Genes. 2009; 38(1):85-95. Epub 2008/11/15. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11262-008-0293-2 <lb/>PMID: 19009341. <lb/>5. Gallardo C, Okoth E, Pelayo V, Anchuelo R, Martin E, Simon A, et al. African swine fever viruses with <lb/>two different genotypes, both of which occur in domestic pigs, are associated with ticks and adult wart-<lb/>hogs, respectively, at a single geographical site. J Gen Virol. 2011; 92(Pt 2):432-44. Epub 2010/10/23. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.025874-0 PMID: 20965989. <lb/>6. Gallardo C, Fernandez-Pinero J, Pelayo V, Gazaev I, Markowska-Daniel I, Pridotkas G, et al. Genetic <lb/>variation among African swine fever genotype II viruses, eastern and central Europe. Emerging infec-<lb/>tious diseases. 2014; 20(9):1544-7. Epub 2014/08/26. https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2009.140554 PMID: <lb/>25148518; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4178389. <lb/>7. Nix RJ, Gallardo C, Hutchings G, Blanco E, Dixon LK. Molecular epidemiology of African swine fever <lb/>virus studied by analysis of four variable genome regions. Arch Virol. 2006; 151(12):2475-94. Epub <lb/>20060703. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-006-0794-z PMID: 16817033. <lb/>8. Qu H, Ge S, Zhang Y, Wu X, Wang Z. A systematic review of genotypes and serogroups of African <lb/>swine fever virus. Virus Genes. 2022; 58(2):77-87. Epub 20220121. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11262-<lb/>021-01879-0 PMID: 35061204; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8778497. <lb/>9. Sereda AD, Balyshev VM, Kazakova AS, Imatdinov AR, Kolbasov DV. Protective Properties of Attenu-<lb/>ated Strains of African Swine Fever Virus Belonging to Seroimmunotypes I-VIII. Pathogens (Basel, <lb/>Switzerland). 2020; 9(4). Epub 20200409. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens9040274 PMID: <lb/>32283790; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7238197. <lb/>10. Malogolovkin A, Burmakina G, Titov I, Sereda A, Gogin A, Baryshnikova E, et al. Comparative analysis <lb/>of African swine fever virus genotypes and serogroups. Emerging infectious diseases. 2015; 21 <lb/>(2):312-5. Epub 2015/01/28. https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2102.140649 PMID: 25625574; PubMed Cen-<lb/>tral PMCID: PMC4313636. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>11. Luka PD, Achenbach JE, Mwiine FN, Lamien CE, Shamaki D, Unger H, et al. Genetic Characterization <lb/>of Circulating African Swine Fever Viruses in Nigeria (2007-2015). Transboundary and emerging dis-<lb/>eases. 2017; 64(5):1598-609. Epub 2016/08/03. https://doi.org/10.1111/tbed.12553 PMID: 27480888. <lb/>12. Minoungou GL, Diop M, Dakouo M, Ouattara AK, Settypalli TBK, Lo MM, et al. Molecular characteriza-<lb/>tion of African Swine fever viruses in Burkina Faso, Mali, and Senegal 1989-2016: Genetic diversity of <lb/>ASFV in West Africa. Transboundary and emerging diseases. 2021; 68(5):2842-52. Epub 2021/07/30. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/tbed.14240 PMID: 34323385. <lb/>13. Wade A, Achenbach JE, Gallardo C, Settypalli TBK, Souley A, Djonwe G, et al. Genetic characteriza-<lb/>tion of African swine fever virus in Cameroon, 2010-2018. Journal of microbiology (Seoul, Korea). <lb/>2019; 57(4):316-24. Epub 2019/04/01. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12275-019-8457-4 PMID: 30929230. <lb/>14. Masembe C, Adedeji AJ, Jambol AR, Weka R, Muwanika V, Luka PD. Diversity and emergence of new <lb/>variants of African swine fever virus Genotype I circulating in domestic pigs in Nigeria (2016-2018). Vet <lb/>Med Sci. 2023; 9(2):819-28. Epub 20221115. https://doi.org/10.1002/vms3.988 PMID: 36377750. <lb/>15. Adedeji AJ, Luka PD, Atai RB, Olubade TA, Hambolu DA, Ogunleye MA, et al. First-Time Presence of <lb/>African Swine Fever Virus Genotype II in Nigeria. Microbiol Resour Announc. 2021; 10(26):e0035021. <lb/>Epub 20210701. https://doi.org/10.1128/MRA.00350-21 PMID: 34197187; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC8248863. <lb/>16. Mouiche MMM, Noumedem RNG, Namegni RP, Feussom JMK, Moffo F, Okah-Nnane NH, et al. Afri-<lb/>can swine fever in the northern regions of Cameroon: seroprevalence survey and spatiotemporal analy-<lb/>sis of outbreaks from 2010 to 2017. Tropical animal health and production. 2021; 53(2):214. Epub 2021/ <lb/>03/21. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11250-021-02641-2 PMID: 33742284. <lb/>17. Ebwanga EJ, Ghogomu SM, Paeshuyse J. Molecular Characterization of ASFV and Differential Diag-<lb/>nosis of Erysipelothrix in ASFV-Infected Pigs in Pig Production Regions in Cameroon. Vet Sci. 2022; 9 <lb/>(8). Epub 2022/08/26. https://doi.org/10.3390/vetsci9080440 PMID: 36006355; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC9416451. <lb/>18. Mazur-Panasiuk N, Walczak M, Juszkiewicz M, Woźniakowski G. The Spillover of African Swine Fever <lb/>in Western Poland Revealed Its Estimated Origin on the Basis of O174L, K145R, MGF 505-5R and IGR <lb/>I73R/I329L Genomic Sequences. Viruses. 2020; 12(10). Epub 20200927. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>v12101094 PMID: 32992547; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7601147. <lb/>19. Tran HTT, Truong AD, Dang AK, Ly DV, Nguyen CT, Chu NT, et al. Circulation of two different variants <lb/>of intergenic region (IGR) located between the I73R and I329L genes of African swine fever virus strains <lb/>in Vietnam. Transboundary and emerging diseases. 2021; 68(5):2693-5. Epub 2021/01/21. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1111/tbed.13996 PMID: 33471420. <lb/>20. Tran HTT, Truong AD, Dang AK, Ly DV, Chu NT, Van Hoang T, et al. Novel method for sub-grouping of <lb/>genotype II African swine fever viruses based on the intergenic region between the A179L and A137R <lb/>genes. Vet Med Sci. 2022; 8(2):607-9. Epub 20211229. https://doi.org/10.1002/vms3.702 PMID: <lb/>34967133; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8959334. <lb/>21. Fiori MS, Sanna D, Scarpa F, Floris M, Di Nardo A, Ferretti L, et al. A Deeper Insight into Evolutionary <lb/>Patterns and Phylogenetic History of ASFV Epidemics in Sardinia (Italy) through Extensive Genomic <lb/>Sequencing. Viruses. 2021; 13(10). Epub 20211004. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13101994 PMID: <lb/>34696424; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8539718. <lb/>22. Ekue NF, Wilkinson PJ, Wardley RC. Infection of pigs with the Cameroon isolate (Cam/82) of African <lb/>swine fever virus. J Comp Pathol. 1989; 100(2):145-54. Epub 1989/02/01. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>0021-9975(89)90125-4 PMID: 2715397. <lb/>23. Rathakrishnan A, Reis AL, Moffat K, Dixon LK. Isolation of Porcine Bone Marrow Cells and Generation <lb/>of Recombinant African Swine Fever Viruses. Methods in molecular biology (Clifton, NJ). 2022; <lb/>2503:73-94. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-0716-2333-6_5 PMID: 35575887. <lb/>24. King DP, Reid SM, Hutchings GH, Grierson SS, Wilkinson PJ, Dixon LK, et al. Development of a Taq-<lb/>Man PCR assay with internal amplification control for the detection of African swine fever virus. Journal <lb/>of virological methods. 2003; 107(1):53-61. Epub 2002/11/26. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0166-0934(02) <lb/>00189-1 PMID: 12445938. <lb/>25. Prjibelski A, Antipov D, Meleshko D, Lapidus A, Korobeynikov A. Using SPAdes De Novo Assembler. <lb/>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics. 2020; 70(1):e102. https://doi.org/10.1002/cpbi.102 PMID: 32559359. <lb/>26. Tcherepanov V, Ehlers A, Upton C. Genome Annotation Transfer Utility (GATU): rapid annotation of <lb/>viral genomes using a closely related reference genome. BMC genomics. 2006; 7:150. Epub 2006/06/ <lb/>15. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-7-150 PMID: 16772042; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC1534038. <lb/>27. Cackett G, Matelska D, Sy ´kora M, Portugal R, Malecki M, Ba ¨hler J, et al. The African Swine Fever Virus <lb/>Transcriptome. J Virol. 2020; 94(9). Epub 2020/02/23. https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00119-20 PMID: <lb/>32075923; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7163114. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 9 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>28. Lehwark P, Greiner S. GB2sequin-A file converter preparing custom GenBank files for database sub-<lb/>mission. Genomics. 2019; 111(4):759-61. Epub 20180526. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygeno.2018.05. <lb/>003 PMID: 29842948. <lb/>29. Ya ´ñez RJ, Rodrı ´guez JM, Nogal ML, Yuste L, Enrı ´quez C, Rodrı ´guez JF, et al. Analysis of the complete <lb/>nucleotide sequence of African swine fever virus. Virology. 1995; 208:259-78. https://doi.org/10.1006/ <lb/>viro.1995.1149 PMID: 11831707 <lb/>30. Owolodun OA, Bastos AD, Antiabong JF, Ogedengbe ME, Ekong PS, Yakubu B. Molecular characteri-<lb/>sation of African swine fever viruses from Nigeria (2003-2006) recovers multiple virus variants and reaf-<lb/>firms CVR epidemiological utility. Virus Genes. 2010; 41(3):361-8. Epub 2010/01/07. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s11262-009-0444-0 PMID: 20052526. <lb/>31. Chapman DA, Tcherepanov V, Upton C, Dixon LK. Comparison of the genome sequences of non-path-<lb/>ogenic and pathogenic African swine fever virus isolates. J Gen Virol. 2008; 89(Pt 2):397-408. Epub <lb/>2008/01/17. https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.83343-0 PMID: 18198370. <lb/>32. Mebus CA, Dardiri AH. Additional characteristics of disease caused by the African swine fever viruses <lb/>isolated from Brazil and the Dominican Republic. Proc Annu Meet U S Anim Health Assoc. 1979;( <lb/>83):227-39. PMID: 298918. <lb/>33. Mebus CA, Dardiri AH, Hamdy FM, Ferris DH, Hess WR, Callis JJ. Some characteristics of african <lb/>swine fever viruses isolated from Brazil and the Dominican Republic. Proc Annu Meet U S Anim Health <lb/>Assoc. 1978;(82):232-6. PMID: 287093 <lb/>34. Boinas FS, Hutchings GH, Dixon LK, Wilkinson PJ. Characterization of pathogenic and non-pathogenic <lb/>African swine fever virus isolates from Ornithodoros erraticus inhabiting pig premises in Portugal. J Gen <lb/>Virol. 2004; 85(Pt 8):2177-87. Epub 2004/07/23. https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.80058-0 PMID: <lb/>15269356. <lb/>35. Franzoni G, Dei Giudici S, Loi F, Sanna D, Floris M, Fiori M, et al. African Swine Fever Circulation <lb/>among Free-Ranging Pigs in Sardinia: Data from the Eradication Program. Vaccines. 2020;8(3). Epub <lb/>20200921. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines8030549 PMID: 32967098; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC7563918. <lb/>36. Cackett G, Portugal R, Matelska D, Dixon L, Werner F. African Swine Fever Virus and Host Response: <lb/>Transcriptome Profiling of the Georgia 2007/1 Strain and Porcine Macrophages. J Virol. 2022; 96(5): <lb/>e0193921. Epub 20220112. https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.01939-21 PMID: 35019713; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC8906413. <lb/>37. Wo ¨hnke E, Fuchs W, Hartmann L, Blohm U, Blome S, Mettenleiter TC, et al. Comparison of the Prote-<lb/>omes of Porcine Macrophages and a Stable Porcine Cell Line after Infection with African Swine Fever <lb/>Virus. Viruses. 2021;13(11). Epub 20211101. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13112198 PMID: 34835004; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8620826. <lb/>38. Alejo A, Matamoros T, Guerra M, Andres G. A proteomic atlas of the African swine fever virus particle. J <lb/>Virol. 2018; 92(23):e01293-18. Epub 2018/09/07. https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01293-18 PMID: <lb/>30185597. <lb/>39. Portugal R, Coelho J, Hoper D, Little NS, Smithson C, Upton C, et al. Related strains of African swine <lb/>fever virus with different virulence: genome comparison and analysis. J Gen Virol. 2015; 96(Pt 2):408-<lb/>19. Epub 2014/11/20. https://doi.org/10.1099/vir.0.070508-0 PMID: 25406173. <lb/>40. Rodriguez JM, Moreno LT, Alejo A, Lacasta A, Rodriguez F, Salas ML. Genome Sequence of African <lb/>Swine Fever Virus BA71, the Virulent Parental Strain of the Nonpathogenic and Tissue-Culture Adapted <lb/>BA71V. PloS one. 2015; 10(11):e0142889. Epub 2015/12/01. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0142889 PMID: 26618713; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4664411. <lb/>41. Spinard E, O&apos;Donnell V, Vuono E, Rai A, Davis C, Ramirez-Medina E, et al. Full genome sequence for <lb/>the African swine fever virus outbreak in the Dominican Republic in 1980. Scientific reports. 2023; 13 <lb/>(1):1024. Epub 20230119. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-25987-5 PMID: 36658154. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>ASFV genome sequences from Cameroon <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0293049 March 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 9 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>