<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:02:17.257Z">11/20/2025 10:02:17 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:02:04.855193Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:02:04.855193Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Research Article <lb/>Wensheng Zhao, Guotao Fang, Xiao Qin*, and Jie Mao <lb/>Multiscale characterization of the UV aging <lb/>resistance and mechanism of light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/rams-2023-0152 <lb/>received July 01, 2023; accepted December 06, 2023 <lb/>Abstract: To clarify the effect and mechanism of hindered <lb/>amine light stabilizer (HALS) on the UV aging behavior of <lb/>asphalt binder, T622-HALS was selected as the modifier <lb/>for UV aging resistance of asphalt. The physicochemical <lb/>properties and microstructure of T622 light stabilizer <lb/>were comprehensively analyzed. The light stabilizer-mod-<lb/>ified asphalt was prepared and placed in the UV radiation <lb/>chamber for UV aging treatment. Scanning electron micro-<lb/>scope and atomic force microscope were used to analyze <lb/>the microscopic morphology evolution of light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt induced by UV radiation. The thermal <lb/>properties and functional group composition changes in <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt during UV aging were stu-<lb/>died by using the thermogravimetric and infrared spectro-<lb/>scopy combined testing system. The decay laws of the <lb/>physical and rheological performances of light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt were studied during UV aging process, <lb/>and the effect of light stabilizer on the UV aging behavior <lb/>of asphalt binder was clarified. The research results indi-<lb/>cated that HALSs could alleviate the microcracks and <lb/>roughness change on the surface of asphalt and reduce <lb/>the content of functional groups such as carbonyl and sulf-<lb/>oxide in asphalt. Furthermore, HALS could reduce the <lb/>value difference of physical and rheological properties of <lb/>asphalt before and after UV aging, significantly improving <lb/>the UV aging resistance of asphalt binder. <lb/>Keywords: asphalt, UV aging, characterization <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Asphalt pavement is prone to material and structural dur-<lb/>ability issues during service, leading to service failure. The <lb/>aging of asphalt due to heat and ultraviolet radiation is an <lb/>important factor leading to the degradation of asphalt <lb/>pavement performance, which is a particularly common <lb/>problem in high-altitude areas [1,2]. Asphalt aging behavior <lb/>could be mainly derived from its molecular structure <lb/>changes irreversibly with UV radiation or heat effect, <lb/>resulting in degraded flexibility of asphalt mixture and <lb/>cracking problem [3,4]. The aging of asphalt mainly includes <lb/>two types: ultraviolet aging and thermal oxygen aging, <lb/>among which ultraviolet aging mainly refers to the aging <lb/>of asphalt during the application of pavement in the open <lb/>traffic environment. Thermal oxygen aging refers to the <lb/>aging of asphalt during production, storage, transportation, <lb/>as well as the mixing, transportation, and paving stages of <lb/>asphalt mixtures [5]. To mitigate the UV aging problem of <lb/>asphalt pavement during application, light absorbing or <lb/>shielding materials could be added to the asphalt to enhance <lb/>its resistance to UV aging by shielding UV light, isolating oxygen, <lb/>or capturing oxygen-containing free radicals [6,7]. Currently, the <lb/>main modifying agents used in asphalt consist of carbon black, <lb/>nano oxides, layered silicates, UV absorbers, and layered double <lb/>hydroxy composite metal hydroxides [8-12]. These commonly <lb/>used modifying agents could improve the UV light aging resis-<lb/>tance of asphalt [13]. However, the addition of carbon black and <lb/>layered silicate would reduce the low-temperature performance <lb/>of asphalt. The compatibility between nano oxide, layered <lb/>double hydroxyl composite metal hydroxide, and asphalt is <lb/>poor, which would lead to the degradation of UV resistance <lb/>[14,15]. As a new type of asphalt aging control agent, ultraviolet <lb/>light absorbers have good compatibility with asphalt and excel-<lb/>lent dispersibility, gradually becoming one of the important <lb/>choices for ultraviolet aging control of pavement materials. <lb/></body>

	<front>Wensheng Zhao: National Engineering Research Center of Highway <lb/>Maintenance Technology, Changsha University of Science &amp; Technology, <lb/>Changsha, 410114, China; School of Traffic &amp; Transportation Engineering, <lb/>Changsha University of Science &amp; Technology, Changsha, 410114, China <lb/>Guotao Fang: Guangzhou HuaHui Traffic Technology Co.,Ltd., <lb/>Guangzhou 510335, China <lb/> <lb/>* Corresponding author: Xiao Qin, School of Transportation and Civil <lb/>Engineering and Architecture, Foshan University, Foshan 528000, China, <lb/>e-mail: qinnao@126.com <lb/>Jie Mao: Engineering Department, Guangdong GuanYue Highway &amp; <lb/>Bridge Co., Ltd., Guangzhou 511450, China <lb/>Reviews on Advanced Materials Science 2024; 63: 20230152 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

	<body>As an excellent UV absorber, hindered amine light <lb/>stabilizer (HALS) could achieve UV resistance improve-<lb/>ment through multiple ways such as decomposing hydro-<lb/>peroxide, quenching excited state oxygen, and capturing <lb/>free radicals, of which the most typical mechanism is to <lb/>capture free radicals [16]. HALS belongs to the class of free <lb/>radical trapping agents in light stabilizers, which could <lb/>effectively inhibit the photolysis of organic polymer com-<lb/>pounds, have low mobility, and withstand long-term oxida-<lb/>tion [17-19]. The HALS achieves UV aging resistance by <lb/>quenching singlet oxygen, capturing free radicals, and <lb/>decomposing hydrogen peroxide compounds [20]. HALSs <lb/>have been gradually applied as modifiers in asphalt bin-<lb/>ders due to their excellent resistance to UV aging, thereby <lb/>forming a good inhibitory effect on the UV aging behavior <lb/>of asphalt binders. Regarding the main UV resistance-improving <lb/>mechanism of HALS, researcher explored through different <lb/>aspects. For quenching singlet oxygen, researchers [21-24] <lb/>found that the conjugated structural groups contained in <lb/>organic polymer materials absorb the energy of ultraviolet <lb/>rays to produce singlet oxygen and R-O radicals. R-O• radi-<lb/>cals would trigger HALS to generate hindered amine nitrogen <lb/>oxygen radical compounds, which could efficiently reduce <lb/>the energy of singlet oxygen in the electronic excited state <lb/>and transform it into the oxygen stable state. Regarding cap-<lb/>turing free radicals, current studies supposed that HALS is the <lb/>derivative of tetramethylpiperidine, which is oxidized by per-<lb/>oxides generated by polymer light to form stable tetramethyl-<lb/>piperidine nitroxide radicals. It could efficiently capture alkyl, <lb/>alkoxy, and peroxyalkyl radicals generated by UV excitation, <lb/>generate stable compounds without destructive effects, and <lb/>continue to interact with the radicals to regenerate tetra-<lb/>methylpiperidine nitroxide radicals [25,26]. For decomposing <lb/>hydrogen peroxide compounds, HALS could effectively con-<lb/>vert hydrogen peroxide compounds into highly efficient and <lb/>stable nitrogen oxygen free radical compounds [27,28]. At <lb/>present, research on the use of HALSs for the control of <lb/>asphalt UV aging mainly focuses on the rheological properties <lb/>and changes of internal microstructure or components of <lb/>modified asphalt after UV aging. Feng and Xu [29,30] investi-<lb/>gated the impact of HALS on the technical property of asphalt <lb/>and revealed that HALS could achieve the UV aging delay <lb/>of asphalt and also could improve the thermal stability of <lb/>asphalt. Zhang [6] focused on the rheological properties of <lb/>HALS-modified asphalt and proposed the optimal evaluating <lb/>indices of rheological properties. Liu and Sun [13] explored <lb/>the effect of HALS on the micro-structure and functional <lb/>group, which confirms the improving effect of HALS of UV <lb/>resistance of asphalt. Yu and Qian [19,31] clarified the varia-<lb/>tion of microstructure during the whole UV aging period and <lb/>confirmed the typical UV aging microstructure of asphalt. <lb/>Although the results of current studies clarify the feasibility <lb/>of HALS in asphalt pavement materials, the actual improving <lb/>effect of HALS is uncertain and unstable because of unclear <lb/>mechanisms. Moreover, there is a lack of research on the <lb/>actual intervention mechanism of HALSs on asphalt UV aging <lb/>behavior [32]. However, the chemical composition of asphalt <lb/>materials is extremely complex, which has significant differ-<lb/>ences from polymer materials of certain molecular chain <lb/>configurations and degree of polymerization. Simply repli-<lb/>cating the application experience of HALS in polymer mate-<lb/>rials has certain blindness for the UV aging control of asphalt <lb/>pavement materials, which also makes it difficult for HALS to <lb/>maintain efficient and stable performance during the UV <lb/>aging resistance of asphalt binder. <lb/>Based on this research gap, for the purpose of exploring <lb/>the effect and mechanism of HALS on the UV resistance of <lb/>asphalt, this article selects T622 HALS as the modifier and <lb/>investigates the impact of T622 on the performance, micro-<lb/>structure, and chemical composition to explore its effect <lb/>mechanism on asphalt. Scanning electron microscope <lb/>(SEM) and atomic force microscope (AFM) were used to <lb/>analyze the microscopic morphology evolution of light <lb/>stabilizer-modified asphalt induced by UV aging. The <lb/>thermal properties and functional group composition <lb/>changes in light stabilizer-modified asphalt during UV <lb/>aging process were studied by applying the thermogravi-<lb/>metric and infrared spectroscopy combined testing system. <lb/>The characteristics of rheological performance, micromor-<lb/>phology, and chemical property of light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt were systematically studied during the whole UV <lb/>aging process to clarify the effect and mechanism of HALS <lb/>on the UV aging behavior of asphalt binder. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Materials <lb/>2.1.1 Light stabilizer <lb/>Based on the excellent application effect of light stabilizer <lb/>in polymer, Tinuvin622 (T622) HALS was preferred as anti-<lb/>aging agent to prepare modified asphalt. Its molecular for-<lb/>mula is C 15 H 29 NO 6 , molecular weight is 319.4, and fineness <lb/>is 300 mesh. The application dosage of light stabilizer in <lb/>asphalt was 0.2-0.8%, and the selected HALS was purchased <lb/>from Guangzhou Honghai New Materials Technology Co., <lb/>Ltd. The mechanism of HALSs when blended with asphalt <lb/>is shown in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

	<page>2</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>2.1.2 Asphalt <lb/>70# base asphalt was selected as the carrier for the pre-<lb/>paration of light stabilizer-modified asphalt. The technical <lb/>performance of 70# base asphalt was tested according to <lb/>the &quot;Test Specification for Asphalt and Asphalt Mixtures in <lb/>Highway Engineering&quot; (JTG E20-2019). The index values of <lb/>technical performances of 70# matrix asphalt are shown in <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>2.1.3 Preparation of light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>The preparation process of light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>is mainly as follows (Figure 2) (Sun et al. 2020, 2021): First, <lb/>place the 70# base asphalt into the oven of 130°C for 2 h of <lb/>insulation. Pour the molten asphalt into a clean beaker and <lb/>place it on the oil bath heating device at 160 ± 5°C for insula-<lb/>tion. Add the pre-weighed HALS (T622) into the asphalt and <lb/>stir the mixture at the shear speed of 3,000 rpm for 5 min. <lb/>Place the prepared light stabilizer-modified asphalt into the <lb/>oven of 120°C constant temperature to swelling and obtain <lb/>the sample of light stabilizer-modified asphalt. <lb/>2.2 Methodology <lb/>2.2.1 Sample preparation method <lb/>The samples of physical tests and rheological properties <lb/>(DSR and BBR) were made according to the &quot;Test Specification <lb/>for Asphalt and Asphalt Mixtures in Highway Engineering&quot; (JTG <lb/>E20-2019) and subjected to UV radiation. The samples of <lb/>micro tests (TG, SEM, AFM, and FTIR) in this study were <lb/>prepared to the film of 2 mm thick first. The modified <lb/>asphalt film was subjected to UV aging treatment and <lb/>then made into samples for experimental tests. For micro-<lb/>experiment (SEM, AFM, FTIR-TG), the samples were <lb/>obtained from the surface of film and then were per-<lb/>formed tests. The UV aging samples of different tests <lb/>are shown in Figure 3. <lb/>2.2.2 UV aging treatment method <lb/>The most unfavorable ultraviolet radiation conditions are <lb/>taken as the main calculation basis, and the conversion <lb/>method based on energy conversion is used to convert <lb/>indoor and outdoor ultraviolet aging time (Formula 1). <lb/>The annual radiation intensity of sunlight in high-altitude areas <lb/>is about 7,000 MJ•m -2 , with ultraviolet radiation accounting for <lb/>about 6% of the total amount of sunlight. Therefore, it can be <lb/>calculated that the average annual intensity of ultraviolet <lb/>Figure 1: Mechanism of hindered amine light stabilizers when blended with asphalt. <lb/>Table 1: Technical performance values of 70# matrix asphalt <lb/>Test items <lb/>Result <lb/>Technical requirement <lb/>Penetration (0.1 mm) <lb/>62.8 <lb/>60-80 <lb/>15°C Ductility (cm) <lb/>&gt;100 <lb/>&gt;100 <lb/>Softening point (°C) <lb/>47.6 <lb/>≥45 <lb/>Brookfield viscosity <lb/>(135°C, mPa•s) <lb/>509.7 <lb/>-<lb/>Solubility (%) <lb/>99.7 <lb/>≥99.5 <lb/>Wax content (%) <lb/>2.0 <lb/>≤2.2 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>3 <lb/></page>

	<body>radiation is about 420 MJ•m -2 . The UV radiant intensity of the <lb/>artificially accelerated UV light source is about 375 W•m -2 , <lb/>which can convert the artificially accelerated UV aging time <lb/>to about 305 h. The indoor UV aging equipment is an HD-E802-S <lb/>UV aging test chamber produced by Haida International Equip-<lb/>ment Co., Ltd. The UV radiation intensity was 300 W•m -2 and <lb/>the radiation area was 0.8 m 2 . <lb/>= <lb/>× <lb/>-<lb/>T <lb/>W <lb/>θ <lb/>W <lb/>/3,600 <lb/>, <lb/>UV indoor <lb/>solar <lb/>indoor <lb/>(1) <lb/>where T UV-indoor : indoor UV treatment time (h), W solar : the <lb/>annual radiation intensity of sunlight in high-altitude areas <lb/>(MJ•m -2 ), θ: the rate of ultraviolet radiation accounting for <lb/>the total amount of sunlight (%), and W indoor : UV radiant <lb/>intensity of the artificially accelerated UV light source. <lb/>2.2.3 X-ray diffraction (XRD) test <lb/>The chemical structure of the HALS was characterized by <lb/>applying the German Bruker D8 ADVANCE X-ray diffraction <lb/>instrument. The molecular crystal structure information <lb/>was calculated using the Scheler formula. The experimental <lb/>Figure 2: Preparation process of hindered amine light stabilizer-modified asphalt. <lb/>Figure 3: UV aging samples of different tests. <lb/></body>

	<page>4</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>scanning angle range was 1.5-60°, the scanning rate was <lb/>5°•min -1 , and the step size was 0.02°. <lb/>2.2.4 Focused ion beam scanning electron microscopy/ <lb/>energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy test (FIB-<lb/>SEM/EDS) <lb/>The focused ion beam scanning electron microscopy (FIB-<lb/>SEM) was used to characterize the micromorphology of the <lb/>HALS and modified asphalt of different UV aging times. <lb/>EDS spectroscopy was used to analyze the elemental com-<lb/>position of HALS. The micromorphology magnification <lb/>included 2,000, 4,000, and 10,000 times. <lb/>2.2.5 AFM <lb/>The surface roughness of UV-aged modified asphalt was <lb/>characterized by using the Bruker Dimension FastScan <lb/>scanning probe microscope. The fast scanning probe was <lb/>used to scan the micromorphology of the sample surface in <lb/>ScanAsyst intelligent mode. The instrument probe used <lb/>was the silicon nitride cantilever probe, and the scanning <lb/>field sizes were 80 μm × 80 μm. <lb/>2.2.6 Thermogravimetric-infrared spectroscopy <lb/>combined test (FTIR-TG) <lb/>The thermal properties and functional group composition <lb/>of T622 light stabilizer and its modified asphalt were ana-<lb/>lyzed by using the TG 209 F1 thermogravimetric infrared <lb/>spectroscopy system produced by NETZSCH in Germany. <lb/>The infrared spectroscopy test was conducted in the nitrogen <lb/>atmosphere under the condition of 32 times and the resolu-<lb/>tion of 4 cm -1 . The reaction gas for thermogravimetric ana-<lb/>lysis was nitrogen, with the purge flow rate of 50 mL•min -1 , <lb/>the heating rate of 10°C•min -1 , and the test temperature range <lb/>of 30-500°C. <lb/>2.2.7 Physical and mechanical properties <lb/>The penetration, softening point, and ductility tests were <lb/>carried out in accordance with the &quot;Test Specification for <lb/>Asphalt and Asphalt Mixtures in Highway Engineering&quot; (JTG <lb/>E20-2019). The testing temperature for penetration test was <lb/>25°C. The ductility test temperature was 15°C and the stretching <lb/>speed was 5 cm•min -1 . The starting temperature of the soft-<lb/>ening point test was 25°C and the heating rate was 5°C•min -1 . <lb/>2.2.8 Rheological properties <lb/>2.2.8.1 Temperature scanning (TS) test <lb/>The TS test adopted strain control mode. The control strain <lb/>was 12% and the test frequency was 10 rad•s -1 . The 25 mm <lb/>parallel plate was used for testing and the plate spacing <lb/>was 1 mm. The test temperature range was 46∼82°C, and <lb/>the heating interval was 6°C. At each set temperature, the <lb/>test was held for 10 min and the shear composite modulus <lb/>and phase angle values were recorded by every 2 min. Five <lb/>data points were obtained at each set temperature and the <lb/>average value was calculated. <lb/>2.2.8.2 Rheological test of low-temperature <lb/>bending beam <lb/>According to JTG E20-2019 &quot;Test Specification for Asphalt <lb/>and Asphalt Mixtures in Highway Engineering&quot; T0627 <lb/>Asphalt bending creep stiffness test (Bending beam rhe-<lb/>ometer method), the BBR test was conducted. The BBR test <lb/>was conducted by using the Cannon TE-BBR bending <lb/>beam rheometer and the test temperature was -12°C. <lb/>The creep stiffness S and creep rate m of modified asphalt <lb/>were tested at 60 s. <lb/>3 Results and discussion <lb/>3.1 Analysis of physicochemical properties of <lb/>HALSs <lb/>3.1.1 XRD test <lb/>The XRD diffraction test results of T622 light stabilizer are <lb/>shown in Figure 4. From Figure 4, it could be analyzed that <lb/>the T622 light stabilizer not only has peaks around 15°but <lb/>also has a certain range of broad peaks after 30°. This <lb/>indicated that the structure of T622 HALS coexisted with <lb/>crystalline and amorphous structures. According to the <lb/>calculation of crystallinity and Xie Le formula, its crystal-<lb/>linity is about 64.22%. <lb/>3.1.2 FIB-SEM/EDS <lb/>At the magnification of 2,000 times (Figure 5a), the T622 <lb/>light stabilizer mainly consists of circular structures. In <lb/>addition to the elliptical structures of similar sizes, there <lb/>are a small number of rod-shaped structures and larger <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>5 <lb/></page>

	<body>elliptical structures. When the complete elliptical structure <lb/>in the characterization results is further magnified to 5,000 <lb/>times (Figure 5b), it could be observed that the surface of <lb/>the ellipse is relatively smooth. There are a small number <lb/>of horizontally distributed cracks in the middle, and one of <lb/>the open cracks partially displays its internal structure. <lb/>There are vertical cracks on the left edge, which has the <lb/>color difference between the structural edge and inside <lb/>part. This might be due to the height difference between <lb/>the edge structure and the internal structure, resulting in <lb/>uneven color distribution in the electron microscopy char-<lb/>acterization results, which indicates that the surface of the <lb/>T622 structure has certain high and low fluctuations and <lb/>roughness. Under 10,000 times magnification (Figure 5c), <lb/>there are many cracks, grooves, potholes, and layers on the <lb/>surface, resulting in the more complex structural on T622 <lb/>particle surface. Figure 5d and e shows the distribution of <lb/>the two elements with the highest content, verifying that <lb/>the key elements of T622 light stabilizer are mainly C and <lb/>O. The distribution of these two elements in the structure is <lb/>basically consistent with the position of the microstruc-<lb/>ture, which are distributed on both the surface and plane <lb/>of the structure. <lb/>3.1.3 TG test <lb/>From the analysis of the thermogravimetric curve in Figure 6, it <lb/>could be known that the T622 light stabilizer begins to decom-<lb/>pose when the temperature rises to 205°C. Meanwhile, the DTG <lb/>curve shows that the T622 light stabilizer exhibits the maximum <lb/>weight loss peak at 357°C. At 407°C, the residual mass of T622 <lb/>light stabilizer is only 0.78%, almost completely decomposed, <lb/>Figure 4: XRD test results of T622. <lb/>Figure 5: Micromorphology and element composition results of T622. (a) SEM-2000 times; (b) SEM-5000 times; (c) SEM-10000 times; (d) EDS-C <lb/>element; (e) EDS-O element and (f) EDS result. <lb/></body>

	<page>6</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>and the pyrolysis reaction has basically ended. Afterwards, as <lb/>the temperature continues increasing to the ending temperature <lb/>of 500°C, the weight change of T622 light stabilizer is almost zero. <lb/>According to the pyrolysis curve and Table 2, the initial decom-<lb/>position temperature of T622 light stabilizer is 205°C. According <lb/>to the DTG curve, as the temperature increases, the decomposi-<lb/>tion rate of T622 light stabilizer is faster. The temperature corre-<lb/>sponding to the maximum weight loss rate is 357°C. Under the <lb/>influence of high temperature, the internal structural chain <lb/>breaks, and almost all the materials undergo pyrolysis. The <lb/>remaining might be residual carbon materials that could not <lb/>be further decomposed. <lb/>3.1.4 Dynamic FTIR test <lb/>From Figure 7, it could be analyzed that the T622 light <lb/>stabilizer is always in the stable stage during the first <lb/>28 min of dynamic heating, indicating that there is little <lb/>detection of material production during this time period, <lb/>and the intensity is almost at the zero scale position. After-<lb/>wards, as the temperature increases, the strength curve <lb/>begins to change. The infrared spectra of three character-<lb/>istic time points are obtained for analysis, namely 29.28 min <lb/>when the intensity began to change, 33.36 min when the <lb/>intensity reached its maximum value, and 39.32 min when <lb/>the intensity decreased to its minimum value. At 29.28 min, <lb/>substances are produced and the intensity of the G-S curve <lb/>begins to change. Multiple characteristic peaks with lower <lb/>intensity could be identified through spectral analysis, with <lb/>1809.86 and 1044.18 cm -1 being the C]O bond stretching <lb/>vibration of anhydride and the C-O bond of saturated fatty <lb/>anhydride, respectively. As the temperature continues to <lb/>rise, it reaches the maximum intensity at 33.36 min, and the <lb/>characteristic peak intensity in the spectrogram increases sig-<lb/>nificantly. A total of 2974.58 cm -1 represents the characteristic <lb/>peak of methyl group, and the two characteristic peaks <lb/>appearing in the range of 1751.17 and 1,050-1,300 cm -1 are <lb/>the C]O bond stretching vibration absorption of ester <lb/>group. When the time reaches 39.32 min, the strength curve <lb/>has already tended to be flatten out. At the same time, the <lb/>absorption peak in the spectral curve decreases and the <lb/>position of its characteristic peak remains unchanged. <lb/>3.2 Microscopic morphology evolution of <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>3.2.1 SEM test <lb/>3.2.1.1 Matrix asphalt <lb/>Figure 8 shows the characterization results of the UV-<lb/>induced microstructure of matrix asphalt with different <lb/>scanning times. From Figure 6a and b, it could be observed <lb/>that after 76.25 h UV aging treatment, there are obvious <lb/>aggregated parallel cracks (marked in yellow) on the sur-<lb/>face of asphalt, and there are locally closed like fragmenta-<lb/>tion areas (marked in red). After zooming in 500 times <lb/>Figure 6: Thermogravimetric analysis results of T622 light stabilizer. (a) TG and (b) DTG. <lb/>Table 2: Pyrolysis characteristic values of T622 light stabilizer <lb/>Modifier <lb/>T initial /°C <lb/>T end /°C <lb/>T max /°C <lb/>Residual rate/% <lb/>T622 <lb/>205 <lb/>407 <lb/>357 <lb/>0.78 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>7 <lb/></page>

	<body>(Figure 8c), it is found that the middle of the crack mostly <lb/>presents the straight line shape, while both ends show the <lb/>certain angle of deflection. There is no trend of intercon-<lb/>nectivity or continuity between different cracks. However, <lb/>when further amplification to 1,000 times (Figure 8c) and <lb/>2,000 times (Figure 8e), it could be confirmed that there is <lb/>no connection between cracks, which had independent <lb/>forms instead of connections. When the UV aging time is <lb/>extended to 152.5 h, it could be observed from Figure 8f that <lb/>a series of closed blocks appear on the asphalt surface, and <lb/>there is a clear shared boundary between these blocks. <lb/>After amplifying on the partially closed block (Figure 8g), <lb/>it could be found that the boundary of the block evolved <lb/>into the banded protrusion instead of crack. After further <lb/>amplification of the boundary, the morphology of the pro-<lb/>truding structure could be clearly observed, which has a <lb/>certain height difference compared to the surrounding flat <lb/>area that is mostly in the striped state. This is very similar to <lb/>the crack morphology that occurred at 75.25 h, possibly due <lb/>to the increasing temperature of asphalt after absorbing <lb/>ultraviolet radiation energy, which causes asphalt flowing <lb/>and filling the crack area to form the convex structure. <lb/>When the UV aging time reaches 228 h, it can be <lb/>observed from Figure 8k that dense parallel cracks appear <lb/>again on the asphalt surface. Different from 76.25 h, there <lb/>are also vertical cracks intersecting parallel cracks on the <lb/>surface of UV-aged asphalt at 228 h. This causes parallel <lb/>cracks to connect with each other, leading to the appear-<lb/>ance of closed cracks and blocky fragments. The cracks <lb/>amplified to 1,000 times and 2,000 times (Figure 8l and m) <lb/>reveal the presence of vertical crack connections between <lb/>different parallel cracks and the appearance of obvious <lb/>closed cracks, most of which are rectangular structures. <lb/>After further amplifying the rectangular structure (Figure <lb/>8n and o), the circular structure with the diameter of <lb/>approximately 1.5 μm is identified inside it. When the UV <lb/>aging time reaches 305 h, it can be observed from Figure <lb/>8p-r that the closed cracks on the asphalt surface disappear, <lb/>mainly appearing as parallel cracks. At the same time, the <lb/>density and number of cracks significantly decreased. After <lb/>locally enlarging the cracks to 4,000 and 8,000 times (Figure <lb/>8s and t), it is found that circular protrusions and holes of <lb/>different diameters appear in the surrounding areas of the <lb/>cracks. <lb/>Figure 7: Infrared spectral analysis results of T622 light stabilizer. (a) 2D result; (b) 3D result; (c) Intensity and (d) Transmittance. <lb/></body>

	<page>8</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>3.2.1.2 T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>Figure 9 shows the microstructure of T622 light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt at different UV stages. From the micro-<lb/>structure of the asphalt surface aged for 76.25 h in Figure <lb/>9a, it could be seen that there is the valley-shaped &quot;fold <lb/>structure&quot; in the micro area of the asphalt surface. The <lb/>structural form presents the micromorphology of depres-<lb/>sion in the middle and protrusions around it (marked in <lb/>yellow), whose width ranged approximately from 9.21 to <lb/>33.51 μm. At the magnification of 2,000 times (Figure 9d), it <lb/>could be observed that there are irregular protrusions in <lb/>the interval area of the fold structure. As the UV aging time <lb/>prolongs, the protruding structures gradually aggregate. <lb/>The edges of the structure tend to be smooth, and there <lb/>are no obvious wrinkles on the asphalt surface within the <lb/>characterization area. The UV aging time is extended by <lb/>152.25 h, and it can be observed from Figure 9k that the <lb/>connection between fold structures is closer and there is <lb/>obvious trend of interconnectivity between structures. <lb/>Further amplified to 2,000 times (Figure 9i) and 4,000 times <lb/>(Figure 9j), the boundaries formed by the folded structure <lb/>gradually blur, the structure sinks in and begins to merge <lb/>with adjacent structures, gradually transforming into par-<lb/>allel &quot;crack structures.&quot; From Figure 7n and o, it can be <lb/>seen that when the UV aging time is extended to 228 h, the <lb/>initial crack structure formed on the asphalt surface trans-<lb/>forms into the long strip like &quot;ridge&quot; structure similar to <lb/>the fold structure and gradually evolves into the tightly <lb/>connected fold structure. As the UV aging process deepens, <lb/>the density of fold structures increases significantly and is <lb/>parallel to each other, resulting in a narrow and elongated <lb/>overall structure. After UV aging for 305 h (Figure 9p), <lb/>the typical morphology changes from the original parallel <lb/>state &quot;fold structure&quot; to the potential cross-state &quot;network&quot; <lb/>structure. The structure presents the irregular block <lb/>shape, but the smooth area between the structures <lb/>increases without obvious crack boundaries. This indi-<lb/>cates that long-term UV aging has the significant impact <lb/>on the surface morphology of asphalt, forming potential <lb/>fragmented block-shaped areas. <lb/>Figure 8: Ultraviolet-induced microscopic morphology of matrix asphalt. (a) 76.25 h-95 times; (b) 76.25 h-200 times; (c) 76.25 h-500 times; <lb/>(d) 76.25 h-1000 times; (e) 152.5 h-200 times; (f) 152.5 h-500 times; (g) 152.5 h-1000 times; (h) 152.5 h-2000 times; (i) 225 h-500 times; (j) 225 h-1000 times; <lb/>(k) 225 h-2000 times; (l) 225 h-4000 times; (m) 305 h-500 times; (n) 305 h-1000 times; (o) 305 h-4000 times and (p) 305h-8000 times. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>9 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.2.2 AFM test <lb/>3.2.2.1 Matrix asphalt <lb/>Figures 10-11 show the AFM characterization results of <lb/>matrix asphalt under different UV aging times. It is found <lb/>from the AFM results that the roughness change of the base <lb/>asphalt results in the obvious bright and dark domain <lb/>zoning in the 2D morphology, and the granular structure <lb/>is evenly dispersed in the figure, with the overall surface <lb/>tending to be flat. In Figure 10b, there is a clear clustering <lb/>region boundary between the bright and dark domains, <lb/>indicating that as the UV aging process progresses, the <lb/>Figure 9: SEM morphology of T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt. (a) 76.25 h-200 times; (b) 76.25 h-500 times; (c) 76.25 h-1000 times; (d) 76.25 <lb/>h-2000 times; (e) 152.5 h-200 times; (f) 152.5 h-500 times; (g) 152.5 h-1000 times; (h) 152.5 h-2000 times; (i) 225 h-200 times; (j) 225 h-500 times; (k) <lb/>225 h-1000 times; (l) 225 h-2000 times; (m) 305 h-200 times; (n) 305 h-500 times; (o) 305 h-1000 times and (p) 305 h-4000 times. <lb/>Figure 10: AFM characterization results and grayscale processing of matrix asphalt at different UV aging times. (a) 0 h-2D; (b) 76.25 h-2D; (c) 152.5 h-<lb/>2D; (d) 228 h-2D; (e) 305 h-2D; (f) 0 h-2D; (g) 76.25 h-3D; (h) 152.5 h-3D; (i) 228 h-3D and (j) 305 h-3D. <lb/></body>

	<page>10</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>overall morphology of asphalt gradually becomes more <lb/>complex, which is also gradually reflected in subsequent <lb/>Figure 10c and d. As the UV aging time continues to extend, <lb/>the distribution of bright regions gradually concentrates, <lb/>and the boundary between bright and dark regions in <lb/>Figure 11d becomes more obvious. In the 3D analysis <lb/>results, the changes in surface morphology are more sig-<lb/>nificant. The total height of the aged matrix asphalt surface <lb/>in Figure 11b decreases, manifested as the uniformly dis-<lb/>tributed &quot;needle-like structure&quot; in the 3D morphology. <lb/>When the aging time reaches 228 h, the area of the bright <lb/>region begins to concentrate, and a large diameter aggre-<lb/>gated &quot;columnar structure&quot; appears in Figure 11d. When <lb/>the UV aging time reaches 305 h, the bright regions in <lb/>Figure 10e are highly concentrated, and there is a clear <lb/>aggregation convex structure on the surface of the matrix <lb/>asphalt in the 3D morphology image. <lb/>3.2.2.2 T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>Figure 11 shows the AFM characterization results of T622 <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt under different UV aging <lb/>times. According to Figure 11b, when the UV aging time <lb/>is 76.25 h, the boundary between the bright and dark <lb/>areas on the surface is not obvious and the distribution <lb/>of light and dark is mixed. According to the analysis in <lb/>Figure 11c and h, when the UV aging time reaches 152.5 h, <lb/>the micro surface height distribution of modified asphalt <lb/>is uniform and the fluctuation and protrusion structures <lb/>are reduced. When the aging time reaches 305 h, the <lb/>asphalt surface exhibits the bright and dark color distribu-<lb/>tion once again, presenting complex morphologies such as <lb/>peaks and valleys. <lb/>3.3 Thermophysical properties and <lb/>functional group composition of light <lb/>stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>3.3.1 TG test <lb/>3.3.1.1 Matrix asphalt <lb/>According to Figure 12 and Table 3, the initial decomposi-<lb/>tion temperature of 70# asphalt decreases from 232.6°C for <lb/>76.25 h to 158.8°C for 305 h. Under the influence of prolonged <lb/>UV aging time, the significant decrease in initial decomposi-<lb/>tion temperature leads to the later thermal decomposition of <lb/>asphalt at lower temperatures. The difference in decomposi-<lb/>tion temperature between the beginning and ending of aged <lb/>asphalt reached 73.8°C, and the decrease in decomposition <lb/>temperature indicates that the anti UV aging performance of <lb/>the asphalt stays in the low level without modification. At <lb/>the ending temperature, the residual weight rate of asphalt <lb/>remains around 20%, indicating that the remaining portion <lb/>is relatively stable and not directly related to the duration of <lb/>ultraviolet light exposure. <lb/>3.3.1.2 T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>From Figure 13 and Table 4, it can be seen that with the <lb/>extension of UV aging time, the initial weight loss tempera-<lb/>ture of T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt gradually <lb/>decreases from 180.2 to 172.9°C, with the temperature dif-<lb/>ference of about 7.3°C, which is much lower than the 73.8°C <lb/>of 70# asphalt. This indicates that the addition of HALSs <lb/>alleviates the impact of ultraviolet radiation effectively on <lb/>the thermal properties of asphalt. The increase in initial <lb/>decomposition temperature of modified asphalt is related <lb/>Figure 11: AFM characterization results and grayscale processing of T622-modified asphalt at different UV aging times. (a) 0 h-2D; (b) 76.25 h-2D; <lb/>(c) 152.5 h-2D; (d) 228 h-2D; (e) 305 h-2D; (f) 0h-2D; (g) 76.25 h-3D; (h) 152.5 h-3D; (i) 228 h-3D and (j) 305 h-3D. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<body>to the extension of aging time, which leads to the volatiliza-<lb/>tion and migration of light components, thereby affecting <lb/>the changes in thermal properties of asphalt. According to <lb/>the DTG curve analysis, the T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt corresponding to the four aging time points shows <lb/>the maximum weight loss rate in sequence within 450-460°C. <lb/>The temperature difference between the front and rear <lb/>remained around 3°C and dropped to the lowest point of <lb/>all aging times at the temperature corresponding to the <lb/>weight loss rate at the final aging time. This indicates that <lb/>T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt would undergo early <lb/>weight loss decomposition after long-term UV aging. The gra-<lb/>dual decrease in the final residual rate indicates that the <lb/>extension of UV aging time affects the final quality loss of <lb/>T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt. <lb/>3.3.2 FTIR test <lb/>3.3.2.1 Matrix asphalt <lb/>From Figure 14, it could be analyzed that the strong absorp-<lb/>tion peaks generated by 70# matrix asphalt under ultra-<lb/>violet radiation range from 2,800 to 3,000 cm -1 , and the <lb/>absorption peaks in this range are mainly caused by the <lb/>stretching vibration peaks of methylene and methyl. In <lb/>addition, there are intermediate strength carbonyl func-<lb/>tional groups at the wavenumber position of 1,700 cm -1 , <lb/>which are generated due to the reaction of internal com-<lb/>ponents of asphalt caused by temperature rise during the <lb/>experiment, such as carbonyl groups generated by oxygen <lb/>absorption reaction. The sulfoxide group is produced by the <lb/>reaction of asphalt-containing sulfides. As the temperature <lb/>Figure 12: Thermogravimetric curves of 70# matrix asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h-TG; (b) 152.5 h-TG; (c) 228 h-TG; (d) 305 h-TG; <lb/>(e) 76.25 h-DTG; (f) 152.5 h-DTG; (g) 228 h-DTG; (h) 305 h-DTG; (i) Comparison-TG and (j) Comparison-DTG. <lb/>Table 3: Thermogravimetric index of 70# asphalt under different UV aging times <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Initial decomposition <lb/>temperature (°C) <lb/>Temperature corresponding to <lb/>maximum weight loss rate (°C) <lb/>Weight loss rate (%) <lb/>76.25 <lb/>232.6 <lb/>459.6 <lb/>77.51 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>226.6 <lb/>455.1 <lb/>78.76 <lb/>228 <lb/>200.7 <lb/>450 <lb/>80.63 <lb/>305 <lb/>158.8 <lb/>447.6 <lb/>81.04 <lb/></body>

	<page>12</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>increases, the reaction rate of the matrix asphalt also <lb/>changes accordingly. <lb/>From Figure 15, it could be known that the extension of <lb/>UV aging time is not significantly related to the time when <lb/>the matrix asphalt product begins to form but corresponds <lb/>to the temperature at which reaches its peak. As the UV <lb/>aging time prolongs, the characteristic peak temperature <lb/>gradually increases, but the increase rate is relatively slow, <lb/>increasing by about 10°C throughout the entire UV aging <lb/>cycle. When prolonged ultraviolet radiation for 228 and <lb/>305 h, the absorption peak intensity in the region increases <lb/>at around 1,500 cm -1 This indicates that there is a signifi-<lb/>cant difference in the functional groups generated during <lb/>this period compared to before, which might be due to the <lb/>UV aging extension of asphalt binder. <lb/>Due to the differences in the spectra of 70# matrix <lb/>asphalt after aging compared to light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt, it is necessary to redefine the quantitative calcula-<lb/>tion formula for the spectra of 70# matrix asphalt. The <lb/>index ∑A is defined as follows: <lb/>∑ = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>A A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A . <lb/>1700 <lb/>1601 <lb/>1456 <lb/>1377 <lb/>1300 <lb/>1030 <lb/>902 <lb/>746 <lb/>(2) <lb/>According to the analysis of exponential growth of <lb/>functional groups in Table 5 and Figure 16, under the <lb/>action of 228-305 h ultraviolet radiation, the aging degree <lb/>of matrix asphalt without HALS is significantly greater <lb/>than that at the first two time points. After UV aging, the <lb/>functional group exponential growth of 70# matrix asphalt <lb/>increases by 7.82 times for the carbonyl group, 8.07 times <lb/>Figure 13: Thermogravimetric curves of T622-modified asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h-TG; (b) 152.5 h-TG; (c) 228 h-TG; (d) 305 h-TG; <lb/>(e) 76.25 h-DTG; (f) 152.5 h-DTG; (g) 228 h-DTG; (h) 305 h-DTG; (i) Comparison-TG and (j) Comparison-DTG. <lb/>Table 4: Thermogravimetric index of T622-modified asphalt under different UV aging times <lb/>Aging time <lb/>Initial decomposition <lb/>temperature (°C) <lb/>Temperature corresponding to <lb/>maximum weight loss rate (°C) <lb/>Weight loss rate (%) <lb/>76.25 h <lb/>180.2 <lb/>449.5 <lb/>81.4 <lb/>152.5 h <lb/>178.8 <lb/>456.9 <lb/>82.6 <lb/>228 h <lb/>177.1 <lb/>455.0 <lb/>83.0 <lb/>305 h <lb/>172.9 <lb/>453.1 <lb/>83.0 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<body>for the sulfoxide group, and 5.94 times for the aromatic func-<lb/>tional group. The exponential growth of the carbonyl group <lb/>and the sulfoxide group increases significantly, indicating that <lb/>the matrix asphalt has experienced obvious aging after a long <lb/>time of ultraviolet radiation, and the ultraviolet aging destroys <lb/>the colloidal structural stability inside asphalt. <lb/>3.3.2.2 T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>From Figures 17 and 18, it could be shown that the infrared <lb/>spectrum of T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt shows <lb/>almost no changes in the first 20 min (i.e., 230°C), with the <lb/>difference only manifested in the initial reaction time. After <lb/>10 min gentle period, the reaction begins to occur around <lb/>30 min. The degree of reaction increases gradually with time, <lb/>reaching its maximum peak around 43 min, corresponding to <lb/>435°C in the spectrogram. The strong absorption peak and the <lb/>shoulder peak of 2,860 cm -1 appear at 2,920 cm -1 , specifically <lb/>the asymmetric and symmetric stretching vibration peaks of <lb/>C-H in methylene -CH 2 -. The absorption peak of about <lb/>1,457 cm -1 is a shear vibration of methylene -CH 2 -. <lb/>Figure 14: 3D and 2D infrared spectra of 70# matrix asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h-2D; (b) 76.25 h-3D; (c) 152.5 h-2D; (d) 152.5 h-3D; <lb/>(e) 228 h-2D; (f) 228 h-3D; (g) 305 h-2D and (h) 305 h-3D. <lb/>Figure 15: Infrared spectra of 70# matrix asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h; (b) 152.5 h; (c) 228 h; (d) 305 h and (e) GS intensity. <lb/>Table 5: Aging index of characteristic functional groups of 70# matrix asphalt <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Index of characteristic functional groups <lb/>= = <lb/>I C O <lb/>I Ar <lb/>= = <lb/>I S O <lb/>76.25 <lb/>0.0832 <lb/>0.1181 <lb/>0.1181 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>0.0354 <lb/>0.0887 <lb/>0.0752 <lb/>228 <lb/>0.3526 <lb/>0.6135 <lb/>0.6718 <lb/>305 <lb/>0.7338 <lb/>1.0716 <lb/>0.8194 <lb/></body>

	<page>14</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>According to the analysis in Figures 17 and 18, the <lb/>functional group composition in the asphalt after UV aging <lb/>listed is basically consistent. The main difference is due to <lb/>the difference of aging time. This indicates that under the <lb/>modification effect of light stabilizers, asphalt could still <lb/>exhibit good performance when suffering from different <lb/>times of ultraviolet irradiation. The quantitative calcula-<lb/>tion of ∑A in the spectrum of T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt is redefined as follows: <lb/>∑ = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>A A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A . <lb/>1700 <lb/>1644 <lb/>1601 <lb/>1550 <lb/>1456 <lb/>1377 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1141 <lb/>1100 <lb/>1030 <lb/>890 <lb/>744 <lb/>(3) <lb/>Figure 16: Aging index variation of characteristic functional groups of 70# matrix asphalt. (a) I Ar ; (b) I C=O ; (c) I S=O and (d) Comparision. <lb/>Figure 17: 3D and 2D infrared spectra of T622-modified asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h-2D; (b) 76.25 h-3D; (c) 152.5 h-2D; <lb/>(d) 152.5 h-3D; (e) 228 h-2D; (f) 228 h-3D; (g) 305 h-2D and (h) 305 h-3D. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>15 <lb/></page>

	<body>From Table 6 and Figure 19, it could be analyzed that <lb/>with the extension of UV radiation time, there is a signifi-<lb/>cant increase in aromatic functional groups and carbonyl <lb/>index, with a more significant increase in the range of <lb/>76.25-152.5 h. This indicates that the aging of T622 asphalt <lb/>during this period is relatively affected by ultraviolet <lb/>radiation, which accelerates the transformation of internal <lb/>components in asphalt. After 152.5 h, the increase in UV <lb/>aging index becomes relatively slow, and the aromatic <lb/>functional groups also decreased to the certain extent. For <lb/>the sulfoxide group, the index remains at a high level at <lb/>76.25 h of the early stage of UV aging and at 305 h of the end <lb/>of UV aging, while it is relatively low at the intermediate time <lb/>points of 152.5 and 228 h. Although T622 light stabilizer-mod-<lb/>ified asphalt would still produce corresponding functional <lb/>groups under the influence of ultraviolet radiation, the growth <lb/>rate and exponential growth amount of relevant functional <lb/>map are significantly lower than that of base asphalt. This also <lb/>shows that the added light stabilizer could mitigate the <lb/>transmission of asphalt components during the UV aging <lb/>period. At the same time, the overall stability of the internal <lb/>colloidal structure of asphalt is strengthened, and the aging <lb/>resistance of asphalt is improved under the action of ultra-<lb/>violet radiation. <lb/>3.4 Physical and rheological properties of <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>3.4.1 Physical property <lb/>3.4.1.1 Matrix asphalt <lb/>The physical properties of 70# matrix asphalt under dif-<lb/>ferent UV aging times are shown in Table 7. From Table 7, it <lb/>could be seen that with the extension of UV aging time, the <lb/>penetration of 70# matrix asphalt shows a significant down-<lb/>ward trend, indicating that UV radiation would increase the <lb/>hardness of asphalt. The softening point of asphalt is signif-<lb/>icantly increased with the extension of UV aging time, <lb/>mainly due to the increase of heavy components in the <lb/>asphalt, which leads to the increase of asphalt viscosity. <lb/>The ductility of 70# matrix asphalt shows a significant <lb/>decrease with the UV aging process, which is directly related <lb/>Figure 18: Infrared spectra of T622-modified asphalt under different UV aging times. (a) 76.25 h; (b) 152.5 h; (c) 228 h; (d) 305 h and (e) GS intensity. <lb/>Table 6: Aging index of characteristic functional groups of T622-mod-<lb/>ified asphalt <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Index of characteristic functional groups <lb/>= = <lb/>I C O <lb/>I Ar <lb/>= = <lb/>I S O <lb/>76.25 <lb/>0.0209 <lb/>0.0122 <lb/>0.1481 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>0.0579 <lb/>0.0277 <lb/>0.1081 <lb/>228 <lb/>0.0599 <lb/>0.0233 <lb/>0.0445 <lb/>305 <lb/>0.0602 <lb/>0.0298 <lb/>0.1306 <lb/></body>

	<page>16</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>to the degradation in deformability of the asphalt, and this is <lb/>basically consistent with the change law of penetration. In <lb/>summary, UV aging could cause the matrix asphalt to <lb/>harden, manifested by the increase in the softening point <lb/>and the significant decrease in penetration and ductility of <lb/>the asphalt binder. <lb/>3.4.1.2 T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt <lb/>The physical performance test results of T622 light stabi-<lb/>lizer-modified asphalt under different UV aging times are <lb/>shown in Tables 8 and 10. According to the analysis in <lb/>Table 8, there is a certain difference in the penetration <lb/>difference of T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt within <lb/>the range of 0-305 h for UV aging. The penetration <lb/>Figure 19: Aging index variation of characteristic functional groups of T622-modified asphalt. (a) I Ar ; (b) I C=O ; (c) I S=O and (d) Comparision. <lb/>Table 7: Basic properties of 70# asphalt after UV aging <lb/>Aging <lb/>time (h) <lb/>Penetration <lb/>(0.1 mm) <lb/>Softening <lb/>point (°C) <lb/>Ductility <lb/>(cm) <lb/>76.25 <lb/>47.4 <lb/>48.7 <lb/>17.1 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>45.1 <lb/>51.4 <lb/>14.5 <lb/>228 <lb/>42.0 <lb/>55.8 <lb/>11.2 <lb/>305 <lb/>41.3 <lb/>59.4 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>Table 8: Penetration of ultraviolet aging T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Penetration (25°C, 0.1 mm) <lb/>0.2% <lb/>0.4% <lb/>0.6% <lb/>0.8% <lb/>76.25 <lb/>57.2 <lb/>55.8 <lb/>53.2 <lb/>51.2 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>55.9 <lb/>54.6 <lb/>53 <lb/>49.8 <lb/>228 <lb/>53.4 <lb/>52.5 <lb/>51.1 <lb/>48.9 <lb/>305 <lb/>50.1 <lb/>49.2 <lb/>46.4 <lb/>45.8 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>17 <lb/></page>

	<body>difference of modified asphalt before and after UV aging <lb/>with the content of T622 light stabilizer 0.4% is the smallest, <lb/>which indicates that the anti-aging performance of modified <lb/>asphalt is optimal when the content of T622 light stabilizer is <lb/>0.4%. From Table 9, it could be seen that after 305 h of UV <lb/>aging, the modified asphalt with the T622 light stabilizer con-<lb/>tent of 0.8% has the highest ductility difference, which is <lb/>related to the improvement effect of light stabilizers on <lb/>asphalt ductility. The difference in ductility between 0.2 and <lb/>0.4% T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt before and after UV <lb/>aging is the smallest, both around 4 cm. However, after UV <lb/>aging, the ductility of modified asphalt of high content T662 is <lb/>significantly higher than that of modified asphalt of low con-<lb/>tent. According to the analysis in Table 10, after 305 h of UV <lb/>aging, the difference in softening points of T622 light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt with different modifier dosages is around <lb/>3°C, and there is no significant increase or change. This indi-<lb/>cates that the T622 modifier could alleviate the impact of UV <lb/>aging effectively on the high-temperature performance of <lb/>asphalt, thereby achieving good UV aging resistance. <lb/>3.4.2 TS <lb/>Figure 20 shows the phase angle, complex modulus, and <lb/>rutting factor of TS tests for 70# matrix asphalt and light <lb/>stabilizer-modified asphalt, respectively. Through the ana-<lb/>lysis in Figure 20, it could be analyzed that the phase angle <lb/>of different types of asphalt increases with temperature, <lb/>which means that temperature change increases the visc-<lb/>osity of asphalt and reduces its elasticity. Meanwhile, with <lb/>the extension of UV aging time, the phase angles of 70# <lb/>matrix asphalt and light stabilizer-modified asphalt both <lb/>significantly decrease, indicating that UV radiation could <lb/>enhance the elastic response of asphalt, and the enhance-<lb/>ment effect becomes more obvious with the extension of <lb/>UV radiation time. It is worth noting that the phase angle of <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt decreases compared to the <lb/>matrix asphalt with the decrease in UV irradiation time, <lb/>indicating that T622 light stabilizer could enhance the anti-<lb/>UV aging effect of asphalt binder. The complex modulus of <lb/>different types of asphalt decreases gradually with tem-<lb/>perature. As the UV aging time prolongs, the complex mod-<lb/>ulus of asphalt increases significantly, indicating that after <lb/>the action of UV radiation, the asphalt binder exhibits <lb/>varying degrees of hardening and its resistance to defor-<lb/>mation is enhanced. Compared with the base asphalt, it <lb/>could be found that the increase of the complex modulus <lb/>of T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt has significantly <lb/>decreased, which proves that the anti-aging modifier has <lb/>good anti-UV aging performance and could inhibit the signifi-<lb/>cant changes of performance indices caused by UV radiation. <lb/>Meanwhile, when the UV aging time is within the range of <lb/>76.25-152.5 h, the complex modulus difference of light stabi-<lb/>lizer-modified asphalt is relatively small. With the extension <lb/>of UV irradiation time, the difference of complex modulus of <lb/>light stabilizer-modified asphalt becomes apparent gradually <lb/>and the hardness increases significantly. This indicates that in <lb/>the early stage of the UV radiation process, the influence of UV <lb/>radiation on the deformation resistance of asphalt is not sig-<lb/>nificant. As the UV radiation time continues to extend, its impact <lb/>increases gradually, resulting in a significant increase in the <lb/>hardness of the asphalt binder. The variation pattern of the <lb/>rutting factor is basically consistent with the complex modulus, <lb/>which gradually decreases with temperature, indicating that <lb/>ultraviolet radiation could improve the deformation resistance <lb/>of asphalt under high-temperature conditions. As the UV aging <lb/>time prolongs, the improvement effect gradually strengthens. It <lb/>is worth noting that compared to the base asphalt, the rutting <lb/>factor difference of T622-modified asphalt is not significant <lb/>between 76.25 and 152.5 h. As the UV aging time further <lb/>extends, the rutting factor of T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt decreases relatively, indicating that HALS could <lb/>improve the UV aging resistance of asphalt binder. <lb/>3.4.3 BBR test <lb/>Table 11 shows BBR test results of T622 light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt. According to Table 11, at different UV <lb/>Table 10: Softening point of ultraviolet aging T622 light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Softening point (°C) <lb/>0.2% <lb/>0.4% <lb/>0.6% <lb/>0.8% <lb/>76.25 <lb/>51.8 <lb/>52.8 <lb/>53.5 <lb/>55.3 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>52.2 <lb/>53.3 <lb/>54.6 <lb/>56.1 <lb/>228 <lb/>53.7 <lb/>54.3 <lb/>55.2 <lb/>57.9 <lb/>305 <lb/>54.9 <lb/>55.5 <lb/>56.5 <lb/>59.1 <lb/>Table 9: Ductility of ultraviolet aging T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt <lb/>Aging time (h) <lb/>Ductility (10°C, cm) <lb/>0.2% <lb/>0.4% <lb/>0.6% <lb/>0.8% <lb/>76.25 <lb/>9.4 <lb/>11.1 <lb/>12.9 <lb/>14.6 <lb/>152.5 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>10.2 <lb/>11.2 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>228 <lb/>6.3 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>9 <lb/>10.4 <lb/>305 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>8.6 <lb/></body>

	<page>18</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 20: Phase angle, complex modulus, and rutting factor of base asphalt and modified asphalt at different UV aging times. (a) Phase angle-70# <lb/>asphalt; (b) Phase angle-T622 modified asphalt; (c) Complex modulus-70# asphalt; (d) Complex modulus-T622 modified asphalt; (e) Rutting factor-70# <lb/>asphalt and (f) Rutting factor-T622 modified asphalt. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>19 <lb/></page>

	<body>aging times, the creep modulus of T622 light stabilizer-<lb/>modified asphalt is lower than that of 70# asphalt, and <lb/>the creep rate is greater than that of 70# asphalt, which <lb/>indicates that T622 light stabilizer could improve the low-<lb/>temperature performance of asphalt directly. As the UV aging <lb/>time prolongs, the creep modulus of asphalt shows an upward <lb/>trend, while the creep rate decreases gradually. This indicates <lb/>that within the range of 76.25-305 h, prolonging the aging time <lb/>would degrade the low-temperature performance of asphalt. <lb/>When the UV aging time is extended from 76.25 to 152.5, 228, <lb/>and 305 h, the creep modulus S of 70# asphalt increases by 12, <lb/>21, and 25%, respectively, while the creep rate m decreases by <lb/>6, 11, and 15%. For T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt, the <lb/>creep modulus S increases by 7, 12, and 20% respectively, and <lb/>the creep rate m decreases by 2, 5, and 8%. The rate of increase <lb/>in creep modulus S and the rate of decrease in creep rate m <lb/>are significantly lower than those of 70# asphalt. Therefore, it <lb/>could be inferred that the T622 light stabilizer could reduce the <lb/>impact of ultraviolet light on asphalt performance effectively <lb/>and delay asphalt aging of asphalt. <lb/>4 Conclusions <lb/>1) The typical microstructure of T622-modified asphalt <lb/>during the UV aging process is &quot;fold structure&quot;. The fold <lb/>structure is essentially formed by the evolution of crack <lb/>structures. The surface of T622-modified asphalt forms <lb/>cracks with aging, and folds are formed due to the <lb/>healing effect of asphalt. <lb/>2) At the four UV aging times, T622 light stabilizer-modified <lb/>asphalt shows the maximum weight loss rate in sequence <lb/>at 450-460°C. The temperature difference remains <lb/>around 3°C and the temperature corresponding to the <lb/>weight loss rate at the final aging time decreases to the <lb/>lowest point of all aging times, indicating that T622 light <lb/>stabilizer-modified asphalt would undergo early weight <lb/>loss decomposition after long-term UV aging. <lb/>3) Although the T622 light stabilizer-modified asphalt would <lb/>still produce corresponding functional groups under the <lb/>influence of ultraviolet radiation, the growth rate and <lb/>exponential growth amount of the relevant functional <lb/>group are significantly lower than that of the base <lb/>asphalt, which indicates that the light stabilizer could <lb/>mitigate the transmission of asphalt components during <lb/>the UV aging period. <lb/>4) As the UV aging process prolongs, T622-modified asphalt <lb/>exhibits UV aging behavior from rheological properties, <lb/>manifested by the decrease of phase angle, increase of <lb/>rutting factor and complex modulus, and significant <lb/>decrease of creep rate, which suggests that the elasticity <lb/>and hardness of asphalt increase with UV aging time. The <lb/>aging degree of light stabilizer-modified asphalt is signif-<lb/>icantly lower than that of 70# base asphalt, indicating <lb/>that the addition of HALS could effectively improve the <lb/>UV aging resistance of asphalt. <lb/>5) The mechanism of HALS on asphalt has been explored <lb/>in this study preliminarily. In future studies, the corre-<lb/>lation between the improving effect and mechanism <lb/>would be expected to build, which could be provided <lb/>reference for controlling the improving effect of HALS <lb/>on the UV resistance of asphalt. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: This paper describes research activ-<lb/>ities mainly requested and sponsored by Open Fund of <lb/>National Engineering Research Center of Highway Main-<lb/>tenance Technology (Changsha University of Science&amp; <lb/>Technology) (kfj220104). <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding information: This article describes research activ-<lb/>ities mainly sponsored by the Open Fund of National <lb/>Engineering Research Center of Highway Maintenance <lb/>Technology (Changsha University of Science &amp; Technology) <lb/>(kfj220104). That sponsorship and interest are gratefully <lb/>acknowledged. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions: All authors contributed to the study <lb/>conception and design. Material preparation, data collec-<lb/>tion, and analysis were performed by Wensheng Zhao, <lb/>Guotao Fang, Xiao Qin, and Jie Mao. The first draft of the <lb/>manuscript was written by Wensheng Zhao and all authors <lb/></div>

	<body>Table 11: BBR test results <lb/>Asphalt <lb/>76.25 h <lb/>152.5 h <lb/>228 h <lb/>305 h <lb/>S (MPa) <lb/>m <lb/>S (MPa) <lb/>m <lb/>S (MPa) <lb/>m <lb/>S (MPa) <lb/>m <lb/>70# asphalt <lb/>192 <lb/>0.372 <lb/>215 <lb/>0.353 <lb/>232 <lb/>0.335 <lb/>241 <lb/>0.319 <lb/>T662 asphalt <lb/>171 <lb/>0.414 <lb/>183 <lb/>0.405 <lb/>191 <lb/>0.393 <lb/>205 <lb/>0.379 <lb/></body>

	<page>20</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All <lb/>authors have accepted responsibility for the entire content <lb/>of this manuscript and approved its submission. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest: The authors state no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement: All data generated or ana-<lb/>lyzed during this study are included in this published <lb/>article. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Li, Y., J. Feng, S. Wu, A. Chen, D. Kuang, Y. Gao, et al. Review of <lb/>ultraviolet ageing mechanisms and anti-ageing methods for <lb/>asphalt binders. Journal of Road Engineering, Vol. 2, 2022, <lb/>id. 137-155. <lb/>[2] Liu, S., J. Jin, H. Yu, Y. Gao, Y. Du, X. Sun, et al. Performance <lb/>enhancement of modified asphalt via coal gangue with micro-<lb/>structure control. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 367, 2023, <lb/>id. 130287. <lb/>[3] Sun, X., Z. Ou, Q. Xu, X. Qin, Y. Guo, J. Lin, et al. Feasibility analysis of <lb/>resource application of waste incineration fly ash in asphalt pave-<lb/>ment materials. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, <lb/>Vol. 30, 2022, pp. 1-16. <lb/>[4] Sun, X., J. Yuan, Z. Liu, X. Qin, and Y. Yin. Evaluation and charac-<lb/>terization on the segregation and dispersion of anti-UV aging <lb/>modifying agent in asphalt binder. Construction and Building <lb/>Materials, Vol. 289, 2021, id. 123204. <lb/>[5] Yin, F., E. Arámbula-Mercado, A. Epps Martin, D. Newcomb, and N. <lb/>Tran. Long-term ageing of asphalt mixtures. Road Materials and <lb/>Pavement Design, Vol. 18, 2017, pp. 2-27. <lb/>[6] Zhang, H., Z. Chen, G. Xu, and C. Shi. on of aging behaviors of <lb/>asphalt binders through different rheological indices. Fuel, Vol. 221, <lb/>2018, pp. 78-88. <lb/>[7] Li, Y., S. Wu, Q. Liu, Y. Dai, C. Li, H. Li, et al. Aging degradation of <lb/>asphalt binder by narrow-band UV radiations with a range of <lb/>dominant wavelengths. Construction and Building Materials, <lb/>Vol. 220, 2019, pp. 637-650. <lb/>[8] Yu, H., D. Yao, G. Qian, J. Cai, X. Gong, and L. Cheng. Effect of <lb/>ultraviolet aging on dynamic mechanical properties of SBS mod-<lb/>ified asphalt mortar. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 281, <lb/>2021, id. 122328. <lb/>[9] Sun, X., X. Qin, Z. Liu, Y. Yin, C. Zou, and S. Jiang. New preparation <lb/>method of bitumen samples for UV aging behavior investigation. <lb/>Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 233, 2020, id. 117278. <lb/>[10] Crucho, J., L. Picado-Santos, J. Neves, and S. Capitão. A review of <lb/>nanomaterials&apos; effect on mechanical performance and aging of <lb/>asphalt mixtures. Applied Sciences, Vol. 9, 2019, id. 3657. <lb/>[11] Polo-Mendoza, R., G. Martinez-Arguelles, L. F. Walubita, F. Moreno-<lb/>Navarro, F. Giustozzi, L. Fuentes et al. Ultraviolet ageing of <lb/>bituminous materials: A comprehensive literature review from 2011 <lb/>to 2022. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 350, 2022, id. <lb/>128889. <lb/>[12] Xu, S., J. Yu, Y. Ke, L. Xue, and C. Hu. Preparation and anti-ultraviolet <lb/>aging performance of organic layered double hydroxides/bitumen <lb/>composites. Journal of Wuhan University of Technology-Mater. Sci. Ed., <lb/>Vol. 34, 2019, pp. 979-986. <lb/>[13] Liu, Z., X. Sun, X. Qin, and Y. Yin. Micro-analysis of the fusion <lb/>process between light stabilizer and asphalt using different char-<lb/>acterizing methods. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 287, <lb/>2021, id. 123045. <lb/>[14] Ma, F., C. Zhu, Z. Fu, C. Li, Y. Hou, X. Jiang et al. Analysis of <lb/>rheological behavior and anti-aging properties of SBS <lb/>modified asphalt incorporating UV absorbent and naphthenic <lb/>oil (NPO). Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 377, 2023, <lb/>id. 130958. <lb/>[15] Liao, M., Z. Liu, Y. Gao, L. Liu, and S. Xiang. Study on UV aging <lb/>resistance of nano-TiO2/montmorillonite/styrene-butadiene <lb/>rubber composite modified asphalt based on rheological and <lb/>microscopic properties. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 301, <lb/>2021, id. 124108. <lb/>[16] Liu, L., Z. Liu, L. Hong, and Y. Huang. Effect of ultraviolet absorber <lb/>(UV-531) on the properties of SBS-modified asphalt with different <lb/>block ratios. Construction and Building Materials, Vol. 234, 2020, id. <lb/>117388. <lb/>[17] Liu, H., Z. Zhang, J. Xie, Z. Gui, N. Li, and Y. Xu. Analysis of OMMT <lb/>strengthened UV aging-resistance of Sasobit/SBS modified asphalt: <lb/>Its preparation, characterization and mechanism. Journal of Cleaner <lb/>Production, Vol. 315, 2021, id. 128139. <lb/>[18] Guo, M., X. Liu, Y. Jiao, Y. Tan, and D. Luo. Rheological character-<lb/>ization of reversibility between aging and rejuvenation of common <lb/>modified asphalt binders. Construction and Building Materials, <lb/>Vol. 301, 2021, id. 124077. <lb/>[19] Qian, G., G. Yuan, D. Zhang, and Z. Li. Effect of Composite Light <lb/>Stabilizer on the Anti-Ultraviolet Aging Property of Matrix <lb/>Asphalt. Journal of Materials in Civil Engineering, Vol. 33, 2021, <lb/>id. 04021176. <lb/>[20] Sun, X., Y. Zhang, Q. Peng, J. Yuan, Z. Cang, and J. Lv. Study on <lb/>adaptability of rheological index of nano-PUA-modified asphalt <lb/>based on geometric parameters of parallel plate. Nanotechnology <lb/>Reviews, Vol. 10, 2021, pp. 1801-1811. <lb/>[21] Hodgson, J. L., and M. L. Coote. Clarifying the mechanism of the <lb/>Denisov cycle: how do hindered amine light stabilizers protect <lb/>polymer coatings from photo-oxidative degradation? <lb/>Macromolecules, Vol. 43, 2010, pp. 4573-4583. <lb/>[22] Jiang, X., J. Gabrielson, H. Titi, B. Huang, Y. Bai, P. Polaczyk, et al. <lb/>Field investigation and numerical analysis of an inverted pavement <lb/>system in Tennessee, USA. Transportation Geotechnics, Vol. 35, 2022, <lb/>id. 100759. <lb/>[23] Gryn&apos;ova, G., K. U. Ingold, and M. L. Coote. New insights into the <lb/>mechanism of amine/nitroxide cycling during the hindered <lb/>amine light stabilizer inhibited oxidative degradation of polymers. <lb/>Journal of the American Chemical Society, Vol. 134, 2012, pp. <lb/>12979-12988. <lb/>[24] Jiang, X., H. Titi, Y. Ma, P. Polaczyk, M. Zhang, J. Gabrielson, et al. <lb/>Evaluating the performance of inverted pavement structure using <lb/>the accelerated pavement test (APT). Construction and Building <lb/>Materials, Vol. 346, 2022, id. 128489. <lb/>[25] Yu, H., Z. Zhu, Z. Leng, C. Wu, Z. Zhang, D. Wang, et al. Effect of <lb/>mixing sequence on asphalt mixtures containing waste tire rubber <lb/>and warm mix surfactants. Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 246, <lb/>2020, id. 119008. <lb/>[26] Jiang, X., J. Gabrielson, B. Huang, Y. Bai, P. Polaczyk, M. Zhang, et al. <lb/>Evaluation of inverted pavement by structural condition indicators <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">UV aging resistance characterization  </note>

	<page>21 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>from falling weight deflectometer. Construction and Building <lb/>Materials, Vol. 319, 2022, id. 125991. <lb/>[27] Abouelsaad, A., and G. White. The combined effect of ultraviolet <lb/>irradiation and temperature on hot mix asphalt mixture aging. <lb/>Sustainability, Vol. 14, 2022, id. 5942. <lb/>[28] Gijsman, P., H. J. Smelt, and D. Schumann. Hindered amine light <lb/>stabilizers: an alternative for radiation cross-linked UHMwPE <lb/>implants. Biomaterials, Vol. 31, 2010, pp. 6685-6691. <lb/>[29] Feng, Z. G., H. J. Bian, X. J. Li, and J. Y. Yu. FTIR analysis of UV aging <lb/>on bitumen and its fractions. Materials and Structures, Vol. 49, 2016, <lb/>pp. 1381-1389. <lb/>[30] Xu, X., H. Guo, X. Wang, M. Zhang, Z. Wang, and B. Yang. Physical <lb/>properties and anti-aging characteristics of asphalt modified with <lb/>nano-zinc oxide powder. Construction and Building Materials, <lb/>Vol. 224, 2019, pp. 732-742. <lb/>[31] Yu, H., X. Bai, G. Qian, H. Wei, X. Gong, J. Jin, et al. Impact of <lb/>ultraviolet radiation on the aging properties of SBS-modified <lb/>asphalt binders. Polymers, Vol. 11, 2019, id. 1111. <lb/>[32] Feczkó, T., M. Kovács, and Voncina, B. Improvement of fatigue resis-<lb/>tance of spirooxazine in ethyl cellulose and poly (methyl methacrylate) <lb/>nanoparticles using a hindered amine light stabilizer. Journal of <lb/>Photochemistry and Photobiology A: Chemistry, Vol. 247, 2012, pp. 1-7. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>22</page>

	<note place="headnote"> Wensheng Zhao et al. </note>


  </text>

</TEI>