<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T15:20:12.850Z">11/13/2025 3:20:12 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T15:20:02.142968Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T15:20:02.142968Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Moving towards a person-centred HIV care <lb/>cascade: An exploration of potential biases <lb/>and errors in routine data in South Africa <lb/>David Etoori ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Alison Wringe 2 , Georges Reniers 2,3 , Francesc Xavier Gomez-Olive 3 , <lb/>Brian Rice 2,4 <lb/>1 University College London, London, United Kingdom, 2 London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, <lb/>London, United Kingdom, 3 MRC/WITS Rural Public Health and Health Transitions Research Unit <lb/>(Agincourt), School of Public Health, University of Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa, 4 University <lb/>of Sheffield, School of Health and Related Research, Sheffield, United Kingdom <lb/>* d.etoori@ucl.ac.uk <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In 2022, in recognition of lags in data infrastructure, the World Health Organisation (WHO) <lb/>recommended the use of routinely linked individual patient data to monitor HIV programmes. <lb/>The WHO also recommended a move to person-centred care to better reflect the experi-<lb/>ences of people living with HIV. The switch from aggregated service level data to person-<lb/>centred data will likely introduce some biases and errors. However, little is understood about <lb/>the direction and magnitude of these biases. We investigated HIV-testing and HIV-care <lb/>engagement from 2014 to 2018 in the Agincourt Health and Demographic Surveillance Sys-<lb/>tem (HDSS). We digitised and linked HIV patient clinic records to HDSS population data in <lb/>order to estimate biases in routine clinical data. Using this linked data, we followed all indi-<lb/>viduals linked to HIV-related clinic data throughout their care pathway. We built sequences <lb/>to represent these pathways. We performed sequence and cluster analyses for all individu-<lb/>als to categorise patterns of care engagement and identified factors associated with differ-<lb/>ent engagement patterns using multinomial logistic regression. Our analyses included 4947 <lb/>individuals who were linked to 5084 different patient records. We found that routine data <lb/>would have inflated patient numbers by 2% due to double counting. We also found that 2% <lb/>of individuals included in our analyses had received multiple HIV tests. These phenomena <lb/>were driven by undocumented transfers. Further analysis of engagement patterns found a <lb/>low level of stable engagement in care (&lt;33%). Engagement fell into three distinct clusters: <lb/>(i) characterised by high rates of late ART initiation, unstable engagement in care, and high <lb/>mortality (53.9%), (ii) characterised by early ART initiation followed by prolonged periods of <lb/>LTFU (13.7%), and (iii) characterised by early ART initiation followed by stable engagement <lb/>in care (32.4%). Compared to cluster (i) older individuals were less likely to be in cluster (ii) <lb/>and more likely to be in cluster (iii). Those who initiated ART prior to 2016 were more likely <lb/>to be in cluster (ii) and (iii) compared to cluster (i). Those who initiated ART for PMTCT <lb/>(RRR: 1.88 (95% CI: 1.45, 2.44)) or TB coinfection (RRR: 2.11 (95% CI: 1.27, 3.50)) were <lb/>more likely to be in cluster (ii) when compared to those who initiated ART due to CD4 eligibil-<lb/>ity criteria. Males (RRR: 0.63 (95% CI: 0.51, 0.77)) were less likely to be in cluster (iii) <lb/>PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/>1 / 13 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Etoori D, Wringe A, Reniers G, Gomez-<lb/>Olive FX, Rice B (2024) Moving towards a person-<lb/>centred HIV care cascade: An exploration of <lb/>potential biases and errors in routine data in South <lb/>Africa. PLOS Glob Public Health 4(6): e0002509. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 <lb/>Editor: Rashmi Josephine Rodrigues, St John&apos;s <lb/>National Academy of Health Sciences, INDIA <lb/>Received: September 14, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: May 9, 2024 <lb/>Published: June 6, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Etoori et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data are available on <lb/>reasonable request. Data may be obtained from a <lb/>third party and are not publicly available. Under our <lb/>data agreements with MRC/Wits Rural Public <lb/>compared to cluster (i) as were those who initiated ART for PMTCT (RRR: 0.77 (95% CI: <lb/>0.62, 0.97)) or under test and treat guidelines when compared to those who initiated ART <lb/>due to CD4 eligibility. Only a minority of patients are consistently engaged in care while the <lb/>majority cycle between engagement and disengagement. Individual level data could be use-<lb/>ful in monitoring programmes and accurately reporting patient figures if it is of high quality, <lb/>has minimal missingness and is properly linked in order to account for biases that accrue <lb/>from using this kind of data. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>With antiretroviral therapy (ART) programmes entering their third decade in sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa (SSA), there is now a concerted effort to attain sustainable HIV epidemic control by <lb/>2030 [1-3]. Since their inception in the early 2000s, SSA ART programmes have evolved rap-<lb/>idly and have done a commendable job in expanding access to treatment for people living with <lb/>HIV (PLHIV) [4, 5]. Expansion has been characterised by ART availability in a greater number <lb/>of facilities, decentralised service delivery to bring ART closer to patients, and patient-centred <lb/>care with multiple models of treatment delivery, all leading to improved convenience for <lb/>patients [6]. In South Africa, the benefits of treatment are reflected in the finding that the life <lb/>expectancy of PLHIV who are virally suppressed is only slightly lower than among people who <lb/>are HIV-uninfected. However, PLHIV who are not virally suppressed have substantially lower <lb/>life expectancy that uninfected individuals [7]. <lb/>The expansion in treatment programmes has not been matched by an appropriate growth <lb/>in data infrastructure, with many programmes in SSA still reliant on paper registers. Where <lb/>electronic medical records (EMR) have been implemented, they are often standalone, rather <lb/>than being networked across health facilities, resulting in programmes often only being able to <lb/>monitor facility-based retention rather than whole programme retention [8, 9]. This limitation <lb/>in monitoring individual care pathways is of concern given the importance of measuring and <lb/>promoting optimal adherence to ART to achieve viral suppression, and the need to better <lb/>understand patterns of engagement with HIV services, as well as transfers between these <lb/>services. <lb/>In recognition that as the number of PLHIV in care increases so too does the number of <lb/>care pathways, researchers have proposed a person-centred cascade that takes what some have <lb/>called the &quot;side door&quot; into consideration [10]. This new cascade is designed to better reflect <lb/>individual pathways of care including, for example, cases of loss to follow-up where individuals <lb/>have reengaged at a different facility. An ability to monitor pathways of care such as this would <lb/>ultimately show that ART programmes are doing better than has previously been reported [10, <lb/>11]. However, the current data infrastructure does not have the capability to do this. <lb/>In 2022, the World Health Organisation (WHO) published guidelines on strategic informa-<lb/>tion for HIV advocating for a shift away from aggregated service level data to a people-centred <lb/>approach supported by disaggregated longitudinal routine data [12, 13]. These guidelines <lb/>included advice on patient monitoring systems, recommending the use of unique identifiers <lb/>and promoting the routine collection of patient-level data for reporting on programme, <lb/>national and global indicators. <lb/>In SSA advances are being made in moving towards a patient-centred approach. For exam-<lb/>ple, in South Africa, efforts are underway to consolidate person-centred clinical data across <lb/>government services [14]. Record linkage using demographic surveillance data has also shown <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<front>Health and Health Transitions Research Unit <lb/>(Agincourt), we are unable to share the data used <lb/>for these analyses directly with others. Data are <lb/>however available by request here: https://www. <lb/>agincourt.co.za/?page_id=188 and with permission <lb/>of the MRC/Wits Rural Public Health and Health <lb/>Transitions Research Unit (Agincourt). <lb/>Funding: This study was made possible with <lb/>support from the Economic and Social Research <lb/>Council (ES/JS00021/1 to ED), the Bill and Melinda <lb/>Gates Foundation for the MeSH Consortium <lb/>(OPP1120138 to BR), the Bill and Melinda Gates <lb/>Foundation ALPHA grant (OPP1164897 to GR), <lb/>and the MRC SHAPE UTT grant (MR/P014313/1 to <lb/>AW). The funders had no role in study design, data <lb/>collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>promise in improving reporting of patient outcomes in the national treatment database [15]. <lb/>The ongoing transfer of paper-based clinical registers to electronic reporting, however, intro-<lb/>duces new biases and errors. While the general direction of the potential biases has been recog-<lb/>nised [15], there have been few efforts to ascertain the magnitude of these biases and how they <lb/>may affect global targets. It is important to fill this knowledge gap as inaccurate estimates not <lb/>only lead to inaccurate programme indicators but may lead to insufficient resource allocation <lb/>[16], and bias projections for packages such as SPECTRUM due to erroneous modelling <lb/>parameters [17]. <lb/>In this study, we use public health facility ART data linked to population-based data in <lb/>rural South Africa to evaluate this routine data source (health facility data) for the potential <lb/>biases that might accrue when utilising it to measure programmatic indicators (e.g., numbers <lb/>tested, new HIV diagnoses, numbers engaged in care) and progress towards national and <lb/>global targets. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Setting and study population <lb/>Data for this study are taken from the Agincourt Health and Demographic Surveillance System <lb/>(HDSS) run by the MRC/Wits Rural Public Health and Health Transitions Research Unit <lb/>(Agincourt). Agincourt comprises 120,000 residents in 31 villages and is located in Mpuma-<lb/>langa province, South Africa where HIV prevalence was 22.8% among adults 15 to 49 years in <lb/>2017 [18-20]. Since 1992, the MRC/Wits Agincourt Research Unit has conducted an annual <lb/>demographic surveillance survey where vital events (births, deaths and migration data) are col-<lb/>lected from residents, based on a comprehensive household registration system [19, 21-23]. <lb/>Since 2014, HIV patient visits to ART clinics in the area have been logged by fieldworkers and <lb/>linked to the HDSS using Point-of-Contact Interactive Record Linkage (PIRL) which has been <lb/>described in detail elsewhere [24, 25]. The HDSS also collects verbal autopsy data to ascertain <lb/>probable causes of death [26, 27]. <lb/>The study population included all ART patients aged 18 years or older, enrolled at an ART <lb/>clinic (8 clinics in total) after record linkage was established in April 2014 and who had been <lb/>matched to a resident record within the HDSS database. Test and treat was adopted in 2016 <lb/>[28]. This cohort was followed until July 11, 2018, when data extraction occurred. De-identi-<lb/>fied clinical and demographic data used in these analyses were accessed on August 1, 2019. <lb/>Data preparation and statistical analysis <lb/>As facilities usually organise refill schedules around a 28-day schedule (2 days of extra pills), <lb/>each refill was equated to one month (1 month equals 28 days). As we had no adherence data, <lb/>we assumed that individuals were taking treatment as prescribed. For each eligible individual, <lb/>we allocated a treatment pathway of up to 56 months (maximum follow-up in the data) from <lb/>the first date that an ART facility record was opened for them (either HIV diagnosis or ART <lb/>initiation). Considering the data requirements of a person-centred cascade, we assigned care <lb/>pathways into seven possible states (Table 1). <lb/>We identified clusters with similar care engagement patterns using Optimal Matching dis-<lb/>tances [29, 30]. Using a binary variable coded as 1 if an individual was a member of a given <lb/>cluster and 0 otherwise, factors associated with membership to each engagement-cluster were <lb/>determined using multinomial logistic regression. We calculated counts and proportions for <lb/>socio-demographic and baseline clinical characteristics and report confidence intervals for <lb/>proportions of patients with multiple HIV tests. For continuous variables, we report the <lb/>median and interquartile range. Missingness in exposure variables ranged from 4-7%. In <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>logistic regression models, we only conducted complete case analyses. Sequence analyses were <lb/>conducted using the TraMineR R-package [31]. All other analyses were conducted using Stata <lb/>16 [32]. To explore potential biases and errors we considered individuals who have tested <lb/>more than once, those who have been linked to more than one clinic record, and those LTFU. <lb/>Ethical approval <lb/>Ethical approval was obtained from the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine <lb/>Research Ethics Committee, the University of Witwatersrand Human Research Ethics Com-<lb/>mittee, and the Mpumalanga Department of Health Public Health Research Committee. All <lb/>methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations and written <lb/>informed consent was obtained from all participants and from a parent and/or legal guardian <lb/>of minors (subjects under 18) in the study. <lb/>Results <lb/>Population characteristics <lb/>Over the study period, 8079 patient records were entered into the PIRL database. Of these, <lb/>5084 (62.9%) were linked to an HDSS resident and met the inclusion criteria. These 5084 <lb/>patient records were linked to 4947 unique HDSS residents (134 unique individuals linked to <lb/>multiple patient records). (S1 Fig) The 4947 individuals had a median age of 34 years (IQR: 27, <lb/>43) at ART initiation, and median baseline CD4 of 272 cells/μL (IQR: 140, 435). The 134 indi-<lb/>viduals with multiple linkages had a median age of 28 years (IQR: 24, 35), a median baseline <lb/>CD4 of 268 cells/μL (IQR: 149, 425), 114 (85.1%) were female, 54 (40.3%) initiated ART in <lb/>2015, 33 (24.6%) in 2016, and 31 (23.1%) in 2014; and 63 (47.0%) initiated ART due to CD4 <lb/>criteria and 38 (28.4%) for prevention of mother-to-child transmission (PMTCT). Of the 134 <lb/>(2.7%) with multiple patient records, 127 (2.6%) had transferred once, 3 (0.1%) had transferred <lb/>twice, and 4 (0.1%) had re-engaged at the same facility but had been given a new file number. <lb/>Of 133 total transfers, 106 (79.7%) were undocumented according to PIRL records. <lb/>Based on patient records, 226 (4.6%) patients were recorded as transfers-in from facilities <lb/>outside the HDSS and 47 (0.9%) were recorded as transfers-in from facilities within the HDSS <lb/>at their first facility. For the 47 transfers-in from HDSS facilities, we could not identify any ear-<lb/>lier records within PIRL, suggesting missed links or that they never had a treatment file opened <lb/>at these facilities (e.g., newly diagnosed who request to start treatment at another facility). <lb/>Table 1. Description of possible states. <lb/>State <lb/>Definition <lb/>HIV+ no ART <lb/>Either diagnosed HIV-positive but ART not initiated at one of the facilities under <lb/>surveillance, or ART initiated but with no follow-up visits following initiation. <lb/>On ART <lb/>At least one health facility visit following the ART initiation visit. Individuals remained on <lb/>ART until the next scheduled visit. <lb/>Late <lb/>Up to 3 months late for a scheduled ART refill visit. <lb/>Lost to follow-up <lb/>(LTFU) <lb/>More than 3 months late for a scheduled ART refill visit. <lb/>Deceased <lb/>Registered as deceased from data extracted from HDSS records. <lb/>Transferred <lb/>Treatment collection from a health facility within the HDSS other than the initiating <lb/>facility. <lb/>Re-engaged <lb/>Resumed treatment at initiating facility following LTFU (i.e., returned following a period <lb/>of &gt;3 months after a scheduled ART refill visit). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Testing and ART initiation statistics <lb/>Of 4947 individuals, 93 [1.9% (95% CI: 1.5-2.3)] had multiple HIV tests conducted. The over-<lb/>whelming majority of patients with multiple HIV tests were among those who had transferred <lb/>once (i.e., linked to two records) [90/127, 70.9% (95% CI: 62.1-78.6)] and the remainder were <lb/>for those who had transferred twice (i.e., linked to three records) [3/3, 100% (95% CI: 29.2-<lb/>100)]. Multiple HIV tests were more common for undocumented transfers (89/106 [84.0% <lb/>(95% CI: 75.6-90.4)] compared to documented transfers 4/27 [14.8% (95% CI: 4.2-33.7)]). <lb/>Median time between tests was 438.5 days (IQR: 222-805). <lb/>Almost half of the 4947 individuals (46.0%; 2277) did not initiate ART immediately (i.e., <lb/>within the first month) following their diagnosis. This proportion, however, declined over the <lb/>study period from 48.2% (432/897)) in 2014 to 32.7% (122/373) in 2018. <lb/>Engagement sequences and clusters <lb/>The 4947 individuals contributed 147,651 person-months of engagement data to the sequence <lb/>analysis corresponding to 85509 (57.9%) months in care, 47306 (32.0%) months out of care <lb/>(LTFU), 11226 (7.6%) months late for a scheduled appointment, and 3610 (2.4%) for those <lb/>deceased. Fig 1 illustrates the proportion of patients in each state over their engagement period <lb/>(in months) by reason for ART initiation. Patients who initiated treatment for prevention of <lb/>mother-to-child transmission (PMTCT) or under test and treat (strategy where persons diag-<lb/>nosed receive early treatment regardless of disease stage) contributed very little time [PMTCT: <lb/>161/25,949 months (0.62%); test and treat: 80/9,453 months (0.85%)] to the deceased state <lb/>even later in their treatment course. Patients who initiated ART due to WHO stage (i.e., late-<lb/>stage disease) had the largest contribution [466/6,937 months (6.72%)] to the deceased state. <lb/>Fig 1. Chronograms of engagement in care by reason for ART initiation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Some patients who initiated ART for PMTCT or under test and treat also had prolonged peri-<lb/>ods where large proportions did not initiate ART (Fig 1). <lb/>An analysis of average time spent in each state shows that males were most likely to have <lb/>died (males: on average 5% of sequence time versus females: 2%) as were individuals in the 55 <lb/>+ age group (18-24: 1%, 25-34: 2%, 35-44: 3%, 45-54: 3%, 55+: 6%), those who initiated ART <lb/>with Tuberculosis (TB), or other opportunistic infections (OIs) as measured by WHO stage at <lb/>ART initiation (PMTCT: 1%, CD4: 2%, WHO stage: 6%, TB: 3%, test and treat: 1%), those <lb/>who initiated ART in 2014 (2014: 4%, 2015: 2%, 2016: 2%, 2017: 1%, 2018: 1%), or with lower <lb/>baseline CD4 (&lt;100: 6%, 100-199: 3%, 200-349: 2%, 350-499: 1%, 500+: 1%). Younger <lb/>patients were most likely to be LTFU (18-24: 30%, 25-34: 23%, 35-44: 17%, 45-54: 15%, 55+: <lb/>10%), as were patients who initiated ART for PMTCT (PMTCT: 29%, CD4: 17%, WHO stage: <lb/>21%, TB: 24%, test and treat: 13%), and patients who initiated ART in earlier years (2014: 20%, <lb/>2015: 22%, 2016: 20%, 2017: 12%, 2018: 2%). There were no discernible differences in person-<lb/>months spent in the late sequence state. (S2-S6 Figs) <lb/>We identified three distinct patterns of engagement through cluster analysis of the 4947 <lb/>sequences: (i) characterised by high rates of late ART initiation, unstable engagement in care, <lb/>and high mortality (n = 2666, 53.9%), (ii) characterised by early ART initiation followed by <lb/>prolonged periods of LTFU (n = 679, 13.7%), and (iii) characterised by early ART initiation <lb/>followed by stable engagement in care (n = 1602, 32.4%). (Table 2) Fig 2 shows individual <lb/>patient trajectories further illustrating that even within the three broader engagement patterns, <lb/>patient experiences of care are not monolithic. For example, for patients in the stable engage-<lb/>ment category, there are intermittent periods of LTFU and for patients in the prolonged LTFU <lb/>category, there are periods of re-engagement in care. <lb/>In the multinomial logistic regression model, older individuals (35 and older) were less <lb/>likely to be in cluster 2 (early ART/prolonged LTFU) compared to cluster 1 (late ART/unsta-<lb/>ble) [e.g., RRR 55+ years versus 25-34 years: 0.44 (95% CI: 0.28, 0.72)]. Individuals who initi-<lb/>ated ART for PMTCT when compared to those who initiated ART due to CD4 eligibility <lb/>criteria were more likely to be in cluster 2 than cluster 1 [RRR: 1.88 (95% CI: 1.45, 2.44)] as <lb/>were those who initiated ART due to TB coinfection. Individuals who initiated ART prior to <lb/>2016 were more likely to be in cluster 2 compared to cluster 1 [2014 vs 2016 RRR: 1.97 (95% <lb/>CI: 1.49, 2.61)]. Older individuals were more likely to be in cluster 3 (early ART/stable) com-<lb/>pared to cluster 1 as were individuals who initiated ART prior to 2016. Males were less likely <lb/>to be in cluster 3 compared to cluster 1 as were individuals who initiated ART for PMTCT and <lb/>those who initiated ART under test and treat (Table 3). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In recognition that people often receive services, including HIV diagnoses, multiple times in <lb/>the same or different locations, and that care pathways following a diagnosis can often be com-<lb/>plex, WHO in 2022 recommended the collection and use of routinely linked individual data <lb/>on HIV diagnoses and care to monitor people&apos;s movement over time between facilities and <lb/>locations [33]. To better reflect the actual experiences of people living with diagnosed HIV, <lb/>WHO also recommended the use of a new person-centred cascade. Ehrenkranz et al present a <lb/>cascade that can track individuals as they cycle between disengagement and reengagement in <lb/>care [11]. To achieve this individual-level data linked over time and space are required. Using <lb/>a novel approach linking population-based demographic surveillance data and clinic records, <lb/>we followed individuals across their treatment journey in order to assess the added value of <lb/>disaggregated longitudinal patient-level data and identify and describe potential biases and <lb/>errors. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>In our cohort of South African patients, we found 2% inflation of patient numbers due to <lb/>double counting as a result of undocumented transfer. Of the 2.7% of people transferring <lb/>between facilities during the study period, 80% of these were undocumented. We also report <lb/>2% of individuals having multiple positive tests, with individuals with undocumented transfers <lb/>more likely to have multiple HIV diagnoses. HIV testing data in this setting has not been digi-<lb/>tised and we relied heavily on tests that had been recorded in patient records. As such, this is <lb/>likely an underestimation of retesting in this setting. This is especially pertinent as one study <lb/>where testing data was digitised and linked to individuals in the Western Cape of South Africa <lb/>found that 51% of positive diagnoses were from individuals previously diagnosed [34]. As <lb/>Table 2. Demographic and clinical characteristics of the study cohort and engagement-cluster members. <lb/>Demographics <lb/>Engagement clusters <lb/>All <lb/>% <lb/>Late ART/ Unstable <lb/>% <lb/>Early ART/Prolonged LTFU <lb/>% <lb/>Early ART/Stable <lb/>% <lb/>4947 <lb/>2666 <lb/>679 <lb/>1602 <lb/>Age group <lb/>18-24 <lb/>766 <lb/>15.5 <lb/>431 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>162 <lb/>23.9 <lb/>173 <lb/>10.8 <lb/>25-34 <lb/>1831 <lb/>37 <lb/>987 <lb/>37.0 <lb/>296 <lb/>43.6 <lb/>548 <lb/>34.2 <lb/>35-44 <lb/>1264 <lb/>25.5 <lb/>687 <lb/>25.8 <lb/>133 <lb/>19.6 <lb/>444 <lb/>27.7 <lb/>45-54 <lb/>637 <lb/>12.9 <lb/>341 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>58 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>238 <lb/>14.9 <lb/>55+ <lb/>449 <lb/>9.1 <lb/>220 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>30 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>199 <lb/>12.4 <lb/>Baseline CD4 <lb/>&lt;100 <lb/>868 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>469 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>116 <lb/>17.1 <lb/>283 <lb/>17.7 <lb/>100-199 <lb/>869 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>467 <lb/>17.5 <lb/>104 <lb/>15.3 <lb/>298 <lb/>18.6 <lb/>200-349 <lb/>1244 <lb/>25.1 <lb/>656 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>184 <lb/>27.1 <lb/>404 <lb/>25.2 <lb/>350-499 <lb/>882 <lb/>17.8 <lb/>427 <lb/>16 <lb/>128 <lb/>18.9 <lb/>327 <lb/>20.4 <lb/>500+ <lb/>870 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>491 <lb/>18.4 <lb/>123 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>256 <lb/>16.0 <lb/>Missing <lb/>214 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>156 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>24 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>34 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>3740 <lb/>75.6 <lb/>1943 <lb/>72.9 <lb/>517 <lb/>76.1 <lb/>1280 <lb/>79.9 <lb/>Male <lb/>1207 <lb/>24.4 <lb/>723 <lb/>27.1 <lb/>162 <lb/>23.9 <lb/>322 <lb/>20.1 <lb/>Baseline WHO stage <lb/>I <lb/>3572 <lb/>72.2 <lb/>1978 <lb/>74.2 <lb/>464 <lb/>68.3 <lb/>1130 <lb/>70.5 <lb/>II <lb/>574 <lb/>11.6 <lb/>264 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>71 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>239 <lb/>14.9 <lb/>III <lb/>385 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>195 <lb/>7.3 <lb/>67 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>123 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>IV <lb/>56 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>29 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>7 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>Missing <lb/>360 <lb/>7.3 <lb/>200 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>70 <lb/>10.3 <lb/>90 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>ART reason <lb/>PMTCT <lb/>966 <lb/>19.5 <lb/>494 <lb/>18.5 <lb/>213 <lb/>31.4 <lb/>259 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>2582 <lb/>52.2 <lb/>1200 <lb/>45 <lb/>297 <lb/>43.7 <lb/>1085 <lb/>67.7 <lb/>WHO stage <lb/>237 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>117 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>38 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>82 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>TB <lb/>154 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>76 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>32 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>46 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>Test and Treat <lb/>660 <lb/>13.4 <lb/>576 <lb/>21.6 <lb/>26 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>58 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>Missing <lb/>348 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>203 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>73 <lb/>10.8 <lb/>72 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>ART year <lb/>2014 <lb/>897 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>244 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>162 <lb/>23.9 <lb/>491 <lb/>30.7 <lb/>2015 <lb/>1246 <lb/>25.2 <lb/>331 <lb/>12.4 <lb/>277 <lb/>40.8 <lb/>638 <lb/>39.8 <lb/>2016 <lb/>1395 <lb/>28.2 <lb/>697 <lb/>26.1 <lb/>225 <lb/>33.1 <lb/>473 <lb/>29.5 <lb/>2017 <lb/>1036 <lb/>20.9 <lb/>1021 <lb/>38.3 <lb/>15 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2018 <lb/>373 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>373 <lb/>14.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>ART is increasingly offered to healthier patients, undocumented transfers are becoming a <lb/>more common occurrence in treatment programmes likely linked to labour migration [35], <lb/>illustrating the need for robust cascades that takes into consideration, movements between <lb/>clinics and regions and non-linear care pathways. <lb/>Using analysis of patient engagement sequences, we identified low levels (&lt;33%) of stable <lb/>engagement in care, categorising three distinct patterns of engagement. These were (1) high <lb/>rates of late ART initiation, unstable engagement in care, and high mortality, (2) early ART <lb/>initiation followed by prolonged periods of LTFU, and (3) early ART initiation followed by <lb/>stable engagement in care. Historically, HIV programmes have used aggregate data which <lb/>lacks the nuance of individual level data. The cluster analysis demonstrates the multiple ways <lb/>that individuals engage with care showing that this does not follow a linear path. This is some-<lb/>thing that would not be possible with aggregate data. The clusters could also potentially assist <lb/>programmes in estimating how many individuals within their programmes might have similar <lb/>HIV care engagement profiles. We found that early ART initiation is still lagging, similar to <lb/>other studies [36] and could reflect several reasons including individual readiness. Addition-<lb/>ally, TB coinfection is common in this setting and delayed ART is recommended in such cases <lb/>[37]. Individuals who were pregnant or who had OIs were more likely to initiate ART early <lb/>consistent with treatment recommendations. However, these groups were likely to experience <lb/>prolonged LTFU similar to findings from other studies [38]. Our findings suggest that two <lb/>thirds of the treatment cohort have cyclical engagement patterns. We saw that LTFU is not a <lb/>Fig 2. Index plots of the three engagement clusters showing individual patient trajectories. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases and errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>terminal state, and individuals move between periods of engagement and disengagement, <lb/>something that only patient-centred data can capture. We also found that engagement <lb/>sequences are as unique as the individual, as such, programmes will need to evolve to offer tai-<lb/>lored care to fit patients&apos; individual needs. <lb/>Although we were able to link individuals across facilities, we report there being a large pro-<lb/>portion of individuals who remain LTFU from this network. This likely speaks to two points. <lb/>Firstly, the South African population is highly mobile [39], a consequence of historic inequality <lb/>where economic opportunities were only available in select parts of the country. We have <lb/>shown previously that individuals from this region transferred their care as far as Cape Town, <lb/>in the Western Cape [35]. Secondly, ascertainment of deaths is still difficult even with demo-<lb/>graphic surveillance data. Given that membership in the prolonged LTFU category was associ-<lb/>ated with TB coinfection as the ART initiation reason (a factor associated with high mortality <lb/>in other cohorts [40, 41]), it is likely that some of these individuals might have died. Our find-<lb/>ings illustrate that there is still a need for routine reporting mechanisms that accurately docu-<lb/>ment mortality a gap also recognised by WHO, which recommends cross referencing other <lb/>data sources where deaths are recorded to improve accuracy of this information [33]. We have <lb/>reported previously that LTFU misclassifies a large proportion of patient outcomes [15]. As <lb/>such, ascertainment of outcomes following LTFU will be important in order to more accu-<lb/>rately estimate programmatic metrics. We should note that we were unable to link 37% of <lb/>patients who claimed residency in the HDSS which might have resolved some of the LTFU. <lb/>Our study has some limitations. Linkage errors, especially due to missed matches, may bias <lb/>our findings. Our linkage covered a small group of public health facilities offering ART in a <lb/>rural community and did not extend to several private facilities that offer services to the com-<lb/>munity or to public facilities in surrounding areas where some members of the community <lb/>Table 3. Factors associated with engagement-cluster membership. <lb/>Early ART/Prolonged LTFU (n = 679) vs Late ART/Unstable Early ART/Stable (n = 1,602) vs Late ART/Unstable <lb/>RRR (95% CI) <lb/>p-value <lb/>RRR (95% CI) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age group <lb/>18-24 <lb/>1.42 (1.08, 1.87) <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.84 (0.65, 1.08) <lb/>0.18 <lb/>25-34 <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>35-44 <lb/>0.75 (0.57, 0.99) <lb/>0.04 <lb/>1.29 (1.05, 1.60) <lb/>0.016 <lb/>45-54 <lb/>0.63 (0.43, 0.92) <lb/>0.017 <lb/>1.29 (0.99, 1.68) <lb/>0.057 <lb/>55+ <lb/>0.44 (0.28, 0.72) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.38 (1.03, 1.86) <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>Male <lb/>1.23 (0.95, 1.59) <lb/>0.123 <lb/>0.63 (0.51, 0.77) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>ART reason <lb/>PMTCT <lb/>1.88 (1.45, 2.44) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>0.77 (0.62, 0.97) <lb/>0.024 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>WHO stage <lb/>1.24 (0.81, 1.89) <lb/>0.322 <lb/>0.75 (0.53, 1.05) <lb/>0.095 <lb/>TB <lb/>2.11 (1.27, 3.50) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.87 (0.54, 1.38) <lb/>0.55 <lb/>Test and Treat <lb/>0.73 (0.47, 1.16) <lb/>0.186 <lb/>0.51 (0.36, 0.72) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>ART year <lb/>2014 <lb/>1.97 (1.49, 2.61) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2.95 (2.39, 3.63) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2015 <lb/>2.61 (2.06, 3.30) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2.79 (2.31, 3.36) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2016 <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>Reference <lb/>__ <lb/>2017 <lb/>0.04 (0.02, 0.07) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Omitted <lb/>__ <lb/>2018 <lb/>Omitted <lb/>__ <lb/>Omitted <lb/>__ <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>could be receiving care. More extensive geographical linkage, and the inclusion of public and <lb/>private facilities could reveal higher proportions of retesting and silent transfers, and as such <lb/>our estimates should be interpreted as lower limits for adjustment factors for estimates from <lb/>routine programme data. Due to the routine nature of data, some variables had a high level of <lb/>missing values. As we did not have adherence data, the assumption that individuals were in <lb/>care between treatment refills might misclassify some individuals. Optimal matching has some <lb/>limitations similar to other statistical models used for cluster analysis (e.g., a statistical tech-<lb/>nique cannot speak to individual lived experiences). <lb/>In our setting, we not only highlight the feasibility and utility of linking individual level <lb/>data across time and space but also fairly modest frequency of retesting and double <lb/>counting of patients on ART, highlighting the importance of silent transfers in increasing the <lb/>occurrence of these phenomena. Our findings suggest that HIV programmes in SSA may need <lb/>to pay particular attention to younger individuals, pregnant women, individuals with OIs, <lb/>those with higher CD4 counts at diagnosis, and males as these groups are least likely to remain <lb/>stable on ART and could benefit from extra interventions. <lb/>To better understand and improve programme performance, we need to strengthen data qual-<lb/>ity, sustainability and use through precise analysis and the characterisation and correction of <lb/>potential biases. With the aspiration of populating provincial and national level person-centred <lb/>HIV care cascades, we need to expand the reach of data linkage across facilities to more accurately <lb/>describe individual level pathways of care, thereby minimising potential biases and errors. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. Inclusivity in global research. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Fig. Flow chart of individuals included in the analysis. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Fig. Proportion of sequence time spent in each state on average by age. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Fig. Proportion of sequence time spent in each state on average by ART initiation rea-<lb/>son. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S4 Fig. Proportion of sequence time spent in each state on average by baseline CD4. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S5 Fig. Proportion of sequence time spent in each state on average by sex. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Fig. Proportion of sequence time spent in each state on average by year of ART initia-<lb/>tion. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors would like to thank all the participants in the study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: David Etoori, Alison Wringe, Georges Reniers. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Data curation: David Etoori. <lb/>Formal analysis: David Etoori. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Alison Wringe, Georges Reniers, Brian Rice. <lb/>Investigation: David Etoori. <lb/>Methodology: Francesc Xavier Gomez-Olive, Brian Rice. <lb/>Project administration: Francesc Xavier Gomez-Olive. <lb/>Supervision: Alison Wringe, Georges Reniers, Francesc Xavier Gomez-Olive. <lb/>Visualization: David Etoori. <lb/>Writing -original draft: David Etoori, Brian Rice. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: David Etoori, Alison Wringe, Georges Reniers, Francesc Xavier <lb/>Gomez-Olive, Brian Rice. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. UNAIDS. 90-90-90: An Ambitious Treatment Target to Help End the AIDS Epidemic. [Internet]. 2014 <lb/>[cited 2016 Sep 16]. Available from: http://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/media_asset/90-90-90_ <lb/>en_0.pdf <lb/>2. Sidibe ´M, Loures L, Samb B. The UNAIDS 90-90-90 target: a clear choice for ending AIDS and for sus-<lb/>tainable health and development. J Int AIDS Soc. 2016; 19(1):21133. https://doi.org/10.7448/IAS.19.1. <lb/>21133 PMID: 27424601 <lb/>3. UNAIDS. Miles to go: closing gaps, breaking barriers, righting injustices [Internet]. 2018 [cited 2022 Jun <lb/>18]. Available from: https://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/media_asset/miles-to-go_en.pdf <lb/>4. Weller I. Delivery of Antiretroviral Therapy in Sub-Saharan Africa. Clin Infect Dis. 2006 Sep 15; 43 <lb/>(6):777-8. https://doi.org/10.1086/507113 PMID: 16912955 <lb/>5. Ford N, Calmy A, Mills EJ. The first decade of antiretroviral therapy in Africa. Glob Health. 2011 Sep 29; <lb/>7(1):33. https://doi.org/10.1186/1744-8603-7-33 PMID: 21958478 <lb/>6. Rabkin M, El-Sadr WM, De Cock KM, Bellagio HIV/Health Systems Working Group1. The impact of HIV <lb/>scale-up on health systems: A priority research agenda. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr 1999. 2009 Nov; <lb/>52 Suppl 1:S6-11. https://doi.org/10.1097/QAI.0b013e3181bbcd69 PMID: 19858943 <lb/>7. Payne CF, Houle B, Chinogurei C, Herl CR, Kabudula CW, Kobayashi LC, et al. Differences in healthy <lb/>longevity by HIV status and viral load among older South African adults: an observational cohort model-<lb/>ling study. Lancet HIV. 2022 Oct 1; 9(10):e709-16. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-3018(22)00198-9 <lb/>PMID: 36179754 <lb/>8. Gourlay A, Wringe A, Todd J, Michael D, Reniers G, Urassa M, et al. Challenges with routine data <lb/>sources for PMTCT programme monitoring in East Africa: insights from Tanzania. Glob Health Action. <lb/>2015; 8:29987. https://doi.org/10.3402/gha.v8.29987 PMID: 26715204 <lb/>9. Etoori D, Wringe A, Renju J, Kabudula CW, Gomez-Olive FX, Reniers G. Challenges with tracing <lb/>patients on antiretroviral therapy who are late for clinic appointments in rural South Africa and recom-<lb/>mendations for future practice. Glob Health Action [Internet]. 2020 Apr 28 [cited 2020 Jul 31]; 13(1). <lb/>Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7241554/ https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>16549716.2020.1755115 PMID: 32340584 <lb/>10. Hallett TB, Eaton JW. A side door into care cascade for HIV-infected patients? J Acquir Immune Defic <lb/>Syndr 1999. 2013 Jul; 63 Suppl 2:S228-232. https://doi.org/10.1097/QAI.0b013e318298721b PMID: <lb/>23764640 <lb/>11. Ehrenkranz P, Rosen S, Boulle A, Eaton JW, Ford N, Fox MP, et al. The revolving door of HIV care: <lb/>Revising the service delivery cascade to achieve the UNAIDS 95-95-95 goals. PLoS Med. 2021 May <lb/>24; 18(5):e1003651. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1003651 PMID: 34029346 <lb/>12. WHO. Consolidated guidelines on the use of antiretroviral drugs for treating and preventing HIV infec-<lb/>tion Recommendations for a public health approach [Internet]. 2016. Available from: http://www.who. <lb/>int/hiv/pub/arv/arv-2016/en/ <lb/>13. World Health Organisation. Consolidated guidelines on person-centred HIV patient monitoring and <lb/>case surveillance [Internet]. 2017. Available from: https://www.who.int/hiv/pub/guidelines/person-<lb/>centred-hiv-monitoring-guidelines/en/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Boulle A, Vega I de, Moodley M, Shand L, Loff A, Fredericks 004E, et al. Data Centre Profile: The Pro-<lb/>vincial Health Data Centre of the Western Cape Province, South Africa. Int J Popul Data Sci [Internet]. <lb/>2019 Nov 20 [cited 2023 Jun 30]; 4(2). Available from: https://ijpds.org/article/view/1143 https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.23889/ijpds.v4i2.1143 PMID: 32935043 <lb/>15. Etoori D, Wringe A, Kabudula CW, Renju J, Rice B, Gomez-Olive FX, et al. Misreporting patient out-<lb/>comes in the South African national HIV treatment database: consequences for programme planning, <lb/>monitoring, and evaluation. Front Public Health [Internet]. 2020 [cited 2020 Mar 24]; 8. Available from: <lb/>https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2020.00100/full#supplementary-material <lb/>16. Mate KS, Bennett B, Mphatswe W, Barker P, Rollins N. Challenges for routine health system data man-<lb/>agement in a large public programme to prevent mother-to-child HIV transmission in South Africa. PloS <lb/>One. 2009; 4(5):e5483. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0005483 PMID: 19434234 <lb/>17. Ghys PD, Brown T, Grassly NC, Garnett G, Stanecki KA, Stover J, et al. The UNAIDS Estimation and <lb/>Projection Package: a software package to estimate and project national HIV epidemics. Sex Transm <lb/>Infect. 2004 Aug 1; 80(suppl 1):i5-9. https://doi.org/10.1136/sti.2004.010199 PMID: 15249692 <lb/>18. Human Sciences Research Council (HSRC). The fifth South African national HIV prevalence, inci-<lb/>dence, behaviour and communication survey, 2017 (SABSSM V) [Internet]. 2018 [cited 2021 Nov 13]. <lb/>Available from: http://www.hsrc.ac.za/uploads/pageContent/9234/SABSSMV_Impact_Assessment_ <lb/>Summary_ZA_ADS_cleared_PDFA4.pdf <lb/>19. Kahn K, Collinson MA, Go ´mez-Olive ´FX, Mokoena O, Twine R, Mee P, et al. Profile: Agincourt health <lb/>and socio-demographic surveillance system. Int J Epidemiol. 2012 Aug; 41(4):988-1001. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1093/ije/dys115 PMID: 22933647 <lb/>20. Kabudula CW, Houle B, Collinson MA, Kahn K, Tollman S, Clark S. Assessing Changes in Household <lb/>Socioeconomic Status in Rural South Africa, 2001-2013: A Distributional Analysis Using Household <lb/>Asset Indicators. Soc Indic Res. 2016 Jun 28;1-27. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-016-1397-z PMID: <lb/>28931968 <lb/>21. Tollman SM. The Agincourt field site-evolution and current status. South Afr Med J Suid-Afr Tydskr Vir <lb/>Geneeskd. 1999 Aug; 89(8):853-8. PMID: 10488361 <lb/>22. Tollman SM, Herbst K, Garenne M, Gear JS, Kahn K. The Agincourt demographic and health study-<lb/>site description, baseline findings and implications. South Afr Med J Suid-Afr Tydskr Vir Geneeskd. <lb/>1999 Aug; 89(8):858-64. PMID: 10488362 <lb/>23. Tollman S, Kahn K. Report on the meeting &apos;Strengthening ties: the Agincourt field site in its African con-<lb/>text.&apos; Trop Med Int Health. 1997; 2(9):920-3. <lb/>24. Rentsch CT, Kabudula CW, Catlett J, et al. Point-of-contact Interactive Record Linkage (PIRL): A soft-<lb/>ware tool to prospectively link demographic surveillance and health facility data. Gates Open Res [Inter-<lb/>net]. 2017; 1(8). Available from: https://gatesopenresearch.org/articles/1-8/v1 https://doi.org/10.12688/ <lb/>gatesopenres.12751.2 PMID: 29528050 <lb/>25. Kabudula CW, Clark BD, Go ´mez-Olive ´FX, Tollman S, Menken J, Reniers G. The promise of record <lb/>linkage for assessing the uptake of health services in resource constrained settings: a pilot study from <lb/>South Africa. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2014 May 24; 14:71. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2288-14-71 <lb/>PMID: 24884457 <lb/>26. Byass P, Hussain-Alkhateeb L, D&apos;Ambruoso L, Clark S, Davies J, Fottrell E, et al. An integrated <lb/>approach to processing WHO-2016 verbal autopsy data: the InterVA-5 model. BMC Med. 2019 30; 17 <lb/>(1):102. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-019-1333-6 PMID: 31146736 <lb/>27. Kabudula CW, Houle B, Collinson MA, Kahn K, Go ´mez-Olive ´FX, Tollman S, et al. Socioeconomic dif-<lb/>ferences in mortality in the antiretroviral therapy era in Agincourt, rural South Africa, 2001-13: a popula-<lb/>tion surveillance analysis. Lancet Glob Health. 2017; 5(9):e924-35. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-<lb/>109X(17)30297-8 PMID: 28807190 <lb/>28. South Africa: National Department of Health. Implementation of the universal test and treat strategy for <lb/>HIV positive patients and differentiated care for stable patients [Internet]. 2016 [cited 2019 Jul 24]. Avail-<lb/>able from: https://sahivsoc.org/Files/22%208%2016%20Circular%20UTT%20%20%20Decongestion <lb/>%20CCMT%20Directorate.pdf <lb/>29. Abbott A, Forrest J. Optimal Matching Methods for Historical Sequences. J Interdiscip Hist. 1986; 16 <lb/>(3):471. <lb/>30. Abbott A, Tsay A. Sequence Analysis and Optimal Matching Methods in Sociology: Review and Pros-<lb/>pect. Sociol Methods Res. 2000 Aug 1; 29(1):3-33. <lb/>31. Gabadinho A, Ritschard G, Mu ¨ller NS, Studer M. Analyzing and Visualizing State Sequences in R with <lb/>TraMineR. J Stat Softw. 2011 Apr 7; 40(1):1-37. <lb/>32. StataCorp. Stata Statistical Software. College Station, TX: StataCorp LLC; 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>33. WHO. Consolidated guidelines on person-centred HIV strategic information: strengthening routine data <lb/>for impact [Internet]. 2022 [cited 2023 Jun 30]. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications-detail-<lb/>redirect/9789240055315 <lb/>34. Jacob N, Rice B, Kalk E, Heekes A, Morgan J, Hargreaves J, et al. Utility of digitising point of care HIV <lb/>test results to accurately measure, and improve performance towards, the UNAIDS 90-90-90 targets. <lb/>PLOS ONE. 2020 Jun 30; 15(6):e0235471. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0235471 PMID: <lb/>32603374 <lb/>35. Etoori D, Kabudula CW, Wringe A, Rice B, Renju J, Gomez-Olive FX, et al. Investigating clinic transfers <lb/>among HIV patients considered lost to follow-up to improve understanding of the HIV care cascade: <lb/>Findings from a cohort study in rural north-eastern South Africa. PLOS Glob Public Health. 2022 May <lb/>24; 2(5):e0000296. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0000296 PMID: 36962304 <lb/>36. Lilian RR, Rees K, McIntyre JA, Struthers HE, Peters RPH. Same-day antiretroviral therapy initiation for <lb/>HIV-infected adults in South Africa: Analysis of routine data. PLoS ONE. 2020 Jan 14; 15(1):e0227572. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0227572 PMID: 31935240 <lb/>37. Meintjes G, Moorhouse MA, Carmona S, Davies N, Dlamini S, van Vuuren C, et al. Adult antiretroviral <lb/>therapy guidelines 2017. South Afr J HIV Med. 2017; 18(1):776. https://doi.org/10.4102/sajhivmed. <lb/>v18i1.776 PMID: 29568644 <lb/>38. Knettel BA, Cichowitz C, Ngocho JS, Knippler ET, Chumba LN, Mmbaga BT, et al. Retention in HIV <lb/>Care During Pregnancy and the Postpartum Period in the Option B+ Era: A Systematic Review and <lb/>Meta-Analysis of Studies in Africa. JAIDS J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr [Internet]. 2017 Dec 4 [cited <lb/>2018 Jan 7];Publish Ahead of Print. Available from: http://journals.lww.com/jaids/Abstract/ <lb/>publishahead/Retention_in_HIV_Care_During_Pregnancy_and_the.96776.aspx <lb/>39. Collinson MA. Striving against adversity: the dynamics of migration, health and poverty in rural South <lb/>Africa. Glob Health Action. 2010 Jun 3; 3. <lb/>40. Hunt PW, Lee SA, Siedner MJ. Immunologic Biomarkers, Morbidity, and Mortality in Treated HIV Infec-<lb/>tion. J Infect Dis. 2016 Oct 1; 214(Suppl 2):S44-50. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiw275 PMID: <lb/>27625430 <lb/>41. Lelisho ME, Wotale TW, Tareke SA, Alemu BD, Hassen SS, Yemane DM, et al. Survival rate and pre-<lb/>dictors of mortality among TB/HIV co-infected adult patients: retrospective cohort study. Sci Rep. 2022 <lb/>Nov 1; 12(1):18360. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-23316-4 PMID: 36319734 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Biases errors in routine HIV data in South Africa <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002509 June 6, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 13 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>