<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-18T16:51:53.482Z">11/18/2025 4:51:53 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T16:51:02.811438Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-18T16:51:02.811438Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening results: A <lb/>systematic literature review and meta-<lb/>analysis <lb/>Melissa Lopez Varon ID <lb/>1,2 *, Yimin Geng 3 , Bryan M. Fellman 4 , Catherine Troisi 5 , Maria <lb/>E. Fernandez 2 , Ruosha Li 6 , Belinda Reininger 7 , Kathleen M. Schmeler ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Emma Allanson 8 <lb/>1 Gynecologic Oncology &amp; Reproductive Medicine, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, <lb/>Houston, Texas, United States of America, 2 Health Promotion &amp; Behavioral Sciences, The University of <lb/>Texas Health Science Center at Houston School of Public Health, Houston, Texas, United States of America, <lb/>3 Research Medical Library, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, United <lb/>States of America, 4 Biostatistics, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, <lb/>United States of America, 5 Management, Policy &amp; Community Health, The University of Texas Health <lb/>Science Center at Houston School of Public Health, Houston, Texas, United States of America, <lb/>6 Biostatistics, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston School of Public Health, Houston, <lb/>Texas, United States of America, 7 Health Promotion &amp; Behavioral Sciences, The University of Texas Health <lb/>Science Center at Houston School of Public Health, Brownsville Regional Campus, Brownsville, Texas, <lb/>United States of America, 8 The Division of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, The University of Western <lb/>Australia, Perth, Western Australia, Australia <lb/>* mslopez1@mdanderson.org <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Ensuring timely follow-up of abnormal screening results is essential for eliminating cervical <lb/>cancer. <lb/>Objective <lb/>The purpose of the study was to review single and multicomponent interventions designed <lb/>to improve follow-up of women with abnormal cervical cancer screening results. We report <lb/>on effectiveness across studies, and describe what aspects of these interventions might be <lb/>more impactful. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Publications were searched between January 2000 and December 2022. The search <lb/>included observational, quasi-experimental (pre-post studies) and randomized controlled <lb/>studies describing at least one intervention to increase follow-up of women with abnormal <lb/>cervical cancer screening results. Outcomes of studies included completion of any follow-up <lb/>(i.e., attending a follow-up appointment), timely diagnosis (i.e., colposcopy results within 90 <lb/>days of screening) and time to diagnostic resolution (i.e., days between screening and final <lb/>diagnosis). We assessed risk of bias for observational and quasi-experimental studies using <lb/>the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) tool and the Cochrane collaboration tool for randomized <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/>1 / 21 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Varon ML, Geng Y, Fellman BM, Troisi C, <lb/>Fernandez ME, Li R, et al. (2024) Interventions to <lb/>increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer <lb/>screening results: A systematic literature review <lb/>and meta-analysis. PLoS ONE 19(2): e0291931. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 <lb/>Editor: Rebecca F. Baggaley, University of <lb/>Leicester, UNITED KINGDOM <lb/>Received: December 16, 2022 <lb/>Accepted: September 10, 2023 <lb/>Published: February 21, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Varon et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its Supporting information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: This research was in part supported by <lb/>the National Institutes of Health through MD <lb/>Anderson&apos;s 30 Cancer Center Support Grant <lb/>CA016672. The funders had no role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to <lb/>publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>studies. We conducted a meta-analysis using studies where data were provided to estimate <lb/>a summary average effect of the interventions on follow-up of patients and to identify char-<lb/>acteristics of studies associated with an increased effectiveness of interventions. We <lb/>extracted the comparison and intervention proportions of women with follow-up before and <lb/>after the intervention (control and intervention) and plotted the odds ratios (ORs) of complet-<lb/>ing follow-up along with the 95% confidence intervals (CIs) using forest plots for the inter-<lb/>ventions vs. controls when data were available. <lb/>Findings <lb/>From 7,457 identified studies, 28 met the inclusion criteria. Eleven (39%) of the included <lb/>studies had used a randomized design. Most studies (63%) assessed completion of any <lb/>follow-up visit as the primary outcome, whereas others measured time to definite diagnosis <lb/>(15%) or diagnostic resolution (22%). Navigation was used as a type of intervention in 63% <lb/>of the included studies. Most interventions utilized behavioral approaches to improve out-<lb/>comes. The overall estimate of the OR for completion of follow-up for all interventions was <lb/>1.81 (1.36-2.42). The highest impact was for programs using more than one approach <lb/>(multicomponent interventions) to improve outcomes with OR = 3.01 (2.03-4.46), com-<lb/>pared with studies with single intervention approaches with OR = 1.56 (1.14-2.14). No sta-<lb/>tistical risks were noted from publication bias or small-study effects in the studies <lb/>reviewed. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Our findings revealed large heterogeneity in how follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer <lb/>screening results was defined. Our results suggest that multicomponent interventions were <lb/>more effective than single component interventions and should be used to improve follow-<lb/>up after abnormal cervical cancer screening results. Navigation appears to be an important <lb/>tool for improving follow-up. We also provide recommendations for future studies and impli-<lb/>cations for policy in terms of better defining outcomes for these interventions. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Rationale <lb/>The World Health Organization (WHO) cervical cancer strategy to eliminate cancer as a pub-<lb/>lic health problem, calls for 70% of women to be screened with a high-performance test at least <lb/>twice in their lifetime [1, 2]. In the U.S. there are currently no indicators in the Healthy People <lb/>2030 for increasing rates of follow-up of women with abnormal cervical screening results [3]. <lb/>Furthermore, cervical cancer screening rates have increased over the last two decades [4], and <lb/>it is estimated that 81.1% of eligible women of all races currently have access to screening [5]. <lb/>The trends for cervical cancer incidence and mortality have, however, remained stagnant and <lb/>improved by only 28% during the same timeframe, with 9.7 new cases per 100,000 women in <lb/>1999 and 7.5 new cases per 100,000 women in 2017 [6], with new cases disproportionately <lb/>affecting women living in under-resourced communities, such as Black and Hispanic women. <lb/>In order to achieve the elimination of cervical cancer as a public health problem, defined by <lb/>WHO as four or fewer cases of cervical cancer diagnosed per 100,000 women per year, follow-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>up with appropriate diagnosis and treatment of high-risk women with abnormal screening test <lb/>results remains critical. The WHO goal is that 90% of these women receive appropriate follow-<lb/>up and treatment as indicated [1]. <lb/>There are many factors that could be taken into consideration as barriers to adequate and <lb/>timely follow up after abnormal screenings. Women are lost to follow-up in systems due par-<lb/>tially to a lack of education about cervical cancer and the importance of early detection and <lb/>treatment [7, 8], system barriers such as lack of systems in place to remind patients of appoint-<lb/>ments or lack of infrastructure and training to perform diagnostics/treatment or lack of clini-<lb/>cal resources [9-11]. These barriers should be addressed by sound programs that would ideally <lb/>address many of these at once. In 2016, the US Community Preventive Services Task Force <lb/>(CPSTF) recommended that multicomponent interventions be implemented to increase par-<lb/>ticipation in cervical cancer screening [12]. Multicomponent interventions are defined as &quot;. . . <lb/>two or more interventions to reduce structural barriers.&quot; They performed a systematic review <lb/>and found that the use of multicomponent interventions demonstrated a median increase in <lb/>screening participation of 6.1 percentage points when compared with no intervention. The <lb/>CPSTF states that if access to follow-up treatment is provided, these interventions might <lb/>improve the health of populations in need or underserved. Despite clear evidence and recom-<lb/>mendations for using multicomponent interventions to increase screening, the taskforce did <lb/>not include recommendations for interventions for timely diagnosis and follow-up once an <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening result is returned [12]. Increasing cervical cancer screening <lb/>at the population level is only effective in preventing cervical cancer if there is an effort to <lb/>improve adherence rates to diagnosis, early detection, and treatment of preinvasive disease for <lb/>those with abnormal screening results. <lb/>Given the importance of timely, effective follow-up and management of women with <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening results, we searched the literature for interventions <lb/>aimed to increase these outcomes. A previous report by Yabroff et al. [13] in 2000 described <lb/>a qualitative meta-analysis of interventions tested using randomized or concurrently con-<lb/>trolled study designs that may impact follow-up for women with abnormal screenings. In <lb/>this study the interventions were classified as cognitive, behavioral, or sociologic, and the <lb/>analysis showed that combining these types of intervention approaches offered no additional <lb/>benefit to follow-up outcomes as compared to interventions with a single approach. In sev-<lb/>eral cases the combination of strategies resulted in lower follow-up. Additionally, they found <lb/>that the most effective interventions were cognitive interventions, which were defined as <lb/>those with educational components, providing new information and altering misconcep-<lb/>tions/mis-information. <lb/>We undertook an updated assessment of the literature following Yabroff&apos;s classifications to <lb/>identify the interventions that have been used recently to increase follow-up of women with <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening results across multiple study designs and to explore their <lb/>level of effectiveness in reaching outcomes. Our goal was to assess the effectiveness of single vs. <lb/>multicomponent interventions developed to improve follow-up of women with abnormal cer-<lb/>vical cancer screening results. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Protocol and registration <lb/>This systematic review was conducted in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for <lb/>Systematic Reviews (PRISMA) guidelines, and the protocol was prospectively registered with <lb/>PROSPERO (CRD42020189341). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Criteria for considering studies for this review <lb/>All studies published between January 2000 and December 2022 that described interventions <lb/>targeting improvements in follow-up for women with abnormal cervical cancer screening <lb/>results were considered. All study designs and methodologies were included in our search <lb/>including retrospective and prospective cohort studies, other observational studies, random-<lb/>ized, cluster randomized or non-randomized controlled trials, quantitative and qualitative <lb/>method studies, secondary data analysis and meta-analysis of data. We considered all types of <lb/>study designs that had a comparison group including pre-and post-assessments of medical <lb/>records, studies with a described evaluation scheme, observational studies, and randomized <lb/>studies to better understand the type of intervention approaches for follow-up of abnormal <lb/>screening results. <lb/>Eligible studies were those with available data for abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/>(either visual inspection with acetic acid (VIA), cytology (Pap test) or human papillomavirus <lb/>(HPV) testing), and those that provided quantifiable outcome data on follow-up of women <lb/>with abnormal results and described the individual components of the interventions used to <lb/>improve follow-up. Studies were restricted to English language publications. Exclusion criteria <lb/>included studies without comparison groups or study protocols without defined outcomes. <lb/>Information sources and search strategy <lb/>We searched Ovid MEDLINE, Ovid Embase, Ovid PsycInfo, EBSCO CINAHL, PubMed and <lb/>Wiley-Blackwell Cochrane Library databases for publications in English language from Janu-<lb/>ary 2000 to December 2022. Disease, screening and follow-up concepts were searched using <lb/>subject headings and keywords as needed. The search terms were combined by &quot;or&quot; if they rep-<lb/>resented the similar concept, and by &quot;and&quot; if they represented different concepts. The complete <lb/>search strategies are detailed in S1-S5 Tables of S1 File. <lb/>Study selection <lb/>Two authors (MLV and EA) independently assessed the titles and abstracts of the identified stud-<lb/>ies after duplicates were removed, using Covidence software, which was used as the review man-<lb/>agement system. Full texts were then reviewed to determine if they met the inclusion criteria. <lb/>If the abstracts were conference proceedings or protocols the authors searched for contact <lb/>information from authors and if available, attempted to contact the authors and co-authors. <lb/>One co-author of two abstracts responded with information that the manuscript was in devel-<lb/>opment and not able to be shared for inclusion. <lb/>Data extraction <lb/>Data were extracted independently by MLV and EA. Any differences in data extraction were <lb/>discussed between the two authors and resolved. Collected data points included study design, <lb/>study location, setting, type of abnormal screening result, outcome definition and type of inter-<lb/>vention; which were classified as single component (i.e. utilizing only one intervention strat-<lb/>egy) or as multicomponent (using more than one intervention strategy) [13]. Given the <lb/>frequency of patient navigation programs in cervical cancer screening, we decided to include <lb/>the use of patient navigation in our data extraction categories; this was added to what we had <lb/>described in the registered PROSPERO protocol. We intended to follow the PROSPERO pro-<lb/>tocol exactly as stated, however adaptations had to be made throughout the development of <lb/>the review in terms of defining the control groups, as well as performing subgroup analyses. <lb/>These adaptations helped improve the quality of the current study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>We classified the types of interventions using the same categories (cognitive, behavioral, <lb/>sociological as well as combined interventions) used by Yabroff et al. [13]. Intervention types <lb/>were classified as: 1) behavioral if they were designed to act on follow-up behaviors directly <lb/>with cues to action; 2) cognitive if they consisted of educational activities offering new infor-<lb/>mation or knowledge; and 3) sociologic if they made use of social norms or peers to increase <lb/>compliance with follow-up. <lb/>These intervention types were selected and agreed upon by both reviewers as described by <lb/>Yabroff&apos;s manuscript; the same classification was also used by others to group interventions to <lb/>increase cancer screening rates [14, 15]. <lb/>Assessment of risk of bias <lb/>Risk of bias was assessed using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale [16] for observational and quasi-<lb/>experimental studies and the Cochrane collaboration tool for assessing risk of bias in random-<lb/>ized studies [17]. Two authors (MLV and EA) performed individual assessments at the study <lb/>level using the scales independently and resolved conflicts or differences by discussion to form <lb/>consensus. A score of &quot;1&quot; was given at any category where the study provided that information <lb/>and there was no concern of bias in that category, and a score of &quot;0&quot; was given when there was <lb/>concern for bias. <lb/>Meta-analysis and synthesis of results <lb/>A meta-analysis using random-effects model was performed to estimate a summary average <lb/>effect of interventions and to identify whether single component or multicomponent interven-<lb/>tions were associated with increased effectiveness of follow-up. When data were provided, we <lb/>extracted the comparison and intervention data, calculated and plotted the odds ratios (ORs) <lb/>of completing follow-up along with the 95% confidence intervals (CIs) using forest plots for <lb/>the intervention vs. control groups, p-values of &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. <lb/>The meta-analysis was performed separately for observational and randomized controlled <lb/>studies to account for methodological variability. We assessed the studies&apos; heterogeneity using <lb/>the I 2 statistic described by Higgins et al. [18]. The I 2 statistic was used to measure whether the <lb/>studies considered in the meta-analysis are estimating the same effect. I 2 values of less than <lb/>25% represent low heterogeneity, whereas I 2 values between 25 and 50% represent moderate <lb/>heterogeneity, between 50 and 90% represent substantial heterogeneity and between 90-100% <lb/>represent considerable heterogeneity. We calculated prediction intervals to estimate between-<lb/>study variance. <lb/>We estimated potential publication bias (i.e., tendency to publish either positive or negative <lb/>results) using funnel plots and confirmed using the Egger&apos;s test for small-study effects. Symme-<lb/>try in a funnel plot suggests that publication bias is not present. The vertical line in the funnel <lb/>plot will indicate the fixed-effects summary estimate. The other lines in the plot will represent <lb/>the 95% CI for a given standard error assuming no heterogeneity among studies. The possible <lb/>sources for the asymmetry are selection biases (publication bias or selective outcome report-<lb/>ing), poor methodological quality leading to spuriously inflated effects in smaller studies, true <lb/>heterogeneity, artifact, and chance. <lb/>All statistical analyses were performed using Stata/MP v17.0 (College Station, TX). <lb/>Summary measures <lb/>We report proportions of women with follow-up in the intervention vs. the comparison group <lb/>as extracted from the papers (ORs calculated using proportions from each publication when <lb/>available). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>The original protocol submitted had an end date of August 2020. We updated the search <lb/>until December 31, 2022. In this updated search, 698 new studies were identified and screened, <lb/>and one additional paper was included for data extraction. Furthermore, we updated the <lb/>search once again until December 1, 2022, no additional papers were found in this updated <lb/>search. <lb/>Results <lb/>Study selection <lb/>We assessed the titles and abstracts of the 7,457 studies, 49 duplicate studies were removed <lb/>with the EndNote X9 library tool. We used the Covidence software to manage the review <lb/>(Veritas Health Innovation, Melbourne, Australia. Available at www.covidence.org). After <lb/>this, the reviewers removed 7,333 studies which were not considered relevant after assessing <lb/>the publications&apos; abstracts (these included studies without interventions, basic-research studies <lb/>about HPV vaccination, non-programmatic papers, etc.). <lb/>Seventy-four full text articles were reviewed, and 28 studies met the inclusion criteria <lb/>(Fig 1). Forty-six studies were removed at this step and a list of these excluded publications is <lb/>available upon request. <lb/>Characteristics of included studies <lb/>The characteristics of the 28 studies included in this review are summarized in Table 1. Of the <lb/>28 studies included, 13 were observational (cohort = 10) or quasi-experimental (pre-post = 3) <lb/>studies [19-31], 11 were randomized studies [32-42] and four were a secondary data analysis: <lb/>three belonging to the national patient navigation research program (PNRP), and one a meta-<lb/>analysis also from the national navigation research program [43-46]. <lb/>The majority of included studies were performed in the United States (n = 22, 79%) and six <lb/>were international including locations in Canada (n = 2), Denmark (n = 1), Tanzania (n = 1), <lb/>Uganda (n = 1) and the United Kingdom (n = 1) [22, 25, 29, 36, 37, 41]. Of the 18 studies that <lb/>described the location of the study, all were based in urban locations. <lb/>Many of the studies focused on the follow-up of women in low-resource populations/set-<lb/>tings. Of the 28 studies included for data extraction, 10 focused on interventions directed <lb/>towards low-income populations [20, 22, 23, 26, 31, 34, 35, 38, 42, 46], five addressed follow-<lb/>up for racial minorities [21, 24, 30, 40, 43], one focused on addressing follow-up of women <lb/>older than 65 years of age [33] and three served a combination of minority and low-income <lb/>populations [28, 32, 39]. Nine of the studies did not describe a specific patient population <lb/>group [19, 25, 27, 29, 36, 37, 41, 44, 45]. <lb/>The majority of the studies focused on addressing follow-up for women with abnormal Pap <lb/>test results (cytology) and two focused on women who had abnormal HPV testing results [37, <lb/>40]. Two did not specify the type of abnormal result [26, 33] and one focused on abnormal <lb/>VIA results [29]. <lb/>Main outcome measurement <lb/>Follow-up of women with abnormal results was heterogeneously described in the included <lb/>studies. Follow-up was defined in one of three ways: 1. completion of at least one follow-up <lb/>visit (included scheduled, attended, and completed); 2. timely diagnosis (diagnostic resolution <lb/>at a certain timepoint determined by the authors); and 3. time to definitive diagnosis (days <lb/>between screening and a final diagnosis). Of the 28 studies, 18 (64%) measured completion of <lb/>any follow-up visit (including completion of colposcopy or any follow-up appointment). Four <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the 28 (14%) studies measured timely diagnostic resolution at a given time (a time between <lb/>screening and diagnosis as defined by the authors) [19, 23, 44, 45] and 6 of the 28 (21%) studies <lb/>focused on measuring time to definite diagnosis [28, 31, 33, 39, 43, 46]. <lb/>The measured time to follow-up ranged between 1-3 months [19, 28, 29, 31], 4-6 months <lb/>[20, 22, 25, 33, 35, 42, 45], 7-12 months [23, 36, 38, 46], two did not state the time of follow-up <lb/>[27, 41] and 11 followed patients for 12+ months. <lb/>Characteristics of the interventions described in the selected studies <lb/>Patient navigation was the most common type of intervention implemented in the studies we <lb/>reviewed. Of the included 28 studies, 10 did not use navigation [20, 23, 25, 29, 32, 36-38, 40, <lb/>41] and 18 used navigation, including nine studies funded as part of the National PNRP sup-<lb/>ported by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) [48]. This program uses navigators to address <lb/>and overcome barriers to cancer screening and follow-up. Some of the publications were from <lb/>Fig 1. Prisma chart. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Study characteristics. <lb/>Number of studies <lb/>Percentage of studies <lb/>References <lb/>Study design <lb/>Observational and quasi-experimental <lb/>13 <lb/>46% <lb/>[19-31] <lb/>Randomized controlled trial <lb/>11 <lb/>39% <lb/>[32-42] <lb/>Secondary analysis of data <lb/>4 <lb/>14% <lb/>[43-46] <lb/>Study location <lb/>United States <lb/>22 <lb/>79% <lb/>[19-21, 23, 24, 26-28, 30-35, 38-40, 42-46] <lb/>Outside of the United States a <lb/>6 <lb/>21% <lb/>[22, 25, 29, 36, 37, 41] <lb/>Type of patient population <lb/>Low-Income populations <lb/>10 <lb/>36% <lb/>[20, 22, 23, 26, 31, 34, 35, 42, 46, 47] <lb/>Racial Minorities <lb/>5 <lb/>18% <lb/>[21, 24, 30, 40, 43] <lb/>Women older than 65 years of age <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[33] <lb/>Combination <lb/>3 <lb/>11% <lb/>[28, 32, 45] <lb/>Not stated <lb/>9 <lb/>32% <lb/>[19, 25, 27, 29, 36, 37, 41, 44, 45] <lb/>Type of abnormal exam <lb/>Citology <lb/>23 <lb/>82% <lb/>[19-25, 27, 28, 30-32, 34, 35, 38, 39, 41-46] <lb/>HPV Test <lb/>2 <lb/>7% <lb/>[37, 40] <lb/>VIA/VILI <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[29] <lb/>Not specified <lb/>2 <lb/>7% <lb/>[26, 33] <lb/>Main outcome measurement <lb/>Completion of any follow up visit <lb/>18 <lb/>64% <lb/>[20-22, 24-27, 29, 30, 32, 34-37, 40-42, 47] <lb/>Diagnostic resolution <lb/>4 <lb/>14% <lb/>[19, 23, 44, 45] <lb/>Time to definite diagnosis <lb/>6 <lb/>21% <lb/>[28, 31, 33, 39, 43, 46] <lb/>Follow up adherence assessed <lb/>1-3 months <lb/>4 <lb/>14% <lb/>[19, 28, 29, 31] <lb/>4-6 months <lb/>8 <lb/>29% <lb/>[20, 22, 25, 33, 35, 39, 42, 45] <lb/>7-12 months <lb/>4 <lb/>14% <lb/>[23, 36, 38, 46] <lb/>12+ months <lb/>10 <lb/>36% <lb/>[21, 24, 26, 30, 32, 34, 37, 40, 43, 44] <lb/>Not stated <lb/>2 <lb/>7% <lb/>[27, 41] <lb/>Characteristics of Interventions <lb/>Type of intervention <lb/>Behavioral <lb/>9 <lb/>32% <lb/>[19, 20, 23, 25, 26, 29, 33, 35, 36] <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[40] <lb/>Sociologic <lb/>0 <lb/>0% <lb/>Combined strategies <lb/>18 <lb/>64% <lb/>[21, 22, 24, 27, 28, 30-32, 34, 37-39, 41-46] <lb/>Complexity of intervention <lb/>Single Intervention <lb/>23 <lb/>82% <lb/>[19, 20, 22, 23, 25-27, 29-33, 36-43, 45, 46, 48] <lb/>Multi-component <lb/>5 <lb/>18% <lb/>[21, 24, 28, 34, 35] <lb/>Use of patient navigation <lb/>Yes <lb/>18 <lb/>64% <lb/>[19, 21, 22, 24, 26-28, 31, 33-35, 39, 42-46] <lb/>No <lb/>10 <lb/>36% <lb/>[20, 23, 25, 29, 32, 36-38, 40, 41] <lb/>Intervention delivery strategy <lb/>App or SMS <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[37] <lb/>Letter <lb/>5 <lb/>18% <lb/>[12, 25, 29, 31, 36, 41] <lb/>Phone Calls <lb/>2 <lb/>7% <lb/>[12, 26, 38] <lb/>Electronic Medical Records <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[23] <lb/>Combination <lb/>19 <lb/>68% <lb/>[19-22, 24, 27, 28, 30-35, 39, 42-46] <lb/>Target for interventions <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>sites that participated in a nine-site national research program developed to overcome barriers <lb/>in delays in cancer care, targeting populations that are more vulnerable such as Hispanic-<lb/>Latina and Black populations. The intervention delivery strategies included text messages [37], <lb/>letters [25, 29, 36, 40, 41], phone calls [26, 38], processes embedded within the electronic medi-<lb/>cal record [23] and combinations of multiple communication styles (n = 19). Most of the inter-<lb/>ventions addressed changes at the patient level (n = 25), one focused on educating family <lb/>members [29] and two addressed barriers for medical providers [23, 35]. <lb/>Of the 28 studies, nine were classified as behavioral interventions [19, 20, 23, 25, 26, 29, 33, <lb/>35, 36], one of them used a cognitive (educational) approach [40], and none used the sociologic <lb/>approach as described by Yabroff [13]. The majority (n = 18, 64%) used combined permuta-<lb/>tions of the three main approaches. Details and examples of interventions are shown in Table 2. <lb/>Most of the interventions utilized were single component interventions (n = 23) and five <lb/>were multicomponent interventions [21, 24, 28, 34, 35]. An example of a single component <lb/>intervention was using navigation alone. Examples of multicomponent interventions included <lb/>systems to identify patients at high-risk of missing appointments (first component) combined <lb/>with patient navigators to educate patients about the importance of following up after abnor-<lb/>mal results are received, whereby the patient navigator offers to schedule appointments and <lb/>sets up reminders for patients before their appointments (second component). Another exam-<lb/>ple of a multicomponent intervention was use of navigators to provide surveys identifying <lb/>knowledge gaps or socioeconomic barriers for patients to receive follow-up (first component), <lb/>combined with colposcopy clinics scheduled after hours or on weekends to reduce barriers to <lb/>access care within working hours (second component). <lb/>Completion of follow-up. We calculated the odds of completing follow-up in the 21 stud-<lb/>ies where data were available. Table 3 shows the summaries of the overall estimates of patients <lb/>completing follow-up along with subgroup estimates by type of intervention (behavioral, <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Number of studies <lb/>Percentage of studies <lb/>References <lb/>Family members <lb/>1 <lb/>4% <lb/>[29] <lb/>Patients <lb/>25 <lb/>89% <lb/>[19-22, 24-28, 30-34, 36-46] <lb/>Providers <lb/>2 <lb/>7% <lb/>[12, 23, 35] <lb/>Total number of interventions <lb/>28 <lb/>a Canada, Denmark, Tanzania, Uganda, United Kingdom <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.t001 <lb/>Table 2. Examples of different intervention approaches classified by mechanism of action. <lb/>Types of <lb/>interventions <lb/>Examples of interventions <lb/>Navigator could <lb/>perform <lb/>Behavioral <lb/>• Appointment reminders for patients <lb/>• Electronic medical record-based identification of patients who need <lb/>follow up <lb/>• Sharing pathology results with patients directly instead of sending <lb/>them to the doctors&apos; offices. <lb/>Yes <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>• Educational flyers, flip charts, videos about high-risk HPV <lb/>• Letters informing patients about the need for follow up <lb/>Yes <lb/>Sociologic <lb/>• Videos of women who have had abnormal screenings to educate <lb/>peers <lb/>NA <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>cognitive, combined), complexity of interventions (single, multicomponent), and navigation <lb/>(yes, no). The overall estimate of the OR of completing follow-up in the intervention group vs. <lb/>control group was OR = 1.81 (95% CI, 1.36-2.42) indicating that interventions (regardless of <lb/>mechanism) significantly increased follow-up in participating women. The overall heterogene-<lb/>ity of the interventions assessed by the I 2 score was high (I 2 = 95.75%). <lb/>The largest intervention effects were seen in programs utilizing multicomponent interven-<lb/>tions; patients in the intervention group had three times the odds of receiving follow-up in <lb/>comparison to patients in the comparison groups, OR = 3.01 (95% CI, 2.03-4.46). The hetero-<lb/>geneity of these studies was moderate (I 2 = 58.47%). Single interventions still had a moderate <lb/>significant effect on follow-up, with patients in the intervention arm having 56% of the odds of <lb/>receiving follow-up in comparison to those in the control group; OR = 1.56 (95% CI, 1.14-<lb/>2.14). Multicomponent studies had significantly higher completion of follow-up compared to <lb/>single component studies. The test of group differences between single and multicomponent <lb/>interventions was statistically significant, indicating that both groups were substantially differ-<lb/>ent (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>When examining type of intervention according to the Yabroff classifications, the one <lb/>intervention classified as cognitive alone did not have a positive impact on follow-up for <lb/>patients with abnormal screening results, and patients in this intervention were less likely to <lb/>receive follow-up in comparison to the control groups, OR = 0.74 (95% CI, 0.25-2.17). Inter-<lb/>ventions that combined behavioral and cognitive components had a significantly higher effect <lb/>on follow-up; patients in the intervention arm had 87% of the odds to have follow-up in com-<lb/>parison to the control groups, OR = 1.87 (95% CI, 1.31-2.68). These studies still had a high <lb/>heterogeneity of effects (I 2 = 92.98%). The test of group differences between behavioral, cogni-<lb/>tive, and combined studies was non-statistically significant. <lb/>Because of the high proportion of studies using navigation as an intervention, we assessed <lb/>the ORs of follow-up for interventions using navigation as a strategy and those not using navi-<lb/>gation. Navigation interventions had a statistically significant positive effect on follow-up with <lb/>patients in the navigation group having more than twice the odds of receiving follow-up in <lb/>comparison to patients in the control group, OR = 2.32 (95% CI, 1.57-3.42). In contrast the <lb/>interventions not using navigation had a lower effect on follow-up that was not statistically sig-<lb/>nificant, OR = 1.31 (95% CI, 0.92-1.88). The statistical test to assess group differences of navi-<lb/>gation vs. no navigation was statistically significant (p = 0.035). <lb/>Table 3. Overall estimates and confidence intervals for follow-up. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>N studies <lb/>Estimate (95% CI) <lb/>p-value ^I2 <lb/>OR-overall <lb/>21 <lb/>1.81 (1.36-2.43) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>95.75% <lb/>OR-Multi-component <lb/>5 <lb/>3.01 (2.03-4.46) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>58.47% <lb/>OR-Single intervention <lb/>16 <lb/>1.56 (1.14-2.14) <lb/>0.006 <lb/>96.22% <lb/>OR-Behavioral intervention <lb/>7 <lb/>1.88 (1.10-3.21) <lb/>0.021 <lb/>96.90% <lb/>OR-Cognitive Intervention <lb/>1 <lb/>0.74 (0.25-2.17) <lb/>0.580 <lb/>1-study <lb/>OR-Combined intervention <lb/>13 <lb/>1.87 (1.31-2.68) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>92.98% <lb/>OR-No navigation <lb/>9 <lb/>1.31 (0.92-1.88) <lb/>0.139 <lb/>92.32% <lb/>OR-Navigation <lb/>12 <lb/>2.32 (1.57-3.42) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>94.01% <lb/>^p-value is test of theta = 0 (i.e., OR = 1) <lb/>-Test of group differences for type of intervention; p = 0.263; <lb/>Single component vs multicomponent interventions; p = 0.011; <lb/>patient navigation; p = 0.035 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 2 shows the forest plots of ORs for completing follow-up for the included studies. We <lb/>present non-RCTs and RCTs separately. Both groups had high heterogeneity of effects, how-<lb/>ever non-RCTs had a higher heterogeneity score (I 2 = 96.56%) in comparison to RCTs (I 2 = <lb/>88.26%). The size and direction of the effects on both groups were statistically significant <lb/>(OR = 2.06 in non-RCTs and OR = 1.50 in RCTs) indicating that the implemented interven-<lb/>tions had an effect on the study groups regardless of the study design. The 95% prediction <lb/>interval in the non-RCTs was (CI = 0.526, 8.063) and for RCTs was (CI = 0.318, 7.077). <lb/>As planned in our analysis we assessed completion of follow-up in the single vs. multicom-<lb/>ponent interventions. Fig 3 shows the Forest plots for the ORs detailing the differences <lb/>between multicomponent interventions and single interventions. Overall, multicomponent <lb/>interventions improved completion of follow-up, OR = 3.01 (95% CI, 2.03-4.46), with moder-<lb/>ate heterogeneity (I 2 = 58.47%) as seen in the forest plot. By contrast, single interventions had <lb/>a more modest effect on follow-up, OR = 1.56 (95% CI, 1.14-2.14), although the heterogeneity <lb/>was high (I 2 = 95.75%). <lb/>Risk of bias assessment for quasi-experimental and cohort studies <lb/>The results of the risk of bias assessment for the 17 non-randomized before and after and <lb/>cohort studies are summarized in Table 4. In terms of selection bias, most of the studies com-<lb/>pared the outcomes using a representative exposed cohort, however 7 of the 17 studies <lb/>(41.17%) may have some bias due to the selection of the non-exposed cohort, as these were his-<lb/>torical controls used as baseline data prior of the intervention of the study [20, 22, 24, 26, 28, <lb/>30, 31, 45]. No bias was identified in terms of ascertainment of the exposure as this was a tem-<lb/>poral exposure in most of the studies, likewise we did not identify concerns in the demonstra-<lb/>tion that the outcome of interest was not present at the start of the study (also due to the <lb/>temporal nature of study designs). In terms of comparability of the studies, we identified <lb/>potential bias in two of the studies where important covariates or confounding variables were <lb/>either not included or not stated explicitly [24, 25]. None of the studies controlled for any addi-<lb/>tional factors in their analysis. In terms of bias in assessment of outcome, one of the studies <lb/>was identified to have concerns about the assessment of the outcome [27]. We identified insuf-<lb/>ficient or inappropriate length of follow-up in one of the studies [24] and concerns about ade-<lb/>quacy of follow-up in two studies [23, 24]. <lb/>Risk of bias assessment for randomized studies <lb/>The risk of bias for the 11 included randomized studies is summarized in Table 5. None of the <lb/>studies had an overall high risk of bias and four of them had an overall low risk of bias [32, 35, <lb/>36, 38], the remaining seven studies were identified as having some concerns of risk of bias <lb/>with the most common category of bias being deviations from the intended interventions [33, <lb/>34, 37, 39-41] and potential biases in the selection of the reported results. Three studies were <lb/>identified as having some concerns in the randomization process. <lb/>Risk of publication bias <lb/>We assessed publication bias using a funnel plot (Fig 4), we also confirmed these results using <lb/>a regression-based Egger test for small study effects. The plot in Fig 4 appears to be asymmetri-<lb/>cal in the lower left, indicating possible bias in publication for smaller studies with negative <lb/>effects, however when we confirmed using Egger&apos;s test, the test results were Z = 1.35, greater <lb/>than Z = 0.1772, which indicates that there is not a statistically significant publication bias or <lb/>small-study effects in the included literature. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 2. Forest plots of meta-analysis for ORs of completing follow up (RCTs and observational studies presented separately). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>This systematic literature review gathered information from publications addressing follow-up <lb/>of women with abnormal cervical cancer screening results between 2000 and 2022. A total of <lb/>7,457 papers were included in this review and we assessed the evidence of 28 studies that fit the <lb/>inclusion criteria. These studies implemented either single or multicomponent interventions <lb/>to improve follow-up of women with abnormal screening results. The overall OR of estimated <lb/>effects was 1.81 increase in the odds of follow-up for abnormal cervical cancer screening result <lb/>[95% CI, 1.36-2.42]. <lb/>The greatest effect was seen with multicomponent interventions to follow-up women with <lb/>abnormal results (The combined estimate of effects was OR = 1.81 higher odds of follow-up <lb/>Fig 3. Forest plots of meta-analysis for ORs of completing follow up (single and multicomponent interventions <lb/>presented separately). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>for abnormal cervical cancer screening results). This is particularly relevant and consistent <lb/>with findings from systematic reviews related to screening and recommendations provided by <lb/>the CPSTF recommendation to increase cervical cancer screening [12]. Our findings also sug-<lb/>gest that multicomponent interventions should also be considered as an approach to increase <lb/>follow-up for women with abnormal cervical cancer screening results. <lb/>The use of patient navigation had statistically significant effects on the follow-up of women <lb/>with abnormal screening results with an OR = 2.32 (95% CI, 1.57-3.42) in navigation studies <lb/>vs. OR = 1.31 (95% CI, 0.92-1.88) in studies that did not include navigation. The use of patient <lb/>navigators, community healthcare workers or patient advocates has been increasing over the <lb/>last decade with good outcomes for increasing cancer screening rates [21, 49-51]. Increased <lb/>use of patient navigators should be considered not only in cervical cancer screening programs <lb/>to increase screening rates, but also to increase patient follow-up and adherence to recom-<lb/>mended treatment for vulnerable populations at higher risk of loss to follow-up. <lb/>When comparing types of intervention approaches as defined by Yabroff and colleagues, <lb/>behavioral interventions alone (including interventions addressing/changing behaviors such <lb/>as patient reminders, appointments) had an increased effect in follow-up (p = 0.021). Cogni-<lb/>tive interventions alone had no effect on follow-up, however only one study implemented this <lb/>Table 4. Bias assessment for quasi-experimental and observational studies. <lb/>SELECTION <lb/>COMPARABILITY OUTCOME <lb/>Total <lb/>Study ID <lb/>REC <lb/>SNE <lb/>AE <lb/>DONP <lb/>SCI <lb/>SCAF <lb/>AO <lb/>LFW <lb/>FC <lb/>Ell, 2002 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>Dunn, 2013 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>Cardini, 2001 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Dupuis, 2010 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>Kupets, 2018 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Luckett, 2015 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Markossian, 2012 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Mutyaba, 2009 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Paskett, 2016 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Percac-Lima, 2013 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Simon, 2015 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>Charlot, 2015 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Clark, 2011 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Kuroki, 2021 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Rodday, 2015 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Battaglia, 2012 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Freund, 2014 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>REC: Representativeness of the exposed cohort <lb/>SNE: Selection of the non-exposed cohort <lb/>AE: Ascertainment of exposure <lb/>DONP: Demonstration that the outcome of interest was not present at start of study <lb/>SCI: Study control for the most important factors (Age, SES, education, language) <lb/>SCAF: Study control for any additional factors (Mode of intervention) <lb/>AO: Assessment of outcome <lb/>LFW: Was follow-up long enough for outcomes to occur <lb/>FC: Adequacy of Follow up of cohorts <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>single strategy. Interventions combining these approaches had a statistically significant effect <lb/>on follow-up (OR = 1.87), emphasizing the likely importance of utilizing more than one <lb/>approach for increasing success in follow-up rates. <lb/>The findings from our review differ from the results of Yabroff&apos;s publication from 2000 [13] <lb/>which concluded that multicomponent or combinations of interventions offered no additional <lb/>benefits in follow-up rates. The different analytical approaches in the Yabbrof study in com-<lb/>parison to ours could make the direct comparison difficult. <lb/>They also concluded that the most effective interventions were cognitive interventions (as <lb/>opposed to behavioral interventions) using interactive telephone counseling with an increase <lb/>of compliance between 24-31%. Perhaps having someone to perform the interactive call like a <lb/>&quot;navigator&quot; could be what made the intervention impactful. Additionally, the papers included <lb/>in Yabroff&apos;s review have similar numbers of interventions classified as cognitive and behavioral <lb/>whereas in our study, most interventions were characterized as behavioral. The length of fol-<lb/>low-up in our study was mostly classified as longer than 12 months, followed by 4-6 months. <lb/>In Yabroff&apos;s study, follow-up was mainly 4-6 months, followed by 1-3 months. Our systematic <lb/>literature review included 28 studies and Yabroff&apos;s included 10 studies. Our inclusion criteria <lb/>opened the search to studies of multiple study designs whereas Yabroff&apos;s included only con-<lb/>trolled intervention trials with overall a shorter period of follow-up. The existing literature <lb/>supports the use of multicomponent interventions to improve patient outcomes and cancer <lb/>Table 5. Bias assessment for randomized studies. <lb/>Unique ID <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Comparator <lb/>Outcome <lb/>D1 D2 D3 D4 D5 Overall <lb/>Breitkopf, 2014 Counseling <lb/>Standard of Care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Desalvo, 2018 <lb/>Patient Navigation <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Diagnostic resolution <lb/>Engelstad, 2001 Care clinic intervention <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Engelstad, 2005 Navigation <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Kristiansen, <lb/>2019 <lb/>Citology results from path <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Linde, 2020 <lb/>Text messages <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Miller, 2013 <lb/>Telephone reminder and counseling Enhanced standard of care with phone <lb/>reminder <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Paskett, 2011 <lb/>Patient Navigation <lb/>Standard of Care <lb/>Time to definite diagnosis <lb/>Sanderson, 2015 Printed materials <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of follow up <lb/>Tomlinson, <lb/>2004 <lb/>Information leaflets and appt <lb/>reminders <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Wagner, 2007 <lb/>Tailored outreach intervention <lb/>Standard of care <lb/>Completion of any follow <lb/>up <lb/>Green-Low Risk <lb/>Yellow-Some Concerns <lb/>Red-High Risk <lb/>D1: Randomization process <lb/>D2: Deviations from the intended interventions <lb/>D3: Missing outcome data <lb/>D4: Measurement of outcome <lb/>D5: Selection of the reported result <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>screenings [52-54], which validates our main conclusion that implementing such strategies <lb/>also increases the odds of follow-up in women in the multicomponent intervention groups vs. <lb/>those in the control groups. <lb/>An important strength of this study is that we included publications where the authors had <lb/>used various types of study designs and outcomes defining follow-up for abnormal cervical <lb/>cancer screenings globally. This broad search allowed us to include publications that used <lb/>observational, quasi-experimental and experimental designs to assess the impact of their inter-<lb/>ventions. Additionally, the decision to include categories of types of interventions helped us <lb/>tease out the more impactful types of interventions to improve patient follow-up. Further-<lb/>more, we performed an extensive search of the grey literature and reached out to authors of <lb/>abstracts and conference proceedings seeking to learn about their findings. <lb/>This study also has limitations. The main limitation is that there is a high degree of statisti-<lb/>cal heterogeneity between the studies. There is also potential for reporting biases, particularly <lb/>when multiple papers drew data from the same national patient navigation program. In terms <lb/>of inclusion criteria and heterogeneity due to differences in the women included in the <lb/>Fig 4. Funnel plot to identify risk of publication bias. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>different studies, we consider that even though there was heterogeneity in the racial, geo-<lb/>graphic, and income characteristics of patients, the studies are addressing the needs of high-<lb/>risk populations. The control groups in these studies are composed of the same populations, <lb/>allowing us to be confident about the comparability of the results and that the effect of such <lb/>interventions is transferable to the larger -same-populations. <lb/>One general limitation in terms of measuring outcomes is that there is currently no clear <lb/>consensus on how to define appropriate follow-up of women with abnormal cervical cancer <lb/>screening results. This resulted in studies providing their own definitions of follow up. We <lb/>made an effort to characterize and summarize these differences by providing three categories <lb/>for outcome follow up: 1. Completion of at least one follow-up appointment; 2. Diagnostic res-<lb/>olution; and 3. Time to definite diagnosis. Clear guidance on the definition of acceptable out-<lb/>comes of follow-up for abnormal screening results is complex due to different guideline <lb/>recommendations for patient follow-up depending on their individual risk. In practice, fol-<lb/>low-up of abnormal results also needs to be paired with appropriate treatment, and this was <lb/>not assessed in our study. Women with an abnormal cervical screening results are recom-<lb/>mended to have, depending on their location and resources available [55], further diagnostic <lb/>investigations and/or treatment. Diagnostic investigations include colposcopy and targeted <lb/>cervical biopsy. The results of this may lead to a recommendation of treatment of confirmed <lb/>high-grade cervical abnormalities, which may be done with excisional procedure (e.g., large <lb/>loop excisional procedure) or cervical cryotherapy or thermal ablation. In some settings where <lb/>resources are scarcer, women may proceed straight to treatment based on inspection of the <lb/>cervix, without the need for colposcopy and cervical biopsy first. <lb/>Another limitation of our report is the classification of studies. We understand that this <lb/>classification is not ideal as all interventions are intending to address behaviors, however we <lb/>used these categories to organize the data in a meaningful way and to provide a comparable <lb/>framework to update the results of the study by Yabroff et al. [13]. We acknowledge that <lb/>there is overlap in these categories and that there is some subjectivity in how the different <lb/>interventions were classified. However, to be able to organize the data in a meaningful way, <lb/>and to use a framework that could be compared to a previous review, we used these three <lb/>categories. <lb/>Considering that some delay in attendance, especially for high-risk populations, may be <lb/>expected, some flexibility should be included as one of the considerations for success. The <lb/>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends that women diagnosed with <lb/>high-grade cervical lesions should be treated within 90 days [47, 56]. For clinical purposes and <lb/>to align interventions, another potential measure of impact to be used, could be from the <lb/>WHO&apos;s strategy to eliminate cervical cancer as a public health problem: that 90% of women <lb/>with identified abnormal results receive treatment. <lb/>Most of the studies included in this review (63%) measured completion of any follow-up, <lb/>which could include attending a follow-up appointment at any time. A limitation with this <lb/>type of outcome is that it does not assess the success of the interventions in terms of early diag-<lb/>nosis and most importantly appropriate treatment of women with preinvasive disease. Consid-<lb/>ering the current variability in definition of outcomes, our recommendation is that further <lb/>studies use the framework from WHO&apos;s elimination strategy to eliminate cervical cancer as a <lb/>public health problem and use the 90% of women with abnormal results treated within a rea-<lb/>sonable timeframe (90 days) from our clinical perspective. <lb/>Seeking to explore how these multicomponent interventions could be designed by future <lb/>programs, we looked at the study with the lowest effect (Clark 2011) in this group. The authors <lb/>described a need to include more efforts on implementing system changes to address the social <lb/>determinants of health (including social support and childcare). In contrast, the study with the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<body>highest effect (Ell 2022) explicitly stated that their multicomponent intervention sought to <lb/>address personal and systems barriers to follow-up adherence, highlighting the importance of <lb/>system strengthening as part of multicomponent programs. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The implementation of evidence-based interventions to improve the follow-up of women with <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening results will aid in the goal to eliminate cervical cancer as a <lb/>public health problem globally, yet this remains a challenge for populations at high risk. Our <lb/>goal was to assess the effectiveness of interventions on the impact of patient follow-up after <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening results. We conclude that even though there are challenges <lb/>in describing outcomes of successful interventions for follow-up, multicomponent interven-<lb/>tions are beneficial and impactful to improve follow-up rates. Additionally, the use of patient <lb/>navigation in these interventions seems promising and should continue to be explored and <lb/>assessed. <lb/>Most of the papers included in this study implemented interventions that targeted patients <lb/>directly. Future interventions seeking to make improvements at the policy, system and pro-<lb/>vider level may be beneficial as there are barriers to access care at all of these levels. Future tri-<lb/>als should also assess steps beyond adherence to an initial follow-up visit and focus on <lb/>assessing the proportion of patients with appropriate treatment after receiving abnormal <lb/>screening results. A target goal would be 90% of patients receiving appropriate treatment <lb/>within 90 days of abnormal test results. It is important to continue to assess the cost-effective-<lb/>ness of these multicomponent interventions so that they can be recommended and imple-<lb/>mented broadly. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. Prisma 2020 checklist for systematic reviews. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 File. S1-S5 Tables. Search strategies for Ovid MEDLINE (S1), Ovid Embase (S2), Ovid <lb/>PsycInfo (S3), EBSCO CINAHL (S4) and Cochrane Library (S5). <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 File. Full data extracted for this systematic review with meta-analysis. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Melissa Lopez Varon, Yimin Geng, Catherine Troisi, Maria E. Fernandez, <lb/>Ruosha Li, Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Data curation: Melissa Lopez Varon, Yimin Geng, Bryan M. Fellman, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Formal analysis: Melissa Lopez Varon, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Kathleen M. Schmeler. <lb/>Investigation: Melissa Lopez Varon, Catherine Troisi, Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma <lb/>Allanson. <lb/>Methodology: Melissa Lopez Varon, Yimin Geng, Bryan M. Fellman, Catherine Troisi, <lb/>Ruosha Li, Belinda Reininger, Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Project administration: Melissa Lopez Varon. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Software: Melissa Lopez Varon, Bryan M. Fellman, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Supervision: Melissa Lopez Varon, Catherine Troisi, Maria E. Fernandez, Belinda Reininger, <lb/>Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Validation: Melissa Lopez Varon, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Visualization: Melissa Lopez Varon, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Melissa Lopez Varon, Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma Allanson. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Melissa Lopez Varon, Yimin Geng, Bryan M. Fellman, Catherine <lb/>Troisi, Maria E. Fernandez, Ruosha Li, Belinda Reininger, Kathleen M. Schmeler, Emma <lb/>Allanson. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Canfell K., Towards the global elimination of cervical cancer. Papillomavirus Research, 2019. 8: p. <lb/>100170. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pvr.2019.100170 PMID: 31176807 <lb/>2. Brisson M. and Drolet M., Global elimination of cervical cancer as a public health problem. The Lancet <lb/>Oncology, 2019. 20(3): p. 319-321. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30072-5 PMID: 30795952 <lb/>3. Promotion, U.S.D.o.H.a.H.S.a.O.o.D.P.a.H., Healthy People 2030, Cancer. 2021. <lb/>4. Watson M., Benard V., and Flagg E.W., Assessment of trends in cervical cancer screening rates using <lb/>healthcare claims data: United States, 2003-2014. Preventive medicine reports, 2018. 9: p. 124-130. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2018.01.010 PMID: 29527465 <lb/>5. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), N.C.f.H.S., National Health Interview Survey, <lb/>1987-2018. CDC, 2020. <lb/>6. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, C.f.D.C.a.P.a.N.C.I., U.S. Cancer Statistics Data <lb/>Visualizations Tool, based on November 2018 submission data. (1999-2016). <lb/>7. Ashing-Giwa K.T., et al., The impact of cervical cancer and dysplasia: a qualitative, multiethnic study. <lb/>Psycho-Oncology: Journal of the Psychological, Social and Behavioral Dimensions of Cancer, 2004. <lb/>13(10): p. 709-728. https://doi.org/10.1002/pon.785 PMID: 15386644 <lb/>8. Eggleston K.S., et al., Understanding barriers for adherence to follow-up care for abnormal pap tests. <lb/>Journal of Women&apos;s Health, 2007. 16(3): p. 311-330. https://doi.org/10.1089/jwh.2006.0161 PMID: <lb/>17439377 <lb/>9. Salcedo M., et al., Addressing high cervical cancer rates in the Rio Grande Valley along the Texas-<lb/>Mexico border: a community-based initiative focused on education, patient navigation, and medical pro-<lb/>vider training/telementoring. Perspectives in public health, 2021: p. 1757913921994610. <lb/>10. Boom K., et al., Perspectives on cervical cancer screening and prevention: challenges faced by provid-<lb/>ers and patients along the Texas-Mexico border. Perspectives in public health, 2019. 139(4): p. 199-<lb/>205. https://doi.org/10.1177/1757913918793443 PMID: 30117782 <lb/>11. Jones M., et al., Identifying Barriers to Treatment for Women With Cervical Dysplasia in Rural Northern <lb/>British Columbia. Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology Canada, 2018. 40(11): p. 1401-1408. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.jogc.2018.02.009 PMID: 30477637 <lb/>12. Force C.P.S.T., Increasing Cervical Cancer Screening: Multicomponent Interventions. 2016, CPSTF. <lb/>13. Yabroff K.R., Kerner J.F., and Mandelblatt J.S., Effectiveness of interventions to improve follow-up after <lb/>abnormal cervical cancer screening. Preventive medicine, 2000. 31(4): p. 429-439. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1006/pmed.2000.0722 PMID: 11006069 <lb/>14. Yabroff K.R., Mangan P., and Mandelblatt J., Effectiveness of interventions to increase Papanicolaou <lb/>smear use. The Journal of the American Board of Family Practice, 2003. 16(3): p. 188-203. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3122/jabfm.16.3.188 PMID: 12755245 <lb/>15. Mandelblatt J.S. and Yabroff K.R., Effectiveness of interventions designed to increase mammography <lb/>use: a meta-analysis of provider-targeted strategies. Cancer Epidemiology and Prevention Biomarkers, <lb/>1999. 8(9): p. 759-767. PMID: 10498394 <lb/>16. Stang A., Critical evaluation of the Newcastle-Ottawa scale for the assessment of the quality of nonran-<lb/>domized studies in meta-analyses. European journal of epidemiology, 2010. 25(9): p. 603-605. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s10654-010-9491-z PMID: 20652370 <lb/>17. Higgins J.P., et al., The Cochrane Collaboration&apos;s tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. <lb/>Bmj, 2011. 343. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.d5928 PMID: 22008217 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>18. Higgins J.P. and Thompson S.G., Quantifying heterogeneity in a meta-analysis. Statistics in medicine, <lb/>2002. 21(11): p. 1539-1558. https://doi.org/10.1002/sim.1186 PMID: 12111919 <lb/>19. Battaglia T.A., et al., Boston Patient Navigation Research Program: the impact of navigation on time to <lb/>diagnostic resolution after abnormal cancer screening. Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp; Prevention, <lb/>2012. 21(10): p. 1645-54. https://doi.org/10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-12-0532 PMID: 23045539 <lb/>20. Cardini V.A., et al., Low-income minority women at risk for cervical cancer: a process to improve adher-<lb/>ence to follow-up recommendations. Public Health Reports, 2001. 116(6): p. 608-616. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1093/phr/116.6.608 PMID: 12196621 <lb/>21. Clark C.R., et al., Case management intervention in cervical cancer prevention: the Boston REACH <lb/>coalition women&apos;s health demonstration project. Progress in Community Health Partnerships, 2011. 5 <lb/>(3): p. 235-47. https://doi.org/10.1353/cpr.2011.0034 PMID: 22080772 <lb/>22. Dunn S., et al., Improved adherence to colposcopy through nurse-led telephone counselling and multi-<lb/>faceted patient support. Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology Canada: JOGC, 2013. 35(8): p. 723-<lb/>729. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1701-2163(15)30863-X PMID: 24007708 <lb/>23. Dupuis E.A., et al., Tracking abnormal cervical cancer screening: evaluation of an EMR-based interven-<lb/>tion. Journal of General Internal Medicine, 2010. 25(6): p. 575-80. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-010-<lb/>1287-z PMID: 20204536 <lb/>24. Ell K., et al., Abnormal cervical screen follow-up among low-income Latinas: Project SAFe. Journal of <lb/>Womens Health &amp; Gender-Based Medicine, 2002. 11(7): p. 639-51. https://doi.org/10.1089/ <lb/>152460902760360586 PMID: 12396896 <lb/>25. Kupets R., Tavasoli S., and Kane E., Impact of patient directed cytology results correspondence pro-<lb/>gram on appropriate management of high grade cytology. Journal of Lower Genital Tract Disease, <lb/>2018. 22 (2 Supplement 1): p. S7. <lb/>26. Kuroki L., et al., Addressing Unmet Basic Needs to Improve Colposcopy Adherence Among Women <lb/>With Abnormal Cervical Cancer Screening. Journal of lower genital tract disease, 2021. 25(2): p. 106-<lb/>112. https://doi.org/10.1097/LGT.0000000000000593 PMID: 33631781 <lb/>27. Luckett R., et al., Effect of patient navigator program on no-show rates at an academic referral colpos-<lb/>copy clinic. Journal of Women&apos;s Health, 2015. 24(7): p. 608-15. https://doi.org/10.1089/jwh.2014.5111 <lb/>PMID: 26173000 <lb/>28. Markossian T.W., Darnell J.S., and Calhoun E.A., Follow-up and timeliness after an abnormal cancer <lb/>screening among underserved, urban women in a patient navigation program. Cancer Epidemiology, <lb/>Biomarkers &amp; Prevention, 2012. 21(10): p. 1691-700. <lb/>29. Mutyaba T., et al., Male partner involvement in reducing loss to follow-up after cervical cancer screening <lb/>in Uganda. International Journal of Gynaecology &amp; Obstetrics, 2009. 107(2): p. 103-6. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.ijgo.2009.07.019 PMID: 19716557 <lb/>30. Percac-Lima S., et al., The impact of a culturally tailored patient navigator program on cervical cancer <lb/>prevention in Latina women. Journal of Women&apos;s Health, 2013. 22(5): p. 426-31. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1089/jwh.2012.3900 PMID: 23621746 <lb/>31. Simon M.A., et al., Evaluating a bilingual patient navigation program for uninsured women with abnor-<lb/>mal screening tests for breast and cervical cancer: implications for future navigator research. American <lb/>Journal of Public Health, 2015. 105(5): p. e87-94. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2014.302341 PMID: <lb/>25713942 <lb/>32. Breitkopf C.R., et al., Intervention to improve follow-up for abnormal Papanicolaou tests: a randomized <lb/>clinical trial. Health Psychology, 2014. 33(4): p. 307. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0032722 PMID: 23730719 <lb/>33. DeSalvo J.M., et al., Characterizing Time to Diagnostic Resolution After an Abnormal Cancer Screening <lb/>Exam in Older Adult Participants in the Ohio Patient Navigation Research Program. Journal of Aging &amp; <lb/>Health, 2018. 30(8): p. 1284-1304. https://doi.org/10.1177/0898264317715184 PMID: 28649914 <lb/>34. Engelstad L.P., et al., Abnormal Pap smear follow-up in a high-risk population. Cancer Epidemiology <lb/>and Prevention Biomarkers, 2001. 10(10): p. 1015-1020. PMID: 11588126 <lb/>35. Engelstad L.P., et al., The effectiveness of a community outreach intervention to improve follow-up <lb/>among underserved women at highest risk for cervical cancer. Preventive medicine, 2005. 41(3-4): p. <lb/>741-748. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2005.06.003 PMID: 16125761 <lb/>36. Kristiansen B.K., et al., Direct notification of cervical cytology results to women improves follow-up in <lb/>cervical cancer screening-A cluster-randomised trial. Preventive Medicine Reports, 2019. 13: p. 118-<lb/>125. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2018.11.015 PMID: 30568870 <lb/>37. Linde D.S., et al., Effectiveness of One-Way Text Messaging on Attendance to Follow-Up Cervical Can-<lb/>cer Screening Among Human Papillomavirus-Positive Tanzanian Women (Connected2Care): Parallel-<lb/>Group Randomized Controlled Trial. Journal of Medical Internet Research, 2020. 22(4): p. e15863. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2196/15863 PMID: 32238335 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>38. Miller S.M., et al., Tailored telephone counseling to improve adherence to follow-up regimens after an <lb/>abnormal pap smear among minority, underserved women. Patient education and counseling, 2013. <lb/>93(3): p. 488-495. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec.2013.08.008 PMID: 24007767 <lb/>39. Paskett E.D., et al., The Ohio Patient Navigation Research Program: does the American Cancer Soci-<lb/>ety patient navigation model improve time to resolution in patients with abnormal screening tests? 2012, <lb/>AACR. <lb/>40. Sanderson M., et al., Results of a health education message intervention on HPV knowledge and <lb/>receipt of follow-up care among Latinas infected with high-risk human papillomavirus. Journal of health <lb/>care for the poor and underserved, 2015. 26(4): p. 1440-1455. https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2015.0131 <lb/>PMID: 26548691 <lb/>41. Tomlinson A., et al., Does improving communication and information for women increase attendance at <lb/>colposcopy in an inner city clinic? A randomised controlled trial. European Journal of Gynaecological <lb/>Oncology, 2004. 25(4): p. 445-8. PMID: 15285300 <lb/>42. Wagner T.H., et al., Peer Reviewed: The Costs of an Outreach Intervention for Low-Income Women <lb/>With Abnormal Pap Smears. Preventing chronic disease, 2007. 4(1). <lb/>43. Charlot M., et al., Impact of patient and navigator race and language concordance on care after cancer <lb/>screening abnormalities. Cancer, 2015. 121(9): p. 1477-1483. https://doi.org/10.1002/cncr.29221 <lb/>PMID: 25565151 <lb/>44. Freund K.M., et al., Impact of patient navigation on timely cancer care: the Patient Navigation Research <lb/>Program. Journal of the National Cancer Institute, 2014. 106(6): p. dju115. https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/ <lb/>dju115 PMID: 24938303 <lb/>45. Paskett E.D., et al., Impact of Patient Navigation Interventions on Timely Diagnostic Follow Up for <lb/>Abnormal Cervical Screening. Journal of Women&apos;s Health, 2016. 25(1): p. 15-21. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1089/jwh.2014.5094 PMID: 26625131 <lb/>46. Rodday A.M., et al., Impact of patient navigation in eliminating economic disparities in cancer care. Can-<lb/>cer, 2015. 121(22): p. 4025-4034. https://doi.org/10.1002/cncr.29612 PMID: 26348120 <lb/>47. Miller J.W., et al., From cancer screening to treatment: Service delivery and referral in the National B <lb/>reast and C ervical C ancer E arly D etection P rogram. Cancer, 2014. 120(S16): p. 2549-2556. <lb/>48. Freund K.M., et al., National cancer institute patient navigation research program: methods, protocol, <lb/>and measures. Cancer, 2008. 113(12): p. 3391-3399. https://doi.org/10.1002/cncr.23960 PMID: <lb/>18951521 <lb/>49. Christie J., et al., A randomized controlled trial using patient navigation to increase colonoscopy screen-<lb/>ing among low-income minorities. Journal of the National Medical Association, 2008. 100(3): p. 278-<lb/>284. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0027-9684(15)31240-2 PMID: 18390020 <lb/>50. Han H.-R., et al., Tailored lay health worker intervention improves breast cancer screening outcomes in <lb/>non-adherent Korean-American women. Health education research, 2009. 24(2): p. 318-329. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1093/her/cyn021 PMID: 18463411 <lb/>51. Lasser K.E., et al., A multilevel intervention to promote colorectal cancer screening among community <lb/>health center patients: results of a pilot study. BMC family practice, 2009. 10(1): p. 1-7. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1186/1471-2296-10-37 PMID: 19480698 <lb/>52. Reuland D.S., et al., Effect of combined patient decision aid and patient navigation vs usual care for <lb/>colorectal cancer screening in a vulnerable patient population: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA internal <lb/>medicine, 2017. 177(7): p. 967-974. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2017.1294 PMID: <lb/>28505217 <lb/>53. Lau R., et al., Achieving change in primary care-effectiveness of strategies for improving implementa-<lb/>tion of complex interventions: systematic review of reviews. BMJ open, 2015. 5(12): p. e009993. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009993 PMID: 26700290 <lb/>54. Clement S., et al., Complex interventions to improve the health of people with limited literacy: A system-<lb/>atic review. Patient education and counseling, 2009. 75(3): p. 340-351. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec. <lb/>2009.01.008 PMID: 19261426 <lb/>55. Dykens J.A., et al., Evaluating the implementation of cervical cancer screening programs in low-<lb/>resource settings globally: a systematized review. Cancer Causes &amp; Control, 2020. 31(5): p. 417-429. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10552-020-01290-4 PMID: 32185604 <lb/>56. Benard V.B., et al., Vital signs: cervical cancer incidence, mortality, and screening-United States, <lb/>2007-2012. MMWR. Morbidity and mortality weekly report, 2014. 63(44): p. 1004. PMID: 25375072 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Interventions to increase follow-up of abnormal cervical cancer screening results <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291931 February 21, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 21 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>