<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T14:26:49.422Z">11/12/2025 2:26:49 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1093/ofid_ofae542</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: 10.1093/ofid_ofae542</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T14:26:38.141835Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T14:26:38.141835Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>GigaScience , 2024, 13 , 1-7 <lb/>DOI: 10.1093/gigascience/giad099 <lb/>Technical Note <lb/>FAIR data retrieval for sensiti v e clinical research data in <lb/>Galaxy <lb/>Jasper Ouwerkerk 1 , * , † , Helena Rasche 1 , † , John D. Spalding 2 , Saskia Hiltemann 1 , † , and Andrew P. Stubbs 1 , † <lb/>1 Clinical Bioinformatics Group, Department of Pathology, Erasmus Medical Center, 3015 CN, Rotterdam, the Netherlands <lb/>2 CSC-IT Center for Science, 02101 Espoo, Finland <lb/> * Corr espondence addr ess. J asper Ouw erkerk, Clinical Bioinformatics Group, Department of Pathology, Erasmus Medical Center, Wytemaweg 80, 3015 CN, <lb/>Rotterdam, T he Netherlands . E-mail: j.ouwerkerk.1@er asm usmc.nl <lb/> † Contributed equally. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Bac kgr ound: In clinical resear c h, data have to be accessible and reproducible, but the generated data are becoming larger and analysis <lb/>complex. Here we propose a platform for F indable , Accessible , Interoper able , and Reusable (FAIR) data access and creating reproducible <lb/>findings. Standardized access to a major genomic r e positor y, the Eur opean Genome-Phenome Ar c hi v e (EGA), has been achiev ed with <lb/>API services like PyEGA3. We aim to provide a FAIR data analysis service in Galaxy by retrieving genomic data from the EGA and <lb/>provide a generalized &quot;omics&quot; platform for FAIR data analysis. <lb/>Results: To demonstrate this, we implemented an end-to-end Galaxy workflow to r e plicate the findings from an RD-Connect synthetic <lb/>dataset Beyond the 1 Million Genomes (synB1MG) av aila b le fr om the EGA. We dev eloped the PyEGA3 connector within Galaxy to <lb/>easil y download m ultiple datasets fr om the EGA. We added the gene.iobio tool, a diagnostic environment for precision genomics, to <lb/>Galaxy and demonstrate that it provides a more dynamic and interpretable view for trio analysis results. We developed a Galaxy trio <lb/>analysis workflow to determine the pathogenic variants from the synB1MG trios using the GEMINI and gene.iobio tool. The complete <lb/>workflow is av aila b le at WorkflowHub, and an associated tutorial was created in the Galaxy Training Network, which helps researchers <lb/>unfamiliar with Galaxy to run the workflow. <lb/>Conclusions: We showed the feasibility of reusing data from the EGA in Galaxy via PyEGA3 and validated the workflow by rediscov-<lb/>ering spiked-in variants in synthetic data. F inally, w e improved existing tools in Galaxy and created a workflow for trio analysis to <lb/>demonstrate the value of FAIR genomics analysis in Galaxy. <lb/>Ke yw ords: B1MG, FAIR, Galaxy, trio analysis <lb/>Key Points: <lb/>r Secure access to GA4GH EGA service using PyEGA3 <lb/>Galaxy service <lb/>r Standard analysis for B1MG synthetic data <lb/>r Inter activ e gene v ariant detection for trio anal ysis with <lb/>gene.iobio in Galaxy <lb/>r Created a tutorial associated with the Galaxy Training <lb/>Network <lb/></front>
              
    <body>Findings <lb/>Background <lb/>In the past few years , there ha ve been many developments in <lb/>Findable , Accessible , Inter oper able, and Reusable (FAIR) data [ 1 ]. <lb/>FAIR data are data and corresponding metadata that are (i) find-<lb/>able by both machines and humans, (ii) accessible using a stan-<lb/>dard open protocol, (iii) interoperable so they can easily be pro-<lb/>cessed and analyzed, and (iv) resuable so the data can be under-<lb/>stood b y any one and make anal yses r epr oducible [ 2 ]. FAIR data al-<lb/>lo w resear chers to reanalyze data with new genetic analysis tools <lb/>not yet available at the time of data publication. For example, in <lb/>a study on fusion genes, 24 novel fusions in breast cancer were <lb/>found with the introduction of a new tool [ 3 ]. <lb/>Ho w e v er, for man y biomedical anal yses, r esearc hers ar e r e-<lb/>quired to have considerable knowledge on using analysis tools. <lb/>Mor eov er, man y tools r equir e knowledge of Unix commands or <lb/>Python coding [ 4-6 ]. This creates a barrier for clinical r esearc hers <lb/>who want to r eanal yze data, r educing the adoption of implement-<lb/>ing FAIR principles and r eanal yses. <lb/>The Galaxy platform [ 7 ] supports r esearc hers in adopting these <lb/>complex computation tools for their FAIR data analysis. Galaxy is <lb/>an online analysis platform with a plethora of tools to perform <lb/>text/table processing, omics analysis, machine learning, image <lb/>anal ysis, and mor e. All these tools are maintained and developed <lb/>b y a gro wing community. Using the tools does not r equir e an y pr o-<lb/>gramming skills, and they are easy to share with colleagues and <lb/>other r esearc hers. At the end of the analysis, the w orkflo w of tools <lb/>can be exported to r epr oduce the analysis [ 7 ]. These w orkflo ws <lb/>can be made discov er able by uploading the w orkflo w to Work-<lb/>flowHub [ 8 ], a registry for describing, sharing, and publishing sci-<lb/>entific computational w orkflo ws. In ad dition, Galaxy alread y has <lb/>300 + tutorials describing w orkflo ws on genome assembly, ecol-<lb/>ogy, meta-genomics, v ariant anal ysis, and mor e [ 9 ]. This is benefi-<lb/>cial to man y r esearc hers since many complex Unix-based tools <lb/>are essential for biomedical research. An example of such an <lb/></body>

    <front>Recei v ed: J une 28, 2023. Revised: October 16, 2023. Accepted: November 1, 2023 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford Uni v ersity Pr ess GigaScience. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Cr eati v e Commons <lb/>Attribution License ( https://cr eati v ecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided <lb/>the original work is pr operl y cited. <lb/></front>
    
    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/></note>

    <page>2</page>
    
    <note place="headnote">| GigaScience , 2024, Vol. 13, No. 1 <lb/></note>

	<body>application is Circos [ 6 ], which is a complicated visualization tool <lb/>for comparing whole genomes . T his tool has been implemented <lb/>within Galaxy, which makes it simple for any researcher to create <lb/>Circos plots [ 10 ]. <lb/>Even though Galaxy is a well-established platform for analy-<lb/>sis, it still lacks applications for retrieving access-controlled data <lb/>fr om lar ge r e positories lik e the EGA. The EGA controls the ac-<lb/>cessibility to datasets using Data Access Committees (DACs). Re-<lb/>questors can access data from the EGA by contacting the DAC for <lb/>the dataset of inter est. DACs ar e gener all y formed by the organi-<lb/>zation that collected the data and performed the analysis . T his <lb/>allo ws resear chers to access datasets of interest and also manage <lb/>the accessibility of their data at the EGA [ 11 ]. <lb/>In this w ork, w e implemented PyEGA3 [ 12 ], a tool that can ac-<lb/>cess controlled data from the EGA, within Galaxy. Here, access <lb/>to datasets is managed via the EGA. Our implementation of the <lb/>PyEGA3 tool allows to filter datasets , a vailable on the EGA, based <lb/>on their metadata and scale up analysis . T his will be showcased <lb/>by validating our workflow for trio analysis on family trios from <lb/>the Beyond 1 Million Genomes (B1MG) project [ 13 ]. In trio anal-<lb/>ysis, the differences in DN A betw een the maternal, paternal, and <lb/>affected child (i.e., proband) are analyzed to detect causative vari-<lb/>ants causing a particular disease in the proband. To perform the <lb/>trio analysis, we added gene.iobio, a standalone web-based tool, to <lb/>Galaxy [ 14 ]. The complete w orkflo w, including data r etrie v al with <lb/>PyEGA3, is implemented within Galaxy and uploaded to Work-<lb/>flowHub for discov er ability. In addition, we wr ote a tutorial to ex-<lb/>plain our w orkflo w in detail, which is associated with the Galaxy <lb/>Training Network (GTN) [ 15 ]. This study shows it is feasible to <lb/>adopt end-to-end scalable FAIR analysis of clinical data and ul-<lb/>timately for any future analysis on data available at the EGA. <lb/>Results <lb/>PyEGA3 <lb/>PyEGA3 was implemented to r etrie v e access-contr olled data fr om <lb/>the EGA in Galaxy. Authentication of the user is done by pass-<lb/>w or d and username . T his information is encrypted using a Vault <lb/>abstraction [ 16 ] when configured by the Galaxy administrator. In <lb/>addition, LS Login (Pr e viousl y ELIXIR A uthentication and A utho-<lb/>rization Infr astructur e [AAI]) tokens can be used for authentica-<lb/>tion, if set up by the user. The tokens are stored in the Galaxy <lb/>database and tempor aril y v alid (1 hour by default) to shorten <lb/>the window of time for a potential attac k. Curr entl y, the pr o-<lb/>cess of authentication is initiated by linking one&apos;s EGA account to <lb/>their LS Login (possible via https:// ega.ebi.ac.uk:8443/ ega-openid-<lb/>connect-server/ega-login ; previously ELIXIR AAI) account. Next, <lb/>the user logs in to Galaxy via LS Login, which attaches the user&apos;s <lb/>GA4GH passport and access and r efr esh tokens to the user&apos;s ac-<lb/>count in Galaxy. The r efr esh token is used to r egularl y r efr esh <lb/>their credentials, allowing the Galaxy server to act on their be-<lb/>half when the user requests it via tool execution. Upon execut-<lb/>ing a tool, assuming the tool is written to support it, the access <lb/>token or, possibly in the future, passports are attached to the <lb/>tool&apos;s execution such that they can be used to authenticate the <lb/>user. While curr entl y the access token is implemented on an ad <lb/>hoc basis, we intend to dir ectl y implement support for this type <lb/>of tool and authentication method in a future version of Galaxy <lb/>( https:// github.com/ galaxyproject/ galaxy/ issues/ 14578 ). <lb/>The tool implemented in Galaxy has the same functionalities <lb/>as the command-line v ersion-namel y, list a user&apos;s authorized <lb/>datasets, list files in a dataset, and fetch a file or all files in a <lb/>dataset. In ad dition, we ad ded the option to download a speci-<lb/>fied list of files from the EGA. With this option, it is still possible <lb/>to download a specific genomic range (see Fig. 1 ), which is useful <lb/>for large binary alignment map (BAM) and variant calling format <lb/>(VCF) files. <lb/>Gene.iobio <lb/>We also implemented the gene.iobio tool within the Galaxy frame-<lb/>work. Gene.iobio is a tool for precision genomics. The tool is able to <lb/>cr eate dynamic r esults, whic h include cr eating a list of genes for <lb/>the disease of inter est, cr eating an automatic report of pathogenic <lb/>variants within the list of genes, allowing the custom filtering of <lb/>pathogenic v ariants, r eporting phenotypes and publications r e-<lb/>lated to the gene of inter est, and r e vie wing the variants . T hese <lb/>ar e major impr ov ements compar ed to the existing trio analysis <lb/>tool within Galaxy, GEMINI [ 17 ], which was only able to produce <lb/>static plots or large lists of filtered variants. <lb/>Workflow and tutorial <lb/>In this study, we illustrate an end-to-end w orkflo w for trio anal-<lb/>ysis for FAIR data. This w orkflo w r etrie v es and anal yzes files <lb/>fr om lar ge datasets in the EGA and can easil y be ada pted to an y <lb/>other EGA dataset. We illustrate this by analyzing data from the <lb/>EGAD00001008392 [ 18 ] dataset. This dataset contains 6 trio fami-<lb/>lies with different inheritance patterns of digitally spiked-in vari-<lb/>ants, wher e eac h famil y is subject to a differ ent disease. Next, we <lb/>demonstrate the utility of gene.iobio by analyzing the family trios <lb/>and comparing the existing trio analysis tool in Galaxy, GEMINI, <lb/>to the gene.iobio tool. Finally, a comprehensive tutorial is made <lb/>av ailable fr om the Galaxy Tr aining materials [ 19 ] under the topic <lb/>&quot;Variant Analysis,&quot; titled &quot;Trio Analysis Using Synthetic Datasets <lb/>from RD-Connect GPAP)&quot; [ 20 ] to teach users how to access data <lb/>from the EGA and to r e-cr eate and run the w orkflo w fr om scr atc h. <lb/>In addition, the w orkflo w is available at WorkflowHub [ 21 ]. <lb/>Use case: breast cancer <lb/>Her e we r eport on the output pr oduced by gene.iobio to demon-<lb/>strate its added value to the Galaxy platform. To produce these <lb/>results, we used case 5 from the EGA dataset. This case describes <lb/>a family trio where the mother and daughter are affected by <lb/>breast cancer. The case describes an autosomal dominant inher-<lb/>itance pattern, which causes a missense single-nucleotide poly-<lb/>mor phism (SNP) at c hr omosome 17 position 41,215,920, c hanging <lb/>a guanine into a thymine [ 18 ]. <lb/>The BAMs and VCFs of the family trio are first downloaded us-<lb/>ing the PyEGA3 tool in Galaxy. The tool was able to secur el y down-<lb/>load the trios&apos; VCFs and slices of the large BAMs by selecting c hr o-<lb/>mosome 17. After downloading the data from the EGA, the work-<lb/>flow pr epr ocesses the data and pr oduces m ultiple outputs using <lb/>gene.iobio. <lb/>First, a disease/phenotype of interest can be provided to pro-<lb/>duce a list of genes of inter est. To gener ate this list of genes, the <lb/>gene.iobio makes use of the Phenolyzer software [ 22 ]. In this case, <lb/>the disease is breast cancer. The automatic selection of impor-<lb/>tant genes related to the disease speeds up the process of finding <lb/>causativ e v ariants. Alternativ el y, genes can be added manually. <lb/>Next, gene .iobio searches , by default, for causativ e v ariants in <lb/>the top 20 of provided list of genes by filtering all the variants in <lb/>the VCFs using preselected, but customizable , parameters . Fig. 2 <lb/>shows that a spiked-in causativ e v ariant was found with sufficient <lb/>depth and allele counts . In addition, gene .iobio shows the quality <lb/>of the variant, a pathogenicity score, the population frequency, <lb/>a visualization of the inheritance patterns, and statistics on the <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/>Galaxy fair sensitive clinical data retrieval | </note>
    
    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figur e 1: T he Galaxy interface of the added featur e to the PyEga3 tool to download m ultiple files . It takes a tabular data with EGAF IDs . In addition, a <lb/>region can be provided to download a small region in BAMs or VCFs. <lb/>Figure 2: Ov ervie w of gene.iobio r esults for the spiked-in v ariant. The figur e shows statistics on quality of the v ariant, phenotype associations, <lb/>pathogenicity , population frequency , inheritance, and conservation. <lb/>conservation of the variant. This information helps the user to <lb/>determine the legitimacy of the variant. <lb/>Ov er all, gene.iobio pr ovides an inter activ e and visual ov ervie w <lb/>of causativ e v ariant identification. This is a significant impr ov e-<lb/>ment compared to the previous causative variant identification <lb/>tool GEMINI, especially with regards to identifying the quality of <lb/>the causative variant, as illustrated by Fig. 2 . <lb/>Trio analysis comparison <lb/>In addition, we further validated the gene.iobio tool by identify-<lb/>ing the causative variants in all the families a vailable . A compar-<lb/>ison of the results reported by gene.iobio and GEMINI is shown <lb/>in Table 1 . It shows the number of v ariants r eported by GEMINI <lb/>Table 1: Ov ervie w of existing Galaxy trio analysis tools and the <lb/>number of variants they report <lb/>Family <lb/>GEMINI <lb/>Gene.iobio <lb/>Case 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Case 2 <lb/>77 <lb/>1 <lb/>Case 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>Case 4 <lb/>26 <lb/>1 <lb/>Case 5 <lb/>142 <lb/>1 <lb/>Case 6 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/></note>

    <page>4</page>

    <note place="headnote">| GigaScience , 2024, Vol. 13, No. 1 <lb/></note>

    <body>and gene.iobio using the default parameters. The table shows that <lb/>GEMINI does not report any variants for some cases. When GEM-<lb/>INI does r eport v ariants, it r eports the corr ect v ariants. Ho w e v er, it <lb/>also r eports man y false positiv es, since eac h famil y has onl y 1 or <lb/>2 spiked-in causativ e v ariants. In contr ast, gene.iobio does report <lb/>causativ e v ariants for eac h famil y and onl y the corr ect ones . T his <lb/>shows that gene.iobio is not only interpretable but also accurate. <lb/>Limitations and Future Work <lb/>PyEGA passports <lb/>In the current implementation of PyEGA3 in Galaxy, we miss the <lb/>support of authentication with Passports, a Global Alliance for <lb/>Genomics and Health (GA4GH) standard. The GA4GH has de v el-<lb/>oped a set of standards to facilitate data sharing within a feder-<lb/>ated context. To access federated resources and controlled access <lb/>data, the identity of the user accessing the data must be deter-<lb/>mined, along with any data access permissions the user has for <lb/>particular datasets. Two GA4GH standards facilitate this, the AAI <lb/>standard and the Passport standard. The AAI specification pro-<lb/>files OpenID Connect (OIDC) protocol provides a mechanism for <lb/>inter oper ability of identities between different institutions, sup-<lb/>porting federated data access while ensuring the security of the <lb/>data by defining the way identities and access permissions are ex-<lb/>changed between resources . T he Passport standard defines how <lb/>the permissions are represented, in the form of visas . T here are <lb/>5 types of visa: Contr olledAccessGr ants, whic h lists the access <lb/>permissions for the user to controlled access datasets; LinkedI-<lb/>dentities, which allows a user to link different identities to facil-<lb/>itate single sign on; and AffiliationAndRole, AcceptedTermsAnd-<lb/>P olicies , and ResearcherStatus . Passports support tiered access-<lb/>open, r egister ed, and contr olled. Typicall y, the data available to <lb/>the user will increase and the user moves from open to controlled <lb/>access. Any user can access resources on the open access tier, <lb/>while ResearcherStatus indicates the user can access resources at <lb/>the r egister ed access tier, and Contr olledAccessGr ants indicates <lb/>whic h contr olled access r esources the user can access . T he Life <lb/>Science AAI supports GA4GH AAI and Passport standards. A user <lb/>can link their Life Science identity with 1 or more institutional <lb/>or social media identities and use these identities to access re-<lb/>sources, such as Galaxy instances or datasets from the EGA. For <lb/>example, a user can use their linked institutional identity via the <lb/>Life Science AAI to access data from EGA via the EGA Permissions <lb/>API and Data API. In the future, we aim to implement the Passport <lb/>protocol into Galaxy to access data compliant with the GA4GH <lb/>standards [ 23 ]. <lb/>Data management <lb/>In addition to secure data retrieval, Galaxy is working on improv-<lb/>ing secure data management. Currently, data are stored unen-<lb/>crypted on the user&apos;s Galaxy account. But, with PyEGA imple-<lb/>mented in Galaxy, confidential data from the EGA could be left <lb/>unprotected when uploaded to a public Galaxy server. This would <lb/>violate the EGA Data Access Agreement (DAA), which requires the <lb/>user&apos;s institution to pr eserv e the confidentiality of the data. <lb/>Our a ppr oac h for pr ocessing confidential human genetic data <lb/>would curr entl y onl y be in compliance with EGA guidelines and <lb/>the General Data Protection Regulation [ 24 ] when data are stored <lb/>on a private Galaxy managed by the user&apos;s institution. Howe v er, <lb/>data privacy at rest does exist within the community; currently, <lb/>S3 buckets [ 25 ] can be leveraged by Galaxy, which offer the ability <lb/>to encrypt data at rest. In the future, Galaxy&apos;s Crypt4GH [ 26 ] inte-<lb/>gr ation pr oject will pr ovide a mor e deepl y integr ated alternativ e. <lb/>This ongoing project aims to implement Crypt4GH [ 27 ], a stan-<lb/>dardized encryption tool for genetic data, to encrypt data at rest <lb/>in Galaxy automaticall y. Curr entl y, this pr oject does not consider <lb/>memory encryption as e v ery individual tool that works with the <lb/>data must implement support for trusted compute. Alternativ el y, <lb/>directories could be encrypted with a user k e y, which would en-<lb/>sure the cached data are also encrypted. <lb/>Data sharing <lb/>Once EGA data have been uploaded to a Galaxy instance, the data <lb/>and analysis can easily be shared with other users. Currently, a <lb/>user could share a history containing authenticated EGA data <lb/>with another user who does not have DAC access, which is in vi-<lb/>olation of the DAA. Curr entl y, Galaxy implements the ability to <lb/>contr ol priv acy of individual datasets within a history, permitting <lb/>the user to share the anal ysis r esults, without sharing the private <lb/>sour ce data. Ho w e v er, this r emains a manual process . T herefore , <lb/>we propose that in the future, the permission to share DAC ac-<lb/>cess datasets to another Galaxy user is v alidated automaticall y. <lb/>We suggest that this validation should be dataset specific (e.g., <lb/>statistics , figures , and w orkflo ws deriv ed fr om the history should <lb/>be shareable as long as they ares in compliance with the DAA). <lb/>Linking major repositories <lb/>In addition to the EGA, other major data repositories exist that <lb/>have not been linked to Galaxy yet, such as The Cancer Genome <lb/>Atlas Pr ogr am (TCGA) [ 28 ]. The TCGA has its own data r etrie v al <lb/>tool, the GDC Data Transfer Tool [ 29 ], for which separate creden-<lb/>tials within a user&apos;s Galaxy account have to be implemented. It <lb/>would be more efficient for these repositories to support pass-<lb/>ports . T his would gr eatl y simplify the adoption of other major <lb/>repositories in Galaxy in a GA4GH-compliant way, ultimately in-<lb/>creasing the adoption of FAIR data principles. <lb/>An alternative to linking the repositories to Galaxy is to deploy <lb/>a Galaxy instance where the data are stored. This would still re-<lb/>quire the Galaxy instance to download the data from the reposi-<lb/>tory in the Galaxy instance, but the data will ne v er leav e the repos-<lb/>itory itself. Ho w e v er, this would r equir e the data r epository to hav e <lb/>sufficient computing utilities in order to analyze the data with <lb/>Galaxy. In the future, this might be a better alternative to linking <lb/>the repositories itself. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In this study, we implemented PyEGA3 in Galaxy to r etrie v e <lb/>data from the EGA in a GA4GH-compliant manner. In addi-<lb/>tion, gene.iobio was implemented to impr ov e v ariant anal yses <lb/>in Galaxy. These tools were validated by using B1MG data from <lb/>the EGA and creating a findable analysis w orkflo w into Galaxy. <lb/>This work illustrates that gene.iobio is a major impr ov ement com-<lb/>pared to the current trio analysis tool in Galaxy as it creates inter-<lb/>pretable and dynamic plots. In addition, we showed that Galaxy <lb/>makes it feasible and manageable for any researcher to retrieve <lb/>data from the EGA securely and analyze family trio data in a FAIR <lb/>manner. Not only is this work applicable to trio analysis, but it <lb/>is also tr ansfer able to other omics anal ysis, suc h as genome as-<lb/>sembl y, metabolomics, meta genomics, pr oteomics, and tr anscrip-<lb/>tomics. In conclusion, this work illustrates that Galaxy is one step <lb/>closer to becoming a generalized omics platform for FAIR data <lb/>analysis. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/>Galaxy fair sensitive clinical data retrieval | </note>
    
    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <div type="annex">Methods <lb/>Implementation <lb/>The installation and dependencies for gene.iobio are handled <lb/>by Galaxy ( RRID:SCR _ 006281 ). The version of gene.iobio reported <lb/>here is v4.7.1a. <lb/>Tr aining ma terials <lb/>Our w orkflo w simplifies the data collection from the EGA and the <lb/>visualization and analysis of family trios. In addition, we created <lb/>a tutorial for running the w orkflo w on Galaxy. Also, the tutorial <lb/>describes in detail how to gain access to datasets on the EGA to <lb/>simplify the adoption of this w orkflo w for other data on the EGA. <lb/>The tutorial is available at the Galaxy training materials website <lb/>[ 20 ]. <lb/>Preprocessing <lb/>First, a &quot;c hr&quot; pr efix is added to the first column of each chromo-<lb/>somal site in the VCFs, to match it with the built-in r efer ence <lb/>genome from Galaxy (hg19). Second, the VCFs are normalized us-<lb/>ing bcftools [ 30 ]. The normalization process includes left-aligning <lb/>insertion or deletion and splitting multiallelic sites into biallelic <lb/>records . T hird, the VCFs in the EGA dataset are actually genomic <lb/>variant calling format (GVCF) files. A GVCF has a record for (al-<lb/>most) all sites e v en when no v ariant, denoted by &lt; NON_REF &gt; , is <lb/>recorded. In this study, this information is not informative and <lb/>slo ws do wn analysis . T herefore , the records with a &lt; NON_REF &gt; <lb/>site ar e filter ed out. Fourth, the VCFs ar e mer ged into a single VCF <lb/>based on their trio pairing using bcftools . T his creates a VCF where <lb/>eac h r ecord also has a presence/absence column for eac h famil y <lb/>pair. Finall y, the v ariants in the mer ged VCF ar e filter ed and anno-<lb/>tated using the SnpEff tool [ 4 ] as r equir ed by GEMINI. <lb/>Gene.iobio <lb/>Gene.iobio is run with the GRCh37 r efer ence genome. The gene <lb/>list is created using the phenotypes described in Additional file <lb/>1 . The default search filters are used to detect the causative <lb/>variant. <lb/>GEMINI <lb/>For each case, GEMINI ( RRID:SCR _ 014819 ) is prompted to remove <lb/>low-impact se v erity v ariants and to searc h for causativ e v ariants <lb/>that match the inheritance pattern in Additional file 1 . <lb/>Availability of Source Code and <lb/>Requirements <lb/>Galaxy resources <lb/>r Galaxy homepage: https:// galaxyproject.org/ <lb/>r Galaxy tutorials: https://tr aining.galaxypr oject.or g <lb/>r How to install Galaxy: https://getgalaxy.org <lb/>r How to install tools: https://galaxypr oject.or g/admin/tools/ <lb/>add-tool-from-toolshed-tutorial/ <lb/>r Full administr ativ e r esources: https://docs.galaxypr oject.or g/ <lb/>r Galaxy Help Forum: https://help.galaxypr oject.or g/ <lb/>r Connect with the Galaxy Community on Gitter Chat: https: <lb/>// gitter.im/ galaxyproject/ Lobby/ <lb/>ToolShed <lb/>r Pr oject name: ToolShed r epositories maintained by the Inter-<lb/>galactic Utilities Commission <lb/>r GitHub repository: https:// github.com/ galaxyproject/ tools-<lb/>iuc <lb/>r ToolShed repository: https:// toolshed.g2.bx.psu.edu/ <lb/>r License: MIT <lb/>PyEGA3 <lb/>r Project name: p y ega3-uses the EGA REST API to download <lb/>authorized datasets and files <lb/>r GitHub repository: https:// github.com/ galaxyproject/ tools-<lb/>iuc/ tree/ master/ tools/ p y ega3 <lb/>r ToolShed repository: https:// toolshed.g2.bx.psu.edu/ view/ <lb/>iuc/ega _ download _ client <lb/>r Tr aining manual: https://tr aining.galaxypr oject.or g/tr aining-<lb/>material/ topics/ v ariant-anal ysis/ tutorials/ trio-analysis/ <lb/>tutorial.html <lb/>r Operating system(s): Unix (Platform independent with <lb/>Docker, Singularity) <lb/>r Other r equir ements: Galaxy v ersion 22.05 or higher <lb/>r License: Apache-2.0 <lb/>r RRID: SCR_024654 <lb/>Gene.iobio <lb/>r Project name: Gene.iobio-an interactive tool for variant and <lb/>trio analysis <lb/>r GitHub repository: https:// github.com/ galaxyproject/ tools-<lb/>iuc/ tree/ master/ tools/ geneiobio <lb/>r ToolShed repository: https:// toolshed.g2.bx.psu.edu/ view/ <lb/>iuc/geneiobio <lb/>r Training manual: https:// gxy.io/ GTN:T00320 <lb/>r Operating system(s): Unix (Platform independent with <lb/>Docker, Singularity) <lb/>r Other r equir ements: Galaxy v ersion 22.05 or higher <lb/>r License: MIT for academic use. Commercial use of gene.iobio <lb/>is managed by Frameshift Labs who have been granted the <lb/>exclusive commercial license by the University of Utah. <lb/>Additional Files <lb/>Additional file 1. The report describing the family trios. <lb/>Abbreviations <lb/>AAI: Authentication and Authorization; BAM: binary alignment <lb/>map; B1MG: Beyond 1 Million Genomes; DAA: Data Access Agree-<lb/>ment; DAC: Data Access Committee; EGA: European Genome-<lb/>Phenome Arc hiv e; FAIR: Findable , Accessible , Inter oper able, and <lb/>Reusable; GA4GH: Global Alliance for Genomics and Health; GTN: <lb/>Galaxy Training Network; GVCF: genomic variant calling format; <lb/>OIDC: OpenID Connect; TCGA: The Cancer Genome Atlas Pro-<lb/>gram; VCF: variant call format. <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Ac kno wledgments <lb/>We thank the Galaxy community and in particular Wolfgang <lb/>Maier for r e vie wing, testing, and validating the w orkflo w tutorial <lb/>and PyEGA3. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Authors&apos; Contributions <lb/>J .O ., S.H., H.R., and D.S. contributed to writing the manuscript. J .O ., <lb/>S.H., and H.R. contributed to writing the Galaxy w orkflo w tutorial. <lb/>S.H., H.R., and D .D . contributed to implementing the PyEGA3 and <lb/></div>
    
    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>6</page>
    
    <note place="headnote">| GigaScience , 2024, Vol. 13, No. 1 <lb/></note>
    
    <div type="contribution">gene.iobio tool in Galaxy . A.P .S. supervised the project. All authors <lb/>a ppr ov ed the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work has r eceiv ed funding from the EC H2020 project CINECA <lb/>(grant 825775) [ 31 ] as well as the Er asm us + pr ogr am of the <lb/>European Union (Gallantries Project, grant 2020-1-NL01-KA203-<lb/>064717, doi:10.13039/100001501). The data used in this project <lb/>wer e cr eated with the support of the RD-Connect GPAP [ 32 ], EC <lb/>H2020 pr oject EJP-RD (gr ant 825575) [ 33 ], EC H2020 project B1MG <lb/>(grant 951724) [ 34 ], and Generalitat de Catalunya project VEIS <lb/>(grant 001-P-001647) [ 35 ]. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Da ta Av ailability <lb/>The data used in this study were generated by a public human <lb/>whole genome sequencing (WGS) experiment in the Illumina Plat-<lb/>in um initiati v e [ 36 ], whic h was made av ailable by the Ha pMa p <lb/>project [ 37 ]. All data from this project are available at the EGA <lb/>website [ 12 ]. In this study, only the BAMs and VCFs with the <lb/>c hr omosomes containing the spiked-in variants were included. <lb/>These files ar e av ailable under &quot;RD-Connect GPAP Synthetic Data <lb/>Spiked-in Variant Data&quot; at Zenodo [ 38 ]. Other data further sup-<lb/>porting this work are openly available in the GigaScience repository, <lb/>GigaDB [ 39 ]. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing Interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Inau ET, Sack J, Waltemath D, et al. Initiati ves, conce pts, <lb/>and implementation practices of FAIR (Findable, Acces-<lb/>sible, Inter oper able, and Reusable) data principles in <lb/>health data stew ar dship pr actice: pr otocol for a scoping <lb/>r e vie w. JMIR Res Pr otoc 2021;10:e22505. https:// doi.org/ 10.2196/ <lb/>22505 . <lb/>2. Wilkinson MD, Dumontier M, Aalbersberg IJ, et al. The FAIR <lb/>Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stew ar d-<lb/>ship. Sci Data 2016;3:160018. https:// doi.org/ 10.1038/ sdata.2016 <lb/>.18 . <lb/>3. Nicorici D, Ş atalan M, Edgren H, et al. FusionCatcher: a tool <lb/>for finding somatic fusion genes in paired-end RNA-sequencing <lb/>data. bioRxiv. 2014. https:// doi.org/ 10.1101/ 011650 . <lb/>4. Cingolani P, Platts A, Wang LL, et al. A pr ogr am for an-<lb/>notating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide <lb/>pol ymor phisms, SnpEff. Fl y 2012;6:80-92. https:// doi.org/ 10.416 <lb/>1/fly.19695 . <lb/>5. Danecek P, Bonfield JK, Liddle J, et al. Twelve years of SAMtools <lb/>and BCFtools. GigaScience 2021;10:giab008. https:// doi.org/ 10.1 <lb/>093/ gigascience/ giab008 . <lb/>6. Krzywinski M, Schein J, Birol İ, et al. Circos: an information aes-<lb/>thetic for compar ativ e genomics. Genome Res 2009;19:1639-45. <lb/>https:// doi.org/ 10.1101/ gr.092759.109 . <lb/>7. Jalili V, Afgan E, Gu Q, et al. The Galaxy platform for accessi-<lb/>ble, r epr oducible and collabor ativ e biomedical analyses: 2020 <lb/>update. Nucleic Acids Res 2020;48:W395-402. https:// doi.org/ 10 <lb/>.1093/ nar/ gkaa554 . <lb/>8. Goble C, Soiland-Reyes S, Bacall F, et al. Implementing FAIR dig-<lb/>ital objects in the EOSC-life w orkflo w collaboratory. 2021. https: <lb/>//zenodo.org/r ecor d/4605654 . Accessed 21 March 2022. <lb/>9. Galaxy Training Network Stats. https://training.galaxyproject.o <lb/>rg/stats . Accessed 27 October 2022. <lb/>10. Rasche H, Hiltemann S. Galactic circos: user-friendly circos plots <lb/>within the Galaxy platform. GigaScience 2020;9:giaa065. https: <lb/>// doi.org/ 10.1093/ gigascience/ giaa065 . <lb/>11. Lappalainen I, Almeida-King J, Kumanduri V, et al. The Euro-<lb/>pean Genome-Phenome Arc hiv e of human data consented for <lb/>biomedical r esearc h. Nat Genet 2015;47(7):692-5. https://doi.or <lb/>g/ 10.1038/ ng.3312 . <lb/>12. Fr eeber g MA, Fr omont LA, D&apos;Altri T, et al. The European <lb/>Genome-Phenome Arc hiv e in 2021. Nucleic Acids Res <lb/>2021;50:D980-7. <lb/>13. Beyond 1 Million Genomes. https:// b1mg-project.eu/ . Accessed <lb/>30 June 2022. <lb/>14. Sera TD, Velinder M, Ward A, et al. Gene.iobio: an inter activ e <lb/>web tool for v ersatile, clinicall y-driv en v ariant interr ogation and <lb/>prioritization. Sci Rep 2021;11:20307. https:// doi.org/ 10.1038/ s4 <lb/>1598-021-99752-5 . <lb/>15. Hiltemann S, Rasche H, Gladman S, et al. Galaxy training: a pow-<lb/>erful fr ame work for teac hing! PLoS Comput Biol 2023;19(1):1-18. <lb/>https:// doi.org/ 10.1371/ journal.pcbi.1010752 . <lb/>16. Galaxy Vault. https://docs.galaxypr oject.or g/en/master/admin <lb/>/special _ topics/vault.html . Accessed 25 September 2022. <lb/>17. P aila U, Cha pman B A, Kir c hner R, et al. GEMINI: integr ativ e ex-<lb/>ploration of genetic variation and genome annotations. PLoS <lb/>Comput Biol 2013;9:1-8. https:// doi.org/ 10.1371/ journal.pcbi.1 <lb/>003153 . <lb/>18. Rare Disease Synthetic Dataset. https://ega-ar chive.or g/datase <lb/>ts/EGAD00001008392 . Accessed 6 October 2022. <lb/>19. Galaxy Training Network Stats. https://training.galaxyproject.o <lb/>rg/ . Accessed 27 October 2022. <lb/>20. Trio Analysis using synthetic datasets from RD-Connect GPAP. <lb/>https://training.galaxypr oject.or g/tr aining-material/topics/v ari <lb/>ant-analysis/tutorials/trio-analysis/tutorial.html . Accessed 23 <lb/>September 2022. <lb/>21. Trio Analysis. https:// workflowhub.eu/ workflows/363 . Accessed <lb/>5 September 2022 <lb/>22. Yang H, Robinson PN, Wang K. Phenolyzer: phenotype-based pri-<lb/>oritization of candidate genes for human diseases. Nat Methods <lb/>2015;12:841-3. https:// doi.org/ 10.1038/ nmeth.3484 . <lb/>23. Voisin C, Linden M, Dyke SOM et al., GA4GH Passport stan-<lb/>dard for digital identity and access permissions. Cell Genom <lb/>2021;1(2):100030. https:// doi.org/ 10.1016/ j.xgen.2021.100030 . <lb/>24. General Data Protection Regulation. https:// gdpr-info.eu/ . Ac-<lb/>cessed 13 September 2022. <lb/>25. Using <lb/>server-side <lb/>encryption <lb/>with <lb/>customer-provided <lb/>k e ys <lb/>(SSE-C). <lb/>https:// docs.aws.amazon.com/ AmazonS3 <lb/>/latest/ userguide/ ServerSideEncryptionCustomerKeys.h <lb/>tml#specifying-s3-c-encryption . Accessed 29 September <lb/>2022. <lb/>26. Galaxy Crypth4GH Recryptor Service. https://github.com/elixir-<lb/>eur ope/GalaxySensitiv eData-ELIXIR _ IS . Accessed 27 September <lb/>2022. <lb/>27. Senf A, Davies R, Haziza F, et al. Crypt4GH: a file format stan-<lb/>dard enabling native access to encrypted data. Bioinformat-<lb/>ics 2021;37:2753-4. https:// doi.org/ 10.1093/ bioinformatics/bta <lb/>b087 . <lb/>28. The Cancer Genome Atlas Pr ogr am. https://www.cancer.gov/c <lb/>cg/research/ genome-sequencing/ tcga . Accessed 13 September <lb/>2022. <lb/>29. National cancer Institute: Genomic Data Commons. https: <lb/>//github.com/NCI-GDC/gdc-client . Accessed 13 September <lb/>2022. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 <lb/>Galaxy fair sensitive clinical data retrieval | </note>
    
    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>30. Danecek P, Bonfield JK, Liddle J, et al. Twelve years of SAMtools <lb/>and BCFtools. GigaScience 2021;10:giab008. https:// doi.org/ 10.1 <lb/>093/ gigascience/ giab008 . <lb/>31. CINECA Pr oject. https://cordis.europa.eu/pr oject/id/825775 . Ac-<lb/>cessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>32. RD-Connect GPAP Project. https:// platform.rd-connect.eu/ . Ac-<lb/>cessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>33. EJP-RD Pr oject. https://cordis.europa.eu/pr oject/id/825575 . Ac-<lb/>cessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>34. B1MG Pr oject. https://cordis.europa.eu/pr oject/id/951724 . Ac-<lb/>cessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>35. VEIS Project. http:// www.gcatbiobank.org/ investigadors/ projec <lb/>ts/25/veis-european-project-valuation-of-the-european-arch <lb/>ive-of-the-genome-phenome-ega-for-the-industry-and-the-s <lb/>ociety . Accessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>36. Eberle MA, Fritzilas E, Krusche P, et al. A r efer ence data set of <lb/>5.4 million phased human variants validated by genetic inheri-<lb/>tance from sequencing a three-generation 17-member pedigree. <lb/>Genome Res 2016;27:157-64. https:// doi.org/ 10.1101/ gr.210500. <lb/>116 . <lb/>37. Ha pMa p Pr oject. www.genome.gov/10001688/international-ha <lb/>pma p-pr oject . Accessed 2 November 2022. <lb/>38. Ouwerkerk <lb/>J. <lb/>Zenodo: <lb/>RD-Connect <lb/>GPAP <lb/>synthetic data. Zenodo . 2022. https:// doi.org/ 10.5281/ zenodo <lb/>.7273767 . <lb/>39. Ouwerkerk J, Rasche H, Spalding JD, et al. Supporting data for <lb/>&quot;FAIR Data Retrie v al for Sensitiv e Clinical Researc h Data in <lb/>Galaxy.&quot; GigaScience Database. 2023. http://dx.doi.org/10.5524/1 <lb/>02472 . <lb/></listBibl>

    <front>Recei v ed: J une 28, 2023. Revised: October 16, 2023. Accepted: November 1, 2023 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford Uni v ersity Pr ess GigaScience. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Cr eati v e Commons Attribution License <lb/>( https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>
    
    <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giad099/7590576 by guest on 08 September 2025 </note>

	</text>

</TEI>