<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Surgeon and Surgical Trainee Experiences After Adverse Patient Events</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sara P.</forename>
          <surname>Ginzberg</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Julia A.</forename>
          <surname>Gasior</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jesse E.</forename>
          <surname>Passman</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jacob</forename>
          <surname>Stein</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shimrit</forename>
          <surname>Keddem</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jacqueline M.</forename>
          <surname>Soegaard Ballester</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Caitlin B.</forename>
          <surname>Finn</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jennifer S.</forename>
          <surname>Myers</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rachel R.</forename>
          <surname>Kelz</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Judy A.</forename>
          <surname>Shea</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Heather</forename>
          <surname>Wachtel</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:21:32.707Z">11/12/2025 10:21:32 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1001$1$jamanetworkopen.2024.14329</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.14329</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Sara P. Ginzberg, Julia A. Gasior, Jesse E. Passman, Jacob Stein, Shimrit Keddem, Jacqueline M. Soegaard Ballester, Caitlin B. Finn, Jennifer S. Myers, Rachel R. Kelz, Judy A. Shea, Heather Wachtel. (2024). Surgeon and Surgical Trainee Experiences After Adverse Patient Events. JAMA Network Open, 7(6), e2414329. DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.14329</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T10:21:24.609462Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T10:21:24.609462Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Original Investigation | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/>Paul L. Hebert, PhD; Kyle E. Kumbier, MS; Valerie A. Smith, DrPH; Denise M. Hynes, MPH, PhD; Diana J. Govier, PhD; Edwin Wong, PhD; Brystana G. Kaufman, PhD; <lb/>Megan Shepherd-Banigan, PhD; Mazhgan Rowneki, MPH, MBS; Amy S. B. Bohnert, PhD, MHS; George N. Ioannou, MD, MS; Edward J. Boyko, MD, MPH; <lb/>Theodore J. Iwashyna, MD, PhD; Ann M. O&apos;Hare, MA, MD; C. Barrett Bowling, MD, MSPH; Elizabeth M. Viglianti, MD, MPH; Matthew L. Maciejewski, PhD; <lb/>for the VA COVID-19 Observational Research Collaboratory (CORC) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IMPORTANCE The association of COVID-19 infection with outpatient care utilization is unclear. <lb/>Many studies reported population surveillance studies rather than comparing outpatient health care <lb/>use between COVID-19-infected and uninfected cohorts. <lb/>OBJECTIVE To compare outpatient health care use across 6 categories of care (primary care, <lb/>specialty care, surgery care, mental health, emergency care, and diagnostic and/or other care) <lb/>between veterans with or without COVID-19 infection. <lb/>DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS In a retrospective cohort study of Veterans Affairs primary <lb/>care patients, veterans with COVID-19 infection were matched to a cohort of uninfected veterans. <lb/>Data were obtained from the Veterans Affairs Corporate Data Warehouse and the Centers for <lb/>Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Fee-for-Service Carrier/Physician Supplier file from January 2019 <lb/>through December 2022. Data analysis was performed from September 2022 to April 2023. <lb/>EXPOSURE COVID-19 infection. <lb/>MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES The primary outcome was the count of outpatient visits after <lb/>COVID-19 infection. Negative binomial regression models compared outpatient use over a 1-year <lb/>preinfection period, and peri-infection (0-30 days), intermediate (31-183 days), and long-term <lb/>(184-365 days) postinfection periods. <lb/>RESULTS The infected (202 803 veterans; mean [SD] age, 60.5 [16.2] years; 178 624 men [88.1%]) <lb/>and uninfected (202 803 veterans; mean [SD] age, 60.4 [16.5] years; 178 624 men [88.1%]) cohorts <lb/>were well matched across all covariates. Outpatient use in all categories (except surgical care) was <lb/>significantly elevated during the peri-infection period for veterans with COVID-19 infection compared <lb/>with the uninfected cohort, with an increase in all visits of 5.12 visits per 30 days (95% CI, 5.09-5.16 <lb/>visits per 30 days), predominantly owing to primary care visits (increase of 1.86 visits per 30 days; <lb/>95% CI, 1.85-1.87 visits per 30 days). Differences in outpatient use attenuated over time but <lb/>remained statistically significantly higher at 184 to 365 days after infection (increase of 0.25 visit per <lb/>30 days; 95% CI, 0.23-0.27 visit per 30 days). One-half of the increased outpatient visits were <lb/>delivered via telehealth. The utilization increase was greatest for veterans aged 85 years and older <lb/>(6.1 visits, 95% CI, 5.9-6.3 visits) vs those aged 20 to 44 years (4.8 visits, 95% CI, 4.7-4.8 visits) and <lb/>unvaccinated veterans (4.5 visits, 95% CI, 4.3-4.6 visits) vs vaccinated veterans (3.2 visits; 95% CI, <lb/>3.4-4.8 visits). <lb/>(continued) <lb/>Key Points <lb/>Question Do veterans infected with <lb/>COVID-19 have different use of <lb/>outpatient health care after infection <lb/>than veterans who were not infected? <lb/>Findings In this cohort study including <lb/>202 803 veterans with COVID-19 and <lb/>202 803 matched uninfected veterans, <lb/>differences in outpatient health care <lb/>use between infected and uninfected <lb/>patients were highly concentrated in the <lb/>month immediately following infection, <lb/>mostly because of primary care use, of <lb/>which half was provided via telehealth. <lb/>Use of outpatient health care decreased <lb/>in the infected cohort but remained <lb/>slightly greater than in the uninfected <lb/>cohort 12 months after infection. <lb/>Meaning The adverse health outcomes <lb/>of COVID-19 infection translated into <lb/>increased use of outpatient services for <lb/>up to 12 months after infection, <lb/>suggesting persistent effects of post-<lb/>COVID-19 conditions. <lb/>+ Supplemental content <lb/>Author affiliations and article information are <lb/>listed at the end of this article. <lb/>Open Access. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/>1/15 <lb/>Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/>Abstract (continued) <lb/>CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE This study found that outpatient use increased significantly in <lb/>the month after infection, then attenuated but remained greater than the uninfected cohorts&apos; use <lb/>through 12 months, which suggests that there are sustained impacts of COVID-19 infection. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The COVID-19 pandemic strained health care systems worldwide and altered patient access to care. <lb/>Systematic reviews 1-3 of multinational evidence found a nearly universal decline in in-person <lb/>outpatient health care use 4 in the pandemic&apos;s early stages, but a marked increase in the use of <lb/>telehealth. 5-8 Many of these prior health care utilization studies were population-level comparisons <lb/>of health care use before and during the pandemic rather than comparisons of COVID-19-infected <lb/>and uninfected cohorts. This confounds individual-level effects of COVID-19 on health care use with <lb/>the pandemic&apos;s systemic effects on health care delivery. Most studies that have assessed the <lb/>individual-level effect of COVID-19 infection on health care use were based on pre-post designs <lb/>following a positive COVID-19 test 9 or compared patients with post-COVID-19 condition (PCC) with <lb/>COVID-19-positive patients without long-term complications of COVID-19. 10,11 To our knowledge, <lb/>only 2 prior studies 12,13 compared differences in health care use between infected and matched <lb/>uninfected cohorts. Both studies found that COVID-19-infected patients had more health care <lb/>encounters and outpatient visits than did patients without infection over 6 months 12 or 12 months. 13 <lb/>Neither study examined outpatient health care use across specific phases of the clinical presentation <lb/>of COVID-19, for specific components of outpatient care, or for specific modalities (in-person vs <lb/>telehealth). <lb/>In this study, we compare outpatient health care use and its components (eg, primary care and <lb/>specialty care) between matched cohorts of veterans with and without COVID-19 infection for 12 <lb/>months before and 12 months after COVID-19 infection. We also characterize changes in outpatient <lb/>use by modality and examine whether subgroups of veterans were disproportionately affected by <lb/>COVID-19 infection. Comparing cohorts of patients who were exposed to the same economic, social, <lb/>and health care-related burdens associated with the pandemic is necessary to isolate the effect of <lb/>infection from the effect of the pandemic. 14 By examining utilization beyond the acute period, this <lb/>study also provides evidence about the potential impact on long-term health care use that may be <lb/>due to longer term multisystemic symptoms and conditions. Finally, these analyses can inform which <lb/>units within health systems may experience sustained demand in future pandemics and identify <lb/>where telehealth may or may not offload demand for care. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study Design and Population <lb/>In this retrospective cohort study, we compared outpatient health care use for veterans enrolled in <lb/>the Veterans Affairs Health Care System (VA) with COVID-19 infection between March 1, 2020, and <lb/>April 30, 2021, who were matched to uninfected comparators. The study sample included veterans <lb/>who had an assigned VA primary care practitioner or who had at least 1 VA primary care clinic visit in <lb/>the prior 2 years. Matching occurred in a 2-step process, as described elsewhere. 15 First, each <lb/>infected person was exactly matched to persons who remained uninfected as of the calendar month <lb/>of their matched case&apos;s infection date according to sex, state of residence, immunosuppressive <lb/>medication use, and COVID-19 vaccination status. In the second step, veterans with COVID-19 <lb/>infection were matched 1:1 to veterans without infection within their exact matched groups on the <lb/>basis of a propensity score derived from a logistic regression containing 37 categorical and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>continuous electronic health record-based covariates representing demographic, comorbidity, and <lb/>utilization characteristics that were expected to be confounders or risk factors for the outcomes of <lb/>interest (Figure 1). We used 1:1 nearest neighbor matching with replacement. A veteran without <lb/>COVID-19 could serve as a comparator for multiple veterans with COVID-19 infection. 16 Covariate <lb/>balance between cohorts was evaluated using standardized differences. 17 The start of the <lb/>postinfection period for an uninfected control was defined as the midpoint of the month of infection <lb/>for the matched patient. <lb/>This cohort study was approved by the institutional review boards at the Seattle, Washington; <lb/>Portland, Oregon; Durham, North Carolina; Ann Arbor, Michigan; and Palo Alto, California, VA medical <lb/>centers, which waived the requirement to obtain informed consent because this was a retrospective <lb/>study of electronic health records, in accordance with 45 CFR §46. This study follows the <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) reporting <lb/>guidelines for cohort studies. <lb/>Figure 1. Derivation of COVID-19-Infected and Matched Uninfected Cohorts <lb/>208 536 Study eligible cases with a matched <lb/>comparator <lb/>208 006 Infected veterans alive at index date <lb/>5 153 843 Comparators alive at index date e <lb/>208 006 Single best matched comparators g <lb/>202 830 Infected veterans included in all analyses <lb/>202 830 Single best matched comparators <lb/>included in all analyses <lb/>208 462 Infected veterans with unique identifiers <lb/>5 167 906 Comparators with unique identifiers d <lb/>5 173 400 Study eligible comparators with a <lb/>matched comparator c <lb/>74 Excluded for nonunique identifier <lb/>456 Excluded for death date preceding index date <lb/>5494 Excluded for nonunique identifier <lb/>14 063 Excluded for death date preceding <lb/>index date <lb/>4 945 837 Excluded for beyond 1 best match f <lb/>5176 Excluded after updating infection dates h <lb/>22 624 Excluded in prior matching b <lb/>4 116 422 Excluded in prior matching b <lb/>231 160 Veterans with SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>March 2020 to April 2021 <lb/>Infected <lb/>9 291 822 Veterans without SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>March 2020 to April 2021 <lb/>Comparators a <lb/>a There were 1 222 272 comparators matched to more than 1 case. In the numbers <lb/>presented in this figure, comparators who were matched to more than 1 infected case <lb/>have been counted as many times as they appeared in the data set. The number of <lb/>unique comparators at each step in the flow diagram are presented in the <lb/>footnotes below. <lb/>b Those excluded in the prior matching included those with no Care Assessment Need <lb/>score; no primary care practitioner; missing height, weight, or implausible value; age <lb/>missing or implausible value; zip code missing or not in Washington, DC, or 50 states; <lb/>had a Medicare COVID-19 diagnosis; and no suitable match. Those who became a case <lb/>in the same month were also excluded among the comparators. <lb/>c The unique number of uninfected comparators matched to an infected case <lb/>was 3 014 091. <lb/>d The unique number of matched comparators with unique identifiers was 3 012 243. <lb/>e The unique number of alive matched comparators at the index date was 3 006 856. <lb/>f The unique number of matched comparators who were dropped was 2 798 500. <lb/>g The unique number of matched comparators in initial best match was 201 070. Of the <lb/>comparators in the initial best match, 6091 were matched to more than 1 infected case. <lb/>h There were 5052 cases (and their matched comparators) excluded from analysis <lb/>because they had an updated infection date in a prior infection month. An additional <lb/>124 comparators (and their matched case) were excluded from analysis because they <lb/>had an updated infection date in a prior month or the same month as their <lb/>matched case. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Health Care Use Outcomes <lb/>Outpatient use was obtained from the VA Corporate Data Warehouse and the Centers for Medicare <lb/>&amp; Medicaid Services Fee-for-Service Carrier/Physician Supplier file from January 2019 through <lb/>December 2022, which captures outpatient health care use by Medicare-enrolled veterans. Prior <lb/>research indicates that a substantial number of VA enrollees are dual users of care from both <lb/>systems. 18-21 Hospitalization dates from the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Medicare <lb/>Provider Analysis and Review file and Corporate Data Warehouse inpatient records were used to <lb/>eliminate clinician visits that occurred during acute inpatient stays. <lb/>We applied a hierarchical classification algorithm to consistently define categories of VA and <lb/>Medicare outpatient visits, 19-21 according to procedure codes, practitioner specialty codes, and place <lb/>of service codes present in both systems&apos; data. This enabled us to aggregate VA and Medicare use <lb/>into an overall visit outcome and 6 mutually exclusive visit categories (primary care, specialty care, <lb/>surgery care, mental health, emergency care, and diagnostic and/or other care, such as visits with <lb/>nonmedical professionals like chaplains and calls to VA clinical call centers). A visit was defined as a <lb/>unique combination of practitioner specialty code and date, so that a visit to a social worker, an <lb/>internist, and a pharmacist on the same day would constitute 3 visits. VA visits with nurse <lb/>practitioners were assigned to other categories of outpatient utilization, according to the VA clinic <lb/>stop code, as in prior work. 22 Medicare-covered visits with nurse practitioners were attributed to visit <lb/>categories in the same proportion as VA visits, since Medicare claims lack VA clinic stop codes. <lb/>Modality of care (in-person or telehealth) was assigned on the basis of procedure codes, practitioner <lb/>modifier codes, 23,24 and VA stop codes 22 specific to telehealth. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>Data analysis was performed from September 2022 to April 2023. We compared patient <lb/>characteristics between infected and uninfected cohorts. The observation period for health care use <lb/>was divided into a 52-week preinfection period and 3 postinfection periods that correspond to the <lb/>clinical presentation of COVID-19 25 : (1) a 0-to 30-day peri-infection period, (2) a 31-to 182-day <lb/>intermediate postinfection period, and (3) a 183-to 365-day long-term postinfection period. A plot <lb/>of weekly visits over the postinfection period provided visual evidence that these cutoffs were <lb/>reasonable for modeling health care use. Negative binomial models using generalized estimating <lb/>equations with an unstructured covariance matrix and robust SEs were used to estimate the effect of <lb/>infection in each time period, adjusting for infection status, 3 time-period fixed effects, and <lb/>interactions of infection and time-period fixed effects. <lb/>Censoring occurred when 1 of the matched pairs of infected and uninfected veterans died or <lb/>when the uninfected veteran became infected. To maintain balance in veteran characteristics, we <lb/>included visits in each follow-up period only for days that both members of a matched pair were <lb/>uncensored and included an offset to account for number of days uncensored. Three separate <lb/>models were estimated for each modality (in-person, telehealth, and combined telehealth plus <lb/>in-person) for each category of outpatient visits and the sum of all outpatient visits. Difference-in-<lb/>differences estimates were generated to account for time-invariant unobserved confounding. To <lb/>facilitate interpretation and to account for the difference in exposure times among postinfection <lb/>time periods, we normalized estimated differences in numbers of visits between infected and <lb/>uninfected cohorts into a visit rate per 30 days. <lb/>Veteran characteristics were chosen for subgroup analyses according to differences reported in <lb/>the clinical severity of COVID-19 infection, 26-28 including age groups (20-44, 45-54, 55-64, 65-74, <lb/>75-84, and Ն85 years), sex, self-reported race, self-reported Hispanic ethnicity, smoking status, <lb/>immunosuppression at index date, vaccination status at index date, rural or urban residence, <lb/>comorbidity burden (defined as Gagne score 29 quartiles), and the pandemic wave in which the <lb/>infection occurred. 30 Race and ethnicity in the VA Corporate Data Warehouse are collected through <lb/>self-identification either at enrollment or at a health care encounter and are included in this study for <lb/>descriptive purposes and because outpatient visits are known to vary by race and ethnicity. We <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>estimated separate models for total visits for each subgroup with main effects and all 2-way and <lb/>3-way interactions of infection, subgroup membership, and time-period fixed effects. For all <lb/>subgroups except age, these models also included main effects for Medicare eligibility because <lb/>standardized mean differences for Medicare eligibility were greater than 0.1 between infected and <lb/>uninfected comparators. Models for comorbidity subgroups additionally controlled for smoking <lb/>status, and models for vaccination subgroups additionally controlled for age and risk of <lb/>hospitalization or death as measured by the Care Assessment Need 31 score because of standardized <lb/>mean differences greater than 0.1 in these variables for these subgroups. <lb/>In sensitivity analyses, we dropped visits on the date of infection for infected and uninfected <lb/>patients to address the possibility that visits were scheduled solely for COVID-19 testing. We also <lb/>calculated the e-value 32 to assess the extent to which the results were subject to confounding. <lb/>Statistical significance was set a priori at 2-sided P &lt; .05 for analyses and conducted in SAS statistical <lb/>software version 9.4 (SAS Institute) and Stata statistical software version 17 (StataCorp). 33 <lb/>Results <lb/>Patient Characteristics in the Matched Cohorts <lb/>The cohort of 202 830 veterans with COVID-19 infection (mean [SD] age, 60.5 [16.2] years; 178 624 <lb/>men [88.1%]; 1907 American Indian/Alaska Native [0.9%]; 2015 Asian [1.0%]; 46 524 Black or <lb/>African American [22.9%]; 19 796 Hispanic [9.8%]; 1904 Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander <lb/>[0.9%]; 136 035 White, [67.1%]) were well matched to 202 830 veterans without infection (mean <lb/>[SD] age, 60.4 [16.5] years; 178 624 men [88.1%]; 1852 American Indian/Alaska Native [0.9%]; 2070 <lb/>Asian [1.0%]; 46 838 Black or African American [23.1%]; 19 196 Hispanic [9.5%]; 1902 Native <lb/>Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander [0.9%]; 135 916 White [67.0%]) across all sociodemographic and <lb/>measured health characteristics (Table). Most veterans lived in urban areas (145 341 [71.7%] with <lb/>COVID-19 infection and 145 024 [71.5%] without infection), approximately 13% were current <lb/>smokers (25 455 [12.5%] with infection and 25 812 [12.7%] without infection), and a majority were <lb/>Medicare enrolled (105 515 [52.0%] with infection and 113 358 [55.9%] without infection). The most <lb/>prevalent conditions were hypertension (124 175 veterans with COVID-19 [61.2%] and 123 933 <lb/>uninfected veterans [61.1%]), diabetes (69 945 veterans with COVID-19 [34.5%] and 68 891 <lb/>uninfected veterans [34.0%]), and major depression (65 502 veterans with COVID-19 [32.3%] and <lb/>65 491 uninfected veterans [32.3%]). A minority were immunosuppressed (19 789 veterans with <lb/>COVID-19 [9.8%] and 19 789 uninfected veterans [9.8%]) or in a community living center (2081 <lb/>veterans with COVID-19 [1.0%] and 1830 uninfected veterans [0.9%]), which is the VA&apos;s term for a <lb/>nursing home. <lb/>Analyses of Outpatient Use <lb/>Unadjusted counts of outpatient visits (Figure 2) showed only small differences for those with and <lb/>without COVID-19 infection (0.70 visits per week for the infected cohort vs 0.65 visits per week for <lb/>the uninfected cohort in the preinfection period, 52 weeks before infection). There was an increase in <lb/>visits for veterans with COVID-19 infection in the week of infection (4.02 visits vs 0.65 visits the <lb/>previous week) immediately following the infection, with an attenuation after the first 4 weeks <lb/>following infection (from 0.83 to 0.66 visits). Primary care use among infected patients deviated <lb/>from uninfected patients in the week before infection, which might reflect the veterans&apos; discussing <lb/>COVID-19-related symptoms with clinicians by telephone before receiving a positive test. <lb/>The adjusted difference-in-difference analyses (Figure 3) were consistent with the weekly <lb/>unadjusted results. For outpatient visits overall, infected patients had a significant increase in visits <lb/>to 5.12 visits per person (95% CI, 5.09-5.16 visits) in the 30 days after infection compared with <lb/>matched uninfected patients, of which 50% were in person and 50% were via telehealth. The <lb/>differential number of outpatient visits then declined to 0.58 visits (95% CI, 0.56-0.60 visits) per 30 <lb/>days in the intermediate period (31-182 days after infection) and 0.25 visits (95% CI, 0.23-0.27 visits) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table. Baseline Characteristics of Matched Cohorts of Veterans With and Without COVID-19 Infection <lb/>Variable <lb/>Participants, No. (%) a <lb/>SMD <lb/>With COVID-19 infection <lb/>(n = 202 830) <lb/>Without COVID-19 infection <lb/>(n = 202 830) b <lb/>Age, mean (SD), y <lb/>60.5 (16.2) <lb/>60.4 (16.5) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Body mass index, mean (SD) c <lb/>31.4 (6.3) <lb/>31.3 (6.6) <lb/>0.015 <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>21 392 (10.5) <lb/>21 392 (10.5) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Male <lb/>178 624 (88.1) <lb/>178 624 (88.1) <lb/>Unknown <lb/>2814 (1.4) <lb/>2814 (1.4) <lb/>Race <lb/>American Indian/Alaska Native <lb/>1907 (0.9) <lb/>1852 (0.9) <lb/>0.006 <lb/>Asian <lb/>2015 (1.0) <lb/>2070 (1.0) <lb/>Black or African American <lb/>46 524 (22.9) <lb/>46 838 (23.1) <lb/>Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander <lb/>1904 (0.9) <lb/>1902 (0.9) <lb/>White <lb/>136 035 (67.1) <lb/>135 916 (67.0) <lb/>Multiple races <lb/>1921 (0.9) <lb/>1892 (0.9) <lb/>Missing <lb/>12 524 (6.2) <lb/>12 360 (6.1) <lb/>Hispanic ethnicity <lb/>Yes <lb/>19 796 (9.8) <lb/>19 196 (9.5) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>No <lb/>176 121 (86.8) <lb/>176 673 (87.1) <lb/>Missing <lb/>6913 (3.4) <lb/>6961 (3.4) <lb/>Rurality <lb/>Urban <lb/>145 341 (71.7) <lb/>145 024 (71.5) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Not urban (including missing) <lb/>57 489 (28.3) <lb/>57 806 (28.5) <lb/>Smoking status <lb/>Current <lb/>25 455 (12.5) <lb/>25 812 (12.7) <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Former <lb/>85 789 (42.3) <lb/>85 757 (42.3) <lb/>Never <lb/>79 797 (39.3) <lb/>79 962 (39.4) <lb/>Missing <lb/>11 789 (5.8) <lb/>11 299 (5.6) <lb/>CDC high-risk conditions <lb/>Coronary heart disease <lb/>58 044 (28.6) <lb/>57 329 (28.3) <lb/>0.008 <lb/>Cancer <lb/>37 047 (18.3) <lb/>36 797 (18.1) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Chronic kidney disease <lb/>46 077 (22.7) <lb/>45 357 (22.4) <lb/>0.008 <lb/>Congestive heart failure <lb/>21 388 (10.5) <lb/>20 744 (10.2) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>Pulmonary <lb/>44 695 (22.0) <lb/>44 623 (22.0) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Dementia <lb/>10 313 (5.1) <lb/>9883 (4.9) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>69 945 (34.5) <lb/>68 891 (34.0) <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>124 175 (61.2) <lb/>123 933 (61.1) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Liver disease <lb/>14 894 (7.3) <lb/>14 668 (7.2) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Sickle cell <lb/>378 (0.2) <lb/>351 (0.2) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Transplant <lb/>670 (0.3) <lb/>627 (0.3) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Stroke or cerebrovascular disease <lb/>12 544 (6.2) <lb/>12 328 (6.1) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Substance use disorder <lb/>25 145 (12.4) <lb/>25 376 (12.5) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Anxiety <lb/>45 859 (22.6) <lb/>45 701 (22.5) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Bipolar disorder <lb/>7804 (3.8) <lb/>7772 (3.8) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Major depression <lb/>65 502 (32.3) <lb/>65 491 (32.3) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>PTSD <lb/>51 550 (25.4) <lb/>51 798 (25.5) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Schizophrenia <lb/>4563 (2.2) <lb/>4476 (2.2) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>CDC high-risk conditions, mean (SD), No. <lb/>2.29 (1.94) <lb/>2.27 (1.92) <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Mental health conditions (anxiety, bipolar disorder, major depression, PTSD, <lb/>schizophrenia), mean (SD), No. <lb/>0.86 (1.06) <lb/>0.86 (1.05) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Gagne score, mean (SD) <lb/>1.43 (2.34) <lb/>1.40 (2.24) <lb/>0.013 <lb/>Inpatient admissions in prior year, mean (SD), No. <lb/>0.4 (1.2) <lb/>0.4 (1.3) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Primary care visits in prior year, mean (SD), No. <lb/>8.5 (9.7) <lb/>8.3 (10.6) <lb/>0.026 <lb/>Specialty care visits in prior year, mean (SD), No. <lb/>13.9 (14.1) <lb/>13.5 (15.6) <lb/>0.027 <lb/>Mental health visits in prior year, mean (SD), No. <lb/>7.8 (22.6) <lb/>7.8 (21.9) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Immunosuppressed in prior 24 mo <lb/>19 789 (9.8) <lb/>19 789 (9.8) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>(continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table. Baseline Characteristics of Matched Cohorts of Veterans With and Without COVID-19 Infection (continued) <lb/>Variable <lb/>Participants, No. (%) a <lb/>SMD <lb/>With COVID-19 infection <lb/>(n = 202 830) <lb/>Without COVID-19 infection <lb/>(n = 202 830) b <lb/>Residing in community living center at index date <lb/>2081 (1.0) <lb/>1830 (0.9) <lb/>0.013 <lb/>Nosos risk adjustment score <lb/>Missing <lb/>4591 (2.3) <lb/>5341 (2.6) <lb/>0.037 <lb/>Category 1 (&gt;0 to ≤0.417) <lb/>5550 (2.7) <lb/>5109 (2.5) <lb/>Category 2 (&gt;0.417 to ≤0.471) <lb/>9335 (4.6) <lb/>8921 (4.4) <lb/>Category 3 (&gt;0.471 to ≤0.534) <lb/>12 137 (6.0) <lb/>11 943 (5.9) <lb/>Category 4 (&gt;0.534 to ≤0.611) <lb/>14 827 (7.3) <lb/>14 704 (7.2) <lb/>Category 5 (&gt;0.611 to ≤0.707) <lb/>17 280 (8.5) <lb/>17 632 (8.7) <lb/>Category 6 (&gt;0.707 to ≤0.829) <lb/>20 045 (9.9) <lb/>20 437 (10.1) <lb/>Category 7 (&gt;0.829 to ≤0.998) <lb/>22 851 (11.3) <lb/>23 635 (11.7) <lb/>Category 8 (&gt;0.998 to ≤1.259) <lb/>26 237 (12.9) <lb/>26 515 (13.1) <lb/>Category 9 (&gt;1.259 to ≤1.805) <lb/>30 544 (15.1) <lb/>30 679 (15.1) <lb/>Category 10 (&gt;1.805 to infinity) <lb/>39 433 (19.4) <lb/>37 914 (18.7) <lb/>Care Assessment Need score <lb/>Missing <lb/>3900 (1.9) <lb/>4629 (2.3) <lb/>0.034 <lb/>Category 1 (0-20) <lb/>33 770 (16.6) <lb/>33 307 (16.4) <lb/>Category 2 (21-40) <lb/>31 209 (15.4) <lb/>31 235 (15.4) <lb/>Category 3 (41-60) <lb/>37 235 (18.4) <lb/>37 829 (18.7) <lb/>Category 4 (61-80) <lb/>45 479 (22.4) <lb/>45 973 (22.7) <lb/>Category 5 (81-90) <lb/>29 801 (14.7) <lb/>29 758 (14.7) <lb/>Category 6 (91-99) <lb/>21 436 (10.6) <lb/>20 099 (9.9) <lb/>Vaccinated &gt;2 wk before index <lb/>No (January 2021 or later) <lb/>65 714 (32.4) <lb/>65 714 (32.4) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Yes (January 2021 or later) <lb/>3035 (1.5) <lb/>3035 (1.5) <lb/>Not applicable (before January 2021) <lb/>134 081 (66.1) <lb/>134 081 (66.1) <lb/>Index infection month <lb/>March 2020 <lb/>2333 (1.2) <lb/>2333 (1.2) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>April 2020 <lb/>6631 (3.3) <lb/>6631 (3.3) <lb/>May 2020 <lb/>4211 (2.1) <lb/>4211 (2.1) <lb/>June 2020 <lb/>6872 (3.4) <lb/>6872 (3.4) <lb/>July 2020 <lb/>14 667 (7.2) <lb/>14 667 (7.2) <lb/>August 2020 <lb/>8145 (4.0) <lb/>8145 (4.0) <lb/>September 2020 <lb/>6629 (3.3) <lb/>6629 (3.3) <lb/>October 2020 <lb/>11 991 (5.9) <lb/>11 991 (5.9) <lb/>November 2020 <lb/>30 338 (15.0) <lb/>30 338 (15.0) <lb/>December 2020 <lb/>42 264 (20.8) <lb/>42 264 (20.8) <lb/>January 2021 <lb/>35 268 (17.4) <lb/>35 268 (17.4) <lb/>February 2021 <lb/>15 054 (7.4) <lb/>15 054 (7.4) <lb/>March 2021 <lb/>9649 (4.8) <lb/>9649 (4.8) <lb/>April 2021 <lb/>8778 (4.3) <lb/>8778 (4.3) <lb/>Distance to nearest Veterans Affairs medical center, mean (SD), miles <lb/>35.6 (36.5) <lb/>35.7 (35.1) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Reason for Medicare entitlement <lb/>Old age and survivor&apos;s insurance <lb/>59 989 (29.6) <lb/>62 363 (30.7) <lb/>0.093 <lb/>Disability insurance benefits <lb/>9519 (4.7) <lb/>12 587 (6.2) <lb/>End-stage kidney disease <lb/>36 007 (17.8) <lb/>38 408 (18.9) <lb/>Not in Medicare <lb/>97 315 (48.0) <lb/>89 472 (44.1) <lb/>Enrolled in Medicare Advantage <lb/>Yes <lb/>55 343 (27.3) <lb/>59 115 (29.1) <lb/>0.078 <lb/>No <lb/>50 172 (24.7) <lb/>54 243 (26.7) <lb/>Not in Medicare <lb/>97 315 (48.0) <lb/>89 472 (44.1) <lb/>Abbreviations: CDC, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; PTSD, posttraumatic <lb/>stress disorder; SMD, standardized mean difference. <lb/>a A total of 196 235 unique Veteran comparators were used for analysis. Of the 202 830 <lb/>comparators used for analysis, 5793 were matched to more than 1 infected case. <lb/>b The unique number of matched comparators used for analysis was 196 235. Of the <lb/>comparators used for analysis, 5793 were matched to more than 1 infected case. <lb/>c Body mass index is calculated as weight in kilograms divided by height in <lb/>meters squared. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>in the long-term period (183-365 days after infection). Over 1 year, an infected veteran had 9.59 more <lb/>visits (95% CI, 9.38-9.80 visits) than a veteran who remained uninfected for that year. <lb/>The 6 components of overall outpatient visits showed a similar short-term increase and <lb/>subsequent attenuation, with the exception of surgical visits, which remained similar to preinfection <lb/>trends. Although the short-term increase in outpatient visits was observed in the other 5 <lb/>components, they differed in whether the visit increase was related to in-person care or telehealth. <lb/>Visit increases for infected patients occurred for in-person specialty care (0.74 more specialty visits; <lb/>95% CI, 0.73-0.75 visits; 0.59 in-person visits) and emergency care (0.73 visits for emergency care; <lb/>95% CI, 0.72-0.74 visits; 0.72 in-person visits) in the month after infection but not for telehealth. On <lb/>the other hand, visit increases occurred more via telehealth for primary care, mental health care, and <lb/>other care in the month after infection, which persisted. There were 1.86 more primary care visits <lb/>(95% CI, 1.85-1.87 visits) overall in the month after infection for infected patients, with 1.32 of these <lb/>Figure 2. Unadjusted Weekly Outpatient Visit Use for COVID-19-Infected and Uninfected Veterans, by Category of Outpatient Visit, for the 52 Weeks Before <lb/>and 52 Weeks After Infection <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>Emergency care <lb/>A <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>Mental health <lb/>B <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>Primary care <lb/>C <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>Specialty care <lb/>D <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>Surgical care <lb/>E <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Average visits per patient-week <lb/>Time from index date, wk <lb/>All types <lb/>F <lb/>-52 -44 -36 -28 -20 -12 -4 0 4 <lb/>12 <lb/>20 <lb/>28 <lb/>36 <lb/>44 <lb/>52 <lb/>Infected <lb/>Uninfected <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>visits (95% CI, 1.31-1.33 visits) via telehealth. There were 0.19 (95% CI, 0.18-0.10 visits) more mental <lb/>health visits in the month after infection, with 0.11 of these visits (95% CI, 0.10-0.11 visits) occurring <lb/>via telehealth. <lb/>Excluding visits that occurred on the day of a positive test (eFigure and eTable in Supplement 1) <lb/>yielded similar patterns of visits, indicating that care related to the COVID-19 test itself was not <lb/>responsible for elevated visits in the 30 days after infection. When evaluating the potential for <lb/>unobserved confounding via e-value, the e-value for the perioperative period was 4.88, meaning that <lb/>the effect size of a confounder had to be very large (4.88 or greater) to explain away the estimated <lb/>effect. The corresponding e-values for the intermediate and long-term periods were both 1.63. <lb/>Subgroup Analyses <lb/>Results from prespecified subgroup analyses (Figure 4) followed similar health care utilization <lb/>patterns as the main analysis. The visit increases for infected patients were markedly larger for <lb/>veterans aged 85 years and older (6.1 visits; 95% CI, 5.9-6.3 visits) vs those aged 20 to 44 years (4.8 <lb/>visits, 95% CI, 4.7-4.8 visits), veterans with greater comorbidity burden in the fourth quartile (4.2 <lb/>visits; 95% CI, 4.1-4.3 visits) vs those with comorbidity burden in the first quartile (3.5 visits; 95% CI, <lb/>3.4-3.6 visits), unvaccinated veterans (4.5 visits; 95% CI, 4.3-4.6 visits) vs vaccinated veterans (3.2 <lb/>visits; 95% CI, 3.4-4.8 visits), and rural veterans (4.3 visits; 95% CI, 4.3-4.4 visits) vs urban veterans <lb/>(3.1 visits; 95% CI, 3.1-3.2 visits). Hispanic veterans had a larger peri-infection visit increase (5.2 visits; <lb/>95% CI, 5.1-5.3 visits) than non-Hispanic veterans (3.9 visits; 95% CI, 3.9-3.9 visits). The largest <lb/>Figure 3. Difference-in-Difference Estimates of the Association of COVID-19 Infection With Outpatient Visits Over 30 Days Across 3 Postinfection by Category <lb/>and Mode (Telecare vs In-Person) of Outpatient Visit <lb/>No. of visits/patient, scaled <lb/>to 30-d period (95% CI) <lb/>No. of visits/patient <lb/>Primary care <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>Specialty care <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>Surgical care <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>Mental health <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>Emergency care <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>Other <lb/>In person <lb/>Telecare <lb/>Total <lb/>All visit types <lb/>Visits/patient, No. <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Visits/patient, No. <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Visits/patient, No. <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Type of visit <lb/>0.59 (0.58 to 0.59) <lb/>0.54 (0.53 to 0.55) <lb/>1.32 (1.31 to 1.33) <lb/>1.86 (1.85 to 1.87) <lb/>0.00 (-0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.16 (0.15 to 0.16) <lb/>0.74 (0.73 to 0.75) <lb/>-0.01 (-0.01 to -0.00) <lb/>0.01 (0.01 to 0.01) <lb/>0.72 (0.71 to 0.73) <lb/>0.08 (0.07 to 0.09) <lb/>0.11 (0.10 to 0.11) <lb/>0.19 (0.18 to 0.20) <lb/>1.55 (1.53 to 1.56) <lb/>0.01 (0.01 to 0.01) <lb/>0.73 (0.72 to 0.74) <lb/>0.58 (0.57 to 0.59) <lb/>0.97 (0.96 to 0.98) <lb/>2.54 (2.52 to 2.57) <lb/>2.56 (2.55 to 2.58) <lb/>5.12 (5.09 to 5.16) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>No. of visits/patient, scaled <lb/>to 30-d period (95% CI) <lb/>0.10 (0.10 to 0.11) <lb/>0.09 (0.08 to 0.09) <lb/>0.03 (0.03 to 0.04) <lb/>0.12 (0.12 to 0.13) <lb/>0.03 (0.03 to 0.03) <lb/>0.02 (0.02 to 0.02) <lb/>0.12 (0.12 to 0.13) <lb/>0.03 (0.02 to 0.03) <lb/>0.00 (0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.01 (0.01 to 0.01) <lb/>0.06 (0.05 to 0.06) <lb/>0.02 (0.02 to 0.03) <lb/>0.08 (0.07 to 0.08 ) <lb/>0.20 (0.19 to 0.21) <lb/>-0.00 (-0.00 to 0.00) <lb/>0.01 (0.01 to 0.01) <lb/>0.17 (0.16 to 0.18) <lb/>0.03 (0.03 to 0.03) <lb/>0.48 (0.46 to 0.49) <lb/>0.11 (0.10 to 0.12) <lb/>0.58 (0.56 to 0.60) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>No. of visits/patient, scaled <lb/>to 30-d period (95% CI) <lb/>0-30 d After index <lb/>A <lb/>31-182 d After index <lb/>B <lb/>183-365 d After index <lb/>C <lb/>0.06 (0.05 to 0.06) <lb/>0.04 (0.04 to 0.05) <lb/>-0.00 (-0.00 to 0.00) <lb/>0.04 (0.03 to 0.04) <lb/>0.02 (0.01 to 0.02) <lb/>0.00 (0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.06 (0.06 to 0.07) <lb/>0.02 (0.01 to 0.02) <lb/>0.00 (0.00 to 0.00) <lb/>0.00 (0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.03 (0.03 to 0.04) <lb/>0.00 (-0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.04 (0.03 to 0.05) <lb/>0.09 (0.08 to 0.10) <lb/>-0.00 (-0.00 to -0.00) <lb/>0.00 (0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.09 (0.08 to 0.10) <lb/>0.00 (-0.00 to 0.00) <lb/>0.25 (0.24 to 0.27) <lb/>0.01 (-0.00 to 0.01) <lb/>0.25 (0.23 to 0.27) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>effects of COVID-19 infection on visits were in the first wave of the pandemic from March to May <lb/>2020 (5.8 visits; 95% CI, 5.7-5.9 visits), but the effects persisted in wave 2 from June to October <lb/>2020 (4.7 visits; 95% CI, 4.6-4.7 visits), and wave 3 from November 2020 to May 2021 (3.6 visits; <lb/>95% CI, 3.6-3.7 visits). <lb/>Figure 4. Difference-in-Difference Estimates of the Association of COVID-19 Infection With Total Outpatient Visits Over 30 Days Across 3 Postinfection Periods, <lb/>by Patient Subgroups <lb/>Source <lb/>30-d Period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>30-d Period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>30-d Period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Age group, y <lb/>Sex <lb/>Race <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>Rurality <lb/>Smoking status <lb/>Gagne score <lb/>Immunosuppressed <lb/>Vaccinated <lb/>Wave <lb/>≥85 <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Hispanic/Latino <lb/>Not Hispanic/Latino <lb/>Urban <lb/>Current <lb/>Former <lb/>Never <lb/>&lt;0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Yes <lb/>No <lb/>Yes (after Jan 2021) <lb/>No (after Jan 2021) <lb/>No (before Jan 2021) <lb/>Mar 2020-May 2020 <lb/>Jun 2020-Oct 2020 <lb/>Nov 2020-May 2021 <lb/>1 <lb/>≥2 <lb/>Rural and missing <lb/>20-44 <lb/>45-54 <lb/>55-64 <lb/>65-74 <lb/>75-84 <lb/>6.09 (5.89-6.29) <lb/>3.96 (3.93-3.99) <lb/>4.30 (4.21-4.39) <lb/>4.51 (4.19-4.83) <lb/>4.19 (3.89-4.49) <lb/>5.04 (4.75-5.32) <lb/>4.74 (4.67-4.80) <lb/>4.39 (4.27-4.51) <lb/>4.20 (3.92-4.48) <lb/>3.68 (3.65-3.72) <lb/>5.19 (5.09-5.29) <lb/>3.90 (3.87-3.94) <lb/>3.13 (3.08-3.17) <lb/>4.33 (4.29-4.37) <lb/>4.07 (3.99-4.16) <lb/>3.82 (3.77-3.86) <lb/>4.28 (4.24-4.33) <lb/>(3.45-3.62) <lb/>3.64 (3.58-3.71) <lb/>3.87 (3.79-3.95) <lb/>4.19 (4.11-4.28) <lb/>4.39 (4.28-4.49) <lb/>4.03 (3.99-4.06) <lb/>3.19 (2.94-3.45) <lb/>4.48 (4.32-4.64) <lb/>5.13 (4.95-5.30) <lb/>5.80 (5.66-5.94) <lb/>4.68 (4.61-4.74) <lb/>3.65 (3.61-3.68) <lb/>4.77 (4.70-4.83) <lb/>4.93 (4.85-5.01) <lb/>5.36 (5.28-5.44) <lb/>5.14 (5.07-5.21) <lb/>5.19 (5.08-5.30) <lb/>1.09 (0.98-1.20) <lb/>0.44 (0.42-0.46) <lb/>0.37 (0.33-0.42) <lb/>0.50 (0.34-0.66) <lb/>0.59 (0.40-0.77) <lb/>0.48 (0.33-0.63) <lb/>0.53 (0.50-0.57) <lb/>0.37 (0.31-0.43) <lb/>0.44 (0.27-0.61) <lb/>0.40 (0.38-0.42) <lb/>0.43 (0.38-0.48) <lb/>0.44 (0.43-0.46) <lb/>0.37 (0.34-0.39) <lb/>0.46 (0.44-0.48) <lb/>0.57 (0.51-0.62) <lb/>0.44 (0.42-0.47) <lb/>0.38 (0.36-0.40) <lb/>0.29 (0.29-0.33) <lb/>0.29 (0.27-0.31) <lb/>0.41 (0.38-0.44) <lb/>0.69 (0.65-0.72) <lb/>0.51 (0.45-0.58) <lb/>0.43 (0.42-0.45) <lb/>0.34 (0.22-0.47) <lb/>0.43 (0.40-0.46) <lb/>0.51 (0.48-0.54) <lb/>0.68 (0.61-0.76) <lb/>0.46 (0.42-0.49) <lb/>0.41 (0.39-0.43) <lb/>0.34 (0.31-0.38) <lb/>0.41 (0.37-0.46) <lb/>0.61 (0.56-0.66) <lb/>0.71 (0.67-0.75) <lb/>0.79 (0.72-0.85) <lb/>0.31 (0.20-0.42) <lb/>0.21 (0.19-0.22) <lb/>0.20 (0.15-0.25) <lb/>0.20 (0.04-0.36) <lb/>0.23 (0.05-0.40) <lb/>0.31 (0.17-0.46) <lb/>0.29 (0.25-0.32) <lb/>0.19 (0.13-0.25) <lb/>0.20 (0.04-0.36) <lb/>0.18 (0.16-0.20) <lb/>0.22 (0.17-0.27) <lb/>0.21 (0.19-0.23) <lb/>0.17 (0.14-0.19) <lb/>0.22 (0.20-0.24) <lb/>0.25 (0.20-0.31) <lb/>0.20 (0.18-0.23) <lb/>0.19 (0.17-0.21) <lb/>0.17 (0.14-0.20) <lb/>0.16 (0.14-0.18) <lb/>0.20 (0.17-0.23) <lb/>0.26 (0.23-0.30) <lb/>0.23 (0.16-0.30) <lb/>0.21 (0.19-0.22) <lb/>0.19 (0.05-0.32) <lb/>0.26 (0.23-0.28) <lb/>0.25 (0.23-0.27) <lb/>0.34 (0.26-0.42) <lb/>0.23 (0.20-0.26) <lb/>0.19 (0.17-0.21) <lb/>0.19 (0.16-0.23) <lb/>0.26 (0.22-0.31) <lb/>0.32 (0.27-0.37) <lb/>0.30 (0.26-0.34) <lb/>0.24 (0.17-0.30) <lb/>0-30 d After index <lb/>A <lb/>31-182 d After index <lb/>B <lb/>183-365 d After index <lb/>C <lb/>No. of visits/patient, <lb/>scaled to 30-d period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>No. of visits/patient, <lb/>scaled to 30-d period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>No. of visits/patient, <lb/>scaled to 30-d period <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>Multiple <lb/>American Hawaiian &amp; Pacific Islander <lb/>Missing <lb/>American Indian &amp; Alaska Native <lb/>Asian <lb/>Black <lb/>White <lb/>The estimates are the difference between infected patients and uninfected patients in <lb/>the difference from baseline to each of the defined follow-up periods, for each of the <lb/>defined subgroups. Models included fixed effects for Medicare eligibility, which was <lb/>imbalanced between infected and uninfected cohorts within many subgroups. Models <lb/>for comorbidity subgroups additionally controlled for smoking status, and models for <lb/>vaccination subgroups additionally controlled for age and risk of hospitalization or death <lb/>as measured by the Care Assessment Need score because of standardized mean <lb/>differences &gt;0.1 in these variables for these subgroups. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>This cohort study of outpatient health care use between matched cohorts of veterans with and <lb/>without COVID-19 infection in the year before after COVID-19 infection documented in VA and <lb/>Medicare records yielded 3 important findings. First, we found marked increases in visits for veterans <lb/>with COVID-19 infection compared with uninfected comparators in the 30 days following infection <lb/>across all categories of outpatient visits, except for surgical visits. Primary care was the largest <lb/>contributor to this overall outpatient visit increase, representing 36% (1.86 visits/5.12 visits overall) <lb/>of the increase in the first month after infection, half of which was delivered via telehealth. The <lb/>increased telehealth use for primary care and mental health care has been sustained since 2022, <lb/>suggesting that the pandemic induced a modality switch for certain care types that may be more <lb/>patient centered and clinically appropriate for patients with an infectious disease. Future research <lb/>should examine the extent to which the sustained increase in telehealth visits represents patient <lb/>preferences, practitioner or health system transition in modality, or other factors. These results <lb/>reinforce the value in determining which types of care may be equally effective when delivered by <lb/>telehealth and which types of care are best delivered in person. <lb/>Second, outpatient use by veterans with COVID-19 infection decreased after the first 30 days, <lb/>but remained significantly higher than longer-term visits in uninfected veterans. Although the <lb/>difference in COVID-19-attributable visits was less than 1 visit per 30 days, this represents an <lb/>additional 904 000 visits for the 202 000 infected veterans from day 31 to 365 postinfection when <lb/>multiplying the number of infected patients in our sample by the marginal differences in outpatient <lb/>visits. Sustained higher outpatient use may be due to patients with PCC, which merits exploration in <lb/>future work and has potential implications for VA workforce planning. Third, subgroup analyses <lb/>found that the short-term visit increase following COVID-19 infection was greater for older <lb/>veterans, 28 veterans with a high comorbidity burden, Hispanic veterans, 27 rural veterans, and <lb/>veterans who were not 26 Improved access to telehealth for these more vulnerable <lb/>veterans may benefit them and their caregivers, if telehealth obviates the need for caregivers to <lb/>provide veterans with travel for care. <lb/>The largest effects of COVID-19 infection on visits were in the first wave of the pandemic from <lb/>March to May 2020 when COVID-19 testing was scarce, consistent with the hypothesis that the most <lb/>acutely ill veterans were tested for COVID-19 and brought to the clinic in the earliest wave. The <lb/>association of COVID-19 and outpatient visits persisted in wave 2 from June to October 2020 and <lb/>wave 3 from November 2020 May 2021, which suggests testing and access to care alone were not <lb/>responsible for the elevated visits. <lb/>These findings contrast somewhat to a prior analysis 12 that also found elevated visits for COVID-<lb/>19-positive patients 6 months after infection, but these elevated rates were due entirely to higher <lb/>telehealth visits immediately after infection. Outpatient visits were lower overall for COVID-19-<lb/>positive patients than uninfected patients between 2 weeks and 6 months after infection, and lower <lb/>over the entire 6-month period for COVID-19-positive patients for in-person outpatient visits. The <lb/>lower visit rates in that study might be due to sample restriction to patients who were alive for the <lb/>entire 6-month follow-up period, which would exclude the most ill patients with COVID-19 and may <lb/>diminish the visit difference compared with the uninfected cohort, or might be due to differences in <lb/>VA vs non-VA care delivery. Our findings are more consistent with results from a retrospective cohort <lb/>study of Canadian patients with COVID-19 infection matched 1:1 to uninfected patients 13 that found <lb/>elevated outpatient visit rates for infected patients over a 12-month follow-up period. Future work is <lb/>needed to explore inpatient use following COVID-19 infection and outpatient use of patients <lb/>identified with PCC. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>We acknowledge several limitations. These analyses may be subject to unobserved confounding <lb/>because patients were not randomized and we could not exactly match on every available <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>characteristic associated with infection and health care utilization. A difference-in-differences design <lb/>was used as an additional confounding control. Some patients who had COVID-19 but were not <lb/>tested in the VA might have been misclassified. As a result, the estimates reported here are <lb/>potentially biased toward the null. In addition, we lacked data on visits not provided by VA or paid for <lb/>by Medicare. The effect of infection on visits in the peri-infection period maybe an underestimate if <lb/>symptomatic veterans have virtual visits with practitioners before testing positive. In addition, <lb/>telehealth visit counts are assumed to be correctly coded by modality but were not validated. <lb/>Furthermore, these results may not generalize beyond veterans identified with COVID-19 in VA and <lb/>obtaining care in VA or Medicare. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this retrospective cohort study, outpatient use for veterans enrolled in VA for all categories of care <lb/>except surgical care increased in the 30 days after infection, then decreased but remained greater <lb/>than uninfected cohorts&apos; use for at least 12 months after infection. These results suggest long-term <lb/>impacts of COVID-19 infection on outpatient health care use and highlight the important role of <lb/>telehealth in the delivery of primary care to veterans with COVID-19 infections. <lb/></body>

			<front>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Accepted for Publication: December 18, 2023. <lb/>Published: February 9, 2024. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 <lb/>Open Access: This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2024 Hebert PL <lb/>et al. JAMA Network Open. <lb/>Corresponding Author: Matthew L. Maciejewski, PhD, Center of Innovation to Accelerate Discovery &amp; Practice <lb/>Transformation, Durham Veterans Affairs Health Care System, 411 W Chapel Hill St, Ste 600, Durham, NC 27705 <lb/>(matthew.maciejewski@va.gov). <lb/>Author Affiliations: Center for Veteran-Centered and Value-Driven Care, Veterans Affairs Puget Sound Health <lb/>Care System, Seattle, Washington (Hebert, Wong, Ioannou, Boyko, O&apos;Hare); Department of Health Systems and <lb/>Population Health, University of Washington School of Medicine, Seattle (Hebert, Wong); VA Health Services <lb/>Research &amp; Development, Center for Clinical Management and Research, VA Ann Arbor Healthcare System, Ann <lb/>Arbor, Michigan (Kumbier, Bohnert, Iwashyna, Viglianti); Center of Innovation to Accelerate Discovery and Practice <lb/>Transformation (ADAPT), Durham Veterans Affairs Health Care System, Durham, North Carolina (Smith, Kaufman, <lb/>Shepherd-Banigan, Bowling, Maciejewski); Department of Population Health Sciences, Duke University, Durham, <lb/>North Carolina (Smith, Kaufman, Shepherd-Banigan, Maciejewski); Department of Medicine, Duke University, <lb/>Durham, North Carolina (Smith, Bowling, Maciejewski); Center of Innovation to Improve Veteran Involvement in <lb/>Care, Veterans Affairs Portland Health Care System, Portland, Oregon (Hynes, Govier, Rowneki); Health <lb/>Management and Policy, Health Data and Informatics Program, Center for Quantitative Life Sciences, College of <lb/>Health, Oregon State University, Corvallis (Hynes); School of Nursing, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, <lb/>Portland (Govier, Maciejewski); Duke-Margolis Center for Health Policy, Durham, North Carolina (Kaufman, <lb/>Shepherd-Banigan); Department of Anesthesiology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor (Bohnert); Division of <lb/>Gastroenterology, University of Washington, Seattle (Ioannou); Epidemiologic Research and Information Center, <lb/>Veterans Affairs Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle, Washington (Boyko); Department of Epidemiology, <lb/>University of Washington, Seattle (Boyko, O&apos;Hare); Department of Medicine, University of Michigan Medical <lb/>School, Ann Arbor (Iwashyna, Viglianti); School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland <lb/>(Iwashyna); School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland (Iwashyna); Durham Veterans <lb/>Affairs Geriatric Research Education and Clinical Center, Durham Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Durham, North <lb/>Carolina (Bowling). <lb/></front>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Dr Hebert and Mr Kumbier had full access to all of the data in the study and take <lb/>responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. <lb/>Concept and design: Hebert, Smith, Hynes, Govier, Wong, Shepherd-Banigan, Bohnert, Ioannou, Boyko, Iwashyna, <lb/>Bowling, Maciejewski. <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Hebert, Kumbier, Smith, Govier, Wong, Kaufman, Shepherd-<lb/>Banigan, Rowneki, Ioannou, Iwashyna, O&apos;Hare, Viglianti, Maciejewski. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Drafting of the manuscript: Hebert, Hynes, Govier, Maciejewski. <lb/>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: All authors. <lb/>Statistical analysis: Hebert, Kumbier, Smith, Govier, Wong, Maciejewski. <lb/>Obtained funding: Smith, Hynes, Bohnert, Ioannou, Boyko, Iwashyna, O&apos;Hare, Bowling, Maciejewski. <lb/>Administrative, technical, or material support: Hynes, Kaufman, Rowneki, Bohnert, Iwashyna, Bowling, <lb/>Maciejewski. <lb/>Supervision: Smith, Shepherd-Banigan, Maciejewski. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: Dr Hynes reported receiving a Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute <lb/>subcontract from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; grants from Pacific Source Community Services, <lb/>Inc, and the David and Lucille Packard Foundation; and consulting fees from Quality Insights outside the submitted <lb/>work. Dr Maciejewski reported owning Amgen stock through his spouse&apos;s employment. No other disclosures were <lb/>reported. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding/Support: This work was supported by funding from the Veterans Affairs (VA) Health Services Research <lb/>&amp; Development through service awards for the COVID Observational Research Collaborative (No. C19-21-278 and <lb/>C19-21-279) and for use of the VA-linked Medicare data (SDR 02-237 and SDR 98-004). Drs Hynes and <lb/>Maciejewski were supported in part by a VA Research Career Scientist Award (RCS 21-136 and RCS 10-391, <lb/>respectively). Dr Viglianti&apos;s research time during the conduct of the study was supported by a grant from the <lb/>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute. <lb/>Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, <lb/>management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and <lb/>decision to submit the manuscript for publication. <lb/>Group Information: The members of the VA COVID-19 Observational Research Collaboratory (CORC) appear in <lb/>Supplement 2. <lb/>Disclaimer: All statements in this article, including its findings and conclusions, are solely those of the authors and <lb/>do not necessarily represent the views of the US Department of Veterans Affair, the US government, Oregon State <lb/>University, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, Duke University, the University of Washington, Johns Hopkins <lb/>University, and the University of Michigan. No copyrighted material was included in this article. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="availability">Data Sharing Statement: See Supplement 3. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Moynihan R, Sanders S, Michaleff ZA, et al. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on utilisation of healthcare services: <lb/>a systematic review. BMJ Open. 2021;11(3):e045343. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2020-045343 <lb/>2. Amsah N, Md Isa Z, Ahmad N, Abdul Manaf MR. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on healthcare utilization among <lb/>patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(5):4577. doi: <lb/>10.3390/ijerph20054577 <lb/>3. Roy CM, Bollman EB, Carson LM, Northrop AJ, Jackson EF, Moresky RT. Assessing the indirect effects of <lb/>COVID-19 on healthcare delivery, utilization and health outcomes: a scoping review. Eur J Public Health. 2021;31 <lb/>(3):634-640. doi:10.1093/eurpub/ckab047 <lb/>4. Dupraz J, Le Pogam MA, Peytremann-Bridevaux I. Early impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on in-person <lb/>outpatient care utilisation: a rapid review. BMJ Open. 2022;12(3):e056086. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2021-056086 <lb/>5. McCracken CE, Gander JC, McDonald B, et al. Impact of COVID-19 on trends in outpatient clinic utilization: a tale <lb/>of 2 departments. Med Care. 2023;61(4)(suppl 1):S4-S11. doi:10.1097/MLR.0000000000001812 <lb/>6. Park YT, Lee HJ, Choi H, Lee J. Changes in healthcare use by age groups of patients and locations of healthcare <lb/>institutions after the COVID-19 pandemic in Korea: analyzing healthcare big data. Health Policy Technol. 2023;12 <lb/>(1):100723. doi:10.1016/j.hlpt.2023.100723 <lb/>7. Pendrith C, Nayyar D, Chu C, et al. Outpatient visit trends for internal medicine ambulatory care sensitive <lb/>conditions after the COVID-19 pandemic: a time-series analysis. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):198. doi:10.1186/ <lb/>s12913-022-07566-6 <lb/>8. Wiefels MD, Gmunder KN, Ruiz JW. Patient income level and health insurance correlate with differences in <lb/>health care utilization during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Public Health Res. Published online March 9, 2023. doi:10. <lb/>1177/22799036231160624 <lb/>9. Koumpias AM, Schwartzman D, Fleming O. Long-haul COVID: healthcare utilization and medical expenditures <lb/>6 months post-diagnosis. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):1010. doi:10.1186/s12913-022-08387-3 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>10. Castriotta L, Onder G, Rosolen V, et al. Long-COVID and use of healthcare resources: a retrospective <lb/>population-based matched cohort study comparing individuals with and without previous SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>over 6 months. SSRN. Preprint posted online July 5, 2023. doi:10.2139/ssrn.4496142 <lb/>11. Tene L, Bergroth T, Eisenberg A, David SSB, Chodick G. Risk factors, health outcomes, healthcare services <lb/>utilization, and direct medical costs of patients with long COVID. Int J Infect Dis. 2023;128:3-10. doi:10.1016/j.ijid. <lb/>2022.12.002 <lb/>12. Tartof SY, Malden DE, Liu IA, et al. Health care utilization in the 6 months following SARS-CoV-2 infection. JAMA <lb/>Netw Open. 2022;5(8):e2225657. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.25657 <lb/>13. McNaughton CD, Austin PC, Sivaswamy A, et al. Post-acute health care burden after SARS-CoV-2 infection: <lb/>a retrospective cohort study. CMAJ. 2022;194(40):E1368-E1376. doi:10.1503/cmaj.220728 <lb/>14. Katz GM, Bach K, Bobos P, et al. Understanding how post-COVID-19 condition affects adults and health care <lb/>systems. JAMA Health Forum. 2023;4(7):e231933. doi:10.1001/jamahealthforum.2023.1933 <lb/>15. Smith VA, Berkowitz TS, Hebert P, et al. Design and analysis of outcomes following SARS-CoV-2 infection in <lb/>veterans. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2023;23(1):81. doi:10.1186/s12874-023-01882-z <lb/>16. Austin PC. Optimal caliper widths for propensity-score matching when estimating differences in means and <lb/>differences in proportions in observational studies. Pharm Stat. 2011;10(2):150-161. doi:10.1002/pst.433 <lb/>17. Austin PC. Balance diagnostics for comparing the distribution of baseline covariates between treatment <lb/>groups in propensity-score matched samples. Stat Med. 2009;28(25):3083-3107. doi:10.1002/sim.3697 <lb/>18. Hynes DM, Koelling K, Stroupe K, et al. Veterans&apos; access to and use of Medicare and Veterans Affairs health <lb/>care. Med Care. 2007;45(3):214-223. doi:10.1097/01.mlr.0000244657.90074.b7 <lb/>19. Hebert PL, Batten AS, Gunnink E, et al. Reliance on Medicare providers by veterans after becoming age-eligible <lb/>for Medicare is associated with the use of more outpatient services. Health Serv Res. 2018;53(suppl 3):5159-5180. <lb/>doi:10.1111/1475-6773.13033 <lb/>20. Liu CF, Manning WG, Burgess JF Jr, et al. Reliance on Veterans Affairs outpatient care by Medicare-eligible <lb/>veterans. Med Care. 2011;49(10):911-917. doi:10.1097/MLR.0b013e31822396c5 <lb/>21. Liu CF, Batten A, Wong ES, Fihn SD, Hebert PL. Fee-for-Service Medicare-enrolled elderly veterans are <lb/>increasingly voting with their feet to use more VA and less Medicare, 2003-2014. Health Serv Res. 2018;53(suppl <lb/>3):5140-5158. doi:10.1111/1475-6773.13029 <lb/>22. Ferguson JM, Jacobs J, Yefimova M, Greene L, Heyworth L, Zulman DM. Virtual care expansion in the Veterans <lb/>Health Administration during the COVID-19 pandemic: clinical services and patient characteristics associated with <lb/>utilization. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2021;28(3):453-462. doi:10.1093/jamia/ocaa284 <lb/>23. Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. CMS-1693-F: revisions to payment policies under the Medicare <lb/>physician fee schedule, quality payment program and other revisions to part B for CY 2019. November 22, 2018. <lb/>Accessed January 4, 2024. https://www.cms.gov/medicare/medicare-fee-for-service-payment/physicianfeesched/ <lb/>pfs-federal-regulation-notices-items/cms-1693-f <lb/>24. Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. CMS-1734-F CY2021 List of Medicare telehealth services. December <lb/>28, 2020. Accessed January 4, 2024. https://www.cms.gov/medicaremedicare-fee-service-<lb/>paymentphysicianfeeschedpfs-federal-regulation-notices/cms-1734-f <lb/>25. Groff D, Sun A, Ssentongo AE, et al. Short-term and long-term rates of postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>infection: a systematic review. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(10):e2128568. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen. <lb/>2021.28568 <lb/>26. Murata GH, Murata AE, Perkins DJ, et al. Effect of vaccination on the case fatality rate for COVID-19 infections <lb/>2020-2021: multivariate modelling of data from the US Department of Veterans Affairs. BMJ Open. 2022;12(12): <lb/>e064135. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2022-064135 <lb/>27. Feyman Y, Avila CJ, Auty S, et al. Racial and ethnic disparities in excess mortality among U.S. veterans during <lb/>the COVID-19 pandemic. Health Serv Res. 2023;58(3):642-653. doi:10.1111/1475-6773.14112 <lb/>28. Sudre CH, Murray B, Varsavsky T, et al. Attributes and predictors of long COVID. Nat Med. 2021;27(4): <lb/>626-631. doi:10.1038/s41591-021-01292-y <lb/>29. Gagne JJ, Glynn RJ, Avorn J, Levin R, Schneeweiss S. A combined comorbidity score predicted mortality in <lb/>elderly patients better than existing scores. J Clin Epidemiol. 2011;64(7):749-759. doi:10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010. <lb/>10.004 <lb/>30. Han L, Zhao S, Li S, et al. Excess cardiovascular mortality across multiple COVID-19 waves in the United States <lb/>from March 2020 to March 2022. Nat Cardiovasc Res. 2023;2(3):322-333. doi:10.1038/s44161-023-00220-2 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>31. Wang L, Porter B, Maynard C, et al. Predicting risk of hospitalization or death among patients receiving primary <lb/>care in the Veterans Health Administration. Med Care. 2013;51(4):368-373. doi:10.1097/MLR.0b013e31827da95a <lb/>32. VanderWeele TJ, Ding P. Sensitivity analysis in observational research: introducing the E-value. Ann Intern <lb/>Med. 2017;167(4):268-274. doi:10.7326/M16-2607 <lb/>33. StataCorp. Stata Statistical Software: Release 17. StataCorp LLC; 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 1. <lb/>eFigure. Difference-in-Difference Estimates of the Effect of COVID-19 Infection on Outpatient Visits Over 30 Days <lb/>Across Three Post-Infection Time Periods, by Category and Mode (Telecare vs In-Person) of Outpatient Visit, <lb/>Excluding Visits on the Day of Infection <lb/>eTable. Final List of Covariates for Matching <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 2. <lb/>VA COVID-19 Observational Research Collaboratory (CORC) Group Members <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 3. <lb/>Data Sharing Statement <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Pulmonary Medicine <lb/>Changes in Outpatient Health Care Use After COVID-19 Infection Among Veterans <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(2):e2355387. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.55387 (Reprinted) <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15/15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 </note>


	</text>
</TEI>