<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T09:53:13.120Z">11/20/2025 9:53:13 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T09:51:05.981675Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T09:51:05.981675Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Case Report <lb/>Yang Song, Boyu Yang, Wanlei Ren, Doudou Hu* <lb/>Elevation of D-dimer in eosinophilic <lb/>gastrointestinal diseases in the absence <lb/>of venous thrombosis: A case series <lb/>and literature review <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/med-2024-0960 <lb/>received April 28, 2023; accepted April 4, 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction -Eosinophilic gastrointestinal diseases (EGIDs) <lb/>are rare and heterogeneous diseases characterized by exces-<lb/>sive eosinophilic infiltration of the digestive system. D-dimer <lb/>levels and its possible association with disease course were not <lb/>reported. <lb/>Case series -We reported a series of three EGID cases <lb/>presenting with high levels of D-dimer. No evidence for <lb/>potential venous thromboembolism was found through <lb/>computed tomography pulmonary angiogram and vascular <lb/>ultrasounds. Moreover, D-dimer levels decreased after short-<lb/>time systemic prednisolone administration, accompanied by <lb/>remission of clinical symptoms and decrease of peripheral <lb/>eosinophil counts and IgE levels. <lb/>Conclusion -Elevation of D-dimer in EGID may not repre-<lb/>sent thrombotic events but is possibly associated with disease <lb/>severity. More population-based studies are needed to <lb/>delineate the potential relationship among D-dimer, throm-<lb/>bosis, and inflammation in EGID. <lb/>Keywords: eosinophilic gastroenteritis, D-dimer, venous <lb/>thrombosis, case series, literature review <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Eosinophilic gastrointestinal diseases (EGIDs) are charac-<lb/>terized by excessive infiltration of eosinophils in the gastroin-<lb/>testinal tract, ranging from the esophagus to the rectum, which <lb/>includes eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE), eosinophilic gastritis <lb/>(EoG), eosinophilic enteritis, eosinophilic colitis (EoC), etc. [1]. <lb/>Patients suffer from different types of symptoms depending on <lb/>the involved segments, including nausea, abdominal pain, diar-<lb/>rhea, etc. [2]. Most patients are obliged to corticosteroid therapy <lb/>accompanied by various side effects, such as metabolic disor-<lb/>ders [3]. Moreover, more than half of the patients suffer per-<lb/>sistent disease activity or a relapsing and remitting course. <lb/>Laboratory results in EGID are mostly unspecific, including <lb/>eosinophilia [4], iron-deficiency anemia [5], elevation of serum <lb/>IgE [6], etc. However, abnormalities of coagulation parameters <lb/>are not reported in previous cases. In the coagulation process, <lb/>D-dimer is derived from fibrin degradation products (FDPs) <lb/>when plasmin cleaves insoluble fibrin monomers [7]. It has <lb/>been widely used in the identification, evaluation, and treat-<lb/>ment effects of venous thromboembolism (VTE) and various <lb/>artery diseases [8]. However, role of D-dimer in EGID and its <lb/>possible association with VTE are not reported. Thus, we <lb/>report a case series of EGID with an uncommon presentation <lb/>of D-dimer elevation in the absence of VTE. <lb/>2 Case series <lb/>2.1 Case 1 <lb/>A 26-year-old Chinese man, with no significant past med-<lb/>ical history, presented to the clinic with 3-day history of <lb/>abdominal pain localized to the epigastrium. He denied <lb/>any recent travel, sick contact, or drug administration <lb/>prior to the onset of symptoms. The physical examination <lb/>findings were unremarkable. <lb/></body>

    <front>Yang Song: Yantai Nurses School of Shandong, Yantai, Shandong, <lb/>P. R. China <lb/>Boyu Yang: Department of Gastroenterology, Qingdao Hospital, <lb/>University of Health and Rehabilitation (Qingdao Municipal Hospital), <lb/>Qingdao, Shandong 266000, P. R. China <lb/>Wanlei Ren: Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Qingdao <lb/>Central Hospital, University of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences <lb/>(Qingdao Central Hospital), Qingdao, Shandong, P. R. China <lb/> <lb/>* Corresponding author: Doudou Hu, Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, Qingdao Hospital, University of Health and <lb/>Rehabilitation (Qingdao Municipal Hospital), Qingdao, Shandong <lb/>266000, P. R. China, e-mail: hudoudou1984@163.com, <lb/>tel: +86-0532-82789565 <lb/>Open Medicine 2024; 19: 20240960 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

    <body>The total white blood cell count was 10,840/µL (3,500-9,500/ <lb/>µL, reference range in our hospital), and eosinophil count was <lb/>5,130/µL (20-520/µL). The fecal occult blood test was weakly <lb/>positive. The level of immunoglobin (Ig) E was 220 IU/mL <lb/>(≤100 IU/mL) and the patient was weakly allergic to peanut <lb/>and soya bean. D-dimer level was three times more than the <lb/>normal range: 1.57 µg/mL (0-0.5 µg/mL). Liver and renal func-<lb/>tion, serum tumor markers, lipid levels, thyroid function, as <lb/>well as immunity and inflammation-related markers, such as <lb/>IgG, IgG4 isotype, IgA, IgM, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, anti-<lb/>nuclear antibodies, and C-reactive protein were within the <lb/>normal range. <lb/>A contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) scan <lb/>of the chest and abdomen showed diffuse circumferential <lb/>thickening of the esophagus and gastric antrum. The lung, <lb/>liver, gall bladder, bile duct, spleen, and pancreas showed <lb/>no abnormalities and there was no lymph node enlarge-<lb/>ment. Upper endoscopy revealed scattered flat hyperemia and <lb/>erosion of the gastric antrum and duodenum (Figure 1). Colo-<lb/>noscopy showed scattered punctate erosion of the terminal <lb/>ileum (Figure 2). Histological analysis showed moderately <lb/>active gastritis and duodenitis, with more than 30 eosinophils <lb/>per high-power field (HPF) in the gastric antrum (Figure 3). <lb/>Differential diagnosis was also made according to current <lb/>examinations. The patient reported no travel history. Stool tests <lb/>for hookworm, whipworm, ascaris, and amoeba were nega-<lb/>tive. No evidence of parasitic infection was found. 13C-urea <lb/>breath test and pathology analysis for Helicobacter pylori <lb/>were negative. The patient also denied a history of medica-<lb/>tions, including mycophenolate and non-steroidal anti-inflam-<lb/>matory drugs. The diagnosis of EoG was validated. <lb/>We wondered whether D-dimer elevation was a hint <lb/>for venous thrombosis. However, computed tomography <lb/>pulmonary angiogram (CTPA, Figure 4), vascular ultra-<lb/>sound for lower extremity, and mesenteric vessels were nega-<lb/>tive for possible thrombosis. Upon diagnosis, the patient was <lb/>administered systemic steroid therapy (prednisolone 40 mg/ <lb/>day) followed by rapid symptomatic improvement. Five days <lb/>after steroid administration, the eosinophil count was rapidly <lb/>decreased to 590/µL and the D-dimer level was also within the <lb/>normal range: 0.22 µg/mL. IgE was also downregulated to 180 <lb/>IU/mL. The patient was discharged for further monitoring <lb/>and follow-up. <lb/>2.2 Case 2 <lb/>A 67-year-old female was referred to our department for <lb/>abdominal pain over 10 days. She also had a distended <lb/>abdomen and diarrhea. Her past medical history was sig-<lb/>nificant for hypertension and her only surgical history was <lb/>appendectomy due to appendicitis. She was taking val-<lb/>sartan to treat hypertension. Vital signs were stable and <lb/>physical examination findings were not significant. <lb/>Figure 1: Representative images of upper endoscopy indicating scattered flat hyperemia and erosion of the gastric antrum and duodenum. <lb/>(a) Esophagus, (b) gastric fundus, (c) gastric antrum, and (d) duodenum. <lb/></body>

    <page>2 </page>

    <note place="headnote"> Yang Song et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>Labs were notable for a white cell count of 24,870/µL <lb/>and an eosinophil count of 17,970/µL. The fecal occult blood <lb/>test was also positive. The level of IgE was more than the <lb/>upper limit 1,130 IU/mL and she was also weakly allergic to <lb/>soybeans. Her lipid levels were abnormal with total triglyceride <lb/>being 2.37 mmol/L and total cholesterol being 5.81 mmol/L. The <lb/>D-dimer level was also more than the normal range: 0.8 µg/mL. <lb/>Liver and renal function, serum tumor markers, and immunity-<lb/>related markers were within normal range. <lb/>CTPA, vascular ultrasound for the lower extremity, <lb/>and mesenteric vessels also showed no potential throm-<lb/>bosis. CT scan of the chest and abdomen showed cholecys-<lb/>titis and a small amount of pelvic effusion. Upper endoscopic <lb/>findings indicated schistose erythema and erosion of the gas-<lb/>tric antrum and duodenum. Histology of gastric antrum sug-<lb/>gested massive infiltration of eosinophils (approximately 35 <lb/>cells/HPF). Colonoscopy showed no abnormal findings. The <lb/>patient also had no travel history. Stool tests were negative <lb/>for parasitic infection. 13C-urea breath test and pathology <lb/>analysis for H. pylori were negative. Apart from valsartan, <lb/>the patient denied the current administration of medications. <lb/>Diagnosis of EoG was verified. <lb/>She was administered with prednisolone 20 mg/day. <lb/>Following the corticosteroid prescription, abdominal pain <lb/>was soon relieved. Seven days after the prednisolone pre-<lb/>scription, peripheral eosinophils were 2,460/µL. IgE level <lb/>Figure 2: Representative images of colonoscopy indicating scattered punctate erosion of the terminal ileum. (a) Terminal ileum, (b) terminal ileum, (c) <lb/>ileocecal region, (d) transverse colon, (e) descending colon, and (f) rectum. <lb/>Figure 3: Histological images of the gastric antrum showing infiltration <lb/>of eosinophils. (a) and (b) gastric antrum. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Elevation of D-dimer in eosinophilic gastrointestinal diseases  </note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <body>was decreased to 835 IU/mL. D-dimer concentration was <lb/>0.23 µg/mL. <lb/>2.3 Case 3 <lb/>A 28-year-old Congolese male complained of symptoms of <lb/>epigastric pain, abdominal distension, and acid reflux for <lb/>20 days, which were deteriorated after meals. No signifi-<lb/>cant past medical history was reported and physical exam-<lb/>ination was unremarkable. <lb/>The peripheral blood profile showed a leukocytosis <lb/>(11,540/µL) with 42.5% eosinophils (4,900/µL). IgE level <lb/>was slightly high (156 IU/mL). Serum CA-125 was over <lb/>normal range: 122.71U/ml. A high concentration of D-dimer <lb/>(19.59 µg/mL) was also observed. Venous thrombosis was <lb/>preliminarily excluded through CTPA and vascular ultra-<lb/>sound for mesenteric vessels and lower extremity. Chest <lb/>and abdominal CT scans revealed diffuse thickening of the <lb/>small intestine, ascites, and pleural effusion. No solid mass <lb/>was observed. Upper endoscopy showed punctate erythema <lb/>and erosion of the esophagus and gastric corpus, diffuse <lb/>mucosal edema, and erosion of gastric angle and antrum. <lb/>Histological analysis showed severely active gastritis and duo-<lb/>denitis with eosinophil infiltration more than 50/HPF in the <lb/>gastric antrum and descending part of duodenum. He refused <lb/>to undergo a colonoscopy. <lb/>The patient was prescribed prednisolone 30 mg/day to <lb/>induce clinical remission. Shortly after corticosteroid admin-<lb/>istration, he reported significant alleviation of symptoms of <lb/>abdominal pain, distension, and acid reflux. Five days after <lb/>Figure 4: Representative images of CTPA showing no thrombosis. (a) to (d), different slices of CTPA. <lb/>Table 1: Peripheral eosinophil count, D-dimer, and IgE levels of all three cases before and after corticosteroid treatment <lb/>At admission <lb/>After treatment (5-7 days) <lb/>Peripheral eosinophil count <lb/>(cell/µL) <lb/>D-dimer level <lb/>(µg/mL) <lb/>IgE level <lb/>(IU/mL) <lb/>Peripheral eosinophil count <lb/>(cell/µL) <lb/>D-dimer level <lb/>(µg/mL) <lb/>IgE level <lb/>(IU/mL) <lb/>Case 1 5,130 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>220 <lb/>590 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>180 <lb/>Case 2 17,970 <lb/>5.81 <lb/>1,130 <lb/>2,460 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>835 <lb/>Case 3 4,900 <lb/>19.59 <lb/>156 <lb/>50 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>74 <lb/></body>

    <page>4 </page>

    <note place="headnote"> Yang Song et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>treatment, the peripheral eosinophil count was reduced <lb/>to the normal range: 50/µL. D-dimer level was markedly <lb/>decreased to 0.63 µg/mL. IgE level was within normal <lb/>range. The peripheral eosinophil count, D-dimer, and <lb/>IgE levels of all three cases before and after corticos-<lb/>teroid treatment are displayed in Table 1. <lb/>Informed consent: Informed consent has been obtained <lb/>from all individuals included in this study. <lb/>3 Discussion <lb/>The overall prevalence of EoG and EoE is 5.1/100,000 per-<lb/>sons, and the prevalence rate of EoC is 2.1/100,000 in the US <lb/>[9], which makes EGID still a rare disease. No consensus <lb/>has been reached concerning diagnostic criteria for EGID <lb/>and patients showed various clinical symptoms and disease <lb/>courses. In some cases, uncommon clinical presentations <lb/>could be observed. Here, we reported a case series of EGID <lb/>with elevation of D-dimer in the absence of VTE. D-dimer <lb/>levels decreased after short-time prednisolone administra-<lb/>tion, with the remission of clinical symptoms and a decrease <lb/>of peripheral eosinophil counts and IgE levels. <lb/>During coagulation progress, plasmin cleaves cross-<lb/>linked insoluble fibrin monomers to yield by-products <lb/>known as FDPs [10]. Among these products, the remnant <lb/>composed of two adjacent bonded D-domains from cross-<lb/>linked fibrils are what are now known as &quot;D-dimers&quot; [11]. <lb/>Serum D-dimer levels correlate with various pathophysio-<lb/>logical conditions. One of the critical roles is the diagnosis <lb/>of VTE [12]. Increased D-dimer levels indicated highly pos-<lb/>sible active VTE, especially when D-dimer assays were per-<lb/>formed shortly after symptom onset [13]. The sensitivity, <lb/>specificity, and positive predictive value of D-dimer con-<lb/>centration greater than 500 ng/mL for acute pulmonary <lb/>emboli were 93.3, 25.0, and 30.4%, respectively [14]. To <lb/>rule out possible thrombosis, all three cases underwent <lb/>CTPA, as well as vascular ultrasound for mesenteric vessels <lb/>and lower extremity. All results were negative, which indi-<lb/>cated that thrombosis may not be the appropriate explana-<lb/>tion for D-dimer elevation. <lb/>D-dimer was also associated with the onset and disease <lb/>course of various cardiovascular diseases. In acute aortic <lb/>dissection (AAD), D-dimer testing provided high sensitivity <lb/>and a negative likelihood ratio. At a cut-off level of 0.9 and <lb/>0.1 µg/mL, negative predictive value (NPV) achieved 92% <lb/>and 100%, respectively [15]. Similar results confirming <lb/>the high NPV of D-dimer levels in AAD were also demon-<lb/>strated by Cui et al. [16]. Plasma D-dimer was also strongly <lb/>association with aortic aneurysm (AA) for cut-offs 400 <lb/>and 900 ng/mL, respectively, and its high concentration <lb/>(&gt;900 ng/mL) correlated with a faster aneurysmal growth <lb/>rate [17]. However, the role of D-dimers in the diagnosis <lb/>and risk stratification of coronary artery disease (CAD) <lb/>patients remains disputable. The potential hypothesis may <lb/>be that the underlying coronary atherosclerotic activity may <lb/>lead to fibrinolysis, and a subsequent increase in plasma D-<lb/>dimer levels [18]. Its increase might precede the onset of acute <lb/>coronary syndrome (ACS). In this case series, all three cases <lb/>were excluded for AAD and AA based on symptoms, chest CT <lb/>scan, and CTPA. Electrocardiogram and classic cardiac bio-<lb/>markers such as troponin and creatine kinase MB also did not <lb/>support ACS diagnosis. Moreover, the rapid decrease in D-<lb/>dimer concentration after corticosteroid administration was <lb/>not consistent with CAD or ACS disease course. <lb/>Inflammation has been recognized as a regulator of <lb/>coagulation and fibrinolytic system [19,20]. Acute inflam-<lb/>mation is known to shift the hemostatic balance toward a <lb/>prothrombotic and antifibrinolytic state in which there is <lb/>an increase in circulating levels of several key procoagu-<lb/>lant and antifibrinolytic mediators. In HIV patients, D-<lb/>dimer levels were markedly decreased in antiretroviral <lb/>therapy (ART) compared to untreated patients [21]. Stop-<lb/>ping ART in primary HIV patients leads to IL-6 and D-dimer <lb/>significantly increase in pre-treatment concentrations [21]. <lb/>Besides, in type 1 diabetic patients, serum D-dimer levels <lb/>showed a significant positive correlation with TNF-α concen-<lb/>trations, indicating a possible interrelationship between <lb/>inflammation and hypercoagulability status [22]. The poten-<lb/>tial explanation might be that proinflammatory cytokines, <lb/>such as IL-6 and TNF-α, can stimulate the release of pro-coa-<lb/>gulant molecules and inhibit the expression of anti-coagulant <lb/>molecules by endothelial cells, resulting in a hypercoagul-<lb/>ability state [23]. However, such studies were not reported <lb/>in EGID and the correlation needed further validation in <lb/>large-scale population studies. <lb/>In conclusion, we reported a case series of EGID with <lb/>elevation of D-dimer in the absence of VTE. D-dimer levels <lb/>decreased after short-time prednisolone administration, <lb/>with a remission of clinical symptoms and a decrease in <lb/>peripheral eosinophil counts and IgE levels. Further large-<lb/>scale population-based studies are warranted to validate D-<lb/>dimer levels in EGID. <lb/></body>

    <div type="funding">Funding information: Supported by Qingdao Outstanding <lb/>Health Professional Development Fund and National <lb/>Natural Science Foundation of China (81800543). <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions: Boyu Yang and Doudou Hu: patient <lb/>diagnosis and management. Yang Song and Wanlei Ren: data <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">Elevation of D-dimer in eosinophilic gastrointestinal diseases  </note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">collection and draft manuscript preparation. Doudou Hu: <lb/>revising manuscript critically. All authors reviewed and <lb/>approved the final version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest: The authors declare that the research <lb/>was conducted in the absence of any commercial or finan-<lb/>cial relationships that could be construed as a potential <lb/>conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement: The original contributions <lb/>presented in the study are included in the article. Further <lb/>requirements could be directed to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Dellon ES, Gonsalves N, Abonia JP, Alexander JA, Arva NC, Atkins D, <lb/>et al. International consensus recommendations for eosinophilic <lb/>gastrointestinal disease nomenclature. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. <lb/>2022;20(11):2474-84.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2022.02.017. <lb/>[2] Gonsalves N. Eosinophilic gastrointestinal disorders. Clin Rev <lb/>Allergy Immunol. 2019;57(2):272-85. doi: 10.1007/s12016-019-<lb/>08732-1. <lb/>[3] Hua S, Cook D, Walker MM, Talley NJ. Pharmacological treatment of <lb/>eosinophilic gastrointestinal disorders. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol. <lb/>2016;9(9):1195-209. doi: 10.1080/17512433.2016.1190268. <lb/>[4] Lee J, Dierkhising R, Wu TT, Alexander J, Weiler C. Eosinophilic <lb/>gastrointestinal disorders (EGID) with peripheral eosinophilia: a <lb/>retrospective review at Mayo Clinic. Dig Dis Sci. <lb/>2011;56(11):3254-61. doi: 10.1007/s10620-011-1754-3. <lb/>[5] Ekunno N, Munsayac K, Pelletier A, Wilkins T. Eosinophilic gastro-<lb/>enteritis presenting with severe anemia and near syncope. J Am <lb/>Board Fam Med. 2012;25(6):913-8. doi: 10.3122/jabfm.2012.06. <lb/>110269. <lb/>[6] Votto M, De Filippo M, Caminiti L, Carella F, de Castro G, Landi M, <lb/>et al. Eosinophilic gastrointestinal disorders and allergen immu-<lb/>notherapy: Lights and shadows. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. <lb/>2021;32(5):814-23. doi: 10.1111/pai.13458. <lb/>[7] Johnson ED, Schell JC, Rodgers GM. The D-dimer assay. Am J <lb/>Hematol. 2019;94(7):833-9. doi: 10.1002/ajh.25482. <lb/>[8] Weitz JI, Fredenburgh JC, Eikelboom JW. A test in context: D-dimer. J <lb/>Am Coll Cardiol. 2017;70(19):2411-20. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2017. <lb/>09.024. <lb/>[9] Mansoor E, Saleh MA, Cooper GS. Prevalence of eosinophilic gas-<lb/>troenteritis and colitis in a population-based study, from 2012 to <lb/>2017. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017;15(11):1733-41. doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>cgh.2017.05.050. <lb/>[10] Gaffney PJ, Joe F. The lysis of crosslinked human fibrin by plasmin <lb/>yields initially a single molecular complex, D dimer-E. Thromb Res. <lb/>1979;15(5-6):673-87. doi: 10.1016/0049-3848(79)90177-4. <lb/>[11] Gaffney PJ. Fibrin degradation products. A review of structures <lb/>found in vitro and in vivo. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2001;936:594-610. <lb/>[12] Rodger MA, Le Gal G, Wells P, Baglin T, Aujesky D, Righini M, et al. <lb/>Clinical decision rules and D-Dimer in venous thromboembolism: <lb/>current controversies and future research priorities. Thromb Res. <lb/>2014;134(4):763-8. doi: 10.1016/j.thromres.2014.07.031. <lb/>[13] de Bastos M, de Bastos MR, Bogutchi T, Carneiro-Proietti AB, <lb/>Rezende SM. Duration of symptoms and D-dimer testing in the <lb/>ruling-out of venous thromboembolism. J Thromb Haemost. <lb/>2006;4(9):2079-80. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2006.02063.x. <lb/>[14] Goldhaber SZ, Simons GR, Elliott CG, Haire WD, Toltzis R, <lb/>Blacklow SC, et al. Quantitative plasma D-dimer levels among <lb/>patients undergoing pulmonary angiography for suspected pul-<lb/>monary embolism. JAMA. 1993;270(23):2819-22. <lb/>[15] Sodeck G, Domanovits H, Schillinger M, Ehrlich MP, Endler G, <lb/>Herkner H, et al. D-dimer in ruling out acute aortic dissection: a <lb/>systematic review and prospective cohort study. Eur Heart J. <lb/>2007;28(24):3067-75. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehm484. <lb/>[16] Cui JS, Jing ZP, Zhuang SJ, Qi SH, Li L, Zhou JW, et al. D-dimer as a <lb/>biomarker for acute aortic dissection: a systematic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. Medicine (Baltim). 2015;94(4):e471. doi: 10.1097/MD. <lb/>0000000000000471. <lb/>[17] Golledge J, Muller R, Clancy P, McCann M, Norman PE. Evaluation of <lb/>the diagnostic and prognostic value of plasma D-dimer for <lb/>abdominal aortic aneurysm. Eur Heart J. 2011;32(3):354-64. doi: 10. <lb/>1093/eurheartj/ehq171. <lb/>[18] Ridker PM, Vaughan DE, Stampfer MJ, Manson JE, Hennekens CH. <lb/>Endogenous tissue-type plasminogen activator and risk of myo-<lb/>cardial infarction. Lancet. 1993;341(8854):1165-8. doi: 10.1016/0140-<lb/>6736(93)90998-v. <lb/>[19] Esmon CT. Coagulation and inflammation. J Endotoxin Res. <lb/>2003;9(3):192-8. doi: 10.1179/096805103125001603. <lb/>[20] Esmon CT. Crosstalk between inflammation and thrombosis. <lb/>Maturitas. 2004;47(4):305-14. doi: 10.1016/j.maturitas.2003.10.015. <lb/>[21] Hamlyn E, Stohr W, Cooper DA, Fisher M, Tambussi G, Schechter M, <lb/>et al. The effect of short-course antiretroviral therapy initiated in <lb/>primary HIV-1 infection on interleukin-6 and D-dimer levels. AIDS. <lb/>2015;29(11):1355-61. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0000000000000675. <lb/>[22] Domingueti CP, Foscolo RB, Reis JS, Campos FM, Dusse LM, <lb/>Carvalho M, et al. Association of haemostatic and inflammatory <lb/>biomarkers with nephropathy in type 1 diabetes mellitus. J Diabetes <lb/>Res. 2016;2016:2315260. doi: 10.1155/2016/2315260. <lb/>[23] Margetic S. Inflammation and haemostasis. Biochem Med <lb/>(Zagreb). 2012;22(1):49-62. <lb/></listBibl>

    <page>6 </page>

    <note place="headnote"> Yang Song et al. </note>


  </text>

</TEI>