<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T15:08:55.416Z">11/14/2025 3:08:55 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T15:08:36.030627Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T15:08:36.030627Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks and stock price <lb/>reaction <lb/>Yao Gao 1 , Yoshiaki NoseID 2 * <lb/>1 Doshisha Business School Network, Kyoto, Japan, 2 Graduate School of Business, Doshisha University, <lb/>Kyoto, Japan <lb/>* ynose@mail.doshisha.ac.jp <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This study aimed to examine the impact and source of announcements introducing addi-<lb/>tional long-term shareholder perks on stock prices of Japanese listed companies. We pro-<lb/>duced more precise analysis results by categorizing the total sample into favorable change <lb/>and unfavorable change sample. As a result, we found that long-term shareholder perks <lb/>have a positive impact on stock prices through the expansion of the shareholder base in the <lb/>case of a favorable change, whereas there is no negative impact on stock liquidity due to an <lb/>increased number of long term individual shareholders. On the contrary, in the case of an <lb/>unfavorable change, we found a weak trend of shrinkage in the shareholder base due to <lb/>individual shareholders&apos; defection and a consequent decrease in stock liquidity. In the case <lb/>of a favorable change, the long-term shareholder perks program functions as a means to <lb/>increase the number of shareholders and encourage them to hold the shares for a longer <lb/>period of time. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>This study analyzes the impact of the additional introduction of a long-term shareholder perks <lb/>program on the stock prices of Japanese companies that have implemented such programs, <lb/>also identifying the source of the impact. The analysis period covers 11 years, from 2010 to <lb/>2021. In Japan, shareholder perks, which provide shareholders with the company&apos;s goods or <lb/>services in addition to dividends, have been established as a form of payout. In recent years, it <lb/>has become clear that shareholder perks offer benefits that differ from dividends and share <lb/>buybacks [1-3], and interest in shareholder perks is also growing outside Japan [4]. <lb/>In Japan, where shareholder perks are well developed, a system has been introduced to <lb/>favor long-term shareholders. Such perks are provided to shareholders who hold shares <lb/>beyond a certain period of time. The primary purpose of a company&apos;s introduction of a prefer-<lb/>ential long-term shareholder perks program is to encourage individual shareholders to hold <lb/>shares for a long period of time [5]; however, the impact of long-term shareholder programs <lb/>on companies&apos; stock performance remains unclear. It is also not clear whether such programs <lb/>actually encourage individual shareholders to hold shares for the long term. <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/>1 / 19 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Gao Y, Nose Y (2024) Long-term <lb/>shareholder perks and stock price reaction. PLoS <lb/>ONE 19(4): e0300284. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pone.0300284 <lb/>Editor: Junhuan Zhang, Beihang University, CHINA <lb/>Received: October 13, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: February 24, 2024 <lb/>Published: April 18, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Gao, Nose. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its Supporting Information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: Yoshiaki Nose thanks Japan Society for <lb/>the Promotion of Science (JSPS) Grants-in-Aid for <lb/>Scientific Research (22K01566) for financial <lb/>support. The funder had no role in study design, <lb/></front>

	<body>The purpose of this study is twofold. The first intention is to determine the effect of <lb/>announcements of the introduction of long-term shareholder perks on the stock price of firms <lb/>that implement these programs. The second is to obtain some insight into the source of the <lb/>identified stock price effect. Previous studies have found that the announcement of the first <lb/>shareholder perks program has a positive effect on stock prices (e.g., [2]); however, the impact <lb/>of the introduction of &quot;additional long-term&quot; shareholder perks programs is unclear. This <lb/>study is the first to examine the stock price effect of long-term shareholder perks. <lb/>We examine two types of long-term shareholder perks, those that do not change the amount <lb/>of benefits offered to short-term shareholder perks (a favorable change for long-term sharehold-<lb/>ers), and those that reduce benefits for short-term shareholders (an unfavorable change). <lb/>Although individual investors&apos; evaluations of both types of changes may differ, a previous study <lb/>has not distinguished between favorable and unfavorable changes [6]. By reporting the results <lb/>of an analysis dichotomized into favorable and unfavorable changes, this study provides more <lb/>accurate information on the impact of the introduction of long-term shareholder perks. <lb/>The following three notable points are demonstrated in this study. First, announcements of <lb/>the introduction of a long-term shareholder perks program produce positive stock returns in <lb/>the case of a favorable change. Second, a favorable change in long-term shareholder perks can <lb/>cause a significant rise in the ratio of individual shareholders, whereas an unfavorable change <lb/>decreases the ratio of individual shareholders. Furthermore, there is a significant positive cor-<lb/>relation between stock returns and the increase in the ratio of individual shareholders. Third, <lb/>we observed a trend toward higher stock liquidity from a favorable change, and conversely, a <lb/>trend toward lower stock liquidity from an unfavorable change. <lb/>We find that long-term shareholder perks have a positive impact on stock prices through <lb/>the expansion of the shareholder base in the case of a favorable change, while there is no nega-<lb/>tive impact on stock liquidity due to an increased number of long term individual sharehold-<lb/>ers. Conversely, in the case of an unfavorable change, we find a weak trend of shrinkage in the <lb/>shareholder base due to individual shareholders&apos; defection and a consequent decrease in stock <lb/>liquidity. In the case of a favorable change, the long-term shareholder perks program functions <lb/>as a means to increase the number of shareholders and encourage them to hold the shares for a <lb/>longer period of time. <lb/>The structure of this paper is as follows. In Section 2, we outline the individual investor and <lb/>investment environment in Japan, the shareholder perks system and the long-term share-<lb/>holder perks system, and applicable definitions in this study. Section 3 surveys the previous <lb/>studies in this research and presents our hypotheses. Section 4 describes the data and methods <lb/>used in the empirical analysis. Section 5 presents the results of the analysis, and Section 6 sum-<lb/>marizes the study. <lb/>Shareholder perks <lb/>Current status of shareholder perks. Shareholder perks are payout programs in which a <lb/>company offers its own goods, services, or vouchers as special gifts to shareholders who meet <lb/>certain holding period conditions [7]. Because they are often not proportional to the number <lb/>of shares held, shareholder perks are considered to be attractive to small shareholders [8,9]. <lb/>For companies, shareholder perks are among the most representative measures for individual <lb/>shareholder benefits, along with trading unit reductions and individual investor relations. <lb/>Fig 1 presents the long-term shareholder perks program offered by Nissin Foods Holdings Co. <lb/>The popular Cup Noodles and other products are sent once a year to all shareholders who <lb/>hold at least 100 shares, which is the minimum trading unit. Shareholders who hold 300 or <lb/>more shares for three years receive such products twice a year. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<front>data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors declare no <lb/>conflict of interest. <lb/></front>

	<body>The number of companies offering shareholder perks has increased in recent years. In <lb/>1993, about 300 companies offered such perks, but as of September 2022, 1,463 companies <lb/>offered them. This represents about 40% of all listed companies [10]. According to a survey <lb/>conducted by Nikkei, the most common answer regarding the purpose of implementing share-<lb/>holder perks was &quot;to encourage shareholders to hold shares for a long time.&quot; Shareholder <lb/>perks programs have been criticized by institutional investors that cannot use the perks, con-<lb/>tending that the cost of maintaining and managing perks is inflated (Nihon Keizai Shimbun, <lb/>April 5, 2020, morning edition). <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks programs. As noted, long-term shareholder perks pro-<lb/>grams refer to a program that provides upgraded benefits to shareholders who hold their <lb/>shares for a certain period of time (often more than one year). In recent years, an increasing <lb/>number of companies have introduced long-term shareholder perks. As of March 31, 2020, <lb/>580 companies, or nearly 40% of the total number of companies offering shareholder perks, <lb/>had introduced long-term shareholder perks program (Fig 2). <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks can be divided into two patterns when considering individual <lb/>perks programs. The first pattern is that the benefits remain the same, with no required hold-<lb/>ing period, but new perks are added when a shareholder holds shares for a specified period of <lb/>time. This is a change that is more attractive to new individual investors (favorable change). <lb/>The second is the case in which long-term shareholder perks are added, while those without a <lb/>required holding period are downgraded. In this case, perks that were originally available for a <lb/>single day of investment are no longer available unless the shareholder invests for more than <lb/>the specified time. In the second case, the shareholder perks that a new individual shareholder <lb/>receives in the first year are reduced or eliminated, which is considered to be a change that is <lb/>less attractive to new individual investors (unfavorable change). This indicates that the long-<lb/>term shareholder perks programs do not simply grant positive benefits. Even if the amount of <lb/>benefits increases, if the number of shares required and the required investment period also <lb/>increase, individual investors will evaluate the perks negatively. Our study is unique in that it <lb/>analyzes these two forms separately. <lb/>Fig 1. Example of shareholder perks (Nissin Foods Holdings Co.). Source: https://www.nissin.com/jp/ir/investors/ <lb/>preferential/. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 1 shows specific examples of favorable and unfavorable changes. In company (1), in <lb/>addition to the traditional shareholder perks, long-term shareholders receive QUO Cards (a <lb/>well-known money certificate in Japan), which is a favorable change. In company (2), after the <lb/>change, the amount of QUO Cards granted to shareholders who have held their shares for <lb/>more than three years is doubled, which is also a favorable change. In contrast, under company <lb/>(3), shareholders who have not held shares for more than one year are not eligible for the spe-<lb/>cial benefit, and in case (4), although there is a short-term perk, the amount of the perk is <lb/>reduced, which are unfavorable changes. <lb/>Fig 2. Number of companies that have initiated long-term shareholder perks programs. Note: Figures for 2021 are for the six-month period ending October <lb/>31, 2021. Source: Prepared by the authors with reference to each company&apos;s press release information. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.g002 <lb/>Table 1. Examples of favorable and unfavorable changes. <lb/>Favorable or <lb/>unfavorable <lb/>case <lb/>Before change <lb/>After change <lb/>Summary <lb/>Favorable <lb/>1 100 shares or more <lb/>In addition to the above <lb/>Another perks added to long term shareholders <lb/>Dining coupons worth 4,000 <lb/>yen <lb/>100 shares or more <lb/>500 yen QUO card for 1 to 2 years of ownership <lb/>1,000 yen QUO card for shares held for 2 years <lb/>or more <lb/>2 100 shares or more <lb/>100 shares or more <lb/>Increased perks for long-term shareholders <lb/>500 yen QUO card <lb/>500 yen QUO card for less than 3 years <lb/>1,000 yen QUO card for more than 3 years <lb/>Unfavorable <lb/>3 100 shares or more <lb/>100 shares or more <lb/>Perks for long-term shareholders only <lb/>500 yen QUO card <lb/>1,000 yen QUO card for more than 1 year <lb/>4 100 shares or more <lb/>100 shares or more <lb/>Decrease in the amount of perks for short-term <lb/>shareholders <lb/>5000 yen QUO card <lb/>2,000 yen QUO card for less than 1 year <lb/>5,000 yen QUO card for more than 1 year <lb/>Source: Authors&apos; construction based on companies&apos; timely disclosure documents. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Literature review <lb/>Motivation for implementing shareholder perks <lb/>According to a survey by Daiwa Investor Relations (2022), companies implement shareholder <lb/>perks for such purposes as long-term shareholder retention and to increase the number of <lb/>individual shareholders [10]. Nose (2014) surveyed previous studies and categorized the <lb/>motives for implementing shareholder perks programs into shareholder-related motives, stock <lb/>performance-related motives, and other motivations. For shareholder-related motives, the <lb/>author identified an increase in the number of shareholders, lengthened shareholding periods, <lb/>dissolution of cross-shareholdings, prevention of hostile takeovers, and alternative means of <lb/>dividend payments [11]. Regarding motives related to stock performance, the author cites <lb/>increasing stock liquidity, destabilizing/stabilizing stock prices, and linking to stock indices. <lb/>Other motivations include promoting the company&apos;s products and tax savings. <lb/>Yasutake and Nagata (2018) conducted a questionnaire-based survey of 3,702 listed compa-<lb/>nies in 2016 regarding the objectives of long-term perks implementation on the corporate <lb/>side, determining that the two most significant objectives included increasing the number of <lb/>individual shareholders and promoting long-term shareholding [12]. <lb/>Performance of companies implementing shareholder perks <lb/>Although the MM theorem implied that the presence or absence of shareholder perks should <lb/>have no effect on stock prices [13], empirical data have demonstrated a positive stock price <lb/>effect from their implementation. Karpoff et al. (2021) conducted an event study examining a <lb/>sample of 307 firms that announced the introduction of shareholder perks between 2001 and <lb/>2011, finding the announcement of shareholder perks to have a positive short-term stock price <lb/>effect [2]. The authors conclude that investors anticipate an increase in the number of share-<lb/>holders and stock liquidity in companies that introduce shareholder perks, which leads to <lb/>higher stock prices. Karpoff et al. (2021) also examined the impact of the abolition of share-<lb/>holder perks, demonstrating that the cumulative abnormal return in the three days before and <lb/>after the announcement date for the 81 firms that announced the abolition of shareholder <lb/>perks was -5.89%, which was significantly negative at the 1% level [2]. A significantly negative <lb/>stock price effect was also observed for firms that announced a dividend increase at the same <lb/>time as the abolition of shareholder perks [14]. Considering that the announcement of the <lb/>introduction of shareholder perks program was shown to have a positive stock price effect, <lb/>while an announcement of the abolition of shareholder perks, even if accompanied by a divi-<lb/>dend increase, had a negative stock price effect, it can be assumed that shareholder perks exert <lb/>some positive added value. These results are consistent with Serita (2017), who found that <lb/>shareholder perks have a positive effect on stock prices by lowering the implementing firm&apos;s <lb/>cost of capital [15], and Uchida et al. (2022), who reported the share price support effect of <lb/>shareholder perks during the 2008-2009 financial crisis [16]. <lb/>Research has also been conducted regarding the long-term performance of stocks with <lb/>shareholder perks. According to Nose et al. (2021), stock performance rises as the vesting date <lb/>approaches for companies that offer shareholder perks [3]. According to the authors&apos; financial <lb/>visibility hypothesis, shareholder perks are introduced as a way to promote firms&apos; presence to <lb/>individual investors for stocks with low financial visibility among institutional investors. <lb/>While several studies have been conducted regarding shareholder perks programs, a limited <lb/>number have examined long-term shareholder perks programs. Yasutake and Nagata (2018) <lb/>analyzed the number of individual shareholders and Amihud&apos;s (2002) illiquidity index for all <lb/>listed Japanese stocks from 2010 to 2016 [6,17]. The results demonstrated that long-term <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>shareholder perks in general significantly increased the number of individual shareholders at <lb/>the 1% level, while significantly increasing illiquidity at the 5% level. This indicates that while <lb/>shareholder perks are effective in increasing the number of shareholders, they reduce the <lb/>liquidity of shares when long-term shareholder perks are favored, which contradicts past <lb/>research. <lb/>Implications and issues of previous studies <lb/>Although the motives and objectives for introducing shareholder perks may differ among <lb/>firms, the main reasons for introducing them are to increase the number of individual share-<lb/>holders and to encourage shareholders to hold shares for a long period of time. Correspond-<lb/>ingly, many empirical studies have found the introduction of new shareholder perks to have a <lb/>positive impact on stock prices by significantly increasing the number of shareholders and <lb/>improving stock liquidity. Furthermore, although companies have introduced long-term <lb/>shareholder perks to increase the number of long-term shareholders, the impact of the intro-<lb/>duction of such perks on stock prices and stock liquidity remains unclear. <lb/>Specifically, previous studies have identified the following three issues. First, the short-term <lb/>impact of the introduction of long-term shareholder perks on stock prices remains unclear. <lb/>Second, the impact of the introduction of long-term shareholder perks on stock liquidity has <lb/>not been determined. Third, when long-term shareholder perks are examined closely from the <lb/>perspective of individual investors, as established above, there are both favorable and unfavor-<lb/>able changes, but previous studies have not distinguished between the two. <lb/>Our study presents useful empirical results on these issues by examining the effects of the <lb/>introduction of long-term shareholder perks on stock prices and liquidity, and identifying the <lb/>sources of perks&apos; effects on stock returns. <lb/>Hypotheses and analysis methods <lb/>Hypotheses <lb/>This study references Suzuki and Isagawa&apos;s (2008) liquidity enhancement hypothesis, which <lb/>assumes that the introduction of long-term shareholder perks will affect stock prices through <lb/>the same mechanism as the introduction of new shareholder perks [18]. The liquidity hypothe-<lb/>sis was proposed by Amihud and Mendelson (1986), who argued that financial policies that <lb/>increase liquidity by increasing the number of shareholders will lower the cost of capital and <lb/>raise shareholder value [19]. Merton&apos;s (1987), assertion that an expanding shareholder base <lb/>reduces information asymmetry and positively affects stock prices is an additional theoretical <lb/>base [20]. We assume that the introduction of additional &quot;favorable&quot; long-term shareholder <lb/>perks for individual investors further attracts investors&apos; attention and positively affects stock <lb/>prices through an increase in the number of shareholders (expansion of the shareholder base), <lb/>improved liquidity, and lower transaction costs; thus, the first hypothesis is as follows. <lb/>H1 Announcement of a favorable long-term shareholder perk program generates a posi-<lb/>tive stock return. <lb/>The introduction of a favorable long-term shareholder perks program produces the same <lb/>effects as the introduction of a new shareholder perks program, aligning with the liquidity <lb/>enhancement hypothesis. In contrast, an unfavorable long-term shareholder perk program <lb/>either reduces or eliminates the perks for new individual shareholders in the first year. There-<lb/>fore, we assume that only favorable changes are perceived as attractive by new shareholders <lb/>and positively impact stock prices. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>When a stock return is observed, interest shifts to the question of its source, and this study <lb/>then tests the following two hypotheses. <lb/>H2-1 Stock return is positively correlated with an increase in the ratio of individual <lb/>shareholders. <lb/>According to Merton&apos;s (1987) investor recognition hypothesis, an increase in the share-<lb/>holder base leads to participation in trading by investors with diverse opinions regarding the <lb/>future of the company, and investor diversification has a positive impact on the stock price <lb/>[20]. Therefore, we assume that there will be a significant positive correlation between the <lb/>stock price effect and the increase in the ratio of individual shareholders (shareholder base). <lb/>H2-2 Stock return is positively correlated with increased stock liquidity. <lb/>The hypothesis of liquidity increase contends that an expanding shareholder base has a pos-<lb/>itive effect on stock prices through an increase in stock liquidity, while Yasutake and Nagata <lb/>(2022) asserted that long-term shareholder perks have a negative effect on stock liquidity [6]. <lb/>In this study, we reference Suzuki and Isagawa (2008) to set our hypothesis [18]. <lb/>This study analyzes all listed companies that announced the introduction of long-term <lb/>shareholder perks during the 11-year period from April 2010 to the end of March 2021. First, <lb/>we checked each firm&apos;s timely disclosure information and identified 308 firms. We next <lb/>checked whether any other announcement was made that would affect the share price, such as <lb/>increased or decreased profit, increased or decreased dividends, reduction in trading units, <lb/>stock split or merger, or stock repurchase on the same day as the announcement of long-term <lb/>shareholder perks. We found that 104 firms had same-day events, and our sample size is 203 <lb/>firms after excluding these firms. The sample was further classified according to the method <lb/>described in the previous section, identifying 128 firms with favorable changes and 75 firms <lb/>with unfavorable changes. <lb/>Financial data for the sampled firms are obtained from firms&apos; annual securities reports. <lb/>Stock price data are collected from Bloomberg&apos;s stock price database. <lb/>Stock price effect of announcements <lb/>To clarify the effect of long-term shareholder perks announcements on stock prices, we con-<lb/>duct an event study using the date of the announcement as the event date, referencing Karpoff <lb/>et al. (2021) and Huang et al. (2022) [1,2]. <lb/>First, we construct the following market model and estimate αi and βi using an estimation <lb/>period of 130 days from 150 days to 21 days before the event date. <lb/>R it ¼ a i þ b i R mt þ ε it <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>where R it indicates the daily return of sample company i on day t, R mt denotes the daily return <lb/>of TOPIX on day t, andε it is the error term. <lb/>Next, we estimate the daily abnormal return (AR i ) of sample firm i from the above market <lb/>model. AR is obtained by calculating the difference between the theoretical and actual returns <lb/>for 21 days before and after the event date. The cumulative AR is the cumulative abnormal <lb/>return (CAR). The significance of the mean and median of the AR and CAR for each day is <lb/>tested using a t-test and a Wilcoxon rank sum test with AR = 0 as the null hypothesis. <lb/>Changes in shareholder and stock liquidity <lb/>The changes in the number of shareholders and stock liquidity before and after the introduc-<lb/>tion of long-term shareholder perks are examined applying a difference-in-differences (DID) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>analysis, which is conducted by setting control firms against sample firms, referencing Karpoff <lb/>et al. (2021) and Huang et al. (2022) [1,2]. <lb/>The control firms are identified using propensity score matching (PSM). Specifically, the <lb/>group of firms that have introduced long-term perks programs is the sample (treatment) <lb/>group, and firms that do not have a long-term perks program (but have a shareholder perks <lb/>program) are the potential control group. The probability that these firms will introduce long-<lb/>term shareholder perks (propensity score) is then calculated, and firms with similar character-<lb/>istics to the sample firms are selected from the control group and matched on a one-to-one <lb/>basis. Matching is conducted by aligning the timing over the calendar year. Because differences <lb/>in industry can have as large an impact as financial and stock price variables, we ensured that <lb/>the pairs had the same 17 TSE industry sectors. Eq (2) is the logit model used to calculate the <lb/>propensity score. <lb/>Probðdummy for introduction of long term shareholder peks it ¼ 1Þ <lb/>¼ Fðb 0 þ b 1 ln sales itÀ 1 þ b 2 ROA itÀ 1 þ b 3 equity ratio itÀ 1 þ b 4 dividend yield itÀ 1 <lb/>þ b 5 volume turnover ratio itÀ 1 þ b 6 individual shareholders ratio itÀ 1 <lb/>þ b 7 indibilual shareholding ratio itÀ 1 Þ <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>where F is a logistic function, i is the firm, and t-1 is the period immediately before the intro-<lb/>duction of the long-term shareholder perks. The explained variable in the logit model is a <lb/>dummy variable that equals 1 for firms that introduce long-term shareholder perks and 0 for <lb/>firms that do not introduce it (but have shareholder perks with no required period). The finan-<lb/>cial data for each firm are obtained from firms&apos; annual securities reports. The stock price data <lb/>for each company are obtained from the Bloomberg database. <lb/>Table 2 presents the results of the balance evaluation after matching. t-tests are performed <lb/>to verify whether statistically significant differences in the means of the covariate between the <lb/>sample and control groups. The results show no statistically significant differences in any of <lb/>the covariates. <lb/>Changes in the ratio of the number of individual shareholders and the ratio of individual <lb/>shareholdings are examined using a DID analysis. We first calculate the amount of change <lb/>(difference) in each variable from the period immediately prior to the date of the announce-<lb/>ment of the introduction of long-term shareholder perks (-1 period) to the period immedi-<lb/>ately following the announcement (+1 period). Next, the difference between the difference for <lb/>the sample firms and control firms is determined. Fig 3 illustrates the DID analysis. <lb/>The period when the announcement was made (period 0) is not included because of its <lb/>short duration. The change for the sample firms alone is called the unadjusted difference, and <lb/>the difference with control firms is called the adjusted difference. <lb/>Table 2. Covariate checks. <lb/>Sample <lb/>Control <lb/>t-value <lb/>ln Sales <lb/>10.97 <lb/>10.8 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>ROA <lb/>6.95 <lb/>6.33 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>Equity Ratio <lb/>47.04 <lb/>48.81 <lb/>-0.83 <lb/>Dividend yield <lb/>1.82 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>Volume Turnover <lb/>144.77 <lb/>128.32 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>Individual Shareholder Ratio <lb/>96.44 <lb/>96.13 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>Individual Shareholding Ratio <lb/>39.91 <lb/>41.29 <lb/>-0.67 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>We conduct a t-test for the mean and a Wilcoxon signed rank test for the median for these <lb/>variables with the null hypothesis set to 0. <lb/>Unadjusted difference <lb/>¼ Sample firms indicators½x period� À Sample firms indicators½À 1 period� ð3Þ <lb/>Adjusted difference ¼ Change in sample firms À Change in control firms <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>Our analysis of stock liquidity references Karpoff et al. (2021) and Huang et al. (2022) [1,2]. <lb/>Specifically, a DID analysis is conducted to determine the quote spread ratio, the execution <lb/>spread ratio, and Amihud&apos;s (2002) illiquidity indicator [17]. The quote spread ratio is the dif-<lb/>ference between the highest bid and lowest asking prices in the board information divided by <lb/>the median of the two (Eq (5)), in which a higher value indicates a larger spread between buy-<lb/>ers&apos; and sellers&apos; limit prices, and the more difficult it is to close a deal (i.e., low liquidity). Con-<lb/>versely, a smaller value indicates a closer spread between buyers&apos; and sellers&apos; limit prices, <lb/>which makes it easier to close a deal (i.e., high liquidity). We reference Suzuki and Isagawa <lb/>(2008), using the last quote of each trading day [18]. <lb/>The execution spread ratio is the absolute value of the difference between the last execution <lb/>price of a given day and the median quote price immediately following divided by the median <lb/>quote price (Eq (6)). This is &quot;the spread ratio paid by the trader of a stock in return for liquid-<lb/>ity, and represents the size of the transaction cost&quot; [18]. The execution spread ratio can also be <lb/>interpreted as the larger (smaller) the value is, the lower (higher) the liquidity will be. <lb/>Quote spread ratio ¼ <lb/>ðasking price À bid priceÞ <lb/>median of both quotes <lb/>ð5Þ <lb/>Fig 3. Image of difference-in-differences analysis. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Execution spread ratio ¼ <lb/>jexecution price À median of both asking and bid quotesj <lb/>median of both quotes <lb/>ð6Þ <lb/>We measure the changes in these indicators before and after the announcement of the intro-<lb/>duction of the long-term shareholder perks program. Specifically, the period from 140 busi-<lb/>ness days before the announcement to 21 business days prior to the pre-announcement period <lb/>is considered the pre-announcement period and the period from 21 business days following <lb/>the announcement to 140 days after the announcement is considered the post-announcement <lb/>period. The differences in the spread rates are adjusted by the differences in the control sample <lb/>to verify whether significant differences are observed. <lb/>Changes in medium-and long-term liquidity are measured using Amihud&apos;s (2002) illiquid-<lb/>ity, which is an index (Eq (7)) that divides the daily stock return (absolute value) by the trading <lb/>value of the stock on the same day, representing the percentage change in the stock price for a <lb/>¥1 trade. A higher number indicates a greater impact on the volume of stock orders on the <lb/>price of a stock, which is interpreted as lower liquidity. <lb/>Illiquidity i;y ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>D i;y <lb/>X Diy <lb/>t¼1 <lb/>jR iyd j <lb/>VOLD iyd <lb/> * 1; 000; 000 <lb/>ð7Þ <lb/>where R iyd is the return on stock i on day d of year y and VOLD iyd is the value of daily volume <lb/>in yen. D is the number of days for which data are available for stock i in year y. <lb/>In this study, the starting point (year-1) is the period from one and a half years before the <lb/>announcement of the introduction of the long-term shareholder perks program (day-360) to <lb/>day-120, and the averages for the period from day+120 to day+360 is considered year+1, from <lb/>day+361 to day+600 is considered year+2, and from day+601 to day840 is considered year+3. <lb/>The illiquidity of each period is calculated and the differences from year-1 to year+1, year <lb/>+2, and year+3 are adjusted by the differences in the control sample to test whether significant <lb/>differences are found. <lb/>Sources of stock price effects <lb/>To determine whether the number of individual shareholders and stock liquidity are the <lb/>source of the CAR at announcement, we conduct a cross-sectional regression analysis with the <lb/>CAR of each sample firm as the explained variable and the indicators for individual sharehold-<lb/>ers and stock liquidity as the explanatory variables. Note that each explanatory variable is mea-<lb/>sured both before and after the announcement, and is considered a future event at the time of <lb/>the announcement. Therefore, a significant correlation between CAR and each explanatory <lb/>variable suggests that expectations regarding changes in these variables were the source of the <lb/>CAR. The specific proxy variables and their underlying hypotheses are presented in Table 3. <lb/>Table 4 presents the basic statistics for the samples used in this study. <lb/>Results <lb/>Announcement effect of introducing a long-term shareholder perks <lb/>Fig 4 illustrates the CAR trend. The day of the announcement of the introduction of the long-<lb/>term shareholder perks program is set as day0, and the ARs for 10 days before and after the <lb/>announcement are accumulated. The results for the entire sample (dotted line) show that the <lb/>CAR increases around day0 and remains at around 2% on day 10. A similar trend is observed <lb/>when the sample is divided into favorable and unfavorable changes; however, the CAR for <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>favorable changes appears to be higher. These results indicate that announcements of the <lb/>introduction of long-term shareholder perks may have a positive stock price effect. <lb/>Table 5 presents the mean values of ARs for the 21 days before and after the announcement <lb/>date. The results of the t-test and the Wilcoxon rank sum test include the null hypothesis of <lb/>mean and median AR = 0 for each. Examining the total sample, the mean AR was 0.35% for <lb/>day 0, 0.70% for day +1, 0.24% for day +2, and 0.25% for day +3, each of which was statistically <lb/>significant. The median ARs of 0, +1, and +2 days were also significantly positive. Since we <lb/>excluded samples with simultaneous public events such as earnings announcements, these pos-<lb/>itive ARs suggest that the stock market specifically reacted to the introduction of the long-term <lb/>shareholder perks program. <lb/>When the sample is dichotomized into favorable and unfavorable change, the ARs for day0, <lb/>day+1, day+2, and day+3 are significantly positive in the favorable change sample. In contrast, <lb/>the ARs for the unfavorable change sample, while positive, are not significant for mean or <lb/>median. <lb/>Table 6 Panel A shows the results of the t-test and the Wilcoxon rank sum test with 0 as the <lb/>null hypothesis for the mean and median of CAR from day0 to day+1. The mean and median <lb/>CAR (day0!+1) for the entire sample were 1.04% and 0.77%, respectively, both of which are <lb/>significantly positive at the 1% level. At first glance, these results suggest that long-term share-<lb/>holder perks have a positive effect on stock prices in general; however, a different result <lb/>emerges when the sample is divided. <lb/>Table 6 Panel B presents the results of the same analysis as Panel A, dividing the sample <lb/>into favorable and unfavorable changes. The mean and median CAR (day0!+1) for the sam-<lb/>ple of favorable changes are 1.26% and 0.84%, respectively, which are both significant at the <lb/>1% level. In contrast, the mean and median values of the CAR for the unfavorable change sam-<lb/>ple are positive but not statistically significant. <lb/>Table 3. Hypotheses and proxy variables. <lb/>Hypothesis <lb/>Proxy Variables for Hypotheses <lb/>Mark <lb/>H1 <lb/>Announcement of a favorable long-term shareholder perk program generates a positive stock return. <lb/>CAR (0, +1) <lb/>Positive <lb/>H2-1 <lb/>Stock return is positively correlated with an increase in the ratio of individual shareholders. <lb/>DID_Ratio of individual shareholders <lb/>Positive <lb/>DID_Individual Shareholding Ratio <lb/>Positive <lb/>H2-2 <lb/>Stock return is positively correlated with stock liquidity <lb/>Quote/Execution Spread <lb/>Negative <lb/>DID_illiquidity <lb/>Negative <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t003 <lb/>Table 4. Basic statistics of the samples. <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>n <lb/>Min <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>Max <lb/>n <lb/>Min <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>Max <lb/>CAR (0,-1) <lb/>128 <lb/>-9.82 1.26 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>16.58 <lb/>75 <lb/>-14.59 0.68 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>13.94 <lb/>Individual shareholding ratio (y-1) <lb/>128 5.50 <lb/>39.15 <lb/>36.92 <lb/>94.56 <lb/>75 <lb/>5.17 <lb/>41.21 <lb/>38.95 <lb/>88.66 <lb/>Ratio of individual shareholdings (y0) <lb/>127 0.81 <lb/>38.52 <lb/>36.65 <lb/>96.38 <lb/>75 <lb/>3.26 <lb/>42.02 <lb/>41.52 <lb/>88.84 <lb/>Ratio of individual shareholders (y-1) <lb/>128 69.88 <lb/>95.83 <lb/>97.10 <lb/>99.41 <lb/>75 <lb/>89.41 <lb/>97.50 <lb/>98.04 <lb/>99.55 <lb/>Ratio of individual shareholders (y0) <lb/>127 70.01 <lb/>96.09 <lb/>97.23 <lb/>99.45 <lb/>75 <lb/>89.72 <lb/>97.44 <lb/>97.96 <lb/>99.54 <lb/>ROA <lb/>119 <lb/>-4.69 7.23 <lb/>5.28 <lb/>29.75 <lb/>68 <lb/>-1.44 7.35 <lb/>6.04 <lb/>37.25 <lb/>PBR <lb/>126 0.30 <lb/>2.10 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>44.93 <lb/>75 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>2.08 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>19.58 <lb/>illiquidity (y-1) <lb/>123 0.0002 <lb/>0.127 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>2.311 <lb/>71 <lb/>0.00004 <lb/>0.082 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>0.754 <lb/>Quoted spread (immediately before announcement) <lb/>128 0.09 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>75 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>2.71 <lb/>Execution spread (just before announcement) <lb/>128 0.03 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>1.52 <lb/>75 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 4. Changes in cumulative abnormal return. Note: The horizontal axis is the days prior to and following the date of the <lb/>long-term shareholder perks program announcement, which is day0. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.g004 <lb/>Table 5. Announcement effect of introducing long-term shareholder perks. <lb/>All samples <lb/>Favorable change (n = 128) <lb/>Unfavorable change (n = 75) <lb/>Day <lb/>AR <lb/>AR <lb/>AR <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test statistic <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median Test statistic Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test <lb/>statistic <lb/>-10 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>968 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>1.75 * <lb/>0.04 <lb/>628 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.29 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-8 <lb/>-9 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.91 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>572 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>327 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>32 <lb/>-8 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>920 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>618 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-16 <lb/>-7 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-123 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>245 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-1.00 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-202 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.79 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>-460 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>-0.66 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>-84 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-0.44 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-128 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-234 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-133 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-13 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>670 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>237 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>108 <lb/>-3 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>24 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>195 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-0.66 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-117 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-136 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>14 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-65 <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.65 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-113 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-1.51 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-447 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>214 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>2.00 ** <lb/>0.13 <lb/>1,480 * <lb/>0.54 <lb/>3.04 *** <lb/>0.18 <lb/>952 ** <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>3.04 *** <lb/>0.55 <lb/>2,760 *** <lb/>0.72 <lb/>2.65 *** <lb/>0.59 <lb/>1,365 *** <lb/>0.66 <lb/>1.58 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>192 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>1.80 * <lb/>0.18 <lb/>1,444 * <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1.84 * <lb/>0.30 <lb/>880 ** <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>15 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>1.91 * <lb/>0.11 <lb/>1,332 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>1.90 * <lb/>0.15 <lb/>813 * <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-6 <lb/>4 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-521 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>-0.67 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>-362 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>17 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>119 <lb/>-0.23 <lb/>-1.31 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-578 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>1.86 * <lb/>0.39 <lb/>364 * <lb/>6 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>62 <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.18 <lb/>-317 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>203 <lb/>7 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>-1.18 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-1418 * <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.39 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-314 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>-1.64 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-337 * <lb/>8 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>536 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>182 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>113 <lb/>9 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>2.38 ** <lb/>0.28 <lb/>1,834 ** <lb/>0.44 <lb/>2.97 *** <lb/>0.32 <lb/>1,118 *** <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>18 <lb/>10 <lb/>-0.12 <lb/>-0.82 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>-957 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.70 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-446 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.42 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>-86 <lb/>Day is the date of the announcement of the introduction of the long-term shareholder perks program as base date 0. <lb/>A t-test and a Wilcoxon rank sum test are conducted using mean = 0 and median = 0 for AR as the null hypotheses, respectively. <lb/>***, **, and * indicate statistical significance at 1%, 5%, and 10% levels, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>The findings indicate that the introduction of long-term shareholder perks has a positive <lb/>stock price effect in the favorable change case, whereas the introduction of long-term share-<lb/>holder perks did not have a positive effect on stock prices in the case of an unfavorable change <lb/>for new individual investors or for those who intended to hold the shares for a short period of <lb/>time; however, negative stock price effects are also not observed in the case of an unfavorable <lb/>change. <lb/>Changes in shareholder base <lb/>The primary purpose of publicly traded companies introducing shareholder perk programs is <lb/>to attract individual investors. Previous studies have shown that the number of individual <lb/>investors increases significantly in companies that introduce new shareholder perk programs <lb/>[2,18]. Does the introduction of long-term shareholder perks increase the number of individ-<lb/>ual investors? <lb/>Table 7 presents the changes in the ratio of individual shareholders (number of individual <lb/>shareholders divided by the total number of shareholders) and the ratio of individual share-<lb/>holder holdings (number of individual shareholder holdings divided by the number of shares <lb/>outstanding) before and after the introduction of the long-term shareholder perks program <lb/>(the period immediately before and after the introduction). <lb/>The top panel of the table shows the before and after of the sample itself, without calculating <lb/>the difference from the control sample. The average of all samples shows that the share of indi-<lb/>vidual shareholders increased by 0.15 percentage points after the changes. When the sample is <lb/>Table 6. Test results for Cumulative Abnormal Return (CAR). <lb/>Panel A <lb/>All samples <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test statistic <lb/>CAR(day0!+1) <lb/>203 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>3.66 *** <lb/>0.77 <lb/>3133 *** <lb/>Panel B <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test statistic <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test statistic <lb/>CAR(day0!+1) <lb/>128 <lb/>1.26 <lb/>3.79 *** <lb/>0.84 <lb/>1484 *** <lb/>75 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>297 <lb/>*** indicates statistical significance at the 1% level. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t006 <lb/>Table 7. Changes in the ratio of individual shareholders and individual shareholdings. <lb/>Individual Shareholder Ratio <lb/>Individual Shareholding Ratio <lb/>n <lb/>Mean of Difference <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median of Difference Test statistic Mean of Difference <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median of Difference <lb/>Test <lb/>statistic <lb/>No adjustment <lb/>All samples <lb/>202 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>2.42 <lb/>** <lb/>0.04 <lb/>1,605 <lb/>* <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>138 <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>127 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>3.09 <lb/>*** <lb/>0.06 <lb/>1,063 <lb/>*** <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>-90 <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>75 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.93 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-56 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>121 <lb/>DID <lb/>All samples <lb/>202 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>269 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>714 <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>127 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>*** <lb/>0.08 <lb/>790 <lb/>* <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>325 <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>75 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-1.78 <lb/>* <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>-378 <lb/>** <lb/>0.74 <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>97 <lb/>***, **, and * indicate statistical significance at 1%, 5%, and 10% levels, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t007 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>divided into favorable and unfavorable changes, an increase of 0.27 percentage points results <lb/>for favorable changes, which is significant at the 1% level. The lower panel of Table 7 shows the <lb/>DID results adjusted for change in the control sample that are selected using PSM. An increase <lb/>of 0.23 percentage points is observed in the sample of favorable changes, which is significant at <lb/>the 1% level. The median test is also significantly positive at the 10% level. In the case of favor-<lb/>able changes, long-term shareholder perks appear to have the effect of increasing the number <lb/>of individual shareholders or the shareholder base. When the shareholder base expands, inves-<lb/>tors with diverse opinions gather, and this collective knowledge lowers the transaction costs <lb/>associated with information asymmetry, which then lowers the overall cost of capital and has a <lb/>positive impact on stock prices [20]. We interpret the positive CAR as indicating that investors <lb/>who encountered the announcement of long-term shareholder perks anticipated a subsequent <lb/>decrease in the cost of capital due to an expected increase in the number of individual <lb/>shareholders. <lb/>Conversely, the number of individual shareholders decreases in the unfavorable change <lb/>sample, although no significant positive stock price effect was observed. The DID results show <lb/>that the mean and median are -0.17 percentage points and -0.11 percentage points, significant <lb/>at 10% and 5% level, respectively. Our interpretation of this phenomenon is as follows. <lb/>First, an unfavorable change in long-term shareholder perks is effective in retaining existing <lb/>individual shareholders. However, it must be noted that not all individual shareholders invest <lb/>with the primary goal of obtaining these perks. While these perks may be attractive, various <lb/>other factors can influence shareholders to sell their shares. In the event of a favorable change, <lb/>an increase in new individual shareholders is expected, which could compensate for any <lb/>decrease in the existing shareholder base. Conversely, an unfavorable change is less attractive <lb/>to new individual shareholders; therefore, the number of individual shareholders is reduced <lb/>overall. <lb/>Second, individual investors may assess whether a change is favorable or unfavorable at the <lb/>same time the long-term shareholder perk is announced. In Japan, information is actively <lb/>shared through social networking services, and notably unfavorable changes may be reported <lb/>as &quot;sad news.&quot; Such information sharing could serve as a signal for potential reduction in the <lb/>number of new individual shareholders. <lb/>Third, although unfavorable changes in long-term shareholder perks lead to a decrease in <lb/>the number of new individual shareholders and cause a decrease in the overall number of indi-<lb/>vidual shareholders, they do not have a negative impact on the share price, at least not because <lb/>of the benefits favoring existing individual shareholders. <lb/>Individual shareholdings does not change significantly in either the unadjusted analysis or <lb/>the DID for both the favorable and unfavorable change samples. Although the number of indi-<lb/>vidual shareholders increases with a favorable change, it does not significantly increase the per-<lb/>centage of individual shareholdings. Unlike institutional investors, individual shareholders <lb/>have limited purchasing power. In addition, the yield on shareholder perks tends to be highest <lb/>at a minimum lot of 100 shares, and new individual shareholders prefer to invest small <lb/>amounts at the minimum lot; therefore, the number of shares held by individual shareholders <lb/>does not increase as much as the number of shareholders. <lb/>Changes in equity liquidity <lb/>The introduction of new shareholder perk programs increases stock liquidity [18]. In contrast, <lb/>some scholars have suggested that long-term shareholder perk programs have a negative <lb/>impact on liquidity by immobilizing individual shareholders [6]. These previous studies intro-<lb/>duced conceptual considerations, and the quantitative empirical results were unclear. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Therefore, we measure stock liquidity before and after the introduction of long-term share-<lb/>holder perks. <lb/>Table 8 presents the quote and execution spread from 120 business days before to 21 busi-<lb/>ness days before the announcement of the long-term shareholder perk (day-120 to -21) and <lb/>from day+21 to +120. Each represents the amount of change before and after the announce-<lb/>ment. The left-hand side presents the results of the sample only. For the total sample, the <lb/>quoted spread is reduced by -0.007 percentage points on average and by -0.004 percentage <lb/>points at the median. The average and median execution spreads are also reduced by -0.004 <lb/>percentage points and -0.002 percentage points, respectively. Splitting the sample into favor-<lb/>able and unfavorable change categories indicates that the spread reduction is more pro-<lb/>nounced for favorable changes; however, neither the t-test for the mean nor the Wilcoxson <lb/>signed rank test for the median is significant. <lb/>The right-hand side of Table 8 shows the DID results. For favorable change, the quote <lb/>spread is -0.049 percentage points lower on average and -0.008 percentage points lower at the <lb/>median. The execution spread is significant at 10% and 5% levels, with respective mean and <lb/>median decreases of -0.021 percentage points and -0.009 percentage points. <lb/>Long-term shareholder perk plans are found to produce additional spread reductions <lb/>(improved liquidity) in the case of favorable changes. We interpret the liquidity improvement <lb/>effect of a larger shareholder base as outweighing the negative effect of an increase in long <lb/>term individual shareholders. In contrast, in the case of an unfavorable change, the spread <lb/>does not change before adjustment or DID. Equity liquidity was not worsened by the unfavor-<lb/>able change. <lb/>Will the improvement in equity liquidity observed in Table 8 be sustained in the long run, <lb/>or will liquidity deteriorate, as Yasutake and Nagata (2022) contended, due to the immobiliza-<lb/>tion of individual shareholders? Table 9 presents the DID results for Amihud&apos;s (2002) illiquid-<lb/>ity [6]. <lb/>The starting point of the analysis is year-1, which is 360 business days (1.5 years ago, day-<lb/>360) to 120 business days (6 months ago, day-120) from the announcement date of the long-<lb/>Table 8. Change in equity liquidity (short-term). <lb/>Difference in Quote Spread <lb/>Difference of Execution <lb/>Spread <lb/>DID of Quote Spread <lb/>DID of Execution Spread <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>Mean <lb/>Median <lb/>All samples <lb/>203 -0.007 <lb/>-0.004 <lb/>-0.004 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>-0.006 <lb/>-0.014 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>* <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>128 -0.021 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>-0.049 <lb/>-0.008 <lb/>-0.021 <lb/>* <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>** <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>75 <lb/>0.026 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>-0.000 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>0.011 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>-0.007 <lb/>** and * indicate statistical significance at 5% and 10% levels, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t008 <lb/>Table 9. Changes in equity liquidity (long-term). <lb/>DID_Iliquidity (y-1!y+1) <lb/>DID_Iliquidity (y-1!y+2) <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median <lb/>Test statistic <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>t-value <lb/>Median Test statistic <lb/>All samples <lb/>194 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>1,084 <lb/>192 <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>-1.044 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>720 <lb/>Favorable change <lb/>123 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-1.32 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>115 <lb/>121 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.818 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>188 <lb/>Unfavorable change <lb/>71 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.1766 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>361 ** <lb/>71 <lb/>-0.021 <lb/>-0.707 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>177 <lb/>Illiquidity is the percentage change in the share price (in percentage points) relative to the trading value of 1 million yen <lb/>** indicates statistical significance at the 5% level. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t009 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>term shareholder perk. The endpoints of the analysis are year+1, from 121 business days to <lb/>360 business days later (day+121 to +360), and year+2, from 361 business days to 600 business <lb/>days later (day+361 to +600). <lb/>No statistically significant change is observed in Amihud&apos;s (2002) illiquidity from year-1 to <lb/>year+1 and year-1 to year+2 in the favorable change sample. We determine the favorable <lb/>change does not lead to the worsening liquidity that previous studies have warned of. Con-<lb/>versely, the change was positive (i.e., worsening liquidity) for the unfavorable change sample <lb/>from year-1 to year+1, and the median is significant at the 5% level. Unfavorable changes are <lb/>changes that reduce investors&apos; incentives to trade in the short term. Yasutake and Nagata <lb/>(2022) demonstrated a positive correlation between the introduction of long-term perks and <lb/>increased illiquidity (worsened liquidity). However, their analysis did not differentiate between <lb/>favorable and unfavorable changes within their sample. Our results suggest that the positive <lb/>correlation observed by Yasutake and Nagata (2022) was predominantly influenced by the <lb/>sample representing unfavorable changes. <lb/>Cross trading (bridge selling) was introduced in Nose et al.(2021), referring to a transaction <lb/>in which the purchase of cash shares is combined with the margin sale on the last day of the <lb/>shareholder perk rights period to obtain the perk without incurring the risk of price fluctua-<lb/>tion [3]. Cross trading is an extremely short-term transaction, but it provides equity liquidity; <lb/>however, in the event of unfavorable change, investors do not receive shareholder perk in <lb/>cross trades. We contend that the deterioration of liquidity from unfavorable change is due to <lb/>a decrease in the number of short-term individual investors who are interested in trading, <lb/>such as cross traders. <lb/>Sources of CAR <lb/>The introduction of a favorable change to the long-term shareholder perk program yields a sig-<lb/>nificant positive abnormal return. The next question is what is the source of the returns? To <lb/>examine this question, we conduct a cross-sectional regression analysis using the CAR (CAR <lb/>0,+1) between the announcement date and the following day for each sample firm as the <lb/>explained variable, and the favorable change dummy, DID for the ratio of individual share-<lb/>holders, and DID for the ratio of individual shareholdings as explanatory variables. Table 10 <lb/>presents the results. In Model 1, the favorable change dummy is not significantly correlated <lb/>with the CAR. It seems that simply a favorable change does not generate additional returns. <lb/>On the other hand, in Model 2, the individual shareholder ratio DID show a significant posi-<lb/>tive correlation with the CAR at the 5% level. As shown in Table 10, the long-term shareholder <lb/>perk is a measure to raise the number of individual shareholders through the introduction of a <lb/>new shareholder perk program. The introduction of the long-term shareholder perk has a pos-<lb/>itive impact on stock prices due to the market&apos;s expectation of an expansion in the shareholder <lb/>base. Model 3 examines the DID of individual investor shareholdings, which is not signifi-<lb/>cantly correlated with the CAR. <lb/>Table 11 presents the results of the hypotheses tested. First, announcements of long-term <lb/>shareholder perks programs had a positive stock price effect in the favorable change sample; <lb/>thus, H1 is supported for the favorable change sample. Second, the number of individual <lb/>shareholders increased before and after the introduction of the program for favorable change. <lb/>Moreover, the CAR is statistically significant and positively correlated with the increase in the <lb/>number of individual shareholders. This suggests that the expected increase in individual <lb/>shareholders is a source of abnormal returns, and H2-1 is supported for the favorable change. <lb/>The shareholding ratio of individual shareholders was uncorrelated. Third, in the favorable <lb/>change sample, the stock price spread narrowed before and after the introduction of the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>program. In contrast, long-term stock liquidity worsened with the unfavorable change, but did <lb/>not change with the favorable change; thus, H2-2 is validated for the favorable change. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>This study examines the impact and source of announcements introducing long-term share-<lb/>holder perks on stock prices of Japanese listed companies in the 11-year period from 2010 to <lb/>the end of March 2021. We produce more precise analysis results by categorizing the total <lb/>sample of 203 firms into 128 firms with favorable change and 75 firms with unfavorable <lb/>change. <lb/>Table 11. Results of hypotheses testing. <lb/>Hypothesis <lb/>Proxy Variables for <lb/>Hypotheses <lb/>Mark <lb/>Result <lb/>H1 Announcement of a favorable long-term shareholder perk <lb/>program generates a positive stock return. <lb/>CAR (0, +1) <lb/>Positive Supported <lb/>H2-<lb/>1 <lb/>Stock return is positively correlated with an increase in the ratio of <lb/>individual shareholders. <lb/>DID_Ratio of individual <lb/>shareholders <lb/>Positive Supported <lb/>DID_Individual <lb/>Shareholding Ratio <lb/>Positive Unsupported <lb/>H2-<lb/>2 <lb/>Stock return is positively correlated with stock liquidity <lb/>Quote/Execution Spread <lb/>Negative Supported <lb/>DID_illiquidity <lb/>Negative Indirectly supported (illiquidity worsened in <lb/>unfavorable change sample) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t011 <lb/>Table 10. Results of cross-sectional regression analysis. <lb/>Explained Variables: CAR (0, -1) <lb/>Model 1 <lb/>Model 2 <lb/>Model 3 <lb/>Favorable Change Dummy <lb/>0.742 <lb/>(0.635) <lb/>Ratio of individual shareholders y-1 <lb/>-0.058 <lb/>(0.115) <lb/>DID individual shareholder ratio <lb/>0.663 ** <lb/>(0.326) <lb/>Individual shareholding ratio y-1 <lb/>-0.021 <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>DID individual shareholding ratio <lb/>-0.006 <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>ln Total Assets <lb/>-0.475 *** <lb/>-0.469 ** <lb/>-0.611 *** <lb/>(0.182) <lb/>(0.184) <lb/>(0.234) <lb/>ROA <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>-0.007 <lb/>(0.068) <lb/>(0.067) <lb/>(0.070) <lb/>PBR <lb/>-0.119 <lb/>-0.084 <lb/>-0.152 <lb/>(0.172) <lb/>(0.171) <lb/>(0.171) <lb/>Intercept <lb/>6.087 *** <lb/>11.969 <lb/>9.007 *** <lb/>(2.170) <lb/>(11.828) <lb/>(3.321) <lb/>Adjusted R-square <lb/>0.023 <lb/>0.038 <lb/>0.017 <lb/>n <lb/>187 <lb/>187 <lb/>187 <lb/>Figures in parentheses represent standard errors <lb/>***, **, and * indicate statistical significance at the 1%, 5%, and 10% level, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284.t010 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>First, an event study confirms the short-term impact on stock prices. As a result, we reveal a <lb/>significant positive stock price effect in the favorable change sample. We next examine changes <lb/>in the number of shareholders before and after the introduction of the long-term shareholder <lb/>program, uncovering an increasing trend for favorable changes and a decreasing trend for <lb/>unfavorable changes. In a multiple regression analysis using CAR as the explained variable, <lb/>CAR was significantly correlated with an increase in the number of individual shareholders <lb/>after the introduction of the program. <lb/>In summary, four notable points are found in this study. First, a favorable change in the <lb/>long-term shareholder perks program has a positive short-term impact on stock prices. Sec-<lb/>ond, a favorable change increases the number of individual shareholders after its introduction. <lb/>Third, there is a positive correlation between the stock price effect and the rate of increase in <lb/>the number of individual shareholders, indicating that the source of the stock price effect is <lb/>investors&apos; expectation that the long-term shareholder perk will further increase the number of <lb/>shareholders. Fourth, unfavorable changes tend to have a negative impact on the number of <lb/>individual shareholders and stock liquidity. <lb/>Finally, by categorizing the long-term shareholder perks program into favorable and unfa-<lb/>vorable changes, this study conducts a more comprehensive investigation into the effects of <lb/>long-term shareholder perks programs. However, shareholder perk programs significantly dif-<lb/>fer from other forms of payouts due to the wide variety of items offered. Dividends represent <lb/>just one type of benefit. Each company presents its unique items, such as branded products, <lb/>shopping coupons, and regional local specialties from the company&apos;s location. Thus, a detailed <lb/>analysis examining long-term shareholder perks by item type is the next crucial step. The yield <lb/>on shareholder perks also warrants attention. Unlike dividends, the yield on shareholder perks <lb/>cannot be straightforwardly calculated; therefore, developing a highly precise method for cal-<lb/>culating a &apos;yield on perks&apos; is essential. Previous studies have indicated that the introduction of <lb/>the first shareholder perks program leads to a reduction in the cost of equity capital. While not <lb/>presented in this paper, we examined the correlation between the cost of equity capital (as per <lb/>the CAPM model) and CARs in our samples. However, we were unable to draw any conclu-<lb/>sions, either positive or negative, perhaps due to the limited size of the sample. Hence, these <lb/>additional tests will be the focus of future research. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Dataset. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 File. Excel files for figures and tables. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/>Data curation: Yao Gao. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/>Investigation: Yao Gao. <lb/>Project administration: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/>Resources: Yao Gao. <lb/>Software: Yao Gao. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Supervision: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/>Validation: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/>Visualization: Yao Gao. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Yao Gao. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Yoshiaki Nose. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Huang W, Rhee SG, Suzuki K, Yasutake T. Do investors value shareholder perks? Evidence from <lb/>Japan. Journal of Banking &amp; Finance. 2022; 143:106575. <lb/>2. Karpoff JM, Schonlau R, Suzuki K. Shareholder perks and firm value. The Review of Financial Studies. <lb/>2021; 34(12):5676-722. <lb/>3. Nose Y, Miyagawa H, Ito A. How do firms attract the attention of individual investors? Shareholder <lb/>perks and financial visibility. Journal of Behavioral and Experimental Finance. 2021; 31:100520. <lb/>4. Lim K-P, Liu W, Chia Y-E. Firm location, investor recognition, and the liquidity of Chinese publicly listed <lb/>SMEs. Borsa Istanbul Review. 2023; 23(2):334-49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bir.2022.11.002 <lb/>5. Isagawa N, Suzuki K, Yamaguchi S. Complimentary Tickets, Stock Liquidity, and Stock Prices: Evi-<lb/>dence from Japan. Kobe University discussion paper series. 2008; 33. (in Japanese). <lb/>6. Yasutake T, Nagata K A good way to attract individual retail investors?: Field evidence on shareholder <lb/>perks program in Japan. Proceedings of JFA-PBFJ Special Issue Conference. 2022. <lb/>7. Yasutake T. Analyses of the shareholder benefit program in Japan. Theses for the degree of Doctor of <lb/>Philosophy (University of Hawaii at Manoa). 2012. <lb/>8. Chen L, Matsuura Y, Tareq M, Akhtar T. Does the Retail Shareholder-Increasing Strategy Benefit Long-<lb/>Term Management?-Evidence of Shareholder Perks Program in Japan. Available at SSRN: https:// <lb/>ssrn.com/abstract=4438740. 2023. <lb/>9. Suzuki K. Unique dividends for retail shareholders: Evidence from shareholder perks. Kobe University <lb/>discussion paper series. 2015; 20. (in Japanese). https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2615777 <lb/>10. Daiwa Investor Relations Co.Ltd.. Shareholder Perk Guide 2023. 2022. (in Japanese). <lb/>11. Nose Y. A survey on various drives for implementations of shareholder benefit plans.St Andrew&apos;s uni-<lb/>versity Economic and Business Review. 2014; 55(3):153-68. (in Japanese). <lb/>12. Yasutake T, Nagata K. A survey of shareholder perk practices in Japanese firms. The JSRI Journal of <lb/>Financial and Securities Markets. 2018;(104):61-78. (in Japanese). <lb/>13. Modigliani F, Miller MH. The cost of capital, corporation finance and the theory of investment. The Amer-<lb/>ican economic review. 1958; 48(3):261-97. <lb/>14. Nose Y, Miyagawa H, Ito A. The original effect of shareholder perks on stock prices. Securities Analysts <lb/>Journal. 2017; 55(10):82-93. (in Japanese). <lb/>15. Serita T. The Impact of Shareholder Perks on Risks of Stocks: Role of Small Investors. 30th Austral-<lb/>asian Finance and Banking Conference; 2017. <lb/>16. Uchida Y, Chen X, Tongurai J. Shareholder Perks and Stock Performance: Evidence during the Global <lb/>Financial Crisis. Journal of Asia-Pacific Business. 2022; 23(4):338-59. <lb/>17. Amihud Y. Illiquidity and stock returns: cross-section and time-series effects. Journal of financial mar-<lb/>kets. 2002; 5(1):31-56. <lb/>18. Suzuki K. Isagawa N. The short-term impact of the introduction of shareholder perks: An examination of <lb/>stock liquidity and announcement effects. Securities analysts journal. 2008; 46(7):107-21.(in <lb/>Japanese). <lb/>19. Amihud Y, Mendelson H. Asset pricing and the bid-ask spread. Journal of financial Economics. 1986; <lb/>17(2):223-49. <lb/>20. Merton RC. A simple model of capital market equilibrium with incomplete information. The Journal of <lb/>Finance. 1987; 42(3):483-510. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Long-term shareholder perks <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300284 April 18, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 19 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>