<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T15:03:48.570Z">11/14/2025 3:03:48 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T15:03:36.718841Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T15:03:36.718841Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Landscape of toxin-neutralizing therapeutics <lb/>for snakebite envenoming (2015-2022): <lb/>Setting the stage for an R&amp;D agenda <lb/>Juliette Borri ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Jose ´Marı ´a Gutie ´rrez 2 , Cecilie Knudsen 3 , Abdulrazaq G. Habib 4 , <lb/>Maya Goldstein 1 , Andrew Tuttle 1 <lb/>1 Policy Cures Research, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia, 2 Instituto Clodomiro Picado, Facultad de <lb/>Microbiologı ´a, Universidad de Costa Rica, San Jose ´, Costa Rica, 3 VenomAid Diagnostics, Lyngby, <lb/>Denmark, 4 Infectious and Tropical Diseases Unit, Department of Medicine, Bayero University, Kano, Nigeria <lb/>* jborri@policycuresresearch.org <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background <lb/>Progress in snakebite envenoming (SBE) therapeutics has suffered from a critical lack of <lb/>data on the research and development (R&amp;D) landscape. A database characterising this <lb/>information would be a powerful tool for coordinating and accelerating SBE R&amp;D. To <lb/>address this need, we aimed to identify and categorise all active investigational candidates <lb/>in development for SBE and all available or marketed products. <lb/>Methodology/Principal findings <lb/>In this landscape study, publicly available data and literature were reviewed to canvas the <lb/>state of the SBE therapeutics market and research pipeline by identifying, characterising, <lb/>and validating all investigational drug and biologic candidates with direct action on snake <lb/>venom toxins, and all products available or marketed from 2015 to 2022. We identified 127 <lb/>marketed products and 196 candidates in the pipeline, describing a very homogenous mar-<lb/>ket of similar but geographically bespoke products and a diverse but immature pipeline, as <lb/>most investigational candidates are at an early stage of development, with only eight candi-<lb/>dates in clinical development. <lb/>Conclusions/Significance <lb/>Further investment and research is needed to address the shortfalls in products already on <lb/>the market and to accelerate R&amp;D for new therapeutics. This should be accompanied by <lb/>efforts to converge on shared priorities and reshape the current SBE R&amp;D ecosystem to <lb/>ensure translation of innovation and access. <lb/>PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/>1 / 13 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Borri J, Gutie ´rrez JM, Knudsen C, Habib <lb/>AG, Goldstein M, Tuttle A (2024) Landscape of <lb/>toxin-neutralizing therapeutics for snakebite <lb/>envenoming (2015-2022): Setting the stage for an <lb/>R&amp;D agenda. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 18(3): <lb/>e0012052. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pntd.0012052 <lb/>Editor: Wuelton M. Monteiro, Fundac ¸ão de <lb/>Medicina Tropical Doutor Heitor Vieira Dourado, <lb/>BRAZIL <lb/>Received: October 5, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: March 5, 2024 <lb/>Published: March 26, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Borri et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Product and <lb/>candidate data and methodology that underly the <lb/>results reported in this article are already publicly <lb/>available at https://www.policycuresresearch.org/ <lb/>sbe-medicines-database/. Requests for further <lb/>information and questions can be sent to Policy <lb/>Cures Research, requests should be directed to <lb/>info@policycuresresearch.org. Separately, financial <lb/>information on funding for SBE R&amp;D is publicly <lb/>Author summary <lb/>Snakebite envenoming (SBE) is a neglected tropical disease that exerts a high impact <lb/>worldwide, especially in sub-Saharan Africa, Asia, and Latin America. Animal-derived <lb/>antivenoms constitute the only specific, scientifically validated treatment for envenom-<lb/>ings, although new therapeutic alternatives are being pursued. Despite the relevance of <lb/>this disease, there is a critical lack of data on the research and development landscape in <lb/>antivenoms and novel therapeutics. This study describes a thorough search of the state of <lb/>SBE therapeutic market and research pipeline. A total of 127 marketed products and 196 <lb/>candidates were identified. The current antivenom landscape is characterised by a homo-<lb/>geneous market of similar but geographically bespoke products needing improvement. <lb/>The R&amp;D pipeline analysis component revealed a diverse but immature picture since only <lb/>eight candidates are in clinical development. This article interprets the findings of the <lb/>study to provide an initial list of priority areas that sets the stage for further development <lb/>of an R&amp;D agenda to ensure translation of innovation to reduce the impact of SBE. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Snakebite envenoming (SBE) is a complex and neglected global health challenge that kills and <lb/>injures hundreds of thousands of people every year, especially in impoverished rural commu-<lb/>nities in Africa, Asia, and Latin America [1]. In recent years, a concerted effort to raise the pro-<lb/>file of SBE and stimulate investment in R&amp;D has yielded positive outcomes. This includes the <lb/>official inclusion of SBE in the World Health Organization (WHO) Neglected Tropical Disease <lb/>(NTD) portfolio in 2017, a resolution on SBE adopted by the World Health Assembly in 2018, <lb/>and the launch of the WHO 2019-2030 roadmap to prevent and control SBE in 2019 [2,3]. <lb/>Looking to R&amp;D, the community has seen progress in the development of the WHO Target <lb/>Product Profile for sub-Saharan African antivenoms [4], a WHO risk-benefit assessment pro-<lb/>gram for antivenoms [5], and a set of global core outcome measurements for clinical trials on <lb/>SBE [6]. As work in this space progresses, there is a continued and growing need to provide <lb/>the sector with data and information to guide funding decisions and research agendas. <lb/>SBE R&amp;D funding has benefitted from four years of consecutive growth from 2018-2021, <lb/>with more funding invested in that period than in the decade from 2007-2017 [7]. SBE has <lb/>been one of the only WHO NTDs to see increased funding, with many of the other diseases <lb/>experiencing a decline or plateau in recent years [8]. Despite this positive trend, there is con-<lb/>cern around the sustainability of funding and how it will impact translating research into real-<lb/>word solutions. Funding for SBE R&amp;D is concentrated in a select number of both private and <lb/>public backers and is heavily project-linked. As a result, shifts in individual funders and proj-<lb/>ects could potentially severely set back the SBE R&amp;D landscape. Much of the growth in the sec-<lb/>tor has been associated with UK public and philanthropic funders, specifically Wellcome&apos;s £80 <lb/>million programme [8], which has facilitated important basic and early-stage research and <lb/>resolved several barriers to generating knowledge. However, it is due to end in 2026. Another <lb/>top funder of SBE R&amp;D has been the US Department of Defense (DOD), which currently only <lb/>invests in one product developer for one drug, with future investment in SBE research not <lb/>guaranteed. Since 2018, the collective share of total funding from Wellcome and the US DOD <lb/>has risen from a low of 7% in 2019, to 71% in 2022 [8]. Having the bulk of SBE R&amp;D funding <lb/>concentrated in two funders is risky for the sector, even more so when these are not sustainable <lb/>streams. To date, most of the funding has also focused on early-stage R&amp;D, highlighting a lack <lb/>of interest and investment in late-stage R&amp;D, as well as implementation and operational <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<front>available through the G-FINDER portal at https:// <lb/>gfinderdata.policycuresresearch.org/. <lb/>Funding: This analysis was commissioned by <lb/>Wellcome (www.wellcome.org). JB, MG and AT <lb/>received funding from Wellcome for this project. <lb/>The funder provided high-level input to determine <lb/>the scope of the work (inclusion criteria, product <lb/>types and sub-types, timeframe) and signed-off on <lb/>the matrix for data collection which was put <lb/>together by Policy Cures Research with advice <lb/>from the Advisory Committee. The funder had no <lb/>role in the methodology design, data collection, <lb/>data analysis, data interpretation, or writing of the <lb/>article. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/>following competing interests: JMG works at <lb/>Instituto Clodomiro Picado (Universidad de Costa <lb/>Rica), a public research centre and antivenom <lb/>manufacturer. CK works at VenomAid Diagnostics, <lb/>a private company researching diagnostics for <lb/>snakebite. <lb/></front>

	<body>research, manufacturing, and access activities. Actions need to be taken to ensure the transla-<lb/>tion of research from basic and early-stage into clinical development will be resourced and to <lb/>sustain the momentum the sector has garnered to deliver new products to those that need <lb/>them the most. <lb/>Essential to achieving this will be overcoming certain structural issues in the SBE R&amp;D eco-<lb/>system to guarantee a diversified set of investors and portfolios. The solutions to these chal-<lb/>lenges are not yet clear but require robust information about the SBE R&amp;D landscape-data <lb/>which has been previously missing, incomplete, or out-of-date. Here we summarise the results <lb/>of a recent, comprehensive landscape analysis conducted to better understand the state of the <lb/>research pipeline for novel therapeutics and the antivenom market for SBE. It builds on a <lb/>series of foundational reviews on antivenoms [9-11], novel and repurposed drugs, and biolog-<lb/>ics as potential SBE therapeutics [12-17] and diagnostics [18]. The study provides critical data <lb/>to begin asking and answering key questions about the future of the SBE R&amp;D landscape. <lb/>Several reviews on various aspects of the SBE R&amp;D landscape have been undertaken in the <lb/>last decade. These include reviews of the clinical status of available antivenoms in sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa; systematic reviews of clinical outcome measures for SBE in randomised control trials; <lb/>the SBE diagnostic pipeline; small molecule therapies (SMTs) and repurposed drugs; plant <lb/>polyphenols; and traditional medicine as potential SBE therapeutics. Also, prior to this study, <lb/>several comprehensive overviews of novel small molecules and biologics with snake toxin neu-<lb/>tralisation abilities have been published. <lb/>While previous reviews have been critical sources of information on the therapeutics pipe-<lb/>line and market, the last comprehensive landscaping was done in 2018, and only for new thera-<lb/>peutics, not current therapies. The recent years of advancement in SBE R&amp;D funding warrant <lb/>updating the community&apos;s knowledge of the full spectrum of candidates under development <lb/>and products currently available or in use (from 2015-2022). To this end, a database was cre-<lb/>ated based on interactive, open-source information of candidate and product profiles. The <lb/>database includes 127 available products and 196 investigational candidates (in various stages <lb/>of development) and provides a unique, unified data source with standardised information, <lb/>contributing to improved transparency and clarity of the landscape. <lb/>By presenting insight into the state of the current SBE R&amp;D landscape for new and existing <lb/>therapeutics, our results encourage further investment and research into improving products <lb/>on the market as well as maintaining and accelerating development for investigational candi-<lb/>dates to ensure that more products not only reach clinical development but can exit the pipe-<lb/>line. This database contributes to a growing body of evidence on SBE that will shape the R&amp;D <lb/>landscape and inform decisions on how research is prioritised. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Scope <lb/>We established a comprehensive database profiling (a) all drugs and biologics registered and/ <lb/>or available for the treatment of SBE (with direct action on toxins) since 2015 (&apos;products&apos;) and <lb/>(b) all drugs and biologics investigated as potential SBE therapeutics (with direct action on tox-<lb/>ins) since 2015 (&apos;investigational candidates&apos;). Specific exclusions were: adjunct and supportive <lb/>therapies that only modify immune responses and clinical manifestations caused by snake <lb/>venom toxins, including products related to wound and adverse reaction management; <lb/>devices, diagnostics, and other non-medicine-related biomedical products with an indication <lb/>for SBE; and basic and fundamental research not geared towards product development. Fur-<lb/>ther scope considerations are described in detail in S1 Text. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>Development of a medicines database <lb/>The complete methodology of how this database was developed is described in detail in S1 <lb/>Text. To summarise, we undertook a series of partially sequential, partly overlapping, but <lb/>mutually reinforcing steps to develop a database of product and candidate profiles. These <lb/>were: (a) identify and validate products and candidates that are or were in use or in develop-<lb/>ment since 2015 through multiple sources; (b) collect information on the products&apos; and candi-<lb/>dates&apos; preclinical and/or clinical development, and associated data; (c) research additional <lb/>context around the products and candidates (e.g., paraspecificity) to build out individual <lb/>multi-field profiles; (4) validate and sense check candidate profiles through independent, <lb/>external reviews by experts in the field. Fig 1 outlines the methodology followed in the study. <lb/>For the initial candidate and product identification, multiple sources were used to identify <lb/>and retrieve information on individual entries. We searched Adis Insight for up-to-date infor-<lb/>mation on relevant drugs and biologics investigated for SBE. The WHO Snakebite Information <lb/>and Data portal, specifically the Antivenom and Manufacturers table, was searched to extract a <lb/>Fig 1. Methodology flow chart (adapted from McDougall et al., 2022) [19]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>list of marketed products with relevant information on species indication, manufacturers, and <lb/>registration. Data was also extracted from the WHO International Clinical Trials Registry Plat-<lb/>form (ICTRP), which served a dual function of uncovering additional products and/or candi-<lb/>dates for inclusion that had not yet been identified, as well as capturing and linking clinical <lb/>trial data to candidates and products marked for inclusion in the database. The G-FINDER <lb/>R&amp;D funding database, which includes funding from public, private and philanthropic organi-<lb/>sations from HICs and LMICs, was reviewed for relevant grant descriptions. An overview of <lb/>organisations that have participated in the G-FINDER survey over the years can be found on <lb/>the online portal. Publicly available databases from three of the largest funders of medicines <lb/>development were also datamined: the United States National Institutes of Health (US NIH)&apos;s <lb/>RePORTER; the European Commission&apos;s CORDIS; and the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Founda-<lb/>tion&apos;s (BMGF) grants database (data supplied by the Foundation); as well as those of two <lb/>major global funders of SBE therapeutics R&amp;D with available online data: Wellcome&apos;s grant <lb/>funding and the US Department of Defense (DOD) via USASpending.gov. A literature review <lb/>was also conducted using PubMed to validate already identified products and candidates as <lb/>well as uncover new ones for inclusion. Product and candidate entries were not only reviewed <lb/>and de-duplicated at first instance, but results from the different data sources were then com-<lb/>bined and again de-duplicated to ensure maximum coverage, while only unique entries were <lb/>included. <lb/>Much of the information needed to complete profiles were provided through Steps (a) and <lb/>(b). In addition, we conducted desk-based research to source greater detail and context e.g., <lb/>developer websites, grant descriptions, and regulatory documents. Following database comple-<lb/>tion, a series of internal and external independent reviews were undertaken to clean, cross-<lb/>check and validate the data. We sought independent input from members of the project&apos;s <lb/>external expert advisory group. The entire database was reviewed to validate entries or identify <lb/>missing candidates or products; review essential standard labels; and for each, recommend <lb/>corrections, improvements, or additional details. This methodology has been previously vali-<lb/>dated by Policy Cures Research through an earlier project mapping the landscape of the mater-<lb/>nal health medicines pipeline [20]. <lb/>Results <lb/>The result of this landscape analysis was the identification of 127 marketed and/or available <lb/>products since 2015, along with 196 therapeutic candidates which have been actively investi-<lb/>gated in the same period (Fig 2). The landscapes of products and candidates are strikingly dif-<lb/>ferent, highlighting major differences in product types, sub-types, and R&amp;D stage. <lb/>Marketed and/or available products <lb/>We identified an extremely homogenous market of 127 animal-plasma derived immunoglobu-<lb/>lin-based antivenoms with no recombinant-based products and no drug treatments available <lb/>for SBE. Nearly half of all products (61, 48%) are intended for use in the three regions with rec-<lb/>ognised high burdens of SBE: Southeast Asia (23, 18%), South America (20, 16%) and sub-<lb/>Saharan Africa (18, 14%). Looking at the geography of manufacturers, we found that most <lb/>products were produced for domestic needs within the manufacturer&apos;s country or region. <lb/>There was only one manufacturer in sub-Saharan Africa: South African Vaccine Producers. <lb/>Almost all products manufactured for international use (largely for the African market) were <lb/>from private companies, with just one public manufacturer, Instituto Clodomiro Picado from <lb/>Costa Rica. This highlights a concerning concentration of manufacturing and supply power <lb/>within international industry players for markets like Africa, where the need is great. In <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>comparison Central and South America have a larger network of public laboratories that man-<lb/>ufacture products for the region. Across Asia, there is a greater mix of public and private man-<lb/>ufacturers mostly supplying the region-except for Indian manufacturers who export products <lb/>to the African market. <lb/>Overall, most available antivenoms (111, 87%) had some evidence of being approved by <lb/>either national or stringent regulatory approval authorities. For 16 products (13%) we could <lb/>not ascertain clear regulatory approval despite their availability on the market (see S2 Text). <lb/>Perhaps the most concerning finding was the limited publicly available preclinical and clinical <lb/>evidence for products on the market. Just under half (57, 45%) of all products had available <lb/>preclinical data of efficacy, and 29 (51%) of these also had available clinical trial data. Although <lb/>a further 12 products had clinical data, but no publicly available preclinical data, the remaining <lb/>58 products-over a third in total-had no discernible preclinical data at all, despite this being <lb/>the minimum standard for antivenoms to be approved for market use. <lb/>Investigational candidates <lb/>Of the 196 investigational candidates identified, there was a relatively even split between R&amp;D <lb/>into novel drugs i.e., SMTs (105, 54%) and biologics (91, 46%) (S3 Text). This split is indicative <lb/>of a broadening SBE R&amp;D landscape. At the sub-product level, we saw a large variability in bio-<lb/>logics, including novel whole immunoglobulins derived from animal models, pathology-spe-<lb/>cific antivenoms, as well as recombinant antibodies including human antibodies, camelid <lb/>nanobodies, single-chain variable antibody fragments and others. For drug R&amp;D, there was an <lb/>even split between natural-derived (54, 51%) and synthetic SMT candidates (51, 49%). Syn-<lb/>thetic SMTs include synthetic peptides, enzyme inhibitors, DNA aptamers, and nanoparticles, <lb/>featuring some of the most clinically advanced candidates in the pipeline. <lb/>Overall, approximately 64% of SBE investigational candidates were new chemical or biolog-<lb/>ical entities-largely driven by the nature of biologic research being so specific-while 36% were <lb/>repurposed drugs, offering the advantage of existing safety data which could accelerate their <lb/>development. The pipeline of investigational candidates remains immature however, with only <lb/>eight candidates in clinical development (see Table 1). These include two candidates in Phase <lb/>I; five in Phase II; and just one reported in Phase III. However, only four of these candidates <lb/>Fig 2. Summary of the available products and therapeutic candidates identified and included in the database of <lb/>Policy Cures Research. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>appeared in active development (two SMTs and two traditional antivenoms), with the remain-<lb/>ing (traditional antivenoms) having completed trials but with further progress unknown. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Although 127 products may seem sizeable, this does not necessarily translate into a robust <lb/>antivenom market. Some products have efficacy and safety issues, traditional antivenoms are <lb/>expensive to produce, and many exist in a loosely regulated environment. Antivenoms are <lb/>generated against the specific venoms used during animal immunization, with the possibility <lb/>Table 1. Overview of the eight candidates in clinical development. <lb/>Candidate <lb/>Active <lb/>component <lb/>Target <lb/>Phase Active development <lb/>Developers/instigators <lb/>Novel F(ab&apos;)2 antivenom <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Daboia russelii siamensis <lb/>Phase I Active-Phase I <lb/>registered 2020. Not <lb/>yet recruiting. <lb/>Shanghai Serum Biotechnology Co <lb/>Ltd <lb/>DMPS (Unithiol) <lb/>SMT <lb/>Snake venom <lb/>metalloproteases <lb/>Phase I Active-Phase <lb/>I trial (&quot;TRUE-1&quot;) <lb/>registered 2021. <lb/>Recruiting.* <lb/>Liverpool School of Tropical <lb/>Medicine <lb/>Novel ICP-AVRI-UOP Sri <lb/>Lankan polyspecific <lb/>antivenom <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Daboia russelii, Echis <lb/>carinatus, Hypnale hypnale, <lb/>Naja naja <lb/>Phase <lb/>II/III <lb/>Active-Phase II/III <lb/>trial registered 2016, <lb/>updated in 2019. <lb/>Recruitment pending <lb/>2019 <lb/>Instituto Clodomiro Picado, <lb/>University of Peradeniya, Animal <lb/>Venom Research International <lb/>Novel freeze-dried trivalent <lb/>antivenom (FDTAV) <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Bothrops spp., Lachesis spp., <lb/>Crotalus spp. <lb/>Phase <lb/>II <lb/>Completed-Phase <lb/>IIb trial conducted <lb/>2003-2008, <lb/>retrospectively <lb/>registered 2017. <lb/>Results published <lb/>2017. Further <lb/>progress unknown <lb/>Instituto Butantan <lb/>Novel PNG taipan <lb/>antivenom <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Oxyuranus scutellatus <lb/>Phase <lb/>II <lb/>Completed-Phase <lb/>II trial completed <lb/>2016. Results not <lb/>published. Further <lb/>progress unknown. <lb/>Instituto Clodomiro Picado, <lb/>Australian Venom Research Unit <lb/>Novel bivalent snake <lb/>antivenom <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Daboia russelii, <lb/>Echis carinatus <lb/>Phase <lb/>II <lb/>Completed-Phase <lb/>II trial conducted <lb/>in 2015. Results <lb/>published 2017. <lb/>Further progress <lb/>unknown. <lb/>Antisnake venom and Antirabies <lb/>Serology Laboratory, Sindh <lb/>Methyl-varespladib <lb/>SMT <lb/>Snake venom phospholipase <lb/>A 2 s <lb/>Phase <lb/>II <lb/>Active-Phase <lb/>II trial (&quot;BRAVO&quot;) <lb/>registered 2021, completed 2023 and <lb/>awaiting results. Phase II trial <lb/>(&quot;BRAVIO&quot;) registered 2023, <lb/>recruiting* <lb/>Ophirex Inc. <lb/>Snake (Micrurus) North <lb/>American immune F(ab&apos;)2 <lb/>equine <lb/>Serum-derived <lb/>antibodies <lb/>Micrurus fulvius <lb/>Phase <lb/>III <lb/>Completed-Phase <lb/>III trial completed <lb/>2016. No official <lb/>results published. <lb/>Further progress <lb/>unknown. <lb/>University of Arizona <lb/>* Updated for November 2023 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>of also covering venoms of related species (paraspecificity). This method, along with certain <lb/>products, even predate our system of regulatory approval hence why antivenoms have a differ-<lb/>ent R&amp;D pathway to other biological products. This foremost characteristic has a significant <lb/>impact on the therapeutic scope of these products since they are effective in some geographical <lb/>regions only, thus limiting their use in other settings. A growing body of evidence of preclini-<lb/>cal efficacy of antivenoms has been built in recent decades (see for example Segura et al., 2010 <lb/>[21], for the case of Latin America). The latter helps to explain why there is such heterogenous <lb/>clinical data and highlights the need for robust preclinical assessments until we have the <lb/>means to run more large-scale clinical trials. Antivenoms save lives and will continue to play a <lb/>key role in the treatment of SBE, but our data validates a shift towards a dual R&amp;D agenda: <lb/>focusing both on improving existing antivenoms in the short to medium-term, and on devel-<lb/>oping more cost-effective and safer, next-generation SBE therapeutics in the longer term. <lb/>While priorities for improving products already on the market can be framed as short-term <lb/>goals, their application will shape the R&amp;D ecosystem that future candidates will pass through, <lb/>for example via improved preclinical standards. Improvements to products now will therefore <lb/>be a key step in laying the foundation to achieve long-term priorities for next-generation tech-<lb/>nologies. Table 2 outlines potential next steps that could be prioritised in the SBE R&amp;D com-<lb/>munity to accelerate progress both in the short and long-term. <lb/>Table 2. Possible next steps to accelerating SBE R&amp;D. <lb/>Activity <lb/>Scheme (short / long term) <lb/>Establish antivenom paraspecificity and renew efforts <lb/>for improved preclinical testing <lb/>Short-term priority for products to improve coverage and <lb/>efficacy <lb/>Improve manufacturing techniques for traditional <lb/>antivenoms and invest in existing manufacturers to help <lb/>them achieve GMP standards <lb/>Short-term priority for products to ensure safe and <lb/>effective antivenoms and to improve products already in <lb/>the field that do not meet standards <lb/>Map out gaps, needs and priorities in the R&amp;D agenda <lb/>for SBE across different product types, e.g., drugs, <lb/>biologics, diagnostics, and supportive therapies. <lb/>Short-term priority to coordinate and organise the <lb/>research agenda which may take years to deliver <lb/>candidates to the market <lb/>Develop a prioritisation framework to assess candidates <lb/>in the pipeline to guide research and funding decisions <lb/>Develop novel diagnostic tests to support diagnosis, <lb/>epidemiology, and clinical trials <lb/>Short-term priority to support design of new products <lb/>and validation of current products and improve <lb/>epidemiological and clinical data collection <lb/>Align on a chosen governance structure for both <lb/>researchers and funders to facilitate coordination and <lb/>harmonisation <lb/>Short-term priority to ensure efficient use of resources <lb/>and knowledge-sharing <lb/>Map out category 1 and 2 snakes against antivenoms&apos; <lb/>coverage to identify gaps in the market <lb/>Short-and long-term priority for products and <lb/>candidates. Gaps will inform how to redesign current <lb/>immunisation strategies and prioritise candidates <lb/>Update clinical trial protocols including refining clinical <lb/>endpoints <lb/>Short and long-term priority for traditional and next-<lb/>generation technologies, including combination therapies <lb/>(e.g., SMT and traditional antivenom) <lb/>Conduct fit-for-purpose clinical studies to evaluate <lb/>safety and efficacy <lb/>Short and long-term priority to develop capacity and <lb/>experience in running clinical trials to generate evidence <lb/>on SBE products and candidates <lb/>Continue to collect data and produce analysis on the <lb/>state of the research pipeline and market, research <lb/>funding, cost-effectiveness, and impact of SBE <lb/>interventions and return-on-investment <lb/>Short and long-term priority to ensure the SBE R&amp;D <lb/>community has the right evidence to make informed <lb/>decisions and to attract new actors <lb/>Develop novel biologics and small molecule therapies to <lb/>address gaps in traditional antivenoms <lb/>Long-term priority with several years of sustained <lb/>investment <lb/>Promote the integration of access perspectives, and <lb/>coordination with key actors <lb/>Long-term priority to ensure that next-generation <lb/>therapeutics will be accessible once they reach the market <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>Key ways to improve traditional antivenoms could be achieved through R&amp;D focusing on <lb/>(1) improving immunisation strategies by selecting venom immunising mixtures that provide <lb/>wider coverage, (2) introducing new adjuvants to generate a higher immune response, (3) gen-<lb/>erating new protocols for animal bleeding, (4) improving plasma fractionation protocols, (5) <lb/>developing robust preclinical assessment of antivenom efficacy and safety within the 3Rs prin-<lb/>ciple within animal testing (i.e., replacement, reduction, refinement) [22], (6) assessing clinical <lb/>efficacy and safety, and (7) strengthening pharmacovigilance. The combination of sound epi-<lb/>demiological data with proteomics and toxicovenomics analyses provides a robust platform <lb/>for designing improved venom and toxin mixtures for immunisation. The WHO program of <lb/>risk-assessment of antivenoms uses a platform of preclinical evaluation of antivenom efficacy <lb/>that combines antivenomics with neutralisation assays, which enables the assessment of para-<lb/>specific antivenom efficacy [23,24]. Prioritising paraspecificity studies using similar designs <lb/>offers a potential short-term solution for improving existing antivenoms by expanding their <lb/>coverage, and therefore clinical use. <lb/>Furthermore, fit-for-purpose clinical protocols are needed to deliver robust safety and effi-<lb/>cacy data to improve confidence in products on the market [25]. As identified in this study <lb/>and in the literature [10,11], not only is clinical trial data heterogenous but there is also vari-<lb/>ability in the results and outcomes assessed, meaning the availability of clinical data does not <lb/>in itself necessarily translate to safe and effective products. Recently, a global core outcome <lb/>measurement set for snakebite clinical trials was published, an important first step towards <lb/>standardisation and improving clinical trial feasibility [6]. However, while traditional Phase III <lb/>studies remain the gold-standard, innovative approaches that could shorten duration and <lb/>reduce costs of late-stage R&amp;D may be considered in certain strictly defined circumstances <lb/>such as areas of high incidence of snakebites or seasons involving snakes possessing venoms <lb/>known to be highly potent and with no available products that are proven effective. In such sit-<lb/>uations the monitored emergency use of unregistered and investigational interventional <lb/>(MEURI) products approach may merit consideration. <lb/>To achieve these goals, we need to identify and mobilise funders that can invest in all stages <lb/>of R&amp;D. Although there is funding available for preclinical research, there is a lack of funders <lb/>that support later-stage research in antivenom manufacture and testing. As an example, the <lb/>European and Developing Countries Clinical Trials Partnership and African Pharmaceutical <lb/>Technology Foundation have the right mandates for clinical trials and manufacturing activities <lb/>but are not involved in the SBE space. A key issue is the need to fund antivenom manufacture <lb/>in countries with high incidence of SBE. This involves funding for R&amp;D activities, as well as <lb/>for improvements in infrastructure, equipment, training of staff, and implementation of Good <lb/>Manufacturing Practice (GMP). While there is room for improvement in the antivenom mar-<lb/>ket, some gaps cannot be addressed by improving efficacy, access, and coverage alone. Other <lb/>weaknesses of current antivenoms include the fact that they must be administered by trained <lb/>health workers in health centres, and have limited efficacy to abrogate local tissue damage <lb/>inflicted by snake venom [17]. There is therefore a need for treatments which can be adminis-<lb/>tered in the field, like heat-stable SMTs that can inhibit necrotising and haemorrhagic toxins, <lb/>buying time for victims of snakebite and lessening its overall burden [17,26], as well as novel <lb/>biologics which in the long-term could be cheaper to manufacture, more specific and less <lb/>immunogenic [27]. <lb/>Similar to the product market, 197 investigational candidates could easily be (mis)inter-<lb/>preted as a full pipeline. However, the aim of this database was to canvas everything that has <lb/>been researched or was on the market without making a value-based judgment on the actual <lb/>therapeutic potential, meaning there are candidates included which are likely to have low ther-<lb/>apeutic value or tractability. The purpose was to build a comprehensive baseline of everything <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>in motion, with the intention to then narrow down and prioritise. With this in mind, what <lb/>constitutes a &quot;real&quot; candidate is a key question. While therapeutic efficacy is essential, a high-<lb/>potential candidate must also exist within a system where its development can be supported, <lb/>and where it has a realistic deployment plan in terms of manufacturing and access. Currently, <lb/>the asymmetry in funding and support for research (early-stage vs late-stage and manufactur-<lb/>ing) and production capacity (geographic heterogeneity, e.g., Africa) is hindering progress. <lb/>There is a pressing need to clarify the R&amp;D agenda to both prioritise research and improve the <lb/>ecosystem for research-to-market translation. Addressing this requires reflection on the exist-<lb/>ing R&amp;D ecosystem and overcoming bottlenecks inhibiting progress and coordination. <lb/>These major roadblocks are evident in the immature state of the research pipeline. Despite <lb/>increased investment and focus on novel recombinant antibody research for SBE [8], there has <lb/>been limited translation of candidates out of basic and early-stage in the last seven years. There <lb/>are several reasons for this. Despite promising advances [28,29], the first barrier is the diversity <lb/>of relevant toxins in snake venoms, which represents a challenge in developing broadly neu-<lb/>tralising recombinant antibodies. While advancements have been made, they remain largely <lb/>focused on inhibition of specific toxin subfamilies and are not yet sufficiently developed to be <lb/>combined and tested in humans. <lb/>Although it is promising to see growing interest in the field of recombinant antivenoms, <lb/>research projects are largely undertaken by academic institutions, reflecting a sector mostly <lb/>comprised of basic research, with very few academic actors having the capacity or means to <lb/>translate findings into clinical studies and then manufacture. In addition, there is no clear reg-<lb/>ulatory pathway for this new type of recombinant antibody therapy for SBE; it is important <lb/>that discussions on regulatory frameworks for these technologies be developed in parallel with <lb/>R&amp;D [30]. Lastly, with the cost of development increasing with the complexity of clinical trials <lb/>and regulatory frameworks, the current lack of diversity of funders to support late-stage <lb/>research is seriously hindering progress and translation. <lb/>On the other hand, repurposed drugs have shown great success in other NTDs as being <lb/>faster and cheaper to develop. Indeed, methyl-varespladib and unithiol, two repurposed drugs, <lb/>have emerged as the fastest-moving SBE candidates and are already in clinical trials. However, <lb/>given the diversity of snake venom toxins, it is likely that SMTs will need to be applied as com-<lb/>bination therapies either with traditional antivenoms, novel biologics, or a cocktail of SMTs <lb/>[28,31]. Combination therapies add an extra layer of complexity to clinical trials but are likely <lb/>to be necessary to ensure broad acting, safe and effective treatments. <lb/>To push biologic and drug candidates through the pipeline, a properly equipped ecosystem, <lb/>which includes a diverse range of actors with the means and experience to develop and register <lb/>products, will be critical. The current SBE R&amp;D landscape has a distinct lack of large industry <lb/>players and multinational companies, or specialised Product Development Partnerships, <lb/>which historically have been the big movers of NTD products. More coordination is also <lb/>needed between existing actors, ideally through innovative Public-Private-Partnerships to spur <lb/>research between partners with different strengths. Looking ahead, the community must be <lb/>prepared for how a successful recombinant antibody or SMT will be rolled out, at accessible <lb/>cost, to low-resource or hard-to-reach settings, where most snakebites occur. <lb/>Many questions have been raised by this research, including which avenues should be <lb/>prioritised for SBE R&amp;D, how to identify a promising candidate, how to address the asymme-<lb/>try in research and production capacity, and what a productive R&amp;D ecosystem could look <lb/>like (and who should be in it). The study presents a comprehensive baseline but still has limita-<lb/>tions, including the possibility of missing candidates and products for several reasons (see S1 <lb/>Text for full details) and static information current as of September 2022. This calls for further <lb/>studies using additional sources of information, particularly in countries with high incidence <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<body>of SBE. Data interoperability will be key for moving forward, harmonising existing data, and <lb/>generating new evidence on different aspects of the SBE issue to provide a comprehensive <lb/>view of where different fields intersect. For example, intellectual property (IP) is a topic that <lb/>requires further investigation. Although this does not seem to be an issue in the case of anti-<lb/>venoms, it may have implications in terms of costs and accessibility in the case of new drugs <lb/>and recombinant antibodies. This aspect should be explored in future studies, and public <lb/>health authorities should consider the implications and possibilities of IP in the treatment of <lb/>SBE [32]. Ongoing research and focused stakeholder collaboration will enable the community <lb/>to start answering these questions. By mobilising partners, funding and coordination, a serious <lb/>effort to accelerate the improvement and development of the products and candidates identi-<lb/>fied in this landscape could be possible. Ideally, we foresee an established governance structure <lb/>of funders and researchers, and a realistic understanding of the community&apos;s capacities and <lb/>goals, as well as the needs of public health systems, as kickstarting a new phase in the SBE sec-<lb/>tor where all actors converge to work towards a common and unified R&amp;D agenda. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Text. Methodology for development of Snakebite Envenoming Medicines Database for <lb/>therapeutics: investigational candidates and marketed products, 2015-2022). <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Text. List of included marketed and/or available products. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Text. List of included investigational candidates. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We would like to thank the Expert Advisory Group for the Snakebite Medicines Pipeline proj-<lb/>ect for their guidance and expertise in developing and reviewing the database including Ian <lb/>Cameron (MicroPharm), Nicholas Casewell (Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine), Andreas <lb/>Hougaard Laustsen-Kiel (Technical University of Denmark), Matthew Lewin (Ophirex / Cali-<lb/>fornia Academy of Sciences) and Julien Potet (MSF Access). We would also like to thank all <lb/>the colleagues who participated in the June 14 2023 stakeholder consultation on R&amp;D, innova-<lb/>tion and financing for SBE in Africa for fruitful insights. We thank Diogo Martins, George <lb/>Phillips and Nick Cammack from Wellcome for their support of this project. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Data curation: Juliette Borri, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Formal analysis: Juliette Borri, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Investigation: Juliette Borri, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Methodology: Juliette Borri, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Project administration: Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Supervision: Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Validation: Juliette Borri, Jose ´Marı ´a Gutie ´rrez, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/>Visualization: Juliette Borri. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Juliette Borri. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Juliette Borri, Jose ´Marı ´a Gutie ´rrez, Cecilie Knudsen, Abdulrazaq <lb/>G. Habib, Maya Goldstein, Andrew Tuttle. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Gutie ´rrez JM, Calvete JJ, Habib AG, Harrison RA, Williams DJ, Warrell DA. Snakebite envenoming. <lb/>Nature Reviews Disease Primers. 2017; 3(1):17063. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrdp.2017.63 PMID: <lb/>28905944 <lb/>2. Gutie ´rrez JM. Snakebite Envenomation as a Neglected Tropical Disease: New Impetus for Confronting <lb/>an Old Scourge. In: Mackessy SP, editor. Handbook of Venoms and Toxins of Reptiles. 2nd ed. Boca <lb/>Raton, Florida, USA: CRC Press; 2021. p. 471-83. <lb/>3. World Health Organization. Snakebite Envenoming: A Strategy for Prevention and Control. Geneva: <lb/>World Health Organization, 2019. <lb/>4. World Health Organization. Target product profiles for animal plasma-derived antivenoms: antivenoms <lb/>for treatment of snakebite envenoming in sub-Saharan Africa. Geneva: World Health Organization, <lb/>2023. <lb/>5. World Health Organization. Risk Assessment-Snake antivenom: Prequalification of Medical Products <lb/>-IVDs, Medicines, Vaccines and Imunization Devices, Vector Control. Geneva: World Health Organi-<lb/>zation, 2023. https://extranet.who.int/prequal/vaccines/risk-assessment-snake-antivenom <lb/>6. Abouyannis M, Esmail H, Hamaluba M, Ngama M, Mwangudzah H, Mumba N, et al. A global core out-<lb/>come measurement set for snakebite clinical trials. The Lancet Global Health. 2023; 11(2):e296-e300. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00479-X PMID: 36669810 <lb/>7. Policy Cures Research. Global Funding for Snakebite Envenoming Research 2007-2018. Sydney: <lb/>Policy Cures Research, 2019. <lb/>8. Policy Cures Research. G-FINDER data portal: tracking funding for global health R&amp;D. Sydney: Policy <lb/>Cures Research, 2022. <lb/>9. Alirol E, Lechevalier P, Zamatto F, Chappuis F, Alcoba G, Potet J. Antivenoms for Snakebite Envenom-<lb/>ing: What Is in the Research Pipeline? PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2015; 9(9):e0003896. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0003896 PMID: 26355744 <lb/>10. Potet J, Smith J, McIver L. Reviewing evidence of the clinical effectiveness of commercially available <lb/>antivenoms in sub-Saharan Africa identifies the need for a multi-centre, multi-antivenom clinical trial. <lb/>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2019; 13(6):e0007551. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd. <lb/>0007551 PMID: 31233536 <lb/>11. Abouyannis M, Aggarwal D, Lalloo DG, Casewell NR, Hamaluba M, Esmail H. Clinical outcomes and <lb/>outcome measurement tools reported in randomised controlled trials of treatment for snakebite enven-<lb/>oming: A systematic review. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2021; 15(8):e0009589. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0009589 PMID: 34339410 <lb/>12. Puzari U, Fernandes PA, Mukherjee AK. Advances in the Therapeutic Application of Small-Molecule <lb/>Inhibitors and Repurposed Drugs against Snakebite. Journal of Medicinal Chemistry. 2021; 64 <lb/>(19):13938-79. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c00266 PMID: 34565143 <lb/>13. Ferreira SdS Silva DPd, Torres-Rêgo M Silva-Ju ´nior AAd, Fernandes-Pedrosa MdF. The potential of <lb/>phenolic acids in therapy against snakebites: A review. Toxicon. 2022; 208:1-12. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.toxicon.2021.12.019 <lb/>14. Puzari U, Fernandes PA, Mukherjee AK. Pharmacological re-assessment of traditional medicinal <lb/>plants-derived inhibitors as antidotes against snakebite envenoming: A critical review. Journal of Ethno-<lb/>pharmacology. 2022; 292:115208. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2022.115208 PMID: 35314419 <lb/>15. Laustsen AH, Engmark M, Milbo C, Johannesen J, Lomonte B, Gutie ´rrez JM, et al. From Fangs to Phar-<lb/>macology: The Future of Snakebite Envenoming Therapy. Current Pharmaceutical Design. 2016; 22 <lb/>(34):5270-93. https://doi.org/10.2174/1381612822666160623073438 PMID: 27339430 <lb/>16. Knudsen C, Laustsen AH. Recent Advances in Next Generation Snakebite Antivenoms. Tropical Medi-<lb/>cine and Infectious Disease. 2018; 3(2):42. https://doi.org/10.3390/tropicalmed3020042 PMID: <lb/>30274438 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 13 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>17. Gutie ´rrez JM, Albulescu L-O, Clare RH, Casewell NR, Abd El-Aziz TM, Escalante T, et al. The Search <lb/>for Natural and Synthetic Inhibitors That Would Complement Antivenoms as Therapeutics for Snakebite <lb/>Envenoming. Toxins [Internet]. 2021; 13(7). https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins13070451 PMID: 34209691 <lb/>18. Knudsen C, Ju ¨rgensen A, Føns S, Haack AM, Friis RUW, Dam SH, Bush SP, White J and Laustsen <lb/>AH. Snakebite Envenoming Diagnosis and Diagnostics. Frontiers in Immunology. 2021; 12:1-27. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2021.661457. <lb/>19. McDougall ARA, Goldstein M, Tuttle A, Ammerdorffer A, Rushwan S, Hastie R, et al. Innovations in the <lb/>prevention and treatment of postpartum hemorrhage: Analysis of a novel medicines development pipe-<lb/>line database. International Journal of Gynecology &amp; Obstetrics. 2022; 158(S1):31-9. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/ijgo.14200. <lb/>20. Landscape of Medicines Development for Five Pregnancy-related Conditions 2000-2021. Policy <lb/>Cures Research, Concept Foundation, 2021. <lb/>21. Segura A, Castillo MC, Nu ´ñez V, Yarleque ´A, Gonc ¸alves LR, Villalta M, et al. Preclinical assessment of <lb/>the neutralizing capacity of antivenoms produced in six Latin American countries against medically-rele-<lb/>vant Bothrops snake venoms. Toxicon. 2010; 56(6):980-9. Epub 20100716. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>toxicon.2010.07.001 PMID: 20621114. <lb/>22. Hubrecht RC, Carter E. The 3Rs and Humane Experimental Technique: Implementing Change. Ani-<lb/>mals (Basel). 2019; 9(10). Epub 20190930. https://doi.org/10.3390/ani9100754 PMID: 31575048; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6826930. <lb/>23. Gutie ´rrez J, Solano G, Pla D, Herrera M, Segura A ´, Vargas M, et al. Preclinical Evaluation of the Effi-<lb/>cacy of Antivenoms for Snakebite Envenoming: State-of-the-Art and Challenges Ahead. Toxins. 2017; <lb/>9(5):163. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins9050163 PMID: 28505100 <lb/>24. Guidelines for the production, control and regulation of snake antivenom immunoglobulins, Annex 5, <lb/>TRS No 1004. Geneva: World Health Organization, 2017. <lb/>25. Williams DJ, Habib AG, Warrell DA. Clinical studies of the effectiveness and safety of antivenoms. Toxi-<lb/>con. 2018; 150:1-10. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2018.05.001 PMID: 29746978 <lb/>26. Bulfone TC, Samuel SP, Bickler PE, Lewin MR. Developing Small Molecule Therapeutics for the Initial <lb/>and Adjunctive Treatment of Snakebite. J Trop Med. 2018; 2018:4320175. Epub 20180730. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1155/2018/4320175 PMID: 30154870; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6091453. <lb/>27. Laustsen AH, Marı ´a Gutie ´rrez J, Knudsen C, Johansen KH, Bermu ´dez-Me ´ndez E, Cerni FA, et al. Pros <lb/>and cons of different therapeutic antibody formats for recombinant antivenom development. Toxicon. <lb/>2018; 146:151-75. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2018.03.004 PMID: 29534892 <lb/>28. Glanville J, Andrade JC, Bellin M, Kim S, Pletnev S, Tsao D, et al. Venom protection by broadly neutral-<lb/>izing antibody from a snakebite subject. bioRxiv. 2023:2022.09.26.507364. https://doi.org/10.1101/ <lb/>2022.09.26.507364 <lb/>29. Ledsgaard L, Wade J, Jenkins TP, Boddum K, Oganesyan I, Harrison JA, et al. Discovery and optimiza-<lb/>tion of a broadly-neutralizing human monoclonal antibody against long-chain α-neurotoxins from <lb/>snakes. Nature Communications. 2023; 14(1). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-36393-4 PMID: <lb/>36755049 <lb/>30. Laustsen AH, Dorrestijn N. Integrating Engineering, Manufacturing, and Regulatory Considerations in <lb/>the Development of Novel Antivenoms. Toxins (Basel). 2018; 10(8). Epub 20180731. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3390/toxins10080309 PMID: 30065185; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6115708. <lb/>31. Albulescu L-O, Xie C, Ainsworth S, Alsolaiss J, Crittenden E, Dawson CA, et al. A therapeutic combina-<lb/>tion of two small molecule toxin inhibitors provides broad preclinical efficacy against viper snakebite. <lb/>Nature Communications. 2020; 11(1):6094. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-19981-6 PMID: <lb/>33323937 <lb/>32. Bhaumik S, Zwi AB, Norton R, Jagnoor J. How and why snakebite became a global health priority: a pol-<lb/>icy analysis. BMJ Global Health. 2023; 8(8):e011923. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2023-011923 <lb/>PMID: 37604596 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES <lb/>Snakebite envenoming therapeutic landscape <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012052 March 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 13 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>