<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Youth Suicide and Preceding Mental Health Diagnosis</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sofia</forename>
          <surname>Chaudhary</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jennifer A.</forename>
          <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Christian D.</forename>
          <surname>Pulcini</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mark</forename>
          <surname>Zamani</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Matt</forename>
          <surname>Hall</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Kristyn N.</forename>
          <surname>Jeffries</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rachel</forename>
          <surname>Myers</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Joel</forename>
          <surname>Fein</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Bonnie T.</forename>
          <surname>Zima</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Peter F.</forename>
          <surname>Ehrlich</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Elizabeth R.</forename>
          <surname>Alpern</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Stephen</forename>
          <surname>Hargarten</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Karen M.</forename>
          <surname>Sheehan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eric W.</forename>
          <surname>Fleegler</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Monika K.</forename>
          <surname>Goyal</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename/>
          <surname/>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:28:42.591Z">11/12/2025 10:28:42 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1001$1$jamanetworkopen.2024.23996</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.23996</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Sofia Chaudhary, Jennifer A. Hoffmann, Christian D. Pulcini, Mark Zamani, Matt Hall, Kristyn N. Jeffries, Rachel Myers, Joel Fein, Bonnie T. Zima, Peter F. Ehrlich, Elizabeth R. Alpern, Stephen Hargarten, Karen M. Sheehan, Eric W. Fleegler, Monika K. Goyal, None None. (2024). Youth Suicide and Preceding Mental Health Diagnosis. JAMA Network Open, 7(7), e2423996. DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.23996</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T10:28:34.462272Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T10:28:34.462272Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Original Investigation | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor RNA Expression <lb/>of Stress-Related Genes <lb/>Joseph Boyle, PhD; Jessica Yau, MS; Jimmie L. Slade, MMAS, MA; Derrick A. Butts, MS; Yuji Zhang, PhD; Teklu B. Legesse, MD; Ashley Cellini, PA; Kimberly Clark, BS; <lb/>Jong Y. Park, PhD; Jessica Wimbush, CTR; Nicholas Ambulos Jr, PhD; Jing Yin, PhD; Arif Hussain, MD; Eberechukwu Onukwugha, MS, PhD; Cheryl L. Knott, PhD; <lb/>David C. Wheeler, PhD, MS, MPH; Kathryn Hughes Barry, PhD, MPH <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IMPORTANCE African American men experience greater prostate cancer incidence and mortality <lb/>than White men. Growing literature supports associations of neighborhood disadvantage, which <lb/>disproportionately affects African American men, with aggressive prostate cancer; chronic stress and <lb/>downstream biological impacts (eg, increased inflammation) may contribute to these associations. <lb/>OBJECTIVE To examine whether several neighborhood disadvantage metrics are associated with <lb/>prostate tumor RNA expression of stress-related genes. <lb/>DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS This cross-sectional study leveraged prostate tumor <lb/>transcriptomic data for African American and White men with prostate cancer who received radical <lb/>prostatectomy at the University of Maryland Medical Center between August 1992 and January 2021. <lb/>Data were analyzed from May 2023 to April 2024. <lb/>EXPOSURES Using addresses at diagnosis, 2 neighborhood deprivation metrics (Area Deprivation <lb/>Index [ADI] and validated bayesian Neighborhood Deprivation Index) as well as the Racial Isolation <lb/>Index (RI) and historical redlining were applied to participants&apos; addresses. Self-reported race was <lb/>determined using electronic medical records. <lb/>MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES A total of 105 stress-related genes were evaluated with each <lb/>neighborhood metric using linear regression, adjusting for race, age, and year of surgery. Genes in the <lb/>Conserved Transcriptional Response to Adversity (CTRA) and stress-related signaling genes were <lb/>included. <lb/>RESULTS A total of 218 men (168 [77%] African American, 50 [23%] White) with a median (IQR) age <lb/>of 58 (53-63) years were included. African American participants experienced greater neighborhood <lb/>disadvantage than White participants (median [IQR] ADI, 115 [100-130] vs 92 [83-104]; median [IQR] <lb/>RI, 0.68 [0.34-0.87] vs 0.11 [0.06-0.14]). ADI was positively associated with expression for 11 genes; <lb/>HTR6 (serotonin pathway) remained significant after multiple-comparison adjustment (β = 0.003; <lb/>SE, 0.001; P &lt; .001; Benjamini-Hochberg q value = .01). Several genes, including HTR6, were <lb/>associated with multiple metrics. We observed higher expression of 5 proinflammatory genes in the <lb/>CTRA with greater neighborhood disadvantage (eg, CXCL8 and ADI, β = 0.008; SE, 0.003; P = .01; <lb/>q value = .21). <lb/>CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE In this cross-sectional study, the expression of several stress-<lb/>related genes in prostate tumors was higher among men residing in disadvantaged neighborhoods. <lb/>This study is one of the first to suggest associations of neighborhood disadvantage with prostate <lb/>tumor RNA expression. Additional research is needed in larger studies to replicate findings and <lb/>(continued) <lb/>Key Points <lb/>Question Is neighborhood <lb/>disadvantage associated with prostate <lb/>tumor RNA expression of stress-related <lb/>genes among African American and <lb/>White men with prostate cancer? <lb/>Findings In this cross-sectional study of <lb/>218 men with prostate cancer, <lb/>neighborhood disadvantage was <lb/>associated with significantly higher <lb/>tumor expression of stress-related <lb/>genes, including several <lb/>proinflammatory genes. The association <lb/>between the Area Deprivation Index and <lb/>HTR6 (serotonin pathway) remained <lb/>statistically significant after multiple-<lb/>comparison adjustment. <lb/>Meaning These findings suggest that <lb/>neighborhood disadvantage is <lb/>associated with higher expression of <lb/>stress-related genes, which may <lb/>contribute to an increased risk of <lb/>aggressive prostate cancer and warrants <lb/>follow-up in future studies. <lb/>+ Supplemental content <lb/>Author affiliations and article information are <lb/>listed at the end of this article. <lb/>Open Access. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/>1/13 <lb/>Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/>Abstract (continued) <lb/>further investigate interrelationships of neighborhood factors, tumor biology, and aggressive <lb/>prostate cancer to inform interventions to reduce disparities. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Prostate cancer is the leading cause of cancer incidence and second leading cause of cancer mortality <lb/>among men in the United States. 1 Prostate cancer rates are relatively high among African American <lb/>men, with an incidence rate more than 1.5 times and a mortality rate more than 2 times that of White <lb/>men. African American men are more likely to be diagnosed with advanced prostate cancer, partly <lb/>due to reduced access to health care and screening. 2,3 Additionally, African American men are <lb/>thought to be more likely to develop aggressive prostate cancer, which is more likely to be fatal, but <lb/>the reasons are unclear. 3 <lb/>Increasing literature supports that neighborhood disadvantage (eg, neighborhood <lb/>socioeconomic deprivation), which disproportionately affects African American individuals, 4,5 is <lb/>associated with a higher likelihood of advanced or aggressive prostate cancer 5-8 and therefore may <lb/>contribute importantly to disparities. The downward causal model from the University of Chicago <lb/>posits that population-level (eg, neighborhood) factors have downstream biological impacts that <lb/>influence disease development, for example via increased allostatic load due to chronic stress. 9,10 <lb/>Under this framework, we and others hypothesize that neighborhood disadvantage may increase the <lb/>development of aggressive prostate cancer in part through chronic stress and related downstream <lb/>biological effects including increased inflammation, which has been linked with prostate cancer risk <lb/>and progression in previous studies. 11-15 Notably, previous research has also suggested associations <lb/>between neighborhood disadvantage and inflammation-related genes in serum. 16 <lb/>There is also evidence that neighborhood-level effects of historical structural racism (eg, <lb/>residential racial segregation and redlining) influence health, including cancer outcomes, in the <lb/>present day. Residential racial segregation refers to the tendency for members of similar racial groups <lb/>to inhabit the same neighborhoods, which may bring about a concentration of disadvantage, <lb/>depending on the racial group and economics. Redlining refers to a concerted effort by the US <lb/>government to systematically deny mortgage applications or refinancing in certain neighborhoods, <lb/>often based on race. 17-19 Residence in historically redlined neighborhoods has been linked to elevated <lb/>risk of late-stage lung cancer among men, even if such neighborhoods became less deprived over <lb/>time, 20 and to elevated hazards for breast cancer-specific and all-cause mortality in women. 21 <lb/>We hypothesized that neighborhood disadvantage would affect the expression of stress-related <lb/>genes, which in turn would contribute to an increased risk of aggressive prostate cancer. In the <lb/>present study, we assessed associations of 4 neighborhood disadvantage metrics with prostate <lb/>tumor RNA expression of stress-related genes among African American and White men with prostate <lb/>cancer. We included 2 neighborhood deprivation metrics, the publicly available Area Deprivation <lb/>Index (ADI) 22,23 and a validated Neighborhood Deprivation Index (NDI) developed by our group, 24,25 <lb/>which was defined using a flexible bayesian index model that estimates importance weights for <lb/>model components and allows the model to be tailored to the outcome. We also included a measure <lb/>of racial residential segregation known as the Racial Isolation Index (RI), 26 as well as historical <lb/>redlining. It is critical to investigate the association of different neighborhood factors with prostate <lb/>tumor biology to help understand how these factors may contribute to the development of <lb/>aggressive prostate cancer and related disparities. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Study Population <lb/>Our cross-sectional study included 218 men with prostate cancer (168 [77%] African American men <lb/>and 50 [23%] White men) who received radical prostatectomy surgery at the University of Maryland <lb/>Medical Center from August 1992 to January 2021, had available RNA expression data from prostate <lb/>tumor tissue, and had a valid residential, noninstitutional address at the time of diagnosis available <lb/>for geocoding; African American men were overselected (see sample selection flowchart in eFigure 1 <lb/>in Supplement 1). We included self-reported race (via electronic medical records) based on relevance <lb/>of race as a social construct to our hypothesis that neighborhood and social factors may affect <lb/>stress-related pathways. We selected men who received surgery to ensure that there would be <lb/>adequate tissue for downstream molecular assays and due to concern that biopsy samples may not <lb/>reflect the overall tumor. The current study was approved by the institutional review board (IRB) at <lb/>the University of Maryland, Baltimore, which was the IRB of record for this project, and followed the <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) reporting <lb/>guidelines. We obtained a waiver of informed consent as part of the approved IRB protocol for <lb/>this study. <lb/>Study Outcome: RNA Expression <lb/>We leveraged transcriptomic data from formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) prostate tumor <lb/>tissue from our previous studies. The pathology and RNA extraction approaches have been described <lb/>previously 27 (also see more detail in eMethods in Supplement 1). Briefly, RNA was extracted from <lb/>prostate tumor samples using the RNEasy FFPE kit (Qiagen). We obtained RNA expression data from <lb/>the Human Clariom D array, which measures expression for 138 745 transcript clusters (TCs). We <lb/>analyzed a subset of 105 TCs corresponding to stress-related genes, including those in the Conserved <lb/>Transcriptional Response to Adversity (CTRA) 28 and stress-related signaling pathways, <lb/>encompassing the adrenergic, glucocorticoid, dopaminergic, serotoninergic, and muscarinic <lb/>systems 29 (eTable 1 in Supplement 1). Various stress-related signaling genes have been previously <lb/>linked with lethal prostate cancer 29 and there is relevance of CTRA genes (eg, proinflammatory <lb/>genes) to prostate cancer risk and progression. 11-13 <lb/>Neighborhood Measures <lb/>We geocoded the residential address at diagnosis for each participant using ArcGIS (Esri), which is a <lb/>required field within the University of Maryland Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center tumor <lb/>registry. We included several measures of neighborhood disadvantage (more detail appears in <lb/>eMethods in Supplement 1), considering the census tract containing each participant&apos;s address at <lb/>diagnosis as the neighborhood. The first measure was the publicly available ADI, which includes 17 <lb/>neighborhood-level variables in the income, education, employment, and housing quality domains <lb/>and is available for 2005 and later. 22,23 Greater values of the ADI indicate greater deprivation. We <lb/>calculated the ADI measure for 160 participants (117 African American and 43 White). <lb/>Our second measure was a custom NDI that we fit with the validated bayesian index model. 24 <lb/>The construction of the NDI was similar to that of the ADI, but importance weights for index <lb/>components were estimated in modeling, allowing identification of the most important variables for <lb/>the given outcome. Greater values corresponded to greater deprivation. We calculated the NDI <lb/>measure for 211 participants (162 African American and 49 White). <lb/>Our third measure was the spatial RI index, 26 which was available for 2009 and later. This <lb/>measure ranged from 0 to 1, with higher values corresponding to higher African American residential <lb/>segregation. We calculated the RI measure for 136 participants (99 African American and 37 White). <lb/>Our fourth measure was historical redlining. We used the Home Owners&apos; Loan Corporation <lb/>(HOLC) redlining map of the Baltimore area from the 1930s. We categorized redlining as a binary <lb/>variable (lowest grade, D, compared with any other grade [A, B, C, or no grade]). We used the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>digitized redlining map from the Mapping Inequality project. 30 We calculated the redlining measure <lb/>for 218 participants (168 African American and 50 White). <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>We fit linear regression models for each gene in relation to each neighborhood measure, adjusting for <lb/>race, age at surgery, and year of surgery (more detail appears in eMethods in Supplement 1). For the <lb/>ADI, RI, and historical redlining exposures, we fit frequentist linear regression models for the log <lb/>base-2 transformed gene expression values. We reported coefficients, standard errors, P values, and <lb/>q values (P values adjusted for 105 genes tested with each exposure with the Benjamini-Hochberg <lb/>method 31 ), with a conventional .05 level of significance. For the NDI, we fit bayesian linear regression <lb/>models, reporting coefficients, credible intervals, and exceedance probabilities (EPs). We calculated <lb/>Spearman correlations between the continuous neighborhood measures to evaluate their <lb/>agreement. As a sensitivity analysis, we repeated the adjusted models among African American men <lb/>only to assess whether the significant findings were similar to the primary analysis. We also assessed <lb/>characteristics of the larger group of men receiving radical prostatectomy for prostate cancer at the <lb/>University of Maryland Medical Center from 1992 to 2021 to assess the extent to which our sample <lb/>reflected this larger group. We performed an additional sensitivity analysis comparing socioeconomic <lb/>and health care access indicators 32,33 between geographic areas in Maryland (census tracts, <lb/>counties) contributing to our sample vs those that did not to explore the representativeness of our <lb/>sample with respect to Maryland as a whole. Finally, we assessed whether primary payer at diagnosis <lb/>(proxy for individual-level socioeconomic status) confounded any top associations (ie, those with <lb/>P &lt; .05) in the primary analysis. We performed analyses in R version 4.3.1 (R Project for Statistical <lb/>Computing); tests were 2-tailed. Statistical analysis was conducted from May 2023 to April 2024. <lb/>Results <lb/>Most of the sample comprised African American men (168 [77%], with 50 [23%] White men), and <lb/>the median (IQR) age at surgery was 58 (53-63) years (Table 1). Approximately 21% of the men (46 <lb/>men) had an established family history of prostate cancer. Most men had a pathologic tumor stage of <lb/>2 or 3 (163 of 165 men with available data [98%]). The most common Gleason pattern was 3 + 4 (101 <lb/>men [46%]); most participants (150 [69%]) had intermediate-risk prostate cancer per American <lb/>Urological Association definitions. A small population of the men (8 men [6%]) had known nodal <lb/>involvement (pN1). Approximately 93% of the men underwent surgery within 1 year of diagnosis <lb/>(202 men). Aside from a larger proportion of African American men, study participant characteristics <lb/>were generally similar to those of the broader group of African American and White men receiving <lb/>radical prostatectomy for prostate cancer at the University of Maryland Medical Center. Specifically, <lb/>among the 730 men meeting these criteria, the mean (SD) age at surgery was 58.9 (6.6) years, and <lb/>295 (40%) were African American; among the 659 men with available pathologic stage information, <lb/>the distribution was: stage 1, 43 (7%); stage 2, 433 (66%); stage 3, 156 (24%); stage 4, 27 (4%). The <lb/>continuous neighborhood measures were moderately to highly correlated, with correlations of 0.93 <lb/>for ADI and NDI, 0.70 for ADI and RI, and 0.69 for NDI and RI. We found that Maryland areas <lb/>(counties or census tracts) contributing participants to our study did not systematically differ from <lb/>those that did not contribute with respect to socioeconomic indicators or access to health care <lb/>(eTable 2 in Supplement 1). <lb/>Values of the ADI varied across the state of Maryland, with higher deprivation generally <lb/>occurring in Baltimore compared with the rest of the state (eFigure 2 in Supplement 1). Within <lb/>Baltimore, the greatest ADI values were concentrated in central and western neighborhoods of the <lb/>city (Figure 1). Median (IQR) values for the ADI were 115 (100-130) for African American men and 92 <lb/>(83-104) for White men, indicating greater neighborhood deprivation in our sample for African <lb/>American men. Eleven genes were associated with ADI (Table 2). For each of these genes, greater <lb/>deprivation was associated with greater expression. Notably, 1 gene (HTR6 in the serotonin pathway) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>remained significantly associated with ADI after adjustment for multiple comparisons (β = 0.003; SE, <lb/>0.001; P &lt; .001; q value = .01). <lb/>One gene (FOS, a proinflammatory gene in the CTRA) was associated with the NDI estimated by <lb/>the bayesian index model (Table 2), with an exceedance probability of 95.8%, indicating significance. <lb/>Table 1. Study Population Characteristics for African American <lb/>and White Men Who Received Radical Prostatectomy Surgery <lb/>for Prostate Cancer at the University of Maryland Medical Center, <lb/>1992-2021 <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>Participants, <lb/>No. (%) (N = 218) a <lb/>Race <lb/>African American <lb/>168 (77) <lb/>White <lb/>50 (23) <lb/>Age at surgery, median (IQR), y <lb/>58 (53-63) <lb/>Year of surgery <lb/>1992-1997 <lb/>23 (11) <lb/>1998-2004 <lb/>30 (14) <lb/>2005-2010 <lb/>44 (20) <lb/>2011-2016 <lb/>74 (34) <lb/>2017-2021 <lb/>47 (22) <lb/>Family history of prostate cancer <lb/>Yes <lb/>46 (21) <lb/>No <lb/>101 (46) <lb/>Unknown <lb/>71 (33) <lb/>BMI, median (IQR) <lb/>27.7 (25.0-31.5) <lb/>Preoperative PSA, ng/mL <lb/>6.3 (4.9-9.5) <lb/>Pathologic tumor stage <lb/>1 <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>2 <lb/>108 (65) <lb/>3 <lb/>55 (33) <lb/>4 <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>Pathologic nodal involvement <lb/>N0 <lb/>125 (94) <lb/>N1 <lb/>8 (6) <lb/>Pathologic Gleason score or pattern <lb/>Total Gleason score ≤6 <lb/>72 (33) <lb/>3 + 4 <lb/>101 (46) <lb/>4 + 3 or Total Gleason score ≥8 <lb/>45 (21) <lb/>Prostate cancer risk stratification <lb/>Low-risk <lb/>46 (21) <lb/>Intermediate-risk <lb/>150 (69) <lb/>High-risk <lb/>19 (9) <lb/>Indeterminate <lb/>3 (1) <lb/>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index (calculated as weight in kilograms divided <lb/>by height in meters squared); PSA, prostate-specific antigen. <lb/>SI conversion factor: To convert PSA to micrograms per liter, multiply by 1. <lb/>a Some percentages may not sum exactly to 100 due to rounding. There were <lb/>28 missing values for BMI and 50 missing values for preoperative PSA. Count <lb/>and percentage for pathologic tumor stage and pathologic nodal involvement <lb/>are calculated for observations without missing information (unknown status <lb/>for 53 and 85 participants for these variables, respectively, predominantly for <lb/>earlier cases when this information was not required to be collected by the <lb/>tumor registry). Risk stratification was based on guidelines from the American <lb/>Urological Association; pathologic tumor stage and grade and preoperative <lb/>PSA information was used (see eMethods in Supplement 1 for details). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>The most important variables estimated in the NDI for FOS were percentage in tract without a high <lb/>school diploma and percentage of structures in tract that were vacant (weights of 21.9% and 23.9%). <lb/>African American racial isolation measured by the RI index also varied, with larger RI values <lb/>occurring within the Baltimore area than outside it (eFigure 3 in Supplement 1) and particularly in <lb/>central and western neighborhoods in Baltimore (Figure 2). The median (IQR) values for the RI were <lb/>0.68 (0.34-0.87) for African American men and 0.11 (0.06-0.14) for White men, indicating that <lb/>African American men in our sample tended to reside in areas with higher African American <lb/>residential segregation. Seven genes were associated with RI (Table 2), although none of these <lb/>findings persisted after multiple-comparison adjustment. Similar to the top ADI findings, the top <lb/>genes associated with RI showed positive associations with higher disadvantage. <lb/>Sixteen participants in our sample lived in a census tract that formerly received the lowest grade <lb/>(D) from HOLC (Figure 3). Notably, neighborhoods receiving the lowest grade in the 1930s in the <lb/>central and western areas of Baltimore had a large degree of neighborhood deprivation as measured <lb/>by the ADI and RI many decades later (comparing Figure 3 with Figures 1 and 2). Six genes were <lb/>associated with living in a formerly redlined neighborhood (Table 2), and the expression of all but 1 <lb/>gene (ADRB1) was positively associated with the redlined status, although none of these findings <lb/>remained significant after multiple-comparison adjustment. <lb/>Some of the genes were associated with more than 1 neighborhood measure at the P &lt; .05 level. <lb/>HTR6 was associated with both ADI and RI. FOS was associated with both ADI and NDI. IFIT2 and MX2 <lb/>(type I interferon responses) were associated with ADI, RI, and historical redlining. Of note, there <lb/>were several proinflammatory genes that were associated with neighborhood disadvantage at the <lb/>P &lt; .05 level (eg, CXCL8 and ADI, β = 0.008; SE, 0.003; P = .01; q value = .21; IL1B and FOSL2 also <lb/>Figure 1. Area Deprivation Index (ADI) Values of Participants in the Baltimore City Area <lb/>39.35°N <lb/>39.30°N <lb/>39.25°N <lb/>39.20°N <lb/>76.70°W <lb/>76.65°W <lb/>76.60°W <lb/>76.55°W <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>ADI <lb/>Higher values indicate greater neighborhood <lb/>deprivation. Participant locations are slightly <lb/>jittered to maintain confidentiality. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>showed higher expression with higher ADI; FOS with ADI and NDI; and PTGS1 with redlining). <lb/>However, the results were not statistically significant after adjustment for multiple comparisons. <lb/>The top findings for the sensitivity analysis among African American men only (representing the <lb/>majority of the study population) were similar to the results from the primary analysis among African <lb/>American and White men combined (eTable 3 in Supplement 1). Additionally, we found that insurance <lb/>status (primary payer at diagnosis) was not an important confounder of our top associations between <lb/>the neighborhood metrics and prostate tumor RNA expression of stress-related genes, with relatively <lb/>small percentage changes in the coefficient for the neighborhood measures after adjustment for this <lb/>variable (eTable 4 in Supplement 1). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we evaluated neighborhood disadvantage (based on ADI, NDI, RI, and historical <lb/>redlining) and prostate tumor RNA expression of stress-related genes among African American and <lb/>White men. To our knowledge, our study is one of the first to identify associations between <lb/>neighborhood factors and RNA expression in prostate tumor tissue. We identified several <lb/>associations at the P &lt; .05 level between neighborhood factors and stress-related genes. For most of <lb/>the top findings, including 5 proinflammatory genes in the CTRA, higher disadvantage was associated <lb/>Table 2. Summary of Stress-Related Genes Associated With the Neighborhood Measures in Adjusted Models <lb/>Among African American and White Men Who Received Radical Prostatectomy Surgery for Prostate Cancer <lb/>at the University of Maryland Medical Center, 1992-2021 <lb/>TC <lb/>Gene <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Beta (SE) a <lb/>P value a <lb/>q Value b <lb/>ADI, 160 participants <lb/>TC0100007175.hg.1 <lb/>HTR6 <lb/>Serotonin <lb/>0.003 (0.001) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>.01 <lb/>TC0500012405.hg.1 <lb/>HTR4 <lb/>Serotonin <lb/>0.004 (0.001) <lb/>.003 <lb/>.15 <lb/>TC0300009685.hg.1 <lb/>HTR3D <lb/>Serotonin <lb/>0.003 (0.001) <lb/>.006 <lb/>.18 <lb/>TC1000008401.hg.1 <lb/>IFIT5 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.005 (0.002) <lb/>.009 <lb/>.18 <lb/>TC1000008396.hg.1 <lb/>IFIT2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.005 (0.002) <lb/>.009 <lb/>.18 <lb/>TC0400007836.hg.1 <lb/>CXCL8 <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.008 (0.003) <lb/>.01 <lb/>.21 <lb/>TC0200007096.hg.1 <lb/>FOSL2 <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.004 (0.002) <lb/>.02 <lb/>.30 <lb/>TC0200013916.hg.1 <lb/>IL1B <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.005 (0.002) <lb/>.02 <lb/>.30 <lb/>TC2100007205.hg.1 <lb/>MX2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.004 (0.002) <lb/>.03 <lb/>.33 <lb/>TC0100008815.hg.1 <lb/>IFI44L <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.005 (0.003) <lb/>.04 <lb/>.39 <lb/>TC1400007706.hg.1 <lb/>FOS <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.010 (0.005) <lb/>.05 <lb/>.43 <lb/>RI; 136 participants <lb/>TC0100007175.hg.1 <lb/>HTR6 <lb/>Serotonin <lb/>0.179 (0.063) <lb/>.005 <lb/>.54 <lb/>TC2200008174.hg.1 <lb/>IGLL1 <lb/>Antibody synthesis <lb/>0.231 (0.097) <lb/>.02 <lb/>.63 <lb/>TC0300009686.hg.1 <lb/>HTR3C <lb/>Serotonin <lb/>0.324 (0.143) <lb/>.03 <lb/>.63 <lb/>TC1000008396.hg.1 <lb/>IFIT2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.342 (0.152) <lb/>.03 <lb/>.63 <lb/>TC2100007205.hg.1 <lb/>MX2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.318 (0.153) <lb/>.04 <lb/>.63 <lb/>TC1100008123.hg.1 <lb/>ADRBK1 <lb/>Adrenergic <lb/>0.196 (0.095) <lb/>.04 <lb/>.63 <lb/>TC1600008712.hg.1 <lb/>IRF8 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.327 (0.159) <lb/>.04 <lb/>.63 <lb/>Redlining; 218 participants <lb/>TC0900008660.hg.1 <lb/>PTGS1 <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.337 (0.133) <lb/>.01 <lb/>.59 <lb/>TC2100007205.hg.1 <lb/>MX2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.288 (0.115) <lb/>.01 <lb/>.59 <lb/>TC1000008396.hg.1 <lb/>IFIT2 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.266 (0.116) <lb/>.02 <lb/>.59 <lb/>TC1000008968.hg.1 <lb/>ADRB1 <lb/>Adrenergic <lb/>-0.352 (0.154) <lb/>.02 <lb/>.59 <lb/>TC0100018367.hg.1 <lb/>CHRM3 <lb/>Muscarinic <lb/>0.332 (0.153) <lb/>.03 <lb/>.59 <lb/>TC1200008920.hg.1 <lb/>OAS3 <lb/>Type I IFN responses <lb/>0.185 (0.087) <lb/>.03 <lb/>.59 <lb/>NDI; 211 participants <lb/>TC1400007706.hg.1 <lb/>FOS <lb/>Proinflammatory <lb/>0.195 (95% CrI, <lb/>-0.045 to 0.404) <lb/>EP, <lb/>95.8% c <lb/>NA <lb/>Abbreviations: ADI, Area Deprivation Index; CrI, <lb/>credible interval; EP, exceedance probability; IFN, <lb/>interferon; NA, not applicable; NDI, Neighborhood <lb/>Deprivation Index; RI, Racial Isolation Index; TC, <lb/>transcript cluster. <lb/>a From linear regression modeling the given gene <lb/>association with the neighborhood measure, <lb/>adjusted for race, age at surgery, and year of surgery. <lb/>b P value adjusted for multiple comparisons using the <lb/>Benjamini-Hochberg false-discovery rate approach. <lb/>c EP indicates the probability of being greater <lb/>than zero. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>with higher RNA expression. Several of the top genes, including HTR6 (serotonin pathway) were <lb/>associated with more than 1 neighborhood measure. Notably, the association between ADI and HTR6 <lb/>remained statistically significant after multiple-comparison adjustment. <lb/>HTR6, which was positively associated with both ADI and RI, encodes a receptor that is part of <lb/>the 7-transmembrane G protein-coupled receptor family and plays a role in activating the cyclic <lb/>AMP-dependent signaling pathway. This receptor is hypothesized to be involved in regulating <lb/>cholinergic neuronal transmission. Among other roles, the cholinergic system is important in <lb/>regulating immune response, and its dysregulation is thought to contribute to some inflammatory <lb/>and autoimmune conditions. 34 There is also evidence that expression of HTR genes may be <lb/>associated with lethal prostate cancer. A previous study 29 reported mixed associations between <lb/>prostate tumor expression of 17 HTR genes and lethal prostate cancer. Among these, HTR2A and <lb/>HTR2B were positively associated with lethal prostate cancer, while HTR6 was inversely associated. <lb/>It is unclear why the direction of the HTR6 association differs from that we observed for HTR6 and <lb/>neighborhood disadvantage, but this may be due in part to different stage distributions between the <lb/>studies, which could have influenced expression levels and warrants further investigation in <lb/>future studies. <lb/>It is noteworthy that we observed positive associations between neighborhood disadvantage <lb/>and several proinflammatory genes given that these genes tend to be upregulated in the CTRA. 28 A <lb/>recent prostate cancer case-control study 16 found that neighborhood deprivation was associated <lb/>with increased activity scores for serum proteome-defined pathways related to inflammation among <lb/>control participants. Moreover, inflammation has been linked with increased prostate tumor <lb/>development and progression. 11-13 Therefore, findings for these genes were in an expected direction. <lb/>Figure 2. Racial Isolation Index (RI) Values of Participants in the Baltimore City Area <lb/>39.35°N <lb/>39.30°N <lb/>39.25°N <lb/>39.20°N <lb/>76.70°W <lb/>76.65°W <lb/>76.60°W <lb/>76.55°W <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>RI <lb/>Higher values indicate greater African American <lb/>residential segregation. Participant locations are <lb/>slightly jittered to maintain confidentiality. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Findings from our study support and build on existing literature on the emerging importance of <lb/>neighborhood factors for aggressive prostate cancer and prostate cancer disparities. Similar to <lb/>previous studies, 4,5 we found that African American men with prostate cancer were more likely than <lb/>their White counterparts to reside in disadvantaged neighborhoods. Various studies have observed <lb/>associations between neighborhood disadvantage and advanced or aggressive prostate cancer. 5-8 <lb/>Moreover, a study in Detroit 35 found that neighborhood socioeconomic status was an important <lb/>factor contributing to racial disparities in prostate cancer mortality. We recognize there are many <lb/>factors that may contribute to these associations. 36 Here we investigated one biological pathway in <lb/>relation to the neighborhood factors based on accumulating evidence for a role of chronic stress in <lb/>associations for neighborhood factors and aggressive tumor biology. 15 <lb/>Strengths and Limitations <lb/>Our study has several strengths. First, we used several measures of neighborhood disadvantage, <lb/>which provided a more comprehensive view than would have been allowed by analyzing only 1 factor <lb/>and included many components of disadvantage. A second strength was the use of the flexible, <lb/>validated bayesian index regression model to compute the NDI. This model has shown improved <lb/>goodness of fit when compared with other methods, such as principal component analysis and factor <lb/>analysis, which can result in indices that are more difficult to interpret and do not consider the <lb/>relative importance of individual model components for the outcome. 37,38 In our study, FOS was <lb/>associated with both ADI and NDI, but we found that the association was largely driven by 2 NDI <lb/>components. A third strength was the availability of transcriptomic data, which allowed evaluation of <lb/>a number of stress-related genes. <lb/>Study limitations included the relatively small sample sizes for our analyses (ranging from 136 to <lb/>218 based on data availability for different disadvantage metrics in different time periods) and <lb/>Figure 3. Neighborhood Grades From 1930s Home Owners&apos; Loan Corporation Map for Participants <lb/>in the Baltimore Area <lb/>39.40°N <lb/>39.35°N <lb/>39.30°N <lb/>39.20°N <lb/>39.25°N <lb/>76.75°W <lb/>76.70°W <lb/>76.65°W <lb/>76.55°W <lb/>76.60°W <lb/>76.50°W <lb/>A <lb/>HOLC grade <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>All neighborhoods receiving grades are plotted on the <lb/>map, and the residential locations of participants in <lb/>the Baltimore area residing in these neighborhoods are <lb/>overlaid. Participant locations are slightly jittered to <lb/>maintain confidentiality. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>selection of men undergoing surgery. Therefore, our findings may not be generalizable to a broader <lb/>group of men with prostate cancer. However, we found that areas contributing participants to our <lb/>sample did not systematically differ from other areas in Maryland with respect to socioeconomic <lb/>indicators or health care access factors, reducing the likelihood of selection bias. Second, we defined <lb/>the measures of neighborhood disadvantage based on each participant&apos;s residence at diagnosis, and <lb/>we did not have access to their residential histories. This could have resulted in some exposure <lb/>misclassification. Third, we had limited data on individual-level factors (eg, income) that could be <lb/>contributing to our findings as confounders, effect modifiers, or mediators. 39-41 However, we found <lb/>that primary payer at diagnosis (which we expect to be associated with individual socioeconomic <lb/>status) was not an important confounder of the observed associations. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In conclusion, we identified several suggestive associations between neighborhood disadvantage <lb/>metrics and prostate tumor RNA expression of stress-related genes among African American and <lb/>White men with prostate cancer, which warrant follow-up in larger studies. These findings support a <lb/>potential link between neighborhood factors and stress-related pathways, which may in turn <lb/>contribute to an increased risk of aggressive prostate cancer. Additional research is needed to further <lb/>investigate the interrelationships of neighborhood factors, individual factors, prostate tumor biology, <lb/>tumor aggressiveness, and prostate cancer outcomes, including mediation analyses with survival <lb/>outcomes, to help inform interventions that will reduce prostate cancer disparities. <lb/></body>

			<front>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Accepted for Publication: May 9, 2024. <lb/>Published: July 12, 2024. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 <lb/>Open Access: This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2024 Boyle J <lb/>et al. JAMA Network Open. <lb/>Corresponding Author: Kathryn Hughes Barry, PhD, MPH, Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, <lb/>University of Maryland School of Medicine, 660 W Redwood St, Howard Hall 100E, Baltimore, MD 21201 (kbarry@ <lb/>som.umaryland.edu). <lb/>Author Affiliations: Department of Biostatistics, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond (Boyle, Wheeler); <lb/>Massey Comprehensive Cancer Center, Richmond, Virginia (Boyle, Wheeler); Department of Cellular and Molecular <lb/>Biomedical Science, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore (Yau); Maryland Community Health <lb/>Engagement Partnership, Upper Marlboro (Slade); Prostate Health Matters, Washington, DC (Butts); Department <lb/>of Epidemiology and Public Health, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore (Zhang, Barry); Program <lb/>in Oncology, University of Maryland Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center, Baltimore (Zhang, Ambulos, Yin, <lb/>Hussain, Onukwugha, Knott, Barry); Department of Pathology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, <lb/>Baltimore (Legesse); Pathology Biorepository Shared Service, University of Maryland Greenebaum <lb/>Comprehensive Cancer Center, Baltimore (Cellini, Clark); Department of Cancer Epidemiology, H. Lee Moffitt <lb/>Cancer Center, Tampa, Florida (Park); University of Maryland Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center Tumor <lb/>Registry, Baltimore (Wimbush); Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Maryland School of <lb/>Medicine, Baltimore (Ambulos, Yin); Department of Medicine, University of Maryland School of Medicine, <lb/>Baltimore (Hussain); Baltimore Veterans Administration Medical Center, Baltimore, Maryland (Hussain); <lb/>Department of Practice, Sciences, and Health Outcomes Research, University of Maryland School of Pharmacy, <lb/>Baltimore (Onukwugha); Department of Behavioral and Community Health, University of Maryland, College Park, <lb/>College Park (Knott). <lb/></front>
    
            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Drs Barry and Boyle had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for <lb/>the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Drs Wheeler and Barry share senior authorship. <lb/>Concept and design: Boyle, Slade, Butts, Cellini, Knott, Wheeler, Barry. <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Yau, Zhang, Legesse, Clark, Park, Wimbush, Ambulos, Yin, Hussain, <lb/>Onukwugha, Wheeler, Barry. <lb/>Drafting of the manuscript: Boyle, Butts, Barry. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Boyle, Yau, Slade, Zhang, Legesse, Cellini, Clark, <lb/>Park, Wimbush, Ambulos, Yin, Hussain, Onukwugha, Knott, Wheeler, Barry. <lb/>Statistical analysis: Boyle, Yau, Zhang, Wheeler. <lb/>Obtained funding: Barry. <lb/>Administrative, technical, or material support: Yau, Slade, Butts, Zhang, Legesse, Cellini, Clark, Park, Wimbush, <lb/>Ambulos, Yin. <lb/>Supervision: Zhang, Knott, Wheeler, Barry. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: Dr Legesse reported receiving grants from the American Cancer Society and the <lb/>National Cancer Institute during the conduct of the study. Dr Onukwugha reported receiving grants from BeiGene <lb/>Ltd and Organon and Co and receiving personal fees from PhRMA Foundation and the Innovation and Value <lb/>Initiative outside the submitted work. Dr Wheeler reported receiving grants from the American Cancer Society <lb/>during the conduct of the study. Dr Barry reported receiving grants from the National Cancer Institute, the <lb/>American Cancer Society, Maryland Department of Health&apos;s Cigarette Restitution Fund Program, and the National <lb/>Center for Advancing Translational Sciences during the conduct of the study. No other disclosures were reported. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding/Support: This project was supported by an American Cancer Society Institutional Research Grant at the <lb/>University of Maryland Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center (grant No. IRG-18-160-16). This project was <lb/>also supported by the National Cancer Institute (grant Nos. K07 CA230182 and 3K07CA230182-05S1 to Dr Barry; <lb/>NCI-Cancer Center Support Grant P30CA134274). Further support was provided through the Maryland <lb/>Department of Health&apos;s Cigarette Restitution Fund Program (award No. CH-649-CRF; salary support for Dr Barry) <lb/>and a Collaborative Program Award from the University of Maryland Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center <lb/>(to Dr Barry). We also acknowledge the support of the University of Maryland, Baltimore Institute for Clinical and <lb/>Translational Research and the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences CTSA grant No. <lb/>1UL1TR003098. <lb/>Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, <lb/>management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and <lb/>decision to submit the manuscript for publication. <lb/>Meeting Presentations: We presented a talk and poster on this project at the 16th AACR Conference on the <lb/>Science of Cancer Health Disparities in Racial/Ethnic Minorities and the Medically Underserved; September 30, <lb/>2023; Orlando, Florida. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Sharing Statement: See Supplement 2. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Additional Contributions: The authors thank the Pathology and Genomics Shared Services of the University of <lb/>Maryland Marlene and Stewart Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center for their contributions in preparing the <lb/>prostate tumor tissue samples and obtaining the transcriptomic data used in the present study. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Siegel RL, Giaquinto AN, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2024. CA Cancer J Clin. 2024;74(1):12-49. doi:10.3322/ <lb/>caac.21820 <lb/>2. Pietro GD, Chornokur G, Kumar NB, Davis C, Park JY. Racial differences in the diagnosis and treatment of <lb/>prostate cancer. Int Neurourol J. 2016;20(suppl 2):S112-S119. doi:10.5213/inj.1632722.361 <lb/>3. Powell IJ. Epidemiology and pathophysiology of prostate cancer in African-American men. J Urol. 2007;177(2): <lb/>444-449. doi:10.1016/j.juro.2006.09.024 <lb/>4. Onukwugha E, Osteen P, Jayasekera J, Mullins CD, Mair CA, Hussain A. Racial disparities in urologist visits <lb/>among elderly men with prostate cancer: a cohort analysis of patient-related and county of residence-related <lb/>factors. Cancer. 2014;120(21):3385-3392. doi:10.1002/cncr.28894 <lb/>5. Jayasekera J, Onukwugha E, Cadham C, Tom S, Harrington D, Naslund M. Epidemiological determinants of <lb/>advanced prostate cancer in elderly men in the United States. Clin Med Insights Oncol. Published online June 26, <lb/>2019. doi:10.1177/1179554919855116 <lb/>6. Coughlin SS. A review of social determinants of prostate cancer risk, stage, and survival. Prostate Int. 2020;8 <lb/>(2):49-54. doi:10.1016/j.prnil.2019.08.001 <lb/>7. Lynch SM, Mitra N, Ross M, et al. A neighborhood-wide association study (NWAS): example of prostate cancer <lb/>aggressiveness. PLoS One. 2017;12(3):e0174548. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0174548 <lb/>8. Zeigler-Johnson CM, Tierney A, Rebbeck TR, Rundle A. Prostate cancer severity associations with neighborhood <lb/>deprivation. Prostate Cancer. 2011;2011:846263. doi:10.1155/2011/846263 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>9. Gehlert S, Sohmer D, Sacks T, Mininger C, McClintock M, Olopade O. Targeting health disparities: a model linking <lb/>upstream determinants to downstream interventions. Health Aff (Millwood). 2008;27(2):339-349. doi:10.1377/ <lb/>hlthaff.27.2.339 <lb/>10. Taylor SE, Repetti RL, Seeman T. Health psychology: what is an unhealthy environment and how does it get <lb/>under the skin? Annu Rev Psychol. 1997;48(1):411-447. doi:10.1146/annurev.psych.48.1.411 <lb/>11. Rani A, Dasgupta P, Murphy JJ. Prostate cancer: the role of inflammation and chemokines. Am J Pathol. 2019; <lb/>189(11):2119-2137. doi:10.1016/j.ajpath.2019.07.007 <lb/>12. Platz EA, Kulac I, Barber JR, et al. A prospective study of chronic inflammation in benign prostate tissue and risk <lb/>of prostate cancer: linked PCPT and SELECT cohorts. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2017;26(10):1549-1557. <lb/>doi:10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-17-0503 <lb/>13. Zhang Y, Zhou CK, Rencsok EM, et al. A prospective study of intraprostatic inflammation, focal atrophy, and <lb/>progression to lethal prostate cancer. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2019;28(12):2047-2054. doi:10.1158/ <lb/>1055-9965.EPI-19-0713 <lb/>14. Nelson WG, Brawley OW, Isaacs WB, et al. Health inequity drives disease biology to create disparities in <lb/>prostate cancer outcomes. J Clin Invest. 2022;132(3):e155031. doi:10.1172/JCI155031 <lb/>15. Lord BD, Harris AR, Ambs S. The impact of social and environmental factors on cancer biology in Black <lb/>Americans. Cancer Causes Control. 2023;34(3):191-203. doi:10.1007/s10552-022-01664-w <lb/>16. Pichardo MS, Minas TZ, Pichardo CM, et al. Association of neighborhood deprivation with prostate cancer and <lb/>immune markers in African American and European American men. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(1):e2251745. doi: <lb/>10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.51745 <lb/>17. Zenou Y, Boccard N. Racial discrimination and redlining in cities. J Urban Econ. 2000;48(2):260-285. doi:10. <lb/>1006/juec.1999.2166 <lb/>18. Hillier AE. Redlining and the home owners&apos; loan corporation. J Urban Hist. 2003;29(4):394-420. doi:10.1177/ <lb/>0096144203029004002 <lb/>19. Wisniewski RE. Mortgage redlining (disinvestment): the parameters of federal, state, and municipal regulation. <lb/>U Det J Urb L. 1976;54:367-429. <lb/>20. Krieger N, Wright E, Chen JT, Waterman PD, Huntley ER, Arcaya M. Cancer stage at diagnosis, historical <lb/>redlining, and current neighborhood characteristics: breast, cervical, lung, and colorectal cancers, Massachusetts, <lb/>2001-2015. Am J Epidemiol. 2020;189(10):1065-1075. doi:10.1093/aje/kwaa045 <lb/>21. Bikomeye JC, Zhou Y, McGinley EL, et al. Historical redlining and breast cancer treatment and survival among <lb/>older women in the United States. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2023;115(6):652-661. doi:10.1093/jnci/djad034 <lb/>22. Kind AJH, Jencks S, Brock J, et al. Neighborhood socioeconomic disadvantage and 30-day rehospitalization: <lb/>a retrospective cohort study. Ann Intern Med. 2014;161(11):765-774. doi:10.7326/M13-2946 <lb/>23. Singh GK. Area deprivation and widening inequalities in US mortality, 1969-1998. Am J Public Health. 2003;93 <lb/>(7):1137-1143. doi:10.2105/AJPH.93.7.1137 <lb/>24. Wheeler DC, Rustom S, Carli M, Whitehead TP, Ward MH, Metayer C. Bayesian group index regression for <lb/>modeling chemical mixtures and cancer risk. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(7):3486. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>ijerph18073486 <lb/>25. Wheeler DC, Czarnota J, Jones RM. Estimating an area-level socioeconomic status index and its association <lb/>with colonoscopy screening adherence. PLoS One. 2017;12(6):e0179272. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0179272 <lb/>26. Anthopolos R, James SA, Gelfand AE, Miranda ML. A spatial measure of neighborhood level racial isolation <lb/>applied to low birthweight, preterm birth, and birthweight in North Carolina. Spat Spatiotemporal Epidemiol. 2011; <lb/>2(4):235-246. doi:10.1016/j.sste.2011.06.002 <lb/>27. Barry KH, Mohanty K, Erickson PA, et al. MYC DNA methylation in prostate tumor tissue is associated with <lb/>Gleason score. Genes (Basel). 2020;12(1):12. doi:10.3390/genes12010012 <lb/>28. Fredrickson BL, Grewen KM, Coffey KA, et al. A functional genomic perspective on human well-being. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110(33):13684-13689. doi:10.1073/pnas.1305419110 <lb/>29. Lu D, Sinnott JA, Valdimarsdóttir U, et al. Stress-related signaling pathways in lethal and nonlethal prostate <lb/>cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2016;22(3):765-772. doi:10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-15-0101 <lb/>30. Digital Scholarship Lab, University of Richmond. Mapping inequality: redlining in New Deal America. June 23, <lb/>2023. Accessed July 23, 2023. https://dsl.richmond.edu/panorama/redlining/ <lb/>31. Benjamini Y, Hochberg Y. Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple <lb/>testing. J R Stat Soc B. 1995;57(1):289-300. doi:10.1111/j.2517-6161.1995.tb02031.x <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>32. US Department of Agriculture. County-level data sets. Accessed December 14, 2023. https://www.ers.usda.gov/ <lb/>data-products/county-level-data-sets/ <lb/>33. National Cancer Institute. Catchment areas of NCI-designated cancer centers. Accessed December 14, 2023. <lb/>https://gis.cancer.gov/ncicatchment/app/ <lb/>34. Halder N, Lal G. Cholinergic system and its therapeutic importance in inflammation and autoimmunity. Front <lb/>Immunol. 2021;12:660342. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2021.660342 <lb/>35. Snider NG, Hastert TA, Nair M, et al. Area-level socioeconomic disadvantage and cancer survival in <lb/>metropolitan Detroit. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2023;32(3):387-397. doi:10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-<lb/>22-0738 <lb/>36. Cuevas AG, Trudel-Fitzgerald C, Cofie L, Zaitsu M, Allen J, Williams DR. Placing prostate cancer disparities <lb/>within a psychosocial context: challenges and opportunities for future research. Cancer Causes Control. 2019;30 <lb/>(5):443-456. doi:10.1007/s10552-019-01159-1 <lb/>37. Wheeler DC, Jones RM, Schootman M, Nelson EJ. Explaining variation in elevated blood lead levels among <lb/>children in Minnesota using neighborhood socioeconomic variables. Sci Total Environ. 2019;650(Pt 1):970-977. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.09.088 <lb/>38. Lian M, Madden PA, Lynskey MT, et al. Geographic variation in maternal smoking during pregnancy in the <lb/>Missouri Adolescent Female Twin Study (MOAFTS). PLoS One. 2016;11(4):e0153930. doi:10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0153930 <lb/>39. Warnecke RB, Oh A, Breen N, et al. Approaching health disparities from a population perspective: the National <lb/>Institutes of Health Centers for Population Health and Health Disparities. Am J Public Health. 2008;98(9): <lb/>1608-1615. doi:10.2105/AJPH.2006.102525 <lb/>40. Iyer HS, Zeinomar N, Omilian AR, et al. Neighborhood disadvantage, African genetic ancestry, cancer subtype, <lb/>and mortality among breast cancer survivors. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(8):e2331295. doi:10.1001/ <lb/>jamanetworkopen.2023.31295 <lb/>41. Howe CJ, Bailey ZD, Raifman JR, Jackson JW. Recommendations for using causal diagrams to study racial <lb/>health disparities. Am J Epidemiol. 2022;191(12):1981-1989. doi:10.1093/aje/kwac140 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 1. <lb/>eTable 1. List of Stress-Related Genes Evaluated in the Present Study and Their Associated Pathways <lb/>eTable 2. Summary of Comparing Socioeconomic and Health Care Access Indicators Between Counties and Census <lb/>Tracts in Maryland Contributing vs Not Contributing Participants to Our Sample of Men Who Received Radical <lb/>Prostatectomy Surgery for Prostate Cancer at the University of Maryland Medical Center, 1992-2021 <lb/>eTable 3. Summary of Genes Associated With the Neighborhood Measures in Adjusted Models for African <lb/>American Men Who Received Radical Prostatectomy Surgery for Prostate Cancer at the University of Maryland <lb/>Medical Center, 1992-2021 <lb/>eTable 4. Summary of Sensitivity Analysis Additionally Adjusting for Primary Payer at Diagnosis for Genes <lb/>Associated With the Neighborhood Measures in Adjusted Models Among African American and White Men Who <lb/>Received Radical Prostatectomy Surgery for Prostate Cancer at the University of Maryland Medical Center, 1992-<lb/>2021 <lb/>eFigure 1. Flowchart Illustrating Sample Selection <lb/>eFigure 2. Area Deprivation Index Values of Participants in Sample <lb/>eFigure 3. Racial Isolation Index Values of Participants in Sample <lb/>eMethods. <lb/>eReferences. <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 2. <lb/>Data Sharing Statement <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Oncology <lb/>Neighborhood Disadvantage and Prostate Tumor Expression of Stress-Related Genes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(7):e2421903. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.21903 (Reprinted) <lb/>July 12, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 </note>


	</text>
</TEI>