<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Enhancing efficacy of the MEK inhibitor trametinib with paclitaxel in &lt;i&gt;KRAS&lt;/i&gt;-mutated colorectal cancer</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Susmita</forename>
          <surname>Ghosh</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Fan</forename>
          <surname>Fan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Reid</forename>
          <surname>Powell</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yong Sung</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Clifford</forename>
          <surname>Stephan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>E. Scott</forename>
          <surname>Kopetz</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lee M.</forename>
          <surname>Ellis</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rajat</forename>
          <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T16:01:21.002Z">11/12/2025 4:01:21 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1177/17588359241303302</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Susmita Ghosh, Fan Fan, Reid Powell, Yong Sung Park, Clifford Stephan, E. Scott Kopetz, Lee M. Ellis, Rajat Bhattacharya. (2024). Enhancing efficacy of the MEK inhibitor trametinib with paclitaxel in &lt;i&gt;KRAS&lt;/i&gt;-mutated colorectal cancer. Therapeutic Advances in Medical Oncology, 16(None), None. DOI: 10.1177/17588359241303302</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T16:01:11.836223Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T16:01:11.836223Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>https://doi.org/10.1177/17562848241256237 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/17562848241256237 <lb/>Ther Adv Gastroenterol <lb/>2024, Vol. 17: 1-15 <lb/>DOI: 10.1177/ <lb/>17562848241256237 <lb/>© The Author(s), 2024. <lb/>Article reuse guidelines: <lb/>sagepub.com/journals-<lb/>permissions <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/>1 <lb/>Creative Commons Non Commercial CC BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License <lb/>(https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission <lb/>provided the original work is attributed as specified on the Sage and Open Access pages (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). <lb/>TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/>Development and validation of a novel <lb/>therapeutic drug monitoring-based <lb/>nomogram for prediction of primary <lb/>endoscopic response to anti-TNF therapy in <lb/>active Crohn&apos;s disease <lb/>Liang Chen*, Dengfeng Kang*, Leilei Fang, Mingming Sun, Mingsong Li, Guangxi Zhou, <lb/>Chunjin Xu, Zhi Pang, Yulan Ye, Baisui Feng, Huili Wu, Jian Lin, Baijing Ding, Changqin Liu, <lb/>Yanhong Shi and Zhanju Liu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF) monoclonal antibodies, especially infliximab <lb/>(IFX) and adalimumab (ADA), are considered the first-line treatment for active Crohn&apos;s disease <lb/>(CD). However, the predictive role of therapeutic drug monitoring (TDM) of serum anti-TNF in <lb/>monitoring the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) remains controversial. <lb/>Objectives: To explore the correlation between serum anti-TNF levels and early endoscopic <lb/>response in active CD using a TDM-based nomogram. <lb/>Design: Cross-sectional study. <lb/>Methods: The simplified endoscopic activity score for CD (SES-CD), Crohn&apos;s disease activity <lb/>index (CDAI), laboratory parameters, and the serum trough levels of IFX and ADA were <lb/>assessed. <lb/>Results: The trough levels of IFX or ADA were significantly higher in patients with endoscopic <lb/>response compared to non-responders in the development cohort (p &lt; 0.001). The IFX and <lb/>ADA levels showed a weak but significantly negative correlation with SES-CD (p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>CDAI (p &lt; 0.001), and C-reactive protein (CRP) (p &lt; 0.001) at week 14 post-IFX therapy in the <lb/>development cohort. Furthermore, the receiver operating characteristic curve revealed that <lb/>an optimal level of IFX (4.80 μg/mL) and ADA (8.80 μg/mL) exhibited the best performance in <lb/>predicting endoscopic response. Concomitantly, we developed a novel nomogram prediction <lb/>model based on the results of multivariate logistic regression analysis, which consisted of <lb/>CRP, albumin (Alb), and anti-TNF trough levels at week 14. The nomogram showed significant <lb/>discrimination and calibration for both IFX and ADA in the development cohort and performed <lb/>well in the external validation cohort. <lb/>Conclusion: This study demonstrates a robust association between serum concentrations of <lb/>IFX, ADA, Alb, and CRP and primary endoscopic response in active CD patients. Importantly, <lb/>the TDM-and laboratory marker-based nomogram may be used to evaluate the primary <lb/>endoscopic response to anti-TNF therapy, especially for optimizing treatment strategies and <lb/>switching therapy in CD patients. <lb/>Plain language summary <lb/>Therapeutic drug monitoring-based nomogram predicts primary endoscopic response <lb/>in Crohn&apos;s disease <lb/>The present study established a therapeutic drug monitoring-based nomogram, which <lb/>exhibits an exceptional predictive value, remarkable accuracy, and discrimination. This <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Changqin Liu <lb/>Yanhong Shi <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Shanghai Tenth People&apos;s <lb/>Hospital of Tongji <lb/>University, Shanghai <lb/>200072, China <lb/>Changqinliu66@163.com <lb/>shiyanhong71@163.com <lb/>Zhanju Liu <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Shanghai Tenth People&apos;s <lb/>Hospital of Tongji <lb/>University, Shanghai <lb/>200072, China <lb/>liuzhanju88@126.com <lb/>Liang Chen <lb/>Dengfeng Kang <lb/>Leilei Fang <lb/>Mingming Sun <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Shanghai Tenth People&apos;s <lb/>Hospital of Tongji <lb/>University, Shanghai, <lb/>China <lb/>Mingsong Li <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, The <lb/>Third Affiliated Hospital <lb/>of Guangzhou Medical <lb/>University, Guangzhou, <lb/>China <lb/>Guangxi Zhou <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Jining <lb/>Medical College, Jining, <lb/>China <lb/>Chunjin Xu <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, First <lb/>People&apos;s Hospital of <lb/>Shangqiu City Affiliated <lb/>to Xinxiang Medical <lb/>University, Shangqiu, <lb/>China <lb/>Zhi Pang <lb/>Yulan Ye <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, Suzhou <lb/>Municipal Hospital <lb/>Affiliated to Nanjing <lb/>Medical University, <lb/>Suzhou, China <lb/>1256237T AG0010.1177/17562848241256237Therapeutic Advances in GastroenterologyL Chen, D Kang <lb/>research-article20242024 <lb/>Original Research <lb/>Volume 17 <lb/>2 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/>TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>The utilization of monoclonal antibody (mAb) <lb/>therapy targeting tumor necrosis factor (anti-<lb/>TNF), such as infliximab (IFX) and adalimumab <lb/>(ADA), has become a crucial requirement for <lb/>treating active Crohn&apos;s disease (CD). Controlled <lb/>clinical trials have demonstrated the efficacy and <lb/>safety of anti-TNF mAbs in the treatment of <lb/>moderate to severe CD for the induction and <lb/>maintenance of clinical and endoscopic remis-<lb/>sion, reducing hospitalizations, relapse rates, and <lb/>surgeries and improving the quality of life. 1-6 <lb/>However, approximately one-third of the patients <lb/>fail to respond to initial anti-TNF therapies by <lb/>the end of an induction period. Furthermore, 20-<lb/>40% of patients show an initial response but lose <lb/>response over time. 7-10 Thus, strategies to opti-<lb/>mize anti-TNF therapy are necessary. <lb/>Several lines of evidence have demonstrated that <lb/>therapeutic drug monitoring (TDM) is emerging <lb/>as a standardized treatment approach for optimiz-<lb/>ing anti-TNF treatment in inflammatory bowel <lb/>disease (IBD). Some retrospective cohort studies <lb/>have proposed TDM as a strategy to maximize <lb/>the safety, efficacy, and cost-effectiveness of anti-<lb/>TNF therapy. 11-13 It has been well established to <lb/>effectively guide treatment de-escalation for <lb/>etanercept 14 and ADA 15,16 in patients with rheu-<lb/>matoid arthritis. However, the NORwegian <lb/>DRUg Monitoring study trial has shown that the <lb/>routine use of TDM during induction therapy <lb/>with IFX did not improve the rates of disease <lb/>remission. 17 A meta-analysis has also demon-<lb/>strated that the proactive TDM regimen showed <lb/>no significant difference in the maintenance of <lb/>clinical remission compared with conventional <lb/>management [RR, 0.96; 95% confidence interval <lb/>(CI), 0.81-1.13]. 18 However, the role of TDM in <lb/>predicting the efficacy of anti-TNF therapy in <lb/>IBD patients remains controversial, particularly, <lb/>the predictive values of proactive TDM and reac-<lb/>tive TDM. Two induction trials with ADA for <lb/>CD and UC (SERENE-CD and SERENE-UC) <lb/>have indicated that proactive TDM strategy is <lb/>not superior to the reactive TDM for prediction <lb/>of endoscopic and clinical response. 19,20 <lb/>Nevertheless, a pediatric study has indicated that <lb/>proactive monitoring and ADA dose intensifica-<lb/>tion (serum concentrations &gt;5 μg/mL) could <lb/>contribute to significantly higher rates of corticos-<lb/>teroid-free clinical remission than reactive moni-<lb/>toring in cases of loss of response (LOR). 21 <lb/>Despite being controversial, emerging evidence <lb/>has indicated that high serum anti-TNF drug <lb/>concentrations appear to be associated with bet-<lb/>ter clinical outcomes in IBD. 22-25 Furthermore, <lb/>TDM can help to identify the underlying mecha-<lb/>nisms of poor clinical outcomes, such as insuffi-<lb/>cient drug exposure or mechanistic failure due to <lb/>non-adherence or pharmacokinetic issues. 26 It is <lb/>worth mentioning that the majority of TDM-<lb/>related studies have mainly focused on the evalu-<lb/>ation of maintenance therapy instead of the <lb/>induction phase. More importantly, there are <lb/>only limited data mentioning TDM during the <lb/>induction phase in CD and even less data regard-<lb/>ing the therapeutic trough threshold of anti-TNF <lb/>as a target for an induction endpoint. 27 <lb/>To date, there is limited evidence to evaluate the <lb/>predictive value of the TDM strategy for inducing <lb/>the remission of active CD. Hence, in this retro-<lb/>spective clinical study, we aimed to explore the <lb/>correlation between pharmacokinetic parameters <lb/>and primary clinical efficacy and to predict early <lb/>endoscopic response of patients with active CD <lb/>using a novel TDM-based nomogram. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Patients <lb/>Patients diagnosed with active CD were treated <lb/>with anti-TNF mAbs between March 2017 and <lb/>February 2022 at the Center for IBD Research <lb/></body>
    
    <front>algorithmic nomogram holds the potential to enhance clinicians&apos; comprehension of the <lb/>underlying mechanisms contributing to individual patients&apos; failure in achieving expected <lb/>efficacy. Such approach is crucial for optimizing therapy options and facilitating biologic <lb/>switching in refractory Crohn&apos;s disease. <lb/>Keywords: anti-TNF levels, nomogram, primary endoscopic response, TDM <lb/>Received: 9 October 2023; revised manuscript accepted: 4 May 2024. <lb/>Baisui Feng <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, The <lb/>Second Affiliated Hospital <lb/>of Zhengzhou University, <lb/>Zhengzhou, China <lb/>Huili Wu <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Zhengzhou Central <lb/>Hospital Affiliated to <lb/>Zhengzhou University, <lb/>Zhengzhou, China <lb/>Jian Lin <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of <lb/>Putian University, Putian, <lb/>China <lb/>Baijing Ding <lb/>Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, Wuhu <lb/>First People&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Wuhu, Anhui, China <lb/>*These authors <lb/>contributed equally <lb/></front>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <body>and Department of Gastroenterology, Shanghai <lb/>Tenth People&apos;s Hospital of Tongji University as a <lb/>development cohort (n = 279). From May 2022 <lb/>to August 2023, consecutive patients with active <lb/>CD were prospectively enrolled from other nine <lb/>tertiary centers as the validation cohort (n = 137). <lb/>All patients with CD were diagnosed based on the <lb/>European Crohn&apos;s and Colitis Organization <lb/>guidelines. 28 The inclusion criteria for the present <lb/>study were as follows: (1) adult patients <lb/>(18 ⩽ age ⩽ 75); (2) a confirmed diagnosis of CD <lb/>for at least 3 months; (3) simplified endoscopic <lb/>activity score for CD (SES-CD) ⩾ 4 and Crohn&apos;s <lb/>disease activity index (CDAI) &gt; 150 29-31 ; (4) <lb/>without receiving any anti-TNF mAbs and other <lb/>biologics within the previous 3 months; and (5) <lb/>colonoscopy and TDM data for IFX and ADA <lb/>available. Concomitant treatment with immuno-<lb/>suppressants [e.g. azathioprine (AZA), metho-<lb/>trexate], oral 5-aminosalicylic acid, oral <lb/>corticosteroids (tapering regimens), or antibiotics <lb/>was allowed. The exclusion criteria were as fol-<lb/>lows: (1) history of bowel surgery; (2) lack of <lb/>colonoscopy procedures, clinical information, <lb/>and laboratory parameters; and (3) inability to <lb/>assess disease extent. <lb/>Therapeutic drug monitoring <lb/>The serum samples were obtained in all CD <lb/>patients at week 14 after receiving IFX or ADA <lb/>therapy following a protocol as described below <lb/>and sent to the Qingdao Bodhi Huisheng Medical <lb/>Laboratory (Qingdao, China) for further analysis. <lb/>The serum trough levels of IFX and ADA were <lb/>then measured on serum samples using a com-<lb/>mercially available ELISA kit (Tarcine BioMed <lb/>Inc., Beijing, China) according to the manufac-<lb/>turer&apos;s recommendations. All samples were run in <lb/>singlicate and expressed as μg/mL. Free anti-IFX <lb/>or anti-ADA antibodies were measured in parallel <lb/>to drug levels using the ELISA kit. As the kit is <lb/>sensitive to drugs, it only detects anti-drug <lb/>antibodies. <lb/>Study design and assessments <lb/>The reporting of this study adheres to the <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational <lb/>Studies in Epidemiology statement. 32 Two hun-<lb/>dred and seventy-nine patients with active CD <lb/>were included in the development cohort. Among <lb/>them, 158 patients received intravenous infusion <lb/>of IFX (REMICADE; CilagAG, Schaffhausen, <lb/>Switzerland) (5 mg/kg) over 30 min on day 1 <lb/>(namely week 0) and at weeks 2, 6, and 14, while <lb/>121 patients received subcutaneous administra-<lb/>tion of ADA (Humira; AbbVie Inc, Chicago, IL, <lb/>USA) at doses of 160 mg at week 0, 80 mg at week <lb/>2, and thereafter 40 mg every 2 weeks for up to <lb/>14 weeks. The serum levels of IFX and ADA were <lb/>measured just prior to injection at week 14. <lb/>Ileo-colonoscopy was performed before treat-<lb/>ment and at week 14 post-injection. The endo-<lb/>scopic images were evaluated by experienced <lb/>central readers (DK and LC) who received train-<lb/>ing in scoring the SES-CD (score range 0-56). In <lb/>cases of discrepancy in the assessment between <lb/>the two investigators, a third investigator (ZL, <lb/>with 32 years of experience in colonoscopy) <lb/>reviewed the images to make the final decision. <lb/>Clinical assessments were performed using CDAI <lb/>scores and laboratory biomarkers, including <lb/>serum C-reactive protein (CRP), blood platelet <lb/>(Plt), albumin (Alb), and erythrocyte sedimenta-<lb/>tion rate (ESR). <lb/>Study endpoints <lb/>The primary endpoint of this study was to assess <lb/>the association between serum anti-TNF levels <lb/>(ADA and IFX) and primary endoscopic response <lb/>at week 14. The primary endoscopic response <lb/>was defined as a decrease in the SES-CD score by <lb/>&gt;50% compared with the baseline. 30 Exploratory <lb/>endpoints included the associations between <lb/>endoscopic response and the disease severity (i.e. <lb/>CDAI) and laboratory parameters (i.e. CRP, <lb/>ESR, Alb, and Plt). <lb/>Development and validation of a prediction <lb/>nomogram <lb/>Clinical variables were selected using univariate <lb/>and multivariate logistic regression analyses. <lb/>Selected variables were integrated into a predic-<lb/>tion model and presented as a nomogram. The <lb/>nomogram translated complex mathematical <lb/>models into a simple graph of scaled variables, <lb/>facilitating a quick approximation of the event <lb/>probability. A receiver operating characteristic <lb/>(ROC) curve was used to assess the discrimina-<lb/>tion of the nomogram. A calibration plot was <lb/>applied to assess the calibration of the nomogram <lb/>by comparing the actual and predicted probabili-<lb/>ties. The nomogram stability was verified by ten-<lb/>fold cross-validation. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Prospective validation cohort <lb/>We developed a prospective external validation <lb/>cohort from eight tertiary centers between May <lb/>2022 and August 2023 (n = 137). Seventy-nine <lb/>patients received intravenous infusion of IFX <lb/>(REMICADE), and 58 patients received subcu-<lb/>taneous administration of ADA (Humira). The <lb/>serum levels of IFX and ADA were measured just <lb/>prior to injection at week 14. Clinical and labora-<lb/>tory parameters of the patients were collected, as <lb/>mentioned above. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Continuous variables were presented as inter-<lb/>quartile ranges (IQRs). The Chi-square test was <lb/>performed to compare categorical data such as <lb/>patient sex and other clinical features. The <lb/>Mann-Whitney U test was performed to compare <lb/>non-parametric variables such as CDAI and <lb/>SES-CD. The correlations between the anti-TNF <lb/>levels and CDAI, SES-CD, CRP, Plt, Alb, and <lb/>ESR were tested using Spearman&apos;s rank correla-<lb/>tion coefficient. ROC curve analysis was used to <lb/>obtain the cutoff value with optimal sensitivity <lb/>and specificity. Multivariate regression analysis <lb/>was used to identify clinical predictors of endo-<lb/>scopic response. A p value less than 0.05 was con-<lb/>sidered statistically significant. Statistical analyses <lb/>were performed using Statistical Package for the <lb/>Social Sciences software (version 26.0; SPSS <lb/>Inc., New York, NY, USA), Prism software (ver-<lb/>sion 8.0), and R software (version 3.6.3). <lb/>Results <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>In total, 416 patients with active CD were enrolled <lb/>in this study. The clinical characteristics of 279 <lb/>patients in the development cohort are listed in <lb/>Table 1, and 137 patients in the validation cohort <lb/>are exhibited in Supplementary Table 1. Of these <lb/>patients, 237 were treated with IFX, and 179 <lb/>were treated with ADA. Most individuals <lb/>(98.79%) were naïve to biological agents. The <lb/>median age at baseline was 32 years (22.75-<lb/>42 years). The median course duration of these <lb/>patients was 27 months (6.0-65.0 months). <lb/>Among these patients, 232 (55.77%), 114 <lb/>(27.40%), and 150 (36.06%) were taking oral <lb/>5-aminosalicylates, AZA, and corticosteroids, <lb/>respectively. The majority of these patients exhib-<lb/>ited a moderate active disease with a mean CDAI <lb/>of 291.91 (236.20-372.22) and SES-CD of 11 <lb/>(6-19). The baseline clinical characteristics were <lb/>well balanced between the two cohorts <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). <lb/>Clinical predictors of primary endoscopic <lb/>response <lb/>An intention-to-treat analysis revealed that 70 of <lb/>158 patients (44.30%) in the IFX group and 66 <lb/>of 121 patients (54.55%) in the ADA group had <lb/>an endoscopic response at week 14 in the devel-<lb/>opment cohort. Univariate logistic analysis was <lb/>performed to further explore the available factors <lb/>that could predict the primary endoscopic <lb/>response. Notably, the serum trough levels of <lb/>IFX and ADA, but not anti-drug antibodies, were <lb/>significantly higher in patients with endoscopic <lb/>response rather than in non-responders <lb/>(p &lt; 0.001) (Figure 1 and Table 2). Moreover, <lb/>lower levels of SES-CD, CDAI scores, CRP, <lb/>ESR, and Plt, and higher levels of Alb all contrib-<lb/>uted to an endoscopic response in both IFX-and <lb/>ADA-treated groups (p &lt; 0.05) (Table 2). In a <lb/>univariate analysis, the characteristics of CD <lb/>patient, including sex [OR (odds ratio) 0.84, 95% <lb/>CI 0.42-1.69, p = 0.627], age (OR 1.02, 95% CI <lb/>0.99-1.04, p = 0.293), body mass index (OR <lb/>0.99, 95% CI 0.90-1.08, p = 0.750), disease <lb/>duration (OR 1.01, 95% CI 1.00-1.01, p = 0.114), <lb/>and concomitant immunosuppressants (OR 1.51, <lb/>95% CI 0.80-2.84, p = 0.201) showed no statisti-<lb/>cally significant differences in the development <lb/>cohort receiving IFX therapy (Table 2). <lb/>Moreover, the same pattern of changes was also <lb/>observed in the development cohort receiving <lb/>ADA treatment, except for age (OR 1.04, 95% <lb/>CI 1.01-1.07, p = 0.013) and disease duration <lb/>(OR 1.01, 95% CI 1.00-1.02, p = 0.030). <lb/>Correlations among anti-TNF level, CDAI, SES-<lb/>CD, and laboratory parameters <lb/>The correlation between endoscopic response <lb/>and the concentrations of IFX and ADA was <lb/>tested in the development cohort. The trough lev-<lb/>els of IFX demonstrated a weak but significant <lb/>negative correlation with SES-CD (r = -0.374, <lb/>p &lt; 0.001), CDAI (r = -0.383, p &lt; 0.001), and <lb/>CRP (r = -0.335, p &lt; 0.001), respectively [Figure <lb/>2(a)-(c)]. The trough levels of IFX also exhibited <lb/>a weak but significant correlation with ESR <lb/>(r = -0.297, p = 0.002) and Alb (r = 0.409, <lb/>p &lt; 0.001), respectively [Supplementary Figure <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 1. Baseline clinical characteristics. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Total <lb/>IFX <lb/>ADA <lb/>N = 279 <lb/>N = 158 <lb/>N = 121 <lb/>Male, n (%) <lb/>193 (69.18) <lb/>112 (70.89) <lb/>81 (66.94) <lb/>Age (years), median (IQR) <lb/>31.00 (23.00-40.00) <lb/>31.50 (24.00-39.00) <lb/>31.00 (22.00-42.00) <lb/>BMI, median (IQR) <lb/>19.53 (17.30-21.90) <lb/>19.72 (17.40-21.92) <lb/>19.49 (17.28-21.88) <lb/>Duration (months), median (IQR) <lb/>27.00 (6.50-65.00) <lb/>39.00 (12.00-83.00) <lb/>17.00 (6.00-47.00) <lb/>Smoking at first dose, n (%) <lb/>13 (4.66) <lb/>7 (4.43) <lb/>6 (4.96) <lb/>Previous treatment <lb/>5-ASA, n (%) <lb/>162 (58.06) <lb/>101 (63.92) <lb/>61 (50.41) <lb/>Steroids, n (%) <lb/>102 (36.56) <lb/>69 (43.67) <lb/>33 (27.27) <lb/>AZA, n (%) <lb/>83 (29.75) <lb/>59 (37.34) <lb/>24 (19.83) <lb/>MTX, n (%) <lb/>22 (7.89) <lb/>16 (10.13) <lb/>6 (4.96) <lb/>Biologics, n (%) <lb/>5 (1.79) <lb/>4 (2.53) <lb/>1 (0.83) <lb/>IFX, n (%) <lb/>1 (0.36) <lb/>/ <lb/>1 (0.83) <lb/>ADA, n (%) <lb/>3 (1.08) <lb/>3 (1.90) <lb/>/ <lb/>VDZ, n (%) <lb/>1 (0.36) <lb/>1 (0.63) <lb/>/ <lb/>CRP (mg/L), median (IQR) <lb/>12.70 (3.16-28.70) <lb/>10.70 (3.14-29.00) <lb/>14.71 (3.33-28.40) <lb/>ESR (mm/h), median (IQR) <lb/>23.00 (14.00-36.00) <lb/>23.00 (14.00-38.50) <lb/>22.50 (14.25-34.75) <lb/>Alb (g/L), median (IQR) <lb/>40.00 (35.50-44.00) <lb/>40.70 (36.30-46.00) <lb/>39.10 (34.85-42.60) <lb/>Platelet (×10 9 /L), median (IQR) <lb/>290.00 (230.00-366.00) <lb/>273.50 (218.50-364.25) <lb/>312.00 (252.00-368.00) <lb/>CDAI, median (IQR) <lb/>290.12 (237.21-364.20) <lb/>287.67 (231.05-365.22) <lb/>291.37 (249.95-359.70) <lb/>150 &lt; CDAI &lt; 220, n (%) <lb/>57 (20.43) <lb/>36 (22.78) <lb/>21 (17.36) <lb/>220 ⩽ CDAI &lt; 450, n (%) <lb/>184 (65.95) <lb/>96 (60.76) <lb/>88 (72.73) <lb/>CDAI ⩾ 450, n (%) <lb/>38 (13.62) <lb/>26 (16.46) <lb/>12 (9.92) <lb/>SES-CD, median (IQR) <lb/>11 (6.00-18.00) <lb/>11 (6.25-19.00) <lb/>10 (6.00-17.00) <lb/>4 ⩽ SES-CD &lt; 7, n (%) <lb/>71 (25.45) <lb/>40 (25.32) <lb/>31 (25.62) <lb/>7 ⩽ SES-CD &lt; 15, n (%) <lb/>113 (40.50) <lb/>62 (39.24) <lb/>51 (42.15) <lb/>SES-CD ⩾ 15, n (%) <lb/>95 (34.05) <lb/>56 (35.44) <lb/>39 (32.23) <lb/>Location a <lb/>L1, n (%) <lb/>77 (27.60) <lb/>49 (31.01) <lb/>28 (23.14) <lb/>L2, n (%) <lb/>69 (24.73) <lb/>34 (21.52) <lb/>35 (28.93) <lb/>L3, n (%) <lb/>133 (47.67) <lb/>75 (47.47) <lb/>58 (47.93) <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 1. Trough levels of IFX and ADA between responders and non-responders at week 14 post-therapy. <lb/>The trough levels of IFX and ADA were significantly lower among non-responders compared with those in <lb/>responders (p &lt; 0.001; Mann-Whitney U test). <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; IFX, infliximab. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Total <lb/>IFX <lb/>ADA <lb/>N = 279 <lb/>N = 158 <lb/>N = 121 <lb/>Behaviour b <lb/>B1, n (%) <lb/>195 (69.89) <lb/>112 (70.89) <lb/>83 (68.60) <lb/>B2, n (%) <lb/>84 (30.11) <lb/>46 (29.11) <lb/>38 (31.40) <lb/>B3, n (%) <lb/>3 (1.08) <lb/>2 (1.27) <lb/>1 (0.83) <lb/>Perianal fistulas, n (%) <lb/>28 (10.04) <lb/>17 (10.76) <lb/>11 (9.09) <lb/>a L1, ileum only; L2, colon only; L3, ileum and colon. <lb/>b B1, inflammatory; B2, stricturing; B3, penetrating. <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; Alb, albumin; 5-ASA, 5-aminosalicylate; AZA, azathioprine; BMI, body mass index; CDAI, Crohn&apos;s disease activity index; CRP, <lb/>C-reactive protein; ESR, erythrocyte sedimentation rate; IFX, infliximab; IQR, interquartile range; MTX, methotrexate; SES-CD, simple endoscopic <lb/>score for CD; VDZ, vedolizumab. <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>1(A) and (B)]. Moreover, the levels of ADA <lb/>exhibited a modest but significant negative cor-<lb/>relation with SES-CD (r = -0.332, p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>CDAI (r = -0.404, p &lt; 0.001), and CRP <lb/>(r = -0.305, p &lt; 0.001) at week 14 post-ADA <lb/>therapy in the development cohort [Figure 2(d)-<lb/>(f), Supplementary Figure 1(D)-(F)]. <lb/>The cutoff values of IFX and ADA trough levels <lb/>and diagnostic performances <lb/>Endoscopic non-response was considered the <lb/>primary outcome. Endoscopic response was <lb/>defined as a decrease in SES-CD of &gt;50%. 30 <lb/>ROC curves were constructed to determine the <lb/>optimal cutoff levels of IFX or ADA to predict <lb/>treatment failure in the development cohort. IFX <lb/>level of 4.80 μg/mL showed the best performance <lb/>in predicting endoscopic non-response [area <lb/>under the curve (AUC) = 0.770, p &lt; 0.001; sensi-<lb/>tivity = 81.8%, specificity = 64.3%] [Figure 3(a)], <lb/>with a positive predictive value (PPV) of 74.2% <lb/>and a negative predictive value (NPV) of 73.8% <lb/>(Table 3). Similarly, ADA level ⩽8.80 μg/mL <lb/>appeared the best model in predicting endo-<lb/>scopic non-response (AUC = 0.732, p &lt; 0.001; <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 2. Univariate analysis of the variables determining endoscopic non-response to IFX and ADA therapy. <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>IFX (n = 158) <lb/>ADA (n = 121) <lb/>Responders <lb/>(n = 70) <lb/>Non-<lb/>responders <lb/>(n = 88) <lb/>OR (95% <lb/>CI) <lb/>p Value Responders <lb/>(n = 66) <lb/>Non-<lb/>responders <lb/>(n = 55) <lb/>OR (95% <lb/>CI) <lb/>p Value <lb/>Male, n (%) <lb/>51 (72.86) <lb/>61 (69.32) <lb/>0.84 <lb/>(0.42-1.69) <lb/>0.627 <lb/>48 (72.73) <lb/>33 (60.00) <lb/>0.56 <lb/>(0.26-1.21) <lb/>0.140 <lb/>Age (years), median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>30.50 (23.25-<lb/>40.00) <lb/>33.50 (28.00-<lb/>40.00) <lb/>1.02 <lb/>(0.99-1.04) <lb/>0.293 <lb/>26.00 (21.00-<lb/>39.00) <lb/>32.00 (26.00-<lb/>50.00) <lb/>1.04 <lb/>(1.01-1.07) <lb/>0.013 <lb/>BMI, median (IQR) <lb/>19.89 (18.38-<lb/>22.14) <lb/>20.20 (17.65-<lb/>22.48) <lb/>0.99 <lb/>(0.90-1.08) <lb/>0.750 <lb/>20.28 (18.52-<lb/>21.61) <lb/>20.31 (18.63-<lb/>22.71) <lb/>1.02 <lb/>(0.92-1.13) <lb/>0.750 <lb/>Duration (months), <lb/>median (IQR) <lb/>43.00 (14.75-<lb/>75.50) <lb/>60.00 (26.50-<lb/>99.00) <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(1.00-1.01) <lb/>0.114 <lb/>18.50 (11.00-<lb/>37.75) <lb/>26.00 (13.50-<lb/>65.00) <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(1.00-1.02) <lb/>0.030 <lb/>Immunosuppressant, <lb/>n (%) <lb/>31 (44.29) <lb/>48 (54.55) <lb/>1.51 <lb/>(0.80-2.84) <lb/>0.201 <lb/>14 (21.21) <lb/>17 (30.91) <lb/>1.66 <lb/>(0.73-3.78) <lb/>0.226 <lb/>Clinical factors <lb/>Trough level (μg/ <lb/>mL), median (IQR) <lb/>6.35 (3.80-8.58) 3.20 (1.90-4.53) 0.71 <lb/>(0.62-0.82) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>11.07 (6.65-<lb/>13.80) <lb/>5.40 (3.30-9.60) 0.84 <lb/>(0.77-0.92) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Antibody, n (%) <lb/>9 (12.86) <lb/>21 (23.86) <lb/>2.12 <lb/>(0.90-4.99) <lb/>0.084 <lb/>10 (15.15) <lb/>15 (27.27) <lb/>2.10 <lb/>(0.86-5.15) <lb/>0.105 <lb/>CDAI, median (IQR) <lb/>138.61 (118.18-<lb/>160.83) <lb/>199.67 (173.30-<lb/>242.65) <lb/>1.04 <lb/>(1.03-1.05) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>137.90 (115.21-<lb/>151.37) <lb/>196.22 (172.16-<lb/>224.85) <lb/>1.09 <lb/>(1.06-1.13) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>SES-CD, median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>3.00 (0.25-6.00) 9.00 (5.00-<lb/>14.00) <lb/>1.25 <lb/>(1.14-1.37) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>3.00 (0.00-5.00) <lb/>7.00 (5.00-<lb/>11.50) <lb/>1.47 <lb/>(1.27-1.70) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>CRP (mg/L), median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>3.13 (2.91-5.08) 7.23 (5.01-<lb/>16.15) <lb/>1.09 <lb/>(1.03-1.15) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>2.98 (0.71-3.34) <lb/>7.84 (3.31-<lb/>19.58) <lb/>1.07 <lb/>(1.03-1.12) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>ESR (mm/h), median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>9.00 (5.00-<lb/>17.00) <lb/>15.50 (10.75-<lb/>25.00) <lb/>1.05 <lb/>(1.01-1.09) <lb/>0.016 <lb/>10.00 (5.00-<lb/>15.00) <lb/>25.50 (11.00-<lb/>38.75) <lb/>1.06 <lb/>(1.03-1.10) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Alb (g/L), median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>44.05 (41.83-<lb/>47.55) <lb/>39.55 (36.65-<lb/>42.00) <lb/>0.78 <lb/>(0.71-0.85) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>43.65 (39.10-<lb/>46.38) <lb/>38.00 (33.75-<lb/>40.10) <lb/>0.83 <lb/>(0.76-0.90) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Platelet (×10 9 /L), <lb/>median (IQR) <lb/>223.50 (192.25-<lb/>264.50) <lb/>250.50 (201.00-<lb/>304.50) <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(1.00-1.01) <lb/>0.009 <lb/>236.00 (204.00-<lb/>274.50) <lb/>274.00 (240.00-<lb/>344.00) <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(1.00-1.01) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; BMI, body mass index; CDAI, Crohn&apos;s disease activity index; CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein; ESR, erythrocyte <lb/>sedimentation rate; IFX, infliximab; IQR, interquartile range; OR, odds ratio; Plt, platelet; SES-CD, simple endoscopic score for CD. <lb/>sensitivity 72.7%, specificity 65.2%) [Figure <lb/>3(b) and Table 3], with a PPV of 63.5% and <lb/>NPV of 74.1% (Table 3). <lb/>Multivariate outcome analysis <lb/>Multivariate analysis was performed to investi-<lb/>gate the clinical factors in predicting endoscopic <lb/>non-response using multivariate logistic regres-<lb/>sion in the development cohort. The variables <lb/>were selected by comprehensively considering the <lb/>results of the univariate analysis and clinical sig-<lb/>nificance. Multivariate logistic regression analysis <lb/>demonstrated that IFX level (OR 0.81, 95% CI <lb/>0.70-0.93, p = 0.002), CRP (OR 1.08, 95% <lb/>CI 1.02-1.14, p = 0.014), and Alb (OR 0.81, 95% <lb/>CI 0.72-0.90, p &lt; 0.001) were potent predictors <lb/>of endoscopic non-response to IFX therapy <lb/>(Table 4). In addition, ADA level (OR 0.90, 95% <lb/>CI 0.81-0.99, p = 0.030) and Alb value (OR 0.88, <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 2. Correlations among anti-TNF trough levels and CDAI, SES-CD, and serum CRP. (a-c) Correlations <lb/>among IFX trough levels and CDAI (a), SES-CD (b), and CRP (c), respectively. (d-f) Correlations among ADA <lb/>trough levels and CDAI (d), SES-CD (e), and CRP (f), respectively (Spearman&apos;s correlation coefficient). <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; CDAI, Crohn&apos;s disease activity index; CRP, C-reactive protein; IFX, infliximab; SES-CD, simple endoscopic <lb/>score for Crohn&apos;s disease; TNF, tumor necrosis factor. <lb/>Figure 3. ROC curves of the trough levels of IFX and ADA in predicting the endoscopic non-response of the <lb/>patients with CD at week 14 post-therapy. (a) The AUC of the trough levels of IFX (AUC = 0.770). (b) The AUC of <lb/>the trough levels of ADA (AUC = 0.732). <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; AUC, area under the curve; CD, Crohn&apos;s disease; IFX, infliximab; ROC, receiver operating characteristic. <lb/>Table 3. The final performances of trough levels of IFX and ADA for diagnosis of CD. <lb/>Final SES-CD <lb/>results <lb/>IFX a <lb/>ADA b <lb/>Positive result <lb/>Negative result <lb/>Positive result <lb/>Negative result <lb/>Non-response <lb/>72 <lb/>16 <lb/>40 <lb/>15 <lb/>Response <lb/>25 <lb/>45 <lb/>23 <lb/>43 <lb/>The endoscopic response was defined as that SES-CD score decreases by &gt;50% compared with the baseline. <lb/>a Sensitivity, 0.818 (95% CI: 0.738-0.899); specificity, 0.643 (95% CI: 0.531-0.755). <lb/>b Sensitivity, 0.727 (95% CI: 0.590-0.839); specificity, 0.652 (95% CI: 0.524-0.765). <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; CD, Crohn&apos;s disease; CI, confidence interval; IFX, infliximab; SES-CD, simple endoscopic score for CD. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 4. Multivariate analysis of the variables associated with endoscopic response to IFX and ADA induction. <lb/>Variable <lb/>IFX <lb/>ADA <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value <lb/>Trough level (μg/mL) <lb/>0.81 (0.70-0.93) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.90 (0.81-0.99) <lb/>0.030 <lb/>CRP (mg/L) <lb/>1.08 (1.02-1.14) <lb/>0.014 <lb/>1.05 (1.00-1.10) <lb/>0.055 <lb/>Alb (g/L) <lb/>0.81 (0.72-0.90) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.88 (0.80-0.97) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>1.00 (0.96-1.04) <lb/>0.906 <lb/>1.02 (0.98-1.06) <lb/>0.282 <lb/>BMI <lb/>1.02 (0.90-1.15) <lb/>0.733 <lb/>1.04 (0.91-1.18) <lb/>0.561 <lb/>Duration (months) <lb/>1.00 (0.99-1.01) <lb/>0.911 <lb/>1.01 (1.00-1.02) <lb/>0.247 <lb/>Concomitant immunosuppressant therapy <lb/>0.95 (0.39-2.35) <lb/>0.920 <lb/>1.17 (0.40-3.43) <lb/>0.774 <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; Alb, Albumin; BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein; IFX, infliximab; <lb/>OR, odds ratio. <lb/>95% CI 0.80-0.97, p = 0.010) were observed to <lb/>be associated with endoscopic non-response to <lb/>ADA treatment (Table 4). <lb/>Development and validation of nomogram <lb/>prediction models <lb/>We subsequently developed a final prediction <lb/>model based on the results of the multivariate <lb/>logistic regression analysis, which consisted of <lb/>CRP, Alb, and anti-TNF levels at week 14 in the <lb/>development cohort. A prognostic nomogram <lb/>that integrated these three important variables <lb/>was created to calculate the risk probability of <lb/>endoscopic non-response to anti-TNF treatment <lb/>in patients with active CD (Figure 4). The nom-<lb/>ogram was calculated using one scale corre-<lb/>sponding to each clinical variable: a score scale, <lb/>total score scale of each variable, and probability <lb/>scale. The final probability of endoscopic <lb/>response was calculated by adding the scores for <lb/>all variables. ROC curves were established to <lb/>evaluate the predictive ability of the nomogram <lb/>in the development and external validation <lb/>groups, respectively. ROC analysis indicated that <lb/>an AUC of IFX and ADA was 0.874 (95% CI, <lb/>0.812-0.921) and 0.828 (95% CI, 0.748-0.890), <lb/>respectively, in the development model <lb/>[Supplementary Figure 2(A) and (B)], while an <lb/>AUC of IFX and ADA was 0.816 (95% CI, <lb/>0.812-0.921) and 0.817 (95% CI, 0.748-0.890), <lb/>respectively, in the external validation cohort <lb/>[Figure 5(a) and (b)]. The calibration plots dem-<lb/>onstrated that the development model had <lb/>average errors of 0.048 and 0.040 for IFX and <lb/>ADA, respectively [Supplementary Figure 2(C) <lb/>and (D)], while the external validation cohort <lb/>showed errors of 0.037 and 0.031, respectively <lb/>[Figure 5(c) and (d)]. These results indicate no <lb/>significant difference (p &gt; 0.05) between the <lb/>model&apos;s calculated probability and endoscopic <lb/>non-response based on the data. Comparisons <lb/>between the nomogram and three independent <lb/>factors indicated that the nomogram had excel-<lb/>lent predictive value and discrimination in both <lb/>the development (Supplementary Table 2) and <lb/>external validation cohorts (Table 5). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In the present study, we described a robust asso-<lb/>ciation of the trough levels of IFX and ADA, Alb, <lb/>and CRP with endoscopic response in active CD <lb/>patients receiving treatment with anti-TNF <lb/>mAbs. Accordingly, we constructed a novel nom-<lb/>ogram based on anti-TNF serum trough levels, <lb/>Alb, and CRP to predict the LOR when initiating <lb/>anti-TNF therapy. The performance of the nom-<lb/>ogram prediction model was demonstrated by <lb/>ROC analysis and calibration curve in both devel-<lb/>opment and validation cohorts. Clinical and <lb/>endoscopic responses were more likely to occur in <lb/>patients with CD with high trough levels of IFX <lb/>and ADA, high concentrations of Alb levels, and <lb/>low levels of CRP. Overall, our findings revealed <lb/>an association between the concentrations of IFX <lb/>and ADA and early endoscopic response in active <lb/>CD. More importantly, this novel nomogram <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 4. Nomogram based on anti-TNF trough levels, CRP and Alb predicts the risk of endoscopic non-<lb/>response at week 14. (a) Nomogram for CD patients treated with IFX. (b) Nomogram for CD patients treated <lb/>with ADA. For example, a 25-year-old male CD patient treated with IFX for 14 weeks; the laboratory findings <lb/>were as follows: IFX trough levels 1.4 μg/mL, CRP 44.82 mg/L, and Alb 35 g/L. By adopting IFX nomogram to <lb/>this case, a total of 178.8 points (IFX trough level 71.3 points, CRP 45 points, and Alb 62.5 points) was calculated, <lb/>indicating that the probability of endoscopic non-response was above 90%. <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; Alb, albumin; CD, Crohn&apos;s disease; CRP, C-reactive protein; IFX, infliximab; TNF, tumor necrosis factor. <lb/>enables us to optimize individual treatment strat-<lb/>egies and promote clinical response in patients <lb/>with active CD. <lb/>Recent years, several lines of evidence have evalu-<lb/>ated an association of early induction of IFX with <lb/>clinical outcome, while most studies included a <lb/>limited number of patients and focused on main-<lb/>tenance therapy. The cut-offs for IFX levels over <lb/>an early induction period and observation end-<lb/>points for clinical response to IFX induction have <lb/>not been well defined. 9,18,24,25,27,33,34 Therefore, <lb/>the primary aim of this study was to evaluate the <lb/>short-term effects of anti-TNF therapy on the <lb/>induction of endoscopic response in active CD. <lb/>In our study, we found that both IFX and ADA <lb/>levels were higher in primary responders than <lb/>those in non-responders at week 14 post-therapy. <lb/>Furthermore, the serum levels of IFX or ADA <lb/>differed according to the disease activity status, <lb/>which was consistent with previous reports. 35,36 <lb/>Previously, Ward et al. 35 identified target thresh-<lb/>olds for IFX of 1.5, 3.4, and 5.7 μg/mL that were <lb/>in accordance with clinical and biochemical <lb/>remission and calprotectin normalization, respec-<lb/>tively. However, they found no relationship <lb/>between ADA levels and any of the indices of dis-<lb/>ease activity. 35 Nevertheless, other reports have <lb/>shown that ADA target thresholds of 7.1 μg/mL <lb/>have the optimal value to predict mucosal heal-<lb/>ing. 36 It should be pointed out that both studies <lb/>mentioned above focused on anti-TNF mainte-<lb/>nance therapy for IBD patients. In our study, we <lb/>identified target thresholds for IFX (4.80 μg/mL) <lb/>and ADA (8.80 μg/mL), which were significantly <lb/>associated with the endoscopic response over an <lb/>induction period. Concerning the variant concen-<lb/>trations of IFX or ADA in predicting the clinical <lb/>outcome during therapy, different bioavailability, <lb/>pharmacokinetics, and administration methods <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figure 5. External validation of nomogram prediction models. (a) ROC curves of the IFX nomogram. (b) ROC <lb/>curves of the ADA nomogram. Calibration plots of the nomogram of IFX (c) and ADA (d). <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; AUC, area under the curve; IFX, infliximab; ROC, receiver operating characteristic. <lb/>Table 5. The predictive ability of validation cohorts of <lb/>IFX and ADA. <lb/>Variable <lb/>IFX <lb/>ADA <lb/>AUC <lb/>0.816 <lb/>0.817 <lb/>p Value <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>95% CI <lb/>0.713-0.894 <lb/>0.694-0.906 <lb/>SE <lb/>0.769 <lb/>0.760 <lb/>SP <lb/>0.825 <lb/>0.788 <lb/>PPV <lb/>0.811 <lb/>0.731 <lb/>NPV <lb/>0.786 <lb/>0.812 <lb/>ADA, adalimumab; AUC, area under the curve; CI, <lb/>confidence interval; IFX, infliximab; NPV, negative predict <lb/>value; PPV, positive predict value; SE, sensitivity; SP, <lb/>specificity. <lb/>may be all associated with a change in the levels of <lb/>IFX and ADA. The timing of drug level measure-<lb/>ment is also not consistent in ADA and IFX. <lb/>Patients receiving IFX always have trough levels <lb/>measured, while the drug levels of ADA appear to <lb/>be relatively stable across fortnightly treatment <lb/>cycles. Thus, the above factors may cause a differ-<lb/>ent biological threshold for IFX and ADA. <lb/>Currently, predictions of the primary outcome of <lb/>anti-TNF therapy are mostly based on endos-<lb/>copy, radiography, and laboratory examination <lb/>monitoring, and few studies have focused on the <lb/>scoring system to determine patients&apos; risk of <lb/>LOR. In this study, we constructed a nomogram <lb/>based on a combination of parameters (serum <lb/>concentrations of IFX, ADA, Alb, and CRP) to <lb/>predict an early endoscopic response to anti-TNF <lb/>therapy. The nomogram showed an excellent <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>

    <body>prediction with good calibration and was also <lb/>well-performed using a ROC analysis. The nom-<lb/>ogram analysis indicated that lower concentra-<lb/>tions of IFX, ADA, and Alb as well as higher <lb/>levels of CRP were linked to a greater risk of pri-<lb/>mary endoscopic non-response to anti-TNF ther-<lb/>apy. For the training and external validation <lb/>groups of this nomogram, 10-fold cross-valida-<lb/>tion was employed, which showed good stability. <lb/>Both CRP and Alb levels showed significant sta-<lb/>tistical differences in the univariate and multivari-<lb/>ate analyses. Previous studies have indicated that <lb/>Alb level is associated with serum IFX levels, pos-<lb/>sibly contributing to its predictive power for good <lb/>response to IFX. 37 There were also studies dem-<lb/>onstrating that CRP, nutritional status, and a <lb/>combination of parameters (Alb, CRP, and <lb/>endoscopy) could serve as predictive indicators <lb/>for clinical outcomes in patients with IBD. 33,38,39 <lb/>Therefore, the aforementioned studies demon-<lb/>strated the importance of CRP and Alb levels in <lb/>assessing the disease severity of IBD. Few studies <lb/>have investigated the significance of serum levels <lb/>of IFX and anti-IFX antibody (ATI) in predicting <lb/>the clinical outcomes for patients with IBD. Bar-<lb/>Yoseph et al. took advantage of the serum levels <lb/>of IFX and ATI to predict the primary non-<lb/>response in patients with active CD. The AUC of <lb/>the IFX ROC curve at weeks 2 and 6 and the ATI <lb/>ROC curve at week 6 were 0.68, 0.78, and 0.78, <lb/>respectively. 27 In our study, the AUC of the nom-<lb/>ogram prediction model for IFX treatment was <lb/>0.87 and 0.816 in the development and external <lb/>validation groups, respectively, which was signifi-<lb/>cantly higher than that of IFX or ATI concentra-<lb/>tions alone. Additionally, Baert et al. 40 utilized <lb/>the ADA concentration in UC patients at week 4 <lb/>to predict the clinical response at week 12 with a <lb/>sensitivity of 80%, specificity of 56%, PPV of <lb/>85%, and NPV of 47%. In our study, the AUC of <lb/>the nomogram predicting the primary non-<lb/>response to ADA at week 14 was 0.83, with a sen-<lb/>sitivity of 82%, specificity of 76%, PPV of 74%, <lb/>and NPV of 83% in the development cohort. The <lb/>predictive value of ADA was significantly higher <lb/>than that of ADA alone. The same results were <lb/>also observed in the external validation cohort. <lb/>Therefore, we suppose that our TDM-based <lb/>nomogram may offer a more precise prediction of <lb/>early endoscopic response in patients with active <lb/>CD treated with anti-TNF mAbs as compared to <lb/>other parameters such as TDM or biochemical <lb/>biomarker alone. <lb/>The present study has several limitations. First, <lb/>although the relationships between the serum <lb/>concentrations of IFX and ADA, Alb, CRP, and <lb/>the efficacy outcomes are both robust and con-<lb/>sistent, these data are retrospective and may have <lb/>been influenced by other factors in addition to <lb/>both clinical outcomes and drug concentrations. <lb/>Furthermore, as a retrospective study, the grad-<lb/>ing of SES-CD was based solely on previous colo-<lb/>noscopy images in the developmental cohort. <lb/>Third, only 416 patients were included in this <lb/>study, including 237 for IFX and 179 for ADA, <lb/>and more prospective cohort multicenter studies <lb/>are needed to further explore the predictive value <lb/>of the TDM-based nomogram. <lb/>In summary, this study has established a strong <lb/>association between serum concentrations of IFX <lb/>and ADA, Alb, CRP, and primary clinical out-<lb/>comes in CD patients. Importantly, we estab-<lb/>lished a TDM-based nomogram showing an <lb/>excellent predictive value with remarkable accu-<lb/>racy and discrimination. The nomogram algo-<lb/>rithm may enable clinicians to better understand <lb/>the underlying mechanisms by which an individ-<lb/>ual patient fails to achieve the expected efficacy, <lb/>which is important for optimizing therapy options <lb/>and switching biologics in refractory CD. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>This study was approved by the Institutional <lb/>Review Board of the Shanghai Tenth People&apos;s <lb/>Hospital <lb/>(SHSY-IEC-4.1/20-182/01), <lb/>and <lb/>informed consent was waived because of the ret-<lb/>rospective study design. <lb/>Consent for publication <lb/>All authors have provided their consent for <lb/>publication. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>Liang Chen: Data curation; Formal analysis; <lb/>Funding acquisition; Investigation; Resources; <lb/>Writing -original draft. <lb/>Dengfeng Kang: Data curation; Formal analy-<lb/>sis; Methodology; Software. <lb/>Leilei Fang: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Mingming Sun: Data curation; Formal <lb/>analysis. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>13 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Mingsong Li: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Guangxi Zhou: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Chunjin Xu: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Zhi Pang: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Yulan Ye: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Baisui Feng: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Huili Wu: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Jian Lin: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Baijing Ding: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Changqin Liu: Conceptualization; Data cura-<lb/>tion; Methodology; Validation. <lb/>Yanhong Shi: Conceptualization; Data cura-<lb/>tion; Formal analysis; Validation. <lb/>Zhanju Liu: Conceptualization; Project admin-<lb/>istration; Supervision; Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We would like to acknowledge Yisheng Feng and <lb/>Ruijin Wu for their invaluable assistance in data <lb/>collection and manuscript review. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The authors disclosed receipt of the following <lb/>financial support for the research, authorship, <lb/>and/or publication of this article: This work was <lb/>supported by the National Natural Science <lb/>Foundation of China (82270548, 81900491, <lb/>82370532) and Shanghai Hospital Development <lb/>Center Foundation (SHDC12022118). <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that there is no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>The corresponding author can provide the data <lb/>upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

    <front>ORCID iD <lb/>Zhanju Liu <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-<lb/>0326-543X <lb/></front>

    <div type="annex">Supplemental material <lb/>Supplemental material for this article is available <lb/>online. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Hanauer SB, Feagan BG, Lichtenstein GR, et al. <lb/>Maintenance infliximab for Crohn&apos;s disease: the <lb/>ACCENT I randomised trial. Lancet 2002; 359: <lb/>1541-1549. <lb/>2. Matsumoto T, Motoya S, Watanabe K, et al. <lb/>Adalimumab monotherapy and a combination <lb/>with azathioprine for Crohn&apos;s disease: a <lb/>prospective, randomized trial. J Crohns Colitis <lb/>2016; 10: 1259-1266. <lb/>3. Rutgeerts P, Sandborn WJ, Feagan BG, et al. <lb/>Infliximab for induction and maintenance therapy <lb/>for ulcerative colitis. N Engl J Med 2005; 353: <lb/>2462-2476. <lb/>4. Colombel JF, Sandborn WJ, Rutgeerts P, et al. <lb/>Adalimumab for maintenance of clinical response <lb/>and remission in patients with Crohn&apos;s disease: <lb/>the CHARM trial. Gastroenterology 2007; 132: <lb/>52-65. <lb/>5. Sandborn WJ, van Assche G, Reinisch W, et al. <lb/>Adalimumab induces and maintains clinical <lb/>remission in patients with moderate-to-severe <lb/>ulcerative colitis. Gastroenterology 2012; 142: <lb/>257-265.e1-3. <lb/>6. Yu L, Yang X, Xia L, et al. Infliximab <lb/>preferentially induces clinical remission and <lb/>mucosal healing in short course Crohn&apos;s disease <lb/>with luminal lesions through balancing abnormal <lb/>immune response in gut mucosa. Mediators <lb/>Inflamm 2015; 2015: 793764. <lb/>7. Sprakes MB, Ford AC, Warren L, et al. Efficacy, <lb/>tolerability, and predictors of response to <lb/>infliximab therapy for Crohn&apos;s disease: a large <lb/>single centre experience. J Crohns Colitis 2012; 6: <lb/>143-153. <lb/>8. Roda G, Jharap B, Neeraj N, et al. Loss of <lb/>response to anti-TNFs: definition, epidemiology, <lb/>and management. Clin Transl Gastroenterol 2016; <lb/>7: e135. <lb/>9. Argollo M, Kotze PG, Kakkadasam P, et al. <lb/>Optimizing biologic therapy in IBD: how <lb/>essential is therapeutic drug monitoring? Nat Rev <lb/>Gastroenterol Hepatol 2020; 17: 702-710. <lb/>10. Chen L, Xu CJ, Wu W, et al. Anti-TNF and <lb/>immunosuppressive combination therapy is <lb/>preferential to inducing clinical remission in <lb/>patients with active inflammatory bowel disease: <lb/>a systemic review and meta-analysis. J Dig Dis <lb/>2021; 22: 408-418. <lb/>11. Pouillon L, Ferrante M, Van Assche G, et al. <lb/>Mucosal healing and long-term outcomes of <lb/>patients with inflammatory bowel diseases <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Volume 17 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Gastroenterology <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>receiving clinic-based vs trough concentration-<lb/>based dosing of infliximab. Clin Gastroenterol <lb/>Hepatol 2018; 16: 1276-1283.e1. <lb/>12. Van Stappen T, Vande Casteele N, Van Assche <lb/>G, et al. Clinical relevance of detecting anti-<lb/>infliximab antibodies with a drug-tolerant assay: <lb/>post hoc analysis of the TAXIT trial. Gut 2018; <lb/>67: 818-826. <lb/>13. Sethi S, Dias S, Kumar A, et al. Meta-analysis: <lb/>the efficacy of therapeutic drug monitoring of <lb/>anti-TNF-therapy in inflammatory bowel disease. <lb/>Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2023; 57: 1362-1374. <lb/>14. Bouman C, van Herwaarden N, van den Hoogen <lb/>F, et al. Prediction of successful dose reduction <lb/>or discontinuation of adalimumab, etanercept, <lb/>or infliximab in rheumatoid arthritis patients <lb/>using serum drug levels and antidrug antibody <lb/>measurement. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol <lb/>2017; 13: 597-604. <lb/>15. l&apos;Ami MJ, Krieckaert CL, Nurmohamed MT, <lb/>et al. Successful reduction of overexposure in <lb/>patients with rheumatoid arthritis with high <lb/>serum adalimumab concentrations: an open-<lb/>label, non-inferiority, randomised clinical trial. <lb/>Ann Rheum Dis 2018; 77: 484-487. <lb/>16. Chen DY, Chen YM, Hsieh TY, et al. Drug <lb/>trough levels predict therapeutic responses to <lb/>dose reduction of adalimumab for rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis patients during 24 weeks of follow-up. <lb/>Rheumatology (Oxford) 2016; 55: 143-148. <lb/>17. Syversen SW, Goll GL, Jørgensen KK, et al. <lb/>Effect of therapeutic drug monitoring vs standard <lb/>therapy during infliximab induction on disease <lb/>remission in patients with chronic immune-<lb/>mediated inflammatory diseases: a randomized <lb/>clinical trial. JAMA 2021; 325: 1744-1754. <lb/>18. Nguyen NH, Solitano V, Vuyyuru SK, et al. <lb/>Proactive therapeutic drug monitoring versus <lb/>conventional management for inflammatory <lb/>bowel diseases: a systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. Gastroenterology 2022; 163: 937-949.e2. <lb/>19. D&apos;Haens GR, Sandborn WJ, Loftus EV Jr, <lb/>et al. Higher vs standard adalimumab induction <lb/>dosing regimens and two maintenance strategies: <lb/>randomized SERENE CD trial results. <lb/>Gastroenterology 2022; 162: 1876-1890. <lb/>20. Panés J, Colombel JF, D&apos;Haens GR, et al. <lb/>Higher vs standard adalimumab induction and <lb/>maintenance dosing regimens for treatment of <lb/>ulcerative colitis: SERENE UC trial results. <lb/>Gastroenterology 2022; 162: 1891-1910. <lb/>21. Assa A, Matar M, Turner D, et al. Proactive <lb/>monitoring of adalimumab trough concentration <lb/>associated with increased clinical remission in <lb/>children with Crohn&apos;s disease compared with <lb/>reactive monitoring. Gastroenterology 2019; 157: <lb/>985-996.e2. <lb/>22. Seow CH, Newman A, Irwin SP, et al. Trough <lb/>serum infliximab: a predictive factor of clinical <lb/>outcome for infliximab treatment in acute <lb/>ulcerative colitis. Gut 2010; 59: 49-54. <lb/>23. Cornillie F, Hanauer SB, Diamond RH, et al. <lb/>Postinduction serum infliximab trough level and <lb/>decrease of C-reactive protein level are associated <lb/>with durable sustained response to infliximab: a <lb/>retrospective analysis of the ACCENT I trial. Gut <lb/>2014; 63: 1721-1727. <lb/>24. Adedokun OJ, Sandborn WJ, Feagan BG, et al. <lb/>Association between serum concentration of <lb/>infliximab and efficacy in adult patients with <lb/>ulcerative colitis. Gastroenterology 2014; 147: <lb/>1296-1307.e5. <lb/>25. Yarur AJ, Jain A, Hauenstein SI, et al. Higher <lb/>adalimumab levels are associated with histologic <lb/>and endoscopic remission in patients with <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease and ulcerative colitis. Inflamm <lb/>Bowel Dis 2016; 22: 409-415. <lb/>26. Benucci M, Grossi V, Manfredi M, et al. <lb/>Laboratory monitoring of biological therapies in <lb/>rheumatology: the role of immunogenicity. Ann <lb/>Lab Med 2020; 40: 101-113. <lb/>27. Bar-Yoseph H, Levhar N, Selinger L, et al. Early <lb/>drug and anti-infliximab antibody levels for <lb/>prediction of primary nonresponse to infliximab <lb/>therapy. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2018; 47: <lb/>212-218. <lb/>28. Maaser C, Sturm A, Vavricka SR, et al. ECCO-<lb/>ESGAR guideline for diagnostic assessment <lb/>in IBD part 1: initial diagnosis, monitoring of <lb/>known IBD, detection of complications. J Crohns <lb/>Colitis 2019; 13: 144-164. <lb/>29. Daperno M, D&apos;Haens G, Van Assche G, et al. <lb/>Development and validation of a new, simplified <lb/>endoscopic activity score for Crohn&apos;s disease: the <lb/>SES-CD. Gastrointest Endosc 2004; 60: 505-512. <lb/>30. Danese S, Sandborn WJ, Colombel JF, et al. <lb/>Endoscopic, radiologic, and histologic healing <lb/>with vedolizumab in patients with active <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease. Gastroenterology 2019; 157: <lb/>1007-1018.e7. <lb/>31. Best WR, Becktel JM, Singleton JW, et al. <lb/>Development of a Crohn&apos;s disease activity index. <lb/>National Cooperative Crohn&apos;s Disease Study. <lb/>Gastroenterology 1976; 70: 439-444. <lb/>32. von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, et al. The <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">L Chen, D Kang et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tag <lb/></note>

    <page>15 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: <lb/>guidelines for reporting observational studies. <lb/>Lancet 2007; 370: 1453-1457. <lb/>33. Buhl S, Dorn-Rasmussen M, Brynskov J, <lb/>et al. Therapeutic thresholds and mechanisms <lb/>for primary non-response to infliximab in <lb/>inflammatory bowel disease. Scand J Gastroenterol <lb/>2020; 55: 884-890. <lb/>34. Steenholdt C, Bendtzen K, Brynskov J, et al. <lb/>Optimizing treatment with TNF inhibitors in <lb/>inflammatory bowel disease by monitoring drug <lb/>levels and antidrug antibodies. Inflamm Bowel Dis <lb/>2016; 22: 1999-2015. <lb/>35. Ward MG, Warner B, Unsworth N, et al. <lb/>Infliximab and adalimumab drug levels in <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease: contrasting associations with <lb/>disease activity and influencing factors. Aliment <lb/>Pharmacol Ther 2017; 46: 150-161. <lb/>36. Ungar B, Levy I, Yavne Y, et al. Optimizing <lb/>anti-TNF-α therapy: serum levels of infliximab <lb/>and adalimumab are associated with mucosal <lb/>healing in patients with inflammatory bowel <lb/>diseases. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2016; 14: <lb/>550-557.e2. <lb/>37. Gisbert JP and Chaparro M. Predictors of <lb/>primary response to biologic treatment [anti-<lb/>TNF, vedolizumab, and ustekinumab] in patients <lb/>with inflammatory bowel disease: from basic <lb/>science to clinical practice. J Crohns Colitis 2020; <lb/>14: 694-709. <lb/>38. Assa A, Hartman C, Weiss B, et al. Long-<lb/>term outcome of tumor necrosis factor alpha <lb/>antagonist&apos;s treatment in pediatric Crohn&apos;s <lb/>disease. J Crohns Colitis 2013; 7: 369-376. <lb/>39. Grant RK, Jones GR, Plevris N, et al. The ACE <lb/>(albumin, CRP and endoscopy) index in acute <lb/>colitis: a simple clinical index on admission that <lb/>predicts outcome in patients with acute ulcerative <lb/>colitis. Inflamm Bowel Dis 2021; 27: 451-457. <lb/>40. Baert F, Vande Casteele N, Tops S, et al. Prior <lb/>response to infliximab and early serum drug <lb/>concentrations predict effects of adalimumab in <lb/>ulcerative colitis. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2014; <lb/>40: 1324-1332. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">Visit Sage journals online <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/ <lb/>home/tag <lb/>Sage journals </note>

	</text>
</TEI>