<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">&lt;i&gt;Fixing a Hole&lt;/i&gt;: a retrospective cohort study evaluating HAV, HBV, tetanus screening, and vaccination during hospitalization in persons who use substances</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Amber C.</forename>
          <surname>Streifel</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jose Eduardo</forename>
          <surname>Rivera Sarti</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Monica K.</forename>
          <surname>Sikka</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Michael</forename>
          <surname>Conte</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Bradie</forename>
          <surname>Winders</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Cara D.</forename>
          <surname>Varley</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T16:11:39.463Z">11/12/2025 4:11:39 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1177/20499361241245822</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Amber C. Streifel, Jose Eduardo Rivera Sarti, Monica K. Sikka, Michael Conte, Bradie Winders, Cara D. Varley. (2024). &lt;i&gt;Fixing a Hole&lt;/i&gt;: a retrospective cohort study evaluating HAV, HBV, tetanus screening, and vaccination during hospitalization in persons who use substances. Therapeutic Advances in Infectious Disease, 11(None), None. DOI: 10.1177/20499361241245822</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T16:11:30.043682Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T16:11:30.043682Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>https://doi.org/10.1177/17588359231221343 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/17588359231221343 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/>1 <lb/>Ther Adv Med Oncol <lb/>2024, Vol. 16: 1 -12 <lb/>DOI: 10.1177/ <lb/>17588359231221343 <lb/>© The Author(s), 2024. <lb/>Article reuse guidelines: <lb/>sagepub.com/journals-<lb/>permissions <lb/>Creative Commons Non Commercial CC BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License <lb/>(https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission <lb/>provided the original work is attributed as specified on the Sage and Open Access pages (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). <lb/>TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) is an endemic <lb/>malignancy in South China. 1,2 Despite advances <lb/>in treatment modalities and techniques, 20-30% <lb/>of patients experience distant metastasis or <lb/>locoregional relapse. 3 Cisplatin (DDP)-based <lb/></body>

    <front>Combined pre-treatment and <lb/>middle-treatment Epstein-Barr virus <lb/>DNA load contributes to prognostication and <lb/>treatment modification in nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma patients <lb/>Kaiqi Lan*, Jingrong Mao*, Xuesong Sun*, Suchen Li, Siyi Xie, Rui Sun, <lb/>Sailan Liu and Haiqiang Mai <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Objective: To investigate whether pre-treatment and middle-treatment plasma Epstein-<lb/>Barr virus (EBV) DNA loads are useful predictors of prognosis and indicators of therapy <lb/>modification in nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) patients undergoing radical concurrent <lb/>chemoradiotherapy (CCRT). <lb/>Methods: Plasma EBV DNA load was measured by quantitative polymerase chain reaction <lb/>before treatment (pre-DNA) and during the second cycle of DDP (mid-DNA). The primary <lb/>endpoint was 5-year progression-free survival (PFS). <lb/>Results: A total of 775 NPC patients treated with CCRT were included. In total, 553 patients with <lb/>pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and 222 with ⩾4000 copies/mL. A total of 559 patients had mid-<lb/>DNA undetectable and 216 had detectable. Multivariate analysis showed that pre-and mid-<lb/>DNA were independent prognostic predictors of PFS [hazard ratio (HR), 2.035; 95% confidence <lb/>interval (CI), 1.406-2.944; p &lt; 0.001; HR, 1.597; 95% CI, 1.101-2.316; p = 0.014]. The area under <lb/>the curve of the combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA for 5-year PFS was higher than that <lb/>of pre-DNA, mid-DNA, and tumor node metastasis (TNM) stage (0.679 versus 0.622, 0.608, <lb/>0.601). In the low-risk group (pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and undetectable mid-DNA), patients <lb/>receiving ⩽200 mg/m 2 showed similar efficacy as those receiving &gt;200 mg/m 2 cumulative <lb/>cisplatin dose (CCD) but were associated with fewer all-grade late toxicities. However, in <lb/>the high-risk group (pre-DNA ⩾4000 copies/mL or detectable mid-DNA), patients receiving <lb/>&gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD showed a higher 5-year PFS (73.1% versus 58.6%, p = 0.027) and locoregional <lb/>relapse-free survival (88.5% versus 76.1%, p = 0.028) than those receiving ⩽200 mg/m 2 CCD. <lb/>Conclusion: The combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA could be particularly useful for guiding <lb/>risk stratification and early treatment modification for NPC treated with CCRT. A total of <lb/>200 mg/m 2 cisplatin seemed to be the optimal dose for the low-risk patients, while &gt;200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 cisplatin may be adequate to achieve satisfactory survival outcomes in the high-risk group. <lb/>Keywords: concurrent chemotherapy, cumulative cisplatin dose, EBV DNA, nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma <lb/>Received: 11 May 2023; revised manuscript accepted: 29 November 2023. <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Rui Sun <lb/>Sailan Liu <lb/>Haiqiang Mai <lb/>Department of <lb/>Nasopharyngeal <lb/>Carcinoma, Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University Cancer Center, <lb/>No. 651 Dongfeng East <lb/>Road, Guangzhou 510060, <lb/>China <lb/>Sun Yat-sen University <lb/>Cancer Center, State Key <lb/>Laboratory of Oncology in <lb/>South China, Collaborative <lb/>Innovation Center <lb/>for Cancer Medicine, <lb/>Guangdong Provincial <lb/>Clinical Research Center <lb/>for Cancer, Guangdong <lb/>Key Laboratory of <lb/>Nasopharyngeal <lb/>Carcinoma Diagnosis <lb/>and Therapy, Guangzhou, <lb/>China <lb/>sunrui@mail.sysu.edu.cn <lb/>liusl@sysucc.org.cn <lb/>maihq@mail.sysu.edu.cn <lb/>Kaiqi Lan <lb/>Xuesong Sun <lb/>Suchen Li <lb/>Siyi Xie <lb/>Sun Yat-sen University <lb/>Cancer Center, State Key <lb/>Laboratory of Oncology in <lb/>South China, Collaborative <lb/>Innovation Center <lb/>for Cancer Medicine, <lb/>Guangdong Provincial <lb/>Clinical Research Center <lb/>for Cancer, Guangdong <lb/>Key Laboratory of <lb/>Nasopharyngeal <lb/>Carcinoma Diagnosis <lb/>and Therapy, Guangzhou, <lb/>China <lb/>Department of <lb/>Nasopharyngeal <lb/>Carcinoma, Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University Cancer Center, <lb/>Guangzhou, China <lb/>1221343T AM0010.1177/17588359231221343Therapeutic Advances in Medical OncologyK Lan, M Jingrong <lb/>research-article20242024 <lb/>Original Research <lb/>TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/>2 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></front>

    <body>concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) with or <lb/>without induction chemotherapy (IC) or adju-<lb/>vant chemotherapy (AC) has been recommended <lb/>as the fundamental treatment for stage II-IVa <lb/>NPC by the National Comprehensive Cancer <lb/>Network guidelines. 4 Cisplatin administered at <lb/>100 mg/m 2 every 3 weeks is the standard regimen <lb/>for CCRT. Many previous studies have indicated <lb/>that a cumulative cisplatin dose (CCD) of 200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 can significantly improve the prognosis of <lb/>NPC. 5-8 Nevertheless, owing to the tumor heter-<lb/>ogeneity, the survival benefit of intensity of con-<lb/>current DDP remains inconclusive in NPC, <lb/>particularly for patients with a high risk of recur-<lb/>rence. 9,10 Therefore, developing reliable methods <lb/>to detect progression at an early stage may help <lb/>identify high-risk patients who could benefit from <lb/>intensive doses of DDP. <lb/>Plasma Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) DNA is the <lb/>most useful biomarker for prognostication, pre-<lb/>dicting treatment response, and disease surveil-<lb/>lance. 11,12 Many previous studies have reported <lb/>NPC patients with high levels of EBV DNA <lb/>before treatment (pre-DNA) and detectable EBV <lb/>DNA after radiotherapy (RT) completion (post-<lb/>DNA) have a high risk of recurrence and distant <lb/>metastasis. 12,13 Recently, with increasing evidence <lb/>demonstrating that EBV DNA load at treatment <lb/>midcourse is a significant predictor of clinical <lb/>outcome and an indicator for AC, prognostica-<lb/>tion has shifted from post-RT to completion of <lb/>IC. 14,15 Unlike patients who receive IC, mid-RT <lb/>instead of IC completion EBV DNA may be a <lb/>suitable time point for early outcome prediction <lb/>among NPC patients treated with definitive <lb/>CCRT. 16,17 However, the EBV DBA load shows <lb/>dynamic changes, and estimating the risk of treat-<lb/>ment failure with EBV DNA at a single time point <lb/>may be unreliable. Therefore, the prognostic <lb/>value of the combination of different time points <lb/>of EBV DNA is worth investigating. <lb/>In this study, we aimed to compare the prognostic <lb/>value of pre-DNA and mid-DNA levels in NPC <lb/>patients treated with DDP-based CCRT. We <lb/>then combined pre-DNA and mid-DNA to con-<lb/>struct risk stratification. Furthermore, a subgroup <lb/>analysis was conducted to compare the therapeu-<lb/>tic value of CCD in different risk groups. Our <lb/>findings could help clinicians to better predict <lb/>NPC prognosis and guide treatment strategies for <lb/>these patients. <lb/>Patients and methods <lb/>Patients <lb/>A total of 775 patients with locally advanced NPC <lb/>who underwent treatment at Sun Yat-sen University <lb/>Cancer Center between 2012 and 2018 were <lb/>included in our study. The eligibility criteria were <lb/>as follows: (1) pathologically confirmed NPC at <lb/>stage II-IVa according to the eighth edition of the <lb/>International Union Against Cancer/American <lb/>Joint Committee on Cancer TNM staging system; <lb/>(2) treatment with intensity-modulated radiother-<lb/>apy (IMRT) and received DDP dose of 100 mg/m² <lb/>every 3 weeks concurrent chemotherapy regimen; <lb/>(3) complete data of plasma EBV DNA load meas-<lb/>ured by quantitative polymerase chain reaction <lb/>(PCR) before treatment and second-cycle DDP; <lb/>(4) no pregnant women, lactating women or suffer-<lb/>ing from prior/concurrent second primary malig-<lb/>nant tumors; and (5) adequate organ function. The <lb/>study flowchart is presented in Figure 1. All <lb/>included patients underwent complete physical <lb/>examination, EBV serology, electrocardiography, <lb/>fiberoptic nasopharyngoscopy, nasopharyngeal and <lb/>neck magnetic resonance imaging, chest radiogra-<lb/>phy/tomography (CT), abdominal sonography/ <lb/>CT, bone scan, or whole-body fluorodeoxyglucose <lb/>positron emission tomography. <lb/>Real-time quantitative EBV DNA <lb/>Peripheral venous blood (5 mL) was collected <lb/>before treatment and before the second cycle of <lb/>DDP. Plasma EBV DNA loads were routinely <lb/>measured by real-time quantitative PCR. The <lb/>details of the assay have been published previ-<lb/>ously. 18 The cutoff value of the pre-DNA level <lb/>was previously established (4000 copies/mL), 13 <lb/>whereas the cutoff value of the mid-DNA level <lb/>was based on a detectable/undetectable status <lb/>(0 copies/mL). 16,19 <lb/>Treatment <lb/>All the patients were treated with DDP-based <lb/>CCRT. RT was delivered using IMRT. The pre-<lb/>scribed radiation doses for planning target vol-<lb/>ume (PTV)nx, PTVnd, PTV1, and PTV2 were <lb/>68-72, 64-70, 60-64, and 50-54 Gy, respec-<lb/>tively, in 30-33 fractions, delivered daily at five <lb/>fractions per week over 6-7 weeks. DDP was <lb/>administered at 100 mg/m² every 3 weeks during <lb/>RT. Concurrent targeted therapy consisted of <lb/></body>

    <front>Jingrong Mao <lb/>Sun Yat-sen University <lb/>Cancer Center, State <lb/>Key Laboratory of <lb/>Oncology in South <lb/>China, Collaborative <lb/>Innovation Center <lb/>for Cancer Medicine, <lb/>Guangdong Provincial <lb/>Clinical Research <lb/>Center for Cancer, <lb/>Guangdong Key <lb/>Laboratory of <lb/>Nasopharyngeal <lb/>Carcinoma Diagnosis <lb/>and Therapy, <lb/>Guangzhou, China <lb/>Department of Clinical <lb/>Nutrition, Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University Cancer <lb/>Center, Guangzhou, <lb/>China <lb/>*These authors <lb/>contributed equally <lb/></front>

    <note place="headnote">K Lan, M Jingrong et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <body>cetuximab (400 mg/m 2 for week 1 and 250 mg/m 2 <lb/>weekly thereafter) or nimotuzumab (200 mg <lb/>weekly) throughout IMRT weekly for five-six <lb/>cycles. <lb/>Outcome and follow-up <lb/>Our primary endpoint was progression-free sur-<lb/>vival (PFS), which was calculated from the start <lb/>of treatment to the date of disease progression <lb/>or death from any cause. The secondary end-<lb/>points were distant metastasis-free survival <lb/>(DMFS) (defined as the period from the first <lb/>therapy to the date of distant metastasis), <lb/>locoregional relapse-free survival (LRRFS) <lb/>(defined as the time from the first day of first <lb/>therapy to the date of local/regional relapse), <lb/>and overall survival (OS) (defined as the period <lb/>from the first day of first therapy to the date of <lb/>death from any cause). After completing treat-<lb/>ment, physical examination, nasopharyngos-<lb/>copy, chest radiography, abdominal sonography, <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the head <lb/>and neck, and plasma EBV DNA testing were <lb/>performed every 3-6 months in the first 3 years, <lb/>and then every 6 months thereafter until death. <lb/>Late toxicities were recorded according to items <lb/>from the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Categorical variables of the different subgroups <lb/>were compared using the χ 2 (chi-square) or <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test. Survival curves were estimated <lb/>using the Kaplan-Meier method with the log-rank <lb/>test. The Cox proportional hazards regression <lb/>model was used to analyze prognostic factors for <lb/>survival (backward stepwise). All the potential <lb/>prognostic factors were considered in the model <lb/>(age, gender, T stage, N stage, CCD, pre-DNA, <lb/>mid-DNA, pre-DNA + mid-DNA). Receiver <lb/>operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis and <lb/>concordance index (C-index) were performed to <lb/>compare the prognostic value of the TNM stage, <lb/>pre-DNA, mid-DNA, and the combination of pre-<lb/>DNA and mid-DNA. All statistical analyses in our <lb/>study were performed using R version 4.0.2 <lb/>(https://www.r-project.org/, Austria) and SPSS <lb/>26.0 software (IBM, Chicago, USA). p val-<lb/>ues &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. <lb/>Results <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>The median age of the 775 patients was 45 (range, <lb/>13-74) years, with 212 (27.4%) females and 563 <lb/>(72.6%) males. Among all patients, 553 (71.4%) <lb/>Figure 1. Flowchart for patient selection. <lb/>NPC, nasopharyngeal carcinoma. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <body>had pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and 222 (28.6%) <lb/>had ⩾4000 copies/mL. A total of 559 (72.1%) <lb/>patients had undetectable mid-DNA and 216 <lb/>(27.9%) had detectable mid-DNA. Only 42 <lb/>(5.42%) patients received concurrent target RT <lb/>(cetuximab or nimotuzumab) throughout IMRT. <lb/>The differences in demographics and clinical <lb/>characteristics between the different DNA-level <lb/>groups are shown in Table 1. The χ 2 test showed <lb/>higher pre-DNA and detectable mid-DNA were <lb/>significantly associated with advanced N category <lb/>and TNM stage (p &lt; 0.001). In addition, patients <lb/>with pre-DNA ⩾4000 copies/mL and detectable <lb/>mid-DNA were more likely to receive a high <lb/>CCD dose (&gt;200 mg/m 2 ). <lb/>Prognostic value of pre-DNA and mid-DNA <lb/>on survivals <lb/>The median follow-up time was 51.6 months <lb/>(range, 3.6-119 months). A total of 34 patients <lb/>(4.4%) had died and 134 (17.3%) with disease <lb/>progression during follow-up. As shown in Figure <lb/>2, patients with higher pre-DNA (⩾4000 copies/ <lb/>mL) had significant inferior 5-year PFS (67.0% <lb/>versus 85.4%, p &lt; 0.001), DMFS (78.5% versus <lb/>93.5%, p &lt; 0.001), and OS (89.4% versus 96.7%, <lb/>p &lt; 0.001) but not LRRFS (85.7% versus 91.2%, <lb/>p = 0.062) compared with those with lower pre-<lb/>DNA (&lt;4000 copies/mL). In addition, detectable <lb/>mid-DNA had significantly inferior 5-year PFS <lb/>(68.2% versus 84.4%, p &lt; 0.001), DMFS (82.4% <lb/>versus 91.8%, p = 0.001), and LRRFS (83.0% ver-<lb/>sus 92.0%, p = 0.003) but not OS (93.5% versus <lb/>95.2%, p = 0.171), compared to those undetecta-<lb/>ble mid-DNA. As shown in Table 2, the follow-<lb/>ing variables were considered in the Cox <lb/>proportional hazards model: age, gender, T stage, <lb/>N stage, pre-DNA, and mid-DNA. Multivariate <lb/>analysis showed that pre-DNA was a significant <lb/>predictor of PFS [hazard ratio (HR), 2.242; 95% <lb/>confidence interval (CI), 1.532-3.281; p &lt; 0.001], <lb/>DMFS (HR, 2.990; 95% CI, 1.799-4.969; <lb/>p &lt; 0.001), and OS (HR, 4.118; 95% CI, 1.938-<lb/>8.751; p &lt; 0.001), whereas mid-DNA was the sig-<lb/>nificant predictors of PFS (HR, 1.652; 95% CI, <lb/>1.138-2.399; p = 0.008) and LRRFS (HR, 1.965; <lb/>95% CI, 1.144-3.374; p = 0.014). In addition, we <lb/>found that mid-DNA had significantly interacted <lb/>with pre-DNA (Supplemental Figure S1). For <lb/>patients with pre-DNA &lt;4000 and ⩾4000 cop-<lb/>ies/mL, the probabilities of detectable mid-DNA <lb/>were 108 of 553 and 108 of 222, respectively <lb/>(19.5% versus 48.6%, p &lt; 0.001). Moreover, <lb/>patients with pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and <lb/>undetectable mid-DNA had significantly better <lb/>PFS (88.2% versus 67.2%, p &lt; 0.001), DMFS <lb/>(95.3% versus 81.0%, p &lt; 0.001), OS (97.0% ver-<lb/>sus 91.5%, p &lt; 0.001), and LRRFS (93.8% versus <lb/>83.5%, p &lt; 0.001) than the subgroup with detect-<lb/>able mid-DNA or pre-DNA ⩾4000 copies/mL <lb/>(Figure 3). <lb/>Next, we compared the performance of pre-DNA <lb/>and mid-DNA for prognostication. The area under <lb/>the ROC curves (AUC) is shown in Figure 4. The <lb/>AUC for combination of pre-DNA and mid-<lb/>DNA was greater than that for pre-DNA, mid-<lb/>DNA and TNM stage for predicting 5-year PFS <lb/>(0.679 versus 0.622, 0.608, 0.601; p = 0.105, <lb/>p = 0.004, p = 0.024, respectively) and DMFS <lb/>(0.694 versus 0.654, 0.608, 0.599; p = 0.005, <lb/>p = 0.002, p = 0.014, respectively). However, <lb/>AUC for a combination of pre-DNA and mid-<lb/>DNA compared to pre-DNA alone for predicting <lb/>5-year PFS was non-significant (0.679 versus <lb/>0.622, p = 0.105). The comparison of the C-index <lb/>of risk stratification with the TNM stage is listed <lb/>in Supplemental Table S1. The C-index of a <lb/>combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA in pre-<lb/>dicting PFS was 0.642, which was significantly <lb/>higher than that for the TNM stage, with values <lb/>of 0.558 (p &lt; 0.001). Similarly, the C-index for <lb/>DMFS and LRRFS prediction was 0.668 and <lb/>0.602 based on the combination of pre-DNA and <lb/>mid-DNA, which was significantly higher than <lb/>the C-index by TNM stage, with a value of 0.568 <lb/>and 0.537 (p &lt; 0.001, p = 0.040, respectively). <lb/>However, the predictive value of the combination <lb/>of pre-DNA and mid-DNA on OS is lower than <lb/>that of the TNM stage. <lb/>Subgroup analysis for whole patients based <lb/>on risk stratification <lb/>Accordingly, we divided the patients into low-risk <lb/>(pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and undetectable <lb/>mid-DNA) and high-risk groups (pre-DNA <lb/>⩾4000 copies/mL or detectable mid-DNA) <lb/>groups. The patient characteristics according to <lb/>the risk group are listed in Supplemental Table <lb/>S2. There were 445 (57.4%) and 330 (42.6%) <lb/>patients in the low-and high-risk groups, <lb/>respectively. Further multivariate analysis also <lb/>showed that the combination of pre-DNA and <lb/>mid-DNA was an independent prognostic factor <lb/>(Supplemental Table S3). <lb/>In the entire cohort, we found CCD was an inde-<lb/>pendent prognostic factor for PFS. We then <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">K Lan, M Jingrong et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 1. Clinical characteristics (n = 775). <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Total (n = 775) <lb/>Pre-DNA (copies/mL) <lb/>Mid-DNA <lb/>&lt;4000 <lb/>(n = 553) <lb/>⩾4000 <lb/>(n = 222) <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>p Value <lb/>Undetectable <lb/>(n = 559) <lb/>Detectable <lb/>(n = 216) <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>p Value <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>Age (yr) <lb/>1.008 <lb/>0.317 <lb/>2.039 <lb/>0.154 <lb/>Median (range) <lb/>46 (13-74) <lb/>46 (13-74) <lb/>45 (25-68) <lb/>45 (13-68) <lb/>45 (13-68) <lb/>⩽45 <lb/>362 (46.7%) <lb/>252 (45.6%) <lb/>110 (49.5%) <lb/>270 (48.3%) <lb/>92 (42.6%) <lb/>&gt;45 <lb/>413 (53.3%) <lb/>301 (54.4%) <lb/>112 (50.5%) <lb/>289 (51.7%) <lb/>124 (57.4%) <lb/>Gender <lb/>2.731 <lb/>0.102 <lb/>0.780 <lb/>0.378 <lb/>Male <lb/>563 (72.6%) <lb/>411 (74.3%) <lb/>152 (68.5%) <lb/>411 (73.5%) <lb/>152 (70.4%) <lb/>Female <lb/>212 (27.4%) <lb/>142 (25.7%) <lb/>70 (31.5%) <lb/>148 (26.5%) <lb/>64 (29.6%) <lb/>WHO pathologic <lb/>2.772 <lb/>0.091* <lb/>0.274 <lb/>0.596 <lb/>WHO type II <lb/>18 (2.32%) <lb/>16 (2.89%) <lb/>2 (0.90%) <lb/>12 (2.15%) <lb/>6 (2.78%) <lb/>WHO type III <lb/>757 (97.7%) <lb/>537 (97.1%) <lb/>220 (99.1%) <lb/>547 (97.9%) <lb/>210 (97.2%) <lb/>Smoking history <lb/>2.573 <lb/>0.112 <lb/>7.874 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>No <lb/>542 (69.9%) <lb/>396 (71.6%) <lb/>146 (65.8%) <lb/>135 (62.5%) <lb/>407 (72.8%) <lb/>Yes <lb/>233 (30.1%) <lb/>157 (28.4%) <lb/>76 (34.2%) <lb/>81 (37.5%) <lb/>152 (27.2%) <lb/>NPC family history <lb/>1.930 <lb/>0.164 <lb/>0.243 <lb/>0.710 <lb/>No <lb/>678 (87.5%) <lb/>478 (86.4%) <lb/>200 (90.1%) <lb/>191 (88.4%) <lb/>487 (87.1%) <lb/>Yes <lb/>97 (12.5%) <lb/>75 (13.6%) <lb/>22 (9.91%) <lb/>25 (11.6%) <lb/>72 (12.9%) <lb/>T stage <lb/>0.582 <lb/>0.451 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.912 <lb/>T1-2 <lb/>124 (16.0%) <lb/>92 (16.6%) <lb/>32 (14.4%) <lb/>90 (16.1%) <lb/>34 (15.7%) <lb/>T3-4 <lb/>651 (84.0%) <lb/>461 (83.4%) <lb/>190 (85.6%) <lb/>469 (83.9%) <lb/>182 (84.3%) <lb/>N stage <lb/>35.913 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>29.641 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>N0-1 <lb/>351 (45.3%) <lb/>288 (52.1%) <lb/>63 (28.4%) <lb/>287 (51.3%) <lb/>64 (29.6%) <lb/>N2-3 <lb/>424 (54.7%) <lb/>265 (47.9%) <lb/>159 (71.6%) <lb/>272 (48.7%) <lb/>152 (70.4%) <lb/>TNM stage <lb/>44.595 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>27.145 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>II <lb/>41 (5.29%) <lb/>33 (5.97%) <lb/>8 (3.60%) <lb/>37 (6.62%) <lb/>4 (1.85%) <lb/>III <lb/>534 (68.9%) <lb/>414 (74.9%) <lb/>120 (54.1%) <lb/>404 (72.3%) <lb/>130 (60.2%) <lb/>IVa <lb/>200 (25.8%) <lb/>106 (19.2%) <lb/>94 (42.3%) <lb/>118 (21.1%) <lb/>82 (38.0%) <lb/>Dose (Gy) <lb/>2.089 <lb/>0.404* <lb/>0.505 <lb/>0.098* <lb/>&lt;70 <lb/>11 (1.42%) <lb/>10 (1.81%) <lb/>1 (0.45%) <lb/>10 (1.79%) <lb/>1 (0.46%) <lb/>70 <lb/>747 (96.4%) <lb/>531 (96.0%) <lb/>216 (97.3%) <lb/>540 (96.6%) <lb/>207 (95.8%) <lb/>&gt;70 <lb/>17 (2.19%) <lb/>12 (2.17%) <lb/>5 (2.25%) <lb/>9 (1.61%) <lb/>8 (3.70%) <lb/>CTRT <lb/>0.116 <lb/>0.724 <lb/>0.062 <lb/>0.823 <lb/>No <lb/>733 (94.6%) <lb/>524 (94.8%) <lb/>209 (94.1%) <lb/>528 (94.5%) <lb/>205 (94.9%) <lb/>Yes <lb/>42 (5.42%) <lb/>29 (5.24%) <lb/>13 (5.86%) <lb/>31 (5.55%) <lb/>11 (5.09%) <lb/>CCD (mg/m 2 ) <lb/>57.841 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>13.480 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>⩽200 <lb/>380 (49.0%) <lb/>319 (57.7%) <lb/>61 (27.5%) <lb/>297 (53.1%) <lb/>83 (38.4%) <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>395 (51.0%) <lb/>234 (42.3%) <lb/>161 (72.5%) <lb/>262 (46.9%) <lb/>133 (61.6%) <lb/>Others were compared using the χ 2 . <lb/>*p Value was calculated with Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>CCD, cumulative cisplatin dose; CTRT, concurrent target-radiotherapy; mid-DNA, EBV DNA before second cycle cisplatin; NPC, nasopharyngeal carcinoma; pre-DNA, EBV DNA before treatment; <lb/>WHO, World Health Organization; yr, year. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <body>Table 2. Multivariable analysis of prognostic factors. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>PFS <lb/>DMFS <lb/>LRRFS <lb/>OS <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>Age (&gt;45 versus <lb/>⩽45) <lb/>0.928 <lb/>1.016 (0.721-1.432) 0.851 <lb/>0.957 (0.605-1.514) 0.518 <lb/>1.180 (0.714-1.950) 0.022 <lb/>2.349 (1.133-4.867) <lb/>Gender (male <lb/>versus female) <lb/>0.636 <lb/>1.098 (0.746-1.614) 0.724 <lb/>0.915 (0.557-1.502) 0.249 <lb/>1.422 (0.781-2.588) 0.469 <lb/>1.345 (0.603-3.004) <lb/>T stage (T3-4 <lb/>versus T1-2) <lb/>0.745 <lb/>1.083 (0.669-1.754) 0.534 <lb/>1.238 (0.632-2.425) 0.966 <lb/>0.985 (0.496-1.958) 0.065 <lb/>6.534 (0.889-48.017) <lb/>N stage (N2-3 <lb/>versus N0-1) <lb/>0.370 <lb/>1.182 (0.820-1.704) 0.151 <lb/>1.448 (0.874-2.401) 0.971 <lb/>0.990 (0.587-1.671) 0.053 <lb/>2.164 (0.989-4.735) <lb/>Pre-DNA (⩾4000 <lb/>versus &lt;4000) <lb/>&lt;0.001 2.242 (1.532-3.281) &lt;0.001 2.990 (1.799-4.969) 0.121 <lb/>1.570 (0.887-2.777) &lt;0.001 4.118 (1.938-8.751) <lb/>Mid-DNA (&gt;0 <lb/>versus =0) <lb/>0.008 <lb/>1.652 (1.138-2.399) 0.148 <lb/>1.436 (0.880-2.344) 0.014 <lb/>1.965 (1.144-3.374) 0.936 <lb/>0.970 (0.459-2.051) <lb/>CCD (⩽200 <lb/>versus &gt;200) <lb/>0.040 <lb/>1.458 (1.017-2.091) 0.340 <lb/>1.265 (0.781-2.049) 0.071 <lb/>1.628 (0.958-2.766) 0.120 <lb/>1.775 (0.861-3.660) <lb/>CI, confidence interval; DMFS, distant metastasis-free survival; HR, hazard ratio; LRRFS, locoregional relapse-free survival; OS, overall survival; <lb/>PFS, progression-free survival. <lb/>Figure 2. Kaplan-Meier for PFS, DMFS, LRRFS, and OS for all 775 patients with NPC stratified by pre-DNA (&lt;4000 versus <lb/>⩾4000 copies/mL; a-d) and mid-DNA (undetectable versus detectable; e-h). <lb/>DMFS, distant metastasis-free survival; LRRFS, locoregional relapse-free survival; NPC, nasopharyngeal carcinoma; OS, overall survival; PFS, <lb/>progression-free survival. <lb/>evaluated the prognostic impact of CCD in two <lb/>subgroups. The median CCD was 200 mg/m 2 in <lb/>the low-risk group and 280 mg/m 2 in the high-risk <lb/>group, respectively. Because CCD of 200 mg/m 2 <lb/>was the threshold for achieving satisfactory survival <lb/>in the published data, we used CCD of 200 mg/m 2 <lb/>as the cutoff value. In the low-risk group, 262 <lb/>(58.9%) patients received CCD of ⩽200 mg/m 2 , <lb/>and 183 (41.1%) patients received CCD of <lb/>&gt;200 mg/m 2 . Patients receiving CCD of &gt;200 mg/ <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">K Lan, M Jingrong et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <body>m 2 and ⩽200 mg/m 2 had similar 5-year PFS <lb/>(88.3% versus 88.6%, p = 0.753), DMFS (96.4% <lb/>versus 94.5%, p = 0.312), LRRFS (94.8% versus <lb/>93.2%, p = 0.772), and OS (96.3% versus 95.8%, <lb/>p = 0.364). Notably, most patients (226/262, <lb/>86.2%) in the ⩽200 mg/m 2 CCD subgroups <lb/>received a DDP dose of 200 mg/m 2 . However, in <lb/>the high-risk group, 118 (35.8%) patients received <lb/>CCD of ⩽200 mg/m 2 and 212 (64.2%) patients <lb/>received CCD of &gt;200 mg/m 2 . Patients receiving <lb/>CCD of &gt;200 mg/m 2 showed improved 5-year <lb/>PFS (73.1% versus 58.6%, p = 0.027) and LRRFS <lb/>(88.5% versus 76.1%, p = 0.028) than those receiv-<lb/>ing CCD ⩽200 mg/m 2 (Figure 5). Moreover, <lb/>CCD was an independent prognostic factor for <lb/>PFS (HR, 1.570, 95% CI, 1.031-2.391, p = 0.036) <lb/>in the high-risk group, whereas it was not signifi-<lb/>cantly associated with any survival outcome in the <lb/>low-risk group (Table 3). <lb/>Late radiation-related toxicity <lb/>Data from 436 patients were excluded owing to <lb/>missing or inadequate documentation. Regarding <lb/>late toxicities, dry mouth was the most common <lb/>chief complaint during patients&apos; routine <lb/>follow-up visits among all late radiation-related <lb/>toxicities (243 patients; 71.7%). In addition, 188 <lb/>patients (55.5%) had hearing impairment and 85 <lb/>(25.1%) developed skin fibrosis. No treatment-<lb/>related deaths occurred in either of the groups. In <lb/>addition, patients receiving &gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD <lb/>exhibited a higher proportion of peripheral neu-<lb/>ropathy (18.3% versus 8.24%, p = 0.006) and a <lb/>marginally higher proportion of all-grade hearing <lb/>impairment (59.8% versus 51.2%, p = 0.114), dry <lb/>mouth (75.1% versus 68.2%, p = 0.161), and skin <lb/>fibrosis (29.6% versus 20.6%, p = 0.058) than <lb/>those receiving ⩽200 mg/m 2 CCD. However, the <lb/>incidence of grade 3-4 late toxicities was compa-<lb/>rable between the two groups (Table 4). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Based on a relatively large number of patients, we <lb/>found that both pre-DNA and mid-DNA were <lb/>powerful predictors of clinical outcomes in NPC <lb/>patients treated with CCRT. Patients with pre-<lb/>DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and undetectable mid-<lb/>DNA showed a better prognosis than those with <lb/>other combinations. ROC analysis demonstrated <lb/>that the calculated AUC for 5-year PFS and DMFS <lb/>Figure 3. Kaplan-Meier for PFS (a), DMFS (b), LRRFS (c), and OS (d) between the high-and low-risk groups. <lb/>DMFS, distant metastasis-free survival; LRRFS, locoregional relapse-free survival; OS, overall survival; PFS, progression-free survival. <lb/>Figure 4. ROC analysis comparing the prognostic value of pre-DNA, mid-DNA, the combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA, and TNM <lb/>stage in 5-year progression (a), 5-year metastasis (b), 5-year locoregional failure (c), and 5-year death (d). <lb/>ROC, receiver operating curve. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <body>of the combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA had <lb/>a better prognostic value than the TNM stage. <lb/>Accordingly, we identified pre-DNA &lt;4000 cop-<lb/>ies/mL with undetectable mid-DNA as low risk <lb/>and pre-DNA ⩾4000 copies/mL or detectable mid-<lb/>DNA as high risk. In the low-risk group, patients <lb/>who received ⩽200 and &gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD had <lb/>similar prognoses. However, in the high-risk group, <lb/>patients receiving &gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD showed sig-<lb/>nificantly improved 5-year PFS and LRRFS than <lb/>those receiving ⩽200 mg/m 2 , and CCD was an <lb/>independent prognostic factor for PFS. <lb/>Consistently, pre-treatment plasma EBV DNA <lb/>level is a powerful supplement of TNM in predict-<lb/>ing recurrence and metastasis in NPC. 12,16,20 <lb/>Multiple studies have indicated that pre-DNA <lb/>⩾4000 copies/mL have a significantly worse prog-<lb/>nosis than pre-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL. 13,16,21 In <lb/>addition, an expanding body of data suggests that <lb/>undetectable plasma EBV DNA during the mid-<lb/>course of treatment correlates with better tumor <lb/>control and survival. 14-16 Similarly, we found that <lb/>pre-DNA and undetectable mid-DNA levels were <lb/>independent prognostic factors for NPC treated <lb/>with CCRT. It was also observed that patients <lb/>with pre-DNA mid-DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL and <lb/>undetectable mid-DNA had significantly better <lb/>clinical outcomes than other subgroups, and the <lb/>combination of these two timepoints was better <lb/>than either single timepoints or TNM stage for <lb/>predicting the AUC of 5-year PFS and DMFS. <lb/>Although AUC for 5-year PFS for a combination <lb/>of pre-DNA and mid-DNA compared to pre-<lb/>DNA was nonsignificant, there was a considerable <lb/>improvement in accuracy. The possible reason <lb/>might be related to the limitation of sample size, <lb/>which led to lower statistical efficiency. Moreover, <lb/>pre-DNA load may correlate with tumor load, <lb/>while mid-DNA load is more likely to represent <lb/>the sensitivity of chemoradiotherapy. Therefore, <lb/>the combination of pre-DNA and mid-DNA could <lb/>complement each other and contribute to early <lb/>risk stratification and prognosis prediction. Further <lb/>studies are required to validate this hypothesis. <lb/>In two-dimensional RT, a higher cumulative dose <lb/>of cisplatin correlated with improved local con-<lb/>trol. In a combined analysis of NPC 9901 and <lb/>NPC 9902 using two-dimensional radiotherapy <lb/>(2DRT), the dose of cisplatin during the concur-<lb/>rent phase had a significant impact on locore-<lb/>gional failure and OS. 6 However, the benefit of a <lb/>higher dose of cisplatin in the setting of IMRT is <lb/>controversial. Previous studies have demon-<lb/>strated that a CCD of 200 mg/m 2 is associated <lb/>with improved prognosis in NPC. Peng et al. 7 <lb/>found that 200 mg/m 2 CCD might be adequate to <lb/>achieve a survival benefit for NPC patients treated <lb/>with CCRT, while ⩾240 mg/m 2 CCD was not <lb/>Figure 5. Kaplan-Meier for PFS (a), DMFS (b), LRRFS (c), and OS (d) curves for 445 NPC patients stratified by CCD ⩽200 and <lb/>&gt;200 mg/m 2 in a low-risk group. PFS (e), DMFS (f), LRRFS (g), and OS (h) curves for 330 NPC patients stratified by CCD ⩽200 and <lb/>&gt;200 mg/m 2 in the high-risk group. <lb/>CCD, cumulative cisplatin dose; DMFS, distant metastasis-free survival; LRRFS, locoregional relapse-free survival; NPC, nasopharyngeal carcinoma; <lb/>OS, overall survival; PFS, progression-free survival. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">K Lan, M Jingrong et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    <body>observed as an independent prognostic factor. <lb/>Similar results were observed by Wei et al., 22 indi-<lb/>cating that CCD &gt;200 mg/m 2 improved the <lb/>5-year PFS rates and significantly improved <lb/>DMFS compared to CCD ⩽200 mg/m 2 . <lb/>However, because patients with NPC present <lb/>with different prognoses, some predictors have <lb/>been used to identify high-risk patients and mod-<lb/>ify the optimal dose of concurrent DDP. Guo et <lb/>al. 5 reported no significant differences between <lb/>groups receiving 101-200 mg/m 2 and &gt;200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 CCD for low-risk NPC patients with pre-<lb/>DNA &lt;4000 copies/mL, which was confirmed by <lb/>Li et al. 8 Liu et al. 10 found that enhancement of <lb/>CCD (&gt;200 versus &lt;100 mg/m 2 CCD) provided <lb/>a survival benefit for patients who achieved com-<lb/>plete tumor response/partial response after IC but <lb/>not for patients who achieved stable disease/dis-<lb/>ease progression after IC. In addition, Ou et al. 9 <lb/>identified that patients with N2-3 disease might <lb/>benefit from higher CCD (⩾300 mg/m 2 ). In our <lb/>study, we divided the patients into low-and high-<lb/>risk groups based on the combination of pre-<lb/>DNA and mid-DNA levels. In the low-risk group, <lb/>patients receiving ⩽200 mg/m 2 CCD showed effi-<lb/>cacy similar to that of &gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD but <lb/>were associated with fewer all-grade late toxici-<lb/>ties. Consistent with previous studies, 7,22 balanc-<lb/>ing toxicity and efficacy, 200 mg/m 2 seemed to be <lb/>the optimal DDP dose for patients with pre-DNA <lb/>&lt;4000 copies/mL and undetectable mid-DNA. <lb/>Among high-risk patients with pre-DNA <lb/>⩾4000 copies/mL or detectable mid-DNA, appli-<lb/>cation of &gt;200 mg/m 2 CCD was significantly <lb/>Table 3. Summary of multivariate analysis of prognostic factors in high-and low-risk groups. <lb/>Characteristics PFS <lb/>DMFS <lb/>LRRFS <lb/>OS <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p Value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p value HR (95% CI) <lb/>p value HR (95% CI) <lb/>Low-risk group (n = 445) <lb/>Age (&gt;45 <lb/>versus ⩽45) <lb/>0.821 <lb/>0.933 (0.512-1.701) 0.582 <lb/>1.286 (0.525-3.149) 0.577 <lb/>0.793 (0.352-1.790) <lb/>0.215 <lb/>2.330 (0.612-8.874) <lb/>Gender <lb/>(male versus <lb/>female) <lb/>0.124 <lb/>1.888 (0.840-4.244) 0.739 <lb/>0.849 (0.325-2.219) 0.069 <lb/>3.836 (0.900-16.351) 0.536 <lb/>1.627 (0.349-7.592) <lb/>T stage (T3-4 <lb/>versus T1-2) <lb/>0.525 <lb/>1.329 (0.553-3.192) 0.531 <lb/>0.697 (0.226-2.156) 0.233 <lb/>2.436 (0.565-10.510) 0.998 <lb/>* <lb/>N stage (N2-3 <lb/>versus N0-1) <lb/>0.328 <lb/>1.348 (0.742-2.450) 0.980 <lb/>1.011 (0.413-2.474) 0.110 <lb/>1.952 (0.860-4.427) <lb/>0.155 <lb/>2.452 (0.713-8.435) <lb/>CCD (⩽200 <lb/>versus &gt;200) <lb/>0.690 <lb/>1.133 (0.614-2.092) 0.333 <lb/>1.613 (0.613-4.244) 0.722 <lb/>1.163 (0.506-2.676) <lb/>0.512 <lb/>1.564 (0.410-5.961) <lb/>High-risk group (n = 330) <lb/>Age (&gt;45 <lb/>versus ⩽45) <lb/>0.882 <lb/>1.032 (0.681-1.564) 0.478 <lb/>0.824 (0.483-1.406) 0.173 <lb/>1.561 (0.823-2.961) <lb/>0.088 <lb/>2.115 (0.894-5.004) <lb/>Gender <lb/>(male versus <lb/>female) <lb/>0.572 <lb/>0.879 (0.562-1.375) 0.781 <lb/>0.921 (0.517-1.641) 0.857 <lb/>0.938 (0.470-1.873) <lb/>0.718 <lb/>1.190 (0.463-3.056) <lb/>T stage (T3-4 <lb/>versus T1-2) <lb/>0.926 <lb/>1.027 (0.579-1.824) 0.240 <lb/>1.666 (0.711-3.904) 0.328 <lb/>0.676 (0.308-1.481) <lb/>0.142 <lb/>4.502 (0.603-33.584) <lb/>N stage (N2-3 <lb/>versus N0-1) <lb/>0.792 <lb/>1.062 (0.680-1.658) 0.133 <lb/>1.615 (0.864-3.017) 0.152 <lb/>0.626 (0.330-1.187) <lb/>0.185 <lb/>1.959 (0.725-5.292) <lb/>CCD (⩽200 <lb/>versus &gt;200) <lb/>0.036 <lb/>1.570 (1.031-2.391) 0.780 <lb/>1.082 (0.623-1.877) 0.051 <lb/>1.891 (0.997-3.587) <lb/>0.330 <lb/>1.512 (0.658-3.474) <lb/>CCD, cumulative cisplatin dose; CI, confidence interval; DMFS, distant metastasis-free survival; HR, hazard ratio; LRRFS, locoregional relapse-free <lb/>survival; OS, overall survival; PFS, progression-free survival. <lb/>*No patients dead in stage T1-2 patients. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <body>associated with improved PFS and LRRFS. <lb/>Therefore, for patients with higher and sustaina-<lb/>ble monitoring EBV DNA load, except for the <lb/>high dose of CCD to be considered during RT, <lb/>the intensification of therapy such as maintenance <lb/>treatment, targeted therapy, and immunotherapy <lb/>might be augmented into the adjuvant period to <lb/>improve the survival outcomes. <lb/>Despite these positive findings, our study has sev-<lb/>eral limitations. First, because this was a retro-<lb/>spective study, there was an unavoidable selection <lb/>bias, and the results need validation in further <lb/>prospective studies. Second, because a very small <lb/>proportion of patients received concurrent tar-<lb/>geted therapy in this study, the survival benefit of <lb/>targeted therapy between the risk subgroups was <lb/>not discussed. Third, some patients were evalu-<lb/>ated by chest radiography, abdominal sonogra-<lb/>phy, and bone scan for distant disease evaluation <lb/>before treatment, which might reduce and delay <lb/>the detection of metastatic disease. Last but not <lb/>least, the data were obtained exclusively from one <lb/>center; therefore, a multicenter study is required. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Pre-DNA and mid-DNA levels were independent <lb/>prognostic factors in NPC patients treated with <lb/>CCRT. Balancing toxicity and efficacy, 200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 appeared to be the optimal dose in the low-risk <lb/>groups. Considering the higher proportion of <lb/>treatment failures in the high-risk group, &gt;200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 might be required to achieve satisfactory dis-<lb/>ease control. The combination of pre-DNA and <lb/>mid-DNA could help clinicians better identify <lb/>patients at different risks of treatment failure and <lb/>adjust the intensity of the CCD. Further investi-<lb/>gation is necessary to confirm our findings. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>The study was performed in line with the princi-<lb/>ples of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved <lb/>by the Institutional Review Board and Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Sun Yat-sen University Cancer <lb/>Center. <lb/>Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>Kaiqi Lan: Data curation; Formal analysis; <lb/>Methodology; Writing -original draft. <lb/>Jingrong Mao: Conceptualization; Formal <lb/>analysis; Methodology. <lb/>Xuesong Sun: Data curation; Formal analysis. <lb/>Suchen Li: Formal analysis. <lb/></div>

    <body>Table 4. Major late adverse events. <lb/>Toxic effect <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 339) <lb/>Any grade <lb/>Grade 3 or 4 <lb/>CCD ⩽ 200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 (n = 170) <lb/>CCD &gt; 200 mg/m 2 <lb/>(n = 169) <lb/>p Value <lb/>CCD &lt; 200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 (n = 170) <lb/>CCD &gt; 200 mg/ <lb/>m 2 (n = 169) <lb/>p Value <lb/>Hearing <lb/>impairment <lb/>188 (55.5%) 87 (51.2%) <lb/>101 (59.8%) <lb/>0.114 <lb/>10 (5.88%) <lb/>14 (8.28%) <lb/>0.400 <lb/>Dry mouth <lb/>243 (71.7%) 116 (68.2%) <lb/>127 (75.1%) <lb/>0.161 <lb/>9 (5.29%) <lb/>9 (5.33%) <lb/>0.990 <lb/>Skin fibrosis <lb/>85 (25.1%) <lb/>35 (20.6%) <lb/>50 (29.6%) <lb/>0.058 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (0.59%) <lb/>0.499* <lb/>Trismus <lb/>42 (12.4%) <lb/>19 (11.2%) <lb/>23 (13.6%) <lb/>0.503 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Temporal lobe <lb/>injury <lb/>33 (9.73%) <lb/>19 (11.2%) <lb/>14 (8.28%) <lb/>0.377 <lb/>2 (1.18%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.499* <lb/>Cranial <lb/>neuropathy <lb/>45 (13.3%) <lb/>22 (12.9%) <lb/>23 (13.6%) <lb/>0.858 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Peripheral <lb/>neuropathy <lb/>45 (13.3%) <lb/>14 (8.24%) <lb/>31 (18.3%) <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (0.59%) <lb/>0.499* <lb/>*p Values were calculated using the Fisher test. <lb/>CCD, cumulative cisplatin dose. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">K Lan, M Jingrong et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Siyi Xie: Data curation. <lb/>Rui Sun: Conceptualization; Methodology; <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>Sailan Liu: Conceptualization; Methodology; <lb/>Supervision; Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>Haiqiang Mai: Conceptualization; Funding <lb/>acquisition; Supervision; Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank all the patients who participated in this <lb/>study. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The authors disclosed receipt of the following <lb/>financial support for the research, authorship, <lb/>and/or publication of this article: This study was <lb/>funded by grants from the National Key Research <lb/>and <lb/>Development <lb/>Program <lb/>of <lb/>China <lb/>(2022YFC2505800 and 2022YFC2705005), <lb/>National Natural Science Foundation of China <lb/>(No. <lb/>32200651, <lb/>82203776, <lb/>82203125, <lb/>82222050, 82272739, 82272882, 82173287, <lb/>82073003, <lb/>82003267, <lb/>and <lb/>82002852), <lb/>Guangdong Basic and Applied Basic Research <lb/>Foundation (2021B1515230002), Science and <lb/>Technology <lb/>Program <lb/>of <lb/>Guangzhou <lb/>(202201011561 and 2023A04J2127), Sun Yat-<lb/>sen University Clinical Research 5010 Program <lb/>(Nos 201315, 2015021, 2017010, and 2019023), <lb/>Innovative Research Team of High-level Local <lb/>Universities <lb/>in <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>(SSMU-<lb/>ZLCX20180500), <lb/>Postdoctoral <lb/>Innovative <lb/>Talent Support Program (BX20220361), <lb/>Planned Science and Technology Project of <lb/>Guangdong Province (2019B020230002), Key <lb/>Youth Teacher Cultivating Program of Sun Yat-<lb/>sen University (20ykzd24), and Fundamental <lb/>Research Funds for the Central Universities. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that there is no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>The datasets used and analyzed during the cur-<lb/>rent study are available from the corresponding <lb/>author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

    <front>ORCID iD <lb/>Haiqiang Mai <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-<lb/>6735-8670 <lb/></front>

    <div type="annex">Supplemental material <lb/>Supplemental material for this article is available <lb/>online. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Wong KCW, Hui EP, Lo KW, et al. <lb/>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: an evolving <lb/>paradigm. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 2021; 18: 679-695. <lb/>2. Chen YP, Chan ATC, Le QT, et al. <lb/>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Lancet 2019; 394: <lb/>64-80. <lb/>3. Hui EP, Ma BBY, Lam WKJ, et al. Dynamic <lb/>changes of post-radiotherapy plasma Epstein-<lb/>Barr virus DNA in a randomized trial of <lb/>adjuvant chemotherapy versus observation in <lb/>nasopharyngeal cancer. Clin Cancer Res 2021; 27: <lb/>2827-2836. <lb/>4. Caudell JJ, Gillison ML, Maghami E, et al. <lb/>NCCN guidelines(R) insights: head and neck <lb/>cancers, version 1.2022. J Natl Compr Cancer <lb/>Netw 2022; 20: 224-234. <lb/>5. Guo SS, Tang LQ, Zhang L, et al. The impact <lb/>of the cumulative dose of cisplatin during <lb/>concurrent chemoradiotherapy on the clinical <lb/>outcomes of patients with advanced-stage <lb/>nasopharyngeal carcinoma in an era of intensity-<lb/>modulated radiotherapy. BMC Cancer 2015; 15: <lb/>977. <lb/>6. Lee AW, Tung SY, Ngan RK, et al. Factors <lb/>contributing to the efficacy of concurrent-<lb/>adjuvant chemotherapy for locoregionally <lb/>advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: combined <lb/>analyses of NPC-9901 and NPC-9902 trials. Eur <lb/>J Cancer 2011; 47: 656-666. <lb/>7. Peng H, Chen L, Zhang Y, et al. Prognostic <lb/>value of the cumulative cisplatin dose during <lb/>concurrent chemoradiotherapy in locoregionally <lb/>advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a secondary <lb/>analysis of a prospective phase III clinical trial. <lb/>Oncologist 2016; 21: 1369-1376. <lb/>8. Li XY, Luo DH, Guo L, et al. Deintensified <lb/>chemoradiotherapy for pretreatment Epstein-<lb/>Barr virus DNA-selected low-risk locoregionally <lb/>advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a phase <lb/>II randomized noninferiority trial. J Clin Oncol <lb/>2022; 40: 1163-1173. <lb/>9. Ou X, Xu T, He X, et al. Who benefited most <lb/>from higher cumulative dose of cisplatin among <lb/>patients with locally advanced nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma treated by intensity-modulated <lb/>radiation therapy? A retrospective study of 527 <lb/>cases. J Cancer 2017; 8: 2836-2845. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">TherapeuTic advances in <lb/>Medical Oncology <lb/>Volume 16 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">journals.sagepub.com/home/tam <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>10. Liu SL, Sun XS, Yan JJ, et al. Optimal <lb/>cumulative cisplatin dose in nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma patients based on induction <lb/>chemotherapy response. Radiother Oncol 2019; <lb/>137: 83-94. <lb/>11. Wang WY, Twu CW, Chen HH, et al. Long-term <lb/>survival analysis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma by <lb/>plasma Epstein-Barr virus DNA levels. Cancer <lb/>2013; 119: 963-970. <lb/>12. Lin JC, Wang WY, Chen KY, et al. <lb/>Quantification of plasma Epstein-Barr virus <lb/>DNA in patients with advanced nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma. N Engl J Med 2004; 350: 2461-2470. <lb/>13. Chan AT, Lo YM, Zee B, et al. Plasma Epstein-<lb/>Barr virus DNA and residual disease after <lb/>radiotherapy for undifferentiated nasopharyngeal <lb/>carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 2002; 94: 1614-1619. <lb/>14. Huang CL, Sun ZQ, Guo R, et al. Plasma <lb/>Epstein-Barr virus DNA load after induction <lb/>chemotherapy predicts outcome in locoregionally <lb/>advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat <lb/>Oncol Biol Phys 2019; 104: 355-361. <lb/>15. Chen FP, Luo YS, Chen K, et al. Circulating <lb/>Epstein-Barr virus DNA level post induction <lb/>chemotherapy contributes to prognostication in <lb/>advanced-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Eur J <lb/>Cancer 2021; 151: 63-71. <lb/>16. Leung SF, Chan KC, Ma BB, et al. Plasma <lb/>Epstein-Barr viral DNA load at midpoint <lb/>of radiotherapy course predicts outcome in <lb/>advanced-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Ann <lb/>Oncol 2014; 25: 1204-1208. <lb/>17. Prayongrat A, Chakkabat C, Kannarunimit <lb/>D, et al. Prevalence and significance of <lb/>plasma Epstein-Barr virus DNA level in <lb/>nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Radiat Res 2017; <lb/>58: 509-516. <lb/>18. Chen FP, Huang XD, Lv JW, et al. Prognostic <lb/>potential of liquid biopsy tracking in the <lb/>posttreatment surveillance of patients with <lb/>nonmetastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Cancer <lb/>2020; 126: 2163-2173. <lb/>19. Chan ATC, Hui EP, Ngan RKC, et al. <lb/>Analysis of plasma Epstein-Barr virus DNA in <lb/>nasopharyngeal cancer after chemoradiation <lb/>to identify high-risk patients for adjuvant <lb/>chemotherapy: a randomized controlled trial. <lb/>J Clin Oncol 2018; JCO2018777847. <lb/>20. Tang LQ, Li CF, Li J, et al. Establishment and <lb/>validation of prognostic nomograms for endemic <lb/>nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst <lb/>2016; 108(1): djv291. <lb/>21. Leung SF, Zee B, Ma BB, et al. Plasma Epstein-<lb/>Barr viral deoxyribonucleic acid quantitation <lb/>complements tumor-node-metastasis staging <lb/>prognostication in nasopharyngeal carcinoma. <lb/>J Clin Oncol 2006; 24: 5414-5418. <lb/>22. Wei W, Huang Z, Li S, et al. Pretreatment <lb/>Epstein-Barr virus DNA load and cumulative <lb/>cisplatin dose intensity affect long-term outcome <lb/>of nasopharyngeal carcinoma treated with <lb/>concurrent chemotherapy: experience of an <lb/>institute in an endemic area. Oncol Res Treat <lb/>2014; 37: 88-95. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">Visit Sage journals online <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/ <lb/>home/tam <lb/>Sage journals </note>


  </text>

</TEI>