<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T16:25:19.032Z">11/21/2025 4:25:19 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T16:25:09.635707Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T16:25:09.635707Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>2024, Vol. 12, No. 3, pp. 40-47 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.11648/j.bio.20241203.11 <lb/>* Corresponding author: <lb/>Received: 26 March 2024; Accepted: 18 April 2024; Published: 10 May 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © The Author(s), 2024. Published by Science Publishing Group. This is an Open Access article, distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Research Article <lb/>Effect of Productive Tillers on Seed Yield and Seed Quality <lb/>of Sorghum (Sorghum bicolor L.) Varieties in Assosa <lb/>District, Western Ethiopia <lb/>Fekede Tena Ayana , Mosisa Tolosa * <lb/>Holetta Agricultural Research Centre, Ethiopian Institute of Agricultural Research Centre (EIAR), Holetta, Ethiopia <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Poor management of sorghum tillers is a significant problem in the Benishangul-Gumuz region of Ethiopia, affecting seed yield <lb/>and quality. An experiment was conducted to determine the impact of sorghum productive tillers on seed yield and quality. The <lb/>study involved two Sorghum varieties (Assosa-1 and Adukara) and three plant types per spot. The treatments were aligned as <lb/>RCBD and CRD in factorial combination, replicated three and four times for field and laboratory experiments respectively. <lb/>Varieties influenced TSW (P &lt; 0.0001), Number of tiller influenced by number plants head matured for seed production (P ≤ <lb/>0.0001), plants height (P ≤ 0.0004), The interaction effects of varieties and number of tillers per plant influenced yields, <lb/>Panicle length (P &lt; 0.0001). For laboratory experiments varieties influenced Speed of germination (P &lt; 0.0001), number of <lb/>Dead seeds (P &lt; 0.0001). Number of tiller influenced Speed of germination (P &lt; 0.0001), number of Dead seeds, shoot length <lb/>(P &lt; 0.004), Vigor index one and Vigor index two (P≤0.05). The interaction effects of varieties and number of tillers per plant <lb/>influenced Standard germination (P &lt; 0.001). The main shoot plants had the highest number of fertile sorghum heads (86.5), <lb/>followed by primary tillers (27.08). Secondary tillers had the highest plant height (96.52 cm). The main shoot plant yielded more <lb/>seeds than primary and secondary tillers, with the shoot exceeding these yields by 302.96% and 1333%, respectively. Primary <lb/>and secondary tillers had higher percentages of dead seeds than the main shoot plant, 53.5% and 45.2%, respectively. The <lb/>primary and secondary tillers experienced a decline in seedling vigour index one over different periods, while the main sorghum <lb/>plant varieties, Adukara and Assosa-1, showed an upward trend. The germination percentages of the primary and secondary <lb/>tillers were less than the 85% Ethiopian seed standard requirement. Because sorghum tillers lower seed quality, they should be <lb/>eliminated for seed production. If sorghum is grown for grain production, secondary tillers have the benefit of raising overall <lb/>yield production. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Sorghum, Seed, Quality, Main Shoot, Primary Tiller, Secondary Tiller, Yield <lb/></front>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>41 <lb/></page>

    <body>1. Introduction <lb/>Grain sorghum (Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench) is im-<lb/>portant crop in arid and semi-arid regions of the world. <lb/>Ethiopia accounts for 9% of the area producing grain sorghum <lb/>in the Africa, producing on 23010 metric tons [19]. <lb/>It is adapted to hot and dry climates and is more tolerant of <lb/>heat and moisture stress than other crops [3]. It is relatively <lb/>slow growing in early vegetative stages compared to other <lb/>crops [18]. It has been reported to grow more slowly when <lb/>planted early in the growing season [1, 18]. The slow growth <lb/>of grain sorghum in early vegetative stages decreases its <lb/>competitive ability and allows weeds to establish more easily <lb/>than other crops [16]. <lb/>Sorghum is used as a source of food for rural populations. <lb/>In comparison to other food crops, sorghum preferred crop for <lb/>dry land farming agriculture because of its enormous flexi-<lb/>bility and tolerance to unfavorable environments [7, 10]. <lb/>Sorghum is one of Ethiopia&apos;s most stable and varied food <lb/>crops [15]. <lb/>Modern sorghum hybrids produce from zero to four fertile <lb/>tillers in field conditions so that at plant densities below 4 m -2 , <lb/>around 70-80 % of total plant leaf area and grain yield can be <lb/>attributed to tillers [12, 13]. <lb/>Assosa Agricultural Research Center released two varieties <lb/>of sorghum which is highly productive for low land humid <lb/>area of BG region. The verities of sorghum contain a lot of <lb/>potential which is no addressed yet. These are productivity <lb/>under poor soil fertility, tolerance of acidic soil and diseases, <lb/>and large tillering ability. Tillering is an important agronomic <lb/>trait in many high-tillering cereals such as wheat (Triticum <lb/>aestivum), rice (Oryza sativa) and barley (Hordeum vulgare), <lb/>and contributed significantly to improved yield associated <lb/>with the &apos;green revolution&apos; [6]. Crop stand and optimum <lb/>number of crop plant per hectare determine seed yield and <lb/>seed quality in sorghum seed production. Optimum numbers <lb/>of crop per hectare based space between plant and raw. As <lb/>space between plant and raw increase number of plant per <lb/>hectare decrease and vies versa. High or low numbers of crop <lb/>plant population per acre affect not only the yield but also the <lb/>quality of the seed to be produced. Tillering has a significant <lb/>effect on canopy development and, hence, on resource capture, <lb/>crop growth and grain yield in sorghum. Tillering has a major <lb/>influence on plant leaf area development [12] and, hence, on <lb/>crop water-use patterns and adaptation to water-limited en-<lb/>vironments [11]. <lb/>Sorghum varieties released by Assosa Agricultural Re-<lb/>search Center is very poor on the field at early germination <lb/>period. They require proper land preparation, keeping appro-<lb/>priate planning depth, crop protection against insect pest <lb/>(grasshopper, shoot fly) and weeds. The slow growth of grain <lb/>sorghum in early vegetative stages decreases its competitive <lb/>ability and allows weeds to establish more easily than other <lb/>crops [16]. <lb/>But the farm of sorghum seed producer patch in terms of <lb/>plant population due to lack of proper land preparation, <lb/>keeping appropriate planning depth and crop protection <lb/>against insect pest (grasshopper, shoot fly) and weeds. <lb/>Sometime farmers transplant seedlings to solve the problem. <lb/>Due to erratic rain fall and technical transplanting error <lb/>transplanted seedling may die. Sparsely planted sorghum farm <lb/>produce a lot of tillers at each seedlings and cause competition <lb/>of nutrients, moisture, and light during photosynthesis which <lb/>influence on seed yield and seed quality. Sorghum produce <lb/>tillers at different time and matured one after the other. The <lb/>alternate maturity affects the quality of the seed production. <lb/>On the other hand removal of tillers cause continues produc-<lb/>tion of tillers which increase cost of production. <lb/>High seed rate during seed planting production result in <lb/>stunted seedling on the farm due to competition among seed-<lb/>lings. These affect the yield and quality of seed production. <lb/>The alternate tiller emergency and seed maturity affects the <lb/>quality of the seed during seed production. The removal of <lb/>densely populated seedling incurs cost of seed production <lb/>which reduces profitability in seed production business. <lb/>Therefore, the current work proposed to identify effect of <lb/>productive tiller on seed yield and seed quality and to identify <lb/>the effect of tiller on seed production business. <lb/>2. Materials and Methods <lb/>2.1. Description of the Experimental Site <lb/>The research was conducted in Benishangul Gumuze Na-<lb/>tional Regional State, at air port seed production farm sit and <lb/>Bambasi District on farm, in 2017-2019 during the main <lb/>cropping season. The experiment was conducted under both <lb/>fields as well as in a laboratory. Benishangul Gumuze Na-<lb/>tional Regional State is positioned on Geographical location <lb/>of 10004&apos;N latitude, and 34031&apos;E longitude and at altitude <lb/>1570 meter above sea level at distance of 667 km to the west <lb/>of Addis Ababa-Ethiopia. <lb/>2.2. Description of the Material Used <lb/>Planting Materials <lb/>The planting material used for the research was Assosa-1 <lb/>and Adukara sorghum variety, which originated from Assosa <lb/>Agricultural Research Centre. They are adaptable to low land <lb/>humid area. Both released in the year 2015. <lb/>The number of days to flowering is 138 -144 and 148-154, <lb/>on farm average yield is 27.6-41.3qt and 30-30.6 qt per hec-<lb/>tare for Assosa-1 and Adukara respectively. The seed of As-<lb/>sosa-1 is white and Adukara is red in colour [20]. <lb/>2.3. Treatments and Experimental Design <lb/>The treatment aligned as RCBD in factorial combination <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>42 <lb/></page>

    <body>replicated three times and the treatments was consist of <lb/>Number of plant per hole /Main plant (one seedling), two <lb/>plants (one tiller and main seedling), three plants (two tiller <lb/>and main seedling), Planting space 20cm by 75cm. <lb/>2.4. Experimental Procedure <lb/>2.4.1. Sampling <lb/>The land was ploughed, harrowed and well prepared for <lb/>planting by a tractor. The seed was sown in rows at the depth <lb/>of 3 -4 cm. Hand Weeding, hoeing and/ or hand pulling <lb/>operation starts two weeks after planting. Only plants in the <lb/>middle rows were harvested for estimation of yield and <lb/>quality leaving aside those in the border rows as well as <lb/>those at the ends of each row. The crop was harvested <lb/>manually and dried until the moisture content reaches be-<lb/>tween 10 and 12%. The evaluation of the effect of productive <lb/>tillers on seed yield and seed quality of sorghum was done in <lb/>the laboratory for only seeds harvested at maturity. Yields of <lb/>replicated treatments of physiologically mature were bulked <lb/>and thoroughly mixed to take sample of 0.9 kilogram sor-<lb/>ghum seeds tested for seed quality as prescribed by ISTA <lb/>rules. <lb/>2.4.2. Procedure <lb/>Parameters which are indicator for seed quality such as <lb/>analytical purity, thousand seed weight, standard germination, <lb/>vigour, vigour index I, vigour index II, germination rate index <lb/>and speed of germination test determination was tested in the <lb/>laboratory according to ISTA rules for all the treatments <lb/>harvested. Then obtained data were analyzed. <lb/>2.4.3. Data Collected on Field <lb/>Crop Growth Characters such as Plant height (cm), Days to <lb/>flowering, Yield and Yield Components, Panicle length (cm), <lb/>Weight of 1000-grains (g), Seed yield (t ha-1), Seed yield (t <lb/>ha-1) were collected. <lb/>2.4.4. Data Analysis <lb/>All data were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) <lb/>using the Generalized Linear Model (GLM) method of SAS <lb/>(SAS, 2002). Differences between treatment means were <lb/>separated using the Least Significant Difference (LSD) test at <lb/>5% level of significance. <lb/>3. Result and Discussion <lb/>3.1. Thousand Seed Weight (TSW) <lb/>TSW was significantly (P &lt; 0.0001) impacted by the major <lb/>influence of verities, sorghum plant heights and head count <lb/>were not. There was statistical parity across varieties based on <lb/>the quantity of heads and plants per net plot. There was a <lb/>noticeable greater TSW in comparison to the sorghum variety <lb/>of Assos-1 to Adukara sorghum variety (23.89 g). The varie-<lb/>ty&apos;s better yield was partly attributed to more TSW. This is a <lb/>consequence of the genetic variations in crop composition <lb/>across cultivars. The result is consistent with [2, 17], the <lb/>Dibaba variety performed better on average in thousand seed <lb/>weight (42g), which was directly correlated with yield and <lb/>also had a significant impact on germination and vigouresity. <lb/>Table 1. The main effect of varieties on thousand seed weight of <lb/>sorghum during the main cropping season of 2017-2019. <lb/>Variety <lb/>TSW <lb/>AD <lb/>23.8906 a <lb/>AS <lb/>20.0472 b <lb/>Lsd (0.05) <lb/>0.78 <lb/>CV <lb/>5.22 <lb/>P= <lb/>&lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Means followed by the same letter within a column are not signifi-<lb/>cantly different at 5% level of significance. LSD = Least significant <lb/>difference; CV = Coefficient of variation; AD= Adukara; AS = As-<lb/>sosa-1; P= probability; TSW= thousand seed weight <lb/>3.2. Numbers of Head and Plant Heights of <lb/>Sorghum <lb/>Analysis of variance showed that the main effects of main <lb/>shoots and tillers significantly (P ≤ 0.0001) and (P ≤ 0.0004) <lb/>affected the mean numbers of head and plant heights respec-<lb/>tively and TSW did not (Table 2). <lb/>The main shoot plants had the largest mean number of fertile <lb/>sorghum heads (86.5), with primary tillers coming in second <lb/>with 27.08 fertile plant heads. Secondary tillers exceeded both <lb/>primary tillers and the main sorghum plant to attain the greatest <lb/>plant height of 96.52 cm. The lowest mean number of plant <lb/>heads was reported by the secondary tiller. Since a moisture <lb/>shortage was caused by the rain ceasing before the late-emerging <lb/>tillers attained maturity, they produced unproductive tillers. <lb/>Fertility appears to have been significantly influenced by the <lb/>plants assimilate supply, and yield responses to density may be <lb/>connected with resource acquisition and interplant competition. <lb/>The finding is in line with the assimilate supply in the main shoot <lb/>at the time of tiller emergence appears the most likely determi-<lb/>nant of subsequent tiller fertility [2]. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>43 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 2. Main effect of Tiller number of heads and plant height of sorghum during the main cropping season of 2017-2019. <lb/>Tiller <lb/>Numbers of head <lb/>Plant height (cm) <lb/>0 <lb/>86.5 a <lb/>28.02 b <lb/>1 <lb/>27.083 b <lb/>14.72 b <lb/>2 <lb/>10.833 c <lb/>96.52 a <lb/>Lsd(0.05) <lb/>11.45 <lb/>34.14 <lb/>CV <lb/>22.90 <lb/>105.5 <lb/>P <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>≤ 0.0004 <lb/>Means followed by the same letter within a column are not significantly different at 5% level of significance. LSD = Least significant difference; <lb/>CV = Coefficient of variation; T= sorghum tiller; NH = number of head; PH= plant height; <lb/>3.3. Yield and Panicle Lengths of Sorghum <lb/>The average yield and panicle lengths of sorghum were <lb/>significantly (P &lt; 0.0001) impacted by the interaction effects <lb/>of varieties and number of tillers per plant (Table 3). <lb/>A higher average yield of 2685.5 kg was produced by the <lb/>sorghum variety Adukara. It increased 14% over Assosa-1. <lb/>This could be because the genetically promising sorghum <lb/>variety Adukara yields more than Assosa-1. The result is <lb/>consistent with [20]. <lb/>On the other hand the seed recorded from the main shoot <lb/>plant greater than the seed harvested from the primary shoot <lb/>tillers and secondary tillers. The shoot of main plant exceeded <lb/>by yield primary and secondary shoot tillers by 302.96% and <lb/>1333% respectively, while the primary tillers exceeded sec-<lb/>ondary by 255.8%. It showed that main plant shoot is high <lb/>yielder than primary and secondary tillers and primary tiller <lb/>also gave high yield than secondary tillers. <lb/>Table 3. Interaction effect of Varieties and Tiller on seed yield and <lb/>panicle length of sorghum during the main cropping season of <lb/>2017-2019. <lb/>Variety <lb/>Yield (kg) <lb/>Panicle Length (cm) <lb/>AD <lb/>2685.5 a <lb/>20.922 a <lb/>AS <lb/>2355.5 b <lb/>22.45 a <lb/>Tiller <lb/>0 <lb/>4240.7 a <lb/>28.658 a <lb/>1 <lb/>1052.4 b <lb/>12.978 c <lb/>2 <lb/>295.9 c <lb/>18.185 b <lb/>Lsd(0.05) <lb/>372.33 <lb/>3.36 <lb/>CV <lb/>16 <lb/>16.8 <lb/>P <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>Means followed by the same letter within a column are not significantly <lb/>different at 5% level of significance. LSD = Least significant difference; <lb/>CV = Coefficient of variation; AD= Adukara; AS = Assosa-1 <lb/>Despite producing a lesser yield than the parent plant, plant <lb/>tillers have the potential to increase the total yield per hectare in <lb/>the production of sorghum seeds. The report in line with that <lb/>Tillering is an important agronomic trait in many high-tillering <lb/>cereals such as wheat (Triticum aestivum), rice (Oryza sativa) <lb/>and barley (Hordeum vulgare), and contributed significantly to <lb/>improved yield associated with the &apos;green revolution [6]. <lb/>While statistically indicating parity, the panicle length of <lb/>the Assosa-1 sorghum variety measured at a higher 22.45 cm <lb/>than Adukara&apos;s 20.992 cm. The main plant shoot produced the <lb/>longest panicles, measuring 28.658 cm, while the secondary <lb/>tillers shoot ranked second. <lb/>Table 4. Interaction effect of varieties and tiller on speed of germi-<lb/>nation, standard germination and percentage of dead seed of sor-<lb/>ghum during the main cropping season of 2017-2019. <lb/>Variety <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Sp <lb/>SG (%) <lb/>DD (%) <lb/>AD <lb/>18.5275 a <lb/>81.25 a <lb/>16.25 d <lb/>AS <lb/>17.935 a <lb/>81 a <lb/>18.25 d <lb/>1AD <lb/>17.6125 a <lb/>76.5 a <lb/>22.25 b <lb/>1AS <lb/>15.695 b <lb/>70.875 c <lb/>26.5 b <lb/>2AD <lb/>17.3883 a <lb/>75.5 c <lb/>22 b <lb/>2AS <lb/>12.7533 c <lb/>64.667 d <lb/>32.417 a <lb/>Tiller <lb/>0 <lb/>17.8088 a <lb/>78.458 a <lb/>19.625 b <lb/>1 <lb/>14.755 b <lb/>67.5 b <lb/>30.125 a <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>44 <lb/></page>

    <body>Variety <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Sp <lb/>SG (%) <lb/>DD (%) <lb/>2 <lb/>13.815 c <lb/>68.375 b <lb/>28.5 a <lb/>Lsd <lb/>1.18 <lb/>5.27 <lb/>3.55 <lb/>CV <lb/>6.53 <lb/>6.41 <lb/>18.15 <lb/>P <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>≤ 0.001 <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>Means followed by the same letter within a column are not signifi-<lb/>cantly different at 5% level of significance. LSD = Least significant <lb/>difference; CV = Coefficient of variation; AD= Adukara; AS = As-<lb/>sosa-1; 1AD= primary tiller of Adukara; 2AD= secondary tiller of <lb/>Adukara; 1AS= primary tiller of Assosa-1; 2AS=secondary tiller of <lb/>Assosa-1; Sp= speed of germination; SG= standard germination; <lb/>DD= percentage of dead seed <lb/>3.4. Speed of Germination <lb/>The speed of germination as measured in the laboratory <lb/>was substantially (P ≤ 0.0001) impacted by varieties and the <lb/>number of tillers per plant, according to the analysis of vari-<lb/>ance (Table 4). <lb/>The seed from a plot that contained only the main shoot <lb/>plants of the Adukara variety had the highest (18.53 ) mean <lb/>number of speed of germination, while the seed from sec-<lb/>ondary shoot plant of Assosa-1 had the lowest (12.75) mean <lb/>number of speed of germination. <lb/>The speed of germination showed that seed plots of main <lb/>shoot plants with primary and secondary shoot tillers of <lb/>Adukara (2AD) and Adukara and Assosa-1 main shoot vari-<lb/>eties (AD and AS) showed statistical parity, as did the plot <lb/>area of main plants with each of these varieties. This means <lb/>that, compared to the Assosa-1 variety, Adukara sorghum <lb/>variety has an elevated genetic capacity for storing food to <lb/>sustain future seedling growth and development. <lb/>When compared to plots with one and two shoot tillers, the <lb/>speed at which seeds from the plot with the main plant shoot <lb/>germinated was often far faster and the main plant shoot <lb/>produced well-developed, robust seeds, whereas the other <lb/>plant was unable to do so due to competition for nutrients, <lb/>water and sunlight among the main plants and tillers. The <lb/>finding indicated that a prolonged mean germination time <lb/>may be an indication of deteriorated seed quality as a result of <lb/>exposure of the seeds to harsh or unfavourable conditions in <lb/>the field and after harvesting [4]. Such conditions slows the <lb/>rate of emergence and growth of the seedlings [2]. <lb/>The study found that seeds from a plot with only the main <lb/>shoot plants of the Adukara variety had the highest mean <lb/>number of germination speed (18.53), while seeds from a <lb/>secondary shoot plant of Assosa-1 had the lowest speed <lb/>(12.75). This indicates that the Adukara sorghum variety has <lb/>an elevated genetic capacity for storing food to sustain future <lb/>seedling growth and development. <lb/>The main plant shoot plots germinated seeds faster and <lb/>produced robust, well-developed seeds compared to plots <lb/>with one tiller and two shoot tillers, due to competition for <lb/>nutrients, water, and sunlight among the main plants and <lb/>tillers. <lb/>3.5. Standard Germination <lb/>Analysis of variance revealed that number normal seedling <lb/>significantly (P ≤ 0.001) affected by the interaction effects of <lb/>varieties and number of tillers per plants (Table 4). <lb/>The laboratory seed testing showed that the seed harvested <lb/>from the main plant was superior to the seed from primary and <lb/>secondary tillers interims of germination percentage. The <lb/>highest (81.25%) normal germination percentage recorded <lb/>from the seed harvested from the main shoot plant of Adukara <lb/>closely followed by Assoasa-1 sorghum varieties. The ger-<lb/>mination percentage of Adukara from primary shoot tiller <lb/>showed statically parity with the seed of main plant shoot of <lb/>Adukara and Assoasa-1varieties. The seed harvested from the <lb/>secondary tiller recorded the lowest (64.67%) germination <lb/>percentage. The seed harvested from the primary and sec-<lb/>ondary tillers showed statistically parity in germination per-<lb/>centage which is below the standard of Ethiopian seed <lb/>standards. This due to sufficient plant nutrient available for <lb/>seed plots of main plant for fully development of the seeds <lb/>while the others seed plots with primary and secondary tillers <lb/>were in competition for resources. It is reported that Seeds <lb/>produced under conditions of nutrient stress have their <lb/>chemical compounds such as carbohydrates and proteins <lb/>stored and not utilized in the provision of energy and bio-<lb/>chemical building blocks of the seed to enhance germination <lb/>[9]. High grain yield and high seed quality can be achieved by <lb/>the availability of phosphorus and nitrogen at the desired time <lb/>and in optimal amounts [7]. Seeds treated with fertilizer <lb/>contained larger food reserves, which enable them to nourish <lb/>the embryo longer during germination. <lb/>3.6. Dead Seeds <lb/>Analysis of variance reviled that percentage number of <lb/>dead seeds significantly (P ≤ 0.0001) influenced by varieties <lb/>and the number of tiller per plants (Table 4). <lb/>Between 16.25 and 32.42 percent of the seeds harvested <lb/>from main shoot and tiller under examination were dead seed. <lb/>The Assosa-1 sorghum variety&apos;s secondary tiller had the <lb/>greatest proportion of dead seeds (32.42) found. In contrast, <lb/>the main shoot of Adukara plants yielded the lowest propor-<lb/>tion (16.25%), closely followed by the primary shoot of As-<lb/>soasa-1 plants (18.25). Primary and secondary tillers had <lb/>higher percentages of dead seeds than the main sorghum plant, <lb/>53.5%, and 45.2%, respectively. The premature seed devel-<lb/>opment as a result of lack of nutrients owing to plant compe-<lb/>tition and late tiller emergence led to an increase in the <lb/>number of dead seeds from the primary and secondary tillers. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>45 <lb/></page>

    <body>The germination rate of seeds from the primary and secondary <lb/>tillers decreased as a result of the larger number of dead seeds. <lb/>Table 5. Main effect of verities effects on seedling shoots length and <lb/>vigor index of sorghum during the main cropping season of <lb/>2017-2019. <lb/>Variety <lb/>Parameter <lb/>SH (cm) <lb/>VI <lb/>VII <lb/>AD <lb/>17.265 a <lb/>2253.41 a <lb/>54.793 a <lb/>AS <lb/>16.86 a <lb/>2129.59 a <lb/>41.843 a <lb/>1AD <lb/>16.865 a <lb/>2081.22 b <lb/>51.694 a <lb/>1AS <lb/>16.0438 b <lb/>1834.42 a <lb/>45.136 a <lb/>2AD <lb/>16.7175 a <lb/>2013.15 b <lb/>46.769 a <lb/>2AS <lb/>16.0058 b <lb/>1701.28 c <lb/>32.62 b <lb/>Lsd(0.05) <lb/>0.75 <lb/>164.76 <lb/>13.68 <lb/>CV <lb/>4.035 <lb/>7.53 <lb/>27.17 <lb/>P <lb/>≤ 0.004 <lb/>≤ 0.0001 <lb/>≤ 0.02 <lb/>Means followed by the same letter within a column are not signifi-<lb/>cantly different at 5% level of significance. LSD = Least significant <lb/>difference; CV = Coefficient of variation; AD= Adukara; AS = <lb/>Assosa-1; 1AD= primary tiller of Adukara; 2AD= secondary tiller of <lb/>Adukara; 1AS= primary tiller of Assosa-1; 2AS=secondary tiller of <lb/>Assosa-1; SH = shoot length; VI= vigor index one; VII= vigor index <lb/>two <lb/>3.7. Seedling Shoot Length <lb/>The average mean value of seedling shoot length was sig-<lb/>nificantly (P ≤ 0.004) affected by the main effects of the <lb/>number of tillers of the verities (Table 5). <lb/>The seedling shoot length observed from the experiment re-<lb/>vealed that the highest 17.265 cm length of shoot recorded from <lb/>the seed harvested from the main plants of Adukara sorghum <lb/>variety followed by seeds from main plants of Assosa-1, primary <lb/>and secondary tiller of Adukara. While the primary and second-<lb/>ary tiller of Assosa-1 recorded the lower length of seedling <lb/>length. Quality seed produce vigor seedlings with <lb/>well-established seedling. Since the seeds from the main plants <lb/>fully matured than tillers they gave the longest seedling lengths. <lb/>The maximum 17.265 cm length of shoot recorded from the <lb/>seeds extracted from the main plants of the Adukara sorghum <lb/>variety was found in the experiment&apos;s seedling shoot obser-<lb/>vations. The seeds from the main plants of the Assosa-1, <lb/>primary and secondary tillers of Adukara, were next in line. <lb/>However, Assosa-1&apos;s primary and secondary tillers measured <lb/>the shorter seedling length. Vigorous seedlings with <lb/>well-established seedlings are produced by quality seeds. The <lb/>main plants&apos; seeds produced the longest seedling lengths be-<lb/>cause they were far better grown compared to the seeds of the <lb/>tillers. <lb/>3.8. Vigour Index One <lb/>The data in the bar chart illustrates how the number of <lb/>tillers of the sorghum cultivars Adukara and Assosa-1 affected <lb/>seedling vigour index one in the Benishangul Gumuz area <lb/>during the 2019 and 2020 crop seasons. <lb/>Figure 1. The number of tillers of the sorghum cultivars Adukara and Assosa-1 affected seedling vigour index one. <lb/>The primary and secondary tillers had a decline in overall <lb/>seedling vigour index one across the periods, whereas the <lb/>main sorghum plant varieties, Adukara and Assosa-1, exhib-<lb/>ited an upward trend. Vigour index one figures for the two <lb/>varieties of sorghum fluctuated significantly. At the conclu-<lb/>sion of the periods, secondary tillers outran the lowest, despite <lb/>the vigour index-one observing a lower rate in primary and <lb/>secondary tillers for the variety Assosa-1. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>46 <lb/></page>

    <body>In comparison to the main plants of the Assoa-1 variety, the <lb/>main plant of the Adukara sorghum variety had mean vigour <lb/>index one values of almost 2250, which was greater. None-<lb/>theless, the figure demonstrated that the Adukara prime tiller&apos;s <lb/>vigour index-one was somewhat higher than the mean values <lb/>of 2000 and steadily declined compared to the secondary <lb/>tillers, which produced mean values of about 2000. <lb/>Higher vigour index one is the outcome of seedlings with <lb/>greater biomass in their roots and shoots, which is encouraged <lb/>by superior seed quality. More leaves emerge from a shoot <lb/>that is developing quickly, and more leaves are crucial for the <lb/>interception of photosynthetic activity and well-established <lb/>agricultural field performance. According to [14], the finding <lb/>consistent with a high shoot biomass is a sign of higher seed <lb/>vigour and following crop development cycles. [5] claim that <lb/>high-quality seeds promote the growth of seedlings with <lb/>larger biomass roots, which is a sign of their capacity to en-<lb/>dure stress, as well as make it easier for the next generation to <lb/>produce high-quality grains. <lb/>While the primary tiller&apos;s mean vigour index one value was <lb/>marginally below the 2000 mean, the main plant&apos;s vigour <lb/>index one of the Assosa-1 sorghum variety was marginally <lb/>higher than 2000. The same variety&apos;s secondary tillers re-<lb/>ported mean VI values of around 1600, which touched lower <lb/>traces. <lb/>3.9. Vigour Index Two <lb/>The analysis of variance revealed that the number of tillers <lb/>in the verities had a significant (P≤0.05) impact on the seed-<lb/>ling vigor index (VI and VII) (Table 5). <lb/>While Adukara gave the highest 2253.41 following by <lb/>Assosa-1 2129.59 mean value of vigor one. The lowest was <lb/>recorded by seed harvested from secondary tillers of Assosa <lb/>-1. <lb/>On the other hand the seed harvested from Adukara sor-<lb/>ghum varieties gave the highest 54.793. Seedling vigor two <lb/>and the lowest 32.62 value were observed from seed harvested <lb/>from secondary tiller of Assosa-1 variety. Except the lowest <lb/>value of recorded in the experiments all the mean values of <lb/>Vigor index two recorded were statistically parity. <lb/>The highest seedling vigor index two was the results of <lb/>genetic variation among the varieties and fully maturity of the <lb/>seed on the fields. Seed vigor and yield are ultimately influ-<lb/>enced by seed quality, which is heavily influenced by the <lb/>environment during embryogenesis and seed maturity. The <lb/>number of tiller per plants cause competition for plant nutrient <lb/>also affected the seedling vigor. The study in line with the <lb/>finding of stated that Seed vigour is usually influenced by <lb/>genetic constitution during seed development and Seed vigor <lb/>is usually influenced by environmental factors during seed <lb/>development. These environmental factors include soil <lb/>moisture, soil fertility and post maturation/ pre-harvest envi-<lb/>ronment [8]. <lb/>4. Summary and Conclusion <lb/>The study analyzed the seed quality and yield of sorghum <lb/>seeds in Ethiopia, focusing on the main shoot plants and <lb/>tillers. The Adukara sorghum variety showed higher yields <lb/>than the Assosa-1 variety due to its genetic potential. The <lb/>main shoot plant yielded more seeds than primary and sec-<lb/>ondary tillers, with the shoot exceeding these yields by <lb/>302.96% and 1333%, respectively. Primary tillers also <lb/>yielded more seeds than secondary tillers by 255.8%. Seeds <lb/>from the plot with the main plant shoot germinated faster and <lb/>produced robust seeds, while other plants struggled due to <lb/>competition for nutrients, water, and sunlight. Laboratory <lb/>seed testing revealed that seeds from the main plant were <lb/>more successful in germination percentage than those from <lb/>primary and secondary tillers. Primary and secondary tillers <lb/>recorded germination percentages below blew recom-<lb/>mended seed standards. Quality seeds produce vigor seed-<lb/>lings with well-established seedlings, as the seeds from the <lb/>main plants fully matured than the seeds of the tillers. The <lb/>main plants&apos; seeds produced the longest seedling lengths <lb/>because they were far better grown compared to the seeds of <lb/>the tillers. The study also found that seed vigor two and yield <lb/>are influenced by genetic variation among varieties and seed <lb/>maturity on the fields. <lb/>In conclusion, the poor quality of the seed obtained from <lb/>sorghum tiller affects the planting values. In order to prevent <lb/>competition for nutrients among seedlings for seed production <lb/>and to ensure seed quality, the tillers should be regularly <lb/>removed. Conversely, secondary tillers have the potential to <lb/>boost overall yield production but only if sorghum is grown <lb/>for grain production. To reach a definitive conclusion, a <lb/>comparable research comprising the cost of production for <lb/>grain and seed production using various planting spaces <lb/>should be conducted again at different locations. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>AD: Adukara <lb/>ANOVA: Analysis of Variance <lb/>AS: Assosa-1 <lb/>CRD: A completely Randomized Design <lb/>GLM: Generalized Linear Model <lb/>LSD: Least Significant Difference <lb/>RCBD: Randomized compLete Block Design <lb/>SAS: Statistical Analysis System <lb/>TSW: Thousand Seed Weight <lb/>VI: Vigour Index One <lb/>VII: Vigour Index Two <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>I would like to thank to EIAR-TMSR directorate for <lb/>funding the program and experimental research for the ac-<lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">American Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering <lb/>http://www.sciencepg.com/journal/bio <lb/></note>

    <page>47 <lb/></page>

    <div type="acknowledgement">complishment of my work. I would like to extend thank the <lb/>technical staff members of Assosa Seed Laboratory for their <lb/>assistance in conducting the experiments in the laboratory. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Fekede Tena Ayana: Conceptualization, Software, For-<lb/>mal Analysis, Methodology, Writing -original draft, Writing <lb/>-review &amp; editing <lb/>Mosisa Tolosa: Conceptualization, edition <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>Reference <lb/>[1] Allen R. R. and J. T. Musick. (1993) Planting date, water <lb/>management, and maturity length relations for irrigated grain <lb/>sorghum. Soil and Water Division ASAE 36(4): 1123-1129. <lb/>[2] Alimentaires, P. C., A. Production, and F. Sciences. 2002. <lb/>Tillering in Grain Sorghum over a Wide Range of Population <lb/>Densities : Identi ® cation of a Common Hierarchy for Tiller <lb/>Emergence, Leaf Area Development and Fertility. <lb/>[3] Assefa Y., S. A. Staggenborg, and V. P. V. Prasad. (2010) Grain <lb/>sorghum water requirement and responses to drought stress: A <lb/>review. Crop Management <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1094/CM-2010-1109-01-RV <lb/>[4] Bewley, J. D., &amp; Black, M. (2012). Physiology and biochem-<lb/>istry of seeds in relation to germination: volume 2: viability, <lb/>dormancy, and environmental control. Springer Science and <lb/>Business Media. <lb/>[5] Blaha, L., &amp; Pazderu, K. (2013). Influence of the root and seed <lb/>traits on tolerance to abiotic stress. In Agricultural Chemistry. <lb/>IntechOpen. https://doi.org/10.5772/55656 <lb/>[6] Conway G, Toenniessen G. 1999. Feeding the world in the <lb/>twenty-first century. Nature 402: C55-C58. <lb/>[7] Столяр, С. Г., and М. М. Ключевич. 2021. Домінуючі мікози <lb/>Sorghum bicolor в Поліссі України 13: 236-240. <lb/>[8] Gusta, L. V., E. N. Johnson, N. T. Nesbitt, and K. J. Kirkland. <lb/>2004. Effect of seeding date on canola seed quality and seed <lb/>vigour. Can. J. Plant Sci. 84: 463-471. <lb/>[9] Hoover, E. E. 2011. Environmental Factors Affecting Seed <lb/>Germination. Plant Propag. Concepts Lab. Exerc.: 407-409. <lb/>[10] HUANG RD (2018) Research progress on plant tolerance to <lb/>soil salinity and alkalinity in sorghum. J Integr Agric 17: <lb/>739-746. Link: https://bit.ly/3FIELui <lb/>[11] Kim, H. K., E. Van Oosterom, M. Dingkuhn, D. Luquet, and G. <lb/>Hammer. 2010b. Regulation of tillering in sorghum : envi-<lb/>ronmental effects: 57-67. <lb/>[12] Lafarge TA, Hammer GL. 2002a. Predicting plant leaf area <lb/>production: shoot assimilate accumulation and partitioning, <lb/>and leaf area ratio, are stable for a wide range of sorghum <lb/>population densities. Field Crops Research 77: 137-151. <lb/>[13] Lafarge TA, Hammer GL. 2002b. Tillering in grain sorghum <lb/>over a wide range of population densities: modelling dynamics <lb/>of tiller fertility. Annals of Botany 90: 99-110. <lb/>[14] Maucieri, C., Cavallaro, V., Caruso, C., Borin, M., Milani, M., <lb/>&amp; Barbera, A. (2016). Sorghum biomass production for energy <lb/>purpose using treated urban wastewater and different fertiliza-<lb/>tion in a Mediterranean environment. Agriculture, 6(4), 67. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture6040067 <lb/>[15] Mindaye TT, Mace ES, Godwin ID, Jordan DR (2016) Heter-<lb/>osis in locally adapted sorghum genotypes and potential of <lb/>hybrids for increased productivity in contrasting environments <lb/>in Ethiopia. Crop J 4: 479-489. Link: https://bit.ly/3IctvYS <lb/>[16] Stahlman P. W. and G. A. Wicks. (2000) Chapter 3.5: Weeds <lb/>and their control in grain sorghum in Sorghum: Origin, History, <lb/>Technology, and Production. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. <lb/>[17] Temesgen Begna, Hailu Gichile (2022). &quot;Performance Evalu-<lb/>ation and Participatory Variety Selection of Improved High-<lb/>land Sorghum Varieties at West Hararghe Zone&quot; International <lb/>Journal of Research Studies in Agricultural Sciences (IJRSAS), <lb/>8(9), pp. 9-18 http://dx.doi.org/10.20431/2454-6224.0809002 <lb/>[18] Vanderlip R. L. (1993) How a sorghum plant develops. Con-<lb/>tribution No. 1203, pg. 1-19, Kansas State University. <lb/>[19] WA_ Greg Sanders, Moses Lake 2024. USDA Market News <lb/>GR165. (n.d.). 509-393-1343: <lb/>http://www.ams.usda.gov/market-news/livestock-poultry-grai <lb/>n <lb/>[20] Werkissa, Y., and B. Temesgen. 2022. Sorghum breeding in <lb/>Ethiopia: Progress, achievements and challenges. Int. J. Agric. <lb/>Sci. Food Technol. 8: 045-051. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>