<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Reduced Alcohol Consumption and Major Adverse Cardiovascular Events Among Individuals With Previously High Alcohol Consumption</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Dong Oh</forename>
          <surname>Kang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Dae-In</forename>
          <surname>Lee</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Seung-Young</forename>
          <surname>Roh</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jin Oh</forename>
          <surname>Na</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Cheol Ung</forename>
          <surname>Choi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jin Won</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eung Ju</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Seung-Woon</forename>
          <surname>Rha</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Chang Gyu</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ye-Seul</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yonghwan</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hyo-Sun</forename>
          <surname>You</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hee-Taik</forename>
          <surname>Kang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eunseo</forename>
          <surname>Jo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jinseob</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jae-woo</forename>
          <surname>Lee</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jin-Man</forename>
          <surname>Jung</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:00:33.338Z">11/12/2025 10:00:33 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1001$1$jamanetworkopen.2024.4013</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.4013</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Dong Oh Kang, Dae-In Lee, Seung-Young Roh, Jin Oh Na, Cheol Ung Choi, Jin Won Kim, Eung Ju Kim, Seung-Woon Rha, Chang Gyu Park, Ye-Seul Kim, Yonghwan Kim, Hyo-Sun You, Hee-Taik Kang, Eunseo Jo, Jinseob Kim, Jae-woo Lee, Jin-Man Jung. (2024). Reduced Alcohol Consumption and Major Adverse Cardiovascular Events Among Individuals With Previously High Alcohol Consumption. JAMA Network Open, 7(3), e244013. DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.4013</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T09:24:47.014252Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T09:24:47.014252Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Original Investigation | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Engagement Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/>Treated in Primary Care <lb/>Rasha Khatib, PhD, MHS; Nicole Glowacki, MPH; Eva Chang, PhD, MPH; Julie Lauffenburger, PhD, PharmD; Mark J. Pletcher, MD, MPH; Alvia Siddiqi, MD <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IMPORTANCE Patient portals are increasingly used for patient-clinician communication and to <lb/>introduce interventions aimed at improving blood pressure control. <lb/>OBJECTIVE To characterize patient portal use among patients with hypertension managed in <lb/>primary care. <lb/>DESIGN, SETTINGS, AND PARTICIPANTS This retrospective cohort study used electronic health <lb/>records linked with patient portal log file data from a large, diverse Midwestern health care system. <lb/>Patients with hypertension who had a primary care visit from January 1, 2021, to December 31, 2021, <lb/>were included. The first visit in 2021 was considered the baseline visit; patient portal engagement <lb/>was evaluated during the following year. Multivariate logistic regressions, presented as odds ratios <lb/>(ORs) and 95% CIs, were used to evaluate associations between patient characteristics and patient <lb/>portal engagement, adjusting for potential confounders. <lb/>EXPOSURES Primary exposures included 4 sociodemographic factors routinely collected in the <lb/>electronic health record: race and ethnicity, insurance, preferred language, and smoking status. <lb/>MAIN OUTCOMES AND MEASURES Indicators of patient engagement with the patient portal <lb/>included accessing the patient portal at least once, accessing the portal within 7 days of at least <lb/>50.0% of primary care physician (PCP) visits, frequent logins (&lt;28 vs Ն28), messaging (&lt;2 vs Ն2), <lb/>and sharing home blood pressure readings. <lb/>RESULTS Among 366 871 patients (mean [SD], 63.5 [12.6] years), 52.8% were female, 3.4% were <lb/>Asian, 7.8% were Hispanic, 19.7% were non-Hispanic Black, 66.9% were non-Hispanic White, and <lb/>2.3% were of other race or ethnicity. During the 1-year study period starting in 2021, 70.5% accessed <lb/>the patient portal at least once, 60.2% accessed around the time of their PCP visits, 35.7% accessed <lb/>the portal frequently, 28.9% engaged in messaging, and 8.7% shared home blood pressure readings. <lb/>Compared with White patients, non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic patients had lower odds of any <lb/>access (Black: OR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.52-0.54; Hispanic: OR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.64-0.68), access around <lb/>PCP visit time (Black: OR, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.48-0.50; Hispanic: OR, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.60-0.64), <lb/>frequent access (Black: OR, 0.56; 95% CI, 0.55-0.57; Hispanic: OR, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.69-0.73), and <lb/>messaging (Black: OR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.61-0.64); Hispanic: OR, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.69-0.73). <lb/>CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE This cohort study of patients with hypertension found clear <lb/>sociodemographic disparities in patient portal engagement among those treated in primary care. <lb/>Without special efforts to engage patients with portals, interventions that use patient portals to <lb/>target hypertension may exacerbate disparities. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 <lb/>Key Points <lb/>Question Are there disparities in <lb/>engagement with patient portals among <lb/>patients treated for hypertension in <lb/>primary care? <lb/>Findings This cohort study of 366 871 <lb/>patients found that patients with <lb/>hypertension who are Black or Hispanic, <lb/>who are uninsured, whose preferred <lb/>language is not English, and who smoke <lb/>are less likely to engage with <lb/>patient portals. <lb/>Meaning These findings suggest that as <lb/>health care systems use patient portals <lb/>more frequently for hypertension-<lb/>related interventions and programs, <lb/>disadvantaged patient groups are being <lb/>left behind, potentially exacerbating <lb/>existing disparities in blood <lb/>pressure control. <lb/>+ Supplemental content <lb/>Author affiliations and article information are <lb/>listed at the end of this article. <lb/>Open Access. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/>1/13 <lb/>Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Hypertension is a major public health problem affecting close to half of the US population. 1 <lb/>Hypertension management requires regular follow-up appointments with the clinical care team to <lb/>adjust medications until blood pressure is controlled and to monitor progress once control is <lb/>reached. 2 Ongoing communication outside clinic visits between patients and the care team is also <lb/>essential to hypertension management, and electronic health record (EHR) patient portals hold great <lb/>promise in facilitating these communications. 3-5 <lb/>Health care systems and care teams are increasingly relying on patient portals to deliver <lb/>interventions. 6 Patients with hypertension can use the patient portal to communicate with the care <lb/>team about medication titration questions, review their after-visit summary, view their laboratory <lb/>results, and more. These activities have been linked to more engaged patients and better <lb/>management of their disease. 7-9 Patient portals are used as a platform by the care team to provide <lb/>evidence-based educational material to the patient. 9 Patient portals can be used to collect patient-<lb/>reported data, such as home blood pressure readings, to enhance disease management, which has <lb/>been linked to improved blood pressure control and has been recommended in clinical practice <lb/>guidelines. 10,11 More recently, patient portals have been used to invite patients to participate in <lb/>clinical trials, giving these patients the potential advantage of better care that is associated with <lb/>clinical trial participation. 12 <lb/>Disadvantaged patient populations, including patients in racial and ethnic minority groups, <lb/>patients who lack insurance, and patients whose preferred language is not English, are less likely to <lb/>have their blood pressure under control. 13-16 It is unclear how engaged disadvantaged patients are <lb/>with the patient portal. Given the importance of ongoing asynchronous communications for patients <lb/>with hypertension, it is crucial to characterize patient portal use to understand its adoption and reach <lb/>as a platform for hypertension management. It is also important to monitor and evaluate the <lb/>potential digital divide among disadvantaged patient populations who share the greatest burden of <lb/>hypertension and its clinical consequences. 14 With data from a large and diverse Midwestern health <lb/>care system, we aim to characterize patient portal access, using multiple definitions, and the use of <lb/>hypertension-specific functionalities, including messaging the care team and sharing home blood <lb/>pressure readings. <lb/>Methods <lb/>This retrospective cohort study followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies <lb/>in Epidemiology (STROBE) reporting guideline for cohort studies. 17 The study was approved by the <lb/>Advocate Aurora Health Institutional Review Board, which waived informed consent for this <lb/>retrospective, deidentified data set because of minimal risk to patients. <lb/>Study Setting, Data Sources, and Population <lb/>We used data from Advocate Health-Midwest, a large and diverse health care system serving <lb/>Wisconsin&apos;s urban and rural populations and Illinois&apos; metropolitan population. The patient portal was <lb/>introduced to the system in 2012. All patients are automatically offered an activation code at no cost. <lb/>The messaging function between patients and clinicians has been available in the patient portal since <lb/>it was first introduced, and both patients and clinicians can initiate messages. The home blood <lb/>pressure monitoring functionality was introduced in 2018. The care team must create and share a <lb/>home blood pressure monitoring order with the patient before the patient can use the functionality <lb/>to manually enter readings. <lb/>The analytic cohort included adult (aged Ն18 years) patients who have a documented <lb/>hypertension diagnosis (using the International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related <lb/>Health Problems, Tenth Revision [ICD-10] code I10) and at least 1 visit in 2021 to 1 of 312 primary care <lb/>sites (family medicine, internal medicine, or geriatrics) and at least 1 additional primary care visit <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>before 2021. Sociodemographic and clinical data were extracted from the EHR at the baseline visit, <lb/>defined as the first visit in 2021. Each patient was followed up for 1 year to evaluate patient portal <lb/>activity. <lb/>Main Independent Variables <lb/>Independent variables included patient sociodemographic and clinical characteristics. Race and <lb/>ethnicity (self-reported in the EHR as 2 separate fields) were recategorized into 5 mutually exclusive <lb/>race and ethnicity groups, including Asian, Hispanic or Latino, non-Hispanic Black (Black or African <lb/>American = yes, Hispanic or Latino = no or unknown), non-Hispanic White (White = yes, Hispanic or <lb/>Latino = no), and other (American Indian or Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, <lb/>or unknown). Patients who self-reported being Hispanic or Latino were categorized as such <lb/>regardless of their race. Only 9042 patients (2.5%) had unknown race, and 7880 patients (2.2%) had <lb/>unknown ethnicity, resulting in 5028 patients (1.4%) missing data for the combined race and <lb/>ethnicity variable. Preferred language was categorized as English or non-English. Insurance status <lb/>was categorized as commercial, Medicare, Medicaid, or self-pay. Tobacco use, which is a health <lb/>behavior associated with disadvantaged patients and patients with social needs, 18 was defined as <lb/>current vs never or former. <lb/>Clinical characteristics included depression and diabetes identified using ICD-10 codes. <lb/>Uncontrolled baseline blood pressure was defined as a systolic blood pressure of 140 mm Hg or <lb/>higher or a diastolic blood pressure of 90 mm Hg or higher at the baseline visit. Blood pressure-<lb/>lowering medications were grouped by class and categorized into at least 2 medications currently on <lb/>the active medication list vs fewer than 2 medications. 2 The number of primary care physician (PCP) <lb/>visits was defined as clinical encounters at internal medicine, family practice, or geriatrics <lb/>departments and was categorized as 1 to 2 visits vs 3 or more, per clinical practice guideline <lb/>recommendations. 19 <lb/>Outcomes <lb/>Five indicators for patient portal engagement were created. Access was defined by the patient <lb/>having logged into their patient portal account at least once during the 1-year follow-up. Frequency <lb/>of access was also presented as medians (IQRs). The number of patient logins was winsorized at the <lb/>95th percentile. 20,21 Accessed around PCP visit times was defined as logging in up to 7 days before <lb/>or after at least 50.0% of the patient&apos;s PCP encounters during the 1-year study period. Frequent <lb/>access was defined as having at least 28 logins during the 1-year study period. This cutoff was <lb/>selected based on the median number of logins among patients who accessed the portal at least <lb/>once. Messaging was defined as sending more than 1 free-text secure message to the care team <lb/>during the 1-year study period via the patient portal messaging functionality. This function has been <lb/>reported in the literature as a proxy for more active patient engagement given the required <lb/>involvement in sending messages. 22,23 Sharing home blood pressure readings was evaluated among <lb/>the subgroup of patients who received an self-measured blood pressure order from their care team <lb/>and was defined as sharing at least 1 reading. This functionality allows the care team to create an <lb/>order for the patient to manually enter discrete systolic and diastolic readings from their home to be <lb/>shared with the care team. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>Descriptive statistics are reported as numbers (percentages) for categorical or ordinal variables and <lb/>means (SDs) or medians (IQRs) for continuous variables. Five multivariable logistic regression models <lb/>were created to evaluate associations between patient characteristics and each of the 5 patient <lb/>portal engagement indicators. All models included the same independent variables (age, sex, race <lb/>and ethnicity, insurance, primary language, diabetes, tobacco use, depression, uncontrolled baseline <lb/>blood pressure, blood pressure-lowering medications, and number of PCP visits) and presented as <lb/>adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and 95% CIs. The analysis used ORs instead of relative risks even though <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>the outcomes are not expected to be rare; ORs may slightly overestimate relative risks but are <lb/>commonly reported in the literature, and logistic regression models may be more familiar to <lb/>readers. 24 Given the low proportions of missing data from the EHRs used in this study, no imputation <lb/>of missing data was performed. Instead, patients missing any of the baseline visit variables included <lb/>in the regression models were excluded from the cohort (93 patients [&lt;0.1%]). A 2-tailed P &lt; .05 was <lb/>considered statistically significant. Analyses were completed using SAS software, version 9.4 (SAS <lb/>Institute Inc). <lb/>Results <lb/>Description of Study Population <lb/>A total of 366 871 patients (mean [SD], 63.5 [12.6] years) with hypertension were included in the <lb/>analysis (eAppendix in Supplement 1). Of these patients, 52.8% were female and 47.2% were male, <lb/>3.4% were Asian, 7.8% were Hispanic, 19.7% were non-Hispanic Black, 66.9% were non-Hispanic <lb/>White, and 2.3% were of other races and ethnicities. Blood pressure during the baseline visit was <lb/>controlled among 83.3% of patients, 28.1% were prescribed at least 1 blood pressure-lowering <lb/>medication, and 59.1% had 3 or more PCP visits during the 1-year study period (Table 1). <lb/>Overall Engagement With the Patient Portal <lb/>The median (IQR) number of patient portal logins was 28.0 (10.0-65.0) among active users. On <lb/>average, patients logged in a mean (SD) of 46.7 (49.8) times during the year. Figure 1 presents the <lb/>proportion of patient portal engagement by patient sociodemographic characteristics among all <lb/>patients. During the 1-year study, 70.5% of patients accessed the patient portal at least once, 60.2% <lb/>accessed it around PCP visit time, 35.7% accessed frequently, and 28.9% engaged in messaging. <lb/>Only 553 patients (&lt;1.0%) received an order for home blood pressure monitoring; among them, 48 <lb/>(8.7%) engaged in sharing at least 1 reading with the care team (Figure 2). <lb/>Associations With Sociodemographic Characteristics <lb/>Adjusted analyses indicate clear differences in the sociodemographic characteristics of patients with <lb/>hypertension who engaged with the patient portal (Table 2). Compared with White patients, <lb/>non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic patients had lower odds of any access (non-Hispanic Black: OR, <lb/>0.53; 95% CI, 0.52-0.54; Hispanic: OR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.64-0.68), access around PCP visit time (non-<lb/>Hispanic Black: OR, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.48-0.50; Hispanic: OR, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.60-0.64), frequent <lb/>access (non-Hispanic Black: OR, 0.56; 95% CI, 0.55-0.57; Hispanic: OR, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.69-0.73), and <lb/>messaging (non-Hispanic Black: OR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.61-0.64; Hispanic: OR, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.69-0.73). <lb/>All 4593 patients in the self-pay insurance category accessed the patient portal at least once but had <lb/>lower odds of access around PCP visit time (OR, 0.44; 95% CI, 0.42-0.47), frequent access (OR, <lb/>0.50; 95% CI, 0.46-0.53), and messaging (OR, 0.57; 95% CI, 0.53-0.61), compared with patients <lb/>with commercial insurance. Similar trends with lower odds of engagement were observed among <lb/>Medicare and Medicaid patients compared with commercially insured patients. Patients whose <lb/>primary language is not English had lower odds of any access (OR, 0.40; 95% CI, 0.38-0.41), access <lb/>around PCP visit time (OR, 0.35; 95% CI, 0.33-0.36), frequent access (OR, 0.37; 95% CI, 0.35-0.39), <lb/>and messaging (OR, 0.40; 95% CI, 0.38-0.42) compared with patients whose preferred language is <lb/>English. Tobacco users also had lower odds of access (OR, 0.50; 95% CI, 0.49-0.51), access around <lb/>PCP visit time (OR, 0.50; 95% CI, 0.49-0.51), frequent access (OR, 0.58; 95% CI, 0.56-0.59), and <lb/>messaging (OR, 0.55; 95% CI, 0.54-0.57) compared with non-tobacco users (Table 2). Associations <lb/>between patient sociodemographic characteristics and receiving an order for and engaging with <lb/>home blood pressure monitoring showed similar trends with differences in terms of age, race and <lb/>ethnicity, insurance, preferred language, and tobacco use, although not all these associations were <lb/>statistically significant (Table 3). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Associations With Clinical Characteristics <lb/>In the adjusted analysis, the number of PCP visits that the patient attended during the 1-year <lb/>follow-up showed associations across all measures of engagement, with greater odds among <lb/>patients who had 3 or more visits for any access (OR, 1.59; 95% CI, 1.56-1.61), access around PCP visit <lb/>time (OR, 1.63; 95% CI, 1.61-1.66), frequent access (OR, 2.48; 95% CI, 2.45-2.52), and messaging (OR, <lb/>1.82; 95% CI, 1.80-1.85) compared with patients who had only 1 or 2 visits. Home blood pressure <lb/>monitoring showed similar trends but was not statistically significant. In terms of comorbidities, <lb/>patients with diabetes and depression were less likely to access patient portals in general (diabetes: <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of Patients With Hypertension Managed in Primary Care <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>No. (%) of patients <lb/>All patients <lb/>Did not access <lb/>patient portals <lb/>Accessed <lb/>patient portals <lb/>Total patients <lb/>366 871 (100.0) <lb/>108 332 (29.5) <lb/>258 539 (70.5) <lb/>Age group, y <lb/>18-44 <lb/>33 259 (9.1) <lb/>4876 (4.5) <lb/>28 383 (11.0) <lb/>45-64 <lb/>139 166 (37.9) <lb/>34 001 (31.4) <lb/>105 165 (40.7) <lb/>65-74 <lb/>122 811 (33.5) <lb/>37 967 (35.1) <lb/>84 844 (32.8) <lb/>≥75 <lb/>71 635 (19.5) <lb/>31 488 (29.1) <lb/>40 147 (15.5) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>173 191 (47.2) <lb/>54 269 (50.1) <lb/>118 922 (46.0) <lb/>Female <lb/>193 680 (52.8) <lb/>54 063 (49.9) <lb/>139 617 (54.0) <lb/>Race and ethnicity <lb/>Asian <lb/>12 412 (3.4) <lb/>3407 (3.1) <lb/>9005 (3.5) <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>28 697 (7.8) <lb/>10 594 (9.8) <lb/>18 103 (7.0) <lb/>Non-Hispanic Black <lb/>72 119 (19.7) <lb/>26 431 (24.4) <lb/>45 688 (17.7) <lb/>Non-Hispanic White <lb/>245 306 (66.9) <lb/>65 106 (60.1) <lb/>180 200 (69.7) <lb/>Other a <lb/>8337 (2.3) <lb/>2794 (2.6) <lb/>5543 (2.1) <lb/>Insurance <lb/>Commercial <lb/>153 500 (41.8) <lb/>31 093 (28.7) <lb/>122 407 (47.4) <lb/>Medicare <lb/>183 345 (50.0) <lb/>68 244 (63.0) <lb/>115 101 (44.5) <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>25 433 (6.9) <lb/>8995 (8.3) <lb/>16 438 (6.4) <lb/>Self-pay <lb/>4593 (1.3) <lb/>0 <lb/>4593 (1.8) <lb/>Preferred language <lb/>English <lb/>351 303 (95.8) <lb/>100 341 (92.6) <lb/>250 962 (97.1) <lb/>Non-English <lb/>15 568 (4.2) <lb/>7991 (7.4) <lb/>7577 (2.9) <lb/>Tobacco use <lb/>No <lb/>322 205 (87.8) <lb/>90 350 (83.4) <lb/>231 855 (89.7) <lb/>Yes <lb/>44 666 (12.2) <lb/>7982 (16.6) <lb/>26 684 (10.3) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>No <lb/>247 850 (67.6) <lb/>69 080 (63.8) <lb/>178 770 (69.2) <lb/>Yes <lb/>119 021 (32.4) <lb/>39 252 (36.2) <lb/>79 769 (30.9) <lb/>Depression <lb/>No <lb/>302 699 (82.5) <lb/>89 440 (82.6) <lb/>213 259 (82.5) <lb/>Yes <lb/>64 172 (17.5) <lb/>18 892 (17.4) <lb/>45 280 (17.5) <lb/>Prescribed ≥2 BP medications <lb/>No <lb/>263 920 (71.9) <lb/>75 230 (69.4) <lb/>188 690 (73.0) <lb/>Yes <lb/>102 951 (28.1) <lb/>33 102 (30.6) <lb/>69 849 (27.0) <lb/>Uncontrolled baseline BP <lb/>No <lb/>305 650 (83.3) <lb/>88 859 (82.0) <lb/>216 791 (83.9) <lb/>Yes <lb/>61 221 (16.7) <lb/>19 473 (18.0) <lb/>41 748 (16.2) <lb/>No. of PCP visits <lb/>1-2 <lb/>150 126 (40.9) <lb/>49 531 (45.7) <lb/>100 595 (38.9) <lb/>≥3 <lb/>216 745 (59.1) <lb/>58 801 (54.3) <lb/>157 944 (61.1) <lb/>Abbreviations: BP, blood pressure; PCP, primary care <lb/>physician. <lb/>a Other includes American Indian or Alaska Native, <lb/>Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, <lb/>and unknown. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>OR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.89-0.92; depression: OR, 0.96; 95% CI, 0.94-0.98) and around PCP visit time <lb/>(diabetes: OR, 0.92; 95% CI, 0.91-0.94; depression: OR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.90-0.93). However, the <lb/>odds of engaging with messages (diabetes: OR, 1.07; 95% CI, 1.06-1.10; depression: OR, 1.15; 95% CI, <lb/>Figure 1. Patient Portal Engagement by Characteristics of the 366 871 Study Patients <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Patients with hypertension, % <lb/>Type of engagement <lb/>Race and ethnicity <lb/>A <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Patients with hypertension, % <lb/>Preferred language <lb/>C <lb/>Any access <lb/>Accessed around visit <lb/>time (within 7 d of <lb/>≥50% of PCP visits) <lb/>Frequent access <lb/>(≥28 logins) <lb/>Messaging <lb/>(≥2 free-text <lb/>messages) <lb/>Type of engagement <lb/>Any access <lb/>Accessed around visit <lb/>time (within 7 d of <lb/>≥50% of PCP visits) <lb/>Frequent access <lb/>(≥28 logins) <lb/>Messaging <lb/>(≥2 free-text <lb/>messages) <lb/>Asian <lb/>Hispanic or Latino <lb/>Non-Hispanic Black <lb/>Non-Hispanic White <lb/>Other <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Patients with hypertension, % <lb/>Type of engagement <lb/>Insurance <lb/>B <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Patients with hypertension, % <lb/>Tobacco use <lb/>D <lb/>Smoker <lb/>Nonsmoker <lb/>Spanish <lb/>English <lb/>Any access <lb/>Accessed around visit <lb/>time (within 7 d of <lb/>≥50% of PCP visits) <lb/>Frequent access <lb/>(≥28 logins) <lb/>Messaging <lb/>(≥2 free-text <lb/>messages) <lb/>Type of engagement <lb/>Any access <lb/>Accessed around visit <lb/>time (within 7 d of <lb/>≥50% of PCP visits) <lb/>Frequent access <lb/>(≥28 logins) <lb/>Messaging <lb/>(≥2 free-text <lb/>messages) <lb/>Commercial <lb/>Medicare <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>Self-pay <lb/>PCP indicates primary care physician. <lb/>Figure 2. Proportion of Patients Who Engaged With the Patient Portal <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Patients with hypertension, % <lb/>Type of engagement <lb/>Any access <lb/>Accessed around visit <lb/>time (within 7 d of <lb/>≥50% of PCP visits) <lb/>Frequent access <lb/>(≥28 logins) <lb/>Messaging <lb/>(≥2 free-text <lb/>messages) <lb/>Home blood <lb/>pressure readings <lb/>(shared ≥1 reading) a <lb/>Among all patients (n = 366 871) <lb/>Among patients who accessed at least once (n = 258 539) <lb/>PCP indicates primary care physician. <lb/>a Limited to 553 patients who received an order from <lb/>their care team to share home blood pressure (BP) <lb/>readings via the patient portal. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2. Associations Between Patient Characteristics and Patient Engagement With the Patient Portal Among 366 871 Patients With Hypertension a <lb/>Independent variable <lb/>Any access (n = 258 539) <lb/>Accessed within 7 d of PCP visit <lb/>(n = 206 947) <lb/>Frequent access (n = 131 034) <lb/>Messaging (n = 106 034) <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>Age group, y <lb/>18-44 <lb/>28 383 (85.3) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>24 024 (75.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>15 912 (47.8) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>13 743 (41.3) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>45-64 <lb/>105 165 (75.6) <lb/>0.47 (0.45-0.49) 83 978 (64.1) <lb/>0.52 (0.50-0.53) 52 100 (37.4) <lb/>0.56 (0.54-0.57) 44 600 (32.1) <lb/>0.60 (0.59-0.62) <lb/>65-74 <lb/>84 844 (69.1) <lb/>0.43 (0.41-0.44) 69 104 (60.1) <lb/>0.50 (0.48-0.52) 44 170 (36.0) <lb/>0.50 (0.48-0.51) 34 131 (27.8) <lb/>0.53 (0.51-0.55) <lb/>≥75 <lb/>40 147 (56.0) <lb/>0.25 (0.24-0.26) 29 841 (45.3) <lb/>0.27 (0.26-0.28) 18 852 (26.3) <lb/>0.30 (0.29-0.31) 13 560 (18.9) <lb/>0.32 (0.31-0.33) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>118 922 (68.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>94 590 (58.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>55 367 (32.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>43 904 (25.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Female <lb/>139 617 (72.1) <lb/>1.34 (1.32-1.37) 112 357 (62.1) <lb/>1.33 (1.31-1.35) 75 667 (39.1) <lb/>1.45 (1.43-1.47) 62 130 (32.1) <lb/>1.49 (1.46-1.51) <lb/>Race and ethnicity <lb/>Asian <lb/>9005 (72.6) <lb/>1.03 (0.99-1.08) 7163 (61.8) <lb/>0.97 (0.93-1.01) 4186 (33.7) <lb/>0.84 (0.81-0.88) 3535 (28.5) <lb/>0.91 (0.87-0.95) <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>18 103 (63.1) <lb/>0.66 (0.64-0.68) 13 177 (49.3) <lb/>0.62 (0.60-0.64) 8425 (29.4) <lb/>0.71 (0.69-0.73) 6677 (23.3) <lb/>0.71 (0.69-0.73) <lb/>Non-Hispanic Black 45 688 (63.4) <lb/>0.53 (0.52-0.54) 33 789 (50.9) <lb/>0.49 (0.48-0.50) 21 572 (29.9) <lb/>0.56 (0.55-0.57) 17 946 (24.9) <lb/>0.63 (0.61-0.64) <lb/>Non-Hispanic White 180 200 (73.5) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>148 519 (64.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>94 515 (38.5) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>75 721 (30.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Other b <lb/>5543 (66.5) <lb/>0.67 (0.64-0.71) 4299 (54.7) <lb/>0.65 (0.62-0.68) 2336 (28.0) <lb/>0.62 (0.59-0.65) 2155 (25.9) <lb/>0.77 (0.73-0.81) <lb/>Insurance <lb/>Commercial <lb/>122 407 (79.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>101 132 (69.6) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>61 623 (40.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>53 589 (34.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Medicare <lb/>115 101 (62.8) <lb/>0.54 (0.53-0.56) 90 884 (53.4) <lb/>0.61 (0.59-0.62) 59 179 (32.3) <lb/>0.80 (0.78-0.82) 44 117 (24.1) <lb/>0.71 (0.69-0.73) <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>16 438 (64.6) <lb/>0.52 (0.51-0.54) 12 750 (53.5) <lb/>0.58 (0.56-0.60) 9004 (35.4) <lb/>0.83 (0.81-0.86) 7242 (28.5) <lb/>0.76 (0.74-0.78) <lb/>Self-pay <lb/>4593 (100.0) <lb/>NA c <lb/>2181 (49.4) <lb/>0.44 (0.42-0.47) 1228 (26.7) <lb/>0.50 (0.46-0.53) 1086 (23.6) <lb/>0.57 (0.53-0.61) <lb/>Primary language <lb/>English <lb/>250 962 (71.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>202 272 (61.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>128 434 (36.6) 1 [Reference] <lb/>103 990 (29.6) 1 [Reference] <lb/>Non-English <lb/>7577 (48.7) <lb/>0.40 (0.38-0.41) 4675 (32.3) <lb/>0.35 (0.33-0.36) 2600 (16.7) <lb/>0.37 (0.35-0.39) 2044 (13.1) <lb/>0.40 (0.38-0.42) <lb/>Tobacco use <lb/>Never or former <lb/>231 855 (72.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>186 996 (62.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>119 023 (36.9) 1 [Reference] <lb/>96 757 (30.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Current <lb/>26 684 (59.7) <lb/>0.50 (0.49-0.51) 19 951 (47.5) <lb/>0.50 (0.49-0.51) 12 011 (26.9) <lb/>0.58 (0.56-0.59) 9277 (20.8) <lb/>0.55 (0.54-0.57) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>No <lb/>178 770 (72.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>144 378 (61.8) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>87 776 (35.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>71 710 (28.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>79 769 (67.0) <lb/>0.90 (0.89-0.92) 62 569 (56.7) <lb/>0.92 (0.91-0.94) 43 258 (36.3) <lb/>1.07 (1.06-1.10) 34 324 (28.8) <lb/>1.09 (1.07-1.10) <lb/>Depression <lb/>No <lb/>213 259 (70.5) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>171 235 (60.3) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>104 683 (34.6) 1 [Reference] <lb/>84 426 (27.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>45 280 (70.6) <lb/>0.96 (0.94-0.98) 35 712 (59.9) <lb/>0.91 (0.90-0.93) 26 351 (41.1) <lb/>1.15 (1.13-1.17) 21 608 (33.7) <lb/>1.19 (1.17-1.22) <lb/>Prescribed ≥2 BP <lb/>medication <lb/>No <lb/>188 690 (71.5) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>151 635 (61.3) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>94 262 (35.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>78 036 (29.6) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>69 849 (67.9) <lb/>0.92 (0.91-0.94) 55 312 (57.5) <lb/>0.91 (0.89-0.92) 36 772 (35.7) <lb/>1.02 (1.01-1.04) 27 998 (27.2) <lb/>0.93 (0.92-0.95) <lb/>Uncontrolled <lb/>baseline BP <lb/>No <lb/>216 791 (70.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>174 156 (60.8) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>111 191 (36.4) 1 [Reference] <lb/>89 205 (29.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>41 748 (68.2) <lb/>0.89 (0.88-0.91) 32 791 (57.0) <lb/>0.89 (0.87-0.90) 19 843 (32.4) <lb/>0.89 (0.88-0.91) 16 829 (27.5) <lb/>0.96 (0.94-0.98) <lb/>No. of PCP visits <lb/>1-2 <lb/>100 595 (67.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>83 892 (56.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>38 246 (25.5) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>34 848 (23.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>≥3 <lb/>157 944 (72.9) <lb/>1.59 (1.56-1.61) 123 055 (63.4) <lb/>1.63 (1.61-1.66) 92 788 (42.8) <lb/>2.48 (2.45-2.52) 71 186 (32.8) <lb/>1.82 (1.80-1.85) <lb/>Abbreviations: BP, blood pressure; NA, not applicable; OR, odds ratio; PCP, primary care <lb/>physician. <lb/>a Adjusted for age, sex, race and ethnicity, insurance, primary language, diabetes, <lb/>tobacco use, depression, uncontrolled baseline BP, BP-lowering medications, and <lb/>number of PCP visits. <lb/>b Other includes American Indian or Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, other Pacific <lb/>Islander, or unknown. <lb/>c All patients in the self-pay insurance category accessed the patient portal at least once. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>1.13-1.17) and sharing home blood pressure readings (diabetes: OR, 1.09; 95% CI, 1.07-1.10; <lb/>depression: OR, 1.19; 95% CI, 1.17-1.22) were greater (Table 2). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this cohort of more than 300 000 primary care patients with hypertension, 7 of 10 patients <lb/>accessed the patient portal at least once between 2021 and 2022 but only 28.9% engaged in <lb/>messages and 8.7% shared home blood pressure readings. The literature on quantifying patient <lb/>portal engagement shows variable results depending on the patient population, how engagement is <lb/>Table 3. Associations Between Patient Characteristics and Home BP Reading Functionalities in the Patient Portal a <lb/>Independent variable <lb/>BP monitoring order (n = 553) b <lb/>Patients shared BP readings (n = 48) c <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>No. (%) of <lb/>patients <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>Age group, y <lb/>18-44 <lb/>128 (0.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>15 (11.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>45-64 <lb/>246 (0.2) <lb/>0.48 (0.38-0.60) <lb/>21 (8.5) <lb/>0.60 (0.29-1.24) <lb/>65-74 <lb/>136 (0.1) <lb/>0.41 (0.30-0.56) <lb/>8 (5.9) <lb/>0.24 (0.06-0.96) <lb/>≥75 <lb/>43 (0.1) <lb/>0.24 (0.15-0.37) <lb/>4 (9.3) <lb/>0.33 (0.06-1.81) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>238 (0.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>24 (10.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Female <lb/>315 (0.2) <lb/>1.20 (1.01-1.42) <lb/>24 (7.6) <lb/>0.69 (0.37-1.29) <lb/>Race and ethnicity <lb/>Asian <lb/>10 (0.1) <lb/>0.60 (0.45-0.80) <lb/>1 (10.0) <lb/>0.75 (0.09-6.58) <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>33 (0.1) <lb/>0.89 (0.62-1.28) <lb/>2 (6.1) <lb/>0.48 (0.11-2.17) <lb/>Non-Hispanic Black <lb/>142 (0.2) <lb/>1.15 (0.94-1.41) <lb/>8 (5.6) <lb/>0.50 (0.22-1.18) <lb/>Non-Hispanic White <lb/>361 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>37 (10.3) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Other d <lb/>7 (0.1) <lb/>0.51 (0.24-1.09) <lb/>0 <lb/>NA e <lb/>Insurance <lb/>Commercial <lb/>330 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>32 (9.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Medicare <lb/>160 (0.1) <lb/>0.60 (0.45-0.80) <lb/>13 (8.1) <lb/>1.50 (0.44-5.15) <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>57 (0.2) <lb/>0.92 (0.69-1.23) <lb/>3 (5.3) <lb/>0.56 (0.15-2.08) <lb/>Self-pay <lb/>6 (0.1) <lb/>0.63 (0.28-1.41) <lb/>0 <lb/>NA e <lb/>Primary language <lb/>English <lb/>552 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>48 (8.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Non-English <lb/>1 (&lt;0.1) <lb/>0.06 (0.01-0.41) <lb/>0 <lb/>NA e <lb/>Tobacco use <lb/>Never or former <lb/>494 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>45 (9.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Current <lb/>59 (0.1) <lb/>0.70 (0.53-0.92) <lb/>3 (5.1) <lb/>0.41 (0.12-1.41) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>No <lb/>418 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>35 (8.4) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>135 (0.1) <lb/>0.76 (0.62-0.93) <lb/>13 (9.6) <lb/>1.24 (0.60-2.57) <lb/>Depression <lb/>No <lb/>431 (0.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>34 (7.9) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>122 (0.2) <lb/>1.30 (1.05-1.60) <lb/>14 (11.5) <lb/>1.51 (0.74-3.07) <lb/>Prescribed ≥2 BP medications <lb/>No <lb/>392 (0.2) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>34 (8.7) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>161 (0.2) <lb/>1.24 (1.03-1.50) <lb/>14 (8.7) <lb/>0.93 (0.47-1.84) <lb/>Uncontrolled baseline BP <lb/>No <lb/>399 (0.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>31 (7.8) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>Yes <lb/>154 (0.3) <lb/>1.82 (1.51-2.20) <lb/>17 (11.0) <lb/>1.72 (0.90-3.30) <lb/>No. of PCP visits <lb/>1-2 <lb/>199 (0.1) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>14 (7.0) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>≥3 <lb/>354 (0.2) <lb/>1.48 (1.24-1.77) <lb/>34 (9.6) <lb/>1.63 (0.81-3.27) <lb/>Abbreviations: BP, blood pressure; NA, not applicable; <lb/>OR, odds ratio; PCP, primary care physician. <lb/>a Adjusted for age, sex, race and ethnicity, insurance, <lb/>primary language, diabetes, tobacco use, depression, <lb/>uncontrolled baseline BP, BP-lowering medications, <lb/>and number of PCP visits. <lb/>b Among 533 patients who received a BP <lb/>monitoring order. <lb/>c Among the subset of patients with hypertension who <lb/>received an order for home BP readings from the <lb/>care team during the study year. <lb/>d Other includes American Indian or Alaska Native, <lb/>Native Hawaiian, other Pacific Islander, <lb/>and unknown. <lb/>e None of the patients under other race or ethnicity, <lb/>self-pay insurance, and non-English speakers shared <lb/>BP readings with the care team, and therefore an OR <lb/>could not be calculated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>defined, and the time evaluated, with increased engagement in more recent years. 25 An analysis by <lb/>Chan et al 22 reported that 53.4% of primary care patients accessed patient portals, of whom 74.5% <lb/>were active users, defined based on accessing specific functionalities that require more active <lb/>patient involvement. Sun et al 26 reported that 32.9% of patients with diabetes attending outpatient <lb/>clinics used patient portals. <lb/>Given the lack of a unified definition for engagement, we included several definitions beyond <lb/>ever accessing the portal or frequency of access. Our results showed consistent findings of disparities <lb/>in engagement regardless of the engagement definition used and after adjusting for several <lb/>demographic and clinical characteristics. Although an access code for patient portal use is generated <lb/>automatically for all patients attending this health care system, patients belonging to racial and <lb/>ethnic minority groups were less likely to access the patient portal than non-Hispanic White patients. <lb/>Patients whose preferred language is not English were also significantly less likely to engage with the <lb/>patient portal, which is similar to findings in the study by Casillas et al. 27 Although 100% of self-pay <lb/>patients accessed the patient portal at least once, engagement was still low in this subgroup, which <lb/>aligns with lack of engagement in other disadvantaged subgroups evaluated in this analysis. An <lb/>explanation may be that these patients are using the self-pay function in the patient portal. Smoking, <lb/>which is a social determinant of health-associated behavior, was also associated with less <lb/>engagement with patient portals. <lb/>Our results extend the existing literature on the potential digital divide in patient portal <lb/>engagement and highlight major disparities among patients treated for hypertension in primary <lb/>care. 28,29 The digital divide is the uneven distribution of access to, use of, and impact of information <lb/>technologies between demographics and regions. 30 Low patient portal use in vulnerable populations <lb/>may result in intervention-generated inequity, which is a situation whereby an intervention <lb/>inadvertently worsens existing health disparities instead of improving them. 31,32 Research studies, <lb/>interventions, and quality improvement initiatives in hypertension that are delivered via patient <lb/>portals should be mindful of the disparities in engaging with patient portals. Efforts should be made <lb/>and evaluated to reach all patients regardless of their race and ethnicity, insurance status, or <lb/>preferred language. This is especially true for patients with hypertension because these <lb/>subpopulations share the burden of clinical consequences. 7 <lb/>Our study did not explore the underlying reasons behind the digital divide, which may include <lb/>education levels, low socioeconomic status, and lack of internet access. 25,33 These characteristics <lb/>likely mediate some of the associations observed in our analysis. In addition, physician and health <lb/>care system characteristics also likely influence patient portal engagement. 30 Self-reported survey <lb/>data, such as the Health Information National Trends Study, found similar disparities in patient portal <lb/>engagement. In that survey, patients who were non-Hispanic White were more likely to report being <lb/>offered access to the patient portal (76.7%) compared with patients who are non-Hispanic Black <lb/>(66.8%). This disparity highlights the importance of the care team actively discussing and offering <lb/>the patient portal to patients and offering it equally regardless of race or ethnicity. 34 In our analysis, <lb/>the number of patients who received a self-monitored blood pressure order from the care team was <lb/>too small to draw conclusions; however, data suggest that patients who are Hispanic or Latino and <lb/>smokers were less likely to receive an order for self-monitored blood pressure. Future work should <lb/>incorporate implementation science approaches and directly address the key role of physicians and <lb/>staff in promoting more equitable patient portal use. 35 <lb/>Our study also sheds light on clinical characteristics related to hypertension that may be <lb/>associated with patient portal engagement. More PCP visits were associated with greater patient <lb/>portal engagement. This finding suggests that patients engaged with the patient portals are more <lb/>engaged with their PCPs and have more in-clinic communication. Efforts should be made to engage <lb/>patients with less than the guideline-recommended number of PCP visits (ie, &lt;3 visits per year) with <lb/>the patient portal as an alternative (backup) to in-person communications with the PCP. 25,30,33 <lb/>Further research is needed to understand how patient portal engagement is associated with <lb/>reaching blood pressure control. An analysis from 2010 among patients with newly diagnosed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>hypertension showed an association between patient portal access (evaluated subjectively through <lb/>a survey) and blood pressure control. 36 However, the association disappeared after adjusting for <lb/>potential confounders. 36 More recently, a study evaluating associations between patient portal <lb/>access and glycated hemoglobin control among patients with diabetes showed a clear link between <lb/>accessing the portal and better control. 4 More research exploring these associations among patients <lb/>with hypertension is warranted. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>A few limitations should be noted when interpreting our results. First, our data are limited to 1 health <lb/>care system, and patients may seek care and use patient portals elsewhere. Second, unlike other <lb/>studies that report on all the common functionalities of the patient portal, we focus our results on 2 <lb/>functionalities that are relevant to patients with hypertension. Third, many factors may be associated <lb/>with low patient portal engagement (eg, education level, income, and internet access); however, our <lb/>analysis was limited to factors found within the EHR. Fourth, we were only able to evaluate patients&apos; <lb/>engagement in home blood pressure monitoring via the patient portal-specific functionality. Patients <lb/>may share their home blood pressure readings via the messaging functionality; however, this rate <lb/>has been reported to be very low at 1.2% of patients only. 10 Patients may also engage in home blood <lb/>pressure monitoring outside patient portals, such as using automated blood pressure cuffs that <lb/>transmit readings directly to the care team. However, few of these initiatives have been implemented <lb/>in clinical settings given barriers related to the cost of the device to the patient and barriers to <lb/>connecting these devices to the EHR. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this cohort study of patients with hypertension, two-thirds had accessed the patient portal at least <lb/>once, with a median number of logins of 28 per year. Despite the observed high rates of engagement, <lb/>clear disparities were observed in terms of race and ethnicity, insurance status, preferred language, <lb/>and tobacco use. To overcome the digital divide and prevent further disparities in hypertension <lb/>outcomes, it is important to further evaluate patient portal adoption among these subpopulations <lb/>and identify ways of increasing their engagement. <lb/></body>

			<front>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Accepted for Publication: February 28, 2024. <lb/>Published: May 15, 2024. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 <lb/>Open Access: This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2024 Khatib R <lb/>et al. JAMA Network Open. <lb/>Corresponding Author: Rasha Khatib, PhD, MHS, Advocate Aurora Research Institute, Advocate Health, <lb/>945 N 12th St, Milwaukee, WI 53233 (rasha.alkhatib@aah.org). <lb/>Author Affiliations: Advocate Aurora Research Institute, Advocate Health, Milwaukee, Wisconsin (Khatib, <lb/>Glowacki, Chang); Center for Healthcare Delivery Sciences (C4HDS), Department of Medicine, Brigham and <lb/>Women&apos;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts (Lauffenburger); Division of <lb/>Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacoeconomics, Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital and <lb/>Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts (Lauffenburger); Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, <lb/>University of California, San Francisco (Pletcher); Enterprise Population Health, Advocate Health, Rolling <lb/>Meadows, Illinois (Siddiqi). <lb/></front>
    
            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Dr Khatib and Ms Glowacki had full access to all of the data in the study and take <lb/>responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. <lb/>Concept and design: Khatib, Glowacki, Siddiqi. <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: All authors. <lb/>Drafting of the manuscript: Khatib, Glowacki, Siddiqi. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: All authors. <lb/>Statistical analysis: Khatib, Glowacki, Chang. <lb/>Obtained funding: Khatib. <lb/>Administrative, technical, or material support: Lauffenburger. <lb/>Supervision: Khatib, Siddiqi. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: Dr Lauffenburger reported receiving personal fees from the American Heart <lb/>Association and Alosa Health outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding/Support: This project was supported by grant GR-00000214 from the Live Well Intramural Pilot Grant <lb/>Program through Advocate Aurora Research Institute (Dr Khatib). <lb/>Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, <lb/>management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and the <lb/>decision to submit the manuscript for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Sharing Statement: See Supplement 2. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Virani SS, Alonso A, Aparicio HJ, et al; American Heart Association Council on Epidemiology and Prevention <lb/>Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart Disease and stroke statistics-2021 update: <lb/>a report from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2021;143(8):e254-e743. doi:10.1161/CIR. <lb/>0000000000000950 <lb/>2. James PA, Oparil S, Carter BL, et al. 2014 evidence-based guideline for the management of high blood pressure <lb/>in adults: report from the panel members appointed to the Eighth Joint National Committee (JNC 8). JAMA. <lb/>2014;311(5):507-520. doi:10.1001/jama.2013.284427 <lb/>3. Khanijahani A, Akinci N, Quitiquit E. A systematic review of the role of telemedicine in blood pressure control: <lb/>focus on patient engagement. Curr Hypertens Rep. 2022;24(7):247-258. doi:10.1007/s11906-022-01186-5 <lb/>4. Graetz I, Huang J, Muelly ER, Fireman B, Hsu J, Reed ME. Association of mobile patient portal access with <lb/>diabetes medication adherence and glycemic levels among adults with diabetes. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3(2): <lb/>e1921429. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.21429 <lb/>5. Han HR, Gleason KT, Sun CA, et al. Using patient portals to improve patient outcomes: systematic review. JMIR <lb/>Hum Factors. 2019;6(4):e15038. doi:10.2196/15038 <lb/>6. Richwine C, Johnson C, Patel V. Disparities in patient portal access and the role of providers in encouraging <lb/>access and use. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2023;30(2):308-317. doi:10.1093/jamia/ocac227 <lb/>7. Lyles CR, Sarkar U, Schillinger D, et al. Refilling medications through an online patient portal: consistent <lb/>improvements in adherence across racial/ethnic groups. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2016;23(e1):e28-e33. doi:10. <lb/>1093/jamia/ocv126 <lb/>8. Reed ME, Huang J, Brand RJ, et al. Patients with complex chronic conditions: health care use and clinical events <lb/>associated with access to a patient portal. PLoS One. 2019;14(6):e0217636. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0217636 <lb/>9. Johnson AM, Brimhall AS, Johnson ET, et al. A systematic review of the effectiveness of patient education <lb/>through patient portals. JAMIA Open. 2023;6(1):ooac085. doi:10.1093/jamiaopen/ooac085 <lb/>10. North F, Elrashidi MY, Ward WJ, et al. Telemonitoring blood pressure by secure message on a patient portal: <lb/>use, content, and outcomes. Telemed J E Health. 2015;21(8):630-636. doi:10.1089/tmj.2014.0179 <lb/>11. Pickering TG, Miller NH, Ogedegbe G, Krakoff LR, Artinian NT, Goff D; American Heart Association; American <lb/>Society of Hypertension; Preventive Cardiovascular Nurses Association. Call to action on use and reimbursement <lb/>for home blood pressure monitoring: a joint scientific statement from the American Heart Association, American <lb/>Society of Hypertension, and Preventive Cardiovascular Nurses Association. J Cardiovasc Nurs. 2008;23(4): <lb/>299-323. doi:10.1097/01.JCN.0000317429.98844.04 <lb/>12. Bouzalmate-Hajjaj A, Massó Guijarro P, Khan KS, Bueno-Cavanillas A, Cano-Ibáñez N. Benefits of participation <lb/>in clinical trials: an umbrella review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(22):15368. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>ijerph192215368 <lb/>13. Anum Saeed M. Racial Disparities in Hypertension Prevalence and Management: A Crisis Control? American <lb/>College of Cardiology; 2020. <lb/>14. Muntner P, Hardy ST, Fine LJ, et al. Trends in blood pressure control among US adults with hypertension, 1999-<lb/>2000 to 2017-2018. JAMA. 2020;324(12):1190-1200. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.14545 <lb/>15. Oso AA, Adefurin A, Benneman MM, et al. Health insurance status affects hypertension control in a hospital <lb/>based internal medicine clinic. Int J Cardiol Hypertens. 2019;1:100003. doi:10.1016/j.ijchy.2019.100003 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>16. King JB, Pinheiro LC, Bryan Ringel J, et al. Multiple social vulnerabilities to health disparities and hypertension <lb/>and death in the REGARDS study. Hypertension. 2022;79(1):196-206. doi:10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.15196 <lb/>17. von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gøtzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP; STROBE Initiative. The <lb/>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement: guidelines for <lb/>reporting observational studies. Int J Surg. 2014;12(12):1495-1499. doi:10.1016/j.ijsu.2014.07.013 <lb/>18. Davidson KW, Kemper AR, Doubeni CA, et al. Developing primary care-based recommendations for social <lb/>determinants of health: methods of the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173(6): <lb/>461-467. doi:10.7326/M20-0730 <lb/>19. Chobanian AV, Bakris GL, Black HR, et al; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute Joint National Committee <lb/>on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure; National High Blood Pressure <lb/>Education Program Coordinating Committee. The Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, <lb/>Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure: the JNC 7 report. JAMA. 2003;289(19):2560-2572. <lb/>doi:10.1001/jama.289.19.2560 <lb/>20. Jones A, Christiansen P, Field M. Failed attempts to improve the reliability of the alcohol visual probe task <lb/>following empirical recommendations. Psychol Addict Behav. 2018;32(8):922-932. doi:10.1037/adb0000414 <lb/>21. Mark DB, Cowper PA, Anstrom KJ, et al. Economic and quality-of-life outcomes of natriuretic peptide-guided <lb/>therapy for heart failure. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2018;72(21):2551-2562. doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2018.08.2184 <lb/>22. Chan B, Lyles C, Kaplan C, Lam R, Karliner L. A Comparison of electronic patient-portal use among patients <lb/>with resident and attending primary care providers. J Gen Intern Med. 2018;33(12):2085-2091. doi:10.1007/ <lb/>s11606-018-4637-x <lb/>23. Griffin A, Skinner A, Thornhill J, Weinberger M. Patient portals: Who uses them? What features do they use? <lb/>And do they reduce hospital readmissions? Appl Clin Inform. 2016;7(2):489-501. doi:10.4338/ACI-2016-01-<lb/>RA-0003 <lb/>24. Jiroutek MR, Turner JR. Relative vs absolute risk and odds: Understanding the difference. J Clin Hypertens <lb/>(Greenwich). 2019;21(6):859-861. doi:10.1111/jch.13548 <lb/>25. Carini E, Villani L, Pezzullo AM, et al. The impact of digital patient portals on health outcomes, system <lb/>efficiency, and patient attitudes: updated systematic literature review. J Med Internet Res. 2021;23(9):e26189. doi: <lb/>10.2196/26189 <lb/>26. Sun R, Burke LE, Saul MI, Korytkowski MT, Li D, Sereika SM. Use of a patient portal for engaging patients with <lb/>type 2 diabetes: patterns and prediction. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2019;21(10):546-556. doi:10.1089/dia.2019.0074 <lb/>27. Casillas A, Abhat A, Vassar SD, et al. Not speaking the same language-lower portal use for limited English <lb/>proficient patients in the Los Angeles safety net. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2021;32(4):2055-2070. doi:10. <lb/>1353/hpu.2021.0182 <lb/>28. Ukoha EP, Feinglass J, Yee LM. Disparities in electronic patient portal use in prenatal care: retrospective cohort <lb/>study. J Med Internet Res. 2019;21(9):e14445. doi:10.2196/14445 <lb/>29. Wallace LS, Angier H, Huguet N, et al. Patterns of electronic portal use among vulnerable patients in a <lb/>nationwide practice-based research network: from the OCHIN Practice-based Research Network (PBRN). J Am <lb/>Board Fam Med. 2016;29(5):592-603. doi:10.3122/jabfm.2016.05.160046 <lb/>30. Irizarry T, DeVito Dabbs A, Curran CR. Patient portals and patient engagement: a state of the science review. <lb/>J Med Internet Res. 2015;17(6):e148. doi:10.2196/jmir.4255 <lb/>31. Grossman LV, Masterson Creber RM, Benda NC, Wright D, Vawdrey DK, Ancker JS. Interventions to increase <lb/>patient portal use in vulnerable populations: a systematic review. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2019;26(8-9):855-870. <lb/>doi:10.1093/jamia/ocz023 <lb/>32. Veinot TC, Mitchell H, Ancker JS. Good intentions are not enough: how informatics interventions can worsen <lb/>inequality. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2018;25(8):1080-1088. doi:10.1093/jamia/ocy052 <lb/>33. Aljabri D, Dumitrascu A, Burton MC, et al. Patient portal adoption and use by hospitalized cancer patients: <lb/>a retrospective study of its impact on adverse events, utilization, and patient satisfaction. BMC Med Inform Decis <lb/>Mak. 2018;18(1):70. doi:10.1186/s12911-018-0644-4 <lb/>34. National Cancer Institute. Health Information National Trends Survey (HINTS): increase the proportion of <lb/>adults who use IT to track health care data or communicate with providers -HC/HIT-07. Published 2020. <lb/>Accessed February 13, 2024. https://health.gov/healthypeople/objectives-and-data/browse-objectives/health-it/ <lb/>increase-proportion-adults-who-use-it-track-health-care-data-or-communicate-providers-hchit-07 <lb/>35. Lyles CR, Nelson EC, Frampton S, Dykes PC, Cemballi AG, Sarkar U. Using electronic health record portals to <lb/>improve patient engagement: research priorities and best practices. Ann Intern Med. 2020;172(11)(suppl): <lb/>S123-S129. doi:10.7326/M19-0876 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>36. Manard W, Scherrer JF, Salas J, Schneider FD. Patient portal use and blood pressure control in newly <lb/>diagnosed hypertension. J Am Board Fam Med. 2016;29(4):452-459. doi:10.3122/jabfm.2016.04.160008 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 1. <lb/>eAppendix. Patient Flow Diagram <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 2. <lb/>Data Sharing Statement <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Cardiology <lb/>Disparities in Patient Portal Use Among Patients With Hypertension <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(5):e2411649. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.11649 (Reprinted) <lb/>May 15, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13/13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 </note>


	</text>
</TEI>