<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:12:50.649Z">11/20/2025 10:12:50 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:12:40.334504Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:12:40.334504Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Research Article <lb/>Ehab M. Elzayat, Abdelrahman Y. Sherif*, Ahmad Abdul-Wahhab Shahba, Mohsin Kazi, <lb/>Mohammed Alyahya, Hany W. Darwish <lb/>Development and validation of a stability <lb/>indicating UPLC-DAD method coupled with MS-<lb/>TQD for ramipril and thymoquinone in bioactive <lb/>SNEDDS with in silico toxicity analysis of ramipril <lb/>degradation products <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/chem-2024-0070 <lb/>received February 4, 2024; accepted July 12, 2024 <lb/>Abstract: The identification of degradation products of ther-<lb/>apeutic molecules in pharmaceutical formulations has gained <lb/>significant attention due to their potential impact on patient <lb/>safety. Ramipril (RP), an antihypertensive agent, was incorpo-<lb/>rated into a self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (SNEDDS), <lb/>which greatly enhanced its bioavailability. However, none of the <lb/>previous studies have investigated the toxicological effects of <lb/>these degradation products that may form during storage. <lb/>Moreover, a bioactive SNEDDS containing black cumin oil <lb/>(BCO) and its bioactive ingredient, thymoquinone (TQ), was <lb/>used to further enhance the therapeutic activity of RP. To <lb/>assess the stability of the proposed formulation, a validated <lb/>ultrahigh-performance liquid chromatography (UPLC) method <lb/>was developed to simultaneously measure the concentrations <lb/>of RP and TQ. The formulation was subjected to accelerated <lb/>stress conditions to facilitate drug degradation. The resulting <lb/>degradation products were analyzed using mass spectroscopy <lb/>(MS) to determine their molecular mass, and their chemical <lb/>structures were in silico predicted using Zeneth Nexus soft-<lb/>ware, while their toxicity was assessed using in silico Derek <lb/>Nexus software. RP and TQ, along with their degradation pro-<lb/>ducts, were separated using an HSS T3 column at a flow rate of <lb/>0.25 mL/min. The detection wavelengths for RP and TQ were <lb/>210 and 254 nm, respectively. The developed UPLC method <lb/>exhibited acceptable linearity for both RP and TQ, with corre-<lb/>lation coefficient (r 2 ) values exceeding 0.9995 and 0.9998, <lb/>respectively. The method provided accurate, precise, and <lb/>high-resolution analysis of both drugs and their degradation <lb/>products within a short run time of less than 3.2 min. The <lb/>toxicity and mutagenicity of two alkaline degradation pro-<lb/>ducts of RP were predicted using in silico software Derek <lb/>Nexus (version 6.3). Several toxicity endpoints, including chro-<lb/>mosomal damage, skin sensitization, and hepatotoxicity, were <lb/>predicted. Overall, the developed method can be used to eval-<lb/>uate the stability and integrity of RP and TQ during the devel-<lb/>opment of the proposed antihypertensive formulation. <lb/>Keywords: bioactive SNEDDS, ramipril, forced stress degra-<lb/>dation, stability-indicating method, TQD-MS <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The low solubility of therapeutic drug molecules poses a <lb/>challenge to their bioavailability [1]. Extensive research has <lb/>been conducted to develop drug delivery systems that can <lb/>significantly enhance the solubility [2,3]. However, some <lb/>drug molecules face stability issues due to incompatibility <lb/></body>

    <front>Ehab M. Elzayat, Ahmad Abdul-Wahhab Shahba, Mohsin Kazi, <lb/>Mohammed Alyahya: Department of Pharmaceutics, College of <lb/>Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia <lb/> <lb/>* Corresponding author: Abdelrahman Y. Sherif, Department of <lb/>Pharmaceutics, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, <lb/>Saudi Arabia, e-mail: Ashreef@ksu.edu.sa <lb/>Hany W. Darwish: Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, College of <lb/>Pharmacy, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia <lb/>Graphical abstract <lb/>Open Chemistry 2024; 22: 20240070 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

    <body>with excipients in the formulation [4,5]. Therefore, it is <lb/>essential to identify and examine the toxicological degrada-<lb/>tion products formed within these drug delivery systems to <lb/>assess their impact on patient safety [6]. <lb/>Ramipril (RP, Figure 1a) is a commonly used antihy-<lb/>pertensive agent for hypertension treatment [7]. It exerts <lb/>its pharmacological effects by inhibiting angiotensin-con-<lb/>verting enzyme (ACE) [8]. Additionally, RP has shown pro-<lb/>tective effects on mortality following a heart attack [9]. <lb/>However, its limited solubility leads to poor dissolution <lb/>and reduced bioavailability [10]. To address this issue, var-<lb/>ious drug delivery systems have been employed, including <lb/>the self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (SNEDDS), <lb/>which has been extensively used to improve the dissolution <lb/>rate and bioavailability of RP [10-15]. More recently, a bioac-<lb/>tive SNEDDS formulation has been developed to enhance the <lb/>therapeutic activity of loaded drug molecules and improve <lb/>the bioavailability. This is achieved through the incorporation <lb/>of oil-containing phytochemicals with nutraceutical proper-<lb/>ties [16,17]. <lb/>Nigella sativa has a long history of use in various cul-<lb/>tures for treating different diseases, including hyperten-<lb/>sion [18,19]. Recent clinical studies have demonstrated <lb/>that the intake of N. sativa significantly lowers blood pres-<lb/>sure levels compared to control groups [20-22]. Hence, black <lb/>cumin oil (BCO), an extract of N. sativa, can be used to <lb/>enhance the bioavailability and therapeutic activity of RP. <lb/>This is due to the presence of a well-known bioactive com-<lb/>pound called thymoquinone (TQ, Figure 1b) [23], which <lb/>exerts antihypertensive effects by reducing ACE production <lb/>[24,25]. The combination of RP and TQ can potentially offer <lb/>synergistic antihypertensive benefits. <lb/>From a pharmaceutical perspective, BCO can be incor-<lb/>porated into SNEDDS formulations as a bioactive ingre-<lb/>dient to improve the bioavailability of naturally occurring <lb/>TQ, as well as the solubility and bioavailability of RP <lb/>[10,26]. However, there is a need to develop an analytical <lb/>method for quantifying the loaded drugs in the prepared <lb/>SNEDDS formulation during its shelf-life and during its in <lb/>vitro pharmaceutical characterization. <lb/>Furthermore, it is crucial to evaluate the potential toxi-<lb/>city of the detected degradation products [27]. Therefore, in <lb/>silico studies were performed using computational methods, <lb/>specifically Derek Nexus (version 6.3), to assess the potential <lb/>toxicity and mutagenicity of the proposed compound. Derek <lb/>Nexus (version 6.3) software is a specialized software spe-<lb/>cially adopted to assess various toxicity endpoints, such as <lb/>carcinogenicity, genotoxicity, mutagenicity, teratogenicity, <lb/>skin irritation, allergic reactions, and impact on fertility. <lb/>The results from this study could be used as part of an <lb/>ICH M7 workflow [28,29]. <lb/>The main objective of this study was to develop a sta-<lb/>bility-indicating method for analyzing RP and TQ in the <lb/>proposed formulation. The developed method was vali-<lb/>dated for linearity, specificity, accuracy, and precision. It <lb/>was also tested for its ability to separate degradation pro-<lb/>ducts under different stress conditions. The established <lb/>method was then employed as an analytical tool for quan-<lb/>tifying the drugs in the proposed pharmaceutical formula-<lb/>tion. Additionally, mass spectroscopy (MS) was utilized to <lb/>identify the exact degradation products in the formulation. <lb/>The degradation products&apos; chemical structures were further <lb/>confirmed by in silico Zeneth Nexus software. Zeneth soft-<lb/>ware uses a knowledge-based approach to forecast potential <lb/>pathways for degradation and byproducts under various <lb/>stress scenarios. Finally, the in silico prediction of toxicity <lb/>for these degradation products was investigated using the <lb/>Derek Nexus software. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Materials <lb/>RP was purchased from Jai Radhe Sales (Ahmedabad, <lb/>India). TQ was obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, <lb/>MO, USA). Hydrogenated castor oil (HCO-30) was acquired <lb/>from Nicole Chemical Co. (Tokyo, Japan). Transcutol P (TC-<lb/>P) was obtained from Gattefossé (Lyon, France). <lb/>2.2 Preparation of BCO <lb/>The procedure for obtaining BCO was described in a pre-<lb/>vious publication [13]. In summary, black cumin seeds <lb/>(BCS) were collected from the central part of Bangladesh. <lb/>The collected seeds were cleaned using fresh water and <lb/>then dried in open air with exposure to sunlight to remove <lb/>all moisture. The dried seeds were then cold-pressed to <lb/>Figure 1: Chemical structures of (a) RP and (b) TQ. <lb/></body>

    <page>2</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>extract the oil. The obtained oil was stored in an amber <lb/>glass bottle with a screw cap, as shown in Figure 2. <lb/>2.3 Preparation of BCO-based SNEDDS <lb/>formulation <lb/>The SNEDDS formulation was prepared following the pro-<lb/>cedure described in the literature [30]. In a 4 mL glass vial, <lb/>HCO-30, TC, and BCO were accurately weighed in a ratio of <lb/>40:27.75:32.25 to create the RP-free bioactive SNEDDS. After-<lb/>ward, 10 mg of RP was added to 990 mg of the RP-free SNEDDS <lb/>and subjected to vortexing and sonication to ensure complete <lb/>solubilization of the drug. The drug content, specifically RP and <lb/>TQ, was determined using the developed ultrahigh-perfor-<lb/>mance liquid chromatography (UPLC) method to quantify the <lb/>initial concentrations accurately. <lb/>2.4 Preparation of mobile phase (solution A) <lb/>To prepare the mobile phase, 1 g of sodium lauryl sulfate <lb/>was dissolved in a 1 L volumetric flask and then MQ water <lb/>was added to prepare a 0.1% w/v solution. The pH of the <lb/>solution was adjusted to 2.4 ± 0.1 using phosphoric acid. <lb/>The solution was filtered through a 0.45 µm Millipore mem-<lb/>brane filter. Acetonitrile (ACN) was then added to the fil-<lb/>tered solution in a ratio of 55:45 v/v. The resulting mixture <lb/>was further adjusted to a pH of 2.75 ± 0.1 using phosphoric <lb/>acid, and this mixture was named Solution A. <lb/>2.5 Instrumentation and chromatographic <lb/>conditions <lb/>The analysis of RP and TQ in the standard solutions, quality <lb/>control samples, and bioactive SNEDDS formulations was <lb/>carried out using the Waters Acquity UPLC system (Milford, <lb/>MA, USA). The UPLC system consists of a binary solvent pump <lb/>manager connected to a column chamber with controlled <lb/>temperature. The samples were injected through an Acquity <lb/>automatic Sample Manager and passed through a connected <lb/>column. The drug concentrations were analyzed using the <lb/>equipped Acquity photodiode array (PDA) detector. The <lb/>mobile phase used for elution was prepared by combining <lb/>Solution A and ACN in a ratio of 67:33. Separation was per-<lb/>formed on an Acquity UPLC HSS T3 column (2.1 mm × <lb/>100 mm, 1.8 µm). The flow rate of the mobile phase was <lb/>maintained at 0.25 mL/min. A sample volume of 2 µL was <lb/>injected, and the absorbance of RP and TQ was detected at <lb/>210 and 254 nm, respectively. <lb/>2.6 Preparation of standard stock solution, <lb/>calibration, and quality control samples <lb/>To prepare stock solutions of both drugs, 5 mg of each drug <lb/>was dissolved in separate 10 mL volumetric flasks using <lb/>ACN. This resulted in stock solutions with a concentration <lb/>of 500 μg/mL for each drug. From the prepared stock solu-<lb/>tions, serial dilutions were performed by diluting the stock <lb/>solution with ACN to obtain the desired concentration <lb/>range. For RP, the concentrations ranged from 1.5 to <lb/>50 μg/mL, and for TQ the concentrations ranged from 0.5 <lb/>to 50 μg/mL. <lb/>2.7 Validation studies <lb/>2.7.1 Linearity and calibration <lb/>To construct the calibration curves, dilutions of RP and TQ <lb/>with varying concentrations were prepared. These freshly <lb/>prepared standard solutions were then injected in six <lb/>Figure 2: Preparation of BCO: (a) BCS, (b) BCO obtained from compressed BCS, and (c) BCO stored in an amber glass bottle to protect it from light. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP  </note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <body>replicates, and the resulting peak areas were recorded. The <lb/>peak area is a measure of the response obtained from the <lb/>UV absorbance of the compounds. Using the MassLynx software <lb/>(Waters Corporation, Milford, MA, USA), the concentration of RP <lb/>or TQ was plotted against the corresponding measured peak <lb/>area. The linear regression equations were then calculated to <lb/>determine the relationship between the drug concentration and <lb/>absorbance. This included calculating parameters such as the <lb/>slope, intercept, and correlation coefficient (r 2 ) of the calibration <lb/>curves [31]. <lb/>2.7.2 Specificity <lb/>The specificity of the developed analytical method demon-<lb/>strates its capability to accurately determine the drug con-<lb/>centration even in the presence of other components. This <lb/>encompasses assessing any potential interference, such as <lb/>the matrix effect, between the retention time of the drug <lb/>peak and other components. Matrix components were <lb/>injected to evaluate method specificity, and the retention <lb/>times of detected peaks were compared with those of the <lb/>matrix spiked with RP and TQ. This analysis ensured that <lb/>any potential interference was properly identified and <lb/>avoided during drug concentration determination [32]. <lb/>2.7.3 Limit of detection (LOD) and lower limit of <lb/>quantification (LLOQ) <lb/>LOD and LLOQ were estimated based on the calculated <lb/>standard deviation (SD) of responses and slope obtained <lb/>from the calibration curve using the following equations: <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>= <lb/>× <lb/>LOD <lb/>3.3 SD /slope, <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>= <lb/>× <lb/>LLOQ <lb/>10 SD /slope. <lb/>2.7.4 Accuracy and precision <lb/>Accuracy (% recovery) assessed the ability of the developed <lb/>method to detect the drug concentration close to the pre-<lb/>dicted value. This was accomplished by comparing the <lb/>theoretical concentration with the mean concentration of <lb/>the injected sample, which was determined based on the <lb/>constructed calibration curve. Precision (relative standard <lb/>deviation, RSD%) was calculated to evaluate the method&apos;s <lb/>capability to consistently estimate the drug concentration <lb/>close to its expected value. Typically, this was accom-<lb/>plished by comparing the standard deviation value of mul-<lb/>tiple injections to the mean of the results. In this study, <lb/>quality control samples were injected six times over a <lb/>period of 3 days. The recovery (%) and RSD% for each <lb/>concentration were calculated to determine the accuracy <lb/>and precision of the method, respectively. <lb/>2.7.5 Stability of the prepared standard solution <lb/>In order to assess the stability of the calibration curve <lb/>under refrigeration conditions, two concentrations were <lb/>selected for the study. The prepared solutions were stored <lb/>in a freezer at -20°C, and the drug concentrations were <lb/>analyzed using the freshly constructed calibration curve <lb/>on a weekly basis. This allowed for monitoring any poten-<lb/>tial changes in the accuracy and reliability of the calibra-<lb/>tion curve over time in the refrigerated storage conditions. <lb/>2.8 Stability indicating study <lb/>A forced degradation study was conducted to evaluate the <lb/>ability of the developed method to separate the RP and TQ <lb/>peaks from any degradation peaks that may arise under <lb/>various stress conditions. This involved subjecting RP and <lb/>TQ solutions to oxidative, thermal, acid, and alkaline hydro-<lb/>lysis studies. Following the degradation process, the samples <lb/>were filtered using a filter syringe and analyzed using the <lb/>developed UPLC method. <lb/>2.9 Application of the developed method <lb/>A bioactive SNEDDS formulation, loaded with RP, was pre-<lb/>pared to assess the concentrations of RP and TQ after expo-<lb/>sure to stability storage conditions [33]. Initially, the con-<lb/>centrations of RP and TQ in the freshly prepared SNEDDS <lb/>formulation were determined in order to calculate the <lb/>initial drug concentration. The prepared SNEDDS formula-<lb/>tion was then placed in a stability chamber under con-<lb/>trolled conditions (40°C and 75% RH) and stored for a <lb/>period of 2 months. At the end of this incubation period, <lb/>the SNEDDS formulation from the stability chamber was <lb/>retrieved, and a chromatogram of the formulation was <lb/>obtained using the developed UPLC method to evaluate <lb/>its effectiveness in separating the drugs from any potential <lb/>degradation products. <lb/>2.10 Parameters for the MS scan <lb/>The degradation products for the stability sample were <lb/>determined using a triple quadrupole (TQD) mass spectro-<lb/>meter. TQD was operated in positive electrospray <lb/></body>

    <page>4</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>ionization (ESI+) mode. The TQD was run in the MS scan <lb/>mode over the range of 50-1,000 Da. The cone voltage was <lb/>set as 33 V. The capillary voltage, extractor voltage, and RF <lb/>lens were set at 3.3 kV, 3.0 V, and 0.1 V, respectively. The <lb/>source temperature and desolvation temperature were set <lb/>at 150 and 350°C, respectively. Nitrogen was used as the <lb/>desolvation gas. The rate of desolvation gas flow was 600 L/ <lb/>H. The flow of cone gas was kept at 0.0 mL. The chromato-<lb/>graphic conditions regarding the column and mobile phase <lb/>composition were the same as those of the UV method to <lb/>track the molecular weight of the compound peak at its <lb/>exact location. The injection volume was 5 µL. <lb/>2.11 In silico prediction of the chemical <lb/>structure and toxicity of the <lb/>degradation products <lb/>A degradation prediction research was conducted using <lb/>Zeneth software, version 9 (software introduced by Lhasa <lb/>Limited) in a variety of circumstances. All the three <lb/>observed DPs were correctly predicted by the adopted <lb/>Zeneth software. <lb/>Lhasa Limited has introduced a software application <lb/>named Derek Nexus, designed specifically for the assess-<lb/>ment of chemical toxicity as well as mutagenicity. This tool <lb/>employs a knowledge-based approach to generate predic-<lb/>tions, allowing users to evaluate potential hazards asso-<lb/>ciated with a chemical by analyzing various endpoints <lb/>such as mutagenicity, teratogenicity, carcinogenicity, skin <lb/>irritation, hepatotoxicity, and phototoxicity across different <lb/>species. The chemical structure under investigation was <lb/>input, and the prediction process was initiated by executing <lb/>a setup command in Derek Nexus. Detailed explanations of <lb/>the predictions can be found in Section 3. <lb/>3 Results and discussion <lb/>3.1 Optimization of the developed UPLC <lb/>method <lb/>An initial investigation was conducted on various columns <lb/>and different eluent mobile phases to determine the optimal <lb/>system components for separating the drugs and potential <lb/>degradation products. After each optimization, the prepared <lb/>degradation samples of RP and TQ were injected to assess <lb/>the separation of the parent drug peak from the degradation <lb/>products. By employing an isocratic elution method with <lb/>a mobile phase consisting of solution A and ACN in a ratio <lb/>of 67:33, and using an HSS T3 column, it was possible to <lb/>separate both drugs and their degradation peaks. Figure 3 <lb/>depicts the detected peaks of RP and TQ under the optimized <lb/>conditions, along with the UV spectrum analysis to identify <lb/>the maximum wavelength (λ max ) using the connected PDA <lb/>mode. The figure clearly shows that both drugs have distinct <lb/>λ max values, making it impossible to simultaneously deter-<lb/>mine RP and TQ at the same λ max unless the method&apos;s <lb/>sensitivity is compromised. As a result, RP and TQ were <lb/>detected using different UV channels, specifically 210 and <lb/>254 nm, respectively, which aligned with previously pub-<lb/>lished data [34,35]. The retention times of RP and TQ were <lb/>found to be 1.69 and 2.84 min, respectively, with a total run <lb/>time of 3.2 min. <lb/>3.2 Method validation <lb/>3.2.1 Selectivity and system suitability <lb/>Figure 4a and 4b illustrates the chromatograms of the <lb/>injected standard solutions of RP and TQ, respectively. <lb/>In order to examine any potential interference from the <lb/>matrix before validation, an RP-free bioactive SNEDDS <lb/>sample (without BCO) was injected [36]. The obtained chro-<lb/>matogram, as shown in Figure 4, verifies the absence of <lb/>any interference peaks at the retention times of RP and TQ. <lb/>The analysis of both the UV spectrum and the matrix effect <lb/>confirms that the detected peaks indeed correspond to the <lb/>analyzed RP and TQ drugs. <lb/>3.2.2 Linearity <lb/>The validation parameters for RP and TQ were evaluated <lb/>in accordance with the ICH guidelines. Standard solutions <lb/>of RP and TQ were prepared and injected using the pre-<lb/>viously described UPLC method outlined in Section 3.1. Figure <lb/>S1 shows the overlay chromatograms obtained from the <lb/>injected RP and TQ standard solutions. Theoretical drug <lb/>concentrations were plotted against the corresponding <lb/>detected peak areas for RP and TQ, as depicted in Figure S1. <lb/>The resulting calibration curves for RP and TQ demonstrated <lb/>excellent linearity, as indicated by the coefficient of regres-<lb/>sion. The calibration curve for RP showed a linear relationship <lb/>with an r 2 value of 0.9995 within the studied range of 0.5-50 <lb/>ppm (Figure S2 and Table 1). The equation of the calibration <lb/>curve, obtained with software, can be expressed as follows: y = <lb/>267.6 × x + 24.63. Table 2 presents the back calculation results <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP  </note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <body>of the injected replicates. The residual plot in Figure S2 indi-<lb/>cates that the collected data were randomly scattered around <lb/>the zero line, further confirming the linearity of the obtained <lb/>results. <lb/>Regarding TQ, the standard calibration curve was estab-<lb/>lished within the selected range of 0.05-50 ppm (Figure S2). <lb/>Regression analysis revealed a calculated correlation coef-<lb/>ficient (r 2 ) of 0.9998, indicating excellent linearity across <lb/>the studied range. The equation of the calibration curve <lb/>for TQ is represented as Y = 875.9X -2.83. Additionally, <lb/>Figure S2 illustrates the residual plot, confirming the line-<lb/>arity of the calibration curve by displaying a random dis-<lb/>tribution of data points around the zero line. Based on <lb/>these findings, the developed method can be deemed reli-<lb/>able for the simultaneous determination of RP and TQ <lb/>concentrations. <lb/>Figure 3: Detected chromatograms of (a) RP standard solution and (b) TQ standard solution along with their corresponding UV spectra. <lb/></body>

    <page>6</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>3.2.3 LOD and LLOQ <lb/>The LODs for RP and TQ were estimated via the calculated <lb/>slope of intercept method from the constructed calibration <lb/>curve and found to be 0.57 and 0.24 μg/mL, respectively. <lb/>Correspondingly, the calculated LLOQs for both drugs were <lb/>determined to be 1.73 and 0.73 μg/mL for RP and TQ, respec-<lb/>tively. Moreover, the quality control sample prepared to <lb/>represent LLOQ demonstrated good inter-day accuracy <lb/>with % recoveries of 96.92 and 102.2 for RP and TQ, respec-<lb/>tively. Additionally, the calculated RSD% found to be 1.56 <lb/>and 6.12 for RP and TQ, respectively, indicates the accep-<lb/>table precision of the developed UPLC method. <lb/>3.2.4 Accuracy and precision <lb/>To estimate the accuracy of the developed method, percen-<lb/>tage recovery was calculated following the injection of <lb/>quality control samples. In addition, the precision of the <lb/>developed UPLC method was assessed to determine its <lb/>Table 1: Linear regression analysis of RP and TQ via the developed UPLC <lb/>method <lb/>Parameter <lb/>RP <lb/>TQ <lb/>Linearity range (μg/mL) <lb/>1.5-50 <lb/>0.5-50 <lb/>Correlation coefficient (r 2 ) <lb/>0.9995 <lb/>0.9998 <lb/>LOD (μg/mL) <lb/>0.57 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>LLOQ (μg/mL) <lb/>1.73 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>Table 2: Percent recovery of RP and TQ <lb/>Theoretical <lb/>concentration <lb/>(μg/mL) <lb/>Mean <lb/>(μg/mL) <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>(%) <lb/>Precision <lb/>(RSD %) <lb/>RP <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>97.78 <lb/>3.85 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.47 <lb/>98.67 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>5 <lb/>4.97 <lb/>99.33 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>7.63 <lb/>101.78 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>20 <lb/>20.03 <lb/>100.17 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>50 <lb/>49.87 <lb/>99.73 <lb/>1.27 <lb/>TQ <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>94.00 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>93.33 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.43 <lb/>95.56 <lb/>3.85 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.43 <lb/>97.33 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>5 <lb/>4.93 <lb/>98.67 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>7.50 <lb/>100.00 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>20 <lb/>19.97 <lb/>99.83 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>50 <lb/>50.23 <lb/>100.47 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>Table 3: Intra-and inter-day precision for the analysis of RP and TQ <lb/>Quality <lb/>control <lb/>sample <lb/>Intra-day accuracy and <lb/>precision <lb/>Inter-day accuracy and <lb/>precision <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>(%) <lb/>Precision <lb/>(RSD%) <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>(%) <lb/>Precision <lb/>(RSD%) <lb/>RM <lb/>1.5 μg/mL <lb/>97.37 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>96.26 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>4.5 μg/mL <lb/>92.67 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>91.94 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>10.0 μg/mL <lb/>92.1 <lb/>4.65 <lb/>91.56 <lb/>3.37 <lb/>17.5 μg/mL <lb/>105.17 <lb/>3.78 <lb/>106.36 <lb/>3.17 <lb/>40.0 μg/mL <lb/>100.9 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>100.76 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>TQ <lb/>0.5 μg/mL <lb/>105 <lb/>3.82 <lb/>102.12 <lb/>6.12 <lb/>1.5 μg/mL <lb/>96.7 <lb/>4.63 <lb/>96.66 <lb/>3.62 <lb/>10.0 μg/mL <lb/>95.17 <lb/>3.65 <lb/>94.56 <lb/>2.75 <lb/>17.5 μg/mL <lb/>104.73 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>105.52 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>40.0 μg/mL <lb/>100.17 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>100.34 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>Figure 4: Chromatograms of matrix extraction (RP-free bioactive SNEDDS formulation without BCO) against the counterpart spiked with (a) RP and <lb/>(b) TQ. The detections were at 210 and 254 nm, respectively. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP  </note>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <body>repeatability. Five quality control samples were prepared <lb/>for RP, consisting of concentrations of 1.5, 4.5, 10.0, 17.5, and <lb/>40.0 μg/mL, representing LLOQ, 3LLOQ, 20% upper limit, 35% <lb/>upper limit, and 80% upper limit, respectively. Similarly, <lb/>quality control samples were prepared for TQ with concen-<lb/>trations of 0.5, 1.5, 10.0, 17.5, and 40.0, representing LLOQ, <lb/>3LLOQ, 20% upper limit, 35% upper limit, and 80% upper <lb/>limit, respectively. Table 3 presents the % recovery of these <lb/>five concentrations with RSD % for intra-and inter-day mea-<lb/>surements. The % recovery was found to range from 91.6 to <lb/>106.4%, and RSD% was less than 6.2%. <lb/>3.2.5 Stability of the calibration curve in a freezer <lb/>In order to assess the stability of the prepared calibration <lb/>curve in a freezer, two concentrations (5 and 20 μg/mL) <lb/>were chosen. The drug solutions were stored in amber <lb/>vials with tight screw caps. Figure 5 illustrates the percen-<lb/>tage recovery of the injected drug concentrations over a <lb/>2-week period. As shown in the figure, the recovered drug <lb/>concentrations remained within the range of 90-110% <lb/>after 1 week of storage, affirming the reliability of utilizing <lb/>standard solutions for daily routine analysis. However, an <lb/>Figure 5: Histograms of back-calculated concentrations for the standard solution of (a) Ramipril and (b) Thymoquinone stored in the refrigerator for 2 weeks. <lb/>Figure 6: Chromatograms obtained from the forced degradation study, including (a and b) thermally treated, (c and d) acid-treated, (e and f) alkaline-<lb/>treated, and (g and h) oxidative samples of RP and TQ, respectively. <lb/></body>

    <page>8</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>additional week of storage (a total of 2 weeks) led to a <lb/>significant decrease in drug concentrations. Consequently, <lb/>it is recommended to prepare a fresh standard solution <lb/>each week to ensure the accuracy of back-calculated data <lb/>based on the constructed calibration curve. <lb/>3.3 Forced degradation study <lb/>To investigate the effects of acid, alkaline, thermal, and <lb/>oxidative hydrolysis on the prepared stock solutions of <lb/>RP and TQ, they were incubated with 1 N hydrochloric <lb/>acid, 1 N sodium hydroxide, pure water, and 6% hydrogen <lb/>peroxide, respectively. The samples were then heated at <lb/>80 °C for 2 h to accelerate hydrolysis under the tested condi-<lb/>tions. Notably, the alkali-forced degradation study observed <lb/>complete degradation of RP and TQ. Consequently, the sam-<lb/>ples were incubated at room temperature for approximately <lb/>15 min to detect the original parent peaks along with their <lb/>corresponding degradation products. Figure 6 displays the <lb/>chromatograms obtained following RP and TQ hydrolysis <lb/>studies. Furthermore, the resolution value exceeded 1.5, <lb/>indicating that both drugs were well separated without <lb/>any interference [37]. These findings suggest that the devel-<lb/>oped method can accurately quantify both drugs even in the <lb/>presence of degradation products. In addition, Table 4 sum-<lb/>marizes the previously published stability-indicating <lb/>methods in terms of the mobile phase used, column <lb/>type, run time, and detected wavelength. Our method <lb/>demonstrates a significantly shorter run time of just <lb/>3.5 min while effectively detecting both drugs and their <lb/>degradation products, showcasing its superiority over <lb/>the previously published methods. <lb/>3.4 Pharmaceutical application in <lb/>characterization of developed SNEDDS <lb/>formulation <lb/>To assess the pharmaceutical characteristics of the pre-<lb/>pared RP-loaded bioactive SNEDDS formulation, its mixed <lb/>components were examined for their ability to sponta-<lb/>neously form a nanoemulsion upon exposure to aqueous <lb/>media in the gastrointestinal tract (GIT). The formulated <lb/>mixture was diluted and mixed using a magnetic stirrer <lb/>for a duration of 5 min. Subsequently, the particle size of <lb/>the resulting dispersion system was measured using a <lb/>Zetasizer, as depicted in Figure 7. It was observed that <lb/>the dispersed system exhibited a nanosize range, with a <lb/>Table 4: Published stability-indicating methods used quantification of RP and TQ <lb/>Drug name <lb/>Mobile phase <lb/>Stationary phase <lb/>Run time (min) <lb/>Detection wavelength (nm) <lb/>References <lb/>RP <lb/>ACN + 100 mM sodium perchlorate solution (pH 2.5) <lb/>SUPELCOSIL LC-8 column <lb/>8 <lb/>210 <lb/>[38] <lb/>10 mM ammonium acetate buffer (pH 6) + methanol <lb/>cyanopropyl column <lb/>15 <lb/>210 <lb/>[39] <lb/>ACN + water <lb/>C18 column <lb/>7 <lb/>215 <lb/>[40] <lb/>ACN + 50 mM ammonium acetate <lb/>XBridge C18 column <lb/>6 <lb/>240 <lb/>[41] <lb/>ACN + 4.5 M sodium lauryl sulfate as buffer <lb/>Zorbax XDB-C18 column <lb/>3 <lb/>210 <lb/>[34] <lb/>0.1% Sodium lauryl sulfate + ACN <lb/>Acquity UPLC HSS T3 column <lb/>3.25 <lb/>210 <lb/>Current work <lb/>TQ <lb/>Water + ACN <lb/>HSS-T3 C18 column <lb/>3.5 <lb/>294 <lb/>[42] <lb/>0.1% Formic acid + methanol <lb/>C18 column <lb/>12.5 <lb/>254 <lb/>[43] <lb/>0.1% Sodium lauryl sulfate + ACN <lb/>Acquity UPLC HSS T3 column <lb/>3.25 <lb/>254 <lb/>Current work <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP </note>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    <body>PDI value lower than 0.3, indicating the uniformity and <lb/>homogeneity of the dispersion system [44,45]. This finding <lb/>suggests that the prepared formulation has the potential to <lb/>enhance the bioavailability of both RP and TQ, leading to <lb/>improved therapeutic outcomes in the treatment of hyper-<lb/>tension [46,47]. <lb/>Figure 7: Histogram of particle size distribution of RP-loaded bioactive SNEDDS formulation dispersed in distilled water (1:1,000). <lb/>Figure 8: Chromatograms obtained from RP-and TQ-loaded bioactive SNEDDS incubated at 40°C with 75% RH for 2 months. <lb/></body>

    <page>10</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <body>3.5 Application of UPLC <lb/>According to the existing literature, both RP and TQ are <lb/>known to be sensitive to heat and humidity [48,49]. To <lb/>assess the stability of the prepared RP-loaded bioactive <lb/>SNEDDS, an accelerated study was conducted by subjecting <lb/>it to incubation at 40°C/75%RH, aimed at enhancing the degra-<lb/>dation of RP and TQ. Both drugs were extracted from the <lb/>incubated formulation and subsequently injected to evaluate <lb/>the capability of the established method to distinguish the <lb/>parent drug peaks from the resulting degradation products. <lb/>Figure 8 illustrates the chromatograms of stability samples at <lb/>the selected channels (210 and 254 nm) used for the detection <lb/>of RP and TQ, respectively. The figure clearly demonstrates <lb/>that RP was completely degraded, as no peak was detected at <lb/>the drug&apos;s retention time. On the other hand, TQ&apos;s peak was <lb/>detected in the corresponding channel, with no detected <lb/>degradation. Therefore, it can be concluded that the developed <lb/>method successfully separated and quantified RP and TQ even <lb/>in the presence of degradation products. The detected degra-<lb/>dation products were subjected to mass scanning in order to <lb/>identify their respective molecular weights. Figure 9 displays <lb/>the molecular weights of the degradation products at 0.87, <lb/>1.00, and 2.76 min, which were measured as 156.98, 389.16, <lb/>and 399.23, respectively. The molecular weight 421.18 can be <lb/>assumed to be the sodium adduct of 398.22. The molecular <lb/>weights of the three degradation products were extra con-<lb/>firmed by in silico Zeneth software. The Zeneth RP degradation <lb/>prediction model suggests that the main factors responsible for <lb/>RP degradation are amide hydrolysis, alkyl ester hydrolysis, <lb/>and lactamization of the amino acid or derivative. <lb/>The results are displayed in Table 5, showing the mole-<lb/>cular weights of the degradation products, the stress con-<lb/>dition for their formation, and the transformation name. <lb/>Figure 9: Mass spectra of detected degradation products at (a) 0.87, (b) 1.00, and (c) 2.76 min. <lb/>Table 5: Practically observed and theoretically predicted degradation <lb/>products by Zeneth software for RP <lb/>Name Transformation name <lb/>Conditions <lb/>Exact mass <lb/>D1 <lb/>Hydrolysis of amide <lb/>Water; pH <lb/>155.0946 <lb/>D2 <lb/>Hydrolysis of alkyl ester <lb/>Water; pH <lb/>388.1998 <lb/>D3 <lb/>Lactamization of the <lb/>amino acid or derivative <lb/>pH, Temperature 398.2206 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP </note>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    <body>3.6 In silico toxicity prediction of the alkaline <lb/>degradation products of RP <lb/>The toxicity and mutagenicity of the alkaline degradation <lb/>products of RP were estimated using the Derek (version <lb/>6.3). Table 6 presents the results of toxicity and mutagenicity <lb/>studies performed. Predictions were generated by employing <lb/>various criteria, encompassing humans, monkeys, pigs, dogs, <lb/>rabbits, guinea hamsters, mice, primates, rats, bacteria, and <lb/>Salmonella typhimurium. Multiple endpoints, including carcino-<lb/>genicity, chromosomal damage, hepatotoxicity, skin sensitiza-<lb/>tion, teratogenicity, nephrotoxicity, neurotoxicity, phototoxicity, <lb/>phospholipidosis, and numerous disorders, were calculated <lb/>as part of the analysis. The following conclusions are here: the <lb/>first degradation product of PR (retention time = 1.00 min) <lb/>was anticipated to induce hepatotoxicity and teratogenicity <lb/>due to N-acyl-pyrrolidine, -piperidine, or their analogue. But <lb/>this group was also found in RP; accordingly, the toxicity of <lb/>other alkaline degradation products is comparable to the <lb/>main drug. The other two degradation products (retention <lb/>times = 0.87 and 2.76 min) showed no toxicity. <lb/>4 Conclusions <lb/>A validated UPLC method for the simultaneous estimation <lb/>of RP and TQ and their degradation products has been <lb/>successfully established. The results obtained from method <lb/>validation demonstrated good linearity, accuracy, and pre-<lb/>cision, ensuring the reliability of the developed method. <lb/>Furthermore, our proposed RP-loaded bioactive SNEDDS <lb/>formulation displayed the ability to form a nanoemulsion <lb/>upon dispersion. Standard solutions of RP and TQ were <lb/>subjected to various stress conditions, including acid, alka-<lb/>line, thermal, and oxidative hydrolysis, to evaluate the <lb/>stability and degradation behavior of the drugs. The devel-<lb/>oped method effectively separated the parent drug peaks <lb/>from the formed degradation products, enabling accurate <lb/>quantification. Additionally, the validated method was <lb/>employed to estimate the levels of both drugs in the for-<lb/>mulation after exposure to these stress conditions. <lb/>Moreover, we employed the Derek software to evaluate <lb/>the in silico toxicity of the alkaline degradation products <lb/>of RP. The predicted outcomes indicated limited toxicity, <lb/>notably hepatotoxicity and teratogenicity, associated with <lb/>the first degradation product. The present study revealed <lb/>that the developed UPLC method indicated that direct con-<lb/>tact between the SNEDDS formulation and RP resulted in the <lb/>formation of toxicological degradation products during sto-<lb/>rage. Therefore, an alternative approach should be used to <lb/>enhance the dissolution and bioavailability of RP with no <lb/>impact on the safety of treated patients. <lb/></body>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: The authors extend their appreciation <lb/>to Researchers Supporting Project number (RSPD2024R1002), <lb/>King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding information: The authors extend their apprecia-<lb/>tion to Researchers Supporting Project number (RSPD2024R1002), <lb/>King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions: Conceptualization -E.M.E., A.A.S., <lb/>and M.K.; methodology -E.M.E. and A.Y.S.; software -<lb/>E.M.E., A.Y.S., and H.W.D.; validation -E.M.E.; formal <lb/></div>

    <body>Table 6: Toxicity and mutagenicity prediction of alkaline degradation products of RP <lb/>Derek <lb/>Chemical structure <lb/>Structural alert code <lb/>Structural alert <lb/>Endpoints for toxicity <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>N <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>562 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>Teratogenicity <lb/>614 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>Hepatotoxicity <lb/>OH <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>No detected toxicity <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>No detected toxicity <lb/></body>

    <page>12</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">analysis -E.M.E.; investigation -E.M.E., A.Y.S., and A.A.S.; <lb/>resources -M.K.; data curation -E.M.E.; writing -original <lb/>draft preparation -E.M.E., A.Y.S., and H.W.D.; writing -<lb/>review and editing -E.M.E., A.A.S., A.Y.S., and M.A.; visua-<lb/>lization -E.M.E. and A.Y.S.; supervision -E.M.E.; project <lb/>administration -E.M.E.; funding acquisition -E.M.E. All <lb/>authors have read and agreed to the published version of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest: The authors state no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethical approval: The conducted research is not related to <lb/>either human or animal use. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement: Data will be made available <lb/>on request. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Bhalani DV, Nutan B, Kumar A, Singh Chandel AK. Bioavailability <lb/>enhancement techniques for poorly aqueous soluble drugs and <lb/>therapeutics. Biomedicines. 2022;10(9):2055. <lb/>[2] Kesharwani R, Jaiswal P, Patel DK, Yadav PK. Lipid-based drug <lb/>delivery system (LBDDS): An emerging paradigm to enhance oral <lb/>bioavailability of poorly soluble drugs. Biomed Mater Devices. <lb/>2023;1(2):648-63. <lb/>[3] Kumar M, Kumar D, Kumar S, Kumar A, Mandal UK. A recent review <lb/>on bio-availability enhancement of poorly water-soluble drugs by <lb/>using bioenhancer and nanoparticulate drug delivery system. Curr <lb/>Pharm Des. 2022;28(39):3212-24. <lb/>[4] Wu Y, Levons J, Narang AS, Raghavan K, Rao VM. Reactive impu-<lb/>rities in excipients: Profiling, identification and mitigation of dru-<lb/>g-excipient incompatibility. Aaps Pharmscitech. 2011;12:1248-63. <lb/>[5] Bharate SS, Bharate SB, Bajaj AN. Interactions and incompatibilities <lb/>of pharmaceutical excipients with active pharmaceutical ingredi-<lb/>ents: A comprehensive review. J Excip Food Chem. 2016;1(3):3-26. <lb/>[6] Sharma A, Madhunapantula SV, Robertson GP. Toxicological con-<lb/>siderations when creating nanoparticle-based drugs and drug <lb/>delivery systems. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol. 2012;8(1):47-69. <lb/>[7] Vuong AD, Annis LG. Ramipril for the prevention and treatment of <lb/>cardiovascular disease. Ann Pharmacother. 2003;37(3):412-9. <lb/>[8] Abouelkheir M. Evaluation of dual inhibitory effect of anagliptin, <lb/>ramipril and lisinopril on angiotensin-converting enzyme and DPP-<lb/>4 activities. Curr Mol Pharmacol. 2022;15(3):582-8. <lb/>[9] Shafiq S, Shakeel F, Talegaonkar S, Ahmad FJ, Khar RK, Ali M. Design <lb/>and development of oral oil in water ramipril nanoemulsion for-<lb/>mulation: In vitro and in vivo assessment. J Biomed Nanotechnol. <lb/>2007;3(1):28-44. <lb/>[10] Alhasani KF, Kazi M, Ibrahim MA, Shahba AA, Alanazi FK. Self-<lb/>nanoemulsifying ramipril tablets: A novel delivery system for the <lb/>enhancement of drug dissolution and stability. Int J Nanomed. <lb/>2019;5435-48. <lb/>[11] Madhavi K, Shikha A, Yadav JK. Self-nano emulsifying drug delivery <lb/>system of ramipril: Formulation and in vitro evaluation. Int J Pharm <lb/>Pharm Sci. 2016;8(4):291-6. <lb/>[12] Jayapal N, Vishnu YV. Formulation and in vivo evaluation of self-<lb/>nanoemulsifying drug delivery system of ramipril in wistar rats. <lb/>Asian J Pharm Clin Res. 2021;14(7):126-36. <lb/>[13] Shahba AA-W, Sherif AY, Elzayat EM, Kazi M. Combined ramipril and <lb/>black seed oil dosage forms using bioactive self-nanoemulsifying <lb/>drug delivery systems (BIO-SNEDDSs). Pharmaceuticals. <lb/>2022;15(9):1120. <lb/>[14] Shafiq S, Shakeel F. Effect of labrasol on self-nanoemulsification <lb/>efficiency of ramipril nanoemulsion. Die Pharmazie-Int J Pharm Sci. <lb/>2009;64(12):812-7. <lb/>[15] Shafiq S, Shakeel F. Stability and self-nanoemulsification efficiency <lb/>of ramipril nanoemulsion containing labrasol and plurol oleique. <lb/>Clin Res Regul Aff. 2010;27(1):7-12. <lb/>[16] Kazi M, Alhajri A, Alshehri SM, Elzayat EM, Al Meanazel OT, <lb/>Shakeel F, et al. Enhancing oral bioavailability of apigenin using a <lb/>bioactive self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (Bio-SNEDDS): <lb/>In vitro, in vivo and stability evaluations. Pharmaceutics. <lb/>2020;12(8):749. <lb/>[17] Kazi M, Shahba AA, Alrashoud S, Alwadei M, Sherif AY, Alanazi FK. <lb/>Bioactive self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery systems (Bio-SNEDDS) <lb/>for combined oral delivery of curcumin and piperine. Molecules. <lb/>2020;25(7):1703. <lb/>[18] Yimer EM, Tuem KB, Karim A, Ur-Rehman N, Anwar F. Nigella sativa <lb/>L.(black cumin): A promising natural remedy for wide range of <lb/>illnesses. Evid-Based Complement Altern Med. 2019;2019:1-16. <lb/>[19] Majeed A, Muhammad Z, Ahmad H, Hayat SSS, Inayat N, Siyyar S. <lb/>Nigella sativa L.: Uses in traditional and contemporary <lb/>medicines-An overview. Acta Ecol Sin. 2021;41(4):253-8. <lb/>[20] Shoaei-Hagh P, Kamelan Kafi F, Najafi S, Zamanzadeh M, Heidari <lb/>Bakavoli A, Ramezani J, et al. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-<lb/>controlled, clinical trial to evaluate the benefits of Nigella sativa <lb/>seeds oil in reducing cardiovascular risks in hypertensive patients. <lb/>Phytother Res. 2021;35(8):4388-400. <lb/>[21] Fallah Huseini H, Amini M, Mohtashami R, Ghamarchehre M, <lb/>Sadeqhi Z, Kianbakht S, et al. Blood pressure lowering effect of Nigella <lb/>sativa L. seed oil in healthy volunteers: A randomized, double-blind, <lb/>placebo-controlled clinical trial. Phytother Res. 2013;27(12):1849-53. <lb/>[22] Dehkordi FR, Kamkhah AF. Antihypertensive effect of Nigella sativa <lb/>seed extract in patients with mild hypertension. Fundam Clin <lb/>Pharmacol. 2008;22(4):447-52. <lb/>[23] Sherif AY, Shahba AA-W. Development of a multifunctional oral <lb/>dosage form via integration of solid dispersion technology with a <lb/>black seed oil-based self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system. <lb/>Biomedicines. 2023;11(10):2733. <lb/>[24] Ahmad A, Raish M, Alkharfy KM. The potential role of thymoqui-<lb/>none in preventing the cardiovascular complications of COVID-19. <lb/>Vasc Pharmacol. 2021;141:106899. <lb/>[25] Enayatfard L, Mohebbati R, Niazmand S, Hosseini M, Shafei MN. <lb/>The standardized extract of Nigella sativa and its major ingredient, <lb/>thymoquinone, ameliorates angiotensin II-induced hypertension in <lb/>rats. J Basic Clin Physiol Pharmacol. 2018;30(1):51-8. <lb/>[26] Rathore C, Hemrajani C, Sharma AK, Gupta PK, Jha NK, Aljabali AA, <lb/>et al. Self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (SNEDDS) <lb/>mediated improved oral bioavailability of thymoquinone: optimi-<lb/>zation, characterization, pharmacokinetic, and hepatotoxicity stu-<lb/>dies. Drug Deliv Transl Res. 2023;13(1):292-307. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Stability UPLC-DAD method and in silico prediction toxicological degradation products of RP  </note>

    <page>13 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>[27] Devrukhakar PS, Shankar MS, Shankar G, Srinivas R. A stability-<lb/>indicating LC-MS/MS method for zidovudine: Identification, char-<lb/>acterization and toxicity prediction of two major acid degradation <lb/>products. J Pharm Anal. 2017;7(4):231-6. <lb/>[28] Guideline IH, editor. Assessment and control of dna reactive <lb/>(mutagenic) impurities in pharmaceuticals to limit potential carci-<lb/>nogenic risk M7. International conference on harmonization of <lb/>technical requirements for registration of pharmaceuticals for <lb/>human use (ICH). Geneva; 2014. <lb/>[29] Ali AM, Alanazi MM, Attwa MW, Darwish HW. Selective stability <lb/>indicating liquid chromatographic method based on quality by <lb/>design framework and in silico toxicity assessment for infigratinib <lb/>and its degradation products. Molecules. 2023;28(22):7476. <lb/>[30] Nazlı H, Mesut B, Özsoy Y. In vitro evaluation of a solid supersaturated <lb/>self nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (Super-SNEDDS) of aprepi-<lb/>tant for enhanced solubility. Pharmaceuticals. 2021;14(11):1089. <lb/>[31] Proença P, Mustra C, Marcos M, Franco JM, Corte-Real F, Vieira DN. <lb/>Validated UPLC-MS/MS assay for the determination of synthetic <lb/>phosphodiesterase type-5 inhibitors in postmortem blood samples. <lb/>J Forensic Leg Med. 2013;20(6):655-8. <lb/>[32] Ibrahim M, Alhabib NA, Alshora D, Bekhit MMS, Taha E, Mahdi WA, <lb/>et al. Application of quality by design approach in the optimization and <lb/>development of the UPLC analytical method for determination of <lb/>fusidic acid in pharmaceutical products. Separations. 2023;10(5):318. <lb/>[33] Shahba AA, Alanazi FK, Mohsin K, Abdel-Hamid M. Stability <lb/>assessment of cinnarizine in self-emulsifying drug delivery sys-<lb/>tems. Lat Am J Pharm. 2012;31(4):549-54. <lb/>[34] Seshadri RK, Desai MM, Raghavaraju TV, Krishnan D, Rao DV, <lb/>Chakravarthy IE. Simultaneous quantitative determination of <lb/>metoprolol, atorvastatin and ramipril in capsules by a validated <lb/>stability-indicating RP-UPLC method. Sci Pharm. 2010;78(4):821-34. <lb/>[35] Kazi M, Shariare MH, Al-Bgomi M, Hussain MD, Alanazi FK. <lb/>Simultaneous determination of curcumin (Cur) and thymoquinone <lb/>(THQ) in lipid based self-nanoemulsifying systems and its applica-<lb/>tion to the commercial product using UHPLC-UV-Vis spectrophot-<lb/>ometer. Curr Pharm Anal. 2018;14(3):277-85. <lb/>[36] Elzayat EM, Ibrahim MF, Abdel-Rahman AA, Ahmed SM, Alanazi FK, <lb/>Habib WA. A validated stability-indicating UPLC method for deter-<lb/>mination of diclofenac sodium in its pure form and matrix formu-<lb/>lations. Arab J Chem. 2017;10:S3245-54. <lb/>[37] Al-Rifai N, Alshishani A, Darras F, Taha O, Abu-Jalloud S, Shaghlil L, <lb/>et al. Solriamfetol impurities: Synthesis, characterization, and analy-<lb/>tical method (UPLC-UV) validation. J Pharm Anal. 2023;13(4):403-11. <lb/>[38] Belal F, Al-Zaagi I, Gadkariem E, Abounassif M. A stability-indicating <lb/>LC method for the simultaneous determination of ramipril and <lb/>hydrochlorothiazide in dosage forms. J Pharm Biomed Anal. <lb/>2001;24(3):335-42. <lb/>[39] Elshanawane AA, Mostafa SM, Elgawish MS. Application of a vali-<lb/>dated, stability-indicating LC method to stress degradation studies <lb/>of ramipril and moexipril. HCl. Chromatographia. 2008;67:567-73. <lb/>[40] Lakshmi K, Sivasubramanian L. A stability indicating HPLC method <lb/>for the simultaneous determination of valsartan and ramipril in <lb/>binary combination. J Chil Chem Soc. 2010;55(2):223-6. <lb/>[41] Koralla S, Konidala SK, Rao KG, Begum SM. Stability indicating RP-<lb/>HPLC method for simultaneous estimation of ramipril and amlo-<lb/>dipine besylate in pharmaceutical dosage form. Asian J Pharm Res. <lb/>2016;6(4):242-9. <lb/>[42] Pathan SA, Jain GK, Zaidi SM, Akhter S, Vohora D, Chander P, et al. <lb/>Stability-indicating ultra-performance liquid chromatography <lb/>method for the estimation of thymoquinone and its application in <lb/>biopharmaceutical studies. Biomed Chromatogr. <lb/>2011;25(5):613-20. <lb/>[43] Soliman RM, Salam RAA, Eid BG, Khayyat A, Neamatallah T, <lb/>Mesbah MK, et al. Stability study of thymoquinone, carvacrol and <lb/>thymol using HPLC-UV and LC-ESI-MS. Acta Pharm. <lb/>2020;70(3):325-42. <lb/>[44] Danaei M, Dehghankhold M, Ataei S, Hasanzadeh Davarani F, <lb/>Javanmard R, Dokhani A, et al. Impact of particle size and poly-<lb/>dispersity index on the clinical applications of lipidic nanocarrier <lb/>systems. Pharmaceutics. 2018;10(2):57. <lb/>[45] Aguilar-Pérez KM, Medina DI, Parra-Saldívar R, Iqbal HM. Nano-size <lb/>characterization and antifungal evaluation of essential oil mole-<lb/>cules-loaded nanoliposomes. Molecules. 2022;27(17):5728. <lb/>[46] Shafiq S, Shakeel F, Talegaonkar S, Ahmad FJ, Khar RK, Ali M. <lb/>Development and bioavailability assessment of ramipril nanoe-<lb/>mulsion formulation. Eur J Pharm Biopharm. 2007;66(2):227-43. <lb/>[47] Khan R, Nautiyal H, Saleem S. Thymoquinone-loaded nanocarriers <lb/>for healthcare applications. Biomarkers as targeted herbal drug <lb/>discovery. Apple Academic Press; 2021. p. 301-22. <lb/>[48] Agbaria R, Gabarin A, Dahan A, Ben-Shabat S. Anticancer activity of <lb/>Nigella sativa (black seed) and its relationship with the thermal <lb/>processing and quinone composition of the seed. Drug Des Dev <lb/>Ther. 2015;9:3119-24. <lb/>[49] Shafiq S, Shakeel F, Talegaonkar S, Khar RK, Ali M. Nanoemulsion as <lb/>carrier for stability enhancement of ramipril. J Dispers Sci Technol. <lb/>2010;31(7):975-9. <lb/></listBibl>

    <page>14</page>

    <note place="headnote"> Ehab M. Elzayat et al. </note>

	</text>

</TEI>