<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T16:10:10.565Z">11/24/2025 4:10:10 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T16:09:58.033523Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T16:09:58.033523Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/cmc.2024.054377 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Hierarchical Privacy Protection Model in Advanced Metering Infrastructure <lb/>Based on Cloud and Fog Assistance <lb/>Linghong Kuang 1,2 , Wenlong Shi 1,2 and Jing Zhang 1,2,* <lb/>1 School of Computer Science and Mathematics, Fujian University of Technology, Fuzhou, 350118, China <lb/>2 Fujian Provincial Key Laboratory of Big Data Mining and Applications, Fuzhou, 350118, China <lb/>*Corresponding Author: Jing Zhang. Email: jing165455@126.com <lb/>Received: 26 May 2024 Accepted: 18 July 2024 Published: 15 August 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>The Advanced Metering Infrastructure (AMI), as a crucial subsystem in the smart grid, is responsible for measuring <lb/>user electricity consumption and plays a vital role in communication between providers and consumers. However, <lb/>with the advancement of information and communication technology, new security and privacy challenges have <lb/>emerged for AMI. To address these challenges and enhance the security and privacy of user data in the smart <lb/>grid, a Hierarchical Privacy Protection Model in Advanced Metering Infrastructure based on Cloud and Fog <lb/>Assistance (HPPM-AMICFA) is proposed in this paper. The proposed model integrates cloud and fog computing <lb/>with hierarchical threshold encryption, offering a flexible and efficient privacy protection solution that significantly <lb/>enhances data security in the smart grid. The methodology involves setting user protection levels by processing <lb/>missing data and utilizing fuzzy comprehensive analysis to evaluate user importance, thereby assigning appropriate <lb/>protection levels. Furthermore, a hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm is developed to provide differentiated <lb/>protection strategies for fog nodes based on user IDs, ensuring secure aggregation and encryption of user <lb/>data. Experimental results demonstrate that HPPM-AMICFA effectively resists various attack strategies while <lb/>minimizing time costs, thereby safeguarding user data in the smart grid. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>AMI; cloud and fog assistance; fuzzy comprehensive analysis; hierarchical threshold encryption <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Smart Grid (SG) is a modern infrastructure of Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS), encompassing <lb/>multiple domains and facilitating services across seven key areas: power transformation, dispatching, <lb/>consumption, distribution, transmission, generation, and communications [1]. As shown in Fig. 1, the <lb/>SG consists of digital and electrical technologies that communicate and transfer information from one <lb/>device to another [2]. The core unit of the smart grid is the AMI, facilitating bi-directional communi-<lb/>cation and interaction between power consumers and suppliers, while optimizing the organizational <lb/>structure between power loads and supply systems. Given the characteristics of the AMI system, the <lb/>primary distinction between smart grids and traditional power grids lies in the increasing integration <lb/></body>

	<page>3194 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>of power and information networks, leading to a broader spectrum of services. However, concurrently, <lb/>smart grids face escalating privacy and security risks. <lb/>Figure 1: Main components of a smart grid system <lb/>In the smart grid, AMI can provide necessary technical and platform support for energy storage, <lb/>demand response management, real-time interaction, etc. However, despite offering intelligent ser-<lb/>vices, AMI also confronts substantial privacy and security challenges, including hacker attacks, energy <lb/>fraud, and other criminal activities that may result in power outages, leading to significant economic <lb/>losses for power companies and even posing serious impacts on people&apos;s lives [3]. To address the prob-<lb/>lem of privacy leakage in SG, researchers typically employ methods such as anonymity, encryption, <lb/>homomorphic aggregation, and differential privacy. Wang et al. [4] propose a novel privacy-preserving <lb/>data aggregation scheme (PDAM) for IoT-enabled smart grids. This scheme supports efficient data <lb/>source authentication, integrity checking, and secure dynamic user management including join and <lb/>exit procedures. Wang et al. [5] initially cluster raw user electricity data, and then enhance privacy <lb/>protection by combining the clustered data with an adaptive k-anonymity algorithm for optimized <lb/>clustering. This approach ensures comprehensive protection of users&apos; personal privacy information <lb/>and enables real-time collection of electricity consumption data. Hu et al. [6] propose an efficient and <lb/>privacy-preserving data aggregation and trust management scheme (PATM) for IoT smart grid based <lb/>on smart contracts. Various existing methods such as signature authentication, differential privacy, <lb/>and encryption have been studied and designed to address privacy and security concerns in smart <lb/>grids, effectively safeguarding users&apos; personal information from potential attacks [7-9]. <lb/>Unfortunately, there are still some problems in the privacy and security protection of smart <lb/>grids, such as (1) During the analysis, collection, and storage of power consumption information <lb/>within the AMI system, attackers may launch attacks on AMI nodes, leading to the theft of detailed <lb/>personal power consumption data [10,11]. (2) Existing privacy security protection methods often <lb/>overlook the diverse categories and complex characteristics of users. They tend to apply uniform <lb/>privacy protection methods to a large number of users in the SG, resulting in exorbitant costs and <lb/>inability to meet the real-time performance requirements of the SG [12]. (3) Simple privacy protection <lb/>strategies struggle to achieve comprehensive coverage of the AMI system, while complex strategies <lb/>often lack practicality. Given the immense volume of data and computational costs associated with <lb/>AMI, lightweight algorithms are preferable for practical implementation in the SG [13-15]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3195 <lb/></page>

	<body>In order to address the issues of privacy protection in smart grids, a Hierarchical Privacy <lb/>Protection Model in Advanced Metering Infrastructure based on Cloud and Fog Assistance is <lb/>proposed in this paper. The motivation of HPPM-AMICFA is shown intuitively in Fig. 2. Firstly, an <lb/>Advanced Metering Infrastructure based on Cloud and Fog Assistance (AMICFA) is designed, and <lb/>its existing privacy threats are elucidated to establish a foundation for subsequent privacy protection <lb/>solutions. Secondly, a fuzzy comprehensive analysis algorithm with entropy weight method is designed <lb/>to set user protection levels. Finally, a hierarchical threshold privacy protection algorithm is designed. <lb/>This algorithm sets different threshold values for users of varying protection levels based on their user <lb/>IDs, thereby ensuring tailored privacy protection for users. The main contributions of this study are <lb/>summarized as follows: <lb/>1. To address the issue of attackers potentially launching attacks on AMI nodes, a specific <lb/>AMICFA is proposed to better illustrate the privacy threat issue in AMI. By analyzing <lb/>potential security attacks that may occur at various stages of AMICFA, a solid research <lb/>foundation can be provided for the design of subsequent privacy protection methods. <lb/>2. To address the limitations of existing smart grid data protection methods, which ignore user <lb/>diversity and complexity, and to manage the large volume and high computational costs <lb/>of AMI privacy protection data, a dynamic threshold encryption model is proposed. This <lb/>model first employs a fuzzy comprehensive analysis algorithm to set user protection levels, <lb/>minimizing costs while providing tailored privacy protection. Subsequently, a hierarchical <lb/>threshold encryption algorithm is used based on these protection levels, offering a more <lb/>efficient and lightweight method for user privacy protection. <lb/>3. This article proposes a hierarchical privacy protection method with dynamic threshold. The <lb/>analysis of the model&apos;s ability to resist attacks under different attack strategies and the model&apos;s <lb/>runtime cost demonstrates the effectiveness of HPPM-AMICFA. <lb/>Figure 2: The motivation of HPPM-AMICFA. The AMICFA architecture consists of smart meters, fog <lb/>nodes, and cloud server. The red dashed arrows indicate potential privacy threats to AMICFA, while <lb/>the blue dashed arrows indicate encryption methods provided by Trusted authority for AMICFA <lb/></body>

	<page>3196 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>The rest of the paper is organized as follows: Section 2 reviews existing research related to our <lb/>work. The preliminaries are given in Section 3. The privacy protection method is designed in Section 4. <lb/>The simulation analysis is discussed to evaluate the effectiveness of HPPM-AMICFA in Section 5. <lb/>Finally, the conclusions and outlooks are presented in Section 6. <lb/>2 Related Work <lb/>In the smart grid, achieving bidirectional communication between power flow and information <lb/>flow relies heavily on the role of smart meters within the AMI system. Smart meters are pivotal as <lb/>they not only collect and process information but also facilitate command scheduling and terminal <lb/>data transmission. However, the electricity consumption data captured by smart meters, being <lb/>both real and real-time, contains significant amounts of personal privacy information. In recent <lb/>years, numerous scholars have explored privacy protection methods for smart grid data, including <lb/>anonymity, differential privacy, and encryption algorithms. <lb/>Electric power companies can utilize various pieces of information such as house numbers, <lb/>homeowner names, electricity usage behavior, and other data to potentially identify users&apos; personal <lb/>identities, as well as match their consumption patterns and lifestyles. Moreover, when combined <lb/>with anonymous information, other user data can facilitate data matching. Srinivas et al. [16] <lb/>design a novel anonymous signature-based authenticated key exchange scheme named AAS-IoTSG <lb/>specifically tailored for smart grid environments supporting the Internet of Things (IoT). AAS-IoTSG <lb/>offers enhanced security and functional features compared to existing state-of-the-art authentication <lb/>mechanisms in smart grid systems. Wu et al. [17] propose a privacy-preserving data aggregation scheme <lb/>tailored for smart grids, incorporating user anonymity and designated recipients. In this scheme, <lb/>smart meters gather users&apos; power consumption data, encrypt it using homomorphic re-encryption, <lb/>and anonymously transmit the ciphertext. Subsequently, an agent employs distributed re-encryption <lb/>to further encrypt the aggregated data, ensuring that only designated recipients can decrypt it. This <lb/>proposed scheme offers a more secure and flexible solution for privacy-preserving data aggregation <lb/>in smart grid environments. Chen et al. [18] propose a dual-blockchain-assisted secure anonymous <lb/>data aggregation scheme for fog-enabled smart grids, named DA-SADA. This scheme combines <lb/>Paillier encryption, batch aggregate signatures, and anonymous authentication to establish a secure <lb/>anonymous data aggregation mechanism with minimal computational overhead. Adewole et al. [19] <lb/>propose the DFTMicroagg algorithm, which provides dual perturbations to improve the anonymity <lb/>and privacy of smart grid data. This algorithm leverages the benefits of Discrete Fourier Transform <lb/>(DFT) and microaggregation to provide an additional layer of protection. In the context of identity <lb/>anonymity within smart grids, it is crucial not only to ensure the traceability of identity information but <lb/>also to safeguard the anonymity of user identities. However, achieving these goals in low-bandwidth <lb/>and low-capacity electricity meters presents significant challenges. <lb/>Differential privacy protection technology primarily involves the addition of random noise to <lb/>electricity data [20]. This approach helps to thwart attackers from obtaining centralized data. However, <lb/>excessive differential noise can potentially impair the availability of aggregated data. Hence, effectively <lb/>measuring both data availability and privacy is crucial in the context of differential protection <lb/>technology. Dwork [21] first proposes a method of obtaining differential privacy by adding random <lb/>noise, supported by rigorous mathematical proofs. Leveraging the properties of distributed differential <lb/>noise, a distributed protocol is introduced to generate multiple instances of random noise, thereby <lb/>fortifying defenses against malicious attacks, including those perpetrated by database administrators. <lb/>Zhao et al. [22] conduct a study on the privacy of smart meters utilizing differential privacy principles. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3197 <lb/></page>

	<body>They introduce a new random BLH algorithm aimed at ensuring differential privacy effectively. <lb/>Furthermore, they propose the Multitasking BLH Exp3 algorithm, which dynamically updates the <lb/>BLH algorithm based on context and constraints, thereby enhancing its adaptiveness. Gough et al. [23] <lb/>develop an innovative differential privacy compatible algorithm to ensure the protection of data from <lb/>consumer smart meters. This novel algorithm comprehensively examines the impact on the operation <lb/>of distribution networks, considering perspectives such as consumer electricity bills and the power <lb/>system. Gai et al. [24] propose a differential privacy aggregation scheme that operates without the <lb/>need for a trusted authority, thereby supporting dynamic user joining and exiting. Additionally, they <lb/>design a data discretization algorithm based on conditional probability, which effectively enhances <lb/>the accuracy of aggregated data. Zheng et al. [25] propose a decentralized mechanism for privacy <lb/>protection computation in smart grids, called DDP. This mechanism maintains differential privacy <lb/>while extending data cleaning from the range to the time domain. However, the high degree of <lb/>protection for differential privacy and the irreversible protection process may result in reduced data <lb/>availability. <lb/>Nowadays, encryption technology stands as a crucial tool for bolstering data confidentiality and <lb/>is widely employed for privacy protection both at the user and power supply ends of the smart grid. <lb/>Encryption technology is divided into symmetric-key algorithm and asymmetric encryption algorithm <lb/>[26]. Sarenche et al. [27] propose a protocol enabling the secure implementation of various double auc-<lb/>tion mechanisms in smart grids. In this scheme, to safeguard the anonymity and privacy of users, each <lb/>participant is allocated a pseudo-identity, and bids/asks are encrypted using the Paillier cryptosystem. <lb/>Chen et al. [28] propose a smart meter data aggregation scheme utilizing the Paillier homomorphic <lb/>cryptographic system. This scheme allows utility suppliers to aggregate the total consumption of all <lb/>smart meters, while preventing them from accessing the consumption data of individual smart meters. <lb/>Xu et al. [29] propose a privacy protection framework that implements homomorphic encryption with <lb/>trust boundaries for various Smart Meter System (SMS) scenarios as a system privacy protection <lb/>solution for SMS. Since blockchain-based industrial wireless sensor networks can provide secure <lb/>and resilient data transmission to promote intelligent integration, monitoring, and control of smart <lb/>grids, Faheem et al. [30] propose a smart contracts framework in Solana called Advanced Solana <lb/>Blockchain (ASB) for smart grids. This scheme can achieve resilient and secure real-time control <lb/>and monitoring in smart grids. Wang et al. [31] propose two efficient pairing-free ciphertext-policy <lb/>attribute-based schemes. These schemes eliminate computation-intensive bilinear pairing operations, <lb/>thereby enhancing their deployment efficiency in cloud-assisted smart grids. Fan et al. [32] innovatively <lb/>propose a searchable encryption scheme that supports multi keyword subset retrieval to share data <lb/>and reduce local storage on Cloud Edge End Orchestrated (CEEO) securely. Wu et al. [33] design <lb/>HTV-PRE, a homomorphic threshold proxy re-encryption scheme with re-encryption verifiability, <lb/>proposing a robust, lightweight data aggregation scheme with strong privacy protection for smart <lb/>grids. <lb/>Compared to previous network systems, the characteristics presented in the AMI system are <lb/>very unique. For instance, deploying AMI components in the public domain renders simple privacy <lb/>protection methods less effective due to weak security, while complex solutions may have certain <lb/>limitations. Moreover, given the substantial volume of data and computational costs associated with <lb/>AMI, it becomes imperative to explore more convenient and lightweight encryption methods based <lb/>on the design of security models when addressing security issues in AMI. <lb/></body>

	<page>3198 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>3 Preliminaries <lb/>In this section, firstly, some Definitions related to AMICFA will be introduced. Secondly, some <lb/>encryption algorithms will be introduced. <lb/>3.1 Definitions of AMICFA <lb/>The advanced metering infrastructure based on cloud and fog assistance consists of four types of <lb/>entities as shown in Fig. 2: a trusted authority, smart meters, fog nodes, and a cloud server. <lb/>Definition 1 Grid area. In this article, the power grid area is assumed to be divided into several <lb/>sub-regions. Each sub-region contains a group of meter users and is managed by a unique fog node. <lb/>Additionally, there is a single cloud server responsible for overall control of the entire power grid area. <lb/>The overall power grid area G can be represented as G = {(g 1 , . . . , g m ) , C}, where g represents the <lb/>sub-region, m represents the number of sub-regions, and C represents the cloud server. <lb/>Definition 2 Trusted authority. In this article, trusted authority is assumed to be a secure third-<lb/>party platform primarily responsible for generating keys and distributing them to all entities. <lb/>Definition 3 Smart meter. Smart meter users can be represented by SM ij , i ≤ m, j ≤ n, where n <lb/>represents the number of smart meters managed by each fog node. Each smart meter SM ij is capable of <lb/>generating real-time electricity consumption information for users, encrypting and signing the data, <lb/>and providing preliminary protection of personal information privacy. Subsequently, these encrypted <lb/>and signed data reports are transmitted to the corresponding fog nodes for aggregation. <lb/>Definition 4 Fog node. Fog node can be represented by f i , i ≤ m, and is considered to exist in the <lb/>middle of smart meters and cloud server, completing basic deployment operations at the edge of the <lb/>network. Due to the possibility of criminals attacking through identity forgery, data at the fog nodes <lb/>need to be verified through signature verification. <lb/>Definition 5 Cloud server. The cloud server C can decrypt and aggregate data, generate reports on <lb/>the electricity consumption of each sub-region, and send them to the fog nodes to reduce the resource <lb/>occupation of the cloud server. At the same time, since the fog nodes are located at the edge of the <lb/>network, users can achieve real-time querying of electricity consumption data with lower latency. <lb/>3.2 Encryption Algorithm <lb/>Definition 6 Secret sharing [34]. Secret sharing refers to a secure way of sharing secrets among <lb/>multiple participants, forming the basis of a threshold cryptography system. In a secret sharing scheme, <lb/>a secret S is divided into several pieces. The secret S is represented as S = s 1 , s 2 , . . . , s p , and each piece <lb/>s i is sent by the executor to a corresponding user u i from the user set U = u 1 , u 2 , . . . , u p . In this case, <lb/>it is necessary to aggregate the secret pieces of p individuals together in order to decrypt the value of <lb/>S. However, this scheme is relatively fragile, as the secret cannot be reconstructed if any participant is <lb/>absent. <lb/>Definition 7 Threshold secret sharing [35]. Based on considerations of portability and security in <lb/>secret sharing, Pang et al. propose a new (t, n) multi-secret sharing scheme. The basic idea of this <lb/>scheme is that if there are p secret pieces, only k (1 &lt; K &lt; n) personal information needs to be gathered <lb/>to obtain the original secret. Firstly, a polynomial of degree t -1 is generated, as shown in Eq. (1). <lb/>f (x) = a 0 + a 1 x + a 2 x 2 + . . . + a t-1 x t-1 <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3199 <lb/></page>

	<body>where a 0 is the secret number to be shared, and a 1 , a 2 , . . . , a t-1 is the random number generated by the <lb/>executor. Secondly, the secret a 0 needs to be shared and allocated to p users, as shown in Eq. (2). <lb/>s i = f (i) = <lb/>t-1 <lb/>j=0 <lb/>a j * i j , i = 0, 1, . . . , p <lb/>(2) <lb/>It can be seen that as long as any t of s 1 , s 2 , . . . , s p are put together, the secret S can be solved, <lb/>while any t -1 put together cannot obtain the exact solution of S, which meets the requirement of <lb/>(t, n) threshold key sharing. <lb/>Definition 8 Threshold encryption [36]. The threshold encryption scheme is a distributed encryption <lb/>and decryption protocol wherein any user can encrypt data using a public key. In this scheme, the <lb/>data contributor specifies multiple secret holders, and decryption can only be achieved when a certain <lb/>number of secret holders collaborate to aggregate the decryption pieces. Firstly, participants agree on <lb/>a threshold value t and obtain their own private key pieces r. They jointly calculate the data encryption <lb/>public key pk and make it public. Secondly, the data contributor encrypts the raw data R using <lb/>the public key pk, generating encrypted data E (R). Thirdly, participants decrypt E (R) using their <lb/>own private key pieces r to generate the decryption pieces D r (R). Finally, participants aggregate the <lb/>decryption pieces, and only when the aggregated decryption pieces D r (R) from different participants <lb/>are not less than the threshold t, can the decryption be completed, and the original data R be obtained. <lb/>4 HPPM-AMICFA <lb/>The specific process of HPPM-AMICFA proposed in this paper is shown in Fig. 3. Firstly, <lb/>the AMICFA is introduced. Next, protection levels of different users are set, including using fuzzy <lb/>data completion algorithms to complete missing data for users, and then using fuzzy comprehensive <lb/>evaluation algorithms to score the importance of different users to determine the protection levels. <lb/>Finally, user electricity consumption data privacy is protected using a hierarchical threshold encryp-<lb/>tion algorithm. The specific steps are as follows: <lb/>Step 1: The workflow of AMICFA is introduced and the privacy threats that exist within them <lb/>are analyzed. <lb/>Step 2: Missing data processing based on fuzzy data completion algorithm: For users with missing <lb/>data, firstly, take the user&apos;s incomplete power grid data as algorithm input. Then confirm the time <lb/>period and time point of the lost data, use a fuzzy logic algorithm to complete the data. Finally, obtain <lb/>the completed data as the algorithm output. <lb/>Step 3: Rating user importance based on fuzzy comprehensive evaluation algorithm: In order to <lb/>address the challenge of quantifying smart grid user data, smart grid users are initially classified into <lb/>four categories. The classification results and complete user data (including electricity consumption <lb/>levels) are used as inputs for the algorithm. This analysis aims to rate the importance of different users <lb/>and obtain their protection levels as the output of the algorithm. <lb/>Step 4: Protecting user privacy based on hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm: Firstly, <lb/>the user electricity consumption data and user protection levels are used as inputs to the algorithm. <lb/>Then, based on the user IDs and their corresponding different protection levels, different threshold <lb/>encryption strategies are set for each fog node to achieve encrypted protection of user privacy. Finally, <lb/>the algorithm will output privacy protected electricity consumption data. <lb/></body>

	<page>3200 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 3: The workflow of HPPM-AMICFA <lb/>4.1 AMICFA <lb/>4.1.1 Composition of AMICFA <lb/>The model of AMICFA proposed in this paper consists of four entities: a trusted authority, <lb/>smart meters, fog nodes, and a cloud server, as shown in Fig. 2. The trusted authority oversees <lb/>user registration and is responsible for generating system parameters and keys for each user. The <lb/>cloud server, a semi-trusted entity, provides various services including data storage, computation, <lb/>and transmission. It can conduct threshold sharding on encrypted data from fog nodes, decrypt and <lb/>retrieve aggregated data, and perform parsing to obtain electricity consumption data for each sub-<lb/>region, enabling flexible regulation of electricity. Fog nodes aggregate user data within their respective <lb/>regions and verify authenticity through signature verification. Smart meters generate user electricity <lb/>consumption information, encrypt, and sign it before transmitting it to the corresponding fog nodes. <lb/>Compared to traditional models, the AMICFA model utilizes fog nodes to store and process data at <lb/>the network edge more efficiently, thereby reducing transmission costs and enhancing real-time data <lb/>processing capabilities. <lb/>4.1.2 Security Threats in AMICFA <lb/>In the AMICFA scenario, based on existing research and analysis, as well as the characteristics <lb/>of the cloud and fog assistance structure itself, attackers may obtain or tamper with the transmission <lb/>information between nodes, posing a threat to the security of the smart grid. The threats that may <lb/>occur in the AMICFA can be divided into internal and external attacks in this paper. <lb/>Internal attack: The first type of internal attacks consists of malicious node attacks, which occur <lb/>during the data transmission process between users and the fog computing layer. For example, when <lb/>a user transmits electricity data to a fog node, malicious nodes pretend to be legitimate nodes in the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3201 <lb/></page>

	<body>network and initiate proactive attacks (such as identity forgery and data modification) to disrupt the <lb/>authenticity and integrity of private data [37]. The second type of internal attack is described as honest-<lb/>but-curious in terms of fog and cloud nodes, which perform tasks as required, but also access sensitive <lb/>data as much as possible and may be caught by attackers. For example, fog nodes may be vulnerable to <lb/>attacks from undetected malware, which can eavesdrop on data from devices. Therefore, it is necessary <lb/>to ensure that fog nodes do not observe user privacy data throughout the data transmission process. <lb/>Similarly, the model should ensure that the user&apos;s personal privacy data cannot be exported from the <lb/>cloud server [18]. <lb/>External attack: Attackers may attack link connections between various entities to obtain user <lb/>privacy information. Therefore, the system must ensure that attackers are unable to successfully obtain <lb/>private information communication links [38]. <lb/>4.2 Setting User Protection Levels <lb/>4.2.1 Missing Data Processing Based On Fuzzy Data Completion Algorithm <lb/>In incomplete datasets, the algorithm first considers the importance of lost data by determining <lb/>the time period in which the missing data is located. Specifically, data lost during the time interval <lb/>from 23:00 pm to 7:00 am the next day is deemed less critical. Secondly, considering the characteristics <lb/>of the time points where the missing data is located, if the time interval between consecutive missing <lb/>data points is very short and falls outside peak or valley periods, it is also classified as less significant. <lb/>However, other missing data points are regarded as important. For less important data, the linear <lb/>regression method is employed to fill the missing values [39]. Linear regression is a fundamental <lb/>statistical method that provides sufficient accuracy. For less important data, this method can quickly <lb/>and effectively predict missing values, making it more computationally efficient. <lb/>Algorithm 1: Fuzzy data completion algorithm <lb/>Input: <lb/>Incomplete smart grid dataset D, Fuzzy importance matrix A <lb/>Output: <lb/>Complete dataset D <lb/>1 <lb/>for d k in D do <lb/>2 <lb/>if d k = ∅ then <lb/>3 <lb/>importantPer ←Determine the importance of time period (d k ); <lb/>4 <lb/>importantPoi ←Determine the importance of time point (d k ); <lb/>5 <lb/>if importantPer and importantPoi then <lb/>6 <lb/>d k ← <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 d i • a * <lb/>ik <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 a * <lb/>ik <lb/>; <lb/>7 <lb/>else <lb/>8 <lb/>linear regression filling (d k ); <lb/>9 <lb/>end <lb/>10 <lb/>else <lb/>11 <lb/>continuous; <lb/>12 <lb/>end <lb/>13 <lb/>end <lb/>14 <lb/>D ←Completing Data D; <lb/>15 <lb/>Return D <lb/>For important data, a fuzzy data completion algorithm is used to address the uncertainty and <lb/>ambiguity inherent in the missing data, particularly when the data loss occurs non-randomly. This <lb/></body>

	<page>3202 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>method leverages a fuzzy importance matrix to prioritize the imputation process based on the time <lb/>of day and data characteristics, which is particularly suited for datasets with patterned absences, such <lb/>as those frequently encountered in electricity consumption data [40]. Specifically, a fuzzy importance <lb/>matrix is designed as shown in Eq. (3). <lb/>A = <lb/>⎛ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎝ <lb/>a 11 a 12 . . . a 1n <lb/>a 21 a 22 . . . a 2n <lb/>. . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>a n1 a n2 . . . a nn <lb/>⎞ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎠ <lb/>(3) <lb/>where a ij represents the importance of data d i to data d j , a ij ∈ (0, 1). Taking into account the <lb/>communication environment based on the Internet of Things (IoT), the characteristics of the IoT <lb/>are further considered when calculating the importance weights. The importance matrix element a ij is <lb/>calculated by Eq. (4). <lb/>a * <lb/>ij = a ij × P ij × S ij × exp (-<lb/>E ij <lb/>Emax ) <lb/>(4) <lb/>where P ij represents the probability of successful data transmission between d i and d j , E ij represents <lb/>the energy consumption of communication between d i and d j , E max represents the maximum allowable <lb/>energy consumption, and S ij represents the strength of security measures during data transmission. <lb/>Consider these variables as factors that affect the importance weight, and the final completion process <lb/>of missing data is shown in Eq. (5). <lb/>d k = <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 d i • a * <lb/>ik <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 a * <lb/>ik <lb/>(5) <lb/>The missing data can be completed by using the known data and its importance weight to the <lb/>missing data. Unlike traditional methods that may apply a one-size-fits-all approach, a resource <lb/>optimization approach is proposed in this paper, which involves using efficient but relatively simple <lb/>methods for less important data, while retaining more complex and costly methods for important <lb/>data with greater impact. This not only ensures the efficiency of processing, but also ensures the <lb/>accuracy and reliability of key information. By using this method of allocation, it is possible to <lb/>balance processing costs and data quality, thereby achieving the best overall effect. The missing data <lb/>completion process is shown in Algorithm 1. The line 2 to the line 4 calculate the importance of the <lb/>missing data d k . If the missing data is important data, the fuzzy data completion algorithm is used to <lb/>complete the data (line 6). Otherwise, the linear regression method is used (line 8). Finally, after all the <lb/>missing data is filled in, the complete dataset D is obtained (line 14). <lb/>4.2.2 Setting User Protection Level Based on Fuzzy Comprehensive Evaluation Algorithm <lb/>The user electricity consumption data collected by smart meters is not only vast in quantity but <lb/>also diverse in variety, but the data value density is low. Therefore, feature extraction of load-side user <lb/>electricity consumption data can be more concise and effective in classifying the importance of users, <lb/>thereby obtaining the corresponding protection level of users. The load curve features extracted in this <lb/>article include: <lb/>Definition 9 Peak power rate, Ppr. Assuming that the daily peak electricity consumption is PeE <lb/>and the total daily electricity consumption is TE, the Ppr can be calculated by Eq. (6). <lb/>Ppr = <lb/>PeE <lb/>TE <lb/>(6) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3203 <lb/></page>

	<body>Definition 10 Trough power rate, Tpr. Assuming that the daily trough electricity consumption is <lb/>TrE and the total daily electricity consumption is TE, the Tpr can be calculated by Eq. (7). <lb/>Tpr = <lb/>TrE <lb/>TE <lb/>(7) <lb/>Definition 11 Load rate, Lr. Assuming that the daily average power consumption is AvE and the <lb/>total daily electricity consumption is TE, the Lr can be calculated by Eq. (8). <lb/>Lr = <lb/>AvE <lb/>TE <lb/>(8) <lb/>It can be inferred that the feature vector x i = {Ppr i , Tpr i , Lr i , TE i } can be used to represent the <lb/>electricity consumption characteristics of the i-th user. Due to the different modulus values of the four <lb/>elements in the user feature vector, in order to avoid a large proportion of one element and prevent <lb/>errors caused by distance classification, cosine similarity is used to classify user electricity consumption <lb/>behavior in this paper, as shown in Eq. (9). <lb/>simcos (x 1 , x 2 ) = <lb/>x 1 * x 2 <lb/>x 2 <lb/>1 + x 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(9) <lb/>After classifying the user&apos;s electricity consumption data, the user&apos;s electricity consumption behav-<lb/>ior classification can be obtained. This classification, together with the user&apos;s electricity consumption <lb/>levels, serves as the evaluation index for the fuzzy comprehensive evaluation algorithm, allowing for the <lb/>determination of the evaluation level and weight matrix. The specific steps of the fuzzy comprehensive <lb/>evaluation algorithm are as follows: <lb/>Firstly, establishing a comprehensive evaluation factor set I = {EBC, EC}, where EBC = <lb/>{Household, Commercial, Industry, Unused} represents electricity consumption characteristics, and <lb/>the classified user electricity consumption characteristics will belong to one of these. EC = <lb/>{&gt; 420 kWh, 231 ∼ 420 kWh, 50 ∼ 230 kWh, &lt; 50 kWh} represents electricity consumption levels. <lb/>Secondly, establishing an evaluation set V = {Level1, Level2, Level3, Level4} to indicate the <lb/>importance of users. For ease of calculation, set a score for each level, corresponding to V = <lb/>[100, 80, 60, 30]. <lb/>Algorithm 2: Fuzzy comprehensive evaluation algorithm <lb/>Input: <lb/>User electricity consumption characteristics data x, electricity payment status EP, <lb/>weight matrix A, fuzzy membership matrix R and evaluation set V <lb/>Output: <lb/>User protection level rating S <lb/>1 <lb/>EBC ←Using cosine similarity to classify data x; <lb/>2 <lb/>I ← (EBC, EP); <lb/>3 <lb/>for o ij in I do <lb/>4 <lb/>p ij ← o ij -o min / (o max -o min ); <lb/>5 <lb/>end <lb/>6 <lb/>for p ij in I do <lb/>7 <lb/>q ij ← p ij / <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 p ij ; <lb/>8 <lb/>end <lb/>9 <lb/>for j in m do <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

	<page>3204 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>Algorithm 2 (continued) <lb/>10 <lb/>e j ← -<lb/>1 <lb/>ln n <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 q ij ln q ij ; <lb/>11 <lb/>A j = <lb/>1 -e j <lb/>m <lb/>j=1 e j <lb/>; <lb/>12 <lb/>end <lb/>13 <lb/>B ← A * R; //Establishing a fuzzy comprehensive evaluation matrix. <lb/>14 <lb/>S ← B * V ; //Calculate the protection level rating. <lb/>15 <lb/>Return S <lb/>Thirdly, using entropy weight method to determine the weights of each factor. The steps to <lb/>calculate the weight matrix A = [A 1 , A 2 ] using the entropy weight method are as follows: <lb/>1. The elements of matrix I are dimensionless, as shown in Eq. (10). <lb/>p ij = <lb/>o ij -o min <lb/>o max -o min <lb/>(10) <lb/>2. The weight of each factor for n samples is calculated, as shown in Eq. (11). <lb/>q ij = <lb/>p ij <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 p ij <lb/>(11) <lb/>3. The entropy and weight of the j-th factor is calculated, as shown in Eqs. (12)-(13). <lb/>e j = -<lb/>1 <lb/>ln n <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>q ij ln q ij <lb/>(12) <lb/>A j = <lb/>1 -e j <lb/>m <lb/>j=1 e j <lb/>(13) <lb/>Fourthly, setting membership values for fuzzy evaluation factors. Assuming the membership <lb/>matrix of EBC is R 1 = [D 1 , D 2 , D 3 , D 4 ], and the membership matrix of EC is R 2 = [M 1 , M 2 , M 3 , M 4 ]. <lb/>The fuzzy membership matrix is shown in Eq. (14). <lb/>R = <lb/>R 1 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>(14) <lb/>Fifthly, establishing a fuzzy comprehensive evaluation matrix. The fuzzy vector A on I is changed <lb/>to the fuzzy vector B on V through fuzzy transformation as shown in Eq. (15). <lb/>B = A * R <lb/>(15) <lb/>where * represents matrix multiplication. <lb/>S = B * V -1 <lb/>(16) <lb/>Finally, calculate the protection rating for each user as shown in Eq. (16). According to the ratings, <lb/>users with scores in the top 10% are set to a high protection level, while the remaining users are set to <lb/>a low protection level. The fuzzy comprehensive evaluation algorithm is shown in Algorithm 2. First, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3205 <lb/></page>

	<body>use cosine similarity to classify the data x (line 1) and establish a comprehensive evaluation factor set <lb/>I (line 2). Second, the lines 3-12 calculate the weight of each evaluation factor with the entropy weight <lb/>method. Then the weight matrix A and the fuzzy membership matrix R are used to obtain the fuzzy <lb/>comprehensive evaluation matrix B (line 13). Finally, B and the evaluation set V are used to calculate <lb/>the protection level score of each user (line 14) and return them (line 15). <lb/>4.3 Protecting User Electricity Privacy Based on Hierarchical Threshold Encryption Algorithm <lb/>After obtaining the protection levels of electricity users, a hierarchical threshold encryption <lb/>algorithm based on AMICFA is proposed with different electricity users as protection targets. The <lb/>specific process of hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm is shown in Fig. 4. <lb/>Figure 4: The process of hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm <lb/>4.3.1 System Parameter Initialization <lb/>At this stage, initializing the algorithm parameters with a robust key management strategy for <lb/>data-at-rest encryption. Assuming that Trusted Authority (TA) has a global key pool {k ij , k j ; 0 ≤ i ≤ <lb/>w; 0 ≤ j ≤ m}, where keys are regularly rotated and updated to ensure the security of data-at-rest. <lb/>Distinct keys from the pool are distributed to smart meters and fog computing devices by TA for <lb/>secure registration and data-at-rest encryption. The specific generation process of each parameter is <lb/>as follows: <lb/>(1) As part of the initialization, TA selects two secure prime numbers p and q. They are the basis for <lb/>generating other encryption parameters. In the Paillier encryption system, these two prime numbers <lb/>are used to calculate the modulus N, which is N = pq. Modulus N is the core part of subsequent <lb/>encryption and decryption operations, and by ensuring the security and robustness of modulus N, it <lb/>can effectively protect encrypted data from being cracked. The security of data-at-rest depends on the <lb/>strength of these basic encryption parameters. <lb/></body>

	<page>3206 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>(2) λ is the least common multiple of p -1 and q -1, used to calculate the secret parameters in <lb/>Paillier decryption process. The choice of λ is directly related to the security of the entire encryption <lb/>system. If λ is leaked, the entire encryption system will be cracked. Therefore, it is possible to regularly <lb/>replace the relevant prime numbers p and q to update λ, in order to prevent the risks caused by long-<lb/>term use of the same key combination. <lb/>(3) The system randomly selects an integer g that satisfies gcd L g λ modN 2 , N = 1 to obtain <lb/>Paillier public key (g, N). Due to the random selection of g, it becomes extremely difficult to attack <lb/>encrypted data, ensuring the security of the data-at-rest encryption process. <lb/>(4) Individual keys α ij for each smart meter and β j for each fog node are generated. These keys <lb/>can be used to encrypt data-in-transit or data-at-rest, they are regularly updated. Only entities with <lb/>corresponding keys can access and interpret the data to prevent unauthorized access. This ensures that <lb/>data is not tampered with during the transmission from the smart meters to the fog nodes and from <lb/>the fog nodes to the server. <lb/>(5) Threshold pieces quantity c 1 and c 2 are generated, which can be used to define specific <lb/>conditions that need to be met during the encryption and decryption process. c 1 represents the basic <lb/>threshold condition to initiate the decryption process, while c 2 represents the threshold condition that <lb/>needs to be met at a higher level of protection. The threshold encryption algorithm enhances the <lb/>security of data-in-motion. <lb/>(6) Upon successful generation of the system parameters N, λ, g, α ij , β j , c 1 , c 2 , TA will publish the <lb/>public parameters (g, N). These parameters are necessary for encryption operations, and anyone can <lb/>use these public parameters to encrypt data. For private parameters, encrypted channels are usually <lb/>used to securely distribute these keys to the corresponding smart meters and fog nodes. This process <lb/>ensures the security of the keys during transmission. <lb/>4.3.2 Registration Verification <lb/>After initialization, the newly added smart meters need to undergo registration verification. The <lb/>specific steps are as follows: <lb/>(1) The smart meter will generate information RM ij through its built-in algorithm as shown <lb/>in Eq. (17), RM ij mainly including the smart meter ID ij , household information Hold ij , location <lb/>information Loc ij . The registration information has unique identification. <lb/>RM ij = ID ij , Hold ij , Loc ij <lb/>(17) <lb/>(2) To safeguard the confidentiality of RM ij during transmission, the smart meter encrypts this <lb/>information using the public key (g, N) and an encryption parameter α ij provided by TA. The resulting <lb/>ciphertext, shown in Eq. (18), is securely transmitted by encrypted channel to TA, ensuring that <lb/>registration data is protected in transit. <lb/>C ij = g RM ij α N <lb/>ij modN 2 <lb/>(18) <lb/>(3) To ensure the integrity and authenticity of the encrypted registration information while in <lb/>transit, a Hash-based Message Authentication Code (HMAC) is generated. The HMAC algorithm is <lb/>a key based verification method for message integrity, which generates a fixed length message digest as <lb/>output by combining the key and message input. The communication parties confirm the legitimacy <lb/>of the message by comparing this authentication code, and its security is based on the hash encryption <lb/>algorithm used [41]. In order to achieve higher security, SHA-256 is used as the hash function in <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3207 <lb/></page>

	<body>this paper. Taking the private key α ij and RM ij as input for the hash function to generate a message <lb/>verification code from the ciphertext, as shown in Eq. (19), and sent to TA. <lb/>MAC ij = H α ij ⊕ opad |H α ij ⊕ ipad |RM ij <lb/>(19) <lb/>where H represents SHA-256, ipad represents internal padding, and opad represents external padding. <lb/>(4) Upon receipt of the registration data and MAC, TA decrypts the information and verifies <lb/>the MAC by recomputing it. If the received MAC matches the computed one, the registration is <lb/>confirmed as legitimate, and a successful verification message is sent back to the smart meter. This <lb/>two-fold verification process ensures that both the identity of the smart meters and the integrity <lb/>of the transmitted data are secured, thus effectively protecting data-in-transit from interception or <lb/>tampering. If the MAC does not match, the registration is denied. Similarly, the addition of new fog <lb/>node devices also requires registration verification. <lb/>4.3.3 Electricity Data Encryption <lb/>After completing the verification, to prevent real-time electricity data exposure, it is necessary to <lb/>encrypt the electricity data. The specific steps are as follows: <lb/>(1) Smart meters generate electricity consumption data for a given time period T ij , as shown in <lb/>Eq. (20). This data is immediately encrypted to protect it while in transit and in motion, as detailed in <lb/>Eq. (21). The encrypted data, along with a digitally signed signature, is then uploaded to the fog nodes <lb/>for authentication, ensuring that only verified data is processed and aggregated by the fog nodes. <lb/>M ij = ID ij , EC ij , T ij <lb/>(20) <lb/>C ij = g EC ij α N <lb/>ij modN 2 <lb/>(21) <lb/>(2) To mitigate the risk of replay attacks, a pseudo-random number R ij is generated by combining <lb/>the current timestamp T ij with the smart meter&apos;s identity. This unique identifier ensures that each <lb/>transmission is distinct and securely linked to its point of origin, further securing data-in-motion. <lb/>(3) At the fog nodes, further threshold encryption is employed based on the privacy of the data, <lb/>a method that reinforces data-in-motion security by adapting the encryption depth according to the <lb/>user protection levels determined by their ID. The protection level for each fog node (fog pl ) is elevated: <lb/>• If a user in the fog node is judged as a high protection level user, the value of fog pl is increased <lb/>by one. <lb/>• If a user in the fog node is judged as an ordinary user, the value of fog pl remains unchanged. <lb/>Algorithm 3: Hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm <lb/>Input: <lb/>User electricity consumption behavior and electricity consumption information I user , <lb/>User protection level rating S <lb/>Output: <lb/>Privacy protected I user <lb/>1 <lb/>// Generate system parameters. <lb/>2 <lb/>p, q ←TA selects two secure prime numbers; <lb/>3 <lb/>N ← p * q; <lb/>4 <lb/>λ ← lcm (p -1, q -1); <lb/>5 <lb/>// Defined function. <lb/>6 <lb/>L (x) = (x -1) /N; <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

	<page>3208 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>Algorithm 3 (continued) <lb/>7 <lb/>// Generate random integer. <lb/>8 <lb/>α ij ← random (Z); <lb/>9 <lb/>β j ← random (Z); <lb/>10 <lb/>c 1 , c 2 ←Generate by TA; <lb/>11 <lb/>Publish system parameters N, λ, g, α ij , β j , c 1 , c 2 to various entities; <lb/>12 <lb/>// Registration verification. <lb/>13 <lb/>// Registration information. <lb/>14 <lb/>RM ij ← ID ij , Hold ij , Loc ij ; <lb/>15 <lb/>C ij ← g RM ij α N <lb/>ij modN 2 ; <lb/>16 <lb/>MAC ij ← H α ij ⊕ opad |H α ij ⊕ ipad |RM ij ; <lb/>17 <lb/>if MAC == MAC then <lb/>18 <lb/>Agree to register; <lb/>19 <lb/>else <lb/>20 <lb/>Refuse registration; <lb/>21 <lb/>end <lb/>22 <lb/>// Smart meter data encryption; <lb/>23 <lb/>M ij ← ID ij , EC ij , T ij ; <lb/>24 <lb/>C ij ← g EC ij α N <lb/>ij modN 2 ; <lb/>25 <lb/>R ij ← ID ij ∪ T ij ; <lb/>26 <lb/>MAC ij ← H R ij ⊕ opad |H R ij ⊕ ipad |M i,j ; <lb/>27 <lb/>Send user reports to fog nodes; <lb/>28 <lb/>Signature authentication for fog nodes; <lb/>29 <lb/>if ID is the 10% in S then <lb/>30 <lb/>fog pl = fog pl + 1; <lb/>31 <lb/>else <lb/>32 <lb/>fog pl = fog pl + 0; <lb/>33 <lb/>end <lb/>34 <lb/>Tss j ←According to different fog pl values, different threshold encryption strategies are <lb/>adopted for different fog nodes; <lb/>35 <lb/>I user ←Protect user data on fog nodes based on different threshold encryption strategies <lb/>Tss j ; <lb/>36 <lb/>Return I user <lb/>(4) The protection levels of fog nodes are judged based on fog pl . If it is a regular fog node, it only <lb/>needs to meet the basic decryption criteria c 1 on the cloud server to decrypt, that is, it only needs to <lb/>meet the minimum number C (m -1, n) of key fragments, where m represents the total number of key <lb/>fragments involved, n is the actual number of key fragments required during the decryption process. <lb/>If it is a high protection level fog node device, it can only be decrypted if the cloud server meets the <lb/>stringent decryption criteria c 2 . Even if the basic number of decryption fragments is met, additional <lb/>verification or key fragments from another important fog node of the same level are also required <lb/>to finally decrypt the data. This threshold encryption strategy effectively improves the security of the <lb/>system, especially in complex systems involving multiple nodes and different security levels, ensuring <lb/>that sensitive data can only be accessed and decrypted when all set conditions are met. The privacy <lb/>protection process based on hierarchical threshold encryption is shown in Algorithm 3. First, the TA <lb/>generates system parameters and publishes them to corresponding entities (lines 1-11). Then, lines <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3209 <lb/></page>

	<body>12-21 complete the registration verification of the newly added smart meters and fog nodes. Next, <lb/>lines 23-24 handle the encryption of electricity data on the smart meters, while lines 25-28 ensure <lb/>data protection during transmission between the meters and fog nodes. Lines 29-33 determine the <lb/>protection level of the fog nodes based on users&apos; protection levels. Finally, lines 34-35 assign different <lb/>threshold encryption strategies to different fog nodes according to their protection levels, and line 36 <lb/>returns the encrypted user data. <lb/>5 Experiments <lb/>5.1 Experimental Environment <lb/>In this section, the method proposed in this paper is simulated and analyzed. The simulation <lb/>platform utilized is PyCharm, employing Python 3.8. The code runs on the Windows 11 operating <lb/>system with a hardware environment comprising an Intel Core i5-4200H processor with 2.80 GHz <lb/>and 8 GB of memory. The experimental dataset used is based on the database called &quot;Commercial <lb/>and Residential Hourly Load Profiles for all TMY3 Locations in the United States&quot; [42]. This dataset <lb/>encompasses the collection of smart meter data from diverse types of users in 95 cities across the United <lb/>States, with a collection period of one year and a collection interval of one hour. The data format is <lb/>shown in Table 1. <lb/>Table 1: Partial data from electricity load data from various states in the USA <lb/>UserID <lb/>Time <lb/>Facility <lb/>Fans <lb/>Cooling <lb/>Heating <lb/>... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(01:00:00) 105.56575 <lb/>23.04534406 11.6249027 <lb/>8.65660857 <lb/>... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(02:00:00) 95.968336 <lb/>19.27497843 9.215620549 9.411857538 ... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(03:00:00) 113.86157 <lb/>24.09372304 10.62250021 14.1056054 <lb/>... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(04:00:00) 99.424518 <lb/>19.27497843 7.599902891 12.68124854 ... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(05:00:00) 142.72785 <lb/>28.48931737 9.572050659 14.89920319 ... <lb/>0 <lb/>1/2(06:00:00) 173.05479 <lb/>28.07571151 12.45216031 43.1874417 <lb/>... <lb/>5.2 Evaluation Indicators <lb/>5.2.1 Anti-Attack Success Rate <lb/>Due to its own characteristics, ensuring the safe and stable operation of smart grids is of utmost <lb/>importance when confronted with various security threats. In order to verify the defense ability of the <lb/>proposed model against network attacks, the Anti-attack success rate is defined in this paper as shown <lb/>in Eqs. (22)-(24) to verify the effectiveness of HPPM-AMICFA. <lb/>P node = 1 -<lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 α i σ i /n + <lb/>m <lb/>j=1 β j σ i /m + γ <lb/>(22) <lb/>P link = 1 -<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 ε i σ i /n + <lb/>m <lb/>j=1 δ j σ i /m <lb/>(23) <lb/>P success = <lb/>P node + P link <lb/>2 <lb/>(24) <lb/>Assuming equal likelihood of attackers targeting the cloud server, fog nodes, and smart meters, <lb/>let&apos;s denote the total number of smart meters as n and the total number of fog nodes in the power <lb/></body>

	<page>3210 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>grid as m. The probabilities of successfully attacking smart meters, fog nodes, and the cloud server <lb/>are represented by α, β, and γ , respectively. When attackers target the links between entities, let ε <lb/>denote the probability of successfully intercepting the links between smart meters and fog nodes, and <lb/>δ denote the probability of successfully intercepting the links between fog nodes and the cloud server. <lb/>Additionally, the probability of the encryption key being cracked is σ . <lb/>The Anti-attack success rate can be defined as the average of the success rates of nodes and links <lb/>resisting attacks. A higher value indicates a stronger anti-attack capability of the smart grid privacy <lb/>protection scheme, while a lower value suggests lower security. <lb/>5.2.2 Calculate Costs <lb/>The computational cost of privacy protection in smart grid applications is a critical consideration <lb/>due to the large volume of data involved. Achieving privacy protection with minimal computational <lb/>overhead while ensuring security is essential for practical deployment. The calculation of costs <lb/>typically encompasses the following aspects: (1) In the encryption process, smart meters encrypt <lb/>electricity consumption data, and after aggregation, the data is encrypted again at the fog nodes. (2) In <lb/>the aggregation stage, operations are performed on encrypted data to aggregate ciphertexts. (3) In the <lb/>decryption process, cloud server and fog nodes decrypt ciphertexts to analyze user data after obtaining <lb/>encrypted data. <lb/>5.3 Baselines <lb/>Four baseline models are used to compare the performance of the HPPM-AMICFA on the above <lb/>two evaluation indicators: <lb/>1. Paillier encryption algorithm [43]: It is an encryption algorithm based on the composite residue <lb/>class hard problem hypothesis. It mainly consists of three parts: key generation, encryption, <lb/>and decryption. <lb/>2. Privacy preserving Data Aggregation against False data (PDAF) [44]: It is based on Paillier <lb/>homomorphic encryption scheme and uses blinding factors to design a privacy protection <lb/>method to protect privacy in fog computing. <lb/>3. Security Enhanced Data Aggregation (SEDA) [45]: It is a data aggregation scheme for smart <lb/>grid communication security enhancement based on homomorphic cryptosystem, trapdoor <lb/>hash functions and homomorphic authenticators. <lb/>4. Threshold encryption [36]: It is a distributed cryptographic technology based on multi-party <lb/>participation. It can divide a key into multiple parts, and each part can only restore the <lb/>complete key when it reaches a certain threshold. <lb/>5.4 Performance Analysis <lb/>5.4.1 Cluster Analysis of Electricity Consumption Characteristics <lb/>Based on the real test data of electricity loads in various states in the United States, fuzzy <lb/>comprehensive analysis algorithm is utilized to set the protection level of users in this paper. In <lb/>order to obtain the evaluation index of the fuzzy comprehensive analysis algorithm, users need to <lb/>be classified according to the electricity consumption behavior characteristics, so as to obtain the <lb/>electricity consumption characteristics of each type of user as one of the inputs of the algorithm. <lb/>The actual load curves of the power grid are shown in Fig. 5. Using the K-means method to cluster <lb/>the electricity consumption of users, as shown in Fig. 6, it can be seen that users are categorized into <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3211 <lb/></page>

	<body>four groups. Subsequently, features are extracted from the Ppr, Tpr, Lr, and TE of each user&apos;s power <lb/>load curve, allowing each user to be classified into its most similar category. <lb/>Figure 5: Partial actual electricity load curves in the dataset. The curves of different colors represent <lb/>the electricity consumption characteristics of different users, with the horizontal axis representing the <lb/>date and the vertical axis representing the total daily electricity load <lb/>Figure 6: Clustering results of electricity consumption characteristics. (a) Indicating the daily electricity <lb/>consumption characteristic curves of four types of users. (b) Indicating the results of clustering the <lb/>daily electricity consumption characteristics of users <lb/>Each clustering result is optimized by weighted average, and different clustering results are <lb/>categorized into four types of electricity consumption behaviors: Household electricity, Commercial <lb/>electricity, Industrial electricity, and Unused electricity as shown in Fig. 7. These will be used as input <lb/>to the fuzzy comprehensive analysis algorithm together with the user electricity consumption levels. <lb/>5.4.2 Security Analysis <lb/>In the AMICFA model, user electricity data is susceptible to attacks during transmission, and fog <lb/>nodes and cloud server also face the risk of being compromised. Therefore, in order to protect user <lb/>privacy data from leakage, the hierarchical threshold encryption algorithm is proposed in this paper. <lb/></body>

	<page>3212 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>The primary objective of implementing variable thresholds is to provide differentiated protection levels <lb/>that are aligned with the risk profiles and privacy needs of various user categories. By design, this <lb/>method does not merely adjust the number of parties needed for decryption but strategically enhances <lb/>the security barriers based on the potential impact and vulnerability of the data involved. Before <lb/>conducting a comparative analysis of the experimental results, a theoretical analysis of the security <lb/>of the HPPM-AMICFA model is conducted and the advantages are listed below: <lb/>Figure 7: Four types of electricity consumption. (a) Household electricity. (b) Commercial electricity. <lb/>(c) Industrial electricity. (d) Unused electricity <lb/>(1) Enhanced security for sensitive data. For users with higher risk profiles-such as commercial <lb/>or industrial entities where data exposure could lead to significant financial or operational repercus-<lb/>sions-the system requires a higher threshold. This means more shares must be present to decrypt, <lb/>effectively increasing the difficulty for unauthorized access or malicious collusion. <lb/>(2) Flexibility and scalability. This approach allows the system to dynamically adjust the security <lb/>measures based on real-time assessments of risk and privacy requirements. It provides a robust <lb/>framework that can evolve as threats landscape changes or as different user needs emerge. <lb/>(3) Proportional to the data&apos;s sensitivity. Ensuring that more sensitive data has stronger protections <lb/>inherently supports privacy by reducing the likelihood of unauthorized access. <lb/>(4) Adaptive to threat models. The method acknowledges that not all data is equally attractive to <lb/>attackers, and not all users face the same level of threat. Adjusting the decryption threshold according <lb/>to the assessed risk aligns the security measures with the actual needs and threats. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3213 <lb/></page>

	<body>Therefore, while the hierarchical threshold mechanism may superficially appear as merely altering <lb/>the collaborative requirements for decryption, it introduces an additional layer of security, which <lb/>fundamentally enhances user data privacy and security. The advantages of HPPM-AMICFA will be <lb/>verified through the following experimental results analysis. <lb/>5.4.3 Anti-Attack Success Rate Analysis <lb/>In the analysis of the anti-attack success rates, the robustness of the HPPM-AMICFA scheme <lb/>against tampering attacks is focused on, where attackers aim to capture nodes or manipulate data <lb/>links to access and alter user privacy data. Since HPPM-AMICFA can be regarded as an improved <lb/>combination of Paillier and Threshold encryption, a detailed comparison is provided to illustrate its <lb/>superior effectiveness in mitigating threats. This comparison includes the widely used Paillier and <lb/>Threshold encryption algorithms under similar attack conditions. Additionally, HPPM-AMICFA is <lb/>compared with PDAF, which also demonstrates good performance in cloud-fog assistance systems. <lb/>These comparisons further highlight the security and efficiency of HPPM-AMICFA in privacy <lb/>protection within cloud-fog assistance systems. <lb/>Firstly, assuming it is an attack by ordinary criminals who lacks knowledge about the power <lb/>grid&apos;s background. These attackers randomly target nodes, posing risks to both smart meters and <lb/>fog nodes. Various configurations of fog nodes and smart meters across different sub-regions are <lb/>simulated, with the initial attack success probabilities α, β, and γ for each type of node set to 0.3, <lb/>0.2, and 0.1, respectively. Similarly, the initial attack success probabilities ε and δ for each type of <lb/>link are set to 0.2 and 0.2, respectively. These settings are used to measure and compare the success <lb/>rates of both the baseline algorithms and the HPPM-AMICFA scheme in thwarting these attacks. <lb/>As shown in Fig. 8, a distinct advantage in using HPPM-AMICFA is revealed, particularly due to its <lb/>threshold encryption mechanism at the fog nodes. This mechanism ensures that unless the number of <lb/>compromised nodes reaches a critical threshold, the decryption of user data remains unfeasible, thus <lb/>significantly enhancing data security. <lb/>Figure 8: Success rate of resisting attacks without background knowledge <lb/>In simulations involving 100 to 500 smart meters, HPPM-AMICFA consistently outperformed <lb/>the other baseline models in resisting attacks, with success rates ranging from 73% to 92%, showing <lb/>an average improvement of about 14% compared to the Paillier algorithm. Specifically, when the <lb/>total number of smart meters remains unchanged, the two algorithms based on threshold encryption <lb/>consistently perform better than Paillier and PDAF, with the performance difference becoming more <lb/></body>

	<page>3214 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>pronounced as the number of smart meters increases. This is because, with the threshold encryption <lb/>algorithm, even if some node keys are cracked, the attacker cannot obtain useful information as <lb/>long as the decryption threshold is not reached. This method significantly reduces the probability <lb/>of successful key cracking. Additionally, although the anti-attack success rates of HPPM-AMICFA <lb/>are similar to those of traditional threshold encryption algorithms, HPPM-AMICFA consistently <lb/>performs better. This is due to HPPM-AMICFA&apos;s more flexible threshold encryption mechanism, <lb/>which employs different threshold encryption strategies for different nodes, thereby increasing the <lb/>difficulty of decryption and ensuring the security of more important data. Furthermore, compared to <lb/>PDAF, HPPM-AMICFA demonstrates superior effectiveness in protecting the privacy of cloud-fog <lb/>assistance systems in smart grids. <lb/>Furthermore, when considering attacks by adversaries with background knowledge targeting <lb/>specifically important users, the initial values of attack success probabilities α, β, and γ for each type <lb/>of node involved in the experiment are set to 0.5, 0.4, and 0.3, respectively, and for each type of link, <lb/>the probabilities ε and δ are set to 0.4 and 0.4, respectively. The Anti-attack success rates of the two <lb/>protection methods are as shown in Fig. 9. It can be seen that, compared to the other three baselines, <lb/>HPPM-AMICFA still demonstrates the best performance, with an overall average improvement of <lb/>18.5% compared to the Paillier algorithm. However, this time, the performance of traditional threshold <lb/>encryption algorithms does not match that of HPPM-AMICFA, and the gap between them increases <lb/>as the number of smart meters rises. This is because when attackers possess background knowledge, <lb/>they can target specific important user data. Among these methods, only HPPM-AMICFA classifies <lb/>user importance and applies more stringent threshold encryption strategies for more important users. <lb/>Moreover, as the number of smart meters increases, the number of important users also grows, making <lb/>the advantages of HPPM-AMICFA more evident. <lb/>Figure 9: Success rate of resisting attacks with background knowledge <lb/>This result indicates that the enhanced ability of HPPM-AMICFA to resist complex attacks <lb/>and the scalability of HPPM-AMICFA, suggesting its growing effectiveness as the network expands. <lb/>This trend is crucial for smart grid applications where the number of connected devices consistently <lb/>rises, requiring robust security mechanisms that can adapt to increasing complexity and potential <lb/>vulnerabilities. <lb/>These findings clearly demonstrate the superior anti-attack capabilities of HPPM-AMICFA over <lb/>traditional encryption methods, particularly in environments susceptible to both random and targeted <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3215 <lb/></page>

	<body>attacks. By incorporating hierarchical encryption thresholds and leveraging cloud and fog assistance <lb/>architecture, HPPM-AMICFA not only enhances the security of user data but also ensures that the <lb/>smart grid remains resilient against evolving cyber threats. This comparative analysis underscores the <lb/>significant improvements HPPM-AMICFA offers over existing privacy protection methods, affirming <lb/>its potential for widespread adoption in critical energy infrastructure protection. <lb/>5.4.4 Computational Costs Analysis <lb/>To demonstrate the efficiency of the HPPM-AMICFA scheme in handling computational costs, <lb/>particularly in large-scale smart grid environments, it is compared with other baseline models. For <lb/>a more comprehensive experimental comparison, Paillier is replaced with SEDA, which is based <lb/>on a homomorphic cryptosystem. Thus, HPPM-AMICFA is compared with three baseline models <lb/>based on different encryption algorithms in terms of computational costs. This comparison validates <lb/>the effectiveness of HPPM-AMICFA in optimizing computational resources without compromising <lb/>security. <lb/>As shown in Fig. 10, HPPM-AMICFA exhibits significantly lower computational overhead as <lb/>the number of smart meters scales up, maintaining robustness and efficiency. This is evident when <lb/>comparing the total time costs across varying scales of deployment. For instance, at 500 smart meters, <lb/>HPPM-AMICFA demonstrates a 55.3% reduction in computational costs compared to SEDA, which <lb/>records a time cost of 2550 ms, whereas HPPM-AMICFA only requires 1140 ms. Such efficiency <lb/>is achieved through the optimized cryptographic processes employed by HPPM-AMICFA, which <lb/>simplifies computational tasks without reducing cryptographic strength. <lb/>Figure 10: Comparison of computational costs of different algorithms <lb/>The time costs of the two algorithms, PDAF and Threshold encryption, are relatively close overall. <lb/>However, as the number of smart meters increases, PDAF shows slightly better performance than <lb/>Threshold encryption. This is because the PDAF algorithm uses a batch verification mechanism, which <lb/>improves the efficiency of verifying multiple encrypted data points. Despite this, the time cost of these <lb/>two algorithms is generally higher than that of HPPM-AMICFA for the following reasons. <lb/>Throughout the entire execution of the method, the computational cost of hash operations can <lb/>be disregarded. For n smart meter users, utilizing the improved Paillier encryption algorithm (HPPM-<lb/>AMICFA), each meter necessitates two multiplication operations and one exponential operation to <lb/>generate its ciphertext and signature, respectively. Conversely, in the other two algorithms SEDA <lb/></body>

	<page>3216 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<body>and PDAF, each meter requires 2n exponential operations for encryption. In the fog nodes, data <lb/>verification entails m multiplication and exponential operations, while secret sharing requires m <lb/>multiplication operations. Following this, a signature is generated post an exponential operation, after <lb/>which the data is uploaded to the cloud server. Upon the cloud server&apos;s attempt to perform decryption <lb/>operations, it initially needs to aggregate fog nodes data, which, if the number meets the threshold <lb/>value, requires t multiplication operations. The final decryption operation includes a power operation <lb/>and a multiplication operation. <lb/>For the traditional threshold encryption algorithms, multiple key fragments need to be distributed <lb/>to different nodes, which increases the communication overhead during the initial setup. Addition-<lb/>ally, decryption necessitates the participation of multiple nodes to collect enough key fragments, <lb/>which means each decryption requires extra communication. In contrast, HPPM-AMICFA achieves <lb/>hierarchical protection and aggregated data transmission through the collaboration of cloud servers <lb/>and fog nodes. This approach optimizes keys distribution and nodes participation, thereby reducing <lb/>communication overhead. <lb/>In smart grid systems, where real-time data processing and frequent communication are essential, <lb/>the higher computational costs of SEDA, PDAF, and Threshold encryption may not be justifiable <lb/>in all scenarios, especially in systems where rapid data processing is crucial. HPPM-AMICFA offers <lb/>an optimal balance between security and efficiency, making it particularly suitable for modern smart <lb/>grids that face varied and sophisticated cyber threats. <lb/>6 Conclusions and Outlooks <lb/>In response to the potential exposure of user habits and infringement of user privacy during <lb/>data transmission in the AMI system of smart grids, a secure advanced metering infrastructure <lb/>based on cloud and fog assistance in smart grids is designed in this paper. Based on this model, a <lb/>hierarchical privacy protection method based on threshold encryption is proposed. The effectiveness <lb/>of this algorithm in protecting the privacy and security of smart grid data has been verified through <lb/>security analyses and experimental simulations. <lb/>The HPPM-AMICFA model sets the protection levels of smart grid users using fuzzy compre-<lb/>hensive analysis with entropy weight method and provides privacy encryption protection with the <lb/>assistance of fog nodes. While this approach is suitable for the user-side of the smart grid, more <lb/>nuanced privacy protection strategies are required for the supply-side of the grid, where employees <lb/>with varying roles are present. Therefore, a privacy protection strategy under a partial order structure <lb/>for the power grid supply side will be focused on to achieve multi-level privacy protection in the future. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: The authors grate fully acknowledge the helpful comments and suggestions of the <lb/>editors and reviewers, which have improved the presentation. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China <lb/>(Grant Number 61902069), Natural Science Foundation of Fujian Province of China (Grant Number <lb/>2021J011068), Research Initiation Fund Program of Fujian University of Technology (GY-S24002, <lb/>GY-Z21048), Fujian Provincial Department of Science and Technology Industrial Guidance Project <lb/>(Grant Number 2022H0025). <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: The authors confirm contribution to the paper as follows: Study conception <lb/>and design: Linghong Kuang, Wenlong Shi; data collection: Linghong Kuang, Wenlong Shi, Jing <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3217 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Zhang; analysis and interpretation of results: Wenlong Shi, Jing Zhang; draft manuscript preparation: <lb/>Linghong Kuang, Wenlong Shi. All authors reviewed the results and approved the final version of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: The data that support the findings of this study are available from <lb/>the corresponding author upon request. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics Approval: Not applicable. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] M. H. Ullah and J. D. Park, &quot;Distributed energy trading in smart grid over directed communication <lb/>network,&quot; IEEE Trans. Smart Grid, vol. 12, no. 4, pp. 3669-3672, Jul. 2021. doi: 10.1109/TSG.2021.3067172. <lb/>[2] K. Sharma, A. Malik, I. Batra, A. S. M. Sanwar Hosen, M. A. Latif Sarker and D. S. Han, &quot;Technologies <lb/>behind the smart grid and internet of things: A system survey,&quot; Comput. Mater. Contin., vol. 75, no. 3, <lb/>pp. 5049-5072, 2023. doi: 10.32604/cmc.2023.035638. <lb/>[3] A. M. Alkhiari, S. Mishra, and M. AlShehri, &quot;Blockchain-based SQKD and IDS in edge enabled smart <lb/>grid network,&quot; Comput. Mater. Contin., vol. 70, no. 2, pp. 2150-2169, 2022. doi: 10.32604/cmc.2022.019562. <lb/>[4] J. Wang, L. Wu, S. Zeadally, M. K. Khan, and D. He, &quot;Privacy-preserving data aggregation against <lb/>malicious data mining attack for IoT-enabled smart grid,&quot; ACM Trans. Sens. Netw., vol. 17, no. 3, <lb/>pp. 1-25, Jun. 2021. doi: 10.1145/3440249. <lb/>[5] H. Wang, D. He, and S. Zhang, &quot;Balanced anonymity and traceability for outsourcing small-scale data <lb/>linear aggregation in the smart grid,&quot; IET Inf. Secur., vol. 11, no. 3, pp. 131-135, May 2017. doi: <lb/>10.1049/iet-ifs.2016.0150. <lb/>[6] C. Hu, Z. Liu, R. Li, P. Hu, T. Xiang and M. Han, &quot;Smart contract assisted privacy-preserving data <lb/>aggregation and management scheme for smart grid,&quot; IEEE Trans. Dependable Secure Comput., vol. 21, <lb/>no. 4, pp. 1-17, Aug. 2023. doi: 10.1109/TDSC.2023.3300749. <lb/>[7] S. M. Je, H. Woo, J. Choi, S. H. Jung, and J. H. Huh, &quot;A research trend on anonymous signature and <lb/>authentication methods for privacy invasion preventability on smart grid and power plant environments,&quot; <lb/>Energies, vol. 15, no. 12, pp. 4363-4383, Jun. 2022. doi: 10.3390/en15124363. <lb/>[8] L. Ou, Z. Qin, S. Liao, T. Li, and D. Zhang, &quot;Singular spectrum analysis for local differential privacy of <lb/>classifications in the smart grid,&quot; IEEE Internet Things J., vol. 7, no. 6, pp. 5246-5255, Feb. 2020. doi: <lb/>10.1109/JIOT.2020.2977220. <lb/>[9] S. Zhao et al., &quot;Smart and practical privacy-preserving data aggregation for fog-based smart grids,&quot; IEEE <lb/>Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur., vol. 16, pp. 521-536, Aug. 2020. doi: 10.1109/TIFS.2020.3014487. <lb/>[10] S. Desai, R. Alhadad, N. Chilamkurti, and A. Mahmood, &quot;A survey of privacy preserving schemes in IoE <lb/>enabled smart grid advanced metering infrastructure,&quot; Cluster Comput., vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 43-69, Mar. <lb/>2019. doi: 10.1007/s10586-018-2820-9. <lb/>[11] P. O. Ajiboye, K. O. B. O. Agyekum, and E. A. Frimpong, &quot;Privacy and security of advanced metering <lb/>infrastructure (AMI) data and network: A comprehensive review,&quot; J. Eng. Appl. Sci., vol. 71, no. 1, pp. 91, <lb/>Apr. 2024. doi: 10.1186/s44147-024-00422-w. <lb/>[12] S. Chen, L. Yang, Y. Shi, and Q. Wang, &quot;Blockchain-enabled secure and privacy-preserving data aggre-<lb/>gation for fog-based ITS,&quot; Comput. Mater. Contin., vol. 75, no. 2, pp. 3781-3796, Feb. 2023. doi: <lb/>10.32604/cmc.2023.036437. <lb/>[13] H. Yang, S. Liang, X. Luo, D. Tang, H. Li and X. Shen, &quot;PIPC: Privacy-and integrity-preserving clustering <lb/>analysis for load profiling in smart grids,&quot; IEEE Internet Things J., vol. 9, no. 13, pp. 10851-10861, Nov. <lb/>2021. doi: 10.1109/JIOT.2021.3125674. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>3218 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>[14] S. Zhang, J. Rong, and B. Wang, &quot;A privacy protection scheme of smart meter for decentralized smart <lb/>home environment based on consortium blockchain,&quot; Int. J. Electr. Power Energy Syst., vol. 121, no. 10, <lb/>pp. 106140, Oct. 2020. doi: 10.1016/j.ijepes.2020.106140. <lb/>[15] A. Guan and D. J. Guan, &quot;An efficient and privacy protection communication scheme for smart grid,&quot; <lb/>IEEE Access, vol. 8, pp. 179047-179054, Aug. 2020. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3025788. <lb/>[16] J. Srinivas, A. K. Das, X. Li, M. K. Khan, and M. Jo, &quot;Designing anonymous signature-based authenticated <lb/>key exchange scheme for internet of things-enabled smart grid systems,&quot; IEEE Trans. Ind. Inform., vol. 17, <lb/>no. 7, pp. 4425-4436, Jul. 2021. doi: 10.1109/TII.2020.3011849. <lb/>[17] L. Wu, W. Zhang, and W. Zhao, &quot;Privacy preserving data aggregation for smart grid with user anonymity <lb/>and designated recipients,&quot; Symmetry, vol. 14, no. 5, pp. 847, Apr. 2022. doi: 10.3390/sym14050847. <lb/>[18] S. Chen, L. Yang, C. Zhao, V. Varadarajan, and K. Wang, &quot;Double-blockchain assisted secure and <lb/>anonymous data aggregation for fog-enabled smart grid,&quot; Engineering, vol. 8, no. 3, pp. 159-169, Jan. 2022. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.eng.2020.06.018. <lb/>[19] K. S. Adewole and V. Torra, &quot;DFTMicroagg: A dual-level anonymization algorithm for smart grid data,&quot; <lb/>Int. J. Inf. Secur., vol. 21, no. 6, pp. 1299-1321, Sep. 2022. doi: 10.1007/s10207-022-00612-8. <lb/>[20] O. R. Merad Boudia, S. M. Senouci, and M. Feham, &quot;Elliptic curve-based secure multidimensional <lb/>aggregation for smart grid communications,&quot; IEEE Sens. J., vol. 17, no. 23, pp. 7750-7757, Dec. 2017. <lb/>doi: 10.1109/JSEN.2017.2720458. <lb/>[21] C. Dwork, &quot;Differential privacy,&quot; in Int. Colloq. Autom., Lang., Program., Berlin, Heidelberg, 2006, <lb/>pp. 1-12. <lb/>[22] J. Zhao, T. Jung, Y. Wang, and X. Li, &quot;Achieving differential privacy of data disclosure in the smart grid,&quot; <lb/>in IEEE INFOCOM, 2014-IEEE Conf. Comput. Commun., Toronto, ON, Canada, 2014, pp. 504-512. <lb/>[23] M. B. Gough, S. F. Santos, T. AlSkaif, M. S. Javadi, R. Castro and J. P. S. Catalão, &quot;Preserving privacy of <lb/>smart meter data in a smart grid environment,&quot; IEEE Trans. Ind. Inform., vol. 18, no. 1, pp. 707-718, Jan. <lb/>2022. doi: 10.1109/TII.2021.3074915. <lb/>[24] N. Gai, K. Xue, B. Zhu, J. Yang, J. Liu and D. He, &quot;An efficient data aggregation scheme with local <lb/>differential privacy in smart grid,&quot; Digit. Commun. Netw., vol. 8, no. 3, pp. 333-342, Jun. 2022. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.dcan.2022.01.004. <lb/>[25] Z. Zheng, T. Wang, A. K. Bashir, M. Alazab, S. Mumtaz and X. Wang, &quot;A decentralized mechanism based <lb/>on differential privacy for privacy-preserving computation in smart grid,&quot; IEEE Trans. Comput., vol. 71, <lb/>no. 11, pp. 2915-2926, Nov. 2022. doi: 10.1109/TC.2021.3130402. <lb/>[26] M. B. Yassein, S. Aljawarneh, E. Qawasmeh, W. Mardini, and Y. Khamayseh, &quot;Comprehensive study <lb/>of symmetric key and asymmetric key encryption algorithms,&quot; in 2017 Int. Conf. Eng. Technol. (ICET), <lb/>Antalya, Turkey, 2017, pp. 1-7. <lb/>[27] R. Sarenche, M. Salmasizadeh, M. H. Ameri, and M. R. Aref, &quot;A secure and privacy-preserving protocol <lb/>for holding double auctions in smart grid,&quot; Inf. Sci., vol. 557, no. 4, pp. 108-129, May 2021. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.ins.2020.12.038. <lb/>[28] Y. Chen, J. F. Martínez-Ortega, P. Castillejo, and L. López, &quot;A homomorphic-based multiple data <lb/>aggregation scheme for smart grid,&quot; IEEE Sens. J., vol. 19, no. 10, pp. 3921-3929, May 2019. doi: <lb/>10.1109/JSEN.2019.2895769. <lb/>[29] W. Xu, J. Sun, R. Cardell-Oliver, A. Mian, and J. B. Hong, &quot;A privacy-preserving framework using <lb/>homomorphic encryption for smart metering systems,&quot; Sensors., vol. 23, no. 10, pp. 4746, May 2023. doi: <lb/>10.3390/s23104746. <lb/>[30] M. Faheem, H. Kuusniemi, B. Eltahawy, M. S. Bhutta, and B. Raza, &quot;A lightweight smart contracts <lb/>framework for blockchain-based secure communication in smart grid applications,&quot; IET Gener., Transm. <lb/>Distrib., vol. 18, no. 3, pp. 625-638, Jan. 2024. doi: 10.1049/gtd2.13103. <lb/>[31] Y. Wang, B. Chen, L. Li, Q. Ma, H. Li and D. He, &quot;Efficient and secure ciphertext-policy attribute-based <lb/>encryption without pairing for cloud-assisted smart grid,&quot; IEEE Access, vol. 8, pp. 40704-40713, 2020. doi: <lb/>10.1109/ACCESS.2020.2976746. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.2 <lb/></note>

	<page>3219 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>[32] K. Fan et al., &quot;MSIAP: A dynamic searchable encryption for privacy-protection on smart grid with <lb/>cloud-edge-end,&quot; IEEE Trans. Cloud Comput., vol. 11, no. 2, pp. 1170-1181, Apr.-Jun. 2023. doi: <lb/>10.1109/TCC.2021.3134015. <lb/>[33] L. Wu, S. Fu, Y. Luo, H. Yan, H. Shi and M. Xu, &quot;A robust and lightweight privacy-preserving data <lb/>aggregation scheme for smart grid,&quot; IEEE Trans. Dependable Secure Comput., vol. 21, no. 1, pp. 270-283, <lb/>Jan.-Feb. 2024. doi: 10.1109/TDSC.2023.3252593. <lb/>[34] A. Shamir, &quot;How to share a secret,&quot; Commun. ACM, vol. 22, no. 11, pp. 612-613, Nov. 1979. doi: <lb/>10.1145/359168.359176. <lb/>[35] L. J. Pang and Y. M. Wang, &quot;A new (t, n) multi-secret sharing scheme based on Shamir&apos;s secret sharing,&quot; <lb/>Appl. Math. Comput., vol. 167, no. 2, pp. 840-848, Aug. 2005. doi: 10.1016/j.amc.2004.06.120. <lb/>[36] T. Tassa, &quot;Hierarchical threshold secret sharing,&quot; J. Cryptol., vol. 20, no. 2, pp. 237-264, Feb. 2007. doi: <lb/>10.1007/s00145-006-0334-8. <lb/>[37] M. Davoodi, R. Moslemi, W. Song, and J. M. Velni, &quot;A fog-based approach to secure smart grids against <lb/>data integrity attacks,&quot; in 2020 IEEE Power Energy Society Innov. Smart Grid Technol. Conf. (ISGT), <lb/>Washington, DC, USA, 2020, pp. 1-5. <lb/>[38] M. Ghiasi, T. Niknam, Z. Wang, M. Mehrandezh, M. Dehghani and N. Ghadimi, &quot;A comprehensive review <lb/>of cyber-attacks and defense mechanisms for improving security in smart grid energy systems: Past, present <lb/>and future,&quot; Elect. Power Syst. Res., vol. 215, pp. 108975, Feb. 2023. doi: 10.1016/j.epsr.2022.108975. <lb/>[39] G. Huang, &quot;Missing data filling method based on linear interpolation and lightgbm,&quot; J. Phys.: Conf. Ser., <lb/>vol. 1754, pp. 012187, 2021. doi: 10.1088/1742-6596/1754/1/012187. <lb/>[40] S. Bissey, S. Jacques, and J. C. Le Bunetel, &quot;The fuzzy logic method to efficiently optimize electricity <lb/>consumption in individual housing,&quot; Energies, vol. 10, no. 11, pp. 1701, Oct. 2017. doi: 10.3390/en10111701. <lb/>[41] U. Cali, M. Kuzlu, M. Pipattanasomporn, J. Kempf, and L. Bai, &quot;Introduction to security for smart grid <lb/>systems,&quot; in Digitalization of Power Markets and Systems Using Energy Informatics, Springer, Cham, Sep. <lb/>2021, pp. 59-85. doi: 10.1007/978-3-030-83301-5_4. <lb/>[42] Ong, Sean, Clark, and Nathan, &quot;Commercial and residential hourly load profiles for all TMY3 locations in <lb/>the united states,&quot; 2014. Accessed: Dec. 22, 2023. [Online]. Available: http://en.openei.org/datasets/dataset/ <lb/>commercial-and-residential-hourly-load-profiles-for-all-tmy3/ <lb/>[43] P. Paillier, &quot;Public-key cryptosystems based on composite degree residuosity classes,&quot; in Int. conf. Theory <lb/>Appl. Cryptogr. Tech., Berlin, Heidelberg, 1999, pp. 223-238. <lb/>[44] Y. Zhang et al., &quot;Privacy-preserving data aggregation against false data injection attacks in fog computing,&quot; <lb/>Sensors, vol. 18, no. 8, pp. 2659-2675, Aug. 2018. doi: 10.3390/s18082659. <lb/>[45] J. Ni, K. Alharbi, X. Lin, and X. Shen, &quot;Security-enhanced data aggregation against malicious gateways in <lb/>smart grid,&quot; in 2015 IEEE Global Commun. Conf. (GLOBECOM), San Diego, CA, USA, 2015, pp. 1-6. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>