<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:59:35.192Z">11/20/2025 10:59:35 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:59:24.526431Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:59:24.526431Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>EDITED BY <lb/>A. Seval Ozgu-Erdinc, <lb/>Ankara City Hospital, Türkiye <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Gabriela Corina Zaharie, <lb/>University of Medicine and Pharmacy Iuliu <lb/>Hatieganu, Romania <lb/>Rachana Singh, <lb/>Tufts University, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Fan Wu <lb/>gdwufan@126.com <lb/>Xiao-Mei Tong <lb/>tongxm2007@126.com <lb/>Xin-Zhu Lin <lb/>xinzhufj@163.com <lb/> † These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work <lb/>RECEIVED 27 December 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 27 February 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 06 March 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Li Y, Shen W, Zhang R, Mao J, Liu L, Chang Y-M, <lb/>Ye X-Z, Qiu Y-P, Ma L, Cheng R, Wu H, <lb/>Chen D-M, Chen L, Xu P, Mei H, Wang S-N, <lb/>Xu F-L, Ju R, Tong X-M, Lin X-Z and Wu F <lb/>(2024) Hyperglycemia in pregnancy did not <lb/>worsen the short-term outcomes of very <lb/>preterm infants: a propensity score matching <lb/>study. <lb/>Front. Pediatr. 12:1341221. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Li, Shen, Zhang, Mao, Liu, Chang, Ye, <lb/>Qiu, Ma, Cheng, Wu, Chen, Chen, Xu, Mei, <lb/>Wang, Xu, Ju, Tong, Lin and Wu. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic practice. <lb/>No use, distribution or reproduction is <lb/>permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/>Hyperglycemia in pregnancy did <lb/>not worsen the short-term <lb/>outcomes of very preterm <lb/>infants: a propensity score <lb/>matching study <lb/>Ying Li 1 † , Wei Shen 2,3 † , Rong Zhang 4 , Jian Mao 5 , Ling Liu 6 , <lb/>Yan-Mei Chang 7 , Xiu-Zhen Ye 8 , Yin-Ping Qiu 9 , Li Ma 10 , Rui Cheng 11 , <lb/>Hui Wu 12 , Dong-Mei Chen 13 , Ling Chen 14 , Ping Xu 15 , Hua Mei 16 , <lb/>San-Nan Wang 17 , Fa-Lin Xu 18 , Rong Ju 19 , Xiao-Mei Tong 7 * , <lb/>Xin-Zhu Lin 2,3 * and Fan Wu 1,20 * for the Chinese Multicenter <lb/>EUGR Collaborative Group <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Guangzhou Key Laboratory of Neonatal Intestinal Diseases, The Third <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China, 2 Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Women and Children&apos;s Hospital, School of Medicine, Xiamen University, Xiamen, Fujian, <lb/>China, 3 Xiamen Key Laboratory of Perinatal-Neonatal Infection, Xiamen, Fujian, China, 4 Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Children&apos;s Hospital of Fudan University, Shanghai, China, 5 Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Shengjing Hospital of China Medical University, Shenyang, Liaoning, China, 6 Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Guiyang Maternal and Child Health Hospital•Guiyang Children&apos;s Hospital, Guiyang, <lb/>Guizhou, China, 7 Department of Pediatrics, Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing, China, <lb/>8 <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Guangdong Province Maternal and Children&apos;s Hospital, Guangzhou, <lb/>Guangdong, China, 9 Department of Neonatology, General Hospital of Ningxia Medical University, <lb/>Yinchuan, Ningxia, China, 10 Department of Neonatology, Children&apos;s Hospital of Hebei Province, <lb/>Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China, 11 Department of Neonatology, Children&apos; Hospital of Nanjing Medical <lb/>University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China, 12 Department of Neonatology, The First Hospital of Jilin University, <lb/>Changchun, Jilin, China, 13 Department of Neonatology, Quanzhou Maternity and Children&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Quanzhou, Fujian, China, 14 Department of Pediatrics, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, <lb/>Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, Hubei, China, 15 Department of Neonatology, <lb/>Liaocheng People&apos;s Hospital, Liaocheng, Shandong, China, 16 Department of Neonatology, The Affiliate <lb/>Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical University, Hohhot, Inner Mongolia, China, 17 Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Suzhou Municipal Hospital, Suzhou, Jiangsu, China, 18 Department of Neonatology, <lb/>The Third Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China, 19 Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Chengdu Women&apos; and Children&apos;s Central Hospital, School of Medicine, University of <lb/>Electronic Science and Technology of China, Chengdu, Sichuan, China, 20 Guangdong Provincial Key <lb/>Laboratory of Major Obstetric Diseases, Guangdong Provincial Clinical Research Center for Obstetrics <lb/>and Gynecology, The Third Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, <lb/>Guangdong, China <lb/>Background: Hyperglycemia in pregnancy (HGP) has generally been considered <lb/>a risk factor associated with adverse outcomes in offspring, but its impact on the <lb/>short-term outcomes of very preterm infants remains unclear. <lb/>Methods: A secondary analysis was performed based on clinical data collected <lb/>prospectively from 28 hospitals in seven regions of China from September <lb/>2019 to December 2020. According to maternal HGP, all infants were divided <lb/>Abbreviations <lb/>HGP, hyperglycemia in pregnancy; GDM, gestational diabetes mellitus; PGDM, pregestational diabetes <lb/>mellitus; SGA, small for gestational age; VPIs, very preterm infants; NEC, necrotizing enterocolitis; PDA, <lb/>patent ductus arteriosus; IVH, intraventricular hemorrhage; PVL, periventricular leukomalacia; BPD, <lb/>bronchopulmonary dysplasia; ROP, retinopathy of prematurity; RDS, respiratory distress syndrome; <lb/>EUGR, extrauterine growth retardation; PSM, propensity score matching; NICU, neonatal intensive unit; <lb/>GA, gestational age; IUGR, intrauterine growth retardation; EOS, early-onset sepsis; LOS, late-onset <lb/>sepsis; hsPDA, hemodynamically significant PDA; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; FI, feeding <lb/>intolerance; MBDP, metabolic bone disease of prematurity; PNAC, parenteral nutrition-associated <lb/>cholestasis; SD, standard deviation; IGR, increased growth retardation. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 06 March 2024 <lb/>| DOI 10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/>Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>into the HGP group or the non-HGP group. A propensity score matching analysis <lb/>was used to adjust for confounding factors, including gestational age, twin or <lb/>multiple births, sex, antenatal steroid administration, delivery mode and <lb/>hypertensive disorders of pregnancy. The main complications and the short-<lb/>term growth status during hospitalization were evaluated in the HGP and non-<lb/>HGP groups. <lb/>Results: A total of 2,514 infants were eligible for analysis. After matching, there <lb/>were 437 infants in the HGP group and 874 infants in the non-HGP group. <lb/>There was no significant difference between the two groups in main <lb/>complications including respiratory distress syndrome, bronchopulmonary <lb/>dysplasia, necrotizing enterocolitis, retinopathy of prematurity, patent ductus <lb/>arteriosus, culture positive sepsis, intraventricular hemorrhage, periventricular <lb/>leukomalacia, anemia, feeding intolerance, metabolic bone disease of <lb/>prematurity, or parenteral nutrition-associated cholestasis. The incidences of <lb/>extrauterine growth retardation and increased growth retardation for weight and <lb/>head circumference in the non-HGP group were all higher than those in the <lb/>HGP group after matching (P &lt; 0.05). <lb/>Conclusions: HGP did not worsen the short-term outcomes of the surviving very <lb/>preterm infants, as it did not lead to a higher risk of the main neonatal <lb/>complications, and the infants&apos; growth improved during hospitalization. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>hyperglycemia in pregnancy, preterm infant, outcomes, complication, growth retardation <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Hyperglycemia in pregnancy (HGP) is a maternal metabolic <lb/>disorder, and its incidence is increasing worldwide. It includes two <lb/>conditions known as gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) and <lb/>pregestational diabetes mellitus (PGDM), which are defined as <lb/>abnormal glucose tolerance first found during pregnancy or diabetes <lb/>before pregnancy, respectively. Some studies noted that HGP was <lb/>associated with increased adverse effects on fetuses and infants, <lb/>such as intrauterine hypoxia, preterm birth, birth injury, neonatal <lb/>hypoglycemia, respiratory distress, and hyperbilirubinemia (1, 2). <lb/>In addition, HGP can cause fetal overgrowth or backwardness <lb/>in utero and increase the occurrence of macrosomia or small <lb/>for gestational age (SGA) (3). These changes in the growth <lb/>trajectory and metabolic level in infancy can even increase the <lb/>risk of obesity and neurological damage in childhood or <lb/>adulthood (4-7). Therefore, HGP has been regarded as a high-<lb/>risk factor for short-and long-term adverse outcomes in offspring. <lb/>However, the impact of HGP on neonatal complications of very <lb/>preterm infants (VPIs, gestational age &lt;32 weeks) remains <lb/>uncertain. There are some conflicting results in previous studies. <lb/>Boghossian NS et al. (8) found that extremely preterm infants born <lb/>to insulin-dependent diabetic mothers had higher risks of <lb/>necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), sepsis, and small head <lb/>circumference but did not have an increased risk of patent ductus <lb/>arteriosus <lb/>(PDA), <lb/>intraventricular <lb/>hemorrhage <lb/>(IVH), <lb/>periventricular leukomalacia (PVL), or bronchopulmonary <lb/>dysplasia (BPD). Grandi C et al. (9) found that only NEC was <lb/>significantly higher in very low birth weight infants born to <lb/>mothers with HGP. Opara CN et al. (10) noted that HGP was <lb/>associated with an increased incidence and severity of retinopathy <lb/>of prematurity (ROP). In contrast, other reports indicated that <lb/>HGP did not lead to an elevated risk of in-hospital mortality or <lb/>severe morbidity in preterm infants, including respiratory distress <lb/>syndrome (RDS), severe IVH (grade 3-4), PDA treatment, ROP <lb/>treatment, BPD or NEC (11-13). These controversial results may be <lb/>partly attributed to the differences in the characteristics of the study <lb/>populations and diagnostic criteria for HGP. <lb/>Additionally, the influence of HGP on the growth of VPIs <lb/>should be assessed in more detail. Previous studies have found <lb/>maternal early-pregnancy blood glucose levels are associated with <lb/>altered fetal growth patterns, characterized by decreased fetal <lb/>growth rates in mid-pregnancy and increased fetal growth rates <lb/>from late pregnancy onward, which indicate a limited effect of <lb/>increased fetal growth rates in fetuses &lt;32 weeks (14). In contrast, <lb/>they are more prone to extrauterine growth retardation (EUGR) due <lb/>to immaturity and various complications after birth (15). Severe <lb/>EUGR will negatively impact the growth potential of infants (16). <lb/>Therefore, it is necessary to further identify the impact of HGP <lb/>on neonatal complications and growth in VPIs. In this study, to <lb/>minimize the differences in the study population and <lb/>confounding factors, we analyzed the clinical data of VPIs from <lb/>28 hospitals in seven regions of China using propensity score <lb/>matching (PSM) analysis. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Study population <lb/>This was a secondary analysis of clinical data collected by the <lb/>Nutritional Committee of Neonatology Branch of Chinese <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>02 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>Medical Doctor Association, National Multicenter EUGR <lb/>Collaborative Group. The collaborative group was founded in <lb/>2019 to investigate the incidence and risk factors for EUGR in <lb/>VPIs during hospitalization in different regions of mainland China <lb/>(17). The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee <lb/>of the Women and Children&apos;s Hospital Affiliated to Xiamen <lb/>University/Xiamen Maternity and Child Health Care Hospital <lb/>(KY-2019-016). It was registered at http://www.chictr.org.cn, and <lb/>the registration number was ChiCTR1900023418. <lb/>The inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) gestational age &lt;32 <lb/>weeks; (2) admission within 24 h after birth; and (3) a <lb/>hospitalization stay ≥2 weeks. The exclusion criteria were as <lb/>follows: (1) severe congenital malformations or inherited <lb/>metabolic diseases; (2) in-hospital death, treatment interruption <lb/>or automatic discharge; and (3) incomplete or missing data. The <lb/>criteria for discharge were as follows: (1) a weight of 1 800-<lb/>2,000 g or more; (2) a corrected age ≥36 weeks; (3) cured <lb/>primary disease and stable vital signs (infants with BPD were <lb/>allowed to be discharged with oxygen); and (4) oral feeding, with <lb/>a milk volume reaching full enteral feeding. Finally, 2,514 infants <lb/>were included in the analysis (17). In this study, they were <lb/>divided into the HGP or non-HGP groups according to whether <lb/>the mother had HGP or not. <lb/>2.2 Data collection <lb/>From September 2019 to December 2020, the clinical data of <lb/>VPIs admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) of the <lb/>28 included hospitals located in seven regions of mainland China <lb/>were collected prospectively, including four maternal/child health <lb/>centers, eleven children&apos;s hospitals and thirteen tertiary general <lb/>hospitals. According to a unified questionnaire, the general <lb/>clinical data of maternal and pregnancy disorders, perinatal <lb/>conditions, neonatal growth, nutritional support during <lb/>hospitalization, neonatal complications and main treatments were <lb/>collected. To minimize bias among hospitals and investigators, <lb/>comprehensive and systematic training was provided to all the <lb/>staff involved in the survey. Data collected by the researcher at <lb/>each collaborative NICU were supervised and checked by the <lb/>NICU director, who was responsible for quality assurance. <lb/>2.3 Definitions and classifications <lb/>The diagnostic criteria of HGP referred to the guidelines issued <lb/>by the WHO in 2013 (18). Intrauterine growth retardation (IUGR) <lb/>referred to a birth weight, length or head circumference below the <lb/>10th percentile of the growth curve of infants with the same sex <lb/>and gestational age (19). The diagnostic criteria of the main <lb/>complications were the same as those previously described (17). <lb/>Briefly, neonatal RDS was diagnosed in preterm infants with <lb/>respiratory distress shortly after birth. The criterion for grading <lb/>RDS was based on the chest x-ray, and grade 3-4 indicating <lb/>severe RDS. BPD was defined as oxygen dependence for at least <lb/>28 days, and moderate to severe BPD was defined as the need for <lb/>oxygen therapy, positive pressure ventilation or mechanical <lb/>ventilation at the corrected age of 36 weeks or at discharge. The <lb/>diagnosis and grading of NEC were defined according to the <lb/>modified Bell criteria. The diagnosis of early-onset sepsis (EOS) <lb/>or late-onset sepsis (LOS) was defined as clinical symptoms <lb/>before or after 72 h of admission, with or without positive <lb/>cultures from blood or cerebrospinal fluid samples. PDA was <lb/>diagnosed by echocardiography after 72 h of admission, and <lb/>hemodynamically significant PDA (hsPDA) was defined as an <lb/>arterial duct diameter &gt;1.5 mm, a left atrial diameter/aortic <lb/>diameter ≥1.4 or a left ventricular end-diastolic diameter/aortic <lb/>diameter ≥2.1 accompanied by one of the following clinical <lb/>manifestations: heart murmur, tachycardia (sustained ≥160 beats/ <lb/>min), increased breathing, increased pulse pressure (&gt;25 mm <lb/>Hg), hypotension, water pulse, or cardiac enlargement. Treated <lb/>PDA referred to hsPDA requiring fluid intake limitation, the <lb/>administration of diuretics, ibuprofen, or acetaminophen, or <lb/>surgical ligation. ROP and its grades were defined by the <lb/>international classification of ROP. ROP treatment referred to <lb/>intravitreal drug injection, laser therapy or surgery intervention. <lb/>Both IVH and PVL were diagnosed by cranial ultrasonography <lb/>or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Papile&apos;s criterion was <lb/>used to grade IVH, and grades 3-4 was regarded as severe IVH. <lb/>PVL was defined as the degeneration of white matter adjacent to <lb/>the cerebral ventricles following cerebral hypoxia or brain <lb/>ischemia. Anemia was defined as a hemoglobin (Hb) level <lb/>≤130 g/L in venous blood or ≤145 g/L in capillary blood within <lb/>2 weeks after birth and an Hb level ≤100 g/L in venous blood or <lb/>≤110 g/L in capillary blood two weeks later. EUGR referred to a <lb/>weight, length or head circumference at 36 weeks of corrected <lb/>age or at discharge that was below the 10th percentile according <lb/>to the Fenton growth chart for preterm infants. Feeding <lb/>intolerance (FI) was defined as gastric retention up to 25%-50% <lb/>of the previous feeding amount, abdominal distension or bloody <lb/>stool, vomiting or bile reflux after repeated feeding, or coffee-like <lb/>substances in the stomach. Metabolic bone disease of prematurity <lb/>(MBDP) was defined as a serum alkaline phosphatase level <lb/>&gt;900 IU/L, accompanied by a serum phosphorus level <lb/>&lt;1.8 mmol/L. Parenteral nutrition-associated cholestasis (PNAC) <lb/>was defined as conjugated bilirubin levels &gt;1.5 mg/dl (25 μmol/L) <lb/>at 2 consecutive measurements by spectrophotometric <lb/>quantitation, followed by parenteral nutrition for more than 14 <lb/>days and the exclusion of other diseases. Total enteral feeding <lb/>was defined as an enteral feeding amount reaching 150 ml/(kg•d) <lb/>or a total calorie intake reaching 110 kcal/(kg•d). Growth velocity <lb/>(GV) was calculated as follows: GV[g/(kg•d)] = [1,000×ln(Wn/ <lb/>W1)]/(Dn-D1), where Wn is the discharge weight (g), W1 is the <lb/>birth weight (g), Dn is the length of hospital stay (d), and D1 is <lb/>the time to return to birth weight (d). <lb/>2.4 Statistical analysis <lb/>All data were analyzed using SPSS 26.0 software (IBM, <lb/>Armonk, NY, USA). We conducted a 1:2 matched analysis by <lb/>PSM with a nearest-neighbor matching algorithm to adjust for <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>03 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>differences in baseline characteristics between the two groups, <lb/>including gestational age, twin or multiple births, sex, antenatal <lb/>steroid administration, delivery mode and hypertensive disorders <lb/>in pregnancy. These covariates were selected based on reported <lb/>studies (15, 20). Continuous variables are expressed as the mean <lb/>± standard deviation (SD) or median (IQR) according to whether <lb/>the distribution was skewed and were analyzed using a t test or <lb/>Mann-Whitney test. Categorical variables are expressed as <lb/>frequencies (%) and were analyzed using Pearson&apos;s chi-square <lb/>test. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 General characteristics <lb/>In total, 2,514 infants were eligible for statistical analysis (17). <lb/>Before matching, there were 437 infants in the HGP group and <lb/>2,077 infants in the non-HGP group; after matching, the <lb/>numbers of infants in the two groups were 437 and 874, <lb/>respectively. The population characteristics of the two groups <lb/>after matching are shown in Table 1. After matching, all six <lb/>covariates were well balanced, with no significant differences <lb/>between the two groups. <lb/>It was very interesting that fewer infants in the HGP group had <lb/>low Apgar scores (≤7) both at 1 min and 5 min after matching <lb/>(P &lt; 0.05). Moreover, fewer infants in the HGP group required <lb/>invasive ventilation after matching (47.1% vs. 53.2%, P = 0.038). <lb/>No significant difference was found between the two groups in <lb/>the median duration of invasive ventilation, the percentage of <lb/>infants requiring noninvasive ventilation, the median duration of <lb/>noninvasive ventilation, the median total duration of ventilation, <lb/>or the mean corrected age at discharge after matching. <lb/>3.2 The impact of HGP on neonatal <lb/>complications during hospitalization <lb/>To clarify the impact of HGP on the short-term outcomes of <lb/>VPIs, we summarized the main complications of the hospitalized <lb/>infants and made comparisons between the two groups. After <lb/>matching, no difference was noted between the two groups in the <lb/>total incidence of infants with RDS (total RDS and severe RDS), <lb/>BPD (total BPD and moderate to severe BPD), NEC (NEC with <lb/>Bell stage ≥Ⅱa and NEC surgery), ROP (total ROP and ROP <lb/>treatment), PDA (total PDA diagnosed after 72 h and PDA <lb/>treatment), IVH (total IVH and severe IVH), culture-positive <lb/>sepsis (EOS and LOS), anemia (total anemia and anemia <lb/>requiring red blood cell transfusion), PVL, FI, MBDP or PNAC. <lb/>These are shown in Table 2. <lb/>3.3 The effect of HGP on fetal and neonatal <lb/>growth <lb/>Birth weight, length, and head circumference can reflect fetal <lb/>growth. After matching, the mean birth weight, length, and head <lb/>circumference were similar between the two groups, as well as <lb/>the incidence of IUGR respectively. <lb/>During hospitalization, there was no significant difference in <lb/>the percentile of weight loss, age at birth weight recovery, weight <lb/>gained per day after birth weight recovery, length or head <lb/>circumference increased per week between the HGP group and <lb/>the non-HGP group after matching. <lb/>At discharge or at 36 weeks of corrected age, a significant <lb/>difference was noted only in EUGR for weight and head <lb/>circumference (44.5% vs. 36.2%, P = 0.004; 35.5% vs. 28.6%, P = <lb/>0.013), not for length after matching. <lb/>In addition, we calculated the percentage of infants with <lb/>increased growth retardation (IGR) from birth to discharge or at <lb/>36 weeks of corrected age. After matching, the percentages of <lb/>IGR for weight and head circumference, but not for length, in <lb/>the non-HGP group were higher than those in the HGP group <lb/>(40.7% vs. 33.6%, P = 0.013; 26.4% vs. 20.4%, P = 0.016). All these <lb/>are shown in Table 3. <lb/>3.4 Nutritional management during <lb/>hospitalization <lb/>Nutrition intake is very important for infant growth. In this <lb/>study, we also analyzed the nutritional management of the <lb/>infants during hospitalization (Table 4). After matching, the <lb/>TABLE 1 The population characteristics between the HGP group and the <lb/>non-HGP group. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>HGP <lb/>(No. = 437) <lb/>Non-HGP <lb/>(No. = 874) <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>Matching factors <lb/>Gestational age, weeks <lb/>29.71 ± 1.49 <lb/>29.71 ± 1.57 <lb/>0.970 <lb/>&lt;28 weeks <lb/>61 (14.0) <lb/>120 (13.7) <lb/>0.910 <lb/>28-31 weeks <lb/>376 (86.0) <lb/>754 (86.3) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>243 (55.6) <lb/>473 (54.1) <lb/>0.610 <lb/>Female <lb/>194 (44.4) <lb/>401 (45.9) <lb/>Twin or multiple birth <lb/>177 (40.5) <lb/>348 (39.8) <lb/>0.811 <lb/>Antenatal steroids administration <lb/>Total <lb/>338 (77.3) <lb/>676 (77.3) <lb/>&gt;0.999 <lb/>Partial course <lb/>121 (27.7) <lb/>232 (26.5) <lb/>0.660 <lb/>Complete course <lb/>217 (49.7) <lb/>444 (50.8) <lb/>0.696 <lb/>Mothers with HDP <lb/>60 (13.7) <lb/>118 (13.5) <lb/>0.909 <lb/>Cesarean section <lb/>265 (60.6) <lb/>509 (58.2) <lb/>0.404 <lb/>Other factors <lb/>Apgar ≤7 at 1 min <lb/>140 (32.0) <lb/>335 (38.3) <lb/>0.025 <lb/>Apgar ≤7 at 5 min <lb/>33 (7.6) <lb/>112 (12.8) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Required invasive ventilation <lb/>206 (47.1) <lb/>465 (53.2) <lb/>0.038 <lb/>Duration of invasive ventilation, days <lb/>0 (0-3.0) <lb/>0.9 (0-4.0) <lb/>0.879 <lb/>Required non-invasive ventilation <lb/>416 (95.2) <lb/>838 (95.9) <lb/>0.566 <lb/>Duration of non-invasive <lb/>ventilation, days <lb/>15.0 (6.0-29.0) 16.0 (6.0-29.0) <lb/>0.442 <lb/>Total duration of ventilation, days <lb/>17.0 (7.0-33.0) 19.0 (7.0-33.0) <lb/>0.552 <lb/>Length of hospitalization, days <lb/>49.24 ± 19.91 <lb/>50.74 ± 19.83 <lb/>0.198 <lb/>Corrected age at discharge, weeks <lb/>36.77 ± 1.90 <lb/>36.97 ± 1.87 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>HGP, hyperglycemia in pregnancy; HDP, hypertensive disorders of pregnancy. <lb/>Values are mean ± SD, median (IQR) or frequency (%). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>04 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>initial time of enteral feeding in the non-HGP group was slightly <lb/>later than that in the HGP group (24.0 (9.0-44.0) vs. 20.5 (5.0-<lb/>30.0) h, P = 0.009). In addition, cumulative fasting time and age <lb/>at reaching the oral calorie intake target were also longer in the <lb/>non-HGP group than in the HGP group after matching (24.0 <lb/>(17.0-34.0) vs. 23.0 (15.0-32.0) d, P &lt; 0.05). After matching, <lb/>age at achieving total enteral feeding, duration of parenteral <lb/>nutrition, cumulative calories in the first week of <lb/>hospitalization, age at reaching total calorie intake target, <lb/>cumulative amino acid dose in the first week and during the <lb/>whole hospitalization period, cumulative dose of fat emulsion <lb/>in the first week and during the whole hospitalization period, <lb/>were all similar between the two groups. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>In this study, we identified that HGP did not worsen the short-<lb/>term outcomes of the surviving VPIs. Specifically, the VPIs born to <lb/>mothers with HGP did not have a higher risk of main <lb/>complications, including RDS, BPD, NEC, ROP, PDA, IVH, <lb/>PVL, culture-positive sepsis, anemia, FI, MBDP or PNAC. In <lb/>addition, these infants had a lower incidence of EUGR for weight <lb/>and head circumference at discharge or at 36 weeks of corrected <lb/>age, as well as less for weight and head circumference <lb/>during hospitalization. <lb/>To date, only a few studies have explored the association <lb/>between HGP and short-term outcomes in VPIs or very low <lb/>birth weight infants (8-13, 21). The study results were consistent <lb/>regarding the impact of HGP on the increased risk of RDS, BPD, <lb/>severe IVH, PDA requiring treatment, PVL and birth asphyxia <lb/>but were conflicting regarding NEC (8, 9) and ROP (10). These <lb/>inconsistent results may be due to the poor control of <lb/>confounding factors and the difference in the inclusion criteria <lb/>and subjects. To minimize the confounding effect, we conducted <lb/>a 1:2 matched analysis by PSM with a nearest-neighbor matching <lb/>algorithm to adjust for the six covariates, including gestational <lb/>age, sex, antenatal steroid administration, delivery mode, twin or <lb/>multiple births, and maternal gestational hypertension. After <lb/>matching, we did not find a significant difference in the <lb/>occurrence of RDS, BPD, PDA requiring treatment, EOS, IVH or <lb/>PVL between the HGP group and the non-HGP group, which is <lb/>consistent with the studies mentioned above (11-13). <lb/>RDS has been reported to increase in infants born to mothers <lb/>with GDM (2). In recent years, there were three meta-analysis <lb/>TABLE 2 The neonatal complications during hospitalization between the <lb/>HGP group and the non-HGP group. <lb/>Complications <lb/>HGP <lb/>(No. = 437) <lb/>Non-HGP <lb/>(No. = 874) <lb/>P value <lb/>RDS <lb/>Total <lb/>309 (70.7) <lb/>597 (68.3) <lb/>0.375 <lb/>Severe (grade 3-4) <lb/>57 (13.0) <lb/>150 (17.2) <lb/>0.054 <lb/>BPD <lb/>Total <lb/>214 (49.0) <lb/>434 (49.7) <lb/>0.815 <lb/>Moderate to severe <lb/>74 (16.9) <lb/>161 (18.4) <lb/>0.508 <lb/>NEC <lb/>Bell stage ≥Ⅱa <lb/>43 (9.8) <lb/>69 (7.9) <lb/>0.235 <lb/>Surgery NEC <lb/>6 (1.4) <lb/>13 (1.5) <lb/>0.870 <lb/>ROP <lb/>Total <lb/>146 (33.4) <lb/>265 (30.3) <lb/>0.256 <lb/>Treated ROP <lb/>14 (3.2) <lb/>23 (2.6) <lb/>0.555 <lb/>PDA <lb/>Diagnosed after 72 h <lb/>237 (54.2) <lb/>466 (53.3) <lb/>0.754 <lb/>Treated PDA <lb/>153 (35.0) <lb/>296 (33.9) <lb/>0.681 <lb/>IVH <lb/>Total <lb/>164 (37.5) <lb/>316 (36.2) <lb/>0.627 <lb/>Severe (grade 3-4) <lb/>9 (2.1) <lb/>18 (2.1) <lb/>&gt;0.999 <lb/>Culture positive sepsis <lb/>Early onset <lb/>15 (3.4) <lb/>16 (1.8) <lb/>0.072 <lb/>Late onset <lb/>38 (8.7) <lb/>66 (7.6) <lb/>0.470 <lb/>Anemia <lb/>Total <lb/>365 (83.5) <lb/>745 (85.2) <lb/>0.416 <lb/>RBC transfusion <lb/>254 (58.1) <lb/>545 (62.4) <lb/>0.139 <lb/>PVL <lb/>29 (6.6) <lb/>47 (5.4) <lb/>0.358 <lb/>Feeding intolerance <lb/>174 (39.8) <lb/>312 (35.7) <lb/>0.146 <lb/>MBDP <lb/>13 (3.0) <lb/>24 (2.7) <lb/>0.814 <lb/>PNAC <lb/>40 (9.2) <lb/>102 (11.7) <lb/>0.167 <lb/>HGP, hyperglycemia in pregnancy; RDS, respiratory distress syndrome; BPD, <lb/>bronchopulmonary dysplasia; NEC, necrotizing enterocolitis; ROP, retinopathy of <lb/>prematurity; IVH, intraventricular hemorrhage; PDA, patent ductus arteriosus; <lb/>RBC, red blood cells; PVL, periventricular leukomalacia; MBDP, metabolic bone <lb/>disease of prematurity; PNAC, parenteral nutrition-associated cholestasis. Values <lb/>are frequency (%). <lb/>TABLE 3 The fetal and neonatal growth between the HGP group and the <lb/>non-HGP group. <lb/>Factors <lb/>HGP <lb/>(No. = 437) <lb/>Non-HGP <lb/>(No. = 874) <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>At birth <lb/>Birth weight, gram <lb/>1,360 ± 317 <lb/>1,329 ± 293 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>Body length, cm <lb/>38.4 ± 3.2 <lb/>38.3 ± 3.3 <lb/>0.789 <lb/>Head circumference, cm <lb/>27.3 ± 2.0 <lb/>27.1 ± 2.1 <lb/>0.283 <lb/>IUGR for birth weight <lb/>11 (2.5) <lb/>33 (3.8) <lb/>0.233 <lb/>IUGR for body length <lb/>40 (9.2) <lb/>96 (11.0) <lb/>0.305 <lb/>IUGR for head circumference <lb/>36 (8.2) <lb/>79 (9.0) <lb/>0.629 <lb/>Growth rate during hospitalization <lb/>Percentile of weight loss, % <lb/>6.4 ± 4.3 <lb/>6.6 ± 4.2 <lb/>0.514 <lb/>Age at birth weight recovery, days <lb/>9.4 ± 5.9 <lb/>9.1 ± 4.3 <lb/>0.387 <lb/>Weight gained after recovering birth <lb/>weight, grams/(kg.d) <lb/>16.1 ± 5.2 <lb/>16.5 ± 6.2 <lb/>0.227 <lb/>Body length, cm/week <lb/>0.93 ± 0.38 <lb/>0.90 ± 0.41 <lb/>0.201 <lb/>Head circumference, cm/week <lb/>0.62 ± 0.26 <lb/>0.63 ± 0.27 <lb/>0.935 <lb/>At discharge or at 36 weeks of <lb/>corrected age <lb/>Body weight, gram <lb/>2,351 ± 350 <lb/>2,338 ± 390 <lb/>0.534 <lb/>Body length, cm <lb/>45.0 ± 2.3 <lb/>45.0 ± 2.6 <lb/>0.958 <lb/>Head circumference, cm <lb/>31.7 ± 1.4 <lb/>31.7 ± 1.6 <lb/>0.435 <lb/>EUGR for body weight <lb/>158 (36.2) <lb/>389 (44.5) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>EUGR for body length <lb/>162 (37.1) <lb/>370 (42.3) <lb/>0.067 <lb/>EUGR for head circumference <lb/>125 (28.6) <lb/>310 (35.5) <lb/>0.013 <lb/>IGR from birth to discharge or <lb/>36 weeks of corrected age <lb/>IGR for body weight <lb/>147 (33.6) <lb/>356 (40.7) <lb/>0.013 <lb/>IGR for body length <lb/>122 (27.9) <lb/>274 (31.4) <lb/>0.202 <lb/>IGR for head circumference <lb/>89 (20.4) <lb/>231 (26.4) <lb/>0.016 <lb/>HGP, hyperglycemia in pregnancy; IUGR, intrauterine growth retardation; EUGR, <lb/>extrauterine growth retardation. <lb/>IGR, increased growth retardation. Values are mean ± SD or frequency (%). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>05 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>studies referring to mothers with GDM and neonatal <lb/>complications. One study was published in 2019 and noted that <lb/>the odds ratio of RDS was higher in women with GDM and <lb/>insulin use (22). The other two studies were published in 2022 <lb/>and pointed out that regardless of the GDM screening criteria, <lb/>the risk of RDS significantly increased in women with GDM <lb/>compared with the non-GDM group (23, 24). The populations <lb/>involved in all the above meta-analysis studies included term and <lb/>preterm infants. In the survival VPIs, we did not find that HGP <lb/>increased the risk of RDS. Prematurity is the chief cause of RDS, <lb/>and the risk for developing RDS is negatively correlated with <lb/>gestational age (25). Surfactant appears at approximately <lb/>24 weeks of gestation in the cytosol of type II pneumocytes and <lb/>increases with gestational age. It is not measurable in the <lb/>amniotic fluid until approximately 32 weeks (26). Insulin can <lb/>inhibit the secretion of glucocorticoids, which can accelerate <lb/>fetal lung maturation. Women with HGP always have <lb/>hyperinsulinemia, which delays fetal lung maturation and partly <lb/>contributes to RDS. In our study, because the VPIs had a high <lb/>incidence of RDS, the statistical effect of GDM on lung <lb/>maturation might be weakened. <lb/>Consistent with the studies of Persson M et al. and Razak A <lb/>et al. (11, 13), our study found that the risk of NEC in the <lb/>surviving VPIs born to mothers with HGP did not increase when <lb/>compared with the non-HGP group. However, two other studies <lb/>reported that maternal diabetes was a risk factor for NEC in <lb/>preterm infants. One was from Latin America (9), and they <lb/>examined the in-hospital mortality and morbidity in very low <lb/>birth weight infants born to mothers with and without diabetes <lb/>mellitus. After logistic regression analysis, they found that NEC <lb/>(grades 2-3) was the only condition independently associated <lb/>with diabetes mellitus. Another study was from the Eunice <lb/>Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human <lb/>Development Neonatal Research Network (8). They examined <lb/>morbidity in infants born at 22-28 weeks of gestation to mothers <lb/>with insulin-dependent diabetes. The results showed that the <lb/>infants born to mothers with insulin use before pregnancy had a <lb/>higher risk of NEC; however, in this study, the incidence of <lb/>maternal hypertension was also higher in these infants, which <lb/>was found to be associated with NEC among very low birth <lb/>weight infants (27). <lb/>ROP remains one of the predominant causes of blindness in <lb/>preterm infants. The incidence varies with gestational age and <lb/>birth weight (28). Several studies have assessed the other risk <lb/>factors for severe ROP, including sepsis, RDS, BPD, PDA, <lb/>neonatal hyperglycemia, blood transfusion, supplemental oxygen <lb/>administration, mechanical ventilation, and preeclampsia (29-31). <lb/>Opara CN et al. (10) found that maternal diabetes was associated <lb/>with ROP and that the strength of the association increased with <lb/>increasing ROP severity in very low birth weight infants, but the <lb/>baseline characteristics, including gestational age, birth weight, <lb/>neonatal steroid use and sepsis, were significantly different. In <lb/>our study, after matching the confounding covariates in the <lb/>baseline characteristics between the two groups, we did not find <lb/>a significant association between ROP and HGP in VPIs. This is <lb/>similar to other studies (8-13). <lb/>In mothers with HGP, intrauterine hyperglycemia and <lb/>hyperinsulinemia can affect fetal growth, and the impact can last <lb/>for some time after birth. In our study, the incidence of IUGR at <lb/>birth was low in VPIs and were comparable between the HGP <lb/>group and the non-HGP group after matching. At discharge or <lb/>at 36 weeks of corrected age, the incidence of EUGR became <lb/>high. These results were similar to those of previous studies <lb/>(32, 33). In addition, we found that the VPIs in the HGP group <lb/>had a lower rate of EUGR for weight and head circumference, as <lb/>well as less IGR during hospitalization. Although the clear <lb/>mechanisms are still unknown, there are some possible <lb/>explanations in previous reports. Animal experiments found that <lb/>rats exposed to maternal diabetes during pregnancy exhibited <lb/>hyperinsulinemia, which could accelerate physical growth by <lb/>increasing the storage of fat and protein. Other studies reported <lb/>that exposure to human milk from mothers with HGP could <lb/>change hypothalamic function, which might affect the satiety <lb/>center and the regulation of body weight and metabolism <lb/>(34, 35). Interestingly, the metabolic state of germ-free mice <lb/>receiving meconium from VPIs changed significantly with a <lb/>reduction in the plasma levels of insulin and leptin and resulted <lb/>in obvious growth restriction. This suggested that the unique <lb/>microbiota in VPIs may be prone to growth failure (36). <lb/>However, Ting Chen (37) et al. found that the richness and <lb/>diversity of the gut microbiota in mothers with HGP decreased, <lb/>and the pathways related to carbohydrate and nucleotide <lb/>TABLE 4 Comparisons of nutritional intake during hospitalization between the HGP group and the non-HGP group. <lb/>Factors <lb/>HGP (No. = 437) <lb/>Non-HGP (No. = 874) <lb/>P value <lb/>Time to start enteral feeding, hours <lb/>20.5 (5.0-30.0) <lb/>24.0 (9.0-44.0) <lb/>0.009 <lb/>Age at achieving total enteral feeding, days <lb/>25.0 (16.0-35.0) <lb/>26.0 (18.0-37.0) <lb/>0.068 <lb/>Duration of parenteral nutrition, days <lb/>21.0 (12.0-32.0) <lb/>21.0 (14.0-31.5) <lb/>0.151 <lb/>Cumulative fasting time, days <lb/>1.5 (0.7-5.0) <lb/>2.0 (1.0-5.0) <lb/>0.035 <lb/>Cumulative calories in the 1st week of hospitalization, kcal/kg <lb/>505 (430-577) <lb/>496 (419-562) <lb/>0.074 <lb/>Age at reaching total calorie intake target, days <lb/>9.0 (6.0-15.0) <lb/>9.0 (7.0-15.0) <lb/>0.123 <lb/>Age at reaching oral calorie intake target, days <lb/>23.0 (15.0-32.0) <lb/>24.0 (17.0-34.0) <lb/>0.044 <lb/>Cumulative amino acid dose in the 1st week of hospitalization, g/kg <lb/>16.0 (12.9-18.5) <lb/>16.1 (13.4-18.5) <lb/>0.320 <lb/>Cumulative amino acid dose during hospitalization, g/kg <lb/>45.4 (24.0-75.5) <lb/>46.0 (27.0-74.3) <lb/>0.587 <lb/>Cumulative dose of fat emulsion in the 1st week of hospitalization, g/kg <lb/>12.7 (9.7-15.0) <lb/>12.5 (10.0-15.0) <lb/>0.763 <lb/>Cumulative dose of fat emulsion during hospitalization, g/kg <lb/>37.6 (19.4-63.2) <lb/>38.5 (21.3-62.6) <lb/>0.592 <lb/>HGP, hyperglycemia in pregnancy; Values are median (IQR). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>06 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>metabolism were enriched, suggesting that maternal HGP may <lb/>promote the growth of high-energy-supplying microbiota by <lb/>promoting succession and thereby alter the metabolism of <lb/>offspring. On the other hand, postnatal nutrition intake is very <lb/>important to the growth of VPIs. Delayed enteral feeding and <lb/>increased fasting time are associated with EUGR (38, 39). In our <lb/>study, although there was no significant difference between the <lb/>two groups in the duration of parenteral nutrition or age at <lb/>reaching the total calorie intake target, the initial time of enteral <lb/>feeding in the non-HGP group was later than that in the HGP <lb/>group. Moreover, the cumulative fasting time and age at reaching <lb/>the oral calorie intake target were longer in the non-HGP group <lb/>than in the HGP group. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>In conclusion, our study found that HGP did not worsen the <lb/>short-term outcomes of surviving VPIs, as it did not lead to a <lb/>higher risk of the main neonatal complications and even led to <lb/>improved growth during hospitalization. However, there are still <lb/>some limitations in our study. First, the VPIs eligible for analyses <lb/>were only survivors and were not based on the whole population. <lb/>Second, more details, including the pattern of HGP (GDM or <lb/>PGDM) and the treatment of HGP before delivery, could not be <lb/>analyzed. Further studies in the future are needed. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be <lb/>made available by the authors, without undue reservation. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by The Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Women and Children&apos;s Hospital Affiliated to <lb/>Xiamen University/Xiamen Maternity and Child Health Care <lb/>Hospital (KY-2019-016). The studies were conducted in <lb/>accordance with the local legislation and institutional <lb/>requirements. The human samples used in this study were <lb/>acquired from a by-product of routine care or industry. <lb/>Written informed consent for participation was not required <lb/>from the participants or the participants&apos; legal guardians/next <lb/>of kin in accordance with the national legislation and <lb/>institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>YL: Writing -original draft, Data curation, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Methodology, Software. WS: Data curation, Methodology, <lb/>Software, Writing -review &amp; editing. RZ: Data curation, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. JM: Investigation, Resources, Supervision, Visualization, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. LL: Investigation, Resources, <lb/>Supervision, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. Y-MC: <lb/>Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. X-ZY: Investigation, Resources, Software, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. Y-PQ: Investigation, Resources, <lb/>Software, Writing -review &amp; editing. LM: Investigation, <lb/>Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. RC: <lb/>Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>HW: Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. D-MC: Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. LC: Investigation, Resources, Validation, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. PX: Investigation, Resources, <lb/>Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. HM: Investigation, <lb/>Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. S-NW: <lb/>Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>F-LX: Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. RJ: Investigation, Resources, Validation, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing. X-MT: Conceptualization, Project administration, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. X-ZL: Conceptualization, <lb/>Investigation, Project administration, Resources, Software, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. FW: Conceptualization, Formal <lb/>Analysis, Project administration, Supervision, Visualization, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/>This study was supported by Guidance Project of Xiamen <lb/>Medical and Health (grant NO. 3502Z20199077 and <lb/>3502Z20214ZD1225), and Natural Science Foundation of <lb/>Guangdong Province (grant NO. 2021A1515011225). The <lb/>funding sources had no role in the study design and conduct, <lb/>data analysis, or manuscript preparation. <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We acknowledge and thank all the collaborative units in the <lb/>following hospitals and centers for providing data for this study <lb/>(Information of the Chinese Multi-center EUGR Collaborative <lb/>Group). Department of Neonatology, Women&apos;s and Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital Affiliated to Xiamen University/Xiamen maternal and <lb/>Child Health Hospital, Xiamen, Fujian, China (WS, ZZ, and X-<lb/>ZL). Department of Neonatology, the Third Affiliated Hospital of <lb/>Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China <lb/>(FW, Qianxin Tian, and Qiliang Cui). Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Shengjing Hospital of China Medical University, Shenyang, <lb/>Liaoning, China (JM, Yuan Yuan, and Ling Ren). Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Guiyang maternal and Child Health Hospital <lb/>Guiyang Children&apos;s Hospital, Guiyang, Guizhou, China (LL, <lb/>Bizhen Shi, and Yumei Wang). Department of Pediatrics, Peking <lb/>University Third Hospital, Beijing, China (Y-MC, Jinghui Zhang, <lb/>and X-MT). Department of Neonatology, Pediatric Hospital of <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>07 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Fudan University, Shanghai, China (Yan Zhu, WS, RZ, and Chao <lb/>Chen). Department of Neonatology, Guangdong Province <lb/>Maternal and Children&apos;s Hospital, Guangzhou, Guangdong, <lb/>China (Jingjing Zou and X-ZY). Department of Neonatology, <lb/>General hospital of Ningxia Medical University, Yinchuan, <lb/>Ningxia, China (Yuhuai Li, Baoyin Zhao, and Y-PQ). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Children&apos;s Hospital of Hebei <lb/>Province, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China (Shuhua Liu and LM). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Children&apos; hospital of Nanjing <lb/>Medical University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China (Ying Xu and RC). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, The first hospital of Jilin University, <lb/>Changchun, Jilin, China (Wenli Zhou and HW). Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Quanzhou maternity and Children&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Quanzhou, Fujian, China (Zhiyong Liu and D-MC). Department <lb/>of Pediatrics, Tongji Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong <lb/>University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, Hubei, China <lb/>(Jinzhi Gao, Jing Liu, and LC). Department of Neonatology, <lb/>Liaocheng People&apos;s Hospital, Liaocheng, Shandong, China (Cong <lb/>Li, Chunyan Yang, and PX). Department of Neonatology, the <lb/>Affiliate Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical University, Hohhot, <lb/>Inner Mongolia, China (Yayu Zhang, Sile Hu, and HM). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Suzhou Municipal Hospital, Suzhou, <lb/>Jiangsu, China (Zuming Yang, Zongtai Feng, and Sannan Wang). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, The Third Affiliated Hospital of <lb/>Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China (Eryan Meng, <lb/>Lihong Shang, and Falin Xu). Department of Neonatology, <lb/>Chengdu Women&apos; and Children&apos;s Central Hospital, School of <lb/>Medicine, University of Electronic Science and Technology of <lb/>China, Chengdu, Sichuan, China (Shaoping Ou and RJ). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Hunan children&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Changsha, Hunan, China (Guinan Li) Department of <lb/>Neonatology, People&apos;s Hospital of Xinjiang Uygur Autonomous <lb/>Region, Urumqi, Xinjiang, China (Long Li). Department of <lb/>Neonatology, Guangzhou Women and Children&apos;s Medical <lb/>Center, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China (Zhe Zhang). <lb/>Department of Neonatology, Shanghai Children&apos;s Medical <lb/>Center, Shanghai, China (Fei Bei). Department of Neonatology, <lb/>Children&apos;s Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, <lb/>Chongqing, China (Chun Deng). Department of Neonatology, <lb/>the First People&apos;s Hospital of Yulin, Yulin, Guangxi, China (Ping <lb/>Su). Department of Neonatology, the People&apos;s Hospital of Baoji, <lb/>Baoji, Shanxi, China (Lingying Luo). Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Qingdao University, Qingdao, Shandong, <lb/>China (Xiaohong Liu). Departments of Neonatology, Shandong <lb/>Provincial Hospital Affiliated to Shandong First Medical <lb/>University, Jinan, Shandong, China (Lijun Wang). Departments <lb/>of Neonatology, Xi&apos;an Children&apos;s Hospital, Xi&apos;an, Shanxi, <lb/>China (Shuqun Yu). <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed <lb/>or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Szmuilowicz ED, Josefson JL, Metzger BE. Gestational diabetes <lb/>mellitus. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. (2019) 48(3):479-93. doi: 10.1016/j.ecl. <lb/>2019.05.001 <lb/>2. Preda A, Padureanu V, Mota M, Stefan AG, Comanescu AC, Radu L, et al. <lb/>Analysis of maternal and neonatal complications in a group of patients with <lb/>gestational diabetes mellitus. Medicina (Kaunas). (2021) 57(11):1170. doi: 10.3390/ <lb/>medicina57111170 <lb/>3. Yang Y, Wang Z, Mo M, Muyiduli X, Wang S, Li M, et al. The association of <lb/>gestational diabetes mellitus with fetal birth weight. J Diabetes Complications. <lb/>(2018) 32(7):635-42. doi: 10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2018.04.008 <lb/>4. Nouhjah S, Shahbazian H, Latifi SM, Malamiri RA, Ghodrati N. Body mass index <lb/>growth trajectories from birth through 24 months in Iranian infants of mothers with <lb/>gestational diabetes mellitus. Diabetes Metab Syndr. (2019) 13(1):408-12. doi: 10. <lb/>1016/j.dsx.2018.10.002 <lb/>5. Van Dam JM, Garrett AJ, Schneider LA, Hodyl NA, Goldsworthy MR, Coat S, <lb/>et al. Reduced cortical excitability, neuroplasticity, and salivary cortisol in <lb/>11-13-year-old children born to women with gestational diabetes mellitus. <lb/>EBioMedicine. (2018) 31:143-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2018.04.011 <lb/>6. Zhao YL, Ma RM, Lao TT, Chen Z, Du MY, Liang K, et al. Maternal <lb/>gestational diabetes mellitus and overweight and obesity in offspring: a study in <lb/>Chinese children. J Dev Orig Health Dis. (2015) 6(6):479-84. doi: 10.1017/ <lb/>S2040174415007205 <lb/>7. Pathirana MM, Lassi ZS, Ali A, Arstall MA, Roberts CT, Andraweera PH. <lb/>Association between metabolic syndrome and gestational diabetes mellitus in <lb/>women and their children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Endocrine. (2021) <lb/>71(2):310-20. doi: 10.1007/s12020-020-02492-1 <lb/>8. Boghossian NS, Hansen NI, Bell EF, Brumbaugh JE, Stoll BJ, Laptook AR, et al. <lb/>Outcomes of extremely preterm infants born to insulin-dependent diabetic mothers. <lb/>Pediatrics. (2016) 137(6):e20153424. doi: 10.1542/peds.2015-3424 <lb/>9. Grandi C, Tapia JL, Cardoso VC. Impact of maternal diabetes mellitus <lb/>on mortality and morbidity of very low birth weight infants: a multicenter <lb/>Latin America study. J Pediatr (Rio J). (2015) 91(3):234-41. doi: 10.1016/j.jped. <lb/>2014.08.007 <lb/>10. Opara CN, Akintorin M, Byrd A, Cirignani N, Akintorin S, Soyemi K. Maternal <lb/>diabetes mellitus as an independent risk factor for clinically significant retinopathy of <lb/>prematurity severity in neonates less than 1500 g. PLoS One. (2020) 15(8):e0236639. <lb/>doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0236639 <lb/>11. Persson M, Shah PS, Rusconi F, Reichman B, Modi N, Kusuda S, et al. <lb/>Association of maternal diabetes with neonatal outcomes of very preterm and very <lb/>low-birth-weight infants: an international cohort study. JAMA Pediatr. (2018) 172 <lb/>(9):867-75. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.1811 <lb/>12. Deryabina EG, Yakornova GV, Pestryaeva LA, Sandyreva ND. Perinatal outcome <lb/>in pregnancies complicated with gestational diabetes mellitus and very preterm birth: <lb/>case-control study. Gynecol Endocrinol. (2016) 32(sup2):52-5. doi: 10.1080/09513590. <lb/>2016.1232215 <lb/>13. Razak A, Faden M. Association of maternal diabetes mellitus with preterm infant <lb/>outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. <lb/>(2021) 106(3):271-7. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2020-320054 <lb/>14. Geurtsen ML, van Soest EEL, Voerman E, Steegers EAP, Jaddoe VWV, Gaillard <lb/>R. High maternal early-pregnancy blood glucose levels are associated with altered fetal <lb/>growth and increased risk of adverse birth outcome. Diabetologia. (2019) 62 <lb/>(10):1880-90. doi: 10.1007/s00125-019-4957-3 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>08 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>15. Zhao T, Feng HM, Caicike B, Zhu YP. Investigation into the current situation <lb/>and analysis of the factors influencing extrauterine growth retardation in preterm <lb/>infants. Front Pediatr. (2021) 9:643387. doi: 10.3389/fped.2021.643387 <lb/>16. Pampanini V, Boiani A, De Marchis C, Giacomozzi C, Navas R, Agostino R, <lb/>et al. Preterm infants with severe extrauterine growth retardation (EUGR) are at <lb/>high risk of growth impairment during childhood. Eur J Pediatr. (2015) 174 <lb/>(1):33-41. doi: 10.1007/s00431-014-2361-z <lb/>17. Shen W, Zheng Z, Lin XZ, Wu F, Tian QX, Cui QL, et al. Incidence of <lb/>extrauterine growth retardation and its risk factors in very preterm infants during <lb/>hospitalization: a multicenter prospective study. Zhongguo Dang Dai Er Ke Za Zhi. <lb/>(2022) 24(2):132-40. doi: 10.7499/j.issn.1008-8830.2111143 <lb/>18. Organization WH. Diagnostic Criteria and Classification of Hyperglycemia First <lb/>Detected in Pregnancy. (2013) Available online at: http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/ <lb/>10665/85975/1/who_nmh_mnd_13.2_eng.pdf <lb/>19. Fenton TR, Kim JH. A systematic review and meta-analysis to revise the <lb/>fenton growth chart for preterm infants. BMC Pediatr. (2013) 13:59. doi: 10.1186/ <lb/>1471-2431-13-59 <lb/>20. Zhao X, Ding L, Chen X, Zhu X, Wang J. Characteristics and risk factors for <lb/>extrauterine growth retardation in very-low-birth-weight infants. Medicine <lb/>(Baltimore). (2020) 99(47):e23104. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000023104 <lb/>21. Hitaka D, Morisaki N, Miyazono Y, Piedvache A, Nagafuji M, Takeuchi S, et al. <lb/>Neonatal outcomes of very low birthweight infants born to mothers with <lb/>hyperglycaemia in pregnancy: a retrospective cohort study in Japan. BMJ Paediatr <lb/>Open. (2019) 3(1):e000491. doi: 10.1136/bmjpo-2019-000491 <lb/>22. Li Y, Wang W, Zhang D. Maternal diabetes mellitus and risk of neonatal <lb/>respiratory distress syndrome: a meta-analysis. Acta Diabetol. (2019) 56(7):729-40. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s00592-019-01327-4 <lb/>23. Tehrani FR, Naz MSG, Bidhendi-Yarandi R, Behboudi-Gandevani S. Effect of <lb/>different types of diagnostic criteria for gestational diabetes mellitus on adverse <lb/>neonatal outcomes: a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. <lb/>Diabetes Metab J. (2022) 46(4):605-19. doi: 10.4093/dmj.2021.0178 <lb/>24. Ye W, Luo C, Huang J, Li C, Liu Z, Liu F. Gestational diabetes mellitus and <lb/>adverse pregnancy outcomes: systematic review and meta-analysis. Br Med J. (2022) <lb/>377:e067946. doi: 10.1136/bmj-2021-067946 <lb/>25. Dubin SB. Assessment of fetal lung maturity: in search of the holy grail. Clin <lb/>Chem. (1990) 36(11):1867-9. doi: 10.1093/clinchem/36.11.1867 <lb/>26. Leung-Pineda V, Gronowski AM. Biomarker tests for fetal lung maturity. <lb/>Biomark Med. (2010) 4(6):849-57. doi: 10.2217/bmm.10.109 <lb/>27. Bashiri A, Zmora E, Sheiner E, Hershkovitz R, Shoham-Vardi I, Mazor M. <lb/>Maternal hypertensive disorders are an independent risk factor for the development <lb/>of necrotizing enterocolitis in very low birth weight infants. Fetal Diagn Ther. <lb/>(2003) 18(6):404-7. doi: 10.1159/000073132 <lb/>28. Blencowe H, Lawn JE, Vazquez T, Fielder A, Gilbert C. Preterm-associated visual <lb/>impairment and estimates of retinopathy of prematurity at regional and global levels <lb/>for 2010. Pediatr Res. (2013) 74(Suppl 1):35-49. doi: 10.1038/pr.2013.205 <lb/>29. Kim SJ, Port AD, Swan R, Campbell JP, Chan RVP, Chiang MF. Retinopathy of <lb/>prematurity: a review of risk factors and their clinical significance. Surv Ophthalmol. <lb/>(2018) 63(5):618-37. doi: 10.1016/j.survophthal.2018.04.002 <lb/>30. Kumar P, Sankar MJ, Deorari A, Azad R, Chandra P, Agarwal R, et al. Risk <lb/>factors for severe retinopathy of prematurity in preterm low birth weight neonates. <lb/>Indian J Pediatr. (2011) 78(7):812-6. doi: 10.1007/s12098-011-0363-7 <lb/>31. Darlow BA, Hutchinson JL, Henderson-Smart DJ, Donoghue DA, Simpson JM, <lb/>Evans NJ, et al. Prenatal risk factors for severe retinopathy of prematurity among very <lb/>preterm infants of the Australian and New Zealand neonatal network. Pediatrics. <lb/>(2005) 115(4):990-6. doi: 10.1542/peds.2004-1309 <lb/>32. Clark RH, Thomas P, Peabody J. Extrauterine growth restriction remains a <lb/>serious problem in prematurely born neonates. Pediatrics. (2003) 111(5 Pt <lb/>1):986-90. doi: 10.1542/peds.111.5.986 <lb/>33. Multicenter Study Collaborative Group for Evaluation of Outcomes in Very Low <lb/>Birth Weight I. Risk factors for extrauterine growth retardation in very low birth <lb/>weight infants: a multicenter study. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi. (2020) 58(8):653-60. <lb/>doi: 10.3760/cma.j.cn112140-20200326-00308 <lb/>34. Plagemann A, Harder T, Janert U, Rake A, Rittel F, Rohde W, et al. <lb/>Malformations of hypothalamic nuclei in hyperinsulinemic offspring of rats with <lb/>gestational diabetes. Dev Neurosci. (1999) 21(1):58-67. doi: 10.1159/000017367 <lb/>35. Fahrenkrog S, Harder T, Stolaczyk E, Melchior K, Franke K, Dudenhausen JW, <lb/>et al. Cross-fostering to diabetic rat dams affects early development of mediobasal <lb/>hypothalamic nuclei regulating food intake, body weight, and metabolism. J Nutr. <lb/>(2004) 134(3):648-54. doi: 10.1093/jn/134.3.648 <lb/>36. Hiltunen H, Hanani H, Luoto R, Turjeman S, Ziv O, Isolauri E, et al. Preterm <lb/>infant meconium microbiota transplant induces growth failure, inflammatory <lb/>activation, and metabolic disturbances in germ-free mice. Cell Rep Med. (2021) 2 <lb/>(11):100447. doi: 10.1016/j.xcrm.2021.100447 <lb/>37. Chen T, Qin Y, Chen M, Zhang Y, Wang X, Dong T, et al. Gestational diabetes <lb/>mellitus is associated with the neonatal gut microbiota and metabolome. BMC Med. <lb/>(2021) 19(1):120. doi: 10.1186/s12916-021-01991-w <lb/>38. Kakatsaki I, Papanikolaou S, Roumeliotaki T, Anagnostatou NH, Lygerou I, <lb/>Hatzidaki E. The prevalence of small for gestational age and extrauterine growth <lb/>restriction among extremely and very preterm neonates, using different growth <lb/>curves, and its association with clinical and nutritional factors. Nutrients. (2023) 15 <lb/>(15):3290. doi: 10.3390/nu15153290 <lb/>39. Gao L, Shen W, Wu F, Mao J, Liu L, Chang YM, et al. Effect of early initiation of <lb/>enteral nutrition on short-term clinical outcomes of very premature infants: a national <lb/>multicenter cohort study in China. Nutrition. (2023) 107:111912. doi: 10.1016/j.nut. <lb/>2022.111912 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>10.3389/fped.2024.1341221 <lb/></note>


    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pediatrics <lb/></note>

    <page>09 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org </note>


	</text>

</TEI>