<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T16:35:22.947Z">11/24/2025 4:35:22 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T16:35:11.217439Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T16:35:11.217439Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/cmc.2024.048003 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>A Machine Learning Approach to Cyberbullying Detection in Arabic Tweets <lb/>Dhiaa Musleh 1 , Atta Rahman 1,* , Mohammed Abbas Alkherallah 1 , Menhal Kamel Al-Bohassan 1 , <lb/>Mustafa Mohammed Alawami 1 , Hayder Ali Alsebaa 1 , Jawad Ali Alnemer 1 , Ghazi Fayez Al-Mutairi 1 , <lb/>May Issa Aldossary 2 , Dalal A. Aldowaihi 1 and Fahd Alhaidari 3 <lb/>1 Department of Computer Science, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal <lb/>University, P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia <lb/>2 Department of Computer Information Systems, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman <lb/>Bin Faisal University, P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia <lb/>3 Department of Networks and Communications, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman <lb/>Bin Faisal University, P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia <lb/>*Corresponding Author: Atta Rahman. Email: aaurrahman@iau.edu.sa <lb/>Received: 24 November 2023 Accepted: 28 May 2024 Published: 18 July 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>With the rapid growth of internet usage, a new situation has been created that enables practicing bullying. <lb/>Cyberbullying has increased over the past decade, and it has the same adverse effects as face-to-face bullying, like <lb/>anger, sadness, anxiety, and fear. With the anonymity people get on the internet, they tend to be more aggressive and <lb/>express their emotions freely without considering the effects, which can be a reason for the increase in cyberbullying <lb/>and it is the main motive behind the current study. This study presents a thorough background of cyberbullying <lb/>and the techniques used to collect, preprocess, and analyze the datasets. Moreover, a comprehensive review of the <lb/>literature has been conducted to figure out research gaps and effective techniques and practices in cyberbullying <lb/>detection in various languages, and it was deduced that there is significant room for improvement in the Arabic <lb/>language. As a result, the current study focuses on the investigation of shortlisted machine learning algorithms <lb/>in natural language processing (NLP) for the classification of Arabic datasets duly collected from Twitter (also <lb/>known as X). In this regard, support vector machine (SVM), Naïve Bayes (NB), Random Forest (RF), Logistic <lb/>regression (LR), Bootstrap aggregating (Bagging), Gradient Boosting (GBoost), Light Gradient Boosting Machine <lb/>(LightGBM), Adaptive Boosting (AdaBoost), and eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost) were shortlisted and <lb/>investigated due to their effectiveness in the similar problems. Finally, the scheme was evaluated by well-known <lb/>performance measures like accuracy, precision, Recall, and F1-score. Consequently, XGBoost exhibited the best <lb/>performance with 89.95% accuracy, which is promising compared to the state-of-the-art. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Supervised machine learning; ensemble learning; cyberbullying; Arabic tweets; NLP <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Cyberbullying is defined as a person or group using telecommunication and digital devices to <lb/>threaten others via communication networks. It includes verbal abuse, harassment, and aggressive <lb/></body>

	<page>1034 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>words. Cyberbullying may denigrate and unfairly criticize someone or impersonate others&apos; identities. <lb/>It has harmed many individuals worldwide, particularly teenagers, as it gets more accessible on <lb/>widespread social networking sites [1]. Cyberbullying is the act of bullying on the internet, so there is <lb/>no physical damage, but the victims express psychological harm. People will be rude behind the screen, <lb/>and they are anonymous, so there is no liability for the bully. The number of people bullying the victim <lb/>is enough to affect him/her with the words. Because in real life, one is driven by a limited number, <lb/>but on the internet, it is up to thousands [2]. &quot;One in five parents around the world say their child <lb/>has experienced cyberbullying at least once in 2018&quot; [3]. Cyberbullying is rising every day so that the <lb/>numbers might become more extensive. It is, therefore, essential to prevent this by first detection, and <lb/>then remedial actions may be taken employing cyber laws. Nowadays, most use Twitter (also known <lb/>as X) to communicate and express ideas. Twitter has its own rules to stop the horrible act, whether it <lb/>is cyberbullying or other things. However, the problem is that it needs to monitor 192 million [4] when <lb/>you want to monitor up to millions of users and use the site 24 h a day and seven days a week. So, <lb/>humans cannot do this monitoring manually. On the other hand, Machine Learning (ML) has become <lb/>practical and can do the job without human intervention in real-time. Based on a survey conducted <lb/>[4], several implications of cyberbullying have been noticed, as given in Fig. 1. The first Category is <lb/>about those who experienced cyberbullying. The second Category is about its impact, and the third <lb/>Category is about the type of cyberbullying that occurred to the individuals. <lb/>Figure 1: Cyberbullying statistics about its experience, impact, and type <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1035 <lb/></page>

	<body>The survey reveals the potential frequency, harm, and kind of impact social media users have, <lb/>which is worrisome. There is clear evidence and motivation to conduct studies where cyberbullying <lb/>should be adequately monitored, and appropriate measures should be taken by the authorities to <lb/>prevent the consequences in society. It is one of the significant areas to target in Saudi Vision 2030, <lb/>which aims to transform the individual&apos;s lifestyle and improve well-being. In the literature, this task <lb/>has been frequently done for the English language; however, for the Arabic language, studies are <lb/>limited, and more research is needed, especially considering the diverse dialects in the Arabic language. <lb/>Arabic is one of the most popular languages, ranking sixth globally. There are 5.2% of Arabic users on <lb/>the internet [5]. Many teenagers use social media applications like Twitter, Snapchat, Instagram, and <lb/>TikTok. Because of bullies, teenagers may get depressed or fear facing the world. Bullying in the past <lb/>was famous in schools and is now known as cyberbullying on the internet. Many teenagers stayed at <lb/>home because of the Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), spending more time online, and due to <lb/>cyberbullying, faced anxiety and other psychological issues [5]. So, the situation demands a system to <lb/>detect cyberbullying, which can help prevent bullying. Motivated by that, in this paper, we propose to <lb/>develop a model for preprocessing Arabic tweets and detecting cyberbullying using machine learning <lb/>techniques. The proposed research aims to identify cyberbullying in Arabic tweets by automatically <lb/>applying machine learning algorithms with the help of Arabic Natural Language Processing (ANLP) <lb/>approaches. This research is motivated by relatively few studies identifying cyberbullying that have <lb/>been conducted in the Arabic language. While an overwhelming increase in the number of Arabic <lb/>speaking users has been witnessed over last few years due to extended support for the native and non-<lb/>English languages over the social media platforms in general and twitter in particular. This is first of <lb/>its kind study in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. The significant contributions and aims of the study <lb/>that makes it prominent from others, are listed below: <lb/>• Collection and preparation of a standard dataset comprising Arabic tweets collected over the <lb/>entire Arab region, especially Saudi Arabia, to comprehend diverse dialects of the language. <lb/>• A comprehensive review of related literature over the past decade for cyberbullying detection <lb/>in general and particularly in Arabic language. <lb/>• Investigation of several machine learning approaches on the self-curated and secondary dataset <lb/>from the literature. <lb/>• An improvement in the results compared to the state-of-the-art techniques in the literature. <lb/>The rest of the paper is organized as follows: Section 2 provides the background of the study, <lb/>and Section 3 is dedicated to related work. Section 4 contains the proposed methodology. Section 5 <lb/>presents results and discussion, while Section 6 concludes the study. <lb/>2 Background <lb/>Cyberbullying is defined as any harm done constantly and intentionally through the internet. <lb/>Cyberbullying has four core elements: harm, intent, repetition, and imbalance of power. Furthermore, <lb/>to be considered cyberbullying, the bully must cause harm, and the damage must be caused willingly. <lb/>Also, the harm must be repeated; a one-time insult will not be considered cyberbullying. In addition, <lb/>the bully must have a higher power. For example, they are more prevalent [6]. Another study shows an <lb/>increase in cyberbullying, as 56.1% of 351 users have admitted to being affected by cyberbullying. The <lb/>study also demonstrates that the adverse effects of cyberbullying, fear, powerlessness, anger, anxiety, <lb/>and sadness are the same as those of face-to-face bullying [7,8]. Since cyberbullying detection mainly <lb/>relies on NLP algorithms, subsections focus on the commonly used steps to provide a background. <lb/></body>

	<page>1036 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>2.1 Natural Language Processing (NLP) <lb/>Humans use Natural language to communicate, whereas computers only analyze zeros and ones <lb/>[8]. Technology today has advanced, so we can make computers study languages by transferring <lb/>them to their understanding using NLP, which assists computers in understanding human languages. <lb/>Nowadays, we use NLP a lot to communicate with computers and devices daily, for example, language <lb/>translators. However, NLP is an old concept that was proposed in [9]. Then, in 1954, Georgetown <lb/>University and IBM worked together to translate Russian sentences into English. It was an automatic <lb/>system capable of high-quality translation of 250 words and six &quot;grammar&quot; criteria [10]. <lb/>2.1.1 Tokenization <lb/>Tokenization is breaking down a phrase, sentence, paragraph, or even text document into smaller <lb/>pieces like individual words or concepts. Tokens are the names given to each of these smaller units. <lb/>Because Tokenization decreases word typographical variance, it is essential for the feature extraction <lb/>and bag of words (BoW) procedures. Consequently, the words are transformed into features using a <lb/>feature dictionary, vectors, or feature index. The feature&apos;s index is the frequency of (expression) in the <lb/>vocabulary related to its usage [11]. Further, Tokenization can be used to count numbers and the words <lb/>frequency. <lb/>2.1.2 Stemming <lb/>Stemming is the process of reducing a word to its word stem, which affixes to suffixes and prefixes <lb/>or the word&apos;s roots, known as a lemma. The Arabic language is complicated compared to other <lb/>languages in stemming techniques. Table 1 shows some examples of stemming by removing its prefixes <lb/>and suffixes. It may also consider infixes. <lb/>Table 1: Prefix, suffix, and infix example <lb/>Word <lb/>Letter(s) <lb/>Stem <lb/>Type of affix <lb/>Prefix <lb/>Prefix <lb/>Prefix <lb/>Infix <lb/>Suffix <lb/>Suffix <lb/>Suffix <lb/>Kanan et al. [12] mentioned their experience using stemming to reduce the number of words in the <lb/>text. By using the stem, all forms of a word (name, adverb, adjective, or character) are discarded by <lb/>returning the word to its original root. The study focused on removing the prefixes since the authors <lb/>believed it would make document classification more effective. They used three NLP preprocessing <lb/>tools for detection: normalization, stop word removal and stemming. Then, they applied a set of <lb/>machine learning algorithms, for classification: K-nearest neighbors (KNN), SVM, NB, RF, and J48. <lb/>When compared with and without stemming, it was found that stemming increased accuracy and <lb/>F1-score. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1037 <lb/></page>

	<body>2.1.3 Removing Stop Words <lb/>Stop words are used as unnecessary filler words for the sentence; removing them is essential. For <lb/>example, stop words in English are the &apos;A,&apos; &apos;Is,&apos; &apos;The,&apos; and &apos;Are,&apos; and there are many more. The study <lb/>focuses on removing the Arabic stop words. These words have been prepared; some are in Table 2. For <lb/>the Arabic Language, Abu El-Khair [13] defined a list that contains 56 Arabic stop words. <lb/>Table 2: Example of Arabic stop words <lb/># <lb/>W o r d <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>2.1.4 N-Gram <lb/>N-gram is a series of letters that, when combined, will help understand their meaning. We use N-<lb/>gram to spell sentences as every word, two words [14]. Following are examples of different N-grams: <lb/>&quot;My laptop&quot; (2-grams), &quot;I have kids&quot; (3-grams), and &quot;I am a student&quot; (4-grams). There are three <lb/>purposes for using N-gram: first, correcting spelling mistakes. For example, when &quot;Los Angeles&quot; is <lb/>written as &quot;Los Angeles,&quot; N-gram can predict and fix errors. Second, it can choose which words can <lb/>be grouped. For example, it can indicate that &quot;Los&quot; and &quot;Angeles&quot; can be combined as &quot;Los Angeles.&quot; <lb/>Finally, it can assist in anticipating the next word to see the whole meaning if the user erases words <lb/>like &quot;I drink&quot; and can predict the next word, &quot;water or Juice&quot; [15]. <lb/>3 Related Work <lb/>This section will summarize cyberbullying-related studies by reviewing the preprocessing methods <lb/>applied in each research, the classifiers used, the dataset provided, the features set, and the results. <lb/>3.1 Data Collection <lb/>This section presents the different approaches for data collection. First, a group of authors <lb/>obtained their data primarily from Twitter and supplemented it with other sources. For example, Al-<lb/>Ajlan et al. [16] received their dataset from Twitter utilizing the Twitter streaming API and querying <lb/>with a bad word list, and the total number of tweets is 39,000. Haider et al. [17,18] gathered their <lb/>dataset from Twitter and Facebook using two custom-built tools: a Twitter scraper written in PHP <lb/>and a Facebook scraper written in Python. In addition, the tools were linked to the mango database <lb/>server to save data. In [19], the data was gathered by AlHarbi et al. from Twitter through the <lb/>Twitter API, Microsoft-FLOW, and YouTube comments and was then compiled into a single file <lb/>comprising 100,327 tweets and comments. Mouheb et al. [20], a dataset containing 25,000 comments <lb/>and tweets, was gathered from Twitter and YouTube using the YouTube Data API and the Twitter <lb/>API, respectively. Haider et al. [21] gathered a data collection size of 34,890 from Twitter using a <lb/>program created by the author team. Kanan et al. [12] gathered their dataset from Twitter using <lb/></body>

	<page>1038 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>RStudio and Stool, statistical and mathematical tools for extracting tweets. In addition, the dataset <lb/>contains 19,650/6138 tweets. Phanomtip et al. [22] detected cyberbullying in the Twitter dataset, and <lb/>the hate speech tweet dataset was extracted from a paper study, which contained 38,686 and 68,519 <lb/>tweets, respectively. In [23], the dataset was collected by Banerjee et al. from Twitter, and the size <lb/>is 69,874. Likewise, Bharti et al. [24] collected a mixed dataset of two public datasets gathered via <lb/>Twitter API from Twitter. The dataset collected by Almutiry et al. [11] consisted of 17,748 tweets <lb/>obtained from Twitter through the Twitter API and Arabi Tools. Lokhande et al. [25] also used Twitter <lb/>as a dataset because it generates data daily. Almutairi et al. [26], after signing in to Twitter via the <lb/>developer&apos;s app, created a new application. They generated access tokens and access token secrets, <lb/>using Python programming language to access the Twitter API via an open-source library package <lb/>called tweety. Jain et al. [27] utilized a combination of several datasets containing hate speech: the <lb/>hate speech Twitter dataset, the hate speech language dataset with tweets, and the Wikipedia dataset. <lb/>In [28], a Java application was created by Al-Mamun et al. to extract social media data. Twitter <lb/>and Facebook were proposed for Bangla text. Using Facebook Graph API and Twitter Rest API, <lb/>1000 pieces were collected from Facebook, and 1400 Bangla public status updates were obtained <lb/>from Twitter. Authors in [29] used Twitter API to collect data, then preprocessed it with the NL <lb/>Toolkit (NLTK), and the term frequency-inverse document frequency (TF-IDF) vectorizer performed <lb/>the extraction. Balakrishnan et al. [30], using the GamerGate hashtag, collected data from Twitter <lb/>and used the cyberbullying dataset provided by authors in [31] gathered the information from three <lb/>distinct social networks: Twitter, Formspring, and Wikipedia, each focusing on a different aspect of <lb/>cyberbullying-racism and misogyny on Twitter, bullying on Formspring, and Wikipedia attacks. <lb/>The second group of authors collected data from sources other than Twitter in their fundamental <lb/>research. Di-Capua et al.&apos;s [32] dataset was published in public, and the data was taken from <lb/>Formspring, me, and YouTube. Alakrot et al. [33] also used YouTube; their method was to select <lb/>some YouTube channels, upload controversial videos about Arab celebrities, and collect comments <lb/>from them. The data set collected about 15,050 comments. Several authors, like [2], who collected <lb/>Formspring data, namely Me and MySpace, used Formspring. Reynolds et al. [34] also collected <lb/>the data from Formspring. The authors selected random files from the 18,554 users and then used <lb/>Amazon&apos;s Mechanical Turk service to determine the labels for the truth sets. Maral et al. [35] also <lb/>used three datasets in their study: Formspring (a Q&amp;A forum), Wikipedia talk pages (a collaborative <lb/>knowledge repository), and Twitter (a microblogging platform). All these datasets are manually labeled <lb/>and publicly available. In a study by Hani et al. [36], the Kaggle dataset was initially taken from a <lb/>research paper from Formspring and contains 12,773 conversations. Kaggle also has been used by <lb/>Srivastava et al. [37]. The last group of authors used multiple and different ways and datasets for their <lb/>data collection. Rachid et al. [38] collected the dataset from Aljazeera.net (accessed on 10/05/2024), <lb/>and the comments were selected using CrowdFlower. <lb/>Furthermore, the comments were classified into three categories: Obscene (533 comments), <lb/>offensive (25,506 comments), and clean (5653); the data by Husain in [39] was provided by the shared <lb/>task of the fourth workshop on Open-Source Arabic Corpora and Corpora Processing tools (OSACT) <lb/>in Language Resource and Evaluation Conference (LREC) 2020. Furthermore, the data was released <lb/>into three different data parts: training dataset (1000 tweets), development dataset (1367 tweets), and <lb/>testing dataset (5468). In [40], the dataset used by Alfageh et al. was taken from a publicly available <lb/>dataset that contains 15,000 comments from YouTube. In [41], the dataset had 2218 sessions provided <lb/>by a research report collected from Instagram using snowball sampling. Yin et al. [42] used data from <lb/>three datasets: Kongregate, Slashdot, and MySpace. Then, they manually labeled a randomly selected <lb/>subset of the threads from each labeled dataset. A study in [43] provided a semi-synthetic, flexible, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1039 <lb/></page>

	<body>and scalable dataset to mitigate shortcomings of current cyberbullying detection datasets. The dataset <lb/>covers various traits such as hostility, reprise, aim to hurt, and issues among peers. Özel et al. [44] <lb/>manually collected around 900 messages from Twitter and Instagram. However, only half of them <lb/>contained cyberbullying terms. Dadvar et al. [45] collected cyberbullying related data from MySpace <lb/>and Fundacion Barcelona Media. Similarly, Buan et al. [46] used the third version of the bullying traces <lb/>dataset that was created by Professor Zhu at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Authors in [47] <lb/>collected their data from Perverted-Justice (PJ), an American organization investigates, identifies, and <lb/>publicizes the conduct of adults who solicit online sexual conversations with adults posing as minors. <lb/>Based on the brief review of cyberbullying detection datasets, it is apparent that most of the data <lb/>has been collected, processed, and annotated manually by the researchers. Most of the data sources <lb/>are comprised of English language while for Arabic language datasets are limited. Moreover, Twitter <lb/>and Instagram are the most famous targeted social media. <lb/>3.2 Review of Machine Learning Algorithms in NLP <lb/>3.2.1 Support Vector Machine (SVM) <lb/>SVM is a fast and dependable classification algorithm. Supervised machine learning has been shown <lb/>to give excellent and accurate performance results. This section summarizes the primary use of the <lb/>SVM algorithm for word classification, focusing on cyberbullying detection. <lb/>Phanomtip et al. [22] start by filtering the tweets by removing every unimportant information <lb/>like tags (@), URLs, and locations. Then, they used embedding methods: TF-IDF and document to <lb/>vector (Doc2Vec) to extract the vector from the filtering tweet and feed it into the linear SVM for the <lb/>classification. With a large dataset of 68 K tweets, the results state that the experiments for the linear <lb/>SVM gave excellent accuracy in detecting cyberbullying, with 91% and 86% accuracy using TF-IDF <lb/>and Doc2Vec, respectively. For a small dataset, Hani et al. [36] used 1.6 K posts and applied the TF-<lb/>IDF method to extract the vector for the linear SVM. The result was also reasonable accuracy, more <lb/>than 89%. Buan et al. in [46] followed the same approach by applying the linear SVM to distinguish <lb/>between bullying and other texts. The idea was to weigh each term by giving it a gram scale. The <lb/>accuracy of a dataset consisting of more than 14 K tweets was about 77%. Likewise, studies in [47,48] <lb/>used the same feature and the SVM to reduce the number of parts by weighing their importance to the <lb/>class attribute. <lb/>3.2.2 Naïve Bayes (NB) <lb/>NB technique is a simple text categorization algorithm. It is a probabilistic approach for each <lb/>attribute in each class set. It has been effectively used for various issues and applications but excels in <lb/>NLP. The studies using NB as their main algorithm are from Rachid et al. in [38], Mouheb et al. in <lb/>[20], Kanan et al. in [12], Haider et al. in [18], Al-Mamun et al. in [28] and Agrawal et al. in [31]. They <lb/>used the NB model and collected their data set from Twitter but slightly differed in the preprocessing <lb/>step and methodology. First, Rachid et al. [38] eliminated Arabic and English punctuation, HTML <lb/>codecs, numbers and symbols, and words of size one. In addition, diacritics and normalization of <lb/>Arabic text are all part of the preprocessing stages. In addition, the models used are NBM machine <lb/>learning and Bag of a Word, which resulted in 87% Presisions, 35% Recall, and 50% F1-score. Second, <lb/>Mouheb et al. [20], the preprocessing steps include removing Arabic diacritics, Arabic determiner, and <lb/>normalizations. Furthermore, using the NB model resulted in 95% accuracy. Third, Kanan et al. in <lb/>[12], the preprocessing steps removed diacritics, non-Arabic literals, symbols, normalization, stop <lb/>words, stemming, and 91% accuracy. Fourth, Al-Mamun et al. [28] investigated the NB approach <lb/>for cyberbullying detection in users&apos; posts in Bangla text. The NB scored an F1-score equal to <lb/></body>

	<page>1040 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>69% and achieved an accuracy of 60.98%. In English language text, however, the F1-score was <lb/>39%, and the accuracy was 40.98%. Finally, Agrawal et al. in [31] investigated the NB approach <lb/>with character N-grams as a feature selection method. Consequently, the F1-score for the NB was <lb/>35.9% for bullying detection, 68.6% for racism on the Formspring dataset, 64.7% for sexism on the <lb/>Twitter dataset, and 66.5% for attack-related text in Wikipedia. For word unigrams, NB F1-scores <lb/>were 0.025 for bullying in Formspring, 0.617 for racism, 0.635 for sexism on Twitter, and 0.659 for <lb/>the attack on Wikipedia. Alfageh et al. in [40] and Özel et al. in [44] utilized the NBM. To begin <lb/>with, the data set was obtained from YouTube, and the data is balanced; the preprocessing process <lb/>includes the removal of all non-Arabic literals, symbols punctuation, URLs, hashtags and Arabic <lb/>diacritics, normalization, and stemming. The model employed is NBM, which has an accuracy of <lb/>78.4%. Consequently, Özel et al. [44], in their research on detecting cyberbullying for the Turkish <lb/>language NBM, were the most successful in their experiments for running time and accuracy. SVM <lb/>followed them in second place. On the other hand, even though instance-based K-nearest neighbors <lb/>(IBK) have no training, their running duration is lengthy. J48, on the other hand, has a relatively short <lb/>testing time but a pervasive training time. As a result, NBM was the top performer. On the other hand, <lb/>the studies from Bharti et al. [24] performed the worst among all the classifiers and NB algorithms. <lb/>The accuracy was 66.86%, with an F1-score of 68.18% in cyberbullying detection. Further, the decree <lb/>showed an accuracy of 90.59% and an F1-score of 92.79%. <lb/>3.2.3 SVM and NB <lb/>In their study, authors [12] discussed supervised machine learning techniques in Arabic social <lb/>media content for detecting cyberbullying. They rely on the classifying process using several classifiers: <lb/>SVM and NB. They start by stating their dataset of 14 K tweets collected from Twitter using <lb/>RStudio and Rtool and 2 K posts from Facebook. Afterward, they used the Waikato Environment <lb/>for Knowledge Analysis (WEKA) Toolkit to implement preprocessing tools like Stop-Word-Removal <lb/>and Stemming. They conclude that SVM gives a better result when the size of the datasets increases, <lb/>with an F-measure of more than 90%. At the same time, NB gave 10% fewer results than SVM, with an <lb/>F-measure of less than 85%. Haider et al. [18] used the same approach with a massive dataset of 126K <lb/>posts collected from the same sources (Twitter and Facebook). The results also favored SVM with an <lb/>F-measure of more than 92%, while NB achieved an F-measure of 90%. Rachid et al. [38] provided <lb/>a dataset of 32 K collected from Aljazeera.net, considering if it is a balanced or unbalanced dataset. <lb/>They applied two feature extraction methods: TD-IDF and BoW. The result shows that SVM is better <lb/>than NB regardless of whether the dataset is balanced or unbalanced. SVM gave a higher detection <lb/>accuracy when applying the TD-IDF method, while NB used the Bow method. Haider et al. [21] <lb/>provided almost the exact dataset size as Rachid et al., but they collected it from Twitter. Also, they <lb/>applied two different feature extraction methods, Boosting and Bagging. They conclude that SVM beat <lb/>NB by about 0.4% accuracy higher for both ways. Atoum [48] proposed a simulated annealing (SA) <lb/>model for the detection process. He used SVM and NB as supervised machine-learning classification <lb/>tools for this model. He provides a dataset of 5K tweets collected from Twitter API. The experiment <lb/>results indicated that SVM classifiers have outperformed NB classifiers as they achieved an average <lb/>accuracy value of more than 90%, while NB gained about 81%. Bharti et al. [24] followed the same <lb/>approach but with a large dataset of 57 K tweets. The results were similar: SVM accuracy was 91.48%, <lb/>and NB was 91.35%. From the review, we can conclude that SVM is a promising supervised ML model <lb/>for classification regardless of the dataset size. While NB significantly lacks accuracy when the dataset <lb/>decreases [49]. Such as, Dalvi et al. [29] used a minimal dataset; the results were about 71% for the <lb/>SVM model and 52% for the NB model. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1041 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.2.4 Random Forest <lb/>A random forest (RF) comprises many discrete decision trees that perform with a forest. Each <lb/>tree in the RF generates a class prediction, and the class with the most votes becomes the model&apos;s <lb/>prediction. Their performance is strict to match other algorithms because the trees shield each other <lb/>from their faults. While some trees may be incorrect, many others will be correct. They can also handle <lb/>various feature types, including binary, categorical, and numerical. During review RF was used in <lb/>7 out of 36 research. There is only one paper used alone. The others used it with other classifiers <lb/>to compare RF with the others. Al-Ajlan et al. [16] used RF to detect cyberbullying because of its <lb/>prominence in this field. The model was based on the user&apos;s personality and is determined by the Big <lb/>Five and Dark Triad models. Psychopathy 91.8% had the best RF performance in Dark Triad while <lb/>the others followed by a small margin of 2%. The Big Five had RF higher than the rest, with almost <lb/>91% Neuroticism, Extraversion, and Agreeableness, followed by 90%. So, when the lower RF was <lb/>90%, their research shows that the Big Five and Dark Triad models were proven to enhance RF in <lb/>cyberbullying detection considerably. In three of seven of the research, Husain [39], Kanan, et al. [12], <lb/>and Agrawal et al. [31], RF was the second-highest performing model. The first research is Husain <lb/>[39], which detects offensive Arabic language from a dataset of tweets using machine learning models <lb/>in groups (AdaBoost, Bagging, and RF). Count and TF-IDF were utilized for feature extraction. Their <lb/>result showed that bagging at 88% had the best F1-score performance, while the RF was the second <lb/>F1-score by 87%. The second research, Kanan et al. [12], aims to identify such harmful written posts; <lb/>they proposed using Machine Learning. They used a variety of classifier algorithms (KNN, SVM, NB, <lb/>RF, and Decision Trees (also known as J48). The first method involved testing each classifier with all <lb/>the preprocessing stages; RF had a higher F-measure of 94.49%. The second method involved testing <lb/>the classifiers without stemming; RF had the first F1-score of 94.4%. The third method was to try the <lb/>classifiers without removing stop words. RF had the best F-measure of 93.4%. The fourth method <lb/>was to compare the performance of the classifiers with all preprocessing stages on Facebook data only, <lb/>followed by Twitter records, where SVM had the best F-measure of 94.4%, then RF followed by 91.4% <lb/>F-measure on Twitter. While on Facebook, SVM had the first F-measure by 91.7l%, while RF was the <lb/>second by 94.1% F-measure. Remaining studies had RF as the third-best F-measure Rachid et al. [38], <lb/>Bharti et al. [24], and Jain et al. [27]. Whereas Jain et al. [27] used SVM, Logistic Regression (LR), <lb/>RF, and Multi-Layered Perceptron (MLP) for classification. Three feature extraction methods were <lb/>employed: the first technique was the BoW model, second with TF-IDF and last is word to vector <lb/>(word2vec). The greatest F-measure value for the Twitter dataset is obtained as 93.4% when utilizing <lb/>BoW and LR. The second F-measure was RF, with 93.4%. The TF-IDF&apos;s best F-measure was SVC at <lb/>93.9%, followed by LR at 93.6%, and then the third F-measure was RF at 93.3%. The best F1-score <lb/>in word2vec was MLP at 92.2%; RF was the second F-measure at 92.2%. The best F-measure for the <lb/>Wikipedia dataset was 83.7 % when TF-IDF and SVC were employed after LR at 82.5%, then RF <lb/>at 81.8%. Then, BoW was the second-best F-measure. Their best was LR at 82.9%; then RF was the <lb/>second with 81.8% F-measure. Word2Vec had the lowest F-measures. Their highest was MLP, at 82.5%. <lb/>At the same time, the lowest F-measure was RF at 77.6%. Then, Bharti et al. [24] extracted features <lb/>using BoW. They then utilized several classification methods: RF, decision tree, NB, XGBoost, SVM, <lb/>and logistic regression. The best F-measure was LR, with about 94.06%. Then, SVM by 91.99%. The <lb/>third is RF 91.8%. The last research was Rachid et al. [38], who gathered their dataset from the Arabic <lb/>news channel Aljazeera website. The dataset is 32 K comments. Their best machine learning models <lb/>had 85% accuracy; they got that with three different classifiers, RF, XGBoost and SVM with TF-IDF <lb/>and N-gram. <lb/></body>

	<page>1042 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>3.2.5 SVM vs. RF <lb/>Some work has been done using SVM and RF techniques. Rachid et al. [38] used massive and <lb/>imbalance Arabic datasets collected from the Aljazeera.net website. After they implemented the SVM <lb/>algorithm, the F-measure was 98%, and with the RF algorithm, it was 80%. Bharti et al. [24] also used <lb/>the same dataset feature, but the dataset was collected from Twitter in English. The result was 93.3% <lb/>for SVM and 93% for RF. Jain et al. [27] have a dataset like that of Bharti et al. [24], and they got 93.9% <lb/>for SVM and 93.3% for RF. All three researchers used TF-IDF for feature extraction and found that <lb/>SVM is better than RF. On the other hand, Kanan et al. [12] and Husain [39] used large and imbalance <lb/>datasets in the Arabic language. They conclude that RF is better than SVM. SVM is better when the <lb/>dataset is large enough, more than 20 K, and RF will be better when the dataset is less than 20 K. So, <lb/>it shows that there will be no difference if the dataset is an Asian foreign language [50,51]. <lb/>3.2.6 Logic Regression (LR) <lb/>LR is a popular machine learning algorithm that uses the logistic function to classify data. <lb/>Moreover, it is best used if the classification only holds two categories: bullying and non-bullying. <lb/>However, it can be used in multiclass classification if one runs the algorithm multiple times using the <lb/>one-versus-all technique. In most related work, logistic regression showed a higher result than other <lb/>algorithms. Machine learning (ML) has been used as a deep learning (DL) baseline. Bharti et al. [24] <lb/>used LR as one of the ML models, and LR was the best overall, with an accuracy of 92%. <lb/>Rachid et al. [38] have also used LR as a baseline firstly with a BoW on a dataset with more CB <lb/>(cyberbullying) than NCB (non-cyber bullying) and had an F1-score of 30%, which is a very low due <lb/>to the imbalance. The second time, it was used on another imbalance dataset with more NCB than CB <lb/>to make the ratio realistic; the F1-score of the second time was 53%, which is a clear improvement. <lb/>The third time, LR was used with character level TF-IDF N-gram on a balanced dataset, and it got <lb/>an F1-score of 84%. Agrawal et al. [31] used LR with both character N-grams and word unigrams, <lb/>and the highest F1-score was 72% and 76%, respectively. In addition to being used as a baseline for <lb/>DL, LR has been used for ensemble machine learning. Husain in [39] got an F1-score of 81% for LR, <lb/>exceeding the decision tree and being 1% lower than SVM. Haidar et al. [21] had a different purpose for <lb/>LR as they used it as one of five single learners incorporated for stacking ensemble machine learning. <lb/>Jain et al. [27] have experimented with three feature selection methods: BoW, TF-IDF, and word2vec <lb/>on two data sets from Twitter and Wikipedia. They got the highest accuracy of 92% when LR was <lb/>combined with BoW. Alfageh et al. [40] have also used TF-IDF with LR, but the F1-score was lower <lb/>by 1.8% than when it was used with count vectorization, which had an F1-score of 78.6%. <lb/>3.2.7 Other Classifiers <lb/>Authors in [16] proposed a Convolution Neural Network (CNN) for cyberbullying detection by <lb/>adopting profound learning principles instead of machine learning. They implemented their system by <lb/>applying four steps, starting with embedding the texts as a numerical representation. Then, convolving <lb/>the input vectors to detect the features and compress the output of the convolution process to smaller <lb/>matrices so that only significant and transparent parts are considered. The last step includes the dense <lb/>layer, which will feed all the outputs of the previous layers to all NN&apos;s neurons. They provided a dataset <lb/>of 39K tweets collected using Twitter streaming API for the experiment. The results of an automated <lb/>cyberbullying detector with no human involvement were excellent as the accuracy was more than 95% <lb/>of the detection process. Banerjee et al. [23] applied the same method with a larger dataset consisting of <lb/>69K tweets, and the results were also outstanding with more than 93% accuracy. Srivastava et al. [37] <lb/>performed different models of deep learning algorithms in detecting insults in social commentary, and <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1043 <lb/></page>

	<body>the most important of them are Gated Recurrent Units (GRU), Long short-term memory (LSTM), <lb/>and Bidirectional LSTM (BLSTM). They first applied data preprocessing to percolate the comments, <lb/>including text cleaning, Tokenization, stemming, lemmatization, and stop-word removal. After that, <lb/>the filtered data is passed to the deep learning algorithms for prediction. The results were very similar, <lb/>as BLSTM outperformed the others by 82.18% accuracy, while GRU and LSTM achieved 81.46% <lb/>and 80.86%, respectively. In comparing CNN with GRU, LSTM, and BLSTM, Benaissa et al. [38] <lb/>provided a dataset of 32 K Arabic comments collected from Aljazeera.net for testing. From the results, <lb/>it seems CNN surpasses the other models by 1% F1-score. Also, combined, they achieved an average <lb/>of 84% F1-score in a balanced dataset. The KNN is a supervised ML algorithm that may be used <lb/>for both classification and regression tasks [50]. However, it is mainly employed for categorization <lb/>and prediction. It is defined by two characteristics: a non-parametric learning algorithm and a lazy <lb/>learning algorithm. Haidar et al. [21] when they compare KNN by F1-measure to other classifiers. <lb/>They had that KNN is the lowest in bagging, 90.4%, and in Boosting, 89.8%. Also, Kanan et al. [12] <lb/>found that KNN has the lowest F1-score, 78.2%, and 61.9%, in Facebook and Twitter datasets. Al-<lb/>Mamun et al. [28] choose those classifiers (i.e., NB, SVM, Decision Tree, and KNN). In their results, <lb/>KNN was observed better than NB. <lb/>Based on the related work, it is evident that cyberbullying detection in Arabic language is <lb/>among the hottest areas of research that need significant attention [52,53]. More studies are needed <lb/>to investigate the overwhelming amount of data being produced by the social media platforms by <lb/>abundant of users especially in Arabic language. Investigation of smart techniques could potentially <lb/>help identify this adverse effect of social media precisely to prevent undesirable incidents. In this regard, <lb/>nine well-known machine learning algorithms have been shortlisted based on their effectiveness in the <lb/>similar problems observed in the literature. Table 3 presents a summary of the reviewed literature. <lb/>Table 3: Summary of literature review <lb/>Ref. <lb/>Classifier <lb/>Language <lb/>Dataset source and <lb/>size <lb/>Feature extraction <lb/>Metric <lb/>Strength <lb/>Weakness <lb/>[11] <lb/>SVM <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>Light Stemmer, <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>N/A <lb/>Small <lb/>17,748 tweets <lb/>Arabic Stemmer Khoja, <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>85.49% <lb/>dataset <lb/>[12] <lb/>KNN, SVM, <lb/>NB, RF, J48 <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter API, <lb/>4000 tweets <lb/>FB 2138 posts <lb/>N/A <lb/>Multiple <lb/>experiments <lb/>N/A <lb/>[19] <lb/>Lexicon <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter API, <lb/>The content of the <lb/>Original <lb/>Imbalance <lb/>PMI <lb/>YouTube, <lb/>tweet <lb/>dataset, <lb/>data with <lb/>Entropy <lb/>Microsoft Flow. <lb/>lexicon <lb/>stop words <lb/>Chi-square <lb/>100K+ <lb/>approach. <lb/>[22] <lb/>SVM <lb/>English <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>TF-IDF, and <lb/>74% <lb/>Large dataset <lb/>Presumed <lb/>67K tweets <lb/>Doc2Vec <lb/>sentence <lb/>correction <lb/>[24] <lb/>N B ,R F ,J 4 8 <lb/>XGBoost, SVM, <lb/>LR <lb/>English <lb/>From old papers <lb/>57,787 tweets <lb/>BoW <lb/>Accuracy 92.60 <lb/>Precision 98.73 <lb/>F1-score 94.20 <lb/>Recall 92.07 <lb/>6-way <lb/>classification <lb/>Big dataset <lb/>Imbalanced <lb/>dataset <lb/>[25] <lb/>SVM, CNN <lb/>Keras library <lb/>English <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>N/A <lb/>N/A <lb/>N/A <lb/>[26] <lb/>SVM <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>8154 tweets <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>Accuracy 82%, <lb/>Precision 81%, <lb/>F1-score 82% <lb/>Resampling was <lb/>used to <lb/>balancing <lb/>Minimal pre-<lb/>processing <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

	<page>1044 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 3 (continued) <lb/>Ref. <lb/>Classifier <lb/>Language <lb/>Dataset source and <lb/>size <lb/>Feature extraction <lb/>Metric <lb/>Strength <lb/>Weakness <lb/>[27] <lb/>SVM, LR, RF, <lb/>MLP <lb/>English <lb/>Twitter &amp; Wikipedia <lb/>dataset <lb/>35,787 tweets <lb/>40K comments <lb/>BoW <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>word2vec <lb/>Accuracy 92.1% <lb/>Precision 95.9% <lb/>Recall 92.7% <lb/>f-measure 93.9% <lb/>Large dataset <lb/>4-way classifier <lb/>Imbalanced <lb/>dataset <lb/>[33] <lb/>NB, CNB, LR Arabic <lb/>15,000 YouTube <lb/>comments <lb/>TF-IDF Vectorizations F1-score 78.6% Large dataset <lb/>and features <lb/>Minimal pre-<lb/>processing <lb/>[35] <lb/>C N N <lb/>LSTM <lb/>BLSTM <lb/>SSWE <lb/>English <lb/>16K tweets <lb/>10K comments on <lb/>Wikipedia <lb/>12K Q&amp;A <lb/>N/A <lb/>N/A <lb/>Many classifiers Data aug-<lb/>mentation <lb/>was missing <lb/>[37] <lb/>D L ,G R U , <lb/>LSTM, <lb/>BLSTM, RNN <lb/>English <lb/>Kaggle dataset <lb/>N/A <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>82.12% <lb/>4-way <lb/>classification <lb/>Imbalance <lb/>dataset <lb/>Accuracy is <lb/>low <lb/>[38] <lb/>Deep Learning Arabic <lb/>Aljazeera.net <lb/>32K comments <lb/>BoW <lb/>N-grams, OOV <lb/>embeddings <lb/>F-score 84% <lb/>Hybrid <lb/>methods. <lb/>N/A <lb/>[39] <lb/>SVM, LR, J48, <lb/>RF, Bagging, <lb/>AdaBoost <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>7835 tweets <lb/>Count features, <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>Emoticons and <lb/>emojis turned <lb/>into text <lb/>The results <lb/>representa-<lb/>tion is not <lb/>clear <lb/>[46] <lb/>SVM, LSTM, <lb/>GRU <lb/>English <lb/>Bullying traces data <lb/>set. <lb/>7321 tweets <lb/>N/A <lb/>Precision: <lb/>82.56% <lb/>Recall: 86.42% <lb/>Accuracy: <lb/>86.90% <lb/>N/A <lb/>Old and <lb/>small dataset <lb/>[48] <lb/>SVM, NB <lb/>Chi-square <lb/>English <lb/>Twitter API <lb/>5628 tweets <lb/>N/A <lb/>SVM, 4-gram <lb/>92.02% <lb/>N/A <lb/>Small dataset <lb/>[50] <lb/>MARBERT and <lb/>BERT <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Around 24K tweets N/A <lb/>F1-score 75% <lb/>Spam detection Needs <lb/>improvement <lb/>[51] <lb/>Machine <lb/>Learning, SVM, <lb/>NB <lb/>Arabic <lb/>30K tweets and <lb/>comments from <lb/>Twitter/YouTube <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>BoW <lb/>Accuracy SVM: <lb/>95.742% <lb/>NB: 70.942% <lb/>Good accuracy Tweets mixed <lb/>with <lb/>comments <lb/>[52] <lb/>L S T M <lb/>Bi-LSTM <lb/>Arabic <lb/>10K tweets from <lb/>Twitter <lb/>N/A <lb/>Accuracy 88% <lb/>for LSTM and <lb/>BiLSTM <lb/>Three datasets <lb/>used for analysis <lb/>Short and <lb/>imbalance <lb/>dataset <lb/>[53] <lb/>Machine <lb/>Learning <lb/>Arabic <lb/>Twitter with 4140 <lb/>tweets <lb/>AraBERT, TF-IDF <lb/>Accuracy 89% Three datasets <lb/>used <lb/>Limited <lb/>instances <lb/>4 Methodology <lb/>This section covers the steps involved in the proposed study that can be considered as the <lb/>theoretical framework of the study: Dataset collection, dataset preprocessing, features extraction, <lb/>generating the models, and evaluation metrics. Different phases of the proposed methodology are <lb/>shown in Fig. 2. <lb/>4.1 Dataset Collection and Labeling <lb/>The dataset was collected from Arabic Twitter using the API, and it consists of about 9K tweets <lb/>from diverse users from the Middle East, especially Saudi Arabia. It provides a linguistic variety <lb/>in terms of diverse dialects used in the Arab world, not just one standard dialect such as modern <lb/>standard Arabic (MSA), that is mainly used in similar studies conducted in Saudi Arabia. The <lb/>reason behind the MSA is that most of the urban areas Arabic speaking users utilize MSA during <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1045 <lb/></page>

	<body>their conversations [50,51]. While in the rural and semi-urban areas, nonstandard, slang and local <lb/>diverse dialects are mainly observed during the data collection process. The collected tweets dataset <lb/>was manually labeled. In this regard, it was divided into two labels or classes: Bullying and non-<lb/>bullying for binary classification. Within the Bullying class, tweets contained at least one bullying <lb/>word (considering the standard Arabic dictionary), and in the non-bullying class, tweets are entirely <lb/>free of them. <lb/>Figure 2: Different phases of the proposed methodology <lb/>4.2 Dataset Preprocessing <lb/>Preprocessing is a critical stage in a machine learning model since it cleans and prepares the dataset <lb/>so that it may be used to train the classifier. In our case, the tweets are written in various dialects rather <lb/>than traditional Arabic. Therefore, we have applied NLP approaches to cope with various issues posed <lb/>by tweets in the Arabic language. It was applied as follows: <lb/>4.2.1 Data Cleaning, Handling Missing Values and Outliers <lb/>Before any work is done on the dataset, it needs to be cleaned from the inconsistent data by deleting <lb/>the duplicate and broken (inconsistent) Tweets. The missing values and outliers were handled by the <lb/>standard NLP preprocessing methods such as imputation [8]. Oversampling technique has been used <lb/>to balance the collected dataset [8]. Nonetheless, no outliers have been detected in the dataset. <lb/>4.2.2 Normalization <lb/>The dataset was cleaned and normalized into a uniform text. This process was implemented by <lb/>Python programming language using &quot;pyarabic&quot; libraries and regular expressions. Here we remove <lb/>the Hashtags, Usernames, Numbers, URLs, English Letters, Special Characters, Quotations Marks, <lb/>Brackets, Emojis, Repeated Letters, Tashkeel (like: &quot; <lb/>&quot; to &quot; <lb/>&quot;), and Tatweel <lb/>(like: &quot; <lb/>&quot; to &quot; <lb/>&quot;) [8]. <lb/>4.2.3 Stop-Word Removal <lb/>Stop-words are meaningless terms that do not aid in the analysis. We developed a stop-word <lb/>dictionary by collecting it from &quot;countwordsfree.com&quot; (accessed on 10/05/2024). Example stop-words: <lb/>&quot; &quot;, &quot; &quot;, &quot; &quot;, &quot; &quot;, etc. <lb/></body>

	<page>1046 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>4.2.4 Tokenization <lb/>When punctuation and white space marks are encountered, Tokenization is used to split the <lb/>sentences into tokens. For example, &quot; <lb/>&quot; tokenized into &quot; <lb/>&quot;, &quot; <lb/>&quot;, &quot; &quot;. The tokenize <lb/>class from the &quot;pyarabic.araby&quot; package was used. <lb/>4.2.5 Stemming <lb/>Stemming is a technique for returning a word to its root removing suffixes and prefixes. For <lb/>example: &quot; <lb/>&quot; converted into &quot; &quot;. ISRI Stemmer was utilized in this study and was <lb/>imported from &quot;nltk.stem.isri&quot; library. <lb/>4.3 Features Extraction <lb/>Focusing on finding the best ML techniques to detect cyberbullying within Arabic tweets, we <lb/>tested the best model features that gave the highest performance accuracy. N-gram extracted the <lb/>required features with unigram range and TF-IDF methods. Also, nine supervised ML models were <lb/>used to train the dataset, including SVM, NB, RF, LR, LightGBM, CatBoost, XGBoost, AdaBoost, <lb/>and Bagging. <lb/>4.3.1 Term Frequency-Inverse Document Frequency (TF-IDF) <lb/>TF-IDF is most used for text classification and feature extraction. Term frequency is the number <lb/>of times a word appears within a document, as given in Eq. (1). The Inverse Document Frequency <lb/>returns how common or rare a word is in the entire record set, as given in Eq. (2). So, if the word <lb/>is ubiquitous and appears in many records, this number will be 0. Otherwise, it will be 1, as given in <lb/>Eq. (3). <lb/>TF (d) = log(1 + freq(d)) <lb/>(1) <lb/>IDF (t) = log <lb/>n <lb/>DF (t) <lb/>+ 1 <lb/>(2) <lb/>TF -IDF (t, d) = TF (t, d) × IDF(t) <lb/>(3) <lb/>4.3.2 Sequence of N Words (N-Gram) <lb/>N-grams extract the sequence of N words. In our case, we used Unigram with range (min: 1, max: <lb/>1). For example, the sentence &quot; <lb/>&quot; should divided into {&apos; <lb/>&apos;, &apos;, &apos; <lb/>&apos;}. <lb/>4.4 Model Generation and Evaluation <lb/>This study implemented nine supervisor machine learning models using Python, Sklearn, Cat-<lb/>boost, LightGPM, and XGBoost libraries to determine the best classification model. The accuracy as <lb/>given in Eq. (4), precision as given in Eq. (5), recall as given in Eq. (6), and F1-score as given in Eq. (7) <lb/>will be used to evaluate the classifiers in this research. True Positive (TP), True Negative (TN), False <lb/>Positive (FP), and False Negative (FN) will be determined using these equations [49]. <lb/>Accuracy = <lb/>TP + TN <lb/>TP + TN + FP + FN <lb/>(4) <lb/>Precision = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FP <lb/>(5) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1047 <lb/></page>

	<body>Recall = <lb/>TP <lb/>(TP + FN) <lb/>(6) <lb/>F1-score = 2 * <lb/>precision * recall <lb/>precision + recall <lb/>(7) <lb/>5 Results and Discussion <lb/>This section presents the results of all classifiers in detail and demonstrates various effects of <lb/>Unigram and TF-IDF on text classification for each model. After preprocessing the dataset and <lb/>extracting the features, the dataset will be fed to the classifiers to determine whether a tweet is <lb/>cyberbullying. To better evaluate the proposed models, two sets of experiments were conducted in this <lb/>study, the first with the collected dataset and the second with an existing dataset. It is worth noting <lb/>that no overfitting was observed during the analyses. The following sections summarize the results of <lb/>the two experiments. <lb/>5.1 Experimental Results with the Collected Dataset <lb/>The models were built using a diverse dataset collected and curated in this experiment. The dataset <lb/>was collected through Twitter API, consisting of about 9K tweets. Nine classifiers were used in these <lb/>experiments, which are: SVM, RF, LR, AdaBoost, CatBoost, LightGBM, Bagging, XGBoost, and <lb/>NB. The outcomes of each classifier&apos;s model evaluation predictions are shown in Table 4. <lb/>Table 4: Experimental results with the collected dataset <lb/>Classifier <lb/>Feature extraction <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>Recall <lb/>Precision <lb/>F1-score <lb/>SVM <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>87.93 <lb/>83.33 <lb/>85.57 <lb/>84.44 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>86.41 <lb/>83.51 <lb/>82.18 <lb/>82.84 <lb/>RF <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>89.17 <lb/>80.99 <lb/>90.44 <lb/>85.46 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>89.13 <lb/>82.34 <lb/>89.17 <lb/>85.62 <lb/>NB <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>83.43 <lb/>75.14 <lb/>81.29 <lb/>78.09 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>83.43 <lb/>75.14 <lb/>81.29 <lb/>78.09 <lb/>LR <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>88.14 <lb/>78.92 <lb/>89.66 <lb/>83.95 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>87.93 <lb/>82.07 <lb/>86.51 <lb/>84.23 <lb/>CatBoost <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>89.84 <lb/>84.05 <lb/>89.45 <lb/>86.67 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>89.06 <lb/>82.97 <lb/>88.47 <lb/>85.63 <lb/>LightGBM <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>89.63 <lb/>84.41 <lb/>88.65 <lb/>86.45 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>89.49 <lb/>83.24 <lb/>89.28 <lb/>86.15 <lb/>AdaBoost <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>88.21 <lb/>81.44 <lb/>87.68 <lb/>84.45 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>88.42 <lb/>80.9 <lb/>88.65 <lb/>84.6 <lb/>XGBoost <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>89.95 <lb/>84.23 <lb/>89.56 <lb/>88.82 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>89.17 <lb/>82.7 <lb/>88.95 <lb/>85.71 <lb/>Bagging <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>89.27 <lb/>86.67 <lb/>86.12 <lb/>86.39 <lb/>Unigram <lb/>88.39 <lb/>88.02 <lb/>83.36 <lb/>85.63 <lb/></body>

	<page>1048 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 4 shows that XGBoost has the highest accuracy and F1-score, as it reaches 89.95% and <lb/>86.82%, respectively, using TF-IDF as a feature extraction approach. Also, RF achieved 90.44% <lb/>precision using TF-IDF, considered the highest score in the table. The highest score for the Recall <lb/>goes for the Bagging classifier, as it obtained 88.02% using Unigram as feature extraction. The TF-<lb/>IDF approach enhances the classifier&apos;s accuracy more than the N-grams, as shown in Fig. 3. To <lb/>achieve better performance, it is best to use the TF-IDF rather than N-gram for extracting the features <lb/>from text. <lb/>3: The impact of feature extraction on text classification <lb/>5.2 Experimental Results with an Existing Dataset <lb/>To compare the proposed models with existing research, we investigated the proposed methodol-<lb/>ogy using the dataset used by [33]. This dataset contains 15 K tweets; 39% are labeled as cyberbullying. <lb/>Their work passed the dataset through preprocessing steps: Tokenization, filtering, normalization, and <lb/>stemming and then they used N-gram and SVM. In the proposed work, we improved accuracy as <lb/>follows. First, the dataset was imbalanced, so we added more tweets to make it a balanced dataset. <lb/>Second, the dataset goes through many steps of preprocessing techniques: removing repeated tweets, <lb/>tokenization, removing noise (numbers, English letters, emojis), normalization, removing stop words, <lb/>and stemming. After that, we applied TF-IDF and N-gram for feature extraction and SVM for <lb/>classification, following the same steps. It is apparent from Table 4 that the proposed approach <lb/>achieves higher values of evaluation metrics than [33] with the same classifier. Furthermore, we applied <lb/>LR, to investigate the classification result. TF-IDF with SVM has the highest results, followed by N-<lb/>gram with LR and N-gram with SVM. The comparison is given in Table 5. It is also apparent that <lb/>the proposed algorithms are also promising in terms of scalability. The possible reason behind these <lb/>outcomes is TF-IDF that have proven to be instrumental in NLP overall. On contrary, SVM has <lb/>been investigated with N-gram, but it did not provide a similar performance. The same is evident in <lb/>Table 6 where TF-IDF has been combined with XGBoost. As far as the computational complexity of <lb/>the proposed models is concerned, during training ensemble models take longer than the traditional <lb/>models in terms of convergence rate. It is obvious due to the nature of the ensemble algorithms where <lb/>the consensus takes more time. <lb/>5.3 Qualitative Comparison with State-of-the-Art <lb/>To compare the scheme with the state-of-the-art, we have selected some recent studies with three <lb/>common aspects (Language (Arabic), social media (Twitter), and Data collection region). However, <lb/>their dataset was different than the one proposed. In this regard, a comparison was made with three <lb/>recent approaches [52-54] from 2023. The proposed scheme outperforms the schemes given in [52] with <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1049 <lb/></page>

	<body>NB, [53], and [54] in terms of accuracy by 19%, 1.95%, and 0.95%, respectively, while using XGBoost <lb/>with TF-IDF. However, the scheme in [52] outperformed the proposed scheme regarding accuracy <lb/>and precision using the SVM classifier. Nonetheless, the authors mentioned in [52] that the results <lb/>are with a segmented scenario and not generalized for their whole dataset. In terms of precision, the <lb/>proposed scheme using RF with N-gram performs better than [53-54]. Regarding Recall and F1-score, <lb/>the proposed scheme is better than [53] with a litter margin. Nonetheless, the scheme in [54] marginally <lb/>performs better than the proposed scheme regarding Recall and F1-score. The comparison with state-<lb/>of-the-art is presented in Table 6. <lb/>Table 5: Comparison with an existing dataset <lb/>Approach <lb/>Feature extraction Classifier Accuracy Precision Recall <lb/>F1-score <lb/>Alakrot et al. (2018) <lb/>[33] <lb/>N-gram <lb/>SVM <lb/>85% <lb/>81% <lb/>78% <lb/>80% <lb/>Proposed approach N-gram <lb/>SVM <lb/>86.01% <lb/>88.67% <lb/>82.27% <lb/>85.35% <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>SVM <lb/>86.55% <lb/>90.20% <lb/>81.74% <lb/>85.76% <lb/>N-gram <lb/>LR <lb/>86.42% <lb/>89.27% <lb/>82.5% <lb/>85.75% <lb/>Table 6: Comparison with state-of-the-art <lb/>Approach <lb/>Feature extraction Classifier Accuracy Precision Recall <lb/>F1-score <lb/>Alduailaj et al. <lb/>(2023) [51] <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>SVM <lb/>95.742% 92% <lb/>84% <lb/>88% <lb/>BoW <lb/>NB <lb/>70.942% <lb/>Alzaqebah et al. <lb/>(2023) [52] <lb/>None <lb/>LSTM <lb/>88% <lb/>88% <lb/>88% <lb/>88% <lb/>Mursi et al. (2023) <lb/>[53] <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>MLP <lb/>89% <lb/>88% <lb/>90% <lb/>89% <lb/>Proposed <lb/>TF-IDF <lb/>XGBoost 89.95% <lb/>90.44% <lb/>88.02% <lb/>88.82% <lb/>N-gram <lb/>RF <lb/>Unigram <lb/>Bagging <lb/>5.4 Discussion <lb/>The proposed scheme addresses the cyberbullying detection problem from Arabic tweets. It is from <lb/>the hottest areas of research in behavioral studies and modelling of online users [54]. The dataset in this <lb/>regard has been collected from diverse Arab regions, annotated, and preprocessed before applying a <lb/>broad spectrum of approaches in machine learning. The analyses are made with the same dataset and a <lb/>secondary dataset from the literature. The proposed scheme was promising in both cases. Wholistically, <lb/>it was observed that in terms of feature extraction methods, the schemes involving TF-IDF performed <lb/>better than other feature selection methods such as BoW, and N-gram. Moreover, the preprocessing <lb/>techniques used in the studies with the diverse dialects used in the Arabic language tweets make a <lb/>difference. In contrast to schemes in [33,52-54], the proposed scheme is comparable in all metrics. The <lb/>dataset was collected by means of Twitter APIs and fused prior to investigation, and it does not contain <lb/></body>

	<page>1050 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>any users&apos; personal information of any type. The scheme can easily be generalized and/or extended to <lb/>other social media platforms such as YouTube and Facebook comments. The findings of the study <lb/>can be interpreted as: the models can be used in social media platforms to combat cyberbullying by <lb/>identifying potential users and contents containing such offensive language and taking strict actions <lb/>like reporting and blocking the accounts to prevent the emotional and phycological damage to the <lb/>victims of cyberbullying. <lb/>5.5 Limitations of the Study and Future Work <lb/>As far as the limitation of the study is concerned, the dataset is limited in terms of the number <lb/>of instances, though it contains diversified tweet samples collected from diverse middle eastern <lb/>regions with various dialects. Those regions include Iraq, UAE, Oman, Kuwait, Qatar, Jordan, and <lb/>other Arabic speaking nations. The scheme is robust against the dialectic variations and capable of <lb/>handling them effectively as evident in the results and discussion section. Nonetheless, the major <lb/>chunk of dataset was collected from Saudi Arabia&apos;s major cities like Riyadh, Dammam, and Jeddah <lb/>where modern standard Arabic (MSA) dialect is usually evident in social media. That could be a <lb/>potential bias in the dataset. Such issues can be overcome by using data augmentation techniques by <lb/>adding more data with a uniform distribution and balanced sampling techniques. Moreover, accuracy <lb/>and other metrics can be improved by using advanced data preprocessing techniques with different <lb/>feature extraction methods [55], deep learning and ensemble learning approaches. Additionally, the <lb/>encoders/transformers like Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT) with <lb/>their Arabic counter parts namely ARBERT (Arabic BERT) and MARBERT (Modern Standard <lb/>Arabic with BERT) can also be investigated. MARBERT is a large-scale pre-trained masked language <lb/>model focused on both Dialectal Arabic (DA) and MSA [50]. <lb/>6 Conclusions <lb/>Detection of cyberbullying is getting more difficult as internet users have too many ways of <lb/>bullying without being identified. Cyberbullying can threaten individuals and cause the victims to <lb/>commit suicide or go into depression, so its detection is necessary. Several studies have been conducted <lb/>in the literature but mainly in English, while only a few studies exist in Arabic. In this study, we have <lb/>proposed and developed Machine Learning models for Cyberbullying Detection from Arabic tweets <lb/>with diverse dialects. We improved the proposed model significantly using feature extraction methods. <lb/>The dataset achieved high results using XGBoost, Bagging, and RF classifiers, with XGBoost getting <lb/>the highest accuracy of them all at 89.95%, using TF-IDF as feature extraction. In the future, we intend <lb/>to enhance the dataset by data augmentation techniques. Moreover, in future, we aim to improve the <lb/>accuracy of the detection method by applying hybrid models, investigating diverse datasets, and more <lb/>than two feature extraction methods for the NLP, which will help further fine-tune the models. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: The authors like to acknowledge CCSIT, IAU, Dammam for using the resources. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: The authors received no specific funding for this study. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Conceptualization, Dhiaa Musleh; Data curation, Minhal AlBo-Hassan, <lb/>Jawad Alnemer and Ghazy Al-Mutairi; Formal analysis, Atta Rahman, Hayder Alsebaa and Dalal <lb/>Aldowaihi; Funding acquisition, May Aldossary and Fahd Alhaidari; Investigation, Dalal Aldowaihi <lb/>and Fahd Alhaidari; Methodology, Dhiaa Musleh, Mohammed Alkherallah and Hayder Alsebaa; <lb/>Project administration, Atta Rahman; Resources, Jawad Alnemer; Software, Mohammed Alkherallah, <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1051 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Minhal Al-Bo-Hassan, Mustafa Alawami and Jawad Alnemer; Supervision, Dhiaa Musleh and <lb/>Dalal Aldo-waihi; Validation, Mustafa Alawami, Hayder Alsebaa and May Aldossary; Visualization, <lb/>Ghazy Al-Mutairi; Writing-original draft, Mohammed Alkherallah, Minhal AlBo-Hassan, Mustafa <lb/>Alawami and Ghazy Al-Mutairi; Writing-review &amp; editing, Atta Rahman, May Aldossary and Fahd <lb/>Alhaidari. All authors reviewed the results and approved the final version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: The data can be requested from the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] W. N. Hamiza Wan Ali, M. Mohd, and F. Fauzi, &quot;Cyberbullying detection: An overview,&quot; in 2018 Cyber <lb/>Resilience Conf., Putrajaya, Malaysia, 2018, pp. 1-3. doi: 10.1109/CR.2018.8626869. <lb/>[2] B. Sri Nandhini and J. I. Sheeba, &quot;Online social network bullying detection using intelligence technique,&quot; <lb/>Procedia Comput. Sci., vol. 45, no. 1, pp. 485-492, 2015. doi: 10.1016/j.procs.2015.03.085. <lb/>[3] M. Iqbal, &quot;Twitter revenue and usage statistics (2021) Business of App,&quot; Jul. 5, 2021. Accessed: Sep. 14, <lb/>2021. [Online]. Available: https://www.businessofapps.com/data/twitter-statistics/ <lb/>[4] D. Label, &quot;Cyberbullying statistics,&quot; Accessed: Jan. 16, 2021. [Online]. Available: https://www.ditchthelabel. <lb/>org/cyber-bullying-statistics-what-they-tell-us <lb/>[5] &quot;Most common languages used on the internet as of January 2020, by share of internet users,&quot; Jun. 2020. <lb/>Accessed: Sep. 14, 2021. [Online]. Available: https://www.statista.com/statistics/262946/share-of-the-most-<lb/>common-languages-on-the-internet/ <lb/>[6] J. Patchin and S. Hinduja, &quot;Measuring cyberbullying: Implications for research,&quot; Aggress. Violent Behav., <lb/>vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 69-74, Jul.-Aug. 2015. doi: 10.1016/j.avb.2015.05.013. <lb/>[7] D. N. Hoff and S. N. Mitchell, &quot;Cyberbullying: Causes, effects, and remedies,&quot; J. Educ. Adm., vol. 47, no. <lb/>5, pp. 652-665, Aug. 2009. doi: 10.1108/09578230910981107. <lb/>[8] A. Alqarni and A. Rahman, &quot;Arabic tweets-based sentiment analysis to investigate the impact of COVID-<lb/>19 in KSA: A deep learning approach,&quot; Big Data Cogn. Comput., vol. 7, no. 1, pp. 16, 2023. doi: <lb/>10.3390/bdcc7010016. <lb/>[9] W. J. Hutchins, &quot;The georgetown-IBM experiment demonstrated in January 1954,&quot; in 6th Conf. Assoc. <lb/>Mach. Translat. Americas, Washington DC, USA, 2004. <lb/>[10] S. A. Mandal, &quot;Evolution of machine translation,&quot; Towards Data Science, Accessed: Jan. 4, 2023. [Online]. <lb/>Available: https://towardsdatascience.com/evolution-of-machine-translation-5524f1c88b25 <lb/>[11] S. Almutiry and M. Abdel Fattah, &quot;Arabic cyberbullying detection using Arabic sentiment,&quot; Egyptian J. <lb/>Lang. Eng., vol. 8, no. 1, pp. 39-50, Apr. 2021. doi: 10.21608/ejle.2021.50240.1017. <lb/>[12] T. Kanan, A. Aldaaja, and B. Hawashin, &quot;Cyber-bullying and cyber-harassment detection using supervised <lb/>machine learning techniques in Arabic social media contents,&quot; J. Int. Technol., vol. 21, no. 5, pp. 1409-1421, <lb/>Sep. 2020. <lb/>[13] I. Abu El-Khair, &quot;Effects of stop words elimination on Arabic information retrieval,&quot; Int. J. Comput. &amp; <lb/>Inform. Sci., vol. 4, no. 3, pp. 110-133, 2006. <lb/>[14] S. L. Aouragh, A. Yousfi, S. Laaroussi, H. Gueddah, and M. Nejja, &quot;A new estimate of the N-gram language <lb/>model,&quot; Procedia Comput. Sci., vol. 189, no. 1, pp. 211-215, 2021. doi: 10.1016/j.procs.2021.05.111. <lb/>[15] S. Srinidhi, &quot;Understanding Word N-grams and N-gram probability in natural language processing,&quot; <lb/>Towards Data Science, Accessed: Apr. 23, 2021. [Online]. Available: https://towardsdatascience.com/ <lb/>understanding-word-n-grams-and-n-gram-probability-in-natural-language-processing-9d9eef0fa058 <lb/>[16] M. A. Al-Ajlan and M. Ykhlef, &quot;Deep learning algorithm for cyberbullying detection,&quot; Int. J. Adv. Comput. <lb/>Sci. Appl., vol. 9, no. 9, pp. 199-205, 2018. doi: 10.14569/IJACSA.2018.090927. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>1052 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>[17] B. Haidar, M. Chamoun, and A. Serhrouchni, &quot;Arabic cyberbullying detection: Using deep learning,&quot; in <lb/>2018 7th Int. Conf. Comput. Commun. Eng., Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 2018, pp. 284-289. doi: 10.1109/IC-<lb/>CCE.2018.8539303. <lb/>[18] B. Haidar, M. Chamoun, and A. Serhrouchni, &quot;A multilingual system for cyberbullying detection: Arabic <lb/>content detection using machine learning,&quot; Adv. Sci. Technol. Eng. Syst. J., vol. 2, no. 6, pp. 275-284, 2017. <lb/>doi: 10.25046/aj020634. <lb/>[19] M. S. AlHarbi, B. Y. AlHarbi, N. J. AlZahrani, M. M. Alsheail, J. F. Alshobaili and D. M. Ibrahim, <lb/>&quot;Automatic cyber bullying detection in Arabic social media,&quot; Int. J. Eng. Res. Technol., vol. 12, no. 12, <lb/>pp. 2330-2335, 2019. <lb/>[20] D. Mouheb, R. Albarghash, M. F. Mowakeh, Z. A. Aghbari, and I. Kamel, &quot;Detection of Arabic <lb/>cyberbullying on social networks using machine learning,&quot; in 2019 IEEE/ACS 16th Int. Conf. Comput. <lb/>Syst. Appl., Abu Dhabi, UAE, 2019, pp. 1-5. doi: 10.1109/AICCSA47632.2019.9035276. <lb/>[21] B. Haidar, M. Chamoun, and A. Serhrouchni, &quot;Arabic cyberbullying detection: Enhancing performance <lb/>by using ensemble machine learning,&quot; in Proc. IEEE Joint ithings, GreenCom, CPSCom) and SmartData, <lb/>Atlanta, GA, USA, 2019, pp. 323-327. doi: 10.1109/iThings/GreenCom/CPSCom/SmartData.2019.00074. <lb/>[22] A. Phanomtip, T. Sueb-in, and S. Vittayakorn, &quot;Cyberbullying detection on tweets,&quot; in 2021 18th Int. Conf. <lb/>Elect. Eng./Electron., Comput., Telecommun. Inf. Technol., Chiang Mai, Thailand, 2021, pp. 295-298. doi: <lb/>10.1109/ECTI-CON51831.2021.9454848. <lb/>[23] V. Banerjee, J. Telavane, P. Gaikwad, and P. Vartak, &quot;Detection of cyberbullying using deep neural network,&quot; <lb/>in Proc. ICACCS, Coimbatore, India, 2019, pp. 604-607. doi: 10.1109/ICACCS.2019.8728378. <lb/>[24] S. Bharti, A. K. Yadav, M. Kumar, and D. Yadav, &quot;Cyberbullying detection from tweets using deep <lb/>learning,&quot; Kybernetes, vol. 51, no. 9, pp. 1-13, 2021. <lb/>[25] M. Lokhande, A. Suryawanshi, N. Kaulgud, R. Joshi, and P. Ingle, &quot;Detecting cyber bullying on twitter <lb/>using machine learning techniques,&quot; J. Critical Rev., vol. 7, no. 19, pp. 1090-1094, 2020. <lb/>[26] A. R. Almutairi and M. A. Al-Hagery, &quot;Cyberbullying detection by sentiment analysis of tweets&apos; contents <lb/>written in Arabic in Saudi Arabia society,&quot; Int. J. Comput. Sci. Netw. Secur., vol. 21, no. 3, pp. 112-119, <lb/>2021. <lb/>[27] V. Jain, V. Kumar, V. Pal, and D. K. Vishwakarma, &quot;Detection of cyberbullying on social media using <lb/>machine learning,&quot; in 2021 5th Int. Conf. Comput. Methodologies Commun., Erode, India, 2021, pp. 1091-<lb/>1096. doi: 10.1109/ICCMC51019.2021.9418254. <lb/>[28] A. Al-Mamun and S. Akhter, &quot;Social media bullying detection using machine learning on Bangla <lb/>text,&quot; in 2018 10th Int. Conf. Elect. Comput. Eng., Dhaka, Bangladesh, 2018, pp. 385-388. doi: <lb/>10.1109/ICECE.2018.8636797. <lb/>[29] R. R. Dalvi, S. B. Chavan, and A. Halbe, &quot;Detecting twitter cyberbullying using machine learning,&quot; <lb/>in 2020 4th Int. Conf. Intell. Comput. Control Syst., Madurai, India, May 2020, pp. 297-301. doi: <lb/>10.1109/ICICCS48265.2020.9120893. <lb/>[30] V. Balakrishnan, S. Khana, T. Fernandez, and H. R. Arabnia, &quot;Cyberbullying detection on twitter using <lb/>big five and dark triad features,&quot; Pers. Individ. Dif., vol. 141, no. 15, pp. 252-257, Apr. 2019. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.paid.2019.01.024. <lb/>[31] S. Agrawal and A. Awekar, &quot;Deep learning for detecting cyberbullying across multiple social media <lb/>platforms,&quot; in Proc. ECIR 2018, Adv. Inform. Retrieval, Grenoble, France, 2018, pp. 141-153. <lb/>[32] M. di Capua, E. di Nardo, and A. Petrosino, &quot;Unsupervised cyber bullying detection in social <lb/>networks,&quot; in 2016 23rd Int. Conf. Pattern Recognit., Cancun, Mexico, 2016, pp. 432-437. doi: <lb/>10.1109/ICPR.2016.7899672. <lb/>[33] A. Alakrot, L. Murray, and N. Nikolov, &quot;Towards accurate detection of offensive language in <lb/>online communication in Arabic,&quot; Procedia Comput. Sci., vol. 142, no. 1, pp. 315-320, 2018. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.procs.2018.10.491. <lb/>[34] K. Reynolds, A. Kontostathis, and L. Edwards, &quot;Using machine learning to detect cyberbullying,&quot; in Proc. <lb/>10th Int. Conf. ML and Appl. and Workshops, Honolulu, HI, USA, 2011, pp. 241-244. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1053 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>[35] D. Maral and K. Eckert, &quot;Cyberbullying detection in social networks using deep learning based models; a <lb/>reproducibility study,&quot; in 2016 23rd Int. Conf. Pattern Recognit., Bratislava, Slovakia, 2020, pp. 245-255. <lb/>doi: 10.1109/ICPR.2016.7899672. <lb/>[36] J. Hani, M. Nashaat, M. Ahmed, Z. Emad, E. Amer and A. Mohammed, &quot;Social media cyberbullying <lb/>detection using machine learning,&quot; Int. J. Adv. Comput. Sci. Appl., vol. 10, no. 5, pp. 703-707, 2019. doi: <lb/>10.14569/issn.2156-5570. <lb/>[37] G. Srivastava, S. Khan, C. Iwendi, and P. K. Reddy Maddikunta, &quot;Cyberbullying detection solutions based <lb/>on deep learning,&quot; Multimed. Syst., vol. 29, no. 1, pp. 1839-1852, 2023. doi: 10.1007/s00530-020-00701-5. <lb/>[38] B. A. Rachid, H. Azza, and H. H. Ben Ghezala, &quot;Classification of cyberbullying text in Ara-<lb/>bic,&quot; in 2020 Int. Joint Conf. on Neural Netw. (IJCNN) , Glasgow, UK, 2020, pp. 1-7. doi: <lb/>10.1109/IJCNN48605.2020.9206643. <lb/>[39] F. Husain, &quot;Arabic offensive language detection using machine learning and ensemble,&quot; arXiv:2005.08946, <lb/>2020. <lb/>[40] D. Alfageh and T. Alsubait, &quot;Comparison of machine learning techniques for cyberbullying,&quot; Int. J. <lb/>Comput. Sci. Netw. Secur., vol. 21, no. 1, pp. 1-5, 2021. <lb/>[41] I. Nazar, D. S. Zois, and M. Yao, &quot;A hierarchical approach for timely cyberbullying detection,&quot; <lb/>in 2019 IEEE Data Sci. Workshop (DSW), Minneapolis, MN, USA, 2019, pp. 190-195. doi: <lb/>10.1109/DSW.2019.8755598. <lb/>[42] D. Yin, Z. Xue, and L. Hong, &quot;Detection of harassment on Web 2.0,&quot; in Proc. Content Anal. Web Workshop <lb/>at Www, Madrid, Spain, Apr. 21, 2009, pp. 1-6. <lb/>[43] N. Ejaz, F. Razi, and S. Choudhury, &quot;Towards comprehensive cyberbullying detection: A dataset incorpo-<lb/>rating aggressive texts, repetition, peerness, and intent to harm,&quot; Comput. Human Behav., vol. 153, no. 3, <lb/>pp. 108123, 2024. doi: 10.1016/j.chb.2023.108123. <lb/>[44] S. A. Özel, S. Akdemir, H. Aksu, and E. Saraç, &quot;Detection of cyberbullying on social media messages <lb/>in Turkish,&quot; in 2017 Int. Conf. Comput. Sci. Eng. (UBMK), Antalya, Turkey, 2017, pp. 366-370. doi: <lb/>10.1109/UBMK.2017.8093411. <lb/>[45] M. Dadvar and F. deJong, &quot;Cyberbullying detection: A step toward a safer internet yard,&quot; in WWW <lb/>12 Companion: Proc. 21st Int. Conf. on World Wide Web, Lyon France, Apr. 2012, pp. 121. doi: <lb/>10.1145/2187980.2187995. <lb/>[46] T. A. Buan, S. Steria, and R. Ramachandra, &quot;Automated cyberbullying detection in social media using an <lb/>SVM activated stacked convolution LSTM network,&quot; in ICCDA &apos;20: Proc. 2020 4th International Conf. <lb/>Comput. Data Anal., CA, USA, Mar. 2020, pp. 170-174. <lb/>[47] N. Potha and M. Maragoudakis, &quot;Cyberbullying detection using time series modeling,&quot; in Proc. IEEE Int. <lb/>Conf. Data Mining Workshop, Shenzhen, China, 2014, pp. 373-382. <lb/>[48] J. O. Atoum, &quot;Cyberbullying detection through sentiment analysis,&quot; in Proc. Int. Conf. Comput. Sci. <lb/>Comput. Intell. (CSCI), Las Vegas, NV, USA, 2020, pp. 292-297. <lb/>[49] D. A. Musleh et al., &quot;Arabic sentiment analysis of YouTube comments: NLP-Based machine learning <lb/>approaches for content evaluation,&quot; Big Data Cogn. Comput., vol. 7, no. 127, pp. 1-15, 2023. doi: <lb/>10.3390/bdcc7030127. <lb/>[50] A. Alotaibi et al., &quot;Spam and sentiment detection in Arabic tweets using MarBert model,&quot; Math. Model. <lb/>Eng. Prob., vol. 9, no. 6, pp. 1574-1582, 2022. doi: 10.18280/mmep.090617. <lb/>[51] A. M. Alduailaj and A. Belghith, &quot;Detecting Arabic cyberbullying tweets using machine learning,&quot; Mach <lb/>Learn. Knowl. Extr., vol. 5, no. 1, pp. 29-42, 2023. doi: 10.3390/make5010003. <lb/>[52] M. Alzaqebah et al., &quot;Cyberbullying detection framework for short and imbalanced Arabic datasets,&quot; J. <lb/>King Saud Univ.-Comput. Inform. Sci., vol. 35, no. 8, pp. 101652, 2023. doi: 10.1016/j.jksuci.2023.101652. <lb/>[53] K. T. Mursi and A. M. Almalki, &quot;ArCyb: A robust machine-learning model for Arabic cyberbullying <lb/>tweets in Saudi Arabia,&quot; Int. J. Adv. Comput. Sci. Appl., vol. 14, no. 9, pp. 1059-1067, 2023. doi: <lb/>10.14569/IJACSA.2023.01409110. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>1054 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.80, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>[54] Atta-ur-Rahman, S. Dash, A. K. Luhach, N. Chilamkurti, S. Baek and Y. Nam, &quot;A neuro-fuzzy approach <lb/>for user behaviour classification and prediction,&quot; J. Cloud Comput., vol. 8, no. 1, pp. 1-15, 2019. doi: <lb/>10.1186/s13677-019-0144-9. <lb/>[55] V. Balakrisnan and M. Kaity, &quot;Cyberbullying detection and machine learning: A systematic literature <lb/>review,&quot; Artif. Intell. Rev., vol. 56, no. Suppl 1, pp. 1375-1416, 2023. doi: 10.1007/s10462-023-10553-w. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>