<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T13:41:43.639Z">11/21/2025 1:41:43 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T13:41:29.467549Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T13:41:29.467549Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>Plexin B1 controls Treg <lb/>numbers, limits allergic <lb/>airway inflammation, and <lb/>regulates mucins <lb/>Svetlana P. Chapoval 1,2,3 , Hongjuan Gao 2,4 , Rachel Fanaroff 5 † <lb/>and Achsah D. Keegan 1,2,3,6 * <lb/>1 Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, <lb/>MD, United States, 2 Center for Vascular and Inflammatory Diseases, University of Maryland School of <lb/>Medicine, Baltimore, MD, United States, 3 Program in Oncology at the Greenebaum Cancer Center, <lb/>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, United States, 4 Department of Physiology, <lb/>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, United States, 5 Department of Pathology, <lb/>University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, United States, 6 Veteran Affairs (VA) Maryland <lb/>Health Care System, Baltimore Veteran Affairs (VA) Medical Center, Baltimore, MD, United States <lb/>We investigated the effect of global Plexin B1 deficiency on allergic airway <lb/>responses to house dust mite (HDM) or ovalbumin (OVA). In the HDM model, <lb/>there were higher Th2 cytokine levels in the BALF of Plexin B1 knock-out (KO) <lb/>mice compared to wild type (WT), and tissue inflammation and mucus <lb/>production were modestly enhanced. In the OVA model, Plexin B1 deficiency <lb/>led to increases in lung inflammation, mucus production, and lung Th2 cytokines <lb/>accompanied by dysregulated mucin gene expression without affecting anti-<lb/>OVA IgE/IgG1 levels. Spleen cells from Plexin B1 KO mice proliferated more <lb/>robustly than WT cells in vitro to a variety of stimuli. Plexin B1 KO CD4+ T cells <lb/>from spleens expressed higher levels of Ki-67 and CD69 compared to WT cells. <lb/>Spleen cells from naïve Plexin B1 KO mice secreted increased amounts of IL-4 <lb/>and IL-6 when pulsed in vitro with OVA whereas in vivo OVA-primed spleen cells <lb/>produced IL-4/IL-5 when subjected to in vitro OVA restimulation. The <lb/>upregulated allergic inflammatory response in Plexin B1 KO mice was <lb/>associated with a lower number of Tregs in the lung tissues. Moreover, these <lb/>mice displayed lower numbers of Treg cells in the lymphoid tissues at the <lb/>baseline. These results demonstrate a previously unrecognized link between <lb/>Plexin B1, Treg cells, and mucus in allergic lung inflammation. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>semaphorin 4, plexin B1, Tregs, allergy, inflammation <lb/>Abbreviations: OVA, chicken ovalbumin; HDM, house dust mite extract; Sema4A, semaphorin 4A; Sema4D, <lb/>semaphorin 4D; BAL, broncho-alveolar lavage; BALF, broncho-alveolar lavage fluid; H&amp;E, hematoxylin and <lb/>eosin; PAS, periodic acid-Schiff; BrdU, bromodeoxyuridine. <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Hideki Nakano, <lb/>National Institute of Environmental Health <lb/>Sciences (NIH), United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Stephane Lajoie, <lb/>Johns Hopkins University, United States <lb/>Martijn J. Schuijs, <lb/>Flemish Institute for Biotechnology, Belgium <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Achsah D. Keegan <lb/>akeegan@som.umaryland.edu <lb/> † PRESENT ADDRESS <lb/>Rachel Fanaroff, <lb/>Department of Pathology, Memorial Sloan <lb/>Kettering Cancer Center, New York, NY, <lb/>United States <lb/>RECEIVED 19 September 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 15 December 2023 <lb/>PUBLISHED 08 January 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Chapoval SP, Gao H, Fanaroff R and <lb/>Keegan AD (2024) Plexin B1 controls Treg <lb/>numbers, limits allergic airway inflammation, <lb/>and regulates mucins. <lb/>Front. Immunol. 14:1297354. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Chapoval, Gao, Fanaroff and Keegan. <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under <lb/>the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic <lb/>practice. No use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>is permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 08 January 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></front>

		<body>Introduction <lb/>Asthma is a chronic inflammatory lung disease that is <lb/>characterized by airway inflammation, mucus hypersecretion, <lb/>smooth muscle hypertrophy, and oedema of the airway wall <lb/>leading to airway narrowing (1). Asthmatic lung tissue is infiltrated <lb/>with inflammatory cells with notable upregulation of Th2 cytokines <lb/>in a major asthma Th2 endotype (1, 2). Foxp3+ regulatory T cells are <lb/>potent suppressors of Th2 cell activation and Th2-driven lung <lb/>inflammation (3). Therefore, the in vivo stimulation of Treg cells <lb/>can provide a beneficial immunosuppressive effect in overexaggerated <lb/>asthmatic lung response (3-6). Our current study focuses on the <lb/>stimulatory effect of neuroimmune semaphorin 4A (Sema4A) on <lb/>Treg cells by utilizing its receptor Plexin B1 (7, 8). <lb/>Plexin B1 (alternative names: PLXNB1, Semaphorin receptor <lb/>SEP, KIAA0407, PLXN5, SEP) serves as a receptor for class 4 <lb/>semaphorin family proteins, Sema4A and Sema4D (9-13). The role <lb/>of Plexin B1 in autoimmune diseases, cancer, and cardiovascular <lb/>diseases has been extensively studied and mostly associated with its <lb/>engagement of Sema4D (14-19). The role of Plexin B1-Sema4A <lb/>interaction in disease is less defined (10, 12, 20). One report shows <lb/>that the Sema4A-Plexin B1 pathway plays a critical role in the <lb/>directional guidance of axonal elongation during brain <lb/>development and growth cone collapse in mouse hippocampal <lb/>neurons in vitro (20). Wang and associates (12) assessed the <lb/>significance of Sema4A-Plexin B1 pathway in the inflammatory <lb/>response in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) by using human synovial <lb/>fibroblasts of RA (RASFs) in in vitro cultures. When RASFs were <lb/>stimulated with rSema4A, they secreted a substantial amount of IL-<lb/>6 which was almost completely abrogated by siRNA to Plexin B1. <lb/>The authors concluded that an increased expression of Sema4A <lb/>found in synovial fluid of patients with RA is required to <lb/>promote inflammation. <lb/>Sema4A is known to act as an axon guidance molecule in the <lb/>nervous system; in the immune system it can act as a costimulatory <lb/>molecule for T cell activation and a negative regulator of tissue <lb/>inflammation (10, 21-23). We previously showed that Sema4A <lb/>deficient mice displayed enhanced allergic airway inflammation <lb/>accompanied by fewer Treg cells, however the. identity of the <lb/>Sema4A counter receptor(s) responsible for this effect was <lb/>unknown (10, 23). We subsequently reported that Sema4A exerts <lb/>a stabilizing effect on human Treg cells in PBMC and CD4+ T cell <lb/>cultures by engaging Plexin B1 (8). While Sema4A deficient mice <lb/>displayed enhanced allergic airway inflammation accompanied by <lb/>fewer Treg cells, Sema4D deficient mice displayed reduced <lb/>inflammation and increased Treg cell numbers even though both <lb/>Sema4 subfamily members can engage Plexin B1 (10, 23, 24). <lb/>Moreover, Sema4A and Sema4D display opposite effects on <lb/>human Treg cells in in vitro cultures of peripheral blood <lb/>mononuclear cells (PBMC); Sema4D inhibited CD4+CD25 <lb/>+Foxp3+ cell numbers and CD25/Foxp3 expression (7). <lb/>Therefore, to determine the role of Plexin B1 in allergic <lb/>inflammation, we generated and characterized responses to <lb/>allergens in mice lacking Plexin B1, Plexin B1knock-out (KO). <lb/>We observed that mice systemically lacking Plexin B1 have a lower <lb/>pool of Treg cells in lymphoid organs and lungs as compared to wild <lb/>type (WT) mice. Additionally, Plexin B1 was found to control <lb/>selected mucin gene expression. The in vivo Plexin B1 deficiency <lb/>resulted in heightened allergic airway inflammatory response and <lb/>mucin dysregulation in response to allergen exposures. These <lb/>results will be informative for the future design of Sema4A-Plexin <lb/>B1-based therapeutics for allergic asthma, given that Sema4A <lb/>functions as a downregulatory molecule for allergen-induced <lb/>disease in mice (23). <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Mice <lb/>C57BL/6J mice (WT mice) were obtained from Jackson <lb/>Laboratory. Plexin B1 KO mice (Supplementary Figure S1) were <lb/>generated at Cyagen (KOCMP-235611-Plxnb1-B6J-VA, Santa Clara, <lb/>CA; C57BL/6J-Plxnb1 em1cyagen ). In brief, the Plxnb1 gene encoding <lb/>Plexin B1 was altered via Crispr/Cas9 gene targeting in embryonic <lb/>stem cells. Homologous recombination led to deletion of exons 4-16 <lb/>of the Plxnb1 gene (Supplementary Figure S1). The deletion was <lb/>identified via PCR with a forward primer (F1) annealing 5&apos; to exon 4 <lb/>and reverse primer (R1), that anneals 3&apos; to exon 16. Deletion in F1 <lb/>animals was confirmed by Cyagen by sequencing which <lb/>demonstrated a deletion of 5524 bp of mouse Plxnb1 and a 135 bp <lb/>insertion. Heterozygous mice were inter-bred to generate <lb/>homozygous targeted mice. The homozygous Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>were bred at the University of Maryland School of Medicine by <lb/>brother sister mating and genotyped to confirm homozygosity of the <lb/>targeted Plxnb1 allele using the following primer sets: <lb/>Primer&apos;s set 1: (Annealing Temperature 60.0 °C) <lb/>F1: 5&apos;-AATATAGGAGTGAGCATTGGAGCA-3&apos; <lb/>R1: 5&apos;-TCCAGAGTGTTAAGTCTACAGTGG-3&apos; <lb/>Product size: KO 610 bp; WT 5999 bp <lb/>Primer&apos;s set 2: (Annealing Temperature 60.0 °C) <lb/>F1: 5&apos;-AATATAGGAGTGAGCATTGGAGCA-3&apos; <lb/>R2: 5&apos;-CATACCCTATGCAACTGTCCTTGA-3&apos; <lb/>Product size: 588 bp <lb/>Homozygotes Plexin B1 KO display one band of 610 bp (using <lb/>F1, R1 primers), while wild type alleles display one band of 588 bp <lb/>(using F1, R2 primers). WT and Plexin B1 KO (C57BL/6J-<lb/>Plxnb1 em1cyagen ) mice were maintained under specific pathogen-<lb/>free conditions with free access to food and water. All experiments <lb/>with the mice were performed in compliance with the principles <lb/>and procedures outlined in the NIH Guide for Care and Use of <lb/>Animals and were approved by the University of Maryland School <lb/>of Medicine Animal Care and Use Committee. <lb/>Anesthetic <lb/>Avertin in dose of 0.3 mg/kg or 2 mg/kg by i.p. injection was <lb/>used as previously described (25) to anesthetize or euthanize the <lb/>mice, correspondingly. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>02 <lb/></page>

		<body>Kidney size measurements <lb/>Analysis of kidney size was performed as described previously <lb/>(26). Left and right kidneys were dissected from 13-week-old male <lb/>mice. The kidney length and width were measured in mm and <lb/>overall kidney area was calculated as length x width (mm2). <lb/>Experimental protocols <lb/>a) House dust mite (HDM)-induced allergic response. WT and <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice were treated with HDM allergenic extract (lot <lb/>no. 360924, Greer Laboratories, endotoxin concentration: 13.14 EU/ <lb/>50 mg HDM dose) as previously described (27). Briefly, 50 mg of <lb/>extract in 5 ml PBS was applied to anesthetized mice intranasally <lb/>four times six days apart. The resulting inflammatory response was <lb/>assessed 48h after the last HDM application. <lb/>b) OVA-induced allergic response. WT and Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>were immunized with OVA (Endofit OVA, low-endotoxin <lb/>concentration; InVivoGen Labs) adsorbed to Alum as described <lb/>previously (25, 28, 29). Briefly, mice were immunized with either <lb/>100 mg of OVA/Alum or Alum alone by IP injection on day 1 and <lb/>again on day 6. Mice were challenged with aerosolized PBS or 1% <lb/>OVA in PBS for 40 minutes each day on days 12 and 14. The <lb/>assessment of allergic lung response was performed 48h later. <lb/>Bronchoalveolar lavage collection and <lb/>cell composition <lb/>BALs were obtained from euthanized mice and processed as <lb/>previously described (28, 29). Cytospin preparations were made <lb/>with 200 mL of BAL fluid (Cytospin 2; Shandon Inc., Pittsburgh, <lb/>PA) and stained with Diff-Quick (Dade Behring, Deerfield, IL). The <lb/>differential cell counts were determined from 4 high-power fields. <lb/>Histochemistry and score-based <lb/>quantification of lung histology <lb/>Lungs were obtained from euthanized WT and Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>after completion of the allergen treatment protocols and prepared as <lb/>previously described (27, 30). N = 3-7 mice per experimental group in <lb/>3-4 independent experiments were used. Lung sections were processed <lb/>at the University of Maryland School of Medicine&apos;s Pathology <lb/>Histology core within the Center for Innovative Biomedical <lb/>Resources (CIBR) and prepared for histochemistry (H&amp;E and PAS <lb/>stains) of deparaffinized lung tissues. Lung sections were evaluated by <lb/>an investigator blinded to the experimental conditions. H&amp;E and PAS <lb/>stains were evaluated as previously described (27, 30): for H&amp;E, 0, no <lb/>signs of inflammation; 1, light and dispersed infiltrate in only a few <lb/>areas of the section; 2, modest infiltrate surrounding major vessels and <lb/>airways, with little in distal airway unit; 3, moderate infiltrate <lb/>surrounding &lt;50% of distal airways and vessels; and 4, heavy and <lb/>focused eosinophilic infiltrate surrounding numerous distal vessels and <lb/>airways, signs of increased alveolar macrophage numbers with <lb/>macrophage fusions and extracellular matrix deposition. For PAS: 0, <lb/>no signs of mucus in airways or elevated numbers of PAS+ cells; 1, no <lb/>mucus in airways, slight increase in numbers of PAS+ cells in a few <lb/>major airways; 2, some mucus detectable in major airways; 3, mucus <lb/>detected in major airways with &lt;50% of distal airway epithelial cells <lb/>PAS+ in distal airway units; and 4, mucus plugging of airways observed <lb/>in several airways and majority of distal airway epithelial cells are PAS+ <lb/>in multiple distal airways per section. <lb/>Goblet cell hyperplasia <lb/>Goblet cell hyperplasia was evaluated on PAS-stained lung <lb/>sections. For observation consistency, similarly sized PAS+ airways <lb/>were identified on each slide and digitally imaged at 20X magnification. <lb/>PAS+ cells were quantified from two-three images per sample using <lb/>ECHO imaging system. PAS+ cells were counted manually and <lb/>normalized to the length of the basement membrane (31). <lb/>Cytokines, chemokines, Mucin 5AC, and <lb/>soluble Sema4A in BALF <lb/>The levels of BALF cytokines and chemokines were determined <lb/>using Searchlight Proteome Array (Aushon) at the Cytokine Core <lb/>Lab, Center for Innovative Biomedical Resources, University of <lb/>Maryland School of Medicine. The array data were analyzed using <lb/>the ArrayVision software. In studies where the absolute value of BAL <lb/>cytokines varied in independent experiments, cytokine values were <lb/>normalized to allergen-induced fold increase relative to the value of <lb/>control PBS-treated WT mice (set as 1). The Muc5AC concentrations <lb/>in BALF were determined with the use of ELISA kit NBP2-76704 <lb/>(Novus Biologicals) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instruction. <lb/>Mouse Sema4A ELISA kit (MBS3807413, MyBioSource) was used <lb/>to measure the levels of soluble Sema4A in BALF at 48h after last <lb/>OVA challenge. <lb/>WST-1 cell proliferation assay <lb/>The Premix WST-1 Cell Proliferation Assay System (#MK400, <lb/>Takara) was used to assess the number of metabolically active cells, <lb/>a surrogate for cell proliferative responses in vitro. Single cell <lb/>suspensions were prepared from spleens of naïve, or PBS-and <lb/>OVA-injected mice on day 5 post-treatment. Spleen mononuclear <lb/>cells (MNC) were plated to a density of 1 × 10 6 cells/200ml in 96-<lb/>well tissue culture plates (#353072, Falcon) and stimulated with <lb/>either Concanavalin (Con) A (10mg/ml; Invitrogen), LPS (100mg/ <lb/>ml; #L5293, Sigma-Aldrich), OVA (from 0.001 to 100 mg/ml; <lb/>InvivoGen), or OVA 323-339 peptide (200mg/ml; #RP10610, <lb/>GenScript) as previously described (23). After 72h of incubation, <lb/>20ml of tetrazolium salt WST-1 solution was added to each well <lb/>followed by 4h of further incubation. The stable tetrazolium salt is <lb/>cleaved to soluble formazan by a process dependent on the <lb/>glycolytic production of NAD(P)H in viable cells which directly <lb/>correlates to the number of metabolically active cells in the culture. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>03 <lb/></page>

		<body>The plates were read in the ELISA plate reader at 450 nm with a <lb/>reference wavelength of 650nm. <lb/>In vivo proliferation assay and <lb/>measurement of T cell activation <lb/>WT and Plexin B1 KO mice were injected with OVA/Alum/200 <lb/>ml and 1 mg/100 ml BrdU i.p. on day 0 (9). Mice received BrdU <lb/>(EMD Millipore, #19-160) injection the following day. Twenty-four <lb/>hours later mice were sacrificed, spleens were harvested and <lb/>processed to single cell suspensions. Spleen MNC were stained <lb/>with Abs to cell surface markers (CD4 and CD69) and BrdU <lb/>expression was analyzed by flow cytometry employing FITC <lb/>BrdU Flow kit (BD Pharmingen, #51-2354AK) for staining <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s instruction. <lb/>Flow cytometry <lb/>Flow cytometry of lung, lymph node, and spleen single cell <lb/>suspensions was performed as previously described (30, 32, 33) using <lb/>the BD Biosciences Abs for the following cell markers: I-Ab (#562823, <lb/>APC), CD3 (#553061, FITC), CD4 (#563933, PE-Cy7), CD8 (#553036, <lb/>PerCP), CD25 (APC, #557192), and CD45R/B220 (#552771, PerCP-<lb/>Cy5.5). Intracellular staining for Foxp3 was done using anti-Foxp3 Ab <lb/>or rat IgG2a(kappa) isotype control Ab (both AlexaFluor700 and from <lb/>eBioscience, #56-5773-80 and #56-4321-80, correspondingly) with <lb/>mouse Foxp3 Buffer Set (#560409, BD Biosciences). For detection of <lb/>activation marker expression on CD4+ T cells, spleen MNC were <lb/>cultured in vitro in medium (cRPMI) alone, OVA (20 mg/1 x 10 6 cells/ <lb/>well), or ConA from Invitrogen (500X, #00-4978-93; 2 ml/1 x 10 6 cells/ <lb/>well) or from Sigma (C5275, 0.028 mg/well) for 36h. The cells were <lb/>harvested, stained, and analyzed for CD69 expression using anti-CD69 <lb/>PE-labeled Ab from Invitrogen (#12-0691-81) or armenian hamster <lb/>IgG PE (# 12-4888-81) as an isotype control Ab, or for Ki-67 <lb/>intracellular expression using mAb FITC (clone SOL815) from <lb/>Termofisher Scientific with rat IgG2a FITC in control tubes. For <lb/>dead cell discrimination in flow the LIVE/DEAD ™ Fixable Aqua <lb/>Dead Cell Stain Kit was used (Invitrogen). For the assessment of Plexin <lb/>B1 expression on spleen and lymph node T cells, single cell suspensions <lb/>were stained with anti-Plexin B1 primary Ab (clone A-8, Santa Cruz) <lb/>followed by mouse-IgGk BP-CFL 488 (sc-516176, Santa Cruz) or anti-<lb/>mouse IgG-APC (#F0101B, R&amp;D Systems). The cells in the control <lb/>tubes were stained with purified mouse IgG2B (MAB0041, R&amp;D <lb/>Systems) followed by a secondary fluorochrome-labeled Ab. Cells <lb/>were pre-treated with purified rat anti-mouse CD16/CD32 (Mouse BD <lb/>Fc Block) Ab before staining for specific markers. Cells gated by <lb/>forward-and side-scatter parameters were analyzed using the FlowJo <lb/>10 software. <lb/>RT-qPCR <lb/>Total lung RNA was extracted using TRIzol Plus RNA <lb/>Purification Kit (#12183555, Invitrogen) (34). Briefly, the kidney or <lb/>lung tissues samples were placed in 1 ml of TRIzol reagent and <lb/>homogenized using immersion homogenizer (Omni International, <lb/>Southern Labware, Cumming, GA). Chloroform and 4-bromoanisole <lb/>additions were used for lysis, and aqueous solution with RNA was <lb/>treated with ethanol for precipitation. The PureLink RNA Mini Kit <lb/>(Invitrogen) was used for RNA membrane-binding and elution. <lb/>iScript gDNA Clear cDNA Synthesis Kit (Bio-Rad) was used for <lb/>the first strand DNA syntheses at Bio-Rad T100 Thermal Cycler and <lb/>PowerUp SYBR Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) was used <lb/>for qPCR workflow on QuantStudio 3 (Applied Biosystems) with sets <lb/>of primers for mucins and Plxnb1, exons 11 and 38 (17, 35-38) <lb/>shown in Supplementary Table 1 (Integrated DNA Technologies). <lb/>The expression of the target gene was calculated using the 2-DD Ct <lb/>method, and the expression level was relative to Hypoxanthine <lb/>Phosphoribosyltransferase 1 (HPRT1) as the reference gene. RNA <lb/>and DNA concentrations were measured using NanoDrop One <lb/>spectrophotometer (ThermoScientific). <lb/>Total IgE and anti-OVA IgE/IgG1 in sera <lb/>Total and OVA-specific serum IgE/IgG1 Ab levels at different <lb/>time-points during the allergen immunization protocol were <lb/>measured using Mouse IgE ELISA kit (Invitrogen), Mouse anti-<lb/>OVA IgE assay kit (Chondrex), and anti-Ovalbumin IgG1 ELISA <lb/>kit (Cayman Chemical), correspondingly. All ELISA plates were <lb/>read on either iMark (Bio-Rad) or SpectroStar Nano (BMG <lb/>Labtech) microplate reader using the manufacturer specified <lb/>wavelengths for each assay. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>Data were summarized as mean ± SEM. To calculate <lb/>significance levels between experimental groups, two-way <lb/>ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test, ordinary one-<lb/>way ANOVA, and non-parametric Mann-Whitney&apos;s test <lb/>(GraphPrizm8) were performed as indicated in the corresponding <lb/>figure legends. <lb/>Results <lb/>Generation and characterization of Plexin <lb/>B1 KO mice <lb/>We reported previously that Plexin B1 plays a critical role in <lb/>human Treg cell stability and function in vitro (7, 8). To investigate <lb/>the role of Plexin B1 signaling in Treg cell stability and function in <lb/>vivo, Plexin B1 KO mice were generated at Cyagen (Supplementary <lb/>Figure S1A). Plexin B1 KO mice were found to be viable and fertile. <lb/>They displayed an increase in kidney size measured at post-<lb/>gestational week 13 compared to kidneys obtained from age-sex <lb/>matched WT mice consisted with a previous study (26) on the role <lb/>of Plexin B1 in kidney morphogenesis (Supplementary Figure S1B). <lb/>They demonstrated a lack of Plexin B1 transcripts in kidney, a tissue <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>04 <lb/></page>

		<body>known to express high levels of Plexin B1 (Supplementary Figure <lb/>S1C). We further evaluated Plexin B1 transcripts in the lungs of <lb/>mice treated with allergenic stimulations, either OVA/Alum or <lb/>HDM as indicated (Supplementary Figures S1D, E). OVA <lb/>treatment increased lung Plexin B1 expression over the PBS <lb/>control while HDM treatment reduced Plexin B1 in WT mice. <lb/>Plexin B1 transcripts were not detected in lungs isolated from <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice using primer pairs located in exon 11 or <lb/>exon 38. <lb/>Plexin B1 modulates multiple parameters <lb/>of allergic inflammation <lb/>We examined the response of WT and Plexin B1 KO mice to <lb/>house dust mite (HDM), a common human allergen highly <lb/>associated with allergic asthma and disease exacerbation. To <lb/>detail Plexin B1 function in the HDM-induced allergic response, <lb/>WT and Plexin B1 KO mice were subjected to four intranasal <lb/>applications of HDM allergenic extract six days apart. Control mice <lb/>were treated with endotoxin-free PBS. A classical allergic airway <lb/>response was observed in WT mice 48h after the last HDM <lb/>application (Figures 1A-C). This response consisted of prominent <lb/>BAL (Figure 1B) eosinophilic infiltration where more than 50% of <lb/>BAL cells were eosinophils. HDM also stimulated multiple <lb/>peribronchial and perivascular inflammatory infiltrates <lb/>(Figure 1E). The allergic inflammatory response was more <lb/>pronounced in the lung tissues of Plexin B1 KO mice as the <lb/>inflammation score was significantly higher than that in WT mice <lb/>(Figure 1C). Although the overall mucus score did not differ <lb/>significantly between WT and KO mice, the number of <lb/>hyperplastic mucous cells per mm of basal lamina was <lb/>significantly upregulated by Plexin B1 deficiency (Figure 1D). <lb/>Levels of soluble Sema4A in BALF did not differ between <lb/>untreated WT and Plexin B1 KO mice (Figure 1F). However, <lb/>HDM treatment led to a downregulation of BALF Sema4A as <lb/>compared to PBS-treated controls in WT mice but not in Plexin <lb/>B1 KO mice. The relative levels of Th2 cytokines IL-4 and IL-5 in <lb/>BALF (Figure 1H) were increased in Plexin B1 KO mice, however, <lb/>the increase in IL-5 did not achieve statistical significance. IL-13 <lb/>levels in BALF were below the limit of assay detection. IL-6 levels <lb/>were significantly upregulated in HDM-treated Plexin B1KO mice <lb/>(Figure 1H) while CCL11 levels were reduced (Figure 1H). This <lb/>paradoxical decrease in CCL11 may be due to its consumption by <lb/>the increased number of eosinophils. No significant changes in total <lb/>TGFb and IL-10 levels in BALF between PBS-and HDM-treated <lb/>WT and KO mice were detected (data not shown). BALF TNFa <lb/>levels were below the limit of detection (19 pg/ml). Thus, Plexin B1-<lb/>deficiency resulted in enhanced features of HDM-induced <lb/>experimental allergic airway inflammation. <lb/>Since most of the previously published studies on the effects of <lb/>Sema4A and Sema4D deficiencies an allergic inflammation used the <lb/>classic Ova/alum model (23, 24), we also compared the responses of <lb/>WT and Plexin B1 KO mice to the classic OVA/Alum prime, boost, <lb/>and OVA challenge as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section. Allergen exposure of WT mice led to significant increases in <lb/>BAL total cell numbers from 261.0 x10 3 cells in PBS-treated mice to <lb/>2511.0 x 10 3 cells in OVA-treated mice (Figure 2A). Eosinophilia <lb/>was also elevated from 0 eosinophils noted in PBS-treated mice to <lb/>1963.0 x 10 3 after OVA exposure (Figure 2B). However, similar to <lb/>what we observed in Sema4A-deficient mice (23), these increases <lb/>were even more prominent in Plexin B1 KO mice, reaching to <lb/>4573.0 x 10 3 total cells and 3993.0 x10 3 eosinophils after OVA <lb/>exposure. The absolute number of lymphocytes in BAL was equal <lb/>between OVA-treated WT and KO mice amounting to 243.3 x 10 3 <lb/>and 273.1 x 10 3 ), correspondingly. Although the overall lung <lb/>inflammation scores were not significantly different between <lb/>OVA-treated WT and Plexin B1 KO mice (Figure 2C), the mucus <lb/>secretion and the number of hyperplastic mucous cells per mm of <lb/>basal lamina were strikingly increased in mice lacking Plexin B1 <lb/>(Figure 2D). The histology photomicrographs shown in Figures 2E, <lb/>F reflect the BALF cell counts and mucus grading/PAS+ cell counts. <lb/>There was no difference between Plexin B1 KO lungs compared to <lb/>WT lungs in control mice. However, allergen treatment led to <lb/>multiple inflammatory infiltrates in both WT and Plexin B1 KO <lb/>mice. No significant differences in BALF Sema4A levels were <lb/>detected between PBS controls and OVA experimental groups <lb/>(data not shown). Plexin B1 deficiency affected BALF cytokines; <lb/>we observed increased IL-4, IL-5, and TNFa levels (Figure 2G) and <lb/>reduced IL-10 in the BALF of Plexin B1 KO mice compared to WT <lb/>(Figure 2G). The levels of other BALF cytokines and chemokines <lb/>(IL-25, IL-6, IL-33, eotaxin, and RANTES) did not differ between <lb/>OVA-treated WT and Plexin B1 KO mice, whereas the levels of <lb/>TSLP, IFNg, IL-12, and IL-13 were below the assay&apos;s limit of <lb/>detection. The effect of Plexin B1 deficiency on the allergic <lb/>inflammatory response to OVA is similar to the effect of Sema4A <lb/>deficiency we observed in our earlier studies (23). Namely, Plexin <lb/>B1 deficiency leads to increases in BALF and lung tissue <lb/>inflammation, eosinophilia, mucus production, and Th2 cytokines <lb/>in BALF, but downregulates IL-10. These results demonstrate that <lb/>Plexin B1 modulates allergic inflammatory responses in mice <lb/>exposed to two different allergen protocols with some variation in <lb/>impact between the two models. <lb/>Lower number of Treg cells in lymphoid <lb/>organs of mice lacking Plexin B1 <lb/>The overall percentages of CD3+, CD4+, CD8+, MHCII+B220+ <lb/>cells, and CD4+CD25+ T cells in lymph nodes (LN) and spleens did <lb/>not differ between untreated WT and Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S2). However, CD4+ and CD8+ Treg cell <lb/>numbers were affected by Plexin B1 deficiency (Figures 3A-C). <lb/>Among CD4+CD25 high lymph node (LN) cells, 32.7% were Foxp3+ <lb/>in WT mice compared to 22.3% in Plexin B1 KO mice (p=0.031) <lb/>(Figure 3A; Supplementary Figure S3A). The difference in CD4+ <lb/>Treg cell numbers between WT and Plexin B1 KO mice was even <lb/>more pronounced in spleen cells; there were 24.2% CD4+CD25 <lb/>+Foxp3+ cells in WT spleens compared to 12.3% in Plexin B1 KO <lb/>spleen cells (Figure 3A; Supplementary Figure S3B). <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>05 <lb/></page>

		<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Effect of Plexin B1 deficiency on HDM-induced allergic lung inflammation and mucous cell hyperplasia in mice. WT and Plexin B1 KO mice were <lb/>treated with HDM as described in Materials and Methods. BAL was performed and evaluated for total number of cells (A) and eosinophil numbers <lb/>(B). Lung sections were stained with H&amp;E or PAS; the slides were scored for inflammation (C) and overall PAS staining and numbers of mucous cell <lb/>hyperplasia (D) as described in Materials and Methods. Representative photomicrographs of lung tissue stained with H&amp;E (E) and PAS (F) are shown. <lb/>Levels of soluble Sema4A (G) and cytokines (H) in BALF were evaluated as described in Materials and Methods. Data from two independent <lb/>experiments are shown (n=4-5 mice/group) and expressed as fold-increase over a PBS-treated WT control. Data statistics were calculated using <lb/>two-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test, two-tailed Mann-Whitney&apos;s non-parametric test, and Wilcoxon&apos;s non-parametric paired test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>06 <lb/></page>

		<body>We also observed that 2.3% of CD8+ T cells in LN of WT mice <lb/>expressed CD25, and the majority of these cells, 59.7%, were <lb/>Foxp3+; these numbers were significantly reduced in Plexin B1 <lb/>KO mice with 2.4% of CD8+ cells expressing CD25 of which 47.2% <lb/>were Foxp3+ (Figure 3B; Supplementary Figure S3C). In spleens, <lb/>6.5% of CD8+ cells co-expressed CD25 in WT mice while 4.7% of <lb/>CD8+ cells co-expressed CD25 in Plexin B1 KO mice (Figure 3C; <lb/>Supplementary Figure S3D). While 24% of CD25+CD8+ T cells co-<lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Effect of Plexin B1 deficiency on inflammation, mucus production, and cytokine levels in BALF after OVA treatment. WT and Plexin B1 KO mice were <lb/>immunized with alum or OVA/alum and challenged as described in Materials and Methods. BAL was performed and evaluated for total number of <lb/>cells in BAL (A) and eosinophil numbers (B). Lung sections were stained with H&amp;E or PAS and scored for levels of inflammation (C) or overall PAS <lb/>staining and numbers of mucous cell hyperplasia (D) as described in Materials and Methods. Representative photomicrographs for H&amp;E (E) and PAS <lb/>(F) are shown. (G) Levels of cytokines in BALF were evaluated as described in Materials and Methods. Data from two independent experiments are <lb/>shown (n=4-11 mice/group). Data statistics were calculated using two-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test, two-tailed Mann-<lb/>Whitney&apos;s non-parametric test, and Wilcoxon&apos;s non-parametric paired test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>07 <lb/></page>

		<body>express Foxp3 in WT spleens, only 10.8% did so in spleen cells <lb/>isolated from Plexin B1 KO mice. Thus, global Plexin B1 deficiency <lb/>results in reduced CD4+ and CD8+ Treg cell numbers in lymphoid <lb/>organs at baseline. <lb/>Higher allergic lung inflammatory response <lb/>in Plexin B1 KO mice is associated with a <lb/>lower number of Tregs in the lungs <lb/>Since there is a critical role for Tregs in suppression of Th2 <lb/>response to allergen, we analyzed the numbers of Tregs in the lungs of <lb/>WT and Plexin B1 KO mice subjected to OVA priming and challenge <lb/>by multi-color flow cytometry. We observed an increase in CD4 <lb/>+CD25+ T cells in the lungs of OVA-primed Plexin B1 KO mice as <lb/>compared to WT mice (22% versus 8%, respectively, Supplementary <lb/>Figure S4A; Figure 4A). However, there was a significantly lower <lb/>number of Foxp3+ cells among the CD4+CD25+ in OVA-primed <lb/>Plexin B1 KO lungs (8%) as compared to WT (15%) counterparts <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S4B; Figure 4B). These results suggest that the <lb/>increased inflammatory response in the lungs of OVA-primed <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice is accompanied by increased numbers of <lb/>activated T cells (CD4+CD25+) but a reduced numbers of Tregs <lb/>(CD4+CD25+Foxp3+) when compared to WT. <lb/>Treg cells in lungs express low Plexin B1 <lb/>CD4+ T cells in lungs from OVA-primed WT mice demonstrated <lb/>low levels of Plexin B1 expression detected by a shift to the right of the <lb/>anti-Plexin B1 histogram of WT cells when overlayed on stained KO <lb/>cells or the control Ig stain (Figure 4C). Low levels of Plexin B1 were <lb/>also observed on lung Treg cells in OVA-exposed WT mice <lb/>(Figure 4C). Plexin B1 expression was below detection by Flow <lb/>cytometry on naïve CD4+ cells and low on naïve CD8+ cells in <lb/>lymphoid tissues of WT mice (Supplementary Figure S5A) <lb/>consistent with a previous study (39). However, Plexin B1 expression <lb/>was highly upregulated by in vitro ConA stimulation of WT cells but <lb/>not Plexin B1 KO cells (Supplementary Figure S5B). No Plexin B1 <lb/>staining was detected on cells obtained from Plexin B1 KO mice. <lb/>Plexin B1 deficiency has no effect on Ab <lb/>response to OVA <lb/>Sema4A deficiency had a profound effect on the OVA-specific <lb/>serum antibodies in allergen challenged mice (23). To investigate if <lb/>deficiency of the Sema4A receptor, Plexin B1, would mirror this <lb/>effect, we subjected WT and Plexin B1 KO mice to either PBS or <lb/>OVA treatments as shown in Figure 4A. No differences in the total <lb/>serum IgE levels between OVA-immunized/challenged WT and <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice were found at different time points during the <lb/>immunization protocol (Figures 5A, B). Similarly, OVA-specific IgE <lb/>and IgG1 concentrations did not differ significantly between WT <lb/>and Plexin B1 KO mice (Figures 5C, D). Therefore, in contrast to <lb/>our previous findings in mice lacking Sema4A (23), Plexin B1 KO <lb/>mice did not display upregulation of anti-OVA IgE/IgG1. <lb/>Plexin B1 deficiency affects lung mucin <lb/>gene expression and Muc5AC secretion <lb/>Mucin dysregulation is one of the damaging and sometimes fatal <lb/>pathological features of allergic asthma (40, 41). Considering the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Plexin B1 deficiency results in reduced numbers of Treg cells in <lb/>lymphoid tissues. Spleen and lymph node cells were isolated <lb/>from WT and Plexin B1 KO mice and evaluated by flow cytometry <lb/>using direct fluorochrome-labeled Abs to cell surface and <lb/>intracellular markers. The data represent combined values from <lb/>three independent FACS experiments using pooled axillary, <lb/>popliteal, and mesenteric LN (A, B) and two individual spleen <lb/>samples in each (A, C) n=4-6. CD4+CD25+Foxp3+ and CD8 <lb/>+CD25+Foxp3+ cell counts in lymph nodes and spleens of WT <lb/>and Plexin B1 KO mice in three independent experiments (n=10-<lb/>12) are shown in corresponding individual dots. The statistical <lb/>differences between parameters were calculated using the non-<lb/>parametric paired Mann-Whitney test and one-tailed paired <lb/>t-test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>08 <lb/></page>

		<body>elevated mucus score observed on PAS-stained lung tissue slides <lb/>obtained from OVA-treated Plexin B1 KO mouse lungs as compared <lb/>to their similarly treated WT counterparts (Figure 2D), we analyzed <lb/>Muc5AC levels in BALF by ELISA. We found that Muc5AC was <lb/>significantly higher in BALF of OVA-treated Plexin B1 KO mice as <lb/>compared to that in WT mice (Figure 6A). We further analyzed the <lb/>expression of the core mucin mRNA in lung tissue homogenates by <lb/>RT-qPCR. In WT mice, OVA treatment significantly increased <lb/>Muc5ac mRNA while it reduced Muc5b mRNA as compared to PBS <lb/>control (Figure 6B). Interestingly, Plexin B1 KO mice demonstrated <lb/>increased levels of Muc1 (Figure 6B). The expression levels of elevated <lb/>Muc5ac and decreased Muc5b mucins were not further changed in <lb/>Plexin B1 KO lungs by OVA treatment (Figure 6B). Therefore, Plexin <lb/>B1 deficiency led to Muc1, Muc5ac and Muc5b mucin gene <lb/>dysregulation in PBS-treated mouse lungs, and to significantly <lb/>elevated Muc5AC protein levels in BALF with OVA exposure. <lb/>Plexin B1 regulates T cell activation and <lb/>proliferation in responses to antigen <lb/>in vitro <lb/>We next examined the role of Plexin B1 in T cell activation in vitro. <lb/>We obtained similar numbers of total mononuclear cells (MNC) from <lb/>spleens of WT and Plexin B1 KO mice (Figure 7A). Analysis of in vitro <lb/>responses of spleen cells from naïve or OVA-primed mice using the cell <lb/>proliferation agent WST1 (23) demonstrated significantly higher <lb/>numbers of metabolically active Plexin B1 KO cells in culture <lb/>compared to WT (Figure 7B). The metabolic activity of naïve WT <lb/>cells was low in response to medium, OVA, or OVA-peptide (OVA 323-<lb/>339 ), while it was enhanced in response to LPS. Remarkably, naïve <lb/>Plexin B1 KO cells demonstrated high levels of metabolic activity when <lb/>cultured in media alone or stimulated with OVA or OVA-peptide to <lb/>levels significantly higher than WT cells. A similar pattern of <lb/>responsiveness was observed when the cells were isolated from PBS-<lb/>treated mice (Figure 7C). WT cells obtained from mice primed 1x with <lb/>OVA showed basal in vitro proliferation that was increased by <lb/>stimulation with LPS, OVA, or OVA-peptide (Figure 7B). Plexin B1 <lb/>KO cells demonstrated a significantly increased response compared to <lb/>WT cells in all treatment groups. Interestingly, when spleen cells were <lb/>prepared from mice exposed to the full OVA/Alum allergic lung <lb/>inflammation protocol, the in vitro recall responses between WT and <lb/>PlexinB1 KO were not significantly different from each other, however <lb/>the Plexin B1 KO response tended to be slightly less than <lb/>WT (Figure 7C). <lb/>We also examined the proliferative and activation status of cells by <lb/>Flow cytometric analysis (Supplementary Figures S6A, B) for Ki-67 and <lb/>CD69. We observed that Ki-67 expression was significantly higher in <lb/>Plexin B1 KO CD4+ cells in the media-, OVA-, and ConA-stimulated <lb/>cultures as compared to WT cells (Figure 7D). The number of CD4 <lb/>+CD69+ cells doubled in Plexin B1-deficient spleen cells cultured with <lb/>medium alone or stimulated with OVA (Figure 7D). Taken together, <lb/>these results suggest that Plexin B1 plays a role in limiting the <lb/>proliferative response of naïve splenic T-cells during in vitro culture. <lb/>Plexin B1 regulates T cell activation and <lb/>proliferation in vivo <lb/>Considering that splenic T cells from Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>proliferated more robustly to in vitro stimuli as compared to cells <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Increased CD4+CD25+ T cell and decreased Treg cell numbers are <lb/>associated with a heightened allergic response in Plexin B1KO mice. <lb/>Lungs were excised from OVA-immunized and challenged WT and <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice. Lung tissues were digested with collagenase-<lb/>DNAse and single-cell suspensions were analyzed by FACS for the <lb/>expression of CD3, CD4, and CD25 markers. (A) The numbers of <lb/>CD25+ cells among CD4+ T cells were assessed by a sequential <lb/>gating strategy shown in Supplementary Figure S4A. The statistical <lb/>differences between parameters were calculated using the non-<lb/>parametric paired Mann-Whitney test. (B) The percentage of CD4 <lb/>+Foxp3+ Treg cells in PBS-and OVA-treated mice was calculated <lb/>based on the gating strategy shown in Supplementary Figure S4B. <lb/>Data statistics were calculated using two-tailed Mann-Whitney&apos;s non-<lb/>parametric test and Wilcoxon&apos;s non-parametric paired test. (C) Plexin <lb/>B1 staining was evaluated on CD4+ T cells and Treg cells as described <lb/>in Materials and Methods. Histogram overlays were prepared showing <lb/>Plexin B1 on WT versus KO cells (dark gray vs light gray), Plexin B1 on <lb/>WT cells compared to control Ig (dark vs light gray), or Plexin B1 on <lb/>KO cells compared to control Ig (dark vs light gray). The data shown <lb/>are representative of one out of two independent FACS experiments <lb/>with two individual lung samples in each. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>09 <lb/></page>

		<body>obtained from WT spleens, we analyzed in vivo T cell activation <lb/>using the OVA and BrdU treatment of mice followed by <lb/>interchromatin BrdU staining. PBS/Alum-treated mice served as <lb/>controls in this study. The number of CD4+BrdU+ cells in PBS/ <lb/>Alum-treated mice was elevated in Plexin B1 KO splenocytes <lb/>compared to WT. Furthermore, after one OVA/Alum priming <lb/>there were 2-fold more CD4+BrdU+ cells in Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>as compared to WT mice (Figure 8A). We also observed the <lb/>increased relative numbers of CD4+CD69+ cells in spleens of <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice (Supplementary Figure S7) and a shift toward <lb/>higher intensity of BrdU expression in these cells as compared to <lb/>WT mice (Figure 8B). Our data suggest that Plexin B1 plays an <lb/>important role in CD4+ T cell homeostasis at base-line and during <lb/>priming in vivo. <lb/>Plexin B1 KO spleen MNC are Th2-prone <lb/>Since naïve Plexin B1 KO CD4+ T cells demonstrated <lb/>enhanced proliferative and activation markers in response to in <lb/>vitro stimuli, we next examined the levels of Th1/Th2 cytokines in <lb/>the cell culture supernatants. Spleens were obtained from naïve, <lb/>PBS-treated, and OVA-treated mice. Spleen MNC were cultured <lb/>in vitro with OVA as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section. Cell culture supernatants were collected 36h later and <lb/>analyzed for Th1/Th2 cytokine content. In the cultures of naïve <lb/>cells stimulated in vitro with OVA, Plexin B1 KO cells already <lb/>showed measurable IL-4 production as well as IL-6 upregulation <lb/>as compared to WT cells (Figure 9A). For PBS-treated mice, the <lb/>same cytokines were upregulated in Plexin B1 KO cells <lb/>(Figure 9B). As for in vivo OVA-treated and in vitro OVA <lb/>restimulated cells, both IL-4 and IL-5 cytokines were <lb/>upregulated in Plexin B1 KO cell culture supernatants whereas <lb/>substantial levels of IFNg and IL-10 were detected in WT cell <lb/>cultures (Figure 9C). The low level of IL-10 in Plexin B1 KO cell <lb/>cultures correlates with low Treg cell numbers (Figures 3B, D, 9C, <lb/>correspondingly). The levels of IL-13 were below (0.64 pg/ml) the <lb/>assay limits of detection in all samples. Therefore, lymphocytes <lb/>from Plexin B1 KO mice are already Th2-prone and express <lb/>significant, detectable levels of IL-4 in cultures. Moreover, <lb/>immune cells from Ag-primed Plexin B1 KO mice displayed an <lb/>enhanced Th2 response (IL-4 and IL-5) to in vitro <lb/>Ag restimulation. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We previously showed that Sema4A limited allergic <lb/>inflammatory responses in part by stabilizing Treg numbers in <lb/>mice (23). However, Sema4A can utilized at least 3 different <lb/>counter receptors to transmit signals (10), and thus the counter <lb/>receptor critical for mediating allergic control has remained <lb/>unknown. Recently, we reported that Plexin B1 is a critical <lb/>regulator of human Treg cell stability and function (8). In this <lb/>study we evaluated whether Plexin B1 acts as an important <lb/>regulator of mouse Treg cell number and allergic inflammatory <lb/>responses by developing and analyzing responses in novel Plexin <lb/>B1 KO mice. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Plexin B1 deficiency has no effect on total and antigen-specific IgE/IgG1 levels. WT and Plexin B1 KO mice were primed and challenged with OVA <lb/>and sera was collected at various times as described in Materials and Methods (A). (B) Total serum IgE and OVA-specific (C) IgE and (D) IgG1 were <lb/>measured by ELISA. Data represent one experiment for each assay with sera collected from n=3 mice/group (IgE) and n=6 mice/group (IgG1). <lb/>*p=0.0006, PBS treated WT vs Plexin B1 KO mice, day 32 of experimental protocol, non-parametric unpaired Mann-Whitney test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>10 <lb/></page>

		<body>Several other groups previously generated Plexin B1 KO mice, <lb/>however they were not used to study the immune response or in <lb/>models of immune mediated diseases such as asthma. One line was <lb/>generated by inserting a targeting construct into exons 22 and 23 <lb/>encoding the transmembrane domain of the PlexinB1 gene (42) <lb/>while another used loxp-mediated deletion of exons 13-16 (43). Our <lb/>novel Plexin B1 KO mice were generated by Crispr/cas9-mediated <lb/>deletion of exons 4-16 (Supplementary Figure S1). In all cases, <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice were found to be viable and fertile without any <lb/>major developmental defects, somewhat surprising considering the <lb/>extensive expression of Plexin B1 in different tissues during <lb/>ontogenesis including the brain and kidney. Plexin B1 was shown <lb/>to play a redundant role during mouse neuronal development and <lb/>in tumour angiogenesis (42, 43) likely due to functional overlap <lb/>with other Plexin family members. Plexin B1 was found to play a <lb/>role in epithelial branching morphogenesis during kidney <lb/>organogenesis in one line (26, 43). Korostylev et al. reported that <lb/>the global Plexin B1 deficiency led to an increase in kidney size as <lb/>well as ureteric branches at the E13.5 embryonic stage of <lb/>development likely due to Semaphorin 4D-Plexin B1 interactions <lb/>(26). Consistent with a role for Plexin B1 in kidney morphogenesis, <lb/>we observed an increase in kidney size in 11-13 week old male <lb/>Plexin B1 KO mice (Supplementary Figure S1B). In all 3 Plexin B1 <lb/>mouse lines, histological examination of lung tissues revealed <lb/>normal morphology of lung epithelium and normal septation of <lb/>the airways with properly inflated alveoli. <lb/>When analyzing responses of these mice to allergens, we observed <lb/>that the constitutive absence of Plexin B1 led to an upregulation of <lb/>HDM-induced lung tissue inflammation, mucous cell hyperplasia, <lb/>and local IL-4 and IL-6 production (Figure 1). Plexin B1-deficiency in <lb/>mice also led to an upregulation of these and additional features of <lb/>allergic inflammation in the OVA/Alum model including <lb/>eosinophilia, mucus score and mucous cell hyperplasia, and lung <lb/>local Th2 cytokine production. Furthermore, there was less IL-10 in <lb/>BALF of OVA-primed Plexin B1 KO mice consistent with lower <lb/>numbers of lung Tregs (Figures 2, 4). These results are similar to <lb/>those observed in Sema4A-deficient mice (23) and thus suggest that <lb/>Plexin B1may act as an important Sema4A counter receptor for at <lb/>least some aspects of allergic inflammation. <lb/>We found dysregulation of mucin expression in the lungs of <lb/>allergen-treated Plexin B1 KO lungs as compared WT mice; this <lb/>was especially evident when analyzing the degree of airway goblet <lb/>cell metaplasia by density of PAS+ cells per airway (Figures 1, 2). <lb/>Elevated mucus production is a hallmark of asthma and mucus <lb/>plugging of the airways is considered a major cause of death in <lb/>people with asthma (40, 41). Two mucins, MUC5AC and MUC5B, <lb/>were reported to be the most involved in asthma pathogenesis (44). <lb/>However, whereas MUC5B is the predominant mucin produced in <lb/>normal airways in response to external stimuli and does not <lb/>accumulate pathologically in the airways, MUC5AC production is <lb/>highly upregulated in response to Th2 cytokines and has a tendency <lb/>to accumulate and even plug the airways. Murine MUC5B is critical <lb/>for mucociliary clearance and airway defense. Muc5b-deficient mice <lb/>do not clear the aspirated materials from the airways, develop <lb/>chronic bacterial infections, severe inflammation, and airway <lb/>obstruction. In contrast, MUC5AC-deficient mice have normal <lb/>mucociliary transport and anti-bacterial defense, but do not <lb/>develop AHR to allergen challenge (45). Moreover, an inhibition <lb/>of MUC5AC leads to upregulation of MUC2 and MUC5B <lb/>expression (44). In our current study, we found increased <lb/>amounts of MUC5AC secretion in the airways of Plexin B1 KO <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>Plexin B1 regulates mucin expression in lungs. BALF was evaluated <lb/>for MUC5AC by ELISA, n=7 mice/group (A). (B) Lung RNA was <lb/>isolated from the indicated mice and evaluated for mucin gene <lb/>expression by qRT-PCR as described in Materials and Methods <lb/>(n=4-8/group). Data shown as mean ± SEM (A, B) with data statistics <lb/>calculated using two-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple <lb/>comparison test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<body>mice detected in BALF by ELISA (Figure 6A) whereas Muc5B <lb/>expression was downregulated after allergen exposure in both <lb/>mouse lines but also in PBS-treated KO lungs (Figure 6B). In <lb/>addition, Muc1 transcript levels were upregulated in PBS-treated <lb/>Plexin B1 KO lungs as compared to WT mice (Figure 6B). MUC1 <lb/>has been reported to play a protective role in allergic asthma as it <lb/>modulated corticoid resistance in severe asthma, MUC1 levels were <lb/>downregulated in patients with severe asthma, were inversely <lb/>correlated with daily doses of inhaled steroids, and MUC1 -/-mice <lb/>were resistant to the anti-inflammatory dexamethasone treatment <lb/>in OVA model of disease (46). Taken together, the results from the <lb/>PAS staining and analysis, the Muc5AC ELISA in BALF, and the <lb/>qRT-PCR for the mucin protein core genes in the lung demonstrate <lb/>a Plexin B1-dependent mucin dysregulation in mouse lungs. <lb/>Interestingly, we did not detect any differences in the antibody <lb/>responses between OVA-treated WT and Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>(Figures 5B-D) despite significant differences in allergen-induced <lb/>lung inflammatory responses (Figure 2). This result could possibly <lb/>be explained by the differential requirements for Th2 effectors and T <lb/>follicular helper (Tfh) cells important for B cell activation, isotype <lb/>switching, and resulting allergen-specific Ab secretion [reviewed in <lb/>(47, 48)]. The report by Kobayashi and associated (49) has shown <lb/>that natural exposure to allergen induces Th2 and Tfh cells. A <lb/>conditional deficiency of Bcl6 in CD4+ T cells resulted in a marked <lb/>decrease of Tfh cell numbers and, as a result, a substantial decrease <lb/>in anti-allergen IgE antibody levels. However, the Th2 cytokine <lb/>responses and eosinophilic inflammation in the airways were <lb/>unaffected by Bcl6 deficiency. Based on these studies, we predict <lb/>that Plexin B1 may not contribute to Tfh, and that the Sema4A-<lb/>dependent control of allergen induced antibody responses we <lb/>reported previously may be mediated by one of its other counter <lb/>receptors (10, 23). <lb/>While studying lymphocyte responses, we obtained evidence for <lb/>enhanced T-cell activation in Plexin B1 KO mice in vitro and in vivo <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 7 <lb/>Plexin B1 regulates in vitro T cell responses. Spleens were harvested from naïve WT and Plexin B1 KO mice and from OVA-primed counterparts on <lb/>day 5. (A) The total number of isolated mononuclear cells was evaluated. (B) Spleen cells were cultured with or without LPS, OVA, and OVA peptide <lb/>stimulation and evaluated by the WST-1 colorimetric assay. *p=0.005, #p=0.031, **p=0.0001, WT vs KO. (C) Spleens were harvested mice treated <lb/>with PBS or OVA as described in Figure 2 on day 19 (five days after completion of treatment). WST-1 assay was used for colorimetric detection of <lb/>the formazan dye produced by living cells. *p=0.0017, **p,0.0001, WT vs KO. (D) Spleen cells from naïve mice were cultured for 36h and analyzed <lb/>by flow cytometry for CD69 or Ki-67 activation marker expression using gating strategy shown in Supplementary Figure S6. Data for triplicate <lb/>cultures (mean ± SEM) in three in vitro experiments are shown (n=3). Data statistics was calculated using two-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple <lb/>comparison test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>12 <lb/></page>

		<body>(Figure 7). There were increased numbers of metabolically active <lb/>Plexin B1 KO cells cultured in vitro at baseline compared to WT, <lb/>and there were greater numbers of CD4+Ki-67+ and CD4+CD69+ <lb/>cells in vitro even in cells without any previous antigen priming <lb/>(Figure 7 D). It is interesting to note that we obtained similar total <lb/>numbers of spleen cells from naïve WT and KO mice despite the <lb/>enhanced in vitro responses of KO mice, suggesting the presence of <lb/>other mechanisms in vivo that regulate lymphocyte homeostasis. <lb/>We also observed enhanced responses in allergen-treated mice. <lb/>There were greater numbers of CD4+BrDU+ cells in vivo after <lb/>immunization of Plexin B1 KO mice with adjuvant alone (Alum) or <lb/>OVA/Alum as compared to WT (Figure 8). In addition, there were <lb/>increased numbers of CD4+CD25+ T-cells (Foxp3-) in the lungs of <lb/>immunized and challenged Plexin B1 KO mice compared to WT <lb/>(Figure 4A). We also found upregulation of Th2 cytokines in BALF <lb/>from these mice whereas the levels of IL-33 and CCL5 (RANTES) <lb/>were not affected by Plexin B1 deficiency. Furthermore, there was <lb/>an upregulation of Th2 cytokines in Plexin B1 KO spleen MNC <lb/>cultures especially IL-4 and IL-6 in naïve and PBS-primed cells, and <lb/>IL-4 and IL-5 in OVA-primed cells whereas IL-10 was greatly <lb/>downregulated and IFNg undetected as compared to similarly <lb/>exposed WT cells (Figures 9A-C). <lb/>These enhanced parameters of T-cell activation were <lb/>accompanied by a decrease of Treg cell numbers in lymphoid <lb/>tissues (Figure 3) and lungs (Figure 4) in Plexin B1 KO mice <lb/>compared to WT, which we believe explains in part the upregulated <lb/>inflammatory lung response to allergen. We observed lower <lb/>numbers of Treg cells in the periphery of mice lacking Plexin B1 <lb/>consistent with the ability of Sema4A to stabilize human Tregs <lb/>through Plexin B1 in vitro (8). Our data indicate that Plexin B1 is <lb/>critically involved in allergic asthma and plays a suppressor role in <lb/>this disease in part by promoting and stabilizing Treg cells. <lb/>However, the mechanism by which Plexin B1 may stabilize Tregs <lb/>in the mouse is unclear. <lb/>We reported previously that human peripheral CD4+ T cells <lb/>express Plexin B1 on the cell surface (8). In this study, we observed <lb/>that naïve mouse CD4+ T-cells express little to no detectable surface <lb/>Plexin B1 while naïve CD8+ cells express low levels at baseline <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S5) consistent with a previous report (39). <lb/>However, CD4+ T cells and Treg cells in the lung tissues of OVA-<lb/>treated mice demonstrated low Plexin B1 expression (Figure 4C). In <lb/>addition, the in vitro polyclonal stimulation of T cells led to <lb/>significant upregulation of Plexin B1 expression levels on both, <lb/>CD4+ and CD8+ cells (Supplementary Figure S5B) suggesting the <lb/>Plexin B1 expression is induced during activation. A recent study by <lb/>Naito et al. (39) also demonstrated low levels of Plexin B1 <lb/>expression on tumor-infiltrating CD4+ and CD8+ T cells. They <lb/>showed that the tumor cell-derived Sema4A engagement of Plexin <lb/>B1 on CD8+ T cells increased the effector function of CD8+ T cells <lb/>and improved the anti-tumor efficacy of PD-1 blocking Ab. Thus, it <lb/>is possible the mechanism by which global Plexin B1 deficiency <lb/>modulates T-cell responses and Treg numbers is via a direct T-cell <lb/>intrinsic pathway. <lb/>It is also possible that the effect of Plexin B1 deficiency on Treg <lb/>numbers is through an alternate, indirect mechanism. Previous <lb/>reports showed the importance of local IL-33 levels for tissue-<lb/>resident Treg cells to migrate and expand (50-53). We did not find <lb/>any difference in BALF IL-33 levels between PBS-or allergen-treated <lb/>WT and Plexin B1 KO mice (data not shown) whereas Treg cell <lb/>numbers differ significantly (Figure 4). However, IL-33 is known as <lb/>an important mediator of Th2 immune response by enhancing the <lb/>function of OX-40L (54). Bronchial epithelial cells also express low <lb/>levels of Plexin B1 at baseline and strongly upregulate its expression <lb/>with OVA exposure (29), suggesting that epithelial cell Plexin B1 may <lb/>regulate epithelial cell responses including goblet cell hyperplasia and <lb/>cytokine production. Furthermore, using a flow cytometry approach <lb/>we found Plexin B1 expression on mouse lung DC (29) whereas other <lb/>reports showed its expression on human follicular DC and in vitro <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 8 <lb/>Plexin B1 modulates the in vivo CD4+ T cell activation and <lb/>proliferation. Mice were injected i.p. with either PBS/Alum or OVA/ <lb/>Alum and BrdU as described in Materials and Methods section. <lb/>Spleens were harvested from mice 24h after last BrdU injection. <lb/>Spleen MNC were stained with the indicated Abs to cell surface <lb/>markers and for interchromatin BrdU and analyzed by flow <lb/>cytometry. The gating strategy used is detailed in Supplementary <lb/>Figure S7. (A) The panel shows percentage of CD4+BrdU+ cells in <lb/>spleens of OVA-treated WT vs Plexin B1 KO mice. (B) The <lb/>histograms show BrdU expression levels in Plexin B1KO mice (dark <lb/>grey) vs WT (light grey) mice. Data statistics from two experiments <lb/>(n=4) was calculated using two-tailed Mann-Whitney&apos;s non-<lb/>parametric test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>13 <lb/></page>

		<body>activated T cells (55, 56). Therefore, future studies will be needed to <lb/>clarify the precise mechanisms by which Plexin B1 modulates specific <lb/>allergic responses in sufficient detail to establish it as an <lb/>essential immunomodulator. <lb/></body>

		<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be <lb/>made available by the authors, without undue reservation. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The animal study was approved by University of Maryland <lb/>School of Medicine Animal Care and Use Committee. The study <lb/>was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and <lb/>institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

		<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>SC: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Writing -original draft, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. HG: Formal analysis, Investigation, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. RF: Formal analysis, Investigation, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. AK: Conceptualization, Data curation, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Project administration, Resources, <lb/>Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

		<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work <lb/>was supported by the NIH/NIAID grant R01AI122631 (AK), the <lb/>Merit Review Award Number I01 BX001850 from the US <lb/>Department of Veterans Affairs Biomedical R&amp;D Service (AK), <lb/>and the Cancer Center Support Grant P30CA134274. <lb/></div>

		<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors are thankful to Marc Fink for designing and <lb/>ordering primers for qPCR and Xiulan Qi for ordering reagents <lb/>and consumables related to this project. The authors thank the <lb/></div>

		<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 9 <lb/>Cytokine levels in spleen MNC cultures. Spleens were harvested from naïve (A), PBS-(B) or OVA-injected (C) mice five days after last injection. <lb/>Spleen MNC were cultured in cRPMI in 96-well plate in triplicates for 36h with or without OVA. ConA and LPS stimulations of cells served as positive <lb/>controls. The amounts of cytokines in cell culture supernatants were measured using Searchlight Proteome Array. Shown are the levels of Th1/Th2 <lb/>cytokines in different experimental settings which showed the statistically significant differences between WT and KO cells. The levels of IL-13 were <lb/>below the limit of detection. Data statistics was calculated using two-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>14 <lb/></page>

		<div type="annex">Shared Services of the University of Maryland Cancer Center for <lb/>histopathology and cytokine analyses. <lb/></div>

		<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>All authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board <lb/>member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no <lb/>impact on the peer review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, <lb/>or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product <lb/>that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

		<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Gans MD, Gavrilova T. Understanding the immunology of asthma: <lb/>Pathophysiology, biomarkers, and treatments for asthma endotypes. Paediatr Respir <lb/>Rev (2020) 36:118-27. doi: 10.1016/j.prrv.2019.08.002 <lb/>2. Kaur R, Chupp G. Phenotypes and endotypes of adult asthma: Moving toward <lb/>precision medicine. J Allergy Clin Immunol (2019) 144(1):1-12. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jaci.2019.05.031 <lb/>3. Khan MA. Regulatory T cells mediated immunomodulation during asthma: a <lb/>therapeutic standpoint. J Transl Med (2020) 18(1):456. doi: 10.1186/s12967-020-02632-1 <lb/>4. Zhang J, Zou Y, Chen L, Xu Q, Wang Y, Xie M, et al. Regulatory T cells, a viable <lb/>target against airway allergic inflammatory responses in asthma. Front Immunol (2022) <lb/>13:902318. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.902318 <lb/>5. Palomares O, Yaman G, Azkur AK, Akkoc T, Akdis M, Akdis CA. Role of Treg in <lb/>immune regulation of allergic diseases. Eur J Immunol (2010) 40(5):1232-40. <lb/>doi: 10.1002/eji.200940045 <lb/>6. Chantveerawong T, Sangkangjanavanich S, Chiewchalermsri C, Pradubpongsa P, <lb/>Mitthamsiri W, Jindarat S, et al. Increased circulating CRTH2+ Tregs are associated <lb/>with asthma control and exacerbation. Allergy. (2022) 77(2):681-5. doi: 10.1111/ <lb/>all.15145 <lb/>7. Chapoval SP, Lee M, Lemmer A, Ajayi O, Qi X, Neuwald AF, et al. Identifying <lb/>function determining residues in neuroimmune semaphorin 4A. Int J Mol Sci (2022) 23 <lb/>(6):3024. doi: 10.3390/ijms23063024 <lb/>8. Chapoval SP, Hritzo M, Qi X, Tamagnone L, Golding A, Keegan AD. Semaphorin <lb/>4A stabilizes human regulatory T cell phenotype via plexin B1. Immunohorizons. <lb/>(2019) 3(2):71-87. doi: 10.4049/immunohorizons.1800026 <lb/>9. Dasgupta P, Chapoval SP, Smith EP, Keegan AD. Transfer of in vivo primed <lb/>transgenic T cells supports allergic lung inflammation and FIZZ1 and Ym1 production <lb/>in an IL-4Ra and STAT6 dependent manner. BMC Immunol (2011) 12:60. <lb/>doi: 10.1186/1471-2172-12-60 <lb/>10. Nkyimbeng-Takwi E, Chapoval SP. Biology and function of neuroimmune <lb/>semaphorins 4A and 4D. Immunol Res (2011) 50(1):10-21. doi: 10.1007/s12026-010-<lb/>8201-y <lb/>11. Soong J, Scott G. Plexin B1 inhibits MET through direct association and <lb/>regulates Shp2 expression in melanocytes. J Cell Sci (2013) 126(Pt 2):688-95. <lb/>doi: 10.1242/jcs.119487 <lb/>12. Wang L, Song G, Zheng Y, Tan W, Pan J, Zhao Y, et al. Expression of <lb/>Semaphorin 4A and its potential role in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Res Ther <lb/>(2015) 17(1):227. doi: 10.1186/s13075-015-0734-y <lb/>13. Franzolin G, Tamagnone L. Semaphorin signaling in cancer-associated <lb/>inflammation. Int J Mol Sci (2019) 20(2):377. doi: 10.3390/ijms20020377 <lb/>14. Park HJ, Kim Y, Kim MK, Kim HJ, Bae SK, Bae MK. Inhibition of the <lb/>Semaphorin 4D-Plexin-B1 axis prevents calcification in vascular smooth muscle <lb/>cells. BMB Rep (2023) 56(2):160-5. doi: 10.5483/BMBRep.2022-0165 <lb/>15. Lontos K, Adamik J, Tsagianni A, Galson DL, Chirgwin JM, Suvannasankha A. <lb/>The role of semaphorin 4D in bone remodeling and cancer metastasis. Front Endocrinol <lb/>(Lausanne). (2018) 9:322. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2018.00322 <lb/>16. Williamson M, de Winter P, Masters JR. Plexin-B1 signalling promotes <lb/>androgen receptor translocation to the nucleus. Oncogene. (2016) 35(8):1066-72. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/onc.2015.160 <lb/>17. Zhang Z, Lu L, Ye T, Yu S, Zhang J, Zhang M, et al. Inhibition of Semaphorin <lb/>4D/Plexin-B1 signaling inhibits the subchondral bone loss in early-stage osteoarthritis <lb/>of the temporomandibular joint. Arch Oral Biol (2022) 135:105365. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.archoralbio.2022.105365 <lb/>18. Okuno T, Nakatsuji Y, Moriya M, Takamatsu H, Nojima S, Takegahara N, et al. <lb/>Roles of Sema4D-plexin-B1 interactions in the central nervous system for pathogenesis <lb/>of experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. J Immunol (2010) 184(3):1499-506. <lb/>doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.0903302 <lb/>19. Sierra JR, Corso S, Caione L, Cepero V, Conrotto P, Cignetti A, et al. Tumor <lb/>angiogenesis and progression are enhanced by Sema4D produced by tumor-associated <lb/>macrophages. J Exp Med (2008) 205(7):1673-85. doi: 10.1084/jem.20072602 <lb/>20. Yukawa K, Tanaka T, Yoshida K, Takeuchi N, Ito T, Takamatsu H, et al. Sema4A <lb/>induces cell morphological changes through B-type plexin-mediated signaling. Int J <lb/>Mol Med (2010) 25(2):225-30. <lb/>21. Ito D, Kumanogoh A. The role of Sema4A in angiogenesis, immune responses, <lb/>carcinogenesis, and retinal systems. Cell Adh Migr. (2016) 10(6):692-9. doi: 10.1080/ <lb/>19336918.2016.1215785 <lb/>22. Morihana T, Goya S, Mizui M, Yasui T, Prasad DV, Kumanogoh A, et al. An <lb/>inhibitory role for Sema4A in antigen-specific allergic asthma. J Clin Immunol (2013) <lb/>33(1):200-9. doi: 10.1007/s10875-012-9798-5 <lb/>23. Nkyimbeng-Takwi EH, Shanks K, Smith E, Iyer A, Lipsky MM, Detolla LJ, et al. <lb/>Neuroimmune semaphorin 4A downregulates the severity of allergic response. Mucosal <lb/>Immunol (2012) 5(4):409-19. doi: 10.1038/mi.2012.18 <lb/>24. Shanks K, Nkyimbeng-Takwi EH, Smith E, Lipsky MM, DeTolla LJ, Scott DW, <lb/>et al. Neuroimmune semaphorin 4D is necessary for optimal lung allergic <lb/>inflammation. Mol Immunol (2013) 56(4):480-7. doi: 10.1016/j.molimm.2013.05.228 <lb/>25. Chapoval SP, Al-Garawi A, Lora JM, Strickland I, Ma B, Lee PJ, et al. Inhibition <lb/>of NF-kappaB activation reduces the tissue effects of transgenic IL-13. J Immunol <lb/>(2007) 179(10):7030-41. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.179.10.7030 <lb/>26. Korostylev A, Worzfeld T, Deng S, Friedel RH, Swiercz JM, Vodrazka P, et al. A <lb/>functional role for semaphorin 4D/plexin B1 interactions in epithelial branching <lb/>morphogenesis during organogenesis. Development. (2008) 135(20):3333-43. <lb/>doi: 10.1242/dev.019760 <lb/>27. Fink MY, Qi X, Shirey KA, Fanaroff R, Chapoval S, Viscardi RM, et al. Mice <lb/>expressing cosegregating single nucleotide polymorphisms (D298G and N397I) in <lb/>TLR4 have enhanced responses to house dust mite allergen. J Immunol (2022) 208 <lb/>(9):2085-97. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.2100926 <lb/>28. Chapoval SP, Nabozny GH, Marietta EV, Raymond EL, Krco CJ, Andrews AG, <lb/>et al. Short ragweed allergen induces eosinophilic lung disease in HLA-DQ transgenic <lb/>mice. J Clin Invest. (1999) 103(12):1707-17. doi: 10.1172/JCI6175 <lb/>29. Smith EP, Shanks K, Lipsky MM, DeTolla LJ, Keegan AD, Chapoval SP. <lb/>Expression of neuroimmune semaphorins 4A and 4D and their receptors in the lung <lb/>is enhanced by allergen and vascular endothelial growth factor. BMC Immunol (2011) <lb/>12:30. doi: 10.1186/1471-2172-12-30 <lb/>30. Mogie G, Shanks K, Nkyimbeng-Takwi EH, Smith E, Davila E, Lipsky MM, et al. <lb/>Neuroimmune semaphorin 4A as a drug and drug target for asthma. Int <lb/>Immunopharmacol. (2013) 17(3):568-75. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2013.08.005 <lb/>31. Manevski M, Devadoss D, Long C, Singh SP, Nasser MW, Borchert GM, et al. <lb/>Increased expression of LASI lncRNA regulates the cigarette smoke and COPD <lb/>associated airway inflammation and mucous cell hyperplasia. Front Immunol (2022) <lb/>13:803362. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.803362 <lb/>32. Chapoval SP, Lee CG, Tang C, Keegan AD, Cohn L, Bottomly K, et al. Lung <lb/>vascular endothelial growth factor expression induces local myeloid dendritic cell <lb/>activation. Clin Immunol (2009) 132(3):371-84. doi: 10.1016/j.clim.2009.05.016 <lb/>33. Chapoval SP, Dasgupta P, Smith EP, DeTolla LJ, Lipsky MM, Kelly-Welch AE, <lb/>et al. STAT6 expression in multiple cell types mediates the cooperative development of <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>15 <lb/></page>

		<listBibl>allergic airway disease. J Immunol (2011) 186(4):2571-83. doi: 10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.1002567 <lb/>34. Pagano F, Picchio V, Bordin A, Cavarretta E, Nocella C, Cozzolino C, et al. <lb/>Progressive stages of dysmetabolism are associated with impaired biological features of <lb/>human cardiac stromal cells mediated by the oxidative state and autophagy. J Pathol <lb/>(2022) 258(2):136-48. doi: 10.1002/path.5985 <lb/>35. Regev A, Goldman S, Shalev E. Expression of plexin-B1 in the mouse ovary and <lb/>its possible role in follicular development. Fertil Steril. (2005) 84 Suppl 2:1210-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2005.05.011 <lb/>36. Wang J, Homer RJ, Hong L, Cohn L, Lee CG, Jung S, et al. IL-11 selectively <lb/>inhibits aeroallergen-induced pulmonary eosinophilia and Th2 cytokine production. J <lb/>Immunol (2000) 165(4):2222-31. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.165.4.2222 <lb/>37. Van der Sluis M, De Koning BA, De Bruijn AC, Velcich A, Meijerink JP, Van <lb/>Goudoever JB, et al. Muc2-deficient mice spontaneously develop colitis, indicating that <lb/>MUC2 is critical for colonic protection. Gastroenterology. (2006) 131(1):117-29. <lb/>doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2006.04.020 <lb/>38. Song Y, Wang W, Xie Y, Xiang B, Huang X, Guan W, et al. Carbocisteine inhibits <lb/>the expression of Muc5b in COPD mouse model. Drug Des Devel Ther (2019) 13:3259-<lb/>68. doi: 10.2147/DDDT.S198874 <lb/>39. Naito Y, Koyama S, Masuhiro K, Hirai T, Uenami T, Inoue T, et al. Tumor-<lb/>derived semaphorin 4A improves PD-1-blocking antibody efficacy by enhancing CD8 + <lb/>T cell cytotoxicity and proliferation. Sci Adv (2023) 9(20):eade0718. doi: 10.1126/ <lb/>sciadv.ade0718 <lb/>40. Saco TV, Breitzig MT, Lockey RF, Kolliputi N. Epigenetics of mucus <lb/>hypersecretion in chronic respiratory diseases. Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol (2018) 58 <lb/>(3):299-309. doi: 10.1165/rcmb.2017-0072TR <lb/>41. Evans CM, Kim K, Tuvim MJ, Dickey BF. Mucus hypersecretion in asthma: <lb/>causes and effects. Curr Opin Pulm Med (2009) 15(1):4-11. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>MCP.0b013e32831da8d3 <lb/>42. Fazzari P, Penachioni J, Gianola S, Rossi F, Eickholt BJ, Maina F, et al. Plexin-B1 <lb/>plays a redundant role during mouse development and in tumour angiogenesis. BMC <lb/>Dev Biol (2007) 7:55. doi: 10.1186/1471-213X-7-55 <lb/>43. Deng S, Hirschberg A, Worzfeld T, Penachioni JY, Korostylev A, Swiercz JM, <lb/>et al. Plexin-B2, but not Plexin-B1, critically modulates neuronal migration and <lb/>patterning of the developing nervous system in vivo. J Neurosci (2007) 27(23):6333-<lb/>47. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5381-06.2007 <lb/>44. Bonser LR, Erle DJ. Airway mucus and asthma: the role of MUC5AC and <lb/>MUC5B. J Clin Med (2017) 6(12):112. doi: 10.3390/jcm6120112 <lb/>45. Evans CM, Raclawska DS, Ttofali F, Liptzin DR, Fletcher AA, Harper DN, et al. <lb/>The polymeric mucin Muc5ac is required for allergic airway hyperreactivity. Nat <lb/>Commun (2015) 6:6281. doi: 10.1038/ncomms7281 <lb/>46. Milara J, Morell A, de Diego A, Artigues E, Morcillo E, Cortijo J. Mucin 1 <lb/>deficiency mediates corticosteroid insensitivity in asthma. Allergy. (2019) 74:111-21. <lb/>doi: 10.1111/all.13546 <lb/>47. Mintz MA, Cyster JG. T follicular helper cells in germinal center B cell selection <lb/>and lymphomagenesis. Immunol Rev (2020) 296(1):48-61. doi: 10.1111/imr.12860 <lb/>48. Yu D, Walker LSK, Liu Z, Linterman MA, Li Z. Targeting TFH cells in human <lb/>diseases and vaccination: rationale and practice. Nat Immunol (2022) 23(8):1157-68. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/s41590-022-01253-8 <lb/>49. Kobayashi T, Iijima K, Dent AL, Kita H. Follicular helper T cells mediate IgE <lb/>antibody response to airborne allergens. J Allergy Clin Immunol (2017) 139(1):300-<lb/>313.e7. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2016.04.021 <lb/>50. Schiering C, Krausgruber T, Chomka A, Fröhlich A, Adelmann K, Wohlfert EA, <lb/>et al. The alarmin IL-33 promotes regulatory T-cell function in the intestine. Nature. <lb/>(2014) 513(7519):564-8. doi: 10.1038/nature13577 <lb/>51. Nascimento DC, Melo PH, Piñeros AR, Ferreira RG, Colón DF, Donate PB, <lb/>et al. IL-33 contributes to sepsis-induced long-term immunosuppression by <lb/>expanding the regulatory T cell population. Nat Commun (2017) 8:14919. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/ncomms14919 <lb/>52. Ito M, Komai K, Mise-Omata S, Iizuka-Koga M, Noguchi Y, Kondo T, et al. <lb/>Brain regulatory T cells suppress astrogliosis and potentiate neurological recovery. <lb/>Nature. (2019) 565(7738):246-50. doi: 10.1038/s41586-018-0824-5 <lb/>53. Xu L, Li W, Wang X, Zhang L, Qi Q, Dong L, et al. The IL-33-ST2-MyD88 axis <lb/>promotes regulatory T cell proliferation in the murine liver. Eur J Immunol (2018) 48 <lb/>(8):1302-7. doi: 10.1002/eji.201747402 <lb/>54. Murakami-Satsutani N, Ito T, Nakanishi T, Inagaki N, Tanaka A, Vien PTX, <lb/>et al. IL-33 promotes the induction and maintenance of th2 immune responses by <lb/>enhancing the function of OX40 ligand. Allergol Int (2014) 63(3):443-55. doi: 10.2332/ <lb/>allergolint.13-OA-0672 <lb/>55. Granziero L, Circosta P, Scielzo C, Frisaldi E, Stella S, Geuna M, et al. CD100/ <lb/>Plexin-B1 interactions sustain proliferation and survival of normal and leukemic CD5+ <lb/>B lymphocytes. Blood. (2003) 101(5):1962-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2002-05-1339 <lb/>56. Ishida I, Kumanogoh A, Suzuki K, Akahani S, Noda K, Kikutani H. Involvement <lb/>of CD100, a lymphocyte semaphorin, in the activation of the human immune system <lb/>via CD72: implications for the regulation of immune and inflammatory responses. Int <lb/>Immunol (2003) 15(8):1027-34. doi: 10.1093/intimm/dxg098 <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Chapoval et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1297354 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>16 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>