<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T16:36:02.799Z">11/20/2025 4:36:02 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T16:35:45.639664Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T16:35:45.639664Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Phytoplankton physiology and <lb/>functional traits under artificial <lb/>upwelling with varying Si:N <lb/>Joaquin Ortiz 1,2 * , Javier Arı ´stegui 2 , Silvan Urs Goldenberg 1 , <lb/>Mar Ferna ´ndez-Me ´ndez 3 , Jan Taucher 1 , Stephen D. Archer 4 , <lb/>Moritz Baumann 1 and Ulf Riebesell 1 <lb/>1 Marine Biogeochemistry, Biological Oceanography, GEOMAR Helmholtz Centre for Ocean <lb/>Research, Kiel, Germany, 2 Oceanografı ´a Biolo ´gica, Instituto de Oceanografı ´a y Cambio Global <lb/>(IOCAG), Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Spain, 3 Polar <lb/>Biological Oceanography Section, Alfred Wegener Institute Helmholtz Centre for Polar and <lb/>Marine Research, Bremerhaven, Germany, 4 Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences, East <lb/>Boothbay, ME, United States <lb/>Introduction: Artificial upwelling has been discussed as a nature-based solution <lb/>to fertilize currently unproductive areas of the ocean to enhance food web <lb/>productivity and atmospheric CO 2 sequestration. The efficacy of this approach <lb/>may be closely tied to the nutrient stoichiometry of the upwelled water, as Si-<lb/>rich upwelling should benefit the growth of diatoms, who are key players for <lb/>primary production, carbon export and food web efficiency. <lb/>Methods: With a mesocosm experiment in subtropical waters, we assessed <lb/>the physiological and functional responses of an oligotrophic phytoplankton <lb/>community to artificial upwelling under varying Si:N ratios (0.07-1.33). <lb/>Results: Deep water fertilization led to strongly enhanced primary productivity <lb/>rates and net autotrophy across Si scenarios. At the community level, Si-rich <lb/>upwelling50 temporarily increased primary production and consistently <lb/>enhanced diatom growth, producing up to 10-fold higher abundances <lb/>compared to Si-deficient upwelling. At the organism level, contrasting effects <lb/>were observed. On the one hand, silicification and size of diatom cells remained <lb/>unaffected by Si:N, which is surprising given the direct dependency of these traits <lb/>on Si. On the other hand, diatom Chlorophyll a density and carbon density were <lb/>strongly reduced and particulate matter C:N was elevated under Si-<lb/>rich upwelling. <lb/>Discussion: This suggests a reduced nutritional value for higher trophic levels <lb/>under high Si:N ratios. Despite these strong qualitative changes under high Si, <lb/>diatom cells appeared healthy and showed high photosynthetic efficiency. <lb/>Our findings reveal great physiological plasticity and adaptability in <lb/>phytoplankton under artificial upwelling, with Si-dependent trade-offs <lb/>between primary producer quantity and quality. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>primary production, net community production, phytoplankton, stoichiometry, <lb/>trophic transfer, carbon export, carbon dioxide removal, diatom <lb/>Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Michael Yu Roleda, <lb/>University of the Philippines Diliman, <lb/>Philippines <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Rita B. Domingues, <lb/>University of Algarve, Portugal <lb/>Daffne Celeste Lopez Sandoval, <lb/>King Abdullah University of Science and <lb/>Technology, Saudi Arabia <lb/>Maxim Gorbunov, <lb/>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, <lb/>United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Joaquin Ortiz <lb/>joaquin_ortiz@web.de <lb/>RECEIVED 11 October 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 06 December 2023 <lb/>PUBLISHED 04 January 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Ortiz J, Arı ´stegui J, Goldenberg SU, <lb/>Ferna ´ndez-Me ´ndez M, Taucher J, Archer SD, <lb/>Baumann M and Riebesell U (2024) <lb/>Phytoplankton physiology and functional <lb/>traits under artificial upwelling with <lb/>varying Si:N. <lb/>Front. Mar. Sci. 10:1319875. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Ortiz, Arı ´stegui, Goldenberg, <lb/>Ferna ´ndez-Me ´ndez, Taucher, Archer, Baumann <lb/>and Riebesell. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 04 January 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Natural upwelling areas such as eastern boundary upwelling <lb/>systems provide an abundant and constant supply of nutrients to <lb/>surface waters, enabling highly productive ecosystems that deliver a <lb/>large share of the worlds fishery yield (Pauly and Christensen, <lb/>1995). This high productivity is attributed to a short food web with <lb/>high trophic transfer efficiency sustained by the supply of nutrient-<lb/>rich deep water (Sommer et al., 2002). Consequently, the question <lb/>has been raised whether upwelling could be artificially induced in <lb/>oligotrophic, unproductive areas of the ocean as a nature-based <lb/>technology to sustainably increase fishery yields and enhance the <lb/>oceans&apos; carbon sequestration capacity. For the former, this depends <lb/>on the close coupling of primary production to higher trophic levels <lb/>so that loss of biomass through low trophic transfer efficiency is <lb/>maximally reduced (Henson et al., 2019). For the latter, producing <lb/>large amounts of fast sinking carbon-rich biomass is essential so <lb/>that a large portion of organic carbon reaches sequestration depths <lb/>and excess upwelled inorganic carbon is compensated for via high <lb/>C:N ratios. <lb/>In oligotrophic systems, nutrients are locked in deeper waters <lb/>due to stratification. Depending on the remineralization <lb/>stoichiometry of the sinking matter and the water mass <lb/>composition of the water column, bringing water from different <lb/>depths could lead to different nutrient concentrations and ratios. <lb/>For example, south of the Canary Islands Si:N ratios approximate <lb/>0.3-0.5 at 300m, 0.6-0.7 at 1000m and ≥1 beyond 1500m (Schlitzer, <lb/>2022). Therefore, depending on the depth of upwelled water, the <lb/>nutrient composition might differ supporting a different <lb/>phytoplankton community in the sun-lit surface. <lb/>Diatoms play a central role in artificial upwelling, since they are <lb/>major players in global primary production, strong contributors to <lb/>carbon export due to their ballasting silica frustules, and a crucial <lb/>link in short food webs of efficient trophic transfer (Treǵuer et al., <lb/>2018). As such, supporting a large community of diatoms seems <lb/>central to both objectives of artificial upwelling. Diatom <lb/>proliferation largely depends on silicic acid availability as well as <lb/>its ratio to other macronutrients such as nitrogen (N). In theory, <lb/>diatoms thrive best under absolute Si concentrations &gt;2 μM (Egge <lb/>and Aksnes, 1992), with uptake rates that follow Michaelis-Menten <lb/>kinetics and mostly reach half-saturation at &lt;2 μM (Finkel et al., <lb/>2010). The degree of silicification however, can increase with <lb/>availability up to Si concentrations far beyond those of the <lb/>current surface ocean. Under N exhaustion, increases in <lb/>particulate C:N ratios due to diatom carbon overconsumption <lb/>have been observed (Gilpin et al., 2004). <lb/>Recent studies on the effect of a single deep water pulse versus a <lb/>recurring deep water supply have demonstrated that artificial <lb/>upwelling leads to strongly increased primary production, <lb/>biomass and particulate organic carbon export as well as primary <lb/>producer communities dominated by diatoms regardless of the <lb/>upwelling mode (Baumann et al., 2021; Ortiz et al., 2022a; Ortiz <lb/>et al., 2022b). These effects scale with upwelling intensity but are <lb/>influenced differently by the mode of deep water supply. Recurring <lb/>deep water supply sustains higher autotrophic biomass and a net <lb/>autotrophic system whereas a singular pulse leads to a long-term <lb/>balanced or net heterotrophic community as well as stronger <lb/>increases in particulate matter C:N ratios. <lb/>However, the role of silicic acid in ocean biomass production is <lb/>still not clear. And information regarding the optimal nutrient <lb/>composition of upwelled water to achieve the different ecosystem <lb/>services proposed is scarce. Understanding how phytoplankton <lb/>physiology and stoichiometry change when growing under <lb/>different nutrient regimes of the upwelled water will help define <lb/>the depth of the upwelling pipes in different oceanic locations as <lb/>well. It is also needed to improve biogeochemical models applied to <lb/>artificial upwelling (Oschlies et al., 2010), which so far assume <lb/>constant phytoplankton communities, non-flexible C:N ratios and <lb/>do no account for the role of Si as a nutrient. Only then can the <lb/>potential of this approach for carbon dioxide removal and enhanced <lb/>fisheries be represented accurately. <lb/>Building on a previous experiment simulating artificial <lb/>upwelling in natural oligotrophic plankton communities in the <lb/>Canary islands (Baumann et al., 2021; Ortiz et al., 2022a; Ortiz <lb/>et al., 2022b), we set out to explore the impacts of nutrient <lb/>stoichiometry, specifically the Si:N ratio, on phytoplankton <lb/>diversity, physiology and organic matter composition under <lb/>artificial upwelling. For this, we conducted a 33-day long <lb/>mesocosm study in the subtropical oligotrophic waters of the <lb/>Canary region. Artificial upwelling was simulated through the <lb/>recurring supply of deep water with fixed inorganic macro-<lb/>nutrient concentrations and superimposed Si:N ratios ranging <lb/>from strongly limiting to abundant from a diatom growth <lb/>perspective. Community-wide and organism-level effects were <lb/>assessed via phytoplankton abundance, community composition, <lb/>metabolic rates, photosynthetic efficiency, morphology, and <lb/>nutrient utilization. High Si:N upwelling was hypothesized to <lb/>enhance not only the abundance and dominance of diatoms, but <lb/>also the presence of large and heavily silicified species supported by <lb/>excess silicic acid in addition to the abundant supply of nutrients. <lb/>Yet, the observed response was more multifaceted than expected. <lb/>We discuss underlying mechanisms that might have modulated <lb/>some of the surprising outcomes as well as the partly contrasting <lb/>implications for food web enhancement and carbon export under <lb/>artificial upwelling. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>Details on the experimental setup and the environmental <lb/>conditions during this experiment are described in Goldenberg <lb/>et al. (2022). Biogenic silica concentration (BSi) and total particulate <lb/>matter carbon and nitrogen content are covered therein but are also <lb/>used as supporting data in this manuscript. <lb/>2.1 Mesocosm setup, deep water additions <lb/>and sampling <lb/>During September and October of 2019, eight mesocosms, <lb/>consisting of large polyurethane bags with a mean volume of 8.29 <lb/>± 0.07 m 3 were deployed on the east coast of Gran Canary Island for <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<body>a total of 35 experimental days. Total mesocosm length was 4 m <lb/>including a cone-shaped sediment trap at the bottom. In regular <lb/>intervals mesocosms were cleaned from the inside and outside to <lb/>prevent wall growth. <lb/>Deep water for upwelling simulation was collected three times <lb/>by ship from ~120-160 m depth at two different locations (27°5 <lb/>2&apos;16&quot; N, 15°18&apos;48&quot; W and 28°00&apos;01&quot;N, 15°20&apos;11&quot;W). The deep <lb/>water was pumped into 1 m 3 food grade plastic containers (IBC <lb/>tanks) which were then stored in a cooled container at 7°C until use. <lb/>Every other day, starting on day six, 4% of the mesocosm water <lb/>volume was replaced by deep water in all treatments. Additionally, a <lb/>total of 36 larvae and 45 juveniles of the species Atherina presbyter <lb/>were introduced to each mesocosm on day 15. <lb/>Each mesocosm received the same amount of deep water with <lb/>the same nitrate concentration with each addition, but with a <lb/>different Si:N ratio to represent upwelling of waters of different <lb/>depths with Si concentrations ranging from excess to strong <lb/>limitation. The gradient can also be expressed through the <lb/>absolute difference between Si and N in the deep water (Si* = <lb/>[Si Conc ] -[N Conc ], Sarmiento et al., 2004) with an Si* of 0 indicating <lb/>equal amounts of Si and N. Nutrient amendments were performed <lb/>to the collected deep water right before addition to reach 30 μmol L -<lb/>1 N, and phosphate and dissolved inorganic carbon at Redfield <lb/>ratios (1.9 μmol L -1 P, 199 μmol L -1 C). Silicic acid (added as <lb/>Na 2 SiO 3 *5H 2 O) was added directly with the deep water in the <lb/>amounts required for the gradient. The upwelling treatment <lb/>(continuous addition of nutrients) was developed in accordance <lb/>with findings from a previous mesocosm study in the same region <lb/>and season, where we studied the response of the phytoplankton <lb/>community to different modes of artificial upwelling (Ortiz et al., <lb/>2022b). Recurring supply of deep water was found to better sustain <lb/>a productive and net autotrophic community. In the present study, <lb/>this upwelling mode was thus successfully applied as the backbone <lb/>on which the individual Si stoichiometry was imposed. <lb/>For water sampling, 2.3 m long plastic sampling tubes with ball <lb/>valves on both ends were vertically submerged into the mesocosm, <lb/>closed, and pulled out again, hereby sampling ~5 L of depth-<lb/>integrated mesocosm water. The tubes were then shaken gently to <lb/>mix the sample before being emptied into canisters from which each <lb/>parameter was subsampled. <lb/>2.2 Community composition: microscopy, <lb/>cytometry, and pigment analysis <lb/>Phytoplankton taxonomic composition and abundance was <lb/>assessed using light microcopy. Samples were fixed using Lugol&apos;&apos;s <lb/>and then analyzed according to (Utermöhl, 1931) on a <lb/>stereomicroscope (Zeiss Axiovert 100, Carl Zeiss, Germany). <lb/>Species bigger than 5 μm were identified and counted. Taxonomy <lb/>and abundance were used to compute the Shannon diversity index <lb/>(H) for diatoms. Size measurements were performed on 3-10 <lb/>individuals of the most abundant species and the average was <lb/>used to calculate species-specific biovolumes (Hillebrand et al., <lb/>1999; Olenina et al., 2006). If no size measurements were <lb/>available, the average value from the literature for that species <lb/>was used. <lb/>Additionally, to quantify different phytoplankton size clusters, a <lb/>Cytosense flow cytometer (CytoBuoy, Woerden, Netherlands) was <lb/>used in two different settings optimized for small and large taxa: <lb/>Settings for small taxa had a higher sensitivity (red fluorescence <lb/>trigger = 10 mV) but lower flow rate, settings for large taxa the other <lb/>way around (red fluorescence trigger = 18 mV). Sample volume was <lb/>between 0.5-2 ml for small and large settings respectively. Clusters <lb/>were identified based on fluorescence profiles, forward scatter <lb/>(FWS) and side scatter (SWS). FWS signal length was in good <lb/>accordance with size measurements of particle pictures and was <lb/>thus chosen as the measure for cell size. To note, the presented size <lb/>ranges deviate from the canonical 0.2-2 μm, 2-20 μm and &gt;20 μm <lb/>for pico-, nano-and microphytoplankton due to the size range limit <lb/>and settings of the device and should be considered an <lb/>approximation. We grouped the different populations into <lb/>clusters of approximately &lt;10 μm, 10-40 μm and &gt;40 μm in size. <lb/>The broad range of 10-40 μm was chosen because the observed <lb/>phytoplankton bloom emerged over a continuous size range, so that <lb/>populations would have been artificially split in two if the canonical <lb/>size ranges were applied as separators. Specific population plots can <lb/>be found in the Supplementary Material (Supplementary Figure 1). <lb/>Samples for photosynthetic pigment analysis were taken and <lb/>processed as described in (Ortiz et al., 2022b). Pigment-based <lb/>phytoplankton community composition was estimated using <lb/>Chemtax v.1.95 based on Higgins et al. (2011, RMS = 0.024). <lb/>2.3 Primary productivity &amp; photosynthetic <lb/>physiology characterization <lb/>Oxygen production as well as respiration rates were measured <lb/>as described in (Ortiz et al., 2022b) using the Winkler titration <lb/>method and a Dissolved Oxygen Analyzer (SIS Schwentinental, <lb/>Germany). For each treatment, four replicates of initial oxygen <lb/>concentrations, &quot;dark&quot; and &quot;light&quot; incubations were measured <lb/>respectively. All samples were incubated in an outdoor pool with <lb/>constant seawater flow and &quot;light&quot; samples exposed to ambient day <lb/>and night cycles. Light samples were randomly distributed inside <lb/>clear acrylic boxes covered with one layer of blue foil to mimic the <lb/>light spectrum of the water column inside the mesocosms (172 <lb/>Lagoon Blue foil, Lee filters, Burbank, USA). Daily light irradiance <lb/>received by the light incubations ranged from 0.2 to 2141 μmol <lb/>photons m -2 s -1 throughout the experiment as measured by light <lb/>sensor-equipped data loggers inside the incubators (HOBO UA-<lb/>002-64, Australia/New Zealand). The mean of each fourfold <lb/>measurement was used for determining the rates for community <lb/>respiration (CR, Equation 1), net community production (NCP, <lb/>Equation 2) and gross production (GP, Equation 3) as follows: <lb/>CR ½μmol L -1 h -1 = <lb/>Conc I -Conc D <lb/>h D <lb/>(1) <lb/>NCP ½μmol L -1 h -1 = <lb/>Conc L -Conc I <lb/>h L <lb/>(2) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<body>GP ½μmol L -1 h -1 = CR + NCP <lb/>(3) <lb/>Conc I /Conc D /Conc L = mean oxygen concentration of the <lb/>Initial/Dark/Light samples; h D /h L = hours of incubation of Dark/ <lb/>Light samples. Hourly rates were multiplied by 24 to yield <lb/>daily rates. <lb/>It is worth noting that peak primary productivity rates might <lb/>have been missed due to the experimental procedure: deep water <lb/>additions took place on non-sampling days, while incubations for <lb/>primary productivity measurements did not start until the following <lb/>sampling day and then ran for another day in enclosed bottles. If <lb/>nutrients were consumed too quickly the samples might have <lb/>already been somewhat nutrient limited before the start of the <lb/>24h incubations, leading to underestimated NCP. <lb/>For photosynthetic physiology characterization, samples of <lb/>approximately 15 ml were kept in the dark for a minimum of 30 <lb/>min prior to FRRf measurements, in order to relax non-<lb/>photochemical processes. Measurements were carried out using <lb/>a FastOcean FRRf linked to a FastAct module (Chelsea <lb/>Technologies Group Ltd, UK) allowing discrete fluorescence <lb/>measurements in the laboratory at in situ temperatures. For <lb/>each sample, approximately 5 ml subsamples were exposed to a <lb/>single turnover saturation program consisting of 100 x 1 ms <lb/>excitation flashlets on a 2 ms pitch, followed by 40 x 1 ms <lb/>relaxation flashlets on a 50 ms pitch. Each acquisition consisted <lb/>of 40 sequences with an interval of 150 ms between sequences. <lb/>Over the course of the experiment, excitation flashlets ranged <lb/>between 1.00 to 1.30 x 10 22 photons m -2 s -1 of blue (centred at 450 <lb/>nm) light. FastPro8 software (Chelsea Technologies) was used to <lb/>process the data using the biophysical model of (Kolber et al., <lb/>1998). The background fluorescence, attributed to the instrument <lb/>noise and fluorescent dissolved organic matter, was measured in <lb/>0.2 mm-filtered seawater on each sampling date and subtracted <lb/>from the fluorescence data using the FastPro8 software. <lb/>2.4 Estimate of diatom carbon density <lb/>Estimates of overall phytoplankton or taxon specific biomass <lb/>are typically calculated applying conversion factors to measured <lb/>Chla (Sathyendranath et al., 2009) or biovolume (Menden-Deuer <lb/>and Lessard, 2000) and are widely acknowledged to be highly <lb/>uncertain (Leblanc et al., 2012). Considering the physiological <lb/>alterations observed within the diatom community in our study, <lb/>this approach was also not helpful. Taking the fraction of Chla <lb/>attributable to diatoms through pigment ratio analysis and <lb/>converting it to carbon units using fixed diatom-specific Chla:C <lb/>conversion factors throughout the experimental period would by <lb/>default ignore any treatment induced temporal changes in actual <lb/>carbon density. The same applies when calculating biovolume from <lb/>abundances and converting it to carbon units. <lb/>To approximate diatom C, carbon biomass measurements and/ <lb/>or estimates of all organisms other than diatoms were subtracted <lb/>from the measured total particulate organic carbon (POC) <lb/>(Equation 4). Heterotroph C biomass included micro-and <lb/>mesozooplankton (S. Goldenberg, personal correspondence). <lb/>Under the assumption that non-diatom phytoplankton was not or <lb/>much less affected by Si:N all Chla attributable to non-diatoms via <lb/>pigment analysis was pooled and converted to carbon units using a <lb/>Chla:C quotient of 108.4, which represents the mean Chla:C of all <lb/>non-diatom groups, including mixotrophs, as measured by <lb/>Sathyendranath et al. (2009). Taking a mean value of different <lb/>quotients was the least speculative approach, as Chla:C ratios can <lb/>vary substantially not only between species but also between <lb/>oligotrophic and eutrophic systems and numerous other variables <lb/>(Graff et al., 2015). This non-diatom autotroph carbon biomass was <lb/>then also subtracted from POC and the resulting value subsequently <lb/>normalized to diatom abundances, yielding the estimate of diatom <lb/>carbon density per cell. The time frame (day 15-33) was chosen to <lb/>exclude the initial burst in productivity following treatment onset <lb/>and thus better capture the dynamics on the community vs <lb/>organism level once the system was in a more balanced state. <lb/>C content diatom ½pg C cell -1 = <lb/>POC -B heterotroph -B non-diatom autotroph ½pg C L -1 <lb/>abundance diatom ½cells L -1 <lb/>(4) <lb/>2.5 Internal nutrient storage <lb/>Internal nutrient storage (INS; Si, N, P) of cells was measured every <lb/>4 days following Dortch (1982) and Dortch et al. (1984). For this, 0.5-1 <lb/>L of water from the sampling tubes was filtered through 0.2 μm <lb/>polycarbonate membrane filters (47 mm, GTTP) under low vacuum <lb/>pressure (200 mbar) to collect all the cells. The filtrate was discarded. <lb/>Subsequently the Erlenmeyer flask collecting the filtrate was rinsed <lb/>twice with MilliQ water before being attached to the filter holder again <lb/>without removing the filter. 40 mL of boiling MiliQ water were poured <lb/>on the filter and left for 10 minutes for the cells to burst. The filtration <lb/>pump was turned on again and 10 mL of filtrate were collected in a <lb/>nutrient sampling tube for photometric measurement along with the <lb/>water column nutrient samples (Hansen and Koroleff, 1999). A blank <lb/>consisting of filtered boiling water using the same setup was run every <lb/>time INS samples were taken. <lb/>2.6 Suspended organic matter <lb/>For water column particulate organic matter (C, N, P) and <lb/>biogenic silica (BSi), water samples were filtered under low vacuum <lb/>pressure. Filters were analyzed as described in (Goldenberg <lb/>et al., 2022). <lb/>2.7 Data analysis <lb/>To investigate the general Si:N effect and its temporal <lb/>development, we applied a linear mixed model (restricted <lb/>maximum likelihood fit, type III test, Kenward-Roger <lb/>approximation). Si:N was employed as continuous explanatory <lb/>variable, mesocosms as random effect and the interaction of Si:N <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<body>and day (Si:N x Day) as a factor of the repeated measure design. The <lb/>factor Day contains various potential sources, such as the upwelling <lb/>of all other nutrients apart from silicate, enclosure effects and <lb/>environmental conditions, though the latter did not have a <lb/>significant impact on the experimental conditions and parameters <lb/>(Goldenberg et al., 2022). <lb/>In addition, a simple linear regression analysis was performed for <lb/>each sampling day with Si:N as explanatory variable. The slope of <lb/>each regression ± the 95% confidence interval was then plotted to <lb/>show the effect size on each day along with the temporal development. <lb/>The experiment was also divided into an initial response phase <lb/>(I, day 8-22) and a longer-term response phase (II, day 22-33) to <lb/>disentangle the more immediate effects from those that persisted <lb/>throughout the experimental period. These phases were additionally <lb/>analyzed through individual linear regression analyses of the phase-<lb/>averaged response variable. <lb/>Finally, to make the effect size of different parameters <lb/>comparable, the individual phase regression analyses were run <lb/>again with standardized response variables. Each variable was <lb/>standardized to a z-score by subtracting from it its sample mean <lb/>and then dividing it by its standard deviation. From these <lb/>transformed phase regressions, we extracted the slope and <lb/>standard error for a comparative analysis. All data analyses were <lb/>performed with R (R Core Team, 2022; Posit team, 2023). Data were <lb/>checked for deviations from normality using Q-Q plots and <lb/>homogeneity of variance with residual versus fitted plots. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Community functionality <lb/>and composition <lb/>During the initial response phase, the central ecosystem <lb/>function of primary productivity responded in the form of a <lb/>temporary positive Si:N effect on GP, photosynthetic electron <lb/>transport rate, in situ oxygen concentration and CR in the face of <lb/>equal N and P supply (Figures 1A-C; Supplementary Figure 3). The <lb/>increase in oxygen concentration was driven by a 5-fold increase in <lb/>GP. In the longer-term response however, this effect dissipated in all <lb/>three parameters despite the 20-fold difference in Si loading <lb/>between the lowest and highest treatment. In general, deep-water <lb/>upwelling succeeded in sustaining a net autotrophic community <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 1A, Goldenberg et al., 2022). <lb/>The nutrient input from artificial upwelling drove the size <lb/>distribution toward large phytoplankton (Figures 1D, E bottom). <lb/>In addition, increasing Si availability significantly favored large <lb/>phytoplankton (Figures 1D, E). This positive Si:N effect was <lb/>present throughout both experimental phases and culminated in <lb/>an 11 and 5-fold difference in abundances between the highest and <lb/>lowest Si:N in the &gt;40 μm and 10-40 μm clusters respectively (day <lb/>33). Small phytoplankton abundance, on the other hand, benefited <lb/>from Si deficiency (negative Si:N effect) in phase I, but this effect <lb/>dissipated in phase II (Figure 1F). <lb/>Overall, the transient positive Si:N effect on primary <lb/>productivity and community metabolism developed on top of the <lb/>ubiquitously elevated productivity and the persistent positive effects <lb/>on large phytoplankton abundances. This Si:N-driven surplus in <lb/>growth despite similar primary productivity rates across treatments <lb/>in the longer-term implies that phytoplankton functionality must <lb/>have been altered along the Si:N gradient. <lb/>3.2 Diatom performance <lb/>Upwelled Si:N increased diatom abundances throughout both <lb/>phases, which was mirrored by the strong positive effect on biogenic <lb/>silica (Supplementary Figure 4C). This resulted in an almost 10-fold <lb/>larger diatom community after 27 days of treatment (Figure 2A), <lb/>with diatoms quickly outnumbering other phytoplankton classes <lb/>(Figure 2B). This was contrasted by only a brief positive Si:N effect <lb/>on diatom contribution to total Chla (Figure 2C) in the initial <lb/>phase, indicating that changes within the diatom community must <lb/>have occurred. At Si:N ≤1 non-diatom phytoplankton <lb/>concentrations remained relevant during the initial phase, and <lb/>throughout both phases under Si:N 0.07 (Figure 2B). <lb/>Contrary to the initial hypothesis, neither cell size of diatoms <lb/>nor per cell silicification were enhanced under increasing Si <lb/>availability, as revealed by the absence of an Si:N effect in both <lb/>phases (Figures 3A, B). This confirms that both the dominance of <lb/>diatoms over other phytoplankton as well as the pronounced <lb/>treatment effect on concentrations of biogenic silica were <lb/>essentially driven by the increase in cell numbers and not by <lb/>morphological changes. <lb/>On a physiological level, intracellular Si storage increased with <lb/>increasing Si:N with the effect becoming stronger in phase II <lb/>(Figure 3C). Which indicates that excess silicic acid was stored <lb/>inorganically instead of being used to develop thicker frustules. This <lb/>aligns with decreasing residual silicic acid in the mesocosms as the <lb/>experiment evolved (Supplementary Figure 2, Goldenberg et al., <lb/>2022). Both points suggest that the enclosed communities were not <lb/>limited by Si. Rather, periodic N-limitation likely occurred in the <lb/>short periods between nutrient consumption and the following deep <lb/>water addition, with P becoming co-limiting from day 15 onwards <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 2). <lb/>In contrast, light harvesting capacity in terms of per cell Chla <lb/>was about 2.5-fold higher under scarce than under abundant Si <lb/>throughout both response phases (Figure 3D). This indicates that <lb/>per cell Chla content of the phytoplankton community, was <lb/>strongly reduced under high Si:N. This was not a consequence of <lb/>e.g., cellular stress or changing light conditions, since <lb/>photosynthetic efficiency increased slightly with Si:N (Figure 3E). <lb/>Electron transport rates also increased consistently at least until day <lb/>27, implying that phytoplankton (and thus diatom) physiology was <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<body>altered, but not impaired despite the wide range of Si:N <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 3). Also, while light intensity varied from <lb/>day to day, there was no progressive change over time due to the <lb/>developing phytoplankton blooms (Goldenberg et al., 2022). <lb/>Our approach to estimate changes in diatom carbon density <lb/>over time (see section 2.6) revealed that the larger diatom <lb/>communities sustained under higher Si:N upwelling contained <lb/>notably less carbon, as opposed to small communities under low <lb/>Si:N upwelling (Figure 3F). <lb/>In contrast to the positive community-wide effects, <lb/>morphological diatom properties on the individual level (size &amp; <lb/>silicification) did not scale with Si availability. Photosynthetic <lb/>efficiency was unconstrained and slightly higher with increasing <lb/>Si:N, whereas other physiological properties like per cell Chla and <lb/>carbon density persistently decreased with increasing Si:N. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>Our study demonstrates how the manipulation of Si:N ratios <lb/>shapes the response of phytoplankton exposed to nutrient-rich deep <lb/>water upwelling in contrasting ways. <lb/>On the community level, high Si:N upwelling led to higher <lb/>abundances and a diatom-dominated phytoplankton community <lb/>with higher absolute amounts of ballasting BSi and, initially, also <lb/>higher energy input to the system via primary production <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Phytoplankton community metabolism and composition under varying Si:N upwelling. Top parts of each plot show the Si:N effect size (slope ± 95% <lb/>confidence interval of the linear regression for that day (red lines)). Bottom parts show the temporal development of (A) gross production, (B) in situ <lb/>oxygen concentration, (C) community respiration and phytoplankton abundances in the (D) &gt;40 µm, (E) 10-40 µm and (F) &lt;10 µm size range <lb/>clusters. Significant effects of the mixed model across time (Si:N, Day, Si:N x Day) provided in top left corners. 0/I/II = oligotrophic baseline/short-<lb/>term/long-term response phase. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<body>(Figure 4A). High Si:N ratios also temporarily increased suspended <lb/>organic carbon concentrations and particulate matter C:N ratios, <lb/>indicating enhanced carbon sequestration. The latter remained <lb/>b e y o n d R e d fi e l d r a t i o s t h r o u g h o u t t h e e x p e r i m e n t <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 1G). <lb/>On the organism level, high Si availability did not promote the <lb/>growth of larger or more heavily armored diatoms as hypothesized <lb/>but led to strongly reduced per cell Chla and carbon density. Thus, <lb/>differences in Si:N led to a stark differentiation between a large <lb/>population size of reduced organism quality for grazers under high <lb/>Si:N versus a smaller, comparatively more palatable community <lb/>under low Si:N (Figure 4B). In the following sections, we discuss <lb/>these developments step-by-step and deliberate on the potential <lb/>implications for trophic transfer and carbon export under <lb/>artificial upwelling. <lb/>4.1 Phytoplankton physiological and <lb/>community response <lb/>The positive correlation between Si:N and the abundance of <lb/>diatoms and phytoplankton overall was among the strongest <lb/>observed community-wide effects in our study. This would <lb/>suggest that Si availability set the upper boundary for population <lb/>growth. However, small quantities of leftover Si as well as increasing <lb/>internal Si storage indicate that N was the first macronutrient to <lb/>become limiting (Supplementary Figure 2). In fact, both N and P <lb/>were consumed increasingly fast after each addition, with N <lb/>reaching detection limits within 24 hours in almost all treatments. <lb/>The ability of diatoms to modulate Si uptake and their degree of <lb/>silicification in adaptation to shifting nutrient limitations provides a <lb/>mechanistic explanation for this (Martin-Jeźequel et al., 2000; <lb/>McNair et al., 2018). The transient positive Si:N effect on primary <lb/>production likely signaled the alleviation of Si limitation after <lb/>treatment onset, and before the community adjusted its uptake <lb/>speed to the N and P supply. On a similar note, the brief Si:N-<lb/>mediated increase in electron transport rates (Supplementary <lb/>Figure 3) might also hint toward a diatom sub-population that <lb/>responded even quicker than others to the treatment onset. <lb/>The subsequent diminishing of the primary productivity <lb/>response, and the simultaneous emergence of the positive effect <lb/>on C:N ratios, on the other hand, indicate a potential shift in <lb/>growth-limiting factors still within the initial phase (Figure 1A, <lb/>Supplementary Figure 1G). We attribute this to a shift from N-to N <lb/>&amp; P co-limitation, which is corroborated by steadily increasing <lb/>concentrations of organic phosphorus from approximately day 15 <lb/>onwards (Martin et al., 2014; Goldenberg et al., 2022). It might also <lb/>explain the brief disappearance of the Si:N effect in the largest (&gt;40 <lb/>μm) phytoplankton fraction. This shift in limitations represents a <lb/>relevant difference from a physiological point of view since P is <lb/>critical for reproductive processes such as membrane synthesis and <lb/>DNA replication, whereas N is also necessary for the synthesis of <lb/>Chla and amino acids. However, both N-and P-limitation do not <lb/>affect diatom growth as quickly as Si limitation (Parslow et al., 1984; <lb/>Harrison et al., 1990). This is due to Si only being stored in soluble <lb/>pools within the cell, whereas N and P can be salvaged from the <lb/>breakdown of intracellular material if necessary. Which offers an <lb/>explanation to why the phytoplankton community was much less <lb/>dominated by diatoms under Si:N ratios &lt;0.5 in our study. Lastly, a <lb/>limiting role of micronutrients cannot be excluded, though we do <lb/>not have corresponding analyses. Particularly iron measurements <lb/>cannot be performed accurately in the mesocosms due to the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Quantitative diatom performance under varying Si:N upwelling. Top parts of each plot show the Si:N effect size (slope ± 95% confidence interval of <lb/>the linear regression for that day (red lines)). Bottom parts show the temporal development of (A) diatom abundance (B) on-diatom abundance <lb/>assessed through microscopy and (C) relative diatom contribution to total Chla assessed through pigment analysis (Chemtax). Significant effects of <lb/>the mixed model across time (Si:N, Day, Si:N x Day) provided in top left corners. 0/I/II = oligotrophic baseline/short-term/long-term response phase. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<body>presence of metal parts that can alter trace metal concentrations <lb/>which, however, also render iron limitation highly unlikely (Bach <lb/>et al., 2020; Baumann et al., 2023). <lb/>In terms of photosynthetic capacity and efficiency, it is evident <lb/>that the favorable conditions created by the nutrient-rich deep <lb/>water addition and high light availability, sustained a level of <lb/>autotrophy that did not require Chla content to scale <lb/>proportionally with abundances to grow. This is manifested in the <lb/>high degrees of photosynthetic efficiency maintained across all <lb/>treatments despite a decline in fluorescence per cell under <lb/>increasing Si:N. On the contrary, high Si availability with an <lb/>equal supply of N and P, might have further facilitated cell <lb/>division leading to higher abundances but with reduced per cell <lb/>Chla. Since N is necessary for Chla synthesis, the reduction of per <lb/>cell Chla might have been, if anything, another response to the <lb/>intermittent N-limitation in our study caused by the addition of <lb/>deep water every 2 days. It is important to note as well, that Fv/Fm <lb/>has been shown to be a poor indicator of nutrient stress (Gorbunov <lb/>and Falkowski, 2021), so that the persistently stable photosynthetic <lb/>efficiency values observed throughout the experiment might have <lb/>obscured any periods of nutrient limitation. <lb/>A mechanistic rationalization for the sustained high <lb/>photosynthetic efficiency can moreover be found on the organism <lb/>level: The subtle increase in photosynthetic efficiency observed <lb/>under increasing Si:N can be explained by the matching increase <lb/>in diatom abundance, as their frustules have been shown to enhance <lb/>light absorption efficiency (Romann et al., 2015). Inversely, this <lb/>might also explain why the magnitude of the drop in electron <lb/>transport rates during the last 6 days was larger in the low Si:N <lb/>treatments, as these had a less diatom dominated community <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 3). <lb/>Among the rather surprising findings on the organism level <lb/>were the absence of any changes in diatom cell size and per cell <lb/>silicification, as both were expected to increase along with Si:N <lb/>(Figure 4A). Nutrient inputs to an oligotrophic phytoplankton <lb/>community typically trigger a succession not only toward higher <lb/>diatom abundance, but also toward larger cell sizes and diatom <lb/>species (McAndrew et al., 2007; Fawcett and Ward, 2011). In our <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Morphological and physiological effects of varying Si:N upwelling on diatoms and phytoplankton overall. Phase-averaged values and linear <lb/>regressions of (A) diatom cell size and (B) per cell silicification of diatom cells assessed through microscopy and BSi concentration as well as (C) <lb/>intracellular inorganic Si storage and (D) Chla per cell of the large phytoplankton community by proxy of total red FL normalized to abundances in <lb/>the pooled 10-40 µm and &gt;40µm clusters (flow cytometry). (E) shows photosynthetic quantum yield (Fv/Fm) of the whole phytoplankton <lb/>community and (F) the estimate of diatom carbon density. Regression model R 2 and p-values in top left corners. 0/I/II = oligotrophic baseline/short-<lb/>term/long-term response phase. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<body>study, the shift toward larger phytoplankton and diatoms was <lb/>observed. But there were no large taxonomic changes as the <lb/>diatom community was continuously dominated by the two <lb/>chain-forming genera Leptocylindrus &amp; Pseudo-nitzschia. Both <lb/>similar in size and elongated shape, Pseudo-nitzschia was more <lb/>relevant during the short term response and only maintained <lb/>noteworthy relative abundances at Si:N &gt;1 (Goldenberg et al., <lb/>2022). The Si:N dependent increase in large phytoplankton was <lb/>thus driven by Si availability allowing higher reproduction rates of <lb/>the same genus rather than selecting toward larger species; and <lb/>highlights the plasticity and capability of these genera to get the <lb/>most out of any given Si availability scenario under artificial <lb/>upwelling. Their elongated shape and the ability to form chains <lb/>likely represented an additional advantage in terms of nutrient <lb/>uptake capability and grazer protection (Pahlow et al., 1997). <lb/>The lack of any effect on per cell silicification coupled with the <lb/>much larger diatom population under high Si:N upwelling <lb/>additionally confirms that diatoms capitalized on the available Si <lb/>via reproduction rather than investing energy in the development of <lb/>thicker frustules. This is also in line with studies showing a <lb/>reduction in duration of the cell wall synthesis phase under high <lb/>growth rates (Martin-Jeźequel et al., 2000 and references therein). <lb/>Grazing pressure can trigger thicker frustule development or select <lb/>toward more heavily armored species, but was not a dominant <lb/>driver during our study (Grønning and Kiørboe, 2020; Ryderheim <lb/>et al., 2022). This can partly be attributed to the introduction of the <lb/>fish larvae on day 15, which evenly decimated the zooplankton <lb/>community that was responding to the phytoplankton bloom across <lb/>all treatments (S. Goldenberg, pers. comm.). Consequently, we <lb/>cannot fully confirm that the reduced quality of diatoms <lb/>translated into reduced zooplankton growth. Yet there was also <lb/>no Si:N effect on per cell silicification in the timeframe between <lb/>treatment onset and fish introduction (day 6-15, Supplementary <lb/>Figure 1D). A positive effect could have been expected <lb/>independently of the grazing situation, considering that frustules <lb/>provide other benefits such as improved nutrient uptake and light <lb/>harvesting (Mitchell et al., 2013; Romann et al., 2015). An absence <lb/>of heavy armoring in the diatom community would certainly benefit <lb/>the grazer community in terms of prey palatability, at least until the <lb/>&quot;arms race&quot; of pelagic predator-prey interactions is re-established <lb/>(Smetacek, 2012). <lb/>Lastly, it is worth elaborating on the seemingly contradictory <lb/>interpretation of both increased particulate matter C:N and reduced <lb/>diatom carbon density as indicators of reduced quality. Typically, <lb/>high C:N ratios in phytoplankton are associated with reduced <lb/>nutritional value for grazers, as they point toward lower relative <lb/>protein content (Hessen, 1992). Simply put, grazers must consume <lb/>relatively more unnecessary C to gain the same amount of N (or P <lb/>for that matter). In our study, Si:N was the main driver of the <lb/>increase in particulate matter C:N ratios not only in the initial phase <lb/>(Figure 4A), given that it was still present in form of a curvilinear <lb/>relationship in phase II (Goldenberg et al., 2022). High Si:N <lb/>upwelled water consequently reduces phytoplankton quality for <lb/>grazers via high relative carbon content in the organic matter. The <lb/>estimate of carbon density on the other hand gauges the amount of <lb/>carbon per diatom biovolume. A strongly reduced carbon density <lb/>under high Si:N upwelling thus means that diatom cells in those <lb/>treatments had less overall carbon content, i.e., that they were less <lb/>densely packed or &quot;waterier&quot;. Therefore, high C:N and low per cell <lb/>carbon density both indicate that grazers receive less nutritionally <lb/>valuable components per ingested cell when grazing on <lb/>these diatoms. <lb/>4.2 Potential for food web enhancement <lb/>We demonstrated that the reduced N content relative to C as <lb/>well as waterier diatom cells that develop under constant irrigation <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Contrasting effects of Si:N on the community and organism level. (A) Standardized effect sizes during both experimental phases. Large <lb/>phytoplankton refers to abundances in the combined 10-40 &amp; &gt;40 mm cytometry clusters. Significant effects (Slope ± 95% CI does not cross 0) are <lb/>in color and significance levels are denoted (*/**/*** equals p &lt; 0.05/0.01/0.001). (B) Trade-off between diatom quantity and quality exemplified via <lb/>diatom abundance (x-axis) versus per cell Chla content of diatoms (y-axis). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<body>with high Si:N upwelled waters is counterproductive to achieve <lb/>efficient trophic transfer. This stands in contrast to the general <lb/>understanding that diatom dominated phytoplankton communities <lb/>are best to maintain higher trophic levels. Additionally, the <lb/>dominance of chain forming diatom species could further <lb/>contribute to this via reduced palatability. It is worth mentioning, <lb/>however, that our particulate matter C:N ratios included potentially <lb/>carbon rich detritus on top of all the organisms, which might lead to <lb/>an overestimation of C:N ratios of live phytoplankton cells. <lb/>Inversely, a more heterogeneous phytoplankton community <lb/>with lower C:N as observed under low Si:N upwelling would <lb/>promote herbivore growth, as these would profit from more <lb/>nutritious (albeit less numerous) diatoms and the benefits of a <lb/>more mixed diet (Schmidt and Jońasdottir, 1997). Dinoflagellates, <lb/>for example, are also less susceptible to fluctuations in nutrient <lb/>availability and could constitute a more reliable food source (Jones <lb/>et al., 2002). Additionally, a lack of Si does not seem to impact the <lb/>nutritional value of diatoms (and certainly not that of non-<lb/>silicifying phytoplankton), whereas N starvation leads to reduced <lb/>protein content and can thus negatively affect higher trophic levels <lb/>(Harrison et al., 1990). There is also evidence that even excessive <lb/>quantities of low quality food cannot support crustacean growth <lb/>rates comparable to those achieved at low but nutritious <lb/>phytoplankton densities (Sterner et al., 1993). Lastly, if high-<lb/>quality diatoms already thrive at lower-than-expected Si:N ratios, <lb/>Si:N ratios &lt;0.5 in the upwelled water might be enough for the goal <lb/>of increasing food web productivity. <lb/>The absence of an Si:N effect on per cell silicification and the <lb/>overall shift toward larger phytoplankton do speak in favor of high <lb/>Si:N upwelling, at least if a classic pelagic food web structure with <lb/>few trophic levels is maintained (Sommer et al., 2002). However, the <lb/>status of diatoms as the ideal food source for herbivores is <lb/>increasingly debated (Ianora and Miralto, 2010). Solely driving <lb/>the system toward maximum diatom abundance is therefore <lb/>unlikely to create the best conditions for efficient trophic transfer <lb/>under artificial upwelling. <lb/>4.3 Consequences for carbon <lb/>export potential <lb/>When evaluating our findings from a perspective of increasing <lb/>carbon export potential through artificial upwelling we can see <lb/>opposing effects of the Si:N ratio. Here, the same input to the system <lb/>in terms of nutrients and primary production resulted in <lb/>presumably better carbon export conditions under high Si:N <lb/>upwelling: a significantly larger diatom population and more than <lb/>20-fold higher final concentration of suspended BSi in the highest <lb/>treatment (compared to the lowest). Both factors could greatly <lb/>enhance (carbon) export fluxes via unconstrained diatom growth, <lb/>and thus particulate matter generation, and ballasting effects of <lb/>BSi, respectively. <lb/>However, while the upwelling of nutrients alone (N &amp; P) already <lb/>led to a doubling of exported particulate matter and increased the C: <lb/>N ratio of sedimented material, the Si:N treatment had <lb/>counteracting effects on the export flux (Baumann et al., 2023). <lb/>These positive (C export, C:N of exported matter) and negative <lb/>(particle size &amp; velocity) effects were only present in the initial <lb/>phase, where the dominance of diatoms was not yet fully established <lb/>in all treatments. Phytoplankton community composition might <lb/>thus have been a relevant driver of the altered particle properties <lb/>observed by the authors. The reduced diatom carbon density under <lb/>high Si:N might have ultimately also led to the disappearance of the <lb/>positive Si:N effect on carbon export in the longer term. <lb/>Lastly, carbon export fluxes also strongly depend on the <lb/>repackaging of phytoplankton and particulate organic matter <lb/>through grazers, whose role was difficult to evaluate in our study <lb/>due to a strong mismatch between both communities. In essence, <lb/>the effort of actively providing Si-rich artificial upwelling is unlikely <lb/>to produce a relevant added benefit for carbon export as compared <lb/>to lower Si:N upwelling. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>We examined the effects of artificial upwelling with different Si: <lb/>N ratios representing different source depths (~300-2000 m) of the <lb/>upwelled waters, on a natural oligotrophic phytoplankton <lb/>community in the subtropical North Atlantic. Primary <lb/>productivity, phytoplankton abundance and biomass were greatly <lb/>increased under all treatments. Increasing Si availability strongly <lb/>enhanced diatom community size at the expense of their nutritional <lb/>value and a more heterogenous phytoplankton community, thus <lb/>resulting in a quality (low Si:N) versus quantity (high Si:N) trade-<lb/>off. Our findings consequently suggest that low Si:N upwelling <lb/>might create better conditions for efficient trophic transfer via better <lb/>food quality for grazers, while high Si:N upwelling might provide <lb/>higher carbon export via overall biomass and BSi production. <lb/>Whether this might render both goals mutually exclusive under a <lb/>given nutrient signature needs to be investigated. Overall, the <lb/>diatom community showed a remarkable degree of intraspecific <lb/>plasticity that allowed it to thrive even at Si:N ratios considered <lb/>unfavorable and below their own (Brzezinski, 1985; Sarthou et al., <lb/>2005). This warrants a more mechanistic evaluation of the <lb/>conditions required for diatoms to flourish rather than adhering <lb/>to e.g., nutrient threshold values. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online <lb/>repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession <lb/>number(s) can be found below: PANGAEA: https://doi.pangaea.de/ <lb/>10.1594/PANGAEA.962782. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>JO: Formal analysis, Writing -original draft, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing. JA: Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. SUG: <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. MF: Writing -review &amp; editing. JT: <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. SA: Writing -review &amp; editing. MB: <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Writing -review &amp; editing. UR: Funding acquisition, Supervision, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This project <lb/>was conducted in the framework of the projects Ocean Artificial <lb/>Upwelling (Ocean artUp, No. 695094) funded by an Advanced Grant <lb/>of the European Research Council awarded to UR, and Test-ArtUp <lb/>funded by the German Marine Research Alliance (DAM) as part of <lb/>the CDRmare research mission (No. 03F0897B). Additional support <lb/>was provided through Transnational Access funds by the EU project <lb/>AQUACOSM, EU H2020-INFRAIA-project (No. 731065). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We would like to thank the Plataforma Oceanica de Canarias <lb/>(PLOCAN) and the Parque Cientıfco Tecnológico Marino <lb/>(PCTM) for their ongoing support with infrastructure, Acorayda <lb/>Gonzaĺez Peŕez for her technical support in the measurements of <lb/>primary productivity rates, and Madeleine Archer for the <lb/>FRRf measurements. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board <lb/>member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no <lb/>impact on the peer review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Bach, L. T., Paul, A. J., Boxhammer, T., von der Esch, E., Graco, M., Schulz, K. G., <lb/>et al. (2020). Factors controlling plankton community production, export flux, and <lb/>particulate matter stoichiometry in the coastal upwelling system off Peru. Biogeosciences <lb/>17, 4831-4852. doi: 10.5194/bg-17-4831-2020 <lb/>Baumann, M., Goldenberg, S. U., Taucher, J., Fernańdez-Meńdez, M., Ortiz, J., <lb/>Haussmann, J., et al. (2023). Counteracting effects of nutrient composition (Si:N) on <lb/>export flux under artificial upwelling. Front. Mar. Sci. 10. doi: 10.3389/ <lb/>fmars.2023.1181351 <lb/>Baumann, M., Taucher, J., Paul, A. J., Heinemann, M., Vanharanta, M., Bach, L. T., <lb/>et al. (2021). Effect of intensity and mode of artificial upwelling on particle flux and <lb/>carbon export. Front. Mar. Sci. 8. doi: 10.3389/fmars.2021.742142 <lb/>Brzezinski, M. A. (1985). The Si:C:N ratio of marine diatoms: Interspecific variability <lb/>and the effect of some environmental variables. J. Phy 21, 347-357. doi: 10.1111/j.0022-<lb/>3646.1985.00347.x <lb/>Dortch, Q. (1982). Effect of growth conditions on accumulation of internal nitrate, <lb/>ammonium, amino acids, and protein in three marine diatoms. J. Exp. Mar. Biol. Ecol. <lb/>61, 243-264. doi: 10.1016/0022-0981(82)90072-7 <lb/>Dortch, Q., Clayton, J. R., Thoresen, S. S., and Ahmed, S. I. (1984). Species differences <lb/>in accumulation of nitrogen pools in phytoplankton. Mar. Biol. 81, 237-250. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/BF00393218 <lb/>Egge, J., and Aksnes, D. (1992). Silicate as regulating nutrient in phytoplankton <lb/>competition. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 83, 281-289. doi: 10.3354/meps083281 <lb/>Fawcett, S. E., and Ward, B. B. (2011). Phytoplankton succession and nitrogen <lb/>utilization during the development of an upwelling bloom. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 428, <lb/>13-31. doi: 10.3354/meps09070 <lb/>Finkel, Z. V., Matheson, K. A., Regan, K. S., and Irwin, A. J. (2010). Genotypic and <lb/>phenotypic variation in diatom silicification under paleo-oceanographic conditions: <lb/>Diatom silicification. Geobiology 8, 433-445. doi: 10.1111/j.1472-4669.2010.00250.x <lb/>Gilpin, L. C., Davidson, K., and Roberts, E. (2004). The influence of changes in <lb/>nitrogen: silicon ratios on diatom growth dynamics. J. Sea Res. 51, 21-35. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.seares.2003.05.005 <lb/>Goldenberg, S. U., Taucher, J., Fernańdez-Meńdez, M., Ludwig, A., Arıśtegui, J., Baumann, <lb/>M., et al. (2022). Nutrient composition (Si:N) as driver of plankton communities during <lb/>artificial upwelling. Front. Mar. Sci. 9. doi: 10.3389/fmars.2022.1015188 <lb/>Gorbunov, M. Y., and Falkowski, P. G. (2021). Using chlorophyll fluorescence <lb/>kinetics to determine photosynthesis in aquatic ecosystems. Limnol. Oceanography 66, <lb/>1-13. doi: 10.1002/lno.11581 <lb/>Graff, J. R., Westberry, T. K., Milligan, A. J., Brown, M. B., Dall&apos;Olmo, G., Dongen-<lb/>Vogels, V. V., et al. (2015). Analytical phytoplankton carbon measurements spanning <lb/>diverse ecosystems. Deep Sea Res. Part I.: Oceanographic Res. Papers 102, 16-25. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.dsr.2015.04.006 <lb/>Grønning, J., and Kiørboe, T. (2020). Diatom defence: Grazer induction and cost of <lb/>shell-thickening. Funct. Ecol. 34, 1790-1801. doi: 10.1111/1365-2435.13635 <lb/>Hansen, H. P., and Koroleff, F. (1999). &quot;Determination of nutrients,&quot; in Methods of <lb/>Seawater Analysis (Weinheim, Germany: Wiley-VCH), 159-228. <lb/>Harrison, P. J., Thompson, P. A., and Calderwood, G. S. (1990). Effects of nutrient <lb/>and light limitation on the biochemical composition of phytoplankton. J. Appl. Phycol. <lb/>2, 45-56. doi: 10.1007/BF02179768 <lb/>Henson, S., Le Moigne, F., and Giering, S. (2019). Drivers of carbon export efficiency <lb/>in the global ocean. Global Biogeochem. Cycles 33, 891-903. doi: 10.1029/ <lb/>2018GB006158 <lb/>Hessen, D. O. (1992). Nutrient element limitation of zooplankton production. Am. <lb/>Nat. 140, 799-814. doi: 10.1086/285441 <lb/>Higgins, H., Wright, S., and Schluter, L. (2011). &quot;Quantitative interpretation of <lb/>chemotaxonomic pigment data,&quot; in Phytoplankton Pigments: Characterization, <lb/>Chemotaxonomy and Applications in Oceanography (Cambridge, England: <lb/>Cambridge University Press), 257-313. <lb/>Hillebrand, H., Dürselen, C.-D., Kirschtel, D., Pollingher, U., and Zohary, T. (1999). <lb/>Biovolume calculation for pelagic and benthic microalgae. J. Phycol. 35, 403-424. <lb/>doi: 10.1046/j.1529-8817.1999.3520403.x <lb/>Ianora, A., and Miralto, A. (2010). Toxigenic effects of diatoms on grazers, <lb/>phytoplankton and other microbes: a review. Ecotoxicology 19, 493-511. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s10646-009-0434-y <lb/>Jones, R., Flynn, K., and Anderson, T. (2002). Effect of food quality on carbon and <lb/>nitrogen growth efficiency in the copepod Acartia tonsa. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 235, 147-<lb/>156. doi: 10.3354/meps235147 <lb/>Kolber, Z. S., Praśǐl, O., and Falkowski, P. G. (1998). Measurements of variable <lb/>chlorophyll £uorescence using fast repetition rate techniques: defining methodology <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>and experimental protocols. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1367, 88-106. doi: 10.1016/S0005-<lb/>2728(98)00135-2 <lb/>Leblanc, K., Arıśtegui, J., Armand, L., Assmy, P., Beker, B., Bode, A., et al. (2012). A <lb/>global diatom database -abundance, biovolume and biomass in the world ocean. Earth <lb/>Syst. Sci. Data 4, 149-165. doi: 10.5194/essd-4-149-2012 <lb/>Martin, P., Dyhrman, S. T., Lomas, M. W., Poulton, N. J., and van mooy, B. A. S. (2014). <lb/>Accumulation and enhanced cycling of polyphosphate by Sargasso Sea plankton in response to <lb/>low phosphorus. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 111, 8089-8094. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1321719111 <lb/>Martin-Jeźequel, V., Hildebrand, M., and Brzezinski, M. A. (2000). Silicon <lb/>metabolism in diatoms: implications for growth. J. Phycol. 36, 821-840. doi: 10.1046/ <lb/>j.1529-8817.2000.00019.x <lb/>McAndrew, P., Björkman, K., Church, M., Morris, P., Jachowski, N., Williams, P. J., <lb/>et al. (2007). Metabolic response of oligotrophic plankton communities to deep water <lb/>nutrient enrichment. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 332, 63-75. doi: 10.3354/meps332063 <lb/>McNair, H. M., Brzezinski, M. A., and Krause, J. W. (2018). Diatom populations in <lb/>an upwelling environment decrease silica content to avoid growth limitation. Environ. <lb/>Microbiol. 20, 4184-4193. doi: 10.1111/1462-2920.14431 <lb/>Menden-Deuer, S., and Lessard, E. J. (2000). Carbon to volume relationships for <lb/>dinoflagellates, diatoms, and other protist plankton. Limnol. Oceanogr. 45, 569-579. <lb/>doi: 10.4319/lo.2000.45.3.0569 <lb/>Mitchell, J. G., Seuront, L., Doubell, M. J., Losic, D., Voelcker, N. H., Seymour, J., et al. <lb/>(2013). The role of diatom nanostructures in biasing diffusion to improve uptake in a <lb/>patchy nutrient environment. PloS One 8. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0059548 <lb/>Olenina, I., Hajdu, S., Edler, L., Andersson, A., Wasmund, N., Busch, S., et al. (2006). <lb/>Biovolumes and size-classes of phytoplankton in the Baltic Sea HELCOM Balt. Sea <lb/>Environ. Proc. 106, 144 <lb/>Ortiz, J., Arıśtegui, J., Hernańdez-Hernańdez, N., Fernańdez-Meńdez, M., and <lb/>Riebesell, U. (2022a). Oligotrophic phytoplankton community effectively adjusts to <lb/>artificial upwelling regardless of intensity, but differently among upwelling modes. <lb/>Front. Mar. Sci. 9. doi: 10.3389/fmars.2022.880550 <lb/>Ortiz, J., Arıśtegui, J., Taucher, J., and Riebesell, U. (2022b). Artificial upwelling in <lb/>singular and recurring mode: consequences for net community production and <lb/>metabolic balance. Front. Mar. Sci. 8. doi: 10.3389/fmars.2021.743105 <lb/>Oschlies, A., Pahlow, M., Yool, A., and Matear, R. J. (2010). Climate engineering by <lb/>artificial ocean upwelling: Channelling the sorcerer&apos;s apprentice: OCEAN PIPE <lb/>IMPACTS. Geophys. Res. Lett. 37. doi: 10.1029/2009GL041961 <lb/>Pahlow, M., Riebesell, U., and Wolf-Gladrow, D. A. (1997). Impact of cell shape and <lb/>chain formation on nutrient acquisition by marine diatoms. Limnol. Oceanogr. 42, <lb/>1660-1672. doi: 10.4319/lo.1997.42.8.1660 <lb/>Parslow, J. S., Harrison, P. J., and Thompson, P. A. (1984). Saturated uptake kinetics: <lb/>transient response of the marine diatom Thalassiosira pseudonana to ammonium, <lb/>nitrate, silicate or phosphate starvation. Mar. Biol. 83, 51-59. doi: 10.1007/BF00393085 <lb/>Pauly, D., and Christensen, V. (1995). Primary production required to sustain global <lb/>fisheries. Nature 374, 255-257. doi: 10.1038/374255a0 <lb/>Posit team (2023). RStudio: Integrated Development Environment for R. Available at: <lb/>http://www.posit.co/. <lb/>R Core Team (2022). R: A language and environment for statistical computing. <lb/>Available at: https://www.R-project.org/. <lb/>Romann, J., Valmalette, J.-C., Chauton, M. S., Tranell, G., Einarsrud, M.-A., and <lb/>Vadstein, O. (2015). Wavelength and orientation dependent capture of light by diatom <lb/>frustule nanostructures. Sci. Rep. 5, 17403. doi: 10.1038/srep17403 <lb/>Ryderheim, F., Grønning, J., and Kiørboe, T. (2022). Thicker shells reduce <lb/>copepod grazing on diatoms. Limnol. Oceanogr. Lett. 7, 435-442. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>lol2.10243 <lb/>Sarmiento, J. L., Gruber, N., Brzezinski, M. A., and Dunne, J. P. (2004). High-latitude <lb/>controls of thermocline nutrients and low latitude biological productivity. Nature 427, <lb/>56-60. doi: 10.1038/nature02127 <lb/>Sarthou, G., Timmermans, K. R., Blain, S., and Treguer, P. (2005). Growth <lb/>physiology and fate of diatoms in the ocean: a review. J. Sea Res. 53, 25-42. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.seares.2004.01.007 <lb/>Sathyendranath, S., Stuart, V., Nair, A., Oka, K., Nakane, T., Bouman, H., et al. <lb/>(2009). Carbon-to-chlorophyll ratio and growth rate of phytoplankton in the sea. Mar. <lb/>Ecol. Prog. Ser. 383, 73-84. doi: 10.3354/meps07998 <lb/>Schlitzer, R. (2022). Ocean Data View. Available at: https://odv.awi.de. <lb/>Schmidt, K., and Jońasdottir, S. (1997). Nutritional quality of two cyanobacteria:How <lb/>rich is &quot;poor&quot; food? Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 151, 1-10. doi: 10.3354/meps151001 <lb/>Smetacek, V. (2012). Making sense of ocean biota: How evolution and biodiversity of <lb/>land organisms differ from that of the plankton. J. Biosci. 37, 589-607. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s12038-012-9240-4 <lb/>Sommer, U., Stibor, H., Katechakis, A., Sommer, F., and Hansen, T. (2002). &quot;Pelagic <lb/>food web configurations at different levels of nutrient richness and their implications <lb/>for the ratio fish production:primary production,&quot; in Sustainable Increase of Marine <lb/>Harvesting: Fundamental Mechanisms and New Concepts. Eds. O. Vadstein and Y. <lb/>Olsen (Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands), 11-20. <lb/>Sterner, R. W., Hagemeier, D. D., Smith, W. L., and Smith, R. F. (1993). <lb/>Phytoplankton nutrient limitation and food quality for Daphnia. Limnol. Oceanogr. <lb/>38, 857-871. doi: 10.4319/lo.1993.38.4.0857 <lb/>Treǵuer, P., Bowler, C., Moriceau, B., Dutkiewicz, S., Gehlen, M., Aumont, O., et al. <lb/>(2018). Influence of diatom diversity on the ocean biological carbon pump. Nat. Geosci. <lb/>11, 27-37. doi: 10.1038/s41561-017-0028-x <lb/>Utermöhl, H. (1931). Neue Wege in der quantitativen Erfassung des Plankton. (Mit <lb/>besonderer Berücksichtigung des Ultraplanktons.): Mit 4 Abbildungen im Text. SIL <lb/>Proceedings 1922-2010 5, 567-596. doi: 10.1080/03680770.1931.11898492 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Ortiz et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmars.2023.1319875 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Marine Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>