<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T17:52:33.152Z">11/20/2025 5:52:33 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.3389_fresc.2024.1426699</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T17:52:19.744040Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T17:52:19.744040Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>EDITED BY <lb/>Inga Voges, <lb/>University Medical Center Schleswig-Holstein, <lb/>Germany <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Piqueras Laura, <lb/>University of Valencia, Spain <lb/>Darren Woodside, <lb/>Texas Heart Institute, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Marta Scatena <lb/>mscatena@uw.edu <lb/>RECEIVED 24 June 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 21 November 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 11 December 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Zhou H, Scatena M, Tu LN, Giachelli CM and <lb/>Nigam V (2024) Monocyte adhesion to and <lb/>transmigration through endothelium following <lb/>cardiopulmonary bypass shearing is mediated <lb/>by IL-8 signaling. <lb/>Front. Cardiovasc. Med. 11:1454302. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Zhou, Scatena, Tu, Giachelli and <lb/>Nigam. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>Monocyte adhesion to and <lb/>transmigration through <lb/>endothelium following <lb/>cardiopulmonary bypass shearing <lb/>is mediated by IL-8 signaling <lb/>Hao Zhou 1 , Marta Scatena 1 * , Lan N. Tu 2 , Cecilia M. Giachelli 1 and <lb/>Vishal Nigam 2,3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Bioengineering, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, United States, 2 Seattle Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital, Seattle, WA, United States, 3 Department of Pediatrics, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, <lb/>United States <lb/>Introduction: The use of cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) can induce sterile systemic <lb/>inflammation that contributes to morbidity and mortality, especially in children. <lb/>Patients have been found to have increased expression of cytokines and <lb/>transmigration of leukocytes during and after CPB. Previous work has demonstrated <lb/>that the supraphysiologic shear stresses existing during CPB are sufficient to induce <lb/>proinflammatory behavior in non-adherent monocytes. The interactions between <lb/>shear stimulated monocytes and vascular endothelial cells have not been well <lb/>studied and have important translational implications. With these studies, we tested <lb/>the hypothesis that non-physiological shear stress experienced by monocytes <lb/>during CPB affects the integrity and function of the endothelial monolayer. <lb/>Methods: We have used an in vitro CPB model to study the interaction between THP-<lb/>1 monocyte-like cells and human neonatal dermal microvascular endothelial cells <lb/>(HNDMVECs). THP-1 cells were sheared in polyvinyl chloride (PVC) tubing at 2.1 Pa, <lb/>twice of the physiological shear stress, for 2 h. ELISA, adhesion and transmigration <lb/>assays, qPCR, and RNA silencing were used to assess the interactions between <lb/>THP-1 cells and HNDMVECs were characterized after co-culture. <lb/>Results: We found that sheared THP-1 cells adhered to and transmigrated <lb/>through the HNDMVEC monolayer more readily than static THP-1 controls. <lb/>Sheared THP-1 cells disrupted the VE-cadherin and led to the reorganization <lb/>of cytoskeletal F-actin of HNDMVECs. A higher level of IL-8 was detected in <lb/>the sheared THP-1 and HNDMVEC co-culture medium compared to the static <lb/>THP-1 and HNDMVEC medium. Further, treating HNDMVECs with IL-8 <lb/>resulted in increased adherence of non-sheared THP-1 cells, and upregulation <lb/>in HNDMVECs of vascular cell adhesion molecule 1 (VCAM-1) and intercellular <lb/>adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM-1). Finally, inhibition of HNDMVECs CXCR2/IL-8 <lb/>receptor with Reparixin and of IL-8 expression with siRNA blocked sheared <lb/>THP-1 cell adhesion to the endothelial monolayer. <lb/>Conclusions: These results suggest that CPB-like sheared monocytes promote <lb/>IL-8 production followed by increased endothelium permeability, and <lb/>monocyte adhesion and transmigration. This study revealed a novel <lb/>mechanism of post-CPB inflammation and will contribute to the development <lb/>of targeted therapeutics to prevent and repair the damage to neonatal patients. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>cardiopulmonary bypass, monocytes, endothelial cells, IL-8, shear stress <lb/>Abbreviations <lb/>HNDMVEC, human neonatal dermal microvascular endothelial cell; G-THP-1, GFP positive THP-1. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 11 December 2024 <lb/>| DOI 10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/>Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) is a technique that maintains <lb/>blood circulation in an extracorporeal circuit, in which blood is <lb/>propelled by mechanical pumps and flows in plastic tubing. This <lb/>technique provides the surgeon with a bloodless field to conduct <lb/>open-heart surgery, while minimizing the ischemic damage to <lb/>the organs. However, since the blood components are exposed to <lb/>an environment that is very different from the native blood <lb/>vessels during CPB, the incidence of complication occurs at <lb/>a rate of 29.2% (1). These complications can lead to systemic <lb/>inflammation and multiorgan dysfunction, which translates to a <lb/>mortality rate of 10.7% in pediatric patients. Although <lb/>modifications have been made to suppress the inflammatory <lb/>response through corticosteroid administration, coating the CPB <lb/>tubing, and filtering the blood postoperatively, no significant <lb/>improvement has been reported to date (2-6). At present, <lb/>finding a CPB-specific pathway that leads to the inflammatory <lb/>response in pediatric patients is the key to reducing the <lb/>complications and mortality rate. <lb/>Post-CPB complications are largely associated with the <lb/>secretion of inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, <lb/>and Tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) during and after <lb/>bypass (7-16) and disruption of the endothelial barrier function <lb/>(17, 18). However, most current studies are based on clinical <lb/>samples, which are unlikely to decouple the effects of the CPB <lb/>and the surgical intervention. Therefore, it remains challenging <lb/>to find targeted pathways that prevent the inflammatory response <lb/>specific to CPB. Given that blood cells can experience three times <lb/>more shear stress in a CPB circuit compared to that in the native <lb/>blood vessel (19), studying the correlation between CPB shear <lb/>and cytokine released by cells can help unveil CPB-specific <lb/>pathways. Recently, we developed an in vitro model that was <lb/>designed to distinguish the non-CPB factors such as surgical <lb/>trauma, blood transfusion, drug administration, and the specific <lb/>condition of the patient from CPB-specific inflammatory changes <lb/>(19). Using this model, we demonstrated that CPB shear stress <lb/>specifically upregulated the expression of IL-8 and TNF-α in <lb/>monocytes, as well as giving rise to a subpopulation of <lb/>monocytes undergoing TNF-α-mediated necroptosis. While the <lb/>TNF-α-mediated inflammatory response of cells in the CPB <lb/>setting has been well-studied (19-21), the role of IL-8 in <lb/>regulating the cellular response after CPB is still unclear. <lb/>IL-8 is a chemoattractant that regulates the recruitment of <lb/>neutrophils, basophils, and T-cells during inflammation. Cells <lb/>that can secrete IL-8 include monocytes, macrophages, <lb/>neutrophils, and endothelial cells. The receptors for IL-8, CXC <lb/>chemokine receptor (CXCR)1 and CXCR2, are also reported to <lb/>be present in a wide range of cell types, including endothelial <lb/>cells, monocytes, neutrophils, and fibroblasts, with the former <lb/>having more specific affinity to the IL-8 than the latter (22). <lb/>Evidence has shown that in CPB patients, perioperative plasma <lb/>IL-8 level is positively correlated to the length of inotropic <lb/>support, length of mechanical ventilation, and incidence of acute <lb/>kidney injuries (23-27). Thus, IL-8-mediated signaling pathways <lb/>may play an important role in the onset of CPB-induced <lb/>inflammatory response at the cellular level. In this study, we used <lb/>a novel in vitro CPB model to characterize the molecular <lb/>mechanism of how leukocytes affected by CPB shear can induce <lb/>inflammatory response in endothelial cells. We identified the IL-<lb/>8/CXCR2 signaling pathway as a regulator of leukocyte adhesion <lb/>and transmigration through the endothelial cell monolayer. <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Cell line and culture methods <lb/>Primary human neonatal dermal microvascular cells <lb/>(HNDMVECs, Cat #CC-2516) were purchased from Lonza <lb/>(Walkersville, MD) and cultured in endothelial cell growth <lb/>medium MV2 (PromoCell, Heidelberg, Germany, Cat #C-22121) <lb/>and 100 U/ml penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco, Waltham, MA, Cat <lb/>#15140122). A HEK293T cell line was purchased from American <lb/>Type Culture Collection (ATCC) (Manassas, VA, Cat #CRL-3216, <lb/>RRID: CVCL_0063) and cultured in Dulbecco&apos;s Modified Eagle <lb/>Medium (DMEM) (Gibco, Waltham, MA, Cat # 11995065) with <lb/>10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Atlanta Biologicals, Flowery Branch, <lb/>GA, Cat # S11150) and 100 U/ml penicillin-streptomycin. The <lb/>medium was changed every 2 days, and the cells were harvested by <lb/>trypsinization. The human acute leukemia monocytic cell line <lb/>THP-1 (Cat # TIB-202, RRID: CVCL_0006) was purchased from <lb/>ATCC and cultured in Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) <lb/>1640 medium (ATCC Modification) (Gibco, Waltham, MA, Cat <lb/># A1049101) with 10% FBS. The medium was changed every <lb/>2 days. Human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (hPBMCs) <lb/>were purchased from Lonza (Walkersville, MD, Cat # CC-2702) <lb/>and maintained in RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco, Waltham, MA, <lb/>Cat # 11875093) with 10% FBS). <lb/>2.2 Lentiviral production and transduction <lb/>A THP-1 cell line that expresses GFP (G-THP-1) was generated <lb/>through lentiviral transduction. Vectors that contain plasmids of <lb/>pSL3 (vesicular stomatitis virus G envelope), pSL4 (HIV-1 gag/ <lb/>pol packing genes), pSL5 (rev gene required for HIV-1 envelope <lb/>protein expression) were a gift from Dr. Murry (University of <lb/>Washington, Seattle, WA). The plasmid vector pCDH-EF1α-<lb/>MCS*-T2A-GFP was purchased from System Biosciences (Palo <lb/>Alto, CA, Cat # CD526A-1). The lentiviral vector was packaged <lb/>in HEK293T cells as previously described (28). Briefly, 3 × 10 6 of <lb/>HEK293T cells were seeded in 10-cm dishes to reach 60% <lb/>confluence in DMEM with 10% FBS and 100 U/ml penicillin-<lb/>streptomycin. The culture media was changed prior to <lb/>transfection. A total of 20 μg plasmid DNA (7.5 μg pCDH-EF1-<lb/>MCS-T2A-copGFP, 2.5 μg pSL3, 6.7 μg pSL4, 3.3 μg pSL5) and <lb/>24 μl of lipofectamine 2000 (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat <lb/># 11668019) dissolved in 1,600 μl Opti-MEM I Reduced Serum <lb/>Medium (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat # 31985062) were <lb/>used for the transfection of one dish. The media was replaced <lb/>after incubating for 6 h at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 . The virus <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>supernatant was collected at 48 h from the media and filtered <lb/>through a 0.45 µm filter. The media containing the virus was <lb/>applied to the THP-1 cells at a multiplicity of infection of 6 <lb/>while spinning at 800xg for 30 min. The transduced G-THP-1 <lb/>were allowed to expand and sort for GFP expression using a BD <lb/>Aria III cell sorter to obtain over 92% transduction efficiency. <lb/>2.3 siRNA transfection <lb/>HNDMVECs were seeded on 6-well plates at 5,000 cells/cm 2 <lb/>and cultured for 7 days to form a confluent monolayer. <lb/>Lipofectamine RNAiMAX Transfection Reagent (Thermofisher, <lb/>Waltham, MA, Cat # 13778150) was used to prepare liposomes <lb/>with the IL-8 siRNA (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, s7327, Cat <lb/># 4390824) or negative control RNA (Thermofisher, Waltham, <lb/>MA, Cat # 4404021) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instruction. <lb/>Both the transfection reagent and siRNAs were diluted and <lb/>mixed to form a siRNA-lipid complex in OptiMEM I Reduced <lb/>Serum Medium. HNDMVECs were incubated with the siRNA-<lb/>lipid complex for 2 days at 37 °C. To demonstrate that IL-8 <lb/>expression was silenced, HNDMVECs were treated with 10 ng/ml <lb/>recombinant human TNF-α (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, <lb/>Cat # 210-TA) for 1 h. Then, the IL-8 expression in the <lb/>HNDMVECs was measured by quantitative real-time PCR. <lb/>2.4 Cell adhesion assay <lb/>HNDMVECs were seeded on 24-well plates at 5,000 cells/cm 2 <lb/>and cultured 7 days to form a confluent monolayer. Monocytes <lb/>or hPBMCs were sheared as previously described (19). Briefly, <lb/>G-THP-1 cells or hPBMCs at a density of 2 million cells/ml were <lb/>sheared in a 10-foot-long Masterflex Tygon E-3603 L/S13 pump <lb/>tubing (Cole-Parmer, Vernon Hills, IL, Cat # MK-06509-13), using <lb/>a Masterflex miniflex pump model 115/230 VAC 07525-20 (Cole-<lb/>Parmer, Vernon Hills, IL, Cat # MK-07525-20) at 10 ml/min for <lb/>2 h. The tubing was mostly submerged in a water bath with <lb/>temperature control at 37 °C. At the end of the shear, the G-THP-<lb/>1 cells or hPBMCs were collected, spun down, and resuspended in <lb/>fresh media. As a control, G-THP-1 cells or hPBMCs were <lb/>incubated in a polyvinylchloride (PVC) flask at a density of <lb/>2 million cells/ml for 2 h. For the pretreatment groups, <lb/>HNDMVECs were either incubated with 5 nM of Reparixin <lb/>(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, Cat # SML2655-5MG) for 30 min <lb/>or 200 ng/ml of recombinant human IL-8 (R&amp;D Systems, <lb/>Minneapolis, MN, Cat # 208-IL-010/CF) for 1 h. G-THP-1 cells or <lb/>hPBMCs, sheared or statically incubated, were then added to a <lb/>monolayer of HNDMVECs (1 × 10 6 cells per well in a 24-well <lb/>plate), followed by a one-hour incubation. Nonadherent G-THP-1 <lb/>cells or hPBMCs were gently washed twice with sterile phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline (PBS). The adhered G-THP-1 cells were visualized <lb/>using a Nikon Eclipse TE200 microscope (Tokyo, Japan) and a <lb/>Photometric CoolSNAP MYO camera (Tucson, AZ) with a GFP <lb/>filter. The adhered hPBMCs were visualized with the same <lb/>microscope and camera with brightfield imaging. The experiments <lb/>were run in triplicate. The number of adherent G-THP-1 cells or <lb/>hPBMCs was counted in five randomly selected visible fields and <lb/>quantified using ImageJ (29) (RRID:SCR_003070). <lb/>2.5 THP-1 transmigration assay <lb/>HNDMVECs were seeded in the upper chamber of a transwell <lb/>tissue culture insert (6.5 mm diameter, 8 μm pore size <lb/>polycarbonate membrane; Corning, NY, Cat # 3422) at 5,000 cells/ <lb/>cm 2 and cultured for 7 days to form a confluent monolayer. <lb/>Sheared and statically incubated G-THP-1 cells were then added <lb/>to the upper chamber (2 × 10 5 cells/well) with the lower chamber <lb/>filled with RPMI 1640 media. After 24 h of incubation, the upper <lb/>chamber was removed and the THP-1 cells in the lower chamber <lb/>were visualized using a Nikon Eclipse TE200 microscope and a <lb/>Photometric CoolSNAP MYO camera and quantified with ImageJ. <lb/>The ability of transendothelial migration was determined by <lb/>counting the migrated G-THP-1 cells in the lower chamber (30). <lb/>The experiment was run in triplicate. The number of adherent <lb/>G-THP-1 cells was counted in five randomly selected visible fields <lb/>and quantified using ImageJ (29). <lb/>2.6 Immunofluorescent staining <lb/>HNDMVECs were seeded on 8-chamber slides (Corning, NY, <lb/>Cat # 354118) at 5,000 cells/cm 2 and cultured 7 days to form a <lb/>confluent monolayer. The sheared or statically incubated G-THP-<lb/>1 cells were then added to a monolayer of HNDMVECs (1 × <lb/>10 6 cells per well), followed by incubation for 6 h. The cell co-<lb/>cultures were washed twice with sterile PBS and fixed with <lb/>formalin. For staining, the fixed cells were permeabilized with <lb/>0.1% Triton-X-100 for 10 min, blocked with 1% BSA and human <lb/>BD Fc block (BD Bioscience, Franklin Lakes, NJ, Cat # 564219) <lb/>for 1 h, followed by incubation with 1:200 vascular endothelial <lb/>cadherin (VE-cadherin) monoclonal antibody (16B1) Biotin <lb/>Conjugate (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat # 13-1449-82, <lb/>RRID: AB_466611) for 1 h, 1:500 streptavidin Alexa Fluor 594 <lb/>Conjugate (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat # S11227) for <lb/>45 min. Nuclei were stained with DAPI. The slides were then <lb/>washed, mounted, and imaged using a Leica DMI6000 <lb/>microscope (RRID:SCR_018713) with Leica SP8X confocal. <lb/>VE-cadherin staining was quantified using ImageJ (29) (RRID: <lb/>SCR_003070). A minimum of three biological replicas were used <lb/>for each quantification and a minimum of 6 areas per staining. <lb/>For VE-Cadherin staining, images were segmented, and a <lb/>threshold was set on the positive control (no THP1 endothelial <lb/>cells, Figure 2C). Measurement of the treated conditions was <lb/>done using the same positive control threshold. <lb/>2.7 Rhodamine-Phalloidin labeling <lb/>HNDMVECs were seeded on 8-chamber slides at 5,000 cells/cm 2 <lb/>and cultured for 7 days to form a confluent monolayer. The sheared <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>or statically incubated G-THP-1 cells were then added to a <lb/>monolayer of HNDMVECs (1 × 10 6 cells per well), respectively, <lb/>followed by incubation for 6 h. The cell co-cultures were washed <lb/>twice with sterile PBS, fixed with formalin, permeabilized with <lb/>0.1% Triton-X-100, and blocked with 1% BSA. The cells were then <lb/>incubated with Rhodamine Phalloidin (ThermoFisher, Waltham, <lb/>MA, Cat # R415) for 20 min at room temperature, stained with <lb/>DAPI, washed, mounted, and imaged using a Leica DMI6000 <lb/>microscope (RRID:SCR_018713) with Leica SP8X confocal. The <lb/>intercellular gap area was quantified using ImageJ on the slides <lb/>stained by the Rhodamine Phalloidin (29) (RRID:SCR_003070). <lb/>The same threshold strategy as for VE-cadherin we used. Further, <lb/>segmented images were converted to binary images, and a mask <lb/>was added to the binary image to then create regions of interest <lb/>(ROIs). The total area of the ROIs was then calculated. <lb/>2.8 Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays <lb/>(ELISA) <lb/>The media supernatants of the HNDMVECs and sheared or <lb/>statically incubated THP-1 cells were collected at 0.5, 1, 3, and 6 h <lb/>into the co-culture. The levels of IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, and TNF-α were <lb/>measured using ELISA kits from Invitrogen (Cat # BMS224-2, <lb/>88-7066-88, 88-8086-88, BMS223-4, Waltham, MA). Experiments <lb/>were run in both biological and technical triplicate. <lb/>2.9 Quantitative real-time PCR <lb/>HNDMVECs were treated with human recombinant IL-8 for 1 h, <lb/>and total RNA was isolated using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, <lb/>Hilden, Germany, Cat # 74104) and RNase-Free DNAse Set <lb/>(Qiagen, Hilden, Germany, Cat # 79254). Total RNA (150 ng) was <lb/>used for cDNA synthesis using the Omniscript RT Kit (Qiagen, <lb/>Hilden, Germany, Cat # 205113). Quantitative real-time PCR was <lb/>performed on a QuantStudio 6 Pro real-time PCR system <lb/>(Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat # A43180) and TaqMan <lb/>Universal PCR Master Mix (Thermofisher, Waltham, MA, Cat <lb/># 4304437) according to the manufacturer instructions. Both <lb/>biological and technical triplicate were run. TaqMan primers of <lb/>selectin E (Hs00174057_m1, Cat # 4331182), intercellular adhesion <lb/>molecule 1 (ICAM1) (Hs00164932_m1, Cat # 4331182) and <lb/>vascular cell adhesion molecule 1 (VCAM1) (Hs01003372_m1, Cat <lb/># 4331182) were purchased from Thermofisher (Waltham, MA). <lb/>To demonstrate that IL-8 expression was silenced, HNDMVECs <lb/>were treated with 10 ng/ml TNF-α (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, <lb/>MN, Cat # 210-TA) for 1 h, and the IL-8 expression was <lb/>measured. The same preparation was done to perform quantitative <lb/>real-time PCR. Taqman primer of IL-8 (Hs00174103_m1, Cat <lb/># 4331182) was purchased from Thermofisher (Waltham, MA). <lb/>2.10 Flow cytometry <lb/>Cells were with 4% PFA (Electron Microscopy Sciences, <lb/>Hatfield, USA) and then stained with primary antibodies against <lb/>CD62E, E-Selcetin (PE-conjugated) (# 12-0627-42, Thermofisher, <lb/>Walthman, MA), CD54, ICAM-1 (PE-conjugated) (#12-0549-42, <lb/>Thermofisher, Waltham, MA), and CD106, VCAM-1 (#12-1059-<lb/>42, Thermofisher, Waltham, MA) at 4 °C for 1 h in PBS <lb/>supplemented with 0.09% (w/v) sodium azide (ThermoFisher, <lb/>Waltham, USA) and 1% heat-inactivated FBS. Gating was <lb/>performed using isotype controls following singlets and live/dead <lb/>gating. Data were acquired using a BD FACSymphony A3 (BD, <lb/>Franklin Lakes, USA) and analyzed with FlowJo 10 (BD, <lb/>Franklin Lakes, USA). <lb/>2.11 Statistical analysis <lb/>All experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were <lb/>expressed as mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise <lb/>comparisons between groups were conducted using the ANOVA <lb/>test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by <lb/>&quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by a single symbol and <lb/>P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 CPB shear promotes mononuclear cell <lb/>adhesion to and transmigration through the <lb/>endothelial monolayer <lb/>Monocyte infiltration is commonly observed in the <lb/>inflammatory response in CPB (31-33). During this process, <lb/>activated monocytes adhere to the vascular wall, transmigrate <lb/>through the intercellular tight junctions, and reach different <lb/>organs (34-37). To characterize the response of monocytes <lb/>specifically to CPB shear, we sheared the THP-1 cells in the CPB <lb/>circuit, co-cultured them with confluent HNDMVECs for 1 h, <lb/>and quantified the number of adherent THP-1 cells. As shown in <lb/>Figure 1A, exposing THP-1 to shear stress resulted in a two-fold <lb/>increase in THP-1 cells adhering to the HNDMVEC monolayer. <lb/>A similar trend was observed for PBMCs (Supplementary <lb/>Figure S1). Furthermore, significantly more sheared THP-1 cells <lb/>were observed in the bottom chamber of the transwells that had <lb/>been seeded with HNDMVECs compared with static THP-1 cells <lb/>(Figure 1D). These results suggest that exposure to CPB shear-<lb/>induced monocytic cells to be adherent to and to transmigrate <lb/>through a monolayer of endothelial cells. <lb/>3.2 The interaction of sheared THP-1 cells <lb/>with HNDMVECs results in disrupted <lb/>intercellular junction <lb/>The increasing transmigration behavior of sheared monocytes <lb/>prompted us to examine if the sheared cells were disrupting <lb/>the barrier function in the endothelial monolayer. To examine <lb/>the intercellular adherens junction and reorganization of the <lb/>cytoskeleton, HNDMVECs were stained for VE-cadherin and <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>F-Actin after co-culture with sheared or static THP-1 cells. <lb/>Co-culturing with sheared THP-1 cells resulted in the loss of <lb/>adherens junction while they remained intact in endothelial cells <lb/>cultured with static THP-1s (Figures 2A, B). Similarly, the static <lb/>group showed robust actin filament lining intracellularly <lb/>(Figure 3B). In the sheared group, we observed that THP-1 cells <lb/>clustered at the intercellular area (Figure 3A). Further, actin <lb/>filaments reorganized and the intercellular gap areas between <lb/>endothelial cells were increased in the sheared group compared <lb/>to the static group and the endothelial cells without THP-1 <lb/>treatment. These results imply increasing motility of the <lb/>endothelial cells in response to the sheared monocyte insult. <lb/>3.3 The interaction between sheared THP-1 <lb/>and HNDMVECs results in an increased Il-8 <lb/>release level <lb/>To analyze the inflammatory cytokines secreted by sheared or <lb/>static THP-1 cells and HNDMVECs, we collected co-culture media <lb/>at 0.5, 1, 3, and 6 h and measured the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, <lb/>and TNF-α using ELISA. The sheared group released <lb/>significantly more IL-8 than the static group at every time point <lb/>(Figure 4A). The level of IL-8 increased over the period of 6 h in <lb/>the shear group while it leveled off at 3 h in the static group <lb/>(Figure 4A). IL-6 level in the sheared group significantly <lb/>increased at 3 and 6 h but the concentration was about 20-fold <lb/>lower than IL-8 (Figure 4B). No significant release of IL-1β and <lb/>TNF-α was detected throughout the co-culture (Figure 4C, TNF-<lb/>α data not shown). These findings indicate that treating <lb/>HNDMVECs with sheared THP-1 specifically induced IL-8 release. <lb/>3.4 Reparixin, a CXCR2 antagonist, inhibits <lb/>the adhesion of sheared THP-1 cells while <lb/>IL-8 promotes the adhesion of untreated <lb/>THP-1 cells <lb/>Our results suggested that the adhesion of THP-1 cells on <lb/>the endothelial cell is positively correlated to the IL-8 release <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>For cell adhesion assay, G-THP-1 cells were sheared in the in vitro CPB circuit for 2 h or cultured statically in a PVC flask, followed by co-culture with confluent <lb/>HNDMVECs for 1 h. At the end of the co-culture, non-adherent G-THP-1 cells were rinsed, and adherent G-THP-1 cells were quantified. (A) Quantitative <lb/>analysis of adhered G-THP-1 cells on the endothelial cell monolayer. (B) Adhesion of G-THP-1 cells incubated statically in a PVC flask. (C) Adhesion of <lb/>G-THP-1 cells sheared in a CPB circuit. For transmigration assay, G-THP-1 cells were sheared in the in vitro CPB circuit for 2 h or cultured statically in a <lb/>PVC flask. The G-THP-1 cells were then added to confluent HNDMVECs grown on the top chamber of the transwell insert. After an overnight incubation, <lb/>the G-THP-1 cells transmigrated to the bottom chambers were quantified. (D) Quantitative analysis of transmigrated THP-1 cells through endothelial cell <lb/>monolayer. (E) Transmigrated G-THP-1 cells incubated statically in a PVC flask. (F) Transmigration of G-THP-1 cells sheared in a CPB circuit. Scale <lb/>bar = 100 μm. For additional images see Supplementary Figure S2. All experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as <lb/>mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were conducted using the ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. <lb/>Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>during co-culture. To further investigate the role of IL-8 in <lb/>mediating the interaction between THP-1 cells and the <lb/>endothelial cells, we treated the endothelial cells with <lb/>Reparixin, an inhibitor of the IL-8 receptors, CXCR1/2, and <lb/>then co-cultured with sheared THP-1 cells (CXCR2 staining of <lb/>HNDMVECs see Supplementary Figure S5). Reparixin <lb/>treatment reduced the adhesion of sheared THP-1 similar <lb/>to static control (Figure 5C). When we pre-treated <lb/>HNDMVECs with 50 and 200 ng/ml IL-8, the adhesion of <lb/>untreated THP-1 cells was promoted in a dose-dependent <lb/>manner (Figures 6C, D). These results suggested that blocking <lb/>IL-8 signaling through the CXCRs prevented the adhesion of <lb/>shear-activated THP-1 cells. <lb/>3.5 Silencing IL-8 expression in <lb/>endothelial cells reduced the adhesion <lb/>of sheared monocytes <lb/>To further identify the source of IL-8 in the co-culture, we <lb/>silenced the IL-8 expression in the HNDMVECs with siRNA. <lb/>HNDMVECs were incubated with the lipid-siRNA complex for 2 <lb/>days and then stimulated with 10 ng/ml TNF-α for 1 h. Results <lb/>from qPCR showed significant upregulation of IL-8 expression in <lb/>the group not treated with siRNA or treated with scramble <lb/>siRNA, while the IL-8 expression in the group treated with <lb/>siRNA remained low, suggesting IL-8 expression in HNDMVECs <lb/>was silenced (Supplementary Figure S8). The HNDMVECs were <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>VE-cadherin of HNDMVECs co-cultured with (A) sheared THP-1 cells, (B) THP-1 cells statically incubated in PVC flask, and (C) No THP-1 treatment, <lb/>visualized by immunofluorescent staining. For additional images see Supplementary Figure S3. Red = VE-Cadherin, Green = THP-1 Cells, Blue = DAPI. <lb/>Scale bar = 100 μm. (D) Quantification of VE cadherin staining. G-THP-1 cells were sheared in the in vitro CPB circuit for 2 h or cultured statically in a <lb/>PVC flask, followed by co-culture with confluent HNDMVECs for 6 h. After the co-culture, the cells were fixed and stained with VE-cadherin <lb/>antibodies. All experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise <lb/>comparisons between groups were conducted using the ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values <lb/>less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>then co-cultured with sheared THP-1 cells and adhered cells were <lb/>quantified after 1 h. Adhesion of THP-1 cells was significantly <lb/>reduced in the group treated with the siRNA compared with the <lb/>group treated with scramble siRNA or without treatment <lb/>(Figure 7). These results indicate that endothelial-derived IL-8 <lb/>largely contributes to the increased adhesion of sheared THP-1. <lb/>3.6 IL-8 upregulated adhesion molecules on <lb/>the endothelial cells <lb/>To gain mechanistic insight into how IL-8 promotes <lb/>mononuclear cell adherence to endothelial cells, we examined the <lb/>expression of adherence molecules in endothelial cells. qPCR and <lb/>FACS analysis were performed to examine the expression of <lb/>adhesion molecules, including e-selectin, VCAM1, and ICAM1. <lb/>HNDMVECs were treated with IL-8 with TNF-α treatment being <lb/>a positive control to stimulate the endothelial cells. All three <lb/>adhesion molecules were upregulated in the positive control <lb/>group (Figure 8 and Supplementary Figure S10). In the IL-8 <lb/>group, there was a 5-fold increase in both the expressions of <lb/>ICAM1 and VCAM1, while the expression of e-selectin remained <lb/>unchanged (Figure 8). These results indicate that the increasing <lb/>adhesion of sheared THP-1 cells was likely to be mediated by the <lb/>IL-8 signaling pathway through upregulated adhesion molecule <lb/>expression on the endothelial cells. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>With this study, we are, to our knowledge, the first to show that <lb/>CPB shear stress-activated monocytes adhere to and migrate <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>F-actin of HNDMVECs co-cultured with (A) sheared THP-1 cells, THP-1 cells statically incubated in PVC flask, and (C) No THP-1 treatment, stained by <lb/>rhodamine-phalloidin. For additional images see Supplementary Figure S4. Red = F-actin, Green = THP-1 Cells, Blue = DAPI. Scale bar = 100 μm. <lb/>(D) Quantification of intercellular gap area of endothelial cells. All experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as mean ± <lb/>standard deviation within groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were conducted using the ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical <lb/>significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>through an intact and unstimulated endothelial monolayer. We <lb/>used an in vitro CPB model to probe the interaction between <lb/>shear stress-activated THP-1 monocytes and quiescent confluent <lb/>HNDMECs. Our data demonstrated that an average CPB shear <lb/>stress of 2.1 Pa or 21 dyne/cm 2 promoted the adhesion and <lb/>transmigration of monocytes to and through the endothelial <lb/>monolayer. This was accompanied by the disruption of the <lb/>adherens junction and reorganization of the cytoskeleton in the <lb/>endothelial cells (diagram of the experimental setup and results <lb/>see Figure 9). IL-8, which was significantly upregulated in the co-<lb/>culture media, played a pivotal role in mediating the crosstalk <lb/>between monocytes and endothelial cells. Inhibiting the binding <lb/>of IL-8 to the CXCRs on endothelial cells prevented sheared <lb/>monocytes from adhering. Preincubating endothelial cells with <lb/>IL-8 resulted in increasing adhesion of untreated monocytes, <lb/>suggesting endothelial cell activation. We further established that <lb/>endothelial-derived IL-8 was responsible for the sheared-<lb/>monocyte adhesion. Finally, IL-8 also induced ICAM1 and <lb/>VCAM1 expression in HNDMVECs. This suggests that IL-8 may <lb/>promote the adhesion of the CPB shear stress-treated monocytes <lb/>by activating a subset of adhesion molecules on the <lb/>microvascular endothelial cells. <lb/>The sequela of leukocyte rolling and binding to activated <lb/>endothelial cells and transmigration through the endothelial <lb/>monolayer is a fundamental process of inflammation responding <lb/>to mediators produced by a traumatic injury. We have recently <lb/>shown that using in vitro CPB setup recapitulating a prolonged <lb/>CPB surgery, monocytes circulating for 2 h at 21 dyne/cm 2 <lb/>showed increased expression of IL-8 and TNF-α (19). Now we <lb/>also find that these cells can adhere to and transmigrate through <lb/>an endothelial monolayer without additional stimulation. These <lb/>results suggest that CPB shear stress is sufficient to promote <lb/>monocyte adhesion and transmigration. Additionally, loss of <lb/>endothelial membrane VE-cadherin staining correlated with the <lb/>formation of gaps in the monolayer. Interestingly, Baratchi et al., <lb/>using a microfluidic system modeling the change in shear stress <lb/>observed in aortic stenosis, recently described calcium flux-<lb/>dependent activation of monocytes in response to elevated shear <lb/>stress and their ability to adhere to TNF-α stimulated human <lb/>umbilical vein endothelial cells (38). Our data strongly suggest <lb/>that TNF-α was not playing a role in our CPB shear stress-<lb/>induced THP-1/endothelial cell interactions, as we did not find <lb/>changes of TNF-α levels in the co-culture medium, even if TNF-<lb/>α was induced by CPB shear stress in monocytes as shown <lb/>previously (19). A potential explanation for the absence of TNF-<lb/>α in the co-culture is that CPB shear stress-activated THP-1 <lb/>media was refreshed before co-culture with the endothelial <lb/>monolayer, suggesting that when the shear stress stimulus is <lb/>removed, the monocytes stop producing TNF-α. These results <lb/>point to different factors mediating the monocyte-endothelial cell <lb/>interaction in our system. <lb/>We show that the monocyte-endothelial cell interaction was <lb/>promoted by the addition of IL-8 and inhibited by the CXCR <lb/>antagonist Reparixin. These results suggest that IL-8 mediates the <lb/>interaction between monocytes and endothelial cells in CPB <lb/>shear stress conditions. Accordingly, we have previously shown <lb/>that IL-8 in the monocytes is directly upregulated by CPB shear <lb/>stress (19). Here we find that IL-8 was also elevated in the media <lb/>of CPB shear stress-stimulated THP-1 and endothelial cell <lb/>co-cultures. The results of the current study revealed that IL-8 is <lb/>a main cytokine mediating the interaction between monocytes <lb/>and endothelial cells in a CPB setting. To clarify the cell source <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Cytokine levels of (A) IL-8, (B) IL-6, and (C) IL-1β in the co-culture <lb/>media of sheared or static THP-1 cells and HNDMVECs measured <lb/>at 0.5, 1, 3, and 6 h. All experiments were run in triplicate. All <lb/>quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation <lb/>within groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were <lb/>conducted using the ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. <lb/>Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are <lb/>indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are <lb/>indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>of IL-8 in the co-culture system we used siRNA silencing. We <lb/>showed that silencing the IL-8 expression in the endothelial cells <lb/>prevented the adhesion of sheared monocytes. This result <lb/>suggests that the endothelial cells mainly contributed to the IL-8 <lb/>release during the co-culture. The proposed mechanism of <lb/>monocyte adhesion is that CPB shear stress-activated THP-1 cells <lb/>stimulated the IL-8 release from endothelial cells and led to the <lb/>upregulation of endothelial adhesion molecules. This autocrine <lb/>signaling of IL-8 has been reported in endothelial cells to <lb/>support the capillary tube formation and neovascularization in <lb/>the absence of external IL-8 signaling (39-45). The current study <lb/>design limitation did not rule out the possible contribution of IL-<lb/>8 from monocytes knowing that monocytes produce IL-8 (19). It <lb/>is also possible that THP-1 monocytes continue to produce IL-8 <lb/>after the CPB shear stress stimulus is removed and thus promote <lb/>their own adhesion. Interestingly, IL-8 appears to autocrinally <lb/>promote its own transcription in monocytes but not in <lb/>(46), suggesting a feed-forward loop of self-<lb/>activation. Future investigation will be needed to evaluate the <lb/>role of monocyte-derived IL-8 in our system. Apart from the <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>(A) quantitative analysis of sheared G-THP-1 cells adhering to (B) untreated HNDMVECs, (C) HNDMVECs pretreated with 5nM reparixin for 30 min, and <lb/>(D) HNDMVECs pretreated with PBS. Scale bar = 100 μm. For additional images see Supplementary Figure S6. All experiments were run in triplicate. All <lb/>quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were conducted using the <lb/>ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbols and P <lb/>values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>(A) quantitative analysis of statically incubated G-THP-1 cells adhering to (B) untreated HNDMVECs, (C) HNDMVECs pretreated with 50 ng/ml IL-8 for <lb/>1 h, and (D) HNDMVECs pretreated with 200 ng/ml IL-8 for 1 h. For additional images see Supplementary Figure S7. Scale bar = 100 μm. All <lb/>experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise comparisons between <lb/>groups were conducted using the ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are <lb/>indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>change in IL-8 levels, we observed that the IL-6 level increased <lb/>significantly at 6 h post-sheared THP-1 cell/endothelial cells co-<lb/>culture. Although studies have linked IL-6 levels to inflammation <lb/>and postoperative mortality after CPB (47-49), in our model, <lb/>significant sheared monocyte adhesion was detected at 1 h into <lb/>co-culture, prior to IL-6 release, and thus suggesting an IL-6 <lb/>independent mechanism. In addition, we demonstrate strong <lb/>inhibition of CPB-induced THP-1 cell adhesion to endothelial <lb/>monolayer by the CXCR1/2 inhibitor Reparixin and IL-8 siRNA, <lb/>thus causally implicating the detrimental effect of IL-8 in <lb/>FIGURE 7 <lb/>(A) quantitative analysis of (B) statically incubated G-THP-1 cells adhering to HNDMVECs, and sheared G-THP-1 cells adhering to (C) HNDMVECs, <lb/>(D) HNDMVECs treated with IL-8 siRNA, and (E) HNDMVECs treated with negative control siRNA. For additional images see Supplementary <lb/>Figure S9. Scale bar = 100 μm. All experiments were run in triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation within <lb/>groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were conducted using ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by <lb/>&quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbols and P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/>FIGURE 8 <lb/>Expression of e-selectin, ICAM1, and VCAM1 in HNDMVECs treated with IL-8, TNF-α, and control measured by RT-qPCR. All experiments were run in <lb/>triplicate. All quantitative data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation within groups. Pairwise comparisons between groups were conducted <lb/>using ANOVA test and Tukey&apos;s post-hoc test. Statistical significance is denoted by &quot;*&quot;. P values less than 0.05 are indicated by single symbol and <lb/>P values less than 0.01 are indicated by double symbols. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>endothelial function induced by CPB shear stress-activated <lb/>monocytes, which can further lead to vessel leakage and <lb/>monocytes tissue invasion. <lb/>IL-8 is well-known to regulate neutrophil functions by <lb/>promoting chemotaxis, causing the release of lysosomal enzymes, <lb/>upregulation of adhesion molecules, increasing intracellular <lb/>calcium, and priming of the oxidative burst (50-54). Much less <lb/>is known about the functions of IL-8 in monocytes. In flow <lb/>conditions, IL-8 stimulates adhesion to E-selectin-expressing <lb/>endothelial cells and promotes monocyte polarization toward an <lb/>M1 pro-inflammatory phenotype (55-57). In our system, it <lb/>appears that IL-8 promoted endothelial-specific processes <lb/>facilitating monocyte adhesion that was strongly inhibited by <lb/>blocking the IL-8 receptors on endothelial cells. Further studies <lb/>will be necessary to assess the direct effects of IL-8 on CPB shear <lb/>stress-activated monocytes. In addition, endothelial cells have <lb/>been shown to express the IL-8 receptors CXCR1 and CXCR2 <lb/>and respond to IL-8 by activating angiogenesis processes, <lb/>including proliferation, survival, tube morphogenesis, and MMP <lb/>production (58). The binding of IL-8 on endothelial cells can <lb/>induce cytoskeletal reorganization through Rho and Rac signaling <lb/>pathways in a phosphoinositide 3-kinase-dependent manner (59-<lb/>61), which are correlated to the clustering of E-selectin, <lb/>intercellular adhesion molecules, and vascular cell adhesion <lb/>molecules. IL-8 treatment increases the permeability of the <lb/>endothelium, likely facilitating the subsequent transmigration of <lb/>monocytes (24, 59, 62). Further, IL-8 has been shown to activate <lb/>the NF-κB pathway in several immune cell lines, including <lb/>THP-1, and to induce the expression of VCAM-1 and ICAM-1 <lb/>in U937 cells (63). Accordingly, our studies also show that IL-8 <lb/>is a strong inducer of ICAM1 and VCAM1 RNA expression <lb/>in the microvascular endothelial cells. We also observed <lb/>IL-8-dependent endothelial cell cytoskeleton rearrangement and <lb/>VE-cadherin disruption. <lb/>Evidence has shown that inflammation leads to organ <lb/>damage in CPB patients and that elevated plasma level of IL-8, <lb/>among other cytokines, positively correlates with acute kidney <lb/>injury, brain injury in newborns, and intensive care length <lb/>of stay (23-27). Experimental evidence also indicates CPB-<lb/>dependent transmigration and tissue infiltration of leukocytes <lb/>and neutrophils (31). In addition, the inflammatory response to <lb/>CPB can vary by different ages. Pediatric patients are more <lb/>susceptible to brain injuries than adults after CPB (64). However, <lb/>the pathological mechanisms behind organ damage in CPB still <lb/>remain unresolved. This is the first study to our knowledge to <lb/>show that CPB shear stress-activated monocytes affected <lb/>endothelial integrity and promoted monocyte adhesion and <lb/>transmigration in an IL-8-dependent manner, suggesting that IL-<lb/>8-mediated signaling pathway may play an important role in the <lb/>onset of CPB-induced inflammatory response and tissue <lb/>infiltration at the cellular level (cartoon, Figure 10) These studies <lb/>further suggest that blocking IL-8 receptors may prove a <lb/>promising approach to reduce endothelial injury and tissue and <lb/>organ damage observed in prolong CPB and pediatric patients <lb/>undergoing CPB. <lb/>This study has several limitations. The neonatal dermal <lb/>endothelial cells used in this study are derived from only one <lb/>tissue. Indeed, CPB-induced systemic insult involves the <lb/>endothelium of different organs including the brain, kidney, and <lb/>lung (65-67). The endothelial cells from different organs are <lb/>heterogeneous (68, 69) and thus may result in different responses <lb/>to CPB shear and shear-activated blood cells. For example, it is <lb/>established that aortic endothelial cells are more susceptible to <lb/>TNF-α-mediated monocyte adhesion compared to pulmonary <lb/>microvascular endothelial cells and renal glomerular endothelial <lb/>cells (70). Therefore, future studies will focus on characterizing <lb/>the interactions between CPB-affected monocytes and endothelial <lb/>cells isolated from different organs. In addition, THP-1 cells and <lb/>endothelial cells were co-cultured in a static condition. Indeed, it <lb/>is well-established that physiological flow protects endothelial <lb/>cells from injury (71). The static condition also does not fully <lb/>recapitulate the flow condition in which the cellular interactions <lb/>take place during CPB. Future studies will focus on the addition <lb/>of a flow chamber loaded with endothelial cells to the in vitro <lb/>FIGURE 9 <lb/>Cartoon describing a proposed mechanism of shear stress activation THP1 effect on endothelial cells. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>CPB circuit. This will help the characterization of cellular <lb/>interactions more accurately. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are publicly <lb/>available. This data can be found here: https://figshare.com/ <lb/>authors/Hao_Zhou/18715732. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>Ethical approval was not required for the studies on humans in <lb/>accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements <lb/>because only commercially available established cell lines were used. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>HZ: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Resources, Validation. <lb/>MS: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. LT: Conceptualization, Methodology, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. CG: Data curation, Formal Analysis, Funding acquisition, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Resources, <lb/>Software, Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>VN: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. The <lb/>research reported in this publication was supported by the UW <lb/>Royalty Research Fund 143524 granted to Dr. MS, R35 HL <lb/>139602-01, and NIH R35 HL171342 granted to Dr. CG and the <lb/>National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering of <lb/>the National Institutes of Health under Award Number <lb/>T32EB032787. Dr. VN is funded by NIH R01HD106628. The <lb/>authors are very thankful to Dr. Nathaniel Peters at UW <lb/>W. M. Keck Microscopy Center for the necessary training and <lb/>assistance in acquiring images on the Leica SP8X confocal <lb/>microscope, which was funded by a S10 OD016240 NIH grant <lb/>and the UW Student Technology Fee. The content is solely the <lb/>responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent <lb/>the official views of the National Institutes of Health. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board <lb/>member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no <lb/>impact on the peer review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of <lb/>the authors and do not necessarily represent those of <lb/>FIGURE 10 <lb/>Cartoon representing a working model of the shear stress and IL-8 signaling CPB-induced inflammatory response. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<div type="annex">their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, <lb/>the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be <lb/>evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made <lb/>by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by <lb/>the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found <lb/>online at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcvm.2024. <lb/>1454302/full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kansy A, Tobota Z, Maruszewski P, Maruszewski B. Analysis of 14,843 neonatal <lb/>congenital heart surgical procedures in the European association for cardiothoracic <lb/>surgery congenital database. Ann Thorac Surg. (2010) 89(4):1255-9. doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>athoracsur.2010.01.003 <lb/>2. Graham EM, Atz AM, McHugh KE, Butts RJ, Baker NL, Stroud RE, et al. <lb/>Preoperative steroid treatment does not improve markers of inflammation after <lb/>cardiac surgery in neonates: results from a randomized trial. J Thorac Cardiovasc <lb/>Surg. (2014) 147(3):902-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2013.06.010 <lb/>3. Graham EM, Atz AM, Butts RJ, Baker NL, Zyblewski SC, Deardorff RL, et al. <lb/>Standardized preoperative corticosteroid treatment in neonates undergoing cardiac <lb/>surgery: results from a randomized trial. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2011) 142 <lb/>(6):1523-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2011.04.019 <lb/>4. Keski-Nisula J, Pesonen E, Olkkola KT, Peltola K, Neuvonen PJ, Tuominen N, <lb/>et al. Methylprednisolone in neonatal cardiac surgery: reduced inflammation <lb/>without improved clinical outcome. Ann Thorac Surg. (2013) 95(6):2126-32. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2013.02.013 <lb/>5. Horton SB, Butt WW, Mullaly RJ, Thuys CA, O&apos;Connor EB, Byron K, et al. IL-6 <lb/>and IL-8 levels after cardiopulmonary bypass are not affected by surface coating. Ann <lb/>Thorac Surg. (1999) 68(5):1751-5. doi: 10.1016/s0003-4975(99)01066-8 <lb/>6. Chew MS, Brix-Christensen V, Ravn HB, Brandslund I, Ditlevsen E, Pedersen J, <lb/>et al. Effect of modified ultrafiltration on the inflammatory response in paediatric <lb/>open-heart surgery: a prospective, randomized study. Perfusion. (2002) 17 <lb/>(5):327-33. doi: 10.1191/0267659102pf595oa <lb/>7. Ashraf S. Effects of cardiopulmonary bypass on neonatal and paediatric <lb/>inflammatory profiles. Eur J Cardio-Thorac Surg. (1997) 12(6):862-8. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>s1010-7940(97)00261-3 <lb/>8. Alcaraz AJ, Manzano L, Sancho L, Vigil MD, Esquivel F, Maroto E, et al. Different <lb/>proinflammatory cytokine serum pattern in neonate patients undergoing open heart <lb/>surgery. Relevance of IL-8. J Clin Immunol. (2005) 25(3):238-45. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s10875-005-4081-7 <lb/>9. Mahle WT, Matthews E, Kanter KR, Kogon BE, Hamrick SEG, Strickland MJ. <lb/>Inflammatory response after neonatal cardiac surgery and its relationship to <lb/>clinical outcomes. Ann Thorac Surg. (2014) 97(3):950-6. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur. <lb/>2013.10.069 <lb/>10. Liu KD, Altmann C, Smits G, Krawczeski CD, Edelstein CL, Devarajan P, <lb/>et al. Serum interleukin-6 and interleukin-8 are early biomarkers of acute kidney <lb/>injury and predict prolonged mechanical ventilation in children undergoing <lb/>cardiac surgery: a case-control study. Crit Care. (2009) 13(4):R104. doi: 10.1186/ <lb/>cc7940 <lb/>11. Finn A, Naik S, Klein N, Levinsky RJ, Strobel S, Elliott M. Interleukin-8 release <lb/>and neutrophil degranulation after pediatric cardiopulmonary bypass. J Thorac <lb/>Cardiovasc Surg. (1993) 105(2):234-41. doi: 10.1016/s0022-5223(19)33806-1 <lb/>12. Madhok AB, Ojamaa K, Haridas V, Parnell VA, Pahwa S, Chowdhury D. <lb/>Cytokine response in children undergoing surgery for congenital heart disease. <lb/>Pediatr Cardiol. (2006) 27(4):408-13. doi: 10.1007/s00246-006-0934-y <lb/>13. McBride WT, Armstrong MA, Gilliland H, McMurray TJ. The balance of pro <lb/>and anti-inflammatory cytokines in plasma and bronchoalveolar lavage (bal) at <lb/>paediatric cardiac surgery. Cytokine. (1996) 8(9):724-9. doi: 10.1006/cyto.1996.0096 <lb/>14. Song S, Bai C, Zhou J. Serum TNF-α levels in children with congenital heart <lb/>disease undergoing cardiopulmonary bypass: a cohort study in China and a meta-<lb/>analysis of the published literature. J Clin Lab Anal. (2016) 31(6):e22112. doi: 10. <lb/>1002/jcla.22112 <lb/>15. Park KS, Hwan S DO, Chung IY, Kim HS, Kim CS. Change of tumor necrosis <lb/>factor-alpha concentration after pediatric cardiopulmonary bypass and its relationship <lb/>with postoperative course. Korean J Anesthesiol. (2002) 42(1):56. doi: 10.4097/kjae. <lb/>2002.42.1.56 <lb/>16. Hammer S, Fuchs AT, Rinker C, Daebritz S, Kozlik-Feldmann R, Netz H. <lb/>Interleukin-6 and procalcitonin in serum of children undergoing cardiac surgery <lb/>with cardiopulmonary bypass. Acta Cardiol. (2004) 59(6):624-9. doi: 10.2143/ac.59. <lb/>6.2005245 <lb/>17. Koning NJ, Overmars MAH, Van Den Brom CE, Van Bezu J, Simon LE, Vonk <lb/>ABA, et al. Endothelial hyperpermeability after cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary <lb/>bypass as assessed using an in vitro bioassay for endothelial barrier function. Br <lb/>J Anaesth. (2016) 116(2):223-32. doi: 10.1093/bja/aev411 <lb/>18. Feng J, Kant S, Sellke FW. Microvascular dysfunction following cardioplegic <lb/>arrest and cardiopulmonary bypass. VP. (2021) 5:30. doi: 10.20517/2574-1209.2021.57 <lb/>19. Tu LN, Hsieh L, Kajimoto M, Charette K, Kibiryeva N, Forero A, et al. Shear <lb/>stress associated with cardiopulmonary bypass induces expression of inflammatory <lb/>cytokines and necroptosis in monocytes. JCI Insight. (2021) 6(1):e141341. doi: 10. <lb/>1172/jci.insight.141341 <lb/>20. Cain BS, Meldrum DR, Dinarello CA, Meng X, Joo KS, Banerjee A, et al. Tumor <lb/>necrosis factor-alpha and interleukin-1 beta synergistically depress human myocardial <lb/>function. Crit Care Med. (1999) 27(7):1309-18. doi: 10.1097/00003246-199907000-00018 <lb/>21. Meldrum DR, Donnahoo KK. Role of TNF in mediating renal insufficiency <lb/>following cardiac surgery: evidence of a postbypass cardiorenal syndrome. J Surg <lb/>Res. (1999) 85(2):185-99. doi: 10.1006/jsre.1999.5660 <lb/>22. Apostolakis S, Vogiatzi K, Amanatidou V, Spandidos DA. Interleukin 8 and <lb/>cardiovascular disease. Cardiovasc Res. (2009) 84(3):353-60. doi: 10.1093/cvr/cvp241 <lb/>23. Miller EJ, Cohen AB, Nagao S, Griffith D, Maunder RJ, Martin TR, et al. <lb/>Elevated levels of NAP-1/interleukin-8 are present in the airspaces of patients with <lb/>the adult respiratory distress syndrome and are associated with increased mortality. <lb/>Am Rev Respir Dis. (1992) 146(2):427-32. doi: 10.1164/ajrccm/146.2.427 <lb/>24. Petreaca ML, Yao M, Liu Y, DeFea K, Martins-Green M. Transactivation of <lb/>vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2 by interleukin-8 (IL-8/CXCL8) is <lb/>required for IL-8/CXCL8-induced endothelial permeability. MBoC. (2007) 18 <lb/>(12):5014-23. doi: 10.1091/mbc.e07-01-0004 <lb/>25. Gessler P, Pfenninger J, Pfammatter JP, Carrel T, Baenziger O, Dahinden C. <lb/>Plasma levels of interleukin-8 and expression of interleukin-8 receptors on <lb/>circulating neutrophils and monocytes after cardiopulmonary bypass in children. <lb/>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2003) 126(3):718-25. doi: 10.1016/s0022-5223(03)00685-8 <lb/>26. Liangos O, Kolyada A, Tighiouart H, Perianayagam MC, Wald R, Jaber BL. <lb/>Interleukin-8 and acute kidney injury following cardiopulmonary bypass: a prospective <lb/>cohort study. Nephron Clin Pract. (2009) 113(3):c148-54. doi: 10.1159/000232595 <lb/>27. Kalfin RE, Engelman RM, Rousou JA, Flack JE, Deaton DW, Kreutzer DL, et al. <lb/>Induction of interleukin-8 expression during cardiopulmonary bypass. Circulation. <lb/>(1993) 88(5 Pt 2):II401-6. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8222186 <lb/>28. Eaton KV, Yang HL, Giachelli CM, Scatena M. Engineering macrophages to <lb/>control the inflammatory response and angiogenesis. Exp Cell Res. (2015) 339 <lb/>(2):300-9. doi: 10.1016/j.yexcr.2015.11.021 <lb/>29. Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, et al. <lb/>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis. Nat Methods. (2012) 9 <lb/>(7):676-82. doi: 10.1038/nmeth.2019 <lb/>30. Wang Q, Zhao L, Xu C, Zhou J, Wu Y. Fusobacterium nucleatum stimulates <lb/>monocyte adhesion to and transmigration through endothelial cells. Arch Oral Biol. <lb/>(2019) 100:86-92. doi: 10.1016/j.archoralbio.2019.02.013 <lb/>31. Natanov R, Gueler F, Falk CS, Kühn C, Maus U, Boyle EC, et al. Blood cytokine <lb/>expression correlates with early multi-organ damage in a mouse model of moderate <lb/>hypothermia with circulatory arrest using cardiopulmonary bypass. PLoS One. <lb/>(2018) 13(10):e0205437. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0205437 <lb/>32. Xing Z, Han J, Hao X, Wang J, Jiang C, Hao Y, et al. Immature monocytes <lb/>contribute to cardiopulmonary bypass-induced acute lung injury by generating <lb/>inflammatory descendants. Thorax. (2016) 72(3):245-55. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-<lb/>2015-208023 <lb/>33. Evans BJ, Haskard DO, Finch JR, Hambleton IR, Landis RC, Taylor KM. The <lb/>inflammatory effect of cardiopulmonary bypass on leukocyte extravasation in vivo. <lb/>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2008) 135(5):999-1006. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2007.08.071 <lb/>34. Vallely MP, Bannon PG, Hughes CF, Kritharides L. Endothelial cell adhesion <lb/>molecules and cardiopulmonary bypass. Asian Cardiovasc Thorac Ann. (2001) 9 <lb/>(4):349-55. doi: 10.1177/021849230100900429 <lb/>35. Rossaint J, Berger C, Van Aken H, Scheld HH, Zahn PK, Rukosujew A, et al. <lb/>Cardiopulmonary bypass during cardiac surgery modulates systemic inflammation <lb/>by affecting different steps of the leukocyte recruitment cascade. PLoS One. (2012) <lb/>7(9):e45738. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0045738 <lb/>36. Tsuchida M, Watanabe H, Watanabe T, Hirahara H, Haga M, Ohzeki H, et al. <lb/>Effect of cardiopulmonary bypass on cytokine release and adhesion molecule <lb/>expression in alveolar macrophages. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. (1997) 156 <lb/>(3):932-8. doi: 10.1164/ajrccm.156.3.9611055 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>37. Sun YJ, Chen WM, Zhang TZ, Cao HJ, Zhou J. Effects of cardiopulmonary <lb/>bypass on tight junction protein expressions in intestinal mucosa of rats. World <lb/>J Gastroenterol. (2008) 14(38):5868. doi: 10.3748/wjg.14.5868 <lb/>38. Baratchi S, Khoshmanesh K, Woodman OL, Potocnik S, Peter K, McIntyre P. <lb/>Molecular sensors of blood flow in endothelial cells. Trends Mol Med. (2017) 23 <lb/>(9):850-68. doi: 10.1016/j.molmed.2017.07.007 <lb/>39. Li A, Varney ML, Valasek J, Godfrey M, Dave BJ, Singh RK. Autocrine role of <lb/>interleukin-8 in induction of endothelial cell proliferation, survival, migration and <lb/>MMP-2 production and angiogenesis. Angiogenesis. (2005) 8(1):63-71. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s10456-005-5208-4 <lb/>40. Bosch I, Xhaja K, Estevez L, Raines G, Melichar H, Warke RV, et al. Increased <lb/>production of interleukin-8 in primary human monocytes and in human epithelial <lb/>and endothelial cell lines after dengue virus challenge. Virol J. (2002) 76 <lb/>(11):5588-97. doi: 10.1128/jvi.76.11.5588-5597.2002 <lb/>41. Nijhuis CSMO, Vellenga E, Daenen SMGJ, Kamps WA, De Bont ESJM. <lb/>Endothelial cells are main producers of interleukin 8 through toll-like receptor 2 <lb/>and 4 signaling during bacterial infection in leukopenic cancer patients. Clin <lb/>Vaccine Immunol. (2003) 10(4):558-63. doi: 10.1128/cdli.10.4.558-563.2003 <lb/>42. Kaplanski G, Teysseire N, Farnarier C, Kaplanski S, Lissitzky JC, Durand JM, <lb/>et al. IL-6 and IL-8 production from cultured human endothelial cells stimulated by <lb/>infection with Rickettsia conorii via a cell-associated IL-1 alpha-dependent pathway. <lb/>JCI. (1995) 96(6):2839-44. doi: 10.1172/jci118354 <lb/>43. Hastings NE, Feaver RE, Lee MY, Wamhoff BR, Blackman BR. Human IL-8 <lb/>regulates smooth muscle cell VCAM-1 expression in response to endothelial cells <lb/>exposed to atheroprone flow. ATVB. (2009) 29(5):725-31. doi: 10.1161/atvbaha.109. <lb/>184382 <lb/>44. Qazi BS, Tang K, Qazi A. Recent advances in underlying pathologies provide <lb/>insight into interleukin-8 expression-mediated inflammation and angiogenesis. Int. <lb/>J Inflamm. (2011) 2011:1-13. doi: 10.4061/2011/908468 <lb/>45. Nilsen EM, Johansen FE, Jahnsen FL, Lundin KEA, Scholz T, Brandtzaeg P, et al. <lb/>Cytokine profiles of cultured microvascular endothelial cells from the human intestine. <lb/>Gut. (1998) 42(5):635-42. doi: 10.1136/gut.42.5.635 <lb/>46. Browning DD, Diehl WC, Hsu MH, Schraufstatter IU, Ye RD. Autocrine <lb/>regulation of interleukin-8 production in human monocytes. Am J Physiol Lung Cell <lb/>Mol Physiol. (2000) 279(6):L1129-36. doi: 10.1152/ajplung.2000.279.6.l1129 <lb/>47. Puchinger J, Ryz S, Nixdorf L, Edlinger-Stanger M, Lassnigg A, Wiedemann D, <lb/>et al. Characteristics of interleukin-6 signaling in elective cardiac surgery-a <lb/>prospective cohort study. J Clin Med. (2022) 11(3):590. doi: 10.3390/jcm11030590 <lb/>48. Howell KW, Cleveland JC, Meng X, Ao L, Su X, Schwartz RS, et al. Interleukin 6 <lb/>production during cardiac surgery correlates with increasing age. J Surg Res. (2016) <lb/>201(1):76-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2015.10.016 <lb/>49. Bauer A, Korten I, Juchem G, Kiesewetter I, Kilger E, Heyn J. Euroscore and IL-6 <lb/>predict the course in ICU after cardiac surgery. Eur J Med Res. (2021) 26(1):26-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1186/s40001-021-00501-1 <lb/>50. Harada A, Sekido N, Akahoshi T, Wada T, Mukaida N, Matsushima K. Essential <lb/>involvement of interleukin-8 (IL-8) in acute inflammation. J Leukoc Biol. (1994) 56 <lb/>(5):559-64. doi: 10.1002/jlb.56.5.559 <lb/>51. Huber AR, Kunkel SL, Todd RF, Weiss SJ. Regulation of rransendothelial <lb/>neutrophil migration by endogenous interleukin-8. Sci. (1991) 254(5028):99-102. <lb/>doi: 10.1126/science.1718038 <lb/>52. Detmers PA, Lo SK, Olsen-Egbert E, Walz A, Baggiolini M, Cohn ZA. <lb/>Neutrophil-activating protein 1/interleukin 8 stimulates the binding activity of the <lb/>leukocyte adhesion receptor CD11b/CD18 on human neutrophils. JEM. (1990) 171 <lb/>(4):1155-62. doi: 10.1084/jem.171.4.1155 <lb/>53. Bréchard S, Bueb JL, Tschirhart EJ. Interleukin-8 primes oxidative burst in <lb/>neutrophil-like HL-60 through changes in cytosolic calcium. Cell Calcium. (2005) <lb/>37(6):531-40. doi: 10.1016/j.ceca.2005.01.019 <lb/>54. Henkels KM, Frondorf K, Gonzalez-Mejia ME, Doseff AL, Gomez-Cambronero <lb/>J. IL-8-induced neutrophil chemotaxis is mediated by Janus kinase 3 (JAK3). FEBS <lb/>Lett. (2010) 585(1):159-66. doi: 10.1016/j.febslet.2010.11.031 <lb/>55. Meniailo ME, Malashchenko VV, Shmarov VA, Gazatova ND, Melashchenko <lb/>OB, Goncharov AG, et al. Interleukin-8 favors pro-inflammatory activity of human <lb/>monocytes/macrophages. Int Immunopharmacol. (2018) 56:217-21. doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>intimp.2018.01.036 <lb/>56. Gerszten RE, Garcia-Zepeda EA, Lim YC, Yoshida M, Ding HA, Gimbrone MA, <lb/>et al. MCP-1 and IL-8 trigger firm adhesion of monocytes to vascular endothelium <lb/>under flow conditions. Nature. (1999) 398(6729):718-23. doi: 10.1038/19546 <lb/>57. Arndt H, Bolanowski MA, Granger DN. Role of interleukin 8 on leucocyte-<lb/>endothelial cell adhesion in intestinal inflammation. Gut. (1996) 38(6):911-5. <lb/>doi: 10.1136/gut.38.6.911 <lb/>58. Li A, Dubey S, Varney ML, Dave BJ, Singh RK. IL-8 directly enhanced endothelial <lb/>cell survival, proliferation, and matrix metalloproteinases production and regulated <lb/>angiogenesis. J Immun. (2003) 170(6):3369-76. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.170.6.3369 <lb/>59. Schraufstatter IU, Chung J, Burger M. IL-8 activates endothelial cell CXCR1 and <lb/>CXCR2 through rho and rac signaling pathways. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. <lb/>(2001) 280(6):L1094-103. doi: 10.1152/ajplung.2001.280.6.l1094 <lb/>60. Wójciak-Stothard B, Williams L, Ridley AJ. Monocyte adhesion and spreading <lb/>on human endothelial cells is dependent on rho-regulated receptor clustering. JCB. <lb/>(1999) 145(6):1293-307. doi: 10.1083/jcb.145.6.1293 <lb/>61. Lai Y, Shen Y, Liu XH, Zhang Y, Zeng Y, Liu YF. Interleukin-8 induces the <lb/>endothelial cell migration through the activation of phosphoinositide 3-kinase-Rac1/ <lb/>RhoA pathway. Int J Biol Sci. (2011) 7(6):782-91. doi: 10.7150/ijbs.7.782 <lb/>62. Gavard J, Hou X, Qu Y, Masedunskas A, Martin D, Weigert R, et al. A role for a <lb/>CXCR2/phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase γ signaling axis in acute and chronic vascular <lb/>permeability. MCB. (2009) 29(9):2469-80. doi: 10.1128/mcb.01304-08 <lb/>63. Manna SK, Ramesh GT. Interleukin-8 induces nuclear transcription factor-κB <lb/>through a TRAF6-dependent pathway. JBC. (2005) 280(8):7010-21. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.m410994200 <lb/>64. Pironkova RP, Giamelli J, Seiden H, Parnell VA, Gruber D, Sison CP, et al. Brain <lb/>injury with systemic inflammation in newborns with congenital heart disease undergoing <lb/>heart surgery. Exp Ther Med. (2017) 14(1):228-38. doi: 10.3892/etm.2017.4493 <lb/>65. Gillinov AM, Davis EA, Curtis WE, Schleien CL, Koehler RC, Gardner TJ, et al. <lb/>Cardiopulmonary bypass and the blood-brain barrier. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. <lb/>(1992) 104(4):1110-5. doi: 10.1016/s0022-5223(19)34699-9 <lb/>66. Schuller AM, Windolf J, Blaheta R, Cinatl J, Kreuter J, Wimmer-Greinecker G, <lb/>et al. Degradation of microvascular brain endothelial cell β-catenin after co-culture <lb/>with activated neutrophils from patients undergoing cardiac surgery with prolonged <lb/>cardiopulmonary bypass. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. (2005) 329(2):616-23. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.02.019 <lb/>67. Chen K, Wang N, Diao Y, Dong W, Sun Y, Liu L, et al. Hydrogen-rich saline <lb/>attenuates brain injury induced by cardiopulmonary bypass and inhibits <lb/>microvascular endothelial cell apoptosis via the PI3K/AKT/GSK3Β signaling <lb/>pathway in rats. Cell Physiol Biochem. (2017) 43(4):1634-47. doi: 10.1159/000484024 <lb/>68. Marcu R, Choi YJ, Xue J, Fortin CL, Wang Y, Nagao RJ, et al. Human organ-<lb/>specific endothelial cell heterogeneity. iScience. (2018) 4:20-35. doi: 10.1016/j.isci. <lb/>2018.05.003 <lb/>69. Przysinda A, Feng W, Li G. Diversity of organism-wide and organ-specific <lb/>endothelial cells. Curr Cardiol Rep. (2020) 22(4):19. doi: 10.1007/s11886-020-1275-9 <lb/>70. Gunawardana H, Romero T, Yao N, Heidt S, Mulder A, Elashoff DA, et al. <lb/>Tissue-specific endothelial cell heterogeneity contributes to unequal inflammatory <lb/>responses. Sci Rep. (2021) 11(1):1949. doi: 10.1038/s41598-020-80102-w <lb/>71. Liu Z, Ruter DL, Quigley K, Tanke NT, Jiang Y, Bautch VL. Single-Cell RNA <lb/>sequencing reveals endothelial cell transcriptome heterogeneity under homeostatic <lb/>laminar flow. ATVB. (2021) 41(10):2575-84. doi: 10.1161/atvbaha.121.316797 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Zhou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1454302 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org </note>


  </text>


  </TEI>