<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T17:23:42.589Z">11/20/2025 5:23:42 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T17:14:52.503425Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T17:14:52.503425Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Unraveling DDIT4 in the <lb/>VDR-mTOR pathway: a novel <lb/>target for drug discovery in <lb/>diabetic kidney disease <lb/>Hai-tao Lu 1 † , Yuan-yuan Jiao 1,2 † , Tian-yu Yu 1 , Jing-xuan Shi 1,3 , <lb/>Jing-wei Tian 4,5 , Gu-ming Zou 1 , Lin Liu 1 and Li Zhuo 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Nephrology, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China, 2 Department of <lb/>Nephrology, Fuwai Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Science, Beijing, China, 3 Institute of Clinical <lb/>Medical Sciences, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, Beijing, China, 4 Department of Nephrology, Beijing <lb/>Sixth Hospital, Beijing, China, 5 Capital Medical University China-Japan Friendship School of Clinical <lb/>Medicine, Beijing, China <lb/>Introduction: Diabetic kidney disease (DKD) necessitates innovative therapeutic <lb/>strategies. This study delves into the role of DNA damage-inducing transcription <lb/>factor 4 (DDIT4) within the VDR-mTOR pathway, aiming to identify a novel target <lb/>for DKD drug discovery. <lb/>Methods: Transcriptome data from the Gene Expression Omnibus Database <lb/>were analyzed to assess the expression of mTOR and VDR expression in human <lb/>renal tissues. Clinical samples from DKD patients and minimal change disease <lb/>(MCD) controls were examined, and a DKD animal model using 20-week-old db/ <lb/>db mice was established. DDIT4 plasmid transfection was employed to modulate <lb/>the VDR-mTOR pathway, with its components evaluated using <lb/>immunohistochemistry, real-time quantitative PCR (qRT-PCR), Western <lb/>blotting, and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). <lb/>Results: Changes in the expression of the VDR-mTOR pathway were observed in <lb/>both DKD patients and the animal model. Overexpression of DDIT4 increased <lb/>VDR expression and decreased levels of mTOR, p70s6k, and 4E-BP1. <lb/>Furthermore, DDIT4 treatment regulated autophagy by upregulating LC3I <lb/>expression and downregulating LC3II expression. Notably, DDIT4 alleviated <lb/>oxidative stress by reducing the levels of lipid peroxidation product MDA, <lb/>while simultaneously increasing the levels of superoxide dismutase (SOD) and <lb/>glutathione (GSH), underscoring the role of DDIT4 in the pathological process of <lb/>DKD and its potential as a therapeutic target. <lb/>Conclusion: Unraveling DDIT4&apos;s involvement in the VDR-mTOR pathway <lb/>provides insights for innovative DKD drug discovery, emphasizing its potential <lb/>as a therapeutic target for future interventions. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>diabetic kidney disease (DKD), DNA damage inducing transcription factor 4 (DDIT4), <lb/>vitamin D receptor, mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signal pathway, autophagy, <lb/>oxidative stress <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Md Abdul Hye Khan, <lb/>University of Missouri, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Fang-Fang He, <lb/>Huazhong University of Science and <lb/>Technology, China <lb/>Praghalathan Kanthakumar, <lb/>University of Missouri, United States <lb/>Purnima Singh, <lb/>University of Tennessee Health Science Center <lb/>(UTHSC), United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Li Zhuo, <lb/>belindazhl@aliyun.com <lb/> † <lb/>These authors have contributed equally to this <lb/>work and share first authorship <lb/>RECEIVED 25 November 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 06 March 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 19 March 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Lu H-t, Jiao Y-y, Yu T-y, Shi J-x, Tian J-w, <lb/>Zou G-m, Liu L and Zhuo L (2024), Unraveling <lb/>DDIT4 in the VDR-mTOR pathway: a novel <lb/>target for drug discovery in diabetic <lb/>kidney disease. <lb/>Front. Pharmacol. 15:1344113. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Lu, Jiao, Yu, Shi, Tian, Zou, Liu and Zhuo. <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under <lb/>the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic practice. <lb/>No use, distribution or reproduction is <lb/>permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/>Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 19 March 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The global diabetes incidence is rising sharply, becoming a <lb/>major public health challenge. Projections estimate around <lb/>537 million adults with diabetes worldwide by 2021, with China <lb/>leading at an expected 140.9 million cases (Edition, 2022). This <lb/>upward trend is expected to continue, with an estimated rise to <lb/>174.4 million diabetic patients in China by 2045 (Sun et al., 2022). <lb/>Diabetic complications vary widely, with Diabetic Kidney Disease <lb/>(DKD) being a key microvascular complication marked by edema, <lb/>proteinuria, and declining renal function, which may lead to renal <lb/>failure and end-stage renal disease (ESRD) (Afkarian et al., 2016; <lb/>Afkarian et al., 2016). Existing therapeutic strategies, encompassing <lb/>blood sugar control, lipid regulation, and blood pressure <lb/>management, face limitations in effectively slowing DKD <lb/>progression (Alicic and Nicholas, 2022). Microalbuminuria, a key <lb/>indicator of DKD progression and an independent predictor of renal <lb/>function deterioration, underscores the importance of controlling <lb/>albuminuria as a crucial strategy to impede DKD advancement (, <lb/>2020), (McGrath and Edi, 2019; Barrera-Chimal and Jaisser, 2020). <lb/>Recent studies highlight vitamin D and its receptor (VDR) agonists, <lb/>like calcitriol and paricalcitol, as potentially effective in reducing <lb/>proteinuria in DKD patients (Song et al., 2021). Vitamin D, a fat-<lb/>soluble steroid derivative, undergoes metabolism into its active form, <lb/>1.25(OH) 2 D 3 (Abasheva et al., 2022). Emerging evidence suggests that <lb/>1.25(OH) 2 D 3 may impede the mammalian target of rapamycin <lb/>(mTOR) signaling pathway by upregulating DNA damage-inducible <lb/>transcript 4 (DDIT4) (Yang et al., 2015; Wang et al., 2016), presenting <lb/>potential avenues for halting DKD progression. Moreover, oxidative <lb/>stress elevation and diminished antioxidant capacity contribute to <lb/>diabetic renal injury (Li et al., 2021; Yang and Yang, 2022). Selective <lb/>autophagy mediated by nuclear receptor coactivator 4 (NCOA4), <lb/>indicated by ferritin degradation, demonstrates an association with <lb/>DKD (Fuhrmann et al., 2020; Stockwell, 2022). <lb/>DDIT4, also known as regulated in development and DNA damage <lb/>response 1 (REDD1) or Di92, located on human chromosome 10, <lb/>responds to various stimuli, playing pivotal roles in hypoxia, cell <lb/>damage, and diverse stress conditions (Wang et al., 2019; Ding <lb/>et al., 2021; Miller et al., 2021). This highly conserved gene exhibits <lb/>increased expression in response to hypoxia, oxidative stress, DNA <lb/>damage, and other stressors, influencing processes like autophagy, <lb/>apoptosis, and energy stress (Wang et al., 2019; Ding et al., 2021; <lb/>Miller et al., 2021). Our preliminary research implies that modulating <lb/>DDIT4 could impact mTOR signaling (Chen et al., 2018a), suggesting <lb/>its potential importance in VDR-related pathways and autophagy <lb/>regulation. This study aims to elucidate DDIT4 expression changes <lb/>and VDR-related pathway activation in DKD patients and experimental <lb/>mouse models while exploring DDIT4&apos;s role in DKD treatment and its <lb/>impact on autophagy. The findings offer potential novel therapeutic <lb/>strategies for managing DKD. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Experimental design <lb/>We obtained mTOR and VDR transcriptional expression data <lb/>for human renal tissue from the Gene Expression Omnibus <lb/>Database (GSE142025). Clinical samples from DKD patients and <lb/>minimal change disease (MCD) patients served as controls. <lb/>Additionally, 20-week-old male SPF db/db mice and their <lb/>littermates were used as an animal model of DKD. The study <lb/>received approval from the Human Ethics Review Committee of <lb/>the China-Japan Friendship Hospital (Approval Number: 2018-45-<lb/>K34). All volunteers provided their informed consent and signed the <lb/>necessary documents. All animal experiments complied with <lb/>ARRIVE guidelines and the U.K. Animals (Scientific Procedures) <lb/>Act of 1986. <lb/>The study followed these steps: <lb/>1) Transcriptome data analysis: Gene set enrichment analysis <lb/>(GSEA) was performed to analyze mTOR and VDR in the <lb/>transcriptional dataset. <lb/>2) Histological analysis: Kidney tissue samples from both human <lb/>patients and mouse models were subjected to Periodic acid <lb/>Schiff (PAS) staining to assess tissue pathology and <lb/>glomerulosclerosis. <lb/>3) Immunohistochemical (IHC) staining: Molecular expression <lb/>of mTOR, 4E-BP1, p70s6k and VDR was examined in clinical <lb/>and mouse kidney tissues. <lb/>4) Cell Culture: MPC5 and SV40-MES-13 cell lines were <lb/>cultured under high-glucose conditions to create a <lb/>diabetic model, followed by cell transfection with the <lb/>DDIT4 plasmid. <lb/>5) Autophagy analysis: Detection of autophagy marker proteins. <lb/>6) Molecular analysis: qRT-PCR and Western blotting were <lb/>conducted to measure gene and protein expression levels. <lb/>7) Oxidative stress assessment: ELISA was used to measure the <lb/>activities of MDA, SOD, and GSH in cells. <lb/>2.2 Transcriptome data of mTOR and VDR in <lb/>human renal tissue <lb/>All transcriptional expression levels of mTOR and VDR in renal <lb/>tissue from DKD and normal patients were obtained from the Gene <lb/>Expression Omnibus Database (GSE142025) at the following link: <lb/>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/. <lb/>2.3 Periodic acid schiff (PAS) staining <lb/>Mouse kidney tissue was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, <lb/>embedded, and sectioned at 4 μm thickness. The slices were <lb/>dewaxed with xylene, hydrated with a gradient of ethanol, <lb/>stained with alcian blue dye for 10-20 min, oxidized with 1% <lb/>periodate for 5 min, stained with Schiff dye for 10-20 min, <lb/>counterstained with hematoxylin dye for 1-2 min, differentiated <lb/>with a 1% hydrochloric acid ethanol solution for 2-3 s, turned blue <lb/>with ammonia for 3min, dehydrated with gradient ethanol, and <lb/>made transparent with dimethylbenzene. After sealing with <lb/>neutral gum, slices were examined and photographed <lb/>microscopically. PAS scoring criteria are as follows: 0 point, no <lb/>sclerosis; 1 point, ≤10% glomerulosclerosis; 2 points, 10%-25% <lb/>glomerulosclerosis; 3 points, 25%-50% glomerulosclerosis; <lb/>4 points, &gt;50% glomerulosclerosis. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>2.4 Immunohistochemical (IHC) staining <lb/>Clinical kidney samples and mouse kidney tissues were fixed <lb/>with 4% paraformaldehyde, and after paraffin embedding, <lb/>continuous sectioning was performed at a thickness of 4 μM. The <lb/>slices were rehydrated with gradient ethanol solution, repaired with <lb/>citrate antigen repair solution at 95 °C for 15min, inactivated with <lb/>H 2 O 2 at room temperature for 10min, permeabilized with 0.1% <lb/>Triton X-100 at room temperature for 10min, and blocked with a 5% <lb/>BSA sealing solution at 37 °C for 1 h. Subsequently, we applied <lb/>primary antibodies (mTOR, 4E-BP1, p70s6k, and VDR) dropwise <lb/>and incubated them at 37 °C for 2 h. The corresponding secondary <lb/>antibodies were then added dropwise and incubated at room <lb/>temperature for 20 min, The DAB chromogenic agent was then <lb/>added for 5-10 min, and the reaction was terminated using <lb/>hydrogen peroxide and hematoxylin was used for nuclear <lb/>staining for 1 min. Gradient ethanol dehydration, xylene <lb/>transparent, drop neutral gum film, the stained slices were <lb/>observed under a microscope and photographed. <lb/>2.5 Cell culture <lb/>MPC5 cells, cultured in DMEM high-glucose medium, were <lb/>treated with 10% FBS, 1% penicillin-streptomycin, and 10U/mL γ-<lb/>interferon. When the cells covered 70%-80% of the bottom area of <lb/>the bottle, cells were collected to remove γ-Interferon. MPC5 cells <lb/>were further cultured and induced to differentiate for 1-2 weeks. <lb/>The differentiated and mature MPC5 cells were used in subsequent <lb/>experiments. SV40-MES-13 cells were cultured in DMEM/ <lb/>F12 medium containing 10% FBS and 1% penicillin <lb/>streptomycin. The cells were cultured in a 5% CO 2 incubator at <lb/>37 °C for standby. <lb/>2.6 Single gene GSEA pathway analysis <lb/>We performed Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) for mTOR <lb/>and VDR using clusterProfiler, limma, ggplot2, enrichplot, and <lb/>patchwork packages on dataset GSE142025, with p &lt; <lb/>0.05 indicating statistical significance. <lb/>2.7 Cell transfection <lb/>Take MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells in logarithmic growth <lb/>period, and adjust the cell density to 1 × 10 6 cells/dish, inoculated in <lb/>10 cm culture dish, 10 mL for each dish. MPC5 and SV40-MES-<lb/>13 cells in logarithmic growth were adjusted to a density of 1 × 10 6 <lb/>cells/dish and inoculated in 10 cm dishes with 10 mL medium each. <lb/>When the cell fusion degree is 80%-90%, the basic culture medium <lb/>(without added serum) is used to prepare the DDIT4 transfection <lb/>complex according to the operating guide of Lipofectamine <lb/>2000 reagent. The transfection complex was added to MPC5 cells <lb/>and SV40-MES-13 cells and replaced with complete medium after <lb/>6 h. MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells transfected with <lb/>DDIT4 were harvested 24 h later. <lb/>2.8 Cell grouping <lb/>MPC5 and SV40-MES-13 cells were categorized into four <lb/>groups: Control (5.5 mmol glucose and 19.5 mmol mannitol), HG <lb/>(25 mmol glucose), HG + OE-NC (25 mmol glucose with blank <lb/>plasmid), and HG + OE-DDIT4 (25 mmol glucose with <lb/>DDIT4 plasmid). <lb/>2.9 Transmission electron microscope <lb/>Following 24 and 48 h post-treatment, MPC5 and SV40-MES-<lb/>13 cells were prepared for observation under a transmission electron <lb/>microscope. Centrifuge the cells at 3000 rpm at low speed to collect <lb/>the precipitation. After PBS cleaning twice, add 2.5% glutaraldehyde <lb/>to fix for 2-4 h. Cell samples were pre embedded in 3% low melting <lb/>point agar, rinsed with 0.1 M phosphoric acid rinse solution for <lb/>3 times, and then placed in 1% osmic acid for 4 °C fixation for 2 h. <lb/>The samples were successively dehydrated in 30%, 50%, 70%, 80%, <lb/>95%, and 100% ethanol, and then 100% propylene oxide was added <lb/>for 3 times. Penetrate the embedded sample with epoxy propane and <lb/>the embedding solution at room temperature, and treat it at 60 °C for <lb/>48 h to make the resin fully polymerized. The ultrathin microtome <lb/>was used to slice at 70nm, and 3% uranium acetate saturated ethanol <lb/>solution was used for staining for 8 min, then 2.7% lead citrate <lb/>solution was used for staining for 8 min. Observe and take photos <lb/>under the transmission electron microscope. <lb/>2.10 Laser confocal <lb/>MPC5 and SV40-MES-13 cells in logarithmic phase were <lb/>adjusted to 0.8 × 10 4 cells/dish and seeded in 96-well plates, with <lb/>100 μL per well. Cell transfection and grouping treatment are the <lb/>same as 2.2.4 and 2.2.5. After 48 h of grouping treatment, <lb/>MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells were collected for laser <lb/>confocal microscope observation. Cells were fixed with 4% <lb/>paraformaldehyde and stained with DAPI. Observe and take <lb/>photos under laser confocal microscope. <lb/>2.11 qRT-PCR <lb/>MPC5 and SV40-MES-13 cells in the logarithmic growth phase <lb/>were adjusted to a density of 2 × 10 5 cells/dish and seeded into 12-<lb/>well plates, with 1 mL medium per well. Cell transfection and <lb/>grouping treatment are the same as 2.2.4 and 2.2.5. After 48 h of <lb/>grouping treatment, MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells were <lb/>collected for qRT-PCR detection. Each group of cells was added <lb/>with corresponding amount of Trizol lysate to lyse cells and extract <lb/>total RNA from cells. After the total RNA was reverse transcribed <lb/>into cDNA, it was amplified by real-time fluorescence quantitative <lb/>PCR. The total PCR reaction system is 20 µ L: SYBR Green Mix 10 µ <lb/>L, upstream primer 0.4 µ L, downstream primer 0.4 µ L, dd H 2 O <lb/>7.2 µ L, cDNA template 2 µ L. PCR reaction conditions: 94 °C pre <lb/>denaturation for 10 min, 1 cycle; denatured at 94 °C for 20s, annealed <lb/>at 55 °C for 20s, extended at 72 °C for 20s, 40 cycles in total. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>2.12 Western blotting <lb/>Cells from each group were lysed on ice using RIPA buffer <lb/>containing 1% PMSF to extract total protein. The protein <lb/>concentration was determined with BCA kit. The loading mass <lb/>of each pore protein is 30 μ g. Sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) -<lb/>polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) was used for <lb/>electrophoresis, and the protein was transferred to PVDF <lb/>membrane. After 5% BSA was sealed at room temperature for <lb/>1h, rabbit anti VDR (1:1000), rabbit anti mTOR (1:1000), rabbit <lb/>anti p70s6k (1:1000), rabbit anti 4E-BP (1:1000), rabbit anti LC3II <lb/>(1:1000), and rabbit anti LC3I (1:1000) antibodies were added <lb/>respectively. After incubation at 4 °C overnight, the secondary <lb/>antibody corresponding to the primary antibody was added and <lb/>incubated at room temperature for 2 h. ECL luminous solution <lb/>develops color and collects images. GAPDH is the <lb/>internal parameter. <lb/>2.13 ELISA <lb/>Cellular activities of malondialdehyde (MDA), superoxide <lb/>dismutase (SOD), and glutathione (GSH) were measured using <lb/>ELISA kits from Dojindo Company. All tests were carried out in <lb/>strict accordance with the instructions of the kit. <lb/>2.14 Data analysis <lb/>Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 22.0, with data <lb/>presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). The significance <lb/>between multiple groups were determined by one-way variance <lb/>(ANOVA) analysis and LSD post hoc multiple comparison test. <lb/>P &lt; 0.05 means the difference is statistically significant. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Differential expression of mTOR and VDR <lb/>in renal tissues of DKD patients: <lb/>Upregulation of mTOR and downregulation <lb/>of VDR <lb/>The mRNA expressions of mTOR in renal tissue of DKD <lb/>patients were overexpressed compared with control group and has <lb/>a great significance (p &lt; 0.001), the mRNA expressions of VDR <lb/>were decreased in DKD group and has a statistical significance <lb/>compared with control group (p &lt; 0.05) (Figure 1). <lb/>3.2 Structural abnormalities and VDR-mTOR <lb/>signaling pathway changes in DKD patient <lb/>kidney samples <lb/>To investigate alterations in the VDR-mTOR pathway in human <lb/>samples, clinical specimens were subjected to PAS staining and IHC <lb/>staining. Consistent with the aforementioned findings, the average <lb/>glomerular area and the relative area of glomerular extracellular <lb/>matrix in DKD patients increased compared with MCD patients <lb/>(Figure 2). According to the PAS scoring criteria, the <lb/>glomerulosclerosis score of clinical DKD samples was <lb/>significantly higher at 3.33 (n = 3) compared to the <lb/>glomerulosclerosis score of MCD samples, which was 1.33 (n = <lb/>3) (p &lt; 0.05). In addition, IHC results showed that the expression of <lb/>mTOR, p70s6k, 4E-BP1 in DKD patients was significantly higher <lb/>than that in MCD patients, and the expression of VDR was <lb/>significantly lower than that in MCD patients (Figure 2). These <lb/>results suggest that there is renal pathological damage in diabetes <lb/>nephropathy, which may be related to mTOR/4E-<lb/>BP1 signaling pathway. <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Transcriptional expression results of mTOR and VDR in renal tissue of Human. (A) The mRNA expressions of mTOR in renal tissue of DKD patients <lb/>were overexpressed compared with control group and has a great significance (p &lt; 0.001) (B) The mRNA expressions of VDR were decreased in DKD <lb/>group and has a statistical significance compared with control group (p &lt; 0.05). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>3.3 Decline in renal function and metabolic <lb/>abnormalities in DKD model mice <lb/>At the animal level biochemical markers were employed to <lb/>investigate the progression of DKD in db/db mice. As shown in <lb/>Table 1, the GFR of db/db model mice at 8 weeks of age (471.7 ± <lb/>75.8 μL/min) was higher than that of the m/m normal control mice <lb/>(250.3 ± 60.7 μL/min). The GFR further increased significantly at <lb/>20 weeks of age. Urinary microalbumin in the db/db model group at <lb/>20 weeks of age (0.060 ± 0.014 mg) was significantly higher than in <lb/>the m/m normal control group (0.010 ± 0.001 mg) (p &lt; 0.05). <lb/>Fasting blood glucose (FBG) in the db/db model group at <lb/>20 weeks of age (25.9 ± 6.5 mmol/L) was higher than in the m/m <lb/>normal control group (7.0 ± 0.4 mmol/L) (p &lt; 0.05). In conclusion, <lb/>at the age of 20 weeks, db/db mice exhibited significant disparities in <lb/>GFR, u-mAlb and FBG, demonstrating characteristic biochemical <lb/>alterations associated with DKD. <lb/>Given concerns about the potential influence of body size on <lb/>GFR measurements, it is crucial to consider that while db/db mice <lb/>generally have a larger body size, the pronounced increase in GFR <lb/>and altered urine volume primarily reflect the underlying diabetic <lb/>pathology rather than size differences alone. This study&apos;s findings, <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>PAS staining and IHC staining results of clinical kidney samples (4QOx). The results of PAS staining showed that compared with patients with minimal <lb/>change disease, patients with diabetic nephropathy had hyperplasia of glomerular mesangium, thickened base-ment membrane, hypertrophy of <lb/>glomeruli, and formation of K-W nodules. The results of IHC staining showed that compared with MCD patients, the expression of VDR in the kidney <lb/>tissues of DKD patients was reduced, and the expression of mTOR and downstream signaling pathway proteins was increased. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>including the differential urine volume collected over 12 h for <lb/>albumin measurements, underscore the diabetic nephropathy <lb/>model&apos;s validity in db/db mice, revealing significant biochemical <lb/>markers indicative of DKD. <lb/>3.4 Kidney damage and VDR-mTOR <lb/>signaling pathway variations in DKD <lb/>model mice <lb/>The renal tissues of the experimental mice were stained with <lb/>PAS. The results showed that the capillary loops of the glomerulus of <lb/>the 20 weeks old m/m mice were thin and clear, and there were no <lb/>abnormal pathological changes in the renal structure. Compared <lb/>with m/m mice, there were irregular nodular PAS positive material <lb/>deposits in the glomeruli of 20 weeks old db/db mice, glomerular <lb/>mesangial matrix hyperplasia, and basement membrane thickening <lb/>(Figure 3). The results confirmed the successful construction of the <lb/>DKD animal model, with characteristic pathological changes <lb/>observed in kidney tissue of 20-week-old db/db mice. In the <lb/>DKD model group, db/db mice exhibited a PAS <lb/>glomerulosclerosis score of 3.66 (n = 3), which was significantly <lb/>higher than the glomerulosclerosis score of 1.33 (n = 3) observed in <lb/>the control group m/m samples (p &lt; 0.05). In addition, IHC results <lb/>showed that compared with m/m mice, the expression of mTOR, <lb/>p70s6k, 4E-BP1 in db/db mice was significantly increased, and the <lb/>expression of VDR was significantly reduced (Figure 3). The <lb/>findings are consistent with the results of bioinformatics analysis, <lb/>indicating a significant perturbation in the VDR-mTOR <lb/>pathway in DKD. <lb/>3.5 High glucose induces significant <lb/>organelle damage in podocytes and <lb/>mesangial cells <lb/>In order to simulate DKD injury and further elucidate the <lb/>regulatory mechanism of the VDR-mTOR pathway, as well as <lb/>develop appropriate regulatory strategies, we established an <lb/>in vitro cell model of DKD using high glucose culture conditions. <lb/>The cellular and substructural differences were subsequently <lb/>examined through transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The <lb/>transmission electron microscopy results revealed that MPC5 and <lb/>SV40-MES-13 cells exposed to high glucose exhibited significant <lb/>mitochondrial swelling, ridgeline dissolution, vesicular expansion of <lb/>endoplasmic reticulum compared to the control group. The findings <lb/>suggest that podocyte and mesangial cells undergo damage in a high <lb/>glucose environment. Moreover, these changes were more <lb/>pronounced at 48 h than at 24 h (Figure 4). The results showed <lb/>that podocytes and mesangial cells were damaged by high glucose. <lb/>3.6 Visualization of DDIT4 plasmid <lb/>transfection efficiency <lb/>To investigate the protective effect of DDIT4 on a cell model of <lb/>diabetic kidney disease (DKD) and its regulatory role in the VDR-<lb/>mTOR pathway, we performed cell transfection experiments using <lb/>an EGFP-tagged DDIT4 plasmid and utilized laser confocal <lb/>microscopy to visualize the transfection efficiency. Laser confocal <lb/>results showed that in MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells, <lb/>compared with Control group and HG group, HG + OE-NC <lb/>group and HG + OE-DDIT4 group had obvious green <lb/>fluorescence, indicating that plasmid transfection cells were <lb/>successful (Figure 5). In addition, the expression of green <lb/>fluorescence in the HG + OE-DDIT4 group was lower than that <lb/>in the HG + OE-NC group (Figure 5), which confirmed that <lb/>DDIT4 may participate in the pathogenesis of diabetic kidney <lb/>disease and improve the pathological damage of diabetic kidney <lb/>disease. The green fluorescence observed in the HG + OE-DDIT4 <lb/>and HG + OE-NC groups serves as a marker of transfection <lb/>efficiency, <lb/>demonstrating <lb/>successful <lb/>delivery <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>DDIT4 plasmid into cells. The reduced fluorescence intensity in <lb/>the HG + OE-DDIT4 group compared to the HG + OE-NC group <lb/>suggests not only successful transfection but also a subsequent <lb/>cellular response, potentially indicative of DDIT4 exerting its <lb/>protective effects in a high-glucose environment. <lb/>3.7 DDIT4 promotes recovery and growth of <lb/>damaged cells <lb/>Light field cell filming showed that MPC cells and SV40-MES-<lb/>13 cells cultured in high glucose had significant damage compared <lb/>with normal cells, and DDIT4 transfected cells cultured in high <lb/>glucose had mild damage. As can be seen from the fluorescence map, <lb/>the plasmid was successfully transferred into the cells, and the <lb/>transfection effect was better at 48 h (Figure 6). <lb/>3.8 DDIT4 modulates the VDR-mTOR <lb/>pathway to counteract high glucose-<lb/>induced damage <lb/>To investigate the expression of the VDR-mTOR pathway in a <lb/>cellular model of DKD and elucidate the regulatory mechanism of <lb/>DDIT4 on this pathway, we employed quantitative real-time PCR <lb/>(qRT-PCR) and Western Blotting (WB) to assess both the gene and <lb/>TABLE 1 GFR, urinary microalbumin, and fasting blood glucose results of <lb/>mice at different ages. <lb/>8w (n = 6) <lb/>20w (n = 6) <lb/>GFR (uL/min) <lb/>db/db <lb/>471.7 ± 75.8 <lb/>774.1 ± 90.3 <lb/>m/m <lb/>250.3 ± 60.7 <lb/>209.1 ± 37.4 <lb/>u-mAlb(mg) <lb/>db/db <lb/>0.020 ± 0.008 <lb/>0.060 ± 00.014* <lb/>m/m <lb/>0.010 ± 0.008 <lb/>0.010 ± 0.001 <lb/>FBG (mmol/L) <lb/>db/db <lb/>11.5 ± 3.7 <lb/>25.9 ± 6.5* <lb/>m/m <lb/>5.1 ± 1.3 <lb/>7.0 ± 0.4 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>protein expression within the pathway. The results of qRT-PCR <lb/>showed that in MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells, the expressions <lb/>of DDIT4 and VDR in HG group were significantly lower than those <lb/>in Control group (p &lt; 0.01), while the expressions of mTOR, p70s6k <lb/>and 4E-BP1 were significantly higher than those in Control group <lb/>(p &lt; 0.01) (Figure 7); Compared with HG group, the expression of <lb/>DDIT4 and VDR in HG + OE-DDIT4 group increased significantly <lb/>(p &lt; 0.01), while the expression of mTOR, p70s6k, 4E-BP1 decreased <lb/>significantly (p &lt; 0.01, p &lt; 0.05) (Figure 8). DDIT4 is an important <lb/>target of VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E-BP1 signaling pathway induced <lb/>by high glucose in diabetic nephropathy. <lb/>3.9 DDIT4 enhances autophagy by <lb/>modulating LC3I and LC3II expression <lb/>To further elucidate the underlying mechanism of DDIT4&apos;s <lb/>impact on cellular damage, we conducted an investigation into <lb/>the expression levels of autophagy marker proteins LC3I and <lb/>LC3II. Our results showed that compared to the Control group, <lb/>HG group MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells had significantly <lb/>decreased expression of LC3I (p &lt; 0.01) but increased expression <lb/>of LC3II (p &lt; 0.01). However, after OE-DDIT4 treatment under high <lb/>glucose conditions, was a significant increase in LC3I <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>PAS staining and IHC staining results of kidney tissue of experimental mice (400x). The results of PAS staining showed no abnormal pathological <lb/>changes in the kidney structure of the 20 weeks old m/m mice. Compared with m/m mice, db/db mice at the same age had hyperplasia of glome-rular <lb/>mesangium, thickened basement membrane, and hypertrophy of glomeruli. IHC staining results showed that the expression of VDR in the kidney tissue of <lb/>db/db mice was reduced, and the expression of mTOR and downstream signaling pathway proteins was increased. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>expression relative to HG group (p &lt; 0.01), accompanied by a <lb/>significant decrease in LC3II levels (p &lt; 0.05), indicating that <lb/>DDIT4 <lb/>enhances <lb/>autophagy <lb/>in <lb/>a <lb/>high <lb/>glucose <lb/>environment (Figure 9). <lb/>3.10 GSEA pathway anslysis reveals DDIT4-<lb/>regulated mechanisms in VDR and <lb/>mTOR signaling <lb/>Next, we performed GSEA pathway analysis to enrich the <lb/>associated pathways of VDR and mTOR based on the <lb/>differential expression of genes between high and low <lb/>expression groups. In the GSEA analysis of mTOR, several <lb/>significant pathways emerged, including ascorbate and aldarate <lb/>metabolism, histidine metabolism, and neutrophil extracellular <lb/>trap formation, among others, which differentiated the high <lb/>mTOR expression group from the low mTOR expression <lb/>group (Figure 10A). <lb/>Similarly, in the GSEA analysis of VDR, notable enriched <lb/>pathways encompassed ascorbate and aldarate metabolism, <lb/>glycine, serine, and threonine metabolism, glyoxylate and <lb/>dicarboxylate <lb/>metabolism, <lb/>pentose, <lb/>and <lb/>glucuronate <lb/>interconversions, as well as proximal tubule bicarbonate <lb/>reclamation, distinguishing the high VDR expression group from <lb/>the low VDR expression group (Figure 10B). Both mTOR and VDR <lb/>GSEA pathway analyses highlighted essential biochemical processes <lb/>influenced by DDIT4. <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Transmission electron microscope observation results of MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells (500Qx). (A) The results of transmission electron <lb/>microscopy in MPC5 cells. (B) The results of transmission electron microscopy in SV40-MES-13 cells. <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Laser confocal results of MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells. (A) Laser confocal results in MPC5 cells. (B) Laser confocal results in SV40-MES-13 cells. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>3.11 DDIT4 modulates oxidative stress levels <lb/>through VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E-<lb/>BP1 signaling pathway <lb/>To establish the association with cellular oxidative stress levels, <lb/>the oxidative stress-related markers MDA, SOD, and GSH were <lb/>quantified using ELISA methodology. The ELISA results <lb/>demonstrated a significant increase in MDA expression (p &lt; <lb/>0.01) and a significant decrease in SOD and GSH expression <lb/>(p &lt; 0.01) in both MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells when <lb/>compared to the control group. Furthermore, the HG + OE-<lb/>DDIT4 group exhibited a significant reduction in MDA <lb/>expression (p &lt; 0.05) along with a notable increase in SOD and <lb/>GSH expression (p &lt; 0.05), as compared to the HG group <lb/>(Figure 11). The findings are consistent with the results of gene <lb/>set enrichment analysis (GSEA), indicating that DDIT4 may <lb/>modulate cellular oxidative stress levels through involvement in <lb/>the VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E-BP1 signaling pathway, thereby <lb/>ameliorating pathological damage associated with diabetic <lb/>nephropathy. <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>MPC5 cells and SV40-MES-13 cells modeling and transfection. (A) The results of cell transfection in MPC5 cells. (B) The results of cell transfection in <lb/>SV40-MES-13 cells. <lb/>FIGURE 7 <lb/>qRT-PCR results of MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells. (A) The expressions of DDIT4. (B) The expressions of VDR. (C) The expressions of mTOR. (D) <lb/>The expressions of p70s6k. (E) The expressions of 4E-BP1. pp p &lt; 0.01, compared with Control group; #p &lt; 0.05, ##p&lt;0.01, compared with HG <lb/>group. The experiments were independently repl cated three times to ensure the reproducibility and accuracy. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>4 Discussion <lb/>The development of DKD is multifaceted, encompassing glucose <lb/>metabolism disturbances, hemodynamic alterations, cytokine <lb/>expression, oxidative stress, inflammation, and immune <lb/>responses. (Thomas et al., 2015; Tang and Yiu, 2020). Due to the <lb/>complex pathogenesis of DKD involving numerous factors, there is <lb/>currently no specific method for prevention and treatment (Sharov <lb/>et al., 2022). The characteristic pathological features of DKD include <lb/>diffuse thickening of glomerular capillary basement membrane, <lb/>proliferation of mesangial cells and mesangial matrix, and then <lb/>nodular sclerosis (Thomas, 2021). The destruction of glomerular <lb/>filtration membrane structure is the common mechanism <lb/>underlying various glomerular diseases characterized by <lb/>proteinuria. Podocytes, key components of the glomerular <lb/>filtration membrane, are significantly correlated with DKD&apos;s <lb/>onset and progression (Lassén et al., 2022; Zang et al., 2022). <lb/>Under normal conditions, podocytes show increased autophagic <lb/>activity, facilitating organelle renewal and self-metabolism. <lb/>However, in diabetic patients, detrimental factors such as <lb/>elevated glucose levels and metabolites collaborate with podocytes <lb/>often resulting in the accumulation of damaged proteins and <lb/>organelles in cells (Fu et al., 2020). Failure to clear these <lb/>substances promptly leads to cytotoxicity and an irreversible <lb/>decrease in viable cell count. (Dai et al., 2017). The glomerulus <lb/>serves as the characteristic site of renal pathological damage in DKD <lb/>disease. The 2010 pathological staging system for DKD established <lb/>by the Society of Renal Pathology primarily focuses on glomerular <lb/>disorders (Tervaert et al., 2010). In this study, db/db mice were <lb/>utilized to establish an animal model of diabetic kidney disease <lb/>(DKD). The results of glomerular filtration rate (GFR), urinary <lb/>microalbuminuria, and fasting blood glucose levels were consistent <lb/>with the expected changes in biochemical indicators of DKD and <lb/>significantly differed from those observed in control m/m mice. <lb/>Kidney tissue samples from 20-week-old db/db mice, m/m mice, as <lb/>well as patients with minimal change disease (MCD) and DKD <lb/>underwent PAS staining to observe significant physiological <lb/>changes. Immunohistochemical staining was performed to <lb/>analyze the expressions of VDR, mTOR, p70s6k, and 4E-BP1 <lb/>proteins in the VDR-mTOR pathway. Our findings suggest that <lb/>FIGURE 8 <lb/>(A) Western Blotting for VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E -BP1 protein expression in MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells. (A) Western blots of protein <lb/>expressionin MPC5 cells as indicated. (B) Western blots of protein expression in SV40-MES•13 cells as indicated. (C) The relative protein expression of VDR <lb/>to GAPOH. (D) The relat ve protein expression of mTOR to GAPOH. (E) The relative protein expression of p70s6k to GAPDH. (F) The relative protein <lb/>expression of 4E-BP1 to GAPOH. pp &lt; 0.05, ppp &lt; 0.01, compared with Control group; #p &lt; 0.05,##p&lt;0.01, compared with HG group. The <lb/>experiments were independently replicated three times to ensure the reproducibility and accuracy. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>renal pathological injury associated with DKD may be linked to the <lb/>mTOR/4E-BP1 signaling pathway, the result is consistent with <lb/>previous studies. <lb/>Recent research has shown VDR inhibits the mTOR signaling <lb/>pathway by enhancing DDIT4 expression, thereby hindering DKD <lb/>progression (Yang et al., 2015; Shi et al., 2022). mTOR, a serine/ <lb/>FIGURE 9 <lb/>Western Blotting for LC31 and LC311 protein expression in MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells. (A) Western blots of protein expression in MPC5 cells <lb/>asindicated. (B) Western blots of protein expression in SV40-MES-13 cells as indicated. (C) The relative protein expression of LC31to GAPDH. (D) The <lb/>relative protein expression of LC311 to GAPDH. p p &lt; 0.05, pp p &lt; 0.01, compared with Control group; #p &lt; 0.05, ##p &lt; 0.01, compared with HG <lb/>group. The experiments were independently replicated three times to ensure the reproducibility and accuracy. <lb/>FIGURE 10 <lb/>GSEA pathway analysis of mTOR and VDR. (A) GSEA of mTOR (B) GSEA of VOR. Both mTOR and VDR GSEA pathway analysis <lb/>wereinvolvedinoxidative stress. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>threonine kinase, is crucial for regulating cell growth, metabolism, <lb/>and autophagy. There are two different types of mTOR complexes, <lb/>mTOR complex 1 (mTORC 1) and mTOR complex 2 (mTORC 2) <lb/>(Syed et al., 2012). mTORC 2 is closely related to actin cytoskeleton, <lb/>cell polarity and phosphorylated protein kinase B (AKT). mTORC <lb/>1 is activated by the phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase (PI3K) system. <lb/>PI3K can activate AKT (a serine/threonine kinase). After AKT <lb/>activation, it inhibits the expression of tuberous sclerosis protein <lb/>1/2 complex (TSC1/2), thereby promoting the expression of a rich <lb/>homologue of Ras (Rheb) in the brain, ultimately leading to the <lb/>activation of mTORC 1, and then phosphorylating two downstream <lb/>proteins p70s6k and 4E-BP1, leading to increased ribosome and <lb/>protein synthesis (Aoki and Fujishita, 2017; Chen et al., 2018b; Chen <lb/>et al., 2022). Through the above signal pathways, mTOR regulates <lb/>the progress of cell cycle and plays a role in regulating cell growth, <lb/>metabolism and autophagy. High glucose and certain cytokines <lb/>activate the mTOR signaling via the PI3K pathway, promoting <lb/>cell proliferation and protein synthesis. (Yang et al., 2018). The <lb/>mTOR complex is the receptor of amino acid, glucose and energy <lb/>nutritional status, which can sense and transmit external stimulus <lb/>signals in a timely manner. As the junction of multiple signal <lb/>pathways in cells and the central signal factor, mTOR regulates <lb/>cell growth cycle and nutrient metabolism by integrating signals. It <lb/>was found that the expression of mTOR in renal tissues of patients <lb/>with glomerular disease and animal models was significantly <lb/>increased mTOR plays a gating role in autophagy (Saxton and <lb/>Sabatini, 2017; Herb and Schramm, 2021; Tang et al., 2022). <lb/>After activation, mTOR can phosphorylate p70s6k and 4E-BP1 in <lb/>its downstream, and participate in regulating cell apoptosis and <lb/>energy metabolism. In addition, the study also confirmed that in rat <lb/>mesangial cell lines cultured in high glucose environment, mTOR <lb/>regulates cell growth and proliferation by phosphorylating <lb/>downstream proteins p70s6k and 4E-BP1, and DDIT4 inhibits <lb/>cell proliferation by up regulating the expression of mTOR by up <lb/>regulating TSC1/TSC2 complex (Chen et al., 2018a; Herb and <lb/>Schramm, 2021). In osteoblasts, 1.25(OH) 2 D 3 can inhibit cell <lb/>proliferation, and DDIT4 is the direct target of 1.25(OH) 2 D 3 <lb/>(Wang et al., 2016). In β-cells, high glucose can downregulate the <lb/>expression of DDIT4 in cells, and 1.25(OH) 2 D 3 can upregulate the <lb/>expression of DDIT4 in high glucose environment (Yang et al., <lb/>2015). 1.25(OH) 2 D 3 can effectively inhibit the proliferation of <lb/>mesangial cells through the DDIT4/TSC2/mTOR signal pathway <lb/>(Wang et al., 2016). In our study, MPC5 renal podocyte and SV40-<lb/>MES-13 mesangial cell lines were cultured in high glucose to create a <lb/>diabetic cell model. Cell damage induced by high glucose was <lb/>observed using both light microscopy and transmission electron <lb/>microscopy. Subsequently, DDIT4 plasmid transfection was <lb/>employed as a treatment and regulatory method to investigate <lb/>the effects of transfection on cellular damage and downstream <lb/>pathways. The results of qRT-PCR and western blotting <lb/>demonstrated alterations in proteins associated with the VDR/ <lb/>mTOR/p70s6k/4E-BP1 <lb/>pathway, <lb/>confirming <lb/>that <lb/>DDIT4 enhances the pathological damage of DKD by <lb/>participating in VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E-BP1 signal pathway, <lb/>similar to the effect of 1.25(OH) 2 D 3 on mesangial cells. <lb/>Autophagy, a lysosome-mediated degradation process, <lb/>selectively eliminates damaged proteins and organelles to <lb/>maintain cellular homeostasis and supports self-recycling under <lb/>stress. Oxidative stress occurs when there is an imbalance <lb/>between oxidation and antioxidant systems, resulting in cellular <lb/>damage. Accumulating evidence indicates that reactive oxygen <lb/>species (ROS) generated during oxidative stress play a significant <lb/>role in inducing autophagy. Conversely, autophagy acts as a <lb/>protective mechanism by mitigating oxidative damage and <lb/>promoting cell survival. Recently, the discovery of ferritinophagy <lb/>as a selective type of autophagy has inspired further exploration into <lb/>functional interactions between metabolism, immunity, and cell <lb/>death (Liu et al., 2020). Recent studies exhibit that <lb/>mTORC1 <lb/>neutralizes <lb/>ferroptosis <lb/>through <lb/>promoting <lb/>GPX4 protein synthesis and/or inhibiting autophagy (Zhang <lb/>et al., 2021). Our study demonstrates the critical role of the <lb/>VDR/mTOR/p70s6k/4E-BP1 signaling pathway in DKD <lb/>pathogenesis. LC3 (Microtubule-associated proteins 1A/1B light <lb/>chain 3) serves as an autophagic marker protein, with LC3I and <lb/>LC3II being involved in autophagosome membrane elongation, <lb/>fusion, and delivery processes while maintaining oxidative stress <lb/>homeostasis in vivo. During the course of autophagy, the soluble <lb/>form of LC3 (LC3-I), which does not associate with membranes, is <lb/>transformed into the membrane-associated form LC3-II through its <lb/>conjugation with phosphatidylethanolamine (PE). LC3-II then <lb/>binds to the mature autophagic membranes, facilitating an <lb/>increase in the formation of autophagosomes and consequently <lb/>enhancing autophagy. This transformation is catalyzed by an <lb/>amide bond formation with the C-terminal of LC3 through the <lb/>FIGURE 11 <lb/>ELISA results of MPC cells and SV40-MES-13 cells. (A) MDA Concentration.(B) SOD Concentration. (C) GSH Concentration. The experiments were <lb/>independently replicated three times to ensure the reproducibi ty and accuracy. pp p &lt; 0.01, compared with Controlgroup; #p &lt; 0.05, compared with <lb/>HG group. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<body>action of the E2-like enzyme Atg3, and is mediated by an acyl <lb/>transfer reaction catalyzed by Atg7 and Atg3. As a result of the <lb/>conversion of LC3-I to LC3-II, a dynamic equilibrium is established <lb/>that leads to a decrease in LC3-I protein levels and an increase in <lb/>LC3-II protein levels. The GSEA pathway analysis revealed the <lb/>involvement of both mTOR and VDR in the response to <lb/>oxidative stress. Intriguingly, our results suggest a dynamic <lb/>interplay between VDR and DDIT4, traditionally viewed as <lb/>upstream of VDR. The observed increase in VDR expression <lb/>upon DDIT4 transfection points to a potential feedback <lb/>mechanism. This may imply that DDIT4 upregulation could <lb/>indirectly enhance VDR expression, indicative of a compensatory <lb/>cellular response to the high-glucose environment. This complex <lb/>regulatory network, hinted at by the bidirectional influences of <lb/>DDIT4 and VDR, underscores the need for further investigation <lb/>to fully elucidate these interactions and their implications for DKD <lb/>pathogenesis. MDA, as a marker of lipid peroxidation, along with <lb/>SOD and GSH, as key antioxidative enzymes, provide insights into <lb/>the cellular redox state. The reduction of oxidative stress through <lb/>DDIT4-mediated pathways aligns with our observation of enhanced <lb/>autophagy, further reinforcing the potential of DDIT4 as a <lb/>therapeutic target. By detecting MDA, and noting the activities of <lb/>SOD and GSH, we have delineated the antioxidative benefits of <lb/>DDIT4 overexpression, which supports its role in mitigating the <lb/>pathological <lb/>damage <lb/>associated <lb/>with <lb/>diabetic <lb/>nephropathy (Figure 12). <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, exploring DDIT4&apos;s role in the VDR-mTOR <lb/>pathway uncovers a promising therapeutic avenue for DKD <lb/>treatment. The observed changes in the VDR-mTOR pathway in <lb/>both clinical samples and experimental models highlight its <lb/>significance in the pathogenesis of DKD. The ability of DDIT4 to <lb/>modulate key components of this pathway, enhance autophagy, and <lb/>alleviate oxidative stress reveals its potential as a novel drug <lb/>discovery target for DKD. These findings open up new avenues <lb/>for innovative approaches to chronic kidney disease drug discovery. <lb/>Further exploration and validation of the therapeutic potential of <lb/>DDIT4 may offer effective interventions, meeting unmet clinical <lb/>needs in DKD management. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>Publicly available datasets were analyzed in this study. This data <lb/>can be found here: Transcriptional expression levels of mTOR and <lb/>VDR in human renal tissue were obtained from the Gene Expression <lb/>Omnibus Database (GSE142025). <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by The ethics <lb/>committee of China-Japan Friendship Hospital. The studies were <lb/>conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional <lb/>requirements. The participants provided their written informed <lb/>consent to participate in this study. The animal study was <lb/>approved by The ethics committee of China-Japan Friendship <lb/>Hospital. The study was conducted in accordance with the local <lb/>legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed <lb/>consent was obtained from the individual(s) for the publication <lb/>of any potentially identifiable images or data included in this article. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>H-tL: Investigation, Methodology, Validation, Data curation, <lb/>Writing-original draft. Y-yJ: Project administration, Software, <lb/>Visualization, Writing-original draft. T-yY: Validation, <lb/>Writing-original draft. J-xS: Conceptualization, Supervision, <lb/>Writing-original draft. J-wT: Resources, Writing-original draft. <lb/>G-mG: Data curation, Funding acquisition, Software, <lb/></div>

	<body>FIGURE 12 <lb/>Mechanism of the VDR-mTOR Signaling Pathway in DKD Development. The VDR-mTOR signaling pathway plays a pivotal role in the progression of <lb/>diabetic kidney disease {DKD). Under high glucose conditions, VDR expression is suppressed, resulting in reduced DDIT4 expression. Consequently, this <lb/>promotes the expression of mTOR and its downstream signaling molecules, p70s6k and 4EBP-1. Simultaneously, it diminishes levels of the antioxidant <lb/>enzymes SOD and GSH, while increasing the production of the lipid peroxidation product MDA. These molecular changes ultimately mediate <lb/>autophagy. contributing to the initiation and progression of DKD. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/>Writing-review and editing. LL: Data curation, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. LZ: Conceptualization, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Supervision, Validation, Writing-review and editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was <lb/>supported by the Elite Medical Professionals project of China-Japan <lb/>Friendship Hospital (NO.ZRJY2021-BJ07) and the National High <lb/>Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding (2023-NHLHCRF-PY-07). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank Beijing Baiti Biotechnology Co., LTD for their <lb/>invaluable technical support, with special thanks to Wang <lb/>Haiwen and Zhang Xingsong et al. for their assistance in refining <lb/>the experimental protocol as well as contributing to the writing and <lb/>revision of this paper. We acknowledge that a portion of the data <lb/>presented in this article was previously shared as a preprint on <lb/>Research Square under the title &quot;DDIT4 mediated autophagy and <lb/>ferroptosis through VDR-mTOR signaling pathway in the treatment <lb/>of diabetic kidney disease&quot;, available at the following link: https:// <lb/>www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-2314736/v1. We would like to <lb/>extend our gratitude to the preprint server and the reviewers for <lb/>their invaluable feedback, which significantly contributed to the <lb/>enhancement of our research. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Abasheva, D., Dolcet-Negre, M. M., Fernández-Seara, M. A., Mora-Gutiérrez, <lb/>J. M., Orbe, J., Escalada, F. J., et al. (2022). Association between <lb/>circulating levels of 25-hydroxyvitamin D(3) and matrix metalloproteinase-10 <lb/>(MMP-10) in patients with type 2 diabetes. Nutrients 14, 3484. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>nu14173484 <lb/>Afkarian, M., Zelnick, L. R., Hall, Y. N., Heagerty, P. J., Tuttle, K., Weiss, N. S., et al. <lb/>(2016). Clinical manifestations of kidney disease among US adults with diabetes, 1988-<lb/>2014. JAMA 316, 602-610. doi:10.1001/jama.2016.10924 <lb/>Alicic, R., and Nicholas, S. B. (2022). Diabetic kidney disease back in focus: <lb/>management field guide for health care Professionals in the 21st century. Mayo <lb/>Clin. Proc. 97, 1904-1919. doi:10.1016/j.mayocp.2022.05.003 <lb/>Aoki, M., and Fujishita, T. (2017). Oncogenic roles of the PI3K/AKT/mTOR Axis. <lb/>Curr. Top. Microbiol. Immunol. 407, 153-189. doi:10.1007/82_2017_6 <lb/>Barrera-Chimal, J., and Jaisser, F. (2020). Pathophysiologic mechanisms in diabetic <lb/>kidney disease: a focus on current and future therapeutic targets. Diabetes Obes. Metab. <lb/>22 (Suppl. 1), 16-31. doi:10.1111/dom.13969 <lb/>Chen, D. P., Ma, Y. P., Zhuo, L., Zhang, Z., Zou, G. M., Yang, Y., et al. (2018a). <lb/>1,25-Dihydroxyvitamin D(3) inhibits the proliferation of rat mesangial cells <lb/>induced by high glucose via DDIT4. Oncotarget 9, 418-427. doi:10.18632/ <lb/>oncotarget.23063 <lb/>Chen, M., Lu, J., Wei, W., Lv, Y., Zhang, X., Yao, Y., et al. (2018b). Effects of proton <lb/>pump inhibitors on reversing multidrug resistance via downregulating V-ATPases/ <lb/>PI3K/Akt/mTOR/HIF-1α signaling pathway through TSC1/2 complex and Rheb in <lb/>human gastric adenocarcinoma cells in vitro and in vivo. Onco Targets Ther. 11, <lb/>6705-6722. doi:10.2147/OTT.S161198 <lb/>Chen, S., Chen, L., Ye, L., Jiang, Y., Li, Q., Zhang, H., et al. (2022). PP2A-mTOR-<lb/>p70S6K/4E-BP1 axis regulates M1 polarization of pulmonary macrophages and <lb/>promotes ambient particulate matter induced mouse lung injury. J. Hazard. Mat. <lb/>424, 127624. doi:10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.127624 <lb/>Dai, H., Liu, Q., and Liu, B. (2017). Research progress on mechanism of podocyte depletion <lb/>in diabetic nephropathy. J. Diabetes Res. 2017, 2615286. doi:10.1155/2017/2615286 <lb/>Ding, F., Gao, F., Zhang, S., Lv, X., Chen, Y., and Liu, Q. (2021). A review of the <lb/>mechanism of DDIT4 serve as a mitochondrial related protein in tumor regulation. Sci. <lb/>Prog. 104, 36850421997273. doi:10.1177/0036850421997273 <lb/>Edition, I. D. A. (2022). International diabetes federation. org.IDF diabetes atlas-10th <lb/>edition. Available at https://diabetesatlas.org/. <lb/>Fu, Y., Sun, Y., Wang, M., Hou, Y., Huang, W., Zhou, D., et al. (2020). Elevation of <lb/>JAML promotes diabetic kidney disease by modulating podocyte lipid metabolism. Cell. <lb/>Metab. 32, 1052-1062. doi:10.1016/j.cmet.2020.10.019 <lb/>Fuhrmann, D. C., Mondorf, A., Beifuß, J., Jung, M., and Brüne, B. (2020). Hypoxia <lb/>inhibits ferritinophagy, increases mitochondrial ferritin, and protects from ferroptosis. <lb/>Redox Biol. 36, 101670. doi:10.1016/j.redox.2020.101670 <lb/>GBD Chronic Kidney Disease Collaboration (2020). Global, regional, and national <lb/>burden of chronic kidney disease, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the Global <lb/>Burden of Disease Study 2017. Lancet 395 (10225), 709-733. doi:10.1016/S0140-<lb/>6736(20)30045-3 <lb/>Herb, M., and Schramm, M. (2021). Functions of ROS in macrophages and <lb/>antimicrobial immunity. Antioxidants (Basel) 10, 313. doi:10.3390/antiox10020313 <lb/>KDIGO (2020). KDIGO 2020 clinical practice guideline for diabetes <lb/>management in chronic kidney disease. Kidney Int. 98, S1-S115. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>kint.2020.06.019 <lb/>Lassén, E., Bouchareb, R., and Daehn, I. S. (2022). Podocyte as the link between sterile <lb/>inflammation and diabetic kidney disease. Kidney Int. 102, 688-690. doi:10.1016/j.kint. <lb/>2022.07.015 <lb/>Li, S., Zheng, L., Zhang, J., Liu, X., and Wu, Z. (2021). Inhibition of ferroptosis by up-<lb/>regulating Nrf2 delayed the progression of diabetic nephropathy. Free Radic. Biol. Med. <lb/>162, 435-449. doi:10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2020.10.323 <lb/>Liu, J., Kuang, F., Kroemer, G., Klionsky, D. J., Kang, R., and Tang, D. (2020). <lb/>Autophagy-dependent ferroptosis: machinery and regulation. Cell. Chem. Biol. 27, <lb/>420-435. doi:10.1016/j.chembiol.2020.02.005 <lb/>McGrath, K., and Edi, R. (2019). Diabetic kidney disease: diagnosis, treatment, and <lb/>prevention. Am. Fam. Physician 99, 751-759. <lb/>Miller, W. P., Sunilkumar, S., and Dennis, M. D. (2021). The stress response protein <lb/>REDD1 as a causal factor for oxidative stress in diabetic retinopathy. Free Radic. Biol. <lb/>Med. 165, 127-136. doi:10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2021.01.041 <lb/>Saxton, R. A., and Sabatini, D. M. (2017). mTOR signaling in growth, metabolism, <lb/>and disease. Cell. 168, 960-976. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2017.02.004 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Sharov, A. V., Burkhanova, T. M., Taskın Tok, T., Babashkina, M. G., and Safin, D. A. <lb/>(2022). Correction: sharov et al. Computational Analysis of Molnupiravir Int. J. Mol. Sci. <lb/>2022, 23. doi:10.3390/ijms232113026 <lb/>Shi, L., Xiao, C., Zhang, Y., Xia, Y., Zha, H., Zhu, J., et al. (2022). Vitamin D/vitamin D <lb/>receptor/Atg16L1 axis maintains podocyte autophagy and survival in diabetic kidney <lb/>disease. Ren. Fail 44, 694-705. doi:10.1080/0886022X.2022.2063744 <lb/>Song, Z., Xiao, C., Jia, X., Luo, C., Shi, L., Xia, R., et al. (2021). Vitamin D/VDR <lb/>protects against diabetic kidney disease by restoring podocytes autophagy. Diabetes <lb/>Metab. Syndr. Obes. 14, 1681-1693. doi:10.2147/DMSO.S303018 <lb/>Stockwell, B. R. (2022). Ferroptosis turns 10: emerging mechanisms, physiological <lb/>functions, and therapeutic applications. Cell. 185, 2401-2421. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2022. <lb/>06.003 <lb/>Sun, H., Saeedi, P., Karuranga, S., Pinkepank, M., Ogurtsova, K., Duncan, B. B., et al. <lb/>(2022). IDF Diabetes Atlas: global, regional and country-level diabetes prevalence <lb/>estimates for 2021 and projections for 2045. Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract. 183, 109119. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.diabres.2021.109119 <lb/>Syed, F., Sherris, D., Paus, R., Varmeh, S., Singh, S., Pandolfi, P. P., et al. (2012). Keloid <lb/>disease can be inhibited by antagonizing excessive mTOR signaling with a novel dual <lb/>TORC1/2 inhibitor. Am. J. Pathol. 181, 1642-1658. doi:10.1016/j.ajpath.2012.08.006 <lb/>Tang, G., Du, Y., Guan, H., Jia, J., Zhu, N., Shi, Y., et al. (2022). Butyrate ameliorates <lb/>skeletal muscle atrophy in diabetic nephropathy by enhancing gut barrier function and <lb/>FFA2-mediated PI3K/Akt/mTOR signals. Br. J. Pharmacol. 179, 159-178. doi:10.1111/ <lb/>bph.15693 <lb/>Tang, S., and Yiu, W. H. (2020). Innate immunity in diabetic kidney disease. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Nephrol. 16, 206-222. doi:10.1038/s41581-019-0234-4 <lb/>Tervaert, T. W., Mooyaart, A. L., Amann, K., Cohen, A. H., Cook, H. T., Drachenberg, <lb/>C. B., et al. (2010). Pathologic classification of diabetic nephropathy. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. <lb/>21, 556-563. doi:10.1681/ASN.2010010010 <lb/>Thomas, M. C. (2021). Targeting the pathobiology of diabetic kidney disease. Adv. <lb/>Chronic Kidney Dis. 28, 282-289. doi:10.1053/j.ackd.2021.07.001 <lb/>Thomas, M. C., Brownlee, M., Susztak, K., Sharma, K., Jandeleit-Dahm, K. A., <lb/>Zoungas, S., et al. (2015). Diabetic kidney disease. Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim. 1, 15018. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrdp.2015.18 <lb/>Wang, B., Peng, L., Ouyang, H., Wang, L., He, D., Zhong, J., et al. (2019). Induction of <lb/>DDIT4 impairs autophagy through oxidative stress in dry eye. Investig. Ophthalmol. Vis. <lb/>Sci. 60, 2836-2847. doi:10.1167/iovs.19-27072 <lb/>Wang, H., Wang, J., Qu, H., Wei, H., Ji, B., Yang, Z., et al. (2016). In vitro and in vivo <lb/>inhibition of mTOR by 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D(3) to improve early diabetic <lb/>nephropathy via the DDIT4/TSC2/mTOR pathway. Endocrine 54, 348-359. doi:10. <lb/>1007/s12020-016-0999-1 <lb/>Yang, D., Livingston, M. J., Liu, Z., Dong, G., Zhang, M., Chen, J. K., et al. <lb/>(2018). Autophagy in diabetic kidney disease: regulation, pathological role and <lb/>therapeutic potential. Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 75, 669-688. doi:10.1007/s00018-017-<lb/>2639-1 <lb/>Yang, X. D., and Yang, Y. Y. (2022). Ferroptosis as a novel therapeutic target for <lb/>diabetes and its complications. Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne) 13, 853822. doi:10.3389/ <lb/>fendo.2022.853822 <lb/>Yang, Z., Liu, F., Qu, H., Wang, H., Xiao, X., and Deng, H. (2015). 1, 25(OH) <lb/>2D3 protects β cell against high glucose-induced apoptosis through mTOR suppressing. <lb/>Mol. Cell. Endocrinol. 414, 111-119. doi:10.1016/j.mce.2015.07.023 <lb/>Zang, N., Cui, C., Guo, X., Song, J., Hu, H., Yang, M., et al. (2022). cGAS-STING <lb/>activation contributes to podocyte injury in diabetic kidney disease. iScience 25, 105145. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.isci.2022.105145 <lb/>Zhang, Y., Swanda, R. V., Nie, L., Liu, X., Wang, C., Lee, H., et al. (2021). <lb/>mTORC1 couples cyst(e)ine availability with GPX4 protein synthesis and <lb/>ferroptosis regulation. Nat. Commun. 12, 1589. doi:10.1038/s41467-021-21841-w <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Pharmacology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>15 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lu et al. <lb/>10.3389/fphar.2024.1344113 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>