<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T13:29:42.527Z">11/21/2025 1:29:42 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T13:29:24.466011Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T13:29:24.466011Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>An optimized method for IgE-<lb/>mediated degranulation of <lb/>human lung mast cells <lb/>Yitao Gong 1 , Anna-Karin Johnsson 1 , Jesper Säfholm 2,3 , <lb/>Mamdoh Al-Ameri 4,5 , Erik Sachs 4,5 , Kasra Vali 5 , <lb/>Gunnar Nilsson 1,6 and Elin Rönnberg 1 * <lb/>1 Division of Immunology and Allergy, Department of Medicine Solna, and Center for Molecular <lb/>Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, and Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden, <lb/>2 Unit of Integrative Metabolomics, Institute of Environmental Medicine, Karolinska Institutet, <lb/>Stockholm, Sweden, 3 Department of Respiratory Medicine and Allergy, Karolinska University <lb/>Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden, 4 Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska <lb/>Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden, 5 Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Karolinska University <lb/>Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden, 6 Department of Medical Sciences, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden <lb/>Background: Mast cells are critically involved in IgE-mediated diseases, e.g., <lb/>allergies and asthma. Human mast cells are heterogeneous, and mast cells from <lb/>different anatomical sites have been shown to respond differently to certain <lb/>stimuli and drugs. The origin of the mast cells is therefore of importance when <lb/>setting up a model system, and human lung mast cells are highly relevant cells to <lb/>study in the context of asthma. We therefore set out to optimize a protocol of <lb/>IgE-mediated activation of human lung mast cells. <lb/>Methods: Human lung mast cells were extracted from lung tissue obtained from <lb/>patients undergoing pulmonary resection by enzyme digestion and mechanical <lb/>disruption followed by CD117 magnetic-activated cell sorting (MACS) <lb/>enrichment. Different culturing media and conditions for the IgE-mediated <lb/>degranulation were tested to obtain an optimized method. <lb/>Results: IgE crosslinking of human lung mast cells cultured in serum-free media <lb/>gave a stronger response compared to cells cultured with 10% serum. The addition <lb/>of stem cell factor (SCF) did not enhance the degranulation. However, when the <lb/>cells were put in fresh serum-free media 30 minutes prior to the addition of anti-<lb/>IgE antibodies, the cells responded more vigorously. Maximum degranulation was <lb/>reached 10 minutes after the addition of anti-IgE. Both CD63 and CD164 were <lb/>identified as stable markers for the detection of degranulated mast cells over time, <lb/>while the staining with anti-CD107a and avidin started to decline 10 minutes after <lb/>activation. The levels of CD203c and CD13 did not change in activated cells and <lb/>therefore cannot be used as degranulation markers of human lung mast cells. <lb/>Conclusions: For an optimal degranulation response, human lung mast cells <lb/>should be cultured and activated in serum-free media. With this method, a very <lb/>strong and consistent degranulation response with a low donor-to-donor <lb/>variation is obtained. Therefore, this model is useful for further investigations of <lb/>IgE-mediated mast cell activation and exploring drugs that target human lung <lb/>mast cells, for instance, in the context of asthma. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>human lung mast cells, IgE-mediated degranulation, FceRI, degranulation, MRGPRX2 <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Glenn Cruse, <lb/>North Carolina State University, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Graham Mackay, <lb/>The University of Melbourne, Australia <lb/>Margarita Martin, <lb/>University of Barcelona, Spain <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Elin Rönnberg <lb/>elin.ronnberg.hockerlind@ki.se <lb/>RECEIVED 29 February 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 10 May 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 31 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Gong Y, Johnsson A-K, Säfholm J, Al-<lb/>Ameri M, Sachs E, Vali K, Nilsson G and <lb/>Rönnberg E (2024) An optimized method <lb/>for IgE-mediated degranulation of <lb/>human lung mast cells. <lb/>Front. Immunol. 15:1393802. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Gong, Johnsson, Säfholm, Al-Ameri, <lb/>Sachs, Vali, Nilsson and Rönnberg. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the terms <lb/>of the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>in other forums is permitted, provided the <lb/>original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) <lb/>are credited and that the original publication <lb/>in this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Methods <lb/>PUBLISHED 31 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Mast cells are granulated cells that play a major role in allergic <lb/>diseases and asthma. The allergic activation of mast cells occurs by <lb/>crosslinking of allergen-specific IgE antibodies that are bound to the <lb/>high-affinity IgE receptor, FceRI. The mast cells respond to <lb/>this activation by releasing their pre-formed granule content, <lb/>including histamine, mast cell proteases (tryptase and chymase <lb/>carboxypeptidase A3), and heparin, and by de novo synthesizing <lb/>lipid mediators (prostaglandin D 2 , cysteine leukotrienes, etc.) and <lb/>cytokines. These mediators will in turn cause the allergic symptoms, <lb/>such as smooth muscle cell constriction, mucus production, edema, <lb/>and itch (1). <lb/>Mast cells have been shown to be heterogeneous, and human <lb/>mast cells are divided into the MC T and MC TC subtypes, depending <lb/>on their expression of mast cell proteases. MC T expresses tryptase <lb/>and MC TC , in addition to tryptase, also express chymase, <lb/>carboxypeptidase A3, and cathepsin G (2-4). The prevalence of <lb/>these subtypes varies in various tissues, where, for example, mast <lb/>cells in the skin are predominantly of the MC TC type, and in the <lb/>lung, they are predominantly of the MC T type (2). Mast cells from <lb/>the skin have also been shown to express MRGPRX2, a receptor that <lb/>binds numerous basic compounds, such as compound 48/80, <lb/>substance P, LL-37, and various drugs, causing degranulation and <lb/>pseudo-allergic reactions (5-7). Lung mast cells of the MC T type, in <lb/>contrast, lack the expression of this receptor and therefore do not <lb/>respond to these stimuli (8, 9). In addition, it is known that mast <lb/>cells from different tissues have different levels of sensitivity to <lb/>drugs. For example, lung but not skin mast cells are inhibited by <lb/>sodium cromoglycate (10). Therefore, the origin of the mast cells is <lb/>important when setting up a model system and testing the effect of <lb/>potential activators and drugs on human mast cells. Thus, using <lb/>mast cells obtained from human lungs is a highly relevant model for <lb/>studying IgE-mediated degranulation in the context of <lb/>allergic asthma. <lb/>We previously developed a method to extract mast cells from <lb/>human lung tissue with high yield (11). These human lung mast <lb/>cells can be used to study degranulation in different contexts and the <lb/>potential effect of various drugs on the reaction. However, we and <lb/>others found very high donor-to-donor and experiment-to-<lb/>experiment variations in the degranulation response, with some <lb/>donors showing very limited activation while others show a very <lb/>strong response, and a minor change of the conditions will make a <lb/>significant difference in terms of activation (12-15). We therefore <lb/>set out to optimize the conditions in the experiments to obtain a <lb/>high and stable degranulation response of human lung mast cells. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Ethical approval <lb/>The study was approved by the local ethics committee <lb/>(Regionala Etikprövningsnämnden Stockholm, 2018/1819-31/1), <lb/>and all patients gave their informed consent for the collection of <lb/>lung tissue during pulmonary resection procedures due to cancer. <lb/>Lung tissue distal to the tumor was utilized. <lb/>Cell preparation <lb/>Human lung mast cells were obtained from lung tissues as <lb/>essentially described in a previous study (11). In brief, human lung <lb/>tissue was cut into small pieces and enzymatically digested for 30 <lb/>minutes with 0.2 mg/mL DNase I (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, <lb/>USA) and 0.1 mg/mL Liberase TL (Sigma-Aldrich). Thereafter, the <lb/>tissue was vigorously cut by scissors and mechanically disrupted by <lb/>plunging through a syringe. The cells were purified by 30% Percoll <lb/>centrifugation, and red blood cells were lysed using ACK lysis buffer <lb/>(Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA). The cells were then cultured <lb/>in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) <lb/>[StemPro ™ -34 SFM media include the supplied nutrient <lb/>supplement and 2 mM L-glutamine (Sigma-Aldrich) unless <lb/>otherwise stated] overnight, dead cells were thereafter removed by <lb/>Dead Cell Removal Kit (Miltenyi, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany), <lb/>and mast cells were enriched by magnetic-activated cell sorting <lb/>(MACS) enrichment using CD117 MicroBead Kit (Miltenyi). <lb/>Enriched cells were cultured in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media with 2 <lb/>mM L-glutamine or in RPMI 1640 media (HyClone-Cytiva) with <lb/>10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Sigma-Aldrich). Both media were <lb/>supplemented with 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Sigma) and 100 ng/ <lb/>mL stem cell factor (SCF) (Sobi, Stockholm, Sweden). The cells were <lb/>cultured for at least 4 days before IgE-crosslinking experiments <lb/>were performed. <lb/>IgE crosslinking <lb/>One day prior to crosslinking, 1 mg/mL of human IgE <lb/>(Myeloma, Calbiochem, San Diego, CA, USA) was added to the <lb/>media. After washing away unbound IgE, the cells were crosslinked <lb/>with various concentrations of anti-IgE (clone GE-1, Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich) for different time periods at 37°C in StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media or PIPES-BSA buffer [0.2% bovine serum albumin (BSA) <lb/>(Sigma-Aldrich), 9.3 mM PIPES sodium salt (Sigma-Aldrich), 140.0 <lb/>mM sodium acetate trihydrate, 5.0 mM potassium acetate, 0.6 mM <lb/>calcium chloride dihydrate, and 0.11 mM magnesium chloride <lb/>hexahydrate, pH adjusted to 7.4 with 1 M Tris]. After activation, <lb/>cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) + 2% FBS <lb/>and thereafter stained with different antibodies and analyzed by <lb/>flow cytometry. <lb/>MRGPRX2-mediated activation <lb/>The cells were plated and allowed to pre-incubate in fresh <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media for 30 minutes prior to the addition of 10 <lb/>µg/mL compound 48/80 (Sigma-Aldrich). After 10 minutes, the <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>02 <lb/></page>

    <body>cells were washed with PBS + 2% FBS and thereafter stained with <lb/>antibodies and analyzed by flow cytometry. <lb/>Flow cytometry <lb/>The following antibodies/stains were used: anti-CD117-APC <lb/>(clone 104D2, BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA), anti-CD107a-<lb/>APC-H7 (clone H4A3, BD Biosciences), anti-CD164-PE (clone <lb/>67D2, BioLegend, San Diego, CA, USA), anti-CD63-FITC (clone <lb/>H5C6, BD Biosciences), anti-CD63-PE-Cy7 (clone H5C6, BD <lb/>Biosciences), anti-CD13-BV421 (clone WM15, BioLegend), anti-<lb/>CD203c-FITC (clone NP4D6, BioLegend), and Avidin-Alexa Fluor <lb/>488 (Thermo Fisher). Staining was performed by incubation for at <lb/>least 8 minutes at 4°C with the antibodies 1:100 diluted in PBS + 2% <lb/>FBS, followed by washing with PBS + 2% FBS. The cells were <lb/>resuspended in PBS + 2% FBS, and DAPI (BD Biosciences) was <lb/>added to a final dilution of 1:10,000 prior to running the flow <lb/>cytometry on a BD FACSCanto (BD Biosciences). Live Human <lb/>lung mast cells (HLMCs) were gated as DAPI negative and CD117 <lb/>high. Gates for positive degranulation were set according to the anti-<lb/>CD63 (or other markers when they were used) stained non-activated <lb/>control. Flow cytometry data analysis was conducted using FlowJo <lb/>software version 10.8.1 (FlowJo LLC, Ashland, OR, USA). <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Student&apos;s two-tailed t-test was used to compare differences <lb/>between the two groups; the Mann-Whitney test was performed <lb/>when the normality test (a = 0.05) was not passed. One-way <lb/>ANOVA or two-way ANOVA tests with Bonferroni correction <lb/>for multiple comparisons were performed when comparing more <lb/>than two groups. Statistical analyses were performed using <lb/>GraphPad Prism software version 9.4.1. * p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01; <lb/>*** p &lt; 0.001; **** p &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>Stepwise protocol for optimized human <lb/>lung mast cell degranulation <lb/>Materials <lb/>StemPro™-34 SFM media (Gibco) [with the supplied nutrient <lb/>supplement and 2 mM L-glutamine (Sigma-Aldrich)] or <lb/>RPMI 1640 media (HyClone-Cytiva) <lb/>Cell culture flask (T-25, surface: suspension, filter cap, <lb/>SARSTEDT, Nümbrecht Germany) <lb/>96-well cell culture plate (surface: suspension, bottom shape: <lb/>conical, SARSTEDT) <lb/>SCF (Sobi) <lb/>Human IgE, Myeloma (Calbiochem) <lb/>Anti-IgE, clone GE-1 (Sigma-Aldrich) <lb/>Fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) buffer (PBS + <lb/>2% FBS) <lb/>Anti-CD63-PE-Cy7 (clone H5C6, BD Biosciences) <lb/>Anti-CD117-APC (clone 104D2, BD Biosciences) <lb/>DAPI (BD Biosciences) <lb/>BD FACSCanto (BD Biosciences or similar flow cytometer) <lb/>Stepwise protocol <lb/>1. Culture MACS-enriched human lung mast cells with <lb/>StemPro™-34 SFM media with 100 ng/mL SCF at a <lb/>concentration of 0.5 × 10 6 cells/mL in cell culture flasks <lb/>for at least 4 days. <lb/>2. Add 1 mg/mL of human IgE to the media 1 day prior to <lb/>crosslinking and incubate in the cell incubator for <lb/>one night. <lb/>3. Before IgE crosslinking, pre-heat StemPro™-34 SFM media <lb/>(or serum-free RPMI) with and without 4 mg/mL anti-IgE <lb/>antibodies to 37°C. <lb/>4. Collect cells from the flask and count the cell number. <lb/>5. Spin down the cells at 400 ×g for 5 minutes at room <lb/>temperature and discard the supernatant. <lb/>6. Resuspend the cells to the concentration of 10 4 cells/mL <lb/>using pre-heated StemPro™-34 SFM media (or serum-free <lb/>RPMI media). <lb/>7. Add 50 mL of cells per well (5,000 cells per well) into a <lb/>conical bottom 96-well cell culture plate. <lb/>8. Pre-incubate at 37°C for 30 minutes. <lb/>9. Add 50 mL pre-heated 4 mg/mL anti-IgE to wells to make the <lb/>final concentration 2 mg/mL or 50 mL pre-heated media to <lb/>the control sample. <lb/>10. Incubate at 37°C for 10 minutes (optimal degranulation is <lb/>reached at 10 minutes, but this time can be increased to <lb/>investigate other effects). <lb/>11. Spin down the cells at 400 ×g for 5 minutes at 4°C. <lb/>Optional: If the supernatant is collected, transfer the <lb/>supernatant and store it at -20°C for later analysis of <lb/>released mediators; otherwise, discard the supernatant. <lb/>12. Add 200 mL FACS buffer per well, spin down the cells at 400 <lb/>×g for 5 minutes at 4°C (maximum break), and discard <lb/>the supernatant. <lb/>13. Resuspend with 50 mL per well 1:100 diluted anti-CD63 and <lb/>anti-CD117 antibodies in FACS buffer and stain for 8 <lb/>minutes at 4°C (maximum staining is reached at 8 <lb/>minutes, but this time can also be increased). <lb/>14. Spin down the cells at 400 ×g for 5 minutes at 4°C <lb/>(maximum break) and resuspend the cell pellet with 100 <lb/>mL FACS buffer per well. <lb/>15. Prior to running the samples on the flow cytometer, add <lb/>100 mL per well of DAPI 1:5,000 diluted in FACS buffer. <lb/>16. Gate mast cells as live (DAPI low) and CD117 high and set <lb/>a cutoff for degranulated cells according to the anti-CD63 <lb/>stained non-stimulated control. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>03 <lb/></page>

    <body>Results <lb/>HLMC degranulation is increased when <lb/>cultured in serum-free StemPro ™ -34 <lb/>SFM media <lb/>Mast cells were extracted from human lung tissue using <lb/>enzymatic and mechanical disruption of the tissue followed by <lb/>CD117 MACS enrichment. The cells failed to degranulate in <lb/>response to IgE-crosslinking directly after the preparation, they <lb/>needed to rest for a couple of days to be able to respond (data not <lb/>shown), they needed to rest for a couple of days to be able to <lb/>respond. To investigate the effect of different cell culture media on <lb/>HLMC degranulation, the cells were cultured for 4 days with serum-<lb/>free StemPro ™ -34 SFM media or RPMI 1640 media with different <lb/>FBS batches. Although we optimized the extraction of human lung <lb/>mast cells from the tissue (11), the obtained number of these <lb/>primary cells is limited. We therefore used flow cytometry with <lb/>surface CD63 staining as a surrogate marker for degranulation to be <lb/>able to assess degranulation at the single cell level and determine the <lb/>degranulation percentage with relatively few cells utilized. The <lb/>gating strategies and representative CD63 histograms are shown <lb/>in Figure 1A. The degranulation peaked at 2 mg/mL anti-IgE <lb/>antibodies, and cells cultured in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media had <lb/>significantly higher degranulation percentages than cells cultured in <lb/>RPMI 1640 with either of the two FBS batches (Figure 1B). Despite <lb/>having different degranulation percentages, the high-affinity IgE <lb/>receptor (FcϵRI) expression was similar in the different culturing <lb/>conditions (Figure 1C). Because of this, we chose to culture the cells <lb/>in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media and use 2 mg/mL anti-IgE antibodies <lb/>for the rest of the experiments. <lb/>HLMC degranulation response is higher in <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media than in PIPES-<lb/>BSA buffer <lb/>The media that HLMCs are IgE-crosslinked in, i.e., the <lb/>degranulation media, also affect their response. We traditionally <lb/>degranulated mast cells in a PIPES buffer with 2% BSA; however, we <lb/>have not investigated how this buffer affects mast cell degranulation <lb/>in time-course experiments where the cells are kept in the <lb/>degranulation buffer for a longer period. We therefore compared <lb/>the degranulation percentage when the cells were activated in the <lb/>PIPES-BSA buffer or in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media, the media in <lb/>which the HLMCs were cultured. To make this time course <lb/>experimentally feasible, the media were changed to the <lb/>degranulation media, i.e., PIPES-BSA or StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media, the cells were plated, and the anti-IgE antibodies were <lb/>added at different timepoints so that the endpoint and staining of <lb/>the cells with anti-CD63 antibodies were performed at the same <lb/>time (Figure 2A, lower x-axis). This means that the cells had been <lb/>sitting in the degranulation media for different periods of time prior <lb/>to the addition of the anti-IgE antibodies (Figure 2A, upper x-axis). <lb/>At the 120-minute timepoint, when the anti-IgE was added <lb/>immediately after the media change, there was no difference in <lb/>degranulation response between the media (Figure 2A). However, at <lb/>the timepoint of 90 minutes down to 2 minutes of activation, cells <lb/>crosslinked in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media had a substantially higher <lb/>degranulation than those in the PIPES-BSA buffer (Figure 2A). <lb/>PIPES media only contain basic salts, and since the degranulation <lb/>response was the highest for this buffer when the anti-IgE was added <lb/>directly after the media change (120 timepoint), we hypothesized <lb/>that cells that have been incubated for some time in this media may <lb/>show lower degranulation. To test this, we performed IgE <lb/>crosslinking for 10 minutes on cells pre-incubated in PIPES-BSA <lb/>for 30 minutes or immediately after the media change, and the pre-<lb/>incubated cells did indeed show lower degranulation (Figure 2B). <lb/>Thus, the late peak in degranulation in the PIPES buffer is not due <lb/>to a slow degranulation but rather a lowering in the degranulation <lb/>response by pre-incubation in this media prior to IgE crosslinking <lb/>(Figure 2A). The degranulation response reached maximum in the <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media at 10 minutes and was stable up until 90 <lb/>minutes (Figure 2A). Therefore, henceforth, we used StemPro ™ -34 <lb/>SFM media as degranulation media. <lb/>CD63 is a stable marker for <lb/>HLMC degranulation <lb/>In addition to CD63 (16), CD107a, CD164, CD203c, CD13 (17), <lb/>and fluorochrome-labeled avidin (18, 19) can also be used to <lb/>evaluate degranulation by flow cytometry. To test the stability of <lb/>these markers for degranulation over time, HLMCs were stained <lb/>after being crosslinked with 2 mg/mL anti-IgE at 37°C for different <lb/>time periods. The surface expression of CD203c and CD13 did not <lb/>increase in degranulated HLMCs (data not shown). In contrast, <lb/>CD63, CD107a, CD164, and avidin performed similarly and <lb/>reached their maximum 10 minutes after the addition of anti-IgE <lb/>(Figure 3A). These markers also correlated well with each other, <lb/>staining the same degranulated mast cells at the 10 minutes <lb/>timepoint (Figures 3B-D). After 10 minutes, avidin and CD107a <lb/>started to decline, indicating that these markers were not stable over <lb/>time. In contrast, CD63 and CD164 were stable up until 120 <lb/>minutes (Figure 3A). We also investigated the optimal staining <lb/>time for the detection of the different surface markers and found <lb/>that staining the cells for 8 minutes was enough to reach maximum <lb/>signal and clear distinction of degranulated and non-degranulated <lb/>mast cells (Figures 3E-I). <lb/>Change of media and addition of SCF have <lb/>no significant effect on <lb/>HLMC degranulation <lb/>SCF is a pivotal growth factor for human mast cells that they <lb/>require for their survival. Additionally, it is reported that SCF also <lb/>enhances mast cell degranulation (15). We therefore next <lb/>investigated if the degranulation response would differ if it was <lb/>performed at different times in relation to media change and the <lb/>addition of SCF. We hence tested the degranulation response on <lb/>different days after the media change. We replaced the media of the <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>04 <lb/></page>

    <body>B <lb/>A <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Degranulation time course of HLMCs crosslinked in different buffers. (A) The media were changed to either PIPES-BSA buffer or StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media, the cells were plated on a 96-well plate, and 2 mg/mL anti-IgE was added immediately to the 120-minute timepoint; thereafter, anti-IgE was <lb/>added at different timepoint to ensure that the cells had been incubated with anti-IgE for the indicated periods (lower x-axis) of time at the endpoint <lb/>of the experiment. This also leads to the cells being pre-incubated in the media for various timepoints prior to the addition of the anti-IgE (upper x-<lb/>axis). (B) Anti-IgE was added immediately after the media change or after 30-minute pre-incubation in PIPES-BSA media, and the reaction was <lb/>stopped after 10 minutes; each individual donor is represented by a unique symbol. Degranulation was evaluated by flow cytometric detection of <lb/>anti-CD63 staining. n = 3-5; means with SEMs. ns, non significant. *p &lt; 0.05; ****p &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>The effect of different culture media on HLMC degranulation. (A) Gating strategies for the degranulation experiments and representative CD63 <lb/>histograms for control and anti-IgE activated samples. (B) HLMCs were cultured with serum-free StemPro ™ -34 SFM media and RPMI 1640 media <lb/>supplemented with two different batches of FBS for 4 days before they were crosslinked with anti-IgE in PIPES-BSA media. Degranulation was <lb/>evaluated by flow cytometric detection of anti-CD63 staining. n = 5; means with SEMs. (C) The FcϵRI expression [median fluorescence intensity <lb/>(MFI)] in the different treatment groups was detected by flow cytometry; each individual donor is represented by a unique symbol. n = 3; means with <lb/>SEMs. FBS, fetal bovine serum. ns, non significant. *p &lt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>05 <lb/></page>

    <body>HLMCs every 7-8 days, and the degranulation response was stable <lb/>throughout this period (Figure 4A); therefore, it does not matter <lb/>when degranulation experiments are performed in relation to media <lb/>change. We also cultured HLMCs in different SCF concentrations <lb/>(10 ng/mL and 100 ng/mL) in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media for 1 day <lb/>and found no significant difference between the two <lb/>groups (Figure 4B). <lb/>Pre-incubation in fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media before crosslinking significantly <lb/>increases HLMC degranulation <lb/>We noticed in our time course experiments that the <lb/>degranulation response dropped at the last timepoint (Figures 2A, <lb/>3A). Since in the latest timepoint the anti-IgE antibodies were added <lb/>immediately after the media change while in the other timepoints <lb/>the cells had been incubated in the media for various timepoints <lb/>(Figure 2A, upper x-axis), we decided to test whether pre-<lb/>incubating in fresh media could have an impact on the response. <lb/>We found that the degranulation response increased significantly <lb/>when the cells were allowed to be pre-incubated in fresh <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media for 30 minutes before activation, <lb/>compared to cells activated immediately after the media change <lb/>(Figure 5A). In other words, giving the cells fresh StemPro ™ -34 <lb/>SFM media primed HLMCs for degranulation. To exclude that the <lb/>presence of SCF in the StemPro ™ -34 SFM media was the cause of <lb/>the effect, we compared StemPro ™ -34 SFM media with or without <lb/>SCF, and with or without the nutrient supplement that was supplied <lb/>with StemPro ™ -34 SFM media (and normally always added to the <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media), and the results were comparable <lb/>(Figure 5A). We also tested to pre-incubate the cells in RPMI <lb/>media (without serum added) for 30 minutes prior to <lb/>degranulation, and also in this case, the response was increased to <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>A <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Degranulation time course with different degranulation markers. (A) HLMCs were incubated with 2 mg/mL anti-IgE from 0 to 150 minutes before <lb/>being stained with avidin, anti-CD63, anti-CD107a, or anti-CD164 and analyzed by flow cytometry. n = 3; means with SEMs. (B-D) Co-staining of <lb/>indicated markers at 10 minutes after IgE crosslinking is shown. (E-I) Anti-IgE crosslinked HLMCs (10 minutes) were stained with indicated markers <lb/>for different timepoints (indicated in the figure) on ice before being washed and analyzed on the flow cytometer. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>06 <lb/></page>

    <body>a similar extent as in StemPro ™ -34 SFM media. However, when <lb/>cells were pre-incubated in RPMI media with 10% serum, the <lb/>degranulation was significantly reduced (Figure 5B). <lb/>Human lung mast cells do not respond to <lb/>the MRGPRX2 agonist compound 48/80 <lb/>It has been published that HLMCs do not express the <lb/>MRGPRX2 receptor and that they do not degranulate upon <lb/>exposure to MRGPRX2 agonists (8, 9). We tested whether this is <lb/>also true using our optimized culturing/degranulation method with <lb/>MRGPRX2 agonist compound 48/80. In line with previously <lb/>published results, we found that compound 48/80 does not <lb/>induce significant degranulation in HLMCs, while the mast cell <lb/>line LAD-2, in contrast, readily degranulates upon exposure to <lb/>compound 48/80 (Figure 6). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Because of a high variation in the IgE-mediated degranulation <lb/>response that we have observed in HLMCs, we set out to optimize <lb/>the conditions to obtain a higher, more stable, and reproducible <lb/>response by the IgE crosslinking of the HLMCs. <lb/>HLMCs fail to degranulate when the IgE crosslinking is <lb/>performed directly after extraction of the cells from the lung <lb/>tissue (data not shown). The extraction and purification protocols <lb/>are very harsh on the cells, and it is likely that the cells are activated <lb/>in this process. This could be a reason why they cannot degranulate <lb/>in response to the IgE crosslinking; however, it is not possible to <lb/>control for this since we need to extract the cells to perform the <lb/>experiment. Regardless of the reason, the cells need to rest for a few <lb/>days before they can respond to IgE crosslinking by degranulation. <lb/>We found that culturing the HLMCs in a serum-free media results <lb/>in increased IgE-mediated degranulation compared to cells cultured <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Pre-incubation in fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM media increases HLMC degranulation. (A) HLMCs were pre-incubated in fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM media <lb/>with or without SCF/nutrient supplement for 30 minutes at 37°C before IgE crosslinking, or the degranulation was performed immediately after the <lb/>media change (no pre-incubation). (B) HLMCs were pre-incubated in different media, RPMI 1640 media with 10% serum, RPMI alone, or StemPro ™ -34 <lb/>SFM media (with nutrient supplement), for 30 minutes at 37°C before IgE crosslinking, or the degranulation was performed immediately after the media <lb/>change (no pre-incubation). Degranulation was evaluated by flow cytometric detection of anti-CD63 staining. Each individual donor is represented by a <lb/>unique symbol, n = 3; means with SEMs. SCF, stem cell factor; RPMI, RPMI-1640 media. ns, non significant. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; *** p &lt; 0.001. <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Change of media and addition of fresh SCF had no significant effect on HLMC degranulation. (A) IgE crosslinking was performed on different days <lb/>after media change to fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM media and 100 ng/mL SCF. n = 4; means with SEMs. (B) HLMCs were cultured in StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media with different concentrations of SCF for 1 day before IgE crosslinking; each individual donor is represented by a unique symbol. n = 5; means <lb/>with SEMs. Degranulation was evaluated by flow cytometric detection of anti-CD63 staining. SCF, stem cell factor. ns, non significant. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>07 <lb/></page>

    <body>in RPMI with 10% serum. There was no statistical difference in the <lb/>surface expression of the FceRI receptor; thus, the receptor <lb/>expression is not likely to be the cause of the lower response. <lb/>SCF has been reported to prime mast cells and increase the <lb/>degranulation of the cells upon IgE crosslinking (20), also <lb/>specifically in HLMCs (15). In our experiments, SCF did not <lb/>influence the degree of degranulation (Figures 4A, B, 5A). The <lb/>rationale for this inconsistency remains speculative. One possibility <lb/>is that the level of degranulation is already maximized under our <lb/>optimized conditions, leaving no scope for any additional priming <lb/>effect of SCF. <lb/>We found that merely changing the media of the cells, i.e., <lb/>placing them in fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM 30 minutes before <lb/>activation, increased the rate of degranulation (Figure 5A), which <lb/>suggests that there may be some ingredients in StemPro ™ -34 SFM <lb/>media that prime mast cells for degranulation, or there is an <lb/>inhibitory factor in the culture media that is removed. <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media are a trademark serum-free media, <lb/>consisting of a basal liquid medium and a frozen nutrient <lb/>supplement. Initially, we hypothesized that the nutrient <lb/>supplement contained ingredients that primed the mast cells; <lb/>however, using only the basal liquid media without the <lb/>supplement had the same priming effect (Figure 5A). In addition, <lb/>we found that pre-incubating the cells in fresh RPMI media without <lb/>serum added also had the same priming effect (Figure 5B). Pre-<lb/>incubation in serum-containing RPMI 1640 media in contrast <lb/>significantly reduced degranulation, suggesting inhibitory factor(s) <lb/>present in the serum. It has previously been published that a factor <lb/>in serum can inhibit mast cell degranulation (21); however, the <lb/>identity of this factor is unknown. <lb/>Several different markers have been used to identify <lb/>degranulated cells, including CD63, CD13, CD203c, CD107a, <lb/>CD164, and avidin (which binds electrostatically to the <lb/>exteriorized proteoglycans) (17-19). To measure the dynamics of <lb/>these degranulation markers over time on the HLMCs, we set up a <lb/>time course experiment, staining the mast cells at different <lb/>timepoints after the IgE crosslinking. CD203c and CD13 staining <lb/>did not increase in degranulated HLMCs (data not shown), while <lb/>the staining for all the other markers increased and reached <lb/>maximum 10 minutes after the activation (Figure 3A). <lb/>Furthermore, the surface expression of the different markers also <lb/>correlated strongly with each other (Figures 3B-D), showing that <lb/>the markers identify the same degranulated mast cells. CD63 and <lb/>CD164 were quite stable over time, while the CD107a and avidin <lb/>staining started to drop earlier (Figure 3A). This is in contrast to a <lb/>study on basophils where the CD203c, CD164, and CD13 reached <lb/>maximum staining within 5-15 minutes, while CD63 and CD107a <lb/>reached maximum after only 20-40 minutes (17), indicating that <lb/>the degranulation process somewhat differs in basophils and mast <lb/>cells. In summary, the CD63 staining was the marker that showed <lb/>the highest degranulation percentage with a clear distinction <lb/>between degranulated and non-degranulated cells, and it was <lb/>stable over time; therefore, we believe that this is a useful marker <lb/>for studying the degranulation of HLMCs. <lb/>In summary, our optimized method for degranulation of <lb/>HLMCs consists of culturing the HLMCs in serum-free <lb/>StemPro ™ -34 SFM media and pre-incubating the cells for 30 <lb/>minutes in fresh StemPro ™ -34 SFM media (or serum-free RPMI) <lb/>prior to activation by 2 mg/mL anti-IgE. This leads to peak <lb/>degranulation at 10 minutes, which can be measured through <lb/>flow cytometric analysis of CD63. <lb/>This optimized method consistently yields a high and stable <lb/>activation percentage, proving valuable for the analysis of IgE-<lb/>mediated activation in HLMCs and for assessing the impact of <lb/>drugs targeting HLMCs in the context of lung diseases, such <lb/>as asthma. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included <lb/>in the article/supplementary material. Further inquiries can be <lb/>directed to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by Regionala <lb/>etikprövningsnämnden i Stockholm. The studies were conducted in <lb/>accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. <lb/>The participants provided their written informed consent to <lb/>participate in this study. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>YG: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, <lb/>Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. AJ: <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Writing -review &amp; <lb/></div>

    <body>FIGURE 6 <lb/>HLMCs do not degranulate in response to MRGPRX2 agonist <lb/>compound 48/80. HLMCs were pre-incubated in fresh StemPro ™ -<lb/>34 SFM media for 30 minutes prior to addition of 10 µg/mL <lb/>compound 48/80. LAD-2 cells were used as positive control for <lb/>MRGPRX2-induced degranulation. Degranulation was evaluated by <lb/>flow cytometric detection of anti-CD63 staining. Each individual <lb/>donor is represented by a unique symbol, n = 6; means with SEMs. <lb/>ns, non significant. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>08 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">editing. JS: Funding acquisition, Project administration, Resources, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. ES: Resources, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. MA: Resources, Writing -review &amp; editing. KV: Resources, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. GN: Conceptualization, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Project administration, Supervision, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing. ER: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This study <lb/>was supported by grants from the Swedish Research Council, the <lb/>Heart-Lung Foundation, The Swedish Cancer Society, the Ellen, <lb/>Walter and Lennart Hesselman Foundation, the Åke Wiberg <lb/>Foundation, The Konsul ThC Berghs Foundation, The <lb/>Tornspiran Foundation, The Magnus Bergvall Foundation, and <lb/>the Karolinska Institutet. The funding sources were not involved <lb/>in the study design, collection, and interpretation of data; writing <lb/>the report; or the decision to submit the article for publication. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Dahlin JS, Maurer M, Metcalfe DD, Pejler G, Sagi-Eisenberg R, Nilsson G. The <lb/>ingenious mast cell: Contemporary insights into mast cell behavior and function. <lb/>Allergy. (2022) 77:83-99. doi: 10.1111/all.14881 <lb/>2. Irani AA, Schechter NM, Craig SS, DeBlois G, Schwartz LB. Two types of human <lb/>mast cells that have distinct neutral protease compositions. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>(1986) 83:4464-8. doi: 10.1073/pnas.83.12.4464 <lb/>3. Irani AM, Goldstein SM, Wintroub BU, Bradford T, Schwartz LB. Human mast <lb/>cell carboxypeptidase. Selective localization to MCTC cells. J Immunol. (1991) 147:247-<lb/>53. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.147.1.247 <lb/>4. Schechter NM, Irani AM, Sprows JL, Abernethy J, Wintroub B, Schwartz LB. <lb/>Identification of a cathepsin G-like proteinase in the MCTC type of human mast cell. J <lb/>Immunol. (1990) 145:2652-61. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.145.8.2652 <lb/>5. Tatemoto K, Nozaki Y, Tsuda R, Konno S, Tomura K, Furuno M, et al. <lb/>Immunoglobulin E-independent activation of mast cell is mediated by Mrg receptors. <lb/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun. (2006) 349:1322-8. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.08.177 <lb/>6. McNeil BD, Pundir P, Meeker S, Han L, Undem BJ, Kulka M, et al. Identification <lb/>of a mast-cell-specific receptor crucial for pseudo-allergic drug reactions. Nature. <lb/>(2015) 519:237-41. doi: 10.1038/nature14022 <lb/>7. Subramanian H, Gupta K, Guo Q, Price R, Ali H. Mas-related gene X2 (MrgX2) is <lb/>a novel G protein-coupled receptor for the antimicrobial peptide LL-37 in human mast <lb/>cells: resistance to receptor phosphorylation, desensitization, and internalization. J Biol <lb/>Chem. (2011) 286:44739-49. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M111.277152 <lb/>8. Fujisawa D, Kashiwakura J, Kita H, Kikukawa Y, Fujitani Y, Sasaki-Sakamoto T, <lb/>et al. Expression of Mas-related gene X2 on mast cells is upregulated in the skin of <lb/>patients with severe chronic urticaria. J Allergy Clin Immunol. (2014) 134:622-33.e629. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2014.05.004 <lb/>9. Kajiwara N, Sasaki T, Bradding P, Cruse G, Sagara H, Ohmori K, et al. Activation <lb/>of human mast cells through the platelet-activating factor receptor. J Allergy Clin <lb/>Immunol. (2010) 125:1137-45.e1136. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2010.01.056 <lb/>10. Okayama Y, Benyon RC, Rees PH, Lowman MA, Hillier K, Church MK. <lb/>Inhibition profiles of sodium cromoglycate and nedocromil sodium on mediator <lb/>release from mast cells of human skin, lung, tonsil, adenoid and intestine. Clin Exp <lb/>Allergy. (1992) 22:401-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2222.1992.tb03102.x <lb/>11. Ravindran A, Ronnberg E, Dahlin JS, Mazzurana L, Safholm J, Orre AC, et al. An <lb/>optimized protocol for the isolation and functional analysis of human lung mast cells. <lb/>Front Immunol. (2018) 9:2193. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2018.02193 <lb/>12. Havard S, Scola AM, Kay LJ, Ishmael SS, MacGlashan DW Jr., Peachell PT. <lb/>Characterization of syk expression in human lung mast cells: relationship with <lb/>function. Clin Exp Allergy. (2011) 41:378-88. doi: 10.1111/cea.2011.41.issue-3 <lb/>13. Duffy SM, Lawley WJ, Conley EC, Bradding P. Resting and activation-dependent <lb/>ion channels in human mast cells. J Immunol. (2001) 167:4261-70. doi: 10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.167.8.4261 <lb/>14. Lavens SE, Proud D, Warner JA. A sensitive colorimetric assay for the release of <lb/>tryptase from human lung mast cells. vitro J Immunol Methods. (1993) 166:93-102. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0022-1759(93)90332-2 <lb/>15. Bischoff SC, Dahinden CA. c-kit ligand: a unique potentiator of mediator <lb/>release by human lung mast cells. J Exp Med. (1992) 175:237-44. doi: 10.1084/ <lb/>jem.175.1.237 <lb/>16. Schafer T, Starkl P, Allard C, Wolf RM, Schweighoffer T. A granular variant of <lb/>CD63 is a regulator of repeated human mast cell degranulation. Allergy. (2010) <lb/>65:1242-55. doi: 10.1111/j.1398-9995.2010.02350.x <lb/>17. Hennersdorf F, Florian S, Jakob A, Baumgartner K, Sonneck K, Nordheim A, <lb/>et al. Identification of CD13, CD107a, and CD164 as novel basophil-activation markers <lb/>and dissection of two response patterns in time kinetics of IgE-dependent upregulation. <lb/>Cell Res. (2005) 15:325-35. doi: 10.1038/sj.cr.7290301 <lb/>18. Bergstresser PR, Tigelaar RE, Tharp MD. Conjugated avidin identifies cutaneous <lb/>rodent and human mast cells. J Invest Dermatol. (1984) 83:214-8. doi: 10.1111/1523-<lb/>1747.ep12263584 <lb/>19. Joulia R, L&apos;Faqihi FE, Valitutti S, Espinosa E. IL-33 fine tunes mast cell <lb/>degranulation and chemokine production at the single-cell level. J Allergy Clin <lb/>Immunol. (2017) 140:497-509.e410. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2016.09.049 <lb/>20. Halova I, et al. Changing the threshold-Signals and mechanisms of mast cell <lb/>priming. Immunol Rev. (2018) 282:73-86. doi: 10.1111/imr.12625 <lb/>21. Astorquiza MI, Fernandez S. Anaphylaxis inhibitory factor in IgE-dependent <lb/>mast cell stimulation. J Investig Allergol Clin Immunol. (1999) 9:330-4. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Gong et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2024.1393802 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <page>09 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>