<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T11:52:19.304Z">11/20/2025 11:52:19 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T11:52:09.694805Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T11:52:09.694805Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>2D and 3D anticancer properties <lb/>of C2-functionalised <lb/>glucosamine-Pt (IV) prodrugs <lb/>based on cisplatin scaffold <lb/>Eoin Moynihan 1 † , Maria Galiana-Cameo 1 † , Monica Sandri 2 , <lb/>Andrea Ruffini 2 , Silvia Panseri 2 , Trinidad Velasco-Torrijos 1,3 *, <lb/>Monica Montesi 2 * and Diego Montagner 1,3 * <lb/>1 Department of Chemistry, Maynooth University, Maynooth, Ireland, 2 Institute of Science, Technology <lb/>and Sustainability for Ceramics (ISSMC)-National Research Council (CNR), Faenza, Italy, 3 Kathleen <lb/>Londsdale for Human Health Research, Maynooth University, Maynooth, Ireland <lb/>A series of C2-functionalied Pt (IV) glycoconjugates based on glucosamine have <lb/>been synthesised, characterised and tested as anticancer agents on a series of <lb/>different 2D and 3D cancer cell lines. The carbohydrate will act as a targeted <lb/>delivery system to improve the selectivity, exploiting the Warburg Effect and the <lb/>GLUTs receptors that are overexpressed in most of the cancer cells. The hydroxyl <lb/>at C2 of the carbohydrates does not participate in hydrogen bonding with the <lb/>GLUTs receptors, making C2 an attractive position for drug conjugation as seen in <lb/>literature. In this study, we use the amino functionality at the C2 position in <lb/>glucosamine and Copper-catalysed Azide-Alkyne Cycloaddition &quot;click&quot; (CuAAC) <lb/>reaction to connect the prodrug Pt (IV) scaffold to the carbohydrate. We have <lb/>investigated complexes with different linker lengths, as well as acetyl protected <lb/>and free derivatives. To the best of our knowledge, this study represents the first <lb/>series of Pt (IV) glucosamine-conjugates functionalised at C2. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>target therapy, cisplatin, glycoconjugate, glucosamine, anticancer properties <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>The most well-known anticancer metal-based drug is cisplatin approved by FDA in <lb/>1978, followed shortly by the approval of &quot;second generation Pt (II) chemotherapeutics&quot; <lb/>carboplatin (Ho et al., 2016) and oxaliplatin (Alcindor and Beauger, 2011) (Figure 1A) in <lb/>1989 and 2002 respectively. One of the major drawbacks in the use of cisplatin is that it lacks <lb/>specificity for cancer cells and causes damage to healthy cells; specific side effects of cisplatin <lb/>include nephrotoxicity (Miller et al., 2010), ototoxicity (Callejo et al., 2015), neurotoxicity <lb/>(Kanat et al., 2017), cardiotoxicity (Hu et al., 2018) and hepatotoxicity (Taghizadeh et al., <lb/>2021). Some of these side effects can be overcome by the use of second generation <lb/>chemotherapeutics, however, more recently, Pt (IV) prodrugs have shown great <lb/>potential in overcoming cisplatin&apos;s drawbacks (Brandon and Dabrowiak, 1984). Pt (IV) <lb/>complexes are considered prodrugs because they must be reduced intracellularly to the <lb/>counterparts Pt (II) to carry out their anticancer activity (Beirne et al., 2023). <lb/>This study aims to use carbohydrate targeting vectors to circumvent the drawbacks of Pt <lb/>(II)-based chemotherapeutics and to improve selectivity for cancer cells compared to non-<lb/>cancerous tissues. Carbohydrates are metabolised differently in cancer cells compared to <lb/></body>

	<front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Morteza Montazerozohori, <lb/>Yasouj University, Iran <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Shiva Joohari, <lb/>Islamic Azad University, Yasuj, Iran <lb/>Daniela Imperio, <lb/>University of Eastern Piedmont, Italy <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Diego Montagner, <lb/>diego.montagner@mu.ie <lb/>Trinidad Velasco-Torrijos, <lb/>trinidad.velascotorrijos@mu.ie <lb/>Monica Montesi, <lb/>monica.montesi@issmc.cnr.it <lb/> † <lb/>These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work <lb/>RECEIVED 19 February 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 22 April 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 06 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Moynihan E, Galiana-Cameo M, Sandri M, <lb/>Ruffini A, Panseri S, Velasco-Torrijos T, <lb/>Montesi M and Montagner D (2024), 2D and 3D <lb/>anticancer properties of C2-functionalised <lb/>glucosamine-Pt (IV) prodrugs based on <lb/>cisplatin scaffold. <lb/>Front. Chem. 12:1388332. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Moynihan, Galiana-Cameo, Sandri, <lb/>Ruffini, Panseri, Velasco-Torrijos, Montesi and <lb/>Montagner. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 06 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></front>

	<body>healthy cells by deviating from the typical cycle of ATP production. <lb/>Cells switch from oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) to <lb/>glycolysis for the synthesis of ATP, reducing ATP production <lb/>efficiency (Ma et al., 2017b). This lowered energy production <lb/>results in the overexpression of glucose transporter (GLUT) <lb/>proteins on the cell surface, which can be used to selectively <lb/>target cancer cells. This observation was first noted by Otto <lb/>Warburg in the 1920s and was coined &quot;The Warburg Effect&quot; <lb/>(Warburg et al., 1927). This is indeed a viable method of tumour <lb/>targeting, which can be seen in the work from the group of Wang <lb/>et al. (2016), Ma et al. (2016), Ma et al. (2017a), Ma et al. (2018) who <lb/>were among the first to synthesize Pt (IV) glycoconjugates. <lb/>Previously, our group has synthesized libraries of acetylated <lb/>and free glycoconjugated Pt (IV) prodrugs where the carbohydrate <lb/>moieties were functionalized through Copper-catalysed Azide-<lb/>Alkyne Cycloaddition &quot;click&quot; (CuAAC) chemistry on the <lb/>anomeric C1 carbon to target GLUTs on osteosarcoma cell lines <lb/>(Moynihan et al., 2021; Moynihan et al., 2023). However, it is <lb/>recognised that C1 is not an optimal site of functionalization for <lb/>the transport of glucose through GLUTs. GLUTs 1-4 are among <lb/>the most meticulously characterized, with GLUT1 being one of the <lb/>first characterized and crystallized (Deng et al., 2014). Based on the <lb/>data provided by the crystal structure of GLUT1, the optimal <lb/>position to functionalize glucose was determined to be C2. The <lb/>hydroxyl groups at C1, C3, C4, C6 and the ring oxygen are all <lb/>important for hexose binding within the protein binding pocket. <lb/>C4, when switched to the axial position in galactose led to a strong <lb/>decrease in binding affinity in comparison to when the hydroxyl is <lb/>in the equatorial position as in glucose (Barnett et al., 1973; <lb/>Holman, 2020). The hydrogen bond donor and acceptor ability <lb/>of each of these hydroxyl groups is also important for substrate <lb/>recognition. Hydrogen bond acceptor positions being C1, C3 and <lb/>C6, while C4 is the only hydrogen bond donor. The hydroxyl at <lb/>C2 however, does not participate in hydrogen bonding, proven by <lb/>the fact that 2-deoxyglucose is transported by all class 1 GLUTs, <lb/>making C2 an attractive position for drug conjugation (Holman, <lb/>2020). This was further proven by Patra et al. (2016) who <lb/>determined that functionalization in the C2 position of their Pt <lb/>(II) glycoconjugates both improved intracellular platinum <lb/>accumulation as well as the cytotoxicity of the complex. <lb/>Interestingly, the C2 position has long been used to improve the <lb/>uptake of imaging and sensing agents, but to our knowledge, it is <lb/>scarcely taken advantage of in anticancer agents. In particular, 2-<lb/>[ 18 F]-fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (FDG) is used for the detection and <lb/>staging of cancer through positron emission tomography (PET) <lb/>(Carbó and Rodríguez, 2023). FDG is transported into the cell in the <lb/>same manner as glucose, however, In the cytosol, it is <lb/>phosphorylated into fluorodeoxyglucose 6-phosphate by <lb/>hexokinase enzymes. Once in this form, further glycolysis is <lb/>prevented as it cannot be converted to deoxyfructose 6-<lb/>phosphate, leaving fluorodeoxyglucose 6-phosphate trapped <lb/>inside the cell (Pauwels et al., 2000). This accumulation can then <lb/>serve as a contrast agent for imaging by detection of high energy <lb/>gamma rays emitted from the decaying 18 F atoms (Sung et al., 2020). <lb/>The C2 position has also been used to functionalise fluorescent <lb/>probes as sensing agents, which is expertly reviewed by Kim <lb/>et al. (2012). <lb/>To this end, our group successfully synthesized and completely <lb/>characterized a series of C2 modified Pt (IV) glycoconjugates based <lb/>on glucosamine (Figure 1B); the reduction properties and the <lb/>physiological stability through treatment with ascorbic acid is <lb/>also assessed. We took advantage of the amino functionality <lb/>already present in this monossacharide, to avoid lenghty <lb/>synthetic strategies aimed at the selective functionalization of the <lb/>C2 position in glucose. (Wang and Demchenko, 2019). To the best <lb/>of our knowledge, this is the first time that Pt (IV) glucosamine-<lb/>conjugates functionalised at C2 are reported in literature. <lb/>In this study, we aim to comprehensively evaluate the biological <lb/>activity of this series of C2-functionalised glucosamine-conjugates <lb/>Pt (IV) prodrugs, shedding light on their cytotoxicity profiles, and <lb/>potential for targeting different cancer cells. As already <lb/>demonstrated, the presence of the glycoconjugates enhanced the <lb/>tumour-targeting capabilities of the drugs and improved <lb/>pharmacokinetic profiles compared to traditional platinum agents <lb/>(Moynihan et al., 2021). Through their interaction with the class <lb/>1 glucose transporters (GLUTs), which are overexpressed in cancer <lb/>cells, these glycoconjugates enable targeted therapy, delivering <lb/>cisplatin specifically to malignant tissues while minimizing off-<lb/>target effects (Zambrano et al., 2019). <lb/>Through the exploration of the proposed complexes in 2D and <lb/>3D scaffold-based in vitro model, we seek to elucidate the <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>(A) Structures of the three globally approved Pt (II) <lb/>chemotherapeutics, cisplatin, carboplatin and oxaliplatin. (B) General <lb/>structure of the four novel C2 glycoconjugated Pt (IV) pro-drugs <lb/>based on the cisplatin scaffold. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>therapeutic potential of these novel compounds and their role in <lb/>advancing the field of platinum-based chemotherapy. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>All reagents and reactants were purchased from commercial <lb/>sources. The two sources used were Sigma-Aldrich and Fluorochem. <lb/>All solvents were used without further purification. Compounds <lb/>9-13 were synthesised as previously reported (Nokami et al., 2009; <lb/>Miller et al., 2015; Arimitsu et al., 2020). Cisplatin and oxoplatin <lb/>were synthesised as previously reported (Dhara, 1970; Chen <lb/>et al., 2020). <lb/>The elemental analysis studies (carbon, hydrogen, and <lb/>nitrogen) were performed by means of a PerkinElmer <lb/>2400 series II analyzer. HR-Mass Spectra were recorded with a <lb/>Waters LCT Premier XE Spectrometer. NMR: 1 H, 13 C and 195 Pt <lb/>NMR spectra were obtained in a solution of D 2 O or DMSO-d 6 at <lb/>300 K, in 5-mm sample tubes, with a premium shielded Agilent <lb/>Varian 500 MHz (operating at 500.13, 125.75, and 107.49 MHz, <lb/>respectively). The 1 H and 13 C chemical shift was referenced to the <lb/>residual impurity of the solvent. The external reference was <lb/>Na 2 PtCl 4 in D 2 O (adjusted to δ = -1628 ppm from Na 2 PtCl 6 ) <lb/>for 195 Pt. The stability was followed using high-performance liquid <lb/>chromatography (HPLC) with a Phenomenex Luna C18 (5 μM, <lb/>100 Å, 250 mm × 4.60 mm i.d.) column at room temperature at a <lb/>flow rate of 1.0 mL/min with 254 nm UV detection. Mobile phase <lb/>containing 80:20 acetonitrile (0.1% trifluoroacetic acid): water <lb/>(0.1% trifluoroacetic acid): the complexes were dissolved in <lb/>DMF (0.5 mL) and diluted to a final concentration of 0.5 mM <lb/>using acetonitrile and water solution (1/1) and 2 mM 4-(2-<lb/>hydroxyethyl)piperazine-1-ethanesulfonic acid (HEPES) buffer <lb/>(pH 6.8). Infrared (IR) spectra were recorded in the region <lb/>4000-400 cm -1 on a Perkin Elmer precisely spectrum 100 FT/IR <lb/>spectrometer. The solid samples were run using ATR. <lb/>Reduction studies <lb/>Measurements were obtained in a mixture 1/1 of DMSO-d 6 and <lb/>PBS buffer (pH = 6.8) at 300 K, in 5-mm sample tubes, with a <lb/>premium shielded Agilent Varian 500 MHz (operating at <lb/>500.13 MHz). Complex 3 (5 mg, 6.12 µmol) was dissolved in <lb/>250 µL of DMSO-d 6 . Ascorbic acid (10 mg, 10 Equiv.) was <lb/>dissolved in 250 µL of PBS buffer and added to the platinum <lb/>complex. 1 H NMR spectra were recorded every 7 min for 1 h. <lb/>After no reduction had taken place initially, the 1 H NMR <lb/>spectrum was recorded every hour for 4 hours, and finally every <lb/>24 h until full reduction of Pt (IV) to Pt (II) and cleavage of the axial <lb/>ligand was observed after 72 h. Complex 4 (5 mg, 7.19 µmol) was <lb/>dissolved in 250 µL of DMSO-d 6 . Ascorbic acid (12 mg, 10 Equiv.) <lb/>was dissolved in 250 µL of PBS buffer and added to the solution <lb/>containing the complex. The 1 H NMR spectra were recorded every <lb/>7 min for 1 h. After no reduction had taken place initially, the 1 H <lb/>NMR spectrum was recorded every hour for 2 hours, and finally <lb/>every 24 h until full reduction of Pt (IV) to Pt (II) and cleavage of the <lb/>axial ligand was observed after 24 h. <lb/>In vitro biological evaluation <lb/>In vitro screening of the four complexes (1-4) were performed to <lb/>evaluate their biological activity towards different phenotypes of <lb/>tumour cells: three osteosarcoma cell lines (MG63, U2-OS and <lb/>SAOS-2) and one Human Adenocarcinoma cell lines (MDA-MB-<lb/>468) and one Human Glioblastoma cell lines (U87), compared to <lb/>cisplatin. The drugs were reconstituted in Dimethyl Sulfoxide <lb/>(DMSO) at 1 mg/mL concentration before being diluted in <lb/>culture media at the required concentration. A 2D in vitro <lb/>screening of all the drugs was performed at 72 h at different <lb/>concentrations (15, 30, and 60 µM) on all the different cell lines <lb/>in terms of cell viability. <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>(A) 1 H-NMR of complex 1 in DMSO-d 6 ; (B) 195 Pt-NMR of complex 2 in DMSO-d 6 ; (C) HR-MS spectrum of complex 2. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>Based on the outcome of the screening, the anticancer activity of <lb/>complexes 3 and 4 supplied at 30 µM was evaluated in a more <lb/>predictive 3D in vitro scaffold-based model of osteosarcoma. For the <lb/>model, a composite hydroxyapatite-based scaffold (MgHA/Coll) as a <lb/>bone-like matrix was used in combination with MG63 cells and after <lb/>72 h of culture with the complexes, cellular uptake, cell viability and <lb/>morphology were evaluated. For both 2D and 3D in vitro cell <lb/>cultures, cisplatin was used as a control group and cells only <lb/>were used as a negative control. <lb/>Cell culture <lb/>Human Osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 (ATCC ® CRL1427 ™ ), <lb/>SAOS-2 (ATCC ® HTB-85 ™ ), U2-OS (ATCC ® HTB-96 ™ ); Human <lb/>Adenocarcinoma cell lines isolated from breast cancers MDA-MB-468 <lb/>(ATCC ® HTB231 ™ ); and Human Glioblastoma cell lines U87 (ATCC ® <lb/>HTB14 ™ ) were purchased from American Type Culture Collection <lb/>(ATCC) and used for this study. <lb/>MG63 cell line was cultured in DMEM F12-GlutaMAX ™ <lb/>Modified Medium (Gibco) supplemented with 10% Foetal Bovine <lb/>Serum (FBS) (Gibco) and 1% of penicillin/streptomycin mixture <lb/>(pen/strep) (100 U/mL-100 μg/mL, Gibco). SAOS-2 cell line was <lb/>cultured in McCoy&apos;s 5A Modified Medium (Gibco) <lb/>supplemented with 15% and 10% FBS, respectively, and 1% <lb/>pen/strep. U2-OS cells were cultured using McCoy&apos;s 5 A <lb/>(modified) medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% Pen/ <lb/>Strep. MDA MB 468 cells were cultured in growth media using <lb/>RPMI 1640 (Gibco), 10% FBS and 1% Pen/Strep; and U87 cells <lb/>were grown in a complete medium composed of MEM-<lb/>nucleosides no-ascorbic-acid medium (Gibco), 10% FBS and <lb/>1% Pen/Strep. <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Reduction of complexes 3 (A) and 4 (B) by a 10-fold excess of ascorbic acid. Observed as a series of 1 H NMR spectra over 72 h (A) and 24 h (B) in a <lb/>mixture 1/1 of DMSO-d 6 and PBS (pH = 6.8). Peaks represent the triazole protons of complex 3 (A) and 4 (B), which over time are converted to the triazole <lb/>protons of their corresponding ligands 18 and 20, respectively. Showing a complete cleavage of the axial carbohydrate ligand. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>Cells were kept in an incubator at 37 °C under controlled <lb/>humidity and 5% CO 2 atmosphere conditions. Cells were <lb/>detached from culture flasks by trypsinization and centrifuged. <lb/>The cell number and viability were determined by Trypan Blue <lb/>Dye Exclusion test and all cell handling procedures were performed <lb/>under laminar flow hood in sterility conditions. <lb/>Synthesis of bone mimetic scaffolds <lb/>The Mg-doped hydroxyapatite collagen composite scaffolds <lb/>were designed and synthesized at ISSMC of CNR of Italy <lb/>(Krishnakumar et al., 2018). Briefly, an acid aqueous <lb/>suspension was prepared by dispersing 150 g of type I collagen <lb/>gel (Typeone Biomaterials S.r.l., Calimera, LE, Italy) was diluted <lb/>into a phosphoric acid solution (2.4 g in 500 mL; H 3 PO 4 , 85 wt%, <lb/>Sigma) at room temperature to obtain an acidic aqueous <lb/>homogenous suspension. Separately, a basic aqueous <lb/>suspension was obtained by mixing 2.7 g of calcium hydroxide <lb/>(Ca(OH) 2 , 95 wt%, Sigma) and 0.35 g of magnesium chloride <lb/>(MgCl 2 •6H 2 O, 99 wt%, Sigma) in 500 mL of milli-Q water at <lb/>room temperature to obtain a basic aqueous homogenous <lb/>suspension. The acidic suspension was dripped into the basic <lb/>one at 25 °C ± 2 °C under continuous stirring conditions and <lb/>maturated for 2 h. Later, the slurry solution was rinsed thrice <lb/>in milli-Q water and filtered through a metallic sieve (150 m) to <lb/>exclude unreacted counter ions. The recovered slurry solution <lb/>was cross-linked with 2 wt% BDDGE (respect to Collagen) at <lb/>25 °C ± 2 °C for 24 h and at 4 °C for other 24 h. Later, the solution <lb/>was rinsed thrice in milli-Q water to remove any residues and <lb/>freeze-dried (-40 °C and + 25 °C) for 48 h under 0.086 mbar <lb/>vacuum conditions (LIO 3000 PLT, 5PASCAL, Italy). The <lb/>obtained scaffolds (6 × 4 mm) named bone mimetic scaffolds <lb/>were sterilized by 25 kGy γ-ray irradiation before the use. <lb/>3D scaffold-based osteosarcoma models <lb/>(3D OS model) <lb/>For the development of the in vitro 3D scaffold-based <lb/>osteosarcoma model, bone mimetic scaffolds were used as bone-<lb/>like matrix in combination with MG63 cells. The scaffolds were <lb/>conditioned in culture media for 24 h before the cell seeding. <lb/>MG63 cell line was seeded with a density of 3.0 × 10 4 , for cell <lb/>viability evaluation and 5.0 × 10 4 , for platin uptake evaluation, per <lb/>scaffold by dropping the cellular suspension on the material upper <lb/>surface followed by 30 min pre-adhesion at 37 °C before cell media <lb/>addition. The 3D OS model was grown in the incubator under <lb/>standard culture medium condition for 72 h to allow cell grown and <lb/>colonization of the scaffold, then the medium was changed, and the <lb/>drugs were added. The in vitro 3D OS models were cultured in the <lb/>presence of the drugs for 72 h at 37 °C under controlled humidity and <lb/>5% CO 2 atmosphere conditions, the cells grown in 3D in standard <lb/>condition, without the drugs, were used as control group (3D cells <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>2D in vitro drug screening by MTT assay. Cell viability evaluation after 72 h of incubation with complexes. Data are reported in the graph as <lb/>percentage (%) mean ± standard error of the mean. Statistical analyses are reported in the graph, *p-value ≤ 0.05; **p-value ≤ 0.01; ***p-value ≤ <lb/>0.001 and ***p-value ≤ 0.0001. α: cisplatin vs. complex 4 p-value ≤ 0.01 and vs. complex 1, 2, 3 p-value ≤ 0.0001; β: complex 4 respects to complex 1, 2, <lb/>3 p-value ≤ 0.0001. γ: complex 3 vs. all the drugs p-value ≤ 0.0001 and complex 3 vs. 1 p-value ≤ 0.05; ɸ: complex 4 vs. all p-value ≤ 0.000; π: <lb/>cisplatin vs. all p-value ≤ 0.0001; δ: cisplatin vs. all p-value ≤ 0.0001; ε: complex 4 vs. all p-value ≤ 0.0001. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>only). All cell handling procedures were performed under a laminar <lb/>flow hood in sterility conditions. <lb/>MTT cell viability assay <lb/>A quantitative analysis of cell viability was carried out by MTT <lb/>assay, following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. For the in vitro 2D <lb/>cell cultures, all cell lines were seeded at a density of 5.0 × 10 3 cells/ <lb/>well in 96 well-plates. For in vitro 3D cell cultures, see the &quot;3D <lb/>scaffold-based models of osteosarcoma&quot; paragraph. The MTT <lb/>reagent <lb/>[3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium <lb/>bromide] (5 mg/mL) was dissolved in Phosphate Saline Buffer 1X <lb/>(PBS 1X). At 72 h, the cells were incubated with 10% media volume <lb/>MTT solution for 2 h at 37 °C, 5% CO 2 and controlled humidity <lb/>conditions. The cell culture media was removed and substituted with <lb/>DMSO (Merck) dissolving formazan crystals derived from MTT <lb/>conversion by metabolically active cells. For 3D scaffold-based <lb/>models of osteosarcoma, each scaffold was transferred into a <lb/>2 mL Eppendorf and broken by pestles after DMSO addition. <lb/>After 15 min of incubation under slight stirring conditions, the <lb/>absorbance of formazan was red at 570 nm by using a Multiskan FC <lb/>Microplate Photometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The values of <lb/>absorbance are directly proportional to the number of metabolic <lb/>active cells in each well. One experiment was carried out and a <lb/>biological triplicate for each condition was performed. For the 3D <lb/>tumour models, one biological experiment was performed, and two <lb/>scaffolds for each condition were used. <lb/>Cell morphology evaluation <lb/>For the in vitro 3D cell cultures cells were treated as previously <lb/>described. 3D cell cultures were fixed in 4% buffered Paraformaldehyde <lb/>(PFA) following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. The fixed samples <lb/>were permeabilized in PBS 1X with 0.1% (v/v) Triton X-100 (Merck) for <lb/>5 min at room temperature and F-actin filaments were highlighted with <lb/>Alexa Fluor 488 Phalloidin (Invitrogen) for 20 min at room <lb/>temperature in the dark. DAPI (600 nM) counterstaining was <lb/>performed for cell nuclei identification, following the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. The images were acquired by using an Inverted Ti-E <lb/>Fluorescent Microscope. <lb/>Quantification of cellular uptake of Pt <lb/>To evaluate the Pt cell internalization in the 3D tumour models, <lb/>inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry (ICP-<lb/>OES, Agilent Technologies 5100 ICP-OES, Santa Clara, <lb/>United States) was used. The 3D model was prepared and treated <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Effect of complexes 3 and 4 complexes on cellular behaviors and uptake in 3D MG63 model. (A) Cell viability evaluation after 72 h of incubation with <lb/>30 µm of complexes by MTT assay. Data are reported in the graph as percentage (%) mean ± standard error of the mean. Statistical analyses are reported <lb/>in the graph, *p-value ≤ 0.05; **p-value ≤ 0.01; ***p-value ≤ 0.001. (B) ICP-OES analysis of the cell internalized Cisplatin, mean ± standard error. (C). one <lb/>respective image for each drug and cells only shows cell morphology; phalloidin in red stains for actin filaments and DAPI in blue stains for cell nuclei. <lb/>Scale bars 200 µm. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>as mentioned in the previous section. The ICP analysis were <lb/>performed 24 h after the complexes supply. <lb/>Briefly, each sample was washed with 400 µL PBS 1X and stored <lb/>at -80 °C until the analysis. ICP-OES was used for the quantitative <lb/>determination of Pt ions. Briefly, the samples were dissolved with <lb/>500 µL nitric acid (65 wt%) and 2.1 mL of Milli-Q water followed by <lb/>sonication for 30 min in an ultrasonicated bath. Cells only were <lb/>prepared similarly. The analytical wavelength of Pt was 265.945 nm. <lb/>Pt (pg) per scaffold were quantified and a biological triplicate for each <lb/>condition was performed. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed by using GraphPad Prism <lb/>Software (8.0.1 version). Cell viability results were represented in the <lb/>graphs as mean percentage of cell viability respect to cells only (both 2D <lb/>and 3D model) ± standard deviation. The 2D screening results were <lb/>analysed by Two-way analysis of variance (Two-way ANOVA) and <lb/>Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test. The Cell viability and Pt Uptake in <lb/>the 3D model were analysed by One-way analysis of variance (One-way <lb/>ANOVA) and Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test. <lb/>SCHEME 2 <lb/>Synthetic route for the synthesis of complex 2: (i) NaHCO 3, Benzyl chloroformate, H 2 O, 16 h, rt, 92%; (ii) HCl/MeOH soln. 1.25 M, 80 °C, 18 h; (iii) <lb/>Pyridine, Ac 2 O, rt, 16 h, 73%; (iv) Pd/C, H 2 , DCM, rt, 16 h; (v) NaN 3 , Tf 2 O, K 2 CO 3 , CuSO 4 .5H 2 O, DCM, MeOH, H 2 O, rt, 16 h, 35%; (vi) 4-pentynoic acid, <lb/>CuSO 4 .5H 2 O, NaAsc, t-BuOH, H 2 O, rt, 16 h, 65%; (vii) NHS, EDCI, DCM, rt, 16 h, 91%; (viii) Oxoplatin, DMSO, 60 °C, 16 h, 86%. <lb/>SCHEME 1 <lb/>Synthetic route for the synthesis of complex 1: (i) Tf 2 O, NaN 3 , H 2 O, DCM, K 2 CO 3, MeOH, CuSO 4 , Ac 2 O, Pyridine, rt, 16 h, 74%; (ii) 4-pentynoic acid, <lb/>CuSO 4 , NaAsc, t-BuOH, THF, H 2 O, rt, 16 h, 59%; (iii) EDCI, NHS, DCM, rt, 16 h, 89%; (iv) DMSO, 60 °C, 16 h, 67%. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>Results and discussion <lb/>Synthesis and characterisation <lb/>As described in the introduction, the aim of this work is to <lb/>synthesize Pt (IV) anticancer prodrugs, based on the cisplatin <lb/>scaffold which is modified with sugar targeting moieties through <lb/>conjugation at the C2 position of glucosamine. The sugar <lb/>moieties are connected to the platinum centre via a triazolyl <lb/>linker exploiting the versatility and mild conditions of the &quot;click&quot; <lb/>CuAAC reaction, producing four novel complexes, three <lb/>protected with acetyl protecting groups and one free sugar <lb/>derivative. The complexes were successfully synthesized as <lb/>shown in Schemes 1-3, in high yield and purity. (See <lb/>Supplementary Material for a complete description of the <lb/>syntheses and spectroscopical characterisation). <lb/>Scheme 1 shows the synthetic route to produce complex 1, which <lb/>contains a mixture of the α/β-anomers of the glucosamine moiety. The <lb/>synthesis of compound 6 begins from the commercially available <lb/>D-glucosamine hydrochloride which undergoes a diazo transfer <lb/>reaction using the freshly prepared diazo transfer reagent triflyl <lb/>azide, followed by acetylation with acetic anhydride and pyridine. A <lb/>CuAAC &quot;click&quot; reaction is then used to conjugate the resulting azide (6) <lb/>to 4-pentynoic acid (ii), the carboxylic acid product (7) is then <lb/>converted to its corresponding active ester (8) using EDCI and NHS <lb/>(iii). Finally, a trans esterification reaction is used to obtain complex 1 <lb/>with a mixture of α-and β-anomers (iv). The final complex 1 was <lb/>characterised by 1 H, 13 C, 195 Pt-NMR, Elemental Analyses and Mass <lb/>spectroscopy (See Experimental Section). <lb/>To avoid the mixture of α-and β-anomers, complex 2, which is the <lb/>O-methyl derivative of complex 1, in which only the α-anomer is <lb/>present, was synthesized according to Scheme 2. Compounds 9, 10, 11, <lb/>12 and 13 were synthesized according to literature procedures (Nokami <lb/>et al., 2009; Miller et al., 2015; Arimitsu et al., 2020). Briefly, the <lb/>synthesis begins with the protection of D-glucosamine hydrochloride <lb/>using benzyl chloroformate (9), which then undergoes Fischer <lb/>glycosylation with methanol (10) followed by the acetylation of the <lb/>remaining hydroxyl groups, to give the corresponding a-methyl <lb/>O-glycoside after chromatography (11). The C2 amine is reformed <lb/>using hydrogenative deprotection (12) and a diazo transfer with triflyl <lb/>SCHEME 3 <lb/>Synthetic route for the synthesis of 3 and 4: (i) NaHCO 3, Benzyl chloroformate, H 2 O, 16 h, rt, 92%; (ii) HCl/MeOH soln. 1.25 M, 80 °C, 18 h; (iii) Pyridine, <lb/>Ac 2 O, rt, 16 h, 73%; (iv) Pd/C, H 2 , DCM, rt, 16 h; (v) Bromoacetyl bromide, NEt 3 , DCM, N 2 , rt, 16 h, 71%; (vi) NaN 3 , DMF, N 2 , 80 °C, 16 h, 98%; (vii) 4-pentynoic <lb/>acid, NaAsc, CuSO 4 .5H 2 O, t-BuOH, H 2 O, rt, 16 h, 41%; (viii) EDCI, NHS, DCM, rt, 16 h, 82%; (ix) Oxoplatin, DMSO, 60 °C, 16 h, 82%; (x) NEt 3 , MeOH, H 2 O, <lb/>40 °C, 16 h, 98%; (xi) TSTU, NEt 3 , DMF, rt, 20 min, 79%; (xii) Oxoplatin, dry DMSO, 40 °C, 5 days, 39%. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>azide is used to produce 13. The CUAAC reaction (14) and the NHS <lb/>esterification reactions (15) used similar conditions to Scheme 1, <lb/>however, the click reaction in this scheme and in Scheme 3 <lb/>required optimisation through the amount of catalyst used and <lb/>changing the solvent system (See Experimental). The complex 2 <lb/>was characterised using the same techniques for complexes 1. <lb/>Unfortunately, the deprotected derivatives of 1 and 2 could not <lb/>be synthesized: in the case of complex 1, the reactivity of the <lb/>hydroxyl at the anomeric position in the deprotected carboxylic <lb/>acid (7) led to the formation of impurities which we were unable <lb/>to purify in the final product. <lb/>Scheme 3 shows the synthesis of complex 3 and its free sugar <lb/>derivative, complex 4. For the synthesis of these complexes, the azido <lb/>functionality (17) is not directly connected to the carbohydrate ring as in <lb/>intermediates (6, 13), used in the synthesis of complexes 1 and 2; instead, <lb/>a linker featuring an amide rseemblin N-acetyl glucosamine derivatives is <lb/>used. The free amine (12), also intermediate in the synthesis of complex <lb/>2, is now converted to an amide through reaction with bromoacetyl <lb/>bromide 5) and this bromide then undergoes nucleophilic substitution to <lb/>give the corresponding azide (17). Steps (vii), (viii), and (ix) follow the <lb/>same procedures as for Scheme 2 to yield complex 3, however in this case <lb/>it was possible to isolate the free sugar derivative (complex 4). The <lb/>synthesis of this complex begins with a deprotection of the carboxylic <lb/>acid 18 to form compound 20 and the corresponding ester 21 is formed <lb/>using TSTU (N,N,N′,N′-Tetramethyl-O-(N-succinimidyl)uronium <lb/>tetrafluoroborate) in just 20 min (xi). This was then added dropwise <lb/>(under anhydrous conditions) to a suspension of a large excess of <lb/>oxoplatin at 40 °C to yield complex 4 over 5 days (xii). The <lb/>complexes were characterised using the same techniques as for <lb/>complexes 1 and 2. All the complexes show the typical features of Pt <lb/>(IV) species based on cisplatin scaffold (Supplementary Material). For <lb/>example, in Figure 2A is reported the 1 H NMR of complex 1 in DMSO <lb/>where are clearly visible the NH 3 protons of the platinum scaffold <lb/>appearing as a broad triplet at δ 6.00 ppm, that is a typical feature of <lb/>mono-substituted Pt (IV) complexes. In Figure 2B is reported the 195 Pt <lb/>NMR of complex 2 in DMSO which show a peak at δ 1047 ppm, that is <lb/>also typical of Pt complexes when they are in the oxidation state +4. The <lb/>HR-MS spectrum of complex 2 is shown in Figure 2C which show a <lb/>peak m/z (+) 759.1123, 759.1141 corresponding to [M + H] + and <lb/>another at m/z (+) 781.0964 corresponding to [M + Na] + . Both <lb/>peaks show the typical isotip pattern distribution pf Pt-based complexes. <lb/>The complexes were stable in aqueous condition (DMSO/ <lb/>HEPES Buffer 4/6) for up to 4 days at r.t. For a confirmation of <lb/>the activation by intracellular reduction that occur in Pt (IV) species, <lb/>the behaviour of the Pt (IV) prodrugs was studied by the addition of <lb/>ascorbic acid into a solution of complexes 3 and 4 (DMSO-PBS <lb/>buffer 1/1), taken as reference for an acetylated and a free sugar <lb/>derivatives (Nokami et al., 2009). The reduction process was <lb/>followed by 1 H-NMR with complete release of the carbohydrate <lb/>carboxylic acids axial ligand 18 and 20 after 72 h (3) and 24 h (4). <lb/>This can be followed by an upfield movement in chemical shift of the <lb/>singlet triazole peak (Figure 3 and Supplementary Material). <lb/>Biological evaluation <lb/>To comprehensively evaluate the biological activity of C2-<lb/>functionalised glycoconjugates Pt (IV) prodrugs a screening of <lb/>the anticancer effect of the complexes was performed using <lb/>different cell lines in 2D and 3D scaffold-based in vitro models, <lb/>including breast cancer (MDAMB 468), osteosarcoma (U2-OS, <lb/>SOAS-2 and MG63) and glioblastoma (U87) (Giusto et al., 2022). <lb/>As expected, the cell viability evaluation demonstrated a dose-<lb/>dependent cytotoxic effect of all the drugs affecting all the cancer cell <lb/>types, with weak differences depending on the cell phenotypes (Figure 4). <lb/>Looking in detail at the effect of the proposed complexes and <lb/>comparing each other with the reference drug cisplatin, it is possible <lb/>to observe an increased anticancer effect exerted by all the complexes <lb/>compared to cisplatin. Even at a low concentration (15 µM), the <lb/>complexes exhibited a higher cytotoxic impact compared to the <lb/>reference in all cell lines, with exceptions noted in the SAOS2 cell <lb/>line. Statistically significant differences were observed in MDAMB <lb/>48 cells (complexes 1 and 2), U87 cells (complexes 1 and 3), U2-OS <lb/>cells (complexes 1, 2, and 3), and MG63 cells (complexes 1-4). <lb/>Notably, complex 3 demonstrated higher efficacy also compared to <lb/>the other proposed complexes in U2-OS and MG63 cells, with this <lb/>effect strengthened at 30 µM relative to cisplatin and complex 4. At a <lb/>concentration of 60 μM, the complexes consistently exhibited higher <lb/>toxicity compared to cisplatin, with statistically significant <lb/>differences. However, at this elevated concentration, discernible <lb/>distinctions among the complexes were not observed, a trend <lb/>consistent across all cell lines except SAOS-2, where no <lb/>differences were detected (Figure 1). The different cellular <lb/>behaviour observed among the osteosarcoma cell lines can be <lb/>attributed to the intrinsic biological differences of the three <lb/>phenotypes used as models. (Visvader, 2011). <lb/>Even if complexes 1, 2 and 3 are acetylated derivatives, these <lb/>results suggest there may be an involvement of the GLUTs receptor <lb/>in the internalization and related anticancer effect of the cisplatin <lb/>glycoconjugates. It was reasonable to hypothesize that the presence <lb/>of the C2-functionalised glucosamine-conjugates, increases the drug <lb/>uptake in the cancer cells overexpressing the GLUTs receptor, as <lb/>already demonstrated in all the cancer cell lines used, osteosarcoma <lb/>cells, MDAMB 468 and U87 (Adekola et al., 2012). The observed <lb/>behaviour of SAOS-2 cells, where the differences of the complex <lb/>effects with respect to cisplatin are negligible, strengthens the role of <lb/>the GLUT receptor in the increased toxic effect of the complexes. In <lb/>fact, it has been demonstrated that the GLUT1 mRNA level was <lb/>lower in SAOS-2 if compared to MG63 and U2-OS (Cifuentes <lb/>et al., 2011). <lb/>To deeply investigate the strongest effect shown from complex 3, <lb/>a proof of concept in vitro was performed using a more relevant 3D <lb/>scaffold-based cancer model. MG63 cell line was cultured on a 3D <lb/>scaffold that mimics the feature of the bone extracellular matrix, as <lb/>previously demonstrated (Krishnakumar et al., 2018; Bassi et al., <lb/>2020). Together with complex 3, we decided to study the behaviour <lb/>on 3D of complex 4 that is the analogue of 3 with the free sugar (not <lb/>acetylated) to shed further light on the role of the <lb/>carbohydrate moiety. <lb/>The cell viability evaluation confirmed the anticancer effect of 3 <lb/>(very similar to cisplatin) that shows higher activity with respect <lb/>complex 4, in line with what was observed on the 2D studies (Figures <lb/>5A,C). To confirm the role of the carbohydrate, we studied the drug <lb/>uptake by ICP-OES analysis. The results showed that both the tested <lb/>complexes 3 and 4 are highly internalized by the cells compared to <lb/>the cisplatin, with the highest cellular internalisation observed for <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<body>complex 4 possessing the free carbohydrate moiety, supporting the <lb/>role of the GLUT receptor in the cellular uptake (Figure 5B). <lb/>The apparent discrepancy between cytotoxicity and uptake <lb/>results between complexes 3 and 4 can be rationalised by <lb/>analysing the reduction behaviour of the two complexes in the <lb/>presence of ascorbic acid (Figure 3). As discussed earlier, complex 3 <lb/>is reduced in 72 h while complex 4 only in 24 h. Even if complex 4 is <lb/>internalised better than 3 as expected due to the presence of the free <lb/>carbohydrate moiety, once inside the cytoplasm it is quicker <lb/>reduced, forming cisplatin in 24 h. On the other hand, complex 3 <lb/>takes 72 h to completely release cisplatin after internalisation and <lb/>this slow release could explain the higher activity of complex 3 with <lb/>respect to 4 that releases cisplatin too quickly (cytotoxicity studies <lb/>were performed at 72 h). The morphological analysis (Figure 5C) <lb/>reveals that the cells successfully grow and colonize the scaffolds, <lb/>integrating with the bone mimetic matrix. They exhibit the expected <lb/>nuclear and cytoplasmic morphologies, along with cytoplasmic <lb/>extensions characteristic of cells interacting with biomimetic <lb/>materials. A noticeable decrease in cell number and a decline in <lb/>cell morphology are observed in the 3D cell culture treated with the <lb/>complexes and the reference drug compared to untreated cells (cells <lb/>only). This observation confirms the anticancer activity and <lb/>viability results. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In this paper, we have reported the synthesis and <lb/>characterisation of a series of Pt (IV) complexes based on <lb/>cisplatin scaffold tethering in axial position a glucosamine <lb/>moiety conjugated through the C2 position of the sugar ring. <lb/>While different examples of Pt-glycoconjugates complexes are <lb/>reported in literature, also by us (all conjugated via the <lb/>anomeric C1 position), this series represents the first <lb/>example of Pt (IV) prodrugs conjugated with C2-<lb/>functionalised glucosamine derivatives. C2 is an attractive <lb/>position for drug conjugation proven by the fact that 2-<lb/>deoxyglucose is transported by all class 1 GLUTs and <lb/>examples of Pt (II) C2 conjugates supported this point. The <lb/>complexes are very active against a panel of different cancer cell <lb/>lines including breast cancer (MDAMB 468), osteosarcoma <lb/>(U2-OS, SOAS-2 and MG63) and glioblastoma (U87). The <lb/>same very promising results have been obtained also in 3D <lb/>MG63 cell lines. In 3D, the drug uptake of the selected <lb/>complexes 3 and 4 is higher with respect to that one of <lb/>cisplatin indicating a role of the carbohydrate moiety in the <lb/>drug internalisation. Even if a direct comparison with the other <lb/>Pt (IV) C1-functionalised glycoconjugates previously reported <lb/>by us is very difficult to discuss due to the different structures <lb/>and cell lines used, the role of the carbohydrate is demonstrated <lb/>in term of higher cellular uptake and higher anticancer activity. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included in <lb/>the article/Supplementary Material, further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>EM: Data curation, Formal Analysis, Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, Writing-original draft, Writing-review and <lb/>editing. MG-C: Data curation, Formal Analysis, Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, Writing-original draft, Writing-review and <lb/>editing. <lb/>MS: <lb/>Methodology, <lb/>Writing-original <lb/>draft, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. AR: Methodology, Writing-original <lb/>draft, Writing-review and editing. SP: Methodology, <lb/>Writing-original draft, Writing-review and editing. TV-T: <lb/>Conceptualization, <lb/>Formal <lb/>Analysis, <lb/>Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, <lb/>Supervision, <lb/>Writing-original <lb/>draft, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. MM: Conceptualization, Data <lb/>curation, Formal Analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Software, Supervision, Validation, Visualization, <lb/>Writing-original draft, Writing-review and editing. DM: <lb/>Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, Visualization, <lb/>Writing-original draft, Writing-review and editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work <lb/>was <lb/>funded <lb/>by <lb/>the <lb/>European <lb/>Project <lb/>Horizon <lb/>2020 NANO4TARMED (H2020-WIDESPREAD-2020-5; GA <lb/>number 952063). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>EM is grateful to Maynooth University for sponsoring his <lb/>PhD with a Graduate Teaching Fellowship. Science Foundation <lb/>Ireland 2012 Strategic Opportunity Fund (Infrastructure award <lb/>12/RI/2346/SOF) for NMR facilities. The authors would like to <lb/>thank Luca Salvatore for sharing his knowledge on <lb/>collagen matrix. <lb/>In memoriam <lb/>Dedicated to Jan Belza, a Ph.D. candidate of this consortium <lb/>who deceased too soon. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their <lb/></div>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 <lb/></note>

	<div type="annex">affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the <lb/>editors and the reviewers. Any product that may <lb/>be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by <lb/>its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by <lb/>the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Adekola, K., Rosen, S. T., and Shanmugan, M. (2012). Glucose transporters in cancer <lb/>metabolism. Curr. Op. Oncol. 24, 650-654. doi:10.1097/CCO.0b013e328356da72 <lb/>Alcindor, T., and Beauger, N. (2011). Oxaliplatin: a review in the era of molecularly <lb/>targeted therapy. Curr. Oncol. 18, 18-25. doi:10.3747/co.v18i1.708 <lb/>Arimitsu, K., Yagi, Y., Koshino, K., Nishito, Y., Higuchi, T., Yasui, H., et al. (2020). Synthesis <lb/>of 18 F-labeled streptozotocin derivatives and an in-vivo kinetics study using positron emission <lb/>tomography. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 30, 127400. doi:10.1016/j.bmcl.2020.127400 <lb/>Barnett, J. E. G., Holman, G. D., and Munday, K. A. (1973). Structural requirements <lb/>for binding to the sugar-transport system of the human erythrocyte. Biochem. 131, <lb/>211-221. doi:10.1042/bj1310211 <lb/>Bassi, G., Panseri, S., Dozio, S. M., Sandri, M., Campodoni, E., Dapporto, M., et al. <lb/>(2020). Scaffold-based 3D cellular models mimicking the heterogeneity of osteosarcoma <lb/>stem cell niche. Sci. Rep. 10, 22294. doi:10.1038/s41598-020-79448-y <lb/>Beirne, D. F., Farkaš, B., Donati, C., Gandin, V., Rozas, I., Velasco-Torrijos, T., et al. <lb/>(2023). Novel design of dual-action Pt(IV) anticancer pro-drugs based on cisplatin and <lb/>derivatives of the tyrosine kinase inhibitors imatinib and nilotinib. Dalton Trans. 52, <lb/>14110-14122. doi:10.1039/D3DT02030D <lb/>Brandon, R. J., and Dabrowiak, J. C. (1984). Synthesis, characterization, and <lb/>properties, of a group of platinum(IV) complexes. J. Med. Chem. 27, 861-865. <lb/>doi:10.1021/jm00373a009 <lb/>Callejo, A., Sedó-Cabezón, L., Juan, I. D., and Llorens, J. (2015). Cisplatin-induced <lb/>ototoxicity: effects, mechanisms and protection strategies. Toxics 3, 268-293. doi:10. <lb/>3390/toxics3030268 <lb/>Carbó, R., and Rodríguez, E. (2023). Relevance of sugar transport across the cell <lb/>membrane. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 24, 6085. doi:10.3390/ijms24076085 <lb/>Chen, C. K. J., Kappen, P., Gibson, D., and Hambley, T. W. (2020). Trans-<lb/>Platinum(IV) pro-drugs that exhibit unusual resistance to reduction by endogenous <lb/>reductants and blood Serum but are rapidly activated inside cells: 1 H NMR and XANES <lb/>spectroscopy study. Dalton Trans. 49, 7722-7736. doi:10.1039/d0dt01622e <lb/>Cifuentes, M., Garcia, M. A., Arrabal, P. M., Martinez, F., Yanez, M. J., Jara, N., et al. <lb/>(2011). Insulin regulates GLUT1-mediated glucose transport in MG-63 human <lb/>osteosarcoma cells. J. Cell. Physiol. 226, 1425-1432. doi:10.1002/jcp.22668 <lb/>Deng, D., Xu, C., Sun, P., Wu, J., Yan, C., Hu, M., et al. (2014). Crystal structure of the <lb/>human glucose transporter GLUT1. Nature 510, 121-125. doi:10.1038/nature13306 <lb/>Dhara, S. C. (1970). A rapid method for the synthesis of cis-[Pt(NH 3 ) 2 Cl 2 ]. Indian <lb/>J. Chem. 8, 193-194. <lb/>Giusto, E., Zarska, L., Beirne, D. F., Rossi, A., Bassi, G., Ruffini, A., et al. (2022). <lb/>Graphene oxide nanoplatforms to enhance cisplatin-based drug delivery in anticancer <lb/>therapy. Nanomaterials 12, 2372. doi:10.3390/nano12142372 <lb/>Ho, G. Y., Woodward, N., and Coward, J. I. G. (2016). Cisplatin versus carboplatin: <lb/>comparative review of therapeutic management in solid malignancies. Crit. Rev. Oncol. <lb/>Hematol. 102, 37-46. doi:10.1016/j.critrevonc.2016.03.014 <lb/>Holman, G. D. (2020). Structure, function and regulation of mammalian glucose transporters <lb/>of the SLC2 family. Eur. J. Physiol. 472, 1155-1175. doi:10.1007/s00424-020-02411-3 <lb/>Hu, Y., Sun, B., Zhao, B., Mei, D., Gu, Q., and Tian, Z. (2018). Cisplatin-induced <lb/>cardiotoxicity with midrange ejection fraction: a case report and review of the literature. <lb/>Medicine 97, e13807. doi:10.1097/MD.0000000000013807 <lb/>Kanat, O., Ertas, H., and Caner, B. (2017). Platinum-induced neurotoxicity: a review <lb/>of possible mechanisms. World J. Clin. Oncol. 8, 329-333. doi:10.5306/wjco.v8.i4.329 <lb/>Kim, W. H., Lee, J., Jung, D. W., and Williams, D. R. (2012). Visualizing sweetness: <lb/>increasingly diverse applications for fluorescent-tagged glucose bioprobes and their <lb/>recent structural modifications. Sensors 12, 5005-5027. doi:10.3390/s120405005 <lb/>Krishnakumar, G. S., Gostynska, N., Dapporto, M., Campodoni, E., Montesi, M., <lb/>Panseri, S., et al. (2018). Evaluation of different crosslinking agents on hybrid <lb/>biomimetic collagen-hydroxyapatite composites for regenerative medicine. Int. <lb/>J. Biol. Macromol. 106, 739-748. doi:10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.08.076 <lb/>Ma, J., Liu, H., Xi, Z., Hou, J., Li, Y., Niu, J., et al. (2018). Protected and de-protected <lb/>platinum(IV) glycoconjugates with GLUT1 and OCT2-mediated selective cancer <lb/>targeting: demonstrated enhanced transporter-mediated cytotoxic properties in vitro <lb/>and in vivo. Front. Chem. 6, 386. doi:10.3389/fchem.2018.00386 <lb/>Ma, J., Wang, Q., Huang, Z., Yang, X., Nie, Q., Hao, W., et al. (2017a). Glycosylated <lb/>platinum(IV) complexes as substrates for glucose transporters (GLUTs) and organic <lb/>cation transporters (OCTs) exhibited cancer targeting and human Serum albumin <lb/>binding properties for drug delivery. J. Med. Chem. 60, 5736-5748. doi:10.1021/acs. <lb/>jmedchem.7b00433 <lb/>Ma, J., Wang, Q., Yang, X., Hao, W., Huang, Z., Zhang, J., et al. (2016). <lb/>Glycosylated platinum(IV) prodrugs demonstrated significant therapeutic <lb/>efficacy in cancer cells and minimized side-effects. Dalton Trans. 45, <lb/>11830-11838. doi:10.1039/C6DT02207C <lb/>Ma, J., Yang, X., Hao, W., Huang, Z., Wang, X., and Wang, P. G. (2017b). Mono-<lb/>functionalized glycosylated platinum(IV) complexes possessed both PH and redox <lb/>dual-responsive properties: exhibited enhanced safety and preferentially accumulated in <lb/>cancer cells in vitro and in vivo. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 128, 45-55. doi:10.1016/j.ejmech. <lb/>2017.01.032 <lb/>Miller, D. C., Carbain, B., Beale, G. S., Alhasan, S. F., Reeves, H. L., Baisch, U., et al. <lb/>(2015). Regioselective sulfamoylation at low temperature enables concise syntheses of <lb/>putative small molecule inhibitors of sulfatases. Org. Biomol. Chem. 13, 5279-5284. <lb/>doi:10.1039/c5ob00211g <lb/>Miller, R. P., Tadagavadi, R. K., Ramesh, G., and Reeves, W. B. (2010). Mechanisms of <lb/>cisplatin nephrotoxicity. Toxins 2, 2490-2518. doi:10.3390/toxins2112490 <lb/>Moynihan, E., Bassi, G., Ruffini, A., Panseri, S., Montesi, M., Velasco-Torrijos, T., <lb/>et al. (2021). Click Pt(IV)-Carbohydrates pro-drugs for treatment of osteosarcoma. <lb/>Front. Chem. 9, 795997. doi:10.3389/fchem.2021.795997 <lb/>Moynihan, E., Panseri, S., Bassi, G., Rossi, A., Campodoni, E., Dempsey, E., et al. <lb/>(2023). Development of novel Pt(IV)-Carbohydrate derivatives as targeted <lb/>anticancer agents against osteosarcoma. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 24, 6028. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>ijms24076028 <lb/>Nokami, T., Shibuya, A., Manabe, S., Ito, Y., and Yoshida, J. I. (2009). A-and β-<lb/>glycosyl sulfonium ions: generation and reactivity. Chem. Eur. J. 15, 2252-2255. doi:10. <lb/>1002/chem.200802293 <lb/>Patra, M., Awuah, S. G., and Lippard, S. J. (2016). Chemical approach to positional <lb/>isomers of glucose-platinum conjugates reveals specific cancer targeting through <lb/>glucose-transporter-mediated uptake in vitro and in vivo. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 138, <lb/>12541-12551. doi:10.1021/jacs.6b06937 <lb/>Pauwels, E. K. J., Sturm, E. J. C., Bombardieri, E., Cleton, F. J., and Stokkel, M. P. M. <lb/>(2000). Positron-emission tomography with [ 18 F]fluorodeoxyglucose. J. Cancer Res. <lb/>Clin. Oncol. 126, 549-559. doi:10.1007/pl00008465 <lb/>Sung, Y., Tetrault, M. A., Takahashi, K., Ouyang, J., Pratx, G., Fakhri, G. E., et al. <lb/>(2020). Dependence of fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) uptake on cell cycle and dry Mass: a <lb/>single-cell study using a multi-modal radiography platform. Sci. Rep. 10, 4280. doi:10. <lb/>1038/s41598-020-59515-0 <lb/>Taghizadeh, F., Hosseinimehr, S. J., Zargari, M., Karimpour Malekshah, A., Mirzaei, <lb/>M., and Talebpour Amiri, F. (2021). Alleviation of cisplatin-induced hepatotoxicity by <lb/>gliclazide: involvement of oxidative stress and caspase-3 activity. Pharmacol. Res. <lb/>Perspect. 9, e00788. doi:10.1002/prp2.788 <lb/>Visvader, J. E. (2011). Cells of origin in cancer. Nature 469, 314-322. doi:10.1038/ <lb/>nature09781 <lb/>Wang, Q., Huang, Z., Ma, J., Lu, X., Zhang, L., Wang, X., et al. (2016). Design, <lb/>synthesis and biological evaluation of a novel series of glycosylated platinum(IV) <lb/>complexes as antitumor agents. Dalton Trans. 45, 10366-10374. doi:10.1039/c6dt01562j <lb/>Wang, T., and Demchenko, A. V. (2019). Synthesis of carbohydrate building blocks <lb/>via regioselective uniform protection/deprotection strategies. Org. Biomol. Chem. 17, <lb/>4934-4950. doi:10.1039/C9OB00573K <lb/>Warburg, O., Wind, F., and Negelein, N. (1927). The Metabolism of tumors in the <lb/>body. J. Gen. Physiol. 8, 519-530. doi:10.1085/jgp.8.6.519 <lb/>Zambrano, A., Molt, M., Uribe, E., and Salas, M. (2019). Glut 1 in cancer cells and the <lb/>inhibitory action of resveratrol as A potential therapeutic strategy. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 20, <lb/>3374. doi:10.3390/ijms20133374 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Chemistry <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Moynihan et al. <lb/>10.3389/fchem.2024.1388332 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>