<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T17:29:22.725Z">11/20/2025 5:29:22 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T17:29:12.493886Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T17:29:12.493886Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>Adolescent stress accelerates <lb/>postpartum novelty recognition <lb/>impairment in 5xFAD mice <lb/>Owen Leitzel 1,2 † , Jose Francis-Oliveira 1 † , Shaimaa M. Khedr 1 , <lb/>Lila Ariste 1,3 , Stefanie Robel 2 , Shin-ichi Kano 1,4 , Andrew Arrant 5 <lb/>and Minae Niwa 1,4,6 * <lb/>1 Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neurobiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham, <lb/>Birmingham, AL, United States, 2 Department of Cell, Developmental and Integrative Biology, <lb/>University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, United States, 3 Department of Biology, Adelphi <lb/>University, Garden City, NY, United States, 4 Department of Neurobiology, University of Alabama at <lb/>Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, United States, 5 Department of Neurology, University of Alabama at <lb/>Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, United States, 6 Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of <lb/>Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, United States <lb/>Pregnancy and the postpartum period induce physiological changes that can <lb/>influence women&apos;s cognitive functions. Alzheimer&apos;s disease (AD) has a higher <lb/>prevalence in women and is exacerbated by early life stress. In the present study, <lb/>we found that late adolescent social isolation combined with the experience of <lb/>pregnancy and delivery accelerates the onset of cognitive deficits in 5xFAD dams, <lb/>particularly affecting their ability to recognize novelty. These cognitive deficits <lb/>manifested as early as 16 weeks, earlier than the usual timeline for these mice, <lb/>and were closely associated with increased levels of corticosterone, suggesting <lb/>dysregulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. Notably, <lb/>the presence of β-amyloid plaques in brain regions associated with novelty <lb/>recognition did not significantly contribute to these deficits. This highlights the <lb/>potential role of stress and HPA axis dysregulation in the development of cognitive <lb/>impairments related to AD, and underscores the need for further investigation. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>adolescent stress, Alzheimer&apos;s disease, acceleration, corticosterone, novelty <lb/>recognition impairment <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The neuroendocrine, molecular, and physiological adaptations that occur during <lb/>pregnancy, childbirth, and the postpartum period correlate with behavioral changes in <lb/>maternal mood, cognition, and stress control (Leuner and Sabihi, 2016). These adaptations <lb/>reflect the intricate interplay between hormonal fluctuations and neural responses, shaping <lb/>the maternal brain in preparation for caregiving responsibilities (Brunton and Russell, 2008; <lb/>Bale and Epperson, 2015; Morrison et al., 2020). Nonetheless, despite this profound influence, <lb/>women have historically been underrepresented in the field of biomedical research, with <lb/>studies often overlooking the unique physiological and psychological challenges faced during <lb/>the reproductive years (Shors, 2016; Galea et al., 2018). <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease (AD) and other neurodegenerative disease conditions lead to severe <lb/>cognitive decline by disrupting neural circuits responsive to stress (Shors, 2016; Deems and <lb/>Leuner, 2020). Psychosocial stress, including social isolation, along with stress experienced <lb/>during critical periods such as pregnancy, childbirth, and the postpartum period, can <lb/>exacerbate cognitive vulnerabilities. This may lead to an acceleration in the onset or <lb/></body>

    <front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Ben Nephew, <lb/>Worcester Polytechnic Institute, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Kathleen Morrison, <lb/>West Virginia University, United States <lb/>Hugo Marte-Santana, <lb/>Universidad Iberoamericana, <lb/>Dominican Republic <lb/>Hsin-Te Chang, <lb/>Chung Yuan Christian University, Taiwan <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Minae Niwa <lb/>mniwa@uabmc.edu <lb/> † <lb/>These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work and share first authorship <lb/>RECEIVED 08 January 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 03 May 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 15 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Leitzel O, Francis-Oliveira J, Khedr SM, <lb/>Ariste L, Robel S, Kano S-i, Arrant A and <lb/>Niwa M (2024) Adolescent stress accelerates <lb/>postpartum novelty recognition impairment <lb/>in 5xFAD mice. <lb/>Front. Neurosci. 18:1366199. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Leitzel, Francis-Oliveira, Khedr, Ariste, <lb/>Robel, Kano, Arrant and Niwa. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic <lb/>practice. No use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>is permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 15 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/>Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/>Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/>02 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></front>

    <body>progression of symptoms related to AD, including cognition decline <lb/>(Justice, 2018; Lesuis et al., 2018). In the United States alone, <lb/>approximately 6.9 million individuals aged 65 and over suffer from <lb/>AD, with two-thirds being women (Barnes et al., 2005; Snyder et al., <lb/>2016; Deems and Leuner, 2020; Rajan et al., 2021). Furthermore, the <lb/>disproportionate prevalence of AD among women underscores the <lb/>need to understand how sex-specific factors, including hormonal <lb/>fluctuations and stress experiences unique to the female lifespan, <lb/>contribute to cognitive decline and disease susceptibility (Nebel <lb/>et al., 2018). <lb/>Recent studies using animal models, such as transgenic mouse <lb/>models of AD, have provided valuable insights into the role of stress in <lb/>accelerating cognitive impairment. For instance, observations in mice <lb/>with AD-related genetic mutations (AD mice; e.g., 5xFAD mice, APP/ <lb/>PS1 mice) have demonstrated that early life stress, including social <lb/>isolation, can expedite cognitive decline (Dong et al., 2004; Jeong et al., <lb/>2006; Han et al., 2016, 2017; Nakai et al., 2021). These findings not only <lb/>shed light on the pathophysiological mechanisms underlying AD but also <lb/>highlight the broader relevance of stress-induced cognitive impairments. <lb/>We have previously developed a novel concept that subtle <lb/>psychosocial stress in late adolescence can have long-lasting negative <lb/>effects on subsequent brain maturation and behaviors. Specifically, a <lb/>mild three-week social isolation during late adolescence in mice differs <lb/>notably from longer-term isolation (e.g., exposure for several weeks at <lb/>various life stages studied by numerous groups), as it does not itself <lb/>produce significant endocrine, neuronal, or behavioral abnormalities <lb/>(Niwa et al., 2013, 2016; Matsumoto et al., 2017; Lockhart et al., 2018; <lb/>Hikida et al., 2020; Kin et al., 2021). Expanding this paradigm further, <lb/>we recently found that psychosocial stress, specifically social isolation <lb/>during late adolescence, leads to deficits in postpartum social novelty <lb/>recognition only in stressed dams, which are mice that experienced both <lb/>social isolation and pregnancy/delivery (Kin et al., 2023; Niwa et al., <lb/>2024). Additionally, our recent study has identified glucocorticoid-<lb/>mediated functional alteration of the anterior insula (AI) -prelimbic <lb/>cortex (PrL) projections as an underlying cause of social novelty <lb/>recognition deficits in stressed dams (Kin et al., 2023). Notably, <lb/>pathological alterations in human AI, dorsolateral anterior cingulate <lb/>cortex (homologous to the PrL in rodents), and dentate gyrus of <lb/>hippocampus (DG) have been implicated in AD (Bonthius et al., 2005; <lb/>Eimer and Vassar, 2013; Le Heron et al., 2018). Therefore, it is possible <lb/>that genetic variants associated with AD, psychological stress before <lb/>pregnancy, and stressful events later in life such as pregnancy and <lb/>delivery, may interact to strongly accelerate AD-associated symptoms <lb/>later in life. However, the biological mechanisms underlying the <lb/>trajectory from psychological stress before pregnancy to the acceleration <lb/>of AD-related novelty recognition impairment later in life remain to <lb/>be elucidated. Thus, in the present study, we adapted this model to <lb/>examine the effects of late adolescent social isolation on the acceleration <lb/>of deficits in novelty recognition behaviors in 5xFAD dams and virgin <lb/>female mice. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Animals <lb/>B6SJL-Tg(APPSwFlLon,PSEN1*M146L*L286V)6799Vas/Mmjax <lb/>(5xFAD) female mice were originally purchased from the Jackson <lb/>Laboratory (#034840-JAX). All mice used in this study were bred <lb/>in-house over 10 generations of 5xFAD mice. The 5xFAD mice express <lb/>the human mutant amyloid precursor protein (APP) and presenilin 1 <lb/>(PSEN1) transgenes, with three mutations in APP and two in PSEN1. <lb/>These mice develop amyloid-β (Aβ) deposition and gliosis around <lb/>2 months of age, and by 5 months of age, they show synaptic loss and <lb/>cognitive decline (Oakley et al., 2006). Previous studies highlight <lb/>social behavioral deficits emerging around 9-12 months of age in <lb/>these mice, while impairments in non-social cognition manifest as <lb/>early as 5-6 months (Filali et al., 2011; Giannoni et al., 2013; Flanigan <lb/>et al., 2014; Huang et al., 2016; Creighton et al., 2019; Kosel et al., 2019; <lb/>Samaey et al., 2019). Given these robust pathological and behavioral <lb/>features, the 5xFAD model was specifically chosen for the <lb/>present study. <lb/>Mice were kept under standard conditions (23 ± 3°C; 40 ± 5% <lb/>humidity; lights on at 6 am and off at 6 pm) with water and food ad <lb/>libitum. Healthy virgin 5xFAD mice were group-housed or isolated <lb/>from 5-8 weeks of age, corresponding to late adolescence -a critical <lb/>period characterized by significant hormonal changes and the fine-<lb/>tuning of neuronal pathways to facilitate the transition from childhood <lb/>to adulthood (Blakemore, 2008). 5xFAD female mice were also either <lb/>mated in-house with healthy C57BL/6 J male mice at 8 weeks of age, <lb/>followed by pregnancy and delivery, or remained unmated. This <lb/>design generated four experimental groups: unstressed virgins, <lb/>stressed virgins, unstressed dams, and stressed dams. &apos;Virgins&apos; denote <lb/>nulliparous females, indicating mice with no prior mating, pregnancy, <lb/>or delivery experience, while &apos;dams&apos; denote primiparous females, <lb/>indicating those that have given birth once. The experimental design <lb/>and schedule are shown in Figure 1. <lb/>2.2 Behavioral tests <lb/>We performed two behavioral tests across multiple days, <lb/>maintaining consistent conditions in the behavioral room throughout <lb/>the testing period. The novel object recognition test (NORT) and <lb/>social interaction test (SIT) were conducted at two specific time <lb/>points: 40 weeks, a period when cognitive impairment is typically <lb/>observed in 5xFAD mice, and 16 weeks, an earlier timeframe than the <lb/>typical onset of such behavioral deficits (Giannoni et al., 2013; <lb/>Creighton et al., 2019; Yanai and Endo, 2021). Supplementary Figure S1 <lb/>illustrates a flowchart outlining our behavioral testing protocols and <lb/>sample collection processes. <lb/>2.2.1 Novel object recognition test (NORT) <lb/>Novel object recognition test was conducted with one cohort <lb/>assessed at 16 weeks of age and a second cohort evaluated at 40 weeks <lb/>of age, with minor modifications (Sun et al., 2020; Lee et al., 2021). <lb/>Each trial consisted of three phases: habituation, training, and testing, <lb/>each lasting 10 min. During the habituation phase, the subject mouse <lb/>was introduced into a chamber apparatus (40 cm × 40 cm × 42 cm) and <lb/>allowed to habituate for 10 min per day over the course of 3 days. On <lb/>the fourth day, during the training phase, the mouse was once again <lb/>habituated for 10 min in the chamber apparatus. Following this, the <lb/>mouse was briefly removed and then reintroduced into the chamber, <lb/>which contained two identical cone objects, for 2 min. Data during the <lb/>training phase were collected over the subsequent 10 min. On the fifth <lb/>day, the test phase began with a 10-min habituation in the chamber <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/></note>

    <page>03 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>apparatus. Subsequently, the mouse was briefly removed from the <lb/>chamber. During this brief removal, one of the two familiar cone <lb/>objects was replaced with a novel pyramid object. The mouse was then <lb/>returned to the chamber for 2 min, after which data collection took <lb/>place over the following 10 min. All data were manually analyzed by <lb/>reviewing video recordings to identify instances of nose contact or <lb/>physical interactions within a 1 cm boundary zone around the objects. <lb/>Stopwatch timers were used to measure the time spent sniffing. The <lb/>discrimination index was calculated as follows: (time sniffing the <lb/>novel object -time sniffing the familiar object)/(time sniffing the <lb/>novel object + time sniffing the familiar object). An index of 0 <lb/>indicated no recognition of the novel object, positive values indicated <lb/>increased recognition of the novel object, and negative values <lb/>indicated deficits in recognizing the novel object. <lb/>2.2.2 Social interaction test (SIT) <lb/>Social interaction test was conducted as previously described with <lb/>minor modifications (Moy et al., 2004; Kaidanovich-Beilin et al., 2011; <lb/>Sandi and Haller, 2015; Kin et al., 2023; Niwa et al., 2024,). SIT <lb/>consisted of two trials: the Sociability Trial (S-trial) and the Social <lb/>Novelty Trial (SN-trial). These trials were designed to progressively <lb/>increase the complexity of the social context. One day following the <lb/>testing phase of NORT, the subject mouse was placed in the middle of <lb/>a chamber apparatus (40 cm × 40 cm × 42 cm), which was divided into <lb/>three chambers: left, middle, and right. The left and right chambers <lb/>each contained small, barred cages. The subject mouse was allowed to <lb/>habituate to the three-chamber environment for 10 min daily over <lb/>three consecutive days before testing. After this habituation period, the <lb/>mouse was placed into the middle chamber and allowed to habituate <lb/>for 10 min before being confined to the middle chamber. The doors <lb/>were then closed to create three separate chambers, and the subject <lb/>mouse returned to the middle chamber for 5 min. During this period, <lb/>a novel mouse was introduced into one of the barred cages, while a <lb/>mouse-shaped object was placed in the other barred cage. In the <lb/>S-trial, the subject mouse encountered the mouse in the barred cage <lb/>and the object in the other barred cage for 10 min. At the 10-min mark, <lb/>the test mice were again restricted from entering the right and left <lb/>chambers for 5 min, and the mouse-shaped object was replaced with <lb/>another novel mouse. During the SN-trial, the subject mouse <lb/>encountered a familiar mouse in one barred cage and a novel mouse <lb/>in the other barred cage for 10 min. Familiar and novel mice were <lb/>chosen to be age-and sex-matched healthy mice. All data were <lb/>manually analyzed by reviewing video recordings to identify instances <lb/>of nose contact or physical interactions within a 1 cm boundary zone <lb/>around the barred cages either containing mice or mouse-shaped <lb/>objects. Stopwatch timers were used to measure the time spent sniffing. <lb/>Sociability and social novelty indexes were calculated as follows: (time <lb/>interacting with mouse or novel mouse cage -time interacting with <lb/>an object or familiar mouse cage)/(time interacting with a mouse or <lb/>novel mouse cage + time interacting with an object or familiar mouse <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Experimental schedule. (A) Virgin 5xFAD females were group-housed and not mated (unstressed virgins). (B) Virgin 5xFAD females were isolated from 5 <lb/>to 8 weeks of age and not mated (stressed virgins). (C) Virgin 5xFAD females were group-housed, mated with a male at 8 weeks of age, and gave birth <lb/>to pups (unstressed dams). (D) Virgin 5xFAD females were isolated from 5 to 8 weeks of age, mated with a male at 8 weeks of age, and gave birth to <lb/>pups (stressed dams). The novel object recognition test, followed by three-chamber social interaction test, was performed at 16 and 40 weeks of age <lb/>(indicated by the arrows). Different cohorts of mice subjected to behavioral tests at 16 weeks and 40 weeks of age were prepared to avoid the repeated <lb/>exposure to stressful behavioral procedures. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/></note>

    <page>04 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>cage). An index of 0 indicated no preference, while positive indexes <lb/>indicated increased sociability or social novelty behavior, and negative <lb/>indexes indicated social avoidance or deficits in social novelty behavior. <lb/>2.3 Blood collection and brain perfusion <lb/>Brain perfusion and blood collection were performed with minor <lb/>modifications to the methods previously described in the publications <lb/>(Niwa et al., 2013, 2024). To minimize potential circadian rhythm <lb/>influences and the acute effects of stressful behavioral testing, blood <lb/>collection consistently occurred at the same time of day, 24 h after the <lb/>last behavioral testing session. Specifically, 1 day following the <lb/>SN-trials for both the 16 and 40 weeks of age groups, mice were <lb/>anesthetized with isoflurane. Subsequently, 1 mL of blood was <lb/>collected from the right atrium between 8 am and 11 am and <lb/>transferred to 1.5 mL low-binding tubes. Following blood collection, <lb/>mice were subsequently perfused intracardiacally with phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline (PBS), followed by 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA). The <lb/>brains were extracted and post-fixed overnight in 4% PFA at <lb/>4°C. They were subsequently transferred to a 15% sucrose solution in <lb/>PBS for 1 day, followed by a switch to a 30% sucrose solution for <lb/>another day. Brains were then frozen using OCT compound and <lb/>stored at -80°C until sectioning. <lb/>2.4 ThioS staining <lb/>Coronal sections were obtained with a sliding microtome at 30 μm. <lb/>Sections containing the prelimbic cortex (PrL) (approximately <lb/>1.6-2.5 mm anterior from bregma), anterior insula (AI) (approximately <lb/>1.2-2.0 mm anterior from bregma), and dentate gyrus of the <lb/>hippocampus (DG) (approximately 1.3-2.3 mm posterior from bregma) <lb/>were mounted onto ColorFrost Plus slides (Fisher Scientific) and <lb/>allowed to dry overnight. Slides were then submerged for 1 min each in <lb/>70 and 80% ethanol prior to incubation for 15 min in 1% Thioflavin S <lb/>(Acros Organics) in 80% ethanol. Slides were then washed 1 min each <lb/>in 80 and 70% ethanol, then submerged in two changes of deionized <lb/>water prior to coverslipping with ProLong Gold mounting medium <lb/>(Thermo Fisher). Epifluorescent images (EVOS M5000 imaging system, <lb/>Thermo Fisher) were taken from three sections per animal for each <lb/>brain region at 20X (PrL and AI) or 10X (DG) magnification. <lb/>Fluorescence data were thresholded using the &quot;Triangle&quot; autothreshold <lb/>function of ImageJ (Zack et al., 1977) to account for varying background <lb/>fluorescence. The number, total area, and average size of amyloid <lb/>plaques were analyzed using the Analyze Particles function of ImageJ <lb/>software. The average of counting was reported for each animal. <lb/>2.5 Corticosterone assay <lb/>The collected blood was left at room temperature for 1 h, <lb/>followed by centrifugation for 15 min at 4°C at 3,000 rpm to separate <lb/>the supernatant, which was then transferred into 1.5 mL tubes and <lb/>stored in a -80°C freezer. Serum corticosterone levels were <lb/>measured using a commercial ELISA kit (Cayman #501320) as <lb/>described previously with minor modifications (Niwa et al., <lb/>2013, 2024). <lb/>2.6 Statistical analysis <lb/>The normality and homogeneity of variances were assessed using <lb/>the Shapiro-Wilk and Levene&apos;s tests, respectively. In cases where the <lb/>data met the assumptions of normality and homogeneity of variances, <lb/>a two-way ANOVA was conducted, treating late adolescent stress and <lb/>pregnancy/delivery as independent factors. Subsequently, a Bonferroni <lb/>post hoc test was conducted for pairwise comparisons across all <lb/>groups, with adjustments made for multiple comparisons. Conversely, <lb/>for data that did not meet these assumptions, a Mann-Whitney U test <lb/>was employed for each independent factor, without correction for <lb/>multiple comparisons, as this test is suited for comparing two groups. <lb/>Significance was determined at the p &lt; 0.05 level. For correlations, <lb/>we used linear regression and reported the R 2 values. Additional <lb/>statistical details can be found in Supplementary Table S1. Data is <lb/>presented as mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM), and our <lb/>statistical analyses were conducted using GraphPad Prism 8 and <lb/>SPSS 23. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Late adolescent social isolation <lb/>accelerates AD-related novelty recognition <lb/>deficits in 5xFAD dams <lb/>We first conducted NORT and SIT to examine the effects of late <lb/>adolescent stress on non-social and social cognitive behavior, <lb/>particularly focusing on novelty recognition, in 5xFAD mice. Results <lb/>revealed no differences in either NORT or SIT at 40 weeks of age in <lb/>both non-stressed and stressed 5xFAD mice, regardless of their <lb/>pregnancy and delivery history (Figures 2A-C). Notably, a significant <lb/>portion of the 5xFAD mice at 40 weeks of age had already perished by <lb/>the time the behavioral experiments were conducted <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S2). Furthermore, among those that survived <lb/>until 40 weeks, a substantial portion displayed freezing behavior <lb/>during the behavioral tests, leading to their exclusion from the <lb/>analysis. This resulted in a limited sample size for some groups <lb/>(Figure 2). <lb/>In contrast, most 5xFAD mice subjected to behavioral <lb/>experiments at 16 weeks survived, and none exhibited freezing <lb/>behavior during the tests. At 16 weeks, only stressed 5xFAD dams <lb/>displayed behavioral deficits in NORT when compared to the other <lb/>three groups (Figure 3A). During the NORT training phase at <lb/>16 weeks, differences were observed between unstressed virgins <lb/>and dams, regardless of stress exposure, whereas no differences <lb/>were observed among the four groups at 40 weeks <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S3). During the S-trial of SIT at 16 weeks, <lb/>stressed 5xFAD virgins, unstressed 5xFAD dams, and stressed <lb/>5xFAD dams showed deficits in sociability when compared to <lb/>unstressed virgins (Figure 3B). Notably, in the SN-trial of SIT at <lb/>16 weeks, stressed 5xFAD dams exhibited an accelerated behavioral <lb/>deficit in social novelty recognition compared to the other three <lb/>groups (Figure 3C). <lb/>These findings suggest that late adolescent social isolation, in <lb/>conjunction with pregnancy and delivery, accelerated the onset of <lb/>AD-related behavioral deficits in non-social and social novelty <lb/>recognition, but not in sociability. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/></note>

    <page>05 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>3.2 Impaired novelty recognition in 5xFAD <lb/>dams is correlated with increased <lb/>corticosterone levels, but not with <lb/>β-amyloid plaques <lb/>To understand how adolescent stress affects cognitive behaviors <lb/>in 5xFAD dams, we next examined the effects of adolescent stress on <lb/>hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis regulation and <lb/>AD-related neuropathological changes in 5xFAD mice at 16 and <lb/>40 weeks of age. We evaluated serum corticosterone levels and the <lb/>presence of β-amyloid plaques in key brain regions responsible for <lb/>novelty recognition, including AI, PrL, and DG. <lb/>Following the final behavioral testing at 16 weeks of age, serum <lb/>corticosterone levels were increased in response to both late adolescent <lb/>social isolation and pregnancy/delivery (Figure 4A). Notably, the <lb/>combination of late adolescent social isolation and pregnancy/delivery <lb/>resulted in a further increase in serum corticosterone levels <lb/>(Figure 4A). Interestingly, serum corticosterone levels across all four <lb/>groups at 40 weeks of age were similar to those observed in stressed <lb/>dams at 16 weeks of age (Supplementary Figure S4A), suggesting that <lb/>late adolescent stress accelerated the increase in corticosterone levels <lb/>at 16 weeks of age. <lb/>There were no statistically significant differences among the four <lb/>groups in the number, percentage area, and size of β-amyloid plaques <lb/>in AI, PrL, and DG at both 16 and 40 weeks of age, except for the <lb/>comparison between unstressed virgins and stressed virgins regarding <lb/>AI area and DG area at 40 weeks of age, the comparison between <lb/>unstressed virgins and unstressed dams regarding AI size at 40 weeks <lb/>of age, and the comparison between stressed virgins and stressed dams <lb/>regarding DG area and size at 16 weeks of age (Figures 4B-E and <lb/>Supplementary Figures S4B-D, S5). <lb/>Subsequently, we explored the correlations between behavioral <lb/>alterations and molecular changes. We observed negative correlations <lb/>between corticosterone levels and the behavioral indexes for NORT <lb/>and the SN-trial of SIT, but not for the S-trial of SIT (Figure 5). <lb/>Conversely, we found no correlations between the number of <lb/>β-amyloid plaques and the behavioral scores for NORT and SIT S-and <lb/>SN-trials (Supplementary Figure S6). These findings suggest a <lb/>potential link between HPA axis dysregulation and novelty recognition <lb/>impairments in stressed 5xFAD dams, while indicating no direct link <lb/>with β-amyloid plaques. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>The present study investigated the effects of late adolescent <lb/>social isolation combined with pregnancy and delivery on novelty <lb/>recognition deficits in 5xFAD female mice. Drawing upon prior <lb/>research establishing a link between corticosterone levels and <lb/>behavioral outcomes (Kim et al., 2013; Henckens et al., 2016), <lb/>correlation analyses were conducted. Our findings indicate that <lb/>late adolescent social isolation, when coupled with pregnancy and <lb/>delivery, can accelerate the onset of novelty recognition deficits, <lb/>accompanied by increased corticosterone levels. Surprisingly, <lb/>we did not see correlations between β-amyloid plaques and <lb/>behavioral deficits, emphasizing the intricate relationship between <lb/>stress and cognitive impairments associated with AD. This <lb/>suggests that dysfunction in the HPA axis might have a more <lb/>direct association with behavioral impairment than <lb/>β-amyloid plaques. <lb/>Ongoing debate surrounds the involvement of β-amyloid <lb/>plaques in AD pathophysiology (Piller, 2022; Zhang et al., 2023). <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Cognitive behavioral changes in 5xFAD mice at 40 weeks of age. <lb/>(A) Regardless of pregnancy and delivery history, both non-stressed <lb/>and stressed 5xFAD mice exhibited behavioral deficits in the novelty <lb/>object recognition test (NORT). (B) In the social interaction test (SIT), <lb/>both non-stressed and stressed 5xFAD mice showed behavioral <lb/>deficits in the sociability-trial (S-trial), irrespective of their pregnancy <lb/>and delivery history. (C) In SIT, both non-stressed and stressed 5xFAD <lb/>mice demonstrated behavioral deficits in the social novelty-trial <lb/>(SN-trial), regardless of their pregnancy and delivery history. All data <lb/>were non-normally distributed and analyzed using the Mann-<lb/>Whitney U test. All comparisons were non-significant (p &gt; 0.05), <lb/>except stressed virgins vs. stressed dams for NORT (*p = 0.034). <lb/>N = 3-12. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. See <lb/>Supplementary Table S1 for details on the sample size and statistical <lb/>analyses. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/></note>

    <page>06 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>While the present study may present evidence countering the <lb/>&quot;amyloid cascade hypothesis&quot; of AD, we acknowledge the inherent <lb/>limitations in our methods and data, preventing us from <lb/>definitively refuting the role of β-amyloid plaques in AD. For <lb/>instance, prior research has demonstrated that soluble forms of <lb/>β-amyloid protein correlate more strongly with AD-related <lb/>cognitive deficits than plaques (Milligan Armstrong et al., 2021). <lb/>Therefore, our mouse model may feature elevated levels of soluble <lb/>β-amyloid, prompting further exploration in future studies. <lb/>Nevertheless, our findings suggest that other mechanisms, such as <lb/>HPA axis dysregulation, may play a more prominent role in stress-<lb/>induced cognitive impairment. <lb/>Pregnancy and the postpartum period are recognized as sensitive <lb/>periods for women, both hormonally and psychologically. Our study <lb/>delves into the intersection of stress before pregnancy-particularly in <lb/>the context of social isolation during late adolescence-, pregnancy/ <lb/>delivery, and subsequent risk of AD later in life. This is particularly <lb/>pertinent considering the disproportionate risk of AD faced by <lb/>women compared to men, with pregnancy and hormonal fluctuations <lb/>during reproductive years potentially serving as significant <lb/>contributing factors. <lb/>Our study highlights the potential impact of stress during <lb/>critical developmental periods, such as adolescence, on cognitive <lb/>function and AD risk in females. Stress, particularly early life <lb/>stress, is recognized as a risk factor for AD in humans as well <lb/>(Heim and Nemeroff, 2001; Donley et al., 2018). AD patients often <lb/>exhibit elevated levels of corticosteroids in plasma and <lb/>cerebrospinal fluid (Milligan Armstrong et al., 2021). Epigenetic <lb/>modification of HSD11B1, an enzyme involved in cortisol <lb/>metabolism, has been associated with late-onset AD and is <lb/>affected by early life stress (Lemche, 2018). These findings <lb/>underscore the importance of investigating the relationship <lb/>between stress, glucocorticoid levels, and AD pathophysiology in <lb/>the context of pregnancy and the postpartum period, particularly <lb/>in women. <lb/>The behavioral changes we observed cannot solely be attributed <lb/>to short-term factors. Notably, social isolation was applied during late <lb/>adolescence, spanning from 5 to 8 weeks of age. Subsequently, there <lb/>was a minimum additional interval of 3 weeks between mating and <lb/>delivery. Dams were then tested approximately 5 weeks after delivery. <lb/>Thus, the behavioral effects were evaluated at least 5 weeks after the <lb/>last significant stressor, which was delivery, and 8 weeks after the last <lb/>isolation exposure. We posit that these observed effects primarily <lb/>indicate long-term consequences. However, it is essential to <lb/>acknowledge that a different experimental design would be necessary <lb/>to thoroughly assess this assertion. <lb/>In the present study, we did not observe significant effects of <lb/>parturition on behavior associated with AD. The relationship <lb/>between parity and AD risk remains complex and not fully <lb/>understood (Galea et al., 2018; Deems and Leuner, 2020; Jung et al., <lb/>2020). While some research suggests that multiple childbirths may <lb/>offer a protective effect, our focus lies on the impact of one-time <lb/>delivery, which has shown no effect in both our present and published <lb/>studies (Kin et al., 2023; Niwa et al., 2024,). This potential protective <lb/>effect is believed to be linked to hormonal changes, particularly <lb/>increased estrogen during pregnancy. Nonetheless, findings in the <lb/>literature are inconclusive, with some studies indicating no significant <lb/>association. Further investigation is essential to gain a deeper <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Cognitive behavioral changes in 5xFAD mice at 16 weeks of age. (A) Only <lb/>stressed 5xFAD dams displayed behavioral deficits in novelty object <lb/>recognition when compared to the other three groups. Mann-Whitney <lb/>U test: Unstressed virgins vs. stressed dams, ***p &lt; 0.001; stressed virgins <lb/>vs. stressed dams, *p &lt; 0.05; unstressed dams vs. stressed dams, <lb/>*p &lt; 0.05. (B) During the S-trial of SIT, stressed 5xFAD virgins, unstressed <lb/>5xFAD dams, and stressed 5xFAD dams showed deficits in sociability <lb/>when compared to unstressed virgins. Mann-Whitney U test: Unstressed <lb/>virgins vs. stressed virgins, **p &lt; 0.01; unstressed virgins vs. unstressed <lb/>dams, *p &lt; 0.05; unstressed virgins vs. stressed dams, *p &lt; 0.05. (C) In the <lb/>SN-trial of SIT, stressed 5xFAD dams exhibited an accelerated behavioral <lb/>deficit in social novelty recognition compared to the other three groups. <lb/>Two-way ANOVA: For interaction, F (3,56) = 0.325, p = 0.571, partial <lb/>η 2 = 0.006; for stress, F (1,56) = 12.972, p = 0.001, partial η 2 = 0.188; for <lb/>pregnancy/delivery, F (1,56) = 12.842, p = 0.001, partial η 2 = 0.187. Bonferroni: <lb/>Unstressed virgins vs. stressed virgins, *p &lt; 0.05; stressed virgins vs. <lb/>stressed dams, **p &lt; 0.01; unstressed dams vs. stressed dams, **p &lt; 0.01; <lb/>unstressed virgins vs. stressed dams, ***p &lt; 0.001. N = 9-17. Data are <lb/>presented as mean ± SEM. See Supplementary Table S1 for details on the <lb/>sample size and statistical analyses. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>understanding of the underlying mechanisms involved, considering <lb/>genetic and lifestyle factors, especially in the context of female-<lb/>specific AD risk factors. <lb/>This study has several important limitations. Firstly, our 40-week <lb/>cohort had a small sample size, which could impact our statistical <lb/>analyses. Additionally, while mice that died before the 40-week <lb/>behavioral experiments or exhibited freezing behavior during the <lb/>experiments were not included in the analysis, it cannot be ruled out <lb/>that these mice may have shown even more severe behavioral deficits. <lb/>Secondly, we collected blood samples and conducted brain perfusions <lb/>1 day after the stressful behavioral experiments rather than <lb/>immediately afterward. While we interpret that prolonged, rather than <lb/>acute, elevation in corticosterone levels may underlie impaired novelty <lb/>recognition behaviors in stressed dams, we also acknowledge the need <lb/>for a cautious interpretation due to the limited nature of our findings <lb/>and methodological considerations. More frequent sampling and <lb/>detailed examination of glucocorticoid signaling, along with other <lb/>reproductive steroid hormones and diverse brain regions/circuits, <lb/>could yield significant benefits. Thirdly, we focused our study solely <lb/>on 5xFAD mice, making it challenging to conclude the effects of <lb/>5xFAD mutations. Exploring a comparison with a wild-type strain to <lb/>assess the effects of 5xFAD mutations would be an intriguing avenue <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Changes in serum corticosterone levels and the quantity of β-amyloid plaques in 5xFAD mice at 16 weeks of age. (A) Serum corticosterone levels <lb/>increased in response to both late adolescent social isolation and pregnancy/delivery, with a notably accelerated rise when both conditions co-<lb/>occurred. Mann-Whitney U test: Unstressed virgins vs. stressed virgins, *p &lt; 0.05; unstressed virgins vs. unstressed dams, **p &lt; 0.01; unstressed virgins <lb/>vs. stressed dams, ***p &lt; 0.001; stressed virgins vs. stressed dams, **p &lt; 0.05; unstressed dams vs. stressed dams, *p &lt; 0.05. (B-D) Late adolescent social <lb/>isolation and/or pregnancy/delivery did not affect the number of β-amyloid plaques in the anterior insula (AI; B), prelimbic cortex (PrL; C) and dentate <lb/>gyrus of the hippocampus (DG; D), as evaluated by a Two-Way ANOVA, except for the comparison between unstressed virgins vs. stressed dams using <lb/>Bonferroni adjustments (p = 0.027). (E) Representative images of β-amyloid plaques in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus. p &gt; 0.05 for all main <lb/>factors and interaction. N = 7-11. Data are presented as mean ± SEM. See Supplementary Table S1 for details on the sample size and statistical analyses. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>for future research. Fourthly, we only assessed subjects with novelty <lb/>discrimination tasks in the present study. To connect our current <lb/>findings with the broader relevance of stress-induced cognitive <lb/>impairments, further behavioral assessments related to cognition are <lb/>necessary in future studies. Despite these limitations, we believe our <lb/>study provides valuable data indicating the important role of <lb/>adolescent stress in accelerating AD pathology in the context of <lb/>pregnancy and the postpartum period. <lb/>While our study provides novel insights into the intricate <lb/>relationship among stress, hormonal factors, and cognitive deficits in <lb/>the context of AD, particularly in females, and highlights the <lb/>importance of considering these factors in AD research and <lb/>therapeutic development, it is worth noting that this interplay may not <lb/>be exclusive to AD mouse models. Further research, both in animal <lb/>models and in human studies, will be necessary to fully elucidate the <lb/>intricate relationship between stress and AD. Building on our findings, <lb/>this continued investigation will contribute to a deeper understanding <lb/>of the underlying mechanisms and provide insights into how stress <lb/>may affect cognitive function in human AD, particularly in women. <lb/>By elucidating the mechanisms by which stress influences cognitive <lb/>function via HPA axis regulation, especially during vulnerable periods <lb/>such as adolescence, pregnancy, and childbirth, we can not only <lb/>enhance our understanding of AD pathogenesis but also inform <lb/>preventive strategies and interventions aimed at mitigating cognitive <lb/>decline across the lifespan. Therefore, it is imperative to investigate <lb/>how stress interacts with genetic predispositions and life experiences <lb/>to modulate cognitive health, with the ultimate goal of developing <lb/>targeted approaches for the prevention and treatment of cognitive <lb/>impairment, including AD. <lb/>In conclusion, this study contributes to our comprehension of the <lb/>complex interplay between stress, cognitive deficits, and AD in the <lb/>context of women&apos;s health. It highlights the importance of considering <lb/>not only the traditional markers of AD, such as β-amyloid plaques, but <lb/>also the hormonal and stress-related aspects of the disease, particularly <lb/>in females. These findings may contribute to the broader discourse <lb/>concerning AD risk factors and potential avenues for intervention <lb/>and prevention. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will <lb/>be made available by the authors, without undue reservation. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The animal study was approved by UAB Institutional Animal Care <lb/>and Use Committee. The study was conducted in accordance with the <lb/>local legislation and institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>OL: Investigation, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. JF-O: Formal analysis, Writing -original draft, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. SK: Formal analysis, Writing -original draft, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. LA: Investigation, Writing -original draft, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. SR: Writing -original draft, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. S-iK: Supervision, Writing -original draft, Writing <lb/>-review &amp; editing. AA: Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing <lb/></div>

    <body>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Correlations between corticosterone levels and cognitive behaviors <lb/>in 5xFAD mice at 16 weeks of age. (A) Serum corticosterone levels <lb/>were found to be negatively correlated with the novelty recognition <lb/>indexes for NORT. (B) There was no significant correlation between <lb/>corticosterone levels and sociability indexes for SIT during the S-trial. <lb/>(C) A negative correlation was observed between corticosterone <lb/>levels and sociability indexes for SIT during the SN-trial. N = 7-11. R 2 <lb/>and p-values were obtained from Pearson&apos;s correlation test for all <lb/>graphs. See Supplementary Table S1 for details on the sample size <lb/>and statistical analyses. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">-original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. MN: Conceptualization, <lb/>Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, Project administration, Resources, Software, <lb/>Supervision, Validation, Visualization, Writing -original draft, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was <lb/>supported by the National Institute of Health (NIH) R01MH-116869 <lb/>(MN), UAB Comprehensive Neuroscience Center Pilot Award (MN <lb/>and S-iK) and UAB Psychiatry startup funds (MN). <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the members of the Niwa Laboratory and the Kano <lb/>Laboratory for technical assistance and helpful discussions. <lb/>Supplementary Figure S1 was created with BioRender.com. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, <lb/>or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product <lb/>that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>Bale, T. L., and Epperson, C. N. (2015). Sex differences and stress across the lifespan. <lb/>Nat. Neurosci. 18, 1413-1420. doi: 10.1038/nn.4112 <lb/>Barnes, L. L., Wilson, R. S., Bienias, J. L., Schneider, J. A., Evans, D. A., and Bennett, D. A. <lb/>(2005). Sex differences in the clinical manifestations of Alzheimer disease pathology. Arch. <lb/>Gen. Psychiatry 62, 685-691. doi: 10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.685 <lb/>Blakemore, S. J. (2008). The social brain in adolescence. Nat. Rev. Neurosci. 9, 267-277. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/nrn2353 <lb/>Bonthius, D. J., Solodkin, A., and Van Hoesen, G. W. (2005). Pathology of the insular <lb/>cortex in Alzheimer disease depends on cortical architecture. J. Neuropathol. Exp. <lb/>Neurol. 64, 910-922. doi: 10.1097/01.jnen.0000182983.87106.d1 <lb/>Brunton, P. J., and Russell, J. A. (2008). The expectant brain: adapting for motherhood. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Neurosci. 9, 11-25. doi: 10.1038/nrn2280 <lb/>Creighton, S. D., Mendell, A. L., Palmer, D., Kalisch, B. E., Maclusky, N. J., Prado, V. F., <lb/>et al. (2019). Dissociable cognitive impairments in two strains of transgenic Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>disease mice revealed by a battery of object-based tests. Sci. Rep. 9:57, doi: 10.1038/ <lb/>s41598-018-37312-0 <lb/>Deems, N. P., and Leuner, B. (2020). Pregnancy, postpartum and parity: resilience and <lb/>vulnerability in brain health and disease. Front. Neuroendocrinol. 57:100820. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.yfrne.2020.100820 <lb/>Dong, H., Goico, B., Martin, M., Csernansky, C. A., Bertchume, A., and <lb/>Csernansky, J. G. (2004). Modulation of hippocampal cell proliferation, memory, and <lb/>amyloid plaque deposition in APPsw (Tg2576) mutant mice by isolation stress. <lb/>Neuroscience 127, 601-609. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2004.05.040 <lb/>Donley, G. A. R., Lonnroos, E., Tuomainen, T. P., and Kauhanen, J. (2018). Association <lb/>of childhood stress with late-life dementia and Alzheimer&apos;s disease: the KIHD study. Eur. <lb/>J. Pub. Health 28, 1069-1073. doi: 10.1093/eurpub/cky134 <lb/>Eimer, W. A., and Vassar, R. (2013). Neuron loss in the 5xFAD mouse model of <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease correlates with Intraneuronal Abeta42 accumulation and Caspase-3 <lb/>activation. Mol. Neurodegener. 8:2. doi: 10.1186/1750-1326-8-2 <lb/>Filali, M., Lalonde, R., and Rivest, S. (2011). Anomalies in social behaviors and <lb/>exploratory activities in an APPswe/PS1 mouse model of Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Physiol. <lb/>Behav. 104, 880-885. doi: 10.1016/j.physbeh.2011.05.023 <lb/>Flanigan, T. J., Xue, Y., Kishan Rao, S., Dhanushkodi, A., and Mcdonald, M. P. (2014). <lb/>Abnormal vibrissa-related behavior and loss of barrel field inhibitory neurons in 5xFAD <lb/>transgenics. Genes Brain Behav. 13, 488-500. doi: 10.1111/gbb.12133 <lb/>Galea, L. A. M., Qiu, W., and Duarte-Guterman, P. (2018). Beyond sex differences: <lb/>short and long-term implications of motherhood on Women&apos;s health. Curr. Opin. Physio. <lb/>6, 82-88. doi: 10.1016/j.cophys.2018.06.003 <lb/>Giannoni, P., Gaven, F., De Bundel, D., Baranger, K., Marchetti-Gauthier, E., <lb/>Roman, F. S., et al. (2013). Early administration of RS 67333, a specific 5-HT4 <lb/>receptor agonist, prevents amyloidogenesis and behavioral deficits in the 5XFAD <lb/>mouse model of Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Front. Aging Neurosci. 5:96. doi: 10.3389/ <lb/>fnagi.2013.00096 <lb/>Han, B., Wang, J. H., Geng, Y., Shen, L., Wang, H. L., Wang, Y. Y., et al. (2017). Chronic <lb/>stress contributes to cognitive dysfunction and hippocampal metabolic abnormalities in <lb/>APP/PS1 mice. Cell. Physiol. Biochem. 41, 1766-1776. doi: 10.1159/000471869 <lb/>Han, B., Yu, L., Geng, Y., Shen, L., Wang, H., Wang, Y., et al. (2016). Chronic stress <lb/>aggravates cognitive impairment and suppresses insulin associated signaling pathway in <lb/>APP/PS1 mice. J. Alzheimers Dis. 53, 1539-1552. doi: 10.3233/JAD-160189 <lb/>Heim, C., and Nemeroff, C. B. (2001). The role of childhood trauma in the <lb/>neurobiology of mood and anxiety disorders: preclinical and clinical studies. Biol. <lb/>Psychiatry 49, 1023-1039. doi: 10.1016/S0006-3223(01)01157-X <lb/>Henckens, M. J., Klumpers, F., Everaerd, D., Kooijman, S. C., Van Wingen, G. A., and <lb/>Fernandez, G. (2016). Interindividual differences in stress sensitivity: basal and stress-<lb/>induced cortisol levels differentially predict neural vigilance processing under stress. <lb/>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci. 11, 663-673. doi: 10.1093/scan/nsv149 <lb/>Hikida, T., Morita, M., Kuroiwa, M., Macpherson, T., Shuto, T., Sotogaku, N., et al. <lb/>(2020). Adolescent psychosocial stress enhances sensitization to cocaine exposure in <lb/>genetically vulnerable mice. Neurosci. Res. 151, 38-45. doi: 10.1016/j.neures.2019.02.007 <lb/>Huang, H., Nie, S., Cao, M., Marshall, C., Gao, J., Xiao, N., et al. (2016). <lb/>Characterization of AD-like phenotype in aged APPswe/PS1dE9 mice. Age 38, 303-322. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s11357-016-9929-7 <lb/>Jeong, Y. H., Park, C. H., Yoo, J., Shin, K. Y., Ahn, S. M., Kim, H. S., et al. (2006). <lb/>Chronic stress accelerates learning and memory impairments and increases amyloid <lb/>deposition in APPV717I-CT100 transgenic mice, an Alzheimer&apos;s disease model. FASEB <lb/>J. 20, 729-731. doi: 10.1096/fj.05-4265fje <lb/>Jung, J. H., Lee, G. W., Lee, J. H., Byun, M. S., Yi, D., Jeon, S. Y., et al. (2020). <lb/>Multiparity, brain atrophy, and cognitive decline. Front. Aging Neurosci. 12:159, doi: <lb/>10.3389/fnagi.2020.00159 <lb/>Justice, N. J. (2018). The relationship between stress and Alzheimer&apos;s disease. <lb/>Neurobiol Stress 8, 127-133. doi: 10.1016/j.ynstr.2018.04.002 <lb/>Kaidanovich-Beilin, O., Lipina, T., Vukobradovic, I., Roder, J., and Woodgett, J. R. <lb/>(2011). Assessment of social interaction behaviors. J. Vis. Exp., doi: 10.3791/2473 <lb/>Kim, J. G., Jung, H. S., Kim, K. J., Min, S. S., and Yoon, B. J. (2013). Basal blood <lb/>corticosterone level is correlated with susceptibility to chronic restraint stress in mice. <lb/>Neurosci. Lett. 555, 137-142. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2013.09.031 <lb/>Kin, K., Francis-Oliveira, J., Kano, S. I., and Niwa, M. (2023). Adolescent stress impairs <lb/>postpartum social behavior via anterior insula-prelimbic pathway in mice. Nat. <lb/>Commun. 14:2975, doi: 10.1038/s41467-023-38799-6 <lb/>Kin, K., Gaini, R., and Niwa, M. (2021). Effects of social isolation throughout the <lb/>lifespan on behaviors and related neuroendocrine functions in rodents. In: S. D. Sala <lb/>(Ed.) Encyclopedia of behavioural neuroscience, Second Edition. Edinburgh, United <lb/>Kingdom: Elsevier. Available at: https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/ <lb/>B9780128196410000906?via%3Dihub <lb/>Kosel, F., Torres Munoz, P., Yang, J. R., Wong, A. A., and Franklin, T. B. (2019). Age-<lb/>related changes in social behaviours in the 5XFAD mouse model of Alzheimer&apos;s disease. <lb/>Behav. Brain Res. 362, 160-172. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2019.01.029 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Leitzel et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnins.2024.1366199 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Neuroscience <lb/></note>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>Le Heron, C., Apps, M. J., and Husain, M. (2018). The anatomy of apathy: a <lb/>neurocognitive framework for amotivated behaviour. Neuropsychologia 118, 54-67. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2017.07.003 <lb/>Lee, J. H., Kim, J. Y., Noh, S., Lee, H., Lee, S. Y., Mun, J. Y., et al. (2021). Astrocytes <lb/>phagocytose adult hippocampal synapses for circuit homeostasis. Nature 590, 612-617. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-03060-3 <lb/>Lemche, E. (2018). Early life stress and epigenetics in late-onset Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>dementia: a systematic review. Curr. Genomics 19, 522-602. doi: 10.217 <lb/>4/1389202919666171229145156 <lb/>Lesuis, S. L., Hoeijmakers, L., Korosi, A., De Rooij, S. R., Swaab, D. F., Kessels, H. W., <lb/>et al. (2018). Vulnerability and resilience to Alzheimer&apos;s disease: early life conditions <lb/>modulate neuropathology and determine cognitive reserve. Alzheimers Res. Ther. <lb/>10:95, doi: 10.1186/s13195-018-0422-7 <lb/>Leuner, B., and Sabihi, S. (2016). The birth of new neurons in the maternal brain: <lb/>hormonal regulation and functional implications. Front. Neuroendocrinol. 41, 99-113. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.yfrne.2016.02.004 <lb/>Lockhart, S., Sawa, A., and Niwa, M. (2018). Developmental trajectories of brain <lb/>maturation and behavior: relevance to major mental illnesses. J. Pharmacol. Sci. 137, <lb/>1-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jphs.2018.04.008 <lb/>Matsumoto, Y., Niwa, M., Mouri, A., Noda, Y., Fukushima, T., Ozaki, N., et al. (2017). <lb/>Adolescent stress leads to glutamatergic disturbance through dopaminergic <lb/>abnormalities in the prefrontal cortex of genetically vulnerable mice. Psychopharmacology <lb/>234, 3055-3074. doi: 10.1007/s00213-017-4704-8 <lb/>Milligan Armstrong, A., Porter, T., Quek, H., White, A., Haynes, J., Jackaman, C., et al. <lb/>(2021). Chronic stress and Alzheimer&apos;s disease: the interplay between the hypothalamic-<lb/>pituitary-adrenal Axis, genetics and microglia. Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc. 96, <lb/>2209-2228. doi: 10.1111/brv.12750 <lb/>Morrison, K. E., Cole, A. B., Kane, P. J., Meadows, V. E., Thompson, S. M., and <lb/>Bale, T. L. (2020). Pubertal adversity alters chromatin dynamics and stress circuitry in <lb/>the pregnant brain. Neuropsychopharmacology 45, 1263-1271. doi: 10.1038/ <lb/>s41386-020-0634-y <lb/>Moy, S. S., Nadler, J. J., Perez, A., Barbaro, R. P., Johns, J. M., Magnuson, T. R., et al. <lb/>(2004). Sociability and preference for social novelty in five inbred strains: an approach <lb/>to assess autistic-like behavior in mice. Genes Brain Behav. 3, 287-302. doi: <lb/>10.1111/j.1601-1848.2004.00076.x <lb/>Nakai, T., Yamada, K., and Mizoguchi, H. (2021). Alzheimer&apos;s disease animal models: <lb/>elucidation of biomarkers and therapeutic approaches for cognitive impairment. Int. J. <lb/>Mol. Sci. 22:5549. doi: 10.3390/ijms22115549 <lb/>Nebel, R. A., Aggarwal, N. T., Barnes, L. L., Gallagher, A., Goldstein, J. M., <lb/>Kantarci, K., et al. (2018). Understanding the impact of sex and gender in <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease: a call to action. Alzheimers Dement. 14, 1171-1183, doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.jalz.2018.04.008 <lb/>Niwa, M., Jaaro-Peled, H., Tankou, S., Seshadri, S., Hikida, T., Matsumoto, Y., et al. <lb/>(2013). Adolescent stress-induced epigenetic control of dopaminergic neurons via <lb/>glucocorticoids. Science 339, 335-339. doi: 10.1126/science.1226931 <lb/>Niwa, M., Lee, R. S., Tanaka, T., Okada, K., Kano, S., and Sawa, A. (2016). A critical <lb/>period of vulnerability to adolescent stress: epigenetic mediators in mesocortical <lb/>dopaminergic neurons. Hum. Mol. Genet. 25, 1370-1381. doi: 10.1093/hmg/ddw019 <lb/>Niwa, M., Lockhart, S., Wood, D. J., Yang, K., Francis-Oliveira, J., Kin, K., et al. (2024). <lb/>Prolonged HPA axis dysregulation in postpartum depression associated with adverse <lb/>early life experiences during development: a cross-species translational study. Nat <lb/>Mental Health., doi: 10.1038/s44220-024-00217-1 <lb/>Oakley, H., Cole, S. L., Logan, S., Maus, E., Shao, P., Craft, J., et al. (2006). Intraneuronal <lb/>beta-amyloid aggregates, neurodegeneration, and neuron loss in transgenic mice with <lb/>five familial Alzheimer&apos;s disease mutations: potential factors in amyloid plaque <lb/>formation. J. Neurosci. 26, 10129-10140. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1202-06.2006 <lb/>Piller, C. (2022). Blots on a field? Science 377, 358-363. doi: 10.1126/science.add9993 <lb/>Rajan, K. B., Weuve, J., Barnes, L. L., Mcaninch, E. A., Wilson, R. S., and Evans, D. A. <lb/>(2021). Population estimate of people with clinical Alzheimer&apos;s disease and mild <lb/>cognitive impairment in the United States (2020-2060). Alzheimers Dement. 17, 1966-<lb/>1975, doi: 10.1002/alz.12362 <lb/>Samaey, C., Schreurs, A., Stroobants, S., and Balschun, D. (2019). Early cognitive and <lb/>behavioral deficits in mouse models for tauopathy and Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Front. Aging <lb/>Neurosci. 11:335. doi: 10.3389/fnagi.2019.00335 <lb/>Sandi, C., and Haller, J. (2015). Stress and the social brain: behavioural effects and <lb/>neurobiological mechanisms. Nat. Rev. Neurosci. 16, 290-304. doi: 10.1038/nrn3918 <lb/>Shors, T. J. (2016). A trip down memory lane about sex differences in the brain. Philos. <lb/>Trans. R. Soc. Lond. Ser. B Biol. Sci. 371:20150124, doi: 10.1098/rstb.2015.0124 <lb/>Snyder, H. M., Asthana, S., Bain, L., Brinton, R., Craft, S., Dubal, D. B., et al. (2016). <lb/>Sex biology contributions to vulnerability to Alzheimer&apos;s disease: a think tank convened <lb/>by the Women&apos;s Alzheimer&apos;s research initiative. Alzheimers Dement. 12, 1186-1196, doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.jalz.2016.08.004 <lb/>Sun, Q., Li, X., Li, A., Zhang, J., Ding, Z., Gong, H., et al. (2020). Ventral hippocampal-<lb/>prefrontal interaction affects social behavior via Parvalbumin positive neurons in the <lb/>medial prefrontal cortex. Iscience 23:100894. doi: 10.1016/j.isci.2020.100894 <lb/>Yanai, S., and Endo, S. (2021). Functional aging in male C57BL/6J mice across the life-<lb/>span: a systematic behavioral analysis of motor, emotional, and memory function to define <lb/>an aging phenotype. Front. Aging Neurosci. 13:697621. doi: 10.3389/fnagi.2021.697621 <lb/>Zack, G. W., Rogers, W. E., and Latt, S. A. (1977). Automatic measurement of sister <lb/>chromatid exchange frequency. J. Histochem. Cytochem. 25, 741-753. doi: 10.1177/25.7.70454 <lb/>Zhang, Y., Chen, H., Li, R., Sterling, K., and Song, W. (2023). Amyloid Beta-based <lb/>therapy for Alzheimer&apos;s disease: challenges, successes and future. Signal Transduct. <lb/>Target. Ther. 8:248, doi: 10.1038/s41392-023-01484-7 </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>