<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T17:37:30.152Z">11/20/2025 5:37:30 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T17:37:21.005076Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T17:37:21.005076Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Treatment decision for <lb/>recurrences in non-small cell <lb/>lung cancer during or after <lb/>adjuvant osimertinib: an <lb/>international Delphi <lb/>consensus report <lb/>Myriam Mirza 1 * , Aseem Shrivastava 1 , Cecile Matthews 2 , <lb/>Natasha Leighl 3 † , Calvin S. H. Ng 4 † , David Planchard 5,6 † , <lb/>Sanjay Popat 7,8,9 † , Julia Rotow 10 † , Egbert F. Smit 11 † , Ross Soo 12 † , <lb/>Masahiro Tsuboi 13 † , Fan Yang 14 † , Brendon Stiles 15 ‡ , <lb/>Christian Grohe 16 ‡ and Yi-Long Wu 17 ‡ <lb/>1 Charles River Associates, Munich, Germany, 2 Charles River Associates, Cambridge, United Kingdom, <lb/>3 Department of Medical Oncology &amp; Hematology, Princess Margaret Cancer Centre, Toronto, <lb/>ON, Canada, 4 Department of Surgery, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, Hong Kong <lb/>SAR, China, 5 Department of Medical Oncology, Thoracic Group and International Center for Thoracic <lb/>Cancers (CICT), Gustave Roussy, Villejuif, France, 6 Faculty of Medicine, Paris-Saclay University, <lb/>Paris, France, 7 National Heart and Lung Institute, Imperial College, London, United Kingdom, 8 Lung Unit, <lb/>The Royal Marsden, London, United Kingdom, 9 Division of Clinical Studies, The Institute of Cancer <lb/>Research, London, United Kingdom, 10 Lowe Center for Thoracic Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer <lb/>Institute, Boston, MA, United States, 11 Department of Thoracic Oncology, Netherlands Cancer Institute, <lb/>Amsterdam, Netherlands, 12 Department of Haematology-Oncology, National University Hospital, <lb/>Singapore, Singapore, 13 Department of Thoracic Surgery and Oncology, National Cancer Center Hospital <lb/>East, Kashiwa, Japan, 14 Thoracic Surgery Department, Peking University People&apos;s Hospital, Beijing, China, <lb/>15 Thoracic Surgery and Surgical Oncology, Albert Einstein College of Medicine and Montefiore Medical <lb/>Centre, New York, NY, United States, 16 Department of Pneumology, Evangelische Lungenklinik (ELK) <lb/>Berlin, Berlin, Germany, 17 Guangdong Lung Cancer Institute, Guangdong Provincial People&apos;s Hospital <lb/>and Guangdong Academy of Medical Sciences, Guangzhou, China <lb/>Introduction: Osimertinib is recommended by major guidelines for use in the <lb/>adjuvant setting in patients with EGFR mutation-positive NSCLC following the <lb/>significant improvement in disease-free survival observed in the Phase III <lb/>ADAURA trials. Due to limited real-world data in the adjuvant setting, little <lb/>guidance exists on how to approach potential recurrences either during or <lb/>after the completion of the treatment. This study aimed to reach a broad <lb/>consensus on key treatment decision criteria in the events of recurrence. <lb/>Methods: To reach a broad consensus, a modified Delphi panel study was <lb/>conducted consisting of two rounds of surveys, followed by two consensus <lb/>meetings and a final offline review of key statements. An international panel of <lb/>experts in the field of NSCLC (n=12) was used to provide clinical insights regarding <lb/>patient management at various stages of NSCLC disease including patient <lb/>monitoring, diagnostics, and treatment approach for specific recurrence scenarios. <lb/>This study tested recurrences occurring 1) within or outside the central nervous <lb/>system (CNS), 2) during or after the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen in NSCLC disease <lb/>which is 3) amenable or not amenable to local consolidative therapy. <lb/>Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Yusuke Okuma, <lb/>National Cancer Center Hospital, Japan <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Alberto Pavan, <lb/>Azienda ULSS 3 Serenissima, Italy <lb/>Jan Von Der Thüsen, <lb/>Erasmus Medical Center, Netherlands <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Myriam Mirza <lb/>mmirza@crai.com <lb/> † These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work <lb/> ‡ Steering committee members (study <lb/>supervisors) <lb/>RECEIVED 30 October 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 31 December 2023 <lb/>PUBLISHED 23 January 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Mirza M, Shrivastava A, Matthews C, Leighl N, <lb/>Ng CSH, Planchard D, Popat S, Rotow J, <lb/>Smit EF, Soo R, Tsuboi M, Yang F, Stiles B, <lb/>Grohe C and Wu Y-L (2024) Treatment <lb/>decision for recurrences in non-small cell <lb/>lung cancer during or after adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib: an international Delphi <lb/>consensus report. <lb/>Front. Oncol. 13:1330468. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Mirza, Shrivastava, Matthews, Leighl, <lb/>Ng, Planchard, Popat, Rotow, Smit, Soo, <lb/>Tsuboi, Yang, Stiles, Grohe and Wu. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the terms <lb/>of the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>in other forums is permitted, provided the <lb/>original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) <lb/>are credited and that the original publication <lb/>in this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 23 January 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/>Results: Panellists agreed on various aspects of patient monitoring and <lb/>diagnostics including the use of standard techniques (e.g., CT, MRI) and <lb/>tumour biomarker assessment using tissue and liquid biopsies. Consensus was <lb/>reached on 6 statements describing treatment considerations for the specific <lb/>NSCLC recurrence scenarios. Panellists agreed on the value of osimertinib as a <lb/>monotherapy or as part of the overall treatment strategy within the probed <lb/>recurrence scenarios and acknowledged that more clinical evidence is required <lb/>before precise recommendations for specific patient populations can be made. <lb/>Discussion: This study provides a qualitative expert opinion framework for <lb/>clinicians to consider within their treatment decision-making when faced with <lb/>recurrence during or after adjuvant-osimertinib treatment. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>osimertinib, non-small cell lung cancer, adjuvant treatment, EGFR mutation, <lb/>recurrence, treatment sequencing <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>A significant number of NSCLC patients harbor EGFR driver <lb/>mutations (EGFRm NSCLC) which activate EGFR tyrosine kinase <lb/>to have a ligand-independent activity, resulting in tumorigenesis <lb/>(1-3). In US plus Europe and Asia, EGFRm NSCLC patients <lb/>account for ~10-15% and ~30-50% of all NSCLC cases, <lb/>respectively (4). The two most common EGFR mutations are <lb/>short in-frame deletions of exon 19 and a point mutation in exon <lb/>21 which result in the substitution of leucine by arginine at codon <lb/>858 (L858R), together, accounting for ∼85% of all EGFR mutations <lb/>in NSCLC (4). EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs) have <lb/>been shown to significantly improve disease-free survival (DFS) in <lb/>patients with resected early-stage EGFRm NSCLC (5, 6). <lb/>Osimertinib is a third-generation EGFR-TKI approved in many <lb/>countries around the world for both EGFR-TKI sensitizing (exon 19 <lb/>deletion &amp; L858R point mutation in exon 21) and T790M resistance <lb/>mutations in advanced stage NSCLC patients (7). In 2020, primary <lb/>analysis of the pivotal phase 3 ADAURA trial demonstrated a <lb/>substantial DFS benefit in patients with EGFR-mutated NSCLC <lb/>who underwent complete tumor resection, with hazard ratios of <lb/>0.17 (99% CI 0.11 to 0.26; p &lt; 0.001) for stage II to IIIA disease and <lb/>0.20 (99% CI 0.14 to 0.30; p &lt; 0.001) for stage IB to IIIA disease <lb/>compared to placebo. Due to the significant improvement in DFS, <lb/>the independent data monitoring committee recommended <lb/>reporting the trial results two years earlier than originally <lb/>planned, allowing patients to continue in the trial (8). Updated <lb/>data with an additional 2 years of follow-up continued to show a <lb/>sustained DFS benefit (hazard ratios of 0.23 in stage II and IIIA <lb/>disease and 0.27 in stage IB and IIIA disease, respectively), In <lb/>addition, recurrences among all the patients with stage IB to IIIA <lb/>disease were less frequent with osimertinib (93 patients [27%]) than <lb/>with placebo (205 patients [60%]). Recurrences in the osimertinib <lb/>group included distant metastases only (45 patients [13%]), local/ <lb/>regional only (42 patients [12%]), as well as both local/regional and <lb/>distance (6 patients [2%]) (9). <lb/>Most recently, published data on overall survival (OS) in the <lb/>overall population (patients with stage IB to IIIA disease) report an <lb/>OS HR of 0.49 (95% CI 0.34 to 0.70; p &lt; 0.0001) with a 5-year OS <lb/>rate of 88% with osimertinib vs 78% with placebo. In stage II-IIIA <lb/>disease, OS HR was reported to be 0.49 (95% CI 0.33 to 0.73; <lb/>p=0.0001) and the 5-year OS rate was 85% with osimertinib vs 73% <lb/>with placebo. The median OS was not reached in either population <lb/>or treatment group (10). <lb/>While adjuvant-osimertinib demonstrated an unprecedented <lb/>patient benefit in terms of OS improvements, there is a need to <lb/>understand better the optimal management of patients who show <lb/>tumor recurrence either during or after the completion of the <lb/>adjuvant-osimertinib regimen. Given the anticipated emergence <lb/>of a patient population with disease relapse following adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib treatment, and the absence of real-world data or trial <lb/>data, creating formal guidelines on how to approach and manage <lb/>recurrent patients either during or after completion of adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib is not yet possible. The knowledge gap regarding the <lb/>appropriate approach for patient monitoring, diagnostics, and <lb/>treatment sequencing decisions in cases of various recurrence <lb/>scenarios can be bridged via clinical consensus studies. Recent <lb/>Abbreviations: CNS, central nervous system; CT, computerized tomography; <lb/>DFS, disease-free survival; EGFRm, Epidermal growth factor receptor mutation; <lb/>HR, hazard ratio; HRQoL, Health-related quality of life; MDT, multi-disciplinary <lb/>team; MRD, minimal residual disease; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; NGS, <lb/>next-generation sequencing); OS, overall survival; PET, positron emission <lb/>tomography; SBRT, stereotactic body radiation therapy; SRS, stereotactic <lb/>radiosurgery; TKI, tyrosine kinase inhibitor; NSCLC,non-small-cell lung <lb/>cancer; WBRT, whole-brain radiotherapy. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>02 <lb/></page>

			<body>consensus studies echoed the need for further clinical trial data to <lb/>create formal guidelines (11, 12) and outlined the appropriate <lb/>treatment options (including osimertinib) for different recurrence <lb/>scenarios (12). In this consensus paper, we discuss the key clinical <lb/>factors that can be considered during treatment decision-making as <lb/>well as clinical value of osimertinib for various recurrence scenarios. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>The study utilized a modified Delphi method which included <lb/>two rounds of surveys, followed by two consensus meetings and a <lb/>final offline review by an expert panel. The key topics addressed in <lb/>this study are listed in Table 1. <lb/>2.1 Panel selection <lb/>In this study, an international panel of experts was recruited <lb/>with significant expertise in NSCLC as well as patient management <lb/>with EGFR-TKIs or other systemic therapies (n=12). Experts who <lb/>fulfil the following criteria were selected as panelists in this study: a <lb/>physician specializing in NSCLC (medical oncologist or thoracic <lb/>surgeon); based in a specialist lung cancer treatment and research <lb/>center; significant years of experience in practice since completing <lb/>residence/fellowship; over 60% of combined professional time <lb/>dedicated to clinical practice and research activities related to <lb/>NSCLC; regularly treating and managing patients across all stages <lb/>of NSCLC (stage I-III); active advisor/member of a national or <lb/>international society for lung cancer with participation in guideline <lb/>creation for NSCLC in the last 5 years; has published on the topic of <lb/>stage I-III NSCLC in international peer-reviewed journals within <lb/>the last 5 years. <lb/>The steering committee consisted of two medical oncologists <lb/>and one thoracic surgeon from different geographies (Asia, Europe, <lb/>and the USA) to ensure geographic as well as different clinical <lb/>expertise were incorporated in the development of materials. <lb/>2.2 Delphi methodology and <lb/>statement development <lb/>Both surveys were composed of a series of open and close <lb/>ended question and shared via email. All materials tested in the <lb/>study were co-developed and reviewed by the steering committee. <lb/>In Survey 1, panelists were presented with six hypothetical patient <lb/>case studies representing distinct real-world EFGRm NSCLC <lb/>patients who recur during or after the treatment with adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib and were surveyed on their approach to patient <lb/>monitoring, diagnostic workup, and treatment sequencing (see <lb/>Supplementary Data 1 -Table 1 for hypothetical patient cases). <lb/>Most questions were asked in an open-ended style to capture <lb/>individual approach as well as clinical considerations. After <lb/>analysis, topics that reached clinical consensus were reported <lb/>back in Survey 2 as anonymized consolidated feedback and <lb/>those that did not reach consensus were further probed using <lb/>new clinical statements based on insights from Survey 1 (see <lb/>Supplementary Data 2 for both survey 1 and 2). The insights <lb/>gathered from Survey 2 were analyzed to find topics of clinical <lb/>consensus. Statements or insights where clinical consensus was <lb/>not achieved were brought forward to a series of consensus <lb/>meetings (see Supplementary Data 1 -Table 2). <lb/>Two virtual consensus meetings were held where a final set <lb/>of statements were discussed and amended live during the <lb/>meeting. The level of consensus on the amended statements was <lb/>probed through anonymous polls. The statement modification <lb/>process was iterated until an overall clinical consensus (≥80% <lb/>panelist agreement) was achieved for all six statements (see <lb/>Supplementary Data 1 -Table 3 for the evolution of the survey <lb/>statements pre-and post-consensus meeting). The final set of <lb/>consensus statements were shared with all panelists for offline <lb/>review and to capture their final level of agreement. <lb/>2.3 Defining consensus <lb/>Closed statements were ranked on the Likert scale of 1 to 9, <lb/>where 1 equals &quot;strongly disagree with the statement,&quot; and 9 equals <lb/>&quot;strongly agree with the statement,&quot;. Likert scale rating of 7 or <lb/>higher for a given statement from a minimum of 80% of panelists <lb/>was defined as a threshold for a consensus on the statement. In <lb/>contrast, a rating of 3 or lower for a given statement from a <lb/>minimum of 80% of panelists indicated consensus had been <lb/>reached of disagreement with the statement. <lb/>TABLE 1 Key topics addressed in this study i . <lb/>1 <lb/>General treatment decision influencers within NSCLC and recurrence <lb/>scenarios: Patient characteristics and history including age, smoking status, <lb/>the initial stage of the disease, and the subsequent treatment methodology <lb/>2 <lb/>Patient monitoring approach within adjuvant setting: Different <lb/>techniques used and the monitoring frequency both during and after the <lb/>completion of the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen <lb/>3 <lb/>Diagnostic approach upon recurrence suspicion: Different diagnostic <lb/>approaches and their potential impact on the ongoing adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen <lb/>4 <lb/>Treatment and management approaches for CNS and ex-CNS <lb/>recurrence: Treatment decision-making process considering recurrence <lb/>type, timing, and other clinically relevant factors ii <lb/>5 <lb/>Variation in patient management based on the recurrence scenarios: <lb/>Potential differences in the patient monitoring, diagnostic and/or treatment <lb/>approaches for the following distinct recurrence scenarios: <lb/>i. Ex-CNS or CNS recurrences during the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen <lb/>that are amenable to local consolidative therapy iii <lb/>ii. Ex-CNS or CNS recurrences post-adjuvant osimertinib regimen that are <lb/>amenable to local consolidative therapy <lb/>iii. Ex-CNS or CNS recurrences during the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen <lb/>that are not amenable to local consolidative therapy <lb/>iv. Ex-CNS or CNS recurrences post-adjuvant-osimertinib regimen that <lb/>are not amenable to local consolidative therapy <lb/>i <lb/>The table displays the key topics related to disease recurrence events during or after adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib treatment for EGFRm NSCLC. <lb/>ii Clinical considerations of treatment sequencing decisions and potential geographic <lb/>differences in the recommended treatment sequencing were also captured. <lb/>iii <lb/>Local consolidative therapy includes surgery, ablation (percutaneous/endoscopic ablations <lb/>including thermal/cryo ablation), radiotherapy, conformal radiotherapy, or stereotactic body <lb/>radiation therapy (SBRT). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>03 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.4 Limiting bias <lb/>To limit bias, all surveys were conducted anonymously, and <lb/>identity of experts was revealed only during the consensus meetings. <lb/>Furthermore, results from rating exercises were provided as median <lb/>scores and anonymous votes were held to finalize the consensus <lb/>statements. In addition, offline review of the final statements was <lb/>conducted individually without revealing the level of agreement <lb/>from other panelists. <lb/>An independent third-party vendor, Charles River Associates <lb/>(CRA) designed the survey, moderated the consensus meetings, <lb/>analyzed the data and supported the manuscript development. The <lb/>sponsor of the study (AstraZeneca Ltd.) did not participate in <lb/>consensus meetings. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>Surveys 1 and 2 were used to gather a greater understanding of <lb/>the factors influencing treatment sequencing within the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib setting, including recurrence type and timing. A <lb/>summary of the key insights gathered from Surveys 1 and 2 is <lb/>shown in Table 2. <lb/>3.1 Survey 1 <lb/>In Survey 1, six distinct hypothetical NSCLC patient case <lb/>studies were used to understand how panelists approach <lb/>management of different patient types and understand the <lb/>potential differences under varying recurrence scenarios. Patients <lb/>within the case studies had varying EGFRm mutations, ethnicities <lb/>(Asian/non-Asian), age groups (40-65 years old), smoking status, <lb/>past experience with adjuvant chemotherapies, recurrence either <lb/>during or after adjuvant-osimertinib and details of the recurrence. <lb/>All patients within the case studies were given a performance status <lb/>(PS) score of 1. <lb/>Overall, panelists agreed that all the hypothetical patient cases <lb/>are representative of real-world profiles and the use of adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib in these hypothetical patient cases is approved under <lb/>the ADAURA label. Panelists also agreed on the monitoring and <lb/>diagnostic approaches laid out, albeit frequency of monitoring and <lb/>how molecular analysis is conducted remained unclear. Moreover, <lb/>although some panelists mentioned the use of monitoring <lb/>techniques such as minimal residual disease (MRD) tests and <lb/>blood tests (e.g., CEA -carcinoembryonic antigen), it was unclear <lb/>if these techniques would be used for all patients or in specific <lb/>circumstances. Finally, there was a lack of agreement on the value of <lb/>liquid biopsy within the diagnostic process. Overall, despite no <lb/>diagnostic procedural differences between oligometastatic and <lb/>disseminated recurrences being reported there remained a lack of <lb/>clarity as to whether adjuvant-osimertinib regimen should be <lb/>continued during diagnostic workup and up until a new <lb/>treatment strategy is confirmed. <lb/>TABLE 2 Survey 1 and Survey 2 outcomes -Major insights with an <lb/>overall panellists&apos; agreement. <lb/>Survey 1 and 2 Outcomes <lb/>Key topic <lb/>Insights <lb/>Agreement <lb/>reached <lb/>Patient <lb/>monitoring <lb/>during or <lb/>after <lb/>adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib <lb/>regimen <lb/>1 <lb/>Patients monitoring during or after <lb/>ADAURA regimen is conducted <lb/>using CT scan and brain MRI in <lb/>line with local guidelines. <lb/>Survey 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Additional patient monitoring <lb/>techniques like MRD and blood <lb/>tests (e.g., Carcinoembryonic <lb/>antigen assay) can be used as add-<lb/>on techniques but caution is <lb/>recommended as currently there is <lb/>no clinically validated MRD assay <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Tissue biopsy is performed for <lb/>histological and molecular analysis <lb/>to look for actionable targets (e.g., <lb/>EGFR, PDL-1, others) in all <lb/>feasible cases <lb/>Survey 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>Liquid biopsies are performed <lb/>when tissue biopsy is difficult or as <lb/>a second diagnostic method. <lb/>Factors such as patient or doctor <lb/>preference for non-invasive <lb/>procedure also influence the <lb/>decision to perform liquid biopsies <lb/>but they have secondary priority <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>5 <lb/>NGS or other molecular analysis <lb/>procedures are always performed if <lb/>progression is observed <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>6 <lb/>In case of recurrence, osimertinib is <lb/>used during the entire diagnostic <lb/>workup and up until a new <lb/>treatment regimen is decided <lb/>• Use of osimertinib can help avoid <lb/>disease flare (as observed in <lb/>metastatic setting) and decrease the <lb/>risk of progression in the CNS <lb/>• Osimertinib might be part of the <lb/>new treatment regimen depending <lb/>on the re-biopsy results <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>Treatment <lb/>approach: ex-<lb/>CNS and/or <lb/>CNS <lb/>recurrence <lb/>(amenable to <lb/>local <lb/>consolidative <lb/>therapy) <lb/>7 <lb/>Treatment for oligometastatic <lb/>distant recurrence includes local <lb/>consolidative therapies -surgery, <lb/>percutaneous/endoscopic ablations <lb/>including thermal/cryo ablation, <lb/>radiotherapy, conformal <lb/>radiotherapy, or stereotactic body <lb/>radiation therapy (SBRT) <lb/>Survey 1 <lb/>8 <lb/>Treatment strategies for CNS <lb/>recurrence include combination of <lb/>local consolidative therapies <lb/>(surgery or radiotherapy) with <lb/>systemic therapies <lb/>• Surgery will be performed only <lb/>when anatomically feasible <lb/>• Stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) <lb/>and whole-brain radiation therapy <lb/>(WBRT) are the preferred <lb/>radiotherapy options for <lb/>oligometastatic and disseminated <lb/>Survey 1 <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>04 <lb/></page>

			<body>Panelists agreed on treatment approaches for local and distant <lb/>oligometastatic CNS/ex-CNS recurrence as well as disseminated <lb/>CNS/ex-CNS recurrence. However, treatment sequencing <lb/>decision for both ex-CNS and CNS recurrences and the <lb/>associated driving factors were unclear. No consensus was <lb/>observed on how patients treated with the preferred initial <lb/>treatment (e.g., ablative therapy) are therapeutically followed <lb/>up and to what extent osimertinib would be considered a <lb/>therapeutic option. <lb/>3.2 Survey 2 <lb/>Gaps identified in Survey 1 were explored in Survey 2, where <lb/>agreement was reached on all outstanding aspects of diagnosis and <lb/>monitoring. Panelists were presented with different scenarios to <lb/>better understand the treatment sequencing drivers and how <lb/>adjuvant-osimertinib would be considered in the overall <lb/>treatment strategy. These scenarios focused on understanding the <lb/>impact of recurrence location (CNS versus ex-CNS), amenability to <lb/>local consolidative therapy, timing (during or after adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen) as well as time points (3, 6, 18 months after <lb/>initiation of adjuvant-osimertinib versus 3, 12 and 36 months after <lb/>completion with adjuvant-osimertinib regimen). <lb/>While panelists agreed that continuing with adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib is clinically suitable during the diagnostic process <lb/>and can be considered within treatment decision-making in the <lb/>described CNS/ex-CNS recurrence scenarios, how its use would <lb/>be decided remained unclear. Furthermore, there was no <lb/>consensus on how long treatment with osimertinib would <lb/>continue within recurrence scenarios and what considerations <lb/>would influence this decision. Finally, some panelists suggested <lb/>temporarily pausing the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen upon <lb/>recurrence and resuming after ablative therapy, but the <lb/>recommended pause duration and its applicability to all <lb/>ablative therapy procedures are not clear. For recurrences after <lb/>completing the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen, a combination of <lb/>ablative therapy and osimertinib rechallenge was proposed, but it <lb/>remains unclear whether the rechallenge would be performed <lb/>alongside ablative therapy or after its completion. <lb/>3.3 Consensus meeting <lb/>Gaps in key treatment decision factors and the value of <lb/>osimertinib across tested recurrence scenarios were addressed <lb/>during 2 virtual consensus meetings, where experts amended <lb/>wording of original proposed statements in line with best clinical <lb/>practice and experience given limited randomized evidence. A <lb/>summary of the statements that reached a consensus is shown <lb/>in Table 3. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>A lack of clinical guidance on how to treat recurrences during or <lb/>after the completion of the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen has been <lb/>raised in recent publications (11, 12). Our Delphi consensus study <lb/>surveyed an international panel of experts on patient-specific as well <lb/>as recurrence scenario-specific considerations when making <lb/>treatment decisions in the absence of extensive clinical data and <lb/>formalized guidelines. <lb/>Our study approach enables experts to share their own opinions <lb/>based on clinical experience, and, where relevant, knowledge of the <lb/>ADAURA phase 3 data, with the aim of fostering the integration of <lb/>these viewpoints. Overall, our research shows a high consensus <lb/>TABLE 2 Continued <lb/>Survey 1 and 2 Outcomes <lb/>Key topic <lb/>Insights <lb/>Agreement <lb/>reached <lb/>CNS recurrences, respectively <lb/>• Continuation of osimertinib is a <lb/>treatment option depending on the <lb/>recurrence histology <lb/>9 <lb/>In case of recurrence during the <lb/>adjuvant osimertinib regimen that <lb/>is amenable to local consolidative <lb/>therapy, local consolidative therapy <lb/>is performed in parallel to <lb/>continuation of adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib use, if possible <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>10 <lb/>In case of recurrence after the <lb/>adjuvant osimertinib regimen is <lb/>completed, local consolidative <lb/>therapy is performed in parallel to <lb/>rechallenge with osimertinib, <lb/>if possible <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>Treatment <lb/>approach: ex-<lb/>CNS and/or <lb/>CNS <lb/>recurrence <lb/>(not <lb/>amenable to <lb/>local <lb/>consolidative <lb/>therapy) <lb/>11 <lb/>Treatment approach for <lb/>disseminated distant recurrence <lb/>involves systemic therapies based <lb/>on the newly obtained histology. <lb/>Systemic therapies mentioned <lb/>include targeted drugs against the <lb/>resistance mechanism (other TKIs), <lb/>chemotherapy, immunotherapy, <lb/>and combinational approach <lb/>(e.g., chemo + TKI, <lb/>chemo + immunotherapy) i <lb/>Survey 1 <lb/>12 <lb/>In case of ex-CNS or CNS <lb/>recurrence during the adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib regimen and local <lb/>consolidative therapy is not an <lb/>option, systemic therapy based on <lb/>the re-biopsy result is <lb/>recommended with potential to <lb/>include osimertinib depending on <lb/>patient case <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>13 <lb/>In case of recurrence ex-CNS and/ <lb/>or CNS after completion of <lb/>adjuvant osimertinib regimen, <lb/>therapeutic approach will be based <lb/>on re-biopsy results and in <lb/>conjunction with the MDT with <lb/>potential to include osimertinib <lb/>depending on patient case <lb/>Survey 2 <lb/>i <lb/>Combination treatment approach with osimertinib and immunotherapy was flagged as <lb/>unsuitable by KEEs and additional caution was recommended in case of sequential use. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>05 <lb/></page>

			<body>regarding patient considerations and approaches to various <lb/>recurrence scenarios. Statements and considerations that garnered <lb/>consensus can serve as valuable guidance in clinical practice when <lb/>combined with a tailored patient approach and recommendations <lb/>from multidisciplinary teams. <lb/>4.1 Key considerations for adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib and EGFRm NSCLC patient <lb/>monitoring &amp; diagnostic work-up <lb/>Our results show that the decision to use adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>is not driven by patient&apos;s gender, ethnicity, age, smoking or alcohol <lb/>use status, or previous treatment experience with adjuvant-<lb/>chemotherapy. However, the decision to use adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>might change if a patient has poor PS score (PS &gt;1), has high <lb/>comorbidities or is likely to be less compliant with the <lb/>dosing regimen. <lb/>Furthermore, patients receiving adjuvant-osimertinib should be <lb/>monitored using local guidelines which broadly align with <lb/>international guidelines such as ESMO (Table 2 -statement 1). <lb/>In our study, tissue biopsy is recommended in all feasible cases <lb/>in case of progression to assess the suitability of different treatment <lb/>options based on tumor biomarker/mutation profile. The diagnostic <lb/>result from liquid biopsy was highlighted to be less sensitive and <lb/>contingent on site and burden of the recurrence (Table 2 -<lb/>statements 3-5). Therefore, only when tissue biopsy is not <lb/>possible should liquid biopsy be used as it is unable to capture <lb/>histologic transformation and has limited sensitivity from <lb/>amplifications and fusions (12). Moreover, liquid biopsies may <lb/>give false negative or positive results, especially in cases of low <lb/>volume disease with lower than threshold circulating ctDNA (13). <lb/>These recommendations are echoed in the ESMO expert consensus <lb/>on the management of EGFRm NSCLC (12). The panel&apos;s consensus <lb/>is to continue use of adjuvant-osimertinib during the diagnostic <lb/>workup and up until a new treatment regimen is decided for <lb/>patients who present with recurrence during the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen. The continued use of osimertinib can help <lb/>avoid disease flare, a well-established scenario for metastatic <lb/>disease, and to additionally protect against CNS progression <lb/>(Table 2 -statement 6) (9, 14, 15). <lb/>4.2 Key considerations in treatment <lb/>sequencing for adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>recurrence scenarios <lb/>Across all tested scenarios, treatment decisions are taken on a <lb/>patient-by-patient basis and taking input from the multi-<lb/>disciplinary team (MDT), aligning with major guidelines (16-21). <lb/>The following key clinical criteria should be considered during the <lb/>treatment sequencing decision process (Table 2 -statements 7-13): <lb/>• Pattern and location -Number of lesions, size and location <lb/>determine if the recurrence is oligometastatic and amenable <lb/>to local consolidative therapy or disseminated and requires <lb/>TABLE 3 Final consensus statements with an overall panelist agreement. <lb/>Recurrence <lb/>scenarios <lb/>Final Consensus Statement <lb/>Panelist <lb/>Agreement <lb/>ex-CNS or CNS recurrence <lb/>amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy <lb/>1 <lb/>If a patient experiences an ex-CNS or CNS recurrence amenable to local consolidative therapy during the <lb/>adjuvant-osimertinib regimen, in absence of existing evidence, I would use the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen in <lb/>parallel with local consolidative therapy, considering the risk of toxicities, site of recurrence, method of local <lb/>consolidative therapy and after discussion with the MDT <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>11 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/>2 <lb/>If a patient experiences an ex-CNS or CNS recurrence amenable to local consolidative therapy after completion <lb/>of the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen, I would consider rechallenging with osimertinib as an option after local <lb/>consolidative therapy, after discussion with MDT <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>10 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/>ex-CNS and/or CNS <lb/>recurrence during adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen not <lb/>amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy <lb/>3 <lb/>If a patient experiences CNS-only recurrence not amenable to local consolidative therapy during the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen, I would consider continuing with osimertinib as a part of the overall treatment strategy <lb/>when a patient has asymptomatic progression, if fits with the best clinical practice <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>10 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/>4 <lb/>In the absence of randomized evidence, if a patient experiences ex-CNS recurrence not amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy during the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen, I would consider continuation with osimertinib <lb/>as a part of the overall treatment strategy if a patient has asymptomatic progression and if fits with the current <lb/>guideline recommendations <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>10 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/>ex-CNS and/or CNS <lb/>recurrence post-adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen not <lb/>amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy <lb/>5 <lb/>If a patient experiences an ex-CNS and/or CNS recurrence after completion of the adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>regimen, and local consolidative therapy is not an option, I would rechallenge with monotherapy osimertinib <lb/>or osimertinib as a part of the overall treatment strategy irrespective of when the recurrence happens after <lb/>treatment completion, if fits with the best clinical practice and is supported by re-biopsy in all feasible cases <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>12 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/>All ex-CNS and/or CNS <lb/>recurrence types <lb/>6 <lb/>If a patient experiences an ex-CNS and/or CNS recurrence during or after the completion of the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen and I choose to continue with osimertinib as part of the overall treatment strategy, I <lb/>would continue the osimertinib therapy until the clinical situation mandates a change or stop in therapy <lb/>Consensus <lb/>reached <lb/>11 out of 12 <lb/>panelists agreed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>06 <lb/></page>

			<body>treatment with a systemic therapy. Furthermore, limited <lb/>metastases which may include lesions in contralateral lung, <lb/>lymph node, CNS or other organs could be managed with a <lb/>combination of local consolidative therapy and a systemic <lb/>therapy. Panelists did not rule out the treatment value of <lb/>osimertinib in various recurrence scenarios solely based on <lb/>pattern and location. <lb/>• Timing of recurrence -whether and when recurrence occurs <lb/>during or after the adjuvant-osimertinib regimen can indicate <lb/>if the recurrent lesion is sensitive or resistant to osimertinib in <lb/>addition to genetic profiling. Recurrence during the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen (especially ex-CNS) might be a sign of <lb/>acquired resistance to osimertinib, while recurrence after the <lb/>completion of the regimen might indicate a disease flare post-<lb/>treatment cessation. <lb/>• Molecular characterization of the recurrence -Confirming <lb/>molecular histology or biomarker profile informs the <lb/>presence of any actionable target and is necessary when <lb/>considering further treatment with osimertinib. <lb/>It is important to note here that while panelists acknowledge <lb/>osimertinib to be a valuable treatment option for patients with <lb/>complex clinical presentations, including the emergence of distinct <lb/>resistance mechanisms (e.g., MET amplification, PIK3CA mutation, <lb/>BRAF mutation) and/or progression to acquire other genetic <lb/>alterations (e.g., ALK mutation), these specific recurrence <lb/>scenarios were not explored in this study. <lb/>4.2.1 Therapeutic value of osimertinib: ex-CNS or <lb/>CNS recurrences during the adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>regimen that are amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy <lb/>For ex-CNS or CNS recurrences which occur during the <lb/>adjuvant-osimertinib regimen and are amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy (surgery, ablation, or radiotherapy), the <lb/>panel recommended to continue adjuvant-osimertinib treatment <lb/>along with local consolidative therapy if found clinically suitable <lb/>(Table 3 -consensus statement 1). A consensus was achieved in <lb/>pausing osimertinib regimen during radiotherapy due to severe <lb/>toxicity risk in case of combined use, however, length of pause was <lb/>not specified. Pausing the use of therapies such as osimertinib <lb/>during radiotherapy was also recently highlighted in published <lb/>consensus recommendations by the EORTC-ESTRO OligoCare <lb/>consortium, where a consensus was reached to not perform SBRT <lb/>within one week of the administration of anti-EGFR antibody (22). <lb/>However, in the absence of safety data in combining local <lb/>consolidative therapy with osimertinib treatment, recommendations <lb/>on pausing or continuing with osimertinib during ablative or surgical <lb/>procedures could not be reached and instead in the absence of <lb/>treatment guidelines, the decision to pause osimertinib should be <lb/>based on treatment experience from the metastatic setting, i.e., <lb/>considering the extent of recurrence including location, size and <lb/>number of the lesions (note that the treatment guidelines for <lb/>metastatic settings are also not yet established). Additionally, caution <lb/>was recommended when patients are given other drugs (e.g., <lb/>prophylactic antibiotics before local consolidative therapy) that could <lb/>show drug-drug interactions with osimertinib. <lb/>4.2.2 Therapeutic value of osimertinib: ex-CNS or <lb/>CNS recurrences post-adjuvant osimertinib <lb/>regimen that are amenable or not amendable to <lb/>local consolidative therapy <lb/>While the place of osimertinib within the treatment strategy is <lb/>dependent on multiple factors (see Section 4.2), the treatment value <lb/>of rechallenging with osimertinib was thought to increase as <lb/>duration between time to recurrence and completion of the <lb/>adjuvant-osimertinib regimen increases. However, no consensus <lb/>was achieved on the minimum recurrence free time (3, 12 or 36 <lb/>months) to consider osimertinib for rechallenge. <lb/>In cases of post-adjuvant osimertinib regimen recurrence <lb/>scenarios that are amenable to local consolidative therapy and <lb/>rechallenging with osimertinib is suitable, the consensus is to <lb/>rechallenge with osimertinib after the completion of the local <lb/>consolidative therapy (Table 3 -consensus statement 2), <lb/>especially in the case of radiotherapy where parallel use of <lb/>osimertinib is not recommended due to the risk of toxicities. <lb/>However, it is still to be determined whether stand-alone local <lb/>consolidative therapy is sufficient and has curative potential in some <lb/>patient cases or whether it should always be followed with <lb/>osimertinib rechallenge to prevent potential distant metastasis. <lb/>In case of post-adjuvant osimertinib regimen recurrence scenarios <lb/>that are not amenable to local consolidative therapy, rechallenge with <lb/>osimertinib may be of high clinical value and should therefore be <lb/>considered either as osimertinib monotherapy or as a part of treatment <lb/>strategy involving other therapies (Table 3 -consensus statement 5). <lb/>4.2.3 Therapeutic value of osimertinib: ex-CNS or <lb/>CNS recurrences during the adjuvant-osimertinib <lb/>regimen that are not amenable to local <lb/>consolidative therapy <lb/>Our study found that ex-CNS recurrence in the first 6 months is an <lb/>indication of treatment failure of adjuvant-osimertinib, requiring <lb/>change of treatment to either chemotherapy, other targeted therapies, <lb/>or a combination of both. However, for later recurrences, continuation <lb/>of osimertinib as a part of a broad treatment strategy could be <lb/>potentially valuable (Table 3 -consensus statement 4) as it may <lb/>prevent brain metastases, especially in case of ex-CNS recurrence. <lb/>For CNS-only recurrences, the consensus is that continuation of <lb/>osimertinib as a part of a broad treatment strategy could be an effective <lb/>treatment option (Table 3 -consensus statement 3). For indolent CNS <lb/>recurrences, continuation of osimertinib monotherapy could also be a <lb/>valuable treatment option, given the CNS recurrence could stem from <lb/>underexposure to osimertinib. However, further evidence is needed on <lb/>the appropriate osimertinib dosing regimen and/or combination with <lb/>other therapies before these treatment approaches are considered outside <lb/>clinical trials. The use of osimertinib for both ex-CNS and CNS-only <lb/>recurrence was identified to be more suitable for patients with <lb/>asymptomatic progression which indicates that the tumor growth is <lb/>gradual and the risk of resistance to osimertinib is relatively lower than <lb/>within symptomatic progression (Table 3 -consensus statements 3 &amp; 4). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>07 <lb/></page>

			<body>4.2.4 Osimertinib treatment duration for all <lb/>indicated CNS and/or ex-CNS recurrences <lb/>In cases where osimertinib was considered as a treatment <lb/>option within the recurrence scenarios, the consensus was that <lb/>treatment would continue until disease progression or toxicities <lb/>were observed, or patient quality of life deteriorated. For a low <lb/>progression risk patient (e.g., indolent oligometastatic progression), <lb/>the duration of osimertinib treatment should be limited and a <lb/>decision to stop treatment should be taken after monitoring the <lb/>efficacy and patient&apos;s health profile and considering the safety and <lb/>tolerance profile of osimertinib and patient wishes (Table 3 -<lb/>consensus statement 6). For a high progression risk patient, the <lb/>treatment duration would be longer compared to a low progression <lb/>risk patient with an aim to avoid any residual disease flare after <lb/>osimertinib treatment cessation. <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>Outcomes from the phase 3 ADAURA trial show significant <lb/>improvements in DFS and OS for EGFR-mutated NSCLC patients <lb/>with stage IB to IIIA disease. Nonetheless, patterns of recurrence were <lb/>reported within the osimertinib group, although lower compared <lb/>with placebo (9, 10). In the absence of clinical guidance on how to <lb/>treat recurrences during or after the completion of the adjuvant-<lb/>osimertinib regimen, our consensus study offers a qualitative <lb/>framework for clinicians in such scenarios, drawing from <lb/>international expert consensus. While recognizing the importance <lb/>of additional clinical data from trials and real-world settings, the <lb/>study provides broader treatment considerations. It also considers <lb/>osimertinib&apos;s efficacy, as supported by FLAURA, AURA3, and <lb/>ADAURA trials (7, 9, 23), with panelists acknowledging its <lb/>potential benefits across various recurrence scenarios, including <lb/>oligometastatic CNS recurrences and CNS metastases. In addition, <lb/>panelists acknowledged the potential treatment value of combination <lb/>therapies using osimertinib with local consolidative therapy, <lb/>chemotherapy, and other systemic therapies; however, further <lb/>efficacy and safety data is needed. The suitability of each <lb/>combination approach under different recurrence scenarios was not <lb/>tested in this study indicating the need for more discussion on clinical <lb/>experience in the absence of concrete data. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included <lb/>in the article/Supplementary Material. Further inquiries can be <lb/>directed to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>MM: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Supervision, Writing -original draft, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. AS: Conceptualization, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. CM: Conceptualization, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. NL: Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. CN: Writing -review &amp; editing. DP: Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. SP: Writing -review &amp; editing. JR: Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>ES: Writing -review &amp; editing. RS: Writing -review &amp; editing. MT: <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. FY: Writing -review &amp; editing. BS: <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. CG: Supervision, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. Y-LW: Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This study <lb/>was supported by AstraZeneca, Cambridge, UK. An independent <lb/>third party, Charles River Associates (CRA), designed the <lb/>study, moderated the consensus meeting, and supported <lb/>manuscript development. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>All named authors meet the International Committee of <lb/>Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this <lb/>manuscript, take responsibility for the integrity of the work as a <lb/>whole, and have given final approval for the version to be published. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>NL reports research funding from Amgen, AstraZeneca <lb/>Canada, Bayer, EMD Serono, Guardant Health, Lilly, MSD, MSD <lb/>Oncology, Roche Canada, and Takeda; travel and accommodation <lb/>support from Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme. CN reports advisor to <lb/>Medtronic, Johnson &amp; Johnson; speaker fees from AstraZeneca, <lb/>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme, Roche, Medtronic, Johnson &amp; Johnson. DP <lb/>reports being an advisor to AstraZeneca, Bristol-Myers Squibb, <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim, Celgene, Daiichi Sankyo, Eli Lilly, Merck, <lb/>Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, Janssen, and Abbvie; honoraria from <lb/>AstraZeneca, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Celgene, Eli Lilly, Merck, <lb/>Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, Janssen, and Abbvie; travel and <lb/>accommodation grants from AstraZeneca, Roche, Novartis, and <lb/>Pfizer; and conducting clinical trials research as principal or co-<lb/>investigator institutional financial interests for AstraZeneca, <lb/>Bristol-Myers Squibb, Boehringer Ingelheim, Eli Lilly, Merck, <lb/>Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, Medimmun, Sanofi-Aventis, Taiho <lb/>Pharma, Novocure, Daiichi Sankyo, Abbvie, and Janssen. SP <lb/>reports consultancy to Amgen, AstraZeneca, Bayer, BeiGene, <lb/>Blueprint, BMS, Boehringer Ingelheim, Daiichi Sankyo, EQRx, <lb/>GlaxoSmithKline, Guardant Health, Janssen, Lilly, Merck KGaA, <lb/>MSD, Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, Sanofi, Seattle Genetics, Takeda, <lb/>and Turning Point Therapeutics. JR reports being an advisor to <lb/>AbbVie, Amgen, AstraZeneca, BioAtla, BMS, Daichi-Sankyo, G1 <lb/>Therapeutics, Genentech, Gritstone Bio, Guardant, Janssen, Lilly, <lb/>Jazz, Summit Therapeutics Takeda; speaker fees from AstraZeneca; <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>08 <lb/></page>

			<div type="conflict">institutional research funding from BioAtla, AbbVie, AstraZeneca, <lb/>Blueprint, RedCloud, Loxo Oncology, Daiichi Sankyo, Enliven, <lb/>ORIC, and Summit. ES reports being an advisor to AstraZeneca, <lb/>Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Daiichi <lb/>Sankyo, Lilly, Merck KGaA, MSD Oncology, Novartis, Roche/ <lb/>Genentech, Seagen, and Takeda; honoraria from AstraZeneca, <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim, Daiichi Sankyo/Astra Zeneca, and Merck <lb/>KGaA; research funding from AstraZeneca, Bayer, Boehringer <lb/>Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Roche/Genentech. RS <lb/>reports being an advisor to Amgen, AstraZeneca, Bayer, BMS, <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim, Janssen, Lily, Merck, Merck Serono, <lb/>Novartis, Pfizer, Puma, Roche, Taiho, Takeda, Thermo Fisher, <lb/>Yuhan and has received research grants from AstraZeneca and <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim. MT reports being an advisor to AstraZeneca <lb/>Japan, Chugai Pharma, Lilly Japan, MSD, Novartis and MiREXS; <lb/>honoraria from AstraZeneca Japan, Bristol-Myers Squibb Japan, <lb/>Chugai Pharma, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Lilly Japan, Medtronic, MSD <lb/>K.K, Novartis, Ono Pharmaceutical, Taiho Pharmaceutical, and <lb/>Teijin Pharma; research funding from AstraZeneca Japan, <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim KK, Bristol-Myers Squibb KK, Merck, Ono <lb/>Pharmaceutical, BMG Incorporated, and MiREXS. FY reports <lb/>speaker fees from MSD, Pfizer, Roche, AstraZeneca, and Bristol-<lb/>Myers Squibb. BS reports wife&apos;s employment with PPD and Xalud <lb/>Therapeutics; leadership at Verrica Pharmaceuticals; stock and <lb/>other ownership interests in Pfizer, PPD, and Xalud Therapeutics; <lb/>personal honoraria from AstraZeneca, Bristol Myers Squibb, <lb/>Genentech, and Pfizer; consulting or advisor role at AstraZeneca, <lb/>Gala Therapeutics, Medtronic, Arcus Biosciences, and Pfizer; <lb/>research funding from Bristol Myers Squibb Foundation; <lb/>patents, royalties, and other intellectual property related with a <lb/>therapeutic antibody targeting ART1, an extracellular mono-ADP <lb/>ribosyltransferase, for the treatment of cancer patent application <lb/>filed; other relationship with Lung Cancer Research Foundation <lb/>and Lungevity. CG reports being an advisor to AstraZeneca, <lb/>Boehringer Ingelheim, and MSD Oncology; honoraria from <lb/>AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Lilly, MSD Oncology, <lb/>Novartis, Roche, and Takeda; research funding from AstraZeneca; <lb/>travel and accommodation support from Boehringer Ingelheim, <lb/>Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Roche. Y-LW reports being an advisor to <lb/>AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Roche, and Takeda; honoraria <lb/>from AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb/ <lb/>China, Hengrui Pharmaceutical, Lilly, MSD Oncology, Pfizer, and <lb/>Roche; research funding from Boehringer Ingelheim, Pfizer, <lb/>and Roche. <lb/>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted <lb/>in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that <lb/>could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. American Lung Association. EGFR and lung Cancer (2022). Available at: https:// <lb/>www.lung.org/lung-health-diseases/lung-disease-lookup/lung-cancer/symptoms-<lb/>diagnosis/biomarker-testing/egfr (Accessed 13 February 2023). <lb/>2. O&apos;Leary C, Gasper H, Sahin KB, Tang M, Kulasinghe A, Adams MN, et al. <lb/>Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)-mutated non-small-cell lung cancer <lb/>(NSCLC). Pharmaceuticals (2020) 13(10):273. doi: 10.3390/ph13100273 <lb/>3. Ellison G, Zhu G, Moulis A, Dearden S, Speake G, McCormack R. EGFR mutation <lb/>testing in lung cancer: a review of available methods and their use for analysis of tumor <lb/>tissue and cytology samples. J Clin pathol (2013) 66(2):79-89. doi: 10.1136/jclinpath-<lb/>2012-201194 <lb/>4. Melosky B, Kambartel K, Häntschel M, Bennetts M, Nickens DJ, Brinkmann J, <lb/>et al. Worldwide prevalence of epidermal growth factor receptor mutations in non-<lb/>small cell lung cancer: a meta-analysis. Mol Diagn Ther (2022) 26(1):7-18. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s40291-021-00563-1 <lb/>5. Roviello G, Imperatori M, Aieta M, Sollitto F, Landriscina M. Adjuvant treatment <lb/>for EGFR-mutated non-small cell lung cancer: do we have a major breakthrough? J <lb/>Thorac Disease (2018) 10(Suppl 18):S2114. doi: 10.21037/jtd.2018.06.114 <lb/>6. Zhao P, Zhen H, Zhao H, Zhao L, Cao B. Efficacy and safety of adjuvant EGFR-<lb/>TKIs for resected non-small cell lung cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis <lb/>based on randomized control trials. BMC cancer (2022) 22(1):1-5. doi: 10.1186/s12885-<lb/>022-09444-0 <lb/>7. Mok TS, Wu YL, Ahn MJ, Garassino MC, Kim HR, Ramalingam SS, et al. <lb/>Osimertinib or platinum-pemetrexed in EGFR T790M-positive lung cancer. New Engl <lb/>J Med (2017) 376(7):629-40. doi: 10.1056/nejmoa1612674 <lb/>8. Wu YL, Tsuboi M, He J, John T, Grohe C, Majem M, et al. Osimertinib in resected <lb/>EGFR-mutated non-small-cell lung cancer. New Engl J Med (2020) 383(18):1711-23. <lb/>doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2027071 <lb/>9. Herbst RS, Wu YL, John T, Grohe C, Majem M, Wang J, et al. Adjuvant <lb/>osimertinib for resected EGFR-mutated stage IB-IIIA non-small-cell lung cancer: <lb/>updated results from the phase III randomized adaura trial. J Clin Oncol (2023) 41 <lb/>(10):1830. doi: 10.1200/jco.22.02186 <lb/>10. Tsuboi M, Herbst RS, John T, Kato T, Majem M, GrohéC, et al. Overall survival <lb/>with osimertinib in resected EGFR-mutated NSCLC. New Engl J Med (2023) 389:137-<lb/>47. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2304594 <lb/>11. Isla D, Felip E, Garrido P, Insa A, Majem M, Remon J, et al. A Delphi consensus <lb/>panel about clinical management of early-stage EGFR-mutated non-small cell lung <lb/>cancer (NSCLC) in Spain: A Delphi consensus panel study. Clin Trans Oncol (2023) 25 <lb/>(1):283-91. doi: 10.1007/s12094-022-02941-5 <lb/>12. Passaro A, Leighl N, Blackhall F, Popat S, Kerr K, Ahn MJ, et al. ESMO expert <lb/>consensus statements on the management of EGFR mutant non-small-cell lung cancer. <lb/>Ann Oncol (2022) 33(5):466-87. doi: 10.1016/j.annonc.2022.02.003 <lb/>13. College of American Pathologists. The Liquid Biopsy . Available at: https://www. <lb/>cap.org/member-resources/articles/the-liquid-biopsy (Accessed 03 August 2023). <lb/>14. Kunimasa K, Mimura C, Kotani Y. Erlotinib is effective for leptomeningeal <lb/>carcinomatosis due to disease flare after osimertinib treatment failure. J Thorac Oncol <lb/>(2017) 12(7):e93-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jtho.2017.02.025 <lb/>15. Takahashi T, Umeguchi H, Tateishi A, Yoshida T, Motoi N, Ohe Y. Disease flare <lb/>of leptomeningeal metastases without radiological and cytological findings after the <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>09 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>discontinuation of osimertinib. Lung Cancer (2021) 151:1-4. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.lungcan.2020.11.010 <lb/>16. Popat S, Navani N, Kerr KM, Smit EF, Batchelor TJ, Van Schil P, et al. <lb/>Navigating diagnostic and treatment decisions in non-small cell lung cancer: expert <lb/>commentary on the multidisciplinary team approach. Oncol (2021) 26(2):e306-15. <lb/>doi: 10.1002/onco.13586 <lb/>17. NCCN. Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Version 4.2019, NCCN Guidelines (2019). <lb/>Available at: https://www.nccn.org/guidelines/guidelines-process/transparency-<lb/>process-and-recommendations/GetFileFromFileManagerGuid?FileManagerGuidId= <lb/>8fc17b3b-ec6c-4758-b0c7-15c51649fc64. <lb/>18. Planchard D, Popat ST, Kerr K, Novello S, Smit EF, Faivre-Finn C, et al. <lb/>Metastatic non-small cell lung cancer: ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, <lb/>treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol (2018) 29:iv192-237. doi: 10.1093/annonc/ <lb/>mdy275 <lb/>19. Park K, Vansteenkiste J, Lee KH, Pentheroudakis G, Zhou C, Prabhash K, et al. <lb/>Pan-Asian adapted ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for the management of patients <lb/>with locally-advanced unresectable non-small-cell lung cancer: a KSMO-ESMO <lb/>initiative endorsed by CSCO, ISMPO, JSMO, MOS, SSO and TOS. Ann Oncol <lb/>(2020) 31(2):191-201. doi: 10.1016/j.annonc.2019.10.026 <lb/>20. Wu YL, Planchard D, Lu S, Sun H, Yamamoto N, Kim DW, et al. Pan-Asian <lb/>adapted Clinical Practice Guidelines for the management of patients with metastatic <lb/>non-small-cell lung cancer: a CSCO-ESMO initiative endorsed by JSMO, KSMO, <lb/>MOS, SSO and TOS. Ann Oncol (2019) 30(2):171-210. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdy554 <lb/>21. Postmus PE, Kerr KM, Oudkerk M, Senan S, Waller DA, Vansteenkiste J, et al. <lb/>Early and locally advanced non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC): ESMO Clinical <lb/>Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol (2017) 28: <lb/>iv1-21. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdx222 <lb/>22. Kroeze SG, Pavic M, Stellamans K, Lievens Y, Becherini C, Scorsetti M, et al. <lb/>Metastases-directed stereotactic body radiotherapy in combination with targeted <lb/>therapy or immunotherapy: systematic review and consensus recommendations by <lb/>the EORTC-ESTRO OligoCare consortium. Lancet Oncol (2023) 24(3):e121-32. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00752-5 <lb/>23. Ramalingam SS, Vansteenkiste J, Planchard D, Cho BC, Gray JE, Ohe Y, et al. <lb/>Overall survival with osimertinib in untreated, EGFR-mutated advanced NSCLC. New <lb/>Engl J Med (2020) 382(1):41-50. doi: 10.1056/nejmoa1913662 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Mirza et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2023.1330468 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>