<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T13:37:32.445Z">11/21/2025 1:37:32 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T13:37:21.098696Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T13:37:21.098696Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>Pseudomonas aeruginosa gene <lb/>PA4880 encodes a Dps-like <lb/>protein with a Dps fold, <lb/>bacterioferritin-type ferroxidase <lb/>centers, and <lb/>endonuclease activity <lb/>Nimesha Rajapaksha 1 , Huili Yao 1 , Aisha Cook 1 , Steve Seibold 2 , <lb/>Lijun Liu 2 , Kevin P. Battaile 3 , Leo Fontenot 1 , <lb/>Fabrizio Donnarumma 1 , Scott Lovell 2 * and Mario Rivera 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Chemistry, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA, United States, 2 Protein Structure <lb/>&amp; X-ray Crystallography Laboratory, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS, United States, 3 NYX, New York <lb/>Structural Biology Center, Upton, NY, United States <lb/>We report the biochemical, structural, and functional characterization of the <lb/>protein coded by gene PA4880 in the P. aeruginosa PAO1 genome. The <lb/>PA4880 gene had been annotated as coding a probable bacterioferritin. Our <lb/>structural work shows that the product of gene PA4880 is a protein that adopts <lb/>the Dps subunit fold, which oligomerizes into a 12-mer quaternary structure. <lb/>Unlike Dps, however, the ferroxidase di-iron centers and iron coordinating <lb/>ligands are buried within each subunit, in a manner identical to that observed <lb/>in the ferroxidase center of P. aeruginosa bacterioferritin. Since these structural <lb/>characteristics correspond to Dps-like proteins, we term the protein as P. <lb/>aeruginosa Dps-like, or Pa DpsL. The ferroxidase centers in Pa DpsL catalyze <lb/>the oxidation of Fe 2+ utilizing O 2 or H 2 O 2 as oxidant, and the resultant Fe 3+ is <lb/>compartmentalized in the interior cavity. Interestingly, incubating Pa DpsL with <lb/>plasmid DNA results in efficient nicking of the DNA and at higher concentrations <lb/>of Pa DpsL the DNA is linearized and eventually degraded. The nickase and <lb/>endonuclease activities suggest that Pa DpsL, in addition to participating in the <lb/>defense of P. aeruginosa cells against iron-induced toxicity, may also participate <lb/>in the innate immune mechanisms consisting of restriction endonucleases and <lb/>cognate methyl transferases. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Dps, mini ferritin, iron homeostasis, iron metabolism, bacterioferritin, endonuclease, <lb/>oxidative stress <lb/></front>

		<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa is a Gram-negative highly adaptable opportunistic pathogen, <lb/>which is often present in environments influenced by human activity (Crone et al., 2020). P. <lb/>aeruginosa can cause acute and chronic infections in surgical incisions, and in patients with <lb/>burn wounds, catheters, and diabetic foot ulcers (Burrows, 2018; Horcajada et al., 2019). <lb/>Our laboratories have been studying the structure and function of iron storage proteins in P. <lb/></body>

		<front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Gloria C. Ferreira, <lb/>University of South Florida, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Ricardo O. Louro, <lb/>Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Portugal <lb/>Daniel Deredge, <lb/>University of Maryland, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Mario Rivera, <lb/>mrivera@lsu.edu <lb/>Scott Lovell, <lb/>slovell@ku.edu <lb/>RECEIVED 23 February 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 22 April 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 22 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Rajapaksha N, Yao H, Cook A, Seibold S, Liu L, <lb/>Battaile KP, Fontenot L, Donnarumma F, Lovell S <lb/>and Rivera M (2024), Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>gene PA4880 encodes a Dps-like protein with a <lb/>Dps fold, bacterioferritin-type ferroxidase <lb/>centers, and endonuclease activity. <lb/>Front. Mol. Biosci. 11:1390745. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Rajapaksha, Yao, Cook, Seibold, Liu, <lb/>Battaile, Fontenot, Donnarumma, Lovell and <lb/>Rivera. This is an open-access article distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (CC BY). The use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction in other forums is <lb/>permitted, provided the original author(s) and <lb/>the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic practice. <lb/>No use, distribution or reproduction is <lb/>permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/>Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 22 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></front>

		<body>aeruginosa. Ferritin and ferritin-like molecules are particular to iron <lb/>storage because these molecules catalyze the oxidation of Fe 2+ and <lb/>compartmentalize the resultant Fe 3+ in their interior cavity. <lb/>Consequently, in addition to accumulating iron at concentrations <lb/>much higher than those enabled by the poor solubility of Fe 3+ near <lb/>neutral pH, ferritin and ferritin-like molecules minimize the toxic <lb/>effects expected from unregulated Fe 2+ /Fe 3+ redox cycling (Bradley <lb/>et al., 2016; Rivera, 2017; Rivera, 2023). The P. aeruginosa <lb/>PAO1 genome contains four genes encoding iron storage <lb/>proteins: ftnA (PA4235) encodes a bacterial ferritin (FtnA) (Yao <lb/>et al., 2011), bfrB (PA3531) codes for a bacterioferritin (BfrB) <lb/>(Weeratunga et al., 2009; Weeratunga et al., 2010), gene <lb/>PA0962 codes a Dps (Rajapaksha et al., 2023), and gene PA4880, <lb/>the subject of this report, is annotated to encode a probable <lb/>bacterioferritin. Understanding the function of all these proteins <lb/>is an important step toward gaining a more comprehensive <lb/>understanding of the fate of iron in bacterial cells, and how <lb/>storage molecules contribute to managing the benefits and risks <lb/>associated with the chemistry of essential iron. <lb/>Our investigations have recently demonstrated that P. <lb/>aeruginosa stores iron in a heteropolymeric bacterioferritin (Bfr) <lb/>composed from two distinct types of subunits, a bacterial ferritin, <lb/>FtnA coded by gene PA4235, and a bacterioferritin, BfrB, coded by <lb/>PA3531 (Yao et al., 2022). The relative proportion of FtnA and BfrB <lb/>subunits in Bfr is variable and depends on the availability of <lb/>environmental O 2 . The ftnA and bfrB genes are scattered in the <lb/>P. aeruginosa genome and are regulated differently: bfrB <lb/>transcription is stimulated by iron (Palma et al., 2003), whereas <lb/>the ftnA gene is under control of the Anr transcription regulator, <lb/>which functions to enable the adaptation of P. aeruginosa cells to <lb/>microoxic and anoxic growth (Hammond et al., 2015). Mobilization <lb/>of Fe 3+ stored in Bfr, which is required for metabolic homeostasis in <lb/>P. aeruginosa (Punchi Hewage et al., 2020), requires binding of a <lb/>ferredoxin (Bfd), which transfers electrons to the Fe 3+ mineral in the <lb/>Bfr interior cavity for subsequent mobilization of Fe 2+ to the cytosol <lb/>(Weeratunga et al., 2009; Yao et al., 2012). Blocking the Bfr-Bfd <lb/>complex in a P. aeruginosa Δbfd mutant leads to an irreversible <lb/>accumulation of iron in Bfr (Eshelman et al., 2017), and concomitant <lb/>intracellular iron limitation, dysregulated carbon and sulfur <lb/>metabolism, depleted amino acid biosynthesis (Punchi Hewage <lb/>et al., 2020), and inability to mature and maintain biofilms <lb/>(Soldano et al., 2020). The significant consequences of blocking <lb/>the Bfr-Bfd complex on P. aeruginosa fitness motivated the <lb/>discovery of small molecule inhibitors of the BfrB-Bfd complex <lb/>(Punchi Hewage et al., 2019). These inhibitors have been shown to <lb/>kill biofilm-embedded P. aeruginosa (Soldano et al., 2021), therefore <lb/>suggesting the mobilization of iron stored in Bfr as a viable new <lb/>target for antibiotic discovery (Rivera, 2023). <lb/>Much less is known about the function of the other two proteins <lb/>thought to participate in iron storage, the products of genes PA0962, <lb/>and PA4880. A recent investigation has demonstrated that the <lb/>product of gene PA0962 is a Dps (DNA binding protein under <lb/>starvation) (Rajapaksha et al., 2023), but nothing is known about the <lb/>product of gene PA4880, which is annotated as a putative <lb/>bacterioferritin. Hence, the objective of this investigation was to <lb/>characterize biochemically and structurally the product of gene <lb/>PA4880. We found that gene PA4880 does not encode <lb/>bacterioferritin; rather, the product of gene PA4880 is a protein <lb/>exhibiting hybrid structural characteristics that are typical of Dps <lb/>and bacterioferritin. Proteins with these structural characteristics <lb/>have been termed Dps-like, so the product of gene PA4880 in P. <lb/>aeruginosa PAO1 is a Dps-like protein, abbreviated here as Pa DpsL. <lb/>DNA binding proteins from starved cells (Dps) are thought to be <lb/>expressed in response to different stressors, including nutrient <lb/>starvation, osmosis, acidic and basic environments, thermal <lb/>shock, iron-induced toxicity, UV-and gamma radiation, and <lb/>oxidative stress (Nair and Finkel, 2004; Calhoun and Kwon, <lb/>2011; Guerra et al., 2021). Dps are thought to protect DNA by <lb/>binding and shielding, and by preventing oxidative stress caused by <lb/>H 2 O 2 in the presence of iron. Dps are 12-mer assemblies of identical <lb/>subunits with a nearly spherical shell-like structure (~9 nm <lb/>diameter) containing a hollow cavity with (~5 nm diameter) <lb/>(Guerra et al., 2021; Rivera, 2023). The smaller dimensions <lb/>relative to the 24-mer ferritin and bacterioferritin molecules is <lb/>the reason Dps are also known as mini ferritins. The Dps <lb/>subunit fold consists of a four helix bundle similar to the subunit <lb/>fold of ferritin and bacterioferritin but with some unique <lb/>characteristics (Rivera, 2023): (i) The subunits of Dps have an N-<lb/>or C-terminal tail not present in ferritin or bacterioferritin, (ii) the <lb/>long loop connecting helices B and C in the Dps four helix bundle <lb/>contains a short α-helix, which is absent in ferritin and <lb/>bacterioferritin, and (iii) Dps harbor two di-iron ferroxidase <lb/>centers at the interface of each subunit dimer, where the <lb/>ferroxidase center ligands are contributed by residues from both <lb/>subunits. These ferroxidase centers are distinct from the ferroxidase <lb/>centers in ferritin and bacterioferritin, which are buried in the <lb/>middle of each subunit. <lb/>A possible different subgroup, or even possibly an outgroup of <lb/>the ferritin group is the so-called Dps-like (DpsL) proteins (Lundin <lb/>et al., 2012), initially characterized from the hyper thermophilic <lb/>acidophile Sulfolobus solfataricus (Wiedenheft et al., 2005; Gauss <lb/>et al., 2006) and then from the anaerobe Bacteroides fragilis (Gauss <lb/>et al., 2012). Crystallographic studies of DpsL showed a quaternary <lb/>structure (12-mer) characteristic of Dps. However, unlike Dps, <lb/>where the ferroxidase centers are located at the interface of <lb/>subunit dimers, the ferroxidase centers of DpsL are buried within <lb/>the four-helix bundle of each subunit, akin to the ferroxidase centers <lb/>in ferritin or bacterioferritin. We have cloned the PA4880 gene, <lb/>overexpressed the coded protein in E. coli host cells and <lb/>characterized the recombinant protein in solution, and by X-ray <lb/>crystallography. Our findings reveal a protein with a quaternary <lb/>dodecameric assembly where each subunit exhibits a four-helix <lb/>bundle fold characteristic of Dps. Unlike Dps, however, the <lb/>ferroxidase centers are buried within each subunit, in a manner <lb/>reminiscent of bacterioferritin. Consequently, gene PA4880 encodes <lb/>a DpsL protein. <lb/>2 Results and discussion <lb/>2.1 Purification and the oligomerization state <lb/>of Pa DpsL in solution <lb/>In the initial purification experiments, the host E. coli cells were <lb/>lysed in 50 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0), and the <lb/>clarified lysate solution was separated on a HiTrap ™ Q FF anion <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>02 <lb/></page>

		<front>Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></front>

		<body>exchange column using the same buffer and a NaCl gradient. <lb/>Fractions containing Pa DpsL were then chromatographed on a <lb/>Superdex ™ 200 Increase 10/300 GL size exclusion column <lb/>equilibrated and eluted with 50 mM potassium phosphate <lb/>(pH 6.2). Although these conditions allowed isolation of pure <lb/>protein, the yield was low, and the protein was isolated as a <lb/>mixture of 12-mer (small minority) and several other lower <lb/>oligomerization states. Moreover, analysis of the fractions with <lb/>the aid of SDS PAGE showed that the protein eluting as lower <lb/>oligomerization states appeared to be cleaved. As will be discussed in <lb/>Section 2.2, the fractions containing 12-mer were used in initial <lb/>crystallization conditions that led to the structure of a dimer. <lb/>Subsequent screening for conditions to enable purification of the <lb/>protein as a 12-mer in high yield led us to observe that the presence <lb/>of ≥1 mM MgSO 4 in the buffer is required to stabilize the 12-mer <lb/>assembly and to prevent cleavage of the subunits. Consequently, in <lb/>subsequent work the buffers used for cell lysis, chromatography and <lb/>protein storage were supplemented with at least 1 mM MgSO 4 . <lb/>Dodecameric Pa DpsL was purified at pH 7.5 in three <lb/>chromatographic steps, initiated by the fractionation of cell lysate <lb/>on a HiTrap ™ QFF anion exchange column, followed by the <lb/>separation of fractions containing Pa DpsL on a second anion <lb/>exchange column (Source ™ 15Q) and then through a calibrated <lb/>Superdex ™ 200 Increase 10/300 GL size exclusion column. <lb/>Fractions containing pure Pa Dps (assessed by SDS PAGE) <lb/>exhibit an elution volume (Ve) corresponding to dodecameric Pa <lb/>DpsL (Figure 1A, black trace). <lb/>The effect of MgSO 4 on the dodecameric assembly of Pa DpsL was <lb/>investigated by exchanging the protein into 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5), <lb/>followed by sieving the resultant solution through a calibrated <lb/>Superdex TM 200 column. The resulting chromatogram (Figure 1A, <lb/>blue trace) shows that in the absence of MgSO 4 the 12-mer PaDpsL <lb/>disassembles into lower oligomeric states. To determine whether the <lb/>assembly/disassembly process is reversible, the fractions containing <lb/>disassembled Pa DpsL were pooled, reconstituted with 1 mM <lb/>MgSO 4 , equilibrated, and chromatographed through the same <lb/>Superdex size exclusion column equilibrated with 50 mM Tris <lb/>(pH 7.5) containing 1 mM MgSO 4 . The chromatogram (Figure 1A, <lb/>red trace) shows only partial reassembly of the 12-mer. This observation <lb/>is different from that made with 12-mer Pa Dps, which disassembles in <lb/>the absence of MgSO 4 , but can be fully reassembled into 12-mer when <lb/>MgSO 4 is added (Rajapaksha et al., 2023). To investigate the nature of <lb/>the irreversible disassembly of Pa DpsL we resorted to SDS PAGE and <lb/>mass spectrometry. To this end, solutions of Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris <lb/>pH 7.5 in the presence and in the absence of 1 mM MgSO 4 were <lb/>incubated at room temperature for different times prior to freezing and <lb/>subsequent analysis by SDS PAGE. The results (Figure 1B) show that in <lb/>the absence of MgSO 4 the Pa DpsL subunits undergo proteolysis, so it is <lb/>highly probable that disassembly of the 12-mer quaternary structure is <lb/>related to subunit proteolytic cleavage. In contrast, when MgSO 4 is <lb/>present, proteolytic cleavage of the subunits is largely eliminated. Hence, <lb/>the stability imparted by MgSO 4 on the integrity and fold of the <lb/>subunits is probably the reason the 12-mer quaternary structure is <lb/>retained when MgSO 4 is present. <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Biochemical characterization of Pa DpsL in solution. (A) The oligomeric state of Pa DpsL was assessed with the aid of a calibrated size exclusion <lb/>column. Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris pH 7.5 and 1 mM MgSO 4 elutes as a 12-mer (black trace). Removal of the MgSO 4 from the buffer in the sample and from <lb/>the chromatography buffer causes the disassembly of the 12-mer (blue trace). Addition of 1 mM MgSO 4 to the protein eluting in the blue trace <lb/>chromatogram and to the chromatography buffer does not enable the full reassembly of 12-mer (red trace). (B) SDS PAGE shows that incubating Pa <lb/>DpsL in the presence of MgSO 4 stabilizes Pa DpsL; in the absence of MgSO 4 the protein is proteolytically cleaved and degraded. (C) In gel digestion and <lb/>LC-MS/MS analysis of Pa DpsL. SDS PAGE lane (A) 15 μM Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) + 1 mM MgSO 4 . Lane (B) 15 μM Pa DpsL incubated for 6 h in <lb/>50 mM Tris (pH 7.5). Lane M: molecular weight marker. Bands 1, 2 and 3 were excised, the protein digested with trypsin, and the peptides analyzed by LC-<lb/>MS/MS. All the expected peptides were detected in bands 1 and 2, indicating that the protein is intact, whereas the residues shown in blue were not <lb/>detected in band 3, indicating that proteolytic cleavage starts at the amino terminus. (D) Incubating Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris with MgSO 4 , MgCl 2 , or Na 2 SO 4 <lb/>for 6 h prior to SDS PAGE shows that both Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-are required to prevent proteolytic cleavage. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>03 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>Having established that MgSO 4 is required to prevent proteolysis of <lb/>the subunits, we set out to investigate the site of proteolytic cleavage. For <lb/>these experiments we excised each of the bands labeled 1-3 from the <lb/>SDS PAGE gel in Figure 1C, which corresponds to a 6 h incubation <lb/>time, in the presence (lane A) and in the absence (lane B) of MgSO 4 . <lb/>The samples were subjected to in-gel digestion with trypsin, and the <lb/>resultant peptides analyzed by LC-MS/MS. Results from these <lb/>experiments carried out with band 1 (lane A) showed that all the <lb/>peptides expected from trypsin digestion are detected, therefore <lb/>corroborating that the Pa DpsL subunits remain intact when MgSO 4 <lb/>is present in the buffer. A similar observation was made with the protein <lb/>in band 2 (lane B), which corresponds to the relatively small portion of <lb/>DpsL that has not been cleaved after 6 h of incubation. In contrast, <lb/>analysis of the peptides in band 3 (lane B) highlights the absence of the <lb/>N-terminal peptide (blue in Figure 1C), indicating proteolytic cleavage <lb/>at the N-terminal domain. It was still unclear if Mg 2+ , SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>, or both ions <lb/>are required to prevent proteolytic cleavage and stabilize the 12-mer <lb/>quaternary structure. This issue was explored by supplementing the <lb/>50 mM Tris buffer with 1 mM MgCl 2 or 1 mM Na 2 SO 4 and assessing <lb/>the integrity of the subunits with the aid of SDS PAGE after 6 hours of <lb/>incubation. The results (Figure 1D) revealed that both Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>are required for preventing cleavage of the DpsL subunit. It is also <lb/>interesting to note that proteolytic degradation appears to be faster in <lb/>the presence of only SO 4 <lb/>2-than in the presence of only Mg 2+ . The <lb/>possible roles played by Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-ions in stabilizing the integrity <lb/>of the Pa DpsL subunits and the quaternary structure will be discussed <lb/>in Section 2.2, where the crystal structure of Pa PpsL is presented. <lb/>2.2 Crystal structure of a Pa DpsL subunit (Pa <lb/>DpsL dimer) <lb/>As indicated above, the initial protein purification strategy, which <lb/>was carried out in the absence of MgSO 4 , resulted in a very low protein <lb/>yield containing only a small proportion of dodecamer Pa DpsL. <lb/>Fractions containing 12-mer were concentrated in 50 mM phosphate <lb/>buffer pH 6.2 for crystallization screens. Prismatic crystals were <lb/>obtained from the Proplex screen condition D5 (8% (w/v) PEG <lb/>6,000, 100 mM MES pH 6.0, 100 mM MgCl 2 ). Structure solution <lb/>and refinement (Supplementary Table S1) produced a DpsL model <lb/>(1.3 Å resolution) containing one molecule in the asymmetric unit, <lb/>with electron density defining residues Ala31 to Ala171. The <lb/>N-terminal residues Met1 to Ser30 could not be modeled due to <lb/>conformational disorder. The Pa DpsL structure adopts a 4-helix <lb/>bundle (Figure 2A) comprised of α1 (R33-G63), α2 (S67-Q93), α4 <lb/>(L119-L144), and α5 (R152-L176), and the short helix α3 (L105-R108) <lb/>in the middle of the long loop connecting α2 and α4. These structural <lb/>characteristics are typical of the Dps fold. The anomalous scattering <lb/>difference map revealed the presence of two large electron density <lb/>peaks (36.7 σ and 34.6 σ), which were assigned as Fe ions based on the <lb/>electron density maps and coordination distances. Moreover, <lb/>refinement with Zn instead of Fe in the model produced negative <lb/>electron density peaks at these sites. The Fe ions form a dinuclear <lb/>center buried in the middle of the 4-helix bundle, where they are <lb/>coordinated by the side chains of residues E47, E80, H83, E130, E162, <lb/>H165, and two water molecules (Figures 2B,C). The structure of the <lb/>dinuclear center, which is contained within the four-helix bundle, is <lb/>different from the typical architecture of dinuclear iron centers in Dps, <lb/>but nearly identical to the ferroxidase center of P. aeruginosa <lb/>bacterioferritin (BfrB) (Weeratunga et al., 2010). Taken together, <lb/>the structural features of Pa DpsL, which revealed a classic Dps <lb/>fold harboring a bacterioferritin-type ferroxidase center, indicate <lb/>that the product of gene PA4880 is a Dps-like protein (Pa DpsL). <lb/>In agreement, superposition of the Pa DpsL structure dimer generated <lb/>by the crystallographic symmetry operation-x+2, y, -z, as determined <lb/>using PISA (Ciccone et al., 2015) with a dimer from the dodecameric <lb/>DpsL from B. fragilis (PDB 2VZB) results in RMSD = 1.41 Å between <lb/>C α atoms (284 residues). <lb/>2.3 Crystal structure of a Pa DpsL <lb/>dodecamer (Pa DpsL-dd and Pa DpsL-<lb/>dd-Mg) <lb/>As indicated above, protein purification in the presence of <lb/>MgSO 4 enabled isolation of dodecameric DpsL in high yield. The <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Structure of a Pa DpsL subunit (Pa DpsL-dimer). (A) Ribbons rendering of the model illustrating the secondary structure elements along with water <lb/>molecules (red spheres), iron ions in the ferroxidase center (orange spheres), and iron-coordinating residues (green cylinders). (B) 2Fo-Fc electron density <lb/>map (blue mesh) contoured at 1σ showing the ferroxidase center ligands and phased anomalous difference map (purple mesh) contoured at 3σ for the Fe <lb/>ions (orange spheres). (C) Coordination of the Fe ions in the ferroxidase center. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>04 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>protein was used to screen crystallization conditions leading to the <lb/>formation of prismatic crystals from the Salt Rx HT screen condition <lb/>F9 (800 mM lithium sulfate, 100 mM Tris pH 8.5). X-ray diffraction <lb/>from these crystals, followed by structure solution and refinement <lb/>produced the model termed Pa DpsL-dd (2.9 Å resolution), which <lb/>contains 12 molecules (a dodecamer) in the asymmetric unit, <lb/>33 sulfate ions and 24 Fe ions (Figure 3A). The sulfate ions are <lb/>in the 3-fold pores and near sites containing R13, R33, and R103. <lb/>Each of the subunits exhibit a Dps fold identical to that depicted in <lb/>Figure 2A, except that the position of N-terminal residues D8-S30 is <lb/>made evident in the 12-mer structure by well-defined electron <lb/>density (Figure 3B). This reveals that the N-terminal tails are <lb/>directed toward the surface of the 12-mer where they interact <lb/>with an adjacent subunit (Figure 3C). Each of the subunits <lb/>harbors a di-Fe center structurally identical to the ferroxidase <lb/>center of P. aeruginosa bacterioferritin, where the iron ions are <lb/>coordinated as illustrated in Figure 2C. Consequently, the structure <lb/>of the dodecamer corroborated that each of the subunits in Pa DpsL <lb/>exhibit a characteristic Dps fold that harbors a ferroxidase center <lb/>typical of bacterioferritin. <lb/>Prismatic crystals were also obtained from the Salt RxHT <lb/>screen condition G2 (1 M MgSO 4 , 100 mM Bis-Tris pH 7.0). <lb/>Structure solution and refinement produced the model termed <lb/>Pa DpsL-dd-Mg (3.0 Å resolution), which contains 44 sulfate <lb/>ions, 24 Fe ions, and 37 Mg ions. The locations of the Mg 2+ ions <lb/>were identified by analyzing the Fo-Fc difference electron <lb/>density following refinement and by computing a Fo-Fo <lb/>(Agirre et al., 2023) electron density difference map to <lb/>compare the differences between the DpsL-dd-Mg and DpsL-<lb/>dd data sets. Except for the presence of Mg 2+ , the structural <lb/>features observed in the Pa DpsL-dd-Mg are nearly identical to <lb/>those observed in the Pa DpsL-dd structure. The sites where <lb/>Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-ions bind on these structures, as well as the <lb/>possible significance of these bound ions to the stability of Pa <lb/>DpsL is presented in section 2.4. <lb/>2.4 Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-in the quaternary <lb/>structure of Pa DpsL <lb/>As indicated above, a network of Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-ions are observed <lb/>in the structures of 12-mer Pa DpsL (Pa DpsL-dd and Pa DpsL-dd-Mg). <lb/>These ions probably exert a stabilizing role of the secondary, tertiary, <lb/>and quaternary structures of the protein. Four distinct SO 4 <lb/>2-and three <lb/>unique Mg 2+ binding sites have been observed. Both types of ions can be <lb/>visualized in the Pa DpsL-dd-Mg structure (Figure 4A) The SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>binding sites can be observed in sites 1-4. Sulfate site 1 is located <lb/>next to each N-terminal extension, where the electrostatic interactions <lb/>between SO 4 <lb/>2-and the side chains of Arg13 and Arg17 stabilize the two-<lb/>turn helix observed in the N-terminal extension (Figure 4B). Sulfate site <lb/>2 is at the interface of two subunits where the SO 4 <lb/>2-ion is located <lb/>between the two one-turn helices (α3) present in the long loop <lb/>connecting helices α4 and α5, where the anion is electrostatically <lb/>coordinated by the side chains of Arg 103 (Figure 4C). Two Mg 2+ <lb/>ions (Mg site 1) are in proximity to sulfate site 2, where each of the <lb/>cations is coordinated by the side chain of Glu 106, which stems from <lb/>each of the one-turn α3 helices (Figure 4C). Three-fold axes traverse the <lb/>12-mer Pa DpsL, each passing through a pair of three-fold pores formed <lb/>at the intersection of three subunits. As is typical of the Dps quaternary <lb/>structure, each of the two three-fold pores along a three-fold axis has a <lb/>different microenvironment, thus resulting in two types of three-fold <lb/>pores, termed here A and B. Each of the type-A three-fold pores, which <lb/>are formed by residues near the turn separating α1 and α2 contain a <lb/>SO 4 <lb/>2-(site 3), which interacts electrostatically with the three <lb/>Lys65 residues at the pore (Figure 4D). The B-type pores (also <lb/>known as ferritin-like pores), which are formed by residues near the <lb/>turn separating α4 and α5, contain sulfate site 4, where the SO 4 <lb/>2-is <lb/>coordinated to Asn146 and Arg152 (Figure 4E). Mg sites 2 and 3 are in <lb/>relative proximity to one another (Figure 4F). Mg site 2 is near the <lb/>protein surface where it is coordinated by the side chains of Asp 167 and <lb/>Asp 171 in the C-terminal helix (α5), whereas Mg site 3 is in the 12-mer <lb/>interior, where it is coordinated by the side chains of Asp164, Asp168 in <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Structure of the SO 4 <lb/>2--bound dodecamer PaDpsL (Pa DpsL-dd). (A) View of the 12-mer along a 3-fold pore. The Fe and SO 4 <lb/>2-ions are rendered as <lb/>orange and red/yellow spheres, respectively. (B) View of a subunit dimer in the 12-mer showing the N-terminal tails. The Fe ions and coordinating ligands <lb/>in the ferroxidase centers are rendered as orange spheres and sticks, respectively. (C) View along an A-type 3-fold pore formed by the tan, green and <lb/>violet subunits, highlighting the N-terminal tails which are positioned over neighboring subunits. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>05 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>the C-terminal helix and Glu 72 and Glu75 in helix α2. This extensive <lb/>network of Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-ions coordinated to 12-mer DpsL suggest <lb/>that the nature of the stabilizing effect that Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-have on the <lb/>DpsL dodecamer structure originate from the mediation of otherwise <lb/>repulsive electrostatic interactions that would take place among <lb/>positively charged residues in the three-fold pores, or among the <lb/>high density of negative charge concentrated near the C-terminus. <lb/>Hence, in the absence of Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>, one can envision significant <lb/>folding-unfolding transitions affecting secondary, tertiary, and <lb/>quaternary structure, which largely destabilize not only the 12-mer <lb/>structure but also lead to proteolysis of the N-terminal domain. In the <lb/>context of the stabilizing effect that 1 mM MgSO 4 has on the Pa DpsL <lb/>structure, it is interesting to note that the reported concentration of <lb/>Mg 2+ in bacteria is 0.5-2.0 mM (Shin et al., 2014), and that sulfate is the <lb/>second most abundant soluble oxyanion after phosphate in bacterial <lb/>cells (Silver and Walderhaug, 1992). Consequently, given the <lb/>electrostatic role played by Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-in the stabilization of the <lb/>Pa DpsL dodecamer in vitro, it is probable that Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-play a <lb/>similar role in the P. aeruginosa cell, probably aided by other ions such <lb/>as Ca 2+ and phosphate. <lb/>2.5 Pa DpsL catalyzes the oxidation of Fe 2+ <lb/>and compartmentalizes Fe 3+ in its core <lb/>Dps and Dps-like proteins are thought to protect cells from <lb/>stressors such as oxidative pressure, nutrient limitation, and even <lb/>radiation, via two types of activity: (i) the catalytic oxidation of Fe 2+ <lb/>at ferroxidase centers using H 2 O 2 or O 2 as electron acceptors, <lb/>possibly compartmentalizing the Fe 3+ in the protein interior, and <lb/>(ii) shielding genomic DNA via binding and condensation. We <lb/>investigated whether Pa DpsL exhibits similar types of activity. Our <lb/>findings from experiments aimed at probing Fe 2+ oxidation are <lb/>presented in this section and the results from probing the <lb/>interactions of Pa DpsL with DNA are presented in Section 2.6. <lb/>Analysis of iron associated with PaDpsL from several <lb/>preparations showed 8-10 iron atoms/12-mer Pa DpsL. The <lb/>analytical data, which agrees with the presence of iron in the <lb/>ferroxidase centers, as determined by X-ray crystallography, also <lb/>indicate that the interior cavity of the recombinant protein as <lb/>isolated from E. coli cells is devoid of iron. The presence of a <lb/>dinuclear iron center in Pa DpsL which is structurally similar to <lb/>the ferroxidase centers in bacterioferritin, however, suggested <lb/>that Pa DpsL may catalyze the oxidation of Fe 2+ in solution and <lb/>compartmentalize the resultant Fe 3+ in its interior cavity. This <lb/>issue was investigated by titrating solutions of the 12-mer Pa <lb/>DpsL in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) containing 1 mM MgSO 4 with <lb/>aliquots delivering 50 Fe 2+ /12-mer to a total of 300 Fe 2+ /12-mer. <lb/>These experiments were conducted in an anaerobic glove box <lb/>using H 2 O 2 as oxidant, or in air, with O 2 as the electron acceptor, <lb/>in a manner similar to that reported for Pa Dps (Rajapaksha <lb/>et al., 2023). <lb/>UV-vis spectra obtained during the titration in air (Figure 5A) <lb/>show an increase in the absorbance near 320 nm following the <lb/>addition of each aliquot delivering Fe 2+ , indicating the formation of <lb/>Fe 3+ -O moieties. Following the addition of the last Fe 2+ aliquot, the <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Structure of the Mg 2+ and SO 4 <lb/>2-bound dodecamer Pa DpsL (Pa DpsL-dd-Mg). (A) View of the 12-mer showing bound Mg 2+ (blue spheres) and SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>(red/yellow) ions. (B) Sulfate site 1 on the N-terminal tail. (C) Magnesium site 1 and sulfate site 2 located near the short helix (α3) on the loop connecting <lb/>α2 and α4. (D) Sulfate site 3 bound to K65 in a type-A 3-fold pore. (E) Sulfate site 4 in a type-B 3-fold pore, where the sulfate ion is coordinated by the side <lb/>chains of N146 and R152. (F) Magnesium sites 2 and 3 located approximately 13 Å from one another. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>06 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>solution was passed through a desalting column, concentrated, and <lb/>then split in two equivolumes. A small volume from each sample was <lb/>used to analyze the protein and iron concentrations after the <lb/>titration, and the remainder was passed through a Superdex <lb/>S200 column, immediately (0 h) and after 24 h of incubation at <lb/>4 °C. The resulting chromatogram (Figure 5B) indicates that Pa <lb/>DpsL remains as a 12-mer during the titration, and the content of <lb/>protein and iron in the sample showed that ~193 Fe atoms/12-mer <lb/>(~64% of the total Fe delivered) are associated with the protein <lb/>eluting from the S200 column (Figure 5E). Similar analysis carried <lb/>out with the sample incubated 24 h prior to passage through the <lb/>S200 column showed ~286 Fe atoms/12-mer (~95% of the total <lb/>Fe delivered). <lb/>When similar experiments were conducted in an anaerobic <lb/>glove box using H 2 O 2 as the oxidant, the UV-vis spectra <lb/>acquired during the titration show no change following the <lb/>addition of each Fe 2+ aliquot (Figure 5C). Addition of an <lb/>equivalent of H 2 O 2 , however, causes the absorbance near 320 nm <lb/>to increase. After oxidation of the Fe 2+ delivered with the last aliquot, <lb/>the solution was desalted, concentrated, and then split in two for <lb/>processing as described above for the titration in air. These <lb/>experiments showed ~94 Fe atoms/12-mer (30% of the total iron <lb/>delivered) associated with the protein loaded onto the S200 column <lb/>immediately after the titration, and 131 Fe atoms/12-mer (44% of <lb/>the total iron delivered) when the sample was incubated 24 h prior to <lb/>passage through the S200 column. <lb/>The results from the experiments carrying out the titration in air, <lb/>or anaerobically using H 2 O 2 as oxidant show that the iron content in <lb/>Pa DpsL chromatographed 24 h after the titration is significantly <lb/>higher than the iron content in Pa DpsL chromatographed <lb/>immediately after mineralization (0 h). These observations <lb/>suggest that the oxidation of Fe 2+ at ferroxidase centers of Pa <lb/>DpsL is efficient, although the process of mineralization in the <lb/>interior cavity appears to be slower because non-mineralized Fe 3+ in <lb/>the 0 h sample can exit the Pa DpsL cavity and be separated from the <lb/>protein in the size exclusion column. In contrast, samples passed <lb/>through the size exclusion column 24 h after mineralization do not <lb/>lose iron in the column, indicating that a core Fe 3+ mineral has <lb/>formed in the interior cavity. <lb/>To further probe the idea that Fe 3+ is compartmentalized in the <lb/>interior cavity of Pa DpsL, fractions eluting from the Superdex column <lb/>were analyzed in a native PAGE gel, staining with Ferene S to visualize <lb/>iron and then with Coomassie to visualize the protein. The results from <lb/>these experiments (Figure 5F), which show that iron is indeed <lb/>compartmentalized in Pa DpsL, indicate that Pa DpsL probably <lb/>functions in the detoxification of iron-induced oxidative stress. In <lb/>this context, although the oxidation of Fe 2+ by Pa DpsL can be <lb/>carried out with O 2 or with H 2 O 2 as electron acceptors, the process <lb/>in vitro appears to be more efficient when O 2 is the oxidant (Figure 5E). <lb/>Additional studies are needed to gain detailed understanding of the Fe 2+ <lb/>oxidation catalyzed by DpsL, as well as the mineralization process <lb/>leading to the formation of a compartmentalized Fe 3+ mineral. <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Anaerobic and aerobic mineralization of Pa DpsL. (A) Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) containing 1 mM MgSO 4 was titrated in air with aliquots of Fe 2+ <lb/>delivering 50 Fe 2+ /12-mer Pa DpsL until a total of 300 Fe 2+ ions/12-mer had been delivered. The addition of each Fe 2+ aliquot causes an increase in the <lb/>absorbance ca. 320 nm due to the formation of Fe 3+ -O moieties. (B) Pa Dps titrated aerobically with Fe 2+ was separated in a calibrated Superdex <lb/>S200 column immediately after the titration (0 h, black trace), and after incubating 24 h at 4 °C (24 h, red trace). (C) Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) + <lb/>1 mM MgSO 4 was titrated in an anaerobic glove box, first with and aliquot of Fe 2+ (50 Fe 2+ /12-mer) followed by addition of 1 equivalent of H 2 O 2 relative to <lb/>Fe 2+ , until 300 Fe 2+ /12-mer had been added. The addition of an Fe 2+ aliquot does not cause changes to the spectra but the addition of an equivalent of <lb/>H 2 O 2 produces an increase in the absorbance near 320 nm. (D) Pa DpsL titrated anaerobically was separated in a calibrated Superdex S200 column 0 h <lb/>(black) and 24 h (red) after the titration. (E) Iron associated with 12-mer Pa DpsL before and after passage through the Superdex S200 column. Standard <lb/>deviation is from two different experiments. (F) Dodecamer Pa DpsL eluting from the S200 column was loaded onto a native PAGE gel, electrophorized <lb/>and stained first with Ferene S to visualize iron and then with Coomassie to visualize the protein. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>07 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>2.6 Pa DpsL cleaves DNA in vitro <lb/>Dps is thought to bind DNA to protect it from the toxic effects of <lb/>oxidative stress. In this context, it has been reported that E. coli Dps <lb/>and plasmid DNA in solution form a complex too large to enter the <lb/>pores of 1% agarose gels (Almiron et al., 1992). DNA binding, <lb/>however, is not a ubiquitous property of Dps, since several Dps have <lb/>been reported to not bind DNA (Guerra et al., 2021). In addition, <lb/>DNA recognition by Dps is probably non-specific but thought to be <lb/>mediated by electrostatic interactions between positively charged <lb/>residues in the N-or C-terminal tails of 12-mer Dps (or DpsL) and <lb/>DNA (Lee et al., 2015). To test this idea, a constant concentration of <lb/>pUC18 plasmid DNA (~2.7 kbp) was incubated for 15 min with <lb/>increasing concentrations of as isolated Pa DpsL in 50 mM Tris <lb/>buffer (pH 7.5) containing 150 mM NaCl and 1 mM MgSO 4 and the <lb/>resultant mixture loaded onto an agarose gel for electrophoresis. <lb/>Surprisingly, the results from these experiments show that Pa DpsL <lb/>nicks the plasmid DNA (Figure 6A), while in contrast, in the <lb/>presence of bovine serum albumin (BSA) as control, the plasmid <lb/>DNA remains supercoiled (Figure 6B). <lb/>Assuming that the interactions between Pa DpsL and DNA <lb/>which result in nicking of the plasmid DNA are electrostatic in <lb/>nature, the experiments were repeated at low ionic strength, by <lb/>incubating the protein and pUC18 plasmid DNA in 50 mM Tris <lb/>buffer, pH 7.5 containing 1 mM MgSO 4 . In these conditions, the <lb/>plasmid incubated with Pa DpsL is first nicked, then linearized and <lb/>ultimately degraded (Figure 6C), whereas plasmid DNA incubated <lb/>with BSA remains supercoiled (Figure 6D). Similar experiments <lb/>carried out by incubating Pa Dps and pET11a plasmid (~5.7 kbp) in <lb/>50 mM Tris buffer (pH 7.5) containing 1 mM MgSO 4 produced <lb/>analogous results to those observed with the pUC18 plasmid. In the <lb/>presence of 150 mM NaCl the circular plasmid was nicked, whereas <lb/>at low ionic strength the plasmid was degraded <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S1). <lb/>The higher DNA cleaving activity observed at low ionic strength <lb/>is consistent with ionic steering of the DNA Pa DpsL interactions. In <lb/>this context, as discussed in section 2.4 (Figure 4), a network of SO 4 <lb/>2-<lb/>ions bind the dodecamer via electrostatic interactions. Electrostatic <lb/>rendering of the dodecamer surface viewed along each of the two <lb/>types of 3-fold pore (Supplementary Figure S2) suggest possible sites <lb/>where the negatively charged backbone of DNA may interact with <lb/>Pa DpsL, thus facilitating the nicking and cleaving activity of Pa <lb/>DpsL. Additional studies are required to elucidate the mechanism of <lb/>DNA nicking and degradation. <lb/>A similar plasmid DNA nicking and cleaving activity was <lb/>recently reported for Pa Dps (Rajapaksha et al., 2023). <lb/>Consequently, we decided to compare the activity of both <lb/>proteins under identical conditions. To this end, we incubated <lb/>plasmid DNA (constant concentration) with increasing <lb/>concentrations of Pa Dps, or Pa DpsL in Tris buffer (pH 7.5) <lb/>containing 1 mM MgSO 4 for 30 min prior to separating the mix <lb/>on agarose gels. When the reaction is carried out at high ionic <lb/>strength, the plasmid DNA is completely nicked when the Pa DpsL/ <lb/>DNA mole ratio is 25 (Figure 6E), while in contrast, the supercoiled <lb/>plasmid DNA is only partially nicked in the presence of Pa Dps, even <lb/>at the higher Dps/DNA mole ratios (Figure 6F). The higher DNA <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>Pa DpsL cleaves plasmid DNA. pUC18 plasmid DNA was incubated (15 min, 35 °C) with different concentrations of Pa Dps in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) + <lb/>1 mM MgSO 4 with or without 150 mM NaCl, and then separated in a 1% agarose gel. (A, C) Pa DpsL, (B, D) bovine serum albumin (BSA) control. Lane M = <lb/>DNA ladder, lane 1 = DNA control, lanes 2-6, respectively, Pa DpsL/DNA mole ratio = 5, 25, 50, 100, 200. (E, F) The DNA cleaving activity of Pa DpsL and Pa <lb/>Dps was compared by incubating (30 min, 35 °C) each of the proteins with plasmid DNA in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) + 1 mM MgSO 4 with (E, F) and without <lb/>(G, H) 150 mM NaC.l. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>08 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>cleaving activity of Pa DpsL relative to Pa Dps is also observed in the <lb/>gels loaded with the reactions carried at low ionic strength, where it <lb/>is evident that Pa DpsL (Figure 6G) degrades plasmid DNA more <lb/>efficiently than Pa Dps (Figure 6H). <lb/>3 Discussion <lb/>The genome of P. aeruginosa encodes four types of iron storage <lb/>protein, two are ferritin-like molecules (FtnA, BfrB), and two are <lb/>miniferritins (Dps and DpsL). The presence of two genes coding for <lb/>ferritin like molecules has been recently explained by the discovery <lb/>showing that FtnA and BfrB co-assemble into a mixed subunit <lb/>bacterioferritin (Bfr), with the relative proportion of FtnA and BfrB <lb/>subunits dictated by environmental O 2 availability (Yao et al., 2022). <lb/>Transcription of the bfrB gene is induced in response to high <lb/>environmental iron (Ochsner et al., 2002; Wilderman et al., <lb/>2004), while the ftnA gene, which is part of the Anr regulon, is <lb/>transcribed in response to low environmental O 2 (Hammond et al., <lb/>2015). Given that both the FtnA and BfrB subunits of Bfr harbor <lb/>active but structurally distinct ferroxidase centers, it has been <lb/>speculated that the ferroxidase center of BfrB is tuned to react <lb/>rapidly with H 2 O 2 , whereas the ferroxidase center of FtnA may have <lb/>a higher affinity for O 2 , which allows Fe 2+ oxidation and Fe 3+ storage <lb/>under microaerophilic conditions (Yao et al., 2022). <lb/>The P. aeruginosa genome also harbors two genes encoding <lb/>distinct miniferritins, Pa Dps (PA0962) and Pa DpsL (PA4880). <lb/>Although the subunits of both types of protein adopt the classic Dps <lb/>fold and have an N-terminal tail, they differ significantly in the <lb/>structure of their ferroxidase centers. In Pa Dps (Rajapaksha et al., <lb/>2023), like in classic Dps proteins, the dinuclear iron sites of the <lb/>ferroxidase centers are located at the interface of 2-fold symmetry-<lb/>related subunit dimers, and the iron ligands, which are highly <lb/>conserved amongst Dps sequences, are contributed by each of <lb/>the subunits in the dimer (Ilari et al., 2000; Ilari et al., 2002; <lb/>Rajapaksha et al., 2023). In Pa DpsL the ferroxidase center <lb/>dinuclear site and corresponding ligands are contained within <lb/>each of the subunits. Interestingly, the ferroxidase center ligands <lb/>in Pa DpsL are identical to those of Pa BfrB, which is probably one <lb/>reason the PA4880 gene in the P. aeruginosa PAO1 genome has been <lb/>annotated as coding a &quot;possible bacterioferritin&quot;. The structural <lb/>characterization of the product of gene PA4880 presented here <lb/>shows a protein with a Dps fold but with bacterioferritin-like <lb/>ferroxidase centers. Hence, we propose that gene PA4880 should <lb/>be annotated as encoding a Dps-like protein (dpsL). <lb/>Although it is now clear that the P. aeruginosa genome encodes <lb/>two types of Dps proteins, it is not yet completely understood why <lb/>the two types of Dps are needed. Pa Dps has been implicated in the <lb/>defense against oxidative stress and in a protective role against the β-<lb/>lactam antibiotic Meropenem, possibly due to its reactive oxygen <lb/>species (ROS) suppressing activity (Maura et al., 2016). Pa Dps has <lb/>also been implicated in a H3-T6SS-mediated protection of P. <lb/>aeruginosa cells against H 2 O 2 by its predicted ability to catalyze <lb/>the oxidation of Fe 2+ and compartmentalize Fe 3+ in its interior cavity <lb/>(Lin et al., 2023). These conclusions are supported by the more <lb/>recent structural and biochemical characterization of Pa Dps, which <lb/>demonstrated catalytic ferroxidase activity, competency to store Fe 3+ <lb/>in its interior cavity, and the ability to protect P. aeruginosa cells <lb/>from H 2 O 2 -induced toxicity (Rajapaksha et al., 2023). Even less is <lb/>known about Pa DpsL. The dpsL gene (PA4880) is expressed under <lb/>iron-replete conditions and is regulated by the small regulatory <lb/>RNAs PrrF1 and PrrF2 (Wilderman et al., 2004). In agreement, <lb/>proteomic analysis of the P. aeruginosa iron starvation response <lb/>imposed by limiting iron in the media (Nelson et al., 2019), or by <lb/>irreversibly trapping iron in bacterioferritin (Punchi Hewage et al., <lb/>2020), results in low abundance of Pa DpsL. The transcriptional <lb/>response of dpsL to environmental iron levels is also in agreement <lb/>with the structure of Pa DpsL, which harbors ferroxidase centers to <lb/>catalyze the oxidation of Fe 2+ and an interior cavity that can <lb/>compartmentalize Fe 3+ . Taken together, the transcriptomic, <lb/>proteomic, and structural studies converge on a role for Pa DpsL <lb/>in the protection toward iron-induced toxicity. Pa DpsL, however, <lb/>may play additional roles in the cell, since transcriptomic analyses <lb/>have also implicated the dpsL gene in the osmotic stress (Aspedon <lb/>et al., 2006), and in the quorum sensing (Schuster et al., 2003) <lb/>response of P. aeruginosa. <lb/>It is also of note that Pa DpsL, like Pa Dps (Rajapaksha et al., <lb/>2023), can efficiently nick DNA. In this context, restriction-<lb/>modification systems, consisting of a restriction endonuclease <lb/>and cognate methyl transferase, are considered innate immune <lb/>mechanisms that protect their host against foreign DNA <lb/>(Santoshi et al., 2023). Nicking endonucleases, like restriction <lb/>endonucleases, recognize a short specific sequence in double-<lb/>stranded DNA and cleave it at a specific position relative to the <lb/>recognition sequence. Unlike restriction endonucleases, however, <lb/>nicking endonucleases cleave only one DNA strand (Zheleznaya <lb/>et al., 2009). Consequently, it is possible that Pa DpsL, in addition to <lb/>protecting the P. aeruginosa against iron-induced toxicity, may <lb/>contribute to protecting the cell against invading foreign DNA. <lb/>Although the work presented here demonstrates that Pa DpsL can <lb/>efficiently nick plasmid DNA, and at higher concentrations restrict <lb/>and degrade DNA, it is not yet known whether a specific sequence is <lb/>recognized. It is also interesting that both miniferritins in P. <lb/>aeruginosa, Pa Dps (Rajapaksha et al., 2023), and Pa DpsL <lb/>exhibit nuclease activity. This suggests that miniferritins from <lb/>other bacteria may also restrict DNA. Future work aimed at <lb/>probing whether Pa DpsL and Pa Dps recognize specific DNA <lb/>sequences, as well as searching for other miniferritins exhibiting <lb/>nuclease activity will help understand how the nuclease activity of <lb/>these molecules contributes to the bacterial immune response <lb/>and fitness. <lb/>4 Materials and methods <lb/>4.1 Chemicals <lb/>Unless otherwise specified chemicals were purchased from <lb/>Fisher Scientific (Waltman, MA, United States of America). The <lb/>gene encoding Pa DpsL (PA4880) was synthesized, subcloned into a <lb/>pET11a vector, and sequenced (GeneScript Corp., Piscataway, NJ). <lb/>The gene was engineered with silent mutations introducing codons <lb/>favored by E. coli (Ikemura, 1985), and with NdeI and BamHI <lb/>restriction sites at the 5′ and 3&apos; ends, respectively. The pET11a-dpsL <lb/>construct was transformed into E. coli BL21-Gold (DE3) cells <lb/>(Agilent Technologies) for protein expression. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>09 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>4.2 Expression and purification of Pa DpsL <lb/>Pre-cultures were grown overnight from a single colony of E. coli <lb/>BL21-Gold (DE3) cells transformed with the pET11a-dpsL construct <lb/>in LB media containing 50 μg/mL ampicillin. The pre-cultures were <lb/>used to inoculate 1L of fresh LB media, and the expression cultures <lb/>were induced with 0.5 mM isopropyl β-D-1thiogalactopyranoside <lb/>(IPTG) when the optical density at 600 (OD 600 ) reached 0.6-0.8. <lb/>Four hours post-induction the cells were harvested by centrifugation <lb/>and stored at -80 °C until lysis. The initial purification attempts were <lb/>carried out by resuspending the cell pellet in 50 mM potassium <lb/>phosphate (pH 7.0) containing 0.5 mM phenylmethyl sulfonyl <lb/>fluoride (PMSF), and a protease inhibitor cocktail tablet (Thermo <lb/>Scientific). The cells were lysed by ultrasound in an ice bath with the <lb/>aid of a Qsonica Q500 sonicator operating with a 60% pulse <lb/>amplitude and 10 cycles of pulse-on (10 s) pulse-off (45 s). The <lb/>cell lysate was clarified by centrifugation (63,000 x g, 4 °C, 45 min), <lb/>loaded onto a 5 mL HiTrap ™ Q FF (GE Healthcare) column <lb/>equilibrated with lysis buffer, and then eluted with a 0-600 mM <lb/>NaCl gradient. Fractions containing Pa DpsL were combined and <lb/>loaded onto a Superdex ™ 200 Increase 10/300 GL size exclusion <lb/>column (25 mL, GE Healthcare) equilibrated with 50 mM potassium <lb/>phosphate (pH 6.2) containing 0.5 mM PMSF, and a protease <lb/>inhibitor tablet (Thermo Scientific). This protocol allowed <lb/>isolation of small amounts of pure Pa DpsL which consisted of <lb/>12-mer (small minority) and lower oligomerization states. This <lb/>protein was used to grow the prismatic crystals used to <lb/>determine the structure of a Pa DpsL subunit (Pa DpsL-dimer). <lb/>Screening for experimental conditions led us to observe that the <lb/>presence of ≥1 mM MgSO 4 in the buffer stabilizes the 12-mer. <lb/>Consequently, purification of 12-mer Pa DpsL was carried out as <lb/>follows: The cell pellet was resuspended in lysis buffer: 50 mM Tris <lb/>(pH 7.5), 100 mM NaCl, 0.5% Triton X-100, 2 mg/mL lysozyme, <lb/>0.5 mM (PMSF), 1 mM MgSO 4 , 1 mM CaCl 2 , and a protease <lb/>inhibitor cocktail tablet. The cells were lysed with ultrasound and <lb/>the lysate was clarified by centrifugation as described above. The <lb/>clarified lysate was dialyzed against 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 3 mM <lb/>MgSO 4 , 0.5 mM PMSF, and protease inhibitor cocktail tablet at 4 °C. <lb/>The resultant solution was filtered through a 4 μm filter (VWR), and <lb/>then loaded onto a 10 mL HiTrap ™ Q FF anion exchange column, <lb/>washed with the same buffer, and then eluted with a NaCl gradient <lb/>(0-300 mM). Fractions containing Pa DpsL were pooled, dialyzed <lb/>against 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 3 mM MgSO 4 , 0.5 mM PMSF, loaded <lb/>onto Source ™ 15Q anion exchange column (Cytiva), washed with <lb/>the same buffer, and eluted with an NaCl gradient (80-280 mM). <lb/>Fractions containing Pa DpsL were pooled, concentrated, and then <lb/>chromatographed through a calibrated Superdex ™ 200 Increase 10/ <lb/>300 GL size exclusion column (25 mL) equilibrated and eluted with <lb/>50 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 1 mM MgSO 4 . The protein concentration was <lb/>determined with the aid of a bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay kit <lb/>(Pierce ™ BCA Protein Assay Kit, Thermo Scientific) following the <lb/>manufacturer provided instructions. <lb/>4.3 Crystallization and structure solution <lb/>All crystallization experiments were carried out using an <lb/>NT8 drop setting robot (Formulatrix Inc.) and UVXPO MRC <lb/>(Molecular Dimensions) sitting drop vapor diffusion plates at <lb/>18 °C. 100 nL of protein and 100 nL crystallization solution were <lb/>dispensed and equilibrated against 50 μL of the latter. The purified <lb/>Pa DpsL-dimer was concentrated to 8 mg/mL (0.4 mM) in 50 mM <lb/>phosphate buffer, pH 6.2 for crystallization screening. Prismatic <lb/>crystals formed in approximately 1 week from the Proplex screen <lb/>(Molecular Dimensions) condition D5 (8% (w/v) PEG 6,000, <lb/>100 mM MES pH 6.0, 100 mM MgCl 2 ). The protein sample used <lb/>to obtain the structure of dodecameric Pa DpsL (Pa DpsL-dd) and <lb/>the dodecameric form with Mg 2+ (Pa DpsL-dd-Mg) was <lb/>concentrated to 13.3 mg/mL (0.4 mM) in 50 mM potassium <lb/>phosphate pH 6.2, 0.5 mM PMSF. Prismatic crystals formed in <lb/>approximately 1 week from the Salt Rx HT screen (Hampton <lb/>Research) condition F9 (800 mM lithium sulfate, 100 mM Tris <lb/>pH 8.5) for Pa DpsL-dd and from condition G2 (1 M MgSO 4 , <lb/>100 mM Bis-Tris pH 7.0) for Pa DpsL-dd-Mg. Samples were <lb/>transferred to a cryoprotectant solution composed of 80% (v/v) <lb/>crystallization solution and 20% (v/v) glycerol before storing in <lb/>liquid nitrogen. X-ray diffraction data were collected at National <lb/>Synchrotron Light Source II AMX beamline 17-ID-1 using an Eiger <lb/>9M pixel array detector for Pa DpsL-monomer. X-ray diffraction <lb/>data for Pa DpsL-dd and Pa DpsL-dd-Mg were collected at National <lb/>Synchrotron Light Source II NYX beamline 19-ID using a Dectris <lb/>Pilatus 6M pixel array detector. <lb/>Intensities were integrated using XDS (Kabsch, 2010b; a) and the <lb/>Laue class analysis and data were scaled together with Aimless <lb/>(Evans, 2011). Data from three datasets were merged for Pa DpsL-<lb/>dimer to increase the multiplicity and structure solution was <lb/>conducted by SAD phasing using the ShelxCDE (Sheldrick, 2010) <lb/>pipeline which yielded an estimated mean FOM of 0.657 and <lb/>pseudo-free CC of 71.15% for the original enantiomorph. ShelxE <lb/>autotracing produced a Cα model that contained 141 residues which <lb/>was used for the automated building with Arp/warp (Langer et al., <lb/>2008). The final model, containing a monomer in the asymmetric <lb/>unit was obtained by additional refinement and manual model <lb/>building with Phenix (Liebschner et al., 2019) and Coot (Emsley <lb/>et al., 2010), respectively. This model was used for structure solution <lb/>of Pa DpsL-dd, and Pa DpsL-dd-Mg data by molecular replacement <lb/>with Phaser (McCoy et al., 2007). All atoms except solvent molecules <lb/>were refined with anisotropic atomic displacement parameter for Pa <lb/>DpsL monomer. Disordered side chains were truncated to the point <lb/>for which electron density could be observed. Structure validation <lb/>was conducted with Molprobity (Chen et al., 2010) and figures were <lb/>prepared suing the CCP4MG package (McNicholas et al., 2011). <lb/>Structure superposition was conducted with GESMT (Krissinel, <lb/>2012). <lb/>Crystallographic <lb/>data <lb/>are <lb/>provided <lb/>in <lb/>Supplementary Table S1. <lb/>4.4 Titration of Pa Dps with Fe 2+ under <lb/>aerobic and anaerobic conditions <lb/>Anaerobic titrations were conducted in an anaerobic glove box <lb/>(Coy): 12-mer Pa DpsL (1.5 mL, 2.0 μM) in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) <lb/>containing 1 mM MgSO 4 was placed in a container outfitted with a <lb/>magnetic bar and titrated with a solution of 20 mM FeCl 2 , with each <lb/>aliquot delivering 50 Fe 2+ /12-mer, followed by the addition of <lb/>1 equivalent of H 2 O 2 relative to Fe 2+ . After the addition of each <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>10 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<body>aliquot, the solution was stirred for 2 min prior to recording UV-vis <lb/>spectra using a Cary50 spectrophotometer and a 0.2 cm pathlength <lb/>fiber optic probe. After addition of the last aliquot (total of 300 Fe 2+ / <lb/>12-mer) the solution was desalted through a Sephadex G25 M <lb/>column, concentrated to 1,140 μL, and divided into two <lb/>equivolume samples. A 50 μL aliquot was used to analyze the Fe <lb/>content, and a 20 μL aliquot to determine the protein concentration. <lb/>One of the samples (500 μL), termed 0 h, was chromatographed <lb/>through a Superdex ™ 200 Increase 10/300 GL size exclusion column <lb/>equilibrated and eluted with 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) containing 1 mM <lb/>MgSO 4 . The second sample (500 μL) was incubated for 24 h at 4 <lb/>°C <lb/>and then chromatographed through the Superdex ™ 200 Increase <lb/>size exclusion column equilibrated and eluted with 50 mM Tris <lb/>(pH 7.5) containing 1 mM MgSO 4 . Pa DpsL fractions eluting from <lb/>the size exclusion column were pooled and concentrated to 500 μL, <lb/>prior to sampling aliquots for the determination of Fe (50 μL) and <lb/>protein (20 μL) concentrations. The remaining was concentrated to <lb/>100 μL and then used to load native and SDS PAGE gels. Aerobic <lb/>titrations were carried out similarly, except that dissolved O 2 was <lb/>used as the oxidant. <lb/>4.5 Pa DpsL interactions with plasmid DNA <lb/>pUC18 plasmid (4 μL, 15 ng/μL) was mixed with distinct <lb/>concentrations of Pa DpsL (4 μL) in 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) <lb/>containing 1 mM MgSO 4 , with or without 150 mM NaCl, to <lb/>produce solutions containing Pa DpsL/pUC18 M ratio = 5, 25, 50, <lb/>100 and 200. The reactions were incubated (15 min) at 35 °C and then <lb/>quenched by addition of loading dye prior to loading 1% agarose gels for <lb/>electrophoresis (TBE buffer, 80 V, 105 min, room temperature). DNA <lb/>bands were visualized using SYBR safe DNA staining dye. <lb/>4.6 Mass spectrometry <lb/>Bands 1, 2 and 3 in Figure 1C were excised from the SDS PAGE gel, <lb/>and the bands processed as described previously (Yao et al., 2022). In <lb/>brief, the protein in the gel bands was reduced with dithiothreitol and <lb/>alkylated with iodoacetamide before overnigh incubation in buffered <lb/>trypsin solution. The extracted peptides were dried, reconstituted in <lb/>0.1% formic acid and qunatified with the aid of UV-vis <lb/>spectrophotometry in a Biotek Epoch2 plate reader. A total of <lb/>500 ng tryptic peptides was injected in the mass spectrometer. <lb/>Mass spectrometry was conducted on a LC-MS/MS Vanquish <lb/>Neo liquid chromatography system coupled to a Q-Exactive orbitrap <lb/>mass spectrometer equipped with a flex source for nano-LC <lb/>(Thermo Scientific). Chromatography was conducted by first <lb/>loading onto a trap cartridge (Thermo Scientific Acclaim <lb/>PepMap NEO, 5 µm particle size, 1 mm i.d., 5 mm length) at <lb/>20 μL/min using an isocratic program with 98:2, H 2 O: <lb/>acetonitrile (ACN) containing 0.1% formic acid. This step <lb/>allowed for sample pre-concentration and desalting. Analytical <lb/>separation of the trapped peptides was conducted with a nanoLC <lb/>column (Thermo Scientific Acclaim PepMap, 3 µm particle size, <lb/>0.075 mm i.d., 250 mm length) coupled to a metal emitter with an <lb/>i.d. of 30 µm. Separation was carried out with a gradient using two <lb/>mobile phases: A = H 2 O, B = ACN, both containing 0.1% formic <lb/>acid. After the initial 5 min of trapping, the gradient started at 5% B <lb/>(2 min), increased to 10% B in 1 min then to 30% B in 30 min. The <lb/>column was then washed with 90% B (5 min) before returning to 5% <lb/>B for re-equilibration. Ionization was achieved with a constant <lb/>voltage (1.9 kV) in positive ion mode, while the mass <lb/>spectrometer was operated in data-dependent acquisition (DDA) <lb/>mode using a loop count of 10. The chromatographic peak width <lb/>was set to 45 s, the full MS resolution to 70,000 with an adjusted gain <lb/>control (AGC) target of 1e 6 and a maximum injection time (IT) of <lb/>50 ms. The scan range was set to 375-1,400 m/z. The MS/MS <lb/>resolution was set to 17,500 with an AGC target of 1e 5 and a <lb/>maximum IT of 110 ms. The isolation window for the parent ion <lb/>was set to 1.4 m/z while the scan range was automatically adjusted <lb/>based on size and charge of the parent ion. The normalized collision <lb/>energy (NCE) was set to 28. The minimum AGC to trigger an MS/ <lb/>MS scan was set to 1.1e 3 , which resulted in a minimum intensity <lb/>threshold of 1.0e 4 . Only peaks with charges between 2 and 6 were <lb/>considered for MS/MS scans. Isotopes were excluded, and all parent <lb/>ions scanned were temporarily included in an exclusion list for 60 s. <lb/>Raw data were visualized with Thermo Scientific FreeStyle (ver. 1.8) <lb/>to confirm peptide intensity and separation quality. Samples were then <lb/>analyzed with Thermo Scientific Proteome Discoverer 2.4 using both <lb/>Sequest HT and Mascot (Matrix Science, ver. 2.8) as search engines. <lb/>Data were searched against the latest available Uniprot reference <lb/>proteomes for P. aeruginosa (strain ATCC 15692/DSM 22644/CIP <lb/>104116/JCM 14847/LMG 12228/1C/PRS 101/PAO1, proteome ID <lb/>UP000002438) database using a tolerance of 10 ppm for the parent <lb/>ion and 0.2 m/z for the fragments. Carbamidomethylation of cysteine <lb/>was selected as static modification while methionine oxidation was <lb/>selected as dynamic modification. Percolator was used to calculate <lb/>posterior error probabilities for each peptide spectrum match (PSM). A <lb/>second database containing common contaminants was also used to <lb/>filter out unrelated protein hits. A consensus workflow was employed to <lb/>eliminate peptide redundancy, further validate PSM assignment and <lb/>provide protein identification and FDR validation. Both proteins and <lb/>peptides were assigned a high level of confidence if FDR values were <lb/>lower than 0.01 and a medium level of confidence if FDR values were <lb/>between 0.01 and 0.05. Finally, each protein was required to have at least <lb/>1 unique peptide. <lb/></body>

		<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The data presented in the study are deposited in the Worldwide <lb/>Protein Databank (wwPDB), with the accession codes 8W1D <lb/>(Pa DpsL-monomer), 8W1E (Pa DpsL-dd) and 8W1F (Pa DpsL-<lb/>dd-Mg). <lb/></div>

		<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>NR: Visualization, Writing-original draft, Investigation. HY: <lb/>Investigation, Visualization, Conceptualization, Methodology, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. AC: Investigation, Writing-review and <lb/>editing. SS: Investigation, Writing-review and editing. LL: Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, Writing-review and editing. KB: Methodology, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. LF: Investigation, Writing-review and <lb/>editing. FD: Methodology, Writing-review and editing. SL: <lb/></div>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<div type="contribution">Investigation, Methodology, Writing-original draft, Writing-review <lb/>and editing. MR: Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Project <lb/>administration, Resources, Supervision, Validation, Visualization, <lb/>Writing-original draft, Writing-review and editing. <lb/></div>

		<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This research <lb/>was funded by a grant from the National Institutes of Health <lb/>(AI169344) to MR. This research used resources the AMX beamline <lb/>17-ID and NYX beamline 19-ID of the National Synchrotron Light <lb/>Source II, a U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) Office of Science User <lb/>Facility operated for the DOE Office of Science by Brookhaven National <lb/>Laboratory under Contract No. DE-SC0012704. The AMX beamline at <lb/>the Center for BioMolecular Structure (CBMS) is primarily supported <lb/>by the National Institutes of Health, National Institute of General <lb/>Medical Sciences (NIGMS) through a Center Core P30 Grant <lb/>(P30GM133893), and by the DOE Office of Biological and <lb/>Environmental Research (KP1605010). The NYX beamline is <lb/>supported by the New York Structural Biology Center. <lb/></div>

		<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

		<listBibl>References <lb/>Agirre, J., Atanasova, M., Bagdonas, H., Ballard, C. B., Basle, A., Beilsten-Edmands, J., <lb/>et al. (2023). The CCP4 suite: integrative software for macromolecular crystallography. <lb/>Acta Crystallogr. D. Struct. Biol. 79, 449-461. doi:10.1107/S2059798323003595 <lb/>Almiron, M., Link, A. J., Furlong, D., and Kolter, R. (1992). A novel DNA-binding <lb/>protein with regulatory and protective roles in starved Escherichia coli. Genes Dev. 6, <lb/>2646-2654. doi:10.1101/gad.6.12b.2646 <lb/>Aspedon, A., Palmer, K., and Whiteley, M. (2006). Microarray analysis of the osmotic <lb/>stress response in Pseudomonas aeruginosa. J. Bacteriol. 188, 2721-2725. doi:10.1128/ <lb/>JB.188.7.2721-2725.2006 <lb/>Bradley, J. M., Le Brun, N. E., and Moore, G. R. (2016). Ferritins: furnishing proteins <lb/>with iron. J. Biol. Inorg. Chem. 21, 13-28. doi:10.1007/s00775-016-1336-0 <lb/>Burrows, L. L. (2018). The therapeutic pipeline for Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>infections. ACS Infect. Dis. 4, 1041-1047. doi:10.1021/acsinfecdis.8b00112 <lb/>Calhoun, L. N., and Kwon, Y. M. (2011). Structure, function and regulation of the <lb/>DNA-binding protein Dps and its role in acid and oxidative stress resistance in <lb/>Escherichia coli: a review. J. Appl. Microbiol. 110, 375-386. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2672. <lb/>2010.04890.x <lb/>Chen, V. B., Arendall, W. B. R., Headd, J. J., Keedy, D. A., Immormino, R. M., Kapral, <lb/>G. J., et al. (2010). MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular <lb/>crystallography. Acta Cryst. D. 66, 12-21. doi:10.1107/S0907444909042073 <lb/>Ciccone, L., Vera, L., Tepshi, L., Rosalia, L., Rossello, A., and Stura, E. A. (2015). <lb/>Multicomponent mixtures for cryoprotection and ligand solubilization. Biotechnol. <lb/>Rep. (Amst) 7, 120-127. doi:10.1016/j.btre.2015.05.008 <lb/>Crone, S., Vives-Florez, M., Kvich, L., Saunders, A. M., Malone, M., Nicolaisen, M. H., <lb/>et al. (2020). The environmental occurrence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. APMIS 128, <lb/>220-231. doi:10.1111/apm.13010 <lb/>Emsley, P., Lohkamp, B., Scott, W. G., and Cowan, K. (2010). Features and <lb/>development of Coot. Acta Cryst. D66, 486-501. doi:10.1107/S0907444910007493 <lb/>Eshelman, K., Yao, H., Punchi Hewage, A. N. D., Deay, J. J., Chandler, J. R., and <lb/>Rivera, M. (2017). Inhibiting the BfrB:bfd interaction in Pseudomonas aeruginosa causes <lb/>irreversible iron accumulation in bacterioferritin and iron deficiency in the bacterial cell. <lb/>Metallomics 9, 646-659. doi:10.1039/c7mt00042a <lb/>Evans, P. R. (2011). An introduction to data reduction: space-group determination, <lb/>scaling and intentisy statistics. Acta Cryst. D67, 282-292. doi:10.1107/ <lb/>S090744491003982X <lb/>Gauss, G. H., Benas, P., Wiedenheft, B., Young, M., Douglas, T., and Lawrence, C. M. <lb/>(2006). Structure of the DPS-like protein from Sulfolobus solfataricus reveals a <lb/>bacterioferritin-like dimetal binding site within a DPS-like dodecameric assembly. <lb/>Biochemistry 45, 10815-10827. doi:10.1021/bi060782u <lb/>Gauss, G. H., Reott, M. A., Rocha, E. R., Young, M. J., Douglas, T., Smith, C. J., et al. <lb/>(2012). Characterization of the Bacteroides fragilis bfr gene product identifies a bacterial <lb/>DPS-like protein and suggests evolutionary links in the ferritin superfamily. J. Bacteriol. <lb/>194, 15-27. doi:10.1128/JB.05260-11 <lb/>Guerra, J. P. L., Jacinto, J. P., and Tavares, P. (2021). Miniferritins: small <lb/>multifunctional protein cages. Coord. Chem. Rev. 449, 214187. doi:10.1016/j.ccr. <lb/>2021.214187 <lb/>Hammond, J. H., Dolben, E. F., Smith, T. J., Bhuju, S., and Hogan, D. A. (2015). Links <lb/>between Anr and quorum sensing in Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms. J. Bacteriol. 197, <lb/>2810-2820. doi:10.1128/JB.00182-15 <lb/>Horcajada, J. P., Montero, M., Oliver, A., Sorli, L., Luque, S., Gomez-Zorrilla, S., et al. <lb/>(2019). Epidemiology and treatment of multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-<lb/>resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa infections. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 32, e00031. <lb/>doi:10.1128/CMR.00031-19 <lb/>Ikemura, T. (1985). Codon usage and tRNA content in unicellular and <lb/>multicellular organisms. Mol. Biol. Evol. 2, 13-34. doi:10.1093/oxfordjournals. <lb/>molbev.a040335 <lb/>Ilari, A., Ceci, P., Ferrari, D., Rossi, G. L., and Chiancone, E. (2002). Iron <lb/>incorporation into Escherichia coli Dps gives rise to a ferritin-like microcrystalline <lb/>core. J. Biol. Chem. 277, 37619-37623. doi:10.1074/jbc.M206186200 <lb/>Ilari, A., Stefanini, S., Chiancone, E., and Tsernoglou, D. (2000). The dodecameric <lb/>ferritin from Listeria innocua contains a novel intersubunit iron-binding site. Nat. <lb/>Struct. Biol. 7, 38-43. doi:10.1038/71236 <lb/>Kabsch, W. (2010a). Integration, scaling, space-group assignment and post-<lb/>refinement. Acta Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 66, 133-144. doi:10.1107/ <lb/>S0907444909047374 <lb/>Kabsch, W. (2010b). Xds. Acta Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 66, 125-132. doi:10. <lb/>1107/S0907444909047337 <lb/>Krissinel, E. (2012). Enhanced fold recognition using efficient short fragment <lb/>clustering. J. Mol. Biochem. 1, 76-85. <lb/>Langer, G., Cohen, S. X., Lamzin, V. S., and Perrakis, A. (2008). Automated <lb/>macromolecular model building for X-ray crystallography using ARP/wARP version <lb/>7. Nat. Protoc. 3, 1171-1179. doi:10.1038/nprot.2008.91 <lb/>Lee, S. Y., Lim, C. J., Droge, P., and Yan, J. (2015). Regulation of bacterial DNA <lb/>packaging in early stationary phase by competitive DNA binding of Dps and IHF. Sci. <lb/>Rep. 5, 18146. doi:10.1038/srep18146 <lb/>Liebschner, D., Afonine, P. V., Baker, M. L., Bunkoczi, G., Chen, V. B., Croll, T. I., <lb/>et al. (2019). Macromolecular structure determination using X-rays, neutrons and <lb/>electrons: recent developments in Phenix. Acta Crystallogr. D. Struct. Biol. 75, 861-877. <lb/>doi:10.1107/S2059798319011471 <lb/>Lin, J., Yang, J., Cheng, J., Zhang, W., Yang, X., Ding, W., et al. (2023). In vitro and in <lb/>vivo antimicrobial activities of vancomycin and rifampin against Elizabethkingia <lb/>anophelis. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 24, 17012. doi:10.3390/ijms242317012 <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>12 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>Lundin, D., Poole, A. M., Sjoberg, B. M., and Hogbom, M. (2012). Use of structural <lb/>phylogenetic networks for classification of the ferritin-like superfamily. J. Biol. Chem. <lb/>287, 20565-20575. doi:10.1074/jbc.M112.367458 <lb/>Maura, D., Hazan, R., Kitao, T., Ballok, A. E., and Rahme, L. G. (2016). Evidence for <lb/>direct control of virulence and defense gene circuits by the Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>quorum sensing regulator, MvfR. Sci. Rep. 6, 34083. doi:10.1038/srep34083 <lb/>Mccoy, A. J., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Adams, P. D., Winn, M. D., Storoni, L. C., and <lb/>Read, R. J. (2007). Phaser crystallographic software. J. Appl. Cryst. 40, 658-674. doi:10. <lb/>1107/S0021889807021206 <lb/>Mcnicholas, S., Potterton, E., Wilson, K. S., and Noble, M. E. (2011). Presenting your <lb/>structures: the CCP4mg molecular-graphics software. Acta Crystallogr. D. Biol. <lb/>Crystallogr. 67, 386-394. doi:10.1107/S0907444911007281 <lb/>Nair, S., and Finkel, S. E. (2004). Dps protects cells against multiple stresses during <lb/>stationary phase. J. Bacteriol. 186, 4192-4198. doi:10.1128/JB.186.13.4192-4198.2004 <lb/>Nelson, C. E., Huang, W., Brewer, L. K., Nguyen, A. T., Kane, M. A., Wilks, A., et al. <lb/>(2019). Proteomic analysis of the Pseudomonas aeruginosa iron starvation response <lb/>reveals PrrF small regulatory RNA-dependent iron regulation of twitching motility, <lb/>amino acid metabolism, and zinc homeostasis proteins. J. Bacteriol. 201, e00754. doi:10. <lb/>1128/JB.00754-18 <lb/>Ochsner, U. A., Wilderman, P. J., Vasil, A. I., and Vasil, M. L. (2002). GeneChip <lb/>expression analysis of the iron starvation response in Pseudomonas aeruginosa: <lb/>identification of novel pyoverdine biosynthesis genes. Mol. Microbiol. 45, <lb/>1277-1287. doi:10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.03084.x <lb/>Palma, M., Worgall, S., and Quadri, L. E. N. (2003). Transcriptome analysis of the <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa response to iron. Arch. Microbiol. 180, 374-379. doi:10.1007/ <lb/>s00203-003-0602-z <lb/>Punchi Hewage, A. N. D., Fontenot, L., Guidry, J., Weldeghiorghis, T., Mehta, A. K., <lb/>Donnarumma, F., et al. (2020). Mobilization of iron stored in bacterioferritin is required <lb/>for metabolic homeostasis in Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Pathogens 9, 980. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>pathogens9120980 <lb/>Punchi Hewage, A. N. D., Yao, H., Nammalwar, B., Gnanasekaran, K. K., Lovell, S., <lb/>Bunce, R. A., et al. (2019). Small molecule inhibitors of the BfrB-bfd interaction decrease <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa fitness and potentiate fluoroquinolone activity. J. Am. Chem. <lb/>Soc. 141, 8171-8184. doi:10.1021/jacs.9b00394 <lb/>Rajapaksha, N., Soldano, A., Yao, H., Donnarumma, F., Kashipathy, M. M., Seibold, <lb/>S., et al. (2023). Pseudomonas aeruginosa Dps (PA0962) functions in H(2)O(2) <lb/>mediated oxidative stress defense and exhibits in vitro DNA cleaving activity. Int. <lb/>J. Mol. Sci. 24, 4669. doi:10.3390/ijms24054669 <lb/>Rivera, M. (2017). Bacterioferritin: structure, dynamics and protein-protein <lb/>interactions at play in iron storage and mobilization. Acc. Chem. Res. 50, 331-340. <lb/>doi:10.1021/acs.accounts.6b00514 <lb/>Rivera, M. (2023). Mobilization of iron stored in bacterioferritin, a new target for <lb/>perturbing iron homeostasis and developing antibacterial and antibiofilm molecules. <lb/>J. Inorg. Biochem. 247, 112306. doi:10.1016/j.jinorgbio.2023.112306 <lb/>Santoshi, M., Engleng, B., Eligar, S. M., Ratnakar, I. S., Nagamalleshwari, E., and <lb/>Nagaraja, V. (2023). Identification and characterization of a new HNH restriction <lb/>endonuclease with unusual properties. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 107, 6263-6275. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s00253-023-12717-8 <lb/>Schuster, M., Lostroh, C. P., Ogi, T., and Greenberg, E. P. (2003). Identification, <lb/>timing, and signal specificity of Pseudomonas aeruginosa quorum-controlled genes: a <lb/>transcriptome analysis. J. Bacteriol. 185, 2066-2079. doi:10.1128/jb.185.7.2066-2079. <lb/>2003 <lb/>Sheldrick, G. M. (2010). Experimental phasing with SHELXC/D/E: combining chain <lb/>tracing with density modification. Acta Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 66, 479-485. <lb/>doi:10.1107/S0907444909038360 <lb/>Shin, J. H., Wakeman, C. A., Goodson, J. R., Rodionov, D. A., Freedman, B. G., Senger, <lb/>R. S., et al. (2014). Transport of magnesium by a bacterial Nramp-related gene. PLoS <lb/>Genet. 10, e1004429. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1004429 <lb/>Silver, S., and Walderhaug, M. (1992). Gene regulation of plasmid-and chromosome-<lb/>determined inorganic ion transport in bacteria. Microbiol. Rev. 56, 195-228. doi:10. <lb/>1128/mr.56.1.195-228.1992 <lb/>Soldano, A., Yao, H., Chandler, J. R., and Rivera, M. (2020). Inhibiting iron <lb/>mobilization from bacterioferritin in Pseudomonas aeruginosa impairs biofilm <lb/>formation irrespective of environmental iron availability. ACS Infect. Dis. 6, <lb/>447-458. doi:10.1021/acsinfecdis.9b00398 <lb/>Soldano, A., Yao, H., Punchi Hewage, A. N. D., Meraz, K., Annor-Gyamfi, J. K., <lb/>Bunce, R. A., et al. (2021). Small molecule inhibitors of the bacterioferritin (BfrB)-<lb/>Ferredoxin (bfd) complex kill biofilm-embedded Pseudomonas aeruginosa cells. ACS <lb/>Infect. Dis. 7, 123-140. doi:10.1021/acsinfecdis.0c00669 <lb/>Weeratunga, S., Gee, C. E., Lovell, S., Zeng, Y., Woodin, C. L., and Rivera, M. (2009). <lb/>Binding of Pseudomonas aeruginosa apobacterioferritin-associated ferredoxin to <lb/>bacterioferritin B promotes heme mediation of electron delivery and mobilization of <lb/>core mineral iron. Biochemistry 48, 7420-7431. doi:10.1021/bi900561a <lb/>Weeratunga, S., Lovell, S., Yao, H., Battaile, K. P., Fischer, C. J., Gee, C. E., et al. (2010). <lb/>Structural studies of bacterioferritin B (BfrB) from Pseudomonas aeruginosa suggest a <lb/>gating mechanism for iron uptake via the ferroxidase center. Biochemistry 49, <lb/>1160-1175. doi:10.1021/bi9015204 <lb/>Wiedenheft, B., Mosolf, J., Willits, D., Yeager, M., Dryden, K. A., Young, M., et al. <lb/>(2005). An archaeal antioxidant: characterization of a Dps-like protein from Sulfolobus <lb/>solfataricus. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102, 10551-10556. doi:10.1073/pnas. <lb/>0501497102 <lb/>Wilderman, P. J., Sowa, N. A., Fitzgerald, D. J., Fitgerald, P. C., Gottesman, S., <lb/>Ochsner, U. A., et al. (2004). Identification of tandem duplicate regulatory small RNAs <lb/>in Pseudomonas aeruginosa involved in iron homeostasis. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. <lb/>101, 9792-9797. doi:10.1073/pnas.0403423101 <lb/>Yao, H., Jepkorir, G., Lovell, S., Nama, P. V., Weeratunga, S. K., Battaille, K. P., et al. <lb/>(2011). Two disctinct ferritin-like molecules in P. aeruginosa: the product of the bfrA <lb/>gene is a bacterial ferritin (FtnA) not a bacterioferritin (bfr). Biochemistry 50, <lb/>5236-5248. doi:10.1021/bi2004119 <lb/>Yao, H., Soldano, A., Fontenot, L., Donnarumma, F., Lovell, S., Chandler, J. R., et al. <lb/>(2022). Pseudomonas aeruginosa bacterioferritin is assembled from FtnA and BfrB <lb/>subunits with the relative proportions dependent on the environmental oxygen <lb/>availability. Biomolecules 12, 366. doi:10.3390/biom12030366 <lb/>Yao, H., Wang, Y., Lovell, S., Kumar, R., Ruvinsky, A. M., Battaile, K. P., et al. (2012). <lb/>The structure of the BfrB-bfd complex reveals protein-protein interactions enabling <lb/>iron release from bacterioferritin. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134, 13470-13481. doi:10.1021/ <lb/>ja305180n <lb/>Zheleznaya, L. A., Kachalova, G. S., Artyukh, R. I., Yunusova, A. K., Perevyazova, T. <lb/>A., and Matvienko, N. I. (2009). Nicking endonucleases. Biochem. (Mosc) 74, <lb/>1457-1466. doi:10.1134/s0006297909130033 <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<page>13 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Rajapaksha et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmolb.2024.1390745 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>