<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T16:32:51.025Z">11/24/2025 4:32:51 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T16:32:34.971552Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T16:32:34.971552Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/cmc.2023.046876 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Real-Time Detection and Instance Segmentation of Strawberry in <lb/>Unstructured Environment <lb/>Chengjun Wang 1,2 , Fan Ding 2,* , Yiwen Wang 1 , Renyuan Wu 1 , Xingyu Yao 2 , Chengjie Jiang 1 and <lb/>Liuyi Ling 1 <lb/>1 School of Artificial Intelligence, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, 232001, China <lb/>2 School of Mechanical Engineering, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, 232001, China <lb/>*Corresponding Author: Fan Ding. Email: 2021200572@aust.edu.cn <lb/>Received: 17 October 2023 Accepted: 20 November 2023 Published: 30 January 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>The real-time detection and instance segmentation of strawberries constitute fundamental components in the <lb/>development of strawberry harvesting robots. Real-time identification of strawberries in an unstructured envi-<lb/>ronment is a challenging task. Current instance segmentation algorithms for strawberries suffer from issues such <lb/>as poor real-time performance and low accuracy. To this end, the present study proposes an Efficient YOLACT <lb/>(E-YOLACT) algorithm for strawberry detection and segmentation based on the YOLACT framework. The key <lb/>enhancements of the E-YOLACT encompass the development of a lightweight attention mechanism, pyramid <lb/>squeeze shuffle attention (PSSA), for efficient feature extraction. Additionally, an attention-guided context-feature <lb/>pyramid network (AC-FPN) is employed instead of FPN to optimize the architecture&apos;s performance. Furthermore, <lb/>a feature-enhanced model (FEM) is introduced to enhance the prediction head&apos;s capabilities, while efficient fast <lb/>non-maximum suppression (EF-NMS) is devised to improve non-maximum suppression. The experimental results <lb/>demonstrate that the E-YOLACT achieves a Box-mAP and Mask-mAP of 77.9 and 76.6, respectively, on the custom <lb/>dataset. Moreover, it exhibits an impressive category accuracy of 93.5%. Notably, the E-YOLACT also demonstrates <lb/>a remarkable real-time detection capability with a speed of 34.8 FPS. The method proposed in this article presents <lb/>an efficient approach for the vision system of a strawberry-picking robot. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>YOLACT; real-time detection; instance segmentation; attention mechanism; strawberry <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The nutritional value of strawberries is abundant, surpassing that of most fruits on the market <lb/>due to their high content of vitamins, carotene, and other essential nutrients. Additionally, strawberries <lb/>possess a robust aroma and a delightful balance between sweetness and sourness, justifying their title as <lb/>the &quot;Queen of Fruits&quot;. Strawberries have a short maturity period and need to be picked in a short time <lb/>after maturity. Picking at the peak of maturity will cause a serious burden to farmers, and strawberry <lb/>picking is a labor-intensive industry [1]. To mitigate picking costs, researchers have developed a <lb/>range of strawberry harvesting robots as substitutes for manual labor [2]. One of the core points of <lb/></body>

	<page>1482 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>the strawberry-picking robot is strawberry detection. Strawberry detection enables the identification <lb/>and localization of target strawberries within a given area, providing precise targets for subsequent <lb/>automated picking. The complexity of the natural environment and the unstructured characteristics <lb/>of the fruit, however, pose significant challenges to strawberry detection [3,4]. The cultivation methods <lb/>for strawberries are primarily categorized into table-top, bench-type, elevated planting mode, and high-<lb/>ridge planting mode [5]. The high ridge planting mode is the predominant method utilized among <lb/>them; However, it has a more complicated picking environment. The superimposition of strawberries <lb/>exhibiting varying degrees of ripeness, as well as the impact of foliage, rhizomes, and other factors on <lb/>strawberry shading and light conditions, significantly influence the detection process of strawberries. <lb/>The detection of strawberries has garnered significant research interest over the past decade. <lb/>The image color segmentation technique employed by Durand-Petiteville et al. is based on a two-<lb/>dimensional color space [6], enabling the accurate separation of strawberries from strawberry clusters. <lb/>The RGB channel-based color threshold algorithm was employed by Xiong et al. for strawberry <lb/>detection [7], yielding an accuracy rate of only 72% with a single image detection time of 2.9 s. <lb/>Zhao et al. [8] employed an edge detection local operator for the extraction of strawberry contour. <lb/>Xu et al. [9] proposed a cascade algorithm combining support vector machine (SVM) and histogram <lb/>of oriented gradients (HOG) for strawberry detection, which extracts and classifies features of <lb/>strawberries with an accuracy rate of 87%. The aforementioned conventional algorithms, including <lb/>threshold segmentation, edge detection, and SVM algorithm, primarily employ feature extraction <lb/>techniques such as strawberry color analysis and edge identification for strawberry recognition. <lb/>However, these algorithms exhibit limited accuracy and robustness while lacking adaptability to <lb/>unstructured environments, rendering them unsuitable for practical strawberry-picking detection. <lb/>The advancement of deep learning has prompted numerous researchers to employ deep learning <lb/>algorithms for strawberry detection. Sun et al. [10] proposed a strawberry detection model based on <lb/>improved YOLOv4-Tiny, using GhostNet [11] as the feature extraction network, and integrating multi-<lb/>scale features to improve the detection accuracy of small targets. The model detection accuracy was <lb/>92.62%, and the single image detection time was 5.63 ms. The Rotating YOLO (You Only Look Once) <lb/>strawberry detection algorithm proposed by Yu et al. [5] achieves an average recognition rate of 94.43% <lb/>and a single image detection time of 55.56 ms. The aforementioned YOLO-based algorithm, however, <lb/>utilizes the bounding box to roughly estimate the approximate position of the strawberry, thereby <lb/>failing to accurately capture its outline and shape features. This limitation is particularly evident in <lb/>cases involving overlapping strawberries where both missed detection and false detection occur. <lb/>The growth pattern of strawberries is characterized by clustered arrangement, resulting in <lb/>occlusion between the rhizomes, leaves, and strawberries themselves. Accurate localization of target <lb/>strawberries during harvesting is of utmost importance. In contrast to semantic segmentation and <lb/>target detection techniques, instance segmentation not only achieves pixel-level classification but also <lb/>enables precise localization of individual instances [12]. Therefore, instance segmentation currently <lb/>represents the most effective algorithm for detecting strawberries. The detection of strawberries <lb/>using Mask-RCNN [13] was initially introduced by Yu et al. [14], who employed ResNet50 as the <lb/>backbone network and integrated feature pyramid network (FPN) for efficient feature extraction. <lb/>Notably, this algorithm achieved a remarkable category detection accuracy of 95.78% alongside a <lb/>segmentation mAP (mean Average Precision) of 45.36. However, the detection speed is only 5 FPS <lb/>(frames per second). To enhance the detection speed, Pérez-Borrero et al. [15] improved the Mask-<lb/>RCNN, which introduces a novel deep learning-based strawberry instance segmentation method. This <lb/>approach eliminates the classifier and bounding box regressor while simplifying the backbone network <lb/>architecture. Additionally, instead of using non-maximum suppression (NMS), they employ a regional <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1483 <lb/></page>

	<body>grouping and filtering algorithm for improved efficiency. These modifications collectively streamline <lb/>the model. Experimental results demonstrate that this method achieves a segmentation mAP of 43.85 <lb/>with a detection speed of 10 FPS. <lb/>The above instance segmentation algorithm, based on Mask RCNN, effectively enhances the accu-<lb/>racy of detection and segmentation. However, its detection speed fails to meet real-time requirements, <lb/>thereby limiting its applicability in strawberry-picking robots. <lb/>To improve the detection speed, Pérez-Borrero et al. [16] proposed a strawberry instance segmen-<lb/>tation approach based on a fully convolutional neural network, which includes both the network itself <lb/>and a grouping filter algorithm. Additionally, by incorporating a centroid prediction network into the <lb/>U-Net algorithm [17] for each strawberry pixel, the segmentation problem is effectively converted into <lb/>a precise pixel-level classification task. Transpose of traditional segmentation algorithms into instance <lb/>segmentation algorithms. The algorithm achieves a seg mAP of 52.61 and operates at a detection <lb/>speed of 30 FPS. However, it cannot accurately classify strawberries, limiting its segmentation category <lb/>exclusively to strawberry instances. <lb/>The YOLACT [18] algorithm is a real-time instance segmentation method that diverges from the <lb/>serial approach of Mask R-CNN, instead employing two parallel subtasks. And generates instance <lb/>masks by predicting distinct coefficients for each instance alongside a shared global mask, thereby <lb/>obviating the necessity for Rol Align in Mask RCNN to generate local feature maps. Compared <lb/>to Mask R-CNN, YOLACT exhibits a qualitative improvement in detection speed and can achieve <lb/>real-time effects. Similar to Mask R-CNN, YOLACT can simultaneously accomplish segmentation, <lb/>detection, and classification tasks; however, the overall detection accuracy is relatively low. <lb/>The attention mechanism can effectively enhance the feature extraction capabilities and is fre-<lb/>quently incorporated into backbone networks to bolster network performance. Numerous researchers <lb/>have employed the attention mechanism in diverse computer vision tasks, including real-time target <lb/>tracking [19,20], image classification [21], and instance segmentation [22]. Zhang et al. [19] proposed <lb/>a novel channel and spatial attention mechanism to capture contextual information, which enhances <lb/>the feature representation of Siamese networks. Chen et al. [21] proposed a parallel mixed attention <lb/>mechanism integrated into ShuffleNet v2 to effectively suppress irrelevant features and enhance the <lb/>model&apos;s classification capability. <lb/>Currently, the real-time detection and segmentation of strawberries remains a formidable chal-<lb/>lenge due to the intricate and unstructured environment as well as the limited data sets available. <lb/>Moreover, the presence of foliage often obscures many nearly ripe strawberries, leading to potential <lb/>misjudgment. Variations in size and shape among strawberries further complicate the accurate <lb/>segmentation process. <lb/>This study applies the speed advantage of YOLACT to real-time instance segmentation of <lb/>strawberries and designs an efficient YOLACT strawberry instance segmentation and detection <lb/>algorithm. The main contributions are as follows: <lb/>(1) A lightweight and efficient attention module called PSSA module is designed and integrated <lb/>into ResNet as the backbone net of E-YOLACT; <lb/>(2) FPN is replaced with AC-FPN [23] to improve feature representation recognition ability; <lb/>(3) FEM is added in the prediction head to further enhance model detection and segmentation <lb/>capabilities; <lb/></body>

	<page>1484 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>(4) Fast-NMS is improved by proposing EF-NMS which effectively reduces the probability of <lb/>missed detections. <lb/>2 Materials and Methods <lb/>2.1 Image Data Acquisition <lb/>The experimental images were collected from March 01 to March 10, 2023, at the strawberry <lb/>plantation located in Xinhua Village, Huainan City, Anhui Province, China. The strawberry plantation <lb/>employs a ridge planting technique and the primary strawberry cultivars include &quot;Hong Yan&quot; and <lb/>&quot;Feng Xiang&quot;, among others, renowned for their vibrant coloration, substantial size, and succulent <lb/>texture. The image acquisition device used in this study is the iPhone 13, as illustrated in Fig. 1. The <lb/>mobile phone was positioned on a shooting frame, which was placed at the center of the ditch. The <lb/>height of the mobile phone from the ground was set to h = 30 ± 15 cm, while the inclination angle <lb/>ranged between θ = 30 ± 15°. Under the shooting parameters of a height range of 30 ± 15 cm <lb/>and an inclination angle range of 30 ± 15°, it aligns with the end effector posture requirements for <lb/>the strawberry-picking robot. In this configuration, not only can the end effector accurately detect <lb/>strawberries, but it also allows for easy adjustment of its position to facilitate efficient strawberry <lb/>picking. A total of 5000 strawberry images were randomly captured at various time periods (morning, <lb/>afternoon, and evening) and under diverse weather conditions in the strawberry plantation. The images <lb/>were stored in JPEG format with a resolution of 4032 × 3042. <lb/>Figure 1: Diagram of the image acquisition process, where h = 30 ± 15 cm and θ = 30 ± 15°, the white <lb/>dotted arrow indicates the main subject <lb/>2.2 Dataset Construction and Annotation <lb/>The custom strawberry dataset was created by randomly selecting 3000 images from the set of <lb/>captured strawberry images, which included 2800 training sets and 200 validation sets. To test the <lb/>algorithm&apos;s universality, the StrawDI_Db1 dataset [16] is used as the test set in our study. The resolu-<lb/>tion of the collected images is excessively high, which may adversely impact computational efficiency. <lb/>Therefore, we resized the images in the dataset to dimensions of 550 * 420 pixels. Utilize Effective <lb/>interactive segmentation (EISeg) [24] for image annotation, manually segmenting each strawberry <lb/>within the images, and categorizing them as ripe or unripe, as depicted in Fig. 2. The EISeg is a high-<lb/>performance tool for interactive segmentation and automatic labeling, which eliminates the need for <lb/>many contour points to extract segmentation objects. By leveraging pre-trained models, the image <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1485 <lb/></page>

	<body>is pre-labeled, enabling fine-tuning of target object edges through positive points (within the target <lb/>object range) and negative points (out-of-range points representing target objects). After comparing <lb/>the segmentation results obtained from various pre-trained models, we have opted for the Deep High-<lb/>Resolution Representation Net18_Object-Contextual Representations48 (HRNet18_OCR48) [25,26] <lb/>static lightweight model architecture. <lb/>Figure 2: The image annotation process. (a) Original image (b) Mask label image (c) Original image <lb/>with mask label <lb/>2.3 Proposed Methodology <lb/>The present study introduces Efficient YOLACT (E-YOLACT), a real-time detection and instance <lb/>segmentation model for strawberry analysis, which is based on the improvement of YOLACT. This <lb/>novel approach effectively discerns between mature and immature strawberries while accurately <lb/>segmenting them. The proposed model framework of E-YOLACT is illustrated in Fig. 3. Compared <lb/>to target detection and semantic segmentation, instance segmentation poses a more challenging task <lb/>as it necessitates simultaneous target position detection, pixel categorization, and target segmentation <lb/>to generate masks. The complexity of the task poses a significant challenge for achieving real-time <lb/>performance in the instance segmentation algorithm, rendering it unsuitable for integration into <lb/>the robot detection system. The E-YOLACT framework utilizes the backbone network for image <lb/>feature extraction and employs the AC-FPN to effectively enhance the receptive field, facilitating <lb/>the detection of multi-scale features. To improve detection speed, two parallel branch networks were <lb/>developed, consisting of Prediction Head and Protone. The Prediction Head branch is utilized to <lb/>generate the confidence, prototype mask coefficient, and anchor location for each candidate frame <lb/>category. Meanwhile, the Protonet branch is employed to generate K prototype masks for each image. <lb/>Finally, the prototype mask and its corresponding coefficient are linearly combined, followed by <lb/>threshold evaluation and output. This approach significantly enhances the model&apos;s inference speed. <lb/>2.3.1 Backbone Structure <lb/>The YOLACT framework utilizes the ResNet101 or ResNet50 backbones for efficient extraction <lb/>of image features, with ResNet101 consisting of 101 layers and ResNet50 comprising 50 layers <lb/>[27]. To optimize computational efficiency and reduce parameter complexity, a Bottleneck module <lb/>is introduced. The design of Bottleneck is illustrated in Fig. 4a. It primarily comprises two 1 × 1 <lb/>convolutions, with a 3 × 3 convolution positioned in the middle. The primary purpose of the 1 × 1 <lb/>convolution is to effectively reduce the feature dimension and minimize computational complexity. <lb/>Taking ResNet50 as an example, Stage 1 comprises three Bottlenecks, while the remaining stages <lb/>consist of four, six, and three Bottlenecks, respectively. In the case of ResNet101, the Stage 1 to Stage <lb/>4 include three, four, twenty-three, and three Bottlenecks, respectively. <lb/></body>

	<page>1486 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 3: The network structure of the E-YOLACT for visual recognition of strawberries <lb/>Figure 4: Illustration and comparison of ResNet and our proposed PSSANet blocks <lb/>To enhance the performance of ResNet while ensuring computational efficiency, the Bottleneck <lb/>architecture was improved and PSSANet Block was proposed. The primary enhancement of the <lb/>PSSANet Block lies in its utilization of the PSSA module to replace the 3 × 3 convolution opera-<lb/>tion. As illustrated in Fig. 4b, this module not only captures spatial information but also extracts <lb/>channel-related features. The ResNet50 model is selected for enhancement in this study, wherein the <lb/>Bottleneck component of ResNet50 is substituted with the PSSANet Block, resulting in the proposal <lb/>of PSSANet50 as the fundamental architecture for the E-YOLACT. <lb/>2.3.2 PSSA Module <lb/>The SE mechanism [28] serves as a channel attention mechanism, enabling the model to dynami-<lb/>cally adjust channel weights and prioritize valuable channel information. However, it solely focuses on <lb/>capturing attention in the channel dimension and fails to incorporate spatial attention. The CBAM <lb/>[29] sequentially integrates the channel attention mechanism and the spatial attention mechanism, <lb/>enabling comprehensive attention to both spatial and channel aspects of the image. However, this <lb/>sequential approach results in each subsequent attention mechanism receiving a modified version of <lb/>its preceding counterpart as the input source. Consequently, feature learning in later stages may be <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1487 <lb/></page>

	<body>influenced by earlier features, while the high computational complexity of CBAM can impact model <lb/>training speed and inference time. <lb/>To extract richer multi-scale features, inspired by the SA (Shuffle Attention) [30] module and <lb/>the Pyramid Squeeze Attention (PSA) [31] module, a lightweight and efficient attention mechanism <lb/>PSSA module is constructed to replace 3 × 3 convolution. The PSSA module is primarily comprised <lb/>of five sequential steps, as illustrated in Fig. 5. Firstly, the SPC module is utilized for channel <lb/>segmentation, followed by conducting multi-scale feature extraction on the feature map of each <lb/>channel. Furthermore, each feature is bifurcated into two branches along the channel dimension; one <lb/>branch is dedicated to acquiring channel attention features, while the other focuses on capturing spatial <lb/>attention features. Specifically, these dual-branch characteristics employ the Channel Attention (CA) <lb/>Weight module and Spatial Attention (SA) Weight module to extract distinct-scale channel attention <lb/>and spatial attention, respectively, thereby obtaining corresponding vectors for each scale. Thirdly, <lb/>the Softmax function is utilized to recalibrate the features of both multi-scale channel and spatial <lb/>attention vectors. Subsequently, each branch obtains its respective attention weight after undergoing <lb/>new interactions with multi-scale channels and spatial information. Fourth, the recalibrated weights <lb/>of the two branches and the corresponding feature maps are element-wise points multiplied, and the <lb/>output is a multi-scale feature information weighted feature value. The features generated by the last <lb/>two branches are fused through Concat to generate a feature map with both channel attention and <lb/>spatial attention weighting. The feature map has richer multi-scale information capabilities. <lb/>Figure 5: The structure of the proposed Pyramid Squeeze Shuffle Attention (PSSA) module <lb/>The SPC operator is utilized for accomplishing multi-scale feature extraction. The design of the <lb/>SPC operator is illustrated in Fig. 6. Its underlying principle involves targeting the input feature map <lb/>X and initially dividing it into [X 0 , X 1 ,..., X S-1 ], comprising a total of S parts, and the number of <lb/>channels in each part is C&apos; = C/S. Each part of the feature map uses multi-scale convolution kernel <lb/>group convolution to extract feature information of different scales. Group convolution is mainly used <lb/>to reduce the number of parameters, and the size of the Group is adaptively selected according to <lb/>the size of the convolution kernel. The specific calculation method of SPC for multi-scale features is <lb/>presented in formula (1), while the size of the convolution kernel and the Group calculation formula <lb/>are illustrated in formula (2), respectively. <lb/>F i = Conv (K i × K i , G i ) (X i ) , i = 0, 1, 2, • • •, S -1 <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

	<page>1488 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>K i = 2 × (i + 1) + 1, F i ∈ R C ×H×W <lb/>G = 2 <lb/>K-1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>Figure 6: The proposed Squeeze and Concat (SPC) module. The symbol K denotes the size of the <lb/>convolution kernel, G represents the group size, and F signifies the feature <lb/>The SPC module is utilized for acquiring the multi-feature module F i , which is subsequently <lb/>partitioned into F 1i and F 2i based on the channel dimension. The two branches are sent to the channel <lb/>attention module and spatial attention module in parallel to extract the weights associated with spatial <lb/>attention and channel attention. The calculation formula for extracting the weights of F 1i and F 2i is <lb/>denoted as the formula (3). <lb/>Z 1i = CAWeight (F 1i ) , F 1i ∈ R C × H × W <lb/>Z 2i = SAWeight (F 2i ) , F 2i ∈ R C ×H×W <lb/>, C = <lb/>C <lb/>2 <lb/>(3) <lb/>Z 1 = Z 10 ⊕ Z 11 ⊕ • • • ⊕ Z 1S-1 <lb/>Z 2 = Z 20 ⊕ Z 21 ⊕ • • • ⊕ Z 2S-1 <lb/>(4) <lb/>In formulas (3) and (4), the symbol Z 1i and Z 2i represent weights for channel attention and spatial <lb/>attention, respectively; Z 1 and Z 2 represent the complete multi-scale channel attention vector and <lb/>spatial attention vector obtained by concatenating all multi-scale attention vectors; represents the <lb/>concatenation operator. <lb/>The design of the CA Weight module and the SA Weight module is illustrated in Figs. 7a and 7b, <lb/>respectively. The role of the CA Weight module is to weigh the importance of each channel to generate <lb/>more information. First, use global average pooling to embed global information, and generate a 1 <lb/>× 1 × C vector. Subsequently, excitation operations [28] are performed to generate attention weights <lb/>for individual channels. The SA Weight module is mainly used to weigh the importance of spatial <lb/>information. Complementary to channel attention, first use the Group Normbalization (GN) [32] to <lb/>perform normalization processing to obtain spatial statistics, and then perform excitation operations <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1489 <lb/></page>

	<body>to generate spatial attention weights. The calculation formulas of CA and SA Weights are shown in <lb/>formulas (5) and (6). <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎪ ⎨ <lb/>⎪ ⎩ <lb/>g c = <lb/>1 <lb/>H × W <lb/>H <lb/>k=1 <lb/>W <lb/>j=1 <lb/>F 1i (k, j) <lb/>w CA = σ (W 1 δ (W 0 (g c ))) <lb/>(5) <lb/>w SA = σ (W 3 δ (W 2 (GN (F 2i )))) <lb/>(6) <lb/>Figure 7: Weight module structure. (a) CA Weight module, (b) SA Weight module <lb/>In the above formula, the symbol g c represents the global average operator, W 0 -W 3 represents the <lb/>fully connected layer (FC), σ represents the Sigmoid activation function, δ represents the use of the <lb/>Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) operation [33]. <lb/>Apply the softmax function to recalibrate and derive new weights, att 1i and att 2i , for the interaction <lb/>between local and global attention. <lb/>att 1i = Softmax (Z 1i ) = <lb/>exp (Z 1i ) <lb/>S-1 <lb/>i=0 exp (Z 1i ) <lb/>att 2i = Softmax (Z 2i ) = <lb/>exp (Z 2i ) <lb/>S-1 <lb/>i=0 exp (Z 2i ) <lb/>(7) <lb/>Subsequently, the newly obtained multi-scale attention weights att 1i and att 2i are multiplied with <lb/>their corresponding features F 1i and F 2i respectively along the channel dimension to generate novel <lb/>feature representations. <lb/>Y 1i = F 1i att 1i <lb/>Y 2i = F 2i att 2i <lb/>(8) <lb/>where, represents the channel-wise multiplication, the features Y 1i and Y 2i represent novel charac-<lb/>teristics incorporating multi-scale channel attention weights and multi-scale spatial domain attention <lb/>weights, respectively. <lb/>The two novel characteristics are subsequently concatenated to generate a feature Y i encom-<lb/>passing multi-scale channels and spatial attention weights. Subsequently, the features Y i from each <lb/>component are combined to produce the overall feature Y . The Y represents the feature map with <lb/>multi-scale channels and spatial attention weights generated by the PSSA module. <lb/>Y i = Cat ([Y 1i , Y 2i ]) <lb/>(9) <lb/>Y = Cat ([Y 0 , Y 1 , • • •, Y i ]) <lb/>(10) <lb/></body>

	<page>1490 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>The model complexity (i.e., network parameters and FLOPs) of PSSANet and ResNet was <lb/>compared. The parameter amount and FLOPs of PSSANet are 1.2 M and 0.14 G lower than those <lb/>of ResNet, as presented in Table 1. This comparison demonstrates that PSSANet exhibits a lighter <lb/>computational load and demands fewer training resources. <lb/>Table 1: Comparisons of different attention methods on ImageNet-1k in terms of network parameters <lb/>(Param.), and floating-point operations per second (FLOPs) <lb/>Network <lb/>Backbone <lb/>Param./M <lb/>FLOPs/G <lb/>ResNet [27] <lb/>ResNet-50 <lb/>25.56 <lb/>4.12 <lb/>PSSANet (Our) <lb/>24.76 <lb/>3.98 <lb/>2.3.3 AC-FPN <lb/>FPN combines low-resolution features with large receptive fields and high-resolution features <lb/>with small receptive fields to detect objects at different scales by introducing a top-down pathway <lb/>[34]. However, the top-down pathway merely incorporates additional layers to expand the receptive <lb/>field without facilitating effective information dissemination, thereby impeding intercommunication <lb/>of semantic information captured by diverse receptive fields in FPN and subsequently impacting <lb/>performance. <lb/>To address the challenge of achieving effective communication between multi-scale structural <lb/>fields and ensuring the acquisition of appropriate receptive fields during high-resolution input, the <lb/>FPN model was substituted with the AC-FPN. The AC-FPN architecture primarily consists of the <lb/>CEM module and AM module, as illustrated in Fig. 8 [19]. The C5 feature is initially split into two <lb/>pathways and fed into the dual branches of CEM, wherein one branch consists of dilated convolutions <lb/>with varying expansion rates to extract features from different receptive fields. The other branch <lb/>performs an upsampling operation on C5 to preserve the coarse-grained information of the initial <lb/>input. Then perform a concat operation on the output of the two branches. The utilization of CEM can <lb/>enhance contextual information and facilitate the detection of objects at multiple scales. To mitigate <lb/>the superfluous contextual information generated by CEM, AC-FPN introduces the AM module, <lb/>which primarily captures context correlations through the utilization of a self-attention mechanism. <lb/>The C5 is initially processed by both the CEM and AM modules, followed by the fusion of its <lb/>original features to generate P5. Referring to RetinaNet [35], P2 is not generated, P5 is enlarged by <lb/>bilinear interpolation and added to C4 after 1 × 1 convolution to obtain P4. In the same way, P3 <lb/>is obtained. The P6 feature map is obtained by convolving the P5 feature map and subsequently <lb/>convolving the P6 feature map to derive the P7 feature map. Utilizing AC-FPN not only ensures <lb/>enhanced robustness of the mask generated by Protont but also resolves information propagation <lb/>challenges across distinct receptive fields, thereby improving model performance. <lb/>2.3.4 Enhanced Prediction Head <lb/>To enhance detection speed, YOLACT simplifies the prediction head and incorporates the concept <lb/>of shared convolution. Although this design reduces model performance, it effectively promotes <lb/>computational efficiency. Therefore, FEM is designed and integrated into the prediction head to <lb/>improve model performance at a slight cost of increased detection time. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1491 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 8: The structure of the AC-FPN <lb/>The feature enhancement module consists primarily of three sets of dilated convolutions with <lb/>varying layers, drawing inspiration from the RFB [36]. As shown in Fig. 9, the output of the 3 × 3 <lb/>convolution is utilized as the input for the FEM, and initially, feature normalization is performed <lb/>through a 1 × 1 convolution. Subsequently, the feature map is divided into three segments and <lb/>individually fed into three branches comprising dilated convolutions with varying layers. The features <lb/>of the three branches are ultimately integrated through a cascading process. The FEM employs <lb/>dilated convolution to effectively expand the receptive field, thereby circumventing issues such as <lb/>resolution reduction and information loss induced by downsampling. Utilizing the FEM can enhance <lb/>the network&apos;s ability to extract information and ensure the generation of high-resolution feature maps, <lb/>thereby optimizing the positioning and segmentation accuracy of the prediction head. <lb/>Figure 9: The proposed Feature Enhanced Model (FEM) <lb/></body>

	<page>1492 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>2.3.5 Loss Function <lb/>The Loss function is utilized to quantify the disparity between the predicted value of the model <lb/>and the ground truth. The loss function evaluates the disparity between the predicted outcome and <lb/>the actual label, subsequently providing feedback to the model through backpropagation to optimize <lb/>parameters and weights. The smaller the value of the loss function, the greater the model&apos;s robustness <lb/>and performance. To effectively optimize the training outcomes of the model, it is crucial to employ <lb/>diverse types of loss functions tailored for specific tasks. The present study employs a combined <lb/>loss function L, which consists of linearly weighted classification L cls , mask L mask , and bounding box <lb/>regression L box , to train the model. The definitions and calculations of L box and L cls are identical to <lb/>those of L conf (x, c) and L loc(x, l, g) [37]. <lb/>L mask = BCE M, M gt <lb/>(11) <lb/>Among them, the M represents the preassembled mask, the M gt denotes the ground truth mask, <lb/>and pixel-wise binary classification cross-entropy is employed to compute the loss at a per-pixel level. <lb/>L box = <lb/>N <lb/>i∈Pos m∈{cx,cy,w,h} <lb/>x k <lb/>ij smooth L1 I m <lb/>j -<lb/>∧ <lb/>g <lb/>m <lb/>j <lb/>(12) <lb/>L cls = -<lb/>N <lb/>i∈Pos <lb/>x p <lb/>ij log <lb/>∧ <lb/>c p <lb/>i <lb/>-<lb/>i∈Neg <lb/>log <lb/>∧ <lb/>c 0 <lb/>i <lb/>(13) <lb/>smooth L1 = <lb/>0.5x 2 <lb/>|x| -0.5 <lb/>if |x| &lt; 1 <lb/>otherwise <lb/>(14) <lb/>∧ <lb/>c p <lb/>i = <lb/>exp <lb/>∧ <lb/>c p <lb/>i <lb/>p exp <lb/>∧ <lb/>c p <lb/>i <lb/>(15) <lb/>L = L cls + L box + L mask <lb/>(16) <lb/>Among them, the i is the prediction box, the g is the ground truth. (cx, xy) is the center of the <lb/>default box d after compensation (regress to offsets), and (w, h) is the width and height of the default <lb/>box. The utilization of the smooth L1 loss effectively mitigates the issue of gradient explosion during <lb/>the initial stages of training. Additionally, the c represents the softmax loss in a multi-class confidence <lb/>scenario. <lb/>2.3.6 Efficient Fast NMS <lb/>The NMS algorithm [38] is employed to suppress non-maximum elements and identify local <lb/>maximum values. During the evaluation of the detection model, redundant prediction frames can <lb/>be effectively eliminated through the utilization of NMS. After the conventional NMS generates the <lb/>regression coefficients for bounding boxes and category confidences, it computes the intersection over <lb/>union (IoU) between the prediction box with the highest confidence and other prediction boxes. <lb/>It removes all prediction boxes with an IoU greater than a specified threshold and subsequently <lb/>selects the prediction box with the highest confidence among those that remain. This process is <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1493 <lb/></page>

	<body>repeated iteratively by calculating IoU between each remaining prediction box until convergence. <lb/>The Fast NMS proposed by YOLACT aims to simplify the traditional NMS by employing matrix <lb/>parallel elimination of prediction boxes, thereby reducing computational load. However, this approach <lb/>inadvertently eliminates overlapping instances in the prediction frames, leading to a decline in <lb/>detection performance. <lb/>The present article proposes an EF-NMS based on Fast NMS, wherein the initial step involves <lb/>the computation of a c × n × n matrix to determine the IoU value. The first n detections are sorted in <lb/>descending order based on the confidence score for each category, and the IoU value is computed <lb/>between each predicted bounding box. We assign a value of 0 to the lower triangle and diagonal <lb/>elements of matrix X, while retaining the prediction box with the highest confidence. The maximum <lb/>IoU value is then obtained based on the column, and for prediction boxes that exceed the predefined <lb/>IoU threshold N t , their confidence scores are linearly reduced using a weighted approach. The specific <lb/>formula for linear weighting is presented in formula (17). Finally, prediction boxes with confidence <lb/>scores below the threshold S t are eliminated. <lb/>S i = <lb/>S i <lb/>S i (1 -IoU (M i , b i )) , <lb/>IoU (M i , b i ) &lt; N t <lb/>IoU (M i , b i ) ≥ N t <lb/>(17) <lb/>where, the symbol i denotes the number of iterations performed by the loop on each occasion. The <lb/>symbol b i denotes the prediction box to be evaluated in the i-th iteration, M i represents the highest <lb/>confidence in the i-th iteration, and S i represents the confidence score of b i in the i-th iteration. <lb/>3 Experiments and Results <lb/>3.1 Experimental Setting and Evaluation Metrics <lb/>The experimental hardware platform consists of an Intel(R) Core (TM) i7-12700KF CPU and <lb/>a GeForce RTX 3060 NVIDIA GPU. The server system employed is Ubuntu 20, while the model is <lb/>developed using the PyTorch 1.12 framework in conjunction with the Python programming language. <lb/>The input image resolution is set to 550 × 420, with an initial learning rate of 0.001. Additionally, <lb/>a weight decay of 5 × 10 -4 and a momentum value of 0.9 are employed in the training process. <lb/>Furthermore, the learning rate is adjusted by multiplying it by 0.1 at iterations 28000, 36000, and <lb/>40000, respectively. <lb/>The evaluation of the model in this article primarily employs commonly utilized performance <lb/>metrics such as mean average precision (mAP), AP50, and AP75. The calculation of mAP involves <lb/>computing the average value of APs across different categories. The AP50 and AP75 metrics corre-<lb/>spond to the AP values obtained at IoU thresholds of 50 and 75, respectively. The calculation of AP <lb/>is intricately linked to the concepts of precision (P) and recall (R). Specifically, AP quantifies the area <lb/>under the precision-recall curve (P(R)). Precision represents the proportion of samples that are positive <lb/>among the samples that are predicted to be positive. Recall indicates that the prediction result is the <lb/>proportion of the actual number of positive samples in the positive sample to the total number of <lb/>positive samples in the total sample. The calculation formulas of Precision and Recall are shown in <lb/>formulas (18) and (19), respectively. <lb/>Precision = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FP <lb/>(18) <lb/></body>

	<page>1494 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Recall = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FN <lb/>(19) <lb/>AP = <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>P (R) dR <lb/>(20) <lb/>where, the TP means True positive, the FP means False positive, and the FN means False negative. the <lb/>P(R) represents the P(R) curve. <lb/>In the detection task, our given sample classification needs to be combined with the IoU threshold, <lb/>which quantifies the degree of overlap between two boundaries. The calculation of IoU is illustrated <lb/>in Fig. 10. <lb/>Figure 10: The definition of IoU <lb/>3.2 Results of Strawberry Detection and Segmentation <lb/>To validate the performance of the proposed E-YOLACT algorithm for strawberry detection <lb/>and instance segmentation, a total of 200 strawberry images were utilized for rigorous testing and <lb/>evaluation. The comprehensive results are presented in Tables 2 to 4. The visualization of three <lb/>representative strawberry images is illustrated in Fig. 11. <lb/>Table 2: COCO AP results with different models in this study on custom dataset <lb/>Method <lb/>mAP (%) <lb/>AP 50 (%) <lb/>AP 75 (%) <lb/>YOLACT <lb/>64.4 <lb/>89.1 <lb/>69.9 <lb/>Box <lb/>YOLACT++ <lb/>71.4 <lb/>90.6 <lb/>79.7 <lb/>Mask-RCNN <lb/>76.9 <lb/>91.7 <lb/>84.7 <lb/>E-YOLACT <lb/>77.9 <lb/>94.5 <lb/>88.7 <lb/>YOLACT <lb/>62.2 <lb/>87.8 <lb/>64.7 <lb/>Mask YOLACT++ <lb/>68.4 <lb/>89.2 <lb/>76.4 <lb/>Mask-RCNN <lb/>78.7 <lb/>94.6 <lb/>89.4 <lb/>E-YOLACT <lb/>76.6 <lb/>93.6 <lb/>88.3 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1495 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 3: Precision rate with different models in this study on custom dataset <lb/>Method <lb/>Precision (%) <lb/>Ripe <lb/>Unripe <lb/>Overall <lb/>YOLACT <lb/>94.7 <lb/>88.7 <lb/>91.7 <lb/>YOLACT++ <lb/>95.6 <lb/>87.6 <lb/>91.6 <lb/>Mask-RCNN <lb/>95.3 <lb/>89.6 <lb/>92.5 <lb/>E-YOLACT <lb/>96.5 <lb/>90.47 <lb/>93.5 <lb/>Table 4: FPS with different models in this study on custom dataset <lb/>Evaluation <lb/>parameter <lb/>Method <lb/>YOLACT YOLACT++ Mask-RCNN E-YOLACT <lb/>FPS <lb/>42.3 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>9.7 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>Figure 11: Detection results of three representative strawberry images using different instance seg-<lb/>mentation models. The column of original is images of strawberries in unstructured environments for <lb/>different cases. Mask R-CNN is the result of mask R-CNN algorithm detection. YOLACT is the <lb/>result of detection by the original YOLACT algorithm. The E-YOLACT is the result of the algorithm <lb/>detection proposed in this article <lb/>As depicted in Fig. 11, the three images (a) to (c) depict distinct growth conditions of strawberries. <lb/>These images serve as representative examples of challenging strawberry detection scenarios and <lb/>effectively evaluate the model&apos;s performance. The strawberries in (a) have different sizes, which can <lb/></body>

	<page>1496 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>be effectively used to test the model&apos;s ability to detect multi-scale objects. While employing the Mask <lb/>R-CNN algorithm, there are instances of misdetections where a single strawberry is segmented into <lb/>two separate entities; However, Mask R-CNN accurately segmented the edges of the strawberries <lb/>for those instances that were correctly detected. Although YOLACT does not have the problem of <lb/>false detection compared to Mask R-CNN, its segmentation accuracy is extremely low, and cannot <lb/>accurately segment the edges of strawberries in the detection frame. The E-YOLACT effectively avoids <lb/>the issue of false detection encountered by Mask R-CNN and can accurately segment the edges <lb/>of each strawberry. In (b), each strawberry is superimposed and exhibits uniform size. Overlapping <lb/>strawberries are easily detected as a single entity; both Mask R-CNN and YOLACT erroneously detect <lb/>the overlapping strawberries as one, whereas the E-YOLACT is capable of effectively and accurately <lb/>segmenting each overlapping strawberry, demonstrating its proficiency in accurately segmenting and <lb/>detecting overlapping objects. In (c), the strawberries are mainly concentrated at the edge of the image, <lb/>exhibiting a uniform green color similar to that of the background. Additionally, some strawberries <lb/>are partially obscured by leaves and petals, which may lead to potential misidentification as part of <lb/>the background. Despite the satisfactory performance of Mask R-CNN in contour segmentation, <lb/>it still exhibits missed detections and fails to capture small strawberries concealed by petals. however, <lb/>YOLACT can detect strawberries covered by petals, but the segmentation accuracy needs improvement <lb/>as the generated mask fails to fully encompass the entire strawberry. The E-YOLACT can effectively <lb/>and accurately detect each strawberry in the picture and segment it accurately. Although there are very <lb/>few strawberries that are not completely covered by the mask, it has been greatly improved compared <lb/>to YOLACT. <lb/>3.3 Comparison with Other Instance Segmentation Methods <lb/>To further analyze the performance of the E-YOLACT model proposed in this article, we <lb/>employ evaluation metrics including AP, AP50, AP75, FPS, and category accuracy. Additionally, <lb/>a comparative analysis will be conducted with classic instance segmentation algorithms such as <lb/>YOLACT, YOLACT++, and Mask-RCNN. The four models were trained and assessed using the <lb/>same dataset and experimental conditions, as well as a standardized test set. The parameter results <lb/>are presented in Tables 2 to 4. In the strawberry image test conducted, the Box-map values of original <lb/>YOLACT, YOLACT++, and Mask RCNN were 64.4, 71.4, and 76.9, respectively; however, the E-<lb/>YOLACT achieved a Box-map value of 77.9 which is higher than all classic algorithms mentioned <lb/>above. Compared to the original YOLACT, the E-YOLACT showed an improvement of nearly 21%. <lb/>Additionally, the E-YOLACT also outperformed the above-mentioned classic algorithms in terms of <lb/>Box-AP50 and Box-AP75. However, upon comparing the Mask-map values, it is evident that Mask-<lb/>RCNN achieves the highest performance with a score of 78.7, while YOLACT and YOLACT++ <lb/>attain scores of 62.2 and 68.4, respectively, both falling short of surpassing the 70 mark. Despite the <lb/>E-YOLACT&apos;s lower Mask-map value compared to Mask RCNN, it still exhibits a commendable score <lb/>of 76.6, significantly higher than that of YOLACT and YOLACT++. The same trend can be observed <lb/>for AP50 and AP75 metrics. <lb/>Although Mask RCNN&apos;s average precision (AP) score is commendable, its FPS falls significantly <lb/>behind the other three algorithms, with a mere 9.7. In contrast, the YOLACT achieves a maximum FPS <lb/>of 42.3, while both YOLACT++ and the E-YOLACT exhibit comparable performance with respective <lb/>FPS values of 35.6 and 34.8, effectively meeting the real-time detection requirements. Regarding <lb/>Category Precision, including ripe Precision, unripe Precision, and comprehensive Precision, all four <lb/>algorithms achieve a performance exceeding 90%, with the E-YOLACT achieving the highest scores <lb/>of 96.5%, 90.47%, and 93.5%, respectively. Furthermore, as depicted in Fig. 11, it is evident that the <lb/>E-YOLACT effectively distinguishes ripe strawberries. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1497 <lb/></page>

	<body>Compared with YOLACT, although the calculation amount and model size of E-YOLACYT <lb/>increase, and the detection speed decreases, the performance of the model has been greatly improved. <lb/>The performance of the E-YOLACYT model can reach or even exceed Mask RCNN. The detection <lb/>speed, although not comparable to that of YOLACT, significantly surpasses that of Mask RCNN. <lb/>Among strawberry instance segmentation models with equivalent performance, the E-YOLACT <lb/>exhibits the highest detection speed. <lb/>3.4 Ablation Experiments <lb/>To validate the efficacy of various modules and methods proposed in this study for enhancing the <lb/>performance of YOLACT, the PSSANet50, AC-FPN, FEM, and EF-NMS are sequentially integrated <lb/>into the YOLACT framework. The evaluation is conducted based on three metrics: Box-mAP, Mask-<lb/>mAP, and FPS. The experimental results are presented in Table 5. When we replaced ResNet50 with <lb/>PSSANet50 integrated with the PSSA module, despite a decrease in FPS by 2.7, both Box-mAP <lb/>and Mask-mAP increased by 6.1 and 9.1, respectively. This substantiates the efficacy of the PSSA <lb/>module in enhancing feature extraction capabilities; After replacing FPN with AC-FPN, the Box-<lb/>mAP and Mask-mAP of the model exhibited a respective increase of 3.8 and 2.4. However, there <lb/>was a corresponding decrease in FPS by 3.4. The utilization of AC-FPN effectively augmented the <lb/>receptive field and enhanced model performance. The performance enhancement is relatively modest <lb/>when compared to the decrease in speed; The introduction of the EFM module in the prediction <lb/>head resulted in a negligible 0.6 drop in model FPS, indicating minimal impact on detection speed. <lb/>However, both Box-mAP and Mask-mAP exhibited a significant increase of 2.1. By adopting the <lb/>EF-NMS instead of Fast-NMS as proposed in this study, the model&apos;s Box-mAP increased by 1.5 <lb/>and the Mask-mAP improved by 0.8, thereby enhancing the efficiency of NMS. However, employing <lb/>EF-NMS resulted in a decrease of 0.8 FPS for the model, which did affect detection speed but with <lb/>negligible significance. In conclusion, it is evident that each module and method proposed in this article <lb/>significantly enhances the performance of the YOLACT model. <lb/>Table 5: Ablation study of each component in our proposed method on custom dataset <lb/>PSSANet50 <lb/>AC-FPN <lb/>FEM <lb/>EF-NMS Box-mAP Mask-mAP FPS <lb/>64.4 <lb/>62.2 <lb/>42.3 <lb/>√ <lb/>70.5 <lb/>71.3 <lb/>39.6 <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>74.3 <lb/>73.7 <lb/>36.2 <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>76.4 <lb/>75.8 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>√ <lb/>77.9 <lb/>76.6 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>The existing strawberry instance segmentation algorithm faces several challenges, with real-time <lb/>performance being the most critical one. For instance, references [14,15] proposed the strawberry <lb/>instance segmentation model based on Mask-RCNN, achieving frame rates of 5 and 10 FPS, <lb/>respectively, which fall significantly short of meeting real-time requirements. Although the strawberry <lb/>segmentation algorithm proposed by [16] can reach 30 FPS, meeting the temporal constraints, its appli-<lb/>cability is limited to strawberry segmentation only. However, the strawberry-picking robot requires <lb/>the ability to determine whether the strawberries are ripe during the picking process. We propose <lb/></body>

	<page>1498 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>an advanced algorithm called E-YOLACT for strawberry detection and instance segmentation. This <lb/>algorithm not only fulfills the real-time requirements of the vision system employed by the strawberry-<lb/>picking robot but also effectively identifies whether strawberries are ripe. <lb/>The E-YOLACT is an improved version of YOLACT, it is a one-stage algorithm that boasts a <lb/>simpler model architecture compared to the two-stage Mask RCNN, resulting in significantly faster <lb/>detection speeds. However, comparative experiments have shown that YOLACT&apos;s performance falls <lb/>short of that achieved by Mask RCNN. To enhance performance, we propose the PSSA module and <lb/>integrate it into ResNet to augment the performance of YOLACT. The PSSA module effectively <lb/>incorporates both spatial and channel information during feature extraction, thereby enhancing <lb/>Backbone&apos;s feature extraction capability, and the model complexity of PSSANet is lower than ResNet, <lb/>but it uses multiple parallel branches spliced with concat. Although accuracy improves, the number <lb/>of branches affects the GPU&apos;s parallel computing rate and efficiency. Element-wise operation reduces <lb/>FLOPs but occupies GPU computing time. As can be seen from Fig. 11, YOLACT, YOLACT++, <lb/>and Mask RCNN will miss detection when detecting overlapping strawberries. Considering this issue <lb/>arises due to NMS, we have made enhancements based on Fast-NMS and proposed the EF-NMS. Our <lb/>ablation experiments demonstrate that the EF-NMS model significantly improves performance. Fur-<lb/>thermore, in conjunction with Fig. 11, the E-YOLACT equipped with the EF-NMS effectively detects <lb/>overlapping strawberries. However, it is evident from Fig. 11 that the segmentation performance of the <lb/>E-YOLACT falls short compared to Mask RCNN, with some strawberry masks exhibiting incomplete <lb/>coverage. The majority of these strawberries are situated at the periphery of the image and primarily <lb/>consist of unripe ones. Although this situation occurs relatively infrequently, it can result in positioning <lb/>errors for mature strawberries due to inadequate segmentation accuracy. Consequently, it hampers the <lb/>robot&apos;s ability to reach the ideal picking point during strawberry harvesting, leading to unsuccessful <lb/>picking or even surface damage to the strawberries. The effectiveness of the E-YOLACT in identifying <lb/>mature strawberries can be observed in Table 4 and Fig. 11. Although there are occasional errors in <lb/>strawberry identification, the primary misjudgment occurs when mature strawberries are mistakenly <lb/>classified as immature ones due to the similarities between some unripe and ripe strawberries. However, <lb/>since the strawberry-picking robot only selects ripe strawberries during harvesting, this does not impact <lb/>the practical application of the model, the missed ripe strawberries may rot and cause economic losses <lb/>if they are not picked for a long time. <lb/>The E-YOLACT model, similar to YOLACT, employs a one-stage instance segmentation <lb/>approach, which effectively minimizes computational overhead and ensures efficient object detection <lb/>speed. The E-YOLACT framework adopts PSSANet50, as proposed in this article, instead of <lb/>ResNet50. PSSANet50 incorporates both channel and spatial attention mechanisms, enabling effective <lb/>multi-scale feature extraction. In comparison to ResNet50, it exhibits superior capabilities in extracting <lb/>features. The FEM module is incorporated into the prediction head of the E-YOLACT, addressing the <lb/>issue of diminished detection and segmentation performance resulting from the shared convolution <lb/>employed in YOLCAT prediction. However, it should be noted that the segmentation performance still <lb/>falls short when compared to Mask-RCNN. The EF-NMS algorithm employed in the E-YOLACT <lb/>employs multiple iterations to effectively suppress overlapping boxes, thereby mitigating the issue <lb/>of false detections encountered in Mask-RCNN and YOLACT (multiple overlapping strawberries <lb/>are erroneously identified as a single entity). In conclusion, the E-YOLACT demonstrates effective <lb/>real-time detection of strawberries in an unstructured environment. <lb/>Despite improvements in the E-YOLACT&apos;s performance through module integration and refine-<lb/>ment, it still incurs additional time costs and is limited to high computational load GPUs due to <lb/>its large network model parameters. Additionally, accurately detecting strawberry ripeness remains <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1499 <lb/></page>

	<body>a challenge. The lightweight network models are characterized by low complexity and high com-<lb/>putational efficiency. For example, Chen et al. [21] proposed a lightweight garbage classification <lb/>model GCNet with only 1.3 M parameters, achieving an impressive detection time of only 105 <lb/>ms. Considering the benefits of lightweight networks, we propose integrating the PSSA model into <lb/>ShuffleNet or MobileNet as the backbone network in future research to effectively reduce model <lb/>complexity while ensuring accuracy. Moreover, the segmentation performance of the E-YOLACT <lb/>has not met expectations. To address this concern, we propose integrating FPN input features with <lb/>other layers to fuse shallow and deep features, aiming to enhance overall segmentation performance by <lb/>alleviating feature information loss caused by occluded strawberries. The accuracy of the E-YOLACT <lb/>in detecting low-maturity strawberry categories is relatively limited. To address this issue, we plan to <lb/>enhance the prediction head by incorporating a lightweight attention mechanism or feature classifier <lb/>module specifically designed to emphasize strawberry color information. <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>The E-YOLACT model is proposed in this paper to address the real-time detection and segmen-<lb/>tation of strawberries in unstructured environments. To enhance the feature extraction capabilities of <lb/>the backbone network, we propose the PSSA attention mechanism and integrate it into the Bottleneck <lb/>of ResNet, thereby effectively optimizing the extraction capabilities of spatial and channel features. To <lb/>solve the problem of communication obstruction between semantic information of different receptive <lb/>fields in FPN, we introduced AC-FPN. To mitigate the potential reduction in detection performance <lb/>caused by YOLACT&apos;s shared convolution-based prediction head, we propose the integration of <lb/>the FEM based on multi-layer dilated convolution to bolster the predictive capabilities. To address <lb/>the missed detection problem caused by Fast NMS, we propose the EF-NMS as a solution that <lb/>effectively enhances the performance of prediction boxes. Compared to the original YOLACT, the <lb/>E-YOLACT demonstrates superior performance in detection and segmentation. Specifically, the E-<lb/>YOLACT achieves box mAP scores of 77.9, 94.5, and 88.7 for AP50 and, AP75, respectively; mask <lb/>mAP scores of 76.6, 93.6, and 88.3 for AP50, AP75, respectively; category accuracy of 93.5%; and the <lb/>model&apos;s FPS up to 34.8. The E-YOLACT proposed in this article effectively detects and segments <lb/>strawberries; however, it cannot currently digitally assess strawberry maturity. It can only classify <lb/>extreme ripeness and immaturity, and the network model of the E-YOLACT is slightly larger with <lb/>room for improvement in segmentation accuracy. The future work aims to achieve maturity detection <lb/>and further streamline the network model while enhancing its performance. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: We express our gratitude to the members of the Strawberry-Picking Robot Research <lb/>Team from the School of Artificial Intelligence, Anhui University of Science and Technology for their <lb/>invaluable advice and assistance throughout this study. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: This research was funded by Anhui Provincial Natural Science Foundation <lb/>(No. 2208085ME128); the Anhui University-Level Special Project of Anhui University of Science <lb/>and Technology (No. XCZX2021-01); the Research and the Development Fund of the Institute <lb/>of Environmental Friendly Materials and Occupational Health, Anhui University of Science and <lb/>Technology (No. ALW2022YF06); and Anhui Province New Era Education Quality Project (Graduate <lb/>Education) (No. 2022xscx073). <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Study conception and design: Chengjun Wang, Fan Ding, Yiwen Wang; writing-<lb/>original draft: Chengjun Wang, Fan Ding; methodology: Chengjun Wang, Fan Ding; writing-review <lb/>&amp; editing: Yiwen Wang, Renyuan Wu; data curation: Renyuan Wu, Xingyu Yao; validation: Yiwen <lb/></div>

	<page>1500 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">Wang, Chengjie Jiang, Liuyi Ling; project administration: Renyuan Wu, Liuyi Ling. All authors <lb/>reviewed the results and approved the final version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: The data that support the findings of this study are available from <lb/>the corresponding author upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] L. Jie, S. Jiao, X. Wang and H. Wang, &quot;A new type of facility strawberry stereoscopic cultivation mode,&quot; <lb/>China Agricult, vol. 24, no. 2, pp. 61-68, 2019. <lb/>[2] S. Yamamoto, S. Hayashi, H. Yoshida and K. Kobayashi, &quot;Development of a stationary robotic strawberry <lb/>harvester with a picking mechanism that approaches the target fruit from below,&quot; Japan Agricultural <lb/>Research Quarterly, vol. 48, no. 3, pp. 261-269, 2014. <lb/>[3] C. W. Bac, E. J. Henten, J. Hemming and Y. Edan, &quot;Harvesting robots for high-value crops: State-of-the-art <lb/>review and challenges ahead,&quot; Journal of Field Robotics, vol. 31, no. 6, pp. 888-911, 2014. <lb/>[4] D. I. Patrício and R. Rieder, &quot;Computer vision and artificial intelligence in precision agriculture for grain <lb/>crops: A systematic review,&quot; Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, vol. 153, pp. 69-81, 2018. <lb/>[5] Y. Yu, K. Zhang, H. Liu, L. Yang and D. Zhang, &quot;Real-time visual localization of the picking points for a <lb/>ridge-planting strawberry harvesting robot,&quot; IEEE Access, vol. 8, pp. 116556-116568, 2020. <lb/>[6] A. Durand-Petiteville, S. Vougioukas and D. C. Slaughter, &quot;Real-time segmentation of strawberry flesh and <lb/>calyx from images of singulated strawberries during postharvest processing,&quot; Computers and Electronics in <lb/>Agriculture, vol. 142, pp. 298-313, 2017. <lb/>[7] Y. Xiong, C. Peng, L. Grimstad, P. J. From and V. Isler, &quot;Development and field evaluation of a strawberry <lb/>harvesting robot with a cable-driven gripper,&quot; Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, vol. 157, pp. 392-<lb/>402, 2019. <lb/>[8] J. Zhao, G. Pan and W. Guo, &quot;Application of edge detection local operator to strawberry contour <lb/>extraction,&quot; Journal of Agricultural Mechanization Research, vol. 2008, no. 6, pp. 184-186, 2008. <lb/>[9] Y. Xu, K. Imou, Y. Kaizu and K. Saga, &quot;Two-stage approach for detecting slightly overlapping strawberries <lb/>using HOG descriptor,&quot; Biosystems Engineering, vol. 115, no. 2, pp. 144-153, 2013. <lb/>[10] J. Sun, Y. Chen, X. Zhou, J. Shen and X. Wu, &quot;Fast and accurate recognition of the strawberries in <lb/>greenhouse based on improved YOLOv4-Tiny model,&quot; Transactions of the Chinese Society of Agricultural <lb/>Engineering, vol. 38, no. 18, pp. 195-203, 2022. <lb/>[11] K. Han, Y. Wang, Q. Tian, J. Guo, C. Xu et al., &quot;GhostNet: More features from cheap operations,&quot; in 2020 <lb/>IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), Seattle, WA, USA, pp. 1577-1586, <lb/>2020. <lb/>[12] D. Tian, Y. Han, B. Wang, T. Guan, H. Gu et al., &quot;Review of object instance segmentation based on deep <lb/>learning,&quot; Journal of Electronic Imaging, vol. 31, no. 4, pp. 41205, 2021. <lb/>[13] K. He, G. Gkioxari, P. Dollar and R. Girshick, &quot;Mask R-CNN,&quot; in 2017 IEEE Int. Conf. on Computer <lb/>Vision (ICCV), Venice, Italy, pp. 2980-2988, 2017. <lb/>[14] Y. Yu, K. Zhang, L. Yang and D. Zhang, &quot;Fruit detection for strawberry harvesting robot in non-structural <lb/>environment based on Mask-RCNN,&quot; Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, vol. 163, pp. 104846, 2019. <lb/>[15] I. Pérez-Borrero, D. Marín-Santos, M. E. Gegúndez-Arias and E. Cortés-Ancos, &quot;A fast and accurate deep <lb/>learning method for strawberry instance segmentation,&quot; Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, vol. 178, <lb/>pp. 105736, 2020. <lb/>[16] I. Pérez-Borrero, D. Marín-Santos, M. J. Vasallo-Vazquez and M. E. Gegundez-Arias, &quot;A new deep-<lb/>learning strawberry instance segmentation methodology based on a fully convolutional neural network,&quot; <lb/>Neural Computing and Applications, vol. 31, pp. 15059-15071, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1501 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>[17] O. Ronneberger, P. Fischer and T. Brox, &quot;U-Net: Convolutional networks for biomedical image segmenta-<lb/>tion,&quot; in Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention-MICCAI 2015, pp. 234-241, 2015. <lb/>[18] D. Bolya, C. Zhou, F. Xiao and Y. J. Yong, &quot;YOLACT: Real-time instance segmentation,&quot; in 2019 <lb/>IEEE/CVF Int. Conf. on Computer Vision (ICCV), Seoul, Korea (South), pp. 9156-9165, 2019. <lb/>[19] D. Zhang, Z. Zheng, M. Li and R. Liu, &quot;CSART: Channel and spatial attention-guided residual learning <lb/>for real-time object tracking,&quot; Neurocomputing, vol. 436, pp. 260-272, 2021. <lb/>[20] D. Zhang, Z. Zheng, T. Wang and Y. He, &quot;HROM: Learning high-resolution representation and object-<lb/>aware masks for visual object tracking,&quot; Sensors, vol. 20, no. 17, pp. 4807, 2020. <lb/>[21] Z. Chen, J. Yang, L. Chen and H. Jiao, &quot;Garbage classification system based on improved ShuffleNet v2,&quot; <lb/>Resources Conservation and Recycling, vol. 178, pp. 106090, 2022. <lb/>[22] D. Wang and D. He, &quot;Fusion of mask RCNN and attention mechanism for instance segmentation of apples <lb/>under complex background,&quot; Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, vol. 196, pp. 106864, 2022. <lb/>[23] J. Cao, Q. Chen, J. Guo and R. Shi, &quot;Attention-guided context feature pyramid network for object <lb/>detection,&quot; arXiv preprint arXiv:2005.11475, 2020. <lb/>[24] M. Xian, F. Xu, H. D. Cheng, Y. Zhang and J. Ding, &quot;EISeg: Effective interactive segmentation,&quot; in 2016 <lb/>23rd Int. Conf. on Pattern Recognition (ICPR), Cancun, Mexico, pp. 1982-1987, 2016. <lb/>[25] J. Wang, K. Sun, T. Cheng, B. Jiang, C. Deng et al., &quot;Deep high-resolution representation learning for <lb/>visual recognition,&quot; IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, vol. 43, no. 10, pp. <lb/>3349-3364, 2020. <lb/>[26] Y. Yuan, X. Chen and J. Wang, &quot;Object-contextual representations for semantic segmentation,&quot; in Com-<lb/>puter Vision-ECCV 2020, pp. 173-190, 2020. <lb/>[27] K. He, X. Zhang, S. Ren and J. Sun, &quot;Deep residual learning for image recognition,&quot; in 2016 IEEE Conf. <lb/>on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), Las Vegas, NV, USA, pp. 770-778, 2016. <lb/>[28] J. Hu, L. Shen and G. Sun, &quot;Squeeze-and-excitation networks,&quot; in 2018 IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer <lb/>Vision and Pattern Recognition, Salt Lake City, UT, USA, pp. 7132-7141, 2018. <lb/>[29] S. Woo, J. Park, J. Y. Lee and I. S. Kweon, &quot;CBAM: Convolutional block attention module,&quot; in Computer <lb/>Vision-ECCV 2018 (ECCV 2018), Munich, Germany, pp. 3-19, 2018. <lb/>[30] Q. L. Zhang and Y. B. Yang, &quot;SA-Net: Shuffle attention for deep convolutional neural networks,&quot; in <lb/>ICASSP 2021-2021 IEEE Int. Conf. on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), Toronto, ON, <lb/>Canada, pp. 2235-2239, 2021. <lb/>[31] H. Zhang, K. Zu, J. Lu, Y. Zou and D. Meng, &quot;EPSANet: An efficient pyramid squeeze attention block <lb/>on convolutional neural network,&quot; in Computer Vision-ACCV 2022, Springer International Publishing, pp. <lb/>541-557, 2023. <lb/>[32] Y. Wu and K. He, &quot;Group normalization,&quot; in Computer Vision-ECCV 2018. ECCV 2018, vol. 128, Springer <lb/>International Publishing, pp. 742-755, 2020. <lb/>[33] V. Nair and G. E. Hinton, &quot;Rectified linear units improve restricted boltzmann machines,&quot; in ICML&apos;10: <lb/>Proc. of the 27th Int. Conf. on Int. Conf. on Machine Learning, Madison, WI, USA, pp. 807-814, 2010. <lb/>[34] T. Y. Lin, P. Dollar, R. Girshick, K. He, B. Hariharan et al., &quot;Feature pyramid networks for object <lb/>detection,&quot; in 2017 IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), Honolulu, HI, USA, <lb/>pp. 936-944, 2017. <lb/>[35] T. Y. Lin, P. Goyal, R. Girshick, K. He and P. Dollar, &quot;Focal loss for dense object detection,&quot; IEEE <lb/>Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, vol. 42, no. 2, pp. 318-327, 2018. <lb/>[36] S. Liu, D. Huang and Y. Wang, &quot;Receptive field block net for accurate and fast object detection,&quot; in <lb/>Computer Vision-ECCV 2018, Springer International Publishing, pp. 404-419, 2022. <lb/>[37] W. Liu, D. Anguelov, D. Erhan, C. Szegedy, S. Reed et al., &quot;SSD: Single shot multiBox detector,&quot; in <lb/>Computer Vision-ECCV 2016, Springer International Publishing, pp. 21-37, 2016. <lb/>[38] A. Neubeck and L. van Gool, &quot;Efficient non-maximum suppression,&quot; in 18th Int. Conf. on Pattern <lb/>Recognition (ICPR&apos;06), Hong Kong, China, pp. 850-855, 2006. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>