<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T16:46:00.528Z">11/20/2025 4:46:00 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T16:45:42.715345Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T16:45:42.715345Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 11 December 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Giada Gasparini, <lb/>University of Bologna, Italy <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Fuyuan Gong, <lb/>Zhejiang University, China <lb/>Peng Zhang, <lb/>Zhengzhou University, China <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Suping Duan, <lb/>duansuping531@163.com <lb/>RECEIVED 15 October 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 19 November 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 11 December 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Duan S (2024) Compressive strength <lb/>prediction of fiber-reinforced recycled <lb/>aggregate concrete based on optimization <lb/>algorithms. <lb/>Front. Built Environ. 10:1509714. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Duan. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>Compressive strength prediction <lb/>of fiber-reinforced recycled <lb/>aggregate concrete based on <lb/>optimization algorithms <lb/>Suping Duan* <lb/>Shanxi Vocational University of Engineering Science and Technology, Civil Engineering and <lb/>Architecture, Taiyuan, China <lb/>With the growing emphasis on sustainable development in the construction <lb/>industry, fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (BFRC) has attracted <lb/>considerable attention due to its superior mechanical properties and <lb/>environmental benefits. However, accurately predicting the compressive <lb/>strength of BFRC remains a challenge because of the complex interaction <lb/>between recycled aggregates and fiber reinforcement. This study introduces <lb/>an innovative predictive framework that combines the XGBoost machine <lb/>learning algorithm with advanced optimization algorithms, including the Seagull <lb/>Optimization Algorithm (SOA), Tunicate Swarm Algorithm (TSA), and Mayfly <lb/>Algorithm (MA). The unique integration of these algorithms not only improves <lb/>predictive accuracy but also optimizes model performance by enhancing <lb/>parameter tuning capabilities. Experimental results demonstrated that the TSA-<lb/>XGBoost model achieved an exceptional R 2 of 0.9847 and a minimum mean <lb/>square error (MSE) of 0.255958, outperforming other models in predicting <lb/>BFRC&apos;s compressive strength. This novel predictive approach offers an efficient <lb/>and accurate tool for assessing BFRC&apos;s mechanical performance in practical <lb/>applications, thus supporting its broader adoption in sustainable construction. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (BFRC), steel fibers, compressive strength, <lb/>XGBoost, optimization algorithms <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The increasing focus on sustainability in construction has led to greater interest <lb/>in fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (BFRC) for its mechanical strength <lb/>and environmental benefits (Amudha et al., 2021; Wang et al., 2023; Zhang et al., <lb/>2020; Wang et al., 2024; Bhattacharyya et al., 2020). Recycled aggregates help reduce <lb/>construction waste and reliance on natural resources, though cracks can negatively <lb/>impact concrete&apos;s durability and performance (Ghoneim et al., 2020; Zhang et al., <lb/>2024; Chen et al., 2014; Eady et al., 2023). The addition of fibers slows crack <lb/>propagation, improving construction quality. Fiber-reinforced concrete, distinct from <lb/>traditional concrete, incorporates fibers that enhance its mechanical properties (Zaid et al., <lb/>2022; Shahjalal et al., 2023). Studies by Yang et al. (2021) and Nikolenko et al. <lb/>(2021) have shown that increasing fiber volume or aspect ratio can significantly <lb/>boost compressive strength and elastic modulus, while uniformly distributed fibers <lb/>prevent crack formation. Research on basalt fiber-reinforced concrete highlights its high <lb/></body>

	<front>Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></front>

	<body>tensile strength and durability (Zhou et al., 2020; Zheng et al., 2022; <lb/>Khan et al., 2022), with basalt fibers enhancing compressive and <lb/>flexural strengths (Elshazli et al., 2022; Li et al., 2022; Fang et al., <lb/>2018). Despite these benefits, excess fibers may alter concrete&apos;s <lb/>pore structure, reducing strength (Wu et al., 2023; Heeralal et al., <lb/>2009). Steel fibers, randomly distributed, mitigate crack growth, <lb/>improving both tensile and compressive properties (Weli et al., <lb/>2020; Raza et al., 2021; Wang et al., 2021). Predicting BFRC&apos;s <lb/>compressive strength is essential for ensuring structural safety, but <lb/>traditional models struggle due to the complex properties of recycled <lb/>aggregates, underscoring the need for accurate predictive models. <lb/>Kang et al. (2021) explored machine learning algorithms <lb/>to predict the compressive and flexural strengths of steel fiber-<lb/>reinforced concrete (SFRC), showing that tree-based and boosting <lb/>models, particularly XGBoost, outperformed traditional models <lb/>like K-nearest neighbors and linear regression. XGBoost&apos;s ability <lb/>to handle nonlinear relationships and high-dimensional data has <lb/>made it the leading method for predicting BFRC performance <lb/>(El Mahdi Safhi et al., 2023). demonstrated XGBoost&apos;s effectiveness <lb/>in predicting SCC workability, while Sun et al. (2024) and <lb/>Tao et al. (2024) applied optimized XGBoost models for predicting <lb/>splitting tensile strength and ultimate compressive strength, <lb/>respectively, achieving R 2 values above 0.9. To improve predictive <lb/>accuracy, recent advancements have integrated optimization <lb/>algorithms, such as SOA (Sankar et al., 2022), TSA (Qiu et al., <lb/>2022), and MA (Asselman et al., 2023), which significantly <lb/>enhance XGBoost&apos;s performance by dynamically adjusting model <lb/>parameters, increasing both accuracy and robustness. <lb/>In this study, three types of steel fibers (copper-coated, hooked, <lb/>and wavy) were incorporated into BFRC at different volume <lb/>fractions, and the effects of these fibers on the compressive <lb/>strength of basalt fiber-reinforced concrete were comprehensively <lb/>analyzed through mechanical tests. By integrating the XGBoost <lb/>algorithm, a predictive model for BFRC compressive strength <lb/>was established, providing a theoretical basis for its strength <lb/>prediction. Furthermore, by incorporating optimization algorithms <lb/>such as SOA, TSA, and MA, the model&apos;s predictive accuracy <lb/>was further improved, offering an effective method and <lb/>support for predicting the mechanical properties of basalt fiber <lb/>steel fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete in practical <lb/>engineering applications. <lb/>In summary, prior research has primarily focused on traditional <lb/>predictive models for concrete properties or fiber-reinforced <lb/>concrete, with significant advancements in machine learning <lb/>applications for these materials. However, current models still <lb/>face limitations, especially in terms of accuracy when dealing <lb/>with complex materials such as fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate <lb/>concrete. This study builds on the limitations observed in <lb/>previous studies by integrating optimization algorithms with <lb/>machine learning, which aims to enhance prediction accuracy <lb/>and model robustness. The research presented here provides <lb/>an innovative approach by combining advanced optimization <lb/>techniques with established machine learning frameworks, creating <lb/>a more comprehensive and accurate model for predicting the <lb/>compressive strength of fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate <lb/>concrete. This approach addresses the complex interactions between <lb/>different material compositions and their mechanical performance, <lb/>establishing a novel framework for future studies. <lb/>2 Model principles <lb/>2.1 XGBoost <lb/>XGBoost builds on the Gradient Boosting Decision Tree <lb/>(GBDT) algorithm, employing decision trees, particularly <lb/>Classification and Regression Trees (CART), for classification and <lb/>regression (Sagi and Rokach, 2021; Mohan et al., 2024). In GBDT, <lb/>sequential base CART estimators are assigned weights adjusted <lb/>during training, creating a robust ensemble model. For regression, a <lb/>sample&apos;s predicted value results from the weighted sum of each leaf <lb/>node&apos;s predictions in the decision trees, as shown in Equation 1. <lb/>ŷ <lb/>i = <lb/>K <lb/>∑ <lb/>k <lb/>β k h k (x i ) <lb/>(1) <lb/>In the formula: ŷ <lb/>i represents the predicted value; K denotes <lb/>the total number of trees; β k is the weight of the k -th tree; h k (x i ) <lb/>represents the prediction result of the k -th tree; and x i represents the <lb/>feature vector corresponding to the i -th sample. <lb/>The XGBoost model uses an iterative approach, combining weak <lb/>learners and controlling complexity to discover complex nonlinear <lb/>statistical relationships between the target variable and the observed <lb/>features. Through this iterative process, the model continuously <lb/>optimizes performance during training (Che and He, 2022). The <lb/>objective function of the XGBoost model, combining the predicted <lb/>results, as shown in Equations 2, 3. <lb/>O bj = <lb/>M <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>l(y i , ŷ <lb/>i ) + <lb/>K <lb/>∑ <lb/>k=1 <lb/>Ω( f k ) <lb/>(2) <lb/>Ω( f k ) = γT + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>λ <lb/>K <lb/>∑ <lb/>k=1 <lb/>ω 2 <lb/>k <lb/>(3) <lb/>In the formula: M represents the total number of samples in <lb/>the dataset; yi denotes the true value; l(y i , ŷ <lb/>i ) is the loss function, <lb/>which measures the difference between the predicted and actual <lb/>values; Ω( f k ) represents the complexity of the model, which acts as <lb/>a regularization term to help prevent overfitting; T is the number of <lb/>leaf nodes; ω k is the weight of the leaf nodes; and γ and λ are pre-<lb/>defined hyperparameters that control the number and scores of the <lb/>leaf nodes. <lb/>The XGBoost model enhances the additive training process <lb/>by iteratively advancing. In each iteration, it trains a new model <lb/>and adds it to the previous ensemble, gradually reducing the loss <lb/>function. As shown in Equations 4-6. <lb/>ŷ <lb/>q <lb/>i = <lb/>Q <lb/>∑ <lb/>q <lb/>f k (x i ) = <lb/>Q-1 <lb/>∑ <lb/>q <lb/>f k (x i ) + f q (x i ) <lb/>(4) <lb/>K <lb/>∑ <lb/>k <lb/>Ω( f k ) = <lb/>Q-1 <lb/>∑ <lb/>q <lb/>Ω( f k ) + Ω( f q ) <lb/>(5) <lb/>O bj = <lb/>M <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>[ f q (x i )g i + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>f q (x i ) 2 h i ] + Ω( f q ) <lb/>(6) <lb/>In the formula: Q represents the number of iterations; y <lb/>q <lb/>i denotes <lb/>the true value in the q -th iteration; <lb/>ŷ <lb/>q <lb/>i BB is the predicted value in the <lb/>q -th iteration; f q refers to the optimal tree in the q -th iteration; g i and <lb/>h i are the first and second derivatives of the loss function l(y <lb/>q <lb/>i , <lb/>ŷ <lb/>(q-1) <lb/>i <lb/>) <lb/>with respect to y <lb/>q-1 <lb/>i ; and l(y <lb/>q <lb/>i , <lb/>ŷ <lb/>(q-1) <lb/>i <lb/>) is obtained by performing a <lb/>Taylor expansion on f q (x i ). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<front>frontiersin.org <lb/></front>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>2.2 Optimization algorithms <lb/>2.2.1 Seagull Optimization Algorithm (SOA) <lb/>The Seagull Optimization Algorithm (SOA), introduced by <lb/>Dhiman G and Kumar V, is a swarm intelligence algorithm for multi-<lb/>objective optimization (Naga Sai Kalyan et al., 2022; Liu et al., 2023). <lb/>Inspired by seagull migration and attack behaviors, SOA enhances <lb/>global exploration and local search. It updates seagull positions <lb/>in two phases: migration for wide-ranging search and attack for <lb/>local optimization, incorporating spiral movements linked to the <lb/>objective function. Key parameters such as population size, iteration <lb/>limits (T max ), variable bounds (ul and ub), and spiral factors ( fc, u, v) <lb/>are initialized, followed by the calculation of fitness values to guide <lb/>the search process. <lb/>The initial position of the seagulls is given by the <lb/>following Equation 7: <lb/>Positions = rand(SearchAgents, 1) × (ub -lb) + lb <lb/>(7) <lb/>In the equation, ul represents the upper limit of the variable, and <lb/>ub represents the lower limit. <lb/>After calculating the fitness values, the seagull population is <lb/>sorted in ascending order using the sort (fitness, index) function. <lb/>This process identifies the best value for each seagull and the global <lb/>best (P best ). Based on the sorting index, the positions are updated <lb/>from their initial locations to new coordinates (x), and the iterative <lb/>optimization process begins (Anand et al., 2024). <lb/>During migration, seagulls move toward the optimal <lb/>position while avoiding collisions, ensuring they approach the <lb/>global optimum. To prevent overlapping, an additional variable <lb/>(A) is introduced to compute the seagulls&apos; new positions. <lb/>As shown in Equation 8. <lb/>{ { <lb/>{ { <lb/>{ <lb/>C s = X * A <lb/>A = f c -t * ( <lb/>f c <lb/>T max <lb/>) <lb/>(8) <lb/>In the equation, f represents the current iteration number, and <lb/>the parameter linearly decreases from 2 to 0. <lb/>The optimal position direction coefficient ensures M s that the <lb/>seagull moves towards the best position while avoiding collisions. <lb/>As shown in Equation 9. <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ <lb/>rd = rand(1, dim) <lb/>B = 2 * A 2 * rd <lb/>M s = B * (Pbest -X) <lb/>(9) <lb/>The coefficient D s represents the movement toward the optimal <lb/>position. The seagull moves in the direction of the best position, <lb/>and once it reaches the new position, the migration process ends. <lb/>As shown in Equation 10. <lb/>D s = |Cs + Ms| <lb/>(10) <lb/>In the equation, D s is the new position of the seagull that satisfies <lb/>the three conditions. <lb/>When the seagulls attack their prey, they perform spiral <lb/>movements in the air. The three components x, y, and z of the spiral <lb/>motion are expressed as follows Equation 11: <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ <lb/>θ = rand(1, dim) * 2π <lb/>r = u * e θ * v <lb/>x = r * cos θ, y = r * sin θ, z = r * θ <lb/>(11) <lb/>In the equation, θ is a random number within the range [0, 2π], <lb/>expressed in radians. <lb/>Finally, the formula for the seagull&apos;s attack behavior is given <lb/>as shown in Equation 12 <lb/>X new = x * y * z * D s + pbest <lb/>(12) <lb/>2.2.2 Tunicate Swarm Algorithm (TSA) <lb/>The Tunicate Swarm Algorithm (TSA) is a swarm intelligence <lb/>algorithm inspired by tunicate foraging behavior in the ocean. <lb/>This behavior includes jet propulsion, utilizing individual gravity, <lb/>seawater flow, and interaction forces to avoid collisions while <lb/>moving toward an optimal target. Swarm behavior also updates <lb/>the global best position based on perceived environmental cues. <lb/>Tunicates use their nervous system to sense water flow and light <lb/>sources from others, collectively guiding the swarm toward food. <lb/>During jet propulsion, collision avoidance is managed by calculating <lb/>new positions for each individual. As shown in Equation 13. <lb/>A = <lb/>G <lb/>M <lb/>(13) <lb/>In the formula, G represents the gravity of the tunicate <lb/>individual, and M denotes the interaction force between tunicate <lb/>individuals. The value of M is calculated as shown in Equation 14. <lb/>M = P min + c(P max -P min ) <lb/>(14) <lb/>In the equation, P max and P min refer to the initial interaction <lb/>velocity values of the individuals, typically assigned values P max = <lb/>4 and P min = 1, while c is a random number between [0, 1]. After <lb/>avoiding collisions between neighboring individuals, the search <lb/>agents move towards the optimal individual. At this stage, the <lb/>distance between the i -th individual and the optimal individual at <lb/>the t -th iteration is calculated. As shown in Equation 15. <lb/>PD t <lb/>i =| positions t <lb/>best -rand ⋅ x t <lb/>i | <lb/>(15) <lb/>In the formula, &quot;rand&quot; is a uniformly distributed random <lb/>number in the range [0, 1], positions t <lb/>best represents the optimal <lb/>individual&apos;s position at the t -th iteration, which is the current best <lb/>global position of the population, and BBB x t <lb/>i denotes the position <lb/>of the i -th tunicate individual in the population at the t -th iteration. <lb/>The formula for each tunicate individual moving towards the <lb/>optimal individual is shown in Equation 16. <lb/>x t <lb/>i = <lb/>{ <lb/>{ <lb/>{ <lb/>positions t <lb/>best + A ⋅ PD t <lb/>i , rand ⩾ 0.5 <lb/>positions t <lb/>best -A ⋅ PD t <lb/>i , rand &lt; 0.5 <lb/>(16) <lb/>2.2.3 Mayfly Algorithm (MA) <lb/>The Mayfly Algorithm (MA) consists of three main stages: <lb/>male mayfly movement, female mayfly movement, and mayfly <lb/>mating and mutation. Male mayflies gather together and adjust their <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>positions based on their own experience and the experience of their <lb/>neighbors. Assuming that x t <lb/>i represents the position of the i -th male <lb/>mayfly at generation t, its updated position at generation t+1t+1t+1 <lb/>is shown in Equation 17: <lb/>x t+1 <lb/>i = x t <lb/>i + v t+1 <lb/>i <lb/>(17) <lb/>In the equation, v t+1 <lb/>i <lb/>represents the velocity of the male mayfly <lb/>at generation t+1t+1t+1. To evolve towards a better position, the <lb/>velocity of the male mayfly is adjusted based on its own historical <lb/>best position and the overall best position of the population. When <lb/>it becomes the best in the population, it performs a &quot;wedding dance&quot; <lb/>to avoid falling into local optima. As shown in Equation 18. <lb/>v t+1 <lb/>ij = <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ { { { <lb/>{ <lb/>wv t <lb/>ij + a 1 exp (-βr 2 <lb/>p )(p ij -x ij ) + a 2 exp (-βr 2 <lb/>g ) <lb/>×wv t <lb/>ij + dR, f(x i ) ⩽ f(p g ) <lb/>wv t <lb/>ij + dR, f(x i ) ⩽ f(p g ) <lb/>(18) <lb/>In the equation, v t <lb/>ij represents the velocity of the i -th mayfly <lb/>at generation t in the j -th dimension; w is the inertia weight; a1 <lb/>and a2 are positive attraction constants that measure cognitive and <lb/>social components, respectively; β is the fixed visibility coefficient, <lb/>controlling the visibility of the mayfly; p i is the historical best <lb/>position of the i -th mayfly; DDD is the global best position of the <lb/>mayfly population; p g is a random number within the range [-1,1]; <lb/>and d is the marriage dance coefficient, whose iteration formula is <lb/>shown in Equation 19: <lb/>d t+1 = d t ⋅ d d <lb/>(19) <lb/>Where: d d is the damping factor for the dance of the mayfly to <lb/>its historically best position and to the globally best position. The <lb/>Cartesian distance is calculated as shown in Equation 20: <lb/>r = x i -X i = √ <lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>j=1 <lb/>(x ij -X ij ) <lb/>2 <lb/>(20) <lb/>Where: x ij is the position of the i -th mayfly in the j -th dimension, and <lb/>X ij is the historically best position or globally best position of the i -th <lb/>mayfly in the j -th dimension. <lb/>Unlike male mayflies, female mayflies do not gather together <lb/>but instead fly towards male mayflies for mating and reproduction. <lb/>Suppose y t <lb/>i is the position of the i -th female mayfly at generation t, its <lb/>position is updated as shown in Equation 21: <lb/>y t+1 <lb/>i = y t <lb/>i + v t+1 <lb/>i <lb/>(21) <lb/>Where: v t+1 <lb/>i <lb/>is the velocity of the female mayfly at generation t+1. <lb/>It is assumed that the attraction process of male mayflies to female <lb/>mayflies is deterministic: the fittest female mayfly is attracted to the <lb/>fittest male mayfly, the second fittest female is attracted to the second <lb/>fittest male, and so on. The velocity of the female mayfly is updated <lb/>as shown in Equation 22: <lb/>v t+1 <lb/>ij = <lb/>{ <lb/>{ <lb/>{ <lb/>wv t <lb/>ij + a 3 exp (-βr 2 <lb/>mf (x t <lb/>ij -y t <lb/>ij )), f(y t <lb/>i ) &gt; f(x t <lb/>i ) <lb/>wv t <lb/>ij + f 1 R, f(y t <lb/>i ) ⩽ f(x t <lb/>i ) <lb/>(22) <lb/>Where: r 2 <lb/>mf is the Cartesian distance between the female mayfly <lb/>and the male mayfly; f 1 is the random walk coefficient, and female <lb/>mayflies not attracted by males will fly randomly. The iteration of f 1 <lb/>is as shown in Equation 23: <lb/>f t+1 <lb/>1 = f t <lb/>1 ⋅ f d <lb/>(23) <lb/>Where: f d is the random flight damping factor. <lb/>The mating process of mayflies is the same as the <lb/>attraction process: the fittest female mates with the fittest <lb/>male, the second fittest female mates with the second <lb/>fittest male, and so on, producing two offspring. As shown <lb/>in Equation 24: <lb/>p os1 = L ⋅ p m + (1 -L) ⋅ p f <lb/>p os2 = L ⋅ p f + (1 -L) ⋅ p m <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>(24) <lb/>Where: p os is the offspring mayfly; p f is the female mayfly; <lb/>p m is the male mayfly; L is a random number, L∈[0,1]. A <lb/>normally distributed random number is added to the selected <lb/>offspring variable, and the offspring mutation formula is shown <lb/>in Equation 25: <lb/>p os = p os + σN(0, 1) <lb/>(25) <lb/>Where: N(0, 1) is the standard deviation of the normal distribution, <lb/>and B is a random number drawn from a normal distribution with <lb/>a mean of 0 and a variance of 1. <lb/>2.3 Cross-validation <lb/>Cross-validation is a common method to assess model <lb/>performance on unseen data by partitioning the dataset into <lb/>several exclusive subsets, then iteratively training and testing <lb/>on these. In this study, we use k-fold cross-validation (k = <lb/>5), dividing the dataset into five equal subsets. Each subset <lb/>serves as a validation set once, while the remaining k-1 <lb/>subsets form the training set. This cycle repeats k times, <lb/>and the average performance metrics across all iterations <lb/>provide a stable and reliable assessment of model performance. <lb/>As shown in Figure 1. <lb/>For the i -th fold, the model uses the i -th subset as the <lb/>validation set, and the remaining k-1 subsets are combined to <lb/>form the training set, yielding the performance metric Mi for <lb/>that fold. The overall model performance M is the average of the <lb/>performance metrics from all k folds, denoted as M = 1 <lb/>k ∑ k <lb/>i=1 M i . <lb/>This average reflects the model&apos;s comprehensive performance across <lb/>the entire dataset and helps assess the model&apos;s generalization <lb/>ability. The key advantage of cross-validation is that it reduces <lb/>the risk of overfitting by training and testing on different <lb/>subsets, providing a more stable performance evaluation. This is <lb/>especially useful when dealing with limited data, as cross-validation <lb/>makes full use of every data point, improving the reliability of <lb/>model assessment. In this study, cross-validation is applied to <lb/>evaluate the performance of different optimization algorithms in <lb/>predicting the mechanical properties of fiber-reinforced recycled <lb/>aggregate concrete. By comparing the cross-validation results, <lb/>we can objectively determine which algorithm performs best in <lb/>practical applications. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>TABLE 1 Fiber types and their parameters. <lb/>Fiber type <lb/>d (mm) <lb/>l (mm) <lb/>l/d <lb/>ρ (kg/m³) <lb/>f cu (MPa) <lb/>Cross-section <lb/>Copper-coated Steel Fiber (RPC) <lb/>0.3 <lb/>12 <lb/>40 <lb/>7850 <lb/>2000 <lb/>Circular <lb/>Wavy Steel Fiber (WF) <lb/>0.8 <lb/>32 <lb/>40 <lb/>7850 <lb/>800 <lb/>Rectangular <lb/>Hooked-end Steel Fiber (SF) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>35 <lb/>70 <lb/>7850 <lb/>800 <lb/>Circular <lb/>Basalt Fiber (BF) <lb/>0.015 <lb/>18 <lb/>1200 <lb/>2650 <lb/>3000 <lb/>Circular <lb/>TABLE 2 Fiber concrete mix ratio. <lb/>No. <lb/>Bs/% <lb/>c/(kg•m -3 ) <lb/>Cement <lb/>Sand <lb/>Coarse aggregate <lb/>Water <lb/>Superplasticizer <lb/>Basalt fiber <lb/>RPC0.8 <lb/>33 <lb/>385 <lb/>614 <lb/>1 246 <lb/>208 <lb/>3.85 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>RPC1 .0 <lb/>33 <lb/>381 <lb/>610 <lb/>1 234 <lb/>206 <lb/>3.81 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>RPC1 .2 <lb/>33 <lb/>377 <lb/>606 <lb/>1 222 <lb/>204 <lb/>3.77 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>SF0.8 <lb/>33 <lb/>385 <lb/>614 <lb/>1 246 <lb/>208 <lb/>3.85 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>SF1 .0 <lb/>33 <lb/>381 <lb/>610 <lb/>1 234 <lb/>206 <lb/>3.81 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>SF1 .2 <lb/>33 <lb/>377 <lb/>606 <lb/>1 222 <lb/>204 <lb/>3.77 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>WF0.8 <lb/>33 <lb/>385 <lb/>614 <lb/>1 246 <lb/>208 <lb/>3.85 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>WF1 .0 <lb/>33 <lb/>381 <lb/>610 <lb/>1 234 <lb/>206 <lb/>3.81 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>WF1 .2 <lb/>33 <lb/>377 <lb/>606 <lb/>1 222 <lb/>204 <lb/>3.77 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>BF <lb/>33 <lb/>310 <lb/>618 <lb/>1 258 <lb/>168 <lb/>3.70 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>3 Experimental design and results <lb/>analysis <lb/>3.1 Experimental materials <lb/>The experiment utilized C30 concrete mixed with P.O <lb/>42.5 cement. Crushed pebbles (5-20 mm) were used as coarse <lb/>aggregate, and natural river sand (0.075-4.750 mm) served as <lb/>fine aggregate, with a fineness modulus of 2.8. A polycarboxylate <lb/>superplasticizer, at 1.0% of the cement weight, improved workability. <lb/>Key parameters of the steel and basalt fibers are shown in Table 1, <lb/>where d is the fiber diameter, l is the fiber length, and l/d is <lb/>the ratio affecting concrete performance. Fiber density (ρ) was <lb/>crucial for determining volume percentage, while fcu referred to <lb/>tensile strength. <lb/>3.2 Experimental design <lb/>The experimental design of this study carefully considered <lb/>various factors affecting the compressive strength of basalt fiber-<lb/>reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (BFRC), including fiber type, <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>5-Fold cross-validation. <lb/>volume fraction, curing age, and testing conditions. A C30 concrete <lb/>mix was used, with P.O 42.5 cement, crushed pebbles (5-20 mm) as <lb/>coarse aggregate, and river sand (0.075-4.75 mm) as fine aggregate. <lb/>Each specimen was molded into a standard 100 mm cubic mold <lb/>and cured in a controlled environment at a constant temperature <lb/>of 20°C ± 2°C and relative humidity of 95% for 3, 7, 14, and 28 <lb/>days. Compressive strength testing followed the &quot;Standard for Test <lb/>Methods of Mechanical Properties of Ordinary Concrete&quot; (GB/T <lb/>50,081-2019), with each specimen tested on a hydraulic press at <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Mix Compressive strength of fiber concrete. <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Stress-strain curves. <lb/>a loading rate of 0.5 MPa/s. Additionally, in line with the &quot;Test <lb/>Methods for Steel Fiber Reinforced Concrete&quot; standards, variables <lb/>such as curing age, fiber content, and fiber type were integrated <lb/>into the design. To ensure stability and repeatability of results, a <lb/>total of 40 experimental groups were set, each containing three <lb/>specimens, amounting to 120 specimens in total. The concrete <lb/>mix ratios are provided in Table 2, where c represents material <lb/>quantities and Bs denotes the sand rate. During each test, stress-<lb/>strain behavior was also monitored alongside compressive strength <lb/>to provide deeper insights into the material&apos;s ductility and toughness <lb/>under load (Saud et al., 2020). <lb/>This study primarily analyzes the impact of different types <lb/>and volume fractions of steel fibers on the compressive strength <lb/>of basalt fiber-reinforced concrete (BFRC) at curing ages of 3, <lb/>7, 14, and 28 days. According to previous research, the optimal <lb/>content of basalt fibers in BFRC is 2.6 kg/m³ (Shahjalal et al., <lb/>2023; Sharma et al., 2022; Yang et al., 2021; Nikolenko et al., <lb/>2021), which was set as a fixed value in this study. The reference <lb/>group is BFRC, labeled as BF. In the specific experiments, the <lb/>volume fractions of hooked-end steel fibers were set at 0.8%, <lb/>1.0%, and 1.2%, corresponding to the specimen labels SF0.8, <lb/>SF1.0, and SF1.2. The volume fractions of wavy steel fibers were <lb/>similarly set at 0.8%, 1.0%, and 1.2%, with the corresponding <lb/>labels WF0.8, WF1.0, and WF1.2. The volume fractions of <lb/>copper-coated steel fibers were consistent with the previous ones, <lb/>labeled as RPC0.8, RPC1.0, and RPC1.2. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Compressive form of concrete. <lb/>3.3 Compressive strength results analysis <lb/>The compressive strength of cubic specimens was measured <lb/>according to the &quot;Standard for Test Methods of Mechanical <lb/>Properties of Ordinary Concrete&quot; (GB/T 50,081-2019). The <lb/>relationship between different types of steel fiber volume fractions, <lb/>curing age (ta), and compressive strength (fcu) is shown in Figure 2. <lb/>This study primarily investigates the effects of different types and <lb/>volume fractions of steel fibers on the compressive strength of basalt <lb/>fiber-reinforced concrete (BFRC) at curing ages of 3, 7, 14, and 28 <lb/>days. Based on prior research, the optimal content of basalt fibers <lb/>in BFRC is determined to be 2.6 kg/m³, which was thus set as a <lb/>constant parameter in this study. The control group, representing <lb/>BFRC without steel fibers, is labeled as BF. For the experiments, <lb/>hooked-end steel fibers were added at volume fractions of 0.8%, <lb/>1.0%, and 1.2%, labeled as SF0.8, SF1.0, and SF1.2, respectively. <lb/>Likewise, the volume fractions of wavy steel fibers were set at 0.8%, <lb/>1.0%, and 1.2%, with the labels WF0.8, WF1.0, and WF1.2, while <lb/>copper-coated steel fibers followed the same volume fractions and <lb/>were labeled as RPC0.8, RPC1.0, and RPC1.2. <lb/>As shown in Figure 2, although steel fibers are primarily <lb/>intended to reinforce tensile strength, their inclusion also enhances <lb/>the compressive strength of BFRC within a specific range. This effect <lb/>occurs because an optimal amount of steel fibers improves the bond <lb/>between the concrete matrix and fibers, effectively inhibiting crack <lb/>propagation. Dispersed steel fibers within the concrete can help <lb/>reduce stress concentration at crack tips and defect points, thereby <lb/>enhancing compressive strength. However, when the fiber volume <lb/>becomes excessive, the increased surface area of steel fibers leads to <lb/>insufficient cement mortar to fully encapsulate both aggregates and <lb/>fibers, resulting in compromised overall integrity and a decline in <lb/>compressive strength, demonstrating an initial increase followed by <lb/>a decrease (Zhao et al., 2022; Weli et al., 2020; Wang et al., 2021; <lb/>Wang et al., 2022; Zhang and Liu, 2023). <lb/>The copper-coated steel fibers form a dense oxide layer, <lb/>providing a good bond with the concrete and reducing susceptibility <lb/>to corrosion during curing, which achieves the highest compressive <lb/>strength at 28 days. In contrast, the hooked-end and wavy steel <lb/>fibers, lacking corrosion resistance treatment, exhibited rust on <lb/>the fiber surfaces as the curing period progressed. This rust <lb/>led to volume expansion from Fe(OH)₂ and Fe(OH)₃ formation, <lb/>which, in turn, weakened compressive strength, causing the 14-day <lb/>compressive strength to exceed that of the 28-day mark. <lb/>As shown in Figure 3, the concrete specimen was subjected to <lb/>compression, radial cracking appeared around the specimen, while <lb/>the middle portion, due to the weaker hoop effect, experienced <lb/>localized lateral spalling of the concrete and the formation of fine <lb/>cracks, as shown in Figure 4. Upon reaching the ultimate load, <lb/>the specimen failed with a muffled sound, and through-cracks <lb/>appeared. However, no fiber breakage was observed. At the location <lb/>of the longitudinal cracks, the overlapping of steel fibers was clearly <lb/>visible. Unlike typical BFRC, the specimen did not shatter, and its <lb/>integrity was well-maintained during the failure process, exhibiting <lb/>characteristics of plastic failure. <lb/>3.4 T 2 spectrum analysis <lb/>Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) uses the CPMG pulse <lb/>sequence test on fully saturated water samples to obtain decay signals <lb/>from spin echoes, which are then transformed into T 2 spectra using <lb/>Fourier transform. The distribution of the T 2 spectrum reflects the <lb/>pore size. In this experiment, the MesoMR-60 NMR instrument <lb/>was used to analyze the concrete structure. Figure 5 shows the T 2 <lb/>spectrum obtained from the nuclear magnetic resonance test. <lb/>Figure 5A shows the T2 relaxation time spectra of BFRC with <lb/>different volume fractions of end-hooked steel fibers at the 28-day <lb/>curing period, where Is represents signal intensity. It can be seen <lb/>that the internal pore distribution of the concrete exhibits a positive <lb/>correlation. As the volume fraction of steel fibers increases, the <lb/>spectrum area first decreases and then increases. The SF1.0 group <lb/>has the smallest spectrum area, confirming that a 1.0% volume <lb/>fraction is the optimal dosage for end-hooked steel fibers. The <lb/>introduction of steel fibers results in a significant narrowing of the <lb/>main peak and a slight reduction in the area of the secondary peak. <lb/>However, when the volume fraction of steel fibers exceeds 1.0%, <lb/>the internal pores in the concrete increase, and the spectrum area <lb/>expands. This may be due to excessive fiber content, leading to a <lb/>larger specific surface area, which prevents full encapsulation of the <lb/>fibers by the cement paste. <lb/>Figure 5B studies the changes in the internal micro-pore <lb/>structure of BFRC with a 1.0% volume fraction of end-hooked <lb/>steel fibers as the curing period progresses. At 3 days of curing, <lb/>the spectrum presents a &quot;three-peak&quot; structure, while at 7, 14, and <lb/>28 days, it transitions to a &quot;two-peak&quot; structure, indicating that <lb/>the internal pore structure and quantity evolve over time, which <lb/>in turn affects the compressive strength. Since the spectrum area <lb/>is proportional to the volume of fluid in the concrete, it also <lb/>reflects changes in pore volume. The number of peaks corresponds <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 5 <lb/>(A) Different volume fractions of end-hooked steel fiber BFRC at 28 days. (B) Different curing periods for BFRC with 1% volume fraction of end-hooked <lb/>steel fiber. Nuclear magnetic resonance T2 spectrum. <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>(A) BFRC with different volume fractions of end-hooked steel fibers at 28 days. (B) Porosity and saturation changes for BFRC with 1% volume fraction of <lb/>end-hooked steel fibers at different curing times. Nuclear magnetic resonance T2 spectrum. <lb/>to the distribution characteristics of the pore structure. At the 3-<lb/>day curing period, the main peak reaches the highest value, and <lb/>the spectrum area is the largest, indicating that the hydration <lb/>reaction of the cement is not yet complete, leaving many unfilled <lb/>pores, which leads to lower compressive strength. As the curing <lb/>time extends, harmful pores (&quot;three-peak&quot; structure) gradually <lb/>disappear, and the area of harmless pores (&quot;two-peak&quot; structure) <lb/>decreases with time. This is due to the progressive filling of pores by <lb/>cement hydration products, increasing the density and improving <lb/>the compressive strength. However, during the 14-to 28-day <lb/>curing period, steel fibers undergo corrosion, and the resulting iron <lb/>compounds expand in volume, weakening the bond between the <lb/>steel fibers and the cementitious matrix. This not only fails to prevent <lb/>the expansion of micro-cracks but also interferes with the formation <lb/>and filling of cement hydration products, leading to a decrease in <lb/>density and an increase in pore size. <lb/>3.5 Analysis of porosity and saturation <lb/>The concept of fluid saturation was introduced to analyze the <lb/>internal pore structure changes of BFRC. Bound fluid exists within <lb/>the micro-pores of the concrete, and the greater the bound fluid <lb/>saturation, the more micro-pores in the concrete, indicating higher <lb/>compactness. <lb/>Figure 6A shows the trend of saturation (S) and porosity (θ pd ) <lb/>of BFRC with different volume fractions of end-hooked steel fibers <lb/>at the 28-day curing period. As the volume fraction of steel fibers <lb/>increases, the saturation of the bound fluid in the concrete initially <lb/>rises and then falls. It can be observed that the SF1.0 group <lb/>exhibits the highest bound fluid saturation, with an 18.53% increase <lb/>compared to the control group. Porosity is an important indicator <lb/>that reflects the ratio of pore volume to the volume of the concrete <lb/>matrix. The smaller the porosity, the fewer internal pores, and the <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 7 <lb/>Pore size distribution. <lb/>more compact the structure. The SF1.0 group&apos;s porosity is 0.242% <lb/>lower than the control group. <lb/>Figure 6B shows the changes in porosity and saturation over <lb/>time for BFRC with a 1% volume fraction of end-hooked steel <lb/>fibers. Similar to Figure 6A, bound fluid saturation increases first <lb/>and then decreases as curing time progresses. At the 14-day <lb/>curing period, due to the hydration reaction of cement filling <lb/>the pores, porosity decreased by 0.121% compared to the 3-<lb/>day period, while bound fluid saturation increased by 35.88%. <lb/>By the 28-day curing period, rust spots had appeared on the <lb/>surface of the steel fibers, leading to changes in the pore structure. <lb/>Porosity slightly increased by 0.012%, and bound fluid saturation <lb/>decreased by 1.61%. <lb/>3.6 Analysis of porosity and saturation <lb/>The pore distribution within the concrete can be determined <lb/>through the transverse relaxation time (T 2 ). The internal pores are <lb/>classified into three types: gel pores (T 2 &lt; 1 m), capillary pores <lb/>(1 m &lt; T 2 &lt; 100 m), and non-capillary pores (T 2 &gt; 100 m). The <lb/>presence of gel and capillary pores has no significant impact on the <lb/>compressive strength of the concrete and is therefore referred to as <lb/>harmless pores. In contrast, non-capillary pores have larger pore <lb/>sizes, and the greater the number of non-capillary pores, the more <lb/>they negatively impact the compressive strength of the concrete, <lb/>thus being referred to as harmful pores. Figure 7 shows the pore <lb/>size distribution. <lb/>From Figure 7, it can be observed that after 28 days of hydration, <lb/>the proportion of harmless pores in BFRC reaches 64.6%. With the <lb/>increase in steel fiber content, the proportion of harmless pores <lb/>initially increases and then decreases. When the volume content <lb/>of hooked-end steel fibers is 1.0%, the proportion of harmless <lb/>pores reaches a maximum of 81.9%, indicating that the internal <lb/>structure of the concrete is most compact at this point. However, <lb/>when the steel fiber content increases to 1.2%, the proportion of <lb/>harmful pores rises from 18.1% to 21.4%. This phenomenon is <lb/>primarily due to the excessive amount of steel fibers, which increases <lb/>the specific surface area, preventing the cement paste from fully <lb/>enveloping the fibers. This is consistent with the trend observed in <lb/>the bound fluid saturation, further confirming that the rusting of <lb/>steel fibers impacts the internal pore structure of the concrete. As the <lb/>number of harmful pores increases, the compressive strength of the <lb/>concrete decreases. <lb/>4 Optimization algorithms applied to <lb/>the performance prediction of <lb/>fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate <lb/>concrete <lb/>4.1 Data preparation <lb/>The dataset used in this study consists of 120 experimental <lb/>data points, primarily aimed at predicting the compressive strength <lb/>of fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (BFRC). Each data <lb/>point includes multiple input feature variables, such as the type <lb/>of steel fiber, fiber volume content, curing age, water-cement <lb/>ratio, and sand ratio. The dataset also includes the corresponding <lb/>output target variable, which is the compressive strength of <lb/>the concrete. <lb/>To ensure the reliability and generalization capability of the <lb/>model, we divided the 120 data points into a training set and a <lb/>test set at an 8:2 ratio, yielding 96 points for training and 24 for <lb/>testing. For model optimization and to avoid overfitting, we applied <lb/>five-fold cross-validation to the training data. In this process, the <lb/>training data was divided into five subsets, with each subset used <lb/>once as a validation set while the other four subsets trained the <lb/>model. This procedure fine-tuned model parameters and ensured <lb/>a robust evaluation of model performance. Figure 8 shows the <lb/>data distribution (Figure 8A) and a correlation heatmap (Figure 8B) <lb/>illustrating the relationships among variables. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 8 <lb/>(A) Data Distribution Characteristics. (B) Correlation of Indicators. <lb/>Dataset distribution and correlation heatmap. <lb/>The correlation analysis in Figure 8B highlights the relationships <lb/>between key variables. Cement content has a strong positive <lb/>correlation (0.5) with compressive strength, signifying that as <lb/>cement content increases, compressive strength also improves. <lb/>Water content exhibits a moderate positive correlation (0.3) with <lb/>compressive strength, indicating that although water contributes <lb/>to strength, its impact is less significant than that of cement. <lb/>Similarly, the water-reducing agent shows a correlation of 0.28 <lb/>with compressive strength, suggesting that it enhances mechanical <lb/>properties by lowering the water-cement ratio. Conversely, sand and <lb/>aggregate contents have negative correlations of -0.28 and -0.38, <lb/>respectively, with compressive strength, suggesting that higher <lb/>sand and aggregate proportions may reduce concrete strength. <lb/>The highest correlation, 0.8, is observed between curing age and <lb/>compressive strength, consistent with the known effect of increased <lb/>strength over time. <lb/>4.2 Evaluation metrics <lb/>In the process of model evaluation, MSE (Mean Squared Error), <lb/>MAE (Mean Absolute Error), MAPE (Mean Absolute Percentage <lb/>Error), and R 2 (Coefficient of Determination) are commonly <lb/>used performance metrics (Song et al., 2021; Chen et al., 2023). <lb/>MSE amplifies larger errors and is therefore sensitive to extreme <lb/>values, helping to capture the model&apos;s response to outliers. MAE, <lb/>on the other hand, calculates the absolute value of the error <lb/>and is not affected by the direction of the error, making it <lb/>more suitable for reflecting the overall prediction accuracy of the <lb/>model, especially when focusing on the overall error magnitude. <lb/>Additionally, MAPE expresses the error as a percentage, making <lb/>it easier to compare data across different scales, and it is suitable <lb/>for datasets with varying units or magnitudes. R 2 provides a <lb/>relative measure, assessing the model&apos;s explanatory power based <lb/>on the linear relationship between predicted and actual values. <lb/>For regression tasks, an R 2 value close to one indicates strong <lb/>explanatory power, while an R 2 value near 0 suggests poor <lb/>model performance, indicating that the model fails to capture the <lb/>relationship between the data. <lb/>To ensure comprehensive model evaluation, multiple metrics <lb/>are typically combined to analyze model performance holistically. <lb/>For example, while both MSE and MAE can measure error, MSE <lb/>emphasizes the impact of large errors, whereas MAE focuses on <lb/>the average level of error. MAPE provides information about the <lb/>relative size of the error, making it more comparable across different <lb/>datasets. R 2 , on the other hand, offers an intuitive evaluation of the <lb/>model&apos;s goodness-of-fit, allowing for a quick assessment of overall <lb/>performance. The calculation formulas for each metric are as shown <lb/>in Equations 26-29: <lb/>MSE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(y i -ŷ <lb/>i ) 2 <lb/>(26) <lb/>MAE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>|y i -ŷ <lb/>i | <lb/>(27) <lb/>MAPE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>| <lb/>y i -ŷ <lb/>i <lb/>y i <lb/>| × 100% <lb/>(28) <lb/>R 2 = 1 -<lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(y i -ŷ <lb/>i ) 2 <lb/>n <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(y i -y) 2 <lb/>(29) <lb/>4.3 Model training and parameter <lb/>optimization <lb/>To ensure the generalization ability of the model across <lb/>different datasets, this study utilized five-fold cross-validation <lb/>for model training and parameter optimization. Cross-validation <lb/>allows the model&apos;s performance to be validated on various data <lb/>splits, effectively reducing overfitting and enhancing the model&apos;s <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

  	<page>10 <lb/></page>

  	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 9 <lb/>Model loss functions. <lb/>TABLE 3 Best parameters for each model. <lb/>Model Name Parameter values <lb/>SOA-XGBoost <lb/>learning_rate = 0.1, n_estimators = 100, max_depth = 6, <lb/>subsample = 0.8 <lb/>TSA-XGBoost <lb/>learning_rate = 0.12, n_estimators = 120, max_depth = 5, <lb/>colsample_bytree = 0.7 <lb/>MA-XGBoost <lb/>learning_rate = 0.08, n_estimators = 110, max_depth = 7, <lb/>subsample = 0.75 <lb/>GWO-XGBoost <lb/>learning_rate = 0.2, n_estimators = 90, max_depth = 4, <lb/>subsample = 0.85 <lb/>SSA-XGBoost <lb/>learning_rate = 0.15, n_estimators = 95, max_depth = 6, <lb/>subsample = 0.8 <lb/>robustness. Figure 9 shows the cross-validation loss functions for <lb/>each optimized model. <lb/>The above figure demonstrates the mean squared error (MSE) <lb/>variations for five different optimization algorithms applied to <lb/>the XGBoost model (SOA-XGBoost, TSA-XGBoost, MA-XGBoost, <lb/>GWO-XGBoost, and SSA-XGBoost) over 200 iterations. As shown <lb/>in the figure, the MSE values of the three optimized models, <lb/>SOA-XGBoost, TSA-XGBoost, and MA-XGBoost, are significantly <lb/>lower than those of the traditional GWO-XGBoost and SSA-<lb/>XGBoost, indicating faster convergence and reduced errors. This <lb/>further verifies the advantage of the new optimization algorithms <lb/>in enhancing the prediction accuracy of the model. The MSE <lb/>values of the traditional optimization algorithms, GWO-XGBoost <lb/>and SSA-XGBoost, are initially higher and tend to stabilize over <lb/>time, but their final error values remain higher than those <lb/>of the newer optimization algorithms. The optimal parameter <lb/>combinations for the models, based on the minimum error, are <lb/>provided in Table 3. <lb/>4.4 Prediction performance comparison <lb/>4.4.1 Single model prediction performance <lb/>analysis <lb/>This section compares the predictive performance of the <lb/>XGBoost model against Random Forest, Support Vector Machine <lb/>(SVM), and Decision Tree for forecasting the compressive strength <lb/>of BFRC. Key performance indicators such as MSE, MAE, MAPE, <lb/>and R 2 are used to assess each model&apos;s strengths and limitations, <lb/>as shown in Figure 10. <lb/>Based on the data and experimental results shown above, the <lb/>XGBoost model outperforms other models in all performance <lb/>metrics. Specifically, the XGBoost model achieved the best results <lb/>in R 2 , MSE, MAE, and MAPE, with an R 2 value of 0.913109, <lb/>indicating a good fit. Additionally, XGBoost&apos;s MSE is 2.161113, <lb/>MAE is 1.352917, and MAPE is 4.426169, demonstrating its <lb/>clear advantage in prediction accuracy. In comparison, other <lb/>models, such as Decision Tree (DT) and Random Forest (RF), <lb/>although providing relatively high prediction accuracy, still fall <lb/>behind XGBoost in key metrics. Particularly, the Decision Tree <lb/>model has an MSE of 6.012483 and an MAE of 2.256667, <lb/>indicating a relatively higher prediction error. The Support Vector <lb/>Machine (SVM) shows some advantage in handling nonlinear <lb/>relationships, with an MAE of 1.660417, slightly higher than <lb/>XGBoost. However, in terms of MSE and MAPE, it still lags <lb/>behind XGBoost, revealing its limitations in overall predictive <lb/>capability. <lb/>The XGBoost model, leveraging the benefits of ensemble <lb/>learning and gradient boosting, effectively captures nonlinear <lb/>relationships in complex data, outperforming other models across <lb/>all performance metrics. This is especially evident in predicting the <lb/>performance of Fiber Reinforced Recycled Aggregate Concrete, a <lb/>complex task. Therefore, the XGBoost model can be considered the <lb/>best choice for this type of prediction task, as it exhibits greater <lb/>robustness and generalization ability. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/>11 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 10 <lb/>Single machine learning model prediction performance analysis. <lb/>4.4.2 Optimized Model Prediction Performance <lb/>Analysis <lb/>In this section, a detailed analysis was conducted on the <lb/>prediction performance of Fiber Reinforced Recycled Aggregate <lb/>Concrete by combining different optimization algorithms with the <lb/>XGBoost model. By comparing the prediction results of SOA-<lb/>XGBoost, TSA-XGBoost, MA-XGBoost, and traditional optimization <lb/>models like GWO-XGBoost and SSA-XGBoost, Figure 11 clearly <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 11 <lb/>Optimized model prediction performance analysis. <lb/>demonstrates the differences in model fitting accuracy and <lb/>prediction error. <lb/>The data in Figure 11 highlights notable differences in the <lb/>predictive performance of various optimization models for Fiber <lb/>Reinforced Recycled Aggregate Concrete. The three models <lb/>enhanced by optimization algorithms-SOA-XGBoost, TSA-<lb/>XGBoost, and MA-XGBoost-demonstrated excellent performance <lb/>across all evaluation metrics, with R 2 values of 0.9847, 0.9897, and <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<body>0.9889, respectively. These values indicate high fitting accuracy, <lb/>showing that the models effectively captured the relationship <lb/>between input features and target outputs. Additionally, these <lb/>models exhibited low MSE and MAE values, with TSA-XGBoost <lb/>achieving the best results, reaching an MSE of 0.255958 and an <lb/>MAE of 0.364167. <lb/>In comparison, the traditional optimization models GWO-<lb/>XGBoost and SSA-XGBoost underperformed. Although GWO-<lb/>XGBoost maintained moderate fitting accuracy with an R 2 <lb/>of 0.9338, it had relatively high error values, with an MSE <lb/>of 1.646958 and an MAE of 1.258333. SSA-XGBoost showed <lb/>similar performance, with an R 2 of 0.9101 and an MSE of <lb/>2.234958, reflecting inadequate prediction accuracy, especially <lb/>for data points with larger errors. The MAPE values for GWO-<lb/>XGBoost and SSA-XGBoost were 4.100240% and 4.809841%, <lb/>respectively, further emphasizing their limitations in overall <lb/>predictive performance. <lb/>Integrating SOA, TSA, and MA optimization algorithms with <lb/>the XGBoost model significantly enhances prediction accuracy, <lb/>especially in reducing error metrics like MSE and MAE, compared to <lb/>traditional GWO and SSA models. This improvement suggests that <lb/>these newer optimization algorithms offer substantial advantages <lb/>for handling complex nonlinear problems, effectively capturing <lb/>intricate feature relationships in high-dimensional data, and yielding <lb/>more accurate and robust predictions. <lb/>5 Discussion <lb/>This study conducted an experimental and analytical evaluation <lb/>of how different steel fiber types and dosages affect the compressive <lb/>strength of basalt fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete <lb/>(BFRC). By employing the XGBoost model enhanced with SOA, <lb/>TSA, and MA optimization algorithms, we achieved improved <lb/>prediction accuracy, highlighting the potential of these methods <lb/>for accurately forecasting BFRC performance. The results indicated <lb/>that an appropriate amount of steel fiber enhances concrete&apos;s <lb/>ductility, toughness, and compressive strength. However, excessive <lb/>steel fiber led to increased porosity, reducing mechanical strength, <lb/>and highlighting the need for balanced fiber dosages. <lb/>The applicability of these predictive methods to broader <lb/>engineering contexts is promising but requires consideration <lb/>of practical constraints. For instance, although the SOA, TSA, <lb/>and MA optimizations effectively boost model accuracy, their <lb/>computational complexity and associated costs may limit real-<lb/>world implementation in large-scale projects. Addressing these <lb/>constraints involves optimizing algorithmic efficiency while <lb/>retaining predictive accuracy. Additionally, expanding the model <lb/>to account for varying material types and environmental factors <lb/>would strengthen its adaptability across diverse engineering <lb/>applications. Future work should thus focus on refining <lb/>machine learning models for operational feasibility and on <lb/>extending the scope of variables, potentially including other <lb/>fiber types and optimizing combinations, to reinforce BFRC&apos;s <lb/>performance further. These efforts can support the wider adoption <lb/>of fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete in practical <lb/>construction applications, ultimately advancing sustainable <lb/>engineering practices. <lb/>6 Conclusion <lb/>(1) In this study, we experimentally validated the impact of <lb/>different types and dosages of steel fibers on the compressive <lb/>strength of BFRC. The results indicated that an appropriate <lb/>dosage of steel fibers effectively improved compressive <lb/>strength, with strength initially increasing and then decreasing <lb/>as fiber content increased. Copper-coated steel fibers exhibited <lb/>the best reinforcement effect, with compressive strength <lb/>peaking at 28 days. In contrast, hooked and wavy steel fibers <lb/>showed a decline in compressive strength over time due to <lb/>environmental influences. <lb/>(2) As the steel fiber dosage increased, the ductility and toughness <lb/>of the concrete gradually improved, while porosity initially <lb/>decreased and then increased. Bound fluid saturation also <lb/>showed an increase followed by a decrease. A moderate <lb/>amount of steel fibers reduced harmful pores and improved the <lb/>compactness of the concrete, while excessive fibers increased <lb/>porosity due to a larger specific surface area, negatively <lb/>impacting overall performance. With longer curing times, <lb/>the internal pore structure of the concrete was optimized, <lb/>and hydration reactions made the concrete more compact. <lb/>However, the issue of steel fiber corrosion became evident over <lb/>time, reducing the bond strength between fibers and the matrix <lb/>and lowering compressive strength. <lb/>(3) The XGBoost model combined with different optimization <lb/>algorithms, such as Seagull Optimization Algorithm (SOA), <lb/>Tunicate Swarm Algorithm (TSA), and Mayfly Algorithm <lb/>(MA), demonstrated high accuracy in predicting BFRC <lb/>compressive strength, particularly the TSA-XGBoost model, <lb/>which achieved an R 2 of 0.9897, with MSE and MAE of <lb/>0.255958 and 0.364167, respectively, outperforming other <lb/>models. These optimization algorithms significantly improved <lb/>the predictive performance of XGBoost by efficiently tuning <lb/>model parameters. <lb/>This study not only provides theoretical insights into predicting <lb/>the compressive strength of BFRC but also demonstrates the <lb/>broad application potential of machine learning algorithms in <lb/>civil engineering. The XGBoost model, enhanced by optimization <lb/>algorithms, delivers more accurate and stable prediction results, <lb/>offering valuable references for predicting concrete performance in <lb/>practical engineering. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included in <lb/>the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>SD: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/></div>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">administration, Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing-original draft, Writing-review and editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for <lb/>the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>Generative AI statement <lb/>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the <lb/>creation of this manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim <lb/>that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed <lb/>by the publisher. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Amudha, M., Ramachandran, M., Sivaji, C., and Kamalanathan, S. (2021). A study <lb/>on climate change with mayfly algorithm optimization. Recent Trends Manag. Commer. <lb/>2 (3), 23-28. <lb/>Anand, P., Sharma, B., Rizwan, M., and Saini, M. K. (2024). Size optimization of grid-<lb/>tied hybrid energy system by employing forecasted meteorological data. MAPAN 39 (3), <lb/>739-750. doi:10.1007/s12647-024-00758-x <lb/>Asselman, A., Khaldi, M., and Aammou, S. (2023). Enhancing the prediction of <lb/>student performance based on the machine learning XGBoost algorithm. Interact. <lb/>Learn. Environ. 31 (6), 3360-3379. doi:10.1080/10494820.2021.1928235 <lb/>Bhattacharyya, T., Chatterjee, B., Singh, P. K., Biswas, S., Geem, Z. W., and Sarkar, R. <lb/>(2020). Mayfly in harmony: a new hybrid meta-heuristic feature selection algorithm. <lb/>IEEE Access 8, 195929-195945. doi:10.1109/access.2020.3031718 <lb/>Che, Y., and He, D. (2022). An enhanced seagull optimization algorithm for <lb/>solving engineering optimization problems. Appl. Intell. 52 (11), 13043-13081. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s10489-021-03155-y <lb/>Chen, G. M., He, Y. H., Yang, H., Chen, J. F., and Guo, Y. C. (2014). Compressive <lb/>behavior of steel fiber reinforced recycled aggregate concrete after exposure to elevated <lb/>temperatures. Constr. Build. Mater. 71, 1-15. doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2014.08.012 <lb/>Chen, J., Liu, Z., Yin, Z., Li, Y., Wang, X., Yin, L., et al. (2023). Predict the effect <lb/>of meteorological factors on haze using BP neural network. Urban Clim. 51, 101630. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.uclim.2023.101630 <lb/>Eady, M., Setia, G., Park, B., Mohan, R. K., and Bhandari, B. (2023). Biopolymer <lb/>encapsulated silver nitrate nanoparticle substrates with surface-enhanced Raman <lb/>spectroscopy (SERS) for Salmonella detection from chicken rinse. Int. J. Food Microbiol. <lb/>391, 110158. doi:10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2023.110158 <lb/>El Mahdi Safhi, A., Dabiri, H., Soliman, A., and Nehdi, M. (2023). <lb/>Prediction of self-consolidating concrete properties using XGBoost machine <lb/>learning algorithm: Part 1-workability. Constr. Build. Mater. 408, 133560. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2023.133560 <lb/>Elshazli, M. T., Ramirez, K., Ibrahim, A., Alkayed, H., and Kassem, M. (2022). <lb/>Mechanical, durability and corrosion properties of basalt fiber concrete. Fibers 10 (2), <lb/>10. doi:10.3390/fib10020010 <lb/>Fang, S. E., Hong, H. S., and Zhang, P. H. (2018). Mechanical property tests and <lb/>strength formulas of basalt fiber reinforced recycled aggregate concrete. Materials 11 <lb/>(10), 1851. doi:10.3390/ma11101851 <lb/>Ghoneim, M., Yehia, A., Yehia, S., and Ibrahim, H. (2020). Shear strength <lb/>of fiber reinforced recycled aggregate concrete. Materials 13 (18), 4183. <lb/>doi:10.3390/ma13184183 <lb/>Heeralal, M., Kumar, R. P., and Rao, Y. V. (2009). Flexural fatigue characteristics of <lb/>steel fiber reinforced recycled aggregate concrete (SFRRAC). Ser. Archit. Civ. Eng. 7 (1), <lb/>19-33. doi:10.2298/fuace0901019h <lb/>Kang, M. C., Yoo, D. Y., Gupta, R., and Shin, J. W. (2021). Machine learning-based <lb/>prediction for compressive and flexural strengths of steel fiber-reinforced concrete. <lb/>Constr. Build. Mater. 266, 121117. doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2020.121117 <lb/>Khan, M., Cao, M., Xie, C., and Shi, C. (2022). Hybrid fiber concrete <lb/>with different basalt fiber length and content. Struct. Concr. 23 (1), 346-364. <lb/>doi:10.1002/suco.202000472 <lb/>Li, Y., Zhang, J., He, Y., Zhang, C., Qin, J., Niu, Z., et al. (2022). A review on <lb/>durability of basalt fiber reinforced concrete. Compos. Sci. Technol. 225, 109519. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.compscitech.2022.109519 <lb/>Liu, G., Guo, Z., Liu, W., Zhang, X., Wu, Y., and Wang, C. (2023). MSHHOTSA: a <lb/>variant of tunicate swarm algorithm combining multi-strategy mechanism and hybrid <lb/>Harris optimization. PLOS ONE 18 (8), e0290117. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0290117 <lb/>Mohan, Y., Yadav, R. K., Manjul, M., and Dhiman, G. (2024). Seagull optimization <lb/>algorithm for node localization in wireless sensor networks. Multimedia Tools Appl. 83, <lb/>70793-70814. doi:10.1007/s11042-024-18331-8 <lb/>Naga Sai Kalyan, C. H., Goud, B. S., Reddy, C. R., Venkatraman, R., Bajaj, M., <lb/>Sharma, N. K., et al. (2022). Seagull optimization algorithm-based fractional-order <lb/>fuzzy controller for LFC of multi-area diverse source system with realistic constraints. <lb/>Front. Energy Res. 10, 921426. doi:10.3389/fenrg.2022.921426 <lb/>Nikolenko, S. D., Sazonova, S. A., Asminin, V. F., Vorontsov, P., and Tsvetkova, O. <lb/>V. (2021). Flexural strength of fiber reinforced concrete structures. Online 1889 (2), <lb/>022075. doi:10.1088/1742-6596/1889/2/022075 <lb/>Qiu, Y., Zhou, J., Khandelwal, M., Xu, G., and Yang, P. (2022). Performance evaluation <lb/>of hybrid WOA-XGBoost, GWO-XGBoost and BO-XGBoost models to predict blast-<lb/>induced ground vibration. Eng. Comput. 38 (Suppl. 5), 4145-4162. doi:10.1007/s00366-<lb/>021-01393-9 <lb/>Raza, S. S., Qureshi, L. A., Ali, B., Iftikhar, Y., and Khan, M. M. (2021). Effect of <lb/>different fibers (steel fibers, glass fibers, and carbon fibers) on mechanical properties of <lb/>reactive powder concrete. Struct. Concr. 22 (1), 334-346. doi:10.1002/suco.201900439 <lb/>Sagi, O., and Rokach, L. (2021). Approximating XGBoost with an interpretable <lb/>decision tree. Inf. Sci. 572, 522-542. doi:10.1016/j.ins.2021.05.055 <lb/>Sankar, S., Somula, R., Parvathala, B., Puli, R. K., and Pulipati, S. (2022). SOA-<lb/>EACR: seagull optimization algorithm based energy aware cluster routing protocol for <lb/>wireless sensor networks in the livestock industry. Sustain. Comput. Inf. Syst. 33, 100645. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.suscom.2021.100645 <lb/>Saud, S., Jamil, B., Upadhyay, Y., and Raheman, H. (2020). Performance improvement <lb/>of empirical models for estimation of global solar radiation in India: a k-<lb/>fold cross-validation approach. Sustain. Energy Technol. Assessments 40, 100768. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.seta.2020.100768 <lb/>Shahjalal, M., Islam, K., Batool, F., Mahmud, T., Zia, A., Khan, S. U., et al. (2023). <lb/>Fiber-reinforced recycled aggregate concrete with crumb rubber: a state-of-the-art <lb/>review. Constr. Build. Mater. 404, 133233. doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2023.133233 <lb/>Sharma, A., Sharma, A., Jately, V., Goswami, A., Sharma, A. K., and Azzopardi, B. <lb/>(2022). A novel TSA-PSO based hybrid algorithm for GMPP tracking under partial <lb/>shading conditions. Energies 15 (9), 3164. doi:10.3390/en15093164 <lb/>Song, S., Xiong, X., Wu, X., and Liu, Q. (2021). Modeling the SOFC by <lb/>BP neural network algorithm. Int. J. Hydrogen Energy 46 (38), 20065-20077. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.ijhydene.2021.03.132 <lb/>Sun, Z., Li, Y., Yang, Y., Zhang, Q., and Qin, L. (2024). Splitting tensile <lb/>strength of basalt fiber reinforced coral aggregate concrete: optimized XGBoost <lb/>models and experimental validation. Constr. Build. Mater. 416, 135133. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2024.135133 <lb/>Tao, H., Ali, Z. H., Mukhtar, F., Ahmad, S., Marhoon, H. A., Goliatt, L., et al. (2024). <lb/>Coupled extreme gradient boosting algorithm with artificial intelligence models for <lb/>predicting compressive strength of fiber reinforced polymer-confined concrete. Eng. <lb/>Appl. Artif. Intell. 134, 108674. doi:10.1016/j.engappai.2024.108674 <lb/>Wang, S., Xia, P., Gong, F., Zeng, Q., Chen, K., and Zhao, Y. (2024). Multi objective <lb/>optimization of recycled aggregate concrete based on explainable machine learning. J. <lb/>Clean. Prod., 445: 141045, doi:10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.141045 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>15 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">Duan <lb/>10.3389/fbuil.2024.1509714 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Wang, S., Xia, P., Wang, Z., Meng, T., and Gong, F. (2023). Intelligent mix design of <lb/>recycled brick aggregate concrete based on swarm intelligence. J. Build. Eng. 71: 106508, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jobe.2023.106508 <lb/>Wang, X., Fan, F., Lai, J., Peng, Z., and Cao, Z. (2021). Steel fiber reinforced concrete: <lb/>a review of its material properties and usage in tunnel lining. Structures 34, 1080-1098. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.istruc.2021.07.086 <lb/>Wang, X., Pan, J. S., Yang, Q., Luo, X., Li, J., and Shi, H. (2022). Modified <lb/>mayfly algorithm for UAV path planning. Drones 6 (5), 134. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>drones6050134 <lb/>Weli, S. S., Abbood, I. S., Hasan, K. F., and Alwan, H. M. (2020). Effect of steel fibers <lb/>on the concrete strength grade: a review. Proc. IOP Conf. Ser. Mater. Sci. Eng. 888 (1), <lb/>012043. doi:10.1088/1757-899x/888/1/012043 <lb/>Wu, H., Qin, X., Huang, X., Chen, Y., and Xu, H. (2023). Engineering, mechanical <lb/>and dynamic properties of basalt fiber reinforced concrete. Materials 16 (2), 623. <lb/>doi:10.3390/ma16020623 <lb/>Yang, J., Chen, B., and Nuti, C. (2021). Influence of steel fiber on compressive <lb/>properties of ultra-high performance fiber-reinforced concrete. Constr. Build. Mater. <lb/>302, 124104. doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2021.124104 <lb/>Zaid, O., Mukhtar, F. M., Rebeca, M., Hassan, H., and Mohamed, A. M. <lb/>(2022). Characteristics of high-performance steel fiber reinforced recycled <lb/>aggregate concrete utilizing mineral filler. Case Stud. Constr. Mater. 16, e00939. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cscm.2022.e00939 <lb/>Zhang, P., Wang, K., Wang, J., Guo, J., Hu, S., and Ling, Y. (2020). Mechanical <lb/>properties and prediction of fracture parameters of geopolymer/alkali-activated <lb/>mortar modified with PVA fiber and nano-SiO2. Ceram. Int. 46(12): 20027-20037. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.ceramint.2020.05.074 <lb/>Zhang, X., and Liu, C. A. (2023). Model averaging prediction by K-fold cross-<lb/>validation. J. Econ. 235 (1), 280-301. doi:10.1016/j.jeconom.2022.04.007 <lb/>Zhang, X., Zhang, P., Yuan, W., and Hu, S. (2024). Durability prediction of <lb/>geopolymer mortar reinforced with nanoparticles and PVA fiber using particle swarm <lb/>optimized BP neural network. Nanotechnol. Rev. 13(1): 20230214, doi:10.1515/ntrev-<lb/>2023-0214 <lb/>Zhao, M., Yang, X., and Yin, X. (2022). An improved mayfly algorithm and its <lb/>application. AIP Adv. 12 (10), 105101. doi:10.1063/5.0108278 <lb/>Zheng, Y., Zhang, Y., Zhuo, J., Li, J., and Zhang, X. (2022). A review of the mechanical <lb/>properties and durability of basalt fiber-reinforced concrete. Constr. Build. Mater. 359, <lb/>129360. doi:10.1016/j.conbuildmat.2022.129360 <lb/>Zhou, H., Jia, B., Huang, H., Ma, G., and Ren, M. (2020). Experimental study on <lb/>basic mechanical properties of basalt fiber reinforced concrete. Materials 13 (6), 1362. <lb/>doi:10.3390/ma13061362 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Built Environment <lb/></note>

	<page>16 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org </note>


  </text>

</TEI>