<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T11:03:26.659Z">11/20/2025 11:03:26 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T11:03:14.323920Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T11:03:14.323920Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Flow of mangrove ecosystem <lb/>services to coastal communities in <lb/>the Brazilian Amazon <lb/>Margaret Owuor 1,2 , Thuareag M. T. Santos 3 , Philip Otieno 4 , <lb/>Ana Carolina A. Mazzuco 3 , Chima Iheaturu 5 and <lb/>Angelo F. Bernardino 3 * <lb/>1 Wyss Academy for Nature at the University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland, 2 Institute of Ecology and <lb/>Evolution, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland, 3 Departamento de Oceanografia, Universidade Federal <lb/>do Espírito Santo, Vitória, ES, Brazil, 4 Biosfera Research and Consulting Ltd., Nairobi, Kenya, 5 Institute of <lb/>Geography, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland <lb/>Mangrove forests are broadly recognized to support a variety of ecosystem <lb/>services on coastal margins worldwide. These services may significantly <lb/>contribute to the wellbeing of millions of people, but there is limited <lb/>information about their importance in the Global South. This study mapped <lb/>for the first time the flow of ecosystem services in Brazilian Amazon mangroves, <lb/>which represent over 700,000 ha of mangroves in the country. We also identified <lb/>the spatial changes in the flow of services across coastal landscapes, including <lb/>urban, agricultural upland areas and coastal natural protected areas. Our matrix <lb/>model indicated that mangroves, waterbodies, sandflats and mudflats are critical <lb/>to the flow of multiple ecosystem services, including provisioning (fish, <lb/>mariculture), cultural (historical and intrinsic value, research, and education), <lb/>and regulation (climate, flood control, nursery, and breeding grounds). Social <lb/>economic context, occupation, education, and residence time are important <lb/>factors influencing villagers to identify the flow of ecosystem services, which <lb/>could be compared across other coastal marine reserves in South America that <lb/>have similar management of natural resources. Adjacent coastal upland habitats <lb/>such as forests and croplands are important to support many provisioning <lb/>ecosystem services to coastal villagers that would otherwise be obtained from <lb/>mangroves, suggesting that protecting these connected habitats and supporting <lb/>small-scale agriculture may help to avoid deforestation of mangrove forests. As <lb/>over 80% of the mangroves in the country are managed as extractive reserves and <lb/>may support communities with comparable socio-economic characteristics, we <lb/>provide a foundation for the development and replication of ecosystem services <lb/>assessments in Brazilian mangroves, which cover an area of over 1 million <lb/>hectares. Our work highlights the importance of mangrove forests in <lb/>providing food, and cultural services and to increase local climate resilience of <lb/>coastal villages in the Amazon coast. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>wetlands, ecosystem services, marine reserve, management, fishers <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Renato Silvano, <lb/>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Paula Pereyra, <lb/>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil <lb/>Susan Harrell Yee, <lb/>United States Environmental Protection <lb/>Agency, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Angelo F. Bernardino, <lb/>angelo.bernardino@ufes.br <lb/>RECEIVED 30 October 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 23 January 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 07 February 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Owuor M, Santos TMT, Otieno P, Mazzuco ACA, <lb/>Iheaturu C and Bernardino AF (2024), Flow of <lb/>mangrove ecosystem services to coastal <lb/>communities in the Brazilian Amazon. <lb/>Front. Environ. Sci. 12:1329006. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Owuor, Santos, Otieno, Mazzuco, <lb/>Iheaturu and Bernardino. This is an open-access <lb/>article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). <lb/>The use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in this <lb/>journal is cited, in accordance with accepted <lb/>academic practice. No use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction is permitted which does not <lb/>comply with these terms. <lb/>Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 07 February 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Mangrove forests are important coastal ecosystems with <lb/>potential value to climate change mitigation and adaptation <lb/>strategies worldwide (Murdiyarso et al., 2015; Bernardino et al., <lb/>2024). Their efficient capacity as carbon sinks has led to an increased <lb/>interest in evaluating regional and global variability in carbon stocks <lb/>and burial in mangrove forests (Bernardino et al., 2020; Kauffman, <lb/>et al., 2020; Breithaupt and Steinmuller, 2022; Passos et al., 2023). <lb/>Mangroves may offer numerous ecological benefits through carbon <lb/>accumulation and burial in tropical coasts, and many other <lb/>ecosystem services (ES) that provide multiple direct and indirect <lb/>resources to coastal communities (Barbier et al., 2011; Gutting et al., <lb/>2021). Over the past years, scientists have connected mangroves to <lb/>provisioning ES, from fish capture to pharmaceuticals; to regulating <lb/>ES, from natural hazard mitigation to pollination; to cultural ES, <lb/>from aesthetic value to cultural heritage; and to supporting ES, from <lb/>primary production to nursery grounds (Barbier et al., 2011; Himes-<lb/>Cornell et al., 2018; Afonso et al., 2021). As a result, conserving <lb/>mangrove forests is regarded as an important climate adaptation <lb/>strategy to curb carbon emissions, as well as a public good by coastal <lb/>communities regardless of their legal protection as reserves or the <lb/>value assigned to them in economic markets. <lb/>As an opposing pressure, the continuous population growth and <lb/>rapid coastal development have made mangroves one of the planet&apos;s <lb/>most endangered ecosystems (Goldberg et al., 2020). Estimated <lb/>global loss of mangrove cover varies between 0.16% and 0.39% <lb/>annually (Goldberg et al., 2020), and the conversion of mangroves <lb/>into agriculture, aquaculture, and urban areas is a main driver of <lb/>mangrove deforestation (Kauffman, et al., 2016; Kauffman, et al., <lb/>2018a). In parallel to the losses of ecological processes in degraded <lb/>mangroves, which may include carbon capture and forest <lb/>productivity (Gomes et al., 2021a; 2021b), the loss of mangroves <lb/>may limit their potential to deliver ecosystem services in the future. <lb/>Simultaneous with conservation and restoration efforts, mangrove <lb/>sustainability in the long term fundamentally depends on the <lb/>valuation of its ecosystem services (both monetary and non-<lb/>monetary), as well as the identification of the connections (or the <lb/>flow) between the ecosystem, biodiversity, and the benefits <lb/>communities derive. Detailing this information is essential to <lb/>improve management instruments such as spatial planning, <lb/>impact assessment, and environmental fines which currently are <lb/>developed based on very scarce data (CDB, 2012; Canonico <lb/>et al., 2019). <lb/>Since the development of the concepts around ecosystem <lb/>services (ES), a wide range of evaluation frameworks and <lb/>mapping approaches have been developed to fit a variety of <lb/>contexts. ES mapping is particularly useful to link biophysical <lb/>processes underlying ecosystem structure with human-induced <lb/>modifications, such as land-use change (Müller and Burkhard, <lb/>2012). The identification of flow between ecosystem components <lb/>and uses enables the evaluation of services&apos; sustainability <lb/>according to different scenarios and the connection between <lb/>areas or habitats (Bagstad et al., 2013; Burkhard et al., 2014), <lb/>also providing information on the current and future biophysical <lb/>capacity of an area to produce ES. In this study, flow is used in <lb/>context as defined by Burkhard et al. (2014) to mean de facto used <lb/>set (bundles) of ecosystem services and other outputs from <lb/>natural systems in a particular area within a given period. To <lb/>that end, the use of flow maps helps to recognize the spatial <lb/>distribution of ES that could support different types of decision-<lb/>making for the conservation of many ecosystems (Bagstad <lb/>et al., 2013). <lb/>Recent approaches to ES mapping also incorporate stakeholders <lb/>into the modeling process (Campagne and Roche, 2018), thus <lb/>improving legitimacy, enhancing knowledge sharing, and <lb/>highlighting the ES that are most important to a particular <lb/>context. Studies show that the understanding of localization and <lb/>different knowledge systems, as reflected by the different users on <lb/>the uses of mangroves, contributes to management effectiveness by <lb/>improving the role local users play in decision-making as <lb/>beneficiaries of mangrove ecosystem services (Ruslan et al., <lb/>2022). This methodological rationale is appropriate for regions <lb/>where various stakeholders depend on a particular ecosystem but <lb/>have competing interests that affect the ecosystem&apos;s health, which is <lb/>the case of the Amazon mangrove forests in Brazil. Hence, based on <lb/>multiple evidences for the provision of ecosystem services from <lb/>wetlands to local villagers (Barbier et al., 2011; Himes-Cornell et al., <lb/>2018), we hypothesize in this study that indigenous and local <lb/>community groups depend on and access the resources or benefit <lb/>from the regional coastal landscapes. Identifying the flow of <lb/>ecosystem services with stakeholder&apos;s involvement helps them to <lb/>identify areas of resource use and foster the conservation of <lb/>ecosystems they rely on. Considering the fast pace of the current <lb/>changing world, multiple stressors (e.g., climate change, <lb/>infrastructure development, biodiversity loss, and changing <lb/>consumption patterns), the ability to follow changes in ES in <lb/>space and time allows researchers to accurately estimate drivers&apos; <lb/>impact on ES delivery (Campagne and Roche, 2018). Besides, when <lb/>built together with local residents, such evaluations of ES trade-offs <lb/>can significantly enhance policy, community-based conservation, <lb/>and ecosystem-based approaches to the management of such <lb/>resources (Campagne and Roche, 2018). <lb/>Brazilian mangroves are among the largest in the world, of <lb/>which over 70% are located along northern Brazil&apos;s Amazon <lb/>coastline (Bernardino et al., 2021). These mangroves are typically <lb/>managed through reserves of sustainable use to meet conservation <lb/>and development needs (UNEP, 2014). These reserves are the most <lb/>common mangrove management system in South America, where it <lb/>is estimated that nearly 40 million people living in the region might <lb/>be dependent on the ES provided by these unique forests (UNEP, <lb/>2014). However, although multiple mangrove benefits to those <lb/>coastal communities are often recognized, those relationships are <lb/>not yet mapped in detail. In this study, we adopted a rank-matrix <lb/>approach based on local stakeholders&apos; knowledge to identify and <lb/>map the flow of ecosystem services in Brazilian Amazon mangroves <lb/>and associated coastal habitats. The dataset was built through <lb/>community surveys carried out at in several villages in the <lb/>Curuçá region on the Amazon coast, located in Pará state, north <lb/>of Brazil (Figure 1). This evaluation considered a wide range of ES <lb/>types, scored, and connected to different habitats by the local <lb/>communities&apos; knowledge and vision of the ecosystem fluxes. We <lb/>focused on fisher&apos;s as we identified this group were the main <lb/>stakeholders living in the region, and the ones that most heavily <lb/>rely on the ecosystem services from natural mangrove forests. Given <lb/>the proximity and the high conservation status of mangrove forests <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>on the Amazon coast, we hypothesized that mangroves would be key <lb/>to the flow of several ecosystem services to local communities. We <lb/>also hypothesized that perception of the flow of mangrove ecosystem <lb/>services are influenced by a host of socio-demographic <lb/>characteristics including education, type of livelihood, source of <lb/>income and knowledge of the ecosystem services among others <lb/>(Aburto-Oropeza et al., 2008; Hernandez-Blanco et al., 2021). Our <lb/>findings provide a key assessment to improve our understanding of <lb/>the importance of mangroves to coastal villagers in Northern Brazil. <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Study area <lb/>Brazil has the second largest global expanse of mangrove forests <lb/>(11,400 km 2 ), with over ⅔ of those mangroves located in the <lb/>northern region along the Amazon coast (Bernardino et al., 2022; <lb/>Bunting et al., 2022). Amazon mangroves include well-developed <lb/>forests and hold ecosystem carbon stocks that are 2 to 10-fold higher <lb/>than nearby upland forests in the Amazon and Caatinga biomes <lb/>(Kauffman et al., 2018b). Mangrove forests in Brazil have been <lb/>historically protected by law with over 80% of forests within <lb/>protected areas which markedly limited their loss to coastal <lb/>development and aquaculture (Bernardino et al., 2021). <lb/>This study was carried out in Curuçá and nearby villages (00 °43′48″ <lb/>S-47 °51′06″ W) located on the Northern Amazon coast of Brazil <lb/>(Figure 1). It is a humid equatorial region (Amazon Rainforest <lb/>equatorial climate-type Am), characterized by high temperatures <lb/>(27 °C annual average), low thermal amplitude, and high precipitation <lb/>of over 2000 mm per year (Bernardino et al., 2015). Curuçá has over <lb/>40,000 residents and its economy is based on fishing, agriculture, and <lb/>tourism in mangroves. The city is within a coastal extractive reserve (Mãe <lb/>Grande de Curuçá Reserve), which holds one of the largest protected <lb/>areas on the Amazon coast with rich mangrove ecosystems so there is <lb/>good representation for other reserves in the country. The reserve has <lb/>nearly 60 traditional community settlements with approximately <lb/>3,000 families living on estuarine islands, tidal creeks, rivers, beaches, <lb/>and mangroves (Figueiredo et al., 2009). <lb/>2.2 Ecosystem services assessment <lb/>(matrix model) <lb/>To quantify the flow of ecosystem services (ES) within the study <lb/>area we adapted the matrix model (Campagne et al., 2020), which <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Map of the Brazilian Amazon coast indicating the extent of mangrove forests (dark green) and the studied regions in Curuçá. Right panel. Detail of <lb/>Curuçá mangroves and the border of the extractive reserve (RESEX). Map produced with ArcGIS Online 2023, National Geographic Society Subscription <lb/>ID 3968399452. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>was applied and developed in a host of case studies (Jacobs et al., <lb/>2014; Basheer et al., 2022). The matrix model is based on surveying <lb/>stakeholders including local experts from Government research <lb/>organizations, local communities, and laymen who are typically <lb/>engaged in determining ES scoring. The model involves filling a <lb/>matrix (ranking) of ecosystem services against an (or a group of) <lb/>ecosystems. The matrix approach (also referenced as look-up tables) <lb/>is based on the use of a visual panel of geospatial units classified <lb/>according to ecosystem type, land cover, habitats, or other <lb/>geographical classification related to services or goods, which <lb/>allow participants to attribute scores (0-5, from not relevant to <lb/>very high; Table 1) to ES flow, capacity, supply, use, demand, or <lb/>other concepts (MEA, 2005). The ES matrix approach was used to <lb/>map and quantitatively describe the flow of the various mangrove <lb/>services in the study region within the extractive reserve. Rather than <lb/>using an existing matrix from an already published study, we used an <lb/>empty ES matrix that was filled by the participants based on land use <lb/>land over types (seven in total). <lb/>2.3 Data needs and sources <lb/>Application of the matrix model using participatory mapping <lb/>(through workshops) requires a range of datasets obtainable from <lb/>various sources, including land use and land cover maps. The land <lb/>use land cover (LULC) map used in this study was derived from the <lb/>Sentinel-2 (S-2) satellite imagery for the year 2022 (https://sentinel. <lb/>esa.int/web/sentinel/missions/sentinel-2; <lb/>accessed <lb/>on <lb/>27th <lb/>September 2022). The LULC maps for Curuçá were developed <lb/>following best practices for land cover classification using remote <lb/>sensing data (Mountrakis et al., 2011). Specifically, we utilized a <lb/>support vector machine (SVM) classifier, which has demonstrated <lb/>high accuracy for complex land cover categorization from satellite <lb/>imagery (Pal and Mather, 2005). SVMs are supervised, non-<lb/>parametric statistical learning models that construct optimal <lb/>decision boundaries between classes based on labeled training <lb/>samples (Foody and Mathur, 2004). <lb/>We implemented the SVM classifier using S-2 multispectral <lb/>imagery in ESRI ArcGIS Pro software. Class divisions were mapped <lb/>for six categories: Forest formation (Amazon Rainforest, other <lb/>modified forest types); mangroves; other vegetation types <lb/>(cropland, pastureland); coastal areas (mud and sand flats); water <lb/>body areas (ocean, river, lakes, channels, and creeks); and urban <lb/>areas. Rigorous accuracy assessment was performed using standard <lb/>methods (Souza et al., 2020) including high-resolution visual <lb/>inspection with Google Earth, collection of in situ field reference <lb/>data and MAPBIOMAS Project system of Land Cover Class <lb/>Definitions. These maps and habitat classifications tend to be <lb/>easily recognized by local stakeholders and are typical <lb/>representations of ecosystem types on the Brazilian Amazon <lb/>coast. We assessed accuracy both quantitatively using confusion <lb/>matrices and derived statistics, as well as qualitatively using expert <lb/>analysis ensuring class divisions matched typical ecosystem <lb/>representations. <lb/>2.4 Data collection <lb/>Data on the perception of the flows for the mangrove ecosystem <lb/>was collected from the various resource user groups in Curuçá and <lb/>they included: main sources of livelihoods, places of residence, <lb/>access and use of mangrove ecosystem services, and knowledge <lb/>on the role of mangroves and other landscapes in the provision of <lb/>ES. Data collection was based on participatory mapping of the flow <lb/>ES across the various LULC types in Curuçá, Brazil. This was <lb/>conducted by presenting a map of the land use land cover <lb/>classifications to the stakeholders for them to identify where they <lb/>got the ES from. Visual panels for ES prioritization surveys were <lb/>developed based on the LULC maps of the study area. We integrated <lb/>the land cover type into the matrix study to allow the estimation of <lb/>the flow of ES across land use change (Figure 2). The survey was <lb/>designed considering the active participatory engagement of local <lb/>villagers in the ecosystem service (ES) assessment, with a four-step <lb/>process of data acquisition. <lb/>First, a scoping exercise was performed through a focus group <lb/>discussion (involving 20 participants) to identify the ES and the <lb/>LULC classes present in the study region. One workshop was held <lb/>with community-based organizations, covering the entire Curuçá. <lb/>The workshop was held in Boa Vista do Muriá village with <lb/>20 participants from Curuçá and the surrounding villages <lb/>TABLE 1 Policy relevance of the Ecosystem Service Flow Metrics. Values indicate low flow (0) to very high flow (5). <lb/>Social flow of ES <lb/>metrics <lb/>Description <lb/>Relevance for policy, planning and management <lb/>No flow <lb/>Assigned 0 to mean that the ES is not obtained from the land use <lb/>land cover type <lb/>Indicates sites where focus on the conservation of the ES is not necessary <lb/>Very low flow <lb/>Assigned 1 to mean that the ES is only obtained from the land <lb/>use land cover type at very low levels <lb/>Indicates sites where conservation of the ES is not necessary <lb/>Low flow <lb/>Assigned 2 to mean that there is a low access of the ES from the <lb/>land use land cover type <lb/>Indicates sites where rare ES are perceived to have a low flow. Helps to <lb/>understand areas where conservation of ES may not be necessary <lb/>Medium flow <lb/>Assigned 3 to mean that there is an average access of the ES from <lb/>the land use land cover type <lb/>Indicates sites where rare ES are perceived to have a medium flow. Helps to <lb/>understand areas where need for conservation of ES may be monitored <lb/>High flow <lb/>Assigned 4 to mean that there is a high flow of ES in that Land <lb/>Use Land Cover <lb/>Indicates a site where conservation of ES may be necessary <lb/>Very High flow <lb/>Assigned 5 to mean that the highest flow of ES is found in that <lb/>Land Use Land Cover <lb/>Indicates areas with very high flow of the ES and therefore conservation of <lb/>these land use land cover is very important <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>(Abade, Boa vista do Iririteua, Cabeceiras, Coqueiro, Itajuba, <lb/>Livramento, Muriá, Mutucal, Pedras Grandes, Pindorama, Ponta <lb/>de Ramos and Recreio). The participants were representatives of <lb/>governments (4), villagers (6) and local leaders (10). Selection of the <lb/>participants was done bearing in mind the multiplicity of users in <lb/>Curuçá mangrove and was sufficiently diverse to represent most of <lb/>the key stakeholders involved in carrying out research and in the <lb/>conservation. Several issues were discussed during the meetings <lb/>ranging from the topic of ES, defining ES, the potential of Curuçá <lb/>mangrove to provide these services, to the state of management of <lb/>the reserve and the different organizations involved. Participants <lb/>were taken through an introductory session in which they refreshed <lb/>their familiarity with the ecosystem types in Curuçá, defined what ES <lb/>is and discussed the ES classification using the Millennium <lb/>Ecosystem Assessment framework. This discussion included <lb/>elicitation of the different LULC and ES and a total of 24 ES <lb/>were selected and assigned using the categories described in the <lb/>Millennium Ecosystem Assessment (MEA, 2005). <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Land cover land use (LCLU) of the Mãe Grande de Curuçá RESEX, indicating the seven major land cover categories. Map created with ESRI ArcGIS Pro <lb/>software (https://www.esri.com/en-us/arcgis/products/arcgis-pro/overview). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>The second step was the development of land use land cover <lb/>maps that was used at the actual data collection to aid participants to <lb/>visualize the spatial extent of the area during scoring of ES flows <lb/>according to land use land cover type. The process of generation of <lb/>the land use land cover map is described above. Also, during this <lb/>step, a data collection tool was developed based on the information <lb/>collected during the scoping stage. The main components of the data <lb/>collection <lb/>included; <lb/>consent <lb/>form, <lb/>socio-demographic <lb/>characteristics such as duration of stay in the area, gender, <lb/>sources of income, membership to social groups, products <lb/>obtained from the mangroves, knowledge of the ecosystem <lb/>services associated with mangroves, matrix table for scoring the <lb/>flow of an ES against a land use land cover type (scores ranged from <lb/>0 to 5 as discussed in the matrix model section), threats to the land <lb/>covers, among others. The data collection tool and the land use map <lb/>were pretested together with a section of the community (n = 20). <lb/>The third step involved modification of the data collection tool <lb/>based on the feedback from the pretest. One such concern was that <lb/>the tool was long, hence some questions were dropped, the final data <lb/>collection tool was also transformed into a digital survey. The survey <lb/>TABLE 2 Socio-demographic characteristics of community members who contributed to this study from the Curuçá region. <lb/>Variable <lb/>Description <lb/>N Percentage Mean Min Max <lb/>Duration of stay <lb/>Number of years that a household has lived in the village <lb/>108 <lb/>-<lb/>37.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>82 <lb/>Gender <lb/>proportion of households were male compared to females <lb/>108 <lb/>60% <lb/>Membership <lb/>Proportion of households who are members of social groups or organizations 108 18% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Sources of income <lb/>Fishing <lb/>64 <lb/>58.6% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Farming <lb/>30 <lb/>27.5% <lb/>Retirement <lb/>8 <lb/>7.3% <lb/>Government job <lb/>8 <lb/>7.3% <lb/>Private sector job <lb/>4 <lb/>3.7% <lb/>Business <lb/>3 <lb/>2.8% <lb/>Self-employed <lb/>7 <lb/>6% <lb/>Use of mangrove forest products Fishing <lb/>99 <lb/>92% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Materials for making vessels <lb/>7 <lb/>6.5% <lb/>Making fishing gears <lb/>51 <lb/>48% <lb/>Mariculture <lb/>65 <lb/>61% <lb/>Phytotherapy <lb/>57 <lb/>53% <lb/>Firewood <lb/>53 <lb/>49% <lb/>Timber <lb/>30 <lb/>28% <lb/>Livestock feeding <lb/>12 <lb/>11% <lb/>Hunting <lb/>22 <lb/>20% <lb/>Bee keeping <lb/>28 <lb/>26% <lb/>Crafts and ornamentals <lb/>38 <lb/>35.5% <lb/>Knowledge of Mangrove ES <lb/>Nursery and breeding ground <lb/>103 <lb/>94.5% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Flood control <lb/>91 <lb/>83.4% <lb/>Water purification <lb/>37 <lb/>34% <lb/>Sediment control <lb/>88 <lb/>81% <lb/>Climate regulation <lb/>79 <lb/>72% <lb/>Biodiversity <lb/>103 <lb/>94.5% <lb/>Storm protection <lb/>96 <lb/>88% <lb/>Coastal erosion <lb/>90 <lb/>82.6% <lb/>Recreational value <lb/>88 <lb/>81% <lb/>Education and research <lb/>100 <lb/>92% <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>tool was designed in English and translated to Portuguese, and <lb/>uploaded to the ArcGIS Survey123 tool, where it was hosted online <lb/>(https://survey123.arcgis.com/) and later applied the questionnaires <lb/>in the local community (fourth step). <lb/>The fourth step was the actual data collection, the survey tool <lb/>was presented to the local community through workshops where <lb/>discussions around the research and the objectives were discussed <lb/>with the participants. A total of 6 workshops were held, with each <lb/>workshop having around 20 participants. The workshops were held <lb/>in 6 different villages, with each targeting members from 2 villages <lb/>for a total of 12 villages represented. A total 109 valid responses were <lb/>obtained. Identification of the participants was not purely random <lb/>since participants needed to be people knowledgeable with the <lb/>various land use land cover types and ecosystem services. We <lb/>assumed that by selecting participants based on their resource <lb/>use would create a mix of diversity capable of providing insights <lb/>into the flow of the ecosystem services. <lb/>2.5 Data analysis <lb/>Data on the socio-demographic and economic characteristics of <lb/>the respondents were analysed for measures of central tendencies <lb/>and dispersion such as mean, and percentages using STATA 14 <lb/>(Table 2). Inputs from the workshops and group discussions were <lb/>organized in summary matrixes containing the averaged ES scores <lb/>(0-5) attributed by the villagers to the flow or relationship between <lb/>coastal Amazon habitats and ES types. Habitat prioritization was <lb/>evaluated using printed maps of the reserve land cover and <lb/>developed based on the result of the summary matrixes. ES flow <lb/>patterns were represented using maps and plots to allow spatial <lb/>visualization of change in scoring. Inferential analysis was <lb/>performed to acess the variability in the score patterns between <lb/>different landscapes. We used a 1-way (factor = ecosystem) <lb/>permutational multivariate analysis of variance using distance <lb/>matrices (PERMANOVA; Anderson, 2017). PERMANOVAs and <lb/>plot matrixes were built using the results of the individual responses, <lb/>each participant was included as one sample in the analyses (absence <lb/>of scores were not included in the analysis), and pairwise post hoc <lb/>comparisons were added to the significant results (to test the <lb/>dissimilarity between scores of each landscape type). <lb/>Comparisons and statistical analyses were carried out separately <lb/>for each of the three main ES categories (provisioning, cultural, and <lb/>regulation) highlighted by the studies. Data were transformed <lb/>(square-root x+1) before PERMANOVAs to reduce variance <lb/>within analyzed factors (Anderson, 2017). We assumed α = <lb/>0.05 and determined the significant p values. Graphical and <lb/>analytical processing was performed in the R project (R Core <lb/>Team, 2021), using the packages &quot;vegan&quot; for PERMANOVA, <lb/>&quot;ggalluvial&quot; for flow plots (Oksanen et al., 2018; Brunson and <lb/>Quentin, 2020). <lb/>We also conducted a multivariate multiple regression analysis to <lb/>assess factors that influence perception of the flow of ecosystem <lb/>services for each of the seven landscape types evaluated. However, <lb/>we only present the regression results for the mangrove ecosystem <lb/>given the main study objectives. We used a multivariate analysis to <lb/>analyze the relationship between the 24 mangrove ecosystem <lb/>services against a similar set of potential predictors (based on the <lb/>literature; Campagne et al., 2020), which included length of stay, <lb/>membership to social groups, dependence on mangroves, type of <lb/>livelihood, and knowledge of mangrove ecosystem services. The first <lb/>step in the analysis involved running a MANOVA test in STATA <lb/>14 to show whether all the equations taken together were statistically <lb/>significant. Several stepwise fitting of MANOVA was conducted and <lb/>only eight of the ecosystem services were significant when taken <lb/>together. The eight ecosystem services were then subjected to <lb/>multivariate regression analysis to obtain coefficients, standard <lb/>errors, and p-values for each of the predictors in each part of the <lb/>model, as shown in Eq. 1: <lb/>Y ij α + β 1 X 1i + β 2 X 2i + β j X ji + ε i <lb/>(1) <lb/>where: Y ij is the dependent variable, perception of flow j by <lb/>individual i; β represents the mean change in the perception of <lb/>flow (dependent variable) for one unit of change in X variable <lb/>holding other determinants in the model constant, E is the error <lb/>term and X are the factors that affect the perception of flow also <lb/>called the determinants or independent variables. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Socio-economic profile of the <lb/>participants <lb/>The majority of the respondents who participated in the study <lb/>were males (60%) with a strong reliance on fishing (Table 2). The <lb/>average number of years that a resident had stayed in the village at <lb/>the time of data collection was 37.8 years. Other socio-economic <lb/>characteristics considered in the study included duration of stay in <lb/>the area, membership to social groups, sources of income, use of <lb/>mangrove forest products, and knowledge of mangrove ecosystem <lb/>services (Table 2). Only about 18% of the respondents stated that <lb/>they belong to social groups in the community. Fishing was the main <lb/>source of income to about 67% of the respondents, followed by <lb/>farming at 28%. The majority of the respondents (92%) stated that <lb/>fishing was their main occupation, with mariculture within the <lb/>mangroves also important to about 61% of the respondents. <lb/>3.2 Flow of ecosystem services across land <lb/>cover types in Curuçá <lb/>Provisioning ecosystem services identified by the villagers&apos; <lb/>included activities associated with fisheries (fishing catch, fishing <lb/>vessels, mariculture and gear), energy sources (firewood, coal, <lb/>timber), other food supply or maintenance (livestock feeds, <lb/>hunting, and beekeeping), herbal medicine (phytotherapy), and <lb/>handcraft (ornamentals). Out of the twelve (12) provisioning ES <lb/>prioritized, very high flow (score 5) was only found for fish catches, <lb/>which were reportedly associated with mangrove forests, and <lb/>waterbodies (Table 3; Figure 3). Mangrove mariculture, <lb/>phytotherapy, and firewood extraction from forests (Amazon and <lb/>other types) and crop and pasture lands were scored with the <lb/>medium flow (score 3; Table 3). Timber for housing was equally <lb/>reported with medium flow from the Amazon rainforest and other <lb/>types of forests within the reserve. The analysis of the individual <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>score patterns revealed that provisioning ES flow is mostly <lb/>associated with mangroves, the Amazon rainforest and other <lb/>forests, and less associated with urban areas (PERMANOVA F = <lb/>50.2, p = 0.01, Table 4). The Amazon rainforest has consistently <lb/>medium scores (mostly scoring twos and threes) across all the <lb/>provisioning ES when compared to the other landscapes. All the <lb/>other landscapes showed variable ES score patterns, with <lb/>predominant small scores (0 and 1) to several of the provisioning ES. <lb/>The local community identified eight regulating ES flow from <lb/>the coastal habitats in the Curuçá region, which included <lb/>biodiversity conservation, animal nursery and breeding, water <lb/>purification, and other services associated with coastal resilience <lb/>(climate regulation, coastal erosion, flood control, sediment control, <lb/>and storm protection). The majority of the local community <lb/>members are of the view that there is a very high flow (score 5) <lb/>of nursery and breeding for fish and other animals such as crabs, <lb/>birds and monkeys within the mangroves (Figure 4; Table 5). A high <lb/>flow (score 4) was also attributed to nursery and breeding grounds <lb/>for fish and other animals associated with the Amazon rainforest, <lb/>waterbodies, coastal areas (mud and sand flats), and other forest <lb/>types. Flood control and water purification had a high flow (score 4) <lb/>from mangroves, while the Amazon rainforest, other forest types, <lb/>and coastal areas are regarded to offer medium flow (score 3). <lb/>Similarly, biodiversity conservation has a high flow to the mangrove <lb/>ecosystem, while the amazon rainforest, other forest types, coastal <lb/>areas and water bodies are regarded to offer medium flow. Urban <lb/>areas have a low flow (score 2) for all regulating ES presented <lb/>(Figure 4; Table 5). Similar to the provisioning services, most <lb/>regulating ES flow was attributed to the mangroves <lb/>(PERMANOVA F = 64.7, p = 0.01, Table 4), which together with <lb/>the mud and sand flats and the Amazon rainforest showed a similar <lb/>association with all of these services (Figure 4). Crop and pasture <lb/>lands and urban areas scored the least regulating ES flow (scores <lb/>1-2). Crop and pasture lands also scored consistently low for the <lb/>provisioning ES that were considered in the study. Nevertheless, <lb/>they scored high for cultural services; historical value for <lb/>generations, and intrinsic values in particular. <lb/>The majority (over 90%) of the local community members were <lb/>of the view that there is a high flow (score 4) of education and <lb/>research within the mangroves, Amazon rainforest, other forest <lb/>types, coastal areas, and water bodies (Figure 5; Table 6). <lb/>Stakeholders scored a medium flow (score 3) in education and <lb/>research for urban areas. Tourism and recreation have a high flow in <lb/>the mangrove ecosystem, mud and sand flats and urban areas, while <lb/>the Amazon rainforest, other forest types and water bodies were <lb/>regarded to have medium flow (score 3). In general, mangroves had <lb/>a very high flow of historical value for generations, while the other <lb/>land use and land cover (LULC) types are regarded to offer a high <lb/>flow. Similarly, mangroves and coastal areas (mud and sand flats) <lb/>have a very high flow for intrinsic value, while the other LULC <lb/>classes have a high flow of ES (PERMANOVA F = 12.2, p = 0.01). <lb/>3.3 Factors that influence the perception of <lb/>the flow of mangrove ecosystem services <lb/>There was a strong agreement among villagers that there is a <lb/>high flow of ecosystem services to mangroves, including fisheries <lb/>TABLE 3 Average score values of provisioning ecosystem services in the Curuçá region, indicating <lb/>flow intensity between land cover type from 0 (no <lb/>flow), to 5 (very high <lb/>flow). <lb/>Land use <lb/>cover type <lb/>Fish <lb/>catches <lb/>Fishing <lb/>vessels <lb/>Fishing <lb/>gears <lb/>Mariculture Phytotherapy Firewood Coal Timber <lb/>Livestock <lb/>feeds <lb/>Hunting <lb/>Bee <lb/>keeping <lb/>Ornamental <lb/>crafts <lb/>Mangroves <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Amazon rainforest <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Other forest types <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Crop &amp; Pasture <lb/>lands <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Urban areas <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Water body <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Mud &amp; Sand Flats <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>(95%), intergenerational values (91%), intrinsic value (93%), nursery <lb/>and breeding ground (94%), climate regulation (89%), biodiversity <lb/>conservation (96%), and storm protection (87%; Table 7). On the <lb/>other hand, there was also a near-universal understanding among <lb/>villagers that there is a low flow towards the crafting of fishing vessels <lb/>(86%), coal (86%), wood for construction (83%), livestock feeds <lb/>(97%), hunting (95%), and beekeeping (86%) from local mangrove <lb/>forests. The perception on the understanding of the flow was mainly <lb/>influenced by the period each respondent lived in the region, by their <lb/>association with social or environmental organizations, and if they <lb/>lived from fishing or from other activities. <lb/>Our multiple regression analysis suggests that a higher flow of <lb/>mariculture was associated with respondents who depended on <lb/>mangroves for mariculture; while its low flow was scored by <lb/>those who had lived in the village for long (Table 8). Perception <lb/>of low flow of firewood was associated with respondents who <lb/>reported to depend on mariculture, and those who stated that <lb/>mangroves provided water purification services; while high flow <lb/>of firewood was associated with respondents who stated that they <lb/>depended on mangroves for firewood, phytotherapy, fishing, and <lb/>making fishing vessels. Higher flow of tourism and recreation in the <lb/>mangroves was associated with respondents who associated <lb/>mangroves with provision of recreational and water purification <lb/>ecosystem services; while low flow of tourism and recreation was <lb/>associated with respondents who were aware that mangroves <lb/>provided water purification services. Higher flow of flood control <lb/>ecosystem services was associated with respondents who stated that <lb/>they aware of mangroves as important in flood control, sediment <lb/>control, and those who dependent on mangroves as a source of crafts <lb/>and ornamental materials. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>Here we provide the first empirical assessment of ecosystem <lb/>service flow in the Brazilian Amazon coast based on local <lb/>community perceptions. Although there is a growing number of <lb/>studies investigating ecosystem services and their implication for <lb/>management in wetlands (Barbier et al., 2011), most of the studies <lb/>have focused on the United States and Europe with regions such as <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Average score values of ecosystem service flow across provisioning ecosystem services and land cover types in the marine reserve Mae Grande de <lb/>Curuçá, Brazilian Amazon. Areas in blue indicate no flow to very low flow of ecosystem services whereas green areas indicate higher flow. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>Africa and South America recording fewer studies. We found that <lb/>land use land cover was a key determinant of the ecosystem services <lb/>flow in the Amazon coast of Brazil, suggesting that the size, habitat <lb/>composition, and conservation of habitats may determine its ability <lb/>to provide ecosystem services to coastal communities. Respondents <lb/>perceived that the Amazon coast mangroves had the greatest ability <lb/>to provide flow of a number of ecosystem services when compared to <lb/>urban or upland forested and agricultural landscapes, supporting <lb/>our hypothesis that mangroves would offer key ES to coastal <lb/>villagers (Figure 6). In addition, coastal habitats and waterbodies <lb/>that are in proximity to mangroves were also highly relevant to the <lb/>flow of ecosystem services, which suggests the importance of habitat <lb/>connectivity and of marine reserves in preserving coastal ecosystems <lb/>along the land-ocean continuum (Aburto-Oropeza, et al., 2008). <lb/>Mangroves were identified by community members to be key <lb/>in providing provisioning ecosystem services that include a <lb/>number of food items and crafting materials that are essential <lb/>to the lives of coastal villagers. Fish and crustaceans are key protein <lb/>sources of coastal communities globally and the flow of these <lb/>ecosystem services from mangroves and connected coastal <lb/>habitats is widely recognized and valued (Aburto-Oropeza, <lb/>et al., 2008; Hernandez-Blanco et al., 2021). Mangroves and <lb/>connected coastal habitats are important nursery habitats for <lb/>several estuarine and marine species (Acosta and Butler, 1997; <lb/>Hutchison et al., 2014), mainly because these ecosystems promote <lb/>the migration of species and enhance the availability of nutrients <lb/>(Valiela et al., 2013; Lana and Bernardino, 2018). As a result, the <lb/>remarkable stakeholder&apos;s recognition of the joint importance of <lb/>mangroves, waterbodies, and coastal areas (mud and sand flats) to <lb/>the provision of food and materials provides further support for <lb/>their conservation. The need for conservation of upland areas near <lb/>mangroves brings important policy challenges with current <lb/>challenges to control deforestation in the Brazilian Amazon <lb/>(Carvalho et al., 2019). To achieve better outcomes, a strategy <lb/>TABLE 4 PERMANOVA results of ecosystem service flow scores among landscapes studied in the Curuçá region, Brazil. <lb/>Provisioning <lb/>df <lb/>SS <lb/>MS <lb/>F <lb/>p <lb/>R2 <lb/>Ecosystem <lb/>6 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>50.2 <lb/>0.01* <lb/>0.3* <lb/>Residuals <lb/>748 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>Total <lb/>754 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Pairwise post hoc tests <lb/>Mangroves ≠ Amazon rainforest ≠ Coastal areas ≠ Crop and pasture lands ≠ Urban areas ≠ Water bodies <lb/>Other forests ≠ from other land use/land cover categories except Amazon rainforest <lb/>Regulating <lb/>df <lb/>SS <lb/>MS <lb/>F <lb/>p <lb/>R2 <lb/>Ecosystem <lb/>6 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>64.7 <lb/>0.01* <lb/>0.3* <lb/>Residuals <lb/>748 <lb/>11.5 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>Total <lb/>754 <lb/>17.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Pairwise post hoc tests <lb/>Mangroves ≠ Amazon rainforest ≠ Coastal areas ≠ Crop and pasture lands ≠ Urban areas ≠ Water bodies <lb/>Other forests ≠ from other land use/land cover categories except Amazon rainforest <lb/>Crop and pasture lands = Amazon rainforest and coastal areas <lb/>Cultural <lb/>df <lb/>SS <lb/>MS <lb/>F <lb/>p <lb/>R2 <lb/>Ecosystem <lb/>6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>0.01* <lb/>0.1* <lb/>Residuals <lb/>748 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>Total <lb/>754 <lb/>9.7 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Pairwise post hoc tests <lb/>Mangroves ≠ Amazon rainforest ≠ Coastal areas ≠ Crop and pasture lands ≠ Urban areas <lb/>Other forests ≠ from other land use/land cover categories except Amazon rainforest <lb/>Waterbodies ≠ from other land use/land cover categories except Coastal areas <lb/>Crop and pasture lands = Amazon rainforest and coastal areas <lb/>*Indicate significance levels of 0.01. <lb/></body>

<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Average score values of ecosystem service flow across regulating ecosystem services and land cover types in the marine reserve Mae Grande de <lb/>Curuçá, Brazilian Amazon. Areas in blue indicate no flow to very low flow of ecosystem services whereas green areas indicate higher flow. <lb/>TABLE 5 Average score values of regulating ecosystem services in the Curuçá region, indicating flow intensity between land cover types from 0 (no flow), to <lb/>5 (very high flow). <lb/>Land use <lb/>cover <lb/>type <lb/>Nursery <lb/>and <lb/>breeding <lb/>ground <lb/>Flood <lb/>control <lb/>Water <lb/>purification <lb/>Sediment <lb/>control <lb/>Climate <lb/>regulation <lb/>Biodiversity <lb/>conservation <lb/>Storm <lb/>protection <lb/>Coastal <lb/>erosion <lb/>Mangroves <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Amazon <lb/>rainforest <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>Other forest <lb/>types <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>Crop &amp; <lb/>Pasture lands <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Urban areas <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Water body <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>Mud &amp; Sand <lb/>Flats <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>to link current mangrove protection to nearby coastal landscapes <lb/>(rivers, croplands and other forest types) would likely improve the <lb/>national determined targets to lower carbon emissions and <lb/>improve the benefits to coastal communities as these landscapes <lb/>would provide wood that would otherwise be extracted from <lb/>mangroves (Bernardino et al., 2024). <lb/>Provisioning services with medium to low flow were associated <lb/>with mariculture and other extractive activities, which are often <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Average score values of ecosystem service flow across cultural ecosystem services and land cover types in the marine reserve Mae Grande de <lb/>Curuçá, Brazilian Amazon. Areas in blue indicate no flow to very low flow of ecosystem services whereas green areas indicate higher flow. <lb/>TABLE 6 Average score values of cultural ecosystem services in the Curuçá region, indicating flow intensity between land cover types from 0 (no flow), to 5 <lb/>(very high flow). <lb/>Land use cover type <lb/>Education and <lb/>research <lb/>Tourism and <lb/>recreation <lb/>Historical value for <lb/>generations <lb/>Intrinsic <lb/>value <lb/>Mangroves <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>Amazon rainforest <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Other forest types <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Crop &amp; Pasture lands <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Urban areas <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Water body <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Mud &amp; Sand Flats <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>prohibited or controlled in mangroves of the Brazilian Amazon. <lb/>Some of these materials are easily obtained on converted land near <lb/>villages, as indicated by the high flow of these services on those <lb/>landscapes. This is in contrast to many other coastal communities in <lb/>Africa and Asia which widely use mangrove wood for fuel and <lb/>construction (Owuor et al., 2019). Although the diversity and flow <lb/>intensity of provisioning services such as firewood in the Brazilian <lb/>Amazon may be limited due to the availability of urban utilities, <lb/>mangroves may be an important source of these materials in isolated <lb/>or lower-income communities in Africa and Asia (Abdullah-Al-<lb/>Manun et al., 2017; Owuor et al., 2019). The limited use of firewood <lb/>from Amazon mangroves is also explained by the limited road access <lb/>to these areas as a result of their protection. Fragmentation and <lb/>degradation of mangroves will expectedly increase the use of <lb/>firewood and decrease the value of other services provided <lb/>(Brander et al., 2012). As expected, mangroves, coastal areas, and <lb/>forests were also key to the flow of regulating ES on the Amazon <lb/>coast. High-valued regulatory services such as storm protection, <lb/>climate mitigation, and biodiversity conservation were identified in <lb/>Amazon mangroves, which resemble the high flow of those services <lb/>from wetlands globally (Barbier et al., 2011). <lb/>We also observed that cultural ES were important in several land <lb/>use land cover types within the Amazon region, including <lb/>mangroves. Many coastal villagers frequently use these areas for <lb/>cultural ES and have a strong connection to their preservation. This <lb/>is also true for a diverse range of landscapes including nearby <lb/>croplands, forested areas and aquatic habitats. The value of <lb/>nearby continental landscapes to the flow of ecosystem services <lb/>to coastal communities is often unrecognized and unchecked, but <lb/>our results indicate that croplands, and continental forests add <lb/>important flow of cultural and provisioning services to villagers. <lb/>Our results support that the forested and agricultural areas near to <lb/>those villages are extremely important to them, both as a source of <lb/>food (manioc and banana plantations), and also culturally, as they <lb/>spend time in the &quot;farinha houses&quot; processing manioc creating a <lb/>strong connection to these landscapes. Our results also support that <lb/>these communities need to be actively involved in the management <lb/>of those areas, with proper legal framework so they can help enforce <lb/>legal rights and the protection of these habitats. Although many of <lb/>the Brazilian coastal extractive reserves allow the participation of <lb/>stakeholders in management and use decisions, law enforcement, <lb/>and protection are often bypassed by commercial and external users. <lb/>TABLE 7 Percentage scores for the flow of mangrove ecosystem services. <lb/>Mangrove ecosystem services <lb/>High flow (%) <lb/>Medium flow (%) <lb/>Low flow (%) <lb/>Fishing <lb/>95 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>Fishing vessels <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>86 <lb/>Fishing gears <lb/>40 <lb/>10 <lb/>50 <lb/>Mariculture <lb/>64 <lb/>6 <lb/>30 <lb/>Phytotherapy <lb/>27 <lb/>16 <lb/>57 <lb/>Firewood <lb/>18 <lb/>6 <lb/>76 <lb/>Coal <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>86 <lb/>Timber <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>83 <lb/>Livestock feeding <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>97 <lb/>Hunting <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>95 <lb/>Bee keeping <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>86 <lb/>Crafts and ornamentals <lb/>18 <lb/>9 <lb/>73 <lb/>Recreation and tourism <lb/>69 <lb/>12 <lb/>19 <lb/>Historical values for generations <lb/>91 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Intrinsic values <lb/>93 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Nursery and breeding ground <lb/>94 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>Flood control <lb/>76 <lb/>9 <lb/>15 <lb/>Water purification <lb/>73 <lb/>8 <lb/>19 <lb/>Sediment control <lb/>70 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>Climate regulation <lb/>89 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>Biodiversity conservation <lb/>96 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Storm protection <lb/>87 <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>Shoreline erosion <lb/>80 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/></body>

<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

<page>13 <lb/></page>

<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

<body>TABLE 8 Multivariate multiple regression analysis for predictors of the perception of flow of mangrove ecosystem services. <lb/>Dependent variable <lb/>Predictor variable <lb/>Coef. <lb/>Std. Err. <lb/>P &gt; |t| <lb/>Flow of mariculture <lb/>Length stay in the village <lb/>-0.0258 <lb/>0.01114 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>Dependence on mariculture <lb/>1.60531 <lb/>0.41890 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Flow of phytotherapy <lb/>Length of stay in the village <lb/>-0.0244 <lb/>0.00911 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>Retirement <lb/>1.76741 <lb/>0.90446 <lb/>0.054 <lb/>Government job <lb/>1.57596 <lb/>0.90770 <lb/>0.087 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for making fishing vessels <lb/>1.71151 <lb/>0.68665 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for phytotherapy <lb/>1.37642 <lb/>0.34895 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Dependent on mangroves for crafts and ornamentals <lb/>0.5810 <lb/>0.36253 <lb/>0.113 <lb/>Knowledge of water purification <lb/>-0.9323 <lb/>0.38281 <lb/>0.017 <lb/>Knowledge of sediment control <lb/>0.8931 <lb/>0.46616 <lb/>0.059 <lb/>Knowledge of recreational service <lb/>0.8810 <lb/>0 .4407 <lb/>0.049 <lb/>cons <lb/>1.7540 <lb/>0.87163 <lb/>0.048 <lb/>Firewood Flow <lb/>Fishing <lb/>1.1906 <lb/>0.55601 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>Government job <lb/>2.3987 <lb/>0.82730 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for making fishing vessels <lb/>1.2854 <lb/>0.62583 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>Depended on mariculture <lb/>-0.5706 <lb/>0.31225 <lb/>0.072 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for phytotherapy <lb/>0.6649 <lb/>0.31804 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>Depended on firewood <lb/>1.3413 <lb/>0.38118 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Knowledge of water purification <lb/>-0.6836 <lb/>0.34890 <lb/>0.054 <lb/>Flow of crafts/ornamentals <lb/>Retirement <lb/>1.3008 <lb/>0.84918 <lb/>0.130 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for making fishing vessels <lb/>1.30264 <lb/>0.64467 <lb/>0.047 <lb/>Depended on crafts and ornamentals <lb/>2.30456 <lb/>0.34037 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Knowledge of sediment control <lb/>0.75359 <lb/>0 .43767 <lb/>0.089 <lb/>Knowledge of recreational services <lb/>0.64681 <lb/>0.41384 <lb/>0.122 <lb/>_cons <lb/>0.95749 <lb/>0.81835 <lb/>0.246 <lb/>Flow of tourism and recreation <lb/>Knowledge of water purification <lb/>0.58498 <lb/>0.33735 <lb/>0.087 <lb/>Knowledge of sediment control <lb/>-0.69918 <lb/>0.4108167 <lb/>0.093 <lb/>Knowledge of recreational services <lb/>0.76258 <lb/>0.3884467 <lb/>0.053 <lb/>_cons <lb/>3.40462 <lb/>0.7681413 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Flow of flood control <lb/>Depended on crafts and ornaments from mangroves <lb/>0.62289 <lb/>0.320339 <lb/>0.055 <lb/>Knowledge of sediment control <lb/>1.64644 <lb/>0.4119115 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Knowledge of flood control <lb/>1.35892 <lb/>0.43284 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>_cons <lb/>1.63273 <lb/>1.63273 <lb/>0.037 <lb/>Flow of water purification <lb/>Farming <lb/>0.78271 <lb/>0.493716 <lb/>0.117 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for fishing gears <lb/>-0.81205 <lb/>0.37189 <lb/>0.032 <lb/>Depended on mangroves for hunting <lb/>0.80215 <lb/>0.44797 <lb/>0.077 <lb/>Knowledge of water purification <lb/>1.54736 <lb/>0.502628 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>(Continued on following page) <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<body>Based on the multivariate regression, the factors that <lb/>influenced respondents&apos; perception of the flow of the <lb/>mangrove ES were the length of habitation in the area, <lb/>membership to a social group, dependence on mangroves, type <lb/>of livelihood and knowledge of mangrove ecosystem services. The <lb/>perception of the flow of ecosystem services is typically <lb/>influenced by a host of factors, which may include the direct <lb/>reliance on an ecosystem, socio economic and demographic <lb/>characteristics of respondents and awareness and direct use of <lb/>ecosystem services (Hicks and Cinner, 2014; Chen et al., 2015). <lb/>The strong user&apos;s perception of ecosystem services benefits from <lb/>mangroves has direct implications for their future valuation as <lb/>the value of ecosystem services increase in connected wetland <lb/>habitats, so the stakeholder&apos;s recognition would support an area-<lb/>based valuation of those services (Brander et al., 2012). The <lb/>marine reserve in Curuçá has nearly 22,000 ha of mangroves <lb/>and 4,500 ha of coastal areas and waterbodies; which were highly <lb/>associated with ES flow. Our survey covered an estimated <lb/>population of 16,409 residents and 3,963 households (IBGE, <lb/>2010), but the number of residents and non-residents <lb/>benefiting from mangrove services could be much higher as <lb/>the Amazon coastal region is mainly connected by rivers and <lb/>coastal bays. These highly connected landscapes, low <lb/>fragmentation and the large extension of mangroves on this <lb/>Amazon coast suggest that the associated value of those <lb/>mangroves should be extremely high (Brander et al., 2012). <lb/>The strong association between social context and livelihood <lb/>to the perceived flow of ecosystem services in the Brazilian <lb/>Amazon may reasonably match the perceived flow of those <lb/>mangrove services in communities from other regions of the <lb/>country that live within managed extractive reserves. These <lb/>reserves cover 87% of the country&apos;s mangrove area, and over <lb/>2/3 of them allow extractive use of mangroves and nearby coastal <lb/>ecosystems (Bernardino et al., 2021). The consistent management <lb/>of these reserves should facilitate the mapping of ecosystem <lb/>services in the country and their valuation on a nationwide <lb/>scale. Information and education may be also critical to the <lb/>perceived flow of ecosystem services from mangroves and <lb/>other landscapes (Lamarque et al., 2014; Henderson et al., <lb/>2016; Chen et al., 2018), but the effect of education, extension <lb/>projects, access to seminars, or to internet has not been assessed <lb/>in this study. Such strategies could help local communities <lb/>develop more critical thinking and careful observation of <lb/>natural processes. As a result, the perceived flow of ecosystem <lb/>services including invisible ones such as regulating and <lb/>supportive ecosystem services may be more heterogeneous <lb/>spatially and across areas of variable income per capita. <lb/>While this study provides novel insights into community <lb/>perceptions of ecosystem service flows in the Amazon region, some <lb/>limitations should be noted. The data represents a single snapshot in <lb/>time and location. Expanding participatory assessments across multiple <lb/>time periods and mangrove sites would strengthen generalizability. The <lb/>survey data is also subject to individual biases and recall limitations. <lb/>Supplementing surveys with ecological data could further validate <lb/>perceived service flows. Additionally, assessment of the determinants <lb/>of perception of the flow of ecosystem services only focused on <lb/>mangrove services overlooking terrestrial system contributions. <lb/>Future studies should adopt a coupled social-ecological approach <lb/>spanning coastal and inland habitats. Applying an intersectional lens <lb/>to evaluate how gender, age, culture, and other factors shape ecosystem <lb/>service perceptions would also enrich understanding. Long-term <lb/>monitoring is needed to track how development trajectories alter <lb/>ecosystem service flows and community dependencies. Fostering <lb/>participatory co-production of knowledge across stakeholders <lb/>remains essential for informing policies that sustain critical services <lb/>from Amazonian socio-ecological systems. <lb/>Although Brazilian law recognizes mangroves as areas of <lb/>permanent protection, it is not uncommon to identify mangrove <lb/>areas converted to aquaculture, urbanization and deforestation. <lb/>Land Uses and Land Cover (LULC) impacts of mangroves may <lb/>directly remove those forests and lead to a decrease in water quality <lb/>through the release of nutrients, suspended sediments, and related <lb/>impacts (Queiroz et al., 2022a; Queiroz et al., 2022b). As mangroves <lb/>and continuous coastal areas were typically associated with a high <lb/>flow of ecosystem services and hold much of their ecological <lb/>function (e.g., carbon sequestration, productivity), these areas can <lb/>be considered as environmentally critical for conserving. Our work <lb/>supports that not only mangroves, coastal areas, and waterbodies <lb/>may be critical to the livelihoods of coastal villagers. Given that <lb/>many coastal inhabitants are involved with private work and even <lb/>coastal fishers rely on the flow of services from upland forests and <lb/>croplands (wood and other provisioning services), guaranteeing <lb/>access to croplands and conserving upland forests near the coast <lb/>may ensure that coastal communities are able to have a sustained use <lb/>of ES without causing degradation to mangroves. Our work also <lb/>calls for the need to increase studies focusing on the data-scarce <lb/>regions that were not assessed by field work, an attempt that the <lb/>current study makes. Incorporating the values of ecosystems and <lb/>the values they provide into decision-making and policy; and also <lb/>strengthening the engagement of indigenous and local people <lb/>(IPLC) in data collection and research is crucial. These activities <lb/>are stipulated in some of the recent Global debates, such as the <lb/>Post Aichi targets and the Global Biodiversity Framework <lb/>(OECD, 2019). <lb/>TABLE 8 (Continued) Multivariate multiple regression analysis for predictors of the perception of flow of mangrove ecosystem services. <lb/>Dependent variable <lb/>Predictor variable <lb/>Coef. <lb/>Std. Err. <lb/>P &gt; |t| <lb/>Flow of sediment control <lb/>Depended on mangroves for Firewood <lb/>-.098210 <lb/>0.426367 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>Knowledge of sediment control <lb/>2.13935 <lb/>0.475241 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>cons <lb/>1.36297 <lb/>0.888601 <lb/>0.129 <lb/>Observations <lb/>99 <lb/></body>

<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>15 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included in <lb/>the article/Supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by Comitê de ética <lb/>em pesquisa da Universidade Federal do Espírito Santo. The studies <lb/>were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and <lb/></div>

<body>FIGURE 6 <lb/>Schematic flow of provisioning (A), cultural (B) and regulating (C) ecosystem services across landscapes in the study region. <lb/></body>

<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

<page>16 <lb/></page>

<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

<div type="annex">institutional requirements. The participants provided their written <lb/>informed consent to participate in this study. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>MO: Conceptualization, Formal Analysis, Funding acquisition, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Writing-original draft. TS: Formal <lb/>Analysis, Investigation, Writing-review and editing. PO: Formal <lb/>Analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing-original draft. AM: <lb/>Formal Analysis, Investigation, Writing-review and editing. CI: <lb/>Formal Analysis, Investigation, Writing-review and editing. AB: <lb/>Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Project <lb/>administration, Writing-original draft. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work <lb/>was supported by the National Geographic Society and Rolex <lb/>Perpetual Planet Amazon Expedition (PFA-21-PP031). AB was <lb/>also supported by Fundação de Amparo a Pesquisa e Inovação <lb/>do Espirito Santo (Fapes) Edital 18/2023. <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the ICMBio-MMA and the RESEX Mae Grande de <lb/>Curuçá for the permit to conduct the social surveys. We thank Leo <lb/>Modesto, Pablo Albarenga, the EcoLeao employees, and students for <lb/>their assistance with field work. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>Author PO was employed by Biosfera Research and <lb/>Consulting Ltd. <lb/>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted <lb/>in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that <lb/>could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, <lb/>or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product <lb/>that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Abdullah-Al-Manun, M. M., Masum, K. M., Sarker, A. H. M. R., and Mansor, A. <lb/>(2017). Ecosystem services assessment using a valuation framework for the Bangladesh <lb/>Surdabans: livelihood contribution and degradation analysis. J. For. Res. 28, 1-13. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s11676-016-0275-5 <lb/>Aburto-Oropeza, O., Ezcurra, E., Danemann, G., Valdez, V., Murray, J., and Sala, E. <lb/>(2008). Mangroves in the Gulf of California increase fishery yields. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. <lb/>S. A. 105, 10456-10459. doi:10.1073/pnas.0804601105 <lb/>Acosta, C. A., and Butler, M. J. (1997). Role of mangrove habitat as a nursery for <lb/>juvenile spiny lobster, Panulirus argus, in Belize. Mar. Freshw. Res. 48, 721-727. doi:10. <lb/>1071/mf96105 <lb/>Afonso, F., Felix, P. M., Chainho, P., Heumuller, J. A., Lima, R. F., Ribeiro, F., et al. <lb/>(2021). Assessing ecosystem services in mangroves: insights from são tomé island <lb/>(central Africa). Front. Environ. Sci. 9, 501673. doi:10.3389/fenvs.2021.501673 <lb/>Anderson, M. J. (2017). Permutational multivariate analysis of variance <lb/>(PERMANOVA). John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Wiley StatsRef: Statistics Reference Online. <lb/>Bagstad, K. J., Semmens, D. J., Waage, S., and Winthrop, R. (2013). A comparative <lb/>assessment of decision-support tools for ecosystem services quantification and <lb/>valuation. Ecosyst. Serv. 5, 27-39. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser.2013.07.004 <lb/>Barbier, E. B., Hacker, S. D., Kennedy, C., Koch, E. W., Stier, A. C., and Siliman, B. R. <lb/>(2011). The value of estuarine and coastal ecosystem services. Ecol. Monogr. 81, <lb/>169-193. doi:10.1890/10-1510.1 <lb/>Basheer, S., Wang, X., Farooque, A. A., Nawaz, R. A., Liu, K., Adekanmbi, T., et al. <lb/>(2022). Comparison of land use land cover classifiers using different satellite imagery <lb/>and machine learning techniques. Remote Sens. 14, 4978. doi:10.3390/rs14194978 <lb/>Bernardino, A. F., Mazzuco, A. C. A., Costa, R. F., Souza, F., Owuor, M. A., Nobrega, <lb/>G. N., et al. (2024). The inclusion of Amazon mangroves in Brazil&apos;s REDD+ program. <lb/>Nat. Comm. In press. doi:10.1038/s41467-024-45459-w <lb/>Bernardino, A. F., Mazzuco, A. C. A., Souza, F. M., Santos, T. M. T., Sanders, C. J., <lb/>Massone, C. G., et al. (2022). The novel mangrove environment and composition of the <lb/>Amazon Delta. Curr. Biol. 32, 3636-3640.e2. doi:10.1016/j.cub.2022.06.071 <lb/>Bernardino, A. F., Netto, S. A., Pagliosa, P. R., Barros, F., Christofoletti, R. A., Rosa <lb/>Filho, J. S., et al. (2015). Predicting ecological changes on benthic estuarine assemblages <lb/>through decadal climate trends along Brazilian marine ecoregions. Estuar. Coast. Shelf <lb/>Sci. 166, 74-82. doi:10.1016/j.ecss.2015.05.021 <lb/>Bernardino, A. F., Nobrega, G. N., and Ferreira, T. O. (2021). Consequences of <lb/>terminating mangrove&apos;s protection in Brazil. Mar. Policy 125, 104389. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>marpol.2020.104389 <lb/>Bernardino, A. F., Sanders, C. J., Bissoli, L. B., Gomes, L. E. de O., Kauffman, J. B., and <lb/>Ferreira, T. O. (2020). Land use impacts on benthic bioturbation potential and carbon <lb/>burial in Brazilian mangrove ecosystems. Limnol. Oceanogr. 65, 2366-2376. doi:10. <lb/>1002/lno.11458 <lb/>Brander, L. M., Wagtendonk, A. J., Hussain, S. S., McVittie, A., Verburg, P. H., de Groot, R. S., <lb/>et al. (2012). Ecosystem service values for mangroves in Southeast Asia: a meta-analysis and <lb/>value transfer application. Ecosyst. Serv. 1, 62-69. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser.2012.06.003 <lb/>Breithaupt, J. L., and Steinmuller, H. E. (2022). Refining the global estimate of <lb/>mangrove carbon burial rates using sedimentary and geomorphic settings. Geophys. Res. <lb/>Lett. 49, e2022GL100177. doi:10.1029/2022gl100177 <lb/>Brunson, J. C., and Quentin, D. (2020). ggalluvial: alluvial Plots in &apos;ggplot2&apos;. R package <lb/>version 0.12.3. <lb/>Bunting, P., Rosenqvist, A., Hilarides, L., Lucas, R. M., Thomas, N., Tadono, T., et al. <lb/>(2022). Global mangrove extent change 1996-2020: global mangrove watch version 3.0. <lb/>Remote Sens. 14, 3657. doi:10.3390/rs14153657 <lb/>Burkhard, B., Kandziora, M., Hou, Y., and Müller, F. (2014). Ecosystem service <lb/>potentials, flows and demands-concepts for spatial localisation, indication and <lb/>quantification. Landsc. Online 34, 1-32. doi:10.3097/lo.201434 <lb/>Campagne, C. S., and Roche, P. (2018)). May the matrix be with you! Guidelines for <lb/>the application of expert-based matrix approach for ecosystem services assessment and <lb/>mapping. One Ecosyst. 3, e24134. doi:10.3897/oneeco.3.e24134 <lb/>Campagne, C. S., Roche, P., Müller, F., and Burkhard, B. (2020). Ten years of <lb/>ecosystem services matrix: review of a (r)evolution. One Ecosyst. 5, e51103. doi:10.3897/ <lb/>oneeco.5.e51103 <lb/>Canonico, G., Buttigieg, P. L., Montes, E., Muller-Karger, F., Stepien, C., Wright, D., <lb/>et al. (2019). Global observational needs and resources for marine biodiversity. Front. <lb/>Mar. Sci. 6, 367. doi:10.3389/fmars.2019.00367 <lb/>Carvalho, W. D., Mustin, K., Hilario, R. R., Vasconcelos, I. M., Eilers, V., and <lb/>Fearnside, P. M. (2019). Deforestation control in the Brazilian Amazon: a conservation <lb/>struggle being lost as agreements and regulations are subverted and bypassed. Perspec. <lb/>Ecol. Cons. 17, 122-130. doi:10.1016/j.pecon.2019.06.002 <lb/>(CDB) Convention on biological diversity and the united nations. Environment <lb/>programme-world conservation monitoring centre. Best policy guidance for the <lb/>integration of biodiversity and ecosystem services in standards, Montreal, Technical <lb/>Series No. 73, 52 pages. (2012). <lb/>Chen, Y., Yu, Z., Li, X., and Li, P. (2018). How agricultural multiple ecosystem services <lb/>respond to socioeconomic factors in Mengyin County, China. Sci. Total Environ. 630, <lb/>1003-1015. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.02.187 <lb/>Figueiredo, E. M., Furtado, L. G., and Castro, E. R. (2009). Trabalhadores da Pesca e a <lb/>Reserva Extrativista Marinha Mãe Grande de Curuçá -PA: impactos Socioeconômicos <lb/>da Rodovia PA-136. Amazônia Ciência Desenvolv. 5, 231-252. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>17 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Foody, G. M., and Mathur, A. (2004). A relative evaluation of multiclass image <lb/>classification by support vector machines. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens. 42, <lb/>1335-1343. doi:10.1109/tgrs.2004.827257 <lb/>Goldberg, L., Lagomasino, D., Thomas, N., and Fatoyimbo, T. (2020). Global declines in <lb/>human-driven mangrove loss. Glob. Change Biol. 26, 5844-5855. doi:10.1111/gcb.15275 <lb/>Gomes, L. E. O., Sanders, C. J., Nobrega, G. N., Vescovi, L. C., Queiroz, H. M., <lb/>Kauffman, J. B., et al. (2021a). Ecosystem carbon losses following a climate-induced <lb/>mangrove mortality in Brazil. J. Environ. Manage. 297, 113381. doi:10.1016/j.jenvman. <lb/>2021.113381 <lb/>Gomes, L. E. O., Vescovi, L. C., and Bernardino, A. F. (2021b). The collapse of <lb/>mangrove litterfall production following a climate-related forest loss in Brazil. Mar. <lb/>Pollut. Bull. 162, 111910. doi:10.1016/j.marpolbul.2020.111910 <lb/>Gutting, R., Syrbe, R., Grunewald, K., Mehlig, U., Helfer, V., and Zimmer, M. (2021). <lb/>The benefits of combining global and local data-a showcase for valuation and mapping <lb/>of mangrove climate regulation and food provisioning services within a protected area <lb/>in Pará, north Brazil. Land 10, 432. doi:10.3390/land10040432 <lb/>Henderson, K. A., Reis, M., Blanco, C. C., Pillar, V. D., Printes, R. C., Bauch, C. T., et al. <lb/>(2016). Landowner perceptions of the value of natural forest and natural grassland in a mosaic <lb/>ecosystem in southern Brazil. Sustain. Sci. 11, 321-330. doi:10.1007/s11625-015-0319-3 <lb/>Hernandez-Blanco, M., Costanza, R., and Cifuentes-Jara, M. (2021). Economic <lb/>valuation of the ecosystem services provided by the mangroves of the Gulf of <lb/>Nicoya using a hybrid methodology. Ecosyst. Serv. 49, 101258. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser. <lb/>2021.101258 <lb/>Hicks, C. C., and Cinner, J. E. (2014). Social, institutional, and knowledge <lb/>mechanisms mediate diverse ecosystem service benefits from coral reefs. P. Natl. <lb/>Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 111, 17791-17796. doi:10.1073/pnas.1413473111 <lb/>Himes-Cornell, A., Pendleton, L., and Atiyah, P. (2018). Valuing ecosystem services <lb/>from blue forests: a systematic review of the valuation of salt marshes, sea grass beds and <lb/>mangrove forests. Ecosyst. Serv. 30, 36-48. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser.2018.01.006 <lb/>Hutchison, J., Spalding, M., and Ermgassen, P. (2014). &quot;The role of mangroves in fisheries <lb/>enhancement,&quot; in The nature conservancy and wetlands international report, 54pp. <lb/>IBGE [Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatistica] (2010). Sinopse do censo <lb/>demográfico 2010. RJ, Brazil: Rio de Janeiro. 9788524041877. <lb/>Jacobs, S., Burkhard, B., Van Daele, T., Staes, J., and Schneiders, A. (2014). The Matrix <lb/>Reloaded: a review of expert knowledge use for mapping ecosystem services. Ecol. <lb/>Model. 295, 21-30. doi:10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2014.08.024 <lb/>Kauffman, J. B., Adame, M. F., Arifanti, V. B., Schile-Beers, L. M., Bernardino, A. F., <lb/>Bhomia, R. K., et al. (2020). Total ecosystem carbon stocks of mangroves across broad global <lb/>environmental and physical gradients. Ecol. Monogr. 90, e01405. doi:10.1002/ecm.1405 <lb/>Kauffman, J. B., Bernardino, A. F., Ferreira, T. O., Bolton, N. W., Gomes, L. E. O., and <lb/>Nobrega, G. N. (2018a). Shrimp ponds lead to massive loss of soil carbon and <lb/>greenhouse gas emissions in northeastern Brazilian mangroves. Ecol. Evol. 8, <lb/>5530-5540. doi:10.1002/ece3.4079 <lb/>Kauffman, J. B., Bernardino, A. F., Ferreira, T. O., Giovannoni, L. R., Gomes, L. E. O., <lb/>Romero, D. J., et al. (2018b). Carbon stocks of mangroves and salt marshes of the <lb/>Amazon region, Brazil. Biol. Lett. 14, 20180208. doi:10.1098/rsbl.2018.0208 <lb/>Kauffman, J. B., Trejo, H. H., Garcia, M. C. J., Heider, C., and Contreras, W. M. <lb/>(2016). Carbon stocks of mangroves and losses arising from their conversion to cattle <lb/>pastures in the Pantanos de Centla, Mexico. Wetl. Ecol. Manag. 24, 203-216. doi:10. <lb/>1007/s11273-015-9453-z <lb/>Lamarque, P., Meyfroidt, P., Nettier, B., and Lavorel, S. (2014). How ecosystem <lb/>services knowledge and values influence farmers&apos; decision-making. PLoS One 9, <lb/>1075722-e107616. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0107572 <lb/>Lana, P. C., and Bernardino, A. F. (2018). Brazilian estuaries: a benthic perspective. <lb/>Springer International Publishing. <lb/>Mea [Millennium Ecosystem Assessment], (2005). Ecosystems and human well-being: <lb/>synthesis. Washington, DC: Island Press, 155. <lb/>Mountrakis, G., Im, J., and Ogole, C. (2011). Support vector machines in remote <lb/>sensing: a review. ISPRS J. Photogramm. Remote Sens. 66, 247-259. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>isprsjprs.2010.11.001 <lb/>Müller, F., and Burkhard, B. (2012). The indicator side of ecosystem services. Ecosyst. <lb/>Serv. 1, 26-30. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser.2012.06.001 <lb/>Murdiyarso, D., Purbopuspito, J., Kauffman, J. B., Warren, M. W., Sasmito, S. D., <lb/>Donato, D. C., et al. (2015). The potential of Indonesian mangrove forests for <lb/>global climate change mitigation. Nat. Clim. Change 5, 1089-1092. doi:10.1038/ <lb/>nclimate2734 <lb/>Oecd [Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development], (2019). The <lb/>Post-2020 Biodiversity Framework: targets, indicators and measurability implications at <lb/>global and national level. November version. <lb/>Oksanen, J., Blanchet, F. G., Kindt, R., and Legendre, P. (2018). vegan: community <lb/>ecology package. R package version 20-10. Available at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/ <lb/>packages/vegan/index.html. <lb/>Owuor, M. A., Mulwa, R., Otieno, P., Icely, J., and Newton, A. (2019). Valuing <lb/>mangrove biodiversity and ecosystem services: a deliberative choice experiment in Mida <lb/>Creek, Kenya. Ecosyst. Serv. 40, 101040. doi:10.1016/j.ecoser.2019.101040 <lb/>Pal, M., and Mather, P. M. (2005). Support vector machines for classification in <lb/>remote sensing. Int. J. Remote Sens. 26, 1007-1011. doi:10.1080/ <lb/>01431160512331314083 <lb/>Passos, T., Bernardino, A. F., Penny, D., Barcellos, R., Passos, F. U., Nobrega, G. N., <lb/>et al. (2023). Low carbon accumulation in a macro-tidal mangrove forest on the <lb/>Amazon coast. Limnol. Oceanogr. 68, 1936-1948. doi:10.1002/lno.12396 <lb/>Queiroz, H. M., Bragantini, I. O. B. F., Fandino, V. A., Bernardino, A. F., Barcellos, D., <lb/>Ferreira, A. D., et al. (2022a). Degraded mangroves as sources of trace elements to <lb/>aquatic environments. Mar. Poll. Bul. 181, 113834. doi:10.1016/j.marpolbul.2022. <lb/>113834 <lb/>Queiroz, H. M., Ferreira, T. O., Fandino, V. A., Bragantini, I. O. B. F., Barcellos, D., <lb/>Nobrega, G. N., et al. (2022b). Changes in soil iron biogeochemistry in response to <lb/>mangrove dieback. Biogeochemistry 158, 357-372. doi:10.1007/s10533-022-00903-1 <lb/>R Core Team (2021). R: a language and environment for statistical computing. <lb/>Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. URL https://www.R-<lb/>project.org/. <lb/>Ruslan, N. F. N., Gog, H. C., Hattam, C., Edwards-Jones, A., and Moh, H. H. (2022). <lb/>Mangrove ecosystem services: contribution to the well-being of the coastal communities <lb/>in Klang Islands. Mar. Policy 144, 105222. doi:10.1016/j.marpol.2022.105222 <lb/>Souza, C. M., Shimbo, J., Rosa, M. R., Parente, L. L., Alencar, A., Rudorff, B. F. T., <lb/>et al. (2020). Reconstructing three decades of land use and land cover changes in <lb/>Brazilian biomes with landsat archive and Earth engine. Remote Sens. 12, 2735. <lb/>doi:10.3390/rs12172735 <lb/>UNEP [United Nations Environment Programme] (2014). &quot;The importance of <lb/>mangroves to people: a call to action,&quot; in United nations environment programme <lb/>world conservation monitoring centre. Editors J. van Bochove, E. Sullivan, and <lb/>T. Nakamura (Cambridge), 128. <lb/>Valiela, I., Giblin, A., Barth-Jensen, C., Harris, C., Stone, T., Fox, S., et al. (2013). <lb/>Nutrient gradients in Panamanian estuaries: effects of watershed deforestation, rainfall, <lb/>upwelling and within-estuary transformations. Mar. Ecol-Prog. Ser. 482, 1-15. doi:10. <lb/>3354/meps10358 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Environmental Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>18 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Owuor et al. <lb/>10.3389/fenvs.2024.1329006 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>