<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T15:31:23.585Z">11/20/2025 3:31:23 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T15:31:13.532602Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T15:31:13.532602Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Diffusion tensor imaging and <lb/>plasma immunological <lb/>biomarker panel in a rat <lb/>traumatic brain injury (TBI) <lb/>model and in human <lb/>clinical TBI <lb/>Xuan Vinh To 1 , Abdalla Z. Mohamed 1,2 , Paul Cumming 3,4 <lb/>and Fatima A. Nasrallah 1,5 * <lb/>1 The Queensland Brain Institute, The University of Queensland, Queensland, Australia, <lb/>2 Thompson Institute, University of the Sunshine Coast, Queensland, Australia, 3 Department of <lb/>Nuclear Medicine, Bern University Hospital, Bern, Switzerland, 4 School of Psychology and <lb/>Counselling, Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, 5 The Centre <lb/>for Advanced Imaging, The University of Queensland, Queensland, Australia <lb/>Introduction: Neuroinflammatory reactions play a significant role in the <lb/>pathology and long-term consequences of traumatic brain injury (TBI) and <lb/>may mediate salutogenic processes that white matter integrity. This study <lb/>aimed to investigate the relationship between inflammatory markers and white <lb/>matter integrity following TBI in both a rat TBI model and clinical TBI cases. <lb/>Methods: In the rat model, blood samples were collected following a <lb/>controlled cortical impact (CCI) to assess a panel of inflammatory markers; <lb/>MR-based diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) was employed to evaluate white <lb/>matter integrity 60 days post-injury. 15 clinical TBI patients were similarly <lb/>assessed for a panel of inflammatory markers and DTI post-intensive care <lb/>unit discharge. Blood samples from healthy controls were used for <lb/>comparison of the inflammatory markers. <lb/>Results: Time-dependent elevations in immunological markers were <lb/>observed in TBI rats, with a correlation to preserved fractional anisotropy <lb/>(FA) in white matter. Specifically, TBI-induced increased plasma levels of IL-<lb/>1b, IL-6, G-CSF, CCL3, CCL5, and TNF-a were associated with higher white <lb/>matter integrity, as measured by FA. Clinical cases had similar findings: <lb/>elevated inflammatory markers (relative to controls) were associated with <lb/>preservation of FA in vulnerable white matter regions. <lb/>Discussion: Inflammatory markers in post-TBI plasma samples are <lb/>ambivalent with respect to prediction of favourable outcome versus a <lb/>progression to more pervasive pathology and morbidity. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>traumatic brain injury, controlled cortical impact model, inflammatory markers, <lb/>diffusion tensor imaging, fractional anisotropy <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Jorge Goldstein, <lb/>National Scientific and Technical Research <lb/>Council (CONICET), Argentina <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Alipio Pinto, <lb/>University of Buenos Aires, Argentina <lb/>Hailong Song, <lb/>University of Pennsylvania, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Fatima A. Nasrallah <lb/>f.nasrallah@uq.edu.au <lb/>RECEIVED 13 September 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 11 December 2023 <lb/>PUBLISHED 08 January 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>To XV, Mohamed AZ, Cumming P and <lb/>Nasrallah FA (2024) Diffusion tensor imaging <lb/>and plasma immunological biomarker panel <lb/>in a rat traumatic brain injury (TBI) model <lb/>and in human clinical TBI. <lb/>Front. Immunol. 14:1293471. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 To, Mohamed, Cumming and <lb/>Nasrallah. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 08 January 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>With an estimated annual incidence of 295 per 100,000 <lb/>population, traumatic brain injury (TBI) is a major contributor to <lb/>mortality and morbidity across the world (1). According to an <lb/>influential position statement, TBI is &quot;an alteration in brain <lb/>function, or other evidence of brain pathology, caused by an <lb/>external force&quot; (2). In the clinical setting, alteration in brain <lb/>function can refer to loss of or decreased level of consciousness, <lb/>loss of memory immediately before or after the injury, neurologic <lb/>deficits or altered mental state and other evidence of brain <lb/>pathology, which can include visual, neuroradiologic, or <lb/>laboratory-confirmed damage to the brain (2). TBI severity has <lb/>traditionally been classified using the Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) <lb/>(3), which mainly depends on the clinicians&apos; impression of the level <lb/>of consciousness soon after the impact. As such, the GCS may not <lb/>be representative of the diverse nature of TBI and its long-term <lb/>consequences, which can include neuronal cell loss, axonal damage, <lb/>demyelination, disconnection of cortical and subcortical structures, <lb/>and neuroinflammation (4-7). Consequently, clinical assessment of <lb/>symptoms present close to the time of injury are a poor predictor of <lb/>long-time prognosis with respect to morbidity and mortality (8). <lb/>Neuroinflammation and axonal injury are considered key <lb/>elements in the long-term responses to an initial TBI event. <lb/>Notably, neuroinflammation is a complex phenomenon initiated <lb/>post-TBI by acute damage to the blood-brain barrier (BBB), but <lb/>with a complex propagation to a secondary phase that involves <lb/>feedback interaction between pro-and anti-inflammatory <lb/>mechanisms (9). In TBIs, neuroinflammation is neither <lb/>detrimental nor beneficial per se, but entails detrimental processes <lb/>such as neuronal cell death and neurodegeneration, as well as <lb/>beneficial events such as debris clearance and neuronal <lb/>regeneration (9). This link between neuroinflammation and post-<lb/>TBI neural degeneration and regeneration spurred various attempts <lb/>to use biological fluid markers of neuroinflammation as a <lb/>prognostic indicator of TBI. Although, the dynamic evolution of <lb/>immunological biomarker levels in the blood does not necessarily <lb/>correlate with brain findings derived from cerebral-spinal fluid <lb/>(CSF) (10-13), due to ease of access, blood immunological <lb/>biomarkers have been drawing increasing interest as prognostic <lb/>tools for TBI (8). Nevertheless, some early studies (10, 14-17) on <lb/>neuroinflammation biomarkers in TBI often used a reductionist <lb/>approach focusing on a single biomarker or oversimplifying the <lb/>interactions between biomarkers. Future studies into biomarkers in <lb/>TBI may benefit from using more comprehensive biomarker panels. <lb/>Traumatic axonal injuries (TAIs) and white matter damage are <lb/>common pathologies in TBIs, which are often detectable using non-<lb/>invasive neuroimaging techniques. Specifically, computed tomography <lb/>(CT) can detect larger haemorrhagic TAIs, susceptibility-weighted <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can detect smaller haemorrhagic <lb/>TAIs, and diffusion-weighted MRI or diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) <lb/>MRI can detect small non-haemorrhagic TAIs (18) and other <lb/>microstructural changes in human TBIs (19-21) and experimental <lb/>animal TBIs (6, 22-24). Human TBIs are complex in their origins, <lb/>severities, mechanisms of injury, patients&apos; background, immunological <lb/>reactions, and subsequent evolution of the pathologies. Given this <lb/>heterogeneity, animal models of TBI such as the controlled cortical <lb/>impact (CCI) model in the rat (25) provide a robust platform for <lb/>translational studies with reduced inter-subject variability, while <lb/>capturing key aspects of the common pathologies in human TBIs <lb/>(26). DTI generates an index of fractional anisotropy (FA) of water <lb/>diffusion in brain tissue, which is generally reduced in cases of white <lb/>matter damage and TAIs (6, 27). Given the association of <lb/>neuroinflammation with post-TBI neuropathology and the common <lb/>utilisation of DTI in clinical imaging, we hypothesised that <lb/>inflammatory markers in blood should bear a relation to TBI <lb/>outcomes with respect to DTI quantification of TAIs. We tested this <lb/>hypothesis by applying a panel of plasma inflammatory markers in the <lb/>rodent CCI TBI model and in clinical TBI cases, both in relation to DTI <lb/>indices of TAI. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Study subjects and participants <lb/>The animal experiments received approval by the Animal <lb/>Research Ethics Committee (AEC) of the University of <lb/>Queensland (approval number: QBI/036/16/MAIC). Fourteen <lb/>male Sprague-Dawley rats aged 8 to 10 weeks and weighing 300 <lb/>to 340 grams were acquired from the Animal Resource Centre <lb/>(ARC, Western Australia). They were kept in standard laboratory <lb/>conditions with a 12-hour light-dark cycle and provided with <lb/>unrestricted access to food and water. The rats were randomly <lb/>assigned to sham surgery (n = 6) and TBI (n = 8) groups. Blood <lb/>samples were collected from a tail vein of each rat at days 1, 3, 7, and <lb/>60 after the respective surgeries. The plasma fractions were <lb/>separated and stored at -80°C until analysis using the plasma <lb/>biomarker panels of cytokines. Additionally, magnetic resonance <lb/>imaging (MRI) scans were performed at day 60 after the surgeries. <lb/>The human study part was approved by the institutional <lb/>Human Research Ethics Committee (approval number HREC/16/ <lb/>QRBW/604). We obtained informed consent from conscious TBI <lb/>patients or their surrogate decision-makers upon their admission to <lb/>the neurosurgical unit of a level-1 trauma hospital in Brisbane, <lb/>Queensland, Australia. This hospital is part of the Metro North <lb/>Health network, Queensland, Australia, which serves a population <lb/>of approximately 900,000. We excluded individuals who were under <lb/>18 or over 80 years old, had a history of neurodegenerative disease, <lb/>significant mental health disorders, or contraindications for MRI. <lb/>All patients had positive findings on their initial CT scan or met the <lb/>criteria for mild TBI as defined by the National Institute of <lb/>Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) (28) or the <lb/>American Congress of Rehabilitation Medicine (ACRM) (29), <lb/>which include documented loss of consciousness or post-<lb/>traumatic amnesia following a head injury. We collected general <lb/>demographic information and key clinical parameters for all <lb/>participants from their respective clinical charts. These <lb/>parameters included details about the mechanism of injury, the <lb/>initial GCS score, and pupillary reactions at the time of admission. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<body>To serve as a comparison group for the plasma immunological <lb/>biomarker panel, we recruited 19 healthy controls who were <lb/>matched in terms of demographics. The selection criteria for these <lb/>controls included the absence of significant neurodegenerative or <lb/>mental health disorders and no history of diagnosed TBI within the <lb/>previous 12 months. The control group did not undergo MRI scans. <lb/>2.2 Animal TBI experiment <lb/>2.2.1 Controlled cortical impact (CCI) traumatic <lb/>brain injury model <lb/>The procedures for CCI are described in detail in our previous <lb/>publications (24, 30). In brief, we anesthetized the rats with <lb/>isoflurane (5% for induction, 1-2% for maintenance) in a 40:60 <lb/>O 2 :medical air mixture at a flow rate of 2 L/min. After induction, <lb/>the rats were placed in a stereotaxic frame, part of the right scalp <lb/>retracted, and a 5 mm diameter craniotomy window was carefully <lb/>made over the right cerebral hemisphere, centred at 2.5 mm <lb/>posterior to bregma and 3 mm right lateral to the sagittal suture. <lb/>In the TBI group, a CCI injury was induced using a pneumatically <lb/>driven impactor (TBI 0310, Precision System and Instrumentation, <lb/>USA) with a cylindrical 4 mm diameter tip, employing the following <lb/>impact parameters: impact velocity = 5 m/s, penetration depth = <lb/>2 mm, and dwell time = 200 ms. For the sham animals, the <lb/>craniotomy was performed similarly, but no actual impact <lb/>was delivered. <lb/>Following the impact or sham procedure, the bone flap was <lb/>replaced, and the scalp sutured. The total anaesthesia time was <lb/>under 20 minutes. Afterwards, the animals were removed from the <lb/>stereotaxic frame and placed on a heated surface for monitoring and <lb/>recovery. Once the animals displayed full mobility and alertness, <lb/>they were returned to their home cages. Importantly, no animals <lb/>exhibited noticeable signs of motor deficits after the procedure. <lb/>2.2.2 Blood sample collection and plasma <lb/>immunological biomarker quantification <lb/>The details of our procedures for blood sampling and <lb/>quantifying plasma immunological markers are presented in a <lb/>prior publication (30). Blood samples (approximately 1mL) were <lb/>collected at four timepoints (days 1, 3, 7, and 60 post-procedure) <lb/>through tail vein venepuncture into EDTA collection tubes. Blood <lb/>samples were briefly centrifuged to separate the plasma fraction, <lb/>which was then passed through glass wool and a 0.22-micron <lb/>filtration column via a second centrifugation and stored at -80 <lb/>°C <lb/>for further analysis. For immunological biomarker analysis, we used <lb/>a rat cytokine kit from Bio-Rad (Cat# 12005641). The plasma <lb/>samples were thawed, diluted, and then processed exactly <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions, with simultaneous <lb/>detection of analytes in 96-well plates using the robotic liquid <lb/>handling workstation epMotion 5075 (Eppendorf). The assay <lb/>plates were washed using the Bio-Plex Pro II magnetic plate <lb/>washer (Bio-Rad), and the measurements of analytes were <lb/>obtained using the Bio-Plex Systems 200 (Bio-Rad). The analysis <lb/>of samples and creation of reference standard curves [Log(x) -<lb/>Linear(y)] were performed using the Bio-Plex Manager v6.1 <lb/>software (Bio-Rad). The following markers were quantified: <lb/>interleukins (IL) IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-10, <lb/>IL-12p70, IL-13, IL-17a, and IL-18, granulocyte colony-stimulating <lb/>factor (G-CSF), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor <lb/>(GM-CSF), macrophage colony-stimulating factor (M-CSF), <lb/>interferon gamma (IFN-g), chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 1 <lb/>(CXCL1), chemokine ligands (CCL) CCL2, CCL3, CCL5, CCL20, <lb/>vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), and tumour necrosis <lb/>factor alpha (TNF-a). <lb/>2.2.3 Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data <lb/>collection and processing <lb/>Details of the animal MRI procedure are presented in a prior <lb/>publication (30). On day 60 after the sham or TBI procedure, <lb/>anaesthesia for MRI was induced as above using 2-4% isoflurane for <lb/>positioning in an MRI-compatible cradle (Bruker Biospin, <lb/>Germany) equipped with ear bars and bite bars to immobilise the <lb/>head. Isoflurane concentration was reduced to 1-2% for cradle <lb/>positioning. During the MRI scan, we provided further <lb/>anaesthesia with an intraperitoneal bolus dose of 0.1 mg/kg <lb/>medetomidine, followed immediately by intraperitoneal <lb/>continuous infusion of 0.1 mg/kg/h medetomidine. Isoflurane <lb/>concentration was gradually reduced to the 0-0.3% range for <lb/>most of the scan, aiming to maintain a respiration rate in the 60 <lb/>-95 breaths per minute. We applied water circulation by a pump <lb/>and thermostatic heater (SC100, Thermo Scientific, USA) to warm <lb/>the animal cradle, thereby maintaining the animal&apos;s rectal <lb/>temperature at 36 ± 1°C. At the end of the MR examination, we <lb/>applied an intraperitoneal bolus dose of 0.1 mg/kg atipemazole <lb/>(Antisedan, Pfizer, Germany) for medetomidine reversal. <lb/>As described in (23, 24), rat MRI scans were acquired on a 9.4 T <lb/>Bruker system (BioSpec 94/30USR, Bruker, Germany) running the <lb/>Paravision 6.0.1 software (Bruker, Germany), along with a volume <lb/>transmitter coil and a four-element array receiver coil. Anatomical <lb/>imaging was performed using T2-weighted (T2w) rapid-relaxation-<lb/>with-enhancement (RARE) sequence with the following <lb/>parameters: repetition time (TR)/Echo Time (TE) = 5900/65 ms, <lb/>RARE factors = 8, number of averages = 2, FOV = 25.6 × 32 mm, <lb/>matrix size = 256 × 256 × 40, and 0.5 mm-thick slices, giving an <lb/>effective output spatial resolution of 0.1 × 0.125 × 0.5 mm. <lb/>Diffusion-weighted images were collected using a spin-echo echo-<lb/>planar imaging (EPI) sequence with TR/TE = 10000/29 ms, FOV = <lb/>24.8 × 24.8 mm, matrix size = 108 × 108 × 41, and 0.5 mm-thick <lb/>slices with 0.1 mm slice gaps, giving effective output spatial <lb/>resolution of 0.23 × 0.23 × 0.6 mm. A b-value of 750 s/mm 2 and <lb/>32 diffusion-weighted directions, and 4 volumes of b=0 s/mm 2 <lb/>were used. <lb/>Rat MRI data were exported from the scanner to DICOM <lb/>format and converted to NIFTI format using MRIcron (31). The <lb/>MRI images were given a header file with voxel size 10 times larger <lb/>than the original voxel size to enable the use of image processing <lb/>tools originally developed for human brain (32). We have presented <lb/>details of the processing procedures for rat MRI data in a prior <lb/>publication (30). The sham animals&apos; structural images were used to <lb/>construct a study-specific T2w structural template in the SIGMA in <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<body>vivo rat brain template space (33). Spatial normalisations of sham <lb/>and TBI rat brains to this study-specific template were performed <lb/>using the constrained cost function masking (CCFM) approach, <lb/>which is an extension of the original cost function masking <lb/>approach (34). In our modification, the template was registered to <lb/>the individual subject&apos;s image (rather than vice versa) with an <lb/>additional cost function mask that excluded non-brain structures <lb/>(for the template and individual images) and the lesioned areas (for <lb/>the TBI individual images) using symmetric diffeomorphic image <lb/>registration with cross-correlation (SyN-CC) (35), as implemented <lb/>in Advanced Normalization Tool (ANTS v.2.3.4) (36). Using the <lb/>inverse of the transformation, we then warped images in the T2w <lb/>structural image space to the common space. <lb/>Next, the four b=0 volumes were averaged to generate a b=0 <lb/>spatial representation of the diffusion MRI data, which were then <lb/>corrected for motion and eddy current using FSL&apos;s eddy_correct, <lb/>and then registered to the T2w structural image using ANTS SyN-<lb/>CC registration. The warping field obtained from this step was <lb/>combined with the inverse warping field obtained from the template <lb/>to individual T2w structural image registration step to enable the <lb/>warping of images in the diffusion MRI space to the common space. <lb/>Diffusion tensor fitting was performed using the b = 750 s/mm 2 <lb/>volumes as implemented in FSL&apos;s dtifit, and the resulting FA images <lb/>were warped to the common space. <lb/>2.3 Human traumatic brain injury <lb/>data collection <lb/>2.3.1 Magnetic resonance imaging data collection <lb/>All participants were scanned at the earliest availability of the <lb/>hospital&apos;s 3T MRI scanner (Prisma, Siemens Healthcare, Germany) <lb/>after they were determined by the treating physician to be <lb/>sufficiently clinically stable, using a 32-channel head array coil. <lb/>The median time post-injury interval was 8 days, and the <lb/>interquartile range was 3-13 days. Due to COVID restrictions, <lb/>imaging was delayed to 114 days for one patient and 213 days for <lb/>another patient. T2-weighted (T2w) fluid-attenuated inversion <lb/>recovery (FLAIR) was performed with the following parameters: <lb/>TE = 81 ms, TR = 9000 ms, FA = 150 degrees, and effective <lb/>resolution = 0.69 × 0.69 × 3.3 mm. A structural T1-weighted (T1w) <lb/>magnetisation prepared rapid gradient-echo (T1w-MPRAGE) <lb/>sequence was performed with the following parameters: TE = <lb/>2.26 ms, TR = 1900 ms, FA = 9 degrees, effective resolution = 1 <lb/>mm 3 isotropic. The diffusion MRI image was acquired with the <lb/>following parameters: TE = 84 ms, TR = 4700 ms, FA = 90 degrees, <lb/>and effective resolution = 2 mm 3 isotropic, 60 diffusion-weighted <lb/>directions at b value = 3000 s/mm 2 and 12 b0 volumes. <lb/>2.3.2 Blood sampling, processing, and <lb/>quantitation of immune cytokine concentrations <lb/>On the day of the MRI scan, blood samples were obtained from <lb/>the TBI participants using EDTA collection tubes. A 10 ml sample <lb/>of whole blood was collected and centrifuged at 1600 g for 10 <lb/>minutes. The resulting serum was then carefully removed and <lb/>stored at -80 °C until the time of analysis. The multiplexed <lb/>immunoassay procedure utilized the Bio-Plex Pro Human <lb/>Cytokine 27-plex Assay (Catalogue number: M500KCAF0Y) <lb/>following the provided guidelines without any alterations. In <lb/>summary, the frozen samples were defrosted, mixed using a <lb/>vortex, and subsequently centrifuged at 1000 g for 2 minutes at 4 <lb/>°C. As per the manufacturer&apos;s instructions, the samples were diluted <lb/>at a ratio of 1:4 with the sample diluent from the kit, whereupon the <lb/>diluted samples were passed through 0.22 µm high recovery <lb/>Durapore (PVDF) centrifuge filters with rotation at 14,000 g for <lb/>15 minutes at 4 °C. <lb/>For the analysis, both standards and samples were processed <lb/>using a 96-well plate and a robotic liquid handling workstation <lb/>(epMotion 5075; Eppendorf). Subsequent washing of the plate was <lb/>carried out using a Bio-Plex Pro II magnetic plate washer (Bio-Rad), <lb/>and the readings were taken using the Bio-Plex Systems 200. <lb/>Throughout the incubation process at 25 °C, the assay plates were <lb/>gently agitated at 850 rpm under subdued light. The Bio-Plex <lb/>Manager v6.0 software was employed to analyse the samples and <lb/>generate standard curves. In instances where the measured <lb/>concentration of a specific analyte was below the detectable range <lb/>of the standard curves, the value was recorded as zero. The <lb/>following biomarkers were quantified: interleukins (IL) IL-1b, IL-<lb/>4, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8, IL-9, IL-17, and interleukin 1 receptor antagonist <lb/>(IL-1ra), as well as Eotaxin, basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), <lb/>granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), interferon gamma <lb/>(IFN-g), chemokines (C-C motif) ligands 2, 3, 4, and 5 (CCL2, <lb/>CCL3, CCL4, and CCL5), platelet-derived growth factor-BB <lb/>(PDGF-BB), and tumour necrosis factor alpha (TNF-a). <lb/>2.3.3 Magnetic resonance imaging <lb/>data processing <lb/>Each participant&apos;s T2w-FLAIR image was rigidly registered to <lb/>their T1w-MPRAGE image, which was corrected for bias field <lb/>inhomogeneity and segmented into grey matter, white matter, <lb/>cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), skull, and head tissue probability maps <lb/>using SPM12&apos;s Segment tool. The TBI lesion area was identified as <lb/>hyper-intense regions on T2w-FLAIR and hypo-intense or iso-<lb/>intense regions with normal grey matter on T1w-MPRAGE using <lb/>the region competition snakes segmentation (37) implemented in <lb/>ITK-SNAP (v.3.8) with the following procedure: the co-registered <lb/>and bias field-corrected T1w-MPRAGE and T2w-FLAIR images of <lb/>each participant were loaded into ITK-SNAP and a multi-modal <lb/>tissue class classifier pre-segmentation step was employed to <lb/>produce the preliminary segmentation probabilistic map. <lb/>Representative examples of the TBI lesion (as defined above), <lb/>normal grey matter, normal white matter, and the cerebrospinal <lb/>fluid were manually identified for each participant. These example <lb/>regions served as tissue class classifiers for the semi-automatic <lb/>classification pre-segmentation step, which generate tissue class <lb/>probabilistic maps. The tissue class probabilistic map for the <lb/>lesion area were inspected (by XVT) to ensure that it reasonably <lb/>delineated the TBI lesion areas; inevitably, the lesion probabilistic <lb/>maps included non-lesion and non-brain areas, but over the <lb/>positively identified lesion areas, we confirmed that the lesion <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<body>probabilistic maps did not include the adjacent normal-appearing <lb/>brain areas. Once we were satisfied with the probabilistic maps, <lb/>initiation bubbles were seeded over the suspected lesion areas and <lb/>iterative snake evolution was performed to grow the initiation <lb/>bubbles to cover the lesion areas. Here, the curvature parameter <lb/>was set to 0.001. <lb/>The grey matter, white matter, and CSF tissue probabilistic <lb/>maps from SPM12&apos;s segmentation of the T1w-MPRAGE image and <lb/>the segmented TBI lesion map created as above were combined and <lb/>binarized to generate a whole brain mask including the lesion area <lb/>included (typical skull-stripping algorithms like FSL&apos;s BET and <lb/>SPM12&apos;s Segment often miss brain lesion areas). This whole brain <lb/>mask was used to generate a bias field inhomogeneity-corrected and <lb/>skull-stripped T1w-MPRAGE structural image. The generated <lb/>whole brain mask image was subtracted by the TBI lesion map to <lb/>generate a normal appearing brain (NAB) mask, which include the <lb/>normal appearing grey matter, white matter, and the CSF. <lb/>The b0 value images were extracted and merged into a 4D <lb/>image, which was then motion-corrected using FSL&apos;s eddy_correct <lb/>and averaged to generate a b0 spatial representation of diffusion <lb/>MRI data. This b0 spatial representation image was N4ITK bias <lb/>field-corrected (38), and then skull-stripped using FSL&apos;s BET. The <lb/>resultant spatial representation image was affinely registered to the <lb/>inhomogeneity-corrected and skull-stripped T1w-MPRAGE <lb/>structural image. Diffusion MRI data were fitted to the diffusion <lb/>tensor model using FSL&apos;s dtifit. <lb/>All participants&apos; T1w-MPRAGE images were registered to the <lb/>OASIS template of the MICCAI 2012 workshop on multi-atlas <lb/>labelling (39) using the CCFM approach (34), with the NAB mask <lb/>serving as the cost function mask for the individual T1w-MPRAGE <lb/>image and the OASIS template mask as the cost function mask for <lb/>the OASIS template. The deformation model was the Syn-CC <lb/>model (35) as implemented in ANTS (v.2.3.4) (36). The warping <lb/>field obtained from this step was combined with the transformation <lb/>matrix obtained from the diffusion MRI-to-T1w-MPRAGE <lb/>registration step to warp the human diffusion MRI metrics to a <lb/>common space. <lb/>2.4 Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed in GraphPad Prism (v.9.5.1, <lb/>GraphPad Software, Inc., San Diego, California, USA). Normality of <lb/>the data was tested using the Shapiro-Wilk test (40, 41). <lb/>2.4.1 Animal data statistical analysis <lb/>Unpaired Mann-Whitney tests were performed to compare <lb/>plasma levels of immunological biomarkers in the sham and TBI <lb/>groups at different timepoints, with correction for multiple <lb/>comparisons using the two-stage linear step-up procedure of <lb/>Benjamini, Krieger, and Yekutieli for false discovery rate <lb/>correction (42). FDR threshold was set at the desired FDR (Q) &lt; 0.1. <lb/>Data reduction for TBI animals&apos; plasma immunological <lb/>markers at each timepoint was accomplished using principal <lb/>component analysis (PCA) in Prism (v.9.5.1). The plasma <lb/>concentrations of each biomarker across all the TBI animals at <lb/>each timepoint (days 1, 3, 7, or 60 post-TBI) were standardised and <lb/>centred so that the mean was zero and standard deviation was unity <lb/>for each biomarker across the TBI animals. We performed PCA on <lb/>these standardised and centred plasma concentrations at each <lb/>timepoint and selected a maximum of three principal <lb/>components (PCs) for each PCA to minimise over-fitting. The <lb/>summary results for the extracted PCs for the immunological <lb/>biomarker panel at each timepoint are presented in Tables 1A-D. <lb/>We next used the extracted PC scores to perform voxel-wise <lb/>multiple linear regression (MLR) (this procedure is also known as <lb/>Principal Component Regression [PCR] (43)) predicting the <lb/>outcome of DTI metrics at day 60 post-injury using each TBI <lb/>animal&apos;s plasma immunological biomarker panel at each timepoint. <lb/>The voxel-wise MLR was performed using permutation inference <lb/>for the general linear model (44) in FSL&apos;s randomise (45), with the <lb/>TABLE 1 Summary of the principal components (PCs) extracted from the <lb/>plasma immunological panels of rat controlled cortical impact (CCI) <lb/>model of traumatic brain injury (TBI) days 1 (a), 3 (b), 7 (c), and 60 (d) <lb/>post-TBI, and of (e) human TBI patients with a median time post-injury <lb/>of 8 days. <lb/>(a) Rat day 1 post-TBI immunological marker levels <lb/>PC summary <lb/>PC1 <lb/>PC2 <lb/>PC3 <lb/>Eigenvalue <lb/>16.5 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Proportion of variance (%) <lb/>71.6 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>Cumulative proportion of variance (%) <lb/>71.6 <lb/>89.7 <lb/>95.8 <lb/>(b) Rat day 3 post-TBI immunological marker levels <lb/>PC summary <lb/>PC1 <lb/>PC2 <lb/>PC3 <lb/>Eigenvalue <lb/>13.9 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>Proportion of variance (%) <lb/>60.6 <lb/>25.7 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>Cumulative proportion of variance (%) <lb/>60.6 <lb/>86.3 <lb/>94.2 <lb/>(c) Rat day 7 post-TBI immunological marker levels <lb/>PC summary <lb/>PC1 <lb/>PC2 <lb/>PC3 <lb/>Eigenvalue <lb/>9.1 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>Proportion of variance (%) <lb/>39.5 <lb/>26.1 <lb/>18.2 <lb/>Cumulative proportion of variance (%) <lb/>39.5 <lb/>65.5 <lb/>83.7 <lb/>(d) Rat day 60 post-TBI immunological marker levels <lb/>PC summary <lb/>PC1 <lb/>PC2 <lb/>PC3 <lb/>Eigenvalue <lb/>10.7 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>Proportion of variance (%) <lb/>46.4 <lb/>24.3 <lb/>14.6 <lb/>Cumulative proportion of variance (%) <lb/>46.4 <lb/>70.6 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>(e) Human clinical post-TBI immunological marker levels <lb/>PC summary <lb/>PC1 <lb/>PC2 <lb/>PC3 <lb/>Eigenvalue <lb/>5.7 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>Proportion of variance (%) <lb/>26.9 <lb/>24.7 <lb/>19.7 <lb/>Cumulative proportion of variance (%) <lb/>26.9 <lb/>51.7 <lb/>71.4 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<body>number of permutations set to 10,000 or exhaustive, whichever was <lb/>smaller. The resulting statistical maps were corrected for multiple <lb/>comparisons with mass-based FSL&apos;s threshold-free cluster <lb/>enhancement (TFCE) (46) and thresholded at P value &lt; 0.05 <lb/>(two-tailed). <lb/>The voxel-wise regression analysis identified only one region-<lb/>of-interest (ROI), namely the external capsule white matter tract <lb/>contralateral to the injured hemisphere, in which FA correlated the <lb/>animals&apos; PCA-reduced plasma immunological biomarker panel at <lb/>day 60 post-TBI, as displayed in Figures 1A, B. FA values were <lb/>extracted from the identified ROI and used to perform a PCR (43) <lb/>to correlate the FA value from the ROI with the plasma <lb/>immunological biomarker panel results, with up to 3 PCs, as <lb/>above. The PCR extracted the PC scores from the PCA step and <lb/>conducted MLR correlating the variation in the FA of the ROI with <lb/>the 3 PC scores and the resulting regression coefficients were back-<lb/>projected to the original immunological biomarkers; this step <lb/>served to enable a more intuitive understanding the results <lb/>quantifying the relationship between FA variation and the <lb/>variation of each immunological plasma biomarker. The validity <lb/>of the MLR model was tested through a Shapiro-Wilk&apos;s normality <lb/>test (40) of the residuals. <lb/>2.4.2 Human data statistical analysis <lb/>Unpaired Mann-Whitney tests comparing the plasma levels of <lb/>immunological biomarkers were performed to compare TBI and <lb/>control participants, with significance set at P value &lt; 0.05. As with <lb/>the animal plasma immunological biomarker panel, we performed <lb/>data reduction of the human biomarker panel by PCA, with a <lb/>maximum of three PCs. A summary the extracted PCs is presented <lb/>in Table 1E. The extracted PC scores were then used to perform <lb/>voxel-wise MLR for correlating the DTI metrics in TBI patients <lb/>against their PC scores which explained most of the variations in the <lb/>plasma immunological biomarker panel. Implementation of the <lb/>voxel-wise MLR analysis in the human data was much as for the <lb/>animal data, and similarly identified regions in the patients&apos; white <lb/>matter in which FA correlated with the biomarker panel. We <lb/>identified three ROIs for further analysis: corpus callosum (cc), <lb/>longitudinal fasciculus (lf), and the corticospinal tract (cst), as <lb/>shown in Figures 1C, D. FA values were extracted from these <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Voxel-wise multiple linear regression results and the identified regions-of-interest (ROIs) correlating animal (A, B) and human (C, D) fractional <lb/>anisotropy (FA) and the principal components (PCs) extracted from the corresponding plasma immunological biomarkers. The images were overlaid <lb/>on the averaged registered FA maps. (A) Statistical map of multiple linear regression analysis correlating the FA map with the PCs extracted from <lb/>plasma immunological biomarkers panel at day 60 post-injury. (B) ROI selected for the rat data in the right external capsule (blue, ec), ipsilateral to <lb/>the injury. (C) Statistical map of multiple linear regression analysis correlating the TBI patients&apos; FA maps with the PCs extracted from the <lb/>corresponding plasma immunological biomarkers, at a median of eight days post injury. (D) ROIs selected for the human data in the corpus callosum <lb/>(red, cc), corticospinal tract (green, cst), and longitudinal fasciculus (blue, lst). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<body>ROIs were PCR analysis for correlation with the data reduced <lb/>plasma immunological biomarker panel. The analysis steps were <lb/>like those performed on the animal data as presented above. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>We have presented a comparison of the plasma immunological <lb/>biomarkers between sham and TBI groups in these rats in an earlier <lb/>manuscript (30). In brief, IL-1b, IL-7, GM-CSF, and CCL3 were <lb/>elevated in the TBI group compared to the sham group between day <lb/>3 and day 60 post-injury. IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-13, IL-17a, IL-19, <lb/>G-CSF, and IFN-g extremely elevated in several TBI animals at day <lb/>1-7 post-TBI though statistical analysis did not show significant <lb/>group differences at all timepoint post-injury and the animals with <lb/>extreme day 1-7 values apparently normalised at day 60. CCL2, <lb/>CCL20, TNF-a, IL-18, and VEGF never differed significantly <lb/>between the TBI and sham group. IL-1a, IL-12p70, and M-CSF <lb/>were decreased in the TBI group compared to sham group only at <lb/>day 1 post-injury and there was no difference at day 3, 7, or 60. <lb/>Analysis of human TBI and control plasma immunological <lb/>biomarker panels showed that IL-1ra, IL-6, IL-8, and PDGF-BB <lb/>were significantly elevated and IL-13, IFN-g significantly lower in <lb/>the TBI compared to control participants (Figure 2). IL-1b, IL-4, IL-<lb/>7, IL-9, IL-17, Eotaxin, bFGF, G-CSF, CXCL10, CCL2, CCL3, <lb/>CCL4, CCL5, and TNF-a showed insignificant differences <lb/>between TBI and control participants. <lb/>In the experimental animals, voxel-wise MLR analysis showed <lb/>that FA in the contralateral (to the injured hemisphere) ec at day 60 <lb/>post-TBI correlated with the day 60 post-TBI plasma <lb/>immunological biomarker panel (Figure 1A). ROI-based analysis <lb/>showed that the FA in the rat ec ROI correlated positively with the <lb/>day 60 plasma levels of IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-<lb/>10, IL-12p70, IL-17a, IL-18, G-CSF, GM-CSF, IFN-g, CXCL1, <lb/>CCL2, CCL3, VEGF, and TNF-a. The regression equation was <lb/>significant (Table 2, F [3, 4] = 46.6, P value = 0.0014 and Figure 3A) <lb/>with an adjusted R 2 of 0.951. The residuals passed the normality test <lb/>(Shapiro-Wilk test, P value = 0.212), and the MLR model was thus <lb/>considered valid. <lb/>Voxel-wise MLR showed that the FA in various human white <lb/>matter regions correlated significantly with the plasma <lb/>immunological biomarker panel (Figure 1C). FA specifically in <lb/>the cc ROI had a significant positive correlation with IL-6, IL-8, <lb/>IL-9, G-CSF, CXCL10, CCL3, PDGF-BB, CCL4, CCL5, and a <lb/>negative correlation with IL-13 and CCL2. The regression <lb/>equation was significant (Table 3, F [3, 11] = 6.70, P = 0.0078 <lb/>and Figure 3B), with an adjusted R 2 of 0.550. The residuals passed <lb/>the normality test (Shapiro-Wilk test, P value = 0.97) and the MLR <lb/>model was thus considered valid. FA in the lf ROI correlated <lb/>positively with IL-1b, IL-1ra, IL-6, IL-8, IL-9, bFGF, G-CSF, <lb/>CXCL10, CCL3, PDGF-BB, CCL4, CCL5, TNF-a and negatively <lb/>with IL-4, IL-7, IL-13, Eotaxin, and CCL2. The regression equation <lb/>was significant (Table 4, F [3, 11] = 28.4, P value &lt; 0.0001 and <lb/>Figure 3C) with an adjusted R 2 of 0.854. The residuals passed the <lb/>normality test (Shapiro-Wilk test, P value = 0.4382) and the MLR <lb/>model was thus considered valid. FA in the cst correlated positively <lb/>with the plasma levels of IL-1ra, IL-6, IL-8, IL-9, G-CSF, CXCL10, <lb/>CCL3, PDGF-BB, CCL4, CCL5, and negatively with IL-4, IL-7, IL-<lb/>13, Eotaxin, and CCL2. The regression equation was significant <lb/>(Table 5, F (3, 11) = 10.6, P value = 0.0014 and Figure 3D), with an <lb/>adjusted R 2 of 0.672. The residuals passed normality test (Shapiro-<lb/>Wilk test, P value = 0.75) and the MLR model was thus <lb/>considered valid. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>In the rat model of TBI and likewise in the group of TBI <lb/>patients, there was generally agreement in the correlations between <lb/>the biomarkers and diffusion MRI indicators of white matter <lb/>integrity, thus concurring that the observed changes in plasma <lb/>biomarkers were associated with a greater degree of white matter <lb/>integrity, albeit with imperfect agreement of the direction of <lb/>correlations between rat TBI and human results. In the rat CCI <lb/>model, plasma immunological biomarker levels at day 60 post-<lb/>injury were generally associated with higher FA in the ec ROI, <lb/>which general indicates higher white matter integrity in the ec at <lb/>day 60 post-injury (decreased FA is generally associated with poorer <lb/>white matter integrity (47)). Also, the CCI model rats at day 60 <lb/>generally had significantly elevated levels of the same biomarkers or <lb/>had shown increased levels at day 3-7 that had normalised at day 60. <lb/>Mean plasma levels of IL-1ra, IL-6, IL-8, and PDGF-BB were <lb/>significantly higher in the TBI participants compared to control <lb/>samples mostly between day 3 and day 13 post-injury; these <lb/>biomarkers correlated positively with FA in several white matter <lb/>ROIs. Conversely, IL-13 and IFN-g levels were lower in TBI <lb/>participants as compared to control samples, and these same <lb/>biomarkers in the patients correlated negatively with FA. <lb/>While the direction of changes in the immunological biomarker <lb/>and of the association between these biomarkers and white matter <lb/>FA did not match in CCI rats and clinical TBI cases, there was a <lb/>general agreement that levels of a short list of biomarkers were <lb/>associated with preserved white matter integrity. Cross-species <lb/>results regarding the direction of correlation were consistent for <lb/>IL-1b, IL-6, G-CSF, CCL3, CCL5, and TNF-a, but differed for IL-4, <lb/>IL-7, IL-13, and CCL2. The generally positively correlating <lb/>relationships of biomarker levels and white matter integrity in the <lb/>TBI model rats occurred with along with elevations in most of those <lb/>same biomarkers post-TBI. We see a similar phenomenon in the <lb/>TBI participants, whereby certain biomarkers were elevated, and <lb/>correlated positively with FA in the white matter ROIs. However, <lb/>the positive correlation between IL-13 levels with FA in the rat <lb/>model stands in contrast to the negative correlation seen in human <lb/>TBI patients; whereas relative to control samples, the human TBI <lb/>participants showed a significantly reduced plasma IL-13 level at a <lb/>median of 8 days post injury, a few of the TBI rats had extremely <lb/>high IL-13 levels in the first week post-injury. IL-13 administration <lb/>in a mouse model of open-head moderate-severe TBI reduced <lb/>neuronal loss and preserved white matter integrity (48). IL-4 and <lb/>IL-7 had differing trends in correlation with FA; although IL-4 and <lb/>IL-7 concentrations in the human TBI patients&apos; samples did not <lb/>differ from control values, several rats had extremely high levels of <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<body>IL-4 and IL-7 in the first week post-injury (as seen likewise in the <lb/>same rats for IL-13) compared to controls. The interpretation of the <lb/>extremely high levels in a few animals is uncertain, since those <lb/>animals did not have conspicuously larger TBI lesions, greater tissue <lb/>loss, nor notable functional deficits (30). CCL2 levels did not <lb/>significantly differ in the human or rat TBI samples as compared <lb/>to control results. We conclude that, while the specific direction of <lb/>change and effects of the immunological biomarkers can differ <lb/>between animal and human TBI, the observed changes are generally <lb/>associated with preserved white matter integrity in the face of <lb/>the injury. <lb/>Certain biomarkers were significantly elevated in the present <lb/>human TBI participants to an extent correlating significantly to <lb/>TABLE 2 Results of principal component regression (PCR) correlating the fractional anisotropy (FA) in the external capsule (ec) region-of-interest <lb/>(ROI) at day 60 post-injury with the plasma immunological panel at day 60 post-injury in the rat controlled cortical impact (CCI) model of traumatic <lb/>brain injury (TBI). <lb/>Analysis of Variance <lb/>SS <lb/>DF <lb/>MS <lb/>F (DFn, DFd) <lb/>P value <lb/>Regression <lb/>7.59E-03 <lb/>3 <lb/>2.53E-03 <lb/>F (3, 4) = 46.6 <lb/>P=0.0014 <lb/>Residual <lb/>2.17E-04 <lb/>4 <lb/>5.43E-05 <lb/>Total <lb/>7.81E-03 <lb/>7 <lb/>Dependent variable: FA in the external capsule at 60 days post-TBI in rat CCI model. <lb/>Predictor variable: plasma immunological panel at 60 days post-TBI in rat CCI model. <lb/>Bolded values indicate P &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Normality <lb/>of Residuals <lb/>Statistics <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>Passed normality <lb/>test (alpha=0.05)? <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk (W) <lb/>0.8854 <lb/>0.2121 <lb/>Yes <lb/>Parameter estimates <lb/>Variable <lb/>Estimate <lb/>95% CI (asymptotic) <lb/>|t| <lb/>P value <lb/>b0 <lb/>Intercept <lb/>4.07E-01 <lb/>3.73E-01 <lb/>to <lb/>4.41E-01 <lb/>33.5 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b1 <lb/>IL-1b <lb/>1.35E-05 <lb/>7.40E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>1.96E-05 <lb/>6.14 <lb/>0.0036 <lb/>b2 <lb/>IL-1a <lb/>2.84E-05 <lb/>9.18E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>4.77E-05 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>0.0148 <lb/>b3 <lb/>IL-2 <lb/>1.61E-06 <lb/>6.80E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>2.54E-06 <lb/>4.81 <lb/>0.0086 <lb/>b4 <lb/>IL-4 <lb/>3.08E-05 <lb/>1.64E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>4.51E-05 <lb/>5.96 <lb/>0.0040 <lb/>b5 <lb/>IL-5 <lb/>3.01E-05 <lb/>1.39E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>4.63E-05 <lb/>5.16 <lb/>0.0067 <lb/>b6 <lb/>IL-6 <lb/>2.76E-05 <lb/>1.73E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.78E-05 <lb/>7.45 <lb/>0.0017 <lb/>b7 <lb/>IL-7 <lb/>1.63E-05 <lb/>9.31E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>2.33E-05 <lb/>6.46 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>b8 <lb/>IL-10 <lb/>5.08E-05 <lb/>3.18E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>6.97E-05 <lb/>7.44 <lb/>0.0017 <lb/>b9 <lb/>IL-12p70 <lb/>2.31E-05 <lb/>1.52E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.09E-05 <lb/>8.16 <lb/>0.0012 <lb/>b10 <lb/>IL-13 <lb/>9.29E-06 <lb/>-2.31E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>2.09E-05 <lb/>2.22 <lb/>0.0903 <lb/>b11 <lb/>IL-17a <lb/>3.06E-04 <lb/>1.88E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>4.24E-04 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>b12 <lb/>IL-18 <lb/>2.96E-07 <lb/>3.13E-09 <lb/>to <lb/>5.88E-07 <lb/>2.81 <lb/>0.0485 <lb/>b13 <lb/>G-CSF <lb/>7.54E-04 <lb/>3.88E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.12E-03 <lb/>5.72 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>b14 <lb/>M-CSF <lb/>-6.56E-05 <lb/>-2.56E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.24E-04 <lb/>0.959 <lb/>0.3920 <lb/>b15 <lb/>GM-CSF <lb/>1.56E-05 <lb/>8.06E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>2.32E-05 <lb/>5.73 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>b16 <lb/>IFN-g <lb/>2.81E-05 <lb/>1.81E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.81E-05 <lb/>7.78 <lb/>0.0015 <lb/>b17 <lb/>CXCL1 <lb/>2.57E-05 <lb/>1.41E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.74E-05 <lb/>6.12 <lb/>0.0036 <lb/>b18 <lb/>CCL2 <lb/>1.22E-05 <lb/>6.83E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>1.76E-05 <lb/>6.3 <lb/>0.0032 <lb/>b19 <lb/>CCL3 <lb/>8.66E-05 <lb/>5.12E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>1.22E-04 <lb/>6.79 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>b20 <lb/>CCL5 <lb/>2.77E-05 <lb/>-9.33E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>6.48E-05 <lb/>2.08 <lb/>0.1064 <lb/>b21 <lb/>CCL20 <lb/>4.96E-05 <lb/>-2.11E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>3.10E-04 <lb/>0.528 <lb/>0.6255 <lb/>b22 <lb/>VEGF <lb/>1.94E-05 <lb/>2.60E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>3.62E-05 <lb/>3.21 <lb/>0.0327 <lb/>b23 <lb/>TNF-a <lb/>1.48E-05 <lb/>9.52E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>2.01E-05 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>0.0015 <lb/>Adjusted R squared = 0.951. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<body>their white matter integrity, with an R 2 of the MLR model ranging <lb/>from 0.550 to 0.854. Among these, we previously found in a similar <lb/>clinical TBI cohort that plasma IL-1ra correlated with higher BBB <lb/>integrity in the primary TBI brain lesion (49). As an endogenous <lb/>inhibitor of the pro-inflammatory IL-1 (50), IL-1ra is an important <lb/>anti-inflammatory protein in certain autoimmune diseases, <lb/>including rheumatoid arthritis, colitis, and granulomatous <lb/>pulmonary disease (51), and has garnered interest as a <lb/>therapeutic intervention in CNS disorders with an inflammatory <lb/>component (50). We also found elevation of plasma IL-6 and IL-8 <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Quantified plasma concentrations of immunological biomarkers from traumatic brain injury and control group of interleukin (IL)-1b, interleukin 1 <lb/>receptor antagonist (IL-1ra), IL-4, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8, IL-13, IL-17, Eotaxin, basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), granulocyte colony-stimulating factor <lb/>(G-CSF), interferon gamma (IFN-g), granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), C-X-C motif chemokine ligand 10 (CXCL10), chemokine (C-C <lb/>motif) ligands 2 (CCL2), CCL3, platelet-derived growth factor-BB (PDGF-BB), CCL4, CCL5, tumour necrosis factor alpha (TNF-a). Mann-Whitney rank <lb/>test, * P value &lt; 0.05, ** P value &lt; 0.01, **** P value &lt; 0.0001. Bars and whiskers presented the median and inter-quartile range. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<body>in the present TBI participants, to an extent correlating with white <lb/>matter FA, which could suggest a protective effect. On the other <lb/>hand, higher CSF levels of IL-6, IL-8, and other markers including <lb/>IFN-g, IL-1b, and TNF-a were associated with unfavourable <lb/>outcomes in human TBI patients (52). Furthermore, higher <lb/>plasma levels of IL-6 (53-56) and IL-8 (53, 56, 57) were <lb/>associated with post-TBI mortality and respiratory distress (55, <lb/>56) in TBI patients. That higher levels of these biomarkers were <lb/>associated with preserved FA in the present group of TBI patients <lb/>may reflect our recruitment procedure; the patients were scanned <lb/>and had blood drawn only when they were deemed sufficiently <lb/>stable by their treating physicians after emergency treatment and/or <lb/>intensive care, i.e., a median of 8 days after the injury. <lb/>We also found elevated plasma levels of PDGF-BB, which <lb/>showed a positive correlation with white matter FA. Intravenous <lb/>administration of PDGF-BB inhibited endoplasmic reticulum and <lb/>autophagy stress and promoted neurological recovery in a mouse <lb/>model of open-head TBI (58). In another rodent model, TBI <lb/>interfered with PDGF signalling in a manner contributing to BBB <lb/>dysfunction (59). Thus, we see general agreement that PDGF-BB <lb/>may mediate recovery from TBI. <lb/>The biomarkers that were elevated in TBI model rats and in the <lb/>patients are generally known to be associated with negative <lb/>outcomes post-TBI. Nonetheless, we report in this study that <lb/>elevations in several cytokines were associated with higher FA in <lb/>the white matter both in human participants and the experimental <lb/>animals. This discrepancy may bear some relation to acutely life-<lb/>threatening outcomes such as multiple organ failure and respiratory <lb/>distress in the previous clinical studies. However, all our <lb/>participants were sufficiently stable once they were deemed ready <lb/>for MRI, and hence had survived their injury. Since <lb/>neuroinflammation is neither strictly detrimental nor beneficial <lb/>(9), present results elude simple interpretation. Furthermore, <lb/>biomarkers generally show dynamic changes in the aftermath of <lb/>the injury. For example, our earlier analyses of the rat <lb/>immunological panel results indicated a narrow time window of <lb/>approximately 7 days post injury (30) in which there was an <lb/>association with the trans-hemispheric cortical map transfer <lb/>process that occurs after TBI (60-64); we argued that the trans-<lb/>hemispheric cortical map transfer could be a pathological process <lb/>(30). Specifically, among the biomarkers in this study that we found <lb/>to have consistent correlation direction between animals and <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Actual vs. Predicted value results of the Principal Component Regression correlating the (A) fractional anisotropy (FA) in the external capsule (ec) <lb/>region-of-interest (ROI) at day 60 post-injury with the plasma immunological panel at day 60 post-injury in the rat controlled cortical impact (CCI) <lb/>model of traumatic brain injury (TBI), and the (B) FA in the corpus callosum (cc) ROI, (C) FA in the longitudinal fasciculus (lf) ROI, and (D) FA in the <lb/>corticospinal tract (cst) ROI with the plasma immunological panel in clinical traumatic brain injury (TBI) patients at a median of eight days post-injury. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<body>humans (IL-1b, IL-6, G-CSF, CCL3, CCL5, and TNF-a) or differing <lb/>correlation direction (IL-4, IL-7, IL-13, and CCL2), CCL3 and <lb/>CCL5 were both significantly increased in TBI animals at day 7 <lb/>post-injury and associated with a lesser extent of cortical map <lb/>transfer (and potentially lesser pathology), IL-1b and IL-7 were <lb/>significantly increased but no apparent effect on the cortical map <lb/>transfer, TNF-a and CCL2 were not significantly different between <lb/>TBI and sham animals, and IL-6, G-CSF, IL-4, and IL-13 were <lb/>extremely elevated in a few animals and associated with a greater <lb/>extent of cortical map transfer (and potentially pathology) (30). <lb/>CCL3 is an anti-inflammatory chemokine which had mRNA <lb/>upregulation in the peripheral blood in a rat model of lateral fluid <lb/>percussion injury (65). CCL5 protected hippocampal memory <lb/>function in a mouse drop weight model of mild TBI (66). <lb/>We have also found that in both rat model and human TBI <lb/>patients, several biomarkers that were not significantly different <lb/>TABLE 3 Results of principal component regression (PCR) correlating the fractional anisotropy (FA) in the corpus callosum (cc) region-of-interest <lb/>(ROI) with the plasma immunological panel in clinical traumatic brain injury (TBI) patients at a median of 8 days post injury. <lb/>Analysis of Variance <lb/>SS <lb/>DF <lb/>MS <lb/>F (DFn, DFd) <lb/>P value <lb/>Regression <lb/>1.26E-01 <lb/>3 <lb/>4.21E-02 <lb/>F (3, 11) = 6.70 <lb/>P=0.0078 <lb/>Residual <lb/>6.91E-02 <lb/>11 <lb/>6.28E-03 <lb/>Total <lb/>1.95E-01 <lb/>14 <lb/>Dependent variable: FA in the corpus callosum ROI of post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Predictor variable: plasma immunological panel panel post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Bolded values indicate P &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Parameter estimates <lb/>Variable <lb/>Estimate <lb/>95% CI (asymptotic) <lb/>|t| <lb/>P value <lb/>b0 <lb/>Intercept <lb/>3.02E-01 <lb/>1.14E-01 <lb/>to <lb/>4.91E-01 <lb/>3.53 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>b1 <lb/>IL-1b <lb/>2.37E-04 <lb/>-5.92E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.07E-03 <lb/>0.629 <lb/>0.5424 <lb/>b2 <lb/>IL-1ra <lb/>5.59E-06 <lb/>-1.23E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>1.24E-05 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>0.0988 <lb/>b3 <lb/>IL-4 <lb/>-3.37E-03 <lb/>-8.69E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>1.94E-03 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>0.1901 <lb/>b4 <lb/>IL-6 <lb/>2.54E-03 <lb/>1.14E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>3.94E-03 <lb/>3.99 <lb/>0.0021 <lb/>b5 <lb/>IL-7 <lb/>-9.53E-04 <lb/>-2.17E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>2.60E-04 <lb/>1.73 <lb/>0.1118 <lb/>b6 <lb/>IL-8 <lb/>1.12E-03 <lb/>3.60E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.89E-03 <lb/>3.24 <lb/>0.0079 <lb/>b7 <lb/>IL-9 <lb/>4.80E-05 <lb/>5.14E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>9.09E-05 <lb/>2.47 <lb/>0.0314 <lb/>b8 <lb/>IL-13 <lb/>-3.84E-03 <lb/>-6.24E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.44E-03 <lb/>3.52 <lb/>0.0048 <lb/>b9 <lb/>IL-17 <lb/>1.29E-04 <lb/>-2.42E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>2.68E-03 <lb/>0.112 <lb/>0.9132 <lb/>b10 <lb/>Eotaxin <lb/>-3.57E-04 <lb/>-8.19E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.05E-04 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0.1169 <lb/>b11 <lb/>bFGF <lb/>4.16E-04 <lb/>-2.39E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.07E-03 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>0.1897 <lb/>b12 <lb/>G-CSF <lb/>2.27E-04 <lb/>7.68E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.77E-04 <lb/>3.33 <lb/>0.0068 <lb/>b13 <lb/>IFN-g <lb/>-2.15E-03 <lb/>-5.25E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>9.46E-04 <lb/>1.53 <lb/>0.1546 <lb/>b14 <lb/>CXCL10 <lb/>7.62E-05 <lb/>2.53E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>1.27E-04 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>0.0071 <lb/>b15 <lb/>CCL2 <lb/>-5.02E-04 <lb/>-8.25E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.80E-04 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>0.0056 <lb/>b16 <lb/>CCL3 <lb/>5.76E-03 <lb/>2.34E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>9.19E-03 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>0.0035 <lb/>b17 <lb/>PDGF-BB <lb/>1.44E-05 <lb/>6.27E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>2.26E-05 <lb/>3.89 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>b18 <lb/>CCL4 <lb/>2.01E-04 <lb/>5.71E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.44E-04 <lb/>3.08 <lb/>0.0106 <lb/>b19 <lb/>CCL5 <lb/>2.90E-06 <lb/>7.53E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>5.05E-06 <lb/>2.97 <lb/>0.0127 <lb/>b20 <lb/>TNF-a <lb/>4.59E-04 <lb/>-1.20E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.04E-03 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>0.1087 <lb/>Adjusted R squared = 0.550. <lb/>Normality <lb/>of Residuals <lb/>Statistics <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>Passed normality <lb/>test (alpha=0.05)? <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk (W) <lb/>0.9696 <lb/>0.8528 Yes <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<body>between TBI and controls may also have significant correlation with <lb/>white matter FA. As we suggested in our earlier publication (49), the <lb/>variation in these biomarkers among TBI subjects may have simply <lb/>reflected the inherent individual variation in the population and it <lb/>was this individual variation that also contributed to the variation in <lb/>TBI neurological outcomes as reflected by neuroimaging. <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>We found a general agreement in animal and human TBI <lb/>findings that changes (usually increases) in plasma levels for the <lb/>immunological biomarkers panel were associated with preservation <lb/>of white matter integrity, as measured by diffusion MRI. These <lb/>TABLE 4 Results of the principal component regression (PCR) correlating the fractional anisotropy (FA) in the longitudinal fasciculus (lf) region-of-<lb/>interest (ROI) with the plasma immunological panel in clinical traumatic brain injury (TBI) patients at a median of 8 days post injury. <lb/>Analysis of Variance <lb/>SS <lb/>DF <lb/>MS <lb/>F (DFn, DFd) <lb/>P value <lb/>Regression <lb/>4.93E-02 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.64E-02 <lb/>F (3, 11) = 2z8.4 <lb/>P&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Residual <lb/>6.36E-03 <lb/>11 <lb/>5.78E-04 <lb/>Total <lb/>5.57E-02 <lb/>14 <lb/>Dependent variable: FA in the longitudinal fasciculus ROI of post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Predictor variable: cytokine panel post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Bolded values indicate P &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Parameter estimates <lb/>Variable <lb/>Estimate <lb/>95% CI (asymptotic) <lb/>|t| <lb/>P value <lb/>b0 <lb/>Intercept <lb/>3.05E-01 <lb/>2.47E-01 <lb/>to <lb/>3.62E-01 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b1 <lb/>IL-1b <lb/>3.47E-04 <lb/>9.60E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>5.99E-04 <lb/>3.04 <lb/>0.0112 <lb/>b2 <lb/>IL-1ra <lb/>4.78E-06 <lb/>2.71E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>6.85E-06 <lb/>5.09 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>b3 <lb/>IL-4 <lb/>-1.65E-03 <lb/>-3.26E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-3.27E-05 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>0.0462 <lb/>b4 <lb/>IL-6 <lb/>1.52E-03 <lb/>1.10E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>1.95E-03 <lb/>7.88 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b5 <lb/>IL-7 <lb/>-6.45E-04 <lb/>-1.01E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-2.77E-04 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>0.0027 <lb/>b6 <lb/>IL-8 <lb/>8.15E-04 <lb/>5.83E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.05E-03 <lb/>7.75 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b7 <lb/>IL-9 <lb/>2.52E-05 <lb/>1.22E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>3.82E-05 <lb/>4.27 <lb/>0.0013 <lb/>b8 <lb/>IL-13 <lb/>-2.01E-03 <lb/>-2.74E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.28E-03 <lb/>6.07 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b9 <lb/>IL-17 <lb/>6.13E-04 <lb/>-1.61E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>1.39E-03 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>0.1089 <lb/>b10 <lb/>Eotaxin <lb/>-1.96E-04 <lb/>-3.36E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>-5.54E-05 <lb/>3.07 <lb/>0.0106 <lb/>b11 <lb/>bFGF <lb/>3.90E-04 <lb/>1.91E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>5.88E-04 <lb/>4.32 <lb/>0.0012 <lb/>b12 <lb/>G-CSF <lb/>1.60E-04 <lb/>1.14E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>2.06E-04 <lb/>7.73 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b13 <lb/>IFN-g <lb/>-6.02E-04 <lb/>-1.54E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>3.37E-04 <lb/>1.41 <lb/>0.1857 <lb/>b14 <lb/>CXCL10 <lb/>3.94E-05 <lb/>2.40E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>5.49E-05 <lb/>5.63 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>b15 <lb/>CCL2 <lb/>-2.71E-04 <lb/>-3.69E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.73E-04 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b16 <lb/>CCL3 <lb/>3.75E-03 <lb/>2.71E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>4.79E-03 <lb/>7.95 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b17 <lb/>PDGF-BB <lb/>8.62E-06 <lb/>6.14E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>1.11E-05 <lb/>7.65 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b18 <lb/>CCL4 <lb/>1.14E-04 <lb/>7.02E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>1.57E-04 <lb/>5.74 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>b19 <lb/>CCL5 <lb/>1.63E-06 <lb/>9.75E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>2.28E-06 <lb/>5.49 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>b20 <lb/>TNF-a <lb/>3.04E-04 <lb/>1.29E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>4.80E-04 <lb/>3.82 <lb/>0.0028 <lb/>Adjusted R squared = 0.854. <lb/>Normality <lb/>of Residuals <lb/>Statistics <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>Passed normality <lb/>test (alpha=0.05)? <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk (W) <lb/>0.9442 <lb/>0.4382 Yes <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<body>relationships were most apparent during the post-injury period <lb/>where the animals or patients were clinically stable and at low risk <lb/>of mortality and morbidity. We suppose that immunological <lb/>reactions that were seemingly beneficial for white matter integrity <lb/>in the present study might have been associated with negative <lb/>outcomes in earlier studies in patients at risk for especially <lb/>poor outcome. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be <lb/>made available by the authors, without undue reservation. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by institutional <lb/>Human Research Ethics Committee (approval number HREC/16/ <lb/>QRBW/604). The studies were conducted in accordance with the <lb/>local legislation and institutional requirements. The participants <lb/>provided their written informed consent to participate in this study. <lb/></div>

	<body>TABLE 5 Results of principal component regression (PCR) correlating the fractional anisotropy (FA) in the corticospinal tract (cst) region-of-interest <lb/>(ROI) with the plasma immunological panel in clinical traumatic brain injury (TBI) patients at a median of eight days post-injury. <lb/>Analysis of Variance <lb/>SS <lb/>DF <lb/>MS <lb/>F (DFn, DFd) <lb/>P value <lb/>Regression <lb/>3.86E-02 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.29E-02 <lb/>F (3, 11) = 10.6 <lb/>P=0.0014 <lb/>Residual <lb/>1.34E-02 <lb/>11 <lb/>1.22E-03 <lb/>Total <lb/>5.21E-02 <lb/>14 <lb/>Dependent variable: FA in the corticospinal tract ROI of post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Predictor variable: cytokine panel post-TBI in participants. <lb/>Bolded values indicate P &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Parameter estimates <lb/>Variable <lb/>Estimate <lb/>95% CI (asymptotic) <lb/>|t| <lb/>P value <lb/>b0 <lb/>Intercept <lb/>4.02E-01 <lb/>3.19E-01 <lb/>to <lb/>4.85E-01 <lb/>10.7 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>b1 <lb/>IL-1b <lb/>9.12E-05 <lb/>-2.74E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>4.56E-04 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.5935 <lb/>b2 <lb/>IL-1ra <lb/>3.46E-06 <lb/>4.54E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>6.47E-06 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>0.0278 <lb/>b3 <lb/>IL-4 <lb/>-2.93E-03 <lb/>-5.27E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-5.91E-04 <lb/>2.76 <lb/>0.0187 <lb/>b4 <lb/>IL-6 <lb/>1.52E-03 <lb/>9.02E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>2.14E-03 <lb/>5.42 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>b5 <lb/>IL-7 <lb/>-7.45E-04 <lb/>-1.28E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-2.11E-04 <lb/>3.07 <lb/>0.0107 <lb/>b6 <lb/>IL-8 <lb/>6.15E-04 <lb/>2.79E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>9.52E-04 <lb/>4.03 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>b7 <lb/>IL-9 <lb/>1.98E-05 <lb/>9.60E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>3.87E-05 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>0.0411 <lb/>b8 <lb/>IL-13 <lb/>-2.25E-03 <lb/>-3.31E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.19E-03 <lb/>4.68 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>b9 <lb/>IL-17 <lb/>-3.08E-04 <lb/>-1.43E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>8.16E-04 <lb/>0.603 <lb/>0.5586 <lb/>b10 <lb/>Eotaxin <lb/>-2.88E-04 <lb/>-4.91E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>-8.47E-05 <lb/>3.12 <lb/>0.0098 <lb/>b11 <lb/>bFGF <lb/>1.40E-04 <lb/>-1.48E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>4.28E-04 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>0.3084 <lb/>b12 <lb/>G-CSF <lb/>1.31E-04 <lb/>6.53E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>1.98E-04 <lb/>4.38 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>b13 <lb/>IFN-g <lb/>-1.33E-03 <lb/>-2.69E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>3.34E-05 <lb/>2.15 <lb/>0.0549 <lb/>b14 <lb/>CXCL10 <lb/>3.86E-05 <lb/>1.62E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>6.10E-05 <lb/>3.79 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>b15 <lb/>CCL2 <lb/>-3.10E-04 <lb/>-4.52E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>-1.68E-04 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>b16 <lb/>CCL3 <lb/>3.46E-03 <lb/>1.95E-03 <lb/>to <lb/>4.97E-03 <lb/>5.05 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>b17 <lb/>PDGF-BB <lb/>7.01E-06 <lb/>3.41E-06 <lb/>to <lb/>1.06E-05 <lb/>4.29 <lb/>0.0013 <lb/>b18 <lb/>CCL4 <lb/>8.91E-05 <lb/>2.58E-05 <lb/>to <lb/>1.52E-04 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>0.0101 <lb/>b19 <lb/>CCL5 <lb/>1.28E-06 <lb/>3.28E-07 <lb/>to <lb/>2.22E-06 <lb/>2.96 <lb/>0.0129 <lb/>b20 <lb/>TNF-a <lb/>1.31E-04 <lb/>-1.24E-04 <lb/>to <lb/>3.85E-04 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>0.2821 <lb/>Adjusted R squared = 0.672. <lb/>Normality <lb/>of Residuals <lb/>Statistics <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>Passed normality <lb/>test (alpha=0.05)? <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk (W) <lb/>0.9635 <lb/>0.7524 Yes <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">The animal study was approved by Animal Research Ethics <lb/>Committee (AEC) of the University of Queensland (approval <lb/>number: QBI/036/16/MAIC). The study was conducted in <lb/>accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>XVT: Data curation, Formal Analysis, Methodology, Resources, <lb/>Software, Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. AM: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, <lb/>Resources, Writing -review &amp; editing. PC: Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. FN: Conceptualization, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This research <lb/>was supported by Motor Accident Insurance Commission (MAIC), <lb/>The Queensland Government, Australia (grant number: 2014000857). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This study/project/research used NCRIS-enabled Australian <lb/>Proteome Analysis Facility (APAF) infrastructure, Macquarie <lb/>University, New South Wales, Australia. We acknowledge the <lb/>supports from the Queensland NMR Network and the National <lb/>Imaging Facility (a National Collaborative Research Infrastructure <lb/>Strategy capability) for the operation of 9.4T T MRI and the <lb/>computational resources at the Centre for Advanced Imaging, the <lb/>University of Queensland. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board <lb/>member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no <lb/>impact on the peer review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Nguyen R, Fiest KM, McChesney J, Kwon C-S, Jette N, Frolkis AD, et al. The <lb/>international incidence of traumatic brain injury: A systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. Can J Neurol Sci / J Can Des Sci Neurol (2016) 43:774-85. doi: 10.1017/ <lb/>cjn.2016.290 <lb/>2. Menon DK, Schwab K, Wright DW, Maas AI. Position statement: Definition of <lb/>traumatic brain injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil (2010) 91:1637-40. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.apmr.2010.05.017 <lb/>3. McNett M. A review of the predictive ability of glasgow coma scale scores in head-<lb/>injured patients. J Neurosci Nurs (2007) 39:68-75. <lb/>4. Hutchinson EB, Schwerin SC, Avram AV, Juliano SL, Pierpaoli C. Diffusion MRI <lb/>and the detection of alterations following traumatic brain injury. J Neurosci Res (2018) <lb/>96:612-25. doi: 10.1002/jnr.24065 <lb/>5. Loane DJ, Byrnes KR. Role of microglia in neurotrauma. Neurotherapeutics (2010) <lb/>7:366-77. doi: 10.1016/j.nurt.2010.07.002 <lb/>6. Harris NG, Verley DR, Gutman BA, Sutton RL. Bi-directional changes in <lb/>fractional anisotropy after experiment TBI: Disorganization and reorganization? <lb/>Neuroimage (2016) 133:129-43. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.03.012 <lb/>7. Ramlackhansingh AF, Brooks DJ, Greenwood RJ, Bose SK, Turkheimer FE, <lb/>Kinnunen KM, et al. Inflammation after trauma: Microglial activation and traumatic <lb/>brain injury. Ann Neurol (2011) 70:374-83. doi: 10.1002/ana.22455 <lb/>8. Needham EJ, Helmy A, Zanier ER, Jones JL, Coles AJ, Menon DK. The <lb/>immunological response to traumatic brain injury. J Neuroimmunol (2019) 332:112-<lb/>25. doi: 10.1016/j.jneuroim.2019.04.005 <lb/>9. Zheng RZ, Lee KY, Qi ZX, Wang Z, Xu ZY, Wu XH, et al. Neuroinflammation <lb/>following traumatic brain injury: Take it seriously or not. Front Immunol (2022) <lb/>13:855701. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2022.855701 <lb/>10. Zetterberg H, Blennow K. Fluid biomarkers for mild traumatic brain injury and <lb/>related conditions. Nat Rev Neurol (2016) 12:563-74. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2016.127 <lb/>11. Morganti-Kossmann MC, Rancan M, Stahel PF, Kossmann T. Inflammatory <lb/>response in acute traumatic brain injury: A double-edged sword. Curr Opin Crit Care <lb/>(2002) 8:101-5. doi: 10.1097/00075198-200204000-00002 <lb/>12. Thelin EP, Tajsic T, Zeiler FA, Menon DK, Hutchinson PJA, Carpenter KLH, <lb/>et al. Monitoring the neuroinflammatory response following acute brain injury. Front <lb/>Neurol (2017) 8:351. doi: 10.3389/fneur.2017.00351 <lb/>13. McDonald SJ, Sun M, Agoston DV, Shultz SR. The effect of concomitant <lb/>peripheral injury on traumatic brain injury pathobiology and outcome. J <lb/>Neuroinflamm (2016) 13:90. doi: 10.1186/s12974-016-0555-1 <lb/>14. Woodcock T, Morganti-Kossmann MC. The role of markers of inflammation in <lb/>traumatic brain injury. Front Neurol (2013) 4:18. doi: 10.3389/fneur.2013.00018 <lb/>15. Vos PE, Lamers KJB, Hendriks JCM, van Haaren M, Beems T, Zimmerman C, <lb/>et al. Glial and neuronal proteins in serum predict outcome after severe traumatic brain <lb/>injury. Neurology (2004) 62:1303-10. doi: 10.1212/01.WNL.0000120550.00643.DC <lb/>16. Chabok SY, Moghadam AD, Saneei Z, Amlashi FG, Leili EK, Amiri ZM. Neuron-<lb/>specific enolase and S100BB as outcome predictors in severe diffuse axonal injury. J Trauma <lb/>Acute Care Surg (2012) 72:1654-7. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318246887e <lb/>17. Mercier E, Boutin A, Lauzier F, Fergusson DA, Simard J-F, Zarychanski R, et al. <lb/>Predictive value of s-100 protein for prognosis in patients with moderate and severe <lb/>traumatic brain injury: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ (2013) 346:f1757-7. <lb/>doi: 10.1136/bmj.f1757 <lb/>18. Bruggeman GF, Haitsma IK, Dirven CMF, Volovici V. Traumatic axonal injury <lb/>(TAI): definitions, pathophysiology and imaging-a narrative review. Acta Neurochir <lb/>(Wien) (2021) 163:31-44. doi: 10.1007/s00701-020-04594-1 <lb/>19. Wallace EJ, Mathias JL, Ward L. Diffusion tensor imaging changes following <lb/>mild, moderate and severe adult traumatic brain injury: a meta-analysis. Brain Imag <lb/>Behav (2018) 12:1607-21. doi: 10.1007/s11682-018-9823-2 <lb/>20. Hulkower MB, Poliak DB, Rosenbaum SB, Zimmerman ME, Lipton ML. A <lb/>decade of DTI in traumatic brain injury: 10 years and 100 articles later. Am J <lb/>Neuroradiol (2013) 34:2064-74. doi: 10.3174/ajnr.A3395 <lb/>21. Mohamed AZ, Cumming P, Nasrallah FA. White matter alterations are <lb/>associated with cognitive dysfunction decades after moderate-to-Severe traumatic <lb/>brain injury and/or posttraumatic stress disorder. Biol Psychiatry Cognit Neurosci <lb/>Neuroimaging (2021) 6:1100-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bpsc.2021.04.014 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>22. Mac Donald CL, Dikranian K, Song SK, Bayly PV, Holtzman D, Brody D. Detection <lb/>of traumatic axonal injury with diffusion tensor imaging in a mouse model of traumatic brain <lb/>injury. Exp Neurol (2007) 205:116-31. doi: 10.1016/j.expneurol.2007.01.035 <lb/>23. Mohamed AZ, Corrigan F, Collins-Praino LE, Plummer SL, Soni N, Nasrallah <lb/>FA. Evaluating spatiotemporal microstructural alterations following diffuse traumatic <lb/>brain injury. NeuroImage Clin (2020) 25:102136. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2019.102136 <lb/>24. Mohamed AZ, Cumming P, Nasrallah FA. Traumatic brain injury augurs ill for <lb/>prolonged deficits in the brain&apos;s structural and functional integrity following controlled <lb/>cortical impact injury. Sci Rep (2021) 11:21559. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-00660-5 <lb/>25. Osier ND, Dixon CE. The controlled cortical impact model: Applications, <lb/>considerations for researchers, and future directions. Front Neurol (2016) 7:134. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fneur.2016.00134 <lb/>26. Johnson VE, Meaney DF, Cullen DK, Smith DH. Animal models of traumatic <lb/>brain injury. In: Handbook of clinical neurology (2015). p. 115-28. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-<lb/>444-52892-6.00008-8 <lb/>27. Soni N, Mohamed AZ, Kurniawan ND, Borges K, Nasrallah F. Diffusion <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging unveils the spatiotemporal microstructural gray matter <lb/>changes following injury in the rodent brain. J Neurotrauma (2019) 36:1306-17. <lb/>doi: 10.1089/neu.2018.5972 <lb/>28. Haacke EM, Duhaime AC, Gean AD, Riedy G, Wintermark M, Mukherjee P, <lb/>et al. Common data elements in radiologic imaging of traumatic brain injury. J Magn <lb/>Reson Imaging (2010) 32:516-43. doi: 10.1002/jmri.22259 <lb/>29. Kay T, Harrington DE, Adams R, Anderson T, Berrol S, Cicerone K, et al. <lb/>Definition of mild traumatic brain injury. J Head Trauma Rehabil (1993) 8:86-7. <lb/>doi: 10.1097/00001199-199309000-00010 <lb/>30. To XV, Mohamed AZ, Cumming P, Nasrallah FA. Subacute cytokine changes <lb/>after a traumatic brain injury predict chronic brain microstructural alterations on <lb/>advanced diffusion imaging in the male rat. Brain Behav Immun (2022) 102:137-50. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2022.02.017 <lb/>31. Rorden C, Brett M. Stereotaxic display of brain lesions. Behav Neurol (2000) <lb/>12:191-200. doi: 10.1155/2000/421719 <lb/>32. Bajic D, Craig MM, Mongerson CRL, Borsook D, Becerra L. Identifying rodent <lb/>resting-state brain networks with independent component analysis. Front Neurosci <lb/>(2017) 11:685. doi: 10.3389/fnins.2017.00685 <lb/>33. Barrière DA, Magalhães R, Novais A, Marques P, Selingue E, Geffroy F, et al. The <lb/>SIGMA rat brain templates and atlases for multimodal MRI data analysis and <lb/>visualization. Nat Commun (2019) 10:1-13. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-13575-7 <lb/>34. Brett M, Leff AP, Rorden C, Ashburner J. Spatial normalization of brain images <lb/>with focal lesions using cost function masking. Neuroimage (2001) 14:486-500. <lb/>doi: 10.1006/nimg.2001.0845 <lb/>35. Avants BB, Epstein CL, Grossman M, Gee JC. Symmetric diffeomorphic image <lb/>registration with cross-correlation: evaluating automated labeling of elderly and <lb/>neurodegenerative brain. Med Image Anal (2008) 12:26-41. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.media.2007.06.004 <lb/>36. Kim J, Avants B, Patel S, Whyte J, Coslett BH, Pluta J, et al. Structural <lb/>consequences of diffuse traumatic brain injury: a large deformation tensor-based <lb/>morphometry study. Neuroimage (2008) 39:1014-26. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.neuroimage.2007.10.005 <lb/>37. Ho S, Cody H, Gerig G. SNAP : A software package for user-guided geodesic <lb/>snake segmentation. In: 6th international conference on medical image computing and <lb/>computer assisted intervention. Montreal, Canada (2003). Available at: https://www.sci. <lb/>utah.edu/~gerig/publications/MICCAI03-Ho-snap.pdf. <lb/>38. Tustison NJ, Avants BB, Cook PA, Zheng Y, Egan A, PA Y, et al. N4ITK: <lb/>Improved N3 bias correction. IEEE Trans Med Imaging (2010) 29:1310-20. <lb/>doi: 10.1109/TMI.2010.2046908 <lb/>39. Landman B, Warfield S. MICCAI 2012 workshop on multi-atlas labeling. In: MICCAI <lb/>grand challenge and workshop on multi-atlas labeling. Nice: CreateSpace Independent <lb/>Publishing Platform (2012). Available at: http://www.neuromorphometrics.com/2012_ <lb/>MICCAI_Challenge_Data.html. <lb/>40. Shapiro SS, Wilk MB. An analysis of variance test for normality (Complete <lb/>samples). Biometrika (1965) 52:591. doi: 10.2307/2333709 <lb/>41. Yap BW, Sim CH. Comparisons of various types of normality tests. J Stat <lb/>Comput Simul (2011) 81:2141-55. doi: 10.1080/00949655.2010.520163 <lb/>42. Benjamini Y, Krieger AM, Yekutieli D. Adaptive linear step-up procedures that <lb/>control the false discovery rate. Biometrika (2006) 93:491-507. doi: 10.1093/biomet/ <lb/>93.3.491 <lb/>43. Hotelling H. THE RELATIONS OF THE NEWER MULTIVARIATE <lb/>STATISTICAL METHODS TO FACTOR ANALYSIS. Br J Stat Psychol (1957) <lb/>10:69-79. doi: 10.1111/j.2044-8317.1957.tb00179.x <lb/>44. Anderson MJ, Robinson J. Permutation tests for linear models. Aust N Z J Stat <lb/>(2001) 43:75-88. doi: 10.1111/1467-842X.00156 <lb/>45. Winkler AM, Ridgway GR, Webster MA, Smith SM, Nichols TE. Permutation <lb/>inference for the general linear model. Neuroimage (2014) 92:381-97. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.neuroimage.2014.01.060 <lb/>46. Smith SM, Nichols TE. Threshold-free cluster enhancement: Addressing <lb/>problems of smoothing, threshold dependence and localisation in cluster inference. <lb/>Neuroimage (2009) 44:83-98. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.03.061 <lb/>47. Kantarci K, Murray ME, Schwarz CG, Reid RI, Przybelski SA, Lesnick T, et al. <lb/>White-matter integrity on DTI and the pathologic staging of alzheimer&apos;s disease. <lb/>Neurobiol Aging (2017) 56:172-9. doi: 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2017.04.024 <lb/>48. Li Y, Yang Z, Liu B, Valdez C, Chavko M, Cancio LC. Low-level primary blast <lb/>induces neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration in rats. Mil Med (2019) 184:265-<lb/>72. doi: 10.1093/milmed/usy330 <lb/>49. To XV, Donnelly P, Maclachlan L, Mahady K, Apellaniz EM, Cumming P, et al. <lb/>Anti-inflammatory interleukin 1 receptor antagonist concentration in plasma <lb/>correlates with blood-brain barrier integrity in the primary lesion area in traumatic <lb/>brain injury patients. Brain Behav Immun -Heal (2023) 31:100653. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.bbih.2023.100653 <lb/>50. Allan SM, Tyrrell PJ, Rothwell NJ. Interleukin-1 and neuronal injury. Nat Rev <lb/>Immunol (2005) 5:629-40. doi: 10.1038/nri1664 <lb/>51. Arena WP, Malyak M, Guthridge CJ, Gabay C. Interleukin-1 receptor <lb/>antagonist: Role in biology. Annu Rev Immunol (1998) 16:27-55. doi: 10.1146/ <lb/>annurev.immunol.16.1.27 <lb/>52. Nwachuku EL, Puccio AM, Adeboye A, Chang YF, Kim J, Okonkwo DO. Time <lb/>course of cerebrospinal fluid inflammatory biomarkers and relationship to 6-month <lb/>neurologic outcome in adult severe traumatic brain injury. Clin Neurol Neurosurg <lb/>(2016) 149:1-5. doi: 10.1016/j.clineuro.2016.06.009 <lb/>53. Abboud A, Mi Q, Puccio A, Okonkwo D, Buliga M, Constantine G, et al. <lb/>Inflammation following traumatic brain injury in humans: Insights from data-driven <lb/>and mechanistic models into survival and death. Front Pharmacol (2016) 7:342. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fphar.2016.00342 <lb/>54. Maier B, Lefering R, Lehnert M, Laurer HL, Steudel WI, Neugebauer EA, et al. <lb/>Early versus late onset of multiple organ failure is associated with differing patterns of <lb/>plasma cytokine biomarker expression and outcome after severe trauma. Shock (2007) <lb/>28:668-74. doi: 10.1097/shk.0b013e318123e64e <lb/>55. Woiciechowsky C, Schöning B, Cobanov J, Lanksch WR, Volk HD, Döcke WD. <lb/>Early il-6 plasma concentrations correlate with severity of brain injury and pneumonia <lb/>in brain-injured patients. J Trauma (2002) 52:339-45. doi: 10.1097/00005373-<lb/>200202000-00021 <lb/>56. Aisiku IP, Yamal JM, Doshi P, Benoit JS, Gopinath S, Goodman JC, et al. Plasma <lb/>cytokines IL-6, IL-8, and IL-10 are associated with the development of acute respiratory <lb/>distress syndrome in patients with severe traumatic brain injury. Crit Care (2016) 20:1-<lb/>10. doi: 10.1186/s13054-016-1470-7 <lb/>57. Di Battista AP, Rhind SG, Hutchison MG, Hassan S, Shiu MY, Inaba K, et al. <lb/>Inflammatory cytokine and chemokine profiles are associated with patient outcome <lb/>and the hyperadrenergic state following acute brain injury. J Neuroinflamm (2016) <lb/>13:1-14. doi: 10.1186/s12974-016-0500-3 <lb/>58. Wu F, Zhang R, Meng W, Liu L, Tang Y, Lu L, et al. Platelet derived growth <lb/>factor promotes the recovery of traumatic brain injury by inhibiting endoplasmic <lb/>reticulum stress and autophagy-mediated pyroptosis. Front Pharmacol (2022) <lb/>13:862324. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.862324 <lb/>59. Bhowmick S, D&apos;Mello V, Caruso D, Wallerstein A, Abdul-Muneer PM. <lb/>Impairment of pericyte-endothelium crosstalk leads to blood-brain barrier <lb/>dysfunction following traumatic brain injury. Exp Neurol (2019) 317:260-70. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.expneurol.2019.03.014 <lb/>60. Holschneider DP, Guo Y, Wang Z, Roch M, Scremin OU. Remote brain network <lb/>changes after unilateral cortical impact injury and their modulation by <lb/>acetylcholinesterase inhibition. J Neurotrauma (2013) 30:907-19. doi: 10.1089/ <lb/>neu.2012.2657 <lb/>61. Harris NG, Chen SF, Pickard JD. Cortical reorganization after experimental <lb/>traumatic brain injury: A functional autoradiography study. J Neurotrauma (2013) <lb/>30:1137-46. doi: 10.1089/neu.2012.2785 <lb/>62. Le Prieult F, Thal SC, Engelhard K, Imbrosci B, Mittmann T. Acute cortical <lb/>transhemispheric diaschisis after unilateral traumatic brain injury. J Neurotrauma <lb/>(2017) 34:1097-110. doi: 10.1089/neu.2016.4575 <lb/>63. Verley DR, Torolira D, Pulido B, Gutman B, Bragin A, Mayer A, et al. Remote <lb/>changes in cortical excitability after experimental traumatic brain injury and functional <lb/>reorganization. J Neurotrauma (2018) 35:2448-61. doi: 10.1089/neu.2017.5536 <lb/>64. Verley DR, Torolira D, Hessell BA, Sutton RL, Harris NG. Cortical <lb/>neuromodulation of remote regions after experimental traumatic brain injury <lb/>normalizes forelimb function but is temporally dependent. J Neurotrauma (2019) <lb/>36:789-801. doi: 10.1089/neu.2018.5769 <lb/>65. Chio CC, Lin HJ, Tian YF, Chen YC, Lin MT, Lin CH, et al. Exercise attenuates <lb/>neurological deficits by stimulating a critical HSP70/NF-kB/IL-6/synapsin i axis in <lb/>traumatic brain injury rats. J Neuroinflamm (2017) 14:1-18. doi: 10.1186/s12974-017-<lb/>0867-9 <lb/>66. Ho MH, Yen CH, Hsieh TH, Kao TJ, Chiu JY, Chiang YH, et al. CCL5 via GPX1 <lb/>activation protects hippocampal memory function after mild traumatic brain injury. <lb/>Redox Biol (2021) 46:102067. doi: 10.1016/j.redox.2021.102067 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">To et al. <lb/>10.3389/fimmu.2023.1293471 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>15 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>