<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T12:09:50.966Z">11/20/2025 12:09:50 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.3389_fmicb.2024.1488639</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T12:09:27.601634Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T12:09:27.601634Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>EDITED BY <lb/>Bo Kim, <lb/>VA HSR&amp;D Center for Healthcare Organization <lb/>and Implementation Research, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Madhumita Dobe, <lb/>All India Institute of Hygiene and Public Health, <lb/>India <lb/>Carmen Samuel-Hodge, <lb/>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, <lb/>United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Thomas Grice-Jackson <lb/>t.grice-jackson@bsms.ac.uk <lb/>RECEIVED 27 January 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 20 March 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 07 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Grice-Jackson T, Rogers I, Ford E, Dickinson R, <lb/>Frere-Smith K, Goddard K, Silver L, Topham C, <lb/>Nahar P, Musinguzi G, Bastiaens H and <lb/>Van Marwijk H (2024) A community health <lb/>worker led approach to cardiovascular disease <lb/>prevention in the UK-SPICES-Sussex (scaling-<lb/>up packages of interventions for <lb/>cardiovascular disease prevention in selected <lb/>sites in Europe and Sub-saharan Africa): an <lb/>implementation research project. <lb/>Front. Health Serv. 4:1152410. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Grice-Jackson, Rogers, Ford, <lb/>Dickinson, Frere-Smith, Goddard, Silver, <lb/>Topham, Nahar, Musinguzi, Bastiaens and <lb/>Van Marwijk. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>A community health worker <lb/>led approach to cardiovascular <lb/>disease prevention in the <lb/>UK-SPICES-Sussex (scaling-up <lb/>packages of interventions for <lb/>cardiovascular disease prevention <lb/>in selected sites in Europe and <lb/>Sub-saharan Africa): an <lb/>implementation research project <lb/>Thomas Grice-Jackson 1 * , Imogen Rogers 1 , Elizabeth Ford 1 , <lb/>Robert Dickinson 1 , Kat Frere-Smith 1 , Katie Goddard 1 , Linda Silver 1 , <lb/>Catherine Topham 1 , Papreen Nahar 2 , Geofrey Musinguzi 3 , <lb/>Hilde Bastiaens 4 and Harm Van Marwijk 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Primary Care and Public Health, Brighton and Sussex Medical School, Brighton, United <lb/>Kingdom, 2 Department of Global Health Infection, Brighton and Sussex Medical School, University of <lb/>Sussex, Brighton, United Kingdom, 3 Department of Disease Control and Environmental Health, <lb/>Makerere University, Kampala, Central Region, Uganda, 4 Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, <lb/>University of Antwerp, Antwerp, Belgium <lb/>Background: This paper describes a UK-based study, SPICES-Sussex, which <lb/>aimed to co-produce and implement a community-based cardiovascular <lb/>disease (CVD) risk assessment and reduction intervention to support under-<lb/>served populations at moderate risk of CVD. The objectives were to enhance <lb/>stakeholder engagement; to implement the intervention in four research sites <lb/>and to evaluate the use of Voluntary and Community and Social Enterprises <lb/>(VCSE) and Community Health Worker (CHW) partnerships in health interventions. <lb/>Methods: A type three hybrid implementation study design was used with mixed <lb/>methods data. This paper represents the process evaluation of the implementation <lb/>of the SPICES-Sussex Project. The evaluation was conducted using the RE-AIM <lb/>framework. <lb/>Results: Reach: 381 individuals took part in the risk profiling questionnaire and <lb/>forty-one women, and five men participated in the coaching intervention. <lb/>Effectiveness: quantitative results from intervention participants showed <lb/>significant improvements in CVD behavioural risk factors across several measures. <lb/>Qualitative data indicated high acceptability, with the holistic, personalised, and <lb/>person-centred approach being valued by participants. Adoption: 50% of VCSEs <lb/>approached took part in the SPICES programme, The CHWs felt empowered to <lb/>deliver high-quality and mutually beneficial coaching within a strong project <lb/>infrastructure that made use of VCSE partnerships. Implementation: Co-design <lb/>meetings resulted in local adaptations being made to the intervention. 29 (63%) <lb/>of participants completed the intervention. Practical issues concerned how to <lb/>embed CHWs in a health service context, how to keep engaging participants, <lb/>and tensions between research integrity and the needs and expectations of <lb/>those in the voluntary sector. Maintenance: Several VCSEs expressed an interest <lb/>in continuing the intervention after the end of the SPICES programme. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 07 May 2024 <lb/>| DOI 10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/>Frontiers in Health Services <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>Conclusion: Community-engagement approaches have the potential to have <lb/>positively impact the health and wellbeing of certain groups. Furthermore, <lb/>VCSEs and CHWs represent a significant untapped resource in the UK. However, <lb/>more work needs to be done to understand how links between the sectors can <lb/>be bridged to deliver evidence-based effective alternative preventative <lb/>healthcare. Reaching vulnerable populations remains a challenge despite <lb/>partnerships with VCSEs which are embedded in the community. By showing <lb/>what went well and what did not, this project can guide future work in <lb/>community engagement for health. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>community based participatory research, implementation research, RE-AIM (reach, <lb/>effectiveness, adoption, implementation and maintenance), cardiovascular disease, <lb/>community health workers (CHW) <lb/></front>

		<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is among the most prevalent, <lb/>costly to treat, and deadly medical issues in the world (1). As part <lb/>of the continual effort to combat CVD, greater emphasis is being <lb/>placed on prevention. This often takes the form of behavioural or <lb/>lifestyle change, focusing on the reduction of risk factors (e.g., <lb/>hypertension, poor diet, obesity). Reducing these risk factors using <lb/>evidence-based interventions not only works to lower rates of <lb/>CVD, but also impacts rates of a variety of other medical issues, <lb/>including susceptibility to severe COVID-19 infection (2), many <lb/>common Noncommunicable Diseases (NCDs) including Type 2 <lb/>diabetes and a wide range of cancers (3). Furthermore these <lb/>preventative interventions are less expensive than reactionary care <lb/>and can lower the treatment burden on strained medical systems (4). <lb/>Community-Based Participatory Research (CBPR) and <lb/>Community Engagement (CE) have grown increasingly popular as <lb/>potential methods to engender sustainable, long-term change in <lb/>communities-particularly those communities under-served by <lb/>existing medical systems and/or those at heightened risk of CVD <lb/>(5). One&apos;s behaviour is influenced by their environment and the <lb/>community they live in, meaning that tapping into a community&apos;s <lb/>resources can be effective in changing lifestyle behaviour as well as <lb/>having impacts on the wider community (6, 7). The use of <lb/>community-based practices fits within the growing South-North <lb/>collaboration that this project joins as part of an international <lb/>collaboration known as &quot;Scaling-up Packages of Interventions for <lb/>Cardiovascular disease prevention in selected sites in Europe <lb/>and Sub-Saharan Africa: An implementation research project&quot; <lb/>(SPICES). In the Low-and Middle-Income countries (LMIC) <lb/>there is evidence for the successful implementation of evidence-<lb/>based community-based interventions in increasing knowledge of, <lb/>and changing behaviour related to, CVD (8) however their use in <lb/>the Global North is less well tested or understood (9). <lb/>In the UK, the flagship intervention to address preventative <lb/>health issues is the National Health Service&apos;s (NHS) Health Check <lb/>initiative, which is free to individuals ages 40-76 and which <lb/>assesses risk for long term health conditions including CVD (10). <lb/>Following initial assessment by a health professional, patients are <lb/>advised on a course of action which often includes some degree of <lb/>preventative prescribing to address behavioural risk factors (11). <lb/>Just under half of eligible individuals accepts a first health-checks <lb/>appointment (44.2%)-it is associated with increased detection of <lb/>CVD risk, but uptake is skewed by several demographic factors <lb/>(principally, age, gender, and socio-demographics), and it has <lb/>struggled to create change in underserved groups (12, 13). <lb/>Marginalised coastal communities in Sussex face overall below-<lb/>average healthy-life expectancy (14). This, alongside heightening <lb/>inequality and the impact of COVID-19, has left some <lb/>communities in Sussex significantly deprived in terms of access <lb/>and engagement with health services (15). People in these <lb/>communities experience transgenerational poverty, precarity, and <lb/>lifestyle behaviours ingrained into the communities that lead many <lb/>to be at higher risk for CVD. CBPR and CE models have the <lb/>potential to lead to improved health and health behaviours among <lb/>disadvantaged populations if designed properly and implemented <lb/>through effective community consultation and participation (16). <lb/>CBPR and CE offer the chance to bring lessons from effective <lb/>programmes in the Global South and apply them to programmes <lb/>in the Global North. Community-based strategies to promote <lb/>evidence-based preventative health interventions using Community <lb/>Health Workers (CHWs) are often more established in the Global <lb/>South where more tightly knit communities and established <lb/>community health programmes fulfil a range of public health <lb/>needs (17, 18). CHWs interventions are a form of &quot;task-sharing&quot; <lb/>intervention in which responsibility and power is shared between <lb/>professional health workers and communities which have been <lb/>proposed to effectively manage non-communicable disease risk <lb/>(19). Lay Community Health Workers are individuals who are <lb/>trained to perform of health-related functions but lack a formal <lb/>professional health education. They can provide links between local <lb/>communities and health care institutions thereby building and on <lb/>and developing the social capital that already exists in communities <lb/>(20). Although there is plenty of evidence communicating the <lb/>importance and usefulness of these methods (the &quot;what&quot;), there <lb/>remains a lack of attention given to how to do it. This article joins <lb/>the work and voices attempting to begin filling that lacuna. <lb/>Within the literature on CBPR and CE, a handful of common <lb/>themes emerge. The first is a push for human-centred research <lb/>design (21, 22). Yardley et al. (23) focused on this idea in their <lb/>&quot;person-based&quot; approach to digital health interventions, where they <lb/>recommended a &quot;focus on understanding and accommodating the <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>02 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>perspectives of the people who will use the intervention&quot; (24). Hopkins <lb/>and Rippon&apos;s (25) &quot;asset-based&quot; approach to CE interventions <lb/>recommends recognising and adapting to the need, wants, and <lb/>strengths already present in the community. Particularly the <lb/>strengths, or &quot;assets&quot; already present in the community provide an <lb/>opportunity for projects to use those assets. Such an implementation <lb/>approach requires flexibility and adaptability, as well as deep <lb/>involvement with the community. The second theme builds on the <lb/>first, with the idea that not only should project design be person-<lb/>centred, but those participants and other stakeholders in the <lb/>community should be involved at every level of project planning <lb/>through co-design. Yardley et al. (23) included this as a key element <lb/>of their paper, writing that people from the target population should <lb/>be involved in project development as well as at every stage of the <lb/>intervention. Similarly, Berrera et al. (26) emphasise the need to <lb/>adapt all projects to the cultural context of the community. This <lb/>insight speaks to the third theme, continuous evaluation (27). As the <lb/>needs of the community will be ever-shifting, so must the project <lb/>adapt to those needs continually. Instead of designated periods of <lb/>evaluation, a shift to continual processes of qualitative evaluation is <lb/>called for to identify and adjust to the needs of the community. <lb/>These processes require elevated levels of trust and participation <lb/>from the community, which has its own challenges. Trust especially <lb/>takes significant time and resources to develop and is an under-<lb/>studied area of community engagement (28). <lb/>The SPICES-Sussex project was carried out from January 2019 and <lb/>aimed to answer the following overarching research question: How can <lb/>Community Health Workers (CHW) CVD prevention interventions, <lb/>that have been used in the Global South, be developed, and <lb/>implemented in a Global North setting and what barriers and <lb/>enablers exist to their implementation? The project began with a <lb/>situational analysis which included an exploration of the views and <lb/>experiences of the local community with regards to CVD health and <lb/>Community Health Workers and early stakeholder mapping of the <lb/>research sites which was carried out between 2019 and 2020 (29, 30). <lb/>The primary aim of the current paper is to provide a <lb/>comprehensive examination of the project&apos;s implementation <lb/>including complementary mixed methods analyses according to the <lb/>Reach Effectiveness-Adoption Implementation and Maintenance <lb/>(RE-AIM) framework (31). The secondary aims of the project are to <lb/>inform future CE projects what worked (and did not work) for our <lb/>project and to tie insights from our project to broader discussions in <lb/>the discipline. The project is based on a protocol published in 2020 <lb/>prior to the onset of COVID and was conducted through the period <lb/>of the COVID-19 pandemic (29). Subsequently, several aspects of <lb/>the original protocol were adapted to make implementation feasible <lb/>within the constraints of this period (see Supplementary Appendix 2). <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Study design <lb/>The project uses a type 3 hybrid implementation design (29) <lb/>meaning that the primary aim of the research was to determine <lb/>utility of an implementation intervention/strategy whilst the <lb/>secondary aim was to assess clinical outcomes associated with the <lb/>implementation trial. This means that we focused on understanding <lb/>what barriers and enablers existed for the project&apos;s implementation <lb/>and the context within which it operated. Effectiveness of the <lb/>intervention remained important, however we were primarily <lb/>interested in how and why it did (or did not) work. The project <lb/>was carried out at four geographic research sites within Sussex <lb/>(see Section 2.3) and implementation was conducted on an iterative <lb/>basis from research site to research site broadly following the <lb/>Medical Research Council&apos;s (MRC) framework for the development <lb/>and implementation of complex interventions (32). The research <lb/>team developed and then began delivering the intervention at each <lb/>site before moving onto the next. At each site the following stages <lb/>were carried out: (1) Development: this included stakeholder <lb/>mapping, formation of implementation partners, and codesign/local <lb/>adaptation of the intervention [covered in the study&apos;s pre-<lb/>implementation paper (30)]; (2) Implementation: this included the <lb/>delivery of the CHW intervention at the research sites and collection <lb/>of mixed method data pertaining to effectiveness and stakeholder <lb/>experiences, and (3) Evaluation: this included the analysis of the <lb/>mixed method data in line with the MRC guidance on analysis <lb/>complex interventions. <lb/>2.2 Research site and voluntary and <lb/>community sector enterprise partner <lb/>selection <lb/>Four study sites were selected across East Sussex by identifying <lb/>Middle Layer Super Output Area (MSOA) postcodes with high <lb/>levels of deprivation according to the Indices of Multiple <lb/>Deprivation (IMD) (33). Selection of the research sites was based <lb/>on the pre-implementation community mapping phase of the <lb/>project (30). Following on from CBPR practices, VCSEs and <lb/>Volunteer Coordinators (VCs) were recruited to co-design and <lb/>deliver the implementation strategy at each of the research sites. <lb/>VCSEs organisations were recruited as partners at each research <lb/>site. The intervention was primarily run through these organisations <lb/>and a paid staff member was recruited at each organisation. Their <lb/>responsibilities included, CHW management, and participant <lb/>recruitment. They also had a role in local adaptation activities. <lb/>VCSE organisations were eligible to take part in the organisations <lb/>if they were based in the research site, if they had interests and <lb/>existing activities that aligned with the project&apos;s goals (CVD risk <lb/>reduction and community development), and if they had existing <lb/>experience of volunteer recruitment and management. <lb/>2.3 Community health worker recruitment <lb/>and training <lb/>The aim was for each site to recruit a pool of five to eight CHWs. <lb/>As part of this each site was asked for input into local CHW <lb/>recruitment flyers, which were shared on VCSE websites and social <lb/>media pages and shared on social media via existing CHWs at the <lb/>VCSEs. CHWs were recruited through intermediary organisation <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>03 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>recruitment via the VCSE partner organisation. The project was also <lb/>advertised at a Virtual Volunteer Fair. Local contacts and existing <lb/>volunteer pools at the VCSEs meant that the target number of <lb/>CHWs was rapidly recruited at each site. CHWs were eligible to <lb/>take part in the intervention if they were over 18 years of age, if <lb/>they lived within the research site (determined by postcode), and if <lb/>they had some kind of pre-existing relationship with the VCSE <lb/>partner organisation (i.e., as a volunteer). <lb/>Potential CHWs who expressed an interest in the project were <lb/>invited to attend an induction to the project, and then the local <lb/>adaptation co-design meeting. Those who decided they would like <lb/>to become a CHW then went on to receive five online, group <lb/>training sessions (each of which lasted for 2 h, 10 h in total): an <lb/>introductory session, a session covering project policies, heart <lb/>health and the structure of the intervention, and three sessions on <lb/>behaviour change techniques. These training sessions were <lb/>developed and delivered by an external organisation (National <lb/>Centre for Behaviour Change) specifically for the project after a <lb/>consultation and planning process with the research team. Before <lb/>the onset of the intervention at each site CHWs made various <lb/>recommendations in the local adaptation meetings on the design of <lb/>the training programme. These included providing information on <lb/>listening techniques, engaging, and managing resistance, providing <lb/>simple health information, using accessible language, using different <lb/>starting points depending on the CHW&apos;s background knowledge <lb/>and experience, training on conducting coaching virtually, and <lb/>providing a training handbook. A Volunteer coordinator (VC) was <lb/>recruited at each site. This VC was a trained and experience health <lb/>coach (KFS) and provided training support and guidance through <lb/>monthly group training support sessions in addition to the initial <lb/>10 h training block the received prior to the intervention onset. <lb/>These monthly training and support sessions were organised into <lb/>specific themes and agendas that were set with the CHW participants. <lb/>2.4 Local adaptation <lb/>Elements of the evidence-based intervention were tailored to the <lb/>individuals and their community in the stakeholder-mapping phase <lb/>using qualitative interviews, workshops, and focus groups with a <lb/>range of stakeholders across the study site (30). Further rounds of <lb/>local adaptation were carried out with VCs and CHWs at each of the <lb/>research sites to tailor to individuals and their community context <lb/>through iterative co-design workshops (34). CHWs and VCSE also <lb/>agreed on a &quot;volunteer charter&quot; during the co-design session. This <lb/>was a list of principles, behaviours, and practices upon which guided <lb/>interactions between research staff, CHWs, VCSE and participants. <lb/>The charter was designed to ensure that the practices of the project <lb/>aligned with the principles of the CHW and partner organisation. <lb/>2.5 Participant recruitment and screening <lb/>questionnaire <lb/>Participants (who received coaching) were eligible to take part <lb/>in the eligibility screening if they lived in, or adjacent to, the study <lb/>site&apos;s postcode and if they were aged eighteen or older. Participant <lb/>recruitment was also based on intermediary organisation <lb/>recruitment, community outreach, paid social media <lb/>advertisement (through Meta TM ), gatekeeper and snowball <lb/>sampling. Gatekeeper recruitment was conducted when <lb/>interacting with a relevant statutory or non-statutory service <lb/>provider (i.e., a fitness/weight loss group leader) and involved <lb/>asking them to recommend the intervention to their members or <lb/>to recommend participants who may be interested in taking part. <lb/>Snowball sampling involved asking participants who participated <lb/>in the study to sending email invitations to their social group. A <lb/>social media recruitment strategy was undertaken to recruit <lb/>people from the local area to the risk profiling survey to <lb/>supplement the community-based recruitment through the VCSE <lb/>partners. Social media was conducted on Facebook via paid <lb/>advertisement in four waves of recruitment which took place <lb/>over 1-2 weeks at each site. The advert targeted people who were <lb/>35+ and over and to people with 5 km of each research site. <lb/>Messages were changed regularly from a list of recruitment <lb/>messages drafted with CHWs during co-design sessions. <lb/>Additionally, CHWs and VCSE participants were asked to send <lb/>recruitment emails to any social or professional networks they <lb/>thought would be interested in taking part. We did not record <lb/>where participants were recruited. <lb/>Screening and risk profiling for the CVD coaching was carried <lb/>out using the validated non-laboratory based INTERHEART <lb/>questionnaire, presented online, for all participants that expressed <lb/>an interest in the study (35). This questionnaire assessed modifiable <lb/>and non-modifiable CVD risk factors and categorised participants <lb/>as either &quot;Low,&quot; &quot;Moderate.&quot; Or &quot;High&quot; risk. See the protocol paper <lb/>for further information on the INTERHEART risk profiling; for <lb/>more information on the screening questionnaire, see the study <lb/>protocol paper (29, 35). Questionnaire data were collected and <lb/>managed using Research Electronic Data Capture (REDCap) <lb/>electronic data capture tools hosted at the University of Antwerp <lb/>(36). Participants were considered to be eligible for the intervention <lb/>if they were aged eighteen or over, if they lived within the research <lb/>site (determined by postcode), and if they were categorised as <lb/>&quot;Moderate&quot; risk of CVD according to the INTERHEART <lb/>questionnaire. High risk participants were not included as their <lb/>needs were considered to be too high for a pilot study involving <lb/>CHWs. Eligible participants were then emailed by the research <lb/>team with an invitation to take part in the CVD coaching <lb/>intervention. After recruitment for the intervention was closed for <lb/>each site, an online questionnaire survey was sent to eligible <lb/>participants to gather information the reasons for not accepting the <lb/>invitation to the intervention. Open response questions were used <lb/>which the research team later categorised into codes. <lb/>2.6 The CVD prevention coaching <lb/>intervention <lb/>The coaching intervention was based on motivational <lb/>interviewing techniques which are promoted by the European <lb/>commission on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical practice <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>04 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>(37) and which include techniques such as Open questions, <lb/>Affirmation, Reflective listening and Summary reflections (OARS) <lb/>(38, 39). The use of these Behaviour Change Techniques (BCTs) <lb/>used during the intervention were based on five target behaviours <lb/>highlighted by the World Health Organisation including: reduce/ <lb/>cease smoking, increase moderate physical activity, reduce the fat, <lb/>salt, and sugar content of the diet, increase fibre, oily fish (or <lb/>alternatives), fruit, and vegetable content of the diet, reduce <lb/>sedentary hours. The intervention involved six, one-hour long <lb/>coaching sessions between participants and CHWs which were <lb/>delivered every two weeks. Participants were also considered to <lb/>have completed the intervention if they only completed three <lb/>sessions and then notified the team of their withdrawal from <lb/>the intervention. <lb/>The study team included two participant co-ordinators (PCs) <lb/>who managed the participant journey through the intervention, <lb/>sending welcome emails, questionnaires, and invitations to post-<lb/>intervention interviews, and co-ordination between participants <lb/>and CHWs to book coaching sessions. Reminders of appointments <lb/>were also sent to CHWs and participants one week and two days <lb/>before the session. Participants and CHWs were matched, based <lb/>on gender preference and availability, and supported throughout <lb/>the coaching intervention the PCs. CHWs were provided with <lb/>guidance, resources, and signposting information throughout the <lb/>intervention but were also given the flexibility to deliver the <lb/>coaching in a way that suited them and their participant(s). <lb/>Initially, counselling and goalsetting were based on their individual <lb/>item INTERHEART assessment scores. Participants and CHWs <lb/>were then encouraged to create an action plan with appropriate <lb/>goal setting for the behaviours they wanted to change (e.g., diet, <lb/>exercise habits). The goals were set in relation to when, where, <lb/>and how they would undertake the behaviour, e.g., when the <lb/>physical activity will be performed, where it will be performed, <lb/>how often it will be performed (i.e., in a group or using specific <lb/>equipment). CHWs helped participants to analyse any factors <lb/>which might influence their ability to achieve the goals and to <lb/>generate strategies which could help them overcome these barriers <lb/>using problem solving. Full details of the participant journey <lb/>through the intervention are given in Supplementary Appendix 2 <lb/>in the Supplementary Material. All coaching was conducted <lb/>virtually using Zoom TM to host and monitor coaching sessions <lb/>and Microsoft OneDrive to store, recruit, and communicate <lb/>written and visual resources with CHWs and participants. <lb/>Monitoring in Zoom calls was called out by the PCs who checked <lb/>whether both the participant began and ended the coaching <lb/>session. If either the participants or CHW did not join, the PC <lb/>could join the call to help the attendee. Feedback was obtained <lb/>from the participant about the coaching session through emails <lb/>after the session and by inviting participants to a follow-up <lb/>interview after the intervention (see qualitative evaluation). <lb/>2.7 Evaluation <lb/>The evaluation was underpinned by the Reach, Effectiveness, <lb/>Adoption, Implementation, and Maintenance (RE-AIM) <lb/>framework (31) which allows for an understanding of the <lb/>multifaceted and interactive effects of personal, social, and <lb/>environmental factors that determine behaviour; and for identifying <lb/>behavioural and organisational leverage points and intermediaries <lb/>for health promotion within organisations and communities. <lb/>RE-AIM has been used to evaluate programs and setting in <lb/>public health and community settings and is thought to be <lb/>particularly useful when evaluate interventions in &quot;real-world&quot; <lb/>settings (40, 41). It has also been used to evaluate public health <lb/>interventions which make use of community health workers in <lb/>community-based setting (42-44). Results are made up of <lb/>quantitative measures from the participant questionnaires, <lb/>qualitative interviews with the participants, the CHWs, VCSE <lb/>partners, and the research team. Primary quantitative outcome <lb/>measures included implementation measures such as uptake and <lb/>engagement and the pre/post changes to the self-report CVD <lb/>behavioural questions which included the following three <lb/>questionnaires: (1) the INTERHEART CVD risk questionnaire <lb/>collected during the screening process was used as the baseline <lb/>and collected again after completion of the intervention. (2) <lb/>Physical activity levels were measured using the International <lb/>Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) (45). The IPAQ is an <lb/>internationally validated instrument to capture information about <lb/>weekly physical activity habits, behaviours, and routines. (3) Diet <lb/>was assessed using a 20-item questionnaire based on a modified <lb/>version of the UK Diet and Diabetes Questionnaire (46), a brief <lb/>food frequency questionnaire designed to assess conformity to <lb/>healthy eating guidelines, and to assist in the setting of dietary <lb/>goals. It was used to estimate the number of portions eaten daily <lb/>or weekly of fruit and vegetables, oily fish (or alternative), and <lb/>foods high in fat, salt, and sugar, what proportion of the time <lb/>wholegrain cereal products were chosen, weekly units of alcohol <lb/>consumed and the frequency of binge drinking. Due to the small <lb/>sample sizes and non-parametric data used in this study, <lb/>Wilcoxon Sign test was used to evaluate for differences in <lb/>continuous variables whilst McNemar&apos;s test was used for binary <lb/>categorical data. The pre-intervention assessment of the primary <lb/>outcome measures was sent to participants before they <lb/>participated in the intervention (no participant could begin the <lb/>intervention without completing the baseline measures). Post <lb/>intervention primary outcome measures were collected after their <lb/>participant in the intervention was completed. <lb/>Focus groups and one-to-one interviews were conducted with <lb/>four groups of stakeholders: (1) VCSE partners; (2) CHWs; (3) <lb/>members of the research team, (4) participants in the <lb/>intervention. Individual interviews were conducted with VCs, <lb/>members of the research team, and participants, while data from <lb/>the CHWs was collected in focus groups. Discussion guides for <lb/>VCs, CHWs and members of the research team all included <lb/>questions on the respondents&apos; role within the project, the process <lb/>of community engagement, barriers, and facilitators the <lb/>implementation process, recommendations for the future and <lb/>sustainability. Discussion guides for participant interviews <lb/>included questions on how and why participants became <lb/>involved in the project, their experience of the health coaching, <lb/>and their views on the impact and usefulness of the project. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>05 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>Interviews and focus groups were conducted online using Zoom or <lb/>MS Teams. The analysis was conducted by TGJ, IR, and RD and <lb/>using qualitative framework analysis based on the components of <lb/>the RE-AIM framework. Following data collection interviews and <lb/>focus groups were transcribed by a professional transcription <lb/>service and TGJ, IR, and RD familiarised themselves with the full <lb/>set of data. They then undertook line-by-line coding of the data <lb/>in NVivo using descriptive primary codes which were then <lb/>interlinked with secondary codes. These secondary codes were <lb/>then organised under the five elements of the RE-AIM <lb/>framework (Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation, <lb/>Maintenance). The analysis was interpreted, findings were <lb/>synthesised with reference to the stakeholder group and theme <lb/>descriptions were produced with supplementary illustrative quotes. <lb/>The Reach of the intervention was assessed through <lb/>recruitment rates for the VCSE partners, CHWs and Intervention <lb/>participants and qualitative data collected from the VCSE <lb/>partners, and the research team was used to understand barriers <lb/>and facilitators to recruitment. Effectiveness was assessed during <lb/>the primary outcome measures and barriers and facilitators to <lb/>effectiveness were assessed through qualitative interviews with the <lb/>participants and CHWs. Adoption was at the setting level was <lb/>determined through assessment of the retention of VCSE <lb/>partners and qualitatively through interviews with VCSE partners <lb/>and the research team. At the individual level, Adoption was <lb/>assessed through CHW retention rates and qualitatively assessed <lb/>through interviews with the research team and the CHWs. <lb/>Implementation was assessed qualitatively through interviews <lb/>with the intervention participants focusing on intervention <lb/>fidelity. Maintenance was assessed at the setting level qualitatively <lb/>through interviews with VCSE partners and the research team <lb/>and through a report of the status of the intervention after 6 <lb/>months. No individual level maintenance data is reported. A <lb/>description of the data sources which contributed to each <lb/>component of the RE-AIM framework is listed in Table 1. <lb/>2.8 Ethics <lb/>Ethical approval for this research was obtained from Brighton and <lb/>Sussex Medical School&apos;s Research Governance and Ethics Committee <lb/>(R-GEC) (application reference: ER/DG241/17BSMS9E3G/1). This <lb/>ethics review covered the methods described herein, key research <lb/>materials, and recruitment and consent protocols for both <lb/>intervention participants and staff/CHW interviews. Due to the <lb/>changes imposed on the project by COVID-19 (see Supplementary <lb/>TABLE 1 Description of data source used to evaluate the SPICES-Sussex intervention for each of the RE-AIM components. <lb/>Dimension <lb/>Data Source <lb/>Description of the data source <lb/>REACH-The number of VCSE <lb/>partners, CHWs and intervention <lb/>participants and the facilitators and <lb/>barriers to reach and recruitment to the <lb/>intervention <lb/>Recruitment of VCSE partners <lb/>Recruitment and engagement of VCSE partner organisations within each research <lb/>site. <lb/>Community health worker Recruitment <lb/>This covered the number of CHWs recruitment and trained by the project and the <lb/>number who went on to deliver the intervention. <lb/>Participant recruitment <lb/>This included uptake of the intervention by eligible participants who completed the <lb/>screening questionnaire. Only individuals classified as being at &quot;Moderate risk&quot; of <lb/>CVD were eligible for the intervention. <lb/>Reasons for non-participation <lb/>An online questionnaire of eligible participants who did not agreed to take part in the <lb/>intervention. This questionnaire aimed to understand why eligible participants did <lb/>not take-up the intervention. <lb/>Facilitators and barriers to Recruitment <lb/>One-to-one interviews with VCSE partners and intervention participants. The topic <lb/>guide asked questions about the views and experience of participant recruitment and <lb/>the screening questionnaire. (Table 3) <lb/>EFFECTIVENESS-The impact of an <lb/>intervention on primary outcome <lb/>measures and facilitators and barriers to <lb/>the intervention for participants. <lb/>Primary outcome measures <lb/>Quantitative baseline datae and post intervention data from the INTERHEART, <lb/>IPAQ, and UKDDQ. (Figure 1, Supplementary Appendix 1) <lb/>Facilitators and barriers of intervention <lb/>effectiveness <lb/>Qualitative data comes from the interview with intervention participants. It covered <lb/>their views and experiences of which intervention elements acted as barriers and <lb/>facilitators to their experiences of the intervention (Table 4). <lb/>ADOPTION-The number, proportion, <lb/>and representativeness of settings and <lb/>CHWs. Facilitators and barriers to <lb/>VCSE partnership (setting level) and <lb/>CHW experience of the intervention <lb/>(individual level). <lb/>Retention of VCSE partnerships (setting <lb/>level) <lb/>Quantitative data showing the number of VCSE partner sites retained through the <lb/>intervention and reasons for withdrawal. <lb/>Facilitators of VCSE partnerships (setting <lb/>level) <lb/>Qualitative data discussing the factors that impacted VCSE retention with the <lb/>intervention (Table 5) <lb/>Retention of CHWs (individual level) <lb/>Quantitative data showing the number of CHWs retained through the intervention. <lb/>CHW training needs feedback (individual <lb/>level) <lb/>Questionnaire data with CHW feedback on the training provided by in advance of the <lb/>intervention. <lb/>CHW facilitators and barriers to adoption <lb/>of the intervention (individual level) <lb/>Qualitative data discussing the facilitators and barriers to the CHW experience of the <lb/>intervention. (Table 6) <lb/>IMPLEMENTATION-Fidelity and <lb/>consistency to the various elements of <lb/>the intervention and facilitators and <lb/>barriers to fidelity and consistency. <lb/>Participant retention and fidelity <lb/>Quantitative data showing retention and fidelity for intervention participants. <lb/>Participant facilitators and barriers to <lb/>implementation <lb/>Qualitative data discussing the facilitators and barriers to the participant experience of <lb/>the intervention. (Table 7) <lb/>MAINTENANCE-The extent to which <lb/>the intervention become part of the <lb/>VCSE partner&apos;s practices and facilitators <lb/>and barriers to sustainability. <lb/>Status of the intervention <lb/>An update on the status of the intervention 6 months after study closure. <lb/>Facilitators and barriers of intervention <lb/>effectiveness <lb/>Qualitative data comes from the interview with VCSE partners and members of the <lb/>research team. It covered their views and experiences of which intervention elements <lb/>acted as barriers and facilitators to maintenance of the intervention (Table 8). <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>06 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>Appendix 2) and because of minor adaptations from research site to <lb/>research sites; several minor amendments were made (final <lb/>application reference: ER/BSMS9E3G/6). <lb/>Informed consent was obtained in three ways from study <lb/>participants depending on the nature of their participation. (1) <lb/>Online screening questionnaire: these participants were presented <lb/>with an approved information sheet on the first page of the <lb/>online screening questionnaire, they were then provided with an <lb/>Informed Consent Form (ICF) which they had to sign with a <lb/>digital signature. (2) Intervention participants: just prior to <lb/>participation and data collection participants met with a research <lb/>staff member to review the information sheet and to sign the <lb/>ICF if they agreed to participate, consent was sought again for <lb/>those intervention participants who took part in a post-<lb/>intervention interview. (3) CHW and research staff members: <lb/>participants were sent the information sheet and consent form <lb/>several days before their interview and were asked to sign and <lb/>return the ICF prior to their interview appointment. <lb/>3 Findings <lb/>3.1 Participant characteristics <lb/>Risk profiling data was collected from 381 participants (Females: <lb/>310, Males: 71; mean (SD) age = 58 (12.39) years. Forty-Six <lb/>participants began the intervention (39 Females, 7 Males; age = 58 <lb/>(11.94) years. Sixteen participants took part in one-to-one <lb/>interviews at the end of the intervention (thirteen females and two <lb/>males, aged 32-67 years). Seven members of the research team (6 <lb/>females, 1 male), and four VCSE partners (3 females and 1 male) <lb/>took part in the research team interviews. Four focus groups with <lb/>a total of thirteen participants (10 females and 3 males) were <lb/>conducted with CHWs from each of the research sites. Thirteen <lb/>participants (no gender data collected) took part in the post-<lb/>intervention questionnaire for non-participants. <lb/>3.2 Analytical framework <lb/>The remainder of these findings are organised into RE-AIM <lb/>dimensions with various quantitative and qualitative methods <lb/>used to evidence each dimension, see Table 1 for a description of <lb/>each of the data sources. Table 2 summarises concordance and <lb/>discordance with expectations of the intervention [as described in <lb/>the study protocol (29)] in line with the RE-AIM framework. <lb/>Supplementary Appendix 3 summarises changes to the study <lb/>design from the published study protocol. Throughout this <lb/>section participant codes are used to attribute quotations and <lb/>references to specific terminology to a respondent. The codes <lb/>identify the respondent as either a member of the Research team <lb/>(RT), VCSE partners (VCSE), Community Health Worker <lb/>(CHW) or Participants (PP). For VCSEs, CHWs and PPs <lb/>references to their sites are also made (EB, HA, NH, HG). All <lb/>codes refer to gender and (F/M), and their number within each <lb/>respondent category. <lb/>4 Reach <lb/>4.1 Recruitment of voluntary and <lb/>community sector enterprise partners <lb/>A community-mapping exercise was carried out during the <lb/>pre-implementation phase of the project (30) in which three <lb/>partner organisations were identified across three research sites in <lb/>East Sussex (Hastings, East Brighton, and Newhaven). All these <lb/>organisations were volunteer based community organisations <lb/>with a focus on local community development and improving <lb/>health, with the Hastings organisations being focused on health <lb/>and wellbeing. During the intervention set up phase, the East <lb/>Brighton organisations dropped out of the study due to the <lb/>impact of Covid-19 whilst the Hastings, and Newhaven <lb/>organisations were carried forward to deliver the intervention. <lb/>The East Brighton organisations helped the research team to <lb/>develop links with a health and wellbeing organisation that was <lb/>associated with a local General Practice (GP) clinic in East <lb/>Brighton. Finally, a fourth research site was identified in West <lb/>Hove and a final VCSE partner was identified. This organisation <lb/>was a local community development organisation for the area. In <lb/>total four VCSE organisations were partnered with across four <lb/>research sites. In each site a VC was recruited from the partner <lb/>organisation to deliver the intervention with the research team. <lb/>4.2 Community health worker recruitment <lb/>The research team and VCSE partners recruited 38 individuals <lb/>who attended the introductory CHW meetings (Gender: 27 females <lb/>and 11 males, NH n = 7, EB n = 13, HG n = 10, HA n = 8). Twenty-<lb/>seven of these individuals completed the full training for CHWs <lb/>(20 females and 7 males; NH n = 5, EB n = 9, HG n = 7, HA n = 6). <lb/>4.3 Participant recruitment <lb/>Social media recruitment had a wider reach to potential <lb/>participants compared with gatekeeper recruitment, however, <lb/>several participants did not complete the REDCap screening <lb/>questions, had a poor understanding of the study, or were not <lb/>part of the study&apos;s target population. VCSE gatekeepers yielded <lb/>poor recruitment results apart from when a newsletter with a <lb/>particularly large reach was used. Social media was the primary <lb/>strategy for recruiting participants to the study. In total the <lb/>messages reached 13,086 individuals across four waves of <lb/>recruitment and of these 472 (3.6%) engaged with post by <lb/>clicking on the survey link. Of those who clicked on the link <lb/>80% were female and 20% were male. <lb/>The INTERHEART screening data is shown in Figure 1 and <lb/>Supplementary Appendix 1 for all those who completed the <lb/>screening questionnaire (N = 381), participants who started the <lb/>intervention and then withdrew (N = 17), and participants who <lb/>completed the intervention and on whom we have full data <lb/>(n = 27). Of the CVD risk factors measured by the INTERHEART <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>07 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>screening tool, the two most prevalent were stress (reported by <lb/>61% of those screened, 56% of those who started the intervention, <lb/>and 78% of those who went on to complete), and physical <lb/>inactivity (reported by 55%, 81% and 64% respectively). <lb/>Forty-six participants took part in the CVD coaching <lb/>intervention across the four research sites, all of whom <lb/>completed the pre-intervention quantitative questionnaires. <lb/>Sixty-three percent completed the full coaching intervention, <lb/>and one participant withdrew from the project after three <lb/>months. We had full data for twenty-seven of twenty-nine <lb/>participants who completed the full 6-month coaching <lb/>intervention (note: these participants have been removed from <lb/>Supplementary Appendix 1, n = 2), Participants&apos; characteristics <lb/>are summarised in Table 3. Several participants withdrew <lb/>(37%), reasons given for withdrawing were: ill health/poor <lb/>mental health/ill health in the family (13%); the intervention <lb/>was considered a poor fit for the participant/did not meet their <lb/>expectations/they did not need the intervention (9%); other <lb/>commitments got in the way/they were too busy with their <lb/>normal lives (7%); repeated non-attendance at planned <lb/>coaching sessions from the CHW (4%); did not get on well <lb/>with CHW (2%), language issues (2%). <lb/>TABLE 2 Description of concordance/discordance with our pre-implementation expectations of the SPICES intervention for each of the <lb/>RE-AIM components (29). <lb/>Dimension <lb/>Expectation <lb/>Assessment of Concordance or Divergence with Reasons <lb/>REACH <lb/>The majority (&gt;50%) of participants to <lb/>be in the target demographic, i.e., IMD <lb/>based on address in 3 most deprived <lb/>deciles <lb/>30% of participants had an address with a postcode in IMD deciles 1-3, below the target figure of 50%. <lb/>Planned face-to-face recruitment activities which would have taken place within the target areas could not <lb/>take place as a result of the COVID pandemic and recruitment relied instead on social media adverts. As a <lb/>result of low response to these adverts the recruitment area was expanded to include more affluent adjacent <lb/>areas. <lb/>A sample size of 100-150 participants to <lb/>be recruited to take part in the <lb/>intervention <lb/>Forty-six participants took part in the coaching intervention. The number of participants recruited was <lb/>lower than expected, recruitment strategies were impacted by the COVID pandemic (see above). <lb/>Roughly equal proportions of men and <lb/>women to be recruited and to complete <lb/>the intervention. <lb/>Substantially more women than men were recruited-the proportion of women in those recruited to and <lb/>completing the intervention were 89% (41/46) and 87% (26/30) respectively. This is similar to the <lb/>proportions of women and men engaging with the social media adverts for the intervention (80% women). <lb/>Modifications to the intervention should be considered to increase its appeal to men, potentially by utilizing <lb/>&quot;men-friendly&quot; spaces and including activity-based and group sessions. While some of these activities were <lb/>considered in the planning stage of the interventions, restrictions due to the COVID pandemic resulted in <lb/>the intervention being delivered virtually. <lb/>EFFECTIVENESS <lb/>Coaching programme improve lifestyle <lb/>risk factor behaviours amongst <lb/>participants, i.e., improve diet, increase <lb/>exercise, reduce smoking, control and <lb/>drinking. <lb/>Significant changes were observed in the majority of the target behaviours, with reductions in physical <lb/>inactivity, increases in fruit and vegetable and wholegrain intake and reductions in intakes of sugary, salty <lb/>and fatty foods. There was no change in smoking prevalence, but this was very low both before and after the <lb/>intervention (4%)*. <lb/>The intervention is acceptable to <lb/>participants <lb/>Participant interviews overall suggested favourable views of the intervention, with positive aspects including <lb/>supportive and non-judgemental coaching, personalised support, and a feeling of empowerment. Negative <lb/>aspects included being given generic or inappropriate advice and a &quot;lack of direction&quot; in some coaching <lb/>sessions. <lb/>ADOPTION <lb/>At least half of the organisations who <lb/>were engaged with during the pre-<lb/>implementation phase then carried out <lb/>the project <lb/>50% (four out of eight) of the VCSEs approached delivered the coaching programme. <lb/>Reasons for not adopting the intervention including disruption caused by the COVID pandemic, availability <lb/>of funding, staff recruitment issues, and the intervention being a poor fit with the organisations&apos; main remit. <lb/>Approximately five volunteer CHWs to <lb/>be recruited per site and trained at each <lb/>research site <lb/>The number of volunteers recruited per site and completing all training sessions ranged from 5 to <lb/>9. Volunteer recruitment was facilitated by local contacts and existing volunteer pools at the partner VCSEs. <lb/>IMPLEMENTATION At least half of participants to complete <lb/>the intervention by attending a <lb/>minimum of three coaching sessions. <lb/>63% (29/46) of participants completed at least 3 sessions, and 59% (27/46) completed all 6. Attrition did not <lb/>exceed the anticipated value of up to 50%. Dedicated administrative support was key to scheduling <lb/>appointments, as rates of cancellations and rebooking by both participants and volunteers were high. <lb/>Coaching sessions to be delivered at <lb/>approximately monthly intervals. <lb/>The median (IQR) interval between coaching sessions was 28 (22, 35 days). Some participants enrolling at <lb/>sites recruited later in the SPICES programme had sessions more frequently than monthly in order to <lb/>complete the 6 sessions before the programme ended. <lb/>Co-design process leads to in useful <lb/>local adaptations to the coaching <lb/>programme. <lb/>The local co-design process included discussion of recruitment methods, the form of the intervention, and <lb/>the CHW training programme and &quot;charter&quot;. This process worked well for sites joining at the beginning of <lb/>the SPICES programme. However, CHWs sometimes seemed unsure of their role in this, and the capacity <lb/>for meaningful adaptation was less for sites joining later in the programme when delivery methods became <lb/>more fixed. <lb/>MAINTENANCE <lb/>Changes to behavioural risk factors are <lb/>maintained for at least 6 months after <lb/>the coaching ends. <lb/>Due to delays in starting the SPICES programme resulting from the COVID pandemic restrictions it was <lb/>not possible to follow-up the participants for long enough to assess this. <lb/>At least one VCSE to continue the <lb/>coaching after the end of the SPICES <lb/>programme <lb/>One partner VCSE organisation continued the coaching intervention beyond the lifetime of the programme. <lb/>This partner recruited a team to implement the programme and retained many of the same CHWs. Funding <lb/>was supplied by an UK national health service grant. <lb/>*Target behaviours were Reduce/cease smoking, increase moderate physical activity, reduce fat, salt, and sugar content of the diet, increase intake of fibre, fruit and <lb/>vegetables and oily fish (or alternatives), reduce sedentary hours. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>08 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>Due to low initial recruitment rates, the recruitment areas were <lb/>expanded and included more affluent adjacent areas. The <lb/>proportion of those completing the screening questionnaire and <lb/>of those who went on to start the intervention who were in the <lb/>target population (i.e., had an address with a postcode and IMD <lb/>in the most deprived three deciles) was 30% in both cases. <lb/>Despite recruitment being gender neutral and without gender/sex <lb/>related parameters on social media our risk profiling <lb/>questionnaire recruited far more women than men (77% female, <lb/>23% male, see Supplementary Appendix 1). This issue was <lb/>carried forward to the main intervention in which only five of <lb/>the forty-six who initially took part in the study were male. <lb/>4.4 Reasons for non-participation <lb/>Reasons given for not participating included missing or not <lb/>receiving an invitation to take part (n = 4), lack of time due to <lb/>responsibilities and commitments (n = 4), not feeling like the <lb/>intervention was a good fit for them and their circumstances <lb/>(n = 2), not being happy with the CHW allocated to them <lb/>(n = 2), being reluctant to take part in online activities due to a <lb/>lack of privacy at home (n = 1). When asked what would have <lb/>made them more likely to participate the most common response <lb/>was more clarity/detail on what was involved (n = 3). <lb/>4.5 Facilitators and barriers to reach <lb/>Intervention participants referred to several intervention <lb/>components that functioned as facilitators or barriers to the <lb/>reach of the intervention. These barriers and facilitators were <lb/>organised into themes which include: (1) Experience of CHW <lb/>recruitment; (2) The value of community partnerships; (3) The <lb/>experience of the risk profiling questionnaire; (4) Impacts of <lb/>COVID-19. These barriers and facilitators are described in more <lb/>detail in Table 3 and illustrative quotes are provided. <lb/>5 Effectiveness <lb/>5.1 Primary outcomes measures <lb/>For those participants who completed the intervention, the before <lb/>and after measures of cardiovascular risk, diet, physical activity, and <lb/>readiness to change were compared (see Figure 1 and Supplementary <lb/>Appendix 1). Mean INTERHEART score fell significantly from 11.7 <lb/>to 9.9, taking the mean to within the low-risk range. There were also <lb/>significant improvements in the self-reported dietary measures <lb/>including: an increase in the proportion of time wholegrain foods <lb/>were chosen, and the daily portions of fruit and vegetables eaten, and <lb/>decreases in the consumption of fatty, salty, and sugary food. No <lb/>changes were observed in the consumption of oily fish. Self-reported <lb/>levels of physical inactivity also dropped over the course of the <lb/>intervention with the proportion of those classified in the &quot;low&quot; <lb/>physical activity category falling from 40% to 7%. Additionally, the <lb/>self-reported levels of participants&apos; &quot;readiness to change&quot; during the <lb/>intervention increased from 3.6 to 4.5, which indicates increased <lb/>levels of motivation as a result of the intervention. <lb/>5.2 Participant reported facilitators and <lb/>barriers to the effectiveness <lb/>Intervention participants referred to several intervention <lb/>components that functioned as facilitators or barriers to the <lb/>effectiveness of the intervention. These barriers and facilitators <lb/>were organised into themes which include: (1) accountability-<lb/>the ways CHWs kept participants accountable about their health <lb/>behaviours; (2) connection and community-the importance <lb/>of making human connections with the CHWs and feelings of <lb/>community togetherness; (3) judgement-free-the importance <lb/>of a judgement-free intervention experience; (4) motivation and <lb/>support-the coaching role that the intervention took in the lives <lb/>of participants; (5) personalisation-the feeling that the <lb/>intervention was adapted to their own needs and experiences; (6) <lb/>reflection-the value of reflecting on experiences during the <lb/>coaching intervention; (7) self-efficacy-the ways in which <lb/>CHWs made participants feel in control of their health <lb/>behaviours; (8) gradual or modest impact-the feeling that the <lb/>intervention largely lead to modest impacts (9) generic or <lb/>inappropriate advice-the feeling that the information provided <lb/>during the coaching was too generic, obvious, or inappropriate to <lb/>their needs. These barriers and facilitators are described in more <lb/>detail in Table 4 and illustrative quotes are provided. <lb/>6 Adoption <lb/>6.1 Retention of voluntary and community <lb/>sector enterprise partnerships (setting level) <lb/>Of the six VCSE organisation engaged with during the pre-<lb/>implementation phase of the project, four went on to be VCSE <lb/>partner organisations during the implementation phase. Disruption <lb/>and staff pressures resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic were a <lb/>significant barrier to recruiting partner VCSEs, with two <lb/>organisations who had been involved in initial discussions deciding <lb/>not to proceed for this reason. Furthermore, interruptions to <lb/>communication caused by COVID-19 and research team changes <lb/>led to a loss of trust and engagement in some cases. One <lb/>organisation which had a group of people ready to volunteer at the <lb/>beginning of the project later withdrew as this group had <lb/>fragmented due to COVID-19-related delays and substantial <lb/>staffing changes that took place just prior to the implementation <lb/>phase between 2019 and 2020. Other factors impacting on VCSE <lb/>recruitment included the availability of funding, and issues with <lb/>recruiting staff to the VC role. After one of the VCSE partners <lb/>dropped out of the study just prior to the implementation phase, <lb/>the same organisation linked the research team with another <lb/>organisation who eventually functioned as VCSE partners for the <lb/>implementation phase. The need to develop trust, and having the <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>09 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>time to achieve this, was stated by several members of the research <lb/>team as being key to recruiting partner VCSEs. Quality of <lb/>communication was also felt to be especially important. <lb/>6.2 Facilitators of voluntary and community <lb/>sector enterprise partnerships (setting level) <lb/>VCSES and research team members referred to several <lb/>intervention components that functioned as facilitators or <lb/>barriers to setting level adoption. These barriers and facilitators <lb/>were organised into themes which include: (1) Trust-the <lb/>importance of developing trust with community-partners; (2) <lb/>Local Knowledge-the value of local knowledge and to delivering <lb/>appropriate community care; (3) Local Skills-the value of the <lb/>skills and experiences in local communities to delivering the <lb/>intervention. These barriers and facilitators are described in more <lb/>detail in Table 5 and illustrative quotes are provided. <lb/>6.3 Retention of community health workers <lb/>(individual level) <lb/>Of the twenty-seven CHWs who were recruited and trained to <lb/>be a part of the intervention, twenty-one went on to deliver one or <lb/>more session as an active CHW (Gender: 15 females and 6 males <lb/>NH n = 5, EB n = 6 HG n = 5, HA n = 5). Each of these CHWs <lb/>completed the intervention with at least one participant and the <lb/>maximum number of participants who completed the <lb/>intervention with one CHW was three. <lb/>6.4 Community health worker training <lb/>needs feedback (individual level) <lb/>After training sessions in our first site, a short questionnaire was <lb/>conducted with CHWs who attended the training in the formof one-<lb/>to-one discussions with the training coordinator and the research <lb/>team. Questions were asked about the anticipated barriers that <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Primary outcome measures for the &quot;Reach&quot; and &quot;Effectiveness&quot; components of the SPICES-Sussex intervention. (A) The proportion of &quot;Low&quot;, &quot;Medium&quot;, <lb/>and &quot;High&quot; risk participants identified during the Interheart risk profiling questionnaire; (B) the mean Interheart score pre and post intervention for <lb/>those who completed the intervention, p value from paired t-tests; (C) shows the % change regularly of dietary behaviours from pre/post <lb/>intervention UKDDQ score, within-group t-tests; (D) the change in the % of intervention participants classified as having either low or medium/ <lb/>high activity levels pre and post intervention, p value from McNemar&apos;s test. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>10 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>CHWs thought they would face during the coaching as well as key <lb/>training needs. Anticipated barriers and challenges during the <lb/>project included: a sense of mistrust amongst participants, issues of <lb/>poverty and deprivation, triggers, and sensitivities to the <lb/>experiences of participants (i.e., trauma or addition triggers). The <lb/>key training needs identified included: the sharing of personal <lb/>stories to empower participants, how to set achievable health goals, <lb/>preparing CHWs with tools to challenge the participant in a <lb/>supportive way, improving CHW confidence, and advice on how to <lb/>communicate CVD risk to participants in a straightforward way. <lb/>6.5 Community health worker facilitators <lb/>and barriers to adoption (individual level) <lb/>CHWs referred to several intervention components that functioned <lb/>as facilitators or barriers to the adoption of the intervention at the <lb/>individual CHW level. These barriers and facilitators were organised <lb/>into themes which include: (1) Local adaptation and Codesign <lb/>Sessions; (2) CHW motivation for participating; (3) CHW experiences <lb/>of the training; (4) CHW experience of the support provided to them. <lb/>These barriers and facilitators are described in more detail in Table 6 <lb/>and illustrative quotes are provided. <lb/>7 Implementation <lb/>7.1 Participant retention and fidelity <lb/>Overall, 48% (n = 51) of those eligible (n = 106) to take part in the <lb/>intervention agreed to do so and provided consent, of those 90% <lb/>(n = 46) attended their first CHW coaching session and completed <lb/>the baseline questionnaire. Of those who completed their first <lb/>session 63% (n = 29) completed three sessions and 45% completed <lb/>six sessions. For the 46 participants that began the intervention <lb/>there were 276 planned program contacts of which 183 (66%) were <lb/>TABLE 3 Facilitators and barriers to reach and recruitment. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>Experience of CHW <lb/>recruitment <lb/>CHW recruitment was generally considered to be a success by the research <lb/>team and the VCSE partners. This was largely due to the partnership <lb/>between the University and the VCSE organisations, as these partners were <lb/>able to leverage social capital and trust in order to mobilise their existing <lb/>community and volunteer base. <lb/>&quot;I think the people that responded were the ones that worked with us before <lb/>and trusted us, they knew they were going to probably have a positive <lb/>experience volunteering on a new project.&quot; (RT-F-02) <lb/>Following a difficult experience with one CHW, a one-to-one CHW <lb/>induction session was added at the second and subsequent study sites prior <lb/>to the training. This aimed to assess CHW personal qualities, motivation, <lb/>and suitability for the intervention. <lb/>&quot;I think we were so excited to take on volunteers and get them into the <lb/>project that we were happy to take anyone and train them up but … we <lb/>know now that we also need to interview them and make sure they are right <lb/>for the project going forward.&quot; (VCSE-HAF-01) <lb/>Community <lb/>partnerships <lb/>The perceived benefits of recruiting in partnership with VCSEs was <lb/>mentioned by CHWs and the research team. It was thought that links to <lb/>recognised community organisations would improve trust and allow for <lb/>access to VCSE community networks. <lb/>&quot;…they don&apos;t know us, whereas there&apos;s a community group in the <lb/>community they know… it&apos;s real, it&apos;s tangible… so I think going through <lb/>community groups was the best way&quot; (RTF-06) <lb/>However, despite VCSE partners being perceived as a positive for reach <lb/>into the community, members of the research team noted that this did not <lb/>seem to play out in practice, and that whilst VCSEs were effective in <lb/>recruiting CHWs, they had not had the anticipated reach to recruit <lb/>participants. <lb/>&quot;…we thought they would have the reach in the communities to do <lb/>participant recruitment, but they just didn&apos;t&quot;. (RTF-02) <lb/>Participants stated that they took part in the intervention because they were <lb/>&quot;open-minded&quot; to opportunities (NHF-02) or that the intervention came at <lb/>the right time for them (HAF-04). Additionally, the free coaching was a <lb/>major facilitator for some participants, especially for those on a low <lb/>income. Other factors raised by respondents included the helpful nature of <lb/>personalised emails in building a rapport with potential participants and <lb/>facilitating recruitment. <lb/>The risk profiling <lb/>questionnaire <lb/>The online INTERHEART screening tool was felt to present barriers to <lb/>recruitment by all the VCSEs and several members of the research team. <lb/>These included what was perceived to be its unnecessarily complicated <lb/>nature, technical difficulties in completing it, and possible digital exclusion <lb/>in using it with marginalised people. There was a mixed view of the risk <lb/>profiling tool amongst study participants. Participants understood why <lb/>they were being asked the questions and felt that for the most part they <lb/>were clear and easy to answer (PP-NHF-01). Some mentioned that the <lb/>questionnaire was too simplistic to capture their experience, and the <lb/>requirement for a tape measure for waist and hip measurement was said to <lb/>be a barrier. Many found the REDCap platform somewhat &quot;clunky&quot;, <lb/>&quot;tedious&quot;; or annoying to use and that it was reductionist or irrelevant to <lb/>their own personal experience of their health (PP-HAF-09, PP-HGF-11). <lb/>&quot;I found that a bit clunky. It was the clicking of the options and then trying <lb/>to select and the whole journey, and then it felt quite tedious and long to get <lb/>through.&quot; (PP-NHM-09) <lb/>Impacts of <lb/>COVID-10 <lb/>Restrictions resulting from the COVID pandemic presented several barriers <lb/>to participant recruitment. One of these was the inability to promote the <lb/>intervention with face-to-face community engagement due to COVID <lb/>restrictions, with this point being raised by volunteer co-ordinators, CHWs <lb/>and members of the research team. <lb/>&quot;We&apos;ve done emails to people to promote it as much as we can really on our <lb/>side without overdoing it […] if we weren&apos;t in COVID times […] then <lb/>obviously we would be going out physically and promoting the project&quot;. <lb/>(CHW-RTF-16) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>completed. Retention and attendance data are summarised in <lb/>Supplementary Appendix 2. No data was collected on the amount <lb/>of time each participant spent in their coaching session. <lb/>7.2 Participant facilitators and barriers to <lb/>implementation <lb/>Intervention participants referred to several intervention <lb/>components that functioned as facilitators or barriers to the <lb/>implementation of the intervention. These barriers and <lb/>facilitators were organised into themes which include: (1) <lb/>expectations of the coaching intervention, (2) the virtual <lb/>coaching sessions; (3) holistic and flexible, (4) length of the <lb/>coaching session, (5) administrative support, (6) past experiences, <lb/>(6) mental health. These barriers and facilitators are described in <lb/>more detail in Table 7 and illustrative quotes are provided. <lb/>8 Maintenance <lb/>8.1 Status of the intervention after six <lb/>months <lb/>Six months after the intervention&apos;s funding period ended the <lb/>program was being continued at two of the sites. One of the sites <lb/>TABLE 4 Facilitators and barriers to intervention effectiveness. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>Accountability <lb/>CHWs acted as a way of keeping participants accountable to the behaviour or life changes. The regular <lb/>appointments meant that the behaviour change was &quot;always at the back of my mind&quot; (PP-HAF-03). and <lb/>that participants would think about &quot;feeding back&quot; their progress to throughout the month (PP-HAF-09). <lb/>&quot;…it would have been embarrassing to <lb/>go back at the end of the month and <lb/>telling them I&apos;d put on weight.&quot; (PP-<lb/>NHF-01) <lb/>Connection and <lb/>Community <lb/>Being able to talk to someone regularly and openly about their health was seen as a positive of the <lb/>intervention. For some, the fact that the CHW was a stranger facilitated this openness (PP_EDF-14). <lb/>&quot;…she was able to get down to you know, <lb/>where I was at and what I needed.&quot; (PP-<lb/>HGF-11) <lb/>For participants who struggled during the COVID-19 restrictions, who were retired, or who had busy <lb/>working lives the connection provided by the CHWs combated loneliness that they often experienced. <lb/>The knowledge of the local community was useful when CHWs had it or when the participant and the <lb/>CHW shared interests or background, however it was often not that important to participants (PP-HAF-<lb/>04). <lb/>Judgement-free <lb/>CHWs generally treated participants without judgement of their lifestyles. Rather than being &quot;draconian&quot; <lb/>(PP-HGM-12) or being made to feel &quot;stupid&quot; or &quot;wrong&quot; the CHWs provided a safe space in which <lb/>participants could discuss &quot;options&quot; to change their behaviour (PP-HGF-06). Some participants reported <lb/>feeling judged, however, and explained this was a result of the nature of the intervention itself, which <lb/>focused on the need to change their behaviour, rather than of feeling any judgement from their CHW <lb/>specifically. <lb/>&quot;The reason I haven&apos;t been [to lifestyle <lb/>management interventions] before, is <lb/>because I thought they were all going to <lb/>be, erm, quite draconian in the way that <lb/>they delivered their method. But it [the <lb/>intervention] wasn&apos;t like that at all.&quot; <lb/>(HGM-12) <lb/>Motivation and Support The feeling of being supported and mentored by the CHWs was one of the key draws. For some, this <lb/>support took the form of emotional &quot;encouragement, friendliness and a sense of humour&quot; (PP-HGF-11) <lb/>and for others the motivation took the form of a &quot;push in the right direction&quot; (PP-HGM-12). <lb/>&quot;…to my friends I&apos;ve said that she&apos;s <lb/>[CHW name] like a mentor. That [CHW <lb/>name] was a mentor to me.&quot; (PP-HGF-<lb/>11) <lb/>Participants often reported that the CHWs made them feel as if they had been too hard on themselves <lb/>during their past, or that they had felt like a failure in the past (EBF-05). This softer form of motivation <lb/>and support was appreciated by participants. <lb/>Participants generally had good knowledge of CVD health risk factors and they knew that their own <lb/>health was poor and that they needed to make lifestyle changes. However, they reported feeling as though <lb/>they needed extra support and motivation to push them to make changes. <lb/>Personalisation <lb/>Participants reported that the one-to-one coaching felt that it was personal to them or linked back to their <lb/>&quot;story&quot; (PP-NHF-02). This was facilitated by the feeling that their CHWs were listening intently to what <lb/>they said and incorporating it into their personal behaviour change journey (PP-NHM-09), and &quot;going <lb/>the extra mile&quot; for the participants. <lb/>&quot;She went the extra mile, every time we <lb/>finished a session, we&apos;d recap. And then <lb/>the following session, she&apos;d come back, <lb/>and she&apos;d done a bit of research for me, <lb/>which I wasn&apos;t expecting her to do.&quot; (PP-<lb/>NHF-02) <lb/>Reflection <lb/>Reflection on past sessions was used as a tool used by CHWs to promote and document the participant&apos;s <lb/>behaviour change. CHWs used past behaviours as a benchmark for their progress or reflected over their <lb/>achievements at the end (PP-NHF-02). Both participants and CHWs made use of notetaking which <lb/>helped to facilitate this reflection (PP-NHM-07). <lb/>Self-efficacy <lb/>Rather than giving commands or specific instructions to participants CHWs would often work alongside <lb/>the participants as equals (PP-HAF-03). This allowed participants to feel more &quot;in control&quot; (PP-NHF-02) <lb/>and more empowered around their health, and as they advanced, participants reported feeling as though <lb/>they had learnt to respect themselves (PP-NHF-15). <lb/>Gradual and modest <lb/>impacts <lb/>Initial expectation amongst participants was that they had to make drastic lifestyle changes to improve <lb/>their health. However, participants came to realise that minor, achievable, and gradual changes could be <lb/>impactful and should be celebrated (PP-HGM-12). <lb/>&quot;I do feel a little bit proud of…because I <lb/>have lost a little bit of weight, I&apos;d like to <lb/>lose a bit more, erm, but it&apos;s only been <lb/>through sort of small changes.&quot; (PP-<lb/>HAF-03) <lb/>Generic or <lb/>inappropriate advice <lb/>Participants often reported that the coaching sessions lacked purpose or direction and that sometimes it <lb/>was &quot;difficult to know&quot; what they were trying to achieve (PP-NHF-01). The health advice given to them <lb/>was sometimes reported to be inappropriate to their specific needs (i.e., health conditions) or too basic, <lb/>obvious to the participant, or unhelpful. <lb/>&quot;It was difficult to know what we was <lb/>[sic] trying to achieve I think sometimes. <lb/>… we had a couple of times where we <lb/>waffled round in circles and didn&apos;t really <lb/>get anywhere.&quot; (PP-NHF-01) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>12 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>continued it as volunteer opportunity and peer support program <lb/>which was covered by their existing funding for peer support <lb/>programs. A second site was awarded funding from the National <lb/>Health Service to continue the intervention. The latter&apos;s findings <lb/>will be reported as a program evaluation in the future. <lb/>8.2 Facilitators and barriers to maintenance <lb/>Interviewees referred to several intervention components that <lb/>functioned as facilitators or barriers to the maintenance of the <lb/>intervention at the setting level. These barriers and facilitators <lb/>were organised into themes which include: (1) continuity of the <lb/>intervention; (2) funding; (3) infrastructure These barriers and <lb/>facilitators are described in more detail in Table 8 and illustrative <lb/>quotes are provided. <lb/>9 Discussion <lb/>SPICES Sussex developed strategies to implement effective <lb/>community-based CVD risk reduction interventions based on <lb/>behaviour change coaching with CHWs by partnering with and <lb/>leveraging the experience and influence of VCSE in four <lb/>underserved communities in East Sussex, UK. Despite issues with <lb/>recruitment and challenges associated with COVID-19 as well as <lb/>other logistic, management, and research design challenges, the <lb/>project showed clear markers of success. Participants experienced <lb/>the interventions positively and many made gradual, and <lb/>sometimes substantial, lifestyle changes. The quantitative results <lb/>showed significant reduction in participants&apos; CVD risk after taking <lb/>part in the interventions. We think these successes were due to <lb/>implementing our interventions in a flexible, personalised, and <lb/>holistic way, which empowered CHWs to use their skills and <lb/>experiences to aid participants. These results demonstrate how <lb/>CHWs-led and community-based preventative CVD interventions <lb/>could be implemented, such as those seen widely across the Global <lb/>South (17, 18). They also support a &quot;person-based&quot; and &quot;asset-<lb/>based&quot; approach to community-based implementation design <lb/>(23, 25) in which the strengths and assets of communities and <lb/>their members are used to promote health and wellbeing. <lb/>9.1 Intervention design <lb/>The SPICES-Sussex project used community-engagement and <lb/>community health worker approaches to improve CVD health <lb/>that are based on practices developed and tested in Kampala, <lb/>Uganda (47). As part of the SPICES consortium these practices <lb/>were adapted to several global north (UK, France, Belgium) and <lb/>global south settings (South Africa). In the global south social <lb/>public health approaches have long advocated for the <lb/>decentralisation of healthcare to community partners and for a <lb/>greater focus on prevention (48). Community-based public health <lb/>practices such as task-sharing are often utilised in low-resource <lb/>health systems in low-and middle income countries by recruiting <lb/>and training community health workers to deliver low-intensity <lb/>health intervention such as health coaching and signposting (49). <lb/>In global south SPICES settings, there was greater buy-in to <lb/>community-based interventions from governments and much of <lb/>the trust building, and infrastructure for community health <lb/>workers already exists (50). These settings, including the SPICES <lb/>sites that influenced the Sussex site, often rely on voluntary or <lb/>unpaid volunteers to conduct public health work in order to <lb/>lower cost and to make use of existing social networks. <lb/>In resource-rich global north settings, healthcare is far more <lb/>institutionalised and focused on secondary care and the <lb/>TABLE 5 Facilitators and barriers to intervention setting level adoption. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>Trust <lb/>The need to develop trust and having the time to achieve this was stated by <lb/>several members of the research team as being key to recruiting partner <lb/>VCSEs. Quality of communication was also felt to be very important. <lb/>&quot;It needs time for them to see you and understand that you mean well, and <lb/>you&apos;ll be around when something goes wrong, that&apos;s the most important <lb/>thing… It&apos;s basically about listening skills and not going in and assuming <lb/>you have all the answers.&quot; (RT-M-03) <lb/>A key advantage of using the voluntary sector raised by VCs, CHWs and <lb/>members of the research team, was that it was felt to promote trust in the <lb/>strategy to implement the intervention and help it to feel embedded in the <lb/>local community. <lb/>Acceptability of <lb/>CHWs <lb/>CHWs were also felt to have useful local knowledge, and to be &quot;on a similar <lb/>level&quot; to participants, helping to reduce intimidation and the fear of <lb/>judgement when talking about health and lifestyle. <lb/>&quot;I think a volunteer is maybe closer to the people in the community than <lb/>somebody who&apos;s an official, you know, maybe a doctor… I&apos;ve found that the <lb/>ladies that I&apos;m coaching are very happy, and they don&apos;t feel intimidated… <lb/>they feel almost like we&apos;re two friends and we&apos;re going on this journey <lb/>together.&quot; (VCSE-HAF-01) <lb/>Use of volunteers <lb/>as CHWs <lb/>Several respondents also pointed out that CHWs could be a good way of <lb/>dealing with workforce shortages and did not need to be paid. Conversely, <lb/>the CHWs lack of experience and contractual obligation was felt to result in <lb/>several disadvantages. These included frequent cancellations of coaching <lb/>sessions due to competing priorities such as work or childcare, and some <lb/>CHWs were felt by the VCs to lack commitment. They were also felt to <lb/>sometimes lack confidence in dealing with complex issues. <lb/>&quot;The whole way from the very beginning we told them you&apos;re not an expert, <lb/>you&apos;re not a health professional, you don&apos;t have to have all the answers and <lb/>yet it still contributed to them feeling like not particularly confident <lb/>sometimes.&quot; (RT-F-07) <lb/>One VC commented on the high level of investment required from the <lb/>research team to achieve this (to note, an economic assessment of the <lb/>project was not made). <lb/>&quot;it feels like a sort of a lot of investment, lot of capacity on … the sponsor <lb/>side to make that happen … how sustainable that is I don&apos;t know.&quot; (VCSE-<lb/>EBM-04) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>13 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>TABLE 6 Facilitators and barriers to intervention individual level adoption. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>CHW experience of local <lb/>adaptation and co-design <lb/>Several topics were discussed during the local adaptation sessions. These <lb/>included the name to be used for the project at each site, methods of <lb/>participant recruitment, the form of the intervention experience for <lb/>CHWs and participants, the training programme, and the &quot;volunteer <lb/>charter&quot;. VCs and CHWs generally appreciated this process and <lb/>commented that they felt included in decision making and that their <lb/>input was valued. <lb/>&quot;I think that&apos;s been … kind of a strength of like the project is the <lb/>collaborative nature of being open to hearing different viewpoints and <lb/>ways of working and thinking, right, how can we accommodate and how <lb/>can we put this together into a shared plan.&quot; (VCSE-HGF-02) <lb/>However, members of the research team commented that while the <lb/>adaptation sessions worked well for the first sites, there was less room for <lb/>local adaptation at the later sites to join, both because methods of <lb/>delivery became more fixed as the study progressed, and because of a lack <lb/>of time to implement changes. They also commented that CHWs <lb/>sometimes seemed unsure what was expected of them in the co-design <lb/>process. <lb/>&quot;it worked really well for the first site … and then I think it became a <lb/>little bit more challenging later on because we were going to them kind of <lb/>saying, oh, we want to hear your ideas, but actually this is kind of <lb/>already set.&quot; (RT-M-01) <lb/>The local adaptation led to some changes in the way the study was rolled <lb/>out between the sites. These were mostly focused on the support offered <lb/>to the CHWs, including regularity and format of support meetings and <lb/>training offered, and recruitment and outreach approaches, rather than <lb/>changes to the design of the intervention or participant experience. <lb/>&quot;it was almost like they were asking us to come somewhere and get asked <lb/>a bunch of questions about a programme that they don&apos;t know about.&quot; <lb/>(RT-F-02) <lb/>Motivation for CHW <lb/>participation <lb/>Many of the CHWs had a background in health-related areas, such as <lb/>nursing, health coaching or activity and fitness, several also had some <lb/>experience in counselling and behaviour change. A number stated that <lb/>their motivation for volunteering was related to experience of their own <lb/>or a relative&apos;s health problems. <lb/>&quot;As a health coach I know that you can change massively your health <lb/>and take control of it by knowing how to change your habits… I think <lb/>it&apos;s really important because my mother suffers from a heart problem.&quot; <lb/>(CHW-HAF-01) <lb/>The desire to &quot;give back&quot; to the community was also mentioned by <lb/>several CHWs. Some also commented that being involved had helped <lb/>their own physical and mental health. <lb/>&quot;…my major thing for me in my life is giving back…I went into it <lb/>basically for that and to help me… it&apos;s helped my mental health to be <lb/>involved.&quot; (CHW-EBF-02) <lb/>One CHW stated that the CHW role had provided her with potentially <lb/>useful work experience. <lb/>Participants showed appreciation for the CHWs, especially when they <lb/>realised that they were providing their time in a voluntary capacity <lb/>(HAF-04). However, they questioned what the CHWs were getting out of <lb/>the project. Some also showed discontent at the fact that the CHWs were <lb/>not paid. <lb/>&quot;I think I&apos;m going to explore health coach roles after my Masters … so <lb/>it&apos;s given me some really worthwhile experience. &quot; (CHW-EBF-02) <lb/>They also often referred to how much they enjoyed the sessions with <lb/>their CHWs and how they found them to be &quot;pleasant&quot; (HGF-06), <lb/>&quot;personable&quot; (NHM-06), and &quot;supportive&quot; (EBF-05). <lb/>&quot;I&apos;m just so grateful, honestly, I just can&apos;t believe this has been for <lb/>nothing, it blows my mind, err, because it&apos;s really changing my life um <lb/>for the better.&quot; (CHW-NHF-15) <lb/>Experience of CHW <lb/>Training <lb/>As a result of COVID restrictions the training was online, and two of the <lb/>VCs commented that it would have been better delivered face-to-face as <lb/>originally planned. Comments from VCs and CHWs on the training <lb/>programme were generally positive although several VCs and CHWs felt <lb/>the programme was a bit rushed and intense, and several CHWs <lb/>commented that they would have liked more time for role play within the <lb/>sessions. <lb/>&quot;A bit of information overload … I think they found it a bit <lb/>overwhelming&quot; (CHW-HGF-02) <lb/>&quot;I probably didn&apos;t use everything … but I just felt confident… the <lb/>knowledge from the training just gave me the confidence to sort of carry <lb/>that on&quot;. (CHW-EBF-02) <lb/>Both CHWs and VCs noted that instilling confidence in coaching skills, <lb/>rather than just information, had been a key part of the value of the <lb/>training. <lb/>&quot;I knew she had training in, I don&apos;t know exactly what it was, but I knew <lb/>she had training and she&apos;d done certain things herself, and she was <lb/>interested in psychology and things like that. And she brought that in, to <lb/>our conversations, which I found really helpful.&quot; (CHW-NHF-01) <lb/>Participants described the CHWs as &quot;professional&quot; (HAF-04), <lb/>&quot;knowledgeable&quot; (HGF-05), and &quot;wise&quot; (NHF-15). CHWs bought in <lb/>skills of their &quot;background&quot; experiences to the coaching. <lb/>However, some CHWs showed some signs of inexperience such as <lb/>nervousness (HAF-09), a lack of practical suggestions (NHF-16), or <lb/>tendency to talk about themselves (HGF-06). <lb/>Experience of CHW <lb/>Support <lb/>The administrative support provided by the research team was <lb/>considered as &quot;friendly&quot; (HAF-09), &quot;straightforward&quot; (HAF-04), and <lb/>&quot;informative&quot; (HGF-11). These roles were essential for ensuring that the <lb/>participants had a consistent and trustable contact which supported their <lb/>coaching sessions. In addition, the PCs provided IT support which was <lb/>frequently requested by CHWs due to difficulties accessing documents or <lb/>delivering the online coaching. CHWs spoke highly of the administrative <lb/>support offered. <lb/>&quot;Just, yeah, really supported by the administrative team throughout the <lb/>whole process. They were really quick to respond.&quot; (CHW-RTF-05) <lb/>&quot;there&apos;s so many cancellations, we just need to keep on top of <lb/>everything… we had it kind of doubled up so that if we miss something <lb/>somewhere… we wanted to have like a duplicate somewhere else.&quot; <lb/>(RTF-02) <lb/>However, rates of cancellations and rescheduling of appointments by <lb/>both CHWs and participants were high, resulting in a considerable <lb/>workload for the PCs and the need for effective tracking systems. <lb/>&quot;…we almost tailor, you know… oh hello, hope you had a lovely holiday <lb/>…we&apos;re so friendly, and we can have that relationship with them because <lb/>it&apos;s a small tracking system and we do it all ourselves.&quot; (RTF-01) <lb/>The PCs suggested that for the project to work on a larger scale, auto-<lb/>correspondence for reminder emails would be needed, but noted that this <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>14 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>infrastructure <lb/>for <lb/>community-based <lb/>and <lb/>participatory <lb/>interventions is far less well developed. In the UK, most health <lb/>interventions must adhere to the institutional demands of the <lb/>National Health Service which presents a range of resource <lb/>intensive training, recruitment, safeguarding, and management <lb/>practices. There is much less history of CHWs in the UK; the <lb/>role of these workers is not well understood or well defined <lb/>outside of the third/voluntary sector despite recent calls for their <lb/>use during the COVID-19 pandemic (51). This squeezed <lb/>landscape for community-based intervention and the lack of <lb/>familiarity with the role makes the development and <lb/>implementation of these interventions challenging. In the global <lb/>north there are increasing challenges to the volunteer nature of <lb/>CHWs with researchers calling for compensation, capacity <lb/>building, or payment of members of the public involved in <lb/>intervention delivery of research and health interventions on <lb/>moral and efficacy grounds (52, 53). In our study, the decision <lb/>not to pay CHW was made as a result of us following the <lb/>SPICES approach developed in the Global South (17) and <lb/>because the VCSE organisations we partnered with all had <lb/>existing unpaid community volunteer programs. In our post-<lb/>intervention qualitative evaluation interviews, participants and <lb/>CHWs both discussed the value of paying CHWs. Furthermore, <lb/>the drop in CHWs and the small number of participants they <lb/>were able to take on implies that the lack of payment impacted <lb/>the degree to which CHWs were able to engage with the project <lb/>and therefore impacted the intervention&apos;s effectiveness and <lb/>sustainability. In the UK, the NIHR now recommends that <lb/>members of the public who are involved in research are properly <lb/>reimbursed for their involvement and provide frequently updated <lb/>guidelines on how to do so (54). In the future we argue that <lb/>public health intervention that make use of CHWs should <lb/>reimburse and pay them in some way for their involvement. <lb/>Community volunteers with low levels of training (10 h core <lb/>training plus ongoing support), such as those used during this <lb/>study, are not well-suited to complex cases or acute needs that <lb/>required specialised support. In our findings, participants <lb/>complained of generic, inappropriate, or obvious advice from the <lb/>CHWs. Participants did not seem to prioritize the knowledge or <lb/>expertise of the CHWs and instead valued the personalised, <lb/>holistic, and supportive relationships that were offered by the <lb/>CHWs. Participants in the intervention reported having good <lb/>knowledge of what they needed to do to improve their health but <lb/>struggled to do it in practice. Therefore, this kind of intervention <lb/>may be well-suited to providing emotional and social support to <lb/>people at risk of CVD who know what they &quot;should&quot; do but need <lb/>a support and judgement free support mechanism to make changes. <lb/>Interviews with participants revealed a tension in the study <lb/>linked to the use of an individualistic lifestyle change intervention <lb/>situated within a community-based and participatory study. The <lb/>study design did not address community-level, socio-economic, or <lb/>environmental issues known to be vital when addressing CVD <lb/>health (55). Tengland (56) argues that an individualistic lens of <lb/>behavioural change can limit understandings of a person&apos;s CVD <lb/>health. The result can be too narrow, as the &quot;secondary&quot; effects of <lb/>their wider environmental conditions (i.e., powerlessness, lack of <lb/>control, or lack of hope), are not considered. They further suggest <lb/>that interventions should focus more on the attainment of <lb/>instrumental goals, such as increased real opportunities in life. For <lb/>community-based projects to grow further, they should seek to <lb/>become multi-faceted by combining individualistic interventions <lb/>with environment/community activities such as community <lb/>education (57). <lb/>The frequency with which mental health issues were raised in <lb/>discussions was notable. Those who took part in the screening <lb/>reported high levels of stress and depression, and rates were even <lb/>TABLE 6 Continued <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>would result in the loss of personalised messages which they felt helped <lb/>build relationships with participants. <lb/>Most CHWs spoke very highly of the support received, which was felt to <lb/>be particularly important when they were building confidence at the <lb/>beginning of their coaching role. <lb/>&quot;The support is brilliant; we know that we can contact anyone… and in <lb/>our meetings every month it&apos;s been very useful to share ideas and to <lb/>share our thoughts.&quot; (HGF-03) <lb/>Several respondents mentioned that feeling part of a team was an <lb/>important part of the CHW support. <lb/>The personal relationship between CHWs and support staff in which a <lb/>feeling of care, connection, and/or reassurance, was provided was <lb/>repeatedly raised as an important feature of the overall support package. <lb/>&quot;I think they really benefitted from being brought together for kind of <lb/>action learning meetings every month and feeling like they were part of a <lb/>team, I think them having to do it in isolation wouldn&apos;t have worked.&quot; <lb/>(RT-F-04) <lb/>Several CHWs noted that many of their participants were suffering from <lb/>stress and had complex emotional and mental health needs, often linked <lb/>to the COVID pandemic, and the value of support given by the VCs and <lb/>health coach when dealing with this. <lb/>CHWs made substantial use of the signposting and resources that the <lb/>research team prepared for them. They also went beyond these by <lb/>actively seeking out resources that met the participant&apos;s needs and goals. <lb/>CHW&apos;s often also brought their own expertise and knowledge from their <lb/>lives to the coaching i.e., sharing resources for a physical activity that they <lb/>participated in (HGM-12). <lb/>&quot;…a couple of the volunteers would almost want to talk before a session <lb/>and after a session… it was just connection and a chat and feeling <lb/>listened to and supported.&quot; (RTF-07) <lb/>&quot;…the first session I had with one of the participants … she was very <lb/>emotional and cried… I think [CHW trainer] was surprised that this <lb/>lady had so much going on … she was concerned that I was taking <lb/>on a lot from her so it was very helpful to speak to both of them.&quot; <lb/>(CHW-NHF-01) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>15 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>TABLE 7 Facilitators and barriers to intervention implementation. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>Expectation <lb/>Despite numerous attempts to inform participants about what was involved, <lb/>participants reported having a poor understanding of what the program <lb/>entailed. Many of those subsequently reported being pleasantly surprised at <lb/>what they got. <lb/>&apos;When [CHW name] said to me, &quot;What do you want to get out of this?&quot; <lb/>Basically, I said, &quot;Well, I don&apos;t know&quot; (PP-NHF-16) <lb/>Participants noted that the intervention was not well suited to people living <lb/>with complex health conditions, disability, or long-COVID. They <lb/>experienced the intervention as being based on an &quot;individualistic&quot; <lb/>assumption about lifestyle change which relied on making changes which <lb/>were not considerate of their conditions (PP-EBF-13). Poverty and <lb/>vulnerability were also seen as barriers to making many of the lifestyle <lb/>changes promoted during the intervention. <lb/>Virtual coaching <lb/>session <lb/>Although some CHWs expressed a view that face-to-face coaching sessions <lb/>would have been better, most felt that the virtual coaching sessions had gone <lb/>well and had several advantages. Several CHWs suggested that virtual <lb/>coaching provided a helpful distance between the CHW and the participants, <lb/>reducing anxiety on both sides. <lb/>&quot;…because it does have that distance there… maybe makes people more at <lb/>ease to talk about personal things… if I&apos;d been sitting in somebody&apos;s room… <lb/>I don&apos;t know whether people would have opened-up as much&quot;. (PP-NHF-01) <lb/>The convenience of online coaching was also felt to be a facilitator to <lb/>attendance by both CHWs and the VCs. <lb/>&quot;It&apos;s brilliant doing it online, it&apos;s sort of personal enough to make you feel <lb/>guilty, but not so personal that you&apos;re uncomfortable by it.&quot; (PP-NHF-02) <lb/>It was felt that cancellation rates would have been even higher if participants <lb/>had needed to travel to attend sessions in person. Disadvantages of online <lb/>coaching sessions raised by the CHWs included not being able to see the <lb/>participants&apos; body language, and the difficulty of sharing information and <lb/>resources with participants. <lb/>Study participants were also positive about the use of Zoom, reporting that it <lb/>was less hassle than face-to-face (PP-NHF-02) because they &quot;didn&apos;t have to <lb/>go anywhere&quot; (HGF-06). <lb/>Some reported experiencing technical problems such a failing internet <lb/>connections (PP-NHF-01) and there were issues of digital exclusion amongst <lb/>participants which made the use of Zoom more difficult. <lb/>Holistic and <lb/>Flexible <lb/>The &quot;freedom&quot; and flexibility of the coaching session was seen as a positive <lb/>(PP-NHF-02, PP-HGF-11) CHWs were not fixed to &quot;one stance&quot; (PP-HGF-<lb/>06). Sessions were &quot;relaxed&quot; and &quot;laid back&quot; (PP-EBF-09) but they generally <lb/>fell into a rhythm of discussing progress with previously discussed goals, <lb/>before having a period of flexible and open conversations, followed by goal <lb/>setting at the end of the session. Once this rhythm was established <lb/>participants reported that it did not generally change that much. Rather than <lb/>being explicitly focused on CVD health, CHWs and participants took a more <lb/>holistic focus to health. Conversations about one&apos;s health would often &quot;open <lb/>up&quot; into different areas of their lives (PP-HAF-04). <lb/>&quot;it&apos;s just that … when you&apos;re having conversations it opens up, sometimes <lb/>it&apos;ll just open up your thought processes and send you off in other <lb/>directions.&quot; (PP-HAF-04) <lb/>Length of coaching Participants felt that 6, monthly sessions were appropriate as this allowed <lb/>enough time to plan, implement, and experience results of lifestyle changes. <lb/>Their feedback on the length of individual sessions was mixed, with some <lb/>stating that they were far too long whilst others found it very easy to fill the <lb/>hour-long time slot. There was also a desire to carry on with the coaching or <lb/>to have extra support beyond the initial coaching into a &quot;phase 2&quot;. <lb/>&quot;I think a Phase 2 would be good. … I think a Phase 3 would be good. Our <lb/>hearts are with us for a lifetime. So, to assess change, it needs to be over a <lb/>long period of time.&quot; (PP-NHF-02) <lb/>Administrative <lb/>support <lb/>The administrative support provided by the research team to participants of <lb/>the intervention was &quot;friendly&quot; (PP-HAF-09), &quot;straightforward&quot; (PP-HAF-<lb/>04), and &quot;informative&quot; (PP-HGF-11). These roles were essential for ensuring <lb/>that the participants had a consistent and trustable contact which supported <lb/>their coaching sessions. <lb/>Past experiences of <lb/>care <lb/>Negative past experiences of behaviour change were discussed by <lb/>participants with many reporting that they had made many efforts to change <lb/>but that they had &quot;fallen off the bandwagon&quot; (PP-NHM-07). Interactions <lb/>with clinical experts to address lifestyle changes were also commonly <lb/>discussed and were largely viewed negatively. Firstly, clinicians were <lb/>regarded as having highly limited time and participants had to repeatedly <lb/>contact them (PP-NHF-01) or they would meet for very short periods (PP-<lb/>NHM-07). Secondly, interactions with clinicians were often regarded to be <lb/>&quot;impersonal&quot; (PP-NHF-01), &quot;patronising&quot; (PP-HAF-09), or &quot;inconsistent&quot; <lb/>(PP-HAF-09). <lb/>&quot;Well, the clinician&apos;s is not personalised at all. it&apos;s very automatic. And very <lb/>clipped and very brief.&quot; (PP-NHF-01) <lb/>Mental Health <lb/>Despite the focus of the study not being on mental health, participants spoke <lb/>very openly about their mental health. CHWs validated participants and <lb/>helped them to realise that they could make changes. Participants also <lb/>discussed how improving their physical health could feed back on their <lb/>mental health and improve their mood more generally. <lb/>&quot;…as the meetings progressed, I did say that I was feeling much better. And I <lb/>was feeling lighter, lighter-not as in weight-wise, but light in spirit.&quot; <lb/>(PP-HGF-10) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>16 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>higher amongst participants taking part in the programme, <lb/>furthermore, participants reported lower levels of stress and <lb/>depression at the end. This may show that this type of <lb/>intervention is particularly well suited to people with mental <lb/>health concerns for whom talking to someone can make a real <lb/>difference. This was also observed in the SPICES consortium <lb/>partner sites including Brest (France) (58), and Antwerp <lb/>(Belgium) (59). Most non-specialist or non-clinical people do not <lb/>think of their health siloed into CVD, mental health, digestive <lb/>health etc (60). Instead, one&apos;s health is perceived holistically, and <lb/>mental health is often the most prominent barrier and facilitator <lb/>to behaviour change. <lb/>9.2 Implementation strategy <lb/>We adopted a type 3 hybrid implementation study which focused <lb/>primarily on implementation factors rather than evaluation, dropping <lb/>the randomisation approach and embracing flexible more emergent <lb/>iterative development and growth perspective, co-design, and <lb/>contextual/place-based factors. A rigid evaluation linear approach as <lb/>required for a type 1/2 design, which was initially planned, caused <lb/>tensions with the community-based, participatory, and &quot;emergent&quot; <lb/>aspects of the project and (2) the pressures imposed on our <lb/>voluntary sector partners by the pandemic meant that adhering to a <lb/>rigid randomisation approach was less realistic (7). The planned <lb/>approach placed power in the hands of the research team which <lb/>negatively affected our stakeholder relationships, and a rigid <lb/>adherence to study protocols would have meant we could not <lb/>effectively adapt strategies or interventions to context. <lb/>Instead we adopted a type 3 approach, which has been used to <lb/>assess a wide range of preventative health and eHealth <lb/>interventions which operate in communities based on <lb/>participatory principles (61). In their systematic review of such <lb/>strategies to implement interventions, Haldane et al. (62) <lb/>highlight the importance of building mutually beneficial and <lb/>trust-based relationships particularly with marginalised <lb/>stakeholders, and stress the importance of developing strategies <lb/>and interventions contextually whilst reporting and acting on <lb/>lessons learnt throughout the project. Wildman et al. (63) argue <lb/>that successful community-based projects require extensive <lb/>community input, learning and adaptation captured from <lb/>existing programmes to facilitate the replicability of programmes <lb/>in other community contexts. With the more flexible type three <lb/>approach we were able to make local adaptation to meet the <lb/>need and priorities of the local community and local VCSE <lb/>partner organisation thereby listening to the voices of those who <lb/>are involved. This iterative approach to intervention design is <lb/>similar to the &quot;scaling-out&quot; approach suggested by Aaron et al. <lb/>(64) which advocates iterative roll-out and local adaptation in <lb/>place of simply &quot;copy and pasting&quot; interventions across context. <lb/>In reality, during SPICES-Sussex the local adaption became less <lb/>flexible as the intervention became more well-developed as the <lb/>internal factors became more institutionalised within the research <lb/>team. However, the principle of meeting the needs and priorities <lb/>of the local VCSE organisation were maintained from site to site <lb/>and the team sought input from local organisations where possible. <lb/>We do not know whether the changes observed will be <lb/>maintained due to the short follow up period, both at an <lb/>individual level or a setting level (65), and the research lacks an <lb/>economic appraisal. The short follow-up period was forced on <lb/>the research team because of delays to the project caused by <lb/>COVID-19 which meant our funding period was not long <lb/>enough to conduct a follow up assessment. An economic <lb/>TABLE 8 Facilitators and barriers to maintenance. <lb/>Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Illustrative quote <lb/>Continuity of the <lb/>intervention <lb/>All the partner organisations indicated that they would be happy to <lb/>continue with the programme which they felt was a good fit with their <lb/>other initiatives, if it could be sustainably resourced. <lb/>&quot;Speaking informally to some of the clinicians, they&apos;re certainly very keen <lb/>and it does fit exactly perfectly well with what they&apos;re already doing…our <lb/>community works very well when things are happening from within it, and <lb/>that&apos;s a really important feature for us… I think the fact that … it was done <lb/>in such a way it could be built almost from within, and that worked really <lb/>well.&quot; (RT-F-07) <lb/>They also generally felt that the CHWs would be happy to continue to <lb/>deliver the programme, but the volunteers&apos; stated views on this in one focus <lb/>group were mixed-one said they would be happy to continue, another did <lb/>not want to, and another wanted further training if they were to continue. <lb/>Funding <lb/>The main stated requirement for continuing with the intervention was <lb/>funding, in particular for the VC role, and the possible need to recruit extra <lb/>staff in order to maintain the project was also mentioned. One VC <lb/>suggested a small amount of funding for recruitment and promotion would <lb/>also be required. Several VCs commented that they would need continued <lb/>support from the SPICES research team to continue to deliver the <lb/>intervention, particularly with regard to training, recruitment and <lb/>IT support. <lb/>&quot;it would be nice to be reassured that we&apos;ve still got you guys to fall back on <lb/>some of the technical support… and [Health coach name] been just great <lb/>with the coaching, again that&apos;s not my area of expertise.&quot; (NHF-03) <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Members of the research team noted the need to retain a core support team <lb/>to deliver the interventions, particularly the health coach and admin roles. <lb/>Considerable administrative support was required, particularly during <lb/>participant recruitment. Dealing with booking and rescheduling <lb/>appointments was extremely time-consuming. The research team also <lb/>commented that the local primary care system embraced the project much <lb/>more than was anticipated before its start. Integrating it into that system <lb/>thus seemed more feasible than we had predicted. We had expected much <lb/>less enthusiasm from (busy) healthcare providers, so this was really <lb/>good news. <lb/>&quot;…integrating it into a service rather than just thinking of it as a voluntary <lb/>sector thing is really good, and seems to be working out well.&quot; (RTM-01) <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>17 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>appraisal was not considered appropriate because the development <lb/>approach taken during the study meant that any economic <lb/>appraisal was not likely to reflect real-world roll-out. In the <lb/>future we would advocate for greater scaling-out to include a <lb/>larger sample and an economic appraisal. <lb/>9.3 Recruitment and retention <lb/>The impacts of the restrictions placed on the people, <lb/>organisations, and communities involved in this research due to <lb/>COVID-19 were extensive and wide-ranging. The per-<lb/>implementation phase of the research began in January of 2020 <lb/>with the recruitment of an implementation team and participant <lb/>recruitment was due to begin in April 2020. Following the <lb/>outbreak of COVID-19 in the UK, recruitment was stopped from <lb/>16 March 2020 to 1 October 2020. By June 2020, a decision was <lb/>made to fully move to remote delivery of the coaching <lb/>intervention using video conferencing services. <lb/>Research recruitment and retention were near constant <lb/>challenges, and all activities were significantly impacted by the <lb/>Covid restrictions. We believe that the use of the INTERHEART <lb/>tool, presented on the REDCap platform, acted as a barrier to <lb/>recruitment as evidenced through the follow sources: (1) Over 650 <lb/>participants attempted to begin the screening questionnaire and <lb/>our records show those who did not complete it stopped towards <lb/>the beginning or mid-way through the questions, particularly <lb/>when they were asked to measure their waist/hip circumference, <lb/>(2) of the 380 participants who completed the survey only <lb/>approximately 100 were eligible for the intervention meaning we <lb/>were selecting from a very limited pool of participants, (3) many <lb/>of the participants in the per implementation interviews <lb/>mentioned finding the screening tool to be &quot;clunky&quot; or &quot;annoying&quot; <lb/>to use. Its overly &quot;medical&quot; focus, as a basis for lifestyle <lb/>discussions may not have been engaging for the target audience. <lb/>Our initial recruitment strategy was to rely heavily on our VCSE <lb/>partners to act as gatekeepers for recruitment, a practice commonly <lb/>seen in participatory research methods (66). Whilst the VCSE <lb/>partners were adept in the recruitment and management of <lb/>CHWs and in the development of practices and policies, they did <lb/>not seem to have the reach or access for the recruitment of large <lb/>numbers of potential participants. Our experience aligns with that <lb/>of Williams (67), who states that VCSE and end users&apos; <lb/>relationships are often smaller in number but deep, based on trust <lb/>and protection, and covered by a range of risk related policies. <lb/>Instead, we relied heavily on the use of paid for social media <lb/>adverts for recruitment due to our ethics restrictions. Much like <lb/>the experience of other researchers who used these tools, we found <lb/>that they were low cost and reached large numbers of people but <lb/>engagement with the screening and risk profiling and participant <lb/>recruitment was low (68). In future studies, it may be more <lb/>suitable to use social media as an adjunct to mixed recruitment <lb/>strategies which make use of community outreach, primary care <lb/>recruitment, and media outreach (69, 70). <lb/>The study sample was heavily skewed towards middle-aged <lb/>females and much of the sample was not considered to be from <lb/>vulnerable or low socio-economic groups. Furthermore, males are <lb/>under-represented in both the risk profiling and intervention <lb/>samples which represents a divergence with our planned <lb/>recruitment targets in which we aimed for a more representative <lb/>sample. The difficulties in recruiting men and vulnerable and other <lb/>&quot;seldom heard&quot; populations to life style interventions are well-<lb/>recognised (71, 72). Recommended strategies to improve male <lb/>participation in community-based interventions include engaging <lb/>with male-friendly spaces, workplace-based interventions, and <lb/>incorporating activity-based programming, social-support, and <lb/>group activities (73, 74). Some of these elements were suggested <lb/>during the planning phase of SPICES but were not feasible due to <lb/>COVID restrictions (30). <lb/>9.4 Project infrastructure <lb/>We made the key decision to bring VCSE organisations into the <lb/>research team with paid roles to foster stronger community/research <lb/>partnerships as promoted by CBPR researchers (75) and the NHS&apos;s <lb/>PPIE (Public and Patient Involvement and Engagement) initiatives <lb/>(76). Our research shows that the VCSE sector is an untapped <lb/>resource within primary and community care that has a great deal <lb/>of expertise, compassion, and enthusiasm to offer health provision <lb/>(77). To facilitate this community-based project, we focused on the <lb/>concept of trust building throughout the intervention as described <lb/>by Christopher et al. (78). <lb/>VCSE partnerships brought knowledge and expertise of their <lb/>local communities, policies/practices of volunteer management and, <lb/>critically, perspectives of the motivations and drivers for CHWs <lb/>and communities. CHWs were empowered to bring their own <lb/>skills and abilities to the intervention through an asset based and <lb/>flexible project development which included them in the co-design <lb/>of the project (79). The strategies we used to implement the <lb/>interventions were not prescriptive and did not force CHWs to <lb/>follow a set of strict guidelines. This led to a highly personalised, <lb/>flexible, and reflective experience for CHWs. However, our <lb/>experience highlights potential problems with relying on unpaid <lb/>volunteers to deliver complex interventions, including issues with <lb/>volunteer commitment, attendance and drop out. <lb/>Our research highlights the importance of infrastructure when <lb/>managing CHWs and partnering with VCSE sector organisations. <lb/>We developed a bespoke behaviour change training course for <lb/>CHWs, a range of CHW risk appraisal and mitigation policies <lb/>with our VCSE partners, and a dedicated team of participant and <lb/>CHW support and management coordinators. Clear protocols <lb/>were developed and followed for the recruitment, onboarding, <lb/>matching, and hosting of participant coaching sessions whilst <lb/>CHWs were provided with multiple channels of regular <lb/>communication and continuous training and feedback <lb/>opportunities. We support calls for project managers, VCSEs, <lb/>primary care providers, and community members to be more <lb/>explicitly involved in the design and development of <lb/>interventions which affect and include communities (80). <lb/>In this study, the research team also experienced issues of <lb/>positionality throughout the project whereby the lines between <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

	  	<page>18 <lb/></page>

	  	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<body>implementor, community worker, and evaluator were blurred. <lb/>Coulter et al. (81) have pointed out that research that includes <lb/>CHWs in the design and delivery of interventions commonly <lb/>experience a tension between fidelity of the intervention protocol <lb/>and community expectations, needs, and norms. We also <lb/>experienced differing goals between academic and community <lb/>partners (including CHWs), where academic partners prioritized <lb/>data collection and community partners prioritized funding, <lb/>sustainability, and policy. This can be likened to the experience <lb/>of Furman et al. (82) who discussed how community partners <lb/>were hesitant to endorse their research due to conflicts with on-<lb/>the-ground realities of the community members they served. <lb/>9.5 Recommendations <lb/>During this project the research team, VCSE partners, and <lb/>CHWs constantly learnt lessons and were quick to make <lb/>adaptations to their approach based on feedback from a range of <lb/>stakeholders and capturing all of these in this paper would be an <lb/>impossible task. However, several key insights can be drawn from <lb/>our collective experience and evaluation of the project. They include: <lb/>1. Environmental issues are larger and more complex than any <lb/>coaching intervention based on individualistic changes can <lb/>hope to remedy. <lb/>2. The voluntary and community sector has a range of strengths <lb/>and assets based on local experience and knowledge <lb/>developed over significant periods of time that can be used <lb/>for CVD prevention. However, the sector is highly under-<lb/>resourced and spread thinly across a wide range of priorities. <lb/>Individual VCSE partner organisations do not always have <lb/>enough reach to facilitate recruitment. <lb/>3. Community engagement works best if it is built into a project <lb/>early on through co-design and resources and time should be <lb/>allocated to this activity. <lb/>4. CHWs bring significant advantages during the delivery of <lb/>community-based interventions. They are trusted peers, they <lb/>bring their own skills and experience, and they can benefit <lb/>from the intervention alongside the participants. <lb/>5. Strategies to encourage the participation of men should be <lb/>specifically considered during the planning phase. <lb/>6. Virtual coaching interventions are acceptable to participants, <lb/>and in many cases preferable to participants, due to their <lb/>flexibility and ease of use. <lb/>7. The issue of mental health must be addressed even when <lb/>working with unrelated health public conditions. <lb/>8. A strong project infrastructure, made up of well-trained <lb/>support/administrative staff, is essential when delivering <lb/>community-based interventions. <lb/>9. CHWs should be paid or reimbursed for their involvement in <lb/>research and public health interventions. Falling to do so is <lb/>looked down on my stakeholders and has impacts on <lb/>sustainability and effectiveness. <lb/>10. The Global North can look to innovations in the Global <lb/>South for examples of success for community-based <lb/>interventions, however, proper contextual or situational <lb/>analyses must be conducted to understand the needs and <lb/>priorities of target communities. <lb/>9.6 Conclusion <lb/>This study demonstrates the feasibility of a CHW-led <lb/>preventative health interventions could be implemented with <lb/>overseen and unheard communities in the UK. It highlights the <lb/>wealth of untapped resources that exist with VCSE and CHWs <lb/>and suggests how a beneficial community-based service could be <lb/>set up to run alongside and support NHS Health Checks, to <lb/>reduce the incidence of CVD. The aim was to empower CHWs <lb/>to discuss health with people in their communities based on <lb/>behaviour change principles. We have set out what worked well <lb/>and what did not, to facilitate development of future community-<lb/>based interventions in the Global North. We believe that the <lb/>community-based approach need not be restricted to CVD risk <lb/>reduction, and that it could easily be applied to low level mental <lb/>health conditions, diabetes, or other preventable NCDs. If CHWs <lb/>are confident, well supported, and well-trained, they will have the <lb/>skills and ability to contribute to improving the health and <lb/>wellbeing of people in their communities. The benefits do not <lb/>only extend to patients but also to CHWs and to the VCSE <lb/>partners involved. We believe our project shows how these <lb/>interventions can become a supplementary tool that links <lb/>primary care services with the VCSE sector. <lb/></body>

		<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The datasets presented in this study can be found in the <lb/>University of Sussex&apos;s data repository through the following link: <lb/>https://sussex.figshare.com/; (doi: 10.25377/sussex.25569084). <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by Brighton and <lb/>Sussex Medical School Research Governance and Ethics <lb/>Committee (RGEC). The studies were conducted in accordance <lb/>with the local legislation and institutional requirements. The <lb/>participants provided their written informed consent to <lb/>participate in this study. <lb/></div>

		<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>First Author (First Authorship): Thomas Grice-Jackson Second <lb/>Authors (Equal Contribution): Imogen Rogers, Elizabeth Ford, <lb/>Robert Dickson Third Authors (Equal Contribution): Kat-Frere <lb/>Smith, Katie Goddard, Linda Silver, Catherine Topham Fourth <lb/>Author (Equal Contribution): Papreen Nahar, Geofrey <lb/>Musinguzi, Hilde Bastiens. Senior Author (Senior Authorship): <lb/></div>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

	  	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

	  	<page>19 <lb/></page>

	  	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<div type="contribution">Harm Van Marwijk. All authors contributed to the article and <lb/>approved the submitted version. <lb/></div>

		<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This project was funded as part of an EU Commission <lb/>Horizon. CORDIS (The Community Research and Development <lb/>Information Service (CORDIS) Grant agreement number: 733356. <lb/></div>

		<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the following voluntary and community sector <lb/>organisations for their partnerships whilst designing and <lb/>delivering this project: Active Hastings, Wellsbourne <lb/>Healthcare Community Interest Company, Sussex Community <lb/>Development Association, the Crew Club, and the Hangleton <lb/>and Knoll project. We thank the National Centre for <lb/>Behaviour Change for their contribution to the development <lb/>and delivery of the Community Health Workers training. We <lb/>thank all members of the SPICES consortium and European <lb/>Commission who provide consultation and advice throughout <lb/>the project. Finally, we thank all our Community Health <lb/>Workers for giving up their time for this project. They were <lb/>central to every part of this work and their contribution is <lb/>greatly appreciated. We would also like to thank the editorial <lb/>and reviewer team assigned to this manuscript. Their <lb/>contributions improved the quality of our manuscript <lb/>presentation, structure, and discussion. <lb/></div>

		<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed <lb/>or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found <lb/>online at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/frhs.2024. <lb/>1152410/full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

		<listBibl>References <lb/>1. World Health Organisation. Cardiovascular Diseases Fact Sheet. (2022) (cited <lb/>Nov 7, 2022). Cardiovascular diseases Fact Sheet. Available online at: https://www. <lb/>who.int/health-topics/cardiovascular-diseases#tab=tab_1 <lb/>2. Matsushita K, Ding N, Kou M, Hu X, Chen M, Gao Y, et al. The relationship <lb/>of COVID-19 severity with cardiovascular disease and its traditional risk factors: <lb/>a systematic review and meta-analysis. Glob Heart. (2020) 15(1). doi: 10.5334/gh.814 <lb/>3. National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. Prevention of Cardiovascular <lb/>disease (PH25)-Review Proposal (2014). <lb/>4. Marsh K, Phillips CJ, Fordham R, Bertranou E, Hale J. Estimating cost-<lb/>effectiveness in public health: a summary of modelling and valuation methods. <lb/>Health Econ Rev. (2012) 2(1):1-6. doi: 10.1186/2191-1991-2-17 <lb/>5. Brush BL, Mentz G, Jensen M, Jacobs B, Saylor KM, Rowe Z, et al. Success in <lb/>long-standing community-based participatory research (CBPR) partnerships: a <lb/>scoping literature review. Health Educ Behav. (2020) 47(4):556-68. doi: 10.1177/ <lb/>1090198119882989 <lb/>6. Bogart LM, Uyeda K. Community-based participatory research: partnering with <lb/>communities for effective and sustainable behavioral health interventions. Health <lb/>Psychol. (2009) 28(4):391-3. doi: 10.1037/a0016387 <lb/>7. Thomas P. Collaborating for Health. London: Routledge (2017). <lb/>8. Hassen HY, Bowyer M, Gibson L, Abrams S, Bastiaens H. Level of cardiovascular <lb/>disease knowledge, risk perception and intention towards healthy lifestyle and <lb/>socioeconomic disparities among adults in vulnerable communities of Belgium and <lb/>England. BMC Public Health. (2022) 22(1):1-9. doi: 10.1186/s12889-021-12274-7 <lb/>9. Hassen HY, Ndejjo R, Musinguzi G, Van Geertruyden JP, Abrams S, Bastiaens H. <lb/>Effectiveness of community-based cardiovascular disease prevention interventions to <lb/>improve physical activity: a systematic review and meta-regression. Prev Med. <lb/>(2021) 153:106797. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2021.106797 <lb/>10. Robson J, Dostal I, Sheikh A, Eldridge S, Madurasinghe V, Griffiths C, et al. The <lb/>NHS health check in England: an evaluation of the first 4 years. BMJ Open. (2016) 6 <lb/>(1):e008840. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-008840 <lb/>11. Office for Improvement and Disapities, UK Government. NHS Health Checks: <lb/>Applying All Our Health. (2022). Available online at: https://www.gov.uk/government/ <lb/>publications/nhs-health-checks-applying-all-our-health/nhs-health-checks-applying-all-<lb/>our-health (Accessed January 25, 2023). <lb/>12. Martin A, Saunders CL, Harte E, Griffin SJ, MacLure C, Mant J, et al. Delivery <lb/>and impact of the NHS health check in the first 8 years: a systematic review. Br J Gen <lb/>Pract. (2018) 68(672):e449-59. doi: 10.3399/bjgp18X697649 <lb/>13. Tanner L, Kenny RPW, Still M, Ling J, Pearson F, Thompson K, et al. NHS <lb/>health check programme: a rapid review update. BMJ Open. (2022) 12(2):e052832. <lb/>doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-052832 <lb/>14. Agarwal S, Jakes S, Essex S, Page SJ, Mowforth M. Disadvantage in English <lb/>seaside resorts: a typology of deprived neighbourhoods. Tour Manag. (2018) <lb/>69:440-59. doi: 10.1016/j.tourman.2018.06.012 <lb/>15. UK Chief Medical Officer. Health in Coastal Communities. UK Chief Medical <lb/>Officer; (2021). p. 259. <lb/>16. Cyril S, Smith BJ, Possamai-Inesedy A, Renzaho AM. Exploring the role of <lb/>community engagement in improving the health of disadvantaged populations: a <lb/>systematic review. Glob Health Action. (2015) 8(1):29842. doi: 10.3402/gha.v8.29842 <lb/>17. Ndejjo R, Hassen HY, Wanyenze RK, Musoke D, Nuwaha F, Abrams S, et al. <lb/>Community-based interventions for cardiovascular disease prevention in low-and <lb/>middle-income countries: a systematic review. Public Health Rev. (2021) 42. doi: 10. <lb/>3389/phrs.2021.1604018 <lb/>18. Khetan AK, Purushothaman R, Chami T, Hejjaji V, Mohan SKM, Josephson RA, <lb/>et al. The effectiveness of community health workers for CVD prevention in LMIC. <lb/>Glob Heart. (2017) 12(3):233-243. 6. doi: 10.1016/j.gheart.2016.07.001 <lb/>19. Joshi R, Peiris D. Task-sharing for the prevention and control of non-<lb/>communicable diseases. Lancet Glob Health. (2019) 7(6):e686-7. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>S2214-109X(19)30161-5 <lb/>20. Adams C. Toward an institutional perspective on social capital health <lb/>interventions: lay community health workers as social capital builders. Sociol Health <lb/>Illn. (2020) 42(1):95-110. doi: 10.1111/1467-9566.12992 <lb/>21. Van Velsen L, Illario M, Jansen-Kosterink S, Crola C, Di Somma C, Colao A, <lb/>et al. A community-based, technology-supported health service for detecting and <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>20 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>preventing frailty among older adults: a participatory design development process. <lb/>J Aging Res. (2015) 2015:9-18. doi: 10.1155/2015/216084 <lb/>22. Michie S, Abraham C, Whittington C, McAteer J, Gupta S. Effective techniques <lb/>in healthy eating and physical activity interventions: a meta-regression. Health Psychol. <lb/>(2009) 28(6):690. doi: 10.1037/a0016136 <lb/>23. Yardley L, Morrison L, Bradbury K, Muller I. The person-based approach to <lb/>intervention development: application to digital health-related behavior change <lb/>interventions. J Med Internet Res. (2015) 17(1):e4055. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4055 <lb/>24. Person-Based Approach. The Person-Based Approach For Developing Health <lb/>Interventions. (2022). Available online at: https://www.personbasedapproach.org/ <lb/>#:∼:text=What%20is%20the%20Person%2DBased,and%20experiences%20of% <lb/>20intervention%20users (Accessed January 25, 2023). <lb/>25. Hopkins T, Rippon S. Head, Hands and Heart: Asset-Based Approaches in <lb/>Health Care. London: Health Foundations (2015). <lb/>26. Barrera M, Castro FG, Strycker LA, Toobert DJ. Cultural adaptations of <lb/>behavioral health interventions: a progress report. J Consult Clin Psychol. (2013) 81 <lb/>(2):196-205. doi: 10.1037/a0027085 <lb/>27. Moore GF, Audrey S, Barker M, Bond L, Bonell C, Hardeman W, et al.. process <lb/>evaluation of complex interventions: medical research council guidance. Br Med J. <lb/>(2015) 350. doi: 10.1136/bmj.h1258 <lb/>28. Brown A, Ramsay N, Milo M, Moore M, Hossain R. How research-based theatre <lb/>is a solution for community engagement and advocacy at regional medical campuses: <lb/>the health and equity through advocacy, research, and theatre (HEART) program. Can <lb/>Med Educ J. (2018) 9(1):e6. doi: 10.36834/cmej.42191 <lb/>29. Nahar P, Van Marwijk H, Gibson L, Musinguzi G, Anthierens S, Ford E, et al. A <lb/>protocol paper: community engagement interventions for cardiovascular disease <lb/>prevention in socially disadvantaged populations in the UK: an implementation <lb/>research study. Glob Health Res Policy. (2020) 5:1-9. doi: 10.1186/s41256-020-0131-1 <lb/>30. Grice-Jackson T, Rogers I, Ford E, Van Marwijk H, Topham C, Musinguzi G, <lb/>et al. The pre-implementation phase of a project seeking to deliver a community-<lb/>based CVD prevention intervention (SPICES-Sussex): a qualitative study exploring <lb/>views and experience relating to intervention development. Health Promot Pract. <lb/>(2023):15248399231182139. doi: 10.1177/15248399231182139 <lb/>31. Glasgow RE, McKay HG, Piette JD, Reynolds KD. The RE-AIM framework for <lb/>evaluating interventions: what can it tell us about approaches to chronic illness <lb/>management? Patient Educ Couns. (2001) 44(2):119-27. doi: 10.1016/S0738-3991 <lb/>(00)00186-5 <lb/>32. Skivington K, Matthews L, Simpson SA, Craig P, Baird J, Blazeby JM, et al.. A <lb/>new framework for developing and evaluating complex interventions: update of <lb/>medical research council guidance. Br Med J. (2021) 374:1-11. doi: 10.1136/bmj.n2061 <lb/>33. Ministry of Housing, Communities &amp; Local Government UK Government. <lb/>English Indices of Deprivation 2019. (2019) (cited Nov 7, 2022). Available online <lb/>at: https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/english-indices-of-deprivation-2019 <lb/>34. Palmer VJ. The participatory zeitgeist in health care: it is time for a science of <lb/>participation. J Particip Med. (2020) 12(1):e15101. doi: 10.2196/15101 <lb/>35. McGorrian C, Yusuf S, Islam S, Jung H, Rangarajan S, Avezum A, et al. <lb/>Estimating modifiable coronary heart disease risk in multiple regions of the world: <lb/>the INTERHEART modifiable risk score. Eur Heart J. (2011) 32(5):581-9. doi: 10. <lb/>1093/eurheartj/ehq448 <lb/>36. Harris PA, Taylor R, Minor BL, Elliott V, Fernandez M, O&apos;Neal L, et al. The <lb/>REDCap consortium: building an international community of software platform <lb/>partners. J Biomed Inform. (2019) 95:103208. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208 <lb/>37. Piepoli MF, Hoes AW, Agewall S, Albus C, Brotons C, Catapano AL, et al. <lb/>Guidelines: editor&apos;s choice: 2016 European guidelines on cardiovascular disease <lb/>prevention in clinical practice: the sixth joint task force of the European society of <lb/>cardiology and other societies on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical <lb/>practice (constituted by representatives of 10 societies and by invited experts) <lb/>developed with the special contribution of the European association for <lb/>cardiovascular prevention &amp; rehabilitation (EACPR). Eur Heart J. (2016) 37 <lb/>(29):2315. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehw106 <lb/>38. Levounis P, Arnaout B, Marienfeld C. Motivational interviewing for clinical <lb/>practice. Arlington: American Psychiatric Association Publishing (2017). p. 15-35. <lb/>39. Miller WR, Rollnick S. Motivational Interviewing: Helping People Change. New <lb/>York: Guilford press (2012). <lb/>40. Harden SM, Smith ML, Ory MG, Smith-Ray RL, Estabrooks PA, Glasgow RE. <lb/>RE-AIM in clinical, community, and corporate settings: perspectives, strategies, and <lb/>recommendations to enhance public health impact. Front Public Health. (2018) <lb/>6:71. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2018.00071 <lb/>41. Kwan BM, McGinnes HL, Ory MG, Estabrooks PA, Waxmonsky JA, Glasgow <lb/>RE. RE-AIM in the real world: use of the RE-AIM framework for program <lb/>planning and evaluation in clinical and community settings. Front Public Health. <lb/>(2019) 7:345. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2019.00345 <lb/>42. Glasgow RE, Askew S, Purcell P, Levine E, Warner ET, Stange KC, et al. Use of <lb/>RE-AIM to address health inequities: application in a low-income community health <lb/>center-based weight loss and hypertension self-management program. Transl Behav <lb/>Med. (2013) 3(2):200-10. doi: 10.1007/s13142-013-0201-8 <lb/>43. Onono M, Abdi M, Opondo I, Okung&apos;u J, Asadhi E, Nyamai R, et al. Using <lb/>the RE-AIM framework to evaluate the implementation of integrated community <lb/>case management in Kenya. Acta Paediatr. (2018) 107:53-62. doi: 10.1111/apa. <lb/>14662 <lb/>44. Wippold GM, Garcia KA, Frary SG, Griffith DM. Community health worker <lb/>interventions for men: a scoping review using the RE-AIM framework. Health Educ <lb/>Behav. (2023) 51(1):10901981231179498. doi: 10.1177/1090198123117949 <lb/>45. Hagströmer M, Oja P, Sjöström M. The international physical activity <lb/>questionnaire (IPAQ): a study of concurrent and construct validity. Public Health <lb/>Nutr. (2006) 9(6):755-62. doi: 10.1079/PHN2005898 <lb/>46. England CY, Thompson JL, Jago R, Cooper AR, Andrews RC. Development of a <lb/>brief, reliable and valid diet assessment tool for impaired glucose tolerance and <lb/>diabetes: the UK diabetes and diet questionnaire. Public Health Nutr. (2017) 20 <lb/>(2):191-9. doi: 10.1017/S1368980016002275 <lb/>47. Musinguzi LK, Turinawe EB, Rwemisisi JT, de Vries DH, Mafigiri DK, Muhangi <lb/>D, et al. Linking communities to formal health care providers through village health <lb/>teams in rural Uganda: lessons from linking social capital. Hum Resour Health. <lb/>(2017) 15:1-16. doi: 10.1186/s12960-016-0177-9 <lb/>48. Katz E, Chikwenhere Y, Essien E, Olirus Owilli A, Westerhaus M. Rethinking <lb/>global health from south and north: a social medicine approach to global health <lb/>education. Glob Public Health. (2023) 18(1):2191685. doi: 10.1080/17441692.2023. <lb/>2191685 <lb/>49. Anand TN, Joseph LM, Geetha AV, Chowdhury J, Prabhakaran D, Jeemon P. <lb/>Task-sharing interventions for cardiovascular risk reduction and lipid outcomes in <lb/>low-and middle-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin <lb/>Lipidol. (2018) 12(3):626-42. doi: 10.1016/j.jacl.2018.02.008 <lb/>50. Ndejjo R, Wanyenze RK, Nuwaha F, Bastiaens H, Musinguzi G. Barriers and <lb/>facilitators of implementation of a community cardiovascular disease prevention <lb/>programme in Mukono and Buikwe districts in Uganda using the consolidated <lb/>framework for implementation research. Implement Sci. (2020) 15:1-17. doi: 10. <lb/>1186/s13012-020-01065-0 <lb/>51. Haines A, de Barros EF, Berlin A, Heymann DL, Harris MJ. National UK <lb/>programme of community health workers for COVID-19 response. Lancet. (2020) <lb/>395(10231):1173-5. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30735-2 <lb/>52. Ballard M, Odera M, Bhatt S, Geoffrey B, Westgate C, Johnson A. Payment of <lb/>community health workers. Lancet Glob Health. (2022) 10(9):e1242. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>S2214-109X(22)00311-4 <lb/>53. Hanson K, Brikci N, Erlangga D, Alebachew A, De Allegri M, Balabanova D, <lb/>et al. The lancet global health commission on financing primary health care: <lb/>putting people at the centre. Lancet Glob Health. (2022) 10(5):e715-72. doi: 10. <lb/>1016/S2214-109X(22)00005-5 <lb/>54. NIHR. UK Standards for Public Involvement. (2024) (cited Jan 9, 2024). <lb/>Available online at: https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/pi-standards/home <lb/>55. Schmid TL, Pratt M, Howze E. Policy as intervention: environmental and policy <lb/>approaches to the prevention of cardiovascular disease. Am J Public Health. (1995) 85 <lb/>(9):1207-11. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.85.9.1207 <lb/>56. Tengland PA. Behavior change or empowerment: on the ethics of health-<lb/>promotion goals. Health Care Anal. (2016) 24(1):24-46. doi: 10.1007/s10728-013-<lb/>0265-0 <lb/>57. Pennant M, Davenport C, Bayliss S, Greenheld W, Marshall T, Hyde C. <lb/>Community programs for the prevention of cardiovascular disease: a systematic <lb/>review. Am J Epidemiol. (2010) 172(5):501-16. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwq171 <lb/>58. Le Goff D, Barais M, Perraud G, Derriennic J, Aujoulat P, Guillou-Landreat M, <lb/>et al. Innovative cardiovascular primary prevention population-based strategies: a 2-<lb/>year hybrid type 1 implementation randomised control trial (RCT) which evaluates <lb/>behavioural change conducted by community champions compared with brief <lb/>advice only from the SPICES project (scaling-up packages of interventions for <lb/>cardiovascular disease prevention in selected sites in Europe and sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa). BMC Public Health. (2021) 21(1):1-9. doi: 10.1186/s12889-021-11443-y <lb/>59. Aerts N, Anthierens S, Van Bogaert P, Peremans L, Bastiaens H. Prevention of <lb/>cardiovascular diseases in community settings and primary health care: a Pre-<lb/>implementation contextual analysis using the consolidated framework for <lb/>implementation research. Int J Environ Res Public Health. (2022) 19(14):8467. <lb/>doi: 10.3390/ijerph19148467 <lb/>60. Collyer TA, Smith KE. An atlas of health inequalities and health disparities <lb/>research:&quot;how is this all getting done in silos, and why?&quot;. Soc Sci Med. (2020) <lb/>264:113330. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113330 <lb/>61. Van Velsen L, Wentzel J, Van Gemert-Pijnen JE. Designing eHealth that matters <lb/>via a multidisciplinary requirements development approach. JMIR Res Protoc. (2013) 2 <lb/>(1):e2547. doi: 10.2196/resprot.2547 <lb/>62. Haldane V, Chuah FL, Srivastava A, Singh SR, Koh GC, Seng CK, et al. <lb/>Community participation in health services development, implementation, and <lb/>evaluation: a systematic review of empowerment, health, community, and process <lb/>outcomes. PLoS One. (2019) 14(5):e0216112. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0216112 <lb/>63. Wildman JM, Valtorta N, Moffatt S, Hanratty B. &apos;What works here doesn&apos;t work <lb/>there&apos;: the significance of local context for a sustainable and replicable asset-based <lb/>Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/>Frontiers in Health Services <lb/>21 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>community intervention aimed at promoting social interaction in later life. Health Soc <lb/>Care Community. (2019) 27(4):1102-10. doi: 10.1111/hsc.12735 <lb/>64. Aarons GA, Sklar M, Mustanski B, Benbow N, Brown CH. &quot;Scaling-out&quot; <lb/>evidence-based interventions to new populations or new health care delivery <lb/>systems. Implement Sci. (2017) 12:1-13. doi: 10.1186/s13012-016-0533-0 <lb/>65. Luten KA, Reijneveld SA, Dijkstra A, de Winter AF. Reach and effectiveness of <lb/>an integrated community-based intervention on physical activity and healthy eating of <lb/>older adults in a socioeconomically disadvantaged community. Health Educ Res. <lb/>(2016) 31(1):98-106. doi: 10.1093/her/cyv064 <lb/>66. Goodman A, Gatward R. Who are we missing? Area deprivation and survey <lb/>participation. Eur J Epidemiol. (2008) 23(6):379-87. doi: 10.1007/s10654-008-9248-0 <lb/>67. Williams P. &quot;It all sounds very interesting, but we&apos;re just too busy!&quot;: exploring <lb/>why &quot;gatekeepers&quot; decline access to potential research participants with learning <lb/>disabilities. Eur J Spec Needs Educ. (2020) 35(1):1-14. doi: 10.1080/08856257.2019. <lb/>1687563 <lb/>68. McRobert CJ, Hill JC, Smale T, Hay EM, Van der Windt DA. A multi-modal <lb/>recruitment strategy using social media and internet-mediated methods to recruit a <lb/>multidisciplinary, international sample of clinicians to an online research study. <lb/>PLoS One. (2018) 13(7):e0200184. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0200184 <lb/>69. Khatri C, Chapman SJ, Glasbey J, Kelly M, Nepogodiev D, Bhangu A, et al. <lb/>Social media and internet driven study recruitment: evaluating a new model for <lb/>promoting collaborator engagement and participation. PloS one. (2015) 10(3): <lb/>e0118899. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0118899 <lb/>70. UyBico SJ, Pavel S, Gross CP. Recruiting vulnerable populations into research: a <lb/>systematic review of recruitment interventions. J Gen Intern Med. (2007) 22 <lb/>(6):852-63. doi: 10.1007/s11606-007-0126-3 <lb/>71. Shaghaghi A, Bhopal RS, Sheikh A. Approaches to recruiting &quot;hard-to-<lb/>reach&quot;populations into research: a review of the literature. Health Promot Perspect. <lb/>(2011) 1(2):86. doi: 10.5681/hpp.2011.009 <lb/>72. Pagoto SL, Schneider KL, Bodenlos JS, Appelhans BM, Whited MC, Ma Y, et al. <lb/>Association of post-traumatic stress disorder and obesity in a nationally representative <lb/>sample. Obesity. (2012) 20(1):200-5. doi: 10.1038/oby.2011.318 <lb/>73. Oliffe JL, Rossnagel E, Bottorff JL, Chambers SK, Caperchione C, Rice SM. <lb/>Community-based men&apos;s health promotion programs: eight lessons learnt and their <lb/>caveats. Health Promot Int. (2020) 35(5):1230-40. doi: 10.1093/heapro/daz101 <lb/>74. Bell OJ, Flynn D, Clifford T, West D, Stevenson E, Avery L. Identifying <lb/>behavioural barriers and facilitators to engaging men in a community-based lifestyle <lb/>intervention to improve physical and mental health and well-being. Int J Behav <lb/>Nutr Phys Act. (2023) 20(1):1-14. doi: 10.1186/s12966-022-01404-y <lb/>75. Springer MV, Skolarus LE. Community-based participatory research: partnering <lb/>with communities. Stroke. (2019) 50(3):e48-50. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.118.024241 <lb/>76. Holmes L, Cresswell K, Williams S, Parsons S, Keane A, Wilson C, et al. <lb/>Innovating public engagement and patient involvement through strategic <lb/>collaboration and practice. Res Involvement Engagem. (2019) 5(1):1-12. doi: 10. <lb/>1186/s40900-019-0160-4 <lb/>77. Ragsdell G. Voluntary sector organisations: untapped sources of lessons for <lb/>knowledge management. Proceedings of the International Conference on Intellectual <lb/>Capital, Knowledge Management &amp; Organizational Learning (2013). p. 349-55 <lb/>78. Christopher S, Watts V, McCormick AKHG, Young S. Building and maintaining <lb/>trust in a community-based participatory research partnership. Am J Public Health. <lb/>(2008) 98(8):1398-406. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2007.125757 <lb/>79. Bainbridge L, Lunt N. Place, strengths and assets: a case study of how local area <lb/>coordination is supporting individuals and families under conditions of austerity. Br <lb/>J Social Work. (2021) 51(4):1354-73. doi: 10.1093/bjsw/bcab041 <lb/>80. Di Maddaloni F, Davis K. Project manager&apos;s perception of the local <lb/>communities&apos; stakeholder in megaprojects. An empirical investigation in the UK. <lb/>Int J Proj Manag. (2018) 36(3):542-65. doi: 10.1016/j.ijproman.2017.11.003 <lb/>81. Coulter K, Ingram M, McClelland DJ, Lohr A. Positionality of community health <lb/>workers on health intervention research teams: a scoping review. Front Public Health. <lb/>(2020) 8:208. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2020.00208 <lb/>82. Furman L, Matthews L, Davis V, Killpack S, O&apos;Riordan MA. Breast for success: a <lb/>community-academic collaboration to increase breastfeeding among high-risk <lb/>mothers in Cleveland. Prog Community Health Partnersh. (2016) 10(3):341-53. <lb/>doi: 10.1353/cpr.2016.0041 <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Grice-Jackson et al. <lb/>10.3389/frhs.2024.1152410 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Health Services <lb/></note>

		<page>22 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org </note>


	</text>
</TEI>