<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T14:36:21.222Z">11/21/2025 2:36:21 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T14:36:09.768779Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T14:36:09.768779Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Open Access <lb/>IAHS2022 -Variability and change across space, time, extremes, and interfaces <lb/>Use of the HEC RAS model for the analysis of <lb/>exceptional floods in the Ouémé basin <lb/>Ernest Amoussou 1,2 , Félix Toundé Amoussou 2 , Aymar Yaovi Bossa 3 , Domiho Japhet Kodja 2 , Henri <lb/>Sourou Totin Vodounon 1,2 , Constant Houndénou 2 , Valérie Borrell Estupina 4 , Jean-Emmanuel Paturel 5 , <lb/>Gil Mahé 5 , Christophe Cudennec 6 , and Michel Boko 2 <lb/>1 Department of Geography and Regional Planning (DGAT), University of Parakou, Parakou, Benin <lb/>2 Laboratoire Pierre Pagney: Climate, Water, Ecosystem and Development (LACEEDE), <lb/>University of Abomey-Calavi, Abomey-Calavi, Benin <lb/>3 National Water Institute (INE), University of Abomey-Calavi, Abomey-Calavi, Benin <lb/>4 G-EAU, Univ. Montpellier, IRD, INRAE, Montpellier, France <lb/>5 Montpellier HydroSciences Laboratory, University of Montpellier 2, Montpellier, France <lb/>6 The Agro Institute Agrocampus Ouest, Rennes, France <lb/>Correspondence: Ernest Amoussou (ajernest@yahoo.fr) and Félix Toundé Amoussou <lb/>(felixamoussou96@gmail.com) <lb/>Received: 10 June 2022 -Revised: 16 November 2022 -Accepted: 14 March 202 -Published: 18 April 2024 <lb/>Abstract. The Ouémé River basin extends over almost half of Benin&apos;s territory, entirely located in a humid <lb/>tropical climate. This river system includes a deltaic zone (delta of the Ouémé) known for its high agricultural <lb/>potential and thus subject to a socio-economic development agenda. The Ouémé delta is facing recurrent floods <lb/>that maintain rural agricultural population into a retrograding crisis with significant damages such as losses of <lb/>properties. The objective of this study is to improve decision-making in the Ouémé basin through the simulation <lb/>of exceptional floods using the HEC-RAS model. <lb/>The HEC RAS model is a conceptual model, which works through mathematical and physical formulas to <lb/>implement environmental phenomena for forecasting, understanding and analysis purposes. The model inputs <lb/>used are basin GIS data, hydro-meteorological data, characteristics of existing hydraulic structures, etc. The <lb/>targeted outputs include 1D/2D/3D view plans with support of satellite images, tables, graphs and curves. It is <lb/>worth mentioning that the model provides outputs compatible with other tools, such as civil engineering (Civil <lb/>3D, Revit, Infraworks, etc.) and GIS, that help to expand the valorization fields. <lb/>The implementation of the model in the Ouémé basin has made it possible to note: (i) that the recurring <lb/>effect of losses and damages is justified by the settlement of the population on the river banks; (ii) that there <lb/>is an important agricultural production in areas of high flood risk; (iii) that depending on the occurrence of <lb/>the phenomenon, the flooded extent and the height of submersion remains variable, and more important for <lb/>extreme flooding; (iv) about 12.07 % occurrence of river flood against 13.24 % for flash flood at a return period <lb/>of 30 years. Moreover, it is very relevant to note that most of flood waters converge to the western part of the basin <lb/>(an area with a low risk of flooding, stretched over 63.68 km 2 ) and to the eastern part around the Damè-Wogon <lb/>depression (an area at high risk of flooding, stretched over 10.49 km 2 ). <lb/>Keywords. Flood risk; flood damage estimation; Ouémé River <lb/>Basin; HEC-RAS model; exceptional flood <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Water, at the heart of any sustainable development process, is <lb/>also a source of disasters for most human communities and <lb/>ecosystems. These disasters are increasing day by day, an ef-<lb/>fect of global warming that the planet is currently experienc-<lb/>ing. These hydroclimatic consequences result in exceptional <lb/></body>

    <front>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the International Association of Hydrological Sciences. <lb/></front>

    <page>142 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">E. Amoussou et al.: Exceptionnal floods on Ouémé bassin <lb/></note>

    <body>floods and extreme droughts (IPCC, 2007; Marengo and Es-<lb/>pinoza, 2015). A natural hazard for human society and its <lb/>ecosystem that is difficult to predict but can be anticipated to <lb/>mitigate economic, health and other losses (FAO, 2008; Shen <lb/>et al., 2007). Benin, a West African country is not spared, like <lb/>the most watered basins in the golf of guinea (Degan et al., <lb/>2019; Kodja, 2018; Mahé, 2006). However, Bonou district, <lb/>is very heavily watered during the monsoon period (Bani, <lb/>2006), experiences periodic exceptional flooding situations <lb/>which plunge a population with a low standard of living into <lb/>a very unpleasant state. Moreover, with this potential for sus-<lb/>tainable agricultural development and poverty reduction ac-<lb/>cording to the Millenium Municipality Project (PCM, 2015), <lb/>it is urgent to this end, a flood management plan to better <lb/>take advantage of these nationally recognized assets. It is in <lb/>this preventive clause that this research entitled, use of the <lb/>HEC RAS model for the analysis of exceptional floods in the <lb/>Ouémé basin in the Bonou district is organized. It will make <lb/>it possible to show the causes of the losses and damages; <lb/>and propose long-term preventive measures to minimize the <lb/>damage faced with the occurrence of exceptional floods in <lb/>the locality. <lb/>2 Methodology <lb/>2.1 Modeling exceptional floods <lb/>An exceptional flood is a phenomenon deemed to be rare and <lb/>of extreme intensity but whose occurrence is more or less un-<lb/>predictable on a temporal scale (FAO, 2008). It is often ac-<lb/>companied by such extraordinary damage when vulnerable <lb/>to a high intensity downpour (Amoussou et al., 2014). How-<lb/>ever, with modeling using physics, mathematics and com-<lb/>puter tools, it is possible to understand the causes and effects <lb/>of a phenomenon. Thus, the modeling of exceptional floods <lb/>on the district used statistical hydrology tools to determine <lb/>the exceptional events characterizing the district; because hy-<lb/>pothetically it is obvious that the extreme values are at the <lb/>origin of floods. The surface hydraulic modeling tool HEC <lb/>RAS is used to model the exceptional floods for different re-<lb/>turn periods, because it is likely that the extent of the flooded <lb/>areas is a function of the return period. The susceptibility of <lb/>losses and damages is assessed through mapping since land <lb/>use is a factor reacting to remarkable losses and damages <lb/>during floods. <lb/>2.2 Characterization of extreme events in Bonou district <lb/>Bonou district (Fig. 1) is located in the department of <lb/>Ouémé in the south-east of the Republic of Benin between <lb/>6°47 40 and 6°57 38 N of the Northern Latitude and be-<lb/>tween 2°23 70 and 2°35 01 E of East Longitude. <lb/>The average annual rainfall is 1121 mm. It is distributed <lb/>on: <lb/>Figure 1. Administrative map of the study area. <lb/>-two (02) rainy seasons from April to July and from <lb/>September to August when rain floods occur especially <lb/>from June to July. <lb/>-Two (02) dry seasons from December to March and <lb/>from July to August when a river flood is observed <lb/>by the overflow of the Ouémé River during the month <lb/>of September with the contribution of rainfall from the <lb/>North of the country (Totin et al., 2016). <lb/>Indeed, the characterization of the exceptional events of the <lb/>district will take into account the runoff aspect (river flood) <lb/>and the rainfall aspect (rain flood). The determination of <lb/>the peak flows of the Ouémé River and the estimation of <lb/>maximum rainfall are made following the statistical laws <lb/>of GEV (Generalized Extreme Values) including the Gum-<lb/>bel law (Gradex method) being the best suited in our region <lb/>(Lawin et al., 2011). Base on Gumbel equation <lb/>F (x) = e <lb/>(-e -(x-a) <lb/>b <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>and the Hazen formula <lb/>F (x Ri ) = <lb/>(R i -0.5) <lb/>N <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>the maximum daily rainfall and flow are estimated for re-<lb/>turn period of T = 2, 10 and 30 years (Table 1). It shows <lb/>that there is a 50 % chance each year of recording flows of <lb/>around 778.67 m 3 s -1 against once in thirty years (approx-<lb/>imately 3.33 %) for a flow of 1274.81 m 3 s -1 (respectively <lb/>114.74 mm of rainfall). <lb/>2.3 Modeling of extreme floods by HEC RAS at Bonou <lb/>The modeling of extreme floods by HEC RAS results in a <lb/>spatialized hydraulic implementation of the values obtained <lb/>by characterizing the extreme events observables in the dis-<lb/>trict. The output will map, analyze and assess flood risk. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">E. Amoussou et al.: Exceptionnal floods on Ouémé bassin <lb/></note>

    <page>143 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 1. Results of the estimation of flow and precipitation values <lb/>for the return period of 2, 10 and 30 years. <lb/>T (i years) <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>30 <lb/>F (i) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9667 <lb/>U (i) <lb/>0.367 <lb/>2.250 <lb/>3.384 <lb/>Q dmax (i) <lb/>778.65 m 3 s -1 1088.38 m 3 s -1 1274.81 m 3 s -1 <lb/>P dmax (i) <lb/>68.72 mm <lb/>97.28 mm <lb/>114.47 mm <lb/>Table 2. Land cover and manning coefficient. <lb/>Manning <lb/>Land Cover <lb/>coefficient <lb/>Tree cover areas <lb/>0.150 <lb/>Built up areas <lb/>0.028 <lb/>Cropland <lb/>0.030 <lb/>Shrubs cover areas <lb/>0.035 <lb/>(Source: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, HEC5, <lb/>Hydraulic Reference Manuel, CPD-69, 3-16 p., <lb/>2016). <lb/>Beyond the Digital Elevation Model (DEM, resolution = <lb/>30 m × 30 m) of the district, the estimated P dmax and Q dmax <lb/>values, the boundary conditions (precipitation = P dmax , up-<lb/>stream flow = Q dmax , downstream = normal depth), the <lb/>Manning coefficient (Table 2) according to land use, the hy-<lb/>draulic model is computed. <lb/>However, a study focused on the flood hydrograph of <lb/>the catastrophic year 2010 (GFDRR, 2011), like one of <lb/>the recent possible considerations. Indeed, the daily flows <lb/>of 2010 in Bonou shows an annual maximum fluctuating <lb/>around 1026 m 3 s -1 which remains well above the estimated <lb/>biennial flow (778.65 m 3 s -1 ), closer to the ten-year flow <lb/>(1088.38 m 3 s -1 ) and distant from the one in their thirties. <lb/>From this hydrograph, it has been shown that the bien-<lb/>nial flood lasts about 68 d and about 20 d for the ten-year and <lb/>thirty-year ones (Fig. 2). These daily intervals are considered <lb/>for the river simulation and a distributed hyetograph of the <lb/>P dmax value on 1 h for the rainfall. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Modeling <lb/>The results show us the following: <lb/>The compilation of observations from the results can be <lb/>summarized as follows (Tables 3, 4): <lb/>Ultimately, it is very remarkable that the waters are con-<lb/>centrated much further west of the river and upstream to the <lb/>east in the Damè-Wogon depression. <lb/>Figure 2. Stationarity of daily flows at the Bonou station in 2010 <lb/>(Source: DG-Eau, 2012). <lb/>Figure 3. River and rain flooding map (T = 2, 10 years). <lb/>3.2 Susceptibility of losses and damages in the district <lb/>Following the land cover map (ESA Sentinel 2A 2016), from <lb/>which the spatial distribution map of agglomerations and <lb/>crops in the district are extracted. From the latter, we were <lb/>able to highlight the relativity of the damage linked to ex-<lb/>treme floods. This leads to major conclusions such as: <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 <lb/>Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>144 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">E. Amoussou et al.: Exceptionnal floods on Ouémé bassin <lb/></note>

    <body>Table 3. Statistics on modeling results for River flood (Fig. S3 -River flood). <lb/>Type of flood <lb/>River flood <lb/>Return period <lb/>2 years <lb/>10 years <lb/>30 years <lb/>Flooded area (km 2 ) <lb/>10, 49 14, 17 (5, 67 %) 30, 18 (12, 07 %) <lb/>-overflow of water on both sides <lb/>of the Ouémé river but very <lb/>concentrated towards the west <lb/>Remarks <lb/>-very substantial overflow of the river <lb/>towards the Damè-Wogon <lb/>depression (9.7 km 2 ) to the east of the river. <lb/>-agglomeration and culture will be affected <lb/>Table 4. Statistics on modeling results for Rain flood (Fig. S3 -Rain flood). <lb/>Type of flood <lb/>Rain flood <lb/>Return period <lb/>2 years <lb/>10 years <lb/>30 years <lb/>Flooded area (km 2 ) 26, 39 (10, 55 %) 42, 23 (16, 89 %) 98, 10 <lb/>(39, 24 %) <lb/>-four (04) meters of water depth in the shallows <lb/>-affected infrastructure such as the main paved road linking Akpro-Misserete to Dasso <lb/>-the agglomerations and property of the localities of Ahouanzoumè, Damè-Wogon, <lb/>Remarks <lb/>Gnanhoui (Damè-Wogon district); Atchabita, Bonou center, Oué-Bossou <lb/>(district of Bonou); Agomahan, Dogba (district of Atchonsa); Affamè center, <lb/>Affamè Sota (district of Affamè); Abèokuta, Agbosognota, Hounviguè <lb/>(Hounviguè district) will be flooded. <lb/>-settlement of the population along the banks of the <lb/>Ouémé River, <lb/>-a preponderant domination of agricultural activities in <lb/>areas of recurrent flooding (western part of the river) <lb/>and depression (Damè-Wogon). <lb/>3.3 Delimitation of areas at risk of flooding <lb/>The compilation of the various results of the modeling of ex-<lb/>treme floods and the susceptibility of losses and damages <lb/>in the Bonou district makes it possible to generate a map <lb/>(Fig. 4) of the flood zone at different levels of flood risk. <lb/>Indeed, based on the water level and land uses, we dis-<lb/>tinguish mainly two zones; an unwatered area (104.32 km 2 ) <lb/>and an area at risk of flooding (145.68 km 2 ). However, we <lb/>can divide into three risks flooding levels (river and rain) in <lb/>the district, like: <lb/>-high risk (20.13 km 2 ): Ahouanzoumè, Asrossa and <lb/>Gnanhoui-zoumè, <lb/>-medium risk (63.68 km 2 ): Atchabita, Affamè centre, <lb/>Abèokuta, Avlankamè, Agbosota, Dogba, Ouvienou <lb/>and Oué-bossou. <lb/>-low risk (61.87 km 2 ): rest of the localities. Most crops <lb/>such as: maize, tomato, cassava, pepper, etc. are grown <lb/>in high and medium risk areas; a cause of losses <lb/>recorded during floods. <lb/>4 Proposal of territorial development solutions <lb/>Following these different results, some solutions have been <lb/>proposed in a territorial management context. Preventive <lb/>measures not vigorously studied, but serving as a front were <lb/>mentioned. <lb/>Base on those results, for human security and agricultural <lb/>production, we suggest: <lb/>4.1 a. better territorial occupation <lb/>-leave the middle riverbed, a natural water habitat, <lb/>-practice perennial or non-vulnerable crops to low prop-<lb/>agation wave floods in high-risk areas: palm groves, <lb/>teak, mahogany, etc. allowing the flood hydrograph to <lb/>be rolled downstream, <lb/>-Cultivate food crops in low-risk and unwatered areas. <lb/>4.2 b. artificial lake creation (Fig. 5) <lb/>A preliminary study has shown us that an artificial lake will <lb/>retain the excess water capable of flooding the population and <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">E. Amoussou et al.: Exceptionnal floods on Ouémé bassin <lb/></note>

    <page>145 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figure 4. Map of areas at risk of flooding in Bonou district (Source: <lb/>HEC RAS, modelisation, 2020; ESA, Sentinel 2A, 2016). <lb/>Figure 5. Results of an exceptional flood of T = 30 years of 1 d at <lb/>constant flow (Source: HEC RAS, modelisation, 2020; ESA, Sen-<lb/>tinel 2A, 2016). <lb/>crops. Well placed in the depression of Damé-wogon, it is <lb/>located upstream of the cultures of the district. A simulation <lb/>study confirms the effectiveness of its role of protection and <lb/>rolling of river flood waves. This is a clearing of a side of 5 m <lb/>in direct communication with the middle bed of the river. <lb/>We notice; <lb/>-A probable optimal protection of crops and agglomera-<lb/>tions for floods of <lb/>-T &lt;= 10 years <lb/>-a probable extension of the duration of the cropping sea-<lb/>sons during the recession by exploitation of the stored <lb/>water. <lb/>-a limitation of the storable volume in the cuvette for <lb/>T &gt;=10 years. <lb/>4.3 c. Modification of the section of the watercourse <lb/>The activity of dredging the section of the river will widen <lb/>and increase the draft. Therefore, increase the volume of wa-<lb/>ter to be evacuated from the district. <lb/>4.4 d. Installation of channel networks <lb/>To limit the damage linked to rain floods in the fields, net-<lb/>works of meshed channels and directly connected to the mid-<lb/>dle bed of the river can be envisaged. They will make it pos-<lb/>sible to evacuate the water from the fields to the dredging <lb/>river or vice versa. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>This work on the modeling of exceptional floods in Bonou <lb/>district is essentially based on the various tools and data from <lb/>the cartography, on hydroclimatic data and on the use of a <lb/>hydraulic model. The methodology is based on the use of <lb/>various sources of information, statistical analyses, cartogra-<lb/>phy and hydraulic modelling. It obviously made it possible <lb/>to understand that the extreme values of flow and rainfall are <lb/>at the origin of the floods. But specifically, it is the persis-<lb/>tence of fluctuations in these values over time that amplifies <lb/>this cause. <lb/>From this study, it is noted that the extent of the areas <lb/>flooded during a rainfall flooding exceeds the river flooding. <lb/>The extent of these zones decreases with the decrease of the <lb/>return period. This confirms the variation of floodplains ac-<lb/>cording to the type of flood and according to the duration of <lb/>occurrence. <lb/>The occupation of floodplains, the banks of the river and <lb/>the cultivation of crops in the plains are the main causes <lb/>that intensify the losses and damage observed during floods. <lb/>Hence, the occupation of the land is a factor at the base of the <lb/>losses and damages in the district. Moreover, the enhance-<lb/>ment of this work requires the establishment of guidelines to <lb/>manage floods. Among so many recommendations, we sug-<lb/>gest for the safety of goods and services: the transformation <lb/>into an artificial lake/temporary reservoir area, the plain of <lb/>Dame-wogon; to encourage the activity of extracting sand <lb/>from the bed of the Ouémé River and the establishment of <lb/>channel network systems. <lb/>However, the best way to stay safe from river flooding is <lb/>to settle in the eastern part of the river, far from the bank. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability. No data sets were used in this article. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions. Conducted this research: EA. Conceptu-<lb/>alization: EA, FTA, AYB, DJK and HSTV. Methodology and mod-<lb/>elling and data processing: EA, FTA, AYB, DJK, HSTV and CH. <lb/>Writing-Original Draft Preparation: EA, FTA, AYB, DJK, HSTV, <lb/>CH, J-EP and GM. Writing-Review and Editing: VBE, J-EP, GM, <lb/></div>

    <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 <lb/>Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>146 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">E. Amoussou et al.: Exceptionnal floods on Ouémé bassin <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">CC and MB. All authors have read and agreed to the published ver-<lb/>sion of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests. At least one of the (co-)authors is a guest <lb/>member of the editorial board of Proceedings of IAHS for the <lb/>special issue &quot;IAHS2022 -Hydrological sciences in the Anthro-<lb/>pocene: Variability and change across space, time, extremes, and <lb/>interfaces&quot;. The peer-review process was guided by an independent <lb/>editor, and the authors also have no other competing interests to <lb/>declare. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>Special issue statement. This article is part of the special issue <lb/>&quot;IAHS2022 -Hydrological sciences in the Anthropocene: Variabil-<lb/>ity and change across space, time, extremes, and interfaces&quot;. It is a <lb/>result of the XIth Scientific Assembly of the International Associ-<lb/>ation of Hydrological Sciences (IAHS 2022), Montpellier, France, <lb/>29 May-3 June 2022. <lb/>Review statement. This paper was edited by Salvatore Grimaldi <lb/>and reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>Amoussou, E., Camberlin, P., Totin Vodounon, S. H., Tramblay, Y., <lb/>Houndenou, C., Mahé, G., and Boko, M.: Evolution des précipi-<lb/>tations extrêmes dans le bassin-versant du Mono (Bénin -Togo) <lb/>en contexte de la variabilité et de changement climatique, in: Cli-<lb/>mat: Système &amp; Interactions 27éme Colloque de l&apos;Association <lb/>Internationale de Climatologie, Dijon, France, 331-337, ISBN <lb/>978-2-907696-20-3, 2014. <lb/>Bani, G.: Monographie de la commune de Bonou, Afrique conseil, <lb/>25 p., https://docplayer.fr/79623514-Monographie (last access: <lb/>March 2019), 2006. <lb/>Degan, B. A., Gbaguidi, V., Karambiri, H., Alamou, E., and Afouda, <lb/>A. A.: Impact de la variabilité climatique sur l&apos;évolution des <lb/>crues du fleuve Ouémé au Bénin de 1952 à 2011, EPAC/UAC, <lb/>Benin, 204 p., https://biblionumeric.epac-uac.org:9443/jspui/ <lb/>handle/123456789/2216 (last access: March 2019), 2019. <lb/>DG-Eau: Carte hydrogéologique du Bénin: Echelle 1: 500000, Rap-<lb/>port de recherche sur la carte hydrogéologique du Bénin, Min-<lb/>istère des Mines, de l&apos;Energie et de l&apos;Eau, République de Bénin, <lb/>2012. <lb/>FAO: Climate change and Food security: a Framework for Action, <lb/>Rome, conference de Bali, 78 p., https://www.fao.org/3/au035e/ <lb/>au035e.pdf (last access: March 2019), 2008. <lb/>Fatma, C. S. E.: Délimitation des zones inondables par l&apos;utilisation <lb/>combiné du logiciel HEC-RAS et HEC GEORAS cas du cen-<lb/>tre &quot;AIN Jemaa&quot;, Master Sciences et Techniques, 97 p., http: <lb/>//www.secheresse.info/spip.php?article72316 (last access: July <lb/>2019), 2013. <lb/>GFDRR: Rapport d&apos;Evaluation des Besoins Post Catastrophiques <lb/>liées à l&apos;inondation, Bénin, 75 p., https://www.gfdrr.org/sites/ <lb/>default/files/publication/pda-2011-benin-fr.pdf (last access: <lb/>March 2019), 2010. <lb/>HEC-RAS River Analysis System: 2D Modeling user&apos;s man-<lb/>ual, US Army Corps of Engineers, Institute for Water <lb/>Ressources Hydrologic Engineering Center, CPD-68A, <lb/>171 <lb/>p., <lb/>https://www.hec.usace.army.mil/software/hec-ras/ <lb/>documentation/HEC-RAS5.0UsersManual.pdf (last access: 25 <lb/>August 2019), 2016. <lb/>IPCC: Changements climatiques, rapport de synthèse, 103 p., <lb/>https://www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/ar4_syr_fr.pdf <lb/>(last access: April 2019), 2007. <lb/>Kodja, J. D.: Indicateurs des événements hydroclimatiques ex-<lb/>trêmes dans le bassin-versant de l&apos;Ouémé à l&apos;exutoire de Bonou <lb/>en Afrique de l&apos;Ouest, Thèse de Doctorat, Université de Mont-<lb/>pellier, 214 p., https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01869842 (last <lb/>access: July 2019), 2018. <lb/>Lawin, A. E., Afouda, A., and Lebel, T.: Analyse de la <lb/>variabilité du régime pluviométrique dans la région agri-<lb/>cole d&apos;Ina au Bénin, European Journal of Scientific <lb/>Rechearch, ISSN 1450-216 X Vol.50, No.3, 425-439, <lb/>https://www.scirp.org/(S(lz5mqp453edsnp55rrgjct55))/ <lb/>reference/referencespapers.aspx?referenceid=2107220 <lb/>(last <lb/>access: Febuary 2020), 2011. <lb/>Mahé, G.: Variabilité pluie-Débit en Afrique de l&apos;Ouest et Cen-<lb/>trale au 20éme siècle: changements hydroclimatiques, occu-<lb/>pation du sol et modélisation hydrologique, université des <lb/>Sciences et Techniques Montpellier, Ecole Doctorale 148 <lb/>Terre, Eau, Espace, 161 p., https://horizon.documentation.ird.fr/ <lb/>exl-doc/pleins_textes/divers11-03/010043107.pdf (last access: <lb/>January 2021), 2006. <lb/>Marengo, A. J. and Espinoza, J. C.: Extreme seasonal droughts and <lb/>floods in Amazonia: causes, trends and impacts, Int. J. Climatol., <lb/>36, 1033-1050, https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.4420, 2015. <lb/>Pomerleau, J.: Changements climatiques et sécurité en Afrique, <lb/>centre universitaire de formation en environnement, Université <lb/>de Sherbrooke, 99 p., https://savoirs.usherbrooke.ca/bitstream/ <lb/>handle/11143/7402/cufe_Pomerleau_essai97.pdf?sequence=1&amp; <lb/>isAllowed=y (last access: March 2018), 2009. <lb/>Projet Commune du Millénaire de Bonou pour un Développe-<lb/>ment Durable (PCM-Bonou), 92 p., https://bj.chm-<lb/>cbd.net/sites/bj/files/2022-09/Projet (last access: 14 May <lb/>2019), 2015. <lb/>Shen, C., Wang, WC., Hao, Z., and Gong, W.: Exceptional drought <lb/>events over eastern China during the last five centuries, Clim. <lb/>Change, 85, 453-471, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-007-9283-<lb/>y, 2007. <lb/>Totin, V. S., Amoussou, E., Odoulami, L., Boko, M., and Blivi, <lb/>B.: Seuils pluviométriques des niveaux de risques d&apos;inondation <lb/>dans le bassin de l&apos;Ouémé au Bénin, XXIXème colloque de <lb/>l&apos;Association de Climatologie, Lausanne -Besançon, 369-374, <lb/>http://www.climato.be/aic/colloques/LausanneBesancon <lb/>(last <lb/>access: 18 April 2019), 2016. <lb/>U.S. Army Corps of Engineers: HEC5, Hydraulic Refer-<lb/>ence Manuel, CPD-69, 3-16 p., https://www.hec.usace. <lb/>army.mil/software/hec-ras/documentation/HEC-RAS5. <lb/>0ReferenceManual.pdf (last access: 25 August 2019), 2016. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">Proc. IAHS, 385, 141-146, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/piahs-385-141-2024 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>