<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T16:13:20.577Z">11/21/2025 4:13:20 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T16:13:02.378137Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T16:13:02.378137Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Science Reports <lb/>Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake <lb/>Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria): revealed by the <lb/>Hipercorig drilling system and borehole logging <lb/>Marcel Ortler 1 , Achim Brauer 2,3 , Stefano C. Fabbri 4,5,6 , Jean Nicolas Haas 7 , Irka Hajdas 8 , <lb/>Kerstin Kowarik 9 , Jochem Kueck 10 , Hans Reschreiter 11 , and Michael Strasser 1 <lb/>1 Department of Geology, University of Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria <lb/>2 Institute of Geosciences, University Potsdam, Potsdam, Germany <lb/>3 Section Climate Dynamics and Landscape Evolution, GFZ German Research Centre for Geosciences, <lb/>Potsdam, Germany <lb/>4 Institute of Geological Sciences, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland <lb/>5 Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland <lb/>6 Institut des sciences de la mer de Rimouski (ISMER), Université du Québec à Rimouski, Rimouski, Canada <lb/>7 Department of Botany, University of Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria <lb/>8 Laboratory of Ion Beam Physics, ETH Zürich, Zurich, Switzerland <lb/>9 Austrian Archaeological Institute, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Vienna, Austria <lb/>10 Geomechanics and Scientific Drilling, GFZ German Research Centre for Geosciences, Potsdam, Germany <lb/>11 Prehistoric Department, Natural History Museum Vienna, Vienna, Austria <lb/>Correspondence: Marcel Ortler (marcel-luciano.ortler@uibk.ac.at) <lb/>Received: 24 May 2023 -Revised: 8 September 2023 -Accepted: 23 October 2023 -Published: 2 April 2024 <lb/>Abstract. The Hipercorig Hallstatt History (H 3 ) project aims to unravel the entire Late Glacial to Holocene <lb/>sedimentary succession recording past climate, environment, natural hazard impacts, human-environment in-<lb/>teractions, and prehistoric mining history. We successfully cored 51 m of the sedimentary succession of Lake <lb/>Hallstatt, revealing a high-resolution Late Pleistocene to Holocene sediment record, overcoming the previous <lb/>coring limit of 15.63 m (dated to ∼ 2.3 ka cal BP). The novel drilling platform Hipercorig allows the recovery <lb/>of undisturbed long cores and the acquisition of borehole logging data of deep lakes. The sedimentary record <lb/>is spliced to a composite core profile, and for the first time borehole logging data are linked to a core-log seis-<lb/>mic correlation of an intra-mountainous lake of the Eastern Alps. The recovered sequence consists of two major <lb/>lithostratigraphic units: (i) Unit 1 (Holocene, 0-41.7 m below lake floor) with 10 (up to 5.1 m thick) instantaneous <lb/>deposits and (ii) Unit 2 (Late Pleistocene, &gt; 41.7 m below lake floor). The Late Pleistocene sediments comprise <lb/>the Younger Dryas and the deepest recovered sediments likely date back to the Allerød interstadial. Within the <lb/>Holocene, six different periods are observed in the core and borehole logging data, showing distinct physical <lb/>property fluctuations and an overall increase in sedimentation rate upcore. Lake Hallstatt provides a unique pre-<lb/>historic archive, being located within the UNESCO World Heritage area Hallstatt-Dachstein/Salzkammergut, a <lb/>region with a rich history of human salt mining dating back to 3400 cal BP (Middle/Late Bronze Age) and one <lb/>of the oldest documented cultural landscapes worldwide. <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the IODP and the ICDP. <lb/></front>

	<page>2 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The aim of deep drilling in lakes is to recover a high-<lb/>resolution sedimentary stratigraphy to study past climate, en-<lb/>vironment, natural hazard impacts, and human-environment <lb/>interactions. Such lakes can help to improve our understand-<lb/>ing on a local, regional, and sometimes even global scale, <lb/>covering parts of the Quaternary (Litt et al., 2012; Wagner et <lb/>al., 2019) and beyond (Brigham-Grette et al., 2013). Bore-<lb/>hole logging data can help to reconstruct the lithostratigra-<lb/>phy, estimate the clay content, bridge sediment core gaps <lb/>for improved core-log depth correlation, and help to correct <lb/>for core compaction and expansion (Baumgarten et al., 2014, <lb/>2015; Jutzeler et al., 2014). The Hipercorig, a sediment cor-<lb/>ing system, was developed to overcome the financial and lo-<lb/>gistical burden of the usual long-core drilling campaigns. It <lb/>simplifies the coring technique to a degree that the recov-<lb/>ery of 100 m long sediment cores from deep lakes or shallow <lb/>marine environments is much more effective (Harms et al., <lb/>2020). So far, two lakes were cored during an initial test-<lb/>ing phase of the new system: Lake Constance (Germany-<lb/>Austria-Switzerland) with a water depth of up to 204 m and <lb/>87 % core recovery (Harms et al., 2020; Schaller et al., 2022) <lb/>and Mondsee (Austria) with a coring depth of 63 m, access-<lb/>ing sediments dating back to ∼ 18.4 ka cal BP (Harms et al., <lb/>2020). <lb/>Mountainous regions are among the most sensitive to cli-<lb/>mate change and natural hazard processes (Adler et al., 2022) <lb/>of different causes (e.g., meteorological, hydrological, and/or <lb/>seismic hazards) and potentially cascading effects. Such haz-<lb/>ards can range from local-scale events (e.g., debris flows, <lb/>rockfalls, or avalanches; e.g., Kiefer et al., 2021; Knapp et <lb/>al., 2018) to large-scale regional events (e.g., earthquakes, <lb/>droughts, or floods; e.g., Oswald et al., 2021; Swierczynski <lb/>et al., 2013) threatening human lives and infrastructure. Even <lb/>though flood-rich periods in central Europe coincided with <lb/>relatively cold periods in the past 9000 years (e.g., Blöschl <lb/>et al., 2020; Wilhelm et al., 2022), it is expected that ex-<lb/>treme precipitation in mountainous regions will increase in <lb/>the currently warming climate in all IPCC scenarios (Arias et <lb/>al., 2021), with likely cascading effects of, e.g., landslides or <lb/>floods. A clear commitment to assess extreme events is vital <lb/>to reduce the vulnerability and exposure of human societies <lb/>to such hazards. To this end, high-quality observational data <lb/>over long timescales are needed, to evaluate recurrence rates, <lb/>patterns, and magnitudes of potential future extreme events <lb/>with statistical relevance (e.g., Moernaut, 2020; Sabatier et <lb/>al., 2022). However, short historical and even shorter instru-<lb/>mental records limit our knowledge of natural hazard pro-<lb/>cesses, leading to significant uncertainties in risk assessment <lb/>(Costanza et al., 2007; Stein et al., 2012), potentially un-<lb/>derestimating extreme events with low-probability but high-<lb/>impact outcomes. Therefore, studying prehistoric events us-<lb/>ing geological records is needed (i) to reconstruct the past <lb/>occurrence of meteorological, hydrological, and seismolog-<lb/>ical hazards and their anthropogenic impacts, as well as <lb/>their complex interactions, and (ii) to gain a better under-<lb/>standing of magnitude-frequency relations of natural haz-<lb/>ards to reduce epistemic uncertainties in their assessment. <lb/>The intra-mountainous UNESCO area Dachstein/Salzkam-<lb/>mergut (Austria) is an exceptionally well-suited study area <lb/>for investigating natural hazards and human-environmental <lb/>interactions, due to a long history of human impact and set-<lb/>tlement (Reschreiter and Kowarik, 2019) and documented <lb/>historic and prehistoric evidence for human-environmental <lb/>interactions (Barsch et al., 2023; Festi et al., 2021; Grab-<lb/>ner et al., 2021; Knierzinger et al., 2021; Reschreiter and <lb/>Kowarik, 2019). Previous short-core and conventional lake <lb/>coring studies have documented the last ∼ 2.3 kyr cal BP (at <lb/>15.63 m) of Lake Hallstatt&apos;s sedimentary infill (Lauterbach et <lb/>al., 2023; Strasser et al., 2020). <lb/>The Hipercorig Hallstatt History (H 3 ) project overcomes <lb/>the previous coring limitations through the novel Hipercorig <lb/>platform (Harms et al., 2020) and accesses the deeper high-<lb/>resolution lacustrine archive of Lake Hallstatt allowing state-<lb/>of-the-art multiproxy-based research. Here, we present the <lb/>first major event stratigraphy of an intra-mountainous, high-<lb/>resolution lake record of the Eastern Alps, based on the com-<lb/>bination of seismic airgun data, borehole, and core logging. <lb/>The first-time use of borehole logging data on the Hipercorig <lb/>system enables us to better understand and link the cored sed-<lb/>imentary evolution of Lake Hallstatt to the seismic data and <lb/>its seismic stratigraphy. <lb/>2 Regional setting and previous studies <lb/>Lake Hallstatt (47°34 25 N, 13°39 35 E; 508 m above sea <lb/>level, area of 8.55 km 2 , ∼ 7.5 km long, up to 1.4 km wide, <lb/>lake volume ∼ 558 × 10 6 m 3 , maximum water depth 125 m, <lb/>Fig. 1) is a former glacial, fjord-like, intra-mountainous <lb/>lake, classified as oligotrophic, with holomictic-dimictic <lb/>mixing with infrequent meromictic phases (Beiwl and <lb/>Mühlmann, 2008; Ficker et al., 2011). The lake is lo-<lb/>cated in the UNESCO World Heritage region Hallstatt-<lb/>Dachstein/Salzkammergut, Austria. The area is situated in <lb/>the Northern Calcareous Alps, with steep limestone moun-<lb/>tains surrounding it and the still glaciated Dachstein Massif <lb/>to the south and the Totes Gebirge in the northeast within the <lb/>upstream catchment area. <lb/>Today, the north-south-stretching lake can be subdivided <lb/>into two sub-basins: (i) a shallower northern basin (∼ 45 m <lb/>deep) and (ii) a deeper southern basin (∼ 125 m deep; <lb/>Strasser et al., 2020). The formation of the overdeepened <lb/>lake basin occurred through repeated glacial erosion. The <lb/>last glacial cycle ended ∼ 17 ka cal BP with the retreat of <lb/>the Traun Glacier (Van Husen, 1977, 1997, 2011). The pri-<lb/>mary clastic carbonate influx mostly comprises the eroded <lb/>surrounding Triassic limestones of the Dachstein Formation <lb/>(Mandl et al., 2012). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>3 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 1. (a) Location of Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria) in the Alpine Arc (inset) and overview map of the Lake Hallstatt region <lb/>north of the Dachstein Massif and southwest of the Totes Gebirge, with its catchment area outlined on a shaded relief map. The digital <lb/>elevation models were taken from Copernicus Land Monitoring Services (European Digital Elevation Model (EU-DEM), version 1.1) and <lb/>http://data.gv.at (last access: 12 January 2021) (http://geoland.at, last access: 12 January 2021, Umweltbundesamt GmbH, Land Steiermark, <lb/>Land Oberösterreich), including catchment area and water network. (b) Lake Hallstatt overview map, with the N-S and W-E seismic airgun <lb/>transects and the H 3 coring locations (red dot), including the previous HAS_2016-1 core site (yellow dot) of Lauterbach et al. (2023). <lb/>Bathymetry data and mass-transport deposit (MTD) outlines following Strasser et al. (2020). <lb/>The catchment area of Lake Hallstatt covers 646 km 2 , with <lb/>the Traun River in the SE as the main river inflow contribut-<lb/>ing 53 % of total inflow and ∼ 50 % of the total catchment <lb/>area. The Traun inflow has a mean annual discharge (1970-<lb/>2006) of 20.7 m 3 s -1 (Ficker et al., 2011). Other larger trib-<lb/>utaries are the Gosaubach in the northwest, the Waldbach in <lb/>the southwest flowing into the southern basin, and smaller <lb/>tributaries such as the Großer Zlambach in the north flow-<lb/>ing into the northern basin and the Mühlbach at the town <lb/>of Hallstatt, draining the high valley of the Hallstatt salt <lb/>mine area. The mining area is located geologically within <lb/>the upper Permian to Lower Triassic Haselgebirge Formation <lb/>(e.g., Fernández et al., 2021; Schorn and Neubauer, 2014). <lb/>Evidence for large-scale underground rock salt mining dates <lb/>back at least to 3400 cal BP (Grabner et al., 2019). The salt-<lb/>enriched Haselgebirge Formation is also present around Lake <lb/>Altaussee and Grundlsee upstream of Lake Hallstatt, as well <lb/>as around Bad Ischl and Ebensee. <lb/>The history of this Alpine landscape is well-documented <lb/>through archeological data and written records indicating <lb/>that this region was settled more or less continuously since <lb/>the Bronze Age at the latest (Festi et al., 2021; Reschreiter <lb/>and Kowarik, 2019). Due to the economic importance of this <lb/>region a substantial record of written sources exists and pro-<lb/>vides insights into the last 400 years, including mentioning <lb/>catastrophic events such as mass movements, heavy precipi-<lb/>tation with debris flows, shoreline collapses, and earthquakes <lb/>(e.g., Melzner, 2017; Reschreiter and Kowarik, 2019; Rohn <lb/>et al., 2005; Urstöger, 2000). <lb/>On occasion, these sources also convey information on so-<lb/>cietal reaction to these geohazards, including information on <lb/>early geoengineering in the catchments and river redirections <lb/>(Pürstinger, 2017; Urstöger, 2000). Historical information <lb/>from major floods of the Traun river contributed to a compre-<lb/>hensive European flood study also covering the last 500 years <lb/>(Blöschl et al., 2020; Kiss, 2019; Rohr, 2006, 2007). Further-<lb/>more, long-term limnological monitoring data over the last <lb/>century also document the effects of wastewater intrusions <lb/>from salt mining, including the salt mine in Altaussee, on <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>water column stratification in Lake Hallstatt (Ficker et al., <lb/>2011). <lb/>A previous study by Strasser et al. (2020) investigated <lb/>the geomorphology and event stratigraphic record cov-<lb/>ering the last ∼ 130 years of Lake Hallstatt. They re-<lb/>port an ultra-high-resolution sedimentary archive with (mil-<lb/>limeter to sub-millimeter) laminated background sediment <lb/>and sedimentation rates of 0.50 to 0.4 cm yr -1 . High-<lb/>frequency hydroacoustic subsurface imaging was limited <lb/>to 4-5 m of the sedimentary infill and revealed parallel <lb/>and laterally continuous low-to medium-amplitude reflec-<lb/>tions. Several gravitational mass movements were iden-<lb/>tified, and event layers comprising turbidites and mass-<lb/>transport deposits are correlated to specific floods in the 19th <lb/>and 20th century and moderate earthquakes, respectively <lb/>(Strasser et al., 2020). Furthermore, a study of Lauterbach et <lb/>al. (2023) revealed, three large-scale mass movement event <lb/>deposits: E1 -84 ± 48 cal BP; E2 -1058 ± 60 cal BP; E3 -<lb/>2313 ± 131 cal BP (Lauterbach et al., 2023). These were in-<lb/>terbedded within the background sedimentation. Likely, the <lb/>coarse character of the large-scale event deposit of E3 re-<lb/>stricted the previous coring expedition to 15.63 m. <lb/>3 Methods <lb/>3.1 Site survey and site selection <lb/>Hipercorig drilling was planned to be in the depo-center <lb/>of the southern basin near the previous coring location <lb/>(HAS_2016-1, Fig. 1b) (Lauterbach et al., 2023). Previ-<lb/>ous coring in 2016 was abandoned at 15.63 m depth when <lb/>reaching the upper part of E3, a major mass-transport de-<lb/>posit (MTD; Lauterbach et al., 2023). A single-channel seis-<lb/>mic survey was conducted in March 2021, with the objec-<lb/>tive to locate the optimal site for drilling with a potentially <lb/>more complete stratigraphic succession and thinner E3. A <lb/>mini-airgun (Sercel Mini GI, 220 Hz center-frequency) was <lb/>used, with a volume of 0.016 L (1 cubic inch), a pressure of <lb/>80 bar, and a shooting interval of 2 s in combination with a <lb/>12-element single-channel streamer (3 m active length). The <lb/>theoretical vertical resolution is ∼ 1 m. The data were pre-<lb/>processed (using (1) DC (direct current) Removal, (2) TAR <lb/>(True Amplitude Recovery), (3) DC Removal, (4) BPF <lb/>(bandpass filter) 30-90-2000-2500, (5) trace equalization, <lb/>and (6) FX (frequency spatial distance)-Deconvolution and <lb/>BPF 100-150-2000-2500) and applying another bandpass fil-<lb/>ter (100-150-1000-1500) in the IHS Markit Kingdom Suite <lb/>2022, which was also used for seismic interpretation. An <lb/>acoustic velocity of 1500 m s -1 was used for the conversion <lb/>from two-way travel time (TWT) to depth. Due to the limita-<lb/>tion of the single-chamber airgun system, a bubble pulse ef-<lb/>fect (typically at 25 ms, with 60 Hz) is noticeable on the seis-<lb/>mic sections, creating artifacts below 25 ms TWT (∼ 22.5 m <lb/>below lake floor, m b.l.f.) (Lankston, 2017), which hamper <lb/>the interpretation (Fig. 2, green arrows). Based on the new <lb/>seismic airgun data, the H 3 site was selected ∼ 200 m south <lb/>of the HAS_2016-1 coring site. <lb/>3.2 Drilling campaign <lb/>Drilling at the H 3 site was carried out with the Hipercorig <lb/>system at 125 m of water depth between April and June 2021 <lb/>and operated by the UWITEC GmbH (Mondsee, Austria). <lb/>The drilling platform is a combination of a hydraulic down-<lb/>the-hole (DTH) hammer with an established UWITEC piston <lb/>coring system. It is a very versatile mobile, modular barge <lb/>system, with steel casings, a lake bottom ground plate, and <lb/>other auxiliary equipment (Harms et al., 2020). Two holes <lb/>with ∼ 8 m lateral offset (Table 1) were cored with a 1 m ver-<lb/>tical offset, to allow a vertical overlap of both holes (core <lb/>length: 2 m, core diameter: 90 mm). A total length of ∼ 91 m <lb/>(hole A 40 m, hole B 51 m; Fig. 2) of sediment cores was <lb/>retrieved. <lb/>Sediment cores were curated on site with the mobile <lb/>Drilling Information System (mDIS; Behrends et al., 2020), <lb/>kept in ice-cooled Styrofoam boxes on the platform, and <lb/>moved daily to a cool salt mine tunnel at ∼ 8 °C for tem-<lb/>porary storage (1-4 d). The sediment cores were then trans-<lb/>ported to the University of Innsbruck, where they were kept <lb/>at 4 °C. <lb/>3.3 Downhole logging <lb/>At the last day of on-site operations, while recovering the <lb/>casing from hole B, downhole logging was conducted us-<lb/>ing the International Continental Scientific Drilling Program <lb/>(ICDP) memory-logging system (iMLS), a modular &quot;logging <lb/>while tripping&quot; (LWT) system, in online mode for wireline <lb/>measurements (Kück et al., 2021). The data acquisition was <lb/>performed in wireline mode; i.e., the sondes were operated <lb/>on a regular logging cable and winch, with the data being <lb/>read out in real time at the surface. This was possible be-<lb/>cause the otherwise autonomously measuring iMLS mem-<lb/>ory sondes can also be run with a special wireline teleme-<lb/>try (Kück et al., 2021; see more details in Sect. S1 in the <lb/>Supplement). The memory sonde string did the following: <lb/>(i) memory spectrum gamma ray (mSGR) (1.2 m long) mea-<lb/>sured profiles of both the total natural gamma ray (GR) and <lb/>the concentrations of U, K, and Th from the spectrum of <lb/>the natural gamma radiation, and, mounted below, (ii) mem-<lb/>ory magnetic susceptibility (mMS) (1.4 m long) measured <lb/>magnetic susceptibility and temperature. Both sondes have a <lb/>nominal vertical resolution of 0.2 m. The mMS position be-<lb/>low the mSGR in the sonde string results in a magnetic sus-<lb/>ceptibility (MS) profile being 1.4 m longer than that of the <lb/>mSGR data. Once inside the casing pipes the sonde was low-<lb/>ered towards the bottom of the piston corer until the mMS <lb/>sonde stuck out of the corer and the mSGR sonde mounted <lb/>above remained inside the pipes. The mSGR can measure <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>5 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 2. (a) Reflection seismic airgun profiles for Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria) from south to north revealing the upper ∼ 15 m <lb/>of the sedimentary succession at the coring location H 3 (boreholes A and B) and a seismic window (SP 1270-1390) in the southern part <lb/>near the alluvial fan of Hallstatt with ∼ 40 m penetration depth; the green arrow indicates bubble pulse reflection (25 ms). (b) Interpretation <lb/>of profile shown in panel (a). Dark blue, yellow, red, and orange horizons mark the different intervals within E2 showing different facies <lb/>of E2: the upper interval (between dark blue and yellow) representing the turbidite deposit, the interval below (between yellow and red) <lb/>representing the upper part of the mass-transport deposit (MTD), and the interval below that (red to orange) representing the lower, coarser <lb/>part of the MTD; the deeper MTD E3 is indicated as a semi-transparent unit below, with dashed, light blue as the top and dashed light purple <lb/>as the potential bottom; the purple line ∼ 145 m b.l.l. indicates the potential double pulse. (c) Reflection seismic airgun profiles from west to <lb/>east showing the upper ∼ 15 m of the sedimentary succession and bubble pulse reflection (25 ms) as indicated in panel (a). (d) Interpreted <lb/>reflection seismic airgun profiles from west to east, as indicated in panel (b). Abbreviations: SU -seismic unit; TWT -two-way travel time. <lb/>Table 1. Water depths and core recoveries for the Hipercorig Hallstatt History (H 3 ) drilling project at Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, <lb/>Austria). Abbreviations: m b.l.l., meters below lake level (in spring 2021); m b.l.f., meters below lake floor. Drilling hole B is located around <lb/>7-8 m SE of hole A. <lb/>Borehole <lb/>Coordinates <lb/>Water Top depth Top depth Total drilled <lb/>Core <lb/>Core <lb/>depth <lb/>(m b.l.l.) <lb/>(m b.l.f.) <lb/>length (m) recovery recovery <lb/>(m) <lb/>(m) <lb/>(%) <lb/>A <lb/>47.572998°N 13.659365°E <lb/>125 <lb/>125 <lb/>0 <lb/>41 <lb/>38.38 <lb/>94 <lb/>B <lb/>47.572955°N 13.659446°E <lb/>125 <lb/>125 <lb/>0 <lb/>51 <lb/>48.07 <lb/>86 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>through the metal of a casing, but the mMS can only be mea-<lb/>sured in the open hole. <lb/>For the actual logging, both the sonde string and the cas-<lb/>ing pipe were pulled up as synchronously as possible, so that <lb/>the mMS sonde would stay below the pipe. The synchroniza-<lb/>tion happened manually by the logging winch operator and <lb/>the rig operator. Since it was the first time this was attempted, <lb/>the two pulling speeds were not always perfectly matched but <lb/>varied slightly, causing the mMS sonde to briefly slip into the <lb/>housing three times and lose the mMS measurement there. <lb/>This prevented a continuous profile of the magnetic suscepti-<lb/>bility. Despite these gaps in the mMS profile, the profile itself <lb/>is consistent in depth throughout and serves as a depth refer-<lb/>ence. The logging depth scale is in meters below lake level <lb/>(m b.l.l.); i.e., the depth reference is the lake surface at the <lb/>barge. The lake floor is visible in the GR profile as a steep <lb/>slope over about 1 m (124-125 m b.l.l.). It does not appear as <lb/>a sharp edge because the GR sensor first sees the decreasing <lb/>radiation when getting closer to the water and then contin-<lb/>ues to sense gamma radiation from the underlying sediments <lb/>slightly above the lake floor. Further, it can be assumed that <lb/>the lake floor does not show a sharp sediment-water interface <lb/>but that sediments, swirled up by the coring process, proba-<lb/>bly cover the lake floor. <lb/>3.4 Core opening, non-destructive analyses, and core <lb/>description <lb/>The whole-round cores were scanned using X-ray computed <lb/>tomography (CT) with a voxel size of 0.2 × 0.2 × 0.3 mm 3 <lb/>at the Medical University of Innsbruck (Austria) using a <lb/>Siemens SOMATOM Definition AS. A Geotek Multi-Sensor <lb/>Core Logger (MSCL) at the Austrian Core Facility (Depart-<lb/>ment of Geology, University of Innsbruck) measured the <lb/>whole-round cores with 0.5 cm resolution (bulk measure-<lb/>ments: magnetic susceptibility, P-wave velocity, and γ den-<lb/>sity). After core splitting high optical images were obtained <lb/>using a Smartcube Camera Image Scanner (SmartCIS; image <lb/>scans of split core surface at 500 dpi resolution) and the COX <lb/>Analytical Systems Itrax X-ray fluorescence core scanner <lb/>(XRF-CS) (filtered and color-adjusted RGB images with up <lb/>to ∼ 50 µm optical resolution; Croudace et al., 2006). Visual <lb/>core description and sediment classification follow Schnur-<lb/>renberger et al. (2003). The identification of event deposits is <lb/>based on general concepts after Sabatier et al. (2022), using <lb/>mainly sedimentary structures and thickness to distinguish <lb/>major event deposits from background sedimentation, with-<lb/>out further trigger interpretation. Here we indicate event de-<lb/>posits with a minimum thickness of 0.3 m and sequentially <lb/>apply the numbering introduced by Lauterbach et al. (2023) <lb/>at site HAS_2016-1. <lb/>3.5 Stratigraphic correlation <lb/>The first-order composite profile was created to establish <lb/>a continuous sediment sequence. For the construction of <lb/>a common depth scale (composite depth scale), visual tie <lb/>points (identification of coeval, laterally continuous fea-<lb/>tures) were established for both H 3 drilling holes and the <lb/>HAS_2016-1 composite core from Lauterbach et al. (2023). <lb/>The visual tie points occur at different core depths below the <lb/>lake floor (CLF-A) for each hole. The resulting core compos-<lb/>ite below the lake floor (CCLF-A) scale (meters composite <lb/>depth -m c.d.) is based on the horizontal alignment of visual <lb/>tie points and is equivalent to the old Ocean Drilling Program <lb/>(ODP) and Integrated Ocean Drilling Program meters&apos; com-<lb/>posite depth scale (IODP depth scales terminology, 2023). <lb/>Where coring gaps occur at correlative depths or correlation <lb/>between holes is non-conclusive, the floating composite sec-<lb/>tion below is appended to the overlying section above (see <lb/>more details in Sect. S2 and S2.1 and Tables S1, S2, and S3 <lb/>and Fig. S1 as well as Ortler, 2023, for the visualization of <lb/>the MSCL data using 15-point rolling Gaussian smoothing). <lb/>3.6 Core-log correlation <lb/>The core-log correlation was established through the correla-<lb/>tion of a smoothed MSCL MS dataset (centered mean rolling <lb/>average of 40 data points to match the MS borehole logging <lb/>resolution of 0.2 m) and the MS data of the borehole logging <lb/>(see detailed description in Sect. S7). The borehole logging <lb/>MS data (measured in hole B) represents the in situ stratig-<lb/>raphy and was used to anchor the MSCL MS dataset, which <lb/>was adjusted visually based on specific MS peaks and inter-<lb/>vals of both datasets (see tie point table in Table S7). This <lb/>allows us to better understand intervals of potential missing <lb/>sediments (core gaps) and compaction/extension within our <lb/>composite core. <lb/>3.7 Radiocarbon dating and age-depth modeling <lb/>From the two H 3 cores 24 accelerator mass spectrometry <lb/>(AMS) radiocarbon ( 14 C) dates were performed on deter-<lb/>mined macro-remains from terrestrial plants below 18 m c.d. <lb/>extracted by wet sieving of lake sediment samples using a <lb/>mesh size of &gt; 125 µm (Table 2). Small twigs from trees <lb/>and shrubs were determined to taxon/species level by Werner <lb/>H. Schoch (Laboratory for Ancient Wood Research, Switzer-<lb/>land) prior to dating. Core catcher samples were dated for an <lb/>early age estimation directly after sediment coring but with-<lb/>out detailed documentation. <lb/>Radiocarbon measurements were done at the Ion Beam <lb/>Physics Laboratory of ETH Zürich, Switzerland, using the <lb/>dedicated MICADAS system (Synal et al., 2007). Carbonates <lb/>and humic acids were removed using an acid and base treat-<lb/>ment as described by Hajdas (2008) in order to avoid poten-<lb/>tial contaminations. Single radiocarbon ages were calculated <lb/>according to Stuiver and Polach (1977), were than calibrated <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>7 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2. AMS radiocarbon ( 14 C) dates were performed on macro-remains from terrestrial plants extracted from the sediments of Lake <lb/>Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria). All data were calibrated at ETH Zürich with OxCal 4.4.4 (Bronk Ramsey, 2009) and the atmospheric <lb/>calibration curve IntCal20 (Reimer et al., 2020). CC represents core catcher material, which was pushed into mini cores up to 15 cm in length. <lb/>Dates in italics are from event layers (omitted 14 C dates; see Fig. 4). Abbreviations: B -bark; BS -bud scale; CC -core catcher samples; <lb/>ETH -Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule (Switzerland); FL -foliage leaf; L -leaf; Misp -microsporophyl; N -needle; n.d. -not <lb/>determined; n.m. -not measured; P -part; Pe -periderm; SS -short shoot; St -stem; T -twig. <lb/>ETH lab code and Core name &amp; section <lb/>Composite Dated material and dry weight <lb/>δ 13 C mg C <lb/>14 C age Calibrated 14 C <lb/>dating method <lb/>depth (cm) <lb/>depth (m) <lb/>(mg) <lb/>values <lb/>BP ± 1σ <lb/>age ranges <lb/>(g: graphite; GIS: <lb/>(‰) <lb/>(uncal.) <lb/>(cal BP) <lb/>gas ion source) <lb/>121858 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-10-2 (30) <lb/>18.67 <lb/>1 Abies alba T (21) <lb/>-31.2 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>± 22 <lb/>2425-2711 <lb/>135231 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-9-2 (73.5) <lb/>19.066 <lb/>4 Juniperus N-P, 9 Picea abies N-P, <lb/>3 Bryophyta St (3.1) <lb/>-29.8 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>2759-2852 <lb/>121857 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-10-1 (67.5) <lb/>22.19 <lb/>5 Abies alba N-P, 1 Picea abies N-P, <lb/>1 Larix decidua N-P (4) <lb/>-29 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>± 22 <lb/>3453-3562 <lb/>121860 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-10-2 (47) <lb/>22.94 <lb/>1 Fagus sylvatica T-P (37.6) <lb/>-30.8 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>± 22 <lb/>3390-3481 <lb/>135233 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-12-2 (44.5) <lb/>24.111 <lb/>1 Bryophyta St, 1 Larix decidua N, <lb/>2 Larix decidua N-P, 4 FL-P, 1 B-<lb/>P indet., 1 Pinaceae Misp, 1 FL-P <lb/>indet. (3.5) <lb/>-28.4 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>± 26 <lb/>3732-3972 <lb/>121856 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-11-2 (17) <lb/>25.100 <lb/>5 Larix decidua N-P, 1 Pinaceae <lb/>Misp, 1 Bryophyta St, 4 L-P (2.9) <lb/>-28.3 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>± 22 <lb/>4250-4416 <lb/>116852 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-11-CC (6) <lb/>25.986 * <lb/>n.d. <lb/>-28.6 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>4442-4796 <lb/>135232 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-12-1 (41.75) <lb/>26.919 <lb/>1 Pinus cembra SS, 1 Bryophyta St, <lb/>1 Pinaceae N, 1 FL-P (cf. Fagus syl-<lb/>vatica) (2.4) <lb/>-27.1 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>± 27 <lb/>4976-5287 <lb/>121855 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-12-2 (14.25) <lb/>27.64 <lb/>14 Bryophyta St, 1 L-P, 9 T-P indet. <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>-25.9 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>± 23 <lb/>5476-5585 <lb/>121854 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-15-1 (24.5) <lb/>28.64 <lb/>1 Larix decidua N-P, 1 Abies alba <lb/>N-P, 1 Pinus BS, 4 L-P, 3 Bryophyta <lb/>St, 16 T-P indet. (1.8) <lb/>-26.8 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>± 37 <lb/>5749-5988 <lb/>121853 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-15-2 (91) <lb/>30.30 <lb/>1 Juniperus N-P, 3 Abies alba N-P, <lb/>1 B-P (2.2) <lb/>-22.9 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>± 23 <lb/>6303-6399 <lb/>121863 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-16-1 (73) <lb/>32.00 <lb/>2 Picea abies N-P (2.6) <lb/>-26.7 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>± 23 <lb/>6790-6941 <lb/>121861 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-17-1 (69) <lb/>35.05 <lb/>3 Abies alba T-P (4.1) <lb/>-27 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>± 24 <lb/>7171-7414 <lb/>116853 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-16-CC (5.25) 35.341 * <lb/>n.d. <lb/>-28 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>7280-7423 <lb/>121852 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-18-1 (51) <lb/>37.55 <lb/>3 Abies alba N-P, 1 Pinaceae BS, 3 <lb/>Bryophyta St (2.1) <lb/>-27.8 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>± 37 <lb/>7433-7609 <lb/>121851 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-19-2 (16) <lb/>38.88 <lb/>1 Picea abies N-P, 1 Bryophyta St, <lb/>3 T-P indet. (2.5) <lb/>-24.6 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>8374-8452 <lb/>121859 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-19-1 (40) <lb/>40.00 <lb/>1 Conifer T (cf. Picea abies) (78.6) <lb/>-27.8 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>9137-9416 <lb/>135234 (g) <lb/>1001-1-A-19-1 (51) <lb/>40.111 <lb/>1 Lamiaceae St-P, 1 Pinaceae Pe, 3 <lb/>B-P (3.7) <lb/>-26.5 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>8454-8598 <lb/>121850 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-21-2 (34.5) <lb/>42.35 <lb/>9 T-P indet., 2 B-P, 17 Bryophyta <lb/>St, 31 L-P (53) <lb/>-30.9 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>± 25 <lb/>9321-9526 <lb/>131460 (GIS) <lb/>1001-1-B-22-1 (74) <lb/>44.611 <lb/>1 Pinaceae BS, 1 T indet. (2.2) <lb/>n.m. <lb/>0.10 <lb/>± 89 <lb/>9545-10 147 <lb/>121862 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-23-1 (72) <lb/>45.78 <lb/>1 Salix T-P (24.1) <lb/>-30.4 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>± 26 10 880-11 202 <lb/>116854 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-23-CC (2) <lb/>46.976 * <lb/>n.d. <lb/>-25.3 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>± 29 11 198-11 313 <lb/>116855 (GIS) <lb/>1001-1-B-24-CC (4.25) 48.526 * <lb/>n.d. <lb/>-20.1 <lb/>n.m. 10 ± 86 11 880-12 607 <lb/>116856 (g) <lb/>1001-1-B-25-CC (8.25) 50.551 * <lb/>n.d. <lb/>-29.2 <lb/>0.24 10 ± 36 12 682-12 748 <lb/> * Core catcher samples were projected to the corresponding depth, if possible; otherwise, they were set at the bottom of the corresponding core section. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>with OxCal 4.4.4 (Bronk Ramsey, 2009), and were there-<lb/>after transformed into calibrated years BP (before present: <lb/>before 1950 CE) according to the calibration curve IntCal20 <lb/>(Reimer et al., 2020). The Bacon v3.0.0 software package <lb/>for R (Blaauw and Christen, 2011) was used for Bayesian <lb/>age-depth modeling; however, two radiocarbon dates (ETH-<lb/>121857 and ETH-121859; see Table 2) were excluded from <lb/>the age-depth model, as they were sampled within the base <lb/>of event deposits (see Sect. S6 and respective Fig. S2 for <lb/>more details). Furthermore, 17 radiocarbon dates from the <lb/>HAS_2016-1 sediment core (Lauterbach et al., 2023) were <lb/>included into the total age-depth model by projecting them <lb/>onto the H 3 composite core profile using tie points (see Ta-<lb/>ble S5) to cover the upper 15 m of the stratigraphy. <lb/>4 Results <lb/>4.1 Seismic airgun units <lb/>The seismic airgun data show a seismic stratigraphy with <lb/>three distinct seismic units (SUs) characterized by five dif-<lb/>ferent seismic facies (F1-F5, Table S4) at the coring site <lb/>(Fig. 2): SU1 is a ∼ 12 m thick acoustically laminated, high-<lb/>amplitude reflection package (F1) with limited lateral conti-<lb/>nuity. On the whole basin scale, SU1 also comprises several <lb/>zones at different stratigraphic levels with a few meter-thick, <lb/>semi-transparent, and non-continuous reflections (F2) with <lb/>variable amplitudes and hummocky to deformed geometries <lb/>(e.g., shot points (SPs) 1260-1370, 1420-1550, and 1750-<lb/>1990 in Fig. 2a and b; 3270-3290, 3235-3250, and 3190-<lb/>3225 in Fig. 2c and d). At the HAS_2016-1 site, the SU1-to-<lb/>SU2 boundary corresponds to the base of E2 (Fig. 2b). SU2 <lb/>shows more diffuse low-amplitude reflections (F3) above the <lb/>25 ms -1 TWT level dominated by a bubble pulse (green <lb/>arrows in Fig. 2), with higher amplitudes towards the top <lb/>of the unit. In the south of the N-S seismic profile, SU2 <lb/>shows northward-dipping reflections with moderate ampli-<lb/>tudes (F4) and moderate lateral continuity, occasionally in-<lb/>terlayered with chaotic facies. The seismic signal penetration <lb/>to greater depth is generally limited by seismic attenuation, <lb/>related to MTD bodies (as described in core HAS_2016-1 <lb/>(Lauterbach et al., 2023) and the following sections) and free <lb/>gas in the pore space of the sediment causing acoustic blank-<lb/>ing. A ∼ 250 m wide &quot;seismic window&quot; near the Hallstatt <lb/>fan (SP 1270-1390 in Fig. 2a, b) images the deeper sub-<lb/>surface (SU3, down to ∼ 40 m b.l.f.) with northward-inclined <lb/>medium-amplitude reflections (F5) with low lateral continu-<lb/>ity (Fig. 2a, b). <lb/>4.2 Borehole logging units <lb/>Nine logging units were defined based on the downhole log-<lb/>ging measurements collected in hole H 3 B (Fig. 3). Logging <lb/>Unit 1 (LU1, 124-131 m b.l.l.) is characterized by intermedi-<lb/>ate GR values of 55.1 ± 2.9 gAPI and a downhole-decreasing <lb/>trend in MS (with overall low values of 0.9 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI -<lb/>Système International -on average). The turning point with <lb/>the lowest MS value, after the decreasing trend, defines the <lb/>boundary to Logging Unit 2 (LU2). LU2 (131-135.6 m b.l.l.) <lb/>shows on average low MS values of 0.8 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI <lb/>and very low GR values of 39.2 ± 5.6 gAPI and con-<lb/>sist first of an interval of low MS and GR values until <lb/>135.2 m b.l.l. followed by a sharp increase, up to a peak in <lb/>MS value of 1.52 × 10 -4 SI, indicating the transition to Log-<lb/>ging Unit 3 (LU3). LU3 (135.6-139.5 m b.l.l.) consists of <lb/>increased MS values of 1.1 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI and stable GR <lb/>values of 60.3 ± 3.7 gAPI encircled by high GR values at <lb/>the top. The transition to Logging Unit 4 (LU4) is defined <lb/>as the turning point towards low GR value, with a peak <lb/>in K and a low in MS values. LU4 (139.5-140.9 m b.l.l.) <lb/>shows a thin layer with low GR values centered around <lb/>a minimum value of 37.2 gAPI with intermediate MS val-<lb/>ues (1.1 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI on average). The increase in GR <lb/>value at the bottom of the thin layer, as well as the low MS <lb/>value indicate the transition to Logging Unit 5. LU5 (140.9-<lb/>145 m b.l.l.) comprises high GR values (74 ± 7.9 gAPI on <lb/>average) with two prominent thin layers with GR values <lb/>of up to 85.4 gAPI and an MS trough in between. Overall, <lb/>LU5 includes spikey and high MS values with an average of <lb/>1.3 ± 0.2 × 10 -4 SI. The transition to Logging Unit 6 is in-<lb/>dicated with the transition towards lower GR values and a <lb/>peak in MS values. LU6 (145-149.9 m b.l.l.) comprises high <lb/>GR values (64 ± 5.9 gAPI on average) with one prominent <lb/>thin layer of increased GR values of up to 73.6 gAPI. The <lb/>MS values show intermediate values of 1.1 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI <lb/>on average. The transition to Logging Unit 7 is indicated <lb/>with the transition towards increased GR values and a low <lb/>in K and MS values. LU7 (149.9-157.3 m b.l.l.) also indi-<lb/>cates enhanced MS values of 1.3 ± 0.2 × 10 -4 SI (based on <lb/>the 149.9-151.6 m b.l.l.) as well as a peak-shaped evolution <lb/>of high GR values (on average of 68 ± 8.5 gAPI). The tran-<lb/>sition point to Logging Unit 8 (LU8) is defined after the GR <lb/>trough of 49.62 gAPI, towards more stable GR values. LU8 <lb/>(157.3-165.8 m b.l.l.) shows very stable and intermediate GR <lb/>values of 56.46 ± 1.9 gAPI and lower and spikey MS values <lb/>of 1 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI. The transition to Logging Unit 9 (LU9) <lb/>is the lowest MS value before the onset of an increasing trend <lb/>of MS and GR values. LU9 (165.8-173.2 m b.l.l.) shows in-<lb/>creased GR values of 66.3 ± 3.3 gAPI and increased MS val-<lb/>ues of 1.2 ± 0.1 × 10 -4 SI. <lb/>4.3 Lithostratigraphic units <lb/>The sedimentary succession comprises two major lithostrati-<lb/>graphic units: Unit 1 (Holocene, with six subunits) and Unit 2 <lb/>(Late Pleistocene). The sediments are mainly composed of <lb/>carbonate mud, interbedded with multiple millimeter-to <lb/>centimeter-thick light-gray clayey-silt graded deposits (fur-<lb/>ther referred to as turbidites as interpreted and used by <lb/>Lauterbach et al., 2023, and Strasser et al., 2020). Further-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>9 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 3. Borehole logging for the sediments of Lake Hallstatt <lb/>(Salzkammergut, Austria) with natural gamma radiation (GR); <lb/>magnetic susceptibility (MS); and U, K, and Th concentrations. The <lb/>numbers 1-9 represent the identified borehole logging units (LUs). <lb/>The sections with no MS data in interval 1 and interval 7 were dis-<lb/>carded (measurement inside metal casing). <lb/>more multiple &gt; 0.3 m thick deposits occur with a graded, <lb/>coarser-base, homogenous body and clay cap overlying co-<lb/>hesive mixed sedimentary layers interpreted as co-genetic <lb/>turbidites (cf. Lauterbach et al., 2023) and mass-transport de-<lb/>posits (MTDs). The labeled events differentiated by visual <lb/>changes in color, grain size, lamination thickness, structure, <lb/>and MSCL data (γ density and magnetic susceptibility; see <lb/>Figs. 4 and 5, Table S6, and Sect. S3). The presented ages are <lb/>derived from the age-depth model, using precise radiocarbon <lb/>dates performed on plant remains (see Sect. 3.7). <lb/>Unit 1 -Holocene, 0-47.60 m c.d. (present day to <lb/>11 623 ± 150 cal BP) <lb/>Subunit A (0-2.36 m composite depth (m c.d.); bottom: <lb/>304 ± 28 cal BP) consists of laminated to very thin bed-<lb/>ded dark-gray clayey-silty carbonate mud, interbedded <lb/>with millimeter-to centimeter-thick graded turbidites. It <lb/>shows very low mean density values of ∼ 1.30 g cm -3 <lb/>and a drastic increase in magnetic susceptibility up to <lb/>10.57 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 . The transition phase (∼ 5 cm, 2.4-<lb/>2.45 m c.d.) to subunit B is a striking color change <lb/>toward yellowish as well as to lower MS values <lb/>(∼ 3.95 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 ) and higher-density values (Fig. 4). <lb/>E1, mainly present close to the Hallstatt alluvial fan (Lauter-<lb/>bach et al., 2023), within subunit A is not indicated, as it <lb/>shows &lt; 0.3 m thickness at the deep basin. A slight nick <lb/>point within the age-depth model indicates a slight decrease <lb/>in sedimentation rate for subunit A compared to subunit B. <lb/>Subunit B (2.36-6.87 m c.d.; bottom: 711 ± 34 cal BP) is <lb/>a prominent yellowish-gray clastic carbonate mud inter-<lb/>val of ∼ 4.5 m (2.4-6.87 m c.d.) with faintly millimeter-to <lb/>centimeter-scale laminated sediments (Fig. 5). This sequence <lb/>shows a slightly enhanced mean density value of 1.43 g cm -3 <lb/>compared to the two adjacent subunits A and C and a de-<lb/>creasing trend towards subunit A. The transition phase of <lb/>subunit B to subunit C (6.76-6.87 m c.d.) is a striking color <lb/>change from more yellowish to blackish, gray colors, a drop <lb/>in density values and MS values, and a decrease in sedimen-<lb/>tation rate within subunit C. The sedimentation rates of sub-<lb/>units B and A show the highest sedimentation rates. <lb/>Subunit C (6.87-18.23 m c.d.; bottom: <lb/>2239 ± 82 ka cal BP) consist of laminated to very thin bed-<lb/>ded dark-gray clayey-silty carbonate mud (very similar <lb/>to subunit A), interbedded with millimeter-to centimeter-<lb/>thick graded turbidites. The background sedimentation <lb/>shows a mean density of 1.44 g cm -3 and mean MS <lb/>of 4.1 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 with the highest values below E2 <lb/>(10.85 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 ). Subunit C comprises two major <lb/>mass-transport deposits (E2: ∼ 5.1 m thick; E3: ∼ 2.7 m <lb/>thick; see Table S6) forming respective MTDs containing <lb/>pebbles (up to 3 cm in diameter) and related co-genetic tur-<lb/>bidites. E2 shows a distinct bipartite structure in both holes <lb/>(A and B) which is separated by a sandy organic-rich interval <lb/>(9.12-9.42 m c.d.). The basal part (9.42-12.74 m c.d.) shows <lb/>a chaotic mixture at the bottom of a mainly sandy matrix with <lb/>pebbles which transitions to a sandy matrix with pebbles and <lb/>mud clasts, with partly intact laminations or vertical lamina-<lb/>tions and soft sediment deformation and sand package. The <lb/>overlying interval shows amalgamated sandy deposits with <lb/>macro remains, with decreasing thickness towards the over-<lb/>lying turbidite (7.64-9.12 m c.d.), which has a distinct ho-<lb/>mogenous structure with a very thin mud cap (&lt; 0.5 cm). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 4. Composite profile overview for the sediments of Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria). From left to right: core recovery of both <lb/>boreholes and correlation lines (blue: correlation with HAS_2016-1 core possible; green: correlation possible only between the H 3 cores A <lb/>and B). Composite profile of the borehole used (indicated in green and purple). Simplified lithology log for the composite profile (with <lb/>eight major lithology types, including event deposits). Whole-round measured density. Magnetic susceptibility. Age-depth model based on <lb/>35 radiocarbon ( 14 C) dates, with the two 14 C dates shown in red omitted. Identified lithological units for the Late Pleistocene (blue) and <lb/>Holocene (green). <lb/>In comparison to the HAS_2016-1 core (Lauterbach et al., <lb/>2023), we observe a much coarser grain size and less defor-<lb/>mation structures within the basal part of E2. The base of <lb/>E2 shows erosional features and missing laminations com-<lb/>pared to the HAS_2016-1 core, suggesting a hiatus of ∼ 150-<lb/>550 years based on the age-depth model (Fig. 4). Event 3 <lb/>(E3) also shows a bipartite structure with a basal part and an <lb/>overlying turbidite. The basal part varies strongly between <lb/>holes A and B within the individual parallel core segments, <lb/>demonstrating a high spatial heterogeneity of the event de-<lb/>posit. Hole A shows a small (∼ 1 cm) sandy base overlain by <lb/>subvertical laminations and folded laminas (∼ 80 cm), which <lb/>is followed by the turbidite (&gt; 1.9 m), a homogenous pack-<lb/>age. The base of the turbidite was not retrieved in hole A. <lb/>In hole B, the basal part (∼ 45 cm, 17.76-18.23 m c.d.) con-<lb/>sists of a sandy matrix with some pebbles mud clasts, with <lb/>the very bottom part not being retrieved. The top part of the <lb/>basal part comprises an amalgamated organic-rich interval <lb/>(∼ 45 cm, 17.30-17.76 m c.d.) with centimeter-thick sandy <lb/>intersections towards the turbidite. The turbidite is a ∼ 1.8 m <lb/>thick homogenous package with a thin (&lt; 0.5 cm) mud cap. <lb/>The background sedimentation rate between E2 and E3 in-<lb/>dicates a slight increase in sedimentation after E3 and an in-<lb/>creasing trend towards E2. Also, the transition to subunit D <lb/>at the base of E3 (18.23 m c.d.) likely shows a hiatus of up to <lb/>∼ 600 years based on the age-depth model. <lb/>Subunit D (18.23-28.47 m c.d.; bottom: <lb/>5544 ± 93 ka cal BP) is similar in appearance to subunit C <lb/>with increased mean density values of 1.48 g cm -3 and MS <lb/>values of 5.50 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 . It is intercalated with four <lb/>homogenous packages (E4, E5, E6, and E7; see Table S6 for <lb/>depth). E4 and E5 appear to be a stacked event sequence, <lb/>with an interval of ∼ 2.5 cm in between the deposits which <lb/>need to be further investigated. E4 is a light-gray, homoge-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 5. Compilation of drilling core images, for each lithological unit (including subunits) of Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria). <lb/>Each photographic assemblage shows a computer tomography (CT) image (black less dense, white denser), a smart cube image, a smart cube <lb/>color-adjusted image, and two ITRAX images (with different light intensities). In addition, a representative core section is shown for each <lb/>major event deposit (&gt; 0.3 m). <lb/>nous package, with a sandy base. E5 is black (directly after <lb/>core opening) and homogenous with a ∼ 1 cm thick organic-<lb/>rich layer and a sandy base (&lt; 0.5 cm). E6 is a ∼ 60 cm <lb/>thick, medium-gray, homogenous package with a ∼ 2 cm <lb/>thick sandy base and a thin (&lt; 0.5 cm) mud cap. Furthermore, <lb/>the top part of an MTD (E7: min. 0.7 m thick, base not cored) <lb/>is present at the bottom of subunit D with a ∼ 14 cm thick <lb/>light-gray mud sequence and sandy intersections, which are <lb/>deformed at the lower part of the sequence. <lb/>Subunit E (28.47-37.43 m c.d.; bottom: 7525 ± 51 cal BP) <lb/>indicates an overall change within the Holocene unit to <lb/>laminated dark-gray clayey-silty carbonate mud interbed-<lb/>ded with thicker (millimeter-to centimeter-thick) graded <lb/>turbidites and two &gt; 0.3 m thick turbidites. The transition <lb/>occurs likely within the coring gap of ∼ 1 m, and based <lb/>on the age-depth model ∼ 100-800 years could be miss-<lb/>ing. The mean density value is 1.55 g cm -3 and the mean <lb/>MS value is 6.5 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 . This shows an increase <lb/>for both parameters compared to the overlain subunit D. <lb/>The magnetic susceptibility shows overall the highest val-<lb/>ues of the composite core and the highest individual MS <lb/>peaks (23.59 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 ) of background sedimenta-<lb/>tion. Additionally, E8 (∼ 74 cm, 32.02-32.76 m c.d.) repre-<lb/>sents a homogenous, medium-gray to light-gray (∼ 25 cm <lb/>of the top) mud, with no prominent coarse base. E9 <lb/>(∼ 1.44 cm, 36-37.44 m c.d.) shows a similar appearance, <lb/>with a medium-gray, homogenous body and a light-gray up-<lb/>per part (∼ 50 cm) and a 2 cm thick sandy lens as a base. <lb/>Subunit F (37.43-47.60 m c.d.; bottom: <lb/>11 623 ± 150 cal BP) is a laminated dark-gray clayey-silty <lb/>carbonate mud interbedded with millimeter-to centimeter-<lb/>thick graded turbidites similar to subunit E. The mean <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>density value is 1.61 g cm -3 and the mean MS value <lb/>is 4.53 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 . The lowest density values of <lb/>∼ 1.3 g cm -3 are ∼ 43 m c.d. with slightly more black-<lb/>ish sediments compared to the adjacent sediments. E10 <lb/>(∼ 1.14 m, 38.9-40 m c.d.) consist of medium-gray, silty car-<lb/>bonate mud with dark patches and a striking, folded organic-<lb/>rich, sandy base. At ∼ 45 m c.d. E11 occurs (min. 31 cm, <lb/>44.76-45.1 m c.d.) and consists of deformed laminations of <lb/>carbonate mud with chaotically distributed multiple grains <lb/>(&gt; 0.5 cm) and one layer grains (up to 0.5 cm) in the upper <lb/>part of E11. In addition, a distinct increase in the density <lb/>baseline is present at ∼ 47 m c.d. to &gt; 1.69 g cm -3 . <lb/>Unit 2 -Late Pleistocene, ∼ 47.60-55.3 m c.d. (top: <lb/>11 623 ± 150 cal BP; bottom: older than <lb/>12 682-12 748 cal BP; 50.5 m c.d.) <lb/>Unit 2 consists of a Late Pleistocene sedimentary succession <lb/>comprising laminated very thin bedded (1-3 cm) medium-<lb/>gray silty-clayey carbonate mud, with several laminated <lb/>(&lt; 1 cm) intervals and multiple-centimeter-thick light-gray <lb/>and graded turbidites. Within Unit 2 there are three intervals <lb/>observable: (i) a mainly finely laminated (&lt; 1 cm) carbon-<lb/>ate mud (∼ 47.60-∼ 50.5 m c.d.) with increased MS values <lb/>of ∼ 4.63 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 , with the deepest sampled age at <lb/>the base with 12 682-12 748 cal BP; (ii) a darker colored in-<lb/>terval (∼ 50-∼ 54 m c.d.) with a slightly lower magnetic sus-<lb/>ceptibility (∼ 3.94 × 10 -8 m 3 kg -1 ); and (iii) increased den-<lb/>sity values below ∼ 54 m c.d. with ∼ 1.75 g cm -3 . <lb/>5 Discussion <lb/>5.1 Core-log (seismic) integration <lb/>The integration of seismic airgun, borehole logging, and sed-<lb/>iment core data confirms that the boundary between seismic <lb/>units SU1-SU2 corresponds to the base of the E2 MTD at <lb/>both the H 3 site and the HAS_2016-1 site (Figs. 2b, d, and <lb/>6), across which a downhole increasing MS trend is observed <lb/>in both the borehole and core logging data (see detailed de-<lb/>scription of MS-based borehole logging to core logging data <lb/>correlation in Sect. S7 and Table S7). Hence, the logging unit <lb/>LU1 corresponds to subunits A and B and to the upper part of <lb/>SU1. The high-amplitude reflection at ∼ 0.197 s TWT depth <lb/>likely originates from the sharp density contrast at the tran-<lb/>sition from subunit B to C, which also generally shows in-<lb/>creased GR (gamma radiation) values for B and a decrease <lb/>in GR towards C. The lower part of SU1 at the correlative <lb/>depth of E2 shows a disrupted-reflection pattern, which can <lb/>be interpreted as thrusts and ramp features (e.g., Sammartini <lb/>et al., 2019) within the MTD bodies that thin out towards the <lb/>deep basin (Fig. 2b). The bipartite nature of E2 (as described <lb/>in the core data with a turbidite overlying the MTD) is also <lb/>observed in LU2 with the upper part showing low GR val-<lb/>ues and transitioning to comparably higher GR values at the <lb/>base. This is also apparent in the seismic data by a ponding <lb/>deposit overlying the top of the MTD (thick, solid yellow line <lb/>in Fig. 2b). The base of E2 at the H 3 site contains rip-up mud <lb/>clasts and is coarser than at the HAS_2016-1 site. The basal <lb/>part of E2 at the HAS_2016-1 site shows plastic deformation <lb/>(Lauterbach et al., 2023), indicative of basin plane deforma-<lb/>tion (e.g., Sammartini et al., 2019). <lb/>SU2 comprises the lower part of subunit C (including E3) <lb/>and the upper part of subunit D (including E4 and E5; Fig. 6). <lb/>The C-D subunit boundary correlates very well with the <lb/>boundary of LU4 to LU5. The thin layer of low GR values <lb/>at LU4 correlates to the base of E3, representing the MTD of <lb/>E3. However, neither physical properties nor lithologic char-<lb/>acteristics of the subunit boundary and/or the event deposits <lb/>can be conclusively correlated with the diffuse acoustic fa-<lb/>cies in the SU2. A positive-amplitude reflection (peak) with <lb/>reasonable lateral continuity of ∼ 1 km occurring at roughly <lb/>the corresponding depth of E3 at site H 3 is used to tenta-<lb/>tively map the top of the MTD E3 through the basin (dashed <lb/>blue line in Figs. 2b, d and 6). This tentative correlation <lb/>is supported by the sharp density contrast between the tur-<lb/>bidite and the underlying MTD. The turbidite itself, which <lb/>-in comparison to E2 is thicker (∼ 1.8 m) and has higher <lb/>natural radiation -is not recognizable in the seismic data. <lb/>Similarly, the base of E3, characterized by lateral hetero-<lb/>geneity of the MTD as observed in holes A and B, cannot <lb/>be traced (but can tentatively be mapped by the dashed pur-<lb/>ple line, assuming constant depth of the MTD in Fig. 2b). <lb/>E4 and E5 are below or near the resolution of the seismic <lb/>data but observable within LU5 and the upper part of sub-<lb/>unit D. E4 shows increased GR, MS, and density values, <lb/>whereas E5 shows prominent low MS values at the base, <lb/>which correlates between the borehole logging and core log-<lb/>ging dataset (i.e., logging tie points (LTPs) 13-14; Fig. 6; <lb/>Table S7). The SU2-to-SU3 boundary does not correlate to <lb/>any specific characteristics of the logged and cored sedimen-<lb/>tary succession at site H 3 , reflecting the effect of the bubble <lb/>pulse as an artificial effect, as methodologically described in <lb/>Sect. 3.1. <lb/>Below 25 m b.l.f., the lower part of subunit D correlates <lb/>very well to LU6 (including E6 and E7; Fig. 6). The MS val-<lb/>ues of subunit D and LU6 correlate well (see Fig. 6; LTPs 15 <lb/>to 16) and show overall intermediate MS values, respectively, <lb/>whereas E6 and E7 show decreased MS values. Also, the MS <lb/>values in the lower part of LU6 and subunit D show differ-<lb/>ences which are addressed in Sect. 5.2. <lb/>The D-E subunit boundary correlates very well with the <lb/>LU6-LU7 boundary, with the low MS values at the base of <lb/>E7. LU7 correlates to subunit E, including E8 (Fig. 6), and is <lb/>characterized by increased GR and MS values (see LTPs 18 <lb/>and 19). E8 shows stable GR and density values and a strong <lb/>peak in MS values. The transition boundary of LU7-LU8 and <lb/>subunit E-F likely relates to E9, transitioning from increased <lb/>GR and MS values to intermediate GR and MS values down-<lb/>core (LTPs 20-27). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 6. Core-log seismic integration of Lake Hallstatt (Salzkammergut, Austria) with a comparison of seismic airgun and borehole <lb/>logging units and lithological subunits. Note that the three different datasets are plotted against their respective but different depth scale. The <lb/>composite core depth scale (m c.d.) is not corrected for extension. Due to this as well as to the appending of core sections, the composite core <lb/>is ∼ 4 m longer compared to the borehole itself. Dashed and solid lines indicate logging tie points (LTPs) defining the correlation between the <lb/>logging and core data depending on the confidence level (see detailed description in Sect. S7 and Table S7). The main ages of the lithological <lb/>boundaries are indicated (based on the Bacon age-depth model), in comparison to archeological periods. See legend in Fig. 4 for lithology. <lb/>Abbreviations: SU -seismic unit; LU -logging unit; GR -gamma radiation; MS -magnetic susceptibility; TWT -two-way travel time; <lb/>LTP -logging tie point; M.P. -Migration Period; R.P. -Roman Period. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<body>Below E9, LU8 corresponds to subunit F (including E10 <lb/>and E11; Fig. 6). The interval between LTPs 22 and 23 will <lb/>be addressed in the following Sect. 5.2. LU8 and subunit F <lb/>are characterized by intermediate physical properties values; <lb/>nevertheless there is a low-density interval ∼ 42 m c.d. and at <lb/>least one interval prior to E10 with higher MS values. <lb/>The transition of LU8-LU9 is based on the transition of in-<lb/>termediate towards increased MS and GR values and likely <lb/>relates to E11 (Fig. 6; LTPs 27-32). The transition from <lb/>Unit 1 to Unit 2 (indicating the Pleistocene to Holocene tran-<lb/>sition; Fig. 4) likely occurs around 47.6 m c.d. based on vi-<lb/>sual description and after a transition phase of increasing MS <lb/>and GR values (between E11 and ∼ 47.6 m c.d.) as well as <lb/>a dominant change in density values. Furthermore, the MS <lb/>correlation between borehole logging and core logging data <lb/>between LTPs 27 and 33 is more challenging and will be ad-<lb/>dressed in the following Sect. 5.2 (also see Sect. S7). LU9 <lb/>and Unit 2 show increased physical property values until <lb/>∼ 52 m c.d., followed by lower physical property values un-<lb/>til ∼ 54 m c.d., which are followed by a striking increase in <lb/>density values. <lb/>5.2 Advantages of combining borehole logging and <lb/>coring in lakes <lb/>The borehole logging helped to estimate core extension <lb/>(Baumgarten et al., 2015) and allows us to constrain the three <lb/>gaps (Baumgarten et al., 2014), which could not be closed by <lb/>composing the stratigraphy from boreholes A and B. The cor-<lb/>relation of MS peaks between logging and core data across <lb/>the E7 base (LU6 to LU7; and subunit D-E boundary) re-<lb/>veals that the main coring gap (∼ 25 m b.l.f.) is smaller than <lb/>1 m, where challenging drilling conditions occurred in both <lb/>boreholes A and B -see Sect. S5. The coring gap below <lb/>E11 (estimated &lt; 1 m during challenging coring operation in <lb/>borehole B -Sect. S5) is underestimated and could be up to <lb/>1 m based on the borehole logging. Also in borehole B, chal-<lb/>lenging coring operations occurred below E9. The interval <lb/>between E9 and E10 (LTPs 22-23) suggests that LU8 shows <lb/>1 m of more variety, which is not clearly observed within sub-<lb/>unit F. This observation strengthens the assumption that no <lb/>correlation line at the respective depth can be described and <lb/>that up to 1 m of sediment is missing. <lb/>Beside the clear advantages of the borehole logging data <lb/>there are some key differences compared to the core logging <lb/>data, such as the evolution of E2 and E3 within the respective <lb/>datasets. The base of E2 is dominated by a mass-transport de-<lb/>posit (of a carbonate-rich facies) with low-amplitude MS val-<lb/>ues at the base (Fig. 6). Overlying are higher-amplitude MS <lb/>values within an organic-rich interval containing sand, ob-<lb/>served within the core logging data. In contrast, the borehole <lb/>logging MS data show a gradual decrease in MS values from <lb/>the base to the top of the deposit (see more details Sect. S7). <lb/>The interval between logging tie points (LTPs) 16 and 18 <lb/>shows more stable MS values within the borehole logging <lb/>data compared to more MS fluctuations within the core log-<lb/>ging data. These differences might be related to the main cor-<lb/>ing gap occurring at the base of E7. Furthermore, the interval <lb/>between LTPs 27 and 28 shows high-amplitude values within <lb/>the core logging data, which are not observed clearly within <lb/>the borehole logging data. The lack of high-amplitude val-<lb/>ues within the borehole logging data could be related to the <lb/>lower vertical resolution of the borehole logging sensor. Fur-<lb/>ther downcore of LTP 27, mostly only low confidence log-<lb/>ging tie points could be identified. This could be related to <lb/>more appended core segments within the core logging data, <lb/>using only hole B for the deepest part. <lb/>5.3 Lithostratigraphy in chronostratigraphic and <lb/>prehistoric view <lb/>The lithostratigraphic Late Pleistocene-Holocene boundary <lb/>in Lake Hallstatt occurs at ∼ 47.6 m, with a change from <lb/>finely laminated (&lt; 1 cm) gray silty-clayey carbonate mud <lb/>(below) towards laminated dark-gray clayey-silty carbonate <lb/>mud interbedded with millimeter-to centimeter-thick graded <lb/>turbidites (above). The Bacon (Blaauw and Christen, 2011) <lb/>modeled age of 11 623 ± 150 cal BP overlaps the described <lb/>transition at Mondsee with 11 580-11 540 cal BP (Lauter-<lb/>bach et al., 2011), or the Meerfelder Maar varve chronology <lb/>(11 590 varve years BP; Brauer et al., 1999). Also, promi-<lb/>nent end moraines formed during the Younger Dryas (Ege-<lb/>sen Stadial) south of Lake Hallstatt on the Dachstein Massif <lb/>(locally known as Taubenkar stand; Van Husen, 1977). The <lb/>bottommost dated sample, with a radiocarbon age range of <lb/>12 682-12 748 cal BP at ∼ 50.55 m lies within the Allerød-<lb/>Younger Dryas boundary which was described at Mond-<lb/>see with 12 760-12 590 cal BP (Lauterbach et al., 2011). <lb/>Hence, the Allerød-Younger Dryas transition likely occurs <lb/>at ∼ 50.55 m c.d., which aligns with a decrease in GR and <lb/>MS values downcore. <lb/>The Late Pleistocene (Unit 2 and LU9) covers the final <lb/>part of the Upper Paleolithic (until 11 623 cal BP, Fig. 6), <lb/>followed by six subunits (subunit A-F) and eight log-<lb/>ging units (LUs 1-8) formed during the Holocene. The <lb/>Early Holocene (subunit F, LU8) covers the Mesolithic and <lb/>shows moderate fluctuations in physical properties (Fig. 6). <lb/>The subsequent intervals -(i) subunit E/LU7 (onset at <lb/>∼ 7525 ± 51 cal BP), (ii) subunit D, lower part/LU6 (onset <lb/>at 5998 ± 115 cal BP), (iii) subunit D, upper part/LU5 (on-<lb/>set at ∼ 3769 ± 91 cal BP), and (iv) subunit C/LU3 and LU4 <lb/>(onset at ∼ 2576 ± 77 cal BP) -show four distinct phases of <lb/>drastic changes in physical properties (Fig. 6). We observe <lb/>strong variations in the sedimentation rate (indicated by the <lb/>changing slope angle in the age-depth model) and multiple <lb/>large-scale mass movements. Chronologically, these four in-<lb/>tervals cover the prehistoric and large parts of the historical <lb/>period (from the Neolithic to Medieval periods, Fig. 6) and <lb/>thus include the onset and development of human activity in <lb/>the Hallstatt area. The oldest evidence for human activity in <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>15 <lb/></page>

	<body>the vicinity of Lake Hallstatt dates to the 7th and 6th mil-<lb/>lennium BP (Festi et al., 2021). The visually observed sed-<lb/>imentary change (as described in Sect. 4.3), as well as the <lb/>physical property change at the transition towards the Copper <lb/>Age (6250-4150 cal BP; subunit E (upper part) and subunit D <lb/>(lower part)/LU6) will help to better characterize the role of <lb/>human influence in this early phase. It is important to note <lb/>that archeological as well as paleoecological data indicated <lb/>the possibility of salt extraction as early as the 7th/6th mil-<lb/>lennium BP (Festi et al., 2021). Fully developed large-scale <lb/>underground salt mining is evidenced from ∼ 3400 cal BP <lb/>(Middle/Late Bronze Age) onwards. The Bronze Age and <lb/>Early Iron Age mining phases were disrupted by large-scale <lb/>mass movements several times (Festi et al., 2021; Grabner <lb/>et al., 2021; Knierzinger et al., 2021). The highly resolved <lb/>sedimentary record presented here will help elucidate the im-<lb/>pact of mining as well as societal reaction to geohazards at <lb/>a high chronological resolution as well as the chronology of <lb/>the Late Iron Age salt mining in Hallstatt and the question of <lb/>a continuity into Roman times (cf. Festi et al., 2021). <lb/>The Late Holocene consisting of LU1/subunit B and sub-<lb/>unit A, covers the High to Late Medieval period and Modern <lb/>Era, with the onset of subunit B (∼ 711 ± 34 cal BP) likely <lb/>being influenced by increased human environmental interac-<lb/>tion, such as increased salt mining with related timber ex-<lb/>ploitation and forest clearance, transport of timber and salt <lb/>on the lake (Festi et al., 2021; Urstöger, 2000), and poten-<lb/>tial river diversions further upstream close to Lake Altaussee <lb/>(Lamer, 1998). The change to subunit A around the mid-17th <lb/>century CE could be related to systematic forest management <lb/>(Lauterbach et al., 2023; Urstöger, 2000). <lb/>6 Conclusions and outlook <lb/>The Hipercorig system successfully drilled a high-resolution <lb/>Late Pleistocene to Holocene sediment succession of Lake <lb/>Hallstatt and revealed 10 unique major event deposits, with <lb/>more than 0.3 m thickness (E2-E11) and performed bore-<lb/>hole logging through the Hipercorig system for the first time. <lb/>The borehole logging and sediment logging reveal several <lb/>dynamic phases during the Holocene, with changing accu-<lb/>mulation rate and physical property fluctuations, and corre-<lb/>late very well with each other. Also, the upper 15 m of the <lb/>composite profile correlate very well with the HAS_2016-1 <lb/>core (Lauterbach et al., 2023). However, the E2 and E3 event <lb/>deposits show high spatial heterogeneity. <lb/>The inner Alpine landscape of Lake Hallstatt, within the <lb/>UNESCO World Heritage region, is described as a fasci-<lb/>nating geomorphological laboratory (Weidinger and Götz, <lb/>2022). The successful drilling campaign of the Hiper-<lb/>corig platform enables a high-resolution multi-proxy and <lb/>multi-disciplinary-based analysis of the Late Pleistocene to <lb/>Holocene sedimentary succession at Lake Hallstatt. The <lb/>international research team will proceed on several main <lb/>frontiers: (i) archeology, (ii) paleoclimate, and (iii) paleo-<lb/>geohazards. This should be done in order to link the H 3 sedi-<lb/>ment sequence to archeological findings and to better under-<lb/>stand human-environment interaction as well as to disentan-<lb/>gle the probable onset and impact of human activities from <lb/>climatic and environmental drivers within the surroundings <lb/>of Lake Hallstatt. In combination with existing neighboring <lb/>lake research projects (e.g., Mondsee, Lake Altaussee) it will <lb/>be possible to extract local from regional signals and com-<lb/>pare them. Establishing a high-resolution event record for <lb/>Lake Hallstatt will enable the analysis of the magnitude and <lb/>frequency of natural hazards and contribute to a regional/-<lb/>global climatic sediment archive on a Holocene timescale in <lb/>order to better understand the long-term changes within in-<lb/>termountain lake systems. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Code availability. The code for visualizing the MSCL data <lb/>is available at https://github.com/Marcel1415/splice (last access: <lb/>24 May 2023; DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7966002, Or-<lb/>tler, 2023). <lb/>Data availability. Preliminary data outlined in this report are not <lb/>publicly available as they are still being evaluated and expanded. <lb/>Upon completion, all data will be made available when scientific <lb/>papers and reports are published. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available <lb/>online at: https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions. MS, KK, AB, SCF, and HR designed the <lb/>research and secured funding. MO, JK, SCF, AB, IH, JNH, and MS <lb/>analyzed the data. MO and AB conducted the core descriptions, and <lb/>MO developed the composite stratigraphy. MO wrote the paper and <lb/>produced the figures with input from all the co-authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. This research was supported by the Aus-<lb/>trian Academy of Sciences (ÖAW) through (i) the ÖAW-ESS <lb/>Project FACEALPS: 3500 years of man-environmental inter-<lb/>relation in the UNESCO World heritage region of Hallstatt-<lb/>Dachstein/Salzkammergut (PI: Kerstin Kowarik; https://facealps. <lb/></div>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<div type="acknowledgement">wordpress.com, last access: 24 May 2023), (ii) the ÖAW-ESS-<lb/>IGCP Project S 4 LIDE -Hallstatt Studying the Significance of <lb/>Subaqueous Slides in Lake Hallstatt (https://www.uibk.ac.at/en/ <lb/>geologie/research/sediment/research/projects/s4lide-hallstatt/, last <lb/>access: 24 May 2023), and (iii) the ÖAW Project Hipercorig <lb/>Hallstatt History (H 3 ): Accessing a deep time window of Lake <lb/>Hallstatt&apos;s preHistory (PI: Michael Strasser; https://www.uibk.ac. <lb/>at/en/geologie/research/sediment/research/projects/h3-project/, last <lb/>access: 24 May 2023). We also want to thank the project support-<lb/>ers: Freunde des Naturhistorischen Museums Wien, Österreichis-<lb/>che Bundesforste, Salinen Austria AG, Salzwelten GmbH, Frauen-<lb/>hofer IEG (Volker Wittig, Timo König, Sebastian Krusenbaum), <lb/>the German Scientific Earth Probing Consortium (GESEP), and the <lb/>UWITEC GmbH (especially the drilling operators: Richard Nieder-<lb/>reiter and Daniel and Martin Niederreiter). We also thank the <lb/>drilling supervisor Ulli Raschke as well as Markus Erhardt, Ger-<lb/>ald Degenhart, and Wolfgang Recheis for the medical CT measure-<lb/>ments at the Medical University of Innsbruck; Hannah B. Stanger <lb/>for the preparation of the 14 C samples; Werner H. Schoch for the de-<lb/>termination of wood remains; Felix Lang for information on the Ro-<lb/>man Period in our research area; and Chiara Ide, Nicholas J. Lewis, <lb/>Julia Rechenmacher, Johanna G. Pöll, Markus Niederstätter, Anja <lb/>B. Grießer, and Hannah Braun for assisting during the core open-<lb/>ing week. Moreover, we want to thank crucial project members <lb/>Martin Töpfer, Daniel Brandner, and Flavio S. Anselmetti for their <lb/>support and discussions. Copernicus Land Monitoring Services and <lb/>http://data.gv.at (last access: 12 January 2021) are thanked for pro-<lb/>viding the DEM data. IHS Markit is acknowledged for their educa-<lb/>tional grant program providing the Kingdom seismic interpretation <lb/>software. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Financial support. This research was supported by the Austrian <lb/>Academy of Sciences (ÖAWESS Project FACEALPS, ÖAW-ESS-<lb/>IGCP Project S 4 LIDE and the ÖAW Project Hipercorig Hallstatt <lb/>History), the Freunde des Naturhistorischen Museums Wien, Öster-<lb/>reichische Bundesforste, Salinen Austria AG, Salzwelten GmbH, <lb/>Frauenhofer IEG, the German Scientific Earth Probing Consortium <lb/>(GESEP), and UWITEC GmbH. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Nadine Hallmann <lb/>and reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Adler, C., Wester, P., Bhatt, I., Huggel, C., Insarov, G. E., More-<lb/>croft, M. D., Muccione, V., and Prakash, A.: Cross-Chapter <lb/>Paper 5: Mountains, edited by: Pörtner, H. O., Roberts, D. <lb/>C., Tignor, M., Poloczanska, E. S., Mintenbeck, K., Alegría, <lb/>A., Craig, M., Langsdorf, S., Löschke, S., Möller, V., Okem, <lb/>A., and Rama, B., Climate Change 2022: Impacts, Adapta-<lb/>tion and Vulnerability. Contribution of Working Group II to <lb/>the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel <lb/>on Climate Change, Cambridge University Press, 2273-2318, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009325844.022, 2022. <lb/>Arias, P. A., Bellouin, N., Coppola, E., Jones, R. G., Krinner, G., <lb/>Marotzke, J., Naik, V., Palmer, M. D., Plattner, G.-K., Rogelj, J., <lb/>Rojas, M., Sillmann, J., Storelvmo, T., Thorne, P. W., Trewin, B., <lb/>Achuta Rao, K., Adhikary, B., Allan, R. P., Armour, K., Bala, <lb/>G., Barimalala, R., Berger, S., Canadell, J. G., Cassou, C., Cher-<lb/>chi, A., Collins, W., Collins, W. D., Connors, S. L., Corti, S., <lb/>Cruz, F., Dentener, F. J., Dereczynski, C., Di Luca, A., Diongue <lb/>Niang, A., Doblas-Reyes, F. J., Dosio, A., Douville, H., En-<lb/>gelbrecht, F., Eyring, V., Fischer, E., Forster, P., Fox-Kemper, <lb/>B., Fuglestvedt, J. S., Fyfe, J. C., Gillett, N. P., Goldfarb, L., <lb/>Gorodetskaya, I., Gutierrez, J. M., Hamdi, R., Hawkins, E., He-<lb/>witt, H. T., Hope, P., Islam, A. S., Jones, C., Kaufman, D. S., <lb/>Kopp, R. E., Kosaka, Y., Kossin, J., Krakovska, S., Lee, J.-Y., <lb/>Li, J., Mauritsen, T., Maycock, T. K., Meinshausen, M., Min, <lb/>S.-K., Monteiro, P. M. S., Ngo-Duc, T., Otto, F., Pinto, I., Pi-<lb/>rani, A., Raghavan, K., Ranasinghe, R., Ruane, A. C., Ruiz, L., <lb/>Sallée, J.-B., Samset, B. H., Sathyendranath, S., Seneviratne, S. <lb/>I., Sörensson, A. A., Szopa, S., Takayabu, I., Tréguier, A.-M., <lb/>van den Hurk, B., Vautard, R., von Schuckmann, K., Zaehle, <lb/>S., Zhang, X., and Zickfeld, K.: Technical Summary, edited by: <lb/>Masson-Delmotte, V., Zhai, P., Pirani, A., Connors, S. L., Péan, <lb/>C., Berger, S., Caud, N., Chen, Y., Goldfarb, L., Gomis, M. I., <lb/>Huang, M., Leitzell, K., Lonnoy, E., Matthews, J. B. R., May-<lb/>cock, T. K., Waterfield, T., Yelekçi, O., Yu, R., and Zhou, B.: <lb/>Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution <lb/>of Working Group I to the Sixth Assessment Report of the In-<lb/>tergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, Cambridge Univer-<lb/>sity Press, 33-144, https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009157896.002, <lb/>2021. <lb/>Barsch, E., Kowarik, K., Rodler, K., Hörweg, C., Reschreiter, H., <lb/>Sattmann, H., and Walochnik, J.: First molecular data on the hu-<lb/>man roundworm Ascaris lumbricoides species complex from the <lb/>Bronze and Iron Age in Hallstatt, Austria, Sci. Rep., 13, 12055, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-38989-8, 2023. <lb/>Baumgarten, H., Wonik, T., and Kwiecien, O.: Facies characteriza-<lb/>tion based on physical properties from downhole logging for the <lb/>sediment record of Lake Van, Turkey, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 104, <lb/>85-96, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.03.016, 2014. <lb/>Baumgarten, H., Wonik, T., Tanner, D. C., Francke, A., Wag-<lb/>ner, B., Zanchetta, G., Sulpizio, R., Giaccio, B., and No-<lb/>made, S.: Age-depth model of the past 630 kyr for Lake <lb/>Ohrid (FYROM/Albania) based on cyclostratigraphic analysis <lb/>of downhole gamma ray data, Biogeosciences, 12, 7453-7465, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-7453-2015, 2015. <lb/>Behrends, K., Heeschen, K., Kunkel, C., and Conze, R.: The mobile <lb/>Drilling Information System (mDIS) for core repositories, EGU <lb/>General Assembly 2020, Online, 4-8 May 2020, EGU2020-<lb/>13663, https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-egu2020-13663, 2020. <lb/>Beiwl, C. and Mühlmann, H.: Atlas der natürlichen Seen Öster-<lb/>reichs mit einer Fläche &gt; 50 ha: Morphometrie -Typisierung <lb/>-Trophie, Stand 2005, Bundesamt für Wasserwirtschaft, Wien, <lb/>147 pp., ISBN 3-901605-29-0, 2008. <lb/>Blaauw, M. and Christen, J. A.: Flexible paleoclimate age-depth <lb/>models using an autoregressive gamma process, Bayesian Anal., <lb/>6, 457-474, https://doi.org/10.1214/11-BA618, 2011. <lb/>Blöschl, G., Kiss, A., Viglione, A., Barriendos, M., Böhm, O., <lb/>Brázdil, R., Coeur, D., Demarée, G., Llasat, M. C., Macdon-<lb/>ald, N., Retsö, D., Roald, L., Schmocker-Fackel, P., Amorim, I., <lb/>Bělínová, M., Benito, G., Bertolin, C., Camuffo, D., Cornel, D., <lb/>Doktor, R., Elleder, L., Enzi, S., Garcia, J. C., Glaser, R., Hall, J., <lb/>Haslinger, K., Hofstätter, M., Komma, J., Limanówka, D., Lun, <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>D., Panin, A., Parajka, J., Petrić, H., Rodrigo, F. S., Rohr, C., <lb/>Schönbein, J., Schulte, L., Silva, L. P., Toonen, W. H. J., Va-<lb/>lent, P., Waser, J., and Wetter, O.: Current European flood-rich <lb/>period exceptional compared with past 500 years, Nature, 583, <lb/>560-566, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2478-3, 2020. <lb/>Brauer, A., Endres, C., and Negendank, J. F. W.: Lateglacial cal-<lb/>endar year chronology based on annually laminated sediments <lb/>from Lake Meerfelder Maar, Germany, Quatern. Int., 61, 17-25, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1040-6182(99)00014-2, 1999. <lb/>Brigham-Grette, J., Melles, M., Minyuk, P., Andreev, A., Tarasov, <lb/>P., DeConto, R., Koenig, S., Nowaczyk, N., Wennrich, V., Rosén, <lb/>P., Haltia, E., Cook, T., Gebhardt, C., Meyer-Jacob, C., Snyder, J., <lb/>and Herzschuh, U.: Pliocene Warmth, Polar Amplification, and <lb/>Stepped Pleistocene Cooling Recorded in NE Arctic Russia, Sci-<lb/>ence, 340, 1421-1427, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1233137, <lb/>2013. <lb/>Bronk <lb/>Ramsey, <lb/>C.: <lb/>Bayesian <lb/>Analysis <lb/>of <lb/>Ra-<lb/>diocarbon <lb/>Dates, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>51, <lb/>337-360, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200033865, 2009. <lb/>Costanza, R., Graumlich, L., Steffen, W., Crumley, C., Dear-<lb/>ing, J., Hibbard, K., Leemans, R., Redman, C., and Schimel, <lb/>D.: Sustainability or Collapse: What Can We Learn from <lb/>Integrating the History of Humans and the Rest of Na-<lb/>ture?, AMBIO, 36, 522-527, https://doi.org/10.1579/0044-<lb/>7447(2007)36[522:SOCWCW]2.0.CO;2, 2007. <lb/>Croudace, I. W., Rindby, A., and Rothwell, R. G.: ITRAX: <lb/>description and evaluation of a new multi-function X-ray <lb/>core scanner, Geol. Soc. Lond. Spec. Publ., 267, 51-63, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1144/GSL.SP.2006.267.01.04, 2006. <lb/>Fernández, O., Habermüller, M., and Grasemann, B.: Hooked on <lb/>salt: Rethinking Alpine tectonics in Hallstatt (Eastern Alps, Aus-<lb/>tria), Geology, 49, 325-329, https://doi.org/10.1130/G47981.1, <lb/>2021. <lb/>Festi, D., Brandner, D., Grabner, M., Knierzinger, W., Reschre-<lb/>iter, H., and Kowarik, K.: 3500 years of environmen-<lb/>tal sustainability in the large-scale alpine mining district <lb/>of Hallstatt, Austria, J. Archaeol. Sci.-Reports, 35, 102670, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2020.102670, 2021. <lb/>Ficker, H., Gassner, H., Achleitner, D., and Schabetsberger, R.: <lb/>Ectogenic Meromixis of Lake Hallstättersee, Austria Induced <lb/>by Waste Water Intrusions from Salt Mining, Water Air Soil <lb/>Poll., 218, 109-120, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11270-010-0627-2, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Grabner, M., Reschreiter, H., Wächter, E., Mayer, K., Winner, <lb/>G., and Kowarik, K.: Die verwendeten Holzarten im prähis-<lb/>torischen Salzbergbau von Hallstatt, in: Hallstätter Beziehungs-<lb/>geschichten. Wirtschaftsstrukturen und Umfeldbeziehungen der <lb/>bronze-und ältereisenzeitlichen Salzbergbaue von Hallstatt/OÖ. <lb/>Studien zur Kulturgeschichte von Oberösterreich, vol. 50, edited <lb/>by: Kowarik, K., 83-96, ISBN 978-3-85474-353-8, 2019. <lb/>Grabner, M., Wächter, E., Nicolussi, K., Bolka, M., Sormaz, <lb/>T., Steier, P., Wild, E. M., Barth, F. E., Kern, A., Rudor-<lb/>fer, J., Kowarik, K., Stöllner, T., and Reschreiter, H.: Prehis-<lb/>toric salt mining in Hallstatt, Austria. New chronologies out <lb/>of small wooden fragments, Dendrochronologia, 66, 125814, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dendro.2021.125814, 2021. <lb/>Hajdas, I.: Radiocarbon dating and its applications in Qua-<lb/>ternary studies, E&amp;G Quaternary Sci. J., 57, 2-24, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3285/eg.57.1-2.1, 2008. <lb/>Harms, U., Raschke, U., Anselmetti, F. S., Strasser, M., Wittig, V., <lb/>Wessels, M., Schaller, S., Fabbri, S. C., Niederreiter, R., and <lb/>Schwalb, A.: Hipercorig -an innovative hydraulic coring sys-<lb/>tem recovering over 60 m long sediment cores from deep peri-<lb/>alpine lakes, Sci. Dril., 28, 29-41, https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-28-<lb/>29-2020, 2020. <lb/>IODP depth scales terminology: https://www.iodp.org/policies-and-<lb/>guidelines/142-iodp-depth-scales-terminology-april-2011/file, <lb/>last access: 6 February 2023. <lb/>Jutzeler, M., White, J. D. L., Talling, P. J., McCanta, M., Morgan, <lb/>S., Le Friant, A., and Ishizuka, O.: Coring disturbances in IODP <lb/>piston cores with implications for offshore record of volcanic <lb/>events and the Missoula megafloods, Geochem. Geophy. Geosy., <lb/>15, 3572-3590, https://doi.org/10.1002/2014GC005447, 2014. <lb/>Kiefer, C., Oswald, P., Moernaut, J., Fabbri, S. C., Mayr, C., <lb/>Strasser, M., and Krautblatter, M.: A 4000-year debris flow <lb/>record based on amphibious investigations of fan delta activity <lb/>in Plansee (Austria, Eastern Alps), Earth Surf. Dynam., 9, 1481-<lb/>1503, https://doi.org/10.5194/esurf-9-1481-2021, 2021. <lb/>Kiss, A.: Floods and Long-Term Water-Level Changes in Me-<lb/>dieval Hungary, Springer International Publishing, Cham, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-38864-9, 2019. <lb/>Knapp, S., Gilli, A., Anselmetti, F. S., Krautblatter, M., and Haj-<lb/>das, I.: Multistage Rock-Slope Failures Revealed in Lake Sed-<lb/>iments in a Seismically Active Alpine Region (Lake Oeschi-<lb/>nen, Switzerland), J. Geophys. Res.-Earth Surf., 123, 658-677, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2017JF004455, 2018. <lb/>Knierzinger, W., Festi, D., Limbeck, A., Horak, F., Brunnbauer, <lb/>L., Drollinger, S., Wagreich, M., Huang, J.-J. S., Strasser, <lb/>M., Knorr, K.-H., Reschreiter, H., Gier, S., Kofler, W., <lb/>Herzig, C., and Kowarik, K.: Multi-proxy analyses of a <lb/>minerotrophic fen to reconstruct prehistoric periods of hu-<lb/>man activity associated with salt mining in the Hall-<lb/>statt region (Austria), J. Archaeol. Sci.-Reports, 36, 102813, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2021.102813, 2021. <lb/>Kück, J., Groh, M., Töpfer, M., Jurczyk, A., and Harms, U.: New <lb/>geophysical memory-logging system for highly unstable and <lb/>inclined scientific exploration drilling, Sci. Dril., 29, 39-48, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-29-39-2021, 2021. <lb/>Lamer, R.: Das Ausseer Land: Geschichte und Kultur einer Land-<lb/>schaft, Styria, ISBN 978-3222126130, 1998. <lb/>Lankston, R. W.: J. New Display of the 1970 Flathead Lake Seis-<lb/>mic Data, 1970 Flathead Lake Seismic Survey, Edited version of <lb/>the Lankston 2011 Northwest Geology paper, Montana&apos;s Schol-<lb/>arWorks, https://scholarworks.umt.edu/flathead/13 (last access: <lb/>13 May 2023), 2017. <lb/>Lauterbach, S., Brauer, A., Andersen, N., Danielopol, D. L., Dul-<lb/>ski, P., Hüls, M., Milecka, K., Namiotko, T., Obremska, M., <lb/>Von Grafenstein, U., and Declakes Participants: Environmen-<lb/>tal responses to Lateglacial climatic fluctuations recorded in the <lb/>sediments of pre-Alpine Lake Mondsee (northeastern Alps), J. <lb/>Quaternary Sci., 26, 253-267, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.1448, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Lauterbach, S., Strasser, M., Kowarik, K., Reschreiter, H., Mandl, <lb/>G. W., Spötl, C., Plessen, B., and Brauer, A.: Large-scale <lb/>mass movements recorded in the sediments of Lake Hall-<lb/>statt (Austria)-evidence for recurrent natural hazards at a UN-<lb/>ESCO World Heritage site, J. Quaternary Sci., 38, 258-275, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.3472, 2023. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Litt, T., Anselmetti, F. S., Baumgarten, H., Beer, J., Cagatay, N., <lb/>Cukur, D., Damci, E., Glombitza, C., Haug, G., Heumann, G., <lb/>Kallmeyer, H., Kipfer, R., Krastel, S., Kwiecien, O., Meydan, A. <lb/>F., Orcen, S., Pickarski, N., Randlett, M.-E., Schmincke, H.-U., <lb/>Schubert, C. J., Sturm, M., Sumita, M., Stockhecke, M., Tomon-<lb/>aga, Y., Vigliotti, L., Wonik, T., and the PALEOVAN Scientific <lb/>Team: 500,000 Years of Environmental History in Eastern Ana-<lb/>tolia: The PALEOVAN Drilling Project, Sci. Dril., 14, 18-29, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2204/iodp.sd.14.02.2012, 2012. <lb/>Mandl, G. W., Van Husen, D., and Lobitzer, H.: Geologische Karte <lb/>der Republik Österreich 1 : 50 000, Erläuterungen zu Blatt 96 <lb/>Bad Ischl, Geologische Bundesanst, Wien, ISBN 978-3-85316-<lb/>061-9, 2012. <lb/>Melzner, S.: Ereignis-und Schadenskataster von Sturzprozessen <lb/>(Steinschlag/Felssturz) in der Gemeinde Hallstatt, in: Arbeitsta-<lb/>gung &quot;Angewandte Geowissenschaften an der GBA&quot;, edited by: <lb/>Wimmer-Frey, I., Römer, A., and Janda, C., Bad Ischl, Hallstatt, <lb/>Gmunden, 19-22 June 2017, Geologische Bundesanstalt, 289-<lb/>290, ISBN-978-3-85316-092-3, 2017. <lb/>Moernaut, J.: Time-dependent recurrence of strong earth-<lb/>quake shaking near plate boundaries: A lake sed-<lb/>iment <lb/>perspective, <lb/>Earth-Sci. <lb/>Rev., <lb/>210, <lb/>103344, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103344, 2020. <lb/>Ortler, M.: Marcel1415/splice: v0.2-alpha, Zenodo [code], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7966002, 2023. <lb/>Oswald, P., Strasser, M., Hammerl, C., and Moernaut, J.: Seismic <lb/>control of large prehistoric rockslides in the Eastern Alps, Nat. <lb/>Commun., 12, 1059, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21327-<lb/>9, 2021. <lb/>Pürstinger, C.: Verbauungsgeschichte Hallstätter Mühlbach und Re-<lb/>vision des Gefahrenzonenplans der Marktgemeinde Hallstatt, in: <lb/>Arbeitstagung &quot;Angewandte Geowissenschaften an der GBA&quot;, <lb/>edited by: Wimmer-Frey, I., Römer, A., and Janda, C., Bad Is-<lb/>chl, Hallstatt, Gmunden, 19-22 June 2017, Geologische Bunde-<lb/>sanstalt, 132-139, ISBN-978-3-85316-092-3, 2017. <lb/>Reimer, P. J., Austin, W. E. N., Bard, E., Bayliss, A., Blackwell, <lb/>P. G., Bronk Ramsey, C., Butzin, M., Cheng, H., Edwards, R. <lb/>L., Friedrich, M., Grootes, P. M., Guilderson, T. P., Hajdas, I., <lb/>Heaton, T. J., Hogg, A. G., Hughen, K. A., Kromer, B., Manning, <lb/>S. W., Muscheler, R., Palmer, J. G., Pearson, C., van der Plicht, <lb/>J., Reimer, R. W., Richards, D. A., Scott, E. M., Southon, J. R., <lb/>Turney, C. S. M., Wacker, L., Adolphi, F., Büntgen, U., Capano, <lb/>M., Fahrni, S. M., Fogtmann-Schulz, A., Friedrich, R., Köhler, <lb/>P., Kudsk, S., Miyake, F., Olsen, J., Reinig, F., Sakamoto, M., <lb/>Sookdeo, A., and Talamo, S.: The IntCal20 Northern Hemisphere <lb/>Radiocarbon Age Calibration Curve (0-55 cal kBP), Radiocar-<lb/>bon, 62, 725-757, https://doi.org/10.1017/RDC.2020.41, 2020. <lb/>Reschreiter, H. and Kowarik, K.: Bronze Age Mining in <lb/>Hallstatt. A New Picture of Everyday Life in the Salt <lb/>Mines and Beyond, Archaeologia Austriaca, 103, 99-136, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1553/archaeologia103s99, 2019. <lb/>Rohn, J., Ehret, D., Moser, M., and Czurda, K.: Prehistoric <lb/>and recent mass movements of the World Cultural Her-<lb/>itage Site Hallstatt, Austria, Environ. Geol., 47, 702-714, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00254-004-1201-2, 2005. <lb/>Rohr, C.: Measuring the frequency and intensity of floods of the <lb/>Traun River (Upper Austria), 1441-1574, Hydrolog. Sci. J., 51, <lb/>834-847, https://doi.org/10.1623/hysj.51.5.834, 2006. <lb/>Rohr, C.: Extreme Naturereignisse im Ostalpenraum, Natur-<lb/>erfahrung im Spätmittelalter und am Beginn der Neuzeit, <lb/>Umwelthistorische Forschungen, vol. 4, ISBN 9783412200428, <lb/>2007. <lb/>Sabatier, P., Moernaut, J., Bertrand, S., Van Daele, M., Kre-<lb/>mer, K., Chaumillon, E., and Arnaud, F.: A Review of <lb/>Event Deposits in Lake Sediments, Quaternary, 5, 34, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/quat5030034, 2022. <lb/>Sammartini, M., Moernaut, J., Anselmetti, F. S., Hilbe, <lb/>M., Lindhorst, K., Praet, N., and Strasser, M.: An At-<lb/>las of Mass-Transport Deposits in Lakes, in: Submarine <lb/>Landslides, Geophysical Monograph Series, edited by: <lb/>Ogata, K., Festa, A., and Pini, G. A., Wiley, 201-226, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119500513.ch13, 2019. <lb/>Schaller, S., Böttcher, M. E., Buechi, M. W., Epp, L. S., Fabbri, <lb/>S. C., Gribenski, N., Harms, U., Krastel, S., Liebezeit, A., Lind-<lb/>horst, K., Marxen, H., Raschke, U., Schleheck, D., Schmiedinger, <lb/>I., Schwalb, A., Vogel, H., Wessels, M., and Anselmetti, F. S.: <lb/>Postglacial evolution of Lake Constance: sedimentological and <lb/>geochemical evidence from a deep-basin sediment core, Swiss <lb/>J. Geosci., 115, 7, https://doi.org/10.1186/s00015-022-00412-1, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Schnurrenberger, D., Russell, J., and Kelts, K.: Clas-<lb/>sification of lacustrine sediments based on sedi-<lb/>mentary components, J. Paleolimnol., 29, 141-154, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1023270324800, 2003. <lb/>Schorn, A. and Neubauer, F.: The structure of the Hallstatt evap-<lb/>orite body (Northern Calcareous Alps, Austria): A compressive <lb/>diapir superposed by strike-slip shear?, J. Struct. Geol., 60, 70-<lb/>84, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsg.2013.12.008, 2014. <lb/>Stein, S., Geller, R. J., and Liu, M.: Why earthquake hazard maps <lb/>often fail and what to do about it, Tectonophysics, 562-563, 1-<lb/>25, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2012.06.047, 2012. <lb/>Strasser, M., Berberich, T., Fabbri, S., Hilbe, M., Huang, J.-<lb/>J. S., Lauterbach, S., Ortler, M., Rechschreiter, H., Brauer, <lb/>A., Anselmetti, F., and Kowarik, K.: Geomorphology and <lb/>event-stratigraphy of recent mass-movement processes in <lb/>Lake Hallstatt (UNESCO World Heritage Cultural Land-<lb/>scape, Austria), Geol. Soc. Lond. Spec. Publ., 500, 405-426, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1144/SP500-2019-178, 2020. <lb/>Stuiver, M. and Polach, H. A.: Discussion Report-<lb/>ing <lb/>of <lb/>14 C <lb/>Data, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>19, <lb/>355-363, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200003672, 1977. <lb/>Swierczynski, T., Lauterbach, S., Dulski, P., Delgado, J., Merz, B., <lb/>and Brauer, A.: Mid-to late Holocene flood frequency changes <lb/>in the northeastern Alps as recorded in varved sediments of <lb/>Lake Mondsee (Upper Austria), Quaternary Sci. Rev., 80, 78-<lb/>90, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2013.08.018, 2013. <lb/>Synal, H.-A., Stocker, M., and Suter, M.: MICADAS: A new com-<lb/>pact radiocarbon AMS system, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. B, 259, 7-<lb/>13, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nimb.2007.01.138, 2007. <lb/>Urstöger, H. J.: Hallstatt-Chronik: von den Anfängen bis zum <lb/>Jahr 2000. Nach Originalchroniken, Veröffentlichungen über <lb/>Hallstatt, Unterlagen aus dem Museumsarchiv und Berichten <lb/>von Zeitzeugen, Verlag d. Musealvereins Hallstatt, ISBN <lb/>3900998507, 2000. <lb/>Van Husen, D.: Zur Fazies und Stratigraphie der jungpleistozänen <lb/>Ablagerungen im Trauntal, Geolog. Bundesanstalt, 1-130 pp., <lb/>ISSN 0016-7800, 1977. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">M. Ortler et al.: Late Pleistocene to Holocene event stratigraphy of Lake Hallstatt <lb/></note>

	<page>19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Van Husen, D.: LGM and late-glacial fluctuations in <lb/>the Eastern Alps, Quatern. Int., 38-39, 109-118, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1040-6182(96)00017-1, 1997. <lb/>Van Husen, D.: Chapter 2 -Quaternary Glaciations in Austria, <lb/>in: Quaternary Glaciations -Extent and Chronology, edited by: <lb/>Ehlers, J., Gibbard, P. L., and Hughes, P. D., Elsevier, vol. 15, 15-<lb/>28, https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-444-53447-7.00002-7, 2011. <lb/>Wagner, B., Vogel, H., Francke, A., Friedrich, T., Donders, T., <lb/>Lacey, J. H., Leng, M. J., Regattieri, E., Sadori, L., Wilke, T., <lb/>Zanchetta, G., Albrecht, C., Bertini, A., Combourieu-Nebout, N., <lb/>Cvetkoska, A., Giaccio, B., Grazhdani, A., Hauffe, T., Holtvoeth, <lb/>J., Joannin, S., Jovanovska, E., Just, J., Kouli, K., Kousis, I., <lb/>Koutsodendris, A., Krastel, S., Lagos, M., Leicher, N., Levkov, <lb/>Z., Lindhorst, K., Masi, A., Melles, M., Mercuri, A. M., No-<lb/>made, S., Nowaczyk, N., Panagiotopoulos, K., Peyron, O., Reed, <lb/>J. M., Sagnotti, L., Sinopoli, G., Stelbrink, B., Sulpizio, R., <lb/>Timmermann, A., Tofilovska, S., Torri, P., Wagner-Cremer, F., <lb/>Wonik, T., and Zhang, X.: Mediterranean winter rainfall in phase <lb/>with African monsoons during the past 1.36 million years, Na-<lb/>ture, 573, 256-260, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1529-0, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Weidinger, J. T. and Götz, J.: The World Heritage Site Hallstatt-<lb/>Dachstein/Salzkammergut: A Fascinating Geomorphological <lb/>Field Laboratory, in: Landscapes and Landforms of Aus-<lb/>tria, edited by: Embleton-Hamann, C., Springer International <lb/>Publishing, Cham, 265-276, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-<lb/>92815-5_17, 2022. <lb/>Wilhelm, B., Rapuc, W., Amann, B., Anselmetti, F. S., Arnaud, F., <lb/>Blanchet, J., Brauer, A., Czymzik, M., Giguet-Covex, C., Gilli, <lb/>A., Glur, L., Grosjean, M., Irmler, R., Nicolle, M., Sabatier, P., <lb/>Swierczynski, T., and Wirth, S. B.: Impact of warmer climate <lb/>periods on flood hazard in the European Alps, Nat. Geosci., 15, <lb/>118-123, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-021-00878-y, 2022. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/sd-33-1-2024 <lb/>Sci. Dril., 33, 1-19, 2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>