<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-13T14:54:04.894483Z">13.11.2025 14:54:04</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">CYATML</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication"/>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T14:54:04.894483Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-13T14:54:04.894483Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>HAL Id: hal-01471341 <lb/>https://hal.science/hal-01471341v2 <lb/>Submitted on 21 Jan 2018 <lb/>HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access <lb/>archive for the deposit and dissemination of sci-<lb/>entific research documents, whether they are pub-<lb/>lished or not. The documents may come from <lb/>teaching and research institutions in France or <lb/>abroad, or from public or private research centers. <lb/>L&apos;archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est <lb/>destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents <lb/>scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, <lb/>émanant des établissements d&apos;enseignement et de <lb/>recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires <lb/>publics ou privés. <lb/>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License <lb/>Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a <lb/>unilateral contact constraint <lb/>Carlos Yoong, Anders Thorin, Mathias Legrand <lb/>To cite this version: <lb/>Carlos Yoong, Anders Thorin, Mathias Legrand. Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject <lb/>to a unilateral contact constraint. Nonlinear Dynamics, 2018, 91 (4), pp.2453-2476. 10.1007/s11071-<lb/>017-4025-9. hal-01471341v2 <lb/></titlePage>
	  
	  <front>Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact <lb/>constraint <lb/>Carlos Yoong -Anders Thorin -Mathias Legrand <lb/>Abstract This contribution proposes a numerical procedure <lb/>capable of performing nonsmooth modal analysis (mode shapes <lb/>and corresponding frequencies) of the autonomous wave equa-<lb/>tion defined on a finite one-dimensional domain with one end <lb/>subject to a Dirichlet condition and the other end subject to <lb/>a frictionless time-independent unilateral contact condition. <lb/>Nonsmooth modes of vibration are defined as one-parameter <lb/>continuous families of nonsmooth periodic orbits satisfying <lb/>the local equation together with the linear and nonlinear bound-<lb/>ary conditions. The analysis is performed using the Wave <lb/>Finite Element Method, which is a shock-capturing Finite <lb/>Volume Method. As opposed to the traditional Finite Element <lb/>Method with time-stepping schemes, potentially discontinu-<lb/>ous deformation, stress and velocity wave fronts induced by <lb/>the unilateral contact condition are here accurately described, <lb/>which is critical for seeking periodic orbits. Additionally, the <lb/>proposed strategy introduces neither numerical dispersion nor <lb/>artificial dissipation of energy, as required for modal analysis. <lb/>As a consequence of the mixed time-space discretization, no <lb/>impact law is needed for the well-posedness of the problem in <lb/>line with the continuous framework. <lb/>The frequency-energy dependency nonlinear spectrum of <lb/>vibration, shown in the form of backbone curves, provides <lb/>valuable insight on the dynamics. In contrast to the linear sys-<lb/>tem (without the unilateral contact condition) whose modes of <lb/>vibration are standing harmonic waves, the nonsmooth modes <lb/>of vibrations are traveling waves stemming from the unilateral <lb/>contact condition. It is also shown that the vibratory reso-<lb/>nances of the periodically-driven system with light structural <lb/>damping are well predicted by nonsmooth modal analysis. <lb/>Furthermore, the initially unstressed and prestressed configu-<lb/>rations exhibit stiffening and softening behaviors respectively, <lb/>as expected. <lb/>Keywords wave propagation nonsmooth dynamics <lb/>unilateral contact modal analysis nonlinear vibration <lb/>internal resonance <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Many industrial applications require the appropriate prediction <lb/>of the dynamics of colliding elastic bodies in their design pro-<lb/>cess [40]. Through unilateral contact forces preventing inter-<lb/>penetration of matter, a collision initiates a disturbance in the <lb/>form of a stress wave. Analytical solutions to the initial value <lb/>problem are only known for simple cases such as longitudinal <lb/>collision of rods or transverse contact of beams [17]. For more <lb/></body>

			<front>C. Yoong A. Thorin M. Legrand <lb/>Department of Mechanical Engineering, McGill University, 845 Sher-<lb/>brooke West Street, Montréal, Québec, Canada. <lb/>E-mail: carlos.yoong@mail.mcgill.ca <lb/></front>

			<body>general configurations, the solution should be approximated <lb/>numerically. However, common numerical methods, such as <lb/>Finite Element Methods (FEMs) combined with time-stepping <lb/>schemes, exhibit limitations that might be unacceptable [15, <lb/>1, 31]: spurious oscillations commonly known as Gibb&apos;s phe-<lb/>nomenon, dispersion and dissipation errors or chattering when <lb/>constitutive impact laws are implemented. Also, most energy-<lb/>preserving numerical schemes dedicated to contact dynamics <lb/>feature numerical dispersion issues [23]. <lb/>In the framework of undamped linear continuous systems, <lb/>natural modes of vibration are characterized by their natural <lb/>frequencies (eigenvalues) and normalized shapes (eigenfunc-<lb/>tions) [30]. In the phase space, linear modes can be seen as con-<lb/>tinuous families of periodic orbits describing two-dimensional <lb/>planes. For nonlinear dynamical systems, the natural modes <lb/>of vibration are known to form two-dimensional manifolds in <lb/>the phase space tangent to the previously mentioned planes at <lb/>equilibrium points [19]. These manifolds are invariant, i.e. for <lb/>any initial condition on the manifold, the solution will remain <lb/>on it as time advances [33]. Additionally, the nonlinear natural <lb/>frequency of an orbit depends on the total energy of the latter. <lb/>Most investigations and developments on nonlinear modal <lb/>analysis, conventionally within a finite dimensional framework <lb/>or equivalent, have dealt with smooth nonlinearities [19], i.e. <lb/>nonlinear terms differentiable with respect to the unknown of <lb/>the problem, mostly polynomial functions of the displacement <lb/>and velocity. The continuous mechanical system investigated <lb/>in this contribution involves a unilateral contact condition <lb/>stricto sensu. As a consequence, displacements, velocities and <lb/>accelerations are not differentiable with respect to time and <lb/>space in the usual sense. Such systems are named nonsmooth <lb/>systems [2]. Classical tools of nonlinear modal analysis rely on <lb/>smoothness and thus no longer apply. Accordingly, &quot;nonlinear <lb/>normal modes&quot; (NNMs) of vibration for nonsmooth systems <lb/>will be referred to as nonsmooth modes (NSMs), defined as <lb/>one-parameter continuous families of periodic nonsmooth <lb/>orbits. <lb/>The common method to approximate solutions of contin-<lb/>uous systems described by partial differential equations is to <lb/>first obtain, through a semi-discretization in space, a finite-<lb/>dimensional nonlinear Ordinary Differential Equation solely <lb/>depending on time. Unilateral constraints can then be incorpo-<lb/>rated via regularization to enable the use of classical nonlinear <lb/>modal analysis [7, 29, 6, 35, 9, 18, 21]; the main issue lies in <lb/>the high computational effort induced by the contact stiffness. <lb/>Another strategy consists in preserving the nonsmooth nature <lb/>of the system. It can be handled via appropriate time-stepping <lb/>nonsmooth numerical schemes [24] or semi-analytic deriva-<lb/>tions [25, 37] involving energy-preserving impact laws. A few <lb/>closed-form solutions in the form of periodic shock-waves <lb/>of an elastic string vibrating against a point obstacle are re-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>ported using the method of characteristic lines [11, 12]. This <lb/>string system shares similarities with the bar considered in the <lb/>present work for which a single continuous family of periodic <lb/>solutions was exhibited through analytical considerations [5]. <lb/>In the remainder, this family will be shown to form the first <lb/>NSM of the system. The current work proposes an approach <lb/>to numerically approximate any NSM. <lb/>By definition of NSMs, their computation relies on pe-<lb/>riodicity: the state of the system at time t 0 must be recov-<lb/>ered at some t 0 C T where T is the period, requiring nu-<lb/>merical methods that preserve total energy and are not prone <lb/>to numerical dispersion. A considerable amount of research <lb/>has been devoted to this topic with limited success [23, 20, <lb/>3]. In the present work, the Wave Finite Element Method <lb/>(WFEM) [34] is implemented in order to numerically approxi-<lb/>mate the modes of vibration of a one-dimensional finite elastic <lb/>bar subject to frictionless unilateral contact constraints. The <lb/>WFEM is a shock-capturing method-similar to the Godunov <lb/>method [16] commonly used in computation fluid dynamics-<lb/>which consists in finding and tracking waves propagating in a <lb/>mechanical system. Such shock waves are expected because <lb/>of the unilateral contact condition. The proposed method does <lb/>not introduce artificial dissipation of energy nor numerical <lb/>dispersion [41, 34]. Multidimensional problems incorporat-<lb/>ing contact conditions are not targeted in this work due to <lb/>the expected intricate interaction of compressional and shear <lb/>waves. <lb/>The paper is organized as follows. The one-dimensional <lb/>system of interest is outlined in section 2, where three different <lb/>configurations are detailed: unstressed, prestressed and stati-<lb/>cally grazing. The capability of the WFEM to handle unilateral <lb/>contact dynamics is illustrated in section 3 through a bench-<lb/>mark problem offering an exact solution. The overall strategy <lb/>capable of performing nonsmooth modal analysis is described <lb/>in sections 4 and 5. The approximate nonsmooth modes are <lb/>then characterized in section 6. Comparison with periodically <lb/>forced responses is undertaken in section 7. The implemen-<lb/>tation of WFEM is thoroughly detailed in Appendix A for a <lb/>one-dimensional problem. The enforcement of contact con-<lb/>straints within WFEM is explained in Appendix B. <lb/>2 System of interest <lb/>The system of interest is a homogeneous elastic bar of length L <lb/>and constant cross-sectional area S rigidly fixed to the ground <lb/>at its left end and whose right end is subject to a conservative <lb/>unilateral constraint as shown in Fig. 1. Within the framework <lb/>L <lb/>x <lb/>u.x; t / <lb/>g.u.L; t// <lb/>Fig. 1: One-dimensional finite elastic bar subject to unilateral <lb/>contact constraints. <lb/>of infinitely small transformations, the unknown displacement, <lb/>velocity, strain and stress fields are denoted by u.x; t /, v.x; t /, <lb/>&quot;.x; t / and .x; t / respectively where x 2 OE0 I L is the co-<lb/>ordinate of a point of the bar along its longitudinal axis in <lb/>the initial configuration and t denotes time. The quantity r.t / <lb/>is the unilateral contact force emerging at x D L. The mass <lb/>per unit volume is denoted by &gt; 0 and E &gt; 0 stands for <lb/>Young&apos;s modulus which are both, by assumption, space and <lb/>time independent. Any elastic wave traveling within the bar <lb/>thus propagates at constant velocity c D <lb/>p <lb/>E= . The signed <lb/>distance between the right end of the bar and the obstacle, or <lb/>gap function, is defined as g.u.L; t // D g 0 u.L; t /, where <lb/>g 0 is the signed distance between the unconstrained resting <lb/>position and the obstacle. In linear elasticity, the stresses read <lb/>D E&quot; where the axial strains &quot; D u ;x should be physically <lb/>admissible, that is u ;x &gt; 1. Stresses are related to the con-<lb/>tact force by .L; t / D Eu ;x .L; t / D r.t /=S . Unless stated <lb/>otherwise, there is no other external force acting on the system, <lb/>either per unit length or pointwise at the boundary. The full <lb/>formulation reads: <lb/>-Local equation: <lb/>u ;t t Eu ;xx D 0; 8x 2 0 I LOE; 8t &gt; 0 <lb/>(1) <lb/>where . / ;t t stands for the second derivative in time and <lb/>. / ;xx , for the second derivative in space. <lb/>-Homogeneous fixed (Dirichlet) boundary condition (BC) <lb/>at x D 0 and 8t &gt; 0: <lb/>u.0; t / D 0 <lb/>(2) <lb/>-Signorini complementarity condition at x D L and 8t &gt; 0: <lb/>g.u.L; t // 0; r.t / Ä 0; r.t /g.u.L; t // D 0 <lb/>(3) <lb/>-Initial conditions 8x 2 0 I LOE: <lb/>u.x; 0/ D u 0 .x/; v.x; 0/ D v 0 .x/ <lb/>(4) <lb/>where u 0 and v 0 are prescribed functions. <lb/>This problem has a unique solution which conserves the total <lb/>energy [32]. The local equation is the wave equation defined <lb/>on a finite domain. D&apos;Alembert&apos;s exact solution is the sum <lb/>of backward and forward travelling waves propagating with <lb/>velocity c and reads 8x 2 OE0 I L and 8t &gt; 0 [17]: <lb/>2u.x; t / D u ? <lb/>0 .x Cct / C u ? <lb/>0 .x ct / C <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>Z xCct <lb/>x ct <lb/>v ? <lb/>0 .s/ ds (5) <lb/>where u ? <lb/>0 and v ? <lb/>0 are periodic extensions on the real axis of <lb/>u 0 and v 0 defined on OE0 I L only. The period of u ? <lb/>0 and v ? <lb/>0 <lb/>depends on the boundary conditions considered. <lb/>Non-trivial periodic solutions of the contact problem de-<lb/>scribed by Eqs. (1) to (4) are successions of free phases (open <lb/>gap) and contact phases (closed gap). They can therefore be <lb/>understood as the combination of solutions to an hyperbolic <lb/>Partial Differential Equation with a switching boundary con-<lb/>dition at x D L between vanishing stress when the gap is <lb/>open to prescribed displacement when the gap is closed. The <lb/>nonlinearity in the formulation comes from the fact that the <lb/>time of switch depends on the solution. There is also a subtlety <lb/>in the BC switch at x D L: an open gap implies u ;x .L; / D 0 <lb/>while a closed gap implies a non-homogeneous prescribed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>displacement of the form u.L; / D g 0 . Accordingly, when <lb/>the gap is open, BCs at x D 0 and x D L are homogeneous <lb/>and will be referred to as fixed-free BCs in the remainder. <lb/>For a closed gap, the BC at x D 0 is homogeneous while the <lb/>BC at x D L is non-homogeneous: they will be referred as <lb/>fixed-fixed BCs. <lb/>The question is now to find the two functions u 0 and v 0 <lb/>generating a time-periodic state of the system which satisfies <lb/>the local equation (1) and properly switches between fixed-<lb/>free and fixed-fixed BCs to comply with the unilateral contact <lb/>conditions (3). This is achieved using the Wave Finite Element <lb/>Method. <lb/>3 Illustration of the capabilities of WFEM <lb/>The WFEM is detailed, including a readily-implementable <lb/>algorithm, in Appendices A (the WFEM method itself) and B <lb/>(unilateral contact conditions in WFEM). In the sequel, the <lb/>governing Eqs. (1) to (4) are equivalently recast in terms of <lb/>stresses and velocities stacked in a state vector q. The system <lb/>is discretized simultaneously in space and time with mesh <lb/>sizes x D L=N and t D x=c respectively, where N is <lb/>the number of cells used for space discretization. The overall <lb/>dynamics is approximated by Q .n/ D AQ .n 1/ where Q .n/ D <lb/>OEQ .n/ <lb/>1 : : : Q .n/ <lb/>N and Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>stands for the averaged state q in cell <lb/>C i at time t n D nt. The matrix A encompasses stiffness and <lb/>inertial terms as well as the appropriate boundary conditions. <lb/>Two matrices are constructed: A D A f for free-free BCs (open <lb/>gap) and A D A c for fixed-free BCs (closed gap). <lb/>In this section, the capabilities of the WFEM are succinctly <lb/>illustrated on a unilaterally constrained linearly elastic finite <lb/>bar benchmark, for which analytical solutions are known [15]. <lb/>It can be compared to other time-integration schemes based <lb/>on a semi-discretization in space through the commonly used <lb/>FEM [41]. The problem consists in an unclamped homoge-<lb/>neous elastic rod of length L and constant cross-sectional <lb/>area S bouncing against an obstacle due to a distributed inter-<lb/>nal force, as shown in Fig. 2. Parameters reported in [15] are <lb/>F .x; t / D F 0 <lb/>x <lb/>u.x; t/ <lb/>L <lb/>g.u.L; t// <lb/>Fig. 2: Benchmark bouncing homogeneous elastic bar (used <lb/>in section 3). <lb/>considered and listed in Tab. 1. The displacement (retrieved <lb/>from stress via an integration in space), velocity, contact force <lb/>an total energy is depicted for an isolated periodic solution <lb/>in Fig. 3, for N D 100 cells. Total energy and periodicity <lb/>are accurately preserved and the nonsmooth behaviour is well <lb/>recovered. Curves in Fig. 3 and the exact curves are undis-<lb/>tinguishable [41]. In contrast, traditional numerical schemes <lb/>dedicated to contact dynamics and commonly based on the <lb/>standard FEM show spurious oscillations on the contact dis-<lb/>placement and stress [31]. Moreover, these oscillations do not <lb/>Table 1: Simulation parameters for the considered benchmark, <lb/>from [15] <lb/>Parameter Value <lb/>Young&apos;s Modulus, E <lb/>900 Pa <lb/>Density, <lb/>1 kg m 2 <lb/>Rod Length, L 10 m <lb/>Initial Gap, g 0 5 m <lb/>External Body Force, F 0 10 N m 1 <lb/>Wave Velocity, c D <lb/>p <lb/>E= <lb/>30 m s 1 <lb/>0 1 2 3 4 5 <lb/>Displacement, u.L; t / <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Velocity, v.L; t / <lb/>[ 10] <lb/>0 <lb/>-1 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-3 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-5 <lb/>Contact force [ 10 2 <lb/>] <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>Time <lb/>Normalized energy [ 500] <lb/>Fig. 3: Periodic motion of the bouncing bar obtained by <lb/>WFEM. <lb/>disappear when the time step decreases and might increase in-<lb/>stead. Various solutions have been proposed to alleviate these <lb/>difficulties, mainly by adapting the time-domain discretiza-<lb/>tion. They all fail by either adding non-physical damping, or <lb/>not strictly respecting the contact constraint. This is partly ex-<lb/>plained by the inability of standard finite elements to properly <lb/>propagate information. Also, the implementation of an impact <lb/>law yields unavoidable drawbacks, such as chattering if energy <lb/>conservation is targeted [1]. None of these issues are present <lb/>with WFEM that produces accurate approximations with a <lb/>reasonable number of cells. This can be partly explained by <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>the fact that shock wave propagation is accurately captured by <lb/>this scheme. <lb/>4 Periodic solutions <lb/>NSMs are regarded as continuous families of periodic solu-<lb/>tions satisfying the local equations and the boundary con-<lb/>ditions including the unilateral contact conditions. Finding <lb/>a periodic solution translates into finding initial conditions <lb/>u 0 .x/ and v 0 .x/ and a period T which generate a solution <lb/>satisfying Eqs. (1) to (4) in conjunction with the periodicity <lb/>conditions <lb/>( <lb/>u.x; t C T / D u.x; t / <lb/>v.x; t C T / D v.x; t / <lb/>; 8x 2 OE0 I L; 8t &gt; 0: <lb/>(6) <lb/>Without loss of generality, it is assumed that a period starts <lb/>with a free phase at t D 0 and ends with a contact phase at t D <lb/>T . In the general case, a pattern of free and contact phases will <lb/>arise within one period. The k successive transition instants <lb/>between free and contact phases are denoted by T i with 0 &lt; <lb/>T 1 &lt; : : : &lt; T k 1 &lt; T k D T and are unknown. The sought <lb/>solution is then an unknown combination of functions of the <lb/>form (5) where u ? <lb/>0 and v ? <lb/>0 switch between fixed-free BCs <lb/>over OE0 I T 1 , OET 2 I T 3 , etc. and fixed-fixed BCs over OET 1 I T 2 , <lb/>OET 3 I T 4 , etc., which must be periodic in time. Connecting <lb/>these portions of D&apos;Alembert solutions in order to form a <lb/>periodic solution is quite a formidable task. <lb/>The WFEM approximately solves the above problem by <lb/>building two matrices, A f for the fixed-free BC and A c for <lb/>the fixed-fixed BC, so that mapping an initial state to the <lb/>current state after a succession of free and contact phases is <lb/>straightforward via Eq. (40). In contrast to more commonly-<lb/>used time-integration schemes based on FEM, the WFEM <lb/>perfectly preserves energy (in this one-dimensional configura-<lb/>tion at least), which is crucial for the computation of periodic <lb/>solutions. Additionally, for the problem at hand, this scheme <lb/>is not prone to numerical dispersion and does not suffer from <lb/>the well-known Gibb&apos;s phenomenon commonly observed in <lb/>unilateral contact dynamics [15]. <lb/>The FEM framework without regularization of the com-<lb/>plementarity conditions in continuous time is used for the <lb/>calculation of nonsmooth modes in [25, 37, 38]. However, the <lb/>formulation relies on a space-discretization and hence requires <lb/>the incorporation of an impact law-for instance Newton&apos;s im-<lb/>pact law-to ensure the well-posedness of the problem. Since <lb/>energy conservation is necessary to find nonsmooth modes, a <lb/>perfectly elastic impact law should be considered, from which <lb/>would emanate impulsive dynamics and chattering. This ex-<lb/>cludes periodic motions with &quot;lasting&quot; non-impulsive contact <lb/>phases similar to those of the periodically bouncing elastic bar <lb/>exposed earlier. &quot;Lasting&quot; contact phases can only be obtained <lb/>with a dissipative inelastic impact law. By simultaneously <lb/>discretizing the governing equations in space and time in ac-<lb/>cordance with the characteristic lines, the WFEM accurately <lb/>propagates shock waves. This probably explains why no im-<lb/>pact law is needed in this framework; however, the authors are <lb/>not aware of a formal proof of this assertion. <lb/>5 Nonsmooth modal analysis <lb/>Nonsmooth modal analysis characterizes vibratory mechan-<lb/>ical systems with nonsmooth nonlinearities [24, 25, 38] by <lb/>searching for one-parameter continuous families of periodic <lb/>trajectories forming manifolds in the phase space. In this work, <lb/>the targeted solutions are assumed to comprise free phases <lb/>(open gap) as well as contact phases (closed gap), as described <lb/>in section 4. An example of an admissible periodic solution <lb/>with two free phases and two contact phases is depicted in <lb/>Fig. 4. <lb/>u.L; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>closed <lb/>open <lb/>closed <lb/>open <lb/>T <lb/>T 1 <lb/>T 2 <lb/>T 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>t <lb/>Fig. 4: Admissible periodic bar end displacement with closed <lb/>and open gap switches. <lb/>5.1 Problem formulation <lb/>As stated previously, the motion is uniquely determined by <lb/>the initial conditions. The aim is to find such initial conditions <lb/>which generate a periodic motion in the spirit of shooting <lb/>methods [4]. If such periodic solutions exist, the formulation <lb/>reduces to finding their period T and the appropriate initial <lb/>conditions satisfying <lb/>q.x; T / D q.x; 0/; 8x 2 OE0 I L: <lb/>(7) <lb/>In the discrete setting of the WFEM, this reduces to finding <lb/>n T and the vector of initial conditions Q .0/ such that Q .n T / D <lb/>Q .0/ where n T is the number of steps required to cover the <lb/>period T . In their simplest incarnation, the sought periodic <lb/>solutions are only composed of one free phase and one contact <lb/>phase per period 1 even though more complicated patterns <lb/>are expected to exist. Accordingly, the solution is assumed <lb/>to be in open contact (free phase) for m consecutive steps <lb/>and in closed contact (contact phase) for p consecutive steps. <lb/>Invoking Eq. (40), the state of the system after n T D m C p <lb/>time steps emanating from initial state Q .0/ reads <lb/>Q .n T / D A p <lb/>c A m <lb/>f Q .0/ ; <lb/>(8) <lb/>with the origin of time taken at the beginning of the free <lb/>phase. Both matrices A c and A f are known, see Appendix A. <lb/>The duration of free and contact phases corresponding to <lb/>periodic motions are not known a priori, so the integers m and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 With this assumption, the solution features one gap closure and one <lb/>gap opening per period. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>p leading to acceptable solutions are unknowns of the problem. <lb/>By enforcing the periodicity conditions, Eq. (8) simplifies to <lb/>.A p <lb/>c A m <lb/>f <lb/>I/Q .0/ D 0: <lb/>(9) <lb/>An initial condition Q .0/ satisfying Eq. (9) is called a potential <lb/>solution for given p and m. Indeed, potential solutions may <lb/>not be actual solutions of the initial problem: nothing prevents <lb/>them from penetrating the rigid foundation during free phase <lb/>and/or the corresponding contact force could be non-negative: <lb/>these conditions cannot be enforced in Eq. (9). Consequently, <lb/>potential solutions are called admissible solutions if they sat-<lb/>isfy the following additional conditions: <lb/>COND1 Free phase: u .n/ <lb/>N C1=2 6 g 0 and r .n/ D 0 <lb/>for n D 0; 1; : : : ; m. <lb/>COND2 Contact phase: u .n/ <lb/>N C1=2 D g 0 and r .n/ 6 0 <lb/>for n D m C 1; m C 2; : : : ; m C p. <lb/>COND3 Material impenetrability: &quot; .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>&gt; 1 <lb/>for n D 0; 1; : : : ; m C p and i D 1; : : : ; N . <lb/>where u .n/ <lb/>N C1=2 <lb/>u.L; T / and &quot; .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>is the discretized strain <lb/>field, both retrieved from discretized stresses. To summarize, <lb/>periodic solutions satisfying contact conditions are obtained <lb/>by solving the problem: Find m 2 N , p 2 N , and initial con-<lb/>dition Q .0/ 2 R 2N such that Eq. (9) together with COND1, <lb/>COND2 and COND3 are simultaneously satisfied. <lb/>5.2 Solution procedure <lb/>For specified m and p, a periodic motion necessarily corre-<lb/>sponds to an initial condition which is in the kernel of the <lb/>operator S T D A p <lb/>c A m <lb/>f <lb/>I as highlighted in Eq. (9), that <lb/>is Q .0/ 2 ker S T . The dimension h of ker S T depends on <lb/>the doublet .m; p/. A non-trivial solution may exist only if <lb/>h &gt; 0. If h &gt; 0 and fe 1 ; e 2 ; : : : ; e h g is a basis of ker S T , then <lb/>Q .0/ D ˛1e 1 C ˛2e 2 C : : : C ˛he h for some ˛1; ˛2; : : : ; ˛h. <lb/>The state Q .n/ is completely determined by Q .0/ via Eq. (46). <lb/>Accordingly, Q .n/ can be expressed in terms of the coefficients <lb/>˛1; ˛2; : : : ; ˛h only and it suffices to find appropriate values <lb/>such that COND1, COND2 and COND3 are satisfied. <lb/>Finding m, p such that h &gt; 0 is achieved by systematically <lb/>computing h for every combination of m and p within a given <lb/>range. Once an admissible solution is known, other admissible <lb/>solutions can be straightforwardly found in its vicinity. As <lb/>soon as a family of periodic orbits-involving one contact <lb/>phase and one free phase-emerges, it defines a nonsmooth <lb/>mode of vibration. <lb/>6 Results and discussion <lb/>Nonsmooth modes of vibration of the system described in <lb/>section 2 are now constructed. The parameters E, and L <lb/>are arbitrarily chosen to be unity and units are discarded. The <lb/>results are obtained for 1000 cells and time step is calculated <lb/>accordingly, i.e. t D x=c D 1=1000. <lb/>In the linear framework (that is without the contact con-<lb/>ditions), linear natural frequencies of vibration denoted ! k <lb/>for fixed-free boundary conditions and k for fixed-fixed <lb/>boundary conditions are <lb/>! k D <lb/>.2k 1/ c <lb/>2L <lb/>D .2k 1/! 1 ; k 2 N <lb/>k D <lb/>k c <lb/>L <lb/>D k 1 ; k 2 N : <lb/>(10) <lb/>It is expected that the slightly damped linear system under <lb/>consideration periodically forced in a neighborhood of these <lb/>frequencies will resonate. Conversely, in the nonlinear frame-<lb/>work (that is with contact conditions), such frequencies do <lb/>not have the same physical interpretation anymore: the nonlin-<lb/>ear system will resonate close to other unknown frequencies <lb/>which are calculated by the nonsmooth modal analysis, for a <lb/>given level of energy. The nonlinear system can also feature <lb/>internal resonances where two or more NSMs interact [22]; <lb/>for instance, driving the system in the neighborhood of a high-<lb/>frequency NSM may activate a large amplitude low-frequency <lb/>NSM [19]. Note that the system of interest satisfies a com-<lb/>plete internal resonance condition in the sense that ! k and k , <lb/>k D 2; : : : ; 1 are all multiples of ! 1 and 1 , respectively. <lb/>Moreover, a nonlinear system may exhibit subharmonic and <lb/>superharmonic resonances in the vicinity of .p! k /=q, for p, <lb/>q positive integers such that 0 &lt; p=q &lt; 1 and 1 &lt; p=q, <lb/>respectively [19]. <lb/>In this work, Frequency-Energy plots are preferably used, <lb/>quoting [19]: &quot;a nonlinear modal motion is represented by <lb/>a point in such plots, which are drawn at a frequency corre-<lb/>sponding to the minimal period of the periodic motion and <lb/>at an energy equal to the conserved total energy during the <lb/>periodic motion. A branch, represented by a solid line, is a <lb/>family of nonlinear modal motions possessing the same qual-<lb/>itative features&quot;. The terminology &quot;branch&quot; and &quot;backbone <lb/>curve&quot; is used interchangeably in the remainder. The reported <lb/>frequencies are normalized with respect to ! 1 and the energy <lb/>is normalized with respect to the energy of the first linear <lb/>mode grazing orbit satisfying <lb/>max <lb/>t 2R <lb/>u.L; t / D g 0 : <lb/>(11) <lb/>When the calculated periodic solutions have one free phase <lb/>and one contact phase, admissible solutions are only found <lb/>when h D 1 for various .m; p/. For h &gt; 2, potential solu-<lb/>tions failed to satisfy COND1 and COND2 simultaneously, <lb/>hence the distinction between potential and admissible. Ad-<lb/>missible solutions were found only when h equals the number <lb/>of contact phases. Additionally, recent developments, out of <lb/>the scope of the present paper, have shown that if a periodic <lb/>trajectory belongs to a continuum parameterized by T , then <lb/>the displacement must be piecewise-linear with respect to time <lb/>and space. Thus, if a periodic solution does not satisfy this <lb/>property, it is either isolated or part of a continuum of orbits <lb/>sharing the same period. <lb/>A previous investigation on the first main NSM [5] showed <lb/>that the duration of the contact phase pt is related linearly <lb/>to the duration of free phase mt when a solution belongs <lb/>to a family of periodic orbits. Numerical experiments suggest <lb/>that other branches could present similar relations, which are <lb/>employed to bound the range where m and p are iterated <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>4 <lb/>9 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>8 <lb/>5 <lb/>12 <lb/>7 <lb/>16 <lb/>9 <lb/>20 <lb/>11 <lb/>! <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>g <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 5: Frequency-Energy plot in the range OE! 1 ; 1 for <lb/>g 0 &gt; 0 [ <lb/>], g 0 D 0 [ <lb/>] and g 0 &lt; 0 [ <lb/>] with a few <lb/>subharmonics of linear modes [ ]. <lb/>for each potential backbone curve. Once a solution is found, <lb/>a point in a NSM branch is defined by the total energy of <lb/>the admissible periodic motion and the respective frequency <lb/>! D 2 =T , see Fig. 5. <lb/>If the initial gap is positive g 0 &gt; 0 (unstressed bar at <lb/>rest), NSM branches arise in the vicinity of the linear natural <lb/>frequencies ! k and subharmonics p! k =q for p; q 2 N , and <lb/>present a hardening behavior. For a &quot;negative&quot; gap g 0 &lt; 0 <lb/>(prestressed bar at rest), the NSM branches start in the vicinity <lb/>of the linear natural frequencies k and display a softening <lb/>behavior. Finally, if the bar is statically grazing with the rigid <lb/>foundation (grazing bar at rest, that is g 0 D 0), then the NSM <lb/>branches are the vertical asymptotes common to the previous <lb/>backbone curves, as shown in Figs. 5 and 6 for the first and sec-<lb/>ond NSM, respectively. Internal resonance branches, explored <lb/>in subsection 6.3, are omitted in these figures. Identical results <lb/>were already computed for the first main NSM only [5]. Also, <lb/>a similar behavior has been observed in the frequency-energy <lb/>plot of simplified discrete models for the unstressed case with <lb/>penalized contact constraints [7, 29] and with a nonsmooth <lb/>formulation [24]. <lb/>The frequency-energy dependence exhibited by NSM is a <lb/>typical feature of nonlinear systems [19]. Interestingly, when <lb/>g 0 D 0 the system mimics a linear behavior where the fre-<lb/>quency and the shape of the orbits do not depend on their <lb/>energy. However, the behaviour remains globally nonlinear <lb/>because of the BC switches. <lb/>Though the behavior and ranges of frequencies of the <lb/>NSM branches depend on the sign of g 0 , they &quot;converge&quot; to <lb/>the branches of g 0 D 0 when g 0 ! 0, as seen in Fig. 7 for <lb/>the main NSM branch in OE! 1 ; 1 . In other words, there is no <lb/>difference between NSMs with very small positive initial gap, <lb/>zero initial gap or very small initial negative gap. Moreover, <lb/>the normalized shape of the backbone curves depend only on <lb/>the sign of g 0 . Without loss of generality and for illustration <lb/>purposes, g 0 D ˙10 3 or g 0 D 0 in the remainder. <lb/>In the following sections, a detailed study of the NSM <lb/>branches is presented. It should be noted that all the results <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>11 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>16 <lb/>5 <lb/>32 <lb/>9 <lb/>48 <lb/>13 <lb/>! <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>g <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>h <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 6: Frequency-Energy plot in the range OE! 2 ; 2 for <lb/>g 0 &gt; 0 [ <lb/>], g 0 D 0 [ <lb/>] and g 0 &lt; 0 [ <lb/>] with a few <lb/>subharmonics of linear modes [ ]. <lb/>were obtained numerically. The proposed results have to be <lb/>understood as conjectures. <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>! <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>D e c <lb/>r e a s i n g g 0 <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Energy <lb/>Fig. 7: First NSM branch as a function of g 0 . Energy is not <lb/>normalized. The backbone curves for g 0 &gt; 0 [ <lb/>] and <lb/>g 0 &lt; 0 [ <lb/>] slowly &quot;approach&quot; the backbone curve for <lb/>g 0 D 0 [ <lb/>] when g 0 ! 0. <lb/>6.1 Main backbone curves <lb/>The main backbone curves are defined as the NSM branches, <lb/>in the Frequency-Energy plot, starting in the vicinity of: <lb/>-! k , the k-th linear natural frequency for fixed-free BC, <lb/>for positive initial gap g 0 &gt; 0, <lb/>-k , the k-th linear natural frequency for fixed-fixed BC, <lb/>for negative initial gap g 0 &lt; 0. <lb/>-For g 0 D 0, the main backbone curve is a vertical line <lb/>asymptotic to its two above counterparts. Such asymptotes <lb/>are located at ! 1 .! k =! 1 C 1/ 2 =.! k =! 1 C 2/. <lb/>Periodic motions corresponding to the main backbone curves <lb/>in the range OE! 1 ; 1 are depicted in Fig. 8. Such piecewise-<lb/>linear displacements were already observed as isolated pe-<lb/>riodic solutions, without describing a continuum [11, 12]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>T c T b T a <lb/>g 0 <lb/>g 0 &gt; 0 <lb/>Displacement u <lb/>N <lb/>C1=2 <lb/>L=c <lb/>2L=c <lb/>3L=c <lb/>g 0 <lb/>g 0 D 0 <lb/>Displacement u <lb/>N <lb/>C1=2 <lb/>T c <lb/>T b <lb/>T a <lb/>g 0 <lb/>g 0 &lt; 0 <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u <lb/>N <lb/>C1=2 <lb/>Fig. 8: Periodic motions on the main NSM in the range <lb/>OE! 1 I 1 for one contact phase per period, corresponding to <lb/>points &quot;a&quot; [ <lb/>], &quot;b&quot; [ <lb/>] and &quot;c&quot; [ <lb/>] in Fig 5: unstressed <lb/>(top), initially grazing (center) and prestressed (bottom). <lb/>However, previous numerical investigations to locate fami-<lb/>lies of periodic orbits were inaccurate because of numerical <lb/>dispersion stemming from the space semi-discretization [29, <lb/>24]. <lb/>A generic space-time plot of the displacement of the bar <lb/>is provided in Fig. 9. The solution is the combination of <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>Fig. 9: Generic space-time displacement field of the main <lb/>NSM in the range OE! 1 I 1 for g 0 &gt; 0. <lb/>interacting forward and backward traveling waves which prop-<lb/>agate along the characteristic lines (t D ˙x=c), as opposed <lb/>to the linear counterpart modal motions which are sinusoidal <lb/>standing waves as seen in Fig. 10 [17]. <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>Fig. 10: Generic space-time displacement field of the first <lb/>linear mode (linear fixed-free bar without contact constraints) <lb/>at ! 1 . <lb/>Every periodic solution corresponding to the main back-<lb/>bone curve comprises exactly one free phase and one contact <lb/>phase. For a positive as well as negative initial gap, the con-<lb/>tact phase duration increases while the free phase duration <lb/>decreases as the frequency of vibration increases. When the <lb/>initial gap is zero, periodic motions have constant period equal <lb/>to T D 3L=c and the duration of contact closure is L=c while <lb/>the free phase time is 2L=c. It should also be noted that the <lb/>contact force associated to all the depicted motions is piece-<lb/>wise constant on a period. <lb/>The invariant manifold in the unstressed case is plotted <lb/>in the cross-section .u N C1=2 ; v N C1=2 ; u 3=2 /-i.e. (displace-<lb/>ment of the contacting end, velocity of the contacting end, <lb/>displacement of the right-hand side interface of cell C 1 )-of <lb/>the state-space in Fig. 11. The linear portion of the first mode <lb/>u 3=2 <lb/>u 3=2 <lb/>u 3=2 <lb/>u N C1=2 <lb/>u 3=2 <lb/>v N C1=2 <lb/>Fig. 11: Invariant manifold corresponding the main back-<lb/>bone curve in the vicinity of ! 1 plotted in the cross-<lb/>section .u N C1=2 ; v N C1=2 ; u 3=2 /. Gray surface: Poincaré <lb/>cross-section u N C1=2 D g 0 . Periodic orbit [ <lb/>]. Intersec-<lb/>tions between NSM and the Poincaré cross-section [ <lb/>]. <lb/>corresponds to an ellipse (like essentially all linear modes). <lb/>The linear and nonlinear portions of the manifold are not con-<lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>tinuously connected because of the internal resonance property. <lb/>This is visualized in Fig. 12 which shows the grazing periodic <lb/>displacements for the first linear mode and first main NSM, <lb/>both having frequency ! 1 . It should be understood that any <lb/>T 1 <lb/>g 0 <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u <lb/>N <lb/>C1=2 <lb/>Fig. 12: Grazing displacement of the contacting end at ! 1 . <lb/>First linear mode [ <lb/>] and first main NSM [ <lb/>]. <lb/>autonomous solution of frequency ! 1 shall be expressed as an <lb/>infinite Fourier sequence separated in space and time of the <lb/>form <lb/>u.x; t / D <lb/>1 <lb/>X <lb/>kD1 <lb/>sin.! k x=c/.a k cos.! k t / C b k sin.! k t // (12) <lb/>where ! k D .2k 1/ c=.2L/ D .2k 1/! 1 , k 2 N , are <lb/>the linear natural frequencies; the coefficients a k and b k are <lb/>computed from the initial conditions [17] and are not of inter-<lb/>est here. In other words, the full internal resonance condition <lb/>enjoyed by the system is such that the latter exhibits infinitely <lb/>many solutions of frequency ! 1 , the piecewise-linear grazing <lb/>solution being one of them. Accordingly, a discontinuity in <lb/>the manifold is made possible. <lb/>The above internal resonance condition can be annihilated <lb/>by changing the BC at x D 0 from Dirichlet type to Robin <lb/>type saying that the bar is attached to a spring of stiffness ı at <lb/>x D 0: ES u ;x .0; t / ıu.0; t / D 0. The solution can still be <lb/>expressed as an infinite Fourier sequence <lb/>u.x; t / D <lb/>1 <lb/>X <lb/>kD1 <lb/>k .x/.a k cos.! k t / C b k sin.! k t // <lb/>(13) <lb/>similar to Eq. (12) with k .x/ D p k cos.! k x=c/ C sin.! k x=c/ <lb/>where p k D cot.! k L=c/. The ! k are now solutions to the <lb/>transcendental equation ES! D cı cot.!L=c/ and are no <lb/>longer commensurate [30]. Assuming that the grazing solution <lb/>of the first NSM has frequency ! 1 (this should be proven!), <lb/>it will necessarily see the sole contribution of the first lin-<lb/>ear mode, which is the only motion of frequency ! 1 in se-<lb/>quence (13), that is: <lb/>u.x; t / D 1 .x/.a 1 cos.! 1 t / C b 1 sin.! 1 t //: <lb/>(14) <lb/>This necessarily induces a continuous connection between <lb/>linear and nonlinear grazing trajectories. To summarize, the <lb/>above argument stipulates that the internal resonance condition <lb/>is necessary to see a discontinuity in the modal manifold <lb/>between the linear and the nonlinear portions. However, this <lb/>is not a sufficient condition. <lb/>Figure 13 depicts the generic space-time plot (irrespec-<lb/>tive of g 0 ) of the second main backbone curve in the range <lb/>OE! 2 ; 2 showing that the periodic solutions have one &quot;node <lb/>of vibration&quot; along x-similar to the second linear mode of <lb/>the fixed-free bar [17], depicted in Fig. 14. The displace-<lb/>ment u.L; / also features one contact phase per period, by <lb/>assumption. Furthermore, for g 0 D 0, the period is 5L=.4c/ <lb/>comprising one contact phase of duration L=.4c/ and one <lb/>free phase of duration L=c, irrespective of the energy of the <lb/>system. <lb/>For illustration purposes, only the first two main NSMs <lb/>are shown in this section. However, the presented approach <lb/>can be also used to find higher frequency NSM which requires <lb/>a smaller time-step t and therefore, higher computational <lb/>effort. Periodic solutions corresponding to the main backbone <lb/>curves for higher frequencies display a similar structure: one <lb/>free phase, one contact phase, and nodes of vibration along x. <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>Fig. 13: Generic space-time displacement field of the main <lb/>NSM in the range OE! 2 I 2 . Node of vibration [ <lb/>]. <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>Fig. 14: Generic space-time displacement field of the second <lb/>linear mode (linear fixed-free bar without contact constraints) <lb/>at ! 2 . Node of vibration [ <lb/>]. <lb/>6.2 Subharmonic backbone curves <lb/>For g 0 &gt; 0, it was observed empirically that a subharmonic <lb/>backbone curve emanates in the right vicinity of a fixed-free <lb/>BCs linear subharmonic resonance frequency (vertical dashed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>lines in Figs. 5 and 6): <lb/>! D <lb/>2k.n C 1/ 1 <lb/>n C 1 <lb/>! 1 ; n; k 2 N : <lb/>(15) <lb/>For g 0 &lt; 0, a subharmonic backbone curve starts in the left <lb/>vicinity of k and shares an asymptote with the subharmonic <lb/>backbone curve for positive initial gap. Furthermore, for g 0 D <lb/>0, a subharmonic backbone curve is asymptotic to its above <lb/>counterparts. Several numerical experiments suggest that the <lb/>asymptotes (vertical brown lines in Figs. 5 and 6) are located <lb/>at <lb/>! D <lb/>! 1 .n C 1/.! k =! 1 C 1/ 2 <lb/>! k =! 1 .n C 1/ C n C 2 <lb/>; n; k 2 N : <lb/>(16) <lb/>The number of computable subharmonics is determined by <lb/>the discretization time-step; for example, Figs. 5 and 6 display <lb/>only six branches while the time step was t D 10 3 . Four <lb/>periodic solutions corresponding to subharmonic backbone <lb/>curves are depicted in Fig. 15 for g 0 &gt; 0. <lb/>These plots suggests that the periodic motions present n <lb/>grazing instants together with one contact phase, when the <lb/>NSM branch starts in the vicinity of the n-th subharmonic <lb/>of ! k , as inferred from Eq. (15). The displacement of the <lb/>contacting end for points &quot;d &quot; and &quot;g&quot; (see Fig. 6) are similar, <lb/>however the latter has higher frequency. Such feature is also <lb/>expected in periodic motions around subharmonics of higher <lb/>NSM. <lb/>Moreover, periodic solutions belonging to distinct NSM <lb/>branches coexist when the bar is prestressed (g 0 &lt; 0), see <lb/>point &quot;h&quot; in Fig. 6. The corresponding periodic displacements <lb/>of the contacting end are plotted in Fig. 16 where the period <lb/>of vibration is the same. Here, the solutions have longer free <lb/>phases and increasing number of grazing instants with higher <lb/>energy. These grazing instants coincide with the BC switching <lb/>time of lower energy solutions. <lb/>Interestingly, extensive numerical experiments show that <lb/>NSM branches do not appear in the range of frequencies <lb/>OE k ; ! kC1 , k 2 N ; the reason for this is unknown. <lb/>6.3 Internal resonance branches <lb/>The intrinsic discrete nature of the employed numerical algo-<lb/>rithm is such that WFEM cannot capture an actual continuum <lb/>of solutions (see section 5). However, the periodic solutions <lb/>previously presented all belong to numerically &quot;apparent&quot; con-<lb/>tinua parametrized by the energy where the solutions possess <lb/>similar qualitative and quantitative features. The proposed ap-<lb/>proach also leads to sparse periodic solutions, see clouds of <lb/>points in Fig. 17. Presumably, these points are also part of a <lb/>complicated network of backbone curves stemming from main <lb/>and subharmonic branches, however they are much more chal-<lb/>lenging to capture numerically because of the high-frequency <lb/>content in the corresponding mode shapes, see Fig. 18. These <lb/>points seem to be organized on internal resonances backbone <lb/>curves [19] emanating from the main one in the vicinity of the <lb/>frequencies <lb/>! D 2k! 1 =.2k 1/; k D 2; 3; : : : <lb/>(17) <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T d <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T e <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T f <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T g <lb/>Fig. 15: Periodic motions in the vicinity of ! 2 =2 D 3! 1 =2 <lb/>(top), ! 3 =3 D 5! 1 =3 (top-center), ! 4 =4 D 7! 1 =4 (bottom-<lb/>center) and ! 4 =2 D 7! 1 =2 (bottom) corresponding respec-<lb/>tively to points &quot;d &quot;, &quot;e&quot;, &quot;f &quot; and &quot;g&quot; in Figs. 5 and 6. <lb/>Moreover, it is observed in Fig. 17 that there are no internal <lb/>resonance branches in the frequency ranges OE.2k 1/! 1 =.2k <lb/>2/I 2k! 1 =.2k 1/, k D 3; 4; : : : This is not further explored <lb/>in this work. Periodic motions featuring an internal resonance <lb/>in the vicinity of .! 3 C ! 1 /=5 D 6! 1 =5 are displayed in <lb/>Fig. 18. These solutions present two grazing instants and ap-<lb/>pear to correspond to a modal interaction between the first and <lb/>third NSM. In contrast to solutions on the main and subhar-<lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T h <lb/>T 1 <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T h <lb/>T 1 <lb/>T 2 <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T h <lb/>T 1 <lb/>T 2 <lb/>Fig. 16: Periodic motions with same frequency for g 0 &lt; 0 <lb/>corresponding to points &quot;h&quot; in Fig. 6: low energy (top) to high <lb/>energy (bottom). <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>! <lb/>1 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 17: Main NSM branch around ! 1 with additional internal <lb/>resonance branches. <lb/>monic backbone curves for g 0 &gt; 0, the contact duration of <lb/>internally resonant periodic motions decreases with increasing <lb/>frequency: they exhibit a softening behavior. <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T a <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t / <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T b <lb/>Fig. 18: Internal resonances for g 0 &gt; 0 in the vicinity of <lb/>.! 3 C ! 1 /=5 D 6! 1 =5: points &quot;a&quot; (top) and &quot;b&quot; (bottom) in <lb/>Fig. 17. <lb/>It is difficult to compute the occurrence of internal reso-<lb/>nances in systems involving unilateral contact. However, the <lb/>data obtained by WFEM give suggestions about the existence <lb/>of these NSM branches. The characterization of the periodic <lb/>motions associated to internal resonances is helpful to predict <lb/>the possible sudden resonance of real life applications, when <lb/>vibrating around frequencies defined in Eq. (17). <lb/>6.4 Periodic solutions with two contact phases per period <lb/>The previous sections were devoted to solutions with one <lb/>contact phase and one free phase per period, as expressed <lb/>in Eq. (8). In this section, solutions with more than one con-<lb/>tact phase per period are explored. The methodology is un-<lb/>changed, but two additional unknowns (duration of second <lb/>contact phase `t and duration of second free phase mt , <lb/>ànd <lb/>m 2 N ) arise in the new equation <lb/>.A p <lb/>c A k <lb/>f A c A m <lb/>f <lb/>I/Q .0/ D 0; <lb/>(18) <lb/>to be compared with Eq. (9). It appears that non trivial solu-<lb/>tions Q .0/ can be found only if the contact phases have the <lb/>same duration, that is p D `. This might be the consequence <lb/>of the symmetry with respect to time and space of the wave <lb/>equation. For the matrix S T D A p <lb/>c A k <lb/>f A p <lb/>c A m <lb/>f <lb/>I, families of <lb/>periodic solutions satisfying contact conditions were found <lb/>only when h D dim.ker S T / D 2 suggesting that dim.ker S T / <lb/>should equal the number of contact phases for periodic solu-<lb/>tions to exist. <lb/>The solution procedure explained in subsection 5.2 leads <lb/>to a one-dimensional continuum of periodic orbits emerging <lb/>in the vicinity of ! 2 =5 D 3! 1 =5, where ! 2 D 3! 1 , defining <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>a subharmonic backbone curve with two contact phases, as <lb/>illustrated in Fig. 19. This family of periodic orbits appears <lb/>3=5 2=3 <lb/>1 <lb/>4=3 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>! <lb/>1 <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 19: NSM branch with two closed contacts per period in <lb/>the vicinity of ! 2 =5 D 3! 1 =5 [ <lb/>]. First main NSM with <lb/>one closed contact per period [ <lb/>]; g 0 &gt; 0. <lb/>only for g 0 &gt; 0 and presents hardening behavior. The corre-<lb/>sponding space-time displacement field is shown in Fig. 20 <lb/>for an arbitrary frequency. The asymptote of this NSM branch <lb/>appears to be located at 2! 1 =3. <lb/>The contacting end, shown in Fig. 20 features one free <lb/>phase with two grazing instants similar to the first subhar-<lb/>monic of the third NSM at ! 3 =3. Also, as in the case with <lb/>Space x <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u.x; t/ <lb/>g 0 <lb/>L 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>Fig. 20: Generic space-time displacement field with two con-<lb/>tact phases per period of the NSM branch around ! 2 =5. <lb/>one contact phase per period, the amplitude of the displace-<lb/>ments and the duration of the contact phases get larger with <lb/>the frequency of vibration. Interestingly, it resembles the two <lb/>impact-per-period trajectories of a serial spring-mass sys-<lb/>tem constrained by an obstacle with a purely elastic contact <lb/>law [37]. In particular, the solutions have two axes of symme-<lb/>try per period along the time axis, which are located in the <lb/>middle of each free phase. <lb/>A finer discretization is required to obtain additional NSM <lb/>branches with higher number of contact phases. These branches <lb/>might be of interest for the prediction of vibratory responses <lb/>where the elastic bar resonates for excitation frequencies much <lb/>lower than the first linear natural frequency ! 1 . <lb/>6.5 Stability analysis of periodic solutions <lb/>Due to the space-time coupled discretization and the condi-<lb/>tional switching of boundary conditions, a rigorous stability <lb/>analysis of the periodic orbits is a challenging task and re-<lb/>mains an open problem left to future investigations. However, <lb/>as a preliminary insight, the effects of a small sinusoidal per-<lb/>turbation on the initial conditions corresponding to the first <lb/>main NSM were investigated by comparing the unperturbed <lb/>and perturbed solutions time-integrated via WFEM over 1000 <lb/>periods of the unperturbed solution. We found that the per-<lb/>turbed motion remains in the vicinity of the periodic motion, <lb/>thus suggesting that a fraction of first main NSM motions are <lb/>orbitally stable. This is illustrated in Fig. 21 which compares <lb/>the unperturbed and perturbed motions, over the last period of <lb/>integration t 2 OE999T a I 1000T a , corresponding to point &quot;a&quot; <lb/>and g 0 &gt; 0 in Fig. 5. <lb/>999T a <lb/>1000T a <lb/>g 0 <lb/>Time t <lb/>Displacement u <lb/>N <lb/>C1=2 <lb/>Fig. 21: Displacement of the contacting end after 1000T a for <lb/>point &quot;a&quot; in Fig. 5: unperturbed [ <lb/>] and perturbed [ <lb/>]. <lb/>7 Forced response of a mechanical system subject to <lb/>contact constraints <lb/>One important purpose of performing nonsmooth modal anal-<lb/>ysis of a mechanical system is to predict its behavior when <lb/>periodically forced [38, 29]. Accordingly, the frequency re-<lb/>sponse of the previously-investigated elastic bar with peri-<lb/>odic external excitation is now compared to the NSM spec-<lb/>trum. The excitation consists in an external distributed har-<lb/>monic force or a harmonically moving rigid wall that com-<lb/>presses the bar, see Fig 22. The force acting on the bar is <lb/>f .x; t / D f 0 .x/ sin.!t / and the displacement of the mov-<lb/>ing wall is w.t / D w 0 sin.!t / where ! is the frequency of <lb/>excitation and w 0 &gt; g 0 . The gap function is now defined <lb/>as g.u.L; t /; w.t // D g 0 C w.t / u.L; t /. The system has <lb/>been slightly damped by adding a velocity-dependent term <lb/>with a small viscous damping coefficient in the left-hand side <lb/>of Eq. (1). The forced response of this system is obtained <lb/>for various amounts of damping and was computed using the <lb/>WFEM version detailed in Algorithm 2 using a time-stepping <lb/>approach not specifically targeting periodic motions. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>L <lb/>x <lb/>u.x; t / <lb/>f .x; t / D f 0 .x/ sin.!t / <lb/>g <lb/>w.t/ <lb/>Fig. 22: Elastic bar excited by a distributed harmonic force <lb/>and/or a moving rigid wall. <lb/>Periodically moving wall <lb/>The first tested configuration is f 0 D 0 and w 0 ¤ 0. The total <lb/>energy of the steady-state solution averaged over one forcing <lb/>period for increasing frequencies of excitation and various <lb/>amounts of damping is shown in Figs. 23, 24 and 25 (top) for <lb/>a positive, zero and negative initial gap, respectively. <lb/>In the frequency ranges where NSM branches do not exist, <lb/>WFEM could not find externally forced periodic steady-states. <lb/>Instead, quasiperiodic or chaotic forced responses were de-<lb/>tected. Calculating steady-state for each frequency requires <lb/>long computational times which complicates the construction <lb/>of a detailed forced response. <lb/>Periodic distributed force <lb/>The second tested configuration is f 0 ¤ 0 and w 0 D 0, <lb/>corresponding to the elastic bar excited by a distributed force. <lb/>The results for a positive, zero and negative initial gap are <lb/>depicted in Figs. 23, 24 and 25 (bottom) respectively. <lb/>For a positive gap and high frequencies, large damping <lb/>confines the system to linear operating conditions. This is <lb/>one of the reasons why the corresponding plots differ greatly. <lb/>Moreover, similarly to the first configuration, quasiperiodic <lb/>and chaotic solutions are observed in the frequency inter-<lb/>vals where NSM branches do not exist. Presumably, there <lb/>exist infinitely many backbones curves and corresponding &quot;in-<lb/>between&quot; regions with no periodic solutions; only a few are <lb/>plotted in Figs. 23 to 25. <lb/>More importantly, the backbone curves obtained with the <lb/>nonsmooth modal analysis provide an excellent approxima-<lb/>tion of the response resonances. In addition, the internal res-<lb/>onances of the system produce small protuberances in the <lb/>forced response that coincide with the main resonance and <lb/>subharmonic backbone curves. <lb/>The main advantage of the nonsmooth modal analysis is <lb/>the characterization of the vibratory response without rely-<lb/>ing on very expensive numerical time-integration procedures: <lb/>via NSM as presented, the prediction of frequencies of exci-<lb/>tation at which the system will vibrate with high energy is <lb/>straightforward. <lb/>8 Conclusions <lb/>Families of periodic orbits (known as nonsmooth modes of <lb/>vibration) of an autonomous finite elastic bar subject to fric-<lb/>tionless unilateral contact are investigated in this work. Three <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 23: Periodically forced responses of the bar for various <lb/>damping coefficients and g 0 &gt; 0: harmonically moving wall <lb/>(top) and harmonic distributed force (bottom). <lb/>cases were explored: unstressed (g 0 &gt; 0), prestressed (g 0 &lt; <lb/>0) and zero initial gap (g 0 D 0). The computation of peri-<lb/>odic solutions was achieved using the Wave Finite Element <lb/>Method (WFEM), chosen because it preserves energy and <lb/>avoids numerical dispersion. This method consists in discretiz-<lb/>ing simultaneously in time and space the governing dynamic <lb/>equations, resulting in a simple matrix form. Then, the prob-<lb/>lem of finding periodic solutions was formulated as finding a <lb/>vector in the kernel of a matrix supplemented by complemen-<lb/>tarity conditions enforcing unilateral contact constraints. The <lb/>presented methodology can be adapted to multiple contact <lb/>phases per period or to systems coupled by unilateral contact <lb/>conditions. However, it is presently limited to simplified one-<lb/>dimensional problems with a single point of contact on the <lb/>contact boundary. <lb/>It is shown that the elastic bar with unilateral contact has <lb/>a rich dynamical behavior involving subharmonic resonances <lb/>and internal resonances. Similar results are already reported <lb/>in the literature [7, 29]. However, the proposed methodology <lb/>does not necessitate regularized contact conditions. In this <lb/>work, the unilateral contact conditions are treated as a switch <lb/>between Dirichlet and Neumann-type boundary conditions <lb/>when the gap opens or closes: from fixed-free BCs (no con-<lb/>tact) to fixed-fixed BCs (contact) and vice-versa. The found <lb/>nonlinear periodic solutions lying on a NSM are combinations <lb/>of travelling waves with discontinuous wave fronts, as op-<lb/>posed to their linear counterpart (without contact conditions) <lb/>which are standing harmonic waves. Also, the behavior of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>10 1 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>Normalized frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 24: Periodically forced responses of the bar for various <lb/>damping coefficients and g 0 D 0: harmonically moving wall <lb/>(top) and harmonic distributed force (bottom). <lb/>the NSMs depends on the gap at rest: hardening branches for <lb/>g 0 &gt; 0, softening branches for g 0 &lt; 0 and discrete spectrum <lb/>for g 0 D 0. Such behavior was already observed only for the <lb/>first NSM [5]. Moreover, the frequency ranges at which NSM <lb/>branches exist are conjectured. <lb/>Quasi-closed form solutions can be extracted from the <lb/>provided results. They could act as benchmark solutions for <lb/>researchers designing advanced numerical schemes in unilat-<lb/>eral contact dynamics. NSMs stability and the role of coexist-<lb/>ing periodic solutions (same energy and frequency) needs be <lb/>further explored. The relevance of nonsmooth modal analy-<lb/>sis was illustrated by the accurate prediction of periodically <lb/>forced responses, irrespective of the way the external force is <lb/>applied. <lb/>Extension of the proposed approach to multidimensional <lb/>settings with several points of contact is a remarkable chal-<lb/>lenge as the non-dispersive and energy-preserving properties <lb/>of the WFEM in the one-dimensional context will then be lost. <lb/>However, such extension seems feasible with Godunov-type <lb/>discretization and shooting techniques by slightly relaxing the <lb/>imposed periodicity conditions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments CY gratefully acknowledges the financial support <lb/>of SENESCYT-Government of Ecuador and MEDA-McGill University <lb/>fellowships. AT and ML acknowledge the financial support of the grants: <lb/>421542-2012 NSERC Discovery Grant and 2014-NC-173113 FRQNT <lb/>Établissement de Nouveaux Chercheurs Universitaires. ML would like <lb/>to thank Cyril Touzé for mentioning references [11] and [12]. <lb/></div>

			<body>10 1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>frequency of vibration !=! 1 <lb/>Normalized energy <lb/>Fig. 25: Periodically forced responses of the bar for various <lb/>damping coefficients and g 0 &lt; 0: harmonically moving wall <lb/>(top) and harmonic distributed force (bottom). <lb/></body>
	  
	  <div type="annex">A Description of the Wave Finite Element Method <lb/>In this section, the WFEM, introduced by Shorr for the simulation of <lb/>shock wave propagation in solids [34], is thoroughly described. <lb/>A.1 Hyperbolic system of conservation laws <lb/>The local equation (1) can be equivalently written as a system of two <lb/>first order partial differential equations in terms of velocities v.x; t/ and <lb/>stresses .x; t/ <lb/>;t <lb/>E v ;x D 0 <lb/>v ;t <lb/>;x D 0 <lb/>) <lb/>; 8x 2 0 I LOE; 8t &gt; 0 <lb/>(19) <lb/>where . / ;t is the derivation in time and . / ;x is the derivation in space <lb/>of quantity . / [10]. Recall that axial strains &quot; D u ;x are bounded by <lb/>non physical inter-penetration, which translates into u ;x &gt; 1, see <lb/>section 2. Displacements can be straightforwardly recovered by space-<lb/>integration of the strains u.x; / D <lb/>R x <lb/>0 u ;s .s; / ds u.0; /, where <lb/>u.0; / D 0. By posing q D OE v &gt; , Eq. (19) can be recast as <lb/>q ;t C Bq ;x D 0 where B D <lb/>Ä <lb/>0 <lb/>E <lb/>1= <lb/>0 <lb/>: <lb/>(20) <lb/>The eigenvalues of matrix B are 1 D <lb/>p <lb/>E= and 2 D <lb/>p <lb/>E= , <lb/>coinciding with the algebraic propagation velocity of the elastic wave: <lb/>positive and negative for the two waves propagating in opposite directions. <lb/>Since both eigenvalues are distinct and real, Eq. (20) is also referred to <lb/>as a hyperbolic system of conservation laws [10]. <lb/>Equation (20) involves time and space derivatives of q. However, <lb/>observing that q ;t C Bq ;x D 0 is a local form of the conservation law <lb/>of q (implying q. ; t/ can only change due to fluxes at the boundaries) <lb/>corresponding to the following integral form <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/>Z x2 <lb/>x1 <lb/>q.x; t/ dx <lb/>Á <lb/>D B q.x 1 ; t/ q.x 2 ; t/ ; <lb/>(21) <lb/></div>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">it appears that the condition on the smoothness of q is no longer required. <lb/>Therefore, q is allowed to exhibit discontinuities in time and space [14]. <lb/>A.2 Discretization <lb/>The WFEM consists in dividing the spatial and temporal domain into <lb/>grid cells of equal size and keeping track of an approximation to the <lb/>integral of q within every single cell. As depicted in Fig. 26, the bar <lb/>is discretized using a uniform grid of N cells. Each i th cell, denoted <lb/>x i 1=2 <lb/>x iC1=2 <lb/>C i <lb/>C i 1 <lb/>C i C1 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>F <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1=2 <lb/>F <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1=2 <lb/>Fig. 26: Discretization of the spatial domain in grid cells at time t n . <lb/>by C i , is delimited by the interval .x i 1=2 ; x i C1=2 /. Similarly, time is <lb/>discretized into intervals of equal length t D t nC1 t n . The average <lb/>of q. ; t/, over the ith cell at time t n is <lb/>Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>x <lb/>Z x i C1=2 <lb/>x i 1=2 <lb/>q.x; t n / dx D <lb/>1 <lb/>x <lb/>Z <lb/>C i <lb/>q.x; t n / dx <lb/>(22) <lb/>where x D x i C1=2 x i 1=2 is the length of cell i. The integral form <lb/>of conservation law (21) applied to cell C i reads <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/>Z <lb/>C i <lb/>q.x; t/ dx D B q.x i 1=2 ; t / q.x i C1=2 ; t / : <lb/>(23) <lb/>This expression is now employed to develop an explicit time-stepping <lb/>algorithm where Q .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>is approximated by a function of Q .n/ <lb/>i . Equa-<lb/>tion (23) is integrated between t n and t nC1 yielding <lb/>Z <lb/>C i <lb/>q.x; t nC1 / q.x; t n / dx D <lb/>Z tnC1 <lb/>tn <lb/>B q.x i 1=2 ; t / q.x iC1=2 ; t / dt: <lb/>(24) <lb/>Rearranging and dividing by x leads to <lb/>1 <lb/>x <lb/>Z <lb/>C i <lb/>q.x; t nC1 / dx D <lb/>1 <lb/>x <lb/>Z <lb/>C i <lb/>q.x; t n / dx <lb/>Z tnC1 <lb/>tn <lb/>Bq.x i C1=2 ; t / dt C <lb/>Z tnC1 <lb/>tn <lb/>Bq.x i 1=2 ; t / dt <lb/>Á <lb/>: <lb/>(25) <lb/>This equation describes how the cell average should be updated within <lb/>a time step in order to satisfy the conservation of q. In general, the two <lb/>integrals involving Bq on the right-hand side of the equation cannot be <lb/>evaluated exactly. Following [26], we pose <lb/>F .n/ <lb/>i˙1=2 <lb/>1 <lb/>t <lb/>Z tnC1 <lb/>tn <lb/>Bq.x i ˙1=2 ; t / dt <lb/>(26) <lb/>and Eq. (25) simply becomes <lb/>Q .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>D Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>x <lb/>F .n/ <lb/>i C1=2 <lb/>F .n/ <lb/>i 1=2 : <lb/>(27) <lb/>The next subsection is dedicated to the computation of F .n/ <lb/>i˙1=2 , which <lb/>are the time-averaged fluxes at x D x i ˙1=2 . <lb/>q.x; t n / <lb/>x <lb/>x i 1=2 <lb/>x iC1=2 <lb/>x iC3=2 <lb/>x iC5=2 <lb/>x i C7=2 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C2 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>iC3 <lb/>Fig. 27: Reconstruction of q.x; t n / from the average fluxes Q .n/ <lb/>i . <lb/>A.3 Approximation of the time-averaged fluxes <lb/>To approximate the fluxes at the interfaces defined by Eq. (26), the <lb/>state q.x; t n / at time t n is assumed to be a piecewise constant function <lb/>defined for all x, constructed from the cell averages Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>as depicted <lb/>in Fig. 27. This piecewise reconstruction of the function q.x; t n / is <lb/>identical to the Godunov&apos;s approach widely employed in computational <lb/>fluid dynamics [27]. A suitable approximation of the flux F .n/ <lb/>i C1=2 can <lb/>be obtained by solving the problem, either numerically or exactly, of <lb/>the conservation law Eq. (20) together with the following discontinuous <lb/>conditions at time t n [27]: <lb/>.x; t n / D <lb/>( <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>if x 6 x i C1=2 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>if x &gt; x i C1=2 <lb/>v.x; t n / D <lb/>( <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>if x 6 x i C1=2 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>if x &gt; x i C1=2 <lb/>(28) <lb/>which constitutes a Riemann problem centered at x i C1=2 between cells <lb/>C i and C i C1 [27]. The solution to this Riemann problem consists of two <lb/>shock waves propagating along the characteristic lines x D ˙ct, one <lb/>moving to the left into cell C i and one moving to the right into cell C i C1 <lb/>as depicted in a space-time plot in Fig. 28. The shock wave traveling <lb/>to the left, indicated by W 1 , propagates at velocity s 1 and connects <lb/>the state Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>and the interior state Q i generated by such shock wave. <lb/>Moreover, the solution t 7 ! q.x iC1=2 ; t/ is constant over the time <lb/>interval OEt n ; t nC1 . <lb/>t <lb/>.x iC1=2 ; t n / <lb/>x <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>iC1 <lb/>Q <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>Q iC1 <lb/>Q i <lb/>W 1 <lb/>W 2 <lb/>t nC1 <lb/>Fig. 28: Structure of the solution to the Riemann problem depicted in a <lb/>space-time plot. <lb/>The Rankine-Hugoniot jump condition is proven to hold across any <lb/>propagating discontinuity [36] which can be written for the left wave <lb/>W 1 propagating at velocity s 1 and the right wave W 2 propagating at <lb/>velocity s 2 : <lb/>W 1 ! <lb/>( <lb/>s 1 i <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>D E v i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>; <lb/>s 1 v i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>D <lb/>i <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>W 2 ! <lb/>( <lb/>s 2 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>i C1 D E v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v i C1 ; <lb/>s 2 v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v iC1 D <lb/>.n/ <lb/>iC1 <lb/>i C1 : <lb/>(29) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Nonsmooth modal analysis of an elastic bar subject to a unilateral contact constraint <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Because of material continuity, cells C i and C i C1 cannot separate. This <lb/>requires that the interior states must be equal across the material in-<lb/>terface, Q i C1=2 D Q i C1 D Q i . By knowing that the shock speeds <lb/>s 1 D s 2 D <lb/>p <lb/>E= D c are known and constants, the interme-<lb/>diate state is approximated with q.x iC1=2 ; t / <lb/>Q i C1=2 such that <lb/>t n 6 t 6 t nC1 and can be calculated from Eq. (29): <lb/>Q i C1=2 D <lb/>Ä <lb/>i C1=2 <lb/>v i C1=2 <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; .n/ <lb/>i C1 C .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C c v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i C1 Cv .n/ <lb/>i C 1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>: (30) <lb/>Equation (30) is regarded as the exact solution of the Riemann prob-<lb/>lem involving linear elastodynamics [26, 8]. The flux approximation in <lb/>Eq. (26) can be calculated with the solution of a Riemann problem at the <lb/>cell interface as <lb/>F .n/ <lb/>iC1=2 <lb/>B <lb/>t <lb/>Z tnC1 <lb/>tn <lb/>Q i C1=2 dt <lb/>BQ i C1=2 : <lb/>(31) <lb/>In a nonlinear framework for the local equation, a solution to the Rie-<lb/>mann problem should be approximated numerically using Riemann <lb/>solvers [39]. <lb/>A.4 Formulation for inner grid cells <lb/>Inserting Eq. (31) into Eq. (27) produces the iterative scheme <lb/>Q .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>D Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>x <lb/>BQ i C1=2 BQ i 1=2 : <lb/>(32) <lb/>Equation (32) describes the evolution in time of the states of the grid <lb/>cells C i . This subsection provides the formulation for the inner cells, <lb/>where i D 2; : : : ; N <lb/>1. The boundary cells C 1 and C N require a <lb/>different treatment explained in the next subsection. Expressing the flux <lb/>approximation, employing Eq. (31) on the right side of an inner cell <lb/>yields <lb/>BQ i C1=2 D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; <lb/>E v .n/ <lb/>i C1 C v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C 1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>iC1 C .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C c v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>: <lb/>(33) <lb/>Performing the same operation on the left side of the cell reads <lb/>BQ i 1=2 D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; <lb/>E v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C v .n/ <lb/>i 1 C 1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C .n/ <lb/>i 1 C c v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/># <lb/>: <lb/>(34) <lb/>Accordingly, the total flux within an inner cell is the quantity BQ i C1=2 <lb/>BQ i 1=2 which, when substituted into Eq. (32) yields <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>D <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>C <lb/>t <lb/>2x <lb/>&quot; <lb/>E v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i 1 C c .n/ <lb/>iC1 <lb/>2 .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C .n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1 C c v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>2v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>C v .n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/># <lb/>: (35) <lb/>Since the exact solution of a Riemann problem is being used, WFEM <lb/>incorporates an appropriate time-step t D x=c. Then, the stress and <lb/>velocity of a grid cell C i at time t nC1 are calculated as <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; .n/ <lb/>i C1 C .n/ <lb/>i 1 C c v .n/ <lb/>iC1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i C1 C v .n/ <lb/>i 1 C 1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/># <lb/>: <lb/>(36) <lb/>The above strong assumption is suitable only for 1D elastodynamics <lb/>problems, since the wave velocity and the direction of the propagation is <lb/>known. Also, such assumption enforces energy conservation and elim-<lb/>inates numerical dissipation [34]. In the multidimensional framework, <lb/>even though the waves velocities are known, the waves could propagate <lb/>in various direction throughout the physical domain. <lb/>Equation (36) provides the main equation of the WFEM and charac-<lb/>terizes how the average value Q .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>of q in an inner cell C i is updated at <lb/>each time step. As required by the local conservation law (21) resulting <lb/>from the absence of body forces, the evolution of the state of the inner <lb/>cells depends only on the values of the adjacent cells. WFEM can be <lb/>seen as the transference of the whole information embedded in cell C i <lb/>to its adjacent cells at each time step. Employing the latter approach to <lb/>obtain the evolution of cell states, involving discontinuities such as shock <lb/>and rarefaction waves, is well known by the Fluid Mechanics community <lb/>employing Finite Volume Methods [27]. <lb/>A.5 Formulation for boundary grid cells <lb/>To compute the state of the boundary grid cells, the computational do-<lb/>main is extended by including additional cells on both boundaries, known <lb/>as ghost cells [26], whose average values depend on the boundary condi-<lb/>tions. This concept is taken from the Finite Volume Methods. Figure 29 <lb/>depicts ghost cells for a system discretized using N cells. <lb/>C N <lb/>C N C1 <lb/>Ghost cell <lb/>C 1 <lb/>C 0 <lb/>Ghost cell <lb/>Fig. 29: Computational space domain with ghost cells. <lb/>Equation (36) can then be used to update the average value on the <lb/>boundary cells, which have now become inner cells. Only a single ghost <lb/>cell is required at each boundary because the computation of the average <lb/>value depends only on the states of the adjacent cells. For instance, <lb/>the fixed-free elastic bar without the complementarity conditions of <lb/>contact satisfies the two boundary conditions u.0; t/ D v.0; t/ D 0 <lb/>and E u ;x .L; t/ D .L; t/ D 0. These conditions are used to define <lb/>the average values within the ghost cells as follows: <lb/>at ghost cell C 0 : <lb/>( <lb/>0 D 1 <lb/>v 0 D v 1 ; <lb/>at ghost cell C N C1 : <lb/>( <lb/>N C1 D <lb/>N <lb/>v N C1 D v N : <lb/>(37) <lb/>Such average values coincide with the theory of reflection of elastic waves <lb/>from fixed and free boundaries [17], which states that stress waves reflect <lb/>from a fixed boundary with the same sign and from a free boundary with <lb/>the changed sign; similarly, velocity waves reflect from a fixed boundary <lb/>with an opposite sign and from a free boundary with the same sign. The <lb/>evolution of the average values of the boundary cells, C 1 and C N , can be <lb/>calculated by introducing the average values of Eq. (37) into Eq. (36), <lb/>yielding for C 1 : <lb/>Q .nC1/ <lb/>1 <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.n/ <lb/>2 <lb/>C .n/ <lb/>1 <lb/>C c v .n/ <lb/>2 C v .n/ <lb/>1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>2 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>1 C 1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>2 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>1 <lb/># <lb/>(38) <lb/>and for C N : <lb/>Q .nC1/ <lb/>N <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>N C c v .n/ <lb/>N C v .n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>N C v .n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>.n/ <lb/>N C .n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/># <lb/>: <lb/>(39) <lb/>A.6 WFEM generic algorithm <lb/>Altogether, the previous derivations lead to a set of equations that de-<lb/>scribe how q is updated in time for every cell. The different steps are <lb/>summarized in Algorithm 1. Using t D x=c it computes, in the <lb/>Algorithm 1: WFEM Computation procedure <lb/>Input: number of elements N , total number of steps n T , boundary <lb/>conditions, initial conditions, density , wave velocity c <lb/>for n D 0 to n T [Time Loop] do <lb/>Update time instant: t n D nt <lb/>Compute stress and velocity at cell C 1 via Eq. (38) <lb/>for i D 2 to N 1 [Cell Loop] do <lb/>Compute stress and velocity in cell C i via Eq. (36) <lb/>end <lb/>Compute stress and velocity in cell C N via Eq. (39) <lb/>end <lb/>Output: stresses, velocities at instants t 0 ; : : : ; t nT <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">framework of linear elastodynamics, the propagation at finite speed c of <lb/>a wave and accounts for the reflection conditions at the boundaries. By <lb/>definition of t , the CFL condition t Ä x=c is always satisfied, so <lb/>the method is always stable [26, 28]. Additionally, because the global <lb/>error is proportional to the discretization steps, the WFEM is first-order <lb/>accurate both in space and time [34]. <lb/>A.7 Matrix formulation <lb/>Similar to other numerical methods applied on linear systems, the WFEM <lb/>can be rewritten in a convenient matrix form which facilitates the process <lb/>of finding nonsmooth modes of vibration. More specifically, the state vec-<lb/>tor of the system Q .n/ D Q .n/ <lb/>1 : : : Q .n/ <lb/>N <lb/>&gt; 2 R 2N at time t n satisfies <lb/>the identity 2 <lb/>Q .n/ D AQ .n 1/ ; 8n 1 <lb/>(40) <lb/>and Q .0/ is the initial state. The matrix A gathers stiffness and inertial <lb/>terms as well as the type of boundary conditions. It is now derived for the <lb/>fixed-free BC. In a matrix form, Eq. (36), which governs the evolution <lb/>of inner cells, reads <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .nC1/ <lb/>i <lb/># <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Ä 1 0 1 <lb/>c 0 c <lb/>1 <lb/>c 0 1 <lb/>c <lb/>1 0 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i <lb/>.n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i 1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>i C1 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>: <lb/>(41) <lb/>For the boundary cells in Eqs (38) and (39), the matrix form follows as <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.nC1/ <lb/>1 <lb/>v .nC1/ <lb/>1 <lb/># <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Ä 1 1 c c <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>1 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>2 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>(42) <lb/>and <lb/>&quot; <lb/>.nC1/ <lb/>N <lb/>v .nC1/ <lb/>N <lb/># <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Ä 1 <lb/>1 c c <lb/>1 <lb/>c <lb/>1 <lb/>c 1 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/>.n/ <lb/>N <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>N 1 <lb/>v .n/ <lb/>N <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>: <lb/>(43) <lb/>Then the block matrix A 2 R 2N 2N can be constructed using four <lb/>N N matrices A 1 ; A 2 ; A 3 ; A 4 whose expression can be derived from <lb/>A G .a; b; c; d / D <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>a b 0 : : : 0 0 0 <lb/>c 0 b <lb/>0 0 0 <lb/>0 c 0 <lb/>0 0 0 <lb/>: : : <lb/>: : : <lb/>: : : <lb/>: : : <lb/>: : : <lb/>0 0 0 <lb/>0 b 0 <lb/>0 0 0 <lb/>c 0 b <lb/>0 0 0 : : : 0 c d <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>(44) <lb/>with A 1 D A G . 1; 1; 1; 1/, A 2 D cA G . 1; 1; 1; 1/, A 3 D <lb/>A G .1; 1; 1; 1/= c, and A 4 D A G .1; 1; 1; 1/. Then, block matrix <lb/>A is written as <lb/>A D <lb/>Ä <lb/>A 1 A 2 <lb/>A 3 A 4 <lb/>: <lb/>(45) <lb/>Another matrix A can be constructed in the same way for the fixed-fixed <lb/>BC. Finally, the unknown Q .n/ can be directly expressed in terms of the <lb/>initial conditions Q .0/ from Eq. (40) by <lb/>Q .n/ D A n Q .0/ <lb/>(46) <lb/>where A n is known for each type of BC. <lb/>2 For readability purposes, the transpose signs within brackets are <lb/>dropped in the definitions of vectors and Q .n/ D Q .n/&gt; <lb/>1 <lb/>: : : Q .n/&gt; <lb/>N <lb/>&gt; <lb/>is replaced by Q .n/ D Q .n/ <lb/>1 : : : Q .n/ <lb/>N <lb/>&gt; , for instance. <lb/>B Treatment of unilateral contact in WFEM <lb/>The unilateral contact constraints involved in the formulation are enforced <lb/>using the concept of floating boundary conditions [34] which can be <lb/>regarded as a conditional switch between fixed-free and fixed-fixed <lb/>boundary conditions [13] when a penetration is detected during a time <lb/>iteration, as illustrated in Fig. 30. In the continuous framework, these <lb/>two boundary conditions are <lb/>-fixed-free BC (inactive contact) <lb/>u.0; t/ D v.0; t/ D 0; E u ;x .L; t/ D .L; t/ D 0 <lb/>(47) <lb/>-fixed-fixed BC (active contact) <lb/>u.0; t/ D v.0; t/ D 0; u.L; t/ D g 0 ! v.L; t/ D 0: (48) <lb/>The gap function g.u.L; t//, which is a function of the displacement <lb/>u.L; t/ but not an explicit function of t , is discretized in time to calculate <lb/>a possible penetration of the bar as <lb/>g .n/ D g 0 u .n/ <lb/>N C1=2 <lb/>(49) <lb/>where u .n/ <lb/>N C1=2 is the displacement of the contacting interface which can <lb/>be calculated by numerically integrating strains of the bar u .n/ <lb/>;x at time <lb/>t n . This equality is used at each time step to check whether contact is <lb/>active during the next iteration: if g .n/ &gt; 0, a free boundary condition <lb/>is enforced while if g .n/ 6 0, a fixed boundary condition is considered <lb/>via the change of matrix A. <lb/>g .n/ &gt; 0 <lb/>C N <lb/>(a) Inactive contact <lb/>C N <lb/>g .n/ D 0 <lb/>(b) Active contact <lb/>Fig. 30: Conditional switch for contact treatment in WFEM <lb/>Based on the theory of reflection of elastic waves from bound-<lb/>aries [17], the state of the ghost cell C N C1 is updated as follows <lb/>-Active contact [g .n/ 6 0] <lb/>( <lb/>N C1 D N <lb/>v N C1 D v N <lb/>(50) <lb/>-Inactive contact [g .n/ &gt; 0] <lb/>( <lb/>N C1 D <lb/>N <lb/>v N C1 D v N <lb/>(51) <lb/>Equation (36) is subsequently used to calculate the evolution of the <lb/>average values inside the boundary cell C N , as detailed in section A.5. <lb/>Additionally, the contact force r .n/ is calculated by employing Eq. (30): <lb/>r .n/ D S .n/ <lb/>N <lb/>cv .n/ <lb/>N : <lb/>(52) <lb/>The sign of this quantity is tracked to locate the time of release, when <lb/>the bar returns to free condition at x D L. Algorithm 1 is modified to <lb/>include the floating boundary conditions as described in Algorithm 2. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Algorithm 2: Procedure with unilateral contact conditions <lb/>Input: number of elements N , number of steps n T , boundary and <lb/>initial conditions, density , wave velocity c <lb/>for n D 0 to n T [Time Loop] do <lb/>Discrete time instant, t n D nt <lb/>Compute stress and velocity at cell C 1 via Eq. (38) <lb/>for i D 2 to N 1 [Element Loop] do <lb/>Compute stress and velocity at cell C i via Eq. (36) <lb/>end <lb/>-floating boundary conditions -<lb/>if g .n/ D 0 then <lb/>Switch to fixed boundary condition at x N C1=2 <lb/>Compute contact stress r .n/ via Eq. (52) <lb/>if r .n/ &gt; 0 then <lb/>Switch to free boundary condition at x N C1=2 <lb/>Compute gap g .nC1/ <lb/>Compute stress and velocity in cell C N via Eq. (39) <lb/>else <lb/>Keep fixed boundary condition at x N C1=2 <lb/>Compute stress and velocity in cell C N via Eq. (39) <lb/>end <lb/>else <lb/>Keep free boundary condition at x N C1=2 <lb/>Compute gap g .nC1/ and stress and velocity at cell C N via <lb/>Eq. (39) <lb/>end <lb/>-end of floating boundary conditions -<lb/>end <lb/>Output: stresses, velocities, contact force at instants t 0 ; : : : ; t nT <lb/>From the matrix formulation of the WFEM in Eq. (40), two matrices <lb/>A shall then be distinguished: A f for the fixed-free condition (no contact) <lb/>and A c for the fixed-fixed condition (contact). Both matrices embed <lb/>the same stiffness and inertial terms of the system of interest; the only <lb/>unshared information are the boundary conditions. To summarize, the <lb/>developed WFEM with floating boundary conditions is a numerically <lb/>conservative and stable scheme able to properly propagate shock waves <lb/>induced by a switch in the boundary conditions, the latter being governed <lb/>by complementarity constraints. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] ACARY, Vincent. &quot;Energy conservation and dissipation properties <lb/>of time-integration methods for nonsmooth elastodynamics with <lb/>contact&quot;. ZAMM-Journal of Applied Mathematics and Mechanics <lb/>96.5 (2016), 585-603. OAI: hal-01235240. <lb/>[2] ACARY, Vincent and BROGLIATO, Bernard. Numerical Methods <lb/>for Nonsmooth Dynamical Systems. Springer, 2008. OAI: inria -<lb/>00423530. <lb/>[3] ARMERO, Francisco and PETOCZ, Eva. &quot;Formulation and analysis <lb/>of conserving algorithms for frictionless dynamic contact/imp-act <lb/>problems&quot;. Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineer-<lb/>ing 158.3-4 (1998), 269-300. OAI: hal-01435615. <lb/>[4] ASCHER, Uri, MATTHEIJ, Robert, and RUSSELL, Robert. Numeri-<lb/>cal solution of boundary value problems for ordinary differential <lb/>equations. SIAM, 1994. DOI: 10.1137/1.9781611971231. <lb/>[5] ASTASHEV, Vladimir and KRUPENIN, Vitaly. &quot;Longitudinal vibra-<lb/>tions of a thin rod interacting with an immobile limiter&quot;. Journal <lb/>of Machinery Manufacture and Reliability 36.6 (2007), 535-541. <lb/>OAI: hal-01569152. <lb/>[6] ATTAR, Mostafa, KARRECH, Ali, and REGENAUER-LIEB, Klaus. <lb/>&quot;Non-linear modal analysis of structural components subjected to <lb/>unilateral constraints&quot;. Journal of Sound and Vibration 389 (2017), <lb/>380-410. OAI: hal-01513216. <lb/>[7] BABITSKY, Vladimir. Theory of Vibro-Impact Systems and Appli-<lb/>cations. Springer, 2013. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-69635-3. <lb/>[8] BERJAMIN, Harold, LOMBARD, Bruno, CHIAVASSA, Guillaume, <lb/>and FAVRIE, Nicolas. &quot;Analytical solution to the Riemann problem <lb/>of 1D elastodynamics with general constitutive laws&quot;. Wave Motion <lb/>74 (2017), 35-55. OAI: hal-01350116. <lb/>[9] BRAKE, Matthew and WICKERT, Jonathan. &quot;Modal analysis of <lb/>a continuous gyroscopic second-order system with nonlinear con-<lb/>straints&quot;. Journal of Sound and Vibration 329.7 (2010), 893-911. <lb/>OAI: hal-01620571. <lb/>[10] BRESSAN, Alberto. Hyperbolic Systems of Conservation Laws: The <lb/>One-Dimensional Cauchy Problem. Oxford University Press, 2000. <lb/>[11] CABANNES, Henri. &quot;Mouvements périodiques d&apos;une corde vibrante <lb/>en présence d&apos;un obstacle ponctuel&quot;. Journal de Mécanique 20.1 <lb/>(1981), 41-58. OAI: hal-01620614. <lb/>[12] CABANNES, Henri. &quot;Periodic motions of a string vibrating against a <lb/>fixed point-mass obstacle: II&quot;. Mathematical Methods in the Applied <lb/>Sciences 6.1 (1984), 55-67. OAI: hal-01527093. <lb/>[13] CLAUDEL, Christian and BAYEN, Alexandre. &quot;Solutions to swit-<lb/>ched Hamilton-Jacobi equations and conservation laws using hybrid <lb/>components&quot;. Proceedings of 11th International Workshop on Hy-<lb/>brid Systems: Computation and Control. Vol. 4981. Lecture Notes <lb/>in Computer Science. St Louis, USA: Springer, 2008, 101-115. <lb/>OAI: hal-01471102. <lb/>[14] DAFERMOS, Constantine. Hyperbolic Conservation Laws in Con-<lb/>tinuum Physics. Springer, 2010. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-642-04048-1. <lb/>[15] DOYEN, David, ERN, Alexandre, and PIPERNO, Serge. &quot;Time-<lb/>integration schemes for the finite element dynamic Signorini prob-<lb/>lem&quot;. SIAM Journal of Scientific Computing 33.1 (2011), 223-249. <lb/>OAI: hal-00440128. <lb/>[16] GODUNOV, Sergei. &quot;Finite difference method for numerical com-<lb/>putation of discontinuous solutions of the equations of fluid dynam-<lb/>ics&quot;. Matematicheskii Sbornik 47(89).3 (1959), 271-306. OAI: hal-<lb/>01620642. <lb/>[17] GRAFF, Karl. Wave Motion in Elastic Solids. Dover, 1975. <lb/>[18] ISSANCHOU, Clara, BILBAO, Stefan, CARROU, Jean-Loïc Le, TOUZÉ, <lb/>Cyril, and DOARÉ, Olivier. &quot;A modal-based approach to the nonlin-<lb/>ear vibration of strings against a unilateral obstacle: Simulations and <lb/>experiments in the pointwise case&quot;. Journal of Sound and Vibration <lb/>393.Supplement C (2017), 229-251. OAI: hal-01461730. <lb/>[19] KERSCHEN, Gaëtan, PEETERS, Maxime, GOLINVAL, Jean-Claude, <lb/>and VAKAKIS, Alexander. &quot;Nonlinear normal modes, Part I: A use-<lb/>ful framework for the structural dynamicist&quot;. Mechanical Systems <lb/>and Signal Processing 23.1 (2009), 170-194. OAI: hal-01357931. <lb/>[20] KHENOUS, Houari, LABORDE, Patrick, and RENARD, Yves. &quot;Mass <lb/>redistribution method for finite element contact problems in elasto-<lb/>dynamics&quot;. European Journal of Mechanics-A/Solids 27.5 (2009), <lb/>918-932. OAI: hal-00582045. <lb/>[21] KURT, Mehmet, CHEN, Heng, LEE, Young, MCFARLAND, Michael, <lb/>BERGMAN, Lawrence, and VAKAKIS, Alexander. &quot;Nonlinear sys-<lb/>tem identification of the dynamics of a vibro-impact beam: numer-<lb/>ical results&quot;. Archive of Applied Mechanics 82.10 (2012), 1461-<lb/>1479. OAI: hal-01620587. <lb/>[22] LACARBONARA, Walter, REGA, Giuseppe, and NAYFEH, Ali. &quot;Res-<lb/>onant non-linear normal modes. Part I: Analytical treatment for <lb/>structural one-dimensional systems&quot;. International Journal of Non-<lb/>Linear Mechanics 38.6 (2003), 851-872. OAI: hal-01403851. <lb/>[23] LAURSEN, Tod and CHAWLA, Vikas. &quot;Design of energy conserving <lb/>algorithms for frictionless dynamics contact problems&quot;. Interna-<lb/>tional Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering 40.5 (1997), <lb/>863-886. OAI: hal-01435617. <lb/>[24] LAXALDE, Denis and LEGRAND, Mathias. &quot;Nonlinear modal analy-<lb/>sis of mechanical systems with frictionless contact interfaces&quot;. Com-<lb/>putational Mechanics 47.4 (2011), 469-478. OAI: hal-00492775. <lb/>[25] LEGRAND, Mathias, JUNCA, Stéphane, and HENG, Sokly. &quot;Nons-<lb/>mooth modal analysis of a N-degree-of-freedom system undergoing <lb/>a purely elastic impact law&quot;. Communications in Nonlinear Science <lb/>and Numerical Simulation 45 (2017), 190-219. OAI: hal-01185980. <lb/>[26] LEVEQUE, Randall. Finite Volume Methods for Hyperbolic Prob-<lb/>lems. Cambridge University Press, 2002. DOI: 10.1017/CBO9780511791253. <lb/>[27] LEVEQUE, Randall. &quot;Finite-volume methods for non-linear elastic-<lb/>ity in heterogeneous media&quot;. International Journal for Numerical <lb/>Methods in Fluids 40.1-2 (2002), 93-104. OAI: hal-01471101. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[28] LUCIER, Bradley. &quot;Error Bounds for the Methods of Glimm, Go-<lb/>dunov and LeVeque&quot;. SIAM Journal on Numerical Analysis 22.6 <lb/>(1985), 1074-1081. OAI: hal-01435616. <lb/>[29] MOUSSI, El Hadi, BELLIZZI, Sergio, COCHELIN, Bruno, and NIS-<lb/>TOR, Ionel. &quot;Nonlinear normal modes of a two-degree-of-freedom <lb/>piecewise linear system&quot;. Mechanical Systems and Signal Process-<lb/>ing 64-65 (2015), 266-281. OAI: hal-01160325. <lb/>[30] RAO, Singiresu. Vibration of Continuous Systems. Wiley, 2007. <lb/>DOI: 10.1002/9780470117866. <lb/>[31] RENARD, Yves. &quot;The singular dynamic method for constrained <lb/>second order hyperbolic equations: Application to dynamic contact <lb/>problems&quot;. Journal of Computational and Applied Mathematics <lb/>234.3 (2010), 906-923. OAI: hal-01461799. <lb/>[32] SCHATZMAN, Michelle and BERCOVIER, Michel. &quot;Numerical ap-<lb/>proximation of a wave equation with unilateral constraints&quot;. Mathe-<lb/>matics of Computation 53.187 (1989), 55-79. OAI: hal-01295436. <lb/>[33] SHAW, Steven and PIERRE, Christophe. &quot;Normal Modes of Vibra-<lb/>tion for Non-Linear Continuous Systems&quot;. Journal of Sound and <lb/>Vibration 169.3 (1994), 319-347. OAI: hal-01471098. <lb/>[34] SHORR, Boris. The Wave Finite Element Method. Springer, 2004. <lb/>DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-44579-1. <lb/>[35] SILVEIRA, Ricardo, PEREIRA, Wellington, and GONÇALVES, Paulo. <lb/>&quot;Nonlinear analysis of structural elements under unilateral contact <lb/>constraints by a Ritz type approach&quot;. International Journal of Solids <lb/>and Structures 45.9 (2008), 2629-2650. OAI: hal-01620559. <lb/>[36] SMOLLER, Joel. Shock Waves and Reaction-Diffusion Equations. <lb/>Springer, 1994. DOI: 10.1007/978-1-4612-0873-0. <lb/>[37] THORIN, Anders, DELEZOIDE, Pierre, and LEGRAND, Mathias. <lb/>&quot;Non-smooth modal analysis of piecewise-linear impact oscillators&quot;. <lb/>SIAM Journal on Applied Dynamical Systems (2017). OAI: hal-<lb/>01298983. <lb/>[38] THORIN, Anders, LEGRAND, Mathias, and JUNCA, Stéphane. &quot;Non-<lb/>smooth modal analysis: Investigation of a 2-dof spring-mass system <lb/>subject to an elastic impact law&quot;. Proceedings of the 11th Interna-<lb/>tional Conference on Multibody Systems, Nonlinear Dynamics, and <lb/>Control, IDETC/CIE Conference. Boston, USA, 2015. OAI: hal-<lb/>01185973. <lb/>[39] TORO, Eleuterio. Godunov Methods: Theory and Application. Springer, <lb/>2001. DOI: 10.1007/978-1-4615-0663-8. <lb/>[40] WRIGGERS, Peter. Computational Contact Mechanics. Springer, <lb/>2006. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-32609-0. <lb/>[41] YOONG, Carlos, THORIN, Anders, and LEGRAND, Mathias. &quot;The <lb/>Wave Finite Element Method applied to a one-dimensional linear <lb/>elastodynamic problem with unilateral constraints&quot;. Proceedings of <lb/>the 11th International Conference on Multibody Systems, Nonlinear <lb/>Dynamics, and Control, IDETC&amp;CIE Conference. Boston, USA, <lb/>2015. OAI: hal-01194922. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>