<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T10:46:44.102Z">12/2/2025 10:46:44 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1371_journal.pmed.1004338</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T10:46:22.861049Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T10:46:22.861049Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The non-template functions of helper virus<lb/> RNAs create optimal replication conditions to<lb/> enhance the proliferation of satellite RNAs<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zimu Qiao, Jin Wang, Kaiyun Huang, Honghao Hu, Zhouhang Gu, Qiansheng Liao,<lb/> Zhiyou DuID*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>College of Life Sciences and Medicine, Zhejiang Sci-Tech University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>duzy@zstu.edu.cn</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">As a type of parasitic agent, satellite RNAs (satRNAs) rely on cognate helper viruses to<lb/> achieve their replication and transmission. During the infection of satRNAs, helper virus<lb/> RNAs serve as templates for synthesizing viral proteins, including the replication proteins<lb/> essential for satRNA replication. However, the role of non-template functions of helper virus<lb/> RNAs in satRNA replication remains unexploited. Here we employed the well-studied model<lb/> that is composed of cucumber mosaic virus (CMV) and its associated satRNA. In the experi-<lb/>ments employing the CMV trans-replication system, we observed an unexpected phenome-<lb/>non the replication proteins of the mild strain LS-CMV exhibited defective in supporting<lb/> satRNA replication, unlike those of the severe strain Fny-CMV. Independent of translation<lb/> products, all CMV genomic RNAs could enhance satRNA replication, when combined with<lb/> the replication proteins of CMV. This enhancement is contingent upon the recruitment and<lb/> complete replication of helper virus RNAs. Using the method developed for analyzing the<lb/> satRNA recruitment, we observed a markedly distinct ability of the replication proteins from<lb/> both CMV strains to recruit the positive-sense satRNA-harboring RNA3 mutant for replica-<lb/>tion. This is in agreement with the differential ability of both 1a proteins in binding satRNAs<lb/> in plants. The discrepancies provide a convincing explanation for the variation of the replica-<lb/>tion proteins of both CMV strains in replicating satRNAs. Taken together, our work provides<lb/> compelling evidence that the non-template functions of helper virus RNAs create an optimal<lb/> replication environment to enhance satRNA proliferation.<lb/></div>

	Author summary<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Satellite RNAs (satRNAs) are a type of subviral pathogens that encode neither replication<lb/> protein nor coat protein. Consequently, they must compete with helper virus RNAs for<lb/> viral proteins and host resources to ensure their survival. The competition relationship<lb/> has led us to conceptualize that helper virus RNAs might exhibit antagonism with satR-<lb/>NAs during replication. Several studies have highlighted the importance of non-template<lb/> functions of viral RNAs in viral replication, such as viral replicase-mediated RNA<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS PATHOGENS<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1012174 April 17, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 27<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Qiao Z, Wang J, Huang K, Hu H, Gu Z,<lb/> Liao Q, et al. (2024) The non-template functions of<lb/> helper virus RNAs create optimal replication<lb/> conditions to enhance the proliferation of satellite<lb/> RNAs. PLoS Pathog 20(4): e1012174.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.<lb/> org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1012174<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Ying Wang,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Florida,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: October 19, 2023<lb/> Accepted: April 7, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>April 17, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1012174<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Qiao et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement: 
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> Information files.<lb/></note>
			
	<div type="abstract">recruitment and participating in the assembly of viral replication complex. However, it<lb/> remains unknown whether this significance extends to satRNA replication. To address<lb/> this question, we utilized a well-established model involving cucumber mosaic virus and<lb/> its associated satRNAs. Our data provides compelling evidence to uncover the biological<lb/> relevance of the non-template functions of helper virus RNAs in enhancing satRNA repli-<lb/>cation. Thus, our work prompts a reconsideration of the molecular interplay between<lb/> helper virus RNAs and satRNAs in their replication, previously thought to be mutually<lb/> competitive.<lb/></div>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">This work was supported by the grants<lb/> from the National Natural Science Foundation of<lb/> China with the numbers (31870144, 32070154) to<lb/> Z.D. The funder had no role in study design, data<lb/> collection and analysis, decision to publish, or<lb/> preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.<lb/></note>

	Formal analysis:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zimu Qiao, Jin Wang, Kaiyun Huang, Honghao Hu, Zhouhang Gu, Qian-<lb/>sheng Liao, Zhiyou Du.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Funding acquisition:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zhiyou Du.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Methodology:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zimu Qiao, Jin Wang, Kaiyun Huang, Honghao Hu.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Supervision:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zhiyou Du.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Validation:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zhouhang Gu, Zhiyou Du.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Writing -original draft:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zimu Qiao, Kaiyun Huang, Zhiyou Du.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Writing -review &amp; editing: Zhiyou Du.
		</front>
	</text>


  </TEI>