<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-03T15:36:26.564Z">12/3/2025 3:36:26 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-03T15:35:27.077528Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-03T15:35:27.077528Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>TIR domains of TLR family-from the cell<lb/> culture to the protein sample for structural studies<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Vladislav A. Lushpa ☯ , Marina V. Goncharuk ☯ , Irina A. Talyzina ¤a , Alexander S. Arseniev,<lb/> Eduard V. Bocharov, Konstantin S. Mineev ¤b *, Sergey A. GoncharukID*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Shemyakin-Ovchinnikov Institute of Bioorganic Chemistry of the Russian Academy of Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Moscow, Russia<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>¤a Current address: Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics, Columbia University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New York,<lb/> NY, United States of America<lb/></address>


	<byline>
	<affiliation>¤b Current address: Institute of Organic Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Goethe University Frankfurt,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Frankfurt am Main, Germany<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>konstantin.mineev@gmail.com</email>

	(K.S.M.);
	<email>ms.goncharuk@gmail.com</email>

	(S.A.G.) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Toll-like receptors (TLRs) are key players in the innate immune system. Despite the great<lb/> efforts in TLR structural biology, today we know the spatial structures of only four human<lb/> TLR intracellular TIR domains. All of them belong to one of five subfamilies of receptors.<lb/> One of the main bottlenecks is the high-level production of correctly folded proteins in solu-<lb/>ble form. Here we used a rational approach to find the optimal parameters to produce TIR<lb/> domains of all ten human TLR family members in soluble form in E. coli cells. We showed<lb/> that dozens of milligrams of soluble His-tagged TLR2/3/6/7 TIR and MBP-tagged TLR3/5/7/<lb/> 8 TIR can be produced. We also developed the purification protocols and demonstrated by<lb/> CD and NMR spectroscopy that purified TLR2/3/7 TIR demonstrate a structural organization<lb/> inherent to TIR domains. This illustrates the correct folding of produced proteins and their<lb/> suitability for further structural and functional investigations.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304997 July 5, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 14<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Lushpa VA, Goncharuk MV, Talyzina IA,<lb/> Arseniev AS, Bocharov EV, Mineev KS, et al. (2024)<lb/> TIR domains of TLR family-from the cell culture to<lb/> the protein sample for structural studies. PLoS<lb/> ONE 19(7): e0304997.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/<lb/> journal.pone.0304997<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Peter J. Bond,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Bioinformatics Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>SINGAPORE<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: February 7, 2024<lb/> Accepted: June 14, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>July 5, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304997<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Lushpa et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> Information files.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">The work was supported by the Russian<lb/> Science Foundation grant #22-14-00020. The<lb/> funders had no role in study design, data collection<lb/> and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of<lb/> the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>