<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T09:47:10.515Z">12/2/2025 9:47:10 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T09:43:37.880986Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T09:43:37.880986Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression<lb/> from infancy to pre-school age, their early<lb/> predictors, and school-age outcomes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ane Naerde ID 1<lb/> *, Harald Janson ID 1<lb/> , Mike Stoolmiller 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 The Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral Development,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Oslo, Norway,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Oregon Research Institute,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Eugene, Oregon, United States of America<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>ane.narde@nubu.no</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This study identified latent trajectories of physical aggression (TPA) from infancy to pre-<lb/>school age and evaluated (a) effects of early parent, parenting and child predictors on TPA<lb/> as well as on social, behavioral, and academic functioning in Grade 2, and (b) TPA effects<lb/> net of early predictor effects on Grade 2 functioning. We used data from the Behavior Out-<lb/>look Norwegian Developmental Study (BONDS), which included 1,159 children (559 girls).<lb/> Parents reported on risk and protective factors, and on physical aggression from 1 to 5<lb/> years of age; teachers reported on Grade 2 outcomes. We employed latent class growth<lb/> curve analyses and identified nine TPA. In fully adjusted models simultaneously testing all<lb/> associations among predictors, trajectories, and outcomes, maternal and paternal harsh<lb/> parenting, child gender, and sibling presence predicted TPA, which significantly predicted<lb/> externalizing and academic competence in Grade 2. Child gender had a pervasive influence<lb/> on all outcomes as well as on TPA. To our knowledge, this is the first trajectory study to<lb/> determine which predictors are most proximal, more distal, or just confounded, with their rel-<lb/>ative direct effect sizes, and to link early paternal as well as maternal harsh parenting prac-<lb/>tices with children&apos;s TPA. Our findings underscore the need to include fathers in<lb/> developmental research and early prevention and intervention efforts.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 24<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Naerde A, Janson H, Stoolmiller M (2024)<lb/> Modeling trajectories of physical aggression from<lb/> infancy to pre-school age, their early predictors,<lb/> and school-age outcomes. PLoS ONE 19(6):<lb/> e0291704.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.<lb/> pone.0291704<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Umberto Simeoni,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Lausanne:<lb/> Universite de Lausanne,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>SWITZERLAND<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: September 4, 2023<lb/> Accepted: May 16, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>June 3, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Naerde et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
    <note type="availability">Our data is part of an<lb/> ongoing longitudinal study and contains potentially<lb/> sensitive information. The consent of the<lb/> participants of the Behavior Outlook Norwegian<lb/> Developmental Study (BONDS), as approved by<lb/> the Regional Committee for Medical and Health<lb/> Research Ethics in South-East Norway, does not<lb/> include sharing a de-identified data set on an open<lb/> server. However, upon request the dataset may be<lb/> made accessible in our secure data server to<lb/> researchers who meet the criteria for access to<lb/> confidential data, under a data processing<lb/> agreement. Requests should be addressed to the<lb/> Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral<lb/> Development (NUBU), Oslo, Norway (mail:<lb/> post@nubu.no) or to the project leader Ane Naerde<lb/> (ane.narde@nubu.no).<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">AN received a grant from The Research<lb/> Council of Norway (Grant 283438/H20). https://<lb/> www.forskningsradet.no/en/. The funders had no<lb/> role in study design, data collection or analysis,<lb/> decisions to publish, or preparation of the<lb/> manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>