<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin15415055333180834987"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Using unstructured crowd-sourced data to<lb/> evaluate urban tolerance of terrestrial native<lb/> animal species within a California Mega-City<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Joseph N. Curti ID 1<lb/> *, Michelle Barton 2 , Rhay G. Flores 1 , Maren Lechner 1 , Alison Lipman 1 ,<lb/> Graham A. Montgomery 1 , Albert Y. Park 1 , Kirstin Rochel 2 , Morgan W. TingleyID 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Los Angeles, CA, United States<lb/> of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 LA Sanitation and Environment,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Los Angeles City, CA, United States of America<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>jcurti3@g.ucla.edu</email>

	(JNC);
	<email>mtingley@g.ucla.edu</email>

	(MWT) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">In response to biodiversity loss and biotic community homogenization in urbanized land-<lb/>scapes, there are increasing efforts to conserve and increase biodiversity within urban<lb/> areas. Accordingly, around the world, previously extirpated species are (re)colonizing and<lb/> otherwise infiltrating urban landscapes, while other species are disappearing from these<lb/> landscapes. Tracking the occurrence of traditionally urban intolerant species and loss of tra-<lb/>ditionally urban tolerant species should be a management goal of urban areas, but we gen-<lb/>erally lack tools to study this phenomenon. To address this gap, we first used species&apos;<lb/> occurrences from iNaturalist, a large collaborative dataset of species observations, to calcu-<lb/>late an urban association index (UAI) for 967 native animal species that occur in the city of<lb/> Los Angeles. On average, the occurrence of native species was negatively associated with<lb/> our composite measure of urban intensity, with the exception of snails and slugs, which<lb/> instead occur more frequently in areas of increased urban intensity. Next, we assessed<lb/> 8,348 0.25 x 0.25 mile grids across the City of Los Angeles to determine the average grid-<lb/>level UAI scores (i.e., a summary of the UAIs present in a grid cell, which we term Commu-<lb/>nity Urban Tolerance Index or CUTI). We found that areas of higher urban intensity host<lb/> more urban tolerant species, but also that taxonomic groups differ in their aggregate toler-<lb/>ance of urban areas, and that spatial patterns of tolerance vary between groups. The frame-<lb/>work established here has been designed to be iteratively reevaluated by city managers of<lb/> Los Angeles in order to track the progress of initiatives to preserve and encourage urban<lb/> biodiversity, but can be rescaled to sample different regions within the city or different cities<lb/> altogether to provide a valuable tool for city managers globally.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295476 May 29, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 21<lb/></page>

	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Curti JN, Barton M, Flores RG, Lechner<lb/> M, Lipman A, Montgomery GA, et al. (2024) Using<lb/> unstructured crowd-sourced data to evaluate urban<lb/> tolerance of terrestrial native animal species within<lb/> a California Mega-City. PLoS ONE 19(5):<lb/> e0295476.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.<lb/> pone.0295476<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Da ´rius Pukenis Tubelis</editor>,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>UFERSA:<lb/> Universidade Federal Rural do Semi-Arido,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BRAZIL<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: November 28, 2023<lb/> Accepted: March 18, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>May 29, 2024<lb/></date>

	Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the<lb/> benefits of transparency in the peer review<lb/> process; therefore, we enable the publication of<lb/> all of the content of peer review and author<lb/> responses alongside final, published articles. The<lb/> editorial history of this article is available here:<lb/>
	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295476<lb/></idno>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Curti et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">The author(s) received no specific<lb/> funding for this work.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
