<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Barriers and facilitators to parents’ engagement with and perceived impact of a childhood obesity app: A mixed-methods study</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Madison</forename>
          <surname>Milne-Ives</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Em</forename>
          <surname>Rahman</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hannah</forename>
          <surname>Bradwell</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rebecca</forename>
          <surname>Baines</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Timothy</forename>
          <surname>Boey</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Alison</forename>
          <surname>Potter</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Wendy</forename>
          <surname>Lawrence</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Michelle</forename>
          <surname>Helena van Velthoven</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Edward</forename>
          <surname>Meinert</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-04T17:53:44.214Z">12/4/2025 5:53:44 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pdig.0000481</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Madison Milne-Ives, Em Rahman, Hannah Bradwell, Rebecca Baines, Timothy Boey, Alison Potter, Wendy Lawrence, Michelle Helena van Velthoven, Edward Meinert. (2024). Barriers and facilitators to parents’ engagement with and perceived impact of a childhood obesity app: A mixed-methods study. PLOS Digital Health, 3(3), e0000481. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pdig.0000481</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-04T17:47:59.788271Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-04T17:47:59.788271Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Cryptosporidium parvum disrupts intestinal<lb/> epithelial barrier in neonatal mice through<lb/> downregulation of cell junction molecules<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Chaowei Luo 1☯ , Yanhua Xu 1☯ , Jie Zhang 1 , Qing Tian 1 , Yaqiong Guo 1 , Na Li 1 ,<lb/> Yaoyu Feng 1,2 , Rui XuID 1 *, Lihua XiaoID 1,2 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guangzhou, China,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Guangdong Laboratory for Lingnan Modern Agriculture, Center for Emerging and<lb/> Zoonotic Diseases, College of Veterinary Medicine, South China Agricultural University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guangzhou, China<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>ruix@scau.edu.cn</email>

	(RX);
	<email>lxiao1961@gmail.com</email>

	(LX) Abstract
	<div type="abstract">Background<lb/> Cryptosporidium spp. cause watery diarrhea in humans and animals, especially in infants<lb/> and neonates. They parasitize the apical surface of the epithelial cells in the intestinal<lb/> lumen. However, the pathogenesis of Cryptosporidium-induced diarrhea is not fully under-<lb/>stood yet.<lb/> Methodology/principal findings<lb/> In this study, we infected C57BL/6j neonatal mice with C. parvum IIa and IId subtypes, and<lb/> examined oocyst burden, pathological changes, and intestinal epithelial permeability during<lb/> the infection. In addition, transcriptomic analyses were used to study the mechanism of diar-<lb/>rhea induced by the C. parvum IId subtype. The neonatal mice were sensitive to both C. par-<lb/>vum IIa and IId infection, but the IId subtype caused a wide oocyst shedding window and<lb/> maintained the high oocyst burden in the mice compared with the IIa subtype. In addition,<lb/> the mice infected with C. parvum IId resulted in severe intestinal damage at the peak of<lb/> infection, leading to increased permeability of the epithelial barrier. The KEGG, GO and<lb/> GSEA analyses revealed that the downregulation of adherens junction and cell junction mol-<lb/>ecules at 11 dpi. Meanwhile, E-cadherin, which is associated with adherens junction, was<lb/> reduced at the protein level in mouse ileum at peak and late infection.<lb/> Conclusions/significance<lb/> C. parvum IId infection causes more severe pathological damage than C. parvum IIa infec-<lb/>tion in neonatal mice. Furthermore, the impairment of the epithelial barrier during C. parvum<lb/> IId infection results from the downregulation of intestinal junction proteins.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS NEGLECTED TROPICAL DISEASES<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0012212 May 24, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 19<lb/></page>
          a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Luo C, Xu Y, Zhang J, Tian Q, Guo Y, Li N,<lb/> et al. (2024) Cryptosporidium parvum disrupts<lb/> intestinal epithelial barrier in neonatal mice through<lb/> downregulation of cell junction molecules. PLoS<lb/> Negl Trop Dis 18(5): e0012212.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/<lb/> 10.1371/journal.pntd.0012212<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Kevin Shyong-Wei Tan,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>National University<lb/> of Singapore,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>SINGAPORE<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: February 6, 2024<lb/> Accepted: May 13, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>May 24, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Luo et al. This is an open access<lb/> article distributed under the terms of the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution License, which permits<lb/> unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in<lb/> any medium, provided the original author and<lb/> source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">Transcriptomics data<lb/> generated in this project was submitted to the NCBI<lb/> under the BioProject: PRJNA1072559.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">This work was supported by the National<lb/> Key Research and Development Program of China<lb/> (2022YFD1800200 to LX), National Natural Science<lb/> Foundation of China (32030109 to LX), Double<lb/> First-Class Discipline Promotion Project<lb/> (2023B10564003 to LX), and 111 Project (D20008<lb/> to LX). The funders had no role in study design,<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Author summary<lb/> Cryptosporidiosis is a leading cause of moderate to severe diarrhea in children under 2<lb/> years of age. However, the pathogenesis of Cryptosporidium infection is not well under-<lb/>stood. In this study, we used neonatal mice and a virulent C. parvum IId subtype as an<lb/> infection model to study the mechanism of diarrhea associated with cryptosporidiosis.<lb/> The results showed that the C. parvum IId subtype caused intense infection and severe<lb/> pathological changes. At the peak of infection, mice had reduced intestinal digestion and<lb/> absorption, and increased intestinal permeability. Transcriptomic data indicated that<lb/> multiple pathways were involved in regulation of C. parvum IId infection. In particular,<lb/> the adherens junction and cell junction assembly were downregulated. This was further<lb/> supported by the reduction of E-cadherin expression during both peak and recovery peri-<lb/>ods. These data suggest that neonatal mice infect with C. parvum experience extensive<lb/> damage of the intestinal barrier, resulting in diarrhea at the peak of infection.<lb/></div>
          
    <note type="funding">data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or<lb/> preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>