<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-02T12:45:58.008Z">12/2/2025 12:45:58 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-02T12:45:48.310840Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-02T12:45:48.310840Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Efficacy of preoperative lymphoscintigraphy<lb/> in predicting surgical outcomes of<lb/> lymphaticovenous anastomosis in lower<lb/> extremity lymphedema: Clinical correlations<lb/> in gynecological cancer-related lymphedema<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Min Young Yoo ID<lb/> 1,2<lb/> , Kyong-Je Woo 3 , Seo Young Kang 1 , Byung Seok Moon 1 , Bom<lb/> Sahn Kim ID 1☯<lb/> *, Hai-Jeon Yoon ID 1☯ *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Nuclear Medicine, Ewha Womans University College of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, Republic of Korea,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Nuclear Medicine, Inha University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Incheon, Republic of Korea,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Plastic Surgery, Ewha Womans University College of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>haijeon.yoon@gmail.com</email>

	(HJY);
	<email>kbomsahn@ewha.ac.kr</email>

	(BSK) Abstract
	<div type="abstract">Background<lb/> Lymphaticovenous anastomosis (LVA) is a promising microsurgical treatment for lower<lb/> extremity lymphedema (LEL). Lymphoscintigraphy effectively assesses lower limb lym-<lb/>phatic systems before LVA, but its role in predicting the therapeutic outcomes of LVA is<lb/> indeterminate. In this study we investigate the efficacy of preoperative lymphoscintigraphy<lb/> using clinical findings to predict outcomes in gynecological cancer-related LEL patients who<lb/> underwent LVA. Methods<lb/> A retrospective review was conducted on consecutive gynecological cancer patients with<lb/> LEL who had undergone LVA between June 2018 and June 2021. The therapeutic efficacy<lb/> was assessed by measuring the change rate of the lower extremity lymphedema index<lb/> (LELi) six months after surgery. Clinical data and lymphoscintigraphic findings were ana-<lb/>lyzed to assess therapeutic efficacy of LVA. Results<lb/> Out of the 60 evaluated legs, 83.3% of the legs showed improved results after LVA. Univari-<lb/>able linear regression analysis revealed that higher preoperative LELi, and ovarian cancer<lb/> were associated with superior LELi change rate (LC rate). Absence of dermal backflow<lb/> (DBF) on lymphoscintigraphy was associated with inferior LC rate. Multivariable linear<lb/> regression analysis identified ovarian cancer and higher preoperative LELi were indepen-<lb/>dently correlated with favorable outcomes, while the absence of DBF was independently<lb/> correlated with inferior outcomes.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296466 January 2, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 13<lb/></page>
			a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Yoo MY, Woo K-J, Kang SY, Moon BS,<lb/> Kim BS, Yoon H-J (2024) Efficacy of preoperative<lb/> lymphoscintigraphy in predicting surgical<lb/> outcomes of lymphaticovenous anastomosis in<lb/> lower extremity lymphedema: Clinical correlations<lb/> in gynecological cancer-related lymphedema. PLoS<lb/> ONE 19(1): e0296466.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/<lb/> journal.pone.0296466<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Andrea Giannini</editor>,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Sapienza University of<lb/> Rome: Universita degli Studi di Roma La Sapienza</affiliation>,
	</byline>

	<address>ITALY<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: July 31, 2023<lb/> Accepted: December 13, 2023<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>January 2, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Yoo et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the paper and its Supporting information<lb/> files.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">This research was supported by grants<lb/> from the Basic Science Research Program through<lb/> the National Research Foundation of Korea, funded<lb/> by the Ministry of Science and ICT (Grant numbers:<lb/> 2021R1A2C1093636, H.-J.Y.; </note>
			
	<div type="abstract">Conclusion<lb/>The results of this study emphasizes the effectiveness of preoperative lymphoscintigraphy,<lb/> preoperative LELi, and primary malignancy as predictors of LVA outcomes in gynecological<lb/> cancer-related LEL patients.<lb/></div>
			
	<note type="funding">2021R1F1A1060946, B.S.K.;<lb/> 2022R1I1A1A01068463, M.Y.Y). The funders had<lb/> no role in study design, data collection and<lb/> analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the<lb/> manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.</note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>