<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-03T15:15:09.762Z">12/3/2025 3:15:09 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-03T15:14:42.595803Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-03T15:14:42.595803Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Revealing the diversity of Parasmittina<lb/> Osburn, 1952 (Bryozoa, Cheilostomatida)<lb/> from the Southwest Atlantic: Species<lb/> complexes, non-native and new species<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jamile Farias ID<lb/> 1,2,3☯ *, Leandro M. Vieira ID<lb/> 3,4☯<lb/> , Ana C. S. Almeida ID<lb/> 1,2,3☯ *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Programa de Po ´s-Graduac ¸ão em Biodiversidade e Evoluc ¸ão, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal<lb/> da Bahia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Salvador, BA, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Museu de Histo ´ria Natural da Bahia, Setor da Zoologia, Instituto de<lb/> Biologia, Universidade Federal da Bahia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Salvador, BA, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Laborato ´rio de Estudos de Bryozoa-<lb/>LAEBry, Departamento de Zoologia, Centro de Biociências, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Recife,<lb/> PE, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Scientific Associate of the Department of Life Sciences, Natural History Museum,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London,<lb/> United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> *
	<email>jamile.farias04@gmail.commailto</email>

	: (JF);
	<email>carol.salmeida@gmail.com</email>

	(ACSA) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Parasmittina is the most representative cheilostome genus of the family Smittinidae, often<lb/> reported in the fouling non-indigenous marine community. Here, we present a review of Para-<lb/>smittina species reported in the Southwestern Atlantic including the characterization of one<lb/> species from Argentina (P. dubitata) and ten from the Brazilian coast: P. abrolhosensis, P.<lb/> alba, P. bimucronata, P. ligulata comb. nov., P. longirostrata, P. pinctatae, P. serrula, P. sim-<lb/>pulata, P. winstonae and the new species Parasmittina falciformis sp. nov. The new species<lb/> is characterized by a smooth distally primary orifice with 1-2 oral spines, large lyrula, serrated<lb/> condyles with hooked tips, and two types of avicularia-small and subtriangular and large sub-<lb/>lanceolate. This study does not recognize four species previous recorded in Brazil: reports of<lb/> P. betamorphaea and P. trispinosa are now assigned to P. pinctatae; records of P. munita<lb/> belong to P. falciformis sp. nov.; and reports of P. spathulata encompass at least two taxa,<lb/> including P. abrolhosensis and P. simpulata. In this study, five species complexes (P. alba,<lb/> P. longirostrata, P. serrula, P. simpulata and P. winstonae) were identified and require further<lb/> investigations. While six species characterized here were first described based on speci-<lb/>mens from the Southwestern Atlantic (P. abrolhosensis, P. alba, P. dubitata, P. ligulata<lb/> comb. nov., P. simpulata and P. falciformis sp. nov.), the remaining species are mainly<lb/> known from the Indo-Pacific. These taxa are here recognized as exotic (P. longirostrata) and<lb/> cryptogenic (P. bimucronata, P. pinctatae, P. serrula and P. winstonae) in the studied area.<lb/> Most of the non-native taxa are widespread along the Brazilian coast, growing on both artifi-<lb/>cial and natural surfaces, indicating that they are well-established in the area. As non-native<lb/> bryozoans can negatively influence the environment, affecting human economic activities<lb/> and beach usage, further studies on the fauna presented here are suggested to determine<lb/> the origin of these taxa and help prevent bioinvasion events along the SW Atlantic.<lb/></div>

	<title level="j">PLOS ONE<lb/></title>
	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347 August 8, 2024<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 49<lb/></page>
	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Farias J, Vieira LM, Almeida ACS (2024)<lb/> Revealing the diversity of Parasmittina Osburn,<lb/> 1952 (Bryozoa, Cheilostomatida) from the<lb/> Southwest Atlantic: Species complexes, non-native<lb/> and new species. PLoS ONE 19(8): e0304347.<lb/></reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0304347<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Karolina Goździewska-Harłajczuk,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Wrocław<lb/> University of Environmental and Life Sciences:<lb/> Uniwersytet Przyrodniczy we Wroclawiu,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>POLAND<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: February 3, 2024<lb/> Accepted: May 9, 2024<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>August 8, 2024<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024 Farias et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> Information files.<lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">The author(s) received no specific<lb/> funding for this work.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>