<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin7031654628674630852"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License,<lb/> which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the<lb/> original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	<title level="j">Computer Modeling in<lb/> Engineering &amp; Sciences<lb/></title>

	ech<lb/> T<lb/> Press Science<lb/>
	<idno>DOI: 10.32604/cmes.2023.043322</idno>

	<note type="doctype">ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Parametric Optimization of Wheel Spoke Structure for Drag Reduction of an<lb/> Ahmed Body<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Huihui Zhai 1 , Dongqi Jiao 2 and Haichao Zhou 2,*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Institute of Electrical and Information Engineering,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Zhenjiang College, Zhenjiang, 212028, China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 School of Automotive and Traffic Engineering, Jiangsu University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Zhenjiang, 212013, China<lb/></address>

	*Corresponding Author:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Haichao Zhou.</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Email:
	<email>haichaozhou999@163.com<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received: 29 June 2023 Accepted: 20 September 2023</note>

	Published:
	<date>30 December 2023</date>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The wheels have a considerable influence on the aerodynamic properties and can contribute up to 25% of the total<lb/> drag on modern vehicles. In this study, the effect of the wheel spoke structure on the aerodynamic performance of<lb/> the isolated wheel is investigated. Subsequently, the 35°Ahmed body with an optimized spoke structure is used<lb/> to analyze the flow behavior and the mechanism of drag reduction. The Fluent software is employed for this<lb/> investigation, with an inlet velocity of 40 m/s. The accuracy of the numerical study is validated by comparing it<lb/> with experimental results obtained from the classical Ahmed model. To gain a clearer understanding of the effects<lb/> of the wheel spoke parameters on the aerodynamics of both the wheel and Ahmed model, and five design variables<lb/> are proposed: the fillet angle α, the inside arc radius R 1 , the outside radius R 2 , and the same length of the chord<lb/> L 1 and L 2 . These variables characterize the wheel spoke structure. The Optimal Latin Hypercube design method<lb/> is utilized to conduct the experimental design. Based on the simulation results of various wheel spoke designs, the<lb/> Kriging model and the adaptive simulated annealing algorithm is selected to optimize the design parameters. The<lb/> objective is to achieve the best combination for maximum drag reduction. It is indicated that the optimized spoke<lb/> structure resulted in a maximum drag reduction of 5.7% and 4.7% for the drag coefficient of the isolated wheel and<lb/> Ahmed body, respectively. The drag reduction is primarily attributed to changes in the flow state around the wheel,<lb/> which suppressed separation bubbles. Additionally, it influenced the boundary layer thickness around the car body<lb/> and reduced the turbulent kinetic energy in the wake flow. These effects collectively contributed to the observed<lb/> drag reduction.<lb/></div>

	KEYWORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Ahmed body; wheel spoke design; parameter optimization; drag reduction; numerical simulation</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
