<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin7333053271908831570"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License,<lb/> which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the<lb/> original work is properly cited.<lb/> ech<lb/> T<lb/> Press Science<lb/></note>

	<idno>DOI: 10.32604/cmc.2024.048003</idno>

	<note type="doctype">ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Machine Learning Approach to Cyberbullying Detection in Arabic Tweets<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dhiaa Musleh 1 , Atta Rahman 1,* , Mohammed Abbas Alkherallah 1 , Menhal Kamel Al-Bohassan 1 ,<lb/> Mustafa Mohammed Alawami 1 , Hayder Ali Alsebaa 1 , Jawad Ali Alnemer 1 , Ghazi Fayez Al-Mutairi 1 ,<lb/> May Issa Aldossary 2 , Dalal A. Aldowaihi 1 and Fahd Alhaidari 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Computer Science, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Computer Information Systems, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman<lb/> Bin Faisal University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Networks and Communications, College of Computer Science and Information Technology, Imam Abdulrahman<lb/> Bin Faisal University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 1982, Dammam, 31441, Saudi Arabia<lb/></address>

	*Corresponding Author:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Atta Rahman</docAuthor>.
	</byline>

	Email:
	<email>aaurrahman@iau.edu.sa<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received: 24 November 2023 Accepted: 28 May 2024</note>

	Published:
	<date>18 July 2024</date>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">With the rapid growth of internet usage, a new situation has been created that enables practicing bullying.<lb/> Cyberbullying has increased over the past decade, and it has the same adverse effects as face-to-face bullying, like<lb/> anger, sadness, anxiety, and fear. With the anonymity people get on the internet, they tend to be more aggressive and<lb/> express their emotions freely without considering the effects, which can be a reason for the increase in cyberbullying<lb/> and it is the main motive behind the current study. This study presents a thorough background of cyberbullying<lb/> and the techniques used to collect, preprocess, and analyze the datasets. Moreover, a comprehensive review of the<lb/> literature has been conducted to figure out research gaps and effective techniques and practices in cyberbullying<lb/> detection in various languages, and it was deduced that there is significant room for improvement in the Arabic<lb/> language. As a result, the current study focuses on the investigation of shortlisted machine learning algorithms<lb/> in natural language processing (NLP) for the classification of Arabic datasets duly collected from Twitter (also<lb/> known as X). In this regard, support vector machine (SVM), Naïve Bayes (NB), Random Forest (RF), Logistic<lb/> regression (LR), Bootstrap aggregating (Bagging), Gradient Boosting (GBoost), Light Gradient Boosting Machine<lb/> (LightGBM), Adaptive Boosting (AdaBoost), and eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost) were shortlisted and<lb/> investigated due to their effectiveness in the similar problems. Finally, the scheme was evaluated by well-known<lb/> performance measures like accuracy, precision, Recall, and F1-score. Consequently, XGBoost exhibited the best<lb/> performance with 89.95% accuracy, which is promising compared to the state-of-the-art.<lb/></div>

	KEYWORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Supervised machine learning; ensemble learning; cyberbullying; Arabic tweets; NLP</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
