<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin12150888599726213045"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024<lb/> https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under<lb/> the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Research article<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a<lb/> large loss of tundra due to climate warming<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Fredrik Lagergren 1 , Robert G. Björk 2,3 , Camilla Andersson 4 , Danijel Belušić 4,5 , Mats P. Björkman 2,3,a ,<lb/> Erik Kjellström 4 , Petter Lind 4 , David Lindstedt 4 , Tinja Olenius 4 , Håkan Pleijel 6 , Gunhild Rosqvist 7 , and<lb/> Paul A. Miller 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Physical Geography and Ecosystem Science, Lund University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lund, 223 62, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Earth Sciences, University of Gothenburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Gothenburg Global Biodiversity Centre,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Norrköping, 601 76, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Department of Geophysics, Faculty of Science, University of Zagreb,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Zagreb, 10 000, Croatia<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, University of Gothenburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 Department of Physical Geography, Stockholm University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Stockholm, 106 91, Sweden<lb/></address>


	<byline>
	<affiliation>a now at: Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, University of Gothenburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden<lb/></address>

	Correspondence:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Fredrik Lagergren</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<email>fredrik.lagergren@nateko.lu.se</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received: 30 August 2023 -Discussion started: 12 September 2023<lb/> Revised: 11 January 2024 -Accepted: 19 January 2024 -</note>

	Published:
	<date>5 March 2024<lb/></date>

	Abstract.
	<div type="abstract">The Fennoscandian boreal and mountain regions<lb/> harbour a wide range of vegetation types, from boreal forest<lb/> to high alpine tundra and barren soils. The area is facing a<lb/> rise in air temperature above the global average and changes<lb/> in temperature and precipitation patterns. This is expected to<lb/> alter the Fennoscandian vegetation composition and change<lb/> the conditions for areal land use such as forestry, tourism<lb/> and reindeer husbandry. In this study we used a unique high-<lb/>resolution (3 km) climate scenario with considerable warm-<lb/>ing resulting from strongly increasing carbon dioxide emis-<lb/>sions to investigate how climate change can alter the veg-<lb/>etation composition, biodiversity and availability of suitable<lb/> reindeer forage. Using a dynamical vegetation model, includ-<lb/>ing a new implementation of potential reindeer grazing, re-<lb/>sulted in simulated vegetation maps of unprecedented high<lb/> resolution for such a long time period and spatial extent.<lb/> The results were evaluated at the local scale using vegeta-<lb/>tion inventories and for the whole area against satellite-based<lb/> vegetation maps. A deeper analysis of vegetation shifts re-<lb/>lated to statistics of threatened species was performed in<lb/> six &quot;hotspot&quot; areas containing records of rare and threat-<lb/>ened species. In this high-emission scenario, the simulations<lb/> show dramatic shifts in the vegetation composition, acceler-<lb/>ating at the end of the century. Alarmingly, the results sug-<lb/>gest the southern mountain alpine region in Sweden will be<lb/> completely covered by forests at the end of the 21st century,<lb/> making preservation of many rare and threatened species<lb/> impossible. In the northern alpine regions, most vegetation<lb/> types will persist but shift to higher elevations with reduced<lb/> areal extent, endangering vulnerable species. Simulated po-<lb/>tential for reindeer grazing indicates latitudinal differences,<lb/> with higher potential in the south in the current climate. In<lb/> the future these differences will diminish, as the potentials<lb/> will increase in the north, especially for the summer grazing<lb/> grounds. These combined results suggest significant shifts in<lb/> vegetation composition over the present century for this sce-<lb/>nario, with large implications for nature conservation, rein-<lb/>deer husbandry and forestry.<lb/></div>

	Published by
	<publisher>Copernicus Publications</publisher>

	on behalf of the European Geosciences Union.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
