<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-13T14:35:23.527779Z">13.11.2025 14:35:23</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">0506081v3</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication"/>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T14:35:23.527779Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-13T14:35:23.527779Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:math/0506081v3 [math.ST] 21 Mar 2008 <lb/>The Annals of Statistics <lb/>2007, Vol. 35, No. 6, 2313-2351 <lb/>DOI: 10.1214/009053606000001523 <lb/>c Institute of Mathematical Statistics, 2007 <lb/>THE DANTZIG SELECTOR: STATISTICAL ESTIMATION WHEN p <lb/>IS MUCH LARGER THAN n 1 <lb/>By Emmanuel Candes 2 and Terence Tao 3 <lb/>California Institute of Technology and University of California, Los <lb/>Angeles <lb/>In many important statistical applications, the number of vari-<lb/>ables or parameters p is much larger than the number of observations <lb/>n. Suppose then that we have observations y = Xβ + z, where β ∈ R p <lb/>is a parameter vector of interest, X is a data matrix with possibly <lb/>far fewer rows than columns, n ≪ p, and the zi&apos;s are i.i.d. N (0, σ 2 ). <lb/>Is it possible to estimate β reliably based on the noisy data y? <lb/>To estimate β, we introduce a new estimator-we call it the Dantzig <lb/>selector -which is a solution to the ℓ1-regularization problem <lb/>min <lb/>β∈R p <lb/>β ℓ 1 subject to <lb/>X * r ℓ∞ ≤ (1 + t -1 ) 2 log p • σ, <lb/>where r is the residual vector y -X β and t is a positive scalar. We <lb/>show that if X obeys a uniform uncertainty principle (with unit-<lb/>normed columns) and if the true parameter vector β is sufficiently <lb/>sparse (which here roughly guarantees that the model is identifiable), <lb/>then with very large probability, <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ C 2 • 2 log p • σ 2 + <lb/>i <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) . <lb/>Our results are nonasymptotic and we give values for the constant C. <lb/>Even though n may be much smaller than p, our estimator achieves <lb/>a loss within a logarithmic factor of the ideal mean squared error one <lb/>Received August 2005; revised March 2006. <lb/>1 Discussed in 10.1214/009053607000000424, 10.1214/009053607000000433, <lb/>10.1214/009053607000000442, 10.1214/009053607000000451, <lb/>10.1214/009053607000000460 and 10.1214/009053607000000479; rejoinder at <lb/>10.1214/009053607000000532. <lb/>2 Supported in part by NSF Grant DMS-01-40698 and by an Alfred P. Sloan Fellowship. <lb/>3 Supported in part by a grant from the Packard Foundation. <lb/>AMS 2000 subject classifications. Primary 62C05, 62G05; secondary 94A08, 94A12. <lb/>Key words and phrases. Statistical linear model, model selection, ideal estimation, or-<lb/>acle inequalities, sparse solutions to underdetermined systems, ℓ1-minimization, linear <lb/>programming, restricted orthonormality, geometry in high dimensions, random matrices. <lb/>This is an electronic reprint of the original article published by the <lb/>Institute of Mathematical Statistics in The Annals of Statistics, <lb/>2007, Vol. 35, No. 6, 2313-2351. This reprint differs from the original in <lb/>pagination and typographic detail. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/>would achieve with an oracle which would supply perfect information <lb/>about which coordinates are nonzero, and which were above the noise <lb/>level. <lb/>In multivariate regression and from a model selection viewpoint, <lb/>our result says that it is possible nearly to select the best subset of <lb/>variables by solving a very simple convex program, which, in fact, <lb/>can easily be recast as a convenient linear program (LP). <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction. In many important statistical applications, the number <lb/>of variables or parameters p is now much larger than the number of observa-<lb/>tions n. In radiology and biomedical imaging, for instance, one is typically <lb/>able to collect far fewer measurements about an image of interest than the <lb/>unknown number of pixels. Examples in functional MRI and tomography <lb/>all come to mind. High dimensional data frequently arise in genomics. Gene <lb/>expression studies are a typical example: a relatively low number of obser-<lb/>vations (in the tens) is available, while the total number of genes assayed <lb/>(and considered as possible regressors) is easily in the thousands. Other ex-<lb/>amples in statistical signal processing and nonparametric estimation include <lb/>the recovery of a continuous-time curve or surface from a finite number of <lb/>noisy samples. Estimation in this setting is generally acknowledged as an <lb/>important challenge in contemporary statistics; see the recent conference <lb/>held in Leiden, The Netherlands (September 2002), &quot;On high-dimensional <lb/>data p ≫ n in mathematical statistics and bio-medical applications.&quot; It is <lb/>believed that progress may have the potential for impact across many areas <lb/>of statistics [30]. <lb/>In many research fields then, scientists work with data matrices with many <lb/>variables p and comparably few observations n. This paper is about this <lb/>important situation, and considers the problem of estimating a parameter <lb/>β ∈ R p from the linear model <lb/>y = Xβ + z; <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>y ∈ R n is a vector of observations, X is an n × p predictor matrix, and z <lb/>a vector of stochastic measurement errors. Unless specified otherwise, we <lb/>will assume that z ∼ N (0, σ 2 I n ) is a vector of independent normal random <lb/>variables, although it is clear that our methods and results may be extended <lb/>to other distributions. Throughout this paper, we will of course typically <lb/>assume that p is much larger than n. <lb/>1.1. Uniform uncertainty principles and the noiseless case. At first, re-<lb/>liably estimating β from y may seem impossible. Even in the noiseless case, <lb/>one may wonder how one could possibly do this, as one would need to <lb/>solve an underdetermined system of equations with fewer equations than <lb/>unknowns. But suppose now that β is known to be structured in the sense <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>that it is sparse or compressible. For example, suppose that β is S-sparse <lb/>so that only S of its entries are nonzero. This premise radically changes the <lb/>problem, making the search for solutions feasible. In fact, [13] showed that <lb/>in the noiseless case, one could actually recover β exactly by solving the <lb/>convex program ( β ℓ 1 := p <lb/>i=1 | βi |) <lb/>(P 1 ) <lb/>min <lb/>β∈R p <lb/>β ℓ 1 subject to X β = y, <lb/>(1.2) <lb/>provided that the matrix X ∈ R n×p obeys a uniform uncertainty principle. <lb/>(The program (P 1 ) can even be recast as a linear program.) That is, ℓ 1 -<lb/>minimization finds without error both the location and amplitudes-which <lb/>we emphasize are a priori completely unknown-of the nonzero components <lb/>of the vector β ∈ R p . We also refer the reader to [20, 24] and [27] for inspiring <lb/>early results. <lb/>To understand the exact recovery phenomenon, we introduce the notion <lb/>of uniform uncertainty principle (UUP) proposed in [14] and refined in [13]. <lb/>This principle will play an important role throughout, although we empha-<lb/>size that this paper is not about the exact recovery of noiseless data. The <lb/>UUP essentially states that the n × p measurement or design matrix X obeys <lb/>a &quot;restricted isometry hypothesis.&quot; Let X T , T ⊂ {1, . . . , p}, be the n × |T | <lb/>submatrix obtained by extracting the columns of X corresponding to the <lb/>indices in T ; then [13] defines the S-restricted isometry constant δ S of X <lb/>which is the smallest quantity such that <lb/>(1 -δ S ) c 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ X T c 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ S ) c 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>(1.3) <lb/>for all subsets T with |T | ≤ S and coefficient sequences (c j ) j∈T . This prop-<lb/>erty essentially requires that every set of columns with cardinality less than <lb/>S approximately behaves like an orthonormal system. It was shown (also in <lb/>[13]) that if S obeys <lb/>δ S + δ 2S + δ 3S &lt; 1, <lb/>(1.4) <lb/>then solving (P 1 ) recovers any sparse signal β with support size obeying <lb/>|T | ≤ S. <lb/>Actually, [13] derived a slightly stronger result. Introduce the S, S ′ -restricted <lb/>orthogonality constants θ S,S ′ for S + S ′ ≤ p to be the smallest quantities such <lb/>that <lb/>| X T c, X T ′ c ′ | ≤ θ S,S ′ • c ℓ 2 c ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>(1.5) <lb/>holds for all disjoint sets T, T ′ ⊆ {1, . . . , p} of cardinality |T | ≤ S and |T ′ | ≤ <lb/>S ′ . Small values of restricted orthogonality constants indicate that disjoint <lb/>subsets of covariates span nearly orthogonal subspaces. Then the authors <lb/>showed that the recovery is exact, provided <lb/>δ S + θ S,S + θ S,2S &lt; 1, <lb/>(1.6) <lb/>which is a little better since it is not hard to see that δ S+S ′ -δ S ′ ≤ θ S,S ′ ≤ <lb/>δ S+S ′ for S ′ ≥ S ([13], Lemma 1.1). <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>1.2. Uniform uncertainty principles and statistical estimation. Any real-<lb/>world sensor or measurement device is subject to at least a small amount <lb/>of noise. And now one asks whether it is possible to reliably estimate the <lb/>parameter β ∈ R p from the noisy data y ∈ R n and the model (1.1). Frankly, <lb/>this may seem like an impossible task. How can one hope to estimate β, <lb/>when, in addition to having too few observations, these are also contami-<lb/>nated with noise? <lb/>To estimate β with noisy data, we consider, nevertheless, solving the <lb/>convex program <lb/>(DS ) min <lb/>β∈R p <lb/>β ℓ 1 subject to <lb/>X * r ℓ∞ := sup <lb/>1≤i≤p <lb/>|(X * r) i | ≤ λ p • σ <lb/>(1.7) <lb/>for some λ p &gt; 0, where r is the vector of residuals <lb/>r = y -X β. <lb/>(1.8) <lb/>In other words, we seek an estimator β with minimum complexity (as mea-<lb/>sured by the ℓ 1 -norm) among all objects that are consistent with the data. <lb/>The constraint on the residual vector imposes that for each i ∈ {1, . . . , p}, <lb/>|(X * r) i | ≤ λ p • σ, and guarantees that the residuals are within the noise level. <lb/>As we shall see later, this proposal makes sense provided that the columns <lb/>of X have the same Euclidean size and in this paper we will always assume <lb/>they are unit-normed; our results would equally apply to matrices with dif-<lb/>ferent column sizes-one would only need to change the right-hand side to <lb/>|(X * r) i | less or equal to λ p • σ times the Euclidean norm of the ith column <lb/>of X, or to |(X * r) i | ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ 1 • λ p • σ since all the columns have norm less <lb/>than <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ 1 . <lb/>There are many reasons why one would want to constrain the size of <lb/>the correlated residual vector X * r rather than the size of the residual vec-<lb/>tor r. Suppose that an orthonormal transformation is applied to the data, <lb/>giving y ′ = U y, where U * U is the identity. Clearly, a good estimation pro-<lb/>cedure for estimating β should not depend upon U (after all, one could <lb/>apply U * to return to the original problem). It turns out that the esti-<lb/>mation procedure (1.7) is actually invariant with respect to orthonormal <lb/>transformations applied to the data vector since the feasible region is in-<lb/>variant: (U X) T (U X β -U y) = X * (X β -y). In contrast, had we defined the <lb/>feasibility region with sup i |r i | being smaller than a fixed threshold, then <lb/>the estimation procedure would not be invariant. There are other reasons <lb/>aside from this. One of them is that we would obviously want to include in <lb/>the model explanatory variables that are highly correlated with the data y. <lb/>Consider the situation in which a residual vector is equal to a column X i of <lb/>the design matrix X. Suppose, for simplicity, that the components of X i all <lb/>have about the same size, that is, about 1/ <lb/>√ n, and assume that σ is slightly <lb/>larger than 1/ <lb/>√ n. Had we used a constraint of the form sup i |r i | ≤ λ n σ (with <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>perhaps λ n of size about <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log n), the vector of residuals would be feasible, <lb/>which does not make any sense. In contrast, such a residual vector would <lb/>not be feasible for (1.7) for reasonable values of the noise level, and the ith <lb/>variable would be rightly included in the model. <lb/>Again, the program (DS ) is convex, and can easily be recast as a linear <lb/>program (LP), <lb/>min <lb/>i <lb/>u i subject to -u ≤ β ≤ u and <lb/>(1.9) <lb/>-λ p σ1 ≤ X * (y -X β) ≤ λ p σ1, <lb/>where the optimization variables are u, β ∈ R p , and 1 is a p-dimensional <lb/>vector of ones. Hence, our estimation procedure is computationally tractable; <lb/>see Section 4.4 for details. There is indeed a growing family of ever more <lb/>efficient algorithms for solving such problems (even for problems with tens <lb/>or even hundreds of thousands of observations) [8]. <lb/>We call the estimator (1.7) the Dantzig selector ; with this name, we intend <lb/>to pay tribute to the father of linear programming who passed away while we <lb/>were finalizing this manuscript, and to underscore that the convex program <lb/>(DS) is effectively a variable selection technique. <lb/>The first result of this paper is that the Dantzig selector is surprisingly <lb/>accurate. <lb/>Theorem 1.1. Suppose β ∈ R p is any S-sparse vector of parameters <lb/>obeying δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1. Choose λ p = <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p in (1.7). Then with large prob-<lb/>ability, β obeys <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ C 2 <lb/>1 • (2 log p) • S • σ 2 , <lb/>(1.10) <lb/>with C 1 = 4/(1 -δ S -θ S,2S ). Hence, for small values of δ S + θ S,2S , C 1 ≈ 4. <lb/>For concreteness, if one chooses λ p := 2(1 + a) log p for each a ≥ 0, the <lb/>bound holds with probability exceeding 1 -( <lb/>√ π log p • p a ) -1 with the proviso <lb/>that λ 2 <lb/>p substitutes 2 log p in (1.10). <lb/>We will discuss the condition δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1 later but, for the moment, <lb/>observe that (1.10) describes a striking phenomenon: not only are we able to <lb/>reliably estimate the vector of parameters from limited observations, but the <lb/>mean squared error is simply proportional-up to a logarithmic factor-to <lb/>the true number of unknowns times the noise level σ 2 . What is of interest <lb/>here is that one can achieve this feat by solving a simple linear program. <lb/>Moreover, and ignoring the log-like factor, statistical common sense tells us <lb/>that (1.10) is, in general, unimprovable. <lb/>To see why this is true, suppose one had available an oracle letting us know <lb/>in advance the location of the S nonzero entries of the parameter vector, <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>that is, T 0 := {i : β i = 0}. That is, in the language of model selection, one <lb/>would know the right model ahead of time. Then one could use this valuable <lb/>information and construct an ideal estimator β ⋆ by using the least-squares <lb/>projection <lb/>β ⋆ <lb/>T 0 = (X T <lb/>T 0 X T 0 ) -1 X T <lb/>T 0 y, <lb/>where β ⋆ <lb/>T 0 is the restriction of β ⋆ to the set T 0 , and set β ⋆ to zero outside <lb/>of T 0 . (At times, we will abuse notation and also let β I be the truncated <lb/>vector equal to β i for i ∈ I and zero otherwise.) Clearly, <lb/>β ⋆ = β + (X T <lb/>T 0 X T 0 ) -1 X T <lb/>T 0 z <lb/>and <lb/>E β ⋆ -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = E (X T <lb/>T 0 X T 0 ) -1 X T <lb/>T 0 z 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = σ 2 Tr((X T <lb/>T 0 X T 0 ) -1 ). <lb/>Now since all the eigenvalues of X T <lb/>T 0 X T 0 belong to the interval [1-δ S , 1+ δ S ], <lb/>the ideal expected mean squared error would obey <lb/>E β ⋆ -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≥ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 + δ S <lb/>• S • σ 2 . <lb/>Hence, Theorem 1.1 says that the minimum ℓ 1 estimator achieves a loss <lb/>within a logarithmic factor of the ideal mean squared error; the logarithmic <lb/>factor is the price we pay for adaptivity, that is, for not knowing ahead of <lb/>time where the nonzero parameter values actually are. <lb/>In short, the recovery procedure, although extremely nonlinear, is stable <lb/>in the presence of noise. This is especially interesting because the matrix X <lb/>in (1.1) is rectangular; it has many more columns than rows. As such, most <lb/>of its singular values are zero. In solving (DS), we are essentially trying to <lb/>invert the action of X on our hidden β in the presence of noise. The fact <lb/>that this matrix inversion process keeps the perturbation from &quot;blowing <lb/>up&quot;-even though it is severely ill-posed-is perhaps unexpected. <lb/>Presumably, our result would be especially interesting if one could esti-<lb/>mate the order of n parameters with as few as n observations. That is, we <lb/>would like the condition δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1 to hold for very large values of S, for <lb/>example, as close as possible to n (note that for 2S &gt; n, δ 2S ≥ 1 since any <lb/>submatrix with more than n columns must be singular, which implies that <lb/>in any event S must be less than n/2). Now, this paper is part of a larger <lb/>body of work [11, 13, 14] which shows that, for &quot;generic&quot; or random design <lb/>matrices X, the condition holds for very significant values of S. Suppose, for <lb/>instance, that X is a random matrix with i.i.d. Gaussian entries. Then with <lb/>overwhelming probability, the condition holds for S = O(n/ log(p/n)). In <lb/>other words, this setup only requires O(log(p/n)) observations per nonzero <lb/>parameter value; for example, when n is a nonnegligible fraction of p, one <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>only needs a handful of observations per nonzero coefficient. In practice, this <lb/>number is quite small, as few as 5 or 6 observations per unknown generally <lb/>suffice (over a large range of the ratio p/n); see Section 4. Many design <lb/>matrices have a similar behavior and Section 2 discusses a few of these. <lb/>As an aside, it is interesting to note that, for S obeying the condition <lb/>of the theorem, the reconstruction from noiseless data (σ = 0) is exact and <lb/>that our condition is slightly better than (1.6). <lb/>1.3. Oracle inequalities. Theorem 1.1 is certainly noticeable but there <lb/>are instances, however, in which it may still be a little naive. Suppose, for <lb/>example, that β is very small so that β is well below the noise level, that <lb/>is, |β i | ≪ σ for all i. Then with this information we could set β = 0, and the <lb/>squared error loss would then simply be p <lb/>i=1 |β i | 2 , which may potentially <lb/>be much smaller than σ 2 times the number of nonzero coordinates of β. In <lb/>some sense, this is a situation in which the squared bias is much smaller <lb/>than the variance. <lb/>A more ambitious proposal might then ask for a near-optimal trade-off <lb/>coordinate by coordinate. To explain this idea, suppose, for simplicity, that <lb/>X is the identity matrix so that y ∼ N (β, σ 2 I p ). Suppose then that we had <lb/>available an oracle letting us know ahead of time which coordinates of β are <lb/>significant, that is, the set of indices for which |β i | &gt; σ. Then equipped with <lb/>this oracle, we would set β ⋆ <lb/>i = y i for each index in the significant set and <lb/>β ⋆ <lb/>i = 0 otherwise. The expected mean squared error of this ideal estimator <lb/>is then <lb/>E β ⋆ -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = <lb/>p <lb/>i=1 <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ). <lb/>(1.11) <lb/>Here and below, we will refer to (1.11) as the ideal MSE. As is well known, <lb/>thresholding rules with threshold level at about <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p • σ achieve the ideal <lb/>MSE to within a multiplicative factor proportional to log p [21, 22]. <lb/>In the context of the linear model, we might think about the ideal esti-<lb/>mation as follows: consider the least-squares estimator βI = (X T <lb/>I X I ) -1 X T <lb/>I y <lb/>as before and consider the ideal least-squares estimator β ⋆ which minimizes <lb/>the expected mean squared error <lb/>β ⋆ = arg min <lb/>I⊂{1,...,p} <lb/>E β -βI <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 . <lb/>In other words, one would fit all least-squares models and rely on an oracle <lb/>to tell us which model to choose. This is ideal because we can of course not <lb/>evaluate E β -βI <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 since we do not know β (we are trying to estimate it <lb/>after all). But we can view this as a benchmark and ask whether any real <lb/>estimator would obey <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = O(log p) • E β -β ⋆ 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>(1.12) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>with large probability. <lb/>In some sense, (1.11) is a proxy for the ideal risk E β -β ⋆ 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 . Indeed, <lb/>let I be a fixed subset of indices and consider regressing y onto this subset <lb/>(we again denote by β I the restriction of β to the set I). The error of this <lb/>estimator is given by <lb/>βI -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = βI -β I <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 + β I -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 . <lb/>The first term is equal to <lb/>βI -β I = (X T <lb/>I X I ) -1 X T <lb/>I Xβ I c + (X T <lb/>I X I ) -1 X T <lb/>I z, <lb/>and its expected mean squared error is given by the formula <lb/>E βI -β I <lb/>2 = (X T <lb/>I X I ) -1 X T <lb/>I Xβ I c 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 + σ 2 Tr((X T <lb/>I X I ) -1 ). <lb/>Thus, this term obeys <lb/>E βI -β I <lb/>2 ≥ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 + δ |I| <lb/>• |I| • σ 2 <lb/>for the same reasons as before. In short, for all sets I, |I| ≤ S, with δ S &lt; 1, <lb/>say, <lb/>E βI -β 2 ≥ 1 <lb/>2 • <lb/>i∈I c <lb/>β 2 <lb/>i + |I| • σ 2 , <lb/>which gives that the ideal mean squared error is bounded below by <lb/>E β ⋆ -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≥ 1 <lb/>2 • min <lb/>I <lb/>i∈I c <lb/>β 2 <lb/>i + |I| • σ 2 = 1 <lb/>2 • <lb/>i <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ). <lb/>In that sense, the ideal risk is lower bounded by the proxy (1.12). As we <lb/>have seen, the proxy is meaningful since it has a natural interpretation in <lb/>terms of the ideal squared bias and variance, <lb/>i <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) = min <lb/>I⊂{1,...,p} <lb/>β -β I <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 + |I| • σ 2 . <lb/>This raises a fundamental question: given data y and the linear model (1.1), <lb/>not knowing anything about the significant coordinates of β and not being <lb/>able to observe directly the parameter values, can we design an estimator <lb/>which nearly achieves (1.12)? Our main result is that the Dantzig selector <lb/>(1.7) does just that. <lb/>Theorem 1.2. Choose t &gt; 0 and set λ p := (1 + t -1 ) <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p in (1.7). <lb/>Then if β is S-sparse with δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1 -t, our estimator obeys <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ C 2 <lb/>2 • λ 2 <lb/>p • σ 2 + <lb/>p <lb/>i=1 <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) <lb/>(1.13) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>with large probability [the probability is as before for λ p := ( <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + a + t -1 ) × <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p]. Here, C 2 may only depend on δ 2S and θ S,2S ; see below. <lb/>We emphasize that (1.13) is nonasymptotic and our analysis actually <lb/>yields explicit constants. For instance, we also prove that <lb/>C 2 = 2 <lb/>C 0 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>+ 2 <lb/>θ(1 + δ) <lb/>(1 -δ -θ) 2 + <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>and <lb/>C 0 := 2 <lb/>√ <lb/>2 1 + <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>+ (1 + 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>2) <lb/>(1 + δ) 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>, <lb/>(1.14) <lb/>where above and below, we put δ := δ 2S and θ := θ S,2S for convenience. For <lb/>δ and θ small, C 2 is close to <lb/>C 2 ≈ 2(4 <lb/>√ <lb/>2 + 1 + 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>2) + 1 ≤ 16. <lb/>The condition imposing δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1 (or less than 1 -t) has a rather natu-<lb/>ral interpretation in terms of model identifiability. Consider a rank deficient <lb/>submatrix X T ∪T ′ with 2S columns (lowest eigenvalue is 0 = 1 -δ 2S ), and <lb/>with indices in T and T ′ , each of size S. Then there is a vector h obeying <lb/>Xh = 0 and which can be decomposed as h = β -β ′ , where β is supported <lb/>on T and likewise for β ′ ; that is, <lb/>Xβ = Xβ ′ . <lb/>In short, this says that the model is not identifiable since both β and β ′ are <lb/>S-sparse. In other words, we need δ 2S &lt; 1. The requirement δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1 <lb/>(or less than 1 -t) is only slightly stronger than the identifiability condition, <lb/>roughly two times stronger. It puts a lower bound on the singular values <lb/>of submatrices and, in effect, prevents situations where multicollinearity <lb/>between competitive subsets of predictors could occur. <lb/>1.4. Ideal model selection by linear programming. Our estimation pro-<lb/>cedure is of course an implicit method for choosing a desirable subset of <lb/>predictors, based on the noisy data y = Xβ + z, from among all subsets of <lb/>variables. As the reader will see, there is nothing in our arguments that re-<lb/>quires p to be larger than n and, thus, the Dantzig selector can be construed <lb/>as a very general variable selection strategy-hence, the name. <lb/>There is of course a huge literature on model selection, and many pro-<lb/>cedures motivated by a wide array of criteria have been proposed over the <lb/>years-among which [1, 7, 26, 31, 36]. By and large, the most commonly dis-<lb/>cussed approach-the &quot;canonical selection procedure&quot; according to [26]-is <lb/>defined as <lb/>arg min <lb/>β∈R p <lb/>y -X β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 + Λ • σ 2 • β ℓ 0 , <lb/>β ℓ 0 := |{i : βi = 0}|, <lb/>(1.15) <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>which best trades-off between the goodness of fit and the complexity of the <lb/>model, the so-called bias and variance terms. Popular selection procedures <lb/>such as AIC, C p , BIC and RIC are all of this form with different values of <lb/>the parameter Λ; see also [2, 4, 5, 6, 7] for related proposals. To make a <lb/>long story short, model selection is an important area in part because of <lb/>the thousands of people routinely fitting large linear models or designing <lb/>statistical experiments. As such, it has and still receives a lot of attention, <lb/>and progress in this field is likely to have a large impact. Now despite the <lb/>size of the current literature, we believe there are two critical problems in <lb/>this field: <lb/>• First, finding the minimum of (1.15) is in general NP -hard [32]. To the <lb/>best of our knowledge, solving this problem essentially requires exhaustive <lb/>searches over all subsets of columns of X, a procedure which clearly is <lb/>combinatorial in nature and has exponential complexity since for p of size <lb/>about n, there are about 2 p such subsets. (We are of course aware that in <lb/>a few exceptional circumstances, e.g., when X is an orthonormal matrix, <lb/>the solution is computationally feasible and given by thresholding rules <lb/>[7, 21].) <lb/>In other words, solving the model selection problem might be possible <lb/>only when p ranges in the few dozens. This is especially problematic when <lb/>one considers that we now live in a &quot;data-driven&quot; era marked by ever larger <lb/>datasets. <lb/>• Second, estimating β and Xβ-especially when p is larger than n-are two <lb/>very different problems. Whereas there is an extensive literature about the <lb/>problem of estimating Xβ, the quantitative literature about the equally <lb/>important problem of estimating β in the modern setup where p is not <lb/>small compared to n is scarce; see [25]. For completeness, important and <lb/>beautiful results about the former problem (estimating Xβ) include the <lb/>papers [3, 4, 6, 7, 23, 26]. <lb/>In recent years, researchers have of course developed alternatives to overcome <lb/>these computational difficulties, and we would like to single out the popular <lb/>lasso also known as Basis Pursuit [15, 38], which relaxes the counting norm <lb/>β ℓ 0 into the convex ℓ 1 -norm β ℓ 1 . Notwithstanding the novel and exciting <lb/>work of [28] on the persistence of the lasso for variable selection in high <lb/>dimensions-which again is about estimating Xβ and not β-not much is <lb/>yet known about the performance of such strategies although they seem to <lb/>work well in practice; for example, see [35]. <lb/>Against this background, our work clearly marks a significant departure <lb/>from the current literature, both in terms of what it achieves and of its <lb/>methods. Indeed, our paper introduces a method for selecting variables based <lb/>on linear programming, and obtains decisive quantitative results in fairly <lb/>general settings. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>1.5. Extension to nearly sparse parameters. We have considered thus <lb/>far the estimation of sparse parameter vectors, that is, with a number S of <lb/>nonzero entries obeying δ 2S + θ S,2S . We already explained that this condi-<lb/>tion is in some sense necessary as otherwise one might have an &quot;aliasing&quot; <lb/>problem, a situation in which Xβ ≈ Xβ ′ , although β and β ′ might be com-<lb/>pletely different. However, extensions of our results to nonsparse objects are <lb/>possible provided that one imposes other types of constraints to remove the <lb/>possibility of strong aliasing. <lb/>Many such constraints may exist and we consider one of them which <lb/>imposes some decay condition on the entries of β. Rearrange the entries of <lb/>β by decreasing order of magnitude |β (1) | ≥ |β (2) | ≥ • • • ≥ |β (p) | and suppose <lb/>the kth largest entry obeys <lb/>|β (k) | ≤ R • k -1/s , <lb/>(1.16) <lb/>for some positive R and s ≤ 1, say. Can we show that our estimator achieves <lb/>an error close to the proxy (1.11)? The first observation is that, to mimic <lb/>this proxy, we need to be able to estimate reliably all the coordinates which <lb/>are significantly above the noise level, that is, roughly such that |β i | ≥ σ. <lb/>Let S = |{i : |β i | &gt; σ}|. Then if δ 2S + θ S,2S &lt; 1, this might be possible, but <lb/>otherwise, we may simply not have enough observations to estimate that <lb/>many coefficients. The second observation is that for β ∈ R p obeying (1.16), <lb/>i <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) = S • σ 2 + <lb/>i≥S+1 <lb/>|β (i) | 2 ≤ C • (S • σ 2 + R 2 S -2r ) <lb/>(1.17) <lb/>with r = 1/s -1/2. With this in mind, we have the following result. <lb/>Theorem 1.3. Suppose β ∈ R p obeys (1.16) and let S * be fixed such <lb/>that δ 2S * + θ S * ,2S * &lt; 1. Choose λ p as in Theorem 1.1. Then β obeys <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ min <lb/>1≤S≤S * C 3 • 2 log p • (S • σ 2 + R 2 S -2r ) <lb/>(1.18) <lb/>with large probability. <lb/>Note that for each β obeying (1.16), |{i : |β i | &gt; σ}| ≤ (R/σ) 1/s . Then if <lb/>S * ≥ (R/σ) 1/s , it is not hard to see that (1.18) becomes <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ O(log p) • R 2/(2r+1) • (σ 2 ) 2r/(2r+1) , <lb/>(1.19) <lb/>which is the well-known minimax rate for classes of objects exhibiting the <lb/>decay (1.16). Even though we have n ≪ p, the Dantzig selector recovers the <lb/>minimax rate that one would get if we were able to measure all the coordi-<lb/>nates of β directly via ỹ ∼ N (β, σ 2 I p ). In the case where S * ≤ (R/σ) 1/s , the <lb/>method saturates because we do not have enough data to recover the mini-<lb/>max rate, and can only guarantee a squared loss of about O(log p)(R 2 S -2r <lb/> * <lb/>+ <lb/>S * • σ 2 ). Note, however, that the error is well controlled. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>1.6. Variations and other extensions. When X is an orthogonal matrix, <lb/>the Dantzig selector β is then the ℓ 1 -minimizer subject to the constraint <lb/>X * y -β ℓ∞ ≤ λ p • σ. This implies that β is simply the soft-thresholded <lb/>version of X * y at level λ p • σ; thus, <lb/>βi = max(|(X * y) i | -λ p • σ, 0) sgn((X * y) i ). <lb/>In other words, X * y is shifted toward the origin. In Section 4 we will see <lb/>that for arbitrary X&apos;s the method continues to exhibit a soft-thresholding <lb/>type of behavior and as a result, may slightly underestimate the true value <lb/>of the nonzero parameters. <lb/>There are several simple methods which can correct for this bias and <lb/>increase performance in practical settings. We consider one of these based <lb/>on a two-stage procedure: <lb/>1. Estimate I = {i : β i = 0} with Î = {i : βi = 0} with β as in (1.7) (or, more <lb/>generally, with Î = {i : | βi | &gt; α • σ} for some α ≥ 0). <lb/>2. Construct the estimator <lb/>βÎ = (X T <lb/>Î X Î ) -1 X T <lb/>Î y, <lb/>(1.20) <lb/>and set the other coordinates to zero. <lb/>Hence, we rely on the Dantzig selector to estimate the model I, and construct <lb/>a new estimator by regressing the data y onto the model Î. We will refer <lb/>to this variation as the Gauss-Dantzig selector. As we will see in Section 4, <lb/>this recenters the estimate and generally yields higher statistical accuracy. <lb/>We anticipate that all our theorems hold with some such variations. <lb/>Although we prove our main results in the case where z is a vector of <lb/>i.i.d. Gaussian variables, our methods and results would certainly extend to <lb/>other noise distributions. The key is to constrain the residuals so that the <lb/>true vector β is feasible for the optimization problem. In details, this means <lb/>that we need to set λ p so that Z * = sup i | X i , z | is less than λ p σ with large <lb/>probability. When z ∼ N (0, σ 2 I n ), this is achieved for λ p = <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p, but one <lb/>could compute other thresholds for other types of zero-mean distributions <lb/>and derive results similar to those introduced in this paper. In general setups, <lb/>one would perhaps want to be more flexible and have thresholds depending <lb/>upon the column index. For example, one could declare that r is feasible if <lb/>sup i | X i , r |/λ i <lb/>p is below some fixed threshold. <lb/>1.7. Organization of the paper. The paper is organized as follows. We <lb/>begin by discussing the implications of this work for experimental design in <lb/>Section 2. We prove our main results, namely, Theorems 1.1, 1.2 and 1.3, <lb/>in Section 3. Section 4 introduces numerical experiments showing that our <lb/>approach is effective in practical applications. Finally, Section 5 closes the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>paper with a short summary of our findings and of their consequences for <lb/>model selection, and with a discussion of other related work in Section 5.2. <lb/>Finally, the Appendix provides proofs of key lemmas supporting the proof <lb/>of Theorem 1.2. <lb/>2. Significance for experimental design. Before we begin proving our <lb/>main results, we would like to explain why our method might be of interest <lb/>to anyone seeking to measure or sense a sparse high-dimensional vector us-<lb/>ing as few measurements as possible. In the noiseless case, our earlier results <lb/>showed that if β is S-sparse, then it can be reconstructed exactly from n <lb/>measurements y = Xβ, provided that δ + θ &lt; 1 [11, 13]. These were later <lb/>extended to include wider classes of objects, that is, the so called compress-<lb/>ible objects. Against this background, our results show that the Dantzig <lb/>selector is robust against measurement errors (no realistic measuring device <lb/>can provide infinite precision), thereby making it well suited for practical <lb/>applications. <lb/>2.1. Random matrices and designs. An interesting aspect of this theory <lb/>is that random matrices X are in some sense ideal for recovering an object <lb/>from a few projections. For example, if X is a properly normalized Gaussian <lb/>matrix with i.i.d. entries, then the conditions of our theorems hold with <lb/>S ≍ n/ log(p/n) <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>with overwhelming probability [13, 14, 18, 37]. The same relation is also <lb/>conjectured to be true for other types of random matrices such as normalized <lb/>binary arrays with i.i.d. entries taking values ±1 with probability 1/2. Other <lb/>interesting strategies for recovering a sparse signal in the time domain might <lb/>be to sense a comparatively small number of its Fourier coefficients. In fact, <lb/>[14] show that in this case our main condition holds with <lb/>S ≍ n/ log 6 p, <lb/>for nearly all subsets of observed coefficients of size n. Vershynin has in-<lb/>formed us that S ≍ n/ log 5 p also holds, and we believe that S ≍ n/ log p is <lb/>also true. More generally, suppose that X is obtained by randomly sampling <lb/>n rows of a p by p orthonormal matrix U (and renormalizing the columns <lb/>so that they are unit-normed). Then we can take <lb/>S ≍ n/[µ 2 log 5 p], <lb/>with µ the coherence µ := sup ij <lb/>√ <lb/>n|U ij | [14]. <lb/>Of course, all these calculations have implications for random designs. <lb/>For example, suppose that in an idealized application one could-in a first <lb/>experiment-observe β directly and measure y (1) ∼ N (β, σ 2 I p ). Consider <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>a second experiment where one measures instead y ∼ N (Xβ, σ 2 I n ), where <lb/>X is a renormalized random design matrix with i.i.d. entries taking values <lb/>±1 with probability 1/2. Suppose that the signal is S-sparse (note that <lb/>Xβ ℓ 2 ≍ β ℓ 2 ). Then reversing (2.1), we see that with about <lb/>n ≍ S • log(p/S) <lb/>observations, one would get just about the same mean squared error that one <lb/>would achieve by measuring all the coordinates of β directly (and applying <lb/>thresholding). <lb/>Such procedures are not foreign to statisticians. Combining parameters <lb/>by random design or otherwise goes back a long way; see, for example, the <lb/>long history of blood pooling strategies. The theoretical analysis needs of <lb/>course to be validated with numerical simulations, which may give further <lb/>insights about the practical behavior of our methods. Section 4 presents a <lb/>first series of experiments to complement our study. <lb/>2.2. Applications. The ability to recover a sparse or nearly sparse pa-<lb/>rameter vector from a few observations raises tantalizing opportunities and <lb/>we mention just a few to give concrete ideas: <lb/>1. Biomedical imaging. In the field of biomedical imaging, one is often only <lb/>able to collect far fewer measurements than the number of pixels. In mag-<lb/>netic resonance imaging (MRI), for instance, one would like to reconstruct <lb/>high-resolution images from heavily undersampled frequency data, as this <lb/>would allow image acquisition speeds far beyond those offered by current <lb/>technologies; for example, see [33] and [16]. If the image is sparse, as is <lb/>the case in magnetic resonance angiography (or if its gradient is sparse <lb/>or, more generally, if the image is sparse in a fixed basis [9]), then ℓ 1 -<lb/>minimization may have a chance to be very effective in such challenging <lb/>settings. <lb/>2. Analog to digital. By making a number n of general linear measurements <lb/>rather than measuring the usual pixels, one could, in principle, recon-<lb/>struct a compressible or sparse image with essentially the same resolu-<lb/>tion as one would obtain by measuring all the pixels. Now suppose one <lb/>could design analog sensors able to make measurements by correlating <lb/>the signal we wish to acquire against incoherent waveforms as discussed <lb/>in the previous sections. Then one would effectively be able to make up <lb/>a digital image with far fewer sensors than what is usually considered <lb/>necessary [14, 19]. <lb/>3. Sensor networks. There are promising applications in sensor networks <lb/>where taking random projections may yield the same distortion (the same <lb/>quality of reconstruction), but using much less power than what is tradi-<lb/>tionally required [29]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>3. Proof of theorems. We now prove Theorems 1.1, 1.2 and 1.3, and we <lb/>introduce some notation that we will use throughout this section. We let <lb/>X 1 , . . . , X p ∈ R n be the p columns of X (the exploratory variables) so that <lb/>Xβ = β 1 X 1 + • • • + β p X p and (X * y) j = y, X j , 1 ≤ j ≤ p. We recall that the <lb/>columns of X are normalized to have unit norm, that is, X j ℓ 2 = 1. <lb/>Note that it is sufficient to prove our theorems with σ = 1, as the general <lb/>case would follow from a simple rescaling argument. Therefore, we assume <lb/>σ = 1 from now on. Now a key observation is that, with large probability, <lb/>z ∼ N (0, I n ) obeys the orthogonality condition <lb/>| z, X j | ≤ λ p <lb/>for all 1 ≤ j ≤ p, <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>for λ p = <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p. This is standard and simply follows from the fact that, <lb/>for each j, Z j := z, X j ∼ N (0, 1). We will see that if (3.1) holds, then <lb/>(1.10) holds. Note that, for each u &gt; 0, P(sup j |Z j | &gt; u) ≤ 2p • φ(u)/u, where <lb/>φ(u) := (2π) -1/2 e -u 2 /2 , and our quantitative probabilistic statement just <lb/>follows from this bound. Better bounds are possible, but we will not pursue <lb/>these refinements here. As remarked earlier, if the columns were not unit <lb/>normed, one would obtain the same conclusion with λ p = <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ 1 • <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p <lb/>since X j ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ 1 . <lb/>3.1. High-dimensional geometry. It is probably best to start by intro-<lb/>ducing intuitive arguments underlying Theorems 1.1 and 1.2. These ideas <lb/>are very geometrical and we hope they will convey the gist of the proof. <lb/>Consider Theorem 1.1 first, and suppose that y = Xβ + z, where z obeys <lb/>the orthogonality condition (3.1) for some λ p . Let β be the minimizer of <lb/>(1.7). Clearly, the true vector of parameters β is feasible and, hence, <lb/>β ℓ 1 ≤ β ℓ 1 . <lb/>Decompose β as β = β + h and let T 0 be the support of β, T 0 = {i : β i = 0}. <lb/>Then h obeys two geometric constraints: <lb/>1. First, as essentially observed in [20], <lb/>β ℓ 1 -h T 0 ℓ 1 + h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ β + h ℓ 1 ≤ β ℓ 1 , <lb/>where again the ith component of the vector h T 0 is that of h if i ∈ T 0 and <lb/>zero otherwise (similarly for h T c <lb/>0 ). Hence, h obeys the cone constraint <lb/>h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ h T 0 ℓ 1 . <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>2. Second, since <lb/>z -r, X j = X β -Xβ, X j = Xh, X j , <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 1. This figure represents the geometry of the constraints. On the left, the shaded <lb/>area represents the set of h obeying both (3.2) (hourglass region) and (3.3) (slab region). <lb/>The right figure represents the situation in the more general case. <lb/>it follows from the triangle inequality that <lb/>X * Xh ℓ∞ ≤ 2λ p . <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>We will see that these two geometrical constraints imply that h is small in <lb/>the ℓ 2 -norm. In other words, we will show that <lb/>sup <lb/>h∈R p <lb/>h 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>subject to h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ h T 0 ℓ 1 and X * Xh ℓ∞ ≤ 2λ p <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>obeys the desired bound, that is, O(λ 2 <lb/>p • |T 0 |). This is illustrated in Fig-<lb/>ure 1(a). Hence, our statistical question is deeply connected with the geom-<lb/>etry of high-dimensional Banach spaces, and that of high-dimensional spaces <lb/>in general. <lb/>To think about the general case, consider the set of indices T 0 := {i : |β i | &gt; <lb/>σ} and let β T 0 be the vector equal to β on T 0 and zero outside, β = β T 0 + β T c <lb/>0 . <lb/>Suppose now that β T 0 were feasible. Then we would have β ℓ 1 ≤ β T 0 ℓ 1 ; <lb/>writing β = β T 0 + h, the same analysis as that of Theorem 1.1-and outlined <lb/>above-would give <lb/>β -β T 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = O(log p) • |T 0 | • σ 2 . <lb/>From β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ 2 β -β T 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 + 2 β -β T 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 , one would get <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = O(log p) • |T 0 | • σ 2 + 2 <lb/>i : |β i |&lt;σ <lb/>β 2 <lb/>i , <lb/>which is the content of (1.13). Unfortunately, while β T 0 may be feasible for <lb/>&quot;most&quot; S-sparse vectors β, it is not for some, and the argument is consid-<lb/>erably more involved. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.2. Proof of Theorem 1.1. <lb/>Lemma 3.1. Suppose T 0 is a set of cardinality S with δ + θ &lt; 1. For a <lb/>vector h ∈ R p , we let T 1 be the S largest positions of h outside of T 0 . Put <lb/>T 01 = T 0 ∪ T 1 . Then <lb/>h ℓ 2 (T 01 ) ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 Xh ℓ 2 + <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S 1/2 h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) <lb/>and <lb/>h 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ h 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 (T 01 ) + S -1 h 2 <lb/>ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) . <lb/>Proof. Consider the restricted transformation X T 01 : R T 01 → R n , X T 01 c := <lb/>j∈T 01 c j X j . Let V ⊂ R n be the span of {X j : j ∈ T 01 }. Then V is of course <lb/>the range of X T 01 and also the orthogonal complement of the kernel of X T <lb/>T 01 , <lb/>which says that R n is the orthogonal sum V ⊕ V ⊥ . Because δ &lt; 1, we know <lb/>that the operator X T 01 is a bijection from R T 01 to V , with singular values <lb/>between <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ and <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ. As a consequence, for any c ∈ ℓ 2 (T 01 ), we have <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ c ℓ 2 ≤ X T 01 c ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ c ℓ 2 . <lb/>Moreover, letting P V denote the orthogonal projection onto V , we have for <lb/>each w ∈ R n , X T <lb/>T 01 w = X T <lb/>T 01 P V w and it follows that <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ P V w ℓ 2 ≤ X T <lb/>T 01 w ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ P V w ℓ 2 . <lb/>(3.5) <lb/>We apply this to w := Xh and conclude, in particular, that <lb/>P V Xh ℓ 2 ≤ (1 -δ) -1/2 X T <lb/>T 01 Xh ℓ 2 . <lb/>(3.6) <lb/>The next step is to derive a lower bound on P V Xh. To do this, we begin by <lb/>dividing T c <lb/>0 into subsets of size S and enumerate T c <lb/>0 as n 1 , n 2 , . . . , n p-|T 0 | in <lb/>decreasing order of magnitude of h T c <lb/>0 . Set T j = {n ℓ , (j -1)S + 1 ≤ ℓ ≤ jS}. <lb/>That is, T 1 is as before and contains the indices of the S largest coefficients <lb/>of h T c <lb/>0 , T 2 contains the indices of the next S largest coefficients, and so on. <lb/>Decompose now P V Xh as <lb/>P V Xh = P V Xh T 01 + <lb/>j≥2 <lb/>P V Xh T j . <lb/>(3.7) <lb/>By definition, Xh T 01 ∈ V and P V Xh T 01 = Xh T 01 . Further, since P V is an <lb/>orthogonal projection onto the span of the X j &apos;s for j ∈ T 01 , P V Xh T j = <lb/>j∈T 01 c j X j for some coefficients c j , and the following identity holds: <lb/>P V Xh T j <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = P V Xh T j , Xh T j . <lb/>(3.8) <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>By restricted orthogonality followed by restricted isometry, this gives <lb/>P V Xh T j , Xh T j ≤ θ <lb/>j∈T 01 <lb/>|c j | 2 <lb/>1/2 <lb/>h T j ℓ 2 <lb/>≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>P V Xh T j ℓ 2 h T j ℓ 2 , <lb/>which upon combining with (3.8) gives <lb/>P V Xh T j ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>h T j ℓ 2 . <lb/>(3.9) <lb/>We then develop an upper bound on j≥2 h T j ℓ 2 as in [12]. By construction, <lb/>the magnitude of each component h T j+1 [i] of h T j+1 is less than the average <lb/>of the magnitudes of the components of h T j , <lb/>|h T j+1 [i]| ≤ h T j ℓ 1 /S. <lb/>Then h T j+1 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ h T j <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 1 /S and, therefore, <lb/>j≥2 <lb/>h T j ℓ 2 ≤ S -1/2 <lb/>j≥1 <lb/>h T j ℓ 1 = S -1/2 h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) . <lb/>(3.10) <lb/>To summarize, Xh T 01 obeys Xh T 01 ℓ 2 ≥ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ h T 01 ℓ 2 by restricted isom-<lb/>etry, and since j≥2 P V Xh T j ℓ 2 ≤ θ(1 -δ) -1/2 S -1/2 h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) , <lb/>P V Xh ℓ 2 ≥ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ h ℓ 2 (T 01 ) -<lb/>θ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>S -1/2 h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) . <lb/>Combining this with (3.6) proves the first part of the lemma. <lb/>It remains to argue the second part. Observe that the kth largest value <lb/>of h T c <lb/>0 obeys <lb/>|h T c <lb/>0 | (k) ≤ h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 /k <lb/>and, therefore, <lb/>h T c <lb/>01 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ h T c <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 1 <lb/>k≥S+1 <lb/>1/k 2 ≤ h T c <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>ℓ 1 /S, <lb/>which is what we needed to establish. The lemma is proven. <lb/>Theorem 1.1 is now an easy consequence of this lemma. Observe that on <lb/>the one hand, (3.2) gives <lb/>h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ h T 0 ℓ 1 ≤ S 1/2 h T 0 ℓ 2 , <lb/>while on the other hand, (3.3) gives <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 Xh ℓ 2 ≤ (2S) 1/2 • 2λ p , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>since each of the 2S coefficients of X T <lb/>T 01 Xh is at most 2λ p (3.3). In conclusion, <lb/>we apply Lemma 3.1 and obtain <lb/>h ℓ 2 (T 01 ) ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>• <lb/>√ <lb/>2S • 2λ p . <lb/>The theorem follows since h 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ 2 h 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 (T 01 ) . <lb/>3.3. Proof of Theorem 1.3. The argument underlying Theorem 1.3 is <lb/>almost the same as that of Theorem 1.1. We let T 0 be the set of the S largest <lb/>entries of β, and write β = β + h as before. If z obeys the orthogonality <lb/>condition (1.5), β is feasible and <lb/>β T 0 ℓ 1 -h T 0 ℓ 1 + h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 -β T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ β + h ℓ 1 ≤ β ℓ 1 , <lb/>which gives <lb/>h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 ≤ h T 0 ℓ 1 + 2 β T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 . <lb/>The presence of the extra term is the only difference in the argument. We <lb/>then conclude from Lemma 3.1 and (3.3) that <lb/>h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>C <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>• (λ p • S 1/2 + β T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 • S -1/2 ). <lb/>The second part of Lemma 3.1 gives h ℓ 2 ≤ 2 h ℓ 2 (T 01 ) + β T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 • S -1/2 . <lb/>Since for β obeying the decay condition (1.16), β T c <lb/>0 ℓ 1 • S -1/2 ≤ C • R • S -r , <lb/>with r = 1/s -1/2, we have established that, for all S ≤ S * , <lb/>h T c <lb/>0 ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>C <lb/>1 -δ S * -θ θ * ,2S * <lb/>• (λ p • S 1/2 + R • S -r ). <lb/>The theorem follows. <lb/>3.4. Proof of Theorem 1.2. We begin with an auxiliary lemma. <lb/>Lemma 3.2. For any vector β, we have <lb/>Xβ ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>1 + δ( β ℓ 2 + (2S) -1/2 β ℓ 1 ). <lb/>Proof. Let T 1 be the 2S largest positions of β, then T 2 be the next <lb/>largest, and so forth. Then <lb/>Xβ ℓ 2 ≤ Xβ T 1 ℓ 2 + <lb/>j≥2 <lb/>Xβ T j ℓ 2 . <lb/>From restricted isometry, we have <lb/>Xβ T 1 ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 1/2 β T 1 ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 1/2 β ℓ 2 <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>and <lb/>Xβ T j ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 1/2 β T j ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 1/2 (2S) -1/2 β T j-1 ℓ 1 . <lb/>The claim follows. <lb/>We now turn to the proof of Theorem 1.2. As usual, we let β be the ℓ 1 <lb/>minimizer subject to the constraints <lb/>X * (X β -y) ℓ∞ = sup <lb/>1≤j≤p <lb/>| X β -y, X j | ≤ (1 + t -1 )λ, <lb/>(3.11) <lb/>where λ := <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p for short. <lb/>Without loss of generality, we may order the β j &apos;s in decreasing order of <lb/>magnitude <lb/>|β 1 | ≥ |β 2 | ≥ • • • ≥ |β p |. <lb/>(3.12) <lb/>In particular, by the sparsity assumption on β, we know that <lb/>β j = 0 <lb/>for all j &gt; S. <lb/>(3.13) <lb/>In particular, we see that <lb/>j <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>j , λ 2 ) ≤ S • λ 2 . <lb/>Let S 0 be the smallest integer such that <lb/>j <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>j , λ 2 ) ≤ S 0 • λ 2 ; <lb/>(3.14) <lb/>thus, 0 ≤ S 0 ≤ S and <lb/>S 0 • λ 2 ≤ λ 2 + <lb/>j <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>j , λ 2 ). <lb/>(3.15) <lb/>Also, observe from (3.12) that <lb/>S 0 • λ 2 ≥ <lb/>S 0 +1 <lb/>j=1 <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>j , λ 2 ) ≥ (S 0 + 1) min(β 2 <lb/>S 0 +1 , λ 2 ) <lb/>and, hence, min(β 2 <lb/>S 0 +1 , λ 2 ) is strictly less than λ 2 . By (3.12), we conclude <lb/>that <lb/>β j &lt; λ <lb/>for all j &gt; S 0 . <lb/>(3.16) <lb/>Write β = β (1) + β (2) , where <lb/>β <lb/>(1) <lb/>j = β j • 1 1≤j≤S 0 , <lb/>β <lb/>(2) <lb/>j = β j • 1 j&gt;S 0 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Thus, β (1) is a hard-thresholded version of β, localized to the set <lb/>T 0 := {1, . . . , S 0 }. <lb/>By (3.16), β (2) is S-sparse with <lb/>β (2) 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = <lb/>j&gt;S 0 <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>j , λ 2 ) ≤ S 0 • λ 2 . <lb/>As we shall see in the next section, Corollary A.3 allows the decomposition <lb/>β (2) = β ′ + β ′′ , where <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ • S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 , <lb/>(3.17) <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ • S 0 <lb/>(3.18) <lb/>and <lb/>X * Xβ ′′ <lb/>ℓ∞ &lt; <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ. <lb/>(3.19) <lb/>We use this decomposition and observe that <lb/>X * (X(β (1) + β ′ ) -y) = -X * Xβ ′′ -X * z <lb/>and, hence, by (3.1) and (3.19), <lb/>X * (X(β (1) + β ′ ) -y) ℓ∞ ≤ 1 + <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ. <lb/>(3.20) <lb/>By assumption, (1 -δ -θ) -1 ≤ t -1 and, therefore, β (1) + β ′ is feasible, which <lb/>in turn implies <lb/>β ℓ 1 ≤ β (1) + β ′ <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ β (1) <lb/>ℓ 1 + <lb/>(1 + δ) <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S 0 • λ. <lb/>Put β = β (1) + h. Then β ℓ 1 ≥ β (1) ℓ 1 -h ℓ 1 (T 0 ) + h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) so that <lb/>h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) ≤ h ℓ 1 (T 0 ) + <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S 0 • λ, <lb/>(3.21) <lb/>and from (3.11) and (3.20), we conclude that <lb/>X * X(β ′ -h) ℓ∞ ≤ 2 1 + <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ. <lb/>(3.22) <lb/>Figure 1(b) schematically illustrates both these constraints. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>The rest of the proof is essentially the same as that of Theorem 1.1. By <lb/>Lemma 3.1, we have <lb/>h 01 ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 Xh ℓ 2 + <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) . <lb/>On the other hand, from (3.22), we have <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 X(β ′ -h) ℓ 2 ≤ 2 <lb/>√ <lb/>2 1 + <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ, <lb/>while from Lemma 3.2 and (3.18), (3.17), we have <lb/>Xβ ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>2) <lb/>(1 + δ) 3/2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ <lb/>and, hence, by restricted isometry, <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 Xβ ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>2) <lb/>(1 + δ) 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ. <lb/>In short, <lb/>X T <lb/>T 01 Xh ℓ 2 ≤ C 0 • S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ, <lb/>where C 0 was defined in (1.14). We conclude that <lb/>h 01 ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>C 0 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ + <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) . <lb/>Finally, the bound (3.21) gives <lb/>h ℓ 1 (T c <lb/>0 ) ≤ S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>h 01 ℓ 2 + <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S 0 • λ <lb/>and, hence, <lb/>h 01 ℓ 2 ≤ C ′ <lb/>0 • S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ, <lb/>where <lb/>C ′ <lb/>0 := <lb/>C 0 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>+ <lb/>θ(1 + δ) <lb/>(1 -δ -θ) 2 . <lb/>Applying the second part of Lemma 3.1 and (3.21), we conclude <lb/>h ℓ 2 ≤ 2 h 01 ℓ 2 + <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ ≤ C 2 • S <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 • λ <lb/>and the claim follows from (3.15). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.5. Refinements. The constant C 2 obtained by this argument is not <lb/>best possible; it is possible to lower it further, but at the cost of making <lb/>the arguments slightly more complicated. For instance, in Lemma 3.2 one <lb/>can exploit the approximate orthogonality between Xβ T 1 and the Xβ T j &apos;s <lb/>to improve over the triangle inequality. Also, instead of defining T 1 , T 2 , . . . <lb/>to have cardinality S, one can instead choose these sets to have cardi-<lb/>nality ρS for some parameter ρ to optimize in later. We will not pur-<lb/>sue these refinements here. However, we observe that in the limiting case <lb/>δ = θ = 0, then X is an orthogonal matrix, and as we have seen earlier, <lb/>βj = max(|(X * y) j | -λ, 0) sgn((X * y) j ). In this case one easily verifies that <lb/>β -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>p <lb/>i=1 <lb/>min(β 2 <lb/>i , 4λ 2 ). <lb/>This would correspond, roughly speaking, to a value of C 2 = 2 in Theorem <lb/>1.2, and therefore shows that there is room to improve C 2 by a factor of <lb/>roughly 8. <lb/>4. Numerical experiments. This section presents numerical experiments <lb/>to illustrate the Dantzig selector and gives some insights about the numerical <lb/>method for solving (1.9). <lb/>4.1. An illustrative example. In this first example, the design matrix X <lb/>has n = 72 rows and p = 256 columns, with independent Gaussian entries <lb/>(and then normalized so that the columns have unit norm). We then select <lb/>β with S := |{i : β i = 0}| = 8 and form y = Xβ + z, where the z i &apos;s are i.i.d. <lb/>N (0, σ 2 ). The noise level is adjusted so that <lb/>σ = <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>S <lb/>n <lb/>. <lb/>Here and below, the regularizing parameter λ p in (DS) is chosen via Monte <lb/>Carlo simulations, that is, as the empirical maximum of |X * z| i over several <lb/>realizations of z ∼ N (0, I n ). The results are presented in Figure 2. <lb/>First, we note that in this example our procedure correctly identifies all <lb/>the nonzero components of β, and correctly sets to zero all the others. Quan-<lb/>titatively speaking, the ratio ρ 2 between the squared error loss and the ideal <lb/>squared error (1.11) is equal to <lb/>ρ 2 := <lb/>i ( βi -β i ) 2 <lb/>i min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) <lb/>= 10.28. <lb/>(4.1) <lb/>(Note that here 2 log p = 11.09.) Second, and as essentially observed earlier, <lb/>the method clearly exhibits a soft-thresholding type of behavior and as a <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 2. Estimation from y = Xβ + z with X a 72 by 256 matrix with independent Gaus-<lb/>sian entries. A blue star indicates the true value of the parameter and a red circle the <lb/>estimate. In this example, σ = 0.11 and λ = 3.5 so that the threshold is at δ = λ • σ = 0.39. <lb/>(a) Dantzig selector (1.7). Note that our procedure correctly identifies all the nonzero com-<lb/>ponents of β, and correctly sets to zero all the others. Observe the soft-thresholding-like <lb/>behavior. (b) Estimation based on the two-stage strategy (1.20). The signal and estimator <lb/>are very sparse, which is why there is a solid red line at zero. <lb/>result, tends to underestimate the true value of the nonzero parameters. <lb/>However, the two-stage Dantzig selector (1.20) introduced in Section 1.6 <lb/>corrects for this bias. When applied to the same dataset, it recenters the es-<lb/>timator, and yields an improved squared error since now ρ 2 = 1.14; compare <lb/>the results of Figures 2(a) and 2(b). <lb/>In our practical experience, the two-stage or Gauss-Dantzig selector pro-<lb/>cedure tends to outperform our original proposal, and to study its typical <lb/>quantitative performance, we performed a series of experiments designed as <lb/>follows: <lb/>1. X is a 72 by 256 matrix, sampled as before (X is fixed throughout); <lb/>2. select a support set T of size |T | = S uniformly at random, and sample <lb/>a vector β on T with independent and identically distributed entries <lb/>according to the model <lb/>β i = ε i (1 + |a i |), <lb/>where the sign ε i = ±1 with probability 1/2, and a i ∼ N (0, 1) (the moduli <lb/>and the signs of the amplitudes are independent); <lb/>3. make ỹ = Xβ + z, with z ∼ N (0, σ 2 I n ) and compute β by means of the <lb/>two-stage procedure (1.20); <lb/>4. repeat 500 times for each S, and for different noise levels σ. <lb/>The results are presented in Figure 3 and show that our approach works <lb/>well. With the squared ratio ρ 2 as in (4.1), the median and the mean of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. Statistics of the ratio between the squared error <lb/>i ( βi -βi) 2 and the ideal <lb/>mean-squared error <lb/>i min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ). (a) S = 8, σ = 1/3 S/n = 0.11, and the threshold <lb/>is here λ • σ = 0.5814. (b) S = 8, σ = S/n = 0.33, and the threshold is now λ • σ = 1.73. <lb/>ρ 2 are 2.35 and 9.42, respectively, for a noise level σ set at 1/3 S/n. In <lb/>addition, 75% of the time ρ 2 is less than 10. With σ = S/n, the mean and <lb/>median are 12.38 and 13.78, respectively, with a bell-shaped distribution. <lb/>The reader may wonder why the two histograms in Figure 3 look some-<lb/>what different. The answer is simply due to the fact that in Figure 3(a) <lb/>σ = 0.11 and the threshold is about λ • σ = 0.5814, which means that the <lb/>nonzero β i &apos;s are above the noise level. In Figure 3(b), however, σ = 0.33, <lb/>and the threshold is λ • σ = 1.73. This means that a fraction of the nonzero <lb/>components of β are within the noise level and will be set to zero. This <lb/>explains the observed difference in the quantitative behavior. <lb/>4.2. Binary design matrices. We now consider the case where the design <lb/>matrix has i.i.d. entries taking on values ±1, each with probability 1/2 (the <lb/>entries are then divided by <lb/>√ n so that the columns have unit norm). This <lb/>simply amounts to measuring differences among randomly selected subsets <lb/>of coordinates. Note that if X had 0/1 entries, one would measure the aggre-<lb/>gate effect of randomly selected subsets of coordinates, much like in pooling <lb/>design schemes. The number of predictors is set to p = 5,000 and the num-<lb/>ber of observations to n = 1,000. Of interest here is the estimation accuracy <lb/>as the number S of significant parameters increases. The results are pre-<lb/>sented in Table 1. In all these experiments, the nonzero coordinates of the <lb/>parameter vector are sampled as in Section 4.1 and the noise level is ad-<lb/>justed to σ = 1/3 S/n, so that with y = Xβ + z, the variance E z 2 = nσ 2 <lb/>is proportional to E β 2 with the same constant of proportionality (fixed <lb/>signal-to-noise ratio). <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Ratio between the squared error <lb/>i ( βi -βi) 2 and the ideal mean squared error <lb/>i min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ). The binary matrix X is the same in all these experiments, and the noise <lb/>level σ = 1/3 S/n is adjusted so that the signal-to-noise ratio is nearly constant. Both <lb/>estimators and especially the Gauss-Dantzig selector exhibit a remarkable performance <lb/>until a breakdown point around S = 200 <lb/>S <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>Dantzig selector <lb/>22.81 <lb/>17.30 <lb/>28.85 <lb/>18.49 <lb/>25.71 <lb/>49.73 <lb/>74.93 <lb/>Gauss-Dantzig selector <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>1.53 <lb/>13.71 <lb/>48.74 <lb/>Our estimation procedures and most notably the Gauss-Dantzig selector <lb/>are remarkably accurate as long as the number of significant parameters <lb/>is not too large, here about S = 200. For example, for S = 100, the ratio <lb/>between the Gauss-Dantzig selector&apos;s squared error loss and the ideal mean-<lb/>squared error is only 1.53. Figure 4 illustrates the estimation precision in <lb/>this case. <lb/>To confirm these findings, we now sample the amplitudes of the parameter <lb/>vector β according to a Cauchy distribution in order to have a wide range <lb/>of component values β i , some of which are within the noise level, while <lb/>others are way above; X is fixed and we now vary the number S of nonzero <lb/>components of β as before, while σ = 0.5 is now held constant. The results <lb/>are presented in Table 2. Again, the Gauss-Dantzig selector performs well. <lb/>Fig. 4. Estimation from y = Xβ + z with X a 1,000 by 5,000 matrix with independent <lb/>binary entries. A blue star indicates the true value of the parameter and a red circle <lb/>the estimate. (a) True parameter values and estimates obtained via the Dantzig selector <lb/>(1.20). There are S = 100 significant parameters. (b) Same plot but showing the first 500 <lb/>coordinates for higher visibility. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 <lb/>Ratio between the squared error <lb/>i ( βi -βi) 2 and the ideal mean squared error <lb/>i min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ). The binary matrix X, σ = 0.5 and λ • σ = 2.09 are the same in all these <lb/>experiments <lb/>S <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>Gauss-Dantzig selector <lb/>3.70 <lb/>4.52 <lb/>2.78 <lb/>3.52 <lb/>4.09 <lb/>6.56 <lb/>5.11 <lb/>4.3. Examples in signal processing. We are interested in recovering a <lb/>one-dimensional signal f ∈ R p from noisy and undersampled Fourier coeffi-<lb/>cients of the form <lb/>y j = f, φ j + z j , <lb/>1 ≤ j ≤ n, <lb/>where φ j (t), t = 0, . . . , p-1, is a sinusoidal waveform φ j (t) = 2/n cos(π(k j + <lb/>1/2)(t + 1/2)), k j ∈ {0, 1, . . . , p -1}. Consider the signal f in Figure 5; f is <lb/>not sparse, but its wavelet coefficients sequence β is. Consequently, we may <lb/>just as well estimate its coefficients in a nice wavelet basis. Letting Φ be <lb/>the matrix with the φ k &apos;s as rows, and W be the orthogonal wavelet matrix <lb/>with wavelets as columns, we have y = Xβ + z, where X = ΦW , and our <lb/>estimation procedure applies as is. <lb/>The test signal is of size p = 4,096 (Figure 5), and we sample a set of <lb/>frequencies of size n = 512 by extracting the lowest 128 frequencies and ran-<lb/>domly selecting the others. With this set of observations, the goal is to study <lb/>the quantitative behavior of the Gauss-Dantzig selector procedure for var-<lb/>ious noise levels. [Owing to the factor 2/n in the definition of φ j (t), the <lb/>columns of X have size about one and for each column, individual thresholds <lb/>Fig. 5. (a) One-dimensional signal f we wish to reconstruct. (b) First 512 wavelet co-<lb/>efficients of f . <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 3 <lb/>Performance of the Gauss-Dantzig procedure in estimating a signal from undersampled <lb/>and noisy Fourier coefficients. The subset of variables is here estimated by | βi| &gt; σ/4, <lb/>with β as in (1.7). The top row is the value of the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) <lb/>SNR α = X β / <lb/>√ <lb/>nσ 2 <lb/>100 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>i ( βi -βi) 2 / i min(β 2 <lb/>i , σ 2 ) <lb/>15.51 <lb/>2.08 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>0.91 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>λ i -|(X * r) i | ≤ λ i • σ-are determined by looking at the empirical distribu-<lb/>tion of |(X * z) i |.] We adjust σ so that α 2 = Xβ 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 /E z 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 = Xβ 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 /nσ 2 <lb/>for various levels of the signal-to-noise ratio α. We use Daubechies&apos; wavelets <lb/>with four vanishing moments for the reconstruction. The results are pre-<lb/>sented in Table 3. As one can see, high statistical accuracy holds over a <lb/>wide range of noise levels. Interestingly, the estimator is less accurate when <lb/>the noise level is very small (α = 100), which is not surprising, since in this <lb/>case there are 178 wavelet coefficients exceeding σ in absolute value. <lb/>In our last example, we consider the problem of reconstructing an image <lb/>from undersampled Fourier coefficients. Here β(t 1 , t 2 ), 0 ≤ t 1 , t 2 &lt; N , is an <lb/>unknown N by N image so that p is the number of unknown pixels, p = N 2 . <lb/>As usual, the data is given by y = Xβ + z, where <lb/>(Xβ) k = <lb/>t 1 ,t 2 <lb/>β(t 1 , t 2 ) cos(2π(k 1 t 1 + k 2 t 2 )/N ), <lb/>k = (k 1 , k 2 ), <lb/>(4.2) <lb/>or (Xβ) k = t 1 ,t 2 β(t 1 , t 2 ) sin(2π(k 1 t 1 + k 2 t 2 )/N ). In our example [see Fig-<lb/>ure 6(b)], the image β is not sparse, but the gradient is. Therefore, to re-<lb/>construct the image, we apply our estimation strategy and minimize the <lb/>ℓ 1 -norm of the gradient size, also known as the total-variation of β, <lb/>min β TV subject to |(X * r) i | ≤ λ i • σ <lb/>(4.3) <lb/>(the individual thresholds again depend on the column sizes as before); for-<lb/>mally, the total-variation norm is of the form <lb/>β TV = <lb/>t 1 ,t 2 <lb/>|D 1 β(t 1 , t 2 )| 2 + |D 2 β(t 1 , t 2 )| 2 , <lb/>where D 1 is the finite difference D 1 β = β(t 1 , t 2 ) -β(t 1 -1, t 2 ) and D 2 β = <lb/>β(t 1 , t 2 ) -β(t 1 , t 2 -1); in short, β BV is the ℓ 1 -norm of the size of the <lb/>gradient D β = (D 1 β, D 2 β); see also [34]. <lb/>Our example follows the data acquisition patterns of many real imaging <lb/>devices which can collect high-resolution samples along radial lines at rel-<lb/>atively few angles. Figure 6(a) illustrates a typical case where one gathers <lb/>N = 256 samples along each of 22 radial lines. In a first experiment then, <lb/>we observe 22 × 256 noisy real-valued Fourier coefficients and use (4.3) for <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 6. (a) Sampling &quot;domain&quot; in the frequency plane; Fourier coefficients are sampled <lb/>along 22 approximately radial lines; here, n ≈ 0.086p. (b) The Logan-Shepp phantom test <lb/>image. (c) Minimum energy reconstruction obtained by setting unobserved Fourier coeffi-<lb/>cients to zero. (d) Reconstruction obtained by minimizing the total-variation, as in (4.3). <lb/>the recovery problem illustrated in Figure 6. The number of observations is <lb/>then n = 5,632, whereas there are p = 65,536 observations. In other words, <lb/>about 91.5% of the 2D Fourier coefficients of β are missing. The SNR in <lb/>this experiment is equal to Xβ ℓ 2 / z ℓ 2 = 5.85. Figure 6(c) shows the re-<lb/>construction obtained by setting the unobserved Fourier coefficients to zero, <lb/>while (d) shows the reconstruction (4.3). We follow up with a second exper-<lb/>iment where the unknown image is now 512 by so that p = 262,144 and <lb/>n = 22 × 512 = 11,264. The fraction of missing Fourier coefficients is now <lb/>approaching 96%. The SNR ratio is about the same, Xβ ℓ 2 / z ℓ 2 = 5.77. <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 6. Continued. (e) Magnitude of the true Fourier coefficients along a radial line <lb/>(frequency increases from left to right) on a logarithmic scale. Blue stars indicate values <lb/>of log(1 + |(Xβ) k |), while the solid red line indicates the noise level log(1 + σ). Less than <lb/>a third of the frequency samples exceed the noise level. (f) X * z and β are plotted along a <lb/>scanline to convey a sense of the noise level. <lb/>The reconstructions are of very good quality, especially when compared to <lb/>the naive reconstruction which minimizes the energy of the reconstruction <lb/>subject to matching the observed data. Figure 7 also shows the middle hori-<lb/>zontal scanline of the phantom. As expected, we note a slight loss of contrast <lb/>due to the nature of the estimator which here operates by &quot;soft-thresholding&quot; <lb/>the gradient. There are, of course, ways of correcting for this bias, but such <lb/>issues are beyond the scope of this paper. <lb/>4.4. Implementation. In all the experiments above, we used a primal-<lb/>dual interior point algorithm for solving the linear program (1.9). We used <lb/>a specific implementation which we outline, as this gives some insight about <lb/>the computational workload of our method. For a general linear program <lb/>with inequality constraints <lb/>min c * β subject to <lb/>F β ≤ b, <lb/>define <lb/>• f (β) = Xβ -b, <lb/>• r dual = c + X * λ, <lb/>• r cent = -diag(λ)f (β) -1/t, <lb/>where λ ∈ R m are the so-called dual variables, and t is a parameter whose <lb/>value typically increases geometrically at each iteration; there are as many <lb/>dual variables as inequality constraints. In a standard primal-dual method <lb/>(with logarithmic barrier function) [8], one updates the current primal-dual <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 7. (a) and (b). Similar experience as in Figure 6 but at a higher resolution <lb/>(p = 512 2 ) so that now n ≈ 0.043p. (c) and (d). Scanlines of both reconstructions. <lb/>pair (β, λ) by means of a Newton step, and solves <lb/>0 <lb/>F * <lb/>-diag(λ)F -diag(f (β)) <lb/>∆β <lb/>∆λ <lb/>= -<lb/>r dual <lb/>r cent <lb/>; <lb/>that is, <lb/>∆λ = -diag(1/f (β))(diag(λ)F ∆ β -r cent ), <lb/>-[F * diag(λ/f (β))F ]∆β = -(r dual + F * diag(1/f (β))r cent ). <lb/>The current guess is then updated via (β + , λ + ) = (β, λ) + s(∆β, ∆s), where <lb/>the stepsize s is determined by line search or otherwise. Typically, the se-<lb/>quence of iterations stops once the primal-dual gap and the size of the resid-<lb/>ual vector fall below a specified tolerance level [8]. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Letting U = X * X and ỹ = X * y in (1.9), our problem parameters have the <lb/>block structure <lb/>F = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>I <lb/>-I <lb/>-I -I <lb/>U <lb/>0 <lb/>-U <lb/>0 <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/>b = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>δ + <lb/>ỹ <lb/>δ -<lb/>ỹ  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/>c = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>which gives <lb/>F * diag(λ/f )F = <lb/>D 1 + D 2 + U * (D 3 + D 4 )U D 2 -D 1 <lb/>D 2 -D 1 <lb/>D 1 + D 2 <lb/>, <lb/>where D i = diag(λ i /f i ), 1 ≤ i ≤ 4, and <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>f 1 <lb/>f 2 <lb/>f 3 <lb/>f 4 <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>β -u <lb/>-β -u <lb/>U β -δ -<lb/>ỹ <lb/>-U β -δ + <lb/>ỹ  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/>Put r 1 <lb/>r 2 = r dual + F * diag(1/f (β))r cent . It is convenient to solve the system <lb/>F * diag(λ/f )F <lb/>∆ <lb/>β <lb/>∆u <lb/>= <lb/>r 1 <lb/>r 2 <lb/>by elimination and obtain <lb/>(4(D 1 + D 2 ) -1 D 1 D 2 + U * (D 3 + D 4 )U )∆ β = r 1 -(D 1 + D 2 ) -1 (D 1 -D 2 )r 2 , <lb/>(D 1 + D 2 )∆u = r 2 -(D 2 -D 1 )∆ β. <lb/>In other words, each step may involve solving a p by p system of linear <lb/>equations. In fact, when n is less than p, it is possible to solve a smaller <lb/>system thanks to the Sherman-Woodbury-Morrison formula. Indeed, write <lb/>U * (D 3 + D 4 )U = X * B, where B = X(D 3 + D 4 )X * X and put D 12 = 4(D 1 + <lb/>D 2 ) -1 D 1 D 2 . Then <lb/>(D 12 + X T B) -1 = D -1 <lb/>12 -D -1 <lb/>12 X * (I + BD -1 <lb/>12 X * ) -1 BD -1 <lb/>12 . <lb/>The advantage is that one needs to solve the smaller n by n system (I + <lb/>BD -1 <lb/>12 X * )β ′ = b ′ . Hence, the cost of each Newton iteration is essentially <lb/>that of solving an n by n system of linear equations, plus that of forming <lb/>the matrix (I + BD -1 <lb/>12 X * ). As far as the number of Newton iterations is <lb/>concerned, we ran thousands of experiments and have never needed more <lb/>than 45 Newton iterations for convergence. <lb/>Note that in some important applications, we may have fast algorithms for <lb/>applying X and X * to an arbitrary vector, as in the situation where X is a <lb/>partial Fourier matrix, since one can make use of FFT&apos;s. In such settings, one <lb/>never forms X * X and uses iterative algorithms such as Conjugate Gradients <lb/>for solving such linear systems; of course, this speeds up the computations. <lb/>Finally, a collection of MATLAB routines solving (1.9) for reproducing <lb/>some of these experiments and testing these ideas in other setups is available <lb/>at the address www.l1-magic.org/. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. Discussion. <lb/>5.1. Significance for model selection. We would like to briefly discuss <lb/>the implications of this work for model selection. Given a data matrix X <lb/>(with unit-normed columns) and observations y = Xβ + z, our procedure <lb/>will estimate β by that vector with minimum ℓ 1 -norm among all objects <lb/>β <lb/>obeying <lb/>|X * r| i ≤ (1 + t -1 ) 2 log p • σ, <lb/>where r = y -X β. <lb/>(5.1) <lb/>As the theory and the numerical experiments suggest, many of the coor-<lb/>dinates βi will typically be zero (at least under the assumption that the <lb/>true unknown vector β is sparse) and, therefore, our estimation procedure <lb/>effectively returns a candidate model Î := {i : βi = 0}. <lb/>As we have seen, the Dantzig selector is guaranteed to produce optimal <lb/>results if <lb/>δ(X) 2S + θ(X) S,2S &lt; 1 <lb/>(5.2) <lb/>[note that since θ(X) S,2S ≤ δ(X) 3S , it would be sufficient to have δ(X) 2S + <lb/>δ(X) 3S &lt; 1]. We have commented on the interpretation of this condition <lb/>already. In a typical model selection problem, X is given; it is then natural <lb/>to ask if this particular X obeys (5.2) for the assumed level S of sparsity. <lb/>Unfortunately, obtaining an answer to this question might be computation-<lb/>ally prohibitive, as it may require checking the extremal singular values of <lb/>exponentially many submatrices. <lb/>While this may represent a limitation, two observations are in order. First, <lb/>there are empirical evidence and theoretical analysis suggesting approximate <lb/>answers for certain types of random matrices, and there is nowadays a sig-<lb/>nificant amount of activity developing tools to address these questions [17]. <lb/>Second, the failure of (5.2) to hold is in general indicative of a structural <lb/>difficulty of the problem, so that any procedure is likely to be unsuccessful <lb/>for sparsity levels in the range of the critical one. To illustrate this point, <lb/>let us consider the following example. Suppose that δ 2S + θ S,2S &gt; 1. Then <lb/>this says that δ 2S is large and since δ S is increasing in S, it may very well <lb/>be that for S ′ in the range of S, for example, S ′ = 3S, there might be <lb/>submatrices (in fact, possibly many submatrices) with S ′ columns which <lb/>are either rank-deficient or which have very small singular values. In other <lb/>words, the significant entries of the parameter vector might be arranged in <lb/>such a way so that even if one knew their location, one would not be able <lb/>to estimate their values because of rank-deficiency. This informally suggests <lb/>that the Dantzig selector breaks down near the point where any estimation <lb/>procedure, no matter how intractable, would fail. <lb/>Finally, it is worth emphasizing the connections between RIC [26] and <lb/>(1.7). Both methods suggest a penalization which is proportional to the <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>logarithm of the number of explanatory variables-a penalty that is well <lb/>justified theoretically [7]. For example, in the very special case where X is <lb/>orthonormal, p = n, RIC applies a hard-thresholding rule to the vector X * y <lb/>at about O( <lb/>√ <lb/>2 log p), while our procedure translates in a soft-thresholding <lb/>at about the same level; in our convex formulation (1.7), this threshold level <lb/>is required to make sure that the true vector is feasible. In addition, the <lb/>ideas developed in this paper have broad applicability, and it is likely that <lb/>they might be deployed and give similar bounds for RIC variable selection. <lb/>Despite such possible similarities, our method differs substantially from RIC <lb/>in terms of computational effort since (1.7) is tractable while RIC is not. In <lb/>fact, we are not aware of any work in the model selection literature which is <lb/>close in intent and in the results. <lb/>5.2. Connections with other work. In [10] a related problem is studied <lb/>where the goal is to recover a vector β from incomplete and contaminated <lb/>measurements y = Xβ + e, where the error vector (stochastic or determin-<lb/>istic) obeys e 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ D. There, the proposed reconstruction searches, among <lb/>all objects consistent with the data y, for that with minimum ℓ 1 -norm, <lb/>(P 2 ) <lb/>min β ℓ 1 subject to <lb/>y -X β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ D. <lb/>(5.3) <lb/>Under essentially the same conditions as those of Theorems 1.1 and 1.2, <lb/>[10] showed that the reconstruction error is bounded by <lb/>β ♯ -β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ C 2 <lb/>3 • D. <lb/>(5.4) <lb/>In addition, it is also argued that, for arbitrary errors, the bound (5.4) is <lb/>sharp and that, in general, one cannot hope for a better accuracy. <lb/>If one assumes that the error is stochastic as in this paper, however, a <lb/>mean squared error of about D might be far from optimal. Indeed, with <lb/>the linear model (1.1), D ∼ σ 2 χ n and, therefore, D has size about nσ 2 . But <lb/>suppose now β is sparse and has only three nonzero coordinates, say, all <lb/>exceeding the noise level. Then whereas Theorem 1.1 gives a loss of about <lb/>3σ 2 (up to a log factor), (5.4) only guarantees an error of size about nσ 2 . <lb/>What is missing in [10] and is achieved here is the adaptivity to the unknown <lb/>level of sparsity of the object we try to recover. Note that we do not claim <lb/>that the program (P 2 ) is ill-suited for adaptivity. It is possible that refined <lb/>arguments would yield estimators based on quadratically constrained ℓ 1 -<lb/>minimization [variations of (5.3)] obeying the special adaptivity properties <lb/>discussed in this paper. <lb/>Last but not least, and while working on this manuscript, we became <lb/>aware of related work [29]. Motivated by recent results [11, 14, 18], the au-<lb/>thors studied the problem of reconstructing a signal from noisy random pro-<lb/>jections and obtained powerful quantitative estimates which resemble ours. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Their setup is different though, since they exclusively work with random <lb/>design matrices, in fact, random Rademacher projections, and do not study <lb/>the case of fixed X&apos;s. In contrast, our model for X is deterministic and does <lb/>not involve any kind of randomization, although our results can of course <lb/>be specialized to random matrices. But more importantly, and perhaps this <lb/>is the main difference, their estimation procedure requires solving a combi-<lb/>natorial problem much like (1.15), whereas we use linear programming. <lb/>APPENDIX <lb/>This appendix justifies the construction of a pseudo-hard thresholded vec-<lb/>tor which obeys the constraints; see (3.17), (3.18) and (3.19) in the proof of <lb/>Theorem 1.2. <lb/>Lemma A.1 (Dual sparse reconstruction, ℓ 2 version). Let S s.t. δ + θ &lt; <lb/>1, and let c T be supported on T for some |T | ≤ 2S. Then there exist β <lb/>supported on T , and an exceptional set E disjoint from T with <lb/>|E| ≤ S, <lb/>(6.1) <lb/>such that <lb/>Xβ, X j = c j <lb/>for all j ∈ T <lb/>(6.2) <lb/>and <lb/>| Xβ, X j | ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ) <lb/>√ <lb/>S <lb/>c T ℓ 2 <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ (T ∪ E) <lb/>(6.3) <lb/>and <lb/>j∈E <lb/>| Xβ, X j | 2 <lb/>1/2 <lb/>≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 . <lb/>(6.4) <lb/>Also we have <lb/>β ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 <lb/>(6.5) <lb/>and <lb/>β ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>2S <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 . <lb/>(6.6) <lb/>Proof. We define β by <lb/>β T := (X T <lb/>T X T ) -1 c T , <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>and zero outside of T , which gives (6.2), (6.5) and (6.6) by Cauchy-Schwarz. <lb/>Note that Xβ = X T β T . We then set <lb/>E := j / <lb/>∈ T : | Xβ, X j | &gt; <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ) <lb/>√ <lb/>S <lb/>c T ℓ 2 , <lb/>so (6.3) holds. <lb/>Now if T ′ is disjoint from T with |T ′ | ≤ S and d T ′ is supported on T ′ , <lb/>then <lb/>| X T <lb/>T ′ X T β T , d T ′ | ≤ θ β T ℓ 2 d T ′ ℓ 2 <lb/>and, hence, by duality, <lb/>X * X T β T ℓ 2 (T ′ ) ≤ θ β T ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 . <lb/>(6.7) <lb/>If |E| ≥ S, then we can find T ′ ⊂ E with |T ′ | = S. But then we have <lb/>X * X T β T ℓ 2 (T ′ ) &gt; <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S 1/2 c T ℓ 2 |T ′ | 1/2 , <lb/>which contradicts (6.7). Thus, we have (6.1). Now we can apply (6.7) with <lb/>T ′ := E to obtain (6.4). <lb/>Corollary A.2 (Dual sparse reconstruction, ℓ ∞ version). Let c T be <lb/>supported on T for some |T | ≤ S. Then there exists β obeying (6.2) such <lb/>that <lb/>| Xβ, X j | ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ -θ) <lb/>√ <lb/>S <lb/>c T ℓ 2 <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ T. <lb/>(6.8) <lb/>Furthermore, we have <lb/>β ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 <lb/>(6.9) <lb/>and <lb/>β ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>2S <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>c T ℓ 2 . <lb/>(6.10) <lb/>Proof. The proof of this lemma operates by iterating the preceding <lb/>lemma as in Lemma 2.2 of [13]. We simply rehearse the main ingredients <lb/>and refer the reader to [13] for details. <lb/>We may normalize j∈T |c j | 2 = 1. Write T 0 := T and note that |T 0 | ≤ 2S. <lb/>Using Lemma A.1, we can find a vector β (1) and a set T 1 ⊆ {1, . . . , p} such <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>that <lb/>T 0 ∩ T 1 = ∅, <lb/>|T 1 | ≤ S, <lb/>Xβ (1) , X j = c j <lb/>for all j ∈ T 0 , <lb/>| Xβ (1) , X j | ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S 1/2 <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ T 0 ∪ T 1 , <lb/>j∈T 1 <lb/>| Xβ (1) , X j | 2 <lb/>1/2 <lb/>≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>, <lb/>β (1) <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>, <lb/>β (1) <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>2S <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>. <lb/>Applying Lemma A.1 iteratively gives a sequence of vectors β (n+1) ∈ R p and <lb/>sets T n+1 ⊆ {1, . . . , p} for all n ≥ 1 with the properties <lb/>T n+1 ∩ (T 0 ∪ T n ) = ∅, <lb/>|T n+1 | ≤ S, <lb/>Xβ (n+1) , X j = Xβ (n) , X j <lb/>for all j ∈ T n , <lb/>Xβ (n+1) , X j = 0 <lb/>for all j ∈ T 0 , <lb/>| Xβ (n+1) , X j | ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>(1 -δ)S 1/2 <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>n <lb/>∀j / <lb/>∈ T 0 ∪ T n ∪ T n+1 , <lb/>j∈T n+1 <lb/>| Xβ (n+1) , X j | 2 <lb/>1/2 <lb/>≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>n <lb/>, <lb/>β (n+1) <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>n <lb/>, <lb/>β (n+1) <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/>2S <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ <lb/>n <lb/>. <lb/>By hypothesis, we have θ <lb/>1-δ ≤ 1. Thus, if we set <lb/>β := <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=1 <lb/>(-1) n-1 β (n) , <lb/>then the series is absolutely convergent and, therefore, β is a well-defined <lb/>vector. And it turns out that β obeys the desired properties; see Lemma 2.2 <lb/>in [13]. <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<body>Corollary A.3 (Constrained thresholding). Let β be S-sparse such <lb/>that <lb/>β ℓ 2 &lt; λ • S 1/2 <lb/>for some λ &gt; 0. Then there exists a decomposition β = β ′ + β ′′ such that <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>β ℓ 2 , <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>λ <lb/>and <lb/>X * Xβ ′′ <lb/>ℓ∞ &lt; <lb/>1 -δ 2 <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>λ. <lb/>Proof. Let <lb/>T := {j : | Xβ, X j | ≥ (1 + δ)λ}. <lb/>Suppose that |T | ≥ S. Then we can find a subset T ′ of T with |T ′ | = S. Then <lb/>by restricted isometry we have <lb/>(1 + δ) 2 λ 2 S ≤ <lb/>j∈T ′ <lb/>| Xβ, X j | 2 ≤ (1 + δ) Xβ 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 2 β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 , <lb/>contradicting the hypothesis. Thus, |T | &lt; S. Applying restricted isometry <lb/>again, we conclude <lb/>(1 + δ) 2 λ 2 |T | ≤ <lb/>j∈T <lb/>| Xβ, X j | 2 ≤ (1 + δ) 2 β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>and, hence, <lb/>|T | ≤ S := <lb/>β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>λ 2 . <lb/>Applying Corollary A.2 with c j := Xβ, X j , we can find a β ′ such that <lb/>Xβ ′ , X j = Xβ, X j <lb/>for all j ∈ T, <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 2 ≤ <lb/>1 + δ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>β ℓ 2 , <lb/>β ′ <lb/>ℓ 1 ≤ <lb/>(1 + δ) <lb/>√ <lb/>S <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>β ℓ 2 = <lb/>(1 + δ) <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>β 2 <lb/>ℓ 2 <lb/>λ <lb/>and <lb/>| Xβ ′ , X j | ≤ <lb/>θ(1 + δ) <lb/>(1 -δ -θ) <lb/>√ <lb/>S <lb/>β ℓ 2 <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ T. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>By definition of S, we thus have <lb/>| Xβ ′ , X j | ≤ <lb/>θ <lb/>1 -δ -θ <lb/>(1 + δ)λ <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ T. <lb/>Meanwhile, by definition of T , we have <lb/>| Xβ, X j | &lt; (1 + δ)λ <lb/>for all j / <lb/>∈ T. <lb/>Setting β ′′ := β -β ′ , the claims follow. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments. Emmanuel Candès thanks Rob Nowak for sending <lb/>him an early preprint, Hannes Helgason for bibliographical research on this <lb/>project, Justin Romberg for his help with numerical simulations and Anestis <lb/>Antoniadis for comments on an early version of the manuscript. We also <lb/>thank the referees for their helpful remarks. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] Akaike, H. (1974). A new look at the statistical model identification. IEEE Trans. <lb/>Automatic Control 19 716-723. MR0423716 <lb/>[2] Antoniadis, A. and Fan, J. (2001). Regularization of wavelet approximations (with <lb/>discussion). J. Amer. Statist. Assoc. 96 939-967. MR1946364 <lb/>[3] Baraud, Y. (2000). Model selection for regression on a fixed design. Probab. Theory <lb/>Related Fields 117 467-493. MR1777129 <lb/>[4] Barron, A. R., Birgé, L. and Massart, P. (1999). Risk bounds for model selection <lb/>via penalization. Probab. Theory Related Fields 113 301-413. MR1679028 <lb/>[5] Barron, A. R. and Cover, T. M. (1991). Minimum complexity density estimation. <lb/>IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 37 1034-1054. MR1111806 <lb/>[6] Birgé, L. and Massart, P. (1997). From model selection to adaptive estimation. In <lb/>Festschrift for Lucien Le Cam (D. Pollard, E. Torgersen and G. L. Yang, eds.) <lb/>55-87. Springer, New York. MR1462939 <lb/>[7] Birgé, L. and Massart, P. (2001). Gaussian model selection. J. Eur. Math. Soc. 3 <lb/>203-268. MR1848946 <lb/>[8] Boyd, S. and Vandenberghe L. (2004). Convex Optimization. Cambridge Univ. <lb/>Press. MR2061575 <lb/>[9] Candès, E. J. and Romberg, J. (2005). Practical signal recovery from random pro-<lb/>jections. In Computational Imaging III : Proc. SPIE International Symposium <lb/>on Electronic Imaging 1 76-86. San Jose, CA. <lb/>[10] Candès, E. J., Romberg, J. and Tao, T. (2006). Stable signal recovery from in-<lb/>complete and inaccurate measurements. Comm. Pure Appl. Math. 59 1207-1223. <lb/>MR2230846 <lb/>[11] Candès, E. J., Romberg, J. and Tao, T. (2006). Robust uncertainty principles: <lb/>Exact signal reconstruction from highly incomplete frequency information. IEEE <lb/>Trans. Inform. Theory 52 489-509. MR2236170 <lb/>[12] Candès, E. J., Rudelson, M., Vershynin, R. and Tao, T. (2005). Error correction <lb/>via linear programming. In Proc. 46th Annual IEEE Symposium on Foundations <lb/>of Computer Science (FOCS) 295-308. IEEE, Los Alamitos, CA. <lb/>[13] Candès, E. J. and Tao, T. (2005). Decoding by linear programming. IEEE Trans. <lb/>Inform. Theory 51 4203-4215. MR2243152 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. CANDES AND T. TAO <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[14] Candès, E. J. and Tao, T. (2006). Near-optimal signal recovery from random projec-<lb/>tions: Universal encoding strategies? IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 52 5406-5425. <lb/>MR2300700 <lb/>[15] Chen, S. S., Donoho, D. L. and Saunders, M. A. (1998). Atomic decomposition <lb/>by basis pursuit. SIAM J. Sci. Comput. 20 33-61. MR1639094 <lb/>[16] Daniel, B. L., Yen, Y. F., Glover, G. H. et al. (1998). Breast disease: Dynamic <lb/>spiral MR imaging. Radiology 209 499-509. <lb/>[17] Daubechies, I. (2005). Personal communication. <lb/>[18] Donoho, D. L. (2006). For most large underdetermined systems of linear equations <lb/>the minimal ℓ1-norm solution is also the sparsest solution. Comm. Pure Appl. <lb/>Math. 59 797-829. MR2217606 <lb/>[19] Donoho, D. L. (2006). Compressed sensing. IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 52 1289-<lb/>1306. MR2241189 <lb/>[20] Donoho, D. L. and Huo, X. (2001). Uncertainty principles and ideal atomic de-<lb/>composition. IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 47 2845-2862. MR1872845 <lb/>[21] Donoho, D. L. and Johnstone, I. M. (1994). Ideal spatial adaptation by wavelet <lb/>shrinkage. Biometrika 81 425-455. MR1311089 <lb/>[22] Donoho, D. L. and Johnstone, I. M. (1994). Ideal denoising in an orthonormal <lb/>basis chosen from a library of bases. C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris Sér. I Math. 319 <lb/>1317-1322. MR1310679 <lb/>[23] Donoho, D. L. and Johnstone, I. M. (1995). Empirical atomic decomposition. <lb/>Unpublished manuscript. <lb/>[24] Elad, M. and Bruckstein, A. M. (2002). A generalized uncertainty principle and <lb/>sparse representation in pairs of bases. IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 48 2558-<lb/>2567. MR1929464 <lb/>[25] Fan, J. and Peng, H. (2004). Nonconcave penalized likelihood with a diverging <lb/>number of parameters. Ann. Statist. 32 928-961. MR2065194 <lb/>[26] Foster, D. P. and George, E. I. (1994). The risk inflation criterion for multiple <lb/>regression. Ann. Statist. 22 1947-1975. MR1329177 <lb/>[27] Fuchs, J. (2004). On sparse representations in arbitrary redundant bases. IEEE <lb/>Trans. Inform. Theory 50 1341-1344. MR2094894 <lb/>[28] Greenshtein, E. and Ritov, Y. (2004). Persistence in high-dimensional linear pre-<lb/>dictor selection and the virtue of overparametrization. Bernoulli 10 971-988. <lb/>MR2108039 <lb/>[29] Haupt, J. and Nowak, R. (2006). Signal reconstruction from noisy random projec-<lb/>tions. IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory 52 4036-4048. MR2298532 <lb/>[30] Kettenring, J., Lindsay, B. and Siegmund, D., eds. (2003). Statistics: Chal-<lb/>lenges and opportunities for the twenty-first century. NSF report. Available at <lb/>www.pnl.gov/scales/docs/nsf report.pdf. <lb/>[31] Mallows, C. L. (1973). Some comments on CP . Technometrics 15 661-675. <lb/>[32] Natarajan, B. K. (1995). Sparse approximate solutions to linear systems. SIAM J. <lb/>Comput. 24 227-234. MR1320206 <lb/>[33] Peters, D. C., Korosec, F. R., Grist, T. M., Block, W. F., Holden, J. E., <lb/>Vigen, K. K. and Mistretta, C. A. (2000). Undersampled projection re-<lb/>construction applied to MR angiography. Magnetic Resonance in Medicine 43 <lb/>91-101. <lb/>[34] Rudin, L. I., Osher, S. and Fatemi, E. (1992). Nonlinear total variation based <lb/>noise removal algorithms. Physica D 60 259-268. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">THE DANTZIG SELECTOR <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[35] Sardy, S., Bruce, A. G. and Tseng, P. (2000). Block coordinate relaxation meth-<lb/>ods for nonparametric wavelet denoising. J. Comput. Graph. Statist. 9 361-379. <lb/>MR1822091 <lb/>[36] Schwarz, G. (1978). Estimating the dimension of a model. Ann. Statist. 6 461-464. <lb/>MR0468014 <lb/>[37] Szarek, S. J. (1991). Condition numbers of random matrices. J. Complexity 7 131-<lb/>149. MR1108773 <lb/>[38] Tibshirani, R. (1996). Regression shrinkage and selection via the lasso. J. Roy. <lb/>Statist. Soc. Ser. B 58 267-288. MR1379242 <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Applied and Computational Mathematics, MC 217-50 <lb/>California Institute of Technology <lb/>Pasadena, California 91125 <lb/>USA <lb/>E-mail: emmanuel@acm.caltech.edu <lb/>Department of Mathematics <lb/>University of California <lb/>Los Angeles, California 90095 <lb/>USA <lb/>E-mail: tao@math.ucla.edu </front>


	</text>

</TEI>