<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T13:48:10.730Z">11/14/2025 1:48:10 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T12:11:52.702128Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T12:11:52.702128Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Training for endovascular therapy of acute <lb/>arterial disease and procedure-related <lb/>complication: An extracorporeally-perfused <lb/>human cadaver model study <lb/>Viktor Hartung ID <lb/>1 , Anne Marie Augustin 1 , Jan-Peter Grunz ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Henner Huflage ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Jan-<lb/>Lucca Hennes 1 , Florian Kleefeldt ID <lb/>2 <lb/>, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n2 , Dominik Peter 3 , Sven Lichthardt 3 , <lb/>Thorsten Alexander Bley 1 , Philipp Gruschwitz ID <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>1 Department of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital of Wu ¨rzburg, Wu ¨rzburg, <lb/>Germany, 2 Institute of Anatomy and Cell Biology, University of Wu ¨rzburg, Wu ¨rzburg, Germany, <lb/>3 Department of General, Visceral, Transplant, Vascular, and Pediatric Surgery, University Hospital of <lb/>Wu ¨rzburg, Wu ¨rzburg, Germany <lb/>* Gruschwitz_P@ukw.de <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Purpose <lb/>The aim of this study was to evaluate the usability of a recently developed extracorporeally-<lb/>perfused cadaver model for training the angiographic management of acute arterial dis-<lb/>eases and periprocedural complications that may occur during endovascular therapy of the <lb/>lower extremity arterial runoff. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Continuous extracorporeal perfusion was established in three fresh-frozen body donors via <lb/>inguinal and infragenicular access. Using digital subtraction angiography for guidance, both <lb/>arterial embolization (e.g., embolization using coils, vascular plugs, particles, and liquid <lb/>embolic agents) and endovascular recanalization procedures (e.g., manual aspiration or <lb/>balloon-assisted embolectomy) as well as various embolism protection devices were tested. <lb/>Furthermore, the management of complications during percutaneous transluminal angio-<lb/>plasty, such as vessel dissection and rupture, were exercised by implantation of endovascu-<lb/>lar dissection repair system or covered stents. Interventions were performed by two board-<lb/>certified interventional radiologists and one resident with only limited angiographic <lb/>experience. <lb/>Results <lb/>Stable extracorporeal perfusion was successfully established on both thighs of all three <lb/>body donors. Digital subtraction angiography could be performed reliably and resulted in <lb/>realistic artery depiction. The model allowed for repeatable training of endovascular recana-<lb/>lization and arterial embolization procedures with typical tactile feedback in a controlled <lb/>environment. Furthermore, the handling of more complex angiographic devices could be <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/>1 / 14 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Hartung V, Augustin AM, Grunz J-P, <lb/>Huflage H, Hennes J-L, Kleefeldt F, et al. (2024) <lb/>Training for endovascular therapy of acute arterial <lb/>disease and procedure-related complication: An <lb/>extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/>study. PLoS ONE 19(2): e0297800. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 <lb/>Editor: Ezio Lanza, Humanitas Clinical and <lb/>Research Center -IRRCS, ITALY <lb/>Received: August 19, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 12, 2024 <lb/>Published: February 8, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Hartung et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript. <lb/>exercised. Whereas procedural success was be ascertained for most endovascular inter-<lb/>ventions, thrombectomies procedures were not feasible in some cases due to the lack of <lb/>inherent coagulation. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The presented perfusion model is suitable for practicing time-critical endovascular interven-<lb/>tions in the lower extremity runoff under realistic but controlled conditions. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Digital subtraction angiography (DSA) is an established imaging procedure to guide endovas-<lb/>cular therapy during the management of acute and chronic vascular pathologies [1]. Angio-<lb/>graphic intervention allows both, endovascular recanalization and arterial embolization <lb/>procedures. While the former are used to treat acute limb ischemia [2], occluding procedures <lb/>are suitable to stop bleeding from parenchymal organs or after soft tissue trauma [3]. In many <lb/>cases, successful endovascular therapy renders surgical interventions unnecessary or the peri-<lb/>operative risk and subsequent morbidity can at least be reduced before definitive surgical ther-<lb/>apy [4]. Due to this, the number of interventionally treated hemorrhages has increased in <lb/>recent years [5, 6] and the mortality has been substantially reduced [7]. <lb/>Angiographic treatment of time-critical emergencies requires rapid decision-making as <lb/>well as high levels of skill and experience. Therefore, the interventionalist needs profound <lb/>knowledge of treatment options and continuous training of their application [8, 9]. In addi-<lb/>tion, there is a large number of different devices with variable handling, which are often used <lb/>infrequently, resulting in a lack of expertise. Since emergent endovascular treatments are often <lb/>requested outside of the regular working hours, i.e. during on-call duty or weekend shifts [10, <lb/>11], support from more experienced colleagues may not be available all the time. Despite an <lb/>increasing number of simulation courses, training for these time-critical scenarios is still <lb/>largely limited to actual patient treatment under supervision. However, more in-depth training <lb/>before a real-life endovascular procedure would be desirable. <lb/>Mock circulatory loops allow for the training of catheter handling and hands-on exercises <lb/>with other interventional devices. Some larger centers even offer virtual angiography training <lb/>suites, which facilitate the simulation of various interventions, albeit with a limited degree of <lb/>realism and practical applicability due to the absence of human tissue properties and blood <lb/>flow [12]. Both of these aspects have recently been addressed in a human cadaveric model with <lb/>continuous extracorporeal perfusion [13]. While this model has previously been used for <lb/>image quality comparisons between CT angiography scan protocol, its application for endo-<lb/>vascular interventional training procedures has not been investigated yet. <lb/>Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate the perfusion model&apos;s usability for the train-<lb/>ing of DSA-guided management of vascular emergencies and periprocedural complications in <lb/>a realistic but controlled environment. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Cadaveric specimens and perfusion model <lb/>Three fresh-frozen cadavers were obtained from the local anatomical institute in accordance <lb/>with national and European law (fully and irreversible anonymized human biomaterials). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<front>Funding: PG; Z-02CSP/18; Interdisciplinary Center <lb/>for Clinical Research (IZKF) at the University of <lb/>Wu ¨rzburg; https://www.med.uni-wuerzburg.de/ <lb/>izkf/startseite/ JPG.; Z-3BC/02; Interdisciplinary <lb/>Center for Clinical Research (IZKF) at the University <lb/>of Wu ¨rzburg; https://www.med.uni-wuerzburg.de/ <lb/>izkf/startseite/ The funders had no role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to <lb/>publish, or preparation of the manuscript. TAB and <lb/>JPG received speaker honoraria from Siemens <lb/>Healthcare GmbH outside of the presented work. <lb/>The Department of Diagnostic and Interventional <lb/>Radiology of the University Hospital Wu ¨rzburg <lb/>receives ongoing research funding from Siemens <lb/>Healthcare GmbH; https://www.siemens-<lb/>healthineers.com/en-us The funders had no role in <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>Donors had authorized the usage of their bodies for education and research purposes with <lb/>written informed consent during their lifetime (responsibility and accountability by the ana-<lb/>tomical institute). The study received permission from the local institutional review board <lb/>(Ethic Committee of the University of Wu ¨rzburg; protocol number: 20220413 01). <lb/>After thawing of the non-chemically preserved cadavers, accesses to the common femoral <lb/>artery (inguinal) and to the P3 segment of the popliteal artery (infragenicular) were surgically <lb/>established. To achieve this, the vessels were sectioned at the level of the junction with the <lb/>external iliac artery and the tibiofibular trunk, respectively. Remaining thrombotic material <lb/>was removed using a Fogarty catheter. Subsequently, introducer sheaths (Flexor 1 sheath 8/6 <lb/>French; Cook Medical, Bloomington, IN, USA) were inserted and fixated. The superficial fem-<lb/>oral artery (SFA) and popliteal artery were subsequently perfused with a cooled mixture of <lb/>Ringer&apos;s solution and 20% glucose solution (50:50) by means of a peristaltic pump. A sche-<lb/>matic of the experimental setup is shown in Fig 1. Detailed explanations of the preparatory <lb/>work and the materials required can be found elsewhere [13]. <lb/>Digital subtraction angiography <lb/>The cadavers were moved to the angiography suite and sterilely draped. Under continuous <lb/>perfusion, a working sheath was inserted using the Seldinger technique and afterwards transfe-<lb/>moral antegrade fluoroscopic series were acquired in posterior-anterior orientation after man-<lb/>ual injection of diluted contrast medium (50:50 mixture of Imeron 1 350 mg/ml iodine and <lb/>0.9% sodium chloride solution). DSA was performed using a commercially available flat detec-<lb/>tor unit (Azurion 7 C20, Philips Healthcare, Best, The Netherlands) with vendor-recom-<lb/>mended settings for low-dose examinations and a frame rate of 1-2 images/second. <lb/>Interventional procedures <lb/>A representative selection of endovascular recanalization and arterial embolization procedures <lb/>was conducted using the aforementioned in-vitro model. Investigated endovascular recanaliza-<lb/>tion procedures included manual and balloon-assisted aspiration embolectomy. In addition, <lb/>insertion and retrieval of an embolic protection device with a Nitinol &quot;basket&quot; was performed. <lb/>In order to train vascular occlusion procedures, small muscle branches were intentionally per-<lb/>forated to simulate post-traumatic soft tissue bleeding or focal hemorrhages of parenchymal <lb/>organs. After selective catheterization, afferent vessel segments were occluded using coils, <lb/>Fig 1. Schematic of the experimental setup. Right: Body donor in the angiography suite. Left: Perfusion circuit. The fluid reservoir <lb/>(FLUID) compensates the loss of perfusion fluid during the examination. To perform digital subtraction angiography, contrast medium <lb/>(IODINE) is manually injected via the working sheath and the resulting iodinated perfusion fluid is drained in a bag (WASTE). The <lb/>WORKING SHEATH is used as vascular access to perform interventions. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>particle embolization, and/or liquid embolic agents. Treatment strategies for larger vessel inju-<lb/>ries, e.g., in the context of a pelvic fracture, were also trained, including the deployment of a <lb/>vascular plaque for artery occlusion or a covered stent to treat a previously induced hemor-<lb/>rhage. Finally, the management of periinterventional complications was trained. In addition to <lb/>the above-mentioned treatment of a vessel rupture via a covered stent, the focus was on the <lb/>therapy of dissections by means of ordinary vascular stents and special dissection repair sys-<lb/>tems. A summary of the performed endovascular interventions is given in Table 1. <lb/>Results <lb/>Digital subtraction angiography <lb/>Puncture of the femoral artery and insertion of a working sheath could by practiced in all <lb/>cadaveric specimens. Correct intra-arterial needle position was indicated by realistic backflow <lb/>of perfusion fluid. It may be noted that the femoral artery is uncovered after preparation and <lb/>therefore easy to detect even with weak perfusion pressure. Manual DSA was performed as <lb/>usual and appeared visually realistic. Smaller peripheral muscle branches were sufficiently con-<lb/>trasted (e.g., see Fig 2B). <lb/>Arterial embolization procedures <lb/>A muscle branch of the SFA was catheterized using a selective microcatheter (Progreat TM , <lb/>2.7F; Terumo, Tokyo, Japan). Of note, practicing the handling and positioning of this catheter <lb/>is also relevant for the management of hemorrhages in parenchymatous organs. Afterwards, a <lb/>hemorrhage was intentionally caused using a high tip load 0.014&quot; wire (Astato XS; Asahi <lb/>Intecc, Aichi, Japan) with subsequent placement of vascular coils (Concerto TM Detachable <lb/>Coil System, Helix 4 mm x 8 cm; Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN, USA) to stop the contrast <lb/>extravasation (Fig 2). In the DSA control, the vascular branch distal of the coils was mostly <lb/>occluded. <lb/>Two other hemorrhages caused in the same manner were also occluded successfully after <lb/>selective catheterization using combinations of coils (AZUR™ CX, 3 mm x 8 cm, Terumo), liq-<lb/>uid embolic agents (Histoacryl 1 ; B. Braun, Melsungen, Germany) as well as pushable coils <lb/>(Nester 1 Embolization Coils, 3 mm x 7 cm; Cook Medical) and tri-acryl gelatin microspheres <lb/>(Embosphere 1 microspheres, 700-900 μm; Merit Medical Systems, South Jordan, UT, USA) <lb/>as alternative therapeutic options. Images of both techniques are shown in Fig 3. <lb/>To simulate the treatment of larger vessel hemorrhages, e.g., of the internal iliac artery, a <lb/>vascular plaque (Amplatzer TM Vascular Plaque II, 6 mm; Abbott Laboratories, North Chicago, <lb/>IL, USA) was placed in the proximal SFA, repositioned several times for training purposes, <lb/>and released after corrected positioning (Fig 4). <lb/>In another specimen, a vascular transection, which can occur periinterventionally or be of <lb/>traumatic origin, was simulated. For this purpose, an oversized cutting balloon (Cutting Bal-<lb/>loon Wolverine TM , 2/6 mm; Boston Scientific, Marlborough, MA, USA) was expanded in the <lb/>middle third of the SFA and the injured vessel segment was intentionally distended using an <lb/>even more oversized angioplasty balloon (Atlas TM Gold, 18/20 mm; Becton Dickinson, Frank-<lb/>lin Lakes, NJ, USA) until major vessel injury occurred. The rupture was already visible in DSA <lb/>while the balloon was still expanded. Treatment was performed with a self-expanding covered <lb/>stent (Covera TM , 7/60 mm; Becton Dickinson). Subsequent DSA showed complete exclusion <lb/>of the rupture, while remaining perivascular contrast agent was visible in the control angio-<lb/>gram (Fig 5). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>Endovascular recanalization procedures <lb/>For manual aspiration embolectomy, a 6F aspiration catheter (BigLumen Aspiration Catheter, <lb/>straight, 6F; OptiMed, Mannheim, Germany) was inserted. An artificial occlusion simulated <lb/>Table 1. Overview of endovascular interventions. <lb/>Type <lb/>Procedures <lb/>Material <lb/>Manufacturer <lb/>Comment/Limitation <lb/>arterial embolization coil embolization (solo) <lb/>Concerto TM Detachable Coil <lb/>System, <lb/>Helix 4 mm x 8 cm <lb/>Medtronic, <lb/>Minneapolis, MN, <lb/>USA <lb/>almost complete occlusion despite lack of clotting <lb/>coil embolization <lb/>+ liquid embolic <lb/>AZUR™ CX, 3mm x 8cm, <lb/>Histoacryl 1 tissue adhesive <lb/>Terumo, <lb/>Tokyo, Japan <lb/>B. Braun, <lb/>Melsungen, <lb/>Germany <lb/>almost complete occlusion despite lack of clotting <lb/>coil embolization <lb/>+ particle embolization <lb/>Nester 1 Embolization Coils, 3 <lb/>mm x 7 cm <lb/>Embosphere 1 microspheres, <lb/>700-900 μm <lb/>Cook Medical, <lb/>Bloomington, IN, <lb/>USA <lb/>Merit Medical <lb/>Systems, <lb/>South Jordan, UT, <lb/>USA <lb/>almost complete occlusion despite lack of clotting <lb/>vascular plaque <lb/>Amplatzer TM Vascular Plaque <lb/>II, 6 mm <lb/>Abbott <lb/>Laboratories, <lb/>North Chicago, IL, <lb/>USA <lb/>only visual flow occlusion, visual control of <lb/>placement <lb/>covered stent occlusion <lb/>Covera TM , 7/60 mm <lb/>Becton Dickinson, <lb/>Franklin Lakes, NJ, <lb/>USA <lb/>minor residual leakage hardly detectable due to <lb/>remaining extravasation of dye <lb/>temporary balloon occlusion <lb/>Atlas TM Gold, 18/20 mm <lb/>Becton Dickinson, <lb/>Franklin Lakes, NJ, <lb/>USA <lb/>(provoked arterial rupture) <lb/>endovascular <lb/>recanalization <lb/>aspiration embolectomy (manual <lb/>-catheter based) <lb/>BigLumen Aspiration Catheter, <lb/>straight, 6F <lb/>OptiMed, <lb/>Mannheim, <lb/>Germany <lb/>artificial embolus (gelatine sponge) <lb/>balloon embolectomy <lb/>Syntel TM , 4F 80 cm, 0.8 ml <lb/>balloon <lb/>LeMaitre Vascular <lb/>Inc., <lb/>Burlington, MA, <lb/>USA <lb/>embolism protection Nitinol &quot;basket&quot; filter <lb/>SpiderFX TM , 6 mm <lb/>Medtronic, <lb/>Minneapolis, MN, <lb/>USA <lb/>dissection <lb/>management <lb/>self-expanding stents <lb/>E-Luminexx TM , 8/30 mm <lb/>AbsolutePro TM , 9/80 mm <lb/>Becton Dickinson, <lb/>Franklin Lakes, NJ, <lb/>USA <lb/>Abbott <lb/>Laboratories, <lb/>North Chicago, IL, <lb/>USA <lb/>in principle; <lb/>no dissection present; <lb/>practice correct placement and release of different <lb/>models <lb/>balloon-expanding stent <lb/>Herkulink Elite TM , 7/18 mm <lb/>Abbott <lb/>Laboratories, <lb/>North Chicago, IL, <lb/>USA <lb/>in principle; <lb/>no dissection present <lb/>endovascular dissection repair <lb/>system <lb/>Tack 1 6F, 6 x 8 mm <lb/>Philips Healthcare, <lb/>Best, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>in principle; <lb/>no dissection present <lb/>multiple stent system <lb/>VascuFlex 1 Multi-LOC, 6 x 13 <lb/>mm <lb/>B. Braun, <lb/>Melsungen, <lb/>Germany <lb/>in principle; <lb/>no dissection present <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>with hemostatic absorbable gelatine sponge material (CuraSpon 1 ; Cura Medical, Assendelft, <lb/>The Netherlands) was aspirated and retrieved. After complete retrieval, DSA showed an unre-<lb/>markable vascular runoff (Fig 6). In addition to manual aspiration embolectomy, a balloon-<lb/>assisted mechanical embolectomy using a silicone embolectomy catheter (Syntel TM , 4F 80 cm, <lb/>0.8 ml balloon; LeMaitre Vascular Inc., Burlington, MA, USA) was performed. <lb/>To train the application of periprocedural embolic prophylaxis, the insertion and retrieval <lb/>of an embolic protection device comprised of a Nitinol &quot;basket&quot; (SpiderFX TM , 6 mm; Medtro-<lb/>nic) was tested. This tool prevents thrombotic material loosened during thrombectomy/embo-<lb/>lectomy (or atherectomy) and can be retrieved together with the captured emboli (Fig 7). <lb/>Dissection management <lb/>Dissections can occur after angioplasty and immediate management is often mandatory to <lb/>maintain vessel patency. Three different options for dissection management were practiced: <lb/>First, the established scaffolding technique is characterized by the deployment of stents <lb/>adapted to the dissection length. The exact stent placement was trained by releasing a selection <lb/>of stents from different manufacturers (E-Luminexx TM , 8/30 mm; Becton Dickinson | Herku-<lb/>link Elite TM , 7/18 mm; Abbott | AbsolutePro TM , 9/80 mm; Abbott). Second, a dedicated endo-<lb/>vascular dissection repair system (Tack 1 6F, 6 x 8 mm; Philips Healthcare) was used to treat <lb/>another artificially-induced superficial femoral artery dissection. Third, multi-stent systems <lb/>comprise several shorter stents with lower radial force. In this study, a system for spot stenting <lb/>(VascuFlex 1 Multi-LOC, 6 x 13 mm; B. Braun) was tested in the cadaveric perfusion model <lb/>(Fig 8). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The recently developed, continuous extracorporeally perfused human cadaver model allows <lb/>for reliable establishment of vascular access and execution of digital subtraction angiographies. <lb/>It enables the training of endovascular recanalization and arterial embolization procedures as <lb/>well as practicing periprocedural complication management such as dissection and rupture <lb/>Fig 2. Catheterization and treatment of a small vessel hemorrhage by coil embolization. A Intentional penetration <lb/>of a perforator vessel. B Visualization of hemorrhage using digital subtraction angiography. C Deposition of detachable <lb/>coils (Concerto TM , Helix 4 mm x 8 cm; Medtronic). D Occlusion of contrast extravasation after coil embolization. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>repair under realistic conditions with characteristic tactile feedback using the real angiographic <lb/>equipment. <lb/>The frequency of endovascular and thus minimally invasive treatment procedures have <lb/>steadily increased in recent years [5, 6]. In Germany, over 300.000 percutaneous interventions <lb/>were conducted in 2021 with numbers doubled from 2005 [14]. Of these, a substantial percent-<lb/>age comprise emergency procedures in patients with acute, potentially life-threatening condi-<lb/>tions. For example, every tenth to every third polytraumatized patient presents with a <lb/>peripheral vascular injury [15, 16]. While endovascular therapy procedures have been shown <lb/>to be effective alternatives to open surgical treatment [7], the pressure to provide an appropri-<lb/>ate expertise around the clock has markedly increased. In addition to growing numbers of <lb/>Fig 3. Treatment of a small vessel hemorrhage by combinations of coil, liquid tissue adhesive, and particle <lb/>embolization. A Selective catheterization of a muscle branch in the upper leg. B Visualization of the induced <lb/>hemorrhage in DSA. C Deposited coils (AZUR™ CX, 3mm x 8cm, Terumo) in the perforated vessel. D Stagnant <lb/>bleeding in DSA after additional application of liquid embolic (Histoacryl 1 ; B. Braun) E Another intentionally caused <lb/>bleeding visualized over a selective catheter (Progreat TM ; Terumo). F Fractional application of particle embolisate <lb/>(Embosphere 1 microspheres, 700-900 μm; Merit Medical) visible as contrast defects inside the catheter. G Additional <lb/>deposition of two coils (Nester 1 Embolization Coils, 3 mm x 7 cm; Cook Medical). H Cessation of bleeding in the <lb/>DSA control. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>interventions outside regular working hours [10, 11, 17], this also increases the need for appro-<lb/>priately specialized interventionalists as well as in-depth training in the angiographic skills <lb/>required for such procedures. <lb/>Besides supervised learning from experienced colleagues during actual procedures, which is <lb/>generally associated with a non-negligible risk for the patient [8], model-based learning <lb/>Fig 4. Placement and release of a vascular plaque. A Insertion of a vascular plaque (Amplatzer TM Vascular Plaque II, <lb/>6 mm; Abbott) via the working sheath. B Release of the plaque by turning the thread. C Vascular plaque in <lb/>intravascular position. Note: Circumscribed hemorrhage adjacent to the inflow sheath after preparation. Working <lb/>sheath and inflow sheath aligned parallelly. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g004 <lb/>Fig 5. Treatment of a simulated vessel rupture using a covered stent. A Intentional injury of the vessel wall by <lb/>expanding an oversized cutting balloon (Cutting Balloon Wolverine TM , 2/6 mm; Boston Scientific). B Vessel rupture <lb/>induced via balloon angioplasty (Atlas TM Gold, 18/20 mm; Becton Dickinson). C Verification of major hemorrhage <lb/>after balloon deflation. D Implantation of a covered stent (Covera TM , 7/60 mm; Becton Dickinson). E Successful <lb/>exclusion of the vascular transection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 6. Manual aspiration embolectomy of artificial embolus. A Aspiration catheter (BigLumen Aspiration Catheter, <lb/>straight, 6F; OptiMed) filled with contrast agent for improved visibility. Note the attached artificial embolus <lb/>(CuraSpon1; Cura Medical) marked with an arrowhead. B Empty aspiration catheter. C Unremarkable vessel <lb/>delineation after the artificial embolus was successfully retrieved. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g006 <lb/>Fig 7. Balloon-assisted embolectomy and embolic protection. A Silicone balloon embolectomy catheter (Synthel TM , <lb/>4F 80 cm, 0.8 ml; LeMaitre) in intravascular position B/C Embolic protection device with Nitinol &quot;basket&quot; <lb/>(SpiderFX TM , 6 mm; Medtronic) depicted in two different angulations. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g007 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>approaches have emerged as a potential alternative in recent years [18]. Expectedly, multiple <lb/>studies have shown that training generally contributes to a reduction in patient morbidity and <lb/>mortality from interventional procedures [19-22]. Hseino et al. [23] and Patel et al. [24], <lb/>among others, demonstrated a positive learning curve for model-based training of procedures <lb/>such as treatment of the aorta, renal arteries, the carotid artery, and intracranial vessels. In <lb/>addition, dedicated exercises reduced the total treatment and fluoroscopy time [25, 26] with <lb/>less contrast agent administered during the procedures [24, 25, 27, 28]. Apart from objective <lb/>criteria, a subjective increase in knowledge was also demonstrated in self-assessment assays <lb/>[18]. Model-based training allows for controlled honing of skills [29, 30] without a risk to <lb/>patients [31]. In particular, the option to perform interventions in a protected environment <lb/>under supervision [32] with frequent repetition of individual steps leads to a reduction of peri-<lb/>procedural errors [18]. While evidence shows that the translation of skills to patient care is <lb/>generally successful [23, 33], it must be stated that model-based learning can only be a supple-<lb/>ment for actual training in real-world patients [34, 35]. <lb/>Prior studies indicate that both novices [23, 25, 36-38] and more experienced intervention-<lb/>alists [27, 39] benefit from training on models. However, models must be adapted to the <lb/>appropriate level of knowledge or skills and increase in complexity. While simple synthetic <lb/>models are sufficient for beginners to learn how to use a guide wire or catheter, more refined <lb/>models are required for complex procedures. The use of large animal models, while anatomi-<lb/>cally realistic, requires expensive resources such as animal housing and laboratory [33, 40]. <lb/>Moreover, Berry et al. could show that the translation of skills from animal models is worse <lb/>compared to virtual angiography simulations [33]. Finally, there is ongoing debate on the ethi-<lb/>cal adequacy of large animal models, since alternatives are available [41]. <lb/>Currently, the best training options are arguably endovascular simulators and models based <lb/>on human body donors [12]. Virtual simulators are comparatively expensive to set up, require <lb/>maintenance, and may have recurring costs like software licenses and support. In turn, exami-<lb/>nations can be repeated infinitely and the range of interventions that can be simulated is wide. <lb/>Since no x-ray exposure is required, protective garment such as lead aprons can be omitted. <lb/>However, while simulators only generate virtual catheters, balloons, and stents, human cadaver <lb/>models can be used to train the handling of actual devices, some of which are difficult to oper-<lb/>ate. This also applies to procedures with increased complication rates, such as particle or coil <lb/>embolization, the use of liquid embolic agent, mechanical embolectomy systems or the use of <lb/>Fig 8. Variations of vascular dissection treatment options. A Intravascular stent positioning (top: E-Luminexx TM , 8/ <lb/>30 mm; Becton Dickinson | middle: Herkulink Elite TM , 7/18 mm; Abbott | bottom: AbsolutePro TM , 9/80 mm; Abbott). <lb/>B/C Endovascular dissection repair system (Tack 1 6F, 6 x 8 mm; Philips) before (B) and after (C) stent release D/E <lb/>Multiple stent system (VascuFlex 1 Multi-LOC, 6 x 13 mm; B. Braun) before (D) and after (E) stent release. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800.g008 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>closure systems, among others. Contrary to models described in the literature [28, 42, 43], our <lb/>cadaveric model provides a continuous perfusion circuit with the option of realistic DSA of <lb/>the peripheral arterial runoff in a real-life angiography suite. Various angiographic procedures <lb/>can be trained in a controlled environment with an entire team to reinforce and deepen work-<lb/>flows, which has been shown to improve teamwork and therefore patient care [44]. <lb/>Several limitations of the proposed model have to be mentioned. First, cadavers are a <lb/>resource with limited availability imposing recurring costs as opposed to the one-time pur-<lb/>chase of a simulator. This availability problem can primarily be solved through close coopera-<lb/>tion with the providing institutes, and the possibility of multiple use of a single donor for <lb/>different procedures is particularly valuable. In the long term, the shortage of suitable body <lb/>donors can probably only be overcome by raising awareness and thus increasing the willing-<lb/>ness to donate. Second, assistance from surgically experienced colleagues is required for the <lb/>preparation of vascular access and only non-preserved fresh-frozen cadavers are suitable for <lb/>establishment of the model. After thawing, these can be used for a maximum of 48 hours, <lb/>hence only a limited number of procedures per donor is feasible, especially if vascular injuries <lb/>are provoked and/or stents are inserted. Since the perfusion fluid has no intrinsic coagulation, <lb/>efficiency of pro-thrombotic procedures is limited. Third, in this feasibility study, endovascu-<lb/>lar interventions were only performed on three body donors. It may be noted, however, that <lb/>the perfusion model has been successfully established in more than ten body donors in the <lb/>meantime, suggesting good reproducibility. Fourth, a real educational situation was tested <lb/>with one resident performing a coil embolization as a pilot trial. While no structured evalua-<lb/>tion was conducted, further studies are planned to investigate the training potential in compar-<lb/>ison to existing alternatives like virtual angiography suites. Finally, due to the effort and <lb/>resources required to set up the continuous extracorporeal perfusion, we advocate that the <lb/>model should be reserved for advanced training and practice of complex angiographic proce-<lb/>dures and material. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The presented perfusion model is suitable for practicing time-critical endovascular interven-<lb/>tions in the lower extremity runoff under realistic but controlled conditions. <lb/></body>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Henner Huflage, <lb/>Florian Kleefeldt, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Thorsten Alexander Bley, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Data curation: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Henner Huflage, Jan-Lucca Hennes, <lb/>Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Formal analysis: Jan-Lucca Hennes, Dominik Peter, Sven Lichthardt, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Jan-Peter Grunz, Thorsten Alexander Bley, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Investigation: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Henner Huflage, Jan-<lb/>Lucca Hennes, Florian Kleefeldt, Dominik Peter, Sven Lichthardt, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Methodology: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Henner Huflage, Jan-<lb/>Lucca Hennes, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Dominik Peter, Sven Lichthardt, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Project administration: Viktor Hartung, Florian Kleefeldt, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Thorsten Alex-<lb/>ander Bley, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Resources: Henner Huflage, Florian Kleefeldt, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Dominik Peter, Sven <lb/>Lichthardt, Thorsten Alexander Bley. <lb/>Software: Henner Huflage, Thorsten Alexander Bley. <lb/>Supervision: Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Jan-Lucca Hennes, Florian Kleefeldt, <lb/>Thorsten Alexander Bley, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Validation: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Henner Huflage, Jan-<lb/>Lucca Hennes, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Dominik Peter, Sven Lichthardt. <lb/>Visualization: Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Viktor Hartung, Jan-Peter Grunz, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Viktor Hartung, Anne Marie Augustin, Jan-Peter Grunz, Henner <lb/>Huflage, Jan-Lucca Hennes, Florian Kleefeldt, Su ¨leyman Ergu ¨n, Dominik Peter, Sven <lb/>Lichthardt, Thorsten Alexander Bley, Philipp Gruschwitz. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Howard CA, Thal ER, Redman HC, Gibson P. Intra-arterial digital subtraction angiography in the evalu-<lb/>ation of peripheral vascular trauma. Ann Surg. 1989; 210:108-11. https://doi.org/10.1097/00000658-<lb/>198907000-00016 PMID: 2662922. <lb/>2. Schoder M. Acute peripheral arterial ischemia: diagnosis and interventional therapy. Wien Med <lb/>Wochenschr. 2001; 151:541-5. <lb/>3. Spiliopoulos S, Vasiniotis Kamarinos N, Brountzos E. Interventional Angiography Damage Control. <lb/>Curr Trauma Rep. 2018; 4:187-98. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40719-018-0135-1 <lb/>4. Velmahos GC, Chahwan S, Falabella A, Hanks SE, Demetriades D. Angiographic embolization for <lb/>intraperitoneal and retroperitoneal injuries. World J Surg. 2000; 24:539-45. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s002689910087 PMID: 10787073. <lb/>5. Brenner M, Hoehn M, Pasley J, Dubose J, Stein D, Scalea T. Basic endovascular skills for trauma <lb/>course. Bridging the gap between endovascular techniques and the acute care surgeon. J Trauma <lb/>Acute Care Surg. 2014; 77:286-91. https://doi.org/10.1097/TA.0000000000000310 PMID: 25058255. <lb/>6. Reuben BC, Whitten MG, Sarfati M, Kraiss LW. Increasing use of endovascular therapy in acute arterial <lb/>injuries: analysis of the National Trauma Data Bank. J Vasc Surg. 2007; 46:1222-6. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jvs.2007.08.023 PMID: 18154998. <lb/>7. Avery LE, Stahlfeld KR, Corcos AC, Scifres AM, Ziembicki JA, Varcelotti J, et al. Evolving role of endo-<lb/>vascular techniques for traumatic vascular injury: a changing landscape. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. <lb/>2012; 72:41-6; discussion 46-7. https://doi.org/10.1097/TA.0b013e31823d0f03 PMID: 22310114. <lb/>8. Babineau TJ, Becker J, Gibbons G, Sentovich S, Hess D, Robertson S, et al. The &quot;cost&quot; of operative <lb/>training for surgical residents. Arch Surg. 2004; 139:366-9; discussion 369-70. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1001/archsurg.139.4.366 PMID: 15078701. <lb/>9. Hage AN, McDevitt JL, Chick JFB, Vadlamudi V. Acute Limb Ischemia Therapies: When and How to <lb/>Treat Endovascularly. Semin Intervent Radiol. 2018; 35:453-60. Epub 2019/02/05. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1055/s-0038-1676321 PMID: 30728661. <lb/>10. Ota K, Matsubara N. Current Status of Thrombectomy Calls for Acute Ischemic Stroke for a Single Neu-<lb/>rointerventionist in a Regional Hospital. No Shinkei Geka. 2019; 47:1143-9. https://doi.org/10.11477/ <lb/>mf.1436204091 PMID: 31761775. <lb/>11. Zhou Y, Li W, Herath C, Xia J, Hu B, Song F, et al. Off-Hour Admission and Mortality Risk for 28 Specific <lb/>Diseases: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of 251 Cohorts. J Am Heart Assoc. 2016; 5: <lb/>e003102. Epub 2016/03/18. https://doi.org/10.1161/JAHA.115.003102 PMID: 26994132. <lb/>12. Neequaye SK, Aggarwal R, van Herzeele I, Darzi A, Cheshire NJ. Endovascular skills training and <lb/>assessment. J Vasc Surg. 2007; 46:1055-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvs.2007.05.041 PMID: <lb/>17980294. <lb/>13. Gruschwitz P, Hartung V, Kleefeldt F, Peter D, Lichthardt S, Huflage H, et al. Continuous extracorporeal <lb/>femoral perfusion model for intravascular ultrasound, computed tomography and digital subtraction <lb/>angiography. PLoS One. 2023; 18:e0285810. Epub 2023/05/23. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0285810 PMID: 37220113. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>14. Federal Statistical Office, Branch Bonn, Germany. Operations and procedures of full-time patients in <lb/>hospitals (place of residence/treatment). (Percutaneous) transluminal vascular intervention. The Fed-<lb/>eral Health Monitoring System 2023 [updated 7 Aug 2023; cited 7 Aug 2023]. Available from: https:// <lb/>www.gbe-bund.de/gbe/pkg_olap_tables.prc_set_hierlevel?p_uid=gast&amp;p_aid=57570900&amp;p_sprache= <lb/>E&amp;p_help=2&amp;p_indnr=662&amp;p_ansnr=63238794&amp;p_version=4&amp;p_dim=D.390&amp;p_dw=43879&amp;p_ <lb/>direction=drill. <lb/>15. Atia SM, Regal SAEH, Ahmed ME, Mansour MAEd. Incidence of Vascular Injuries in poly-traumatized <lb/>Patients. The Egyptian Journal of Hospital Medicine. 2021; 82:719-29. https://doi.org/10.21608/EJHM. <lb/>2021.152991 <lb/>16. Heberer G, Becker HM, Dittmer H, Stelter WJ. Vascular injuries in polytrauma. World J Surg. 1983; <lb/>7:68-79. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01655914 PMID: 6837068. <lb/>17. Shulkin DJ. Like night and day-shedding light on off-hours care. N Engl J Med. 2008; 358:2091-3. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMp0707144 PMID: 18480201. <lb/>18. See KWM, Chui KH, Chan WH, Wong KC, Chan YC. Evidence for Endovascular Simulation Training. A <lb/>Systematic Review. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2016; 51:441-51. Epub 2015/12/10. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ejvs.2015.10.011 PMID: 26684597. <lb/>19. Fennell VS, Martirosyan NL, Palejwala SK, Lemole GM, Dumont TM. Morbidity and mortality of patients <lb/>with endovascularly treated intracerebral aneurysms: does physician specialty matter. J Neurosurg. <lb/>2016; 124:13-7. Epub 2015/08/14. https://doi.org/10.3171/2014.11.JNS141030 PMID: 26274987. <lb/>20. Goldenberg MG. Evidence that surgical performance predicts clinical outcomes. World J Urol. 2020; <lb/>38:1595-7. Epub 2019/06/29. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00345-019-02857-w PMID: 31256249. <lb/>21. Nathan M, Karamichalis JM, Liu H, Del Nido P, Pigula F, Thiagarajan R, et al. Intraoperative adverse <lb/>events can be compensated by technical performance in neonates and infants after cardiac surgery: a <lb/>prospective study. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2011; 142:1098-107, 1107.e1-5. Epub 2011/08/15. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtcvs.2011.07.003 PMID: 21840545. <lb/>22. Reiley CE, Lin HC, Yuh DD, Hager GD. Review of methods for objective surgical skill evaluation. Surg <lb/>Endosc. 2011; 25:356-66. Epub 2010/07/07. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00464-010-1190-z PMID: <lb/>20607563. <lb/>23. Hseino H, Nugent E, Lee MJ, Hill ADK, Neary P, Tierney S, et al. Skills transfer after proficiency-based <lb/>simulation training in superficial femoral artery angioplasty. Simul Healthc. 2012; 7:274-81. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1097/SIH.0b013e31825b6308 PMID: 22801255. <lb/>24. Patel AD, Gallagher AG, Nicholson WJ, Cates CU. Learning curves and reliability measures for virtual <lb/>reality simulation in the performance assessment of carotid angiography. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006; <lb/>47:1796-802. Epub 2006/04/17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2005.12.053 PMID: 16682303. <lb/>25. Dayal R, Faries PL, Lin SC, Bernheim J, Hollenbeck S, DeRubertis B, et al. Computer simulation as a <lb/>component of catheter-based training. J Vasc Surg. 2004; 40:1112-7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvs. <lb/>2004.09.028 PMID: 15622364. <lb/>26. Hsu JH, Younan D, Pandalai S, Gillespie BT, Jain RA, Schippert DW, et al. Use of computer simulation <lb/>for determining endovascular skill levels in a carotid stenting model. J Vasc Surg. 2004; 40:1118-25. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvs.2004.08.026 PMID: 15622365. <lb/>27. Aggarwal R, Black SA, Hance JR, Darzi A, Cheshire NJW. Virtual reality simulation training can improve <lb/>inexperienced surgeons&apos; endovascular skills. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2006; 31:588-93. Epub <lb/>2006/01/04. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejvs.2005.11.009 PMID: 16387517. <lb/>28. Fargen KM, Arthur AS, Bendok BR, Levy EI, Ringer A, Siddiqui AH, et al. Experience with a simulator-<lb/>based angiography course for neurosurgical residents: beyond a pilot program. Neurosurgery. 2013; <lb/>73 Suppl 1:46-50. https://doi.org/10.1227/NEU.0000000000000059 PMID: 24051882. <lb/>29. Moorthy K, Vincent C, Darzi A. Simulation based training. BMJ. 2005; 330:493-4. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1136/bmj.330.7490.493 PMID: 15746111. <lb/>30. Gallagher AG, Ritter EM, Champion H, Higgins G, Fried MP, Moses G, et al. Virtual reality simulation <lb/>for the operating room: proficiency-based training as a paradigm shift in surgical skills training. Ann <lb/>Surg. 2005; 241:364-72. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.sla.0000151982.85062.80 PMID: 15650649. <lb/>31. Tsang JS, Naughton PA, Leong S, Hill ADK, Kelly CJ, Leahy AL. Virtual reality simulation in endovascu-<lb/>lar surgical training. Surgeon. 2008; 6:214-20. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1479-666x(08)80031-5 PMID: <lb/>18697364. <lb/>32. Hseino H, Nugent E, Cantwell C, Lee MJ, Given M, Hill ADK, et al. Impact of an assistant on the techni-<lb/>cal skills of the primary operator in superficial femoral artery angioplasty. Vasc Endovascular Surg. <lb/>2012; 46:635-9. Epub 2012/09/20. https://doi.org/10.1177/1538574412460771 PMID: 23002121. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>33. Berry M, Lystig T, Beard J, Klingestierna H, Reznick R, Lo ¨nn L. Porcine transfer study. Virtual reality <lb/>simulator training compared with porcine training in endovascular novices. Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. <lb/>2007; 30:455-61. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00270-006-0161-1 PMID: 17225971. <lb/>34. Bloom MB, Rawn CL, Salzberg AD, Krummel TM. Virtual reality applied to procedural testing: the next <lb/>era. Ann Surg. 2003; 237:442-8. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.SLA.0000055279.50681.80 PMID: <lb/>12616131. <lb/>35. Chaer RA, Derubertis BG, Lin SC, Bush HL, Karwowski JK, Birk D, et al. Simulation improves resident <lb/>performance in catheter-based intervention. Results of a randomized, controlled study. Ann Surg. 2006; <lb/>244:343-52. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.sla.0000234932.88487.75 PMID: 16926560. <lb/>36. Coates PJB, Zealley IA, Chakraverty S. Endovascular simulator is of benefit in the acquisition of basic <lb/>skills by novice operators. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2010; 21:130-4. Epub 2009/11/20. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jvir.2009.09.013 PMID: 19931470. <lb/>37. Dawson DL, Meyer J, Lee ES, Pevec WC. Training with simulation improves residents&apos; endovascular <lb/>procedure skills. J Vasc Surg. 2007; 45:149-54. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvs.2006.09.003 PMID: <lb/>17210400. <lb/>38. Voelker W, Petri N, To ¨nissen C, Sto ¨rk S, Birkemeyer R, Kaiser E, et al. Does Simulation-Based Training <lb/>Improve Procedural Skills of Beginners in Interventional Cardiology?-A Stratified Randomized Study. <lb/>J Interv Cardiol. 2016; 29:75-82. Epub 2015/12/16. https://doi.org/10.1111/joic.12257 PMID: <lb/>26671629. <lb/>39. van Herzeele I, Aggarwal R, Neequaye S, Hamady M, Cleveland T, Darzi A, et al. Experienced endo-<lb/>vascular interventionalists objectively improve their skills by attending carotid artery stent training <lb/>courses. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2008; 35:541-50. Epub 2008/02/08. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>ejvs.2007.12.017 PMID: 18262447. <lb/>40. Berry M, Hellstro ¨m M, Go ¨thlin J, Reznick R, Lo ¨nn L. Endovascular training with animals versus virtual <lb/>reality systems: an economic analysis. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2008; 19:233-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jvir.2007.09.004 PMID: 18341955. <lb/>41. Akhtar A. The flaws and human harms of animal experimentation. Camb Q Healthc Ethics. 2015; <lb/>24:407-19. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0963180115000079 PMID: 26364776. <lb/>42. Nesbitt C, Williams R, McCaslin J, Searle R, Mafeld S, Stansby G. Design of a Pulsatile Fresh Frozen <lb/>Human Cadaver Circulation Model for Endovascular Training. Ann Vasc Surg. 2017; 44:425-30. Epub <lb/>2017/05/04. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.avsg.2017.01.024 PMID: 28479447. <lb/>43. Garrett HE. A human cadaveric circulation model. J Vasc Surg. 2001; 33:1128-30. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1067/mva.2001.114214 PMID: 11331864. <lb/>44. Rudarakanchana N, van Herzeele I, Desender L, Cheshire NJW. Virtual reality simulation for the optimi-<lb/>zation of endovascular procedures. Current perspectives. Vasc Health Risk Manag. 2015; 11:195-<lb/>202. Epub 2015/03/10. https://doi.org/10.2147/VHRM.S46194 PMID: 25792841. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Training time-critical endovascular interventions on an extracorporeally-perfused human cadaver model <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297800 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 14 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>