<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T14:49:30.871Z">11/14/2025 2:49:30 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T14:48:45.331641Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T14:48:45.331641Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Identification and characterization of calcium <lb/>binding protein, spermatid-associated 1 <lb/>(CABS1) # in selected human tissues and fluids <lb/>Eduardo Reyes-Serratos 1,2 , Joy Ramielle L. Santos 1,2 , Lakshmi Puttagunta 1,3 , Stephen <lb/>J. Lewis 4 , Mechiko Watanabe 4,5 , Aron Gonshor 6 , Robert Buck 6,7 , A. Dean Befus 1,2 *, <lb/>Marcelo Marcet-PalaciosID 1,8 * <lb/>1 Alberta Respiratory Centre, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada, 2 Division of Pulmonary <lb/>Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada, 3 Department of <lb/>Laboratory Medicine, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada, 4 Departments of Pediatrics and <lb/>Pharmacology, Rainbow Babies and Children&apos;s Hospital, Case Western Reserve University, School of <lb/>Medicine, Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America, 5 Division of Pediatric Cardiology, Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Rainbow Babies and Children&apos;s Hospital, Case Western Reserve University, School of Medicine, <lb/>Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America, 6 GB Diagnostics, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, 7 GB <lb/>Diagnostics, Albuquerque, New Mexico, United States of America, 8 Northern Alberta Institute of <lb/>Technology, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada <lb/>* marcelo@ualberta.ca (MMP); dean.befus@ualberta.ca (ADB) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Calcium binding protein, spermatid associated 1 (CABS1) is a protein most widely studied in <lb/>spermatogenesis. However, mRNA for CABS1 has been found in numerous tissues, albeit <lb/>with little information about the protein. Previously, we identified CABS1 mRNA and protein <lb/>in human salivary glands and provided evidence that in humans CABS1 contains a hepta-<lb/>peptide near its carboxyl terminus that has anti-inflammatory activities. Moreover, levels of <lb/>an immunoreactive form of CABS1 were elevated in psychological stress. To more fully <lb/>characterize human CABS1 we developed additional polyclonal and monoclonal antibodies <lb/>to different sections of the protein and used these antibodies to characterize CABS1 in an <lb/>overexpression cell lysate, human salivary glands, saliva, serum and testes using western <lb/>blot, immunohistochemistry and bioinformatics approaches exploiting the Gene Expression <lb/>Omnibus (GEO) database. CABS1 appears to have multiple molecular weight forms, con-<lb/>sistent with its recognition as a structurally disordered protein, a protein with structural plas-<lb/>ticity. Interestingly, in human testes, its cellular distribution differs from that in rodents and <lb/>pigs, and includes Leydig cells, primary spermatogonia, Sertoli cells and developing sper-<lb/>matocytes and spermatids, Geodata suggests that CABS1 is much more widely distributed <lb/>than previously recognized, including in the urogenital, gastrointestinal and respiratory <lb/>tracts, as well as in the nervous system, immune system and other tissues. Much remains to <lb/>be learned about this intriguing protein. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/>1 / 22 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Reyes-Serratos E, Ramielle L. Santos J, <lb/>Puttagunta L, Lewis SJ, Watanabe M, Gonshor A, <lb/>et al. (2024) Identification and characterization of <lb/>calcium binding protein, spermatid-associated 1 <lb/>(CABS1) # in selected human tissues and fluids. <lb/>PLoS ONE 19(5): e0301855. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 <lb/>Editor: Abeer El Wakil, Alexandria University, <lb/>EGYPT <lb/>Received: September 28, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: March 22, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 16, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Reyes-Serratos et al. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>information files. Also the public repository can be <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Using an experimental model in rats to investigate the neural control of inflammatory reac-<lb/>tions, we identified a superior sympathetic-submandibular gland axis with anti-inflammatory <lb/>activity [1-4]. Ultimately, we established that the protein SMR1 (Submandibular rat 1) con-<lb/>tains a seven amino acid peptide (TDIFEGG) near its carboxyl terminus with anti-inflamma-<lb/>tory activity [3]. Previous work had determined that SMR1 expression was sexually dimorphic, <lb/>much more abundant in male rats than females, and present in the submandibular glands and <lb/>testes [5]. SMR1 was predicted to be a prohormone with several polypeptide derivatives with <lb/>multiple functions [6-11], including vasculature/erectile function, analgesia, and mineralocor-<lb/>ticoid-like activity. Our identification of the anti-inflammatory activity was novel, and we <lb/>characterized it in several models, including immediate hypersensitivity [12], endotoxic shock <lb/>[13], asthma [14, 15], and spinal cord injury [16]. <lb/>However, an analysis of the human genome showed that SMR1 was absent [17], and thus to <lb/>determine if the anti-inflammatory axis identified in the rat existed in humans, we tested if any <lb/>human protein contained a heptamer with a similar sequence to that of TDIFEGG in the rat <lb/>[4, 17, 18]. Human calcium-binding protein, spermatid-associated 1 (CABS1), was identified <lb/>given a heptamer TDIFELL near its carboxyl terminus, which was also shown to have anti-<lb/>inflammatory activity [18]. Moreover, as with SMR1, CABS1 was expressed in testes [19-21], <lb/>and we identified it in submandibular glands as well [18]. CABS1 was found on the human <lb/>chromosome analogous to rat chromosome 14, namely chromosome 4, in a region sharing <lb/>several analogous genes to those in the rat [17]. <lb/>We collaborated with an experimental psychologist, Thomas Ritz, to determine if human <lb/>CABS1 was under autonomic control like SMR1. We established that levels of immunogens in <lb/>saliva that reacted with anti-CABS1 polyclonal antibody (pAb) were associated with acute <lb/>experimental stress [22]. To extend these studies, we developed additional pAb and monoclo-<lb/>nal antibodies (mAb) to human CABS1 (hCABS1). The current study characterizes these anti-<lb/>bodies using extracts of testes and submandibular glands, and saliva, serum and human <lb/>CABS1 overexpression lysate from cultured cells. Our results were then validated using immu-<lb/>nohistochemistry to localize CABS1 in selected human tissues, and bioinformatics analyses of <lb/>CABS1 mRNA expression from public data (GEOdata). Some of this information has been <lb/>reported in the PhD thesis of Eduardo Reyes-Serratos [23]. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Antibodies to human CABS1 <lb/>Polyclonal and monoclonal antibodies were produced in accordance with international stan-<lb/>dards. The University of Alberta guidelines, in accordance with the Canadian Council on Ani-<lb/>mal Care, do not mandate an ethics review of antibody production by accredited commercial <lb/>suppliers. Our supplier, GenScript Biotech, Piscataway, NJ, USA, is fully accredited by the <lb/>Association for Assessment and Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care and NIH Office of <lb/>Laboratory Animal Welfare. <lb/>Polyclonal antibodies. Rabbit pAb were made against two regions of CABS1 (Fig 1). <lb/>Polyclonal antibody (pAb) H1 was raised against hCABS1 amino acid (aa) 375-388 <lb/>TSTTETDIFELLKE (underlined anti-inflammatory sequence [18]). Polyclonal antibodies <lb/>H2.0, H2.1, and H2.2 were raised against hCABS1 aa 184-197 DEADMSNYNSSIKS (region <lb/>deemed to be highly immunogenic for B lymphocytes). <lb/>Monoclonal antibodies. Mice were immunized against peptide sequences of hCABS1 <lb/>(Fig 1). Their spleens were harvested, and spleen-derived B-cells were combined with <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<front>found at: https://sites.ualberta.ca/~marcelo/Data_ <lb/>Repository.zip. <lb/>Funding: MMP, RGPIN-2020-04553, Natural <lb/>Sciences and Engineering Research Council of <lb/>Canada, https://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/. The <lb/>funder had no role in study design, data collection <lb/>and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. ADB, 16BB-MSI-C5 and 18BB-SI-<lb/>C9. AllerGen. https://www.allergen.ca/. The funder <lb/>had no role in study design, data collection and <lb/>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. GB Diagnostics, 10515302 Canada <lb/>Inc. provided funding within the company for <lb/>characterization of the polyclonal and monoclonal <lb/>antibodies to human CABS1 and for their long term <lb/>storage. Drs Buck and Gonshor, co-owners of GB <lb/>Diagnostics contributed to design of the <lb/>monoclonal antibodies and analysis of their <lb/>specificities, as well as to discussions about the <lb/>preparation of the manuscript and its editing. <lb/>Stephen Lewis and Michiko Watanabe have no <lb/>funding to declare. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/>following competing interests: A. Dean Befus, <lb/>together with the University of Alberta holds a <lb/>patent on CABS1 as a biomarker of stress, and an <lb/>associated licensing agreement with GB <lb/>Diagnostics, 10515302 Canada Inc. Aron Gonshor <lb/>and Robert Buck are co-owners of GB Diagnostics <lb/>10515302 Canada Inc. GB Diagnostics helped with <lb/>the processing of the application and partially <lb/>funded the approved USA patent 16/084,617, <lb/>entitled: Calcium Binding Protein, Spermatid <lb/>Specific 1, as a Biomarker for Diagnosis or <lb/>Treatment of Stress. The company is also assisting <lb/>with the application and partially funding of the <lb/>Canadian National Application No. CA 3,017,604, <lb/>Calcium Binding Protein, Spermatid Specific 1, as a <lb/>Biomarker for Diagnosis or Treatment of Stress <lb/>(pending approval). GB Diagnostics 10515302 <lb/>Canada Inc. is developing a stress biomarker test <lb/>for commercial application under its licensing <lb/>agreement with the University of Alberta. The <lb/>commercial affiliation with GB Diagnostics Canada <lb/>Inc. does not alter our adherence to PLOS ONE <lb/>policies on sharing data and materials for this <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></front>

			<body>myelomas to create hybridomas (GenScript Biotech). Monoclonal antibody 13G3 was raised <lb/>against hCABS1 aa 375-388 TSTTETDIFELLKE (underlined anti-inflammatory sequence). <lb/>Monoclonal antibody 15B11 was raised against CABS1 aa 184-197 DEADMSNYNSSIKS. The <lb/>immunogen for monoclonal antibody 4D1 was the complete recombinant hCABS1 protein. <lb/>The mAb detects a region towards the N terminus (aa 40-60 S1 Fig). <lb/>CABS1 transient overexpression cell lysate <lb/>A recombinant hCABS1 overexpression lysate (OEL) produced in Human Embryonic Kidney <lb/>293T (HEK293T) cells (OriGene Technologies Inc., Rockville, MD, USA) was used as a posi-<lb/>tive control in Western Blot (WB). The lysate contains recombinant hCABS1 protein with a <lb/>FLAG tag (aa sequence: DYKDDDDK) adjacent to its carboxyl end. The negative control cell <lb/>lysate (NCL) was from HEK293T cells with the same vector but lacking a hCABS1 cDNA <lb/>insert. As an additional control, we probed the overexpression lysate with ANTI-FLAG 1 M2 <lb/>(Sigma), a mouse mAb targeting FLAG sequence (gift from Drs. Steven Willows and Marianna <lb/>Kulka, Nanotechnology Research Centre, Edmonton, AB). <lb/>Human samples <lb/>Unless otherwise stated, all tissues and fluids were collected and stored under ethics protocols <lb/>approved by the University of Alberta Human Ethics Review Board, (Biomedical Panel). The <lb/>Alberta Research Information Services (ARISE) System approved our protocols Pro00001790 <lb/>(Anti-inflammatory proteins and biomarkers of stress) and Pro00112432 (Distribution and cell-<lb/>type specific localization of CABS1) in writing. Protocol Pro00001790 was initially approved in <lb/>2007 and has been subject to annual review and re-approval as well as amendments. Protocol <lb/>Pro00112432 was approved in 2021 and was annually reviewed and renewed in 2022 and 2023. <lb/>As the human submandibular gland (SMG) and testes samples used in this study were archived <lb/>surgical specimens collected for clinical diagnostic purposes, our protocol was for secondary use <lb/>of the samples and received a waiver of consent from the Ethics Review Board. <lb/>Four samples of human SMG were purchased from the commercial source, Conversant <lb/>Biologic Inc (see below). S2 Table lists all the testes and submandibular gland samples used in <lb/>this study. <lb/>Saliva and serum <lb/>Recruitment for a pool of saliva and serum, each from the same individual, a 30-year-old male, <lb/>started January 1, 2017, and completed June 30, 2018. Written consent was received from the <lb/>study subject. <lb/>Fig 1. The ranges of the amino acid sequence immunogens are indicated across the top row and the mAb and pAb <lb/>are listed in the bottom rows. C = carboxyl terminal, N = amino terminal. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Whole blood (10 mL) was collected in a vacutainer containing no additive, incubated for 45 <lb/>min to allow clotting and centrifuged at 1500 g, 21˚C for 15 min. Serum was aspirated, trans-<lb/>ferred into 300 μL aliquots, and stored at -80˚C. <lb/>Unstimulated whole saliva was collected using the passive drool technique protocol (Sali-<lb/>metrics LLC, Carlsbad, CA, USA) [24] over 15 days. Following breakfast and teeth brushing, <lb/>saliva was collected after 1.5 h. Samples were frozen at -20˚C immediately after collection. <lb/>When the collection was finalized (200 mL), all samples were thawed and pooled. The resulting <lb/>pool was centrifuged at 1500 g, 4˚C for 20 min, and the supernatant was transferred into 50 μL <lb/>aliquots. Prior to analyses, total protein concentration was determined as below. <lb/>Submandibular gland (SMG) <lb/>For tissue lysates to be used for WB, fresh human SMG samples were collected between Janu-<lb/>ary 1, 2009 and June 30, 2018 (n = 8, S2 Table) from patients, female and male, undergoing <lb/>surgical removal of squamous carcinoma at the University of Alberta Hospital (Edmonton, <lb/>Canada). A grossly normal looking portion of each SMG was homogenized at 4˚C using a dilu-<lb/>ent RIPA buffer supplemented with P8340 protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma Aldrich, Mark-<lb/>ham, ON, Canada). The remaining fresh tissue was frozen (-80˚C) for future lysate extraction. <lb/>Post-homogenization, samples were centrifuged at 12,000 g for 20 min, and the supernatant <lb/>was collected, aliquoted, and stored at -80˚C. Before WB analyses, each sample&apos;s total protein <lb/>concentration was determined using a Pierce™ BCA Protein Assay Kit (Thermo Scientific, <lb/>Waltham, MA, USA). <lb/>For immunohistochemical studies surgical specimens of SMG were collected through the <lb/>University of Alberta (n = 3) (secondary use, Pro00112432). The specimens were identified <lb/>between July 30, 2021 to November 17, 2023 from archived samples that were originally col-<lb/>lected for clinical diagnostic purposes. Two samples were from females, aged 62 and 73, and <lb/>one male, aged 69 (S2 Table). SMG samples were fixed in 10% buffered formalin. Following <lb/>paraffin embedding, tissue sections were assessed by microscopy using hematoxylin and eosin <lb/>(H&amp;E) staining to identify areas that appeared to be morphologically normal. Thereafter, adja-<lb/>cent sections were stained with anti-hCABS1 antibodies and normal areas were assessed for <lb/>the distribution of CABS1 immunoreactivity. <lb/>Four specimens of submandibular gland, two from carcinoma resection (one female 40 <lb/>years and one male 62 years), and two from Sjogren&apos;s syndrome subjects, a 43-year-old male <lb/>and an unknown donor (S2 Table), were kindly provided to Dr. Stephen Lewis by GlaxoS-<lb/>mithKline&apos;s (GSK) Immune-inflammation therapy unit&apos;s human biological sample repository, <lb/>arranged by Dr. Alessandra Giarola of Bioelectronics Research and Development. The samples <lb/>were purchased from Conversant Biologics Inc, now Discovery Life Sciences, Huntsville, AL, <lb/>USA 35806. <lb/>Testes <lb/>Archived surgical specimens (n = 4) of testes tissue from 58, 70 and 73 year old, and one of <lb/>unknown age were used for immunohistochemical studies (S2 Table). <lb/>Western blot analysis <lb/>For 1 D electrophoresis, we followed standard BIO-RAD protocols. Briefly, the TGX™ Fas-<lb/>tCast™ 12% Acrylamide Kit (Bio-Rad, Mississauga, ON, CA) was used to prepare 1.5 mm thick <lb/>gels the day before an experiment and polymerized gels were kept at 4˚C. On the day of the <lb/>experiment, 1X WB running buffer (Trizma base-40 mM, glycine-300 mM, methanol-200 <lb/>mL) was prepared and kept at 4˚C. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>For WB, electrophoresed samples in gels were placed in a cassette containing fiber pads, fil-<lb/>ter papers, and a 0.45 μm pore-size nitrocellulose membrane. The cassette was placed in a ver-<lb/>tical transfer chamber with an ice pack on the side in WB transfer buffer; transfer was done at <lb/>0.5 A for 1 h. The nitrocellulose membrane was washed with double distilled water before add-<lb/>ing WB blocking buffer (1% fish skin gelatin [Truin Science Ltd., Edmonton, AB, Canada], 1X <lb/>PBS, 0.1% Tween20). Blocking was done at room temperature for 1 h. The membrane was <lb/>probed overnight at 4˚C with the relevant titrated antibody(-ies) diluted in a 50:50 solution <lb/>containing PBS supplemented with 0.05% Tween 20, and blocking buffer. The antibody solu-<lb/>tion was then removed, and the membrane was washed. LI-COR Biosciences secondary anti-<lb/>bodies were used at 0.05 μg/mL in the same solution as the primary antibodies. The dates <lb/>when the WB experiments were conducted, together with the data files are included in the link <lb/>data repository folder, WB section, https://sites.ualberta.ca/~marcelo/Data_Repository.zip. <lb/>The controls for the pAbs included: no primary antibody just secondary goat anti-mouse <lb/>antibodies (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA) and for some tissues, preimmune serum; for mAbs <lb/>included: no primary antibody, or isotype antibodies concentration-matched to our mAbs. <lb/>Mouse IgG1.κ (R&amp;D systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) was the isotype antibody for mAbs <lb/>15B11 and 13G3; mouse IgG2α.κ (Stemcell™ Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) was the <lb/>isotype antibody for mAb 4D1. There is a repository of detailed blot/gel data together with a <lb/>WB protocol in the linked data repository folder, WB section. <lb/>Molecular weight determination <lb/>All WB included a molecular mass reference (M r ). WB images from studies of pAb produced <lb/>by LI-COR were opened in Microsoft Paint and the M r of each band (kDa) was recorded. For <lb/>M r estimates from studies with mAb, calculations were done manually. <lb/>Immunohistochemical analyses (immunoperoxidase or <lb/>immunofluorescence amplification) <lb/>SMG and testis. For human tissues collected at U of A from archives, immunohistochem-<lb/>ical studies used immunoperoxidase amplification. Sections on slides were baked at 60˚C for 1 <lb/>h and then deparaffinized and retrieved on Dako Omnis fully automated IHC platform (Agi-<lb/>lent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) using EnVision FLEX target retrieval solution, high pH (Dako <lb/>Omnis) at 97˚C for 30 min. Monoclonal antibody 15B11 (targeting the mid region of <lb/>hCABS1) was diluted 1/100 in EnVision FLEX antibody diluent and was applied for 20 min. at <lb/>32˚C followed by EnVision Flex+ Mouse LINKER (Dako Omnis) for 10 min. Negative con-<lb/>trols included the use of no anti-CABS1 mAb, or isotype control antibody as described above <lb/>for WB studies. Subsequently, EnVision FLEX, HRP.Rabbit/Mouse was added for 20 min. <lb/>Visualization was performed using DAB+ substrate chromogen system (Dako Omnis) and <lb/>counter-stained with Gill I Hematoxylin formula (Leica, Wetzlar, Hesse, Germany). All histol-<lb/>ogy and immunostains were reviewed with an Olympus BX41. All histology images were cap-<lb/>tured with a Nikon Eclipse E600 microscope with an attached Nikon Digital-sight DS-Fi2 <lb/>Ki7607 camera. <lb/>Following optimization of the staining protocols on testis tissue using three dilutions of <lb/>15B11 anti-CABS1 mAb, the immunohistochemical studies of SMG and testes used three <lb/>slides of tissue sections for each subject. One slide was used for the test mAb and two slides for <lb/>the negative controls; no primary mAb or concentration-matched isotype control. The average <lb/>area of tissue assessed was: 4.9 cm 2 for SMG and 4.0 cm 2 for testes. Three co-authors (LK, <lb/>ADB and MM-P) reviewed the slides and reached consensus about the results. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>For immunofluorescence studies, SMG tissue (S2 Table) (gift from GSK, see above) was <lb/>sectioned, deparaffinized, rehydrated, and microwaved for 10 min in 10 mM sodium citrate <lb/>(pH 6) for antigen retrieval (i.e., heat-induced antigen retrieval). Subsequently, sections were <lb/>blocked for 30 min at room temperature in blocking buffer (PBS containing 5% bovine serum <lb/>albumin and 0.1% Triton-X 100). Next, blocked sections were incubated overnight at 4˚C with <lb/>the primary pAb (H1.0, H2.0, H2.1, H2.2, or respective preimmune serum, diluted 1/200 in <lb/>blocking buffer. The next day, slides were washed with PBS and incubated for 2 h at room tem-<lb/>perature with the secondary antibody (goat anti-rabbit IgG H+L conjugated with Alexa Fluor <lb/>488, Thermo Scientific), washed with PBS and mounted in VECTASHIELD 1 HardSet™ anti-<lb/>fade medium with DAPI (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA). Images were acquired <lb/>with a Retiga EXi, Fast 1394 digital camera (Teledyne Photometrics, Tucson, AZ, USA) <lb/>attached to a Diaphot 200 inverted phase contrast microscope (Nikon) and evaluated using <lb/>Q-Capture imaging software (Teledyne Photometrics). <lb/>For studies with anti-CABS1 pAb H1.0, H.2.0, H2.1 and H2.2, one slide from each speci-<lb/>men for each pAb was assessed. For each preimmune serum negative control, one slide from <lb/>each specimen was assessed. Four observers reviewed the slides (two co-authors MW and SL, <lb/>one trainee and one technologist) and reached consensus about the results. S3.1-S3.8 Fig pro-<lb/>vide additional images of the immunofluorescence studies of submandibular glands. <lb/>Mass Spectrometry sequencing (MS-seq) <lb/>Transient overexpression samples, OEL and NCL, were separated by 1-D SDS-PAGE and <lb/>stained using Blue Silver dye. To assess the distribution and relative abundance of hCABS1, <lb/>the resolving gels (complete lanes) were cut into 11 equal segments and sent for analysis to the <lb/>Alberta Proteomics and Mass Spectrometry Facility (University of Alberta, Edmonton) for in-<lb/>gel trypsin digestion and MS-seq analysis using a LTQ Orbitrap XL Hybrid Ion Trap-Orbitrap <lb/>mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Data were processed using Proteome Discov-<lb/>erer v.1.4 (Thermo Fisher Scientific) using the Sequest (Thermo Fisher Scientific) database <lb/>search algorithm; only proteins with �2 tryptic peptides identified by MS-seq were included. <lb/>Data on all the peptide fragments detected during our MS-seq studies are attached in the <lb/>linked data repository folder, mass spectroscopy section, https://sites.ualberta.ca/~marcelo/ <lb/>Data_Repository.zip. <lb/>Meta-analysis of studies from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database <lb/>Gene expression data was collected from the GEO database and supplemental data provided in <lb/>previous studies. Relevant studies were identified using specific keywords, including CABS1, <lb/>Normal, and Tissue. Non-normal tissue or treated cell/tissue datasets were excluded from the <lb/>search. Raw data was downloaded and rescaled to 0 to 100% for each dataset using min-max <lb/>normalization. We combined the data from three studies [25-27] and analyzed the data distri-<lb/>bution in a histogram. Over 94% of the data points were observed within 0 to 50%. A continu-<lb/>ous graded color scale of the data distribution was used to create the meta-analysis figure. <lb/>Results <lb/>Detection of recombinant hCABS1 in OEL using pAb and mAb <lb/>pAb. We previously published studies of hCABS1 in OEL and NCL using pAb H2.0 [18]. <lb/>These studies were confirmed and extended with pAb H1.0 and H2.0, H2.1, and H2.2 (Fig 2A, <lb/>reported in PhD thesis, [23]). In addition to the NCL control, the results with the anti-FLAG <lb/>antibody and the no primary antibody are also shown (Fig 2A). H1.0, H2.0, and H2.2 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>specifically detected immunoreactive bands in OEL at 84 and 67 kDa, whereas H2.1 detected <lb/>the 84 kDa band specifically (Fig 2A; n = 8-12 independent experiments). In NCL, these pAbs <lb/>variably detected bands at approximately 76, 55, 47, 34 and 21 kDa (Fig 2A), but nothing at 84 <lb/>and 67 kDa. Antibody to the FLAG marker of rhCABS1 in OEL detected immunoreactive <lb/>Fig 2. Western blot analyses of human CABS1 in transient overexpression lysate (OEL) of HEK 293T cells and in control <lb/>lysate (NCL) of HEK 293T cells transfected with empty plasmid. A) Representative results of four pAb to peptide <lb/>immunogens of hCABS1 are shown (n = 8 to 12 replicates; 1 μg of OEL or NCL lysate were used, for H1.0 and H2.0, 3 ng/μL <lb/>and for H2.1 and H2.2, 2 ng/μL of pAb were used). Negative control studies using no primary antibody were clean. In B) mAb <lb/>13G3 (10 ng/μL), 15B11 (1 ng/μL) and 4D1/ (1ng/μL) were used, and 1 μg of OEL or NCL (n = 3). Controls with no primary <lb/>antibody, or with isotype control antibodies are shown. Antibody to the FLAG tag on the rhCABS1 was used as a control for <lb/>these studies with pAb and mAb. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>bands at 84 and 67 kDa; no bands were detected in NCL. Similarly, MS-seq analyses detected <lb/>rhCABS1 in OEL, but not in NCL. CABS1 peptides were detected in 1D gel segments of 119-<lb/>85, 84-60, 59-40, 39-33, 32-22 and 16-11 kDa (Fig 3), as mentioned briefly in our previous <lb/>report [18]. Two to 10 unique CABS1 peptides were identified in the gel segments (Fig 3B) and <lb/>peptide coverage of the protein in the segments ranged from 7 to 48%. As previously reported <lb/>[18], there was no evidence that peptides from selected regions of hCABS1 were preferentially <lb/>found in different segments of the gel. No peptides were detected above 119 kDa, in the 17-21 <lb/>range or below 10 kDa. The linked data repository folder, mass spectroscopy section has the <lb/>raw MS-seq data of the peptides from various proteins that were detected in OEL and NCL. <lb/>mAb: (n = 3 independent experiments for each). Antibody 13G3 (same immunogen as <lb/>H1 pAb) detected bands at 78, 64, and 53 kDa in OEL, and in NCL, a band at 53 kDa (Fig 2B). <lb/>No bands were observed in membranes probed with no primary antibody, but OEL probed <lb/>with isotype antibody IgG1.κ at the same concentration as 13G3 showed a band at 64 kDa (Fig <lb/>2B). WB analyses using 15B11 (same immunogen as H2.n pAb) showed immunoreactive <lb/>bands at 78, 53, and 47 kDa for OEL, and bands at 53, 47, 38, 33, and 31 kDa in NCL (Fig 2B). <lb/>No immunoreactivity was observed in membranes probed with isotype antibody IgG1.κ at the <lb/>same working concentration as 15B11 or with no primary antibody. Antibody 4D1 shows a <lb/>band at 78 kDa in OEL, and a faint band at 53 kDa in NCL (Fig 2B). No signal was detected in <lb/>membranes probed with no primary antibody, but a membrane probed with isotype antibody <lb/>Fig 3. Estimate of the abundance of rhCABS1 in sections (range of kDa) of 1 D gel analyzed by mass spectroscopy. <lb/>A) relative abundance of rhCABS1 in each gel segment (kDa range); B) the number of rhCABS1 peptides detected in <lb/>each gel segment, the percentage of rhCABS1 covered by the peptides in each segment and the percentage of the total <lb/>rhCABS1 recovered. In summary, our pAbs detected CABS1-specific bands at 84 and 67 kDa in rhCABS1 OEL and <lb/>not in NCL. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>IgG2α.κ showed several bands for NCL in a smear pattern in a range between 100 and 35 kDa. <lb/>Evaluation of these lysates with anti-FLAG antibody showed two bands at 78 and 51 kDa, with <lb/>the 51 kDa band also present in NCL (Fig 2B). <lb/>In summary, our mAbs specifically detected rhCABS1 at 78 kDa in OEL. Given that this <lb/>band was also FLAG positive, we postulate that the 84 kDa band detected with pAbs and this <lb/>band detected at 78 kDa with mAbs are the same (see Discussion). <lb/>Detection of CABS1 using pAbs and mAbs in human fluids and <lb/>submandibular glands lysate <lb/>hCABS1 in submandibular gland lysate. pAb. With each of the four pAb several immu-<lb/>noreactive bands ranging from ~22 to 127 kDa were detected in male SMG lysate (Fig 4A). <lb/>Controls using no primary antibody were negative. There were differences among the pAb in <lb/>the immunoreactive bands that were detected; bands at ~71, 52 and 27 kDa were detected by <lb/>at least three of four pAb. <lb/>mAb. No immunoreactive bands were detected when probing membranes with isotype <lb/>antibody at the same working concentration as the respective primary mAb, or when adding <lb/>no primary antibody. WB analyses of male and female SMG lysates using 13G3 (n = 3) showed <lb/>immunoreactive bands at ~96, 78, 63, 53 and 42 kDa. (Fig 4B). WB analyses of SMG lysate <lb/>using the 15B11 mAb (n = 3 independent experiments) detected a single immunoreactive <lb/>band at 53 kDa in both male and female extracts. WB of SMG lysate using antibody 4D1 <lb/>(n = 3) detected two bands at 63 and 53 kDa in both male and female SMG, and in the male, <lb/>additional bands at 96 and 78 kDa and between 63 and 53 kDa (Fig 4B). <lb/>Thus, with mAbs, SMG lysate has anti-hCABS1 specific immunoreactive bands at ~96, 78, <lb/>63, 53 and 42 kDa with some distinctions among the mAbs used. With pAb, bands at ~71, 52 <lb/>and 27 kDa were detected with 3 of 4 pAb. <lb/>hCABS1 in saliva <lb/>pAbs. Given our experience with careful antigen and antibody titrations using multiple <lb/>human saliva samples with WB [18], and as well many of the same saliva samples with semi-<lb/>automated nano-capillary immunoassay (NCIA) [24], we reassessed our previous optimization <lb/>[18] of antibody and antigen concentrations using pAb and the pooled human saliva from a <lb/>single individual. We determined that optimal specificity was achieved at 2.2 μg of human <lb/>saliva and 0.2 to 0.3 ng/μL of pAbs. At these concentrations in a pilot experiment, no unequiv-<lb/>ocal bands selective to H1 compared to preimmune serum or no primary antibody controls <lb/>were detected in saliva, although a band was seen at 60 kDa (Fig 5A). With H2.0 a selective <lb/>band (versus preimmune serum) was seen at approximately 60 kDa and faint bands were seen <lb/>at ~90 and 27 kDa (Fig 5A). Studies were not done with H2.1 and 2.2. <lb/>mAbs. As with studies using pAb, studies with all three mAb on salivary supernatants <lb/>detected a number of immunoreactive bands. However, many of them appear to be non-spe-<lb/>cific and the only specific immunoreactive band was at ~60 kDa; not detected with only sec-<lb/>ondary antibody or with isotype antibody (Fig 5B). <lb/>In summary, results from WB analyses of human saliva with pAb and mAb suggest that <lb/>there is a specific immunoreactive band of ~60 kDa (see Discussion). <lb/>hCABS1 in serum <lb/>pAbs. For analysis of CABS1 in the pool of human serum and given our experience with <lb/>saliva and in initial pilot experiments with pAbs, we selected 1.5 μg of serum and 0.03 and 0.02 <lb/>ng/μL of pAbs H.1.0, H2.0, and H2.1, H2.2 respectively as appropriate concentrations of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>reagents (S2 Fig). Several immunoreactive bands were detected with the pAbs that were not <lb/>detected in the corresponding preimmune sera (S2 Fig). The bands ranged from ~180-135, <lb/>90-100, 60-75 and 47-56 kDa. Given this complexity of immunoreactive bands with pAb, we <lb/>focused studies on mAb. Controls with no primary antibodies were clean. <lb/>mAbs. For studies of CABS1 immunoreactivity in the serum pool, 1 μg of serum was used <lb/>and 10 ng/μL of mAb (n = 3 for each mAb). When probing serum with 13G3 and 4D1, WB <lb/>Fig 4. Western blot analyses of CABS1 in human female and male submandibular gland lysates. A) As optimized during studies <lb/>with OEL and NCL (Fig 2), H1.0 and H2.0 (3 ng/μL) and H2.1 and 2.2 (2 ng/μL) were used for studies of male SMG lysate (25 μg) <lb/>(n = 6-9). Controls included no primary antibody, n = 3). B) Studies with mAb used 10 μg of lysate in each lane; for mAb 13G3 and <lb/>4D1 10 ng/μL and for 15B11, 1 ng/μL of mAb was used (n = 3). M is male and F is female. Controls with no primary mAb or with <lb/>isotype control mAb are shown and were negative. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>experiments showed a specific immunoreactive band(s) at ~61 in comparison to isotype controls <lb/>(S2 Fig). No signal was present when probing the membrane only with secondary antibody. <lb/>In summary, specific immunoreactive CABS1 was detected in serum at ~61kDa with mAb. <lb/>Immunohistochemical analysis of human testis and SMG <lb/>Because the only previous immunohistochemical studies of CABS1 were done with testes of <lb/>mice [19] and rats [20] and subsequently with pig [21], we conducted immunoperoxidase <lb/>Fig 5. Western blot analyses of CABS1 in human (male) saliva. A) In this experiment (pooled human saliva sample, n = 1, 2 to 4 independent <lb/>replicates), optimal specificity with pAb and preimmune serum (PimmS) was achieved at 2.2 μg of human saliva and 0.2 to 0.3 ng/μL of pAb and <lb/>preimmune sera and no primary antibody control. B) For mAb 13G3 10 ng/μL and for mAb 15B11 and 4D1 1 ng/μL were used together with 10 μg of <lb/>saliva (n = 3 for each mAb). Controls with no primary mAb or with isotype control mAb are shown. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>studies of hCABS1 in human testes for comparison. Thereafter, we investigated hCABS1 <lb/>expression by immunoperoxidase and immunofluorescence in human SMG. <lb/>Testes. Fig 6A, 6C and 6E show the normal morphology of a human testis stained with <lb/>H&amp;E. Seminiferous tubules (ST), interstitial Leydig cells (LC) and, within the tubules, primary <lb/>Fig 6. Immunohistochemical analyses of CABS1 in human testes. A) Low power photomicrograph of the connective <lb/>tissue of the tunica albuginea (TA), seminiferous tubules (ST), and Leydig cells (LC) stained with Hematoxylin &amp; Eosin <lb/>(H&amp;E). B) Low power photomicrograph of ST and LC stained with 15B11 monoclonal antibody to human CABS1. C) <lb/>H&amp;E staining of LC and, in ST, primary spermatogonia (SG), developing spermatocytes (DS) and supporting Sertoli <lb/>cells (SC) (prominent nucleoli). D) Similar image to C, stained with 15B11; note strong staining of LC, and also <lb/>staining of SG, DS and SC. E) H&amp;E stain of the cell types in ST, including spermatids (S). F). CABS1 staining observed <lb/>in seminiferous tubule showing positivity in SG, DS and S G) CABS1 staining including most intensely stained SG, <lb/>with less intense staining in DS and SC; luminal spermatids show variable staining. An adjacent artery (A) also exhibits <lb/>staining in the vascular smooth muscle (SM) and endothelium cells (EC). Ha) Negative control (secondary antibody <lb/>only; isotype controls were also negative) in cells of seminiferous tubules (upper) and (Hb) an adjacent artery. Bars on <lb/>each figure represent size in microns. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>spermatogonia (SG), Sertoli cells (SC), developing spermatocytes (DS) and spermatids (S) can <lb/>be seen (labels). Immunoreactivity using mAb 15B11 detected hCABS1 in LC in the interstitial <lb/>tissue of the testis (Fig 6B, 6D and 6F), and in SG in ST (Fig 6D, 6E and 6H). In some ST devel-<lb/>oping spermatids (S) were also positive for CABS1 immunoreactivity (Fig 6F). Controls done <lb/>with no primary antibody or with isotype control antibody were negative (Fig 6F top and <lb/>lower panel). <lb/>Submandibular glands. Normal morphology of the SMG is shown in Fig 7A and 7D at <lb/>increasing magnification. The lobular structure of the gland can be seen, as well as interlobular <lb/>connective tissue containing vasculature, and excretory ducts (ED). Within the lobes (L), <lb/>serous (SA) and mucous acini (MA) are evident, together with numerous smaller salivary <lb/>ducts (SD) in different planes of section. Using mAb 15B11, salivary ducts of all sizes had <lb/>hCABS1 immunoreactivity in epithelial cells (Fig 7B, 7E, 7G,7H and 7J) Controls with no pri-<lb/>mary antibody or with isotype control antibodies were negative for immunoreactivity <lb/>throughout the SMG (Fig 7C, 7F, 7I and 7L). SA cells were positive and the basal, paranuclear <lb/>regions of MA cells were positive for hCABS1 (Fig 7E); the mucous-containing regions of <lb/>these cells were negative for hCABS1. Interestingly, nerves (N) (Fig 7J and 7K) were hCABS1 <lb/>positive and some vessels had hCABS1 immunoreactivity in endothelial cells (EC, Fig 7K and <lb/>7F shows the negative control for EC). <lb/>Immunofluorescence (see Methods) staining of human submandibular gland sections with <lb/>pAbs H1.0 and H2.1 yielded a punctate pattern throughout the cytoplasm of duct cells (Fig <lb/>7M). Interestingly, pAbs H2.0 and H2.2 exhibited strong CABS1 immunoreactivity in the <lb/>cytoplasm of specific basal (abluminal, AB) epithelial duct cells (Fig 7N). Analyses of SMGs <lb/>immunostained with preimmune sera for the pAb gave no immunoreactivity (Fig 7O). Addi-<lb/>tional figures of our immunofluorescence studies are available in S3.4-S3.8 Fig. Moreover, as <lb/>with immunoperoxidase studies above, in immunofluorescence studies SA and MA were posi-<lb/>tive (S3.1 and S3.2 Fig), as were EC (S3.5 Fig). No obvious differences were detected in <lb/>hCABS1 protein expression in SMG resected from Sjogren&apos;s or cancer subjects (grossly normal <lb/>tissues selected, see Discussion). <lb/>GEOdata assessment of CABS1 tissue distribution and relative abundance <lb/>In our search of hCABS1 expression in different tissues in public domain transcriptome data-<lb/>bases, we selected three papers that surveyed numerous normal human tissues for gene expres-<lb/>sion [25-27]. Dezso et al (2008) [26] used the Applied Biosystems human genome microarray <lb/>of 27,868 genes and 31 normal tissues; She et al (2009) [25] used oligonucleotide arrays from <lb/>Agilent Technologies Inc, detected 18,149 genes from 42 normal human tissues; Wang et al <lb/>2019 [27] used the Illumina HiSeq 2000/2500 system and detected 18,702 protein-encoding <lb/>genes from 29 normal human tissues. Fig 8 summarizes the normalized relative abundance of <lb/>hCABS1 from the transcriptomic data from these three studies. CABS1 expression in testes is <lb/>the best studied of the tissues, but CABS1 mRNA has been found throughout the urogenital, <lb/>gastrointestinal and respiratory tracts, as well as in glands, the nervous system, immune system <lb/>and other sites. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>To validate and extend our previous studies with WB [18, 22] and NCIA [24], we described <lb/>studies of hCABS1 in transient overexpression lysate (OEL), SMG lysates, saliva, serum and <lb/>testis using pAb and mAb. WB and immunohistochemistry studies were used together with <lb/>GEOdata analyses to validate our observations of hCABS1 in these tissues and fluids. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 7. Immunohistochemical analyses of CABS1 in human submandibular glands. A) H&amp;E staining showing lobules (L) of the <lb/>gland together with the excretory salivary duct (ED) in interlobular connective tissue. Within the glandular tissue of the L there are <lb/>sections of smaller collecting salivary ducts (SD) among acini (see below) and associated vasculature. B) Similar section showing <lb/>CABS1 staining of ducts and acini as well as nerve (N). C) Similar section viewed with negative control staining (no primary <lb/>antibody; isotype controls were also negative). D) H&amp;E staining of serous (SA) and mucous acini (MA) and associated SD. E) Tissue <lb/>section similar to D) with CABS1 staining of SD, SA and MA. Mucin is negative. F) Negative control showing acini and thin-walled <lb/>vessel (V), consistent with a capillary. G) CABS1 staining in ED. H) Higher magnification of CABS1 staining in ED epithelium. I) <lb/>Negative control for CABS1 staining in the ED. J) CABS1 staining in nerves (N) within the salivary gland. Also shown is an artery <lb/>(A), and SD. K) CABS1 staining in N as well as in V endothelium. L) Negative control view (no primary antibody, isotype control <lb/>negative as well). M and N) Selective immunofluorescent staining of CABS1 (rabbit polyclonal antibodies H2.1 and H2.2, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>The results of WB studies of OEL conducted with pAb and mAb as well as anti-FLAG anti-<lb/>body are summarized in Table 1. Our previous results using NCIA [24] are also included for <lb/>comparison, as well as the distribution of CABS1 peptides, determined by MS-seq in various <lb/>sections (M r ranges) of a 1 D gel (Table 1). M r estimates of 84 and 78 are likely to be the same <lb/>immunoreactive band given time differences between studies with pAb and mAb, other poten-<lb/>tial technical differences, and methods of M r calculation. Indeed, results with anti-FLAG anti-<lb/>body confirm that 84 (pAb) = 78 (mAb) (see Fig 2B, 4D1). <lb/>For WB studies, estimated M r values are for specific immunoreactive bands detected in <lb/>OEL; no hCABS1 specific bands were detected in NCL (normal control lysate). Several com-<lb/>mercial batches of OEL lysate were used (n = 7), and it is possible (but cannot be confirmed) <lb/>that some of the differences in M r between results with pAb and mAb could reflect differences <lb/>among batches of OEL. M r estimates for pAb studies were derived from LI-COR software, <lb/>whereas for mAb studies estimates were from manual calculations, as the LI-COR software <lb/>was no longer available for our use. The commercial supplier of NCIA Wes™ estimates that <lb/>given their separation matrix, estimates of M r may vary by up to 20% from those derived from <lb/>SDS PAGE separations [24]. The anti-FLAG results were positive controls run with either the <lb/>pAb or mAb WB studies and involved a single source of mAb anti-FLAG. <lb/>MS shows CABS1 fragments in six segments of the 1 D gel ranging from 119-85 kDa to 16-<lb/>11 kDa. Given the peptides identified in gel segments, there is no evidence of selective <lb/>respectively). H2.2 and H2.0 (see also S3.4-S3.8 Fig) showed selective cellular cytoplasmic staining abluminal cells (AB) in the basal <lb/>regions of the epithelium of ED, whereas H2.1 stained the cytoplasm of cells throughout the epithelium. Controls with preimmune <lb/>sera (e.g. H2.2, O) or no primary antibody were negative. Bars on each figure represent size in microns. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g007 <lb/>Fig 8. Meta-analysis of the distribution of CABS1 in normal human tissue across three studies. Each study is represented in a row, and tissues are <lb/>represented in columns. Tissues are grouped in their respective biological system. CABS1 GEOdata was extracted and normalized by dividing each <lb/>expression read by the maximum value observed across tissues within the same study. The normalized percentage of CABS1 expression is shown on a <lb/>continuous graded scale ranging from 0% (grey) to more than 50% (green), as indicated by the color key. A diagonal line in a box indicates the lack of <lb/>data within that tissue. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>fragmentation, i.e., existence of specific portions of CABS1 in distinct gel fragments (data <lb/>repository folder, mass spectroscopy section). <lb/>We have previously published our results with pAbs on immunoreactive bands of hCABS1 <lb/>in SMG lysates [18]. Multiple bands were detected with H2.0 and other pAb, including: bands <lb/>at 51, 33, 27, and, in some SMG lysates, at 20, 17, 16 and 11 kDa. In the present study with <lb/>SMG lysate and using H1.0, 2.0, 2.1, and 2.2 anti-CABS1 pAbs, specific immunoreactive bands <lb/>were detected with at least three of four pAbs at ~71, 52 and 27 kDa (Fig 4A; Table 2). <lb/>With at least two of three anti-CABS1 mAbs, immunoreactive bands were found in SMG <lb/>lysate at 63 and 53 kDa (Fig 4B, Table 2). Human CABS1 immunoreactive bands were detected <lb/>using pAbs and mAbs in saliva at similar molecular sizes, 60 to 63 and 52 to 53 kDa, results <lb/>consistent with our earlier report using NCIA [24] (Table 2). Moreover, using mass spectros-<lb/>copy, rhCABS1 was detected in OEL at 120-85, 84-60, 59-40, 39-22 and 16-11 kDa (Table 1). <lb/>Two of three mAbs identified a specific immunoreactive band in serum at ~61 kDa (S2 Fig). <lb/>However, with four pAbs numerous bands were detected in a serum pool and no obvious <lb/>reproducible profile could be identified. Interestingly, CABS1 has been detected in human <lb/>serum by others using mass spectroscopy, although only a single peptide was identified that <lb/>covered 3.54% of the protein [28]. <lb/>With the newly optimized antigen and pAb concentrations, in contrast to previous work <lb/>[18, 22], we only detected a faint specific band at ~27 kDa in saliva (Table 2). However, a 27 <lb/>Table 1. Estimated M r of CABS1 detected in transient overexpression lysate (OEL) by pAb and mAb in WB and <lb/>nano-capillary immunoassay (NCIA) and by mass spectroscopy (MS). <lb/>Technique <lb/>Antibody Name <lb/>M r (kDa) <lb/>WB pAb <lb/>H1.0 <lb/>84, 67 <lb/>H2.0 <lb/>84, 67 <lb/>H2.1 <lb/>84 <lb/>H2.2 <lb/>84, 67 <lb/>Anti-Flag (+ve Control) <lb/>84, 67 <lb/>MS <lb/>119-85, 84-60, 59-40, 39-33, 32-22, 16-11 <lb/>WB mAb <lb/>13G3 <lb/>78 <lb/>15B11 <lb/>78 <lb/>4D1 <lb/>78 <lb/>Anti-Flag (+ve Control) <lb/>78 <lb/>NCIA <lb/>H1.0 <lb/>94, 65 <lb/>H2.0 <lb/>94, 65 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.t001 <lb/>Table 2. Molecular size estimates of human-specific CABS1 immunoreactivity (polyclonal and monoclonal antibodies) in submandibular gland lysate, saliva and <lb/>serum*. <lb/>Polyclonal Ab <lb/>H1.0 <lb/>H2.0 <lb/>H2.1 <lb/>H2.2 <lb/>Monoclonal Ab <lb/>13G3 <lb/>15B11 <lb/>4D1 <lb/>Submandibular Gland Lysate <lb/>52, 27 <lb/>63, 53 <lb/>71, 52, 27 <lb/>53 <lb/>71, 52, 27 <lb/>63, 53 <lb/>71, 52 <lb/>Saliva <lb/>60 <lb/>60 <lb/>60 <lb/>60 <lb/>NA <lb/>60 <lb/>NA <lb/>NCIA (Saliva) <lb/>60 <lb/>NA <lb/>58, 34 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Serum # <lb/>NA <lb/>61 <lb/>NA <lb/>ND <lb/>NA <lb/>61 <lb/>NA <lb/>*Summary from Figs 4 and 5, and S2 Fig. <lb/># Pilot study (n = 1); multiple bands, no obvious consistency with pAb, labeled Not Applicable (NA). Not detected bands were labeled Not Detected (ND). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>kDa band was detected in SMG lysate, in mass spectroscopy of OEL (32-22 kDa gel fragment) <lb/>and in NCIA (34 kDa given the different gel matrices used, allowing for up to 20% differences <lb/>in M r estimation between polyacrylamide gels and NCIA, see above). <lb/>The challenge in detecting a strong 27 kDa band in human saliva using our newly opti-<lb/>mized pAb protocol, and mAb, may be explained by low abundance of this form of the protein. <lb/>Mass spectroscopic analysis of the entire full gel electrophoresis column of OEL showed that <lb/>the highest CABS1 expression levels were for molecules in the 84-60 kDa range (Fig 3). The <lb/>second highest detected range was 6 times lower expression levels in the 39-33 kDa range. <lb/>Although CABS1 peptides were detected at lower molecular weights, the abundance decreased <lb/>to 19 times lower for the 32-22 kDa range. The concentration of saliva (2.2 μg/well) and pAb <lb/>(0.3 ng/μL) that yielded highest specificity in WB profiles in our newly optimized protocol was <lb/>much lower than concentrations we used in previous pAb studies (saliva, 25 μg; pAb 3 ng/μL) <lb/>[18]. A combination of lower saliva sample concentration, lower pAb and mAb concentra-<lb/>tions, and low relative abundance of 27 kDa CABS1 could explain our ability to detect only a <lb/>faint band of this potential form of CABS1 in saliva. However, it is also possible that our earlier <lb/>results [18] were incorrect. Thus, we are unable to confirm the presence of a relatively abun-<lb/>dant 27 kDa CABS1 form in human saliva. This raises concerns about whether the 27 kDa <lb/>molecular form that we reported to be associated with acute stress is indeed hCABS1; a ques-<lb/>tion that remains pending until new studies are conducted and replicated by others. Regretta-<lb/>bly, we have been unable to sequence hCABS1 from human SMG and saliva using mass <lb/>spectroscopy, possibly because of its low abundance proportionate to other proteins. However, <lb/>our immunohistochemical and GEOdata studies confirm the presence of CABS1 in human <lb/>SMG (see below). <lb/>A limitation of our studies is that they were conducted over 6 years with several pAb and <lb/>mAb and with several samples of OEL and NCL (n = 7 to 8), and SMG lysates (n = 8, S2 <lb/>Table). For serum and saliva, care was taken to create sample pools that were aliquoted and <lb/>frozen (-80˚C), and not repeatedly frozen and thawed. WB optimization protocols varied <lb/>among antibodies and samples but were established with careful titrations. Moreover, although <lb/>M r standards were routinely used, the methods for identification of M r of immunoreactive <lb/>bands varied; initially this was done using the LI-COR software, but beginning in 2019 molec-<lb/>ular weights were calculated manually, as the LI-COR software was no longer available to us. <lb/>These many issues likely influenced the variability encountered in M r estimates using WB. <lb/>Furthermore, it was well-recognized that CABS1 is a structurally disordered protein with con-<lb/>formational plasticity [19, 20, 29-31] and variable estimates of M r of the putatively mature pro-<lb/>tein (66 to 79 kDa), considerably different from that predicted for the newly translated <lb/>polypeptide (42 kDa). This flexible, disordered structure, although potentially of functional <lb/>significance, may also contribute to the variability in M r that we detected among the tissues <lb/>and fluids studied. Another component of the variability in M r for hCABS1 may involve the <lb/>cell of its origin in the tissues (e.g., spermatogonia, epithelium, nerves, etc.), cell type-specific <lb/>processing and CABS1 interactions with charged ligands [29]. <lb/>As previous literature on the cellular localization of CABS1 protein focused on testes in <lb/>rodents [19, 20] and pigs [21], we conducted the first immunohistochemical cellular localiza-<lb/>tion of CABS1 in human testes (Fig 6). An earlier study had indicated that CABS1 mRNA was <lb/>abundant in human testes [32]. We found CABS1 in developing DS, S, in human ST (Fig 6). <lb/>Interestingly, unlike previous rodent and porcine studies, CABS1 was also found in SG, SC <lb/>and LC in human testes. In mice [19] and rats [20] CABS1 was found in late phases of sperma-<lb/>tid development, including in the inner mitochondrial membrane in rats [20] and in the flagel-<lb/>lum in mature sperm [19]. In the pig, CABS1 was found in elongated spermatids and sperm, <lb/>specifically in the principal and end piece of the flagellum, as well as in the acrosome [22]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Interestingly, the shedding of the porcine acrosome (acrosomal reaction) includes the loss of <lb/>CABS1, and the acrosomal reaction can be inhibited by anti-CABS1 antibodies, without an <lb/>effect on sperm viability [22]. The knockdown of CABS1 in mice disrupted sperm tail struc-<lb/>ture, induced an abnormality in the flagellum, specifically at the midpiece-principal region <lb/>junction, and reduced fertility [33]. Taken together this evidence from rat, mouse and pig sug-<lb/>gests that CABS1 is involved in spermatogenesis, sperm motility and the acrosomal reaction. <lb/>Given the presence of CABS1 in human SG, SC and LC, but not these locations in mice, rats <lb/>and pigs, CABS1 may play additional roles in male reproduction in humans, perhaps in associ-<lb/>ation with the unique expression of a peptide sequence near the carboxyl terminus in selected <lb/>primates [29] that has anti-inflammatory activity [18]. <lb/>There are few reports of hCABS1 in the human female urogenital tract [34, 35], although as <lb/>shown in Fig 8, there are numerous reports of CABS1 mRNA. In transcriptomic [25-27] anal-<lb/>yses of healthy human tissues, hCABS1 was identified in endometrium, ovary, fallopian tubes, <lb/>placenta, cervix and urinary bladder. Cerny et al. [34] showed in bovine oviductal epithelial <lb/>cells that levels of CABS1 transcript changed during the estrous cycle. Moreover, Calhoun <lb/>et al. [35] showed that exposure to the toxin bisphenol A during fetal development altered <lb/>CABS1 expression in the fetal uterus and suggested that this may influence uterine function <lb/>later in life. Clearly, much needs to be learned about the roles of CABS1 in reproductive <lb/>physiology. <lb/>Interestingly, our immunohistochemical studies detected human CABS1 in several anatom-<lb/>ical compartments and cell types of SMG, including epithelial cells of SA, MA and SD and ED. <lb/>Connecting hCABS1 to a potential anti-inflammatory role in humans, it has been reported <lb/>that in Sjogren&apos;s syndrome, an autoimmune inflammation of the salivary glands, CABS1 <lb/>mRNA levels were decreased 5.4-fold in comparison to normal [36]. This reduction in <lb/>hCABS1 mRNA in Sjogren&apos;s syndrome was confirmed with laser capture microdissection of <lb/>the acinar and ductal epithelium of minor labial salivary glands [37]. Our immunofluorescence <lb/>studies did not detect obvious differences in CABS1 abundance between SMG from Sjogren&apos;s <lb/>subjects or normal tissue regions from surgical resections for cancer. <lb/>Our observations that nerves and vascular endothelium and smooth muscle in SMG are <lb/>also CABS1 positive are novel observations, further supported by GEOdata sets that identify <lb/>CABS1 in SMG, nerves, endothelium and smooth muscle [25-27]. These studies also suggest <lb/>that hCABS1 is widely distributed in many other tissues including liver, gastrointestinal tract, <lb/>respiratory tract, neuro, endocrine and immune systems. Given the structural plasticity of <lb/>CABS1, its widespread tissue distribution and apparent functional diversity, e.g., from sper-<lb/>matogenesis to anti-inflammatory activities, it is imperative to identify the specific cell types <lb/>that express CABS1 and its functions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Binding of mAb 4D1 to peptide 3 (AA 40-60) of CABS1. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Western blot analyses of CABS1 in human (male) serum. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Immunofluorescence studies of submandibular glands. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Table. Glossary of abbreviations. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S2 Table. Human testes and submandibular gland samples. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 File. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S6 File. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We wish to thank Sarah Canill, Alberta Precision Laboratories, and Yong-Qiu Doughman, <lb/>Case Western Reserve University for assistance with immunohistochemical studies. Mr. Cam-<lb/>eron Lloyd, Anatomical Pathology, University of Alberta Hospital was instrumental in identifi-<lb/>cation of archived tissue specimens. Mr. Jack Moore and Dr. Richard Fahlman of The Alberta <lb/>Proteomics and Mass Spectroscopy Facilities were invaluable in the mass spectroscopy analysis <lb/>of samples. Christopher St. Laurent, University of Alberta, assisted with western blot analyses. <lb/>ER-S received graduate studentships from the Faculties of Graduate Studies and Research, and <lb/>Medicine and Dentistry, University of Alberta. MM-P received funding from the Natural Sci-<lb/>ences and Engineering Research Council, Canada. ADB received funding from AllerGen NCE <lb/>Inc, Canada. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Aron Gonshor, Robert <lb/>Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Data curation: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, Mechiko <lb/>Watanabe, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Formal analysis: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, <lb/>Mechiko Watanabe, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Funding acquisition: A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Investigation: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, Mechiko <lb/>Watanabe, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Methodology: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, Mechiko <lb/>Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Project administration: Lakshmi Puttagunta, Mechiko Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert <lb/>Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Resources: Lakshmi Puttagunta, Stephen J. Lewis, Mechiko Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert <lb/>Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Software: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, A. Dean <lb/>Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Supervision: Mechiko Watanabe, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Validation: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, Stephen J. <lb/>Lewis, Mechiko Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-<lb/>Palacios. <lb/>Visualization: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Puttagunta, Mechiko <lb/>Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Putta-<lb/>gunta, A. Dean Befus, Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Eduardo Reyes-Serratos, Joy Ramielle L. Santos, Lakshmi Putta-<lb/>gunta, Stephen J. Lewis, Mechiko Watanabe, Aron Gonshor, Robert Buck, A. Dean Befus, <lb/>Marcelo Marcet-Palacios. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Ramaswamy K, Mathison R, Carter L, Kirk D, Green F, Davison JS, et al. Marked antiinflammatory <lb/>effects of decentralization of the superior cervical ganglia. J Exp Med. 1990; 172(6):1819-30. Epub <lb/>1990/12/01. https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.172.6.1819 PMID: 2258709. <lb/>2. Mathison R, Davison JS, Befus AD. Neuroendocrine regulation of inflammation and tissue repair by <lb/>submandibular gland factors. Immunol Today. 1994; 15(11):527-32. Epub 1994/11/01. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/0167-5699(94)90209-7 PMID: 7802923. <lb/>3. Mathison RD, Befus AD, Davison JS. A novel submandibular gland peptide protects against endotoxic <lb/>and anaphylactic shock. Am J Physiol. 1997; 273(3 Pt 2):R1017-23. Epub 1997/10/10. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1152/ajpregu.1997.273.3.R1017 PMID: 9321881. <lb/>4. Mathison RD, Davison JS, St Laurent CD, Befus AD. Autonomic regulation of anti-inflammatory activi-<lb/>ties from salivary glands. Chem Immunol Allergy. 2012; 98:176-95. Epub 2012/07/07. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1159/000336513 PMID: 22767064. <lb/>5. Rosinski-Chupin I, Rougeot C, Courty Y, Rougeon F. Localization of mRNAs of two androgen-depen-<lb/>dent proteins, SMR1 and SMR2, by in situ hybridization reveals sexual differences in acinar cells of rat <lb/>submandibular gland. J Histochem Cytochem. 1993; 41(11):1645-9. Epub 1993/11/01. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1177/41.11.8409372 PMID: 8409372. <lb/>6. Rosinski-Chupin I, Tronik D, Rougeon F. High level of accumulation of a mRNA coding for a precursor-<lb/>like protein in the submaxillary gland of male rats. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1988; 85(22):8553-7. <lb/>Epub 1988/11/01. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.85.22.8553 PMID: 3186744. <lb/>7. Rougeot C, Rosinski-Chupin I, Njamkepo E, Rougeon F. Selective processing of submandibular rat 1 <lb/>protein at dibasic cleavage sites. Salivary and bloodstream secretion products. Eur J Biochem. 1994; <lb/>219(3):765-73. Epub 1994/02/01. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1432-1033.1994.tb18556.x PMID: <lb/>8112327. <lb/>8. Rougeot C, Vienet R, Cardona A, Le Doledec L, Grognet JM, Rougeon F. Targets for SMR1-pentapep-<lb/>tide suggest a link between the circulating peptide and mineral transport. Am J Physiol. 1997; 273(4): <lb/>R1309-20. Epub 1997/11/15. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpregu.1997.273.4.R1309 PMID: 9362294. <lb/>9. Rougeot C, Messaoudi M, Hermitte V, Rigault AG, Blisnick T, Dugave C, et al. Sialorphin, a natural <lb/>inhibitor of rat membrane-bound neutral endopeptidase that displays analgesic activity. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci U S A. 2003; 100(14):8549-54. Epub 2003/07/02. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1431850100 PMID: <lb/>12835417. <lb/>10. Messaoudi M, Desor D, Nejdi A, Rougeot C. The endogenous androgen-regulated sialorphin modulates <lb/>male rat sexual behavior. Horm Behav. 2004; 46(5):684-91. Epub 2004/11/24. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>j.yhbeh.2004.06.012 PMID: 15555512. <lb/>11. Davies KP, Tar M, Rougeot C, Melman A. Sialorphin (the mature peptide product of Vcsa1) relaxes cor-<lb/>poral smooth muscle tissue and increases erectile function in the ageing rat. BJU Int. 2007; 99(2):431-<lb/>5. Epub 2006/10/10. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-410X.2006.06577.x PMID: 17026587. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>12. Mathison R, Davison JS, De Sanctis G, Green F, Befus DA. Decentralization of the superior cervical <lb/>ganglia and the immediate hypersensitivity response. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med. 1992; 200(4):542-7. <lb/>Epub 1992/09/01. https://doi.org/10.3181/00379727-200-43468 PMID: 1508947. <lb/>13. Mathison R, Befus D, Davison JS. Removal of the submandibular glands increases the acute hypoten-<lb/>sive response to endotoxin. Circ Shock. 1993; 39(1):52-8.PMID: 8481976 Epub 1993/01/01. 8481976. <lb/>14. Dery RE, Ulanova M, Puttagunta L, Stenton GR, James D, Merani S, et al. Frontline: Inhibition of aller-<lb/>gen-induced pulmonary inflammation by the tripeptide feG: a mimetic of a neuro-endocrine pathway. <lb/>Eur J Immunol. 2004; 34(12):3315-25. Epub 2004/11/19. https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.200425461 PMID: <lb/>15549777. <lb/>15. Mathison R, Davison J, Befus A, Abraham W. The tripeptide feG inhibits asthmatic reactions in sheep. <lb/>Immunology. 2004:515-9. <lb/>16. Bao F, John SM, Chen Y, Mathison RD, Weaver LC. The tripeptide phenylalanine-(D) glutamate-(D) <lb/>glycine modulates leukocyte infiltration and oxidative damage in rat injured spinal cord. Neuroscience. <lb/>2006; 140(3):1011-22. Epub 2006/04/04. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2006.02.061 PMID: <lb/>16581192. <lb/>17. Morris K, Kuo B, Wilkinson MD, Davison JS, Befus AD, Mathison RD. Vcsa1 gene peptides for the treat-<lb/>ment of inflammatory and allergic reactions. Recent Pat Inflamm Allergy Drug Discov. 2007; 1(2):124-<lb/>32. Epub 2007/01/01. https://doi.org/10.2174/187221307780979892 PMID: 19075974. <lb/>18. St Laurent CD, St Laurent KE, Mathison RD, Befus AD. Calcium-binding protein, spermatid-specific 1 is <lb/>expressed in human salivary glands and contains an anti-inflammatory motif. Am J Physiol Regul Integr <lb/>Comp Physiol. 2015; 308(7):R569-75. Epub 2015/01/30. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpregu.00153.2014 <lb/>PMID: 25632019. <lb/>19. Kawashima A, Osman BA, Takashima M, Kikuchi A, Kohchi S, Satoh E, et al. CABS1 is a novel <lb/>calcium-binding protein specifically expressed in elongate spermatids of mice. Biol Reprod. 2009; <lb/>80(6):1293-304. Epub 2009/02/12. https://doi.org/10.1095/biolreprod.108.073866 PMID: <lb/>19208547. <lb/>20. Calvel P, Kervarrec C, Lavigne R, Vallet-Erdtmann V, Guerrois M, Rolland AD, et al. CLPH, a novel <lb/>casein kinase 2-phosphorylated disordered protein, is specifically associated with postmeiotic germ <lb/>cells in rat spermatogenesis. J Proteome Res. 2009; 8(6):2953-65. Epub 2009/03/11. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1021/pr900082m PMID: 19271754. <lb/>21. Shawki HH, Kigoshi T, Katoh Y, Matsuda M, Ugboma CM, Takahashi S, et al. Identification, localization, <lb/>and functional analysis of the homologues of mouse CABS1 protein in porcine testis. Exp Anim. 2016; <lb/>65(3):253-65. Epub 2016/03/11. https://doi.org/10.1538/expanim.15-0104 PMID: 26960363. <lb/>22. Ritz T, Rosenfield D, St Laurent CD, Trueba AF, Werchan CA, Vogel PD, et al. A novel biomarker asso-<lb/>ciated with distress in humans: calcium-binding protein, spermatid-specific 1 (CABS1). Am J Physiol <lb/>Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2017; 312(6):R1004-R16. Epub 2017/04/07. https://doi.org/10.1152/ <lb/>ajpregu.00393.2016 PMID: 28381457. <lb/>23. Reyes Serratos EA. The perplexity of calcium-binding protein, spermatid-associated 1 (CABS1): A mol-<lb/>ecule that despite its name, is present beyond the reproductive tract, with ties to stress, and possessing <lb/>an anti-inflammatory domain only preserved in simians. 2022:1-276. https://doi.org/10.7939/r3-sjxy-<lb/>mk85,. PhD Thesis. University of Alberta. <lb/>24. Reyes-Serratos E, Marcet-Palacios M, Rosenfield D, Ritz T, Befus AD. A method to study protein bio-<lb/>markers in saliva using an automated capillary nano-immunoassay platform (Wes). J Immunol Meth-<lb/>ods. 2020; 479:112749. Epub 2020/01/24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jim.2020.112749 PMID: <lb/>31972214. <lb/>25. She X, Rohl CA, Castle JC, Kulkarni AV, Johnson JM, Chen R. Definition, conservation and epigenetics <lb/>of housekeeping and tissue-enriched genes. BMC Genomics. 2009; 10:269. Epub 2009/06/19. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-10-269 PMID: 19534766. <lb/>26. Dezso Z, Nikolsky Y, Sviridov E, Shi W, Serebriyskaya T, Dosymbekov D, et al. A comprehensive func-<lb/>tional analysis of tissue specificity of human gene expression. BMC Biol. 2008; 6:49. Epub 2008/11/19. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1741-7007-6-49 PMID: 19014478. <lb/>27. Wang D, Eraslan B, Wieland T, Hallstrom B, Hopf T, Zolg DP, et al. A deep proteome and transcriptome <lb/>abundance atlas of 29 healthy human tissues. Mol Syst Biol. 2019; 15(2):e8503. Epub 2019/02/20. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.15252/msb.20188503 PMID: 30777892. <lb/>28. Jin WH, Dai J, Li SJ, Xia QC, Zou HF, Zeng R. Human plasma proteome analysis by multidimensional <lb/>chromatography prefractionation and linear ion trap mass spectrometry identification. J Proteome Res. <lb/>2005; 4(2):613-9. Epub 2005/04/13. https://doi.org/10.1021/pr049761h PMID: 15822942. <lb/>29. Marcet-Palacios M, Reyes-Serratos E, Gonshor A, Buck R, Lacy P, Befus AD. Structural and posttrans-<lb/>lational analysis of human calcium-binding protein, spermatid-associated 1. J Cell Biochem. 2020. <lb/>Epub 2020/07/22. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcb.29824 PMID: 32692864. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>30. Burger VM, Nolasco DO, Stultz CM. Expanding the range of protein function at the far end of the order-<lb/>structure continuum. J Biol Chem. 2016; 291(13):6706-13. Epub 2016/02/07. https://doi.org/10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.R115.692590 PMID: 26851282. <lb/>31. Trivedi R, Nagarajaram HA. Intrinsically disordered proteins: an overview. Int J Mol Sci. 2022; 23(22). <lb/>Epub 2022/11/27. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms232214050 PMID: 36430530. <lb/>32. Jiahao S, Zuomin Z, Jianmin P. Preparation of human testicular cDNA microarray and initial research of <lb/>gene expression library related to spermatogenesis. Chan HS Epithelial Cell Biology-A Primer Beijing: <lb/>Press of Military Medical Science. 2000:274-7. <lb/>33. Zhang X, Zhou W, Zhang P, Gao F, Zhao X, Shum WW, et al. Cabs1 maintains structural integrity of <lb/>mouse sperm flagella during epididymal transit of sperm. Int J Mol Sci. 2021; 22(2). Epub 2021/01/15. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22020652 PMID: 33440775. <lb/>34. Cerny KL, Garrett E, Walton AJ, Anderson LH, Bridges PJ. A transcriptomal analysis of bovine oviductal <lb/>epithelial cells collected during the follicular phase versus the luteal phase of the estrous cycle. Reprod <lb/>Biol Endocrinol. 2015; 13:84. Epub 2015/08/06. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12958-015-0077-1 PMID: <lb/>26242217. <lb/>35. Calhoun KC, Padilla-Banks E, Jefferson WN, Liu L, Gerrish KE, Young SL, et al. Bisphenol A exposure <lb/>alters developmental gene expression in the fetal rhesus macaque uterus. PLoS One. 2014; 9(1): <lb/>e85894. Epub 2014/01/28. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0085894 PMID: 24465770. <lb/>36. Shi H, Cao N, Pu Y, Xie L, Zheng L, Yu C. Long non-coding RNA expression profile in minor salivary <lb/>gland of primary Sjogren&apos;s syndrome. Arthritis Res Ther. 2016; 18(1):109. Epub 2016/05/18. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1186/s13075-016-1005-2 PMID: 27188286. <lb/>37. Dela Cruz A, Kartha V, Tilston-Lunel A, Mi R, Reynolds TL, Mingueneau M, et al. Gene expression alter-<lb/>ations in salivary gland epithelia of Sjogren&apos;s syndrome patients are associated with clinical and histo-<lb/>pathological manifestations. Sci Rep. 2021; 11(1):11154. Epub 2021/05/29. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41598-021-90569-w PMID: 34045583. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>(CABS1) # expression in human tissues and fluids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0301855 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 22 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>