<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-19T14:58:02.350Z">11/19/2025 2:58:02 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-19T14:57:51.714570Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-19T14:57:51.714570Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Overexpression of the flagellar motor protein <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to <lb/>aminoglycosides in a motility-independent <lb/>manner <lb/>Mio Uneme, Kazuya Ishikawa, Kazuyuki Furuta, Atsuko Yamashita ID , Chikara Kaito ID * <lb/>Graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Okayama University, Okayama, <lb/>Japan <lb/>* ckaito@okayama-u.ac.jp <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The flagellar motor proteins, MotA and MotB, form a complex that rotates the flagella by uti-<lb/>lizing the proton motive force (PMF) at the bacterial cell membrane. Although PMF affects <lb/>the susceptibility to aminoglycosides, the effect of flagellar motor proteins on the susceptibil-<lb/>ity to aminoglycosides has not been investigated. Here, we found that MotB overexpression <lb/>increased susceptibility to aminoglycosides, such as kanamycin and gentamicin, in Bacillus <lb/>subtilis without affecting swimming motility. MotB overexpression did not affect susceptibility <lb/>to ribosome-targeting antibiotics other than aminoglycosides, cell wall-targeting antibiotics, <lb/>DNA synthesis-inhibiting antibiotics, or antibiotics inhibiting RNA synthesis. Meanwhile, <lb/>MotB overexpression increased the susceptibility to aminoglycosides even in the motA-<lb/>deletion mutant, which lacks swimming motility. Overexpression of the MotB mutant protein <lb/>carrying an amino acid substitution at the proton-binding site (D24A) resulted in the loss of <lb/>the enhanced aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. These results suggested that MotB <lb/>overexpression sensitizes B. subtilis to aminoglycosides in a motility-independent manner. <lb/>Notably, the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype induced by MotB requires the proton-bind-<lb/>ing site but not the MotA/MotB complex formation. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>The efficacy of antimicrobials is affected by various cellular activities, including drug uptake <lb/>and efflux, degradation, changes in drug targets, and respiratory pathways. Identifying bacte-<lb/>rial factors that affect antibiotic efficacy is important for developing novel drugs that suppress <lb/>antibiotic-resistant bacteria. <lb/>Aminoglycosides are bactericidal antibiotics used against Gram-negative and Gram-posi-<lb/>tive bacteria. Aminoglycosides target the 30S subunit of the ribosome and exert their bacteri-<lb/>cidal activity by inhibiting protein synthesis [1,2]. The bactericidal activity of aminoglycosides <lb/>requires the proton motive force (PMF) of the bacterial cell membrane [3-5]. The reason why <lb/>PMF is required for the action of aminoglycosides is largely unclear, although it is widely <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/>1 / 19 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Uneme M, Ishikawa K, Furuta K, <lb/>Yamashita A, Kaito C (2024) Overexpression of the <lb/>flagellar motor protein MotB sensitizes Bacillus <lb/>subtilis to aminoglycosides in a motility-<lb/>independent manner. PLoS ONE 19(4): e0300634. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 <lb/>Editor: Pushkar P Lele, Texas A&amp;M University, <lb/>UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: October 13, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: March 2, 2024 <lb/>Published: April 26, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Uneme et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>information files. <lb/></front>

	<body>accepted that the uptake of positively charged aminoglycosides requires an electric potential <lb/>difference between the inside and outside of the bacterial cell membrane [4]. Several studies <lb/>have proposed that the reactive oxygen species produced by aerobic respiration [6] or dysregu-<lb/>lation of the electric potential of the bacterial cell membrane [7] affect the bactericidal action <lb/>of aminoglycosides. In both cases, the PMF of the bacterial cell membrane played an important <lb/>role in the efficacy of aminoglycosides. Previous studies have revealed that mutations in the <lb/>electron transport complex [8,9] or F1Fo-ATP synthase [7,10,11], which directly change PMF, <lb/>alter susceptibility to aminoglycosides or its uptake. However, other bacterial factors that affect <lb/>the electric potential difference in the bacterial cell membrane and susceptibility to aminogly-<lb/>cosides have not been identified. <lb/>Many bacterial species use their flagella to move in liquid or host environments [12]. The <lb/>bacterial flagellum is a multi-protein complex comprising more than 25 proteins, but its basic <lb/>structure and rotating mechanism are well conserved across bacterial genera. The bacterial fla-<lb/>gellum has three components: basal body, hook, and filament [13]. The basal body is embed-<lb/>ded in the bacterial cell membrane and functions as a motor. The hook connects the basal <lb/>body to the filament and transmits the torque generated by the motor to the filament protrud-<lb/>ing outside the cell [14]. The driving force of the flagellar motor is the flow of ions through the <lb/>stator complexes of the flagellar motor. The flagellar stator is a hetero-heptameric membrane <lb/>protein complex consisting of five A subunits and two B subunits [15,16]. Escherichia coli and <lb/>Salmonella spp. have a proton-driven stator, MotA/MotB, whereas Vibrio spp. in the oceanic <lb/>environment have a sodium ion-driven stator, PomA/PomB [17-20]. Bacillus subtilis uses <lb/>both stator complexes, proton-driven MotA/MotB and sodium ion-driven MotP/MotS [YtxD/ <lb/>YtxE], in response to the external environment [21-23]. <lb/>We hypothesized that proton transfer by MotA/MotB affects bacterial susceptibility to ami-<lb/>noglycosides. Here, we demonstrated that the overexpression of MotB sensitizes B. subtilis to <lb/>aminoglycosides. Unexpectedly, the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype induced by MotB did <lb/>not require the formation of a complex with MotA. Furthermore, MotB overexpression <lb/>increased the sensitivity to aminoglycosides without affecting B. subtilis motility. We propose <lb/>that overexpressed MotB increases the susceptibility to aminoglycosides in a motility-indepen-<lb/>dent manner. Moreover, we provide an implication for the link between motor proteins and <lb/>antibiotic susceptibility. <lb/>Results <lb/>Overexpression of MotB makes B. subtilis sensitive to aminoglycosides <lb/>without affecting the motility <lb/>We examined the effects of MotA and MotB on the susceptibility of B. subtilis to aminoglyco-<lb/>sides. The motA-and motB-deletion mutants showed survival similar to that of the wildtype <lb/>strain in the presence of kanamycin or gentamicin (Fig 1A). In contrast, the MotB-overex-<lb/>pressed strain displayed decreased survival in the presence of kanamycin or gentamicin com-<lb/>pared to the vector-transformed strain but showed similar survival or growth to the vector-<lb/>transformed strain in the absence of these antibiotics (Fig 1B and S1 Fig). The survival of the <lb/>MotA-overexpressed strain was similar to that of the vector-transformed strain in the presence <lb/>of kanamycin or gentamicin (Fig 1B). In the presence of kanamycin, the strain that overex-<lb/>pressed both MotA and MotB showed decreased survival compared to the vector-transformed <lb/>strain but showed survival similar to that of the MotB-overexpressed strain (Fig 1B). These <lb/>results suggested that MotB overexpression sensitizes B. subtilis to aminoglycosides, but MotA <lb/>overexpression does not. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<front>Funding: This study was supported by JSPS <lb/>Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research (grants <lb/>22K14892, 22H02869, 22K19435, and 23K06130), <lb/>the Takeda Science Foundation (CK), the Ichiro <lb/>Kanehara Foundation (CK), the Ryobi Teien <lb/>Memory Foundation (CK and KI), and Ohmoto <lb/>Ikueikai Student Grant (RS). The funders had no <lb/>role in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>Fig 1. Overexpression of MotB leads to an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype in B. subtilis without altering its <lb/>motility. A. Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV), motB-deletion strain (ΔmotB/EV), and <lb/>motA-deletion strain (ΔmotA/EV) strain, serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing 1 mM IPTG with <lb/>or without kanamycin (1.5 μg/mL) or gentamicin (0.75 μg/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. EV means that the strain was <lb/>transformed using pDR110, an empty vector. Data shown are the means ± standard errors from a minimum of three <lb/>independent experiments. Statistical analyses were performed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple <lb/>comparisons test. B. Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/ <lb/>motB OE ), MotA-overexpressed strain (WT/motA OE ), and MotA/MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motAB OE ), serially <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Next, we examined if MotB overexpression affects B. subtilis motility. To evaluate the <lb/>motility of each strain, we observed spreading in semi-solid agar plates. Notably, there was <lb/>no significant difference in the motility between the vector-transformed strain and the <lb/>MotB-overexpressed strain (Fig 1C). In these assay conditions, the motB-deletion mutant <lb/>showed decreased motility compared to the wildtype strain, and motility was restored by <lb/>MotB overexpression (Fig 1C). To compare the motility of each strain more directly, we <lb/>measured the swimming speed of single cells using a microscope. There was no significant <lb/>difference in the swimming speed between the vector-transformed strain and the MotB-<lb/>overexpressed strain (Fig 1D). The swimming speed of the motB-deletion mutant was <lb/>decreased compared to the wildtype strain, and the speed was increased by MotB overexpres-<lb/>sion to a similar extent as the MotB-overexpressed wildtype strain (Fig 1D). Overexpression <lb/>of MotB in the wildtype strain did not affect the swimming speed but made a difference in <lb/>the susceptibility to aminoglycosides, suggesting no correspondence between the bacterial <lb/>swimming speed and the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. Taken together, these results <lb/>indicate that MotB overexpression leads to an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype without <lb/>affecting motility. <lb/>Overexpression of MotB sensitizes B. subtilis to aminoglycosides in the <lb/>absence of MotA <lb/>MotB forms a complex with MotA and functions as a flagellar motor [24]. We examined the <lb/>requirement of MotA for the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype caused by MotB overexpres-<lb/>sion. Overexpression of MotB in the motA-deletion mutant resulted in decreased survival <lb/>compared to that in the vector-transformed motA-deletion mutant in the presence of kanamy-<lb/>cin or gentamicin (Fig 2). This result suggests that MotA is not required for the aminoglyco-<lb/>side-sensitive phenotype caused by MotB overexpression. <lb/>Overexpression of MotB sensitizes B. subtilis only to aminoglycosides <lb/>We examined whether MotB overexpression affects B. subtilis susceptibility to antimicrobials <lb/>other than aminoglycosides. The survival of the MotB-overexpressed strain was similar to that <lb/>of the vector-transformed strain in the presence of ribosome-targeting antibiotics other than <lb/>aminoglycosides, including erythromycin, chloramphenicol, and tetracycline (Fig 3). In addi-<lb/>tion, the MotB-overexpressed strain showed survival similar to that of the vector-transformed <lb/>strain in the presence of cell wall-targeting antibiotics, including vancomycin and ampicillin, <lb/>DNA synthesis-inhibiting antibiotics, including ciprofloxacin and levofloxacin, and an RNA <lb/>synthesis-inhibiting antibiotic, rifampicin (Fig 3). The minimum inhibitory concentrations <lb/>(MICs) for kanamycin and gentamicin of the MotB-overexpressed strain decreased <lb/>diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing 1 mM IPTG with or without kanamycin (1.2 μg/mL) or <lb/>gentamicin (0.5 μg/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. Data shown are the means ± standard errors from a minimum of three <lb/>independent experiments. Statistical analyses were performed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple <lb/>comparisons test. *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01. C. The swimming motility of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV), <lb/>MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB OE ), motB-deletion strain (ΔmotB/EV), and motB-deletion strain overexpressing <lb/>MotB (ΔmotB/motB OE ) on 0.3% soft agar medium containing 1 mM IPTG. Data shown are the means ± standard <lb/>errors from five independent experiments. Statistical analyses were performed using a one-way ANOVA with <lb/>Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test. ****, p &lt; 0.0001. D. Histograms and normal distribution curves of the single-cell <lb/>speeds of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB OE ), motB-deletion strain <lb/>(ΔmotB/EV), and motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB OE ) in LB medium with 1 mM IPTG. <lb/>ΔmotB/EV was significantly different from WT/EV and ΔmotB/motB OE (p &lt; 0.05), but WT/motB OE was not <lb/>significantly different from WT/EV (p = 0.73). Statistical analyses were performed using Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>approximately 1.5-fold compared with those of the vector-transformed strain, but the MICs <lb/>for the other drugs were the same between the MotB-overexpressed strain and the vector-<lb/>transformed strain (Table 1). These results suggest that MotB overexpression does not affect <lb/>susceptibility to antimicrobials other than aminoglycosides and leads to sensitive phenotypes <lb/>specific to aminoglycosides. <lb/>Overexpression of MotS, a homolog of MotB, does not sensitize B. subtilis <lb/>to aminoglycosides <lb/>In B. subtilis, MotP/MotS converts the transmembrane gradient of sodium ions into energy for <lb/>flagellar rotation in response to environmental changes, such as salinity changes [21-23]. <lb/>Since MotS is homologous to MotB [21], we examined whether MotS overexpression sensitizes <lb/>B. subtilis to aminoglycosides. The survival of the MotS-overexpressed strain was similar to <lb/>that of the vector-transformed strain in the presence of kanamycin or gentamicin (Fig 4A). In <lb/>addition, the strain overexpressing MotS and MotP, the homolog of MotA, showed survival <lb/>similar to that of the vector-transformed strain in the presence of kanamycin or gentamicin <lb/>(Fig 4A). <lb/>To confirm the expression of MotS and MotB, a FLAG tag sequence was fused to the C-ter-<lb/>minus of motS or motB. Western blot analyses confirmed MotS-FLAG and MotB-FLAG <lb/>expressions (Fig 4B, S1 Raw images). These results suggest that the specific function of MotB, <lb/>which does not exist in MotS, leads to susceptibility to aminoglycosides. <lb/>The proton-binding site of MotB is important for the aminoglycoside-<lb/>sensitive phenotype <lb/>When MotA/MotB or MotP/MotS function as a complex, MotB or MotS have been shown <lb/>to be the major determinants of ion bindings [25]. Based on the finding that overexpression <lb/>of MotS, which binds sodium ions, did not cause an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype, <lb/>we examined whether the proton-binding site of MotB plays a role in the aminoglycoside-<lb/>Fig 2. Overexpression of MotB causes the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype independent of MotA. Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed <lb/>strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB-FLAG OE ), motA-deletion strain (ΔmotA/EV), and MotB-overexpressing motA-deletion strain <lb/>(ΔmotA/motB-FLAG OE ), serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing 1 mM IPTG with or without kanamycin (1.5 μg/mL) or <lb/>gentamicin (0.5 μg/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. Data shown are the means ± standard errors from a minimum of three independent experiments. <lb/>Statistical analyses were performed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test. **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 3. Overexpression of MotB does not alter B. subtilis susceptibility to antibiotics other than aminoglycosides. <lb/>Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV) and the MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB OE ), <lb/>serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar medium containing 1 mM IPTG with or without ampicillin (0.2 μg/ <lb/>mL), vancomycin (0.2 μg/mL), erythromycin (0.1 μg/mL), chloramphenicol (1 μg/mL), tetracycline (3.5 μg/mL), <lb/>levofloxacin (50 ng/mL), ciprofloxacin (50 ng/mL), or rifampicin (30 ng/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. Data shown are <lb/>the means ± standard errors from a minimum of three independent experiments. Statistical analyses were calculated <lb/>using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>sensitive phenotype. Based on reports that Asp24 of MotB electrically interacts with protons <lb/>to achieve proton transport in B. subtilis [26,27], we generated motB mutant genes with <lb/>Asp24 substituted with Ala (D24A) or Glu (D24E). Based on the amino acid characteristics, <lb/>D24A MotB does not interact with protons, whereas D24E MotB mimics the interaction of <lb/>wildtype MotB with protons [27]. All motB genes were fused to a FLAG tag sequence at the <lb/>C-terminus to examine the localization of the overexpressed MotB. The D24A MotB-<lb/>Table 1. MIC values of the MotB-overexpressed strain against various antibiotics. <lb/>Strain <lb/>MIC (μg/mL) <lb/>Kan <lb/>Gen <lb/>Amp <lb/>Van <lb/>Erm <lb/>Crm <lb/>Tet <lb/>Levo <lb/>Cip <lb/>Rif <lb/>EV <lb/>3.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.094 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>0.068 <lb/>motB OE <lb/>1.8 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.094 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>0.068 <lb/>Kan, Kanamycin; Gen, Gentamicin; Amp, Ampicillin; Van, Vancomycin; Erm, Erythromycin; Crm, Chloramphenicol; Tet, Tetracycline; Levo, Levofloxacin; Cip, <lb/>Ciprofloxacin; Rif, Rifampicin. Data are an average from three replicates. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.t001 <lb/>Fig 4. Overexpression of MotS, a homolog of MotB, does not cause the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. A. Overnight cultures of the vector-<lb/>transformed strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB OE ), MotS-overexpressed strain (WT/motS OE ), and MotP/MotS-overexpressed <lb/>strain (WT/motPS OE ), serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing 1 mM IPTG with or without kanamycin (1.5 μg/mL) or gentamicin <lb/>(0.5 μg/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. Data shown are the means ± standard errors from three independent experiments. Statistical analyses were <lb/>calculated using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test. **, p &lt; 0.01. B. Western blot using an anti-FLAG antibody for the whole <lb/>cell fraction extracted from overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (motB-FLAG OE ), and MotS-<lb/>overexpressed strain (motS-FLAG OE ). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>overexpressed strain did not show significantly decreased survival compared with the vec-<lb/>tor-transformed strain in the presence of kanamycin or gentamicin (Fig 5A). In contrast, in <lb/>the presence of kanamycin, the D24E MotB-overexpressed strain showed less survival than <lb/>the vector-transformed strain (Fig 5A). Next, to examine the possibility that the amino acid <lb/>substitutions in MotB affect subcellular localization, cytosolic and membrane fractions were <lb/>prepared from these strains, and wildtype and mutant MotB proteins were detected by west-<lb/>ern blotting. FoF1-ATP synthase subunit a (AtpB; [28]) and an RNA polymerase sigma fac-<lb/>tor (SigB; [29,30]) were used as marker proteins for the membrane fraction and the cytosolic <lb/>fraction, respectively. Wildtype MotB, D24A MotB, and D24E MotB were not detected in <lb/>the cytosolic fraction in which the cytosolic protein SigB was detected (Fig 5B, S2 Raw <lb/>images). These proteins were only detected in the membrane fraction in which the mem-<lb/>brane protein AtpB was detected (Fig 5B, S2 Raw images). The expression of D24A MotB <lb/>was higher than that of wildtype MotB, whereas that of D24E MotB was comparable to that <lb/>of wildtype MotB (Fig 5B, S2 Raw images). These results suggest that D24A MotB loses its <lb/>activity, whereas D24E MotB retains it, leading to an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. <lb/>These findings suggest that the proton-binding site of MotB plays an important role in the <lb/>aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. <lb/>The increased expression of the alanine-substituted MotB at the conserved Asp residue has <lb/>also been reported in E. coli [26]. We speculate that D24A MotB was more abundant than <lb/>wildtype MotB due to the structural stabilization of the MotA/MotB complex because the ala-<lb/>nine substitution causes structural alteration of E. coli MotA/MotB [31]. <lb/>Determination of MotB expression level causing aminoglycoside sensitivity <lb/>To determine the protein expression level of MotB that causes the motility activity and the <lb/>aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype, we examined the phenotypes of the motB-deletion <lb/>mutant transformed with motB-FLAG, which was cultured in the presence of various con-<lb/>centrations of isopropyl β-D-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG). Addition of 0.05 mM IPTG <lb/>restored the motility of the motB-deletion mutant to the level of the wildtype strain (Fig 6A), <lb/>but it did not cause the aminoglycoside sensitive-phenotype (Fig 6B). Addition of 0.1 mM <lb/>IPTG restored the motility activity and caused the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype (Fig <lb/>6A and 6B). Thus, a higher concentration of IPTG (0.1 mM) is required to cause the amino-<lb/>glycoside-sensitive phenotype than to cause the motility phenotype (Fig 6C). Western blot <lb/>analysis revealed that the protein expression level of MotB was greater in 0.1 mM IPTG than <lb/>in 0.05 mM IPTG (Fig 6D, S3 Raw images). These results suggest that larger expression levels <lb/>of MotB are required to cause the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype than to cause the <lb/>motility activity. <lb/>To understand the MotB complexes that cause the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype, we <lb/>performed a blue native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and the subsequent western blot <lb/>analysis. With 0.1 mM IPTG, we detected protein bands with various sizes of 60 kDa (black <lb/>arrowhead) and larger than 60 kDa (Fig 6E, S3 Raw images). The signal intensities of the 60 <lb/>kDa band were comparable between 0.1 mM and 0.05 mM IPTG conditions (Fig 6E, S3 Raw <lb/>images). The signal intensities of bands larger than 60 kDa were greater with 0.1 mM IPTG <lb/>than with 0.05 mM IPTG (Fig 6E, S3 Raw images). We estimate that the 60 kDa band repre-<lb/>sents homodimers of MotB-FLAG because MotB has been reported to form a dimer [32], and <lb/>the theoretical molecular size of the dimer of MotB-FLAG is 61 kDa. The bands with larger <lb/>molecular weights may contain the MotA/MotB complex, the complex with flagellar motor, or <lb/>other unknown complexes. These results suggest that overexpressed MotB exists as protein <lb/>complexes to cause the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 5. The proton-binding site of MotB is required for aminoglycoside sensitization. A. Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (WT/ <lb/>EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB-FLAG OE ), D24A MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB(D24A)-FLAG OE ), and D24E MotB-overexpressed <lb/>strain (WT/motB(D24E)-FLAG OE ), serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing 1 mM IPTG with or without kanamycin (1.2 μg/mL) or <lb/>gentamicin (0.5 μg/mL), and incubated at 37˚C. Data shown are the means ± standard errors from a minimum of four independent experiments. <lb/>Statistical analyses were performed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test. *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01. B. Western blot using <lb/>an anti-FLAG antibody for the whole cell fraction, membrane fraction, and cytosolic fraction extracted from overnight cultures of the vector-<lb/>transformed strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB-FLAG OE ), D24A MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB(D24A)-FLAG OE ), D24E <lb/>MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/motB(D24E)-FLAG OE ), AtpB-overexpressed strain (WT/atpB-FLAG OE ), and SigB-overexpressed strain (WT/sigB-<lb/>FLAG OE ). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 6. The overexpressed MotB exists as large protein complexes. A. Swimming motility of the vector-transformed strain <lb/>(WT/EV) and motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ) on 0.3% soft agar medium containing various <lb/>concentrations of IPTG. B. Overnight cultures of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV), MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/ <lb/>motB-FLAG OE ), motB-deletion strain (ΔmotB/EV), and motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ), <lb/>serially diluted (10-fold) and spotted on LB agar containing various concentrations of IPTG with kanamycin (1.5 μg/mL), and <lb/>incubated at 37˚C. C. Relationship between IPTG concentration, swimming motility, and kanamycin sensitivity in the motB-<lb/>deletion strain overexpressing MotB. The CFU ratio of the motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ) to <lb/>the vector-transformed strain (EV) in the presence of kanamycin is shown in the left vertical axis (orange symbols), and the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we found that the overexpression of MotB, a flagellar motor protein, sensitizes B. <lb/>subtilis to aminoglycosides. Notably, we show that MotB leads to aminoglycoside susceptibility <lb/>in a motility-independent manner. Overexpression of MotB in the motA-deletion mutant led <lb/>to an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype, indicating that MotB induces aminoglycoside sus-<lb/>ceptibility independent of MotA. This is the first study to suggest that MotB has potential <lb/>other than as a flagellar motor protein. <lb/>Overexpression of MotB did not affect B. subtilis susceptibilities to ribosome-targeting anti-<lb/>biotics (erythromycin, chloramphenicol, and tetracycline), DNA synthesis-inhibiting antibiot-<lb/>ics (levofloxacin and ciprofloxacin), RNA synthesis-inhibiting antibiotics (rifampicin), or cell <lb/>wall-targeting antibiotics (ampicillin and vancomycin; Fig 3). The aminoglycosides, which are <lb/>affected by MotB overexpression exclusively regarding efficacy, have a structure containing an <lb/>aminocyclitol ring (streptidine or 2-deoxystreptamine) and two or more amino sugars linked <lb/>by glycosidic bonds to it [33]. They contain abundant basic ionizable amino groups as the sub-<lb/>stituents, which make them positively charged and strongly polar compounds [34,35] (S2 Fig). <lb/>Therefore, it has been suggested that the importance of PMF is inducing their crossing of the <lb/>cell membrane and uptake into the bacterial cell. Vancomycin and ampicillin target cell wall <lb/>synthesis, and their uptake into bacterial cells is not required for antibiotic action [36,37]. In <lb/>addition, erythromycin, chloramphenicol, tetracycline, levofloxacin, ciprofloxacin, and rifam-<lb/>picin are hydrophobic molecules, and their uptake into bacterial cells is unlikely to be as <lb/>affected by membrane potential as aminoglycosides. Since MotB overexpression leads to sus-<lb/>ceptibility specific to aminoglycosides among the antibiotics examined in this study, MotB <lb/>overexpression may change cellular activities, such as PMF, which specifically affects amino-<lb/>glycoside susceptibility. <lb/>This study revealed that an amino acid substitution in the proton-binding site of MotB <lb/>(D24A) affects its ability to cause an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype. In addition, MotB <lb/>overexpression resulted in an aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype in the motA-deletion <lb/>mutant. These findings suggest that interactions MotB with MotA are not required for the phe-<lb/>notype but that its proton-binding site plays an important role in inducing the aminoglyco-<lb/>side-sensitive phenotype. We considered the possibility that MotB overexpression may change <lb/>PMF by interacting with protons; however, it is difficult to imagine that MotB can bind pro-<lb/>tons and alter PMF without forming a complex with MotA. In fact, a single-cell motility assay <lb/>revealed that MotB overexpression did not affect the swimming speed. Previous studies have <lb/>analyzed various MotB mutants [38,39], but no studies have analyzed the function of MotB in <lb/>the absence of MotA. This study revealed that overexpressed MotB exists as protein complexes. <lb/>Future studies are needed to examine the effect of MotB overexpression on PMF or complex <lb/>formation and the molecular mechanisms by which MotB overexpression causes the amino-<lb/>glycoside-sensitive phenotype. Furthermore, in addition to the proton binding site in the <lb/>transmembrane domain, MotB has the peptide glycan binding motif and the plug region, <lb/>swimming ratio of the motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ) to the vector-transformed strain (EV) <lb/>is shown in the right vertical axis (blue symbols). Data shown are the average and range of two independent experiments <lb/>including the results shown in A and B. D. Western blot for the whole cell fraction extracted from the motB-deletion strain <lb/>(ΔmotB/EV) and the motB-deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ) that were cultured in the presence of <lb/>various concentrations of IPTG. E. The membrane fractions extracted from the motB-deletion strain (ΔmotB/EV) and motB-<lb/>deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB-FLAG OE ) that were cultured in the presence of various concentrations of <lb/>IPTG were solubilized with 0.5% n-dodesyl-β-D-maltoside and subjected to blue native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and <lb/>western blot. A black arrowhead indicates a 60 kDa band, and white arrowheads indicate 146, 180, 220, 180, and 380 kDa bands. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.g006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>which have important roles in the regulation of proton translocation [39,40]. The requirement <lb/>of these regions of MotB for inducing the aminoglycoside-sensitive phenotype should be <lb/>investigated in the future. <lb/>MotB is well-conserved among various flagellated bacteria. These findings suggest that <lb/>drugs that increase MotB expression have the potential to increase aminoglycoside efficacy. <lb/>The molecular mechanisms that regulate motAB expression have been studied in several bacte-<lb/>rial species. In Dickeya dadantii, SlyA regulates MotA and MotB expression via the PhoP-PhoQ <lb/>two-component system [41]. In Listeria monocytogenes, motAB expression is regulated by the <lb/>virulence regulator PrfA [42]. In Rhizobium leguminosarum, VisN/R-Rem regulates the <lb/>expression of motAB [43]. This information regarding the regulation of motAB is important to <lb/>establish research strategies for identifying drugs that activate motAB transcription. Notably, <lb/>aminoglycosides have been in use since the 1940s. Drugs that increase the efficacy of aminogly-<lb/>cosides could be useful in combating aminoglycoside-resistant bacteria. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Bacteria and culture conditions <lb/>B. subtilis 168 trpC2 and the mutant strains were aerobically cultured in LB at 37˚C. B. subtilis <lb/>gene deletion mutants carrying erythromycin-resistant gene or B. subtilis strain transformed <lb/>with pDR110 were cultured on an LB agar plate supplemented with erythromycin (1 μg/mL) <lb/>or spectinomycin (100 μg/mL), respectively. To overexpress MotB, bacterial strains were cul-<lb/>tured in the LB medium supplemented with 1 mM IPTG. The bacterial strains and plasmids <lb/>used in this study are listed in Table 2. <lb/>Gene deletion mutant <lb/>Genomic DNA was extracted from the motB-deletion mutant (BSU13680) or the motA-dele-<lb/>tion mutant (BSU13690) [44] by using the QIAamp DNA Blood Mini Kit (Qiagen). It was <lb/>Table 2. List of bacterial strains and plasmids used. <lb/>Strain or Plasmid <lb/>Genotype or characteristics <lb/>Reference <lb/>Strains <lb/>Bacillus subtilis 168 <lb/>trpC2 <lb/>BGSC <lb/>BSU13680 <lb/>trpC2 ΔmotB; Erm r <lb/>[44] <lb/>BSU13690 <lb/>trpC2 ΔmotA; Erm r <lb/>[44] <lb/>BSU13680-ML <lb/>trpC2 ΔmotB; markerless <lb/>This study <lb/>BSU13690-ML <lb/>trpC2 ΔmotA; markerless <lb/>This study <lb/>Plasmids <lb/>pDR110 <lb/>An amyE integration vector, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>BGSC [44] <lb/>pDR244 <lb/>Cre recombinase-expressing plasmid, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>BGSC [44] <lb/>pDR110-motB <lb/>pDR110 with motB, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motA <lb/>pDR110 with motA, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motAB <lb/>pDR110 with motAB, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motS <lb/>pDR110 with motS, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motPS <lb/>pDR110 with motPS, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motB-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with motB-FLAG, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motS-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with motS-FLAG, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-atpB-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with atpB-FLAG, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-sigB-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with sigB-FLAG, Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motB(D24A)-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with motB(D24A), Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>pDR110-motB(D24E)-FLAG <lb/>pDR110 with motB(D24E), Amp r , Spc r <lb/>This study <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>used to transform B. subtilis 168 trpC2 strain [45]. Erythromycin-resistant colonies were <lb/>obtained on LB plates supplemented with erythromycin (1μg/mL). The erythromycin-resistant <lb/>cassette in the mutant strains was excised using pDR244, a temperature-sensitive plasmid <lb/>expressing a Cre recombinase. The desired deletion of motB or motA was confirmed using <lb/>PCR. <lb/>Plasmid construction <lb/>DNA fragments containing motB, motA, motAB, motS, motP, atpB, and sigB were amplified by <lb/>PCR using specific primer pairs (Table 3) and a genomic DNA from 168 trpC2 as a template. <lb/>The amplified DNA fragments were inserted into the multiple cloning site of pDR110, <lb/>Table 3. Primers used in this study. <lb/>Primers to construct pDR110-motB and to confirm the motB integration <lb/>motB_F_SalI <lb/>GTCGTCGACGGACAAGCACCGAAAGTCAT <lb/>motB_R_SphI <lb/>GCAGCATGCAGGTAGAGATGTGCACCGAAA <lb/>Primers to construct pDR110-motA and to confirm the motA integration <lb/>motA_F_SalI <lb/>GTCGTCGACGGGCACCAAAACCGATATTA <lb/>motA_R_SphI <lb/>GCAGCATGCTCGCGTACAGCACAATAA <lb/>Primers to construct pDR110-motAB and to confirm the motAB integration <lb/>motA_F_SalI <lb/>GTCGTCGACGGGCACCAAAACCGATATTA <lb/>motB_R_SphI <lb/>GCAGCATGCAGGTAGAGATGTGCACCGAAA <lb/>Primers to construct pDR110-motS and to confirm the motS integration <lb/>motS_F_NheI <lb/>GCTGCTAGCTTTCAGCTCACGGGAAGAAT <lb/>motS_R_SphI <lb/>GCAGCATGCGATACGTTCTGAACAGC <lb/>Primers to construct pDR110-motPS and to confirm the motPS integration <lb/>motP_F_SalI <lb/>GTCGTCGACGAGCAAGCTTCACCTTTATGG <lb/>motS_R_SphI <lb/>GCAGCATGCGATACGTTCTGAACAGC <lb/>Primers to amplify motB-FLAG <lb/>motB-Flag_F <lb/>TAGCAAAAAAGGAAGCCTTGTGA <lb/>motB-Flag_R <lb/>CTTGTCATCGTCGTCCTTGTAGTCTTTTTCATTTGTTTCCGCTG <lb/>Primers to amplify motS-FLAG <lb/>motS-Flag_F <lb/>TAAAGGTCGTTTTTTACTTTGTT <lb/>motS-Flag_R <lb/>CTTGTCATCGTCGTCCTTGTAGTCCGAAGAGGTCGTTTTTGATT <lb/>Primers to amplify atpB-FLAG <lb/>atpB_F <lb/>GTCGTCGACCAGCTTAAACGTTCATCAATGG <lb/>atpB_R_FLAG <lb/>GCAGCATGCTTATTTATCATCATCATCTTTATAATCATGATCATGACTGATTTTATGAGACAT <lb/>Primers to amplify sigB-FLAG <lb/>sigB-SalI-F <lb/>GTCGTCGACCGCTCATGGATGAAGTCAGA <lb/>sigB-flag-SphI-R <lb/>GCAGCATGCTTATTTATCATCATCATCTTTATAATCCATTAACTCCATCGAGGGATCT <lb/>Primers to amplify motB (D24A)-FLAG <lb/>motB(D24A) _F <lb/>ATGGCTCGTTCCTTACGCCGCAATCCTTACTCTTCTCCTGGC <lb/>motB(D24A) _R <lb/>GCCAGGAGAAGAGTAAGGATTGCGGCGTAAGGAACGAGCCAT <lb/>Primers to amplify motB (D24E)-FLAG <lb/>motB(D24E) _F <lb/>ATGGCTCGTTCCTTACGCCGAAATCCTTACTCTTCTCCTGGC <lb/>motB(D24E) _R <lb/>GCCAGGAGAAGAGTAAGGATTTCGGCGTAAGGAACGAGCCAT <lb/>Primers to confirm the replacement of amyE locus <lb/>amyE_F <lb/>TACAGCACCGTCGATCAAAA <lb/>amyE_R <lb/>CTCGGTCCTCGTTACACCAT <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634.t003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>resulting in the plasmids pDR110-motB, pDR110-motA, pDR110-motAB, pDR110-motP, <lb/>pDR110-motS, pDR110-motPS, pDR110-atpB-FLAG, and pDR110-sigB-FLAG. <lb/>The FLAG tag sequence was added to pDR110-motB or pDR110-motS by inverse PCR <lb/>using specific primer pairs (Table 3) and pDR110-motB or pDR110-motS as a template. The <lb/>desired addition of a FLAG tag at the C-terminus of MotB or MotS was confirmed by Sanger <lb/>sequencing. To introduce amino acid substitutions (D24A and D24E) into MotB, thermal <lb/>cycling reactions were performed using primer pairs (Table 3), pDR110-motB-FLAG as a tem-<lb/>plate, and KOD Plus DNA polymerase (Toyobo). The product of the thermal cycling reaction <lb/>was digested with DpnI and used to transform E. coli JM109. The plasmid was extracted, and <lb/>the desired mutations were confirmed by Sanger sequencing. <lb/>Transformation <lb/>Natural transformation was performed to transform 168 trpC2 with the plasmids [45]. The col-<lb/>onies were selected on LB plates supplemented with spectinomycin (100 μg/mL). The desired <lb/>recombination of the plasmid into the amyE locus was confirmed by PCR using primer pairs <lb/>(Table 3) and genomic DNA as the template. <lb/>Evaluation of antibiotic susceptibility <lb/>The autoclaved LB agar medium was mixed with 1 mM IPTG and antimicrobials and poured <lb/>into round or square dishes. B. subtilis overnight cultures were serially diluted 10-fold with LB <lb/>broth in a 96-well microplate, and 5 μL of the diluted bacterial solutions were spotted onto LB <lb/>plates with or without antibiotics using an 8-channel Pipetman. The plates were incubated <lb/>overnight at 37˚C. Colonies were photographed using a digital camera and counted. <lb/>The criteria for CFU counting were set as follows. i) When 5 or more colonies were <lb/>observed in the most diluted spot, we counted the number of colonies. ii) When 4 or fewer col-<lb/>onies were observed in the most diluted spot, we counted the number of colonies in the next <lb/>most diluted spot. iii) When the number of colonies could not be counted due to crowded col-<lb/>onies, we considered the number of colonies to be 20. iv) When the colonies were observed <lb/>only at the edge of the spot, like a circle, we considered the number of colonies to be 10. <lb/>Evaluation of MIC <lb/>Overnight cultures in the presence of 1 mM IPTG were diluted to 10 4 CFU/5 μL and spotted <lb/>on LB agar plates with 1 mM IPTG and serial 1.5-fold dilutions of antibiotics. The MIC was <lb/>determined as the minimum concentration at which no colonies were observed. The values <lb/>reported are the mean of three replicates. <lb/>Swimming motility assay <lb/>2 μL of an OD 600 -adjusted overnight culture was inoculated at the center of LB plates [0.3% <lb/>(W/V) agar] containing 1 mM IPTG. After incubation at 37˚C for 24 h, the diameter of the <lb/>bacterial spread was measured. <lb/>Single-cell motility assay <lb/>For observation of single-cell motility, a previously described method [46] was used with mod-<lb/>ifications. Plastic tape pieces, 20 mm long, were used as spacers between coverslips. A 7-mm <lb/>square in the middle of the tape was cut out to create a chamber, and 3 μL of overnight culture <lb/>mixed with 7 μL of fresh LB (1 mM IPTG) was placed in the chamber. This experiment was <lb/>visualized using a confocal laser scanning microscope (FV3000RS, Olympus) with a 100× <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>objective (UPLAPO100XOHR, Olympus). Images were recorded at 5 frames per second for 20 <lb/>seconds. For image analysis, cell edges in all images were highlighted by replacing each pixel <lb/>with the neighborhood variance using the Variance tool in ImageJ [47] (https://imagej.net/ij/). <lb/>Single-cell motility was analyzed using the TrackMate tool [48] (https://imagej.net/plugins/ <lb/>trackmate/) and the Simple LAC tracker was used for tracking. Track times (between the first <lb/>spot of the track in time and the last spot of the track in time) of each cell were measured, and <lb/>cells with a track time longer than 5.16 seconds were extracted to measure the following <lb/>parameters: mean straight line speed (defined as the net displacement [Track displacement <lb/>feature] divided by the track total time). To unify the number of cells used for statistical analy-<lb/>ses, 80 cells of each strain were randomly selected. Histograms and normal distribution curves <lb/>were created, and statistical significances were determined by Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests <lb/>using Microsoft Excel for Mac Version 16.54. Representative video images are presented in <lb/>(S1-S4 Videos). <lb/>Western blot analysis <lb/>A previously described method [49] was used with modifications for fractionation of the mem-<lb/>brane and cytoplasmic fractions. B. subtilis overnight cultures were washed twice with SMH <lb/>(0.5 M Sucrose, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 20 mM HEPES-NaOH pH 7.3) at room temperature. The cells <lb/>were resuspended in 1/5 the volume of SMH and treated with lysozyme (10 mg/mL). The pro-<lb/>toplasts were collected by centrifugation and flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen. Thawed proto-<lb/>plasts were dissolved in 500 μL of Buffer H (20 mM HEPES pH 7.3, 200 mM NaCl, 1 mM <lb/>DTT, 1 tablet/50 mL protease inhibitor (Complete ULTRA, Roche)). The cell suspension was <lb/>treated with 2 mM MgCl 2 , 2 mM CaCl 2 , DNaseI (0.02 U/μL), and RNaseA (40 μg/mL) at 4˚C <lb/>overnight and used as whole cell fraction. Debris was removed from the whole cell fraction by <lb/>centrifugation at 6,000 × g for 10 minutes at 4˚C [50], and the supernatant was centrifuged at <lb/>100,000 × g for 1 hour at 4˚C. The pellet was dissolved in 100 μL of Buffer H to make the mem-<lb/>brane fraction, and the supernatant was used as the cytosol fraction. <lb/>FLAG-tagged MotB was detected according to a previously described method [45]. Sodium <lb/>dodecyl sulfate (SDS) sample buffer (final 1x) was added to each protein sample and boiled for <lb/>5 min. The samples were electrophoresed in a 12.5% SDS-polyacrylamide gel and the proteins <lb/>were blotted to a 0.45-μm PVDF membrane (Millipore). An anti-DYKDDDDK (anti-FLAG) <lb/>antibody (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan) diluted 1:5,000 in 1x TBST was used as the primary anti-<lb/>body. Horseradish peroxidase RP-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (Promega, Japan) diluted <lb/>1:5,000 in 1× TBST was used as the secondary antibody. Signals were detected using an Image-<lb/>Quant LAS 4000 (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan). <lb/>Blue native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis <lb/>The membrane fractions of bacterial strains were treated with 0.5% n-dodesyl-β-D-maltoside <lb/>and electrophoresed in a 4-20% gradient polyacrylamide gel in a EzRun BlueNative buffer <lb/>(ATTO corp., Tokyo, Japan). The proteins in the gel were transferred to a 0.45-μm PVDF <lb/>membrane (Millipore) using EzFastBlot HMW buffer (ATTO corp) and subjected to western <lb/>blot analysis. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>The statistical analyses were performed using Prism 9 software (GraphPad Software) unless <lb/>otherwise specified. Relevant information on the statistical tests is provided in the captions of <lb/>each figure. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Growth curve of the MotB-overexpressed strain. 50 μL of an OD 600 -adjusted over-<lb/>night culture of the vector-transformed strain (WT/EV) and MotB-overexpressed strain (WT/ <lb/>motB OE ) were aerobically cultured in 5 mL of LB containing 1 mM IPTG at 37˚C. Data shown <lb/>are the means ± standard errors from four independent experiments. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Chemical structural formula of kanamycin and gentamicin. Chemical structures <lb/>were constructed by Marvin Sketch of ChemAxon (16.11.21.0). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Raw images. Original uncropped images for western blots in Fig 4B. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Raw images. Original uncropped images for SDS polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis <lb/>and western blots in Fig 5B. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Raw images. Original uncropped images for western blots in Fig 6D and 6E and a <lb/>marker in blue native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis in Fig 6E. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Video. Video data of swimming and cell tracks of WT/EV. Swimming of the vector-<lb/>transformed strain (WT/EV) captured under a bright field microscope (left) and detected cells <lb/>and trajectories derived from automated tracking using TrackMate (right). Scale bar, 10 μm. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S2 Video. Video data of swimming and cell tracks of WT/motB OE . Swimming of MotB-<lb/>overexpressed strain (WT/motB OE ) captured under a bright field microscope (left) and <lb/>detected cells and trajectories derived from automated tracking using TrackMate (right). Scale <lb/>bar, 10 μm. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S3 Video. Video data of swimming and cell tracks of ΔmotB/EV. Swimming of motB-dele-<lb/>tion strain (ΔmotB/EV) captured under a bright field microscope (left) and detected cells and <lb/>trajectories derived from automated tracking using TrackMate (right). Scale bar, 10 μm. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/>S4 Video. Video data of swimming and cell tracks of ΔmotB/motB OE . Swimming of motB-<lb/>deletion strain overexpressing MotB (ΔmotB/motB OE ) captured under a bright field micro-<lb/>scope (left) and detected cells and trajectories derived from automated tracking using Track-<lb/>Mate (right). Scale bar, 10 μm. <lb/>(MOV) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the National BioResource Project B. subtilis (National Institute of Genetics, Japan) <lb/>for providing the BKE library and the Bacillus Genetic Stock Center for providing B. subtilis <lb/>168 and plasmids. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Mio Uneme, Chikara Kaito. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Data curation: Mio Uneme, Kazuya Ishikawa, Kazuyuki Furuta, Atsuko Yamashita. <lb/>Formal analysis: Mio Uneme, Kazuya Ishikawa, Kazuyuki Furuta, Atsuko Yamashita. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Kazuya Ishikawa, Kazuyuki Furuta, Chikara Kaito. <lb/>Investigation: Mio Uneme, Atsuko Yamashita. <lb/>Methodology: Atsuko Yamashita. <lb/>Supervision: Chikara Kaito. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Mio Uneme. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Mio Uneme, Kazuya Ishikawa, Kazuyuki Furuta, Atsuko Yama-<lb/>shita, Chikara Kaito. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Davis BD. Mechanism of bactericidal action of aminoglycosides. Microbiol Rev. 1987; 51: 341-350. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/mr.51.3.341-350.1987 PMID: 3312985 <lb/>2. Kohanski MA, Dwyer DJ, Wierzbowski J, Cottarel G, Collins JJ. Mistranslation of Membrane Proteins <lb/>and Two-Component System Activation Trigger Antibiotic-Mediated Cell Death. Cell. 2008; 135: 679-<lb/>690. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2008.09.038 PMID: 19013277 <lb/>3. Bryan LE, Van den Elzen HM. Streptomycin accumulation in susceptible and resistant strains of Escher-<lb/>ichia coli and Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1976; 9: 928-938. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1128/AAC.9.6.928 PMID: 820248 <lb/>4. Damper PD, Epstein W. Role of the membrane potential in bacterial resistance to aminoglycoside anti-<lb/>biotics. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1981; 20: 803-808. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.20.6.803 <lb/>PMID: 6173015 <lb/>5. Taber HW, Mueller JP, Miller PF, Arrow AS. Bacterial uptake of aminoglycoside antibiotics. Microbiol <lb/>Rev. 1987; 51: 439-457. https://doi.org/10.1128/mr.51.4.439-457.1987 PMID: 3325794 <lb/>6. Kohanski MA, Dwyer DJ, Hayete B, Lawrence CA, Collins JJ. A Common Mechanism of Cellular Death <lb/>Induced by Bactericidal Antibiotics. Cell. 2007; 130: 797-810. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2007.06. <lb/>049 PMID: 17803904 <lb/>7. Bruni GN, Kralj JM. Membrane voltage dysregulation driven by metabolic dysfunction underlies bacteri-<lb/>cidal activity of aminoglycosides. Elife. 2020; 9: e58706. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.58706 PMID: <lb/>32748785 <lb/>8. Bryan LE, Kwan S. Roles of ribosomal binding, membrane potential, and electron transport in bacterial <lb/>uptake of streptomycin and gentamicin. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1983; 23: 835-845. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1128/AAC.23.6.835 PMID: 6351731 <lb/>9. Ezraty B, Vergnes A, Banzhaf M, Duverger Y, Huguenot A, Brochado AR, et al. Fe-S cluster biosynthe-<lb/>sis controls uptake of aminoglycosides in a ROS-less death pathway. Science. 2013; 340: 1583-1587. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1238328 PMID: 23812717 <lb/>10. Kanner BI, Gutnick DL. Use of neomycin in the isolation of mutants blocked in energy conservation in <lb/>Escherichia coli. J Bacteriol. 1972; 111: 287-289. https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.111.1.287-289.1972 <lb/>PMID: 4273171 <lb/>11. Vestergaard M, Bald D, Ingmer H. Targeting the ATP synthase in bacterial and fungal pathogens: <lb/>beyond Mycobacterium tuberculosis. J Glob Antimicrob Resist. 2022; 29: 29-41. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jgar.2022.01.026 PMID: 35131507 <lb/>12. Berg HC, Anderson RA. Bacteria Swim by Rotating their Flagellar Filaments. Nature. 1973; 245: 380-<lb/>382. https://doi.org/10.1038/245380a0 PMID: 4593496 <lb/>13. Silverman M, Simon M. Flagellar rotation and the mechanism of bacterial motility. Nature. 1974; 249: <lb/>73-74. https://doi.org/10.1038/249073a0 PMID: 4598030 <lb/>14. Hu H, Santiveri M, Wadhwa N, Berg HC, Erhardt M, Taylor NMI. Structural basis of torque generation in <lb/>the bi-directional bacterial flagellar motor. Trends Biochem Sci. 2022; 47: 160-172. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.tibs.2021.06.005 PMID: 34294545 <lb/>15. Deme JC, Johnson S, Vickery O, Aron A, Monkhouse H, Griffiths T, et al. Structures of the stator com-<lb/>plex that drives rotation of the bacterial flagellum. Nat Microbiol. 2020; 5: 1553-1564. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/s41564-020-0788-8 PMID: 32929189 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>16. Santiveri M, Roa-Eguiara A, Ku ¨hne C, Wadhwa N, Hu H, Berg HC, et al. Structure and Function of Sta-<lb/>tor Units of the Bacterial Flagellar Motor. Cell. 2020; 183: 244-257.e16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell. <lb/>2020.08.016 PMID: 32931735 <lb/>17. Manson MD, Tedesco P, Berg HC, Harold FM, Van Der Drift C. A protonmotive force drives bacterial fla-<lb/>gella. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1977; 74: 3060-3064. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.74.7.3060 PMID: <lb/>19741 <lb/>18. Blair DF, Berg HC. The MotA protein of E. coli is a proton-conducting component of the flagellar motor. <lb/>Cell. 1990; 60: 439-449. https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(90)90595-6 PMID: 2154333 <lb/>19. Imae Y, Atsumi T. Na+-driven bacterial flagellar motors. J Bioenerg Biomembr. 1989; 21: 705-716. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00762688 PMID: 2687262 <lb/>20. Asai Y, Kojima S, Kato H, Nishioka N, Kawagishi I, Homma M. Putative channel components for the <lb/>fast-rotating sodium-driven flagellar motor of a marine bacterium. J Bacteriol 1997; 179: 5104-5110. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.179.16.5104-5110.1997 PMID: 9260952 <lb/>21. Ito M, Hicks DB, Henkin TM, Guffanti AA, Powers BD, Zvi L, et al. MotPS is the stator-force generator <lb/>for motility of alkaliphilic Bacillus, and its homologue is a second functional Mot in Bacillus subtilis. Mol <lb/>Microbiol. 2004; 53: 1035-1049. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04173.x PMID: 15306009 <lb/>22. Fukuoka H, Wada T, Kojima S, Ishijima A, Homma M. Sodium-dependent dynamic assembly of mem-<lb/>brane complexes in sodium-driven flagellar motors. Mol Microbiol. 2009; 71: 825-835. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1111/j.1365-2958.2008.06569.x PMID: 19183284 <lb/>23. Terahara N, Kodera N, Uchihashi T, Ando T, Namba K, Minamino T. Na+-induced structural transition <lb/>of MotPS for stator assembly of the Bacillus flagellar motor. Sci Adv. 2017; 3: eaao4119. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1126/sciadv.aao4119 PMID: 29109979 <lb/>24. Stolz B, Berg HC. Evidence for interactions between MotA and MotB, torque-generating elements of <lb/>the flagellar motor of Escherichia coli. J Bacteriol. 1991; 173: 7033-7037. https://doi.org/10.1128/jb. <lb/>173.21.7033-7037.1991 PMID: 1938906 <lb/>25. Ito M, Terahara N, Fujinami S, Krulwich TA. Properties of motility in Bacillus subtilis powered by the H <lb/>+-coupled MotAB flagellar stator, Na+-coupled MotPS or hybrid stators MotAS or MotPB. J Mol Biol. <lb/>2005; 352: 396-408. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2005.07.030 PMID: 16095621 <lb/>26. Zhou J, Sharp LL, Tang HL, Lloyd SA, Billings S, Braun TF, et al. Function of protonatable residues in <lb/>the flagellar motor of Escherichia coli: a critical role for Asp 32 of MotB. J Bacteriol. 1998; 180: 2729-<lb/>2735. https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.180.10.2729-2735.1998 PMID: 9573160 <lb/>27. Takahashi Y, Koyama K, Ito M. Suppressor mutants from MotB-D24E and MotS-D30E in the flagellar <lb/>stator complex of Bacillus subtilis. J Gen Appl Microbiol. 2014; 60: 131-139. https://doi.org/10.2323/ <lb/>jgam.60.131 PMID: 25273986 <lb/>28. Santana M, Ionescu MS, Vertes A, Longin R, Kunst F, Danchin A, et al. Bacillus subtilis F0F1 ATPase: <lb/>DNA sequence of the atp operon and characterization of atp mutants. J Bacteriol. 1994; 176: 6802-11. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.176.22.6802-6811.1994 PMID: 7961438 <lb/>29. Haldenwang WG, Losick R. A modified RNA polymerase transcribes a cloned gene under sporulation <lb/>control in Bacillus subtilis. Nature. 1979; 282: 256-60. https://doi.org/10.1038/282256a0 PMID: <lb/>116131 <lb/>30. Haldenwang WG. The sigma factors of Bacillus subtilis. Microbiol Rev. 1995; 59: 1-30. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1128/mr.59.1.1-30.1995 PMID: 7708009 <lb/>31. Kojima S, Blair DF. Conformational change in the stator of the bacterial flagellar motor. Biochemistry. <lb/>2001; 40: 13041-50. https://doi.org/10.1021/bi011263o PMID: 11669642 <lb/>32. Braun TF, Blair DF. Targeted disulfide cross-linking of the MotB protein of Escherichia coli: evidence for <lb/>two H(+) channels in the stator Complex. Biochemistry. 2001; 40: 13051-9. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>bi011264g PMID: 11669643 <lb/>33. Jana S, Deb JK. Molecular understanding of aminoglycoside action and resistance. Appl Microbiol Bio-<lb/>technol. 2006; 70: 140-50. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-005-0279-0 PMID: 16391922 <lb/>34. Becker B, Cooper MA. Aminoglycoside antibiotics in the 21st century. ACS Chem Biol. 2013; 8: 105-<lb/>15. https://doi.org/10.1021/cb3005116 PMID: 23110460 <lb/>35. Feldman MB, Terry DS, Altman RB, Blanchard SC. Aminoglycoside activity observed on single pre-<lb/>translocation ribosome complexes. Nat Chem Biol. 2010; 6: 244. <lb/>36. Den Blaauwen T, Aarsman ME, Vischer NO, Nanninga N. Penicillin-binding protein PBP2 of Escheri-<lb/>chia coli localizes preferentially in the lateral wall and at mid-cell in comparison with the old cell pole. <lb/>Mol Microbiol. 2003; 47: 539-547. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03316.x PMID: <lb/>12519203 <lb/>37. Pereira PM, Filipe SR, Tomasz A, Pinho MG. Fluorescence ratio imaging microscopy shows decreased <lb/>access of vancomycin to cell wall synthetic sites in vancomycin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2007; 51: 3627-3633. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.00431-07 PMID: <lb/>17646417 <lb/>38. Kojima S, Imada K, Sakuma M, Sudo Y, Kojima C, Minamino T, et al. Stator assembly and activation <lb/>mechanism of the flagellar motor by the periplasmic region of MotB. Mol Microbiol. 2009; 73: 710-718. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06802.x PMID: 19627504 <lb/>39. Hosking ER, Vogt C, Bakker EP, Manson MD. The Escherichia coli MotAB proton channel unplugged. J <lb/>Mol Biol. 2006; 364: 921-937. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2006.09.035 PMID: 17052729 <lb/>40. Morimoto YV, Che YS, Minamino T, Namba K. Proton-conductivity assay of plugged and unplugged <lb/>MotA/B proton channel by cytoplasmic pHluorin expressed in Salmonella. FEBS Lett. 2010; 584: <lb/>1268-72. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.febslet.2010.02.051 PMID: 20178785 <lb/>41. Haque MM, Hirata H, Tsuyumu S. SlyA regulates motA and motB, virulence and stress-related genes <lb/>under conditions induced by the PhoP-PhoQ system in Dickeya dadantii 3937. Res Microbiol. 2015; <lb/>166: 467-475. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.resmic.2015.05.004 PMID: 26027774 <lb/>42. Michel E, Mengaud J, Galsworthy S, Cossart P. Characterization of a large motility gene cluster contain-<lb/>ing the cheR, motAB genes of Listeria monocytogenes and evidence that PrfA downregulates motility <lb/>genes. FEMS Microbiol Lett. 1998; 169: 341-347. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6968.1998.tb13338.x <lb/>PMID: 9868779 <lb/>43. Tambalo DD, Del Bel KL, Bustard DE, Greenwood PR, Steedman AE, Hynes MF. Regulation of flagel-<lb/>lar, motility and chemotaxis genes in Rhizobium leguminosarum by the VisN/R-Rem cascade. Microbi-<lb/>ology. 2010. 156: 1673-1685. https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.035386-0 PMID: 20203055 <lb/>44. Koo B-M, Kritikos G, Farelli JD, Todor H, Tong K, Kimsey H, et al. Construction and Analysis of Two <lb/>Genome-Scale Deletion Libraries for Bacillus subtilis. Cell Syst. 2017; 4: 291-305.e7. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.cels.2016.12.013 PMID: 28189581 <lb/>45. Ishikawa K, Shirakawa R, Takano D, Kosaki T, Furuta K, Kaito C. Knockout of ykcB, a Putative Glyco-<lb/>syltransferase, Leads to Reduced Susceptibility to Vancomycin in Bacillus subtilis. J Bacteriol. 2022; <lb/>204: e0038722. https://doi.org/10.1128/jb.00387-22 PMID: 36409129 <lb/>46. Kinosita Y, Ishida T, Yoshida M, Ito R, Morimoto YV, Goto K, et al. Distinct chemotactic behavior in the <lb/>original Escherichia coli K-12 depending on forward-and-backward swimming, not on run-tumble move-<lb/>ments. Sci Rep. 2020; 10: 15887. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-72429-1 PMID: 32985511 <lb/>47. Schneider CA, Rasband WS, Eliceiri KW. NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis. Nat Meth-<lb/>ods. 2012; 9: 671-5. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2089 PMID: 22930834 <lb/>48. Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, Kaynig V, Longair M, Pietzsch T, et al. Fiji: an open-source <lb/>platform for biological-image analysis. Nat Methods. 2012; 9: 676-82. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth. <lb/>2019 PMID: 22743772 <lb/>49. Doan T, Morlot C, Meisner J, Serrano M, Henriques AO, Moran CP, et al. Novel Secretion Apparatus <lb/>Maintains Spore Integrity and Developmental Gene Expression in Bacillus subtilis. PLoS Genetics. <lb/>2009; 5: e1000566. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000566 PMID: 19609349 <lb/>50. Eymann C, Dreisbach A, Albrecht D, Bernhardt J, Becher D, Gentner S, et al. A comprehensive prote-<lb/>ome map of growing Bacillus subtilis cells. Proteomics. 2004. 4: 2849-2876. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>pmic.200400907 PMID: 15378759 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>MotB sensitizes Bacillus subtilis to aminoglycosides <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300634 April 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 19 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>