<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Effect of molecular structure on the photochemical stability of acceptor and donor polymers used in organic solar cells</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Suraj</forename>
          <surname>Prasad</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Zewdneh</forename>
          <surname>Genene</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Cleber F. N.</forename>
          <surname>Marchiori</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shivam</forename>
          <surname>Singh</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Leif K. E.</forename>
          <surname>Ericsson</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ergang</forename>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>C. Moyses</forename>
          <surname>Araujo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ellen</forename>
          <surname>Moons</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T11:29:03.308Z">11/12/2025 11:29:03 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1039$1$d4ma00447g</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1039/d4ma00447g</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Suraj Prasad, Zewdneh Genene, Cleber F. N. Marchiori, Shivam Singh, Leif K. E. Ericsson, Ergang Wang, C. Moyses Araujo, Ellen Moons. (2024). Effect of molecular structure on the photochemical stability of acceptor and donor polymers used in organic solar cells. Materials Advances, 5(19), 7708-7720. DOI: 10.1039/d4ma00447g</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T11:28:55.178807Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T11:28:55.178807Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Environmental <lb/>Science <lb/>Atmospheres <lb/>rsc.li/esatmospheres <lb/>Volume 4 <lb/>Number 4 <lb/>April 2024 <lb/>Pages 427-502 <lb/>ISSN 2634-3606 <lb/>PAPER <lb/>Kevin M. A. Parker and Michael R. Mainelli <lb/>What happens if we &apos;burn all the carbon&apos;? carbon reserves, <lb/>carbon budgets, and policy options for governments <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>What happens if we &apos;burn all the carbon&apos;? carbon <lb/>reserves, carbon budgets, and policy options for <lb/>governments † <lb/>Kevin M. A. Parker * a and Michael R. Mainelli b <lb/>Our estimates show that &apos;proven reserves&apos; of fossil fuels in 2022, would generate an estimated 4777 Gt of <lb/>CO 2 after allowing for non-fuel uses. This quantity already could &apos;bust CO 2 budgets&apos; for IPCC RCP2.6, <lb/>RCP4.5, and RCP6.0 and is approaching the range for RCP8.5. Notwithstanding these results, fossil fuel <lb/>companies are still exploring and bringing new reserves onstream. We discuss the reasons behind this, <lb/>and propose some policy options for governments as they address this situation. <lb/>Environmental signicance <lb/>In 2006 the authors posed a question to a major oil company, and members of the wider nancial community. What happens if we burn all the oil you have now? <lb/>The answers indicated that the world already had sufficient fossil fuel reserves to raise atmospheric carbon to unacceptable levels of 1000 ppm or more. It looked <lb/>like there was a lot of &apos;unburnable carbon&apos; or &apos;stranded assets&apos; on Oil &amp; Gas company balance sheets. The intention of this paper is improve the 2006 estimates, <lb/>and carry out new calculations based on reserves in 2022. Is there any evidence that the concept of &apos;unburnable carbon&apos; has in fact led to reduction in fossil fuel <lb/>reserves? What might happen to IPCC carbon budgets, and atmospheric CO 2 levels, if these reserves are in fact very &apos;burnable&apos;? Our estimates show that &apos;proven <lb/>reserves&apos; of fossil fuels in 2022, would generate an estimated 4777 Gt of CO 2 aer allowing for non-fuel uses. This quantity already could &apos;bust CO 2 budgets&apos; for <lb/>IPCC RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP6.0, and is approaching the range for RCP8.5. Notwithstanding these results, fossil fuel companies are still exploring and <lb/>bringing new reserves onstream. We discuss the reasons behind this, and propose some policy options for governments as they address this situation. The <lb/>authors for the paper, Dr Kevin Parker, and Professor Michael Mainelli, are respectively Science Advisor and Founder of the leading city of London think-tank Z/ <lb/>Yen Group. Among other achievements, Professor Mainelli is currently serving as Lord Mayor of the City of London, where he is making the Financing of Green <lb/>developments as a theme of his year in office. <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>1.1 Historical background -what happens if we &apos;burn it all&apos;? <lb/>In 2006 the authors posed a question to a major oil company, <lb/>and members of the &apos;London Accord&apos;. What happens if we burn it <lb/>all? (i.e., burn all known reserves on balance sheets). <lb/>The London Accord 1 was an agreement by over 100 <lb/>researchers from 25 organisations around the world to &quot;share <lb/>investment research with policy-makers and the public&quot; on <lb/>climate change for the sake of the planet. The organisations <lb/>included the investment research arms of several global banks, <lb/>research rms, and academics. The London Accord&apos;s thinking <lb/>began at Z/Yen Group, was conducted under the auspices of the <lb/>City of London Corporation with the support of the then Lord <lb/>Mayor, Sir David Lewis, and had signicant operational support <lb/>from British Petroleum (BP). <lb/>In December 2007, the London Accord group published <lb/>a 780 page &apos;open source&apos; research report on the &apos;investability&apos; of <lb/>climate change. 2 Their methodology involved extensive Monte <lb/>Carlo portfolio modelling as used in nancial markets rather <lb/>than macroeconomics, social cost models, or shadow pricing. <lb/>The report&apos;s conclusion was that carbon prices somewhere <lb/>above $30 to $60 per tonne of CO 2 (in 2007 circa V1 = $1.4, i.e. <lb/>V21 to V43 per tonne) would provide sufficient opportunities <lb/>for investment and asset managers to prevent climate change so <lb/>long as governments restricted emission permits above the $30 <lb/>to $60 range. Given that, traditional nancial services could do <lb/>much of the work to prevent climate change. <lb/>For reference, the then price of carbon allowances on the EU <lb/>emissions trading system (EU ETS) had hit a peak of almost V30 <lb/>per tonne in April 2006, but due to oversupply by governments, <lb/>the price dropped 54% from V29.20 to V13.35 in the last week <lb/>of April 2006. At the time of the London Accord&apos;s report launch, <lb/>carbon prices were nearly zero. <lb/>Perhaps the most referred to reference point during the <lb/>period of the report was the concentration of carbon dioxide in <lb/>the atmosphere in parts-per-million (ppm). In 2005-6 it was <lb/>approximately 370, and the likelihood exceeding 400 ppm <lb/>around 2015 was seen as a signicant, negative, milestone. Later, <lb/></body>

			<front>a KKI Associates Ltd, Science and Business Advisor Z/Yen Group, 1 King William Street, <lb/>London EC4N 7 AF, UK. E-mail: kevin@kkitech.com <lb/>b Z/Yen Group, Lord Mayor of the City of London, Mansion House Walbrook, London <lb/>EC4N 8BH, UK <lb/> † Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available. See DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1039/d3ea00107e <lb/>Cite this: Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, <lb/>435 <lb/>Received 7th July 2023 <lb/>Accepted 21st January 2024 <lb/>DOI: 10.1039/d3ea00107e <lb/>rsc.li/esatmospheres <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | 435 <lb/>Environmental Science: <lb/>Atmospheres <lb/>PAPER <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/>View Journal | View Issue <lb/></front>

			<body>a more common reference point was &apos;degrees warming&apos; which <lb/>relies on models. Science advisers on the Intergovernmental <lb/>Panel on Climate Change estimated an atmospheric CO 2 <lb/>concentration of no more than 450 parts per million for 2 <lb/>degrees of warming, or 430 ppm for 1.5 degrees. Still later, &apos;net <lb/>zero&apos; dates and &apos;carbon budgets&apos; have become the more common <lb/>reference. This change derived from the recognition that global <lb/>warming is closely tied to cumulative carbon emissions, thus <lb/>directly linking historic and future reserves exploited over time. <lb/>During the London Accord work, researchers queried BP&apos;s <lb/>involvement. Shouldn&apos;t the traditional &apos;seven sisters&apos; of oil just <lb/>stop? Wouldn&apos;t BP be better to close itself down than spend <lb/>time on the project? At the time BP believed that its reserves <lb/>might only change atmospheric CO 2 by 1.5 to 2 ppm, and that <lb/>the same would be true of the small number of other oil majors. <lb/>Where would the additional 75+ ppm (450-370) come from to <lb/>heat the planet by 2 degrees? <lb/>In 2006 BP&apos;s team and Z/Yen researchers independently <lb/>came up with some new estimates, largely from the reserves of <lb/>the national oil companies, of the CO 2 levels in ppm from <lb/>burning the then known fossil fuel reserves (Fig. 1). 3 <lb/>At the time, fracking and shale gas was in its infancy. With <lb/>fracking and shale gas the numbers could rise much higher. It <lb/>is fair to say that these numbers were considerably higher than <lb/>expected at the time. <lb/>This led to an obvious question, if it would be impossible to <lb/>&apos;burn&apos; reserves above 450 ppm or 500 ppm or 550 ppm because <lb/>society would not allow it, how could the reserves above that <lb/>level be on corporate balance sheets at current market prices? If <lb/>one assumed for the sake of example that 450 ppm was the level <lb/>at which an overheated society would no longer tolerate fossil <lb/>fuel usage, then 1222 -450 = 772 that couldn&apos;t be burnt. In <lb/>rough terms at that time, this meant that up to 92% of listed <lb/>assets had no value. <lb/>These discussions were shared with central bankers as <lb/>a systemic stability issue, especially once they realised the <lb/>extent to which many pension funds relied on income from <lb/>fossil fuel giants like BP and Shell. 4 This led to the formation of <lb/>the think-tank Carbon Tracker, who produced their rst report <lb/>in 2011, 5 coining the phrases &apos;unburnable carbon&apos; and <lb/>&apos;stranded assets&apos;. The nancial community, especially UK <lb/>pension funds, have widely accepted these concepts. <lb/>Meanwhile environmental researchers have realised the <lb/>threat that large fossil fuel reserves pose to the prospect of <lb/>limiting climate change. Researchers are attempting to quantify <lb/>the discrepancies between the carbon budgets for various IPCC <lb/>scenarios and the CO 2 outputs implicit in fossil fuel reserves, <lb/>pointing out that the latter are much larger than the former. <lb/>The work carried out by Z/Yen in 2006 was an estimate based <lb/>on the limited knowledge of the time. The intention of this paper <lb/>is to improve the original estimates, and carry out new calculations <lb/>based on reserves in 2022. Key Questions to be addressed include: <lb/>Is there any evidence that the concept of &apos;unburnable <lb/>carbon&apos; has in fact led to a reduction in fossil fuel reserves? <lb/>What might happen to IPCC carbon budgets, and atmo-<lb/>spheric CO 2 levels, if these reserves are in fact very &apos;burnable&apos;? <lb/>Do the comments around carbon pricing at $30-60 per <lb/>tonne still apply? <lb/>What are the implications of the current situation for both <lb/>nancial organisations and policy makers? <lb/>We leave to other writers the questions around how policy <lb/>changes such as &apos;net zero by 2050&apos; targets might reduce CO 2 <lb/>emissions. Our focus is instead on the question &apos;what is the <lb/>outcome if these policies are not implemented or are unsuccessful?&apos; <lb/>1.2 Carbon budgets <lb/>Since around 2009-10, the concept of the &apos;carbon budget&apos; has <lb/>overtaken a concern for predicted CO 2 concentration levels. The <lb/>carbon budget is the quantity of carbon dioxide (usually <lb/>measured as mass in Gigatonne) &apos;that can be emitted to the <lb/>Fig. 1 2006 predictions of increase in atmospheric CO 2 levels from <lb/>&apos;burning it all&apos; ppm v/v. <lb/>Fig. 2 CO 2 &apos;Budgets&apos; for IPCC Scenarios RCP2.6 to RCP8.5 (IPCC AR5). <lb/></body>

			<page>436</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>atmosphere before global temperature rise can be expected to <lb/>exceed a given limit&apos; 6 <lb/>The IPCC have produced a number of climate scenarios, <lb/>which relate potential climate change to various carbon <lb/>budgets. They are described in the comprehensive summary for <lb/>policy makers as part of the 2018 AR5 report 7 They described <lb/>a series of &apos;representative concentration pathways&apos; (RCP2.6, <lb/>RCP4.5, RCP6.0 and RCP8.5) which specify radiative forcing <lb/>values between 2.6 and 8.5 W m -2 in the year 2100. These <lb/>pathways lead to warming in the 2081-2100 period of 1.6 C, 2.4 <lb/>C, 2.8 C, and 4.3 C respectively (all estimates ± 0.7 C) (Fig. 2). <lb/>Carbon budgets are not xed numbers, but correspond to <lb/>broad estimates of the probabilities of temperature outcomes, <lb/>which are being constantly studied and revised. However the <lb/>overall trend is clear, that budgets are reducing as CO 2 emis-<lb/>sions continue at increasingly high levels. The Global Carbon <lb/>Project 8 in 2022 commented that &apos;The remaining carbon budget <lb/>for a 50% likelihood to limit global warming to 1.5, 1.7, and 2 <lb/>°C <lb/>has, respectively, reduced to 105 GtC (380 GtCO 2 ), 200 GtC (730 <lb/>GtCO 2 ), and 335 GtC (1230 GtCO 2 ) from the beginning of 2023, <lb/>equivalent to 9, 18, and 30 years, assuming 2022 emissions levels.&apos; <lb/>We will use the numbers listed in the budgets above to <lb/>compare with the potential CO 2 emissions from current, proven <lb/>fossil fuel reserves. <lb/>The IPCC RCP pathways can be visualised in a number of <lb/>different ways. One approach (Fig. 3) relates the pathways to <lb/>increasing atmospheric CO 2 . <lb/>Another approach (Fig. 4) is to relate the pathways to <lb/>cumulative anthropogenic CO 2 emissions. <lb/>1.3 Recent work on fossil fuel reserves <lb/>Carbon Tracker reported in 2013 (ref. 9) that potential emissions <lb/>from the world&apos;s 200 largest oil companies could be 1541 GtCO 2 , <lb/>already larger than the IPCC budget for a 2.0 °C rise in tempera-<lb/>ture (986GtCO 2 (ref. 10)). In addition to ecological implications, <lb/>this also suggests that large portions of those companies stated <lb/>reserves are effectively unusable or &apos;stranded assets&apos;. 11 <lb/>The Fossil Fuels registry has pointed out that current <lb/>reserves would already exceed the carbon budgets for a 1.5 <lb/>°C <lb/>rise in temperature, and that the reserves of certain countries, <lb/>including the US, could exceed IPCC targets by themselves. 12,13 <lb/>In 2015, Greenstone and Stewart calculated the impact of <lb/>world fossil fuel reserves as potentially producing 5520 GtCO 2 <lb/>emissions, and used this to estimate consequential temperature <lb/>increases. 14,15 <lb/>In 2016, Heede, (a pioneer in this area), and Oreskes ana-<lb/>lysed the reserves data of the largest seventy eight companies <lb/>and state entities involved in oil, gas and coal extraction. They <lb/>found that the reserves of these organisations would produce <lb/>over 160% of the 2 °C carbon budget pathway from IPCC AR5. 16 <lb/>In contrast to the above studies, Wang et al. argued in 2016 <lb/>that total CO 2 emissions and consequent climate change would <lb/>be limited by supply-side effects, notably that &apos;recoverable <lb/>reserves&apos; (oil that could be produced) were usually considerably <lb/>less than &apos;total reserves&apos; that appeared in estimates and balance <lb/>sheets 17 They expect fossil fuel production to reach a supply-<lb/>limited peak around the mid-21st century. Incorporating this <lb/>in their models limits the maximum atmospheric concentration <lb/>of CO 2 to 610 ppm by 2100, with a corresponding temperature <lb/>rise of 2.6 °C. <lb/>There are considerable variations and hence uncertainties in <lb/>these estimates, as different countries and companies have <lb/>different denition of proven reserves. The BP review of World <lb/>Energy states, for example that &apos;The data series for proved oil <lb/>reserves in this year&apos;s review does not necessarily meet the deni-<lb/>tions, guidelines and practices used for determining proved reserves <lb/>at company level&apos;. 18 Coal reserves, even in the USA, are subject to <lb/>wider variations in estimation methodology, as discussed on <lb/>Global Energy Monitor 19 <lb/>The variations increase in &apos;unconventional&apos; reserves such as <lb/>shale oil and gas. A thorough review of these uncertainties was <lb/>carried out by McGlade in 2012. 20 While some producers exag-<lb/>gerate their reserves for political reasons, using proven reserves <lb/>leads to generally conservative estimates. In addition, changes in <lb/>technology can move potential reserves to proven reserves, <lb/>Fig. 3 Atmospheric CO 2 levels for IPCC scenarios RCP2.6 to RCP8.5 <lb/>(IPCC AR5 data) (Wikimedia Creative Commons License). <lb/>Fig. 4 Cumulative CO 2 emissions: scenarios RCP2.6 to RCP8.5 (IPCC <lb/>AR5 SPM Fig. 10). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>437 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>especially in unconventional sources and new regions (such as the <lb/>offshore Arctic). We discuss this further in our summary below. <lb/>1.4 Carbon sinks <lb/>Previous studies, including our rst analysis in 2005, did not take <lb/>into account carbon sinks in predicting CO 2 levels resulting from <lb/>exploiting all fossil fuel reserves. One important question, is the <lb/>uncertainty of whether current sinks (oceans, soils, forests) <lb/>would continue to function as at present at increasingly high CO 2 <lb/>levels. Friedlingstein expressed this cogently in 2015: 21 <lb/>&apos;It was initially believed that the ocean was the main sink of <lb/>carbon until it became clear that a land sink was needed to close the <lb/>carbon budget. 25 It is now admitted that both the land and the <lb/>ocean play a comparable role, each removing from the atmosphere <lb/>about 25% of the anthropogenic CO 2 emissions. 4,26,27 <lb/>However, the obvious question is whether the ocean and the land <lb/>ecosystems will continue to provide such a service to humanity, <lb/>removing about half of the CO 2 emitted by human activities. <lb/>Without these land and ocean sinks, the atmospheric CO 2 increase <lb/>would be about twice as fast; current atmospheric CO 2 concentra-<lb/>tion would be already above 500 ppm, inducing a warming of more <lb/>than 2 K above pre-industrial level (assuming a median estimate of <lb/>3 K for the climate sensitivity). <lb/>A longer discussion can be found in ESI † to IPCC AR5 (ref. <lb/>22) (ref. 4 in Freidlingstein&apos;s report above). and in ref. 25-27 <lb/>cited above. Tans discusses constraints on the CO 2 budget, <lb/>while two papers by Le Quéré discuss trends in CO 2 sources &amp; <lb/>sinks and set out global carbon budget data. 23-25 <lb/>While the concept of carbon budgets does side step, to some <lb/>extent, the issues around the uncertainty of carbon sinks, we <lb/>have incorporated some simple calculations into this paper. <lb/>Essentially our numbers show &apos;this is the best case estimate for <lb/>carbon dioxide concentrations assuming that carbon sinks continue <lb/>to function as they do at present&apos;. <lb/>2 Methodology <lb/>We have attempted where possible to follow the recommenda-<lb/>tions of the World Resources Institute in distinguishing <lb/>between proven and probable reserves of fossil fuels. 26 We have <lb/>used the US Energy Information Administration estimate of 7% <lb/>of oil and gas fossil reserves 27 are used for non-fuel uses. <lb/>Our major source for 2022 data is the BP Annual Statistical <lb/>Bulletin of World Energy 28 and other sources include the fossil <lb/>fuel registry, 29 the US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Adminis-<lb/>tration, 30 and the US Energy Information Administration data sets. 31 <lb/>Our data for 2005 represents the best retrospective sources we <lb/>can nd for that year, sometime published quite a lot aerwards. <lb/>This can lead to discrepancies with the numbers of our original <lb/>calculations done in 2006, where we were producing &apos;best esti-<lb/>mates&apos; with the data available at the time. In particular, our <lb/>current calculation of 2005 gas reserves is notably lower than our <lb/>original estimate, largely due to the distinction between proven <lb/>and probable reserves. At the end of 2023, we checked whether <lb/>new estimates of reserves had become available during the <lb/>writing of this paper in 2022-23 and found no new numbers. <lb/>All of our data sources, and the relevant calculations, are <lb/>available in a downloadable Excel Workbook. We have also written <lb/>an appendix to this paper going through our step by step calcu-<lb/>lations in a series of tables (e.g. &apos;Table x has the total carbon from <lb/>quoted reserves, Table y deducts non fuel uses, Table z estimates <lb/>the impact of 77 years fossil fuel use at current levels&apos; etc). <lb/>Not all hydrocarbon reserves end up as fuel. The US Energy <lb/>Information Administration estimates that around 7% of oil is <lb/>converted into non-fuel uses such as industrial solvents, lubri-<lb/>cants and bitumen. 32 For natural gas, the proportion looks to be <lb/>slightly lower (3.75%) when comparing current total annual <lb/>consumption of 4 trillion cubic metres with the 150 billion <lb/>cubic metres used in non-fuel applications. The largest of these <lb/>are fertilizer manufacture and methanol production. 33 <lb/>While coal has potential for being a rich source of valuable <lb/>chemical intermediates, this is still a developing application, <lb/>albeit with increasing development in China for olen and <lb/>glycol production. Figures from IEA resources on non-energy <lb/>use of coal suggests these amount to around 4.5%. 34,35 <lb/>The relevant equations for converting commonly used fossil fuel <lb/>quantities to tonnes of carbon dioxide can be summarised as below. <lb/>Coal: (reserves &apos;short tons&apos; × 0.90718 = reserves in metric <lb/>tonnes). <lb/>(reserves in metric tonnes × 0.9 = tonnes carbon in <lb/>anthracite/hard coal). <lb/>(reserves in metric tonnes × 0.6 = tonnes in sub-<lb/>bituminous &apos;brown coal&apos;) <lb/>(tonnes carbon in coal × 3.67 (44/12) = tonnes CO 2 <lb/>from coal reserves). <lb/>(tonnes CO 2 from coal reserves × 0.955 = total CO 2 <lb/>allowing for 4.5% non-fuel use). <lb/>The calculations for coal are fairly straightforward, with the <lb/>major uncertainty being the differing proportions of carbon in <lb/>the various types of coal. <lb/>Oil: (reserves in barrels × 0.1364 = reserves in metric <lb/>tonnes). <lb/>(reserves in tonnes × 0.85 = tonnes of carbon in <lb/>reserves). <lb/>(tonnes carbon in reserves × 3.67 = tonnes CO 2 from <lb/>oil reserves). <lb/>(tonnes CO 2 from oil reserves × 0.93 = total CO 2 <lb/>allowing for 7% non-fuel use). <lb/>Crude oil has a number of fairly standardised industry <lb/>conversion factors owing to the wide variety of Imperial and metric <lb/>units used by the industry for more than a century. A &apos;barrel&apos; of oil <lb/>is, these days, an abstract 42 US gallon quantity derived from <lb/>historic wooden barrels, and the conversion factor of 0.1364 <lb/>reects the average density of the most common crude oils. For tar <lb/>sands, which have a higher density than conventional crude, the <lb/>conversion factor could be higher (around 0.15 tonnes per barrel). <lb/>Gas: (reserves in billion cubic metres × 0.76 = mass of <lb/>natural gas in 10 6 tonnes). <lb/>(tonnes natural gas × 2.75 = tonnes CO 2 from gas <lb/>combustion). <lb/>(tonnes CO 2 from gas combustion × 0.965 = total CO 2 <lb/>allowing for 3.7% non-fuel use <lb/>or <lb/></body>

			<page>438</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>(reserves in billion cubic metres × 34.121 = energy content <lb/>in trillion British Thermal Units -&apos;btu&apos;) <lb/>(Energy content in million btu × 14.43 = kg carbon per <lb/>million btu). <lb/>(kg carbon × 1000 × 3.67 = tonnes carbon dioxide). <lb/>The conversion via energy content (btu) looks unusual but is <lb/>actually widely used in the industry. It allows for variations of <lb/>gas volume at various temperatures and pressures, and the fact <lb/>that natural gas is not pure methane but has variable amounts <lb/>of ethane and higher hydrocarbons. The two methods give <lb/>results that can be reconciled. <lb/>3 Calculation results <lb/>3.1 Fuel reserves and asset life <lb/>Using the proven reserves for fossil fuels, and conversion factors <lb/>mentioned above, allows direct calculation of the CO 2 emitted <lb/>by combustion of those reserves. We have calculated these <lb/>individually for each fossil fuel, and details of those calculations <lb/>can be seen in the appendix to this paper. <lb/>Looking at Table 2 we can see that reserves of all types of <lb/>fossil fuel, except for &apos;Brown Coal&apos;, have increased from 2005 to <lb/>2023. This has implications for the potential life of these <lb/>assets: <lb/>Global coal consumption reached 8 billion (8.0 × 10 9 ) <lb/>tonnes in 2022. 36 Proven coal stocks could supply over 130 years <lb/>of coal consumption at 2022 levels. <lb/>Global Oil consumption reached 36.37 billion barrels pa in <lb/>2022. 37 Proven oil stocks could supply over 47 years of oil <lb/>consumption at 2022 levels. Oil sands and shale fracking add an <lb/>extra 23 years, summing to 70 years. <lb/>Current natural gas consumption is around 4 trillion cubic <lb/>metres pa, 38 so the gas reserves above represent around 46 years <lb/>supply for conventional reserves and an additional 54 years <lb/>when shale gas is included. <lb/>These numbers suggest that there are already sufficient <lb/>reserves of fossil fuels to take the world to, or very close to, the <lb/>year 2100, the endpoint for the various IPCC RCP scenarios. <lb/>3.2 Potential emissions from fossil fuel reserves, allowing <lb/>for non fuel usage <lb/>Using the algorithms described in the Methodology (section 2 <lb/>above), we can estimate the potential CO 2 emissions from <lb/>current proven reserves. This amounts to 4777 Gt CO 2 (Fig. 5). <lb/>Of this 4777 Gt CO 2 total, over half (3048 Gt CO 2 ) comes from <lb/>various forms of coal, 1029 Gt comes from traditional and novel <lb/>oil reserves, and 700 Gt CO 2 from gas. It is notable how the <lb/>advent of new techniques for oil and gas exploitation (tar sands <lb/>and fracking) have more than doubled the potential impact of <lb/>these fuels since 2005. <lb/>Our estimates are slightly lower than some previous ones, <lb/>partly due to the use of more recent data, and partly because of <lb/>taking into account the lower carbon content of &apos;Brown Coals&apos; <lb/>(sub-bituminous and lignite). <lb/>Fig. 6 compares the potential CO 2 emissions from Fig. 5 with <lb/>the IPCC RCP scenarios. The background colours reect the <lb/>Table 2 Proven reserves for major fossil fuels <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 <lb/>2005 <lb/>&apos;Hard coal&apos; anthracite and bituminous <lb/>(billion metric tonnes) <lb/>754 <lb/>478 <lb/>&apos;Brown coal&apos; sub-bituminous and lignite <lb/>(billion metric tonnes) <lb/>321 <lb/>430 <lb/>Oil (billion barrels) <lb/>1735 <lb/>1201 <lb/>Natural gas (trillion cubic metres) <lb/>188 <lb/>156 <lb/>Oil sands (billion barrels) <lb/>423 <lb/>84.7 <lb/>Shale oil (billion barrels) <lb/>419 <lb/>0 <lb/>Shale gas (trillion cubic metres) <lb/>214 <lb/>15 <lb/>Table 1 Data sources and values <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Values <lb/>Data sources <lb/>Global proved coal reserves/tonnes <lb/>1.07411 × 10 12 <lb/>BP <lb/>Global proved oil reserves/barrels <lb/>1.7348 × 10 12 <lb/>BP <lb/>Oil sands reserves/barrels <lb/>4.232 × 10 11 <lb/>BP <lb/>Proven natural gas reserves/10 9 m 3 <lb/>1.881 × 10 5 <lb/>ΕΙΑ <lb/>Shale tight oil reserves/10 9 barrels <lb/>418.9 <lb/>ΕΙΑ <lb/>Shale gas reserves/ 3 <lb/>7576.6 <lb/>ΕΙΑ <lb/>CO 2 /C ratio <lb/>3.67 <lb/>Proportion of carbon in coal <lb/>0.9 <lb/>ΕΙΑ <lb/>Proportion of carbon in sub-bituminous coal &amp; lignite <lb/>0.6 <lb/>ΕΙΑ <lb/>Mass of Earth&apos;s atmosphere/metric tonnes <lb/>5.148 × 10 15 <lb/>Trenbeth &amp; Smith a <lb/>Density of crude oil (tonne/barrel) <lb/>0.1364 <lb/>BP <lb/>Proportion of carbon in oil (w/w) <lb/>0.85 <lb/>Britannica <lb/>Proportion of carbon in natural gas (kg/10 6 btu) <lb/>14.43 <lb/>US EPA <lb/>2022 proportion of CO 2 in atmosphere/ppm <lb/>417 <lb/>NOAA <lb/>Oil reserves used non-combustion purposes (USA) <lb/>7% <lb/>EIA <lb/>Conversion of wt/wt to vol/vol <lb/>0.667 <lb/>Lenntech b <lb/>a Trenbeth K, and Smith L, 2005 The Mass of the Atmosphere: A Constraint on Global Analyses J.Climate, 6, 864-875. b PPM converter for Gases <lb/>https://www.lenntech.com/calculators/ppm/converter-parts-per-million.htm (accessed May 2023). <lb/></body>
    
            <note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>439 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>
    
            <body>Fig. 5 Potential CO 2 emissions deducting non-fuel uses (Gt CO 2 ). <lb/>Fig. 6 Potential CO 2 emissions compared to IPCC RCP scenarios. <lb/></body>

			<page>440</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 7 Potential increase in CO 2 concentration in atmosphere, deducting non-fuel uses (ppm v/v). <lb/>Fig. 8 Potential CO 2 emissions to 2100 (Gt CO 2 ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>441 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>wide range of uncertainty in the IPCC scenarios mentioned in <lb/>Fig. 1 above. RCP 2.6 (light green) was estimated as 510 to 1505 <lb/>GtCO 2 , RCP 4.5 (mauve) was estimated as 2180 to 3690 Gt CO 2 , <lb/>and RCP 6.0 (brown) was 3080 to 4585 Gt CO 2 . <lb/>Potential CO 2 from oil reserves alone (1029 Gt) takes the <lb/>world past the IPCC RCP 2.6 threshold, while adding gas (+700 <lb/>Gt) takes it close to the start of RCP 4.5. Coal reserves alone <lb/>(3048 Gt CO 2 ) take the world close to the threshold of RCP 6.0. <lb/>3.3 Increase in atmospheric CO 2 , allowing for non-fuel <lb/>usage <lb/>Using the algorithms described in the methodology section <lb/>above, we can estimate the possible incremental change in <lb/>atmospheric CO 2 emissions from current proven reserves. For <lb/>our 2022 gures, this amounts to 618 ppm v/v. Added to 2022 <lb/>CO 2 levels of 417 ppm this would result in an atmosphere with <lb/>over 1000 ppm CO 2 . <lb/>Although our re-estimate of 2005 gures is lower than our <lb/>original 2006 calculation, burning all the reserves present in <lb/>2005 would still result in atmospheric CO 2 approaching <lb/>800 ppm (Fig. 7). <lb/>This gure represents the results of the (hopefully) hypo-<lb/>thetical experiment -what happens to CO2 levels if all current <lb/>reserves were combusted in an instantaneous process? While these <lb/>numbers look alarming, there are a number of factors that <lb/>could reduce them somewhat. <lb/>3.4 Calculations for 2100 -burning 77 years of reserves <lb/>The IPCC RCP scenarios predict pathways to various radiative <lb/>forcing values in the year 2100, 77 years in the future from this <lb/>paper. In the graphics and tables above, it can be seen that <lb/>proven reserves are already sufficient to satisfy demands of fossil <lb/>fuels well beyond 2100 at current levels of consumption. For <lb/>example proven coal stocks could last for 130 years at current <lb/>levels of consumption. A reasonable question to ask is, therefore, <lb/>&apos;What happens if we burn 77 years of fossil fuel reserves? This <lb/>methodology reduces coal CO 2 by 77/130 (where 130 is the total <lb/>years of reserves at current consumption), and gas CO 2 by 77/100 <lb/>(where 100 is the years of reserves at current consumption). Oil <lb/>CO 2 is slightly increased, as current reserves are 70 years (Fig. 8). <lb/>This analysis notably reduces the contribution of coal to the <lb/>carbon budget, as a sizeable portion of coal reserves might only <lb/>be consumed aer 2100. Nonetheless, the potential emissions <lb/>from 77 years consuming current reserves are still sufficient to <lb/>exceed the IPCC RCP2.6 and RCP4.5 budgets, and to land within <lb/>the range for RCP6.0 (Fig. 9). <lb/>3.5 Potential CO 2 levels and the impact of carbon sinks <lb/>Steady &apos;business as usual&apos; levels of fossil fuel consumption would <lb/>be to some extent mitigated by various carbon sinks, in soil, <lb/>plants (especially trees) and in the ocean. We can estimate how <lb/>much CO 2 is currently being absorbed by these sinks using data <lb/>from recent years. In 2005, CO 2 levels were 370 ppm and carbon <lb/>emissions were 29.6 billion tonnes. Carbon emission from 2005 <lb/>to 2021 totalled 583 billion tonnes, 39 in theory sufficient to <lb/>increase atmospheric levels by 72.5 ppm. The actual increase <lb/>from 2005 to 2022 was 38 ppm, so that approximately 47% was <lb/>absorbed by carbon sinks. A more detailed tabulation and <lb/>calculation is shown in Table 15 of the appendix to this paper. <lb/>Fig. 10 shows the possible changes to CO 2 levels following <lb/>fossil fuel consumption continuing at current rates until 2100 <lb/>with carbon sinks maintaining their efficiency. Essentially these <lb/>numbers show that &apos;business as usual&apos; carbon dioxide emis-<lb/>sions are likely to produce atmospheric CO 2 levels in 2100 <lb/>exceeding, at best, 620 ppm. If carbon sinks become less <lb/>effective, we could see that rise to around 860 ppm. <lb/>Fig. 9 Potential CO 2 emissions to 2100 compared to IPCC RCP scenarios. <lb/></body>

			<page>442</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>The graphic below relates the numbers from Fig. 10 to the <lb/>IPCC scenarios previously shown in Fig. 3 above (Fig. 11). <lb/>Even if carbon sinks continue to function as at present, there <lb/>is sufficient CO 2 from proven reserves to maintain current rates <lb/>of fossil fuel consumption, taking the world past RCP 4.5 and <lb/>towards RCP 6.0. <lb/>4 Summary and discussion of results <lb/>What are the main points gathered from the data analysis <lb/>above, and what implications does this have for current carbon <lb/>budgets and the future of the fossil fuel industry? Our thoughts <lb/>are as follows. <lb/>4.1 Current reserves generate sufficient CO 2 to &apos;bust&apos; IPCC <lb/>budgets <lb/>Current &apos;proven reserves&apos; at the start of 2022, would generate an <lb/>estimated 4777 Gt CO 2 aer allowing for non-fuel uses. This <lb/>quantity exceeds the mean CO 2 budgets for IPCC RCP2.6 (990 <lb/>Gt), RCP4.5 (2860 Gt), and RCP6.0 (3885 Gt) and is close to the <lb/>lower range for RCP8.5 (5185 Gt). <lb/>Fig. 12 relates the potential CO 2 emissions of current <lb/>reserves to the IPCC RCP pathways mentioned in Fig. 4 above. <lb/>The RCP pathways generate estimates of cumulative CO 2 by <lb/>adding the numbers quoted in the paragraph above to the <lb/>historic emissions from 1870-2010 (for IPCC AR5) and/or 2019 <lb/>(for IPCC AR6). The latter source quotes cumulative historic <lb/>emissions as 2400 Gt CO 2 . Adding the 3400+ Gt from exploiting <lb/>current reserves at their current rate, takes the total to 5800 Gt <lb/>CO 2 by 2100. As Fig. 12 shows, this is very much in the range of <lb/>RCP 6.0 -a temperature anomaly over 2.5 C. These numbers <lb/>provide support for the position of the International Energy <lb/>Agency that &apos;no new long-lead time oil and gas projects are needed. <lb/>Neither are new coal mines, mine extensions, or unabated coal <lb/>plants&apos;. <lb/>4.2 No evidence of peak oil <lb/>Our estimates of the carbon potential of current (early 2022) <lb/>reserves are over 50% higher than our revised estimates from <lb/>2005 proven reserves. Recent attention 40 to new &apos;carbon <lb/>bomb&apos; fossil fuel discoveries suggest this increasing trend is <lb/>set to continue into the short-medium term. These develop-<lb/>ments could add over 600 Gt to our estimates above. Fig. 13 <lb/>Fig. 10 Potential CO 2 concentrations by 2100 with functioning carbon sinks. <lb/>Fig. 11 How current reserves impact potential CO 2 levels in IPCC <lb/>scenarios RCP2.6 to RCP8.5 (IPCC AR5 data). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>443 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 12 Cumulative CO 2 emissions: scenarios RCP2.6 to RCP8.5 (IPCC AR5 SPM Fig. 10). <lb/>Fig. 13 A semi-quantitative representation of the carbon potential of coal, oil and gas reserves. <lb/></body>

			<page>444</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>shows a semi-quantitative representation of this situation. <lb/>The blue, orange and black circles in the foreground indicate <lb/>the relative sizes of CO 2 from gas, oil and coal, and are <lb/>superimposed on translucent circles representing IPCC RCP <lb/>budgets. The oil circle alone is close to exceeding that of <lb/>RCP2.6, especially if these new developments are taken into <lb/>account. <lb/>4.3 Fracking and tar sands are driving reserves increases <lb/>The largest change in proven fossil fuels reserves has been from <lb/>the advent of new sources such as oil from tar sands and both <lb/>oil and gas from fracking oil shale. Gas reserves from shale <lb/>fracking now exceed that in &apos;conventional&apos; gas elds. Worry-<lb/>ingly, &apos;potentially exploitable&apos; shale gas resources in Russia, <lb/>Chain, Argentina and Algeria are around 3 times higher than <lb/>the &apos;proven reserves&apos; (mainly US) in our calculations above. 41 <lb/>4.4 Our numbers are very probably underestimates <lb/>The numbers presented above should be regarded as &apos;lower <lb/>limits&apos; which would almost certainly be exceeded in real life. <lb/>Firstly, oil companies tend to have conservative accounting <lb/>policies -usually recording only those reserves which have <lb/>a very high certainty (&gt;90%) of being successfully exploited. 42 <lb/>Secondly, advances in technology will oen extend the actual <lb/>amount extracted from Oil and Gas elds. This is particularly <lb/>notable for large elds producing over an extended period of time, <lb/>where companies are incentivised to exploit infrastructure in place. <lb/>A well-documented example is BP&apos;s large Forties eld in the <lb/>North Sea. In 1970 when the discovery of the eld was <lb/>announced, it was estimated that the recoverable amount of oil <lb/>was 1.8 billion barrels, 43 and production was expected to stop in <lb/>the 1990&apos;s. In 2003 the eld was sold to a smaller company, <lb/>(Apache Oil) aer BP estimated just 144 million barrels <lb/>remained. By 2010, the eld had produced 2.64 billion barrels. 44 <lb/>The eld is still producing oil in 2023, 45 with estimated <lb/>production by Apache approaching 300 million barrels. 46 <lb/>We also note the number of new discoveries made during the <lb/>preparation of this paper -not yet classied as proven reserves, <lb/>but signicant in size. The &apos;Carbon Bomb&apos; report mentioned <lb/>above (from the Guardian Newspaper) identied 195 oil and gas <lb/>projects that could each add a billion tonnes of CO 2 to the <lb/>atmosphere. 42 These projects are not included in our calcula-<lb/>tions, as they do not yet appear in authoritative sources like the <lb/>BP Guide to World Energy (who have not included reserves <lb/>estimates in the last two surveys). <lb/>5 Conclusions and the way forward <lb/>5.1 Is coal the big problem? <lb/>Even with the advent of shale gas and oil from fracking, coal still <lb/>represents well over 60% of the potential CO 2 emissions from <lb/>fossil fuel reserves. Although coal usage is falling in some <lb/>countries, 38% of global electricity, and over 40% of global CO 2 <lb/>emissions, comes from coal and new thermal coal-burning <lb/>power stations are still being commissioned, notably in <lb/>China, 47 India and many less developed countries. Reasons for <lb/>this include coal becoming cheaper as some countries abandon <lb/>it, the ease of overland transport (in places without pipeline <lb/>infrastructure), and the ease of implementing well tried thermal <lb/>technology. 48,49 For example, several countries in the EU have <lb/>reopened or extended coal power plants following natural gas <lb/>prices rising aer the invasion of Ukraine. 50 <lb/>We might expect that proven coal reserves will continue to <lb/>rise, given the wide distribution of coal around the world (with <lb/>notable untapped reserves in Russian Siberia). However it is also <lb/>likely that some coal will be &apos;le in the ground&apos; as the operating <lb/>cost advantages of other technologies increase. Some thermal <lb/>power stations designed for coal can be converted to run on <lb/>natural gas or biomass, 51 increasing their efficiency as well as <lb/>reducing their carbon footprint. It is also feasible, though <lb/>economically challenging, to mothball coal mines. 52 Individual <lb/>countries can make telling contributions, such as the recent <lb/>decision of India to pause coal generating capacity for ve years 53 <lb/>However, the widespread availability of coal deposits around <lb/>the world means there is always a temptation for users to switch <lb/>back to coal when expedient or cheap. The international commu-<lb/>nity could discourage that &apos;switching-back&apos; by measures such as: <lb/>Technology sharing of renewable electrical generation <lb/>methods such as solar PV. <lb/>Converting coal to gas powered generation. In the <lb/>appendix (Table 16) we show calculations for a 1000 MW coal <lb/>powered plant that would emit 5 million tonnes CO 2 at 60% <lb/>capacity factor. A gas powered 1000 MW plant would emit less <lb/>than 2 million tonnes CO 2 at the same capacity factor (not only <lb/>does gas have a lower carbon content, combined cycle gas <lb/>generators have a better energy efficiency than coal plants 54 ). <lb/>Additionally, gas generation can be used with non-fossil fuel <lb/>biogas sources. <lb/>Subsidizing the decommissioning and removal of coal <lb/>power stations to remove the temptation to switch back. 55 <lb/>Building renewable electrical generating plants on old coal <lb/>plant premises, to take advantage of existing electrical infra-<lb/>structure, generators, and grid connections. A long-term <lb/>example of this is the UK&apos;s new STEP fusion reactor at an old <lb/>coal power site in Nottinghamshire -ultimately using tradi-<lb/>tional steam turbines and generators to connect to the grid. See <lb/>the graphic on Bay-Fusion&apos;s blog page. 56 <lb/>Encouragingly, a 2022 analysis of Chinese coal station <lb/>construction posits that much of the new building is carried out <lb/>by provincial authorities seeking short term economic stimulus. <lb/>The capacity factor of these power plants is below 50%, many <lb/>are loss-making and liable to closure in the not too distant <lb/>future. 57 Coal may indeed be the big problem, but hopefully not <lb/>an insuperable one. <lb/>5.2 Carbon pricing and &apos;shutting down coal&apos; <lb/>The section above leads to the consideration of the role of <lb/>carbon pricing to control emissions. In the introduction above, <lb/>we commented that in 2005 it seemed that carbon prices <lb/>around $30-60 per tonne of CO 2 would allow sufficient invest-<lb/>ment to avoid severe climate change. One positive development <lb/>since then has been the expansion of carbon trading schemes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>445 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>The IMF report that now around 30% of emissions are covered <lb/>by carbon taxes or emissions trading schemes. 58 <lb/>It is perhaps not surprising that much current thinking calls <lb/>for governments to impose/enforce rather higher prices. The <lb/>IMF report mentioned above calls for carbon to be priced <lb/>around $75 per tonne CO 2 . A Reuters poll of climate economists <lb/>in 2012 suggested that prices of $100 per tonne CO 2 were <lb/>required for countries to meet their &apos;net-zero by 2050&apos; targets. 59 <lb/>Our analysis prompts the obvious question -if coal is poten-<lb/>tially responsible for over half of carbon emitted up to 2100, how <lb/>can we get rid of it? The 1000 MW power station mentioned in the <lb/>discussion on coal above might more than halve its emissions by <lb/>converting to gas. Table 16 in the appendix shows how the <lb/>economics of the plant might change. Using medium term prices <lb/>(pre Covid and Ukraine) such a plant would save 16% on its <lb/>annual fuel cost without a carbon tax -perhaps not enough to <lb/>defray the costs of switching? At $20 per tonne this rises to 35% <lb/>saving, at $50 per tonne 44%, and at $75 per tonne 49%. <lb/>This simple analysis shows that prices in the $50-$75 per <lb/>tonne band might induce switching out of coal and consequent <lb/>reduction in emissions. A more sophisticated analysis has been <lb/>carried out by Stanford University in a 2022 report on &apos;carbon <lb/>arbitrage&apos;, the process of investing to &apos;go short on coal&apos;. 60 They <lb/>put the &apos;social cost of carbon&apos; and the corresponding benet of <lb/>removing it at $75 per tonne. <lb/>5.3 Why are fossil fuel companies still exploring for new <lb/>reserves -don&apos;t they believe the science of climate change? <lb/>From the authors&apos; experience, and industry contacts, these are <lb/>some of the reasons that the fossil fuel industry (particularly oil <lb/>companies) are continuing to explore for new reserves. <lb/>(a) Demand for energy: Fossil fuels, such as oil, gas, and coal, <lb/>still account for a signicant portion of global energy consump-<lb/>tion. As the global population continues to grow, and developing <lb/>economies increase their energy needs, there remains a demand <lb/>for these energy sources. Even with the emergence of renewable <lb/>energy sources, fossil fuels still offer a lucrative market with <lb/>established infrastructure and customer base. <lb/>(b) Scepticism around &apos;stranded assets&apos; and Environmental, <lb/>Social, &amp; Governance (ESG) factors in general. While some inves-<lb/>tors have accepted the concept of &apos;stranded assets and &apos;unburn-<lb/>able carbon&apos;, this has not translated into signicant share price <lb/>impact according to a 2015 analysis by Griffin et al. 61 Bebbington 62 <lb/>(2020) amplied this in a series of interviews with Oil industry <lb/>stakeholders and observers -stranded assets were &apos;accepted as <lb/>a concept&apos; but one that had little importance until &apos;information <lb/>was demanded by stock markets and/or governments&apos;. <lb/>(c) Protability and price spikes: Fossil fuel exploration and <lb/>production can be highly protable for companies. Companies <lb/>aim to maximize their prots by meeting the existing demand. <lb/>In particular, companies with lower cost crude can take prot-<lb/>able advantage of price volatility even in an overall declining <lb/>market. In contrast to coal, reducing oil production capacity by <lb/>shutting down entire elds is &apos;lumpy&apos; and there is little option <lb/>to mothball oil wells. 63 This is likely to lead to price spikes in an <lb/>otherwise declining oil price 64,65 A recent article in Reuters <lb/>noted that companies claim to &apos;invest to maintain price <lb/>stability&apos; 66 -although one might be sceptical of this claim given <lb/>the large prots made by companies during the recent oil and <lb/>gas price rises caused by the war in Ukraine. An economically <lb/>rational approach might be to develop a new eld and run it at <lb/>less than full production capacity until prices spike. This <lb/>approach effectively generates a &apos;real option&apos; value to expanding <lb/>or maintaining oil reserves, which has been recognised by <lb/>industry economists since the 1990&apos;s. 67 One could imagine <lb/>these valuations being used in compensation cases if/when <lb/>legislation forces oil elds to be abandoned (see next point). <lb/>(d) The value of &apos;booked reserves&apos;: Companies instinctively <lb/>explore and develop new reserves as their current reserves <lb/>deplete. Given that rms are oen valued by reserve capacity, <lb/>adding to it cheaply (by acquiring rights to undeveloped reserves) <lb/>looks good for shareholders. One might summarise the attitude <lb/>as &apos;if it can be brought onstream quickly and cheaply, then explore <lb/>and drill&apos;. Furthermore, once a reserve has been quantied and <lb/>valued, it can be the subject of compensation claims in Investor-<lb/>State Dispute Settlement (ISDS) cases. 68 ISDS clauses embedded <lb/>in the international energy charter treaty have allowed Oil and <lb/>Gas companies to pursue over 200 court cases against countries <lb/>seeking to implement fossil fuel reduction policies. <lb/>(e) Uncertain transition and new technologies: While there is <lb/>a global push towards transitioning to renewable energy, the <lb/>transition process takes time. Fossil fuel companies may continue <lb/>exploration as they anticipate a gradual shi in energy sources, <lb/>allowing them to adapt their business models and investments <lb/>accordingly. 69 Many Oil and Gas companies are pursuing tech-<lb/>nological solutions that promise the exploitation of fossil fuels in <lb/>a low/lower carbon way. Examples include the production of blue/ <lb/>green hydrogen, 70 carbon capture, 71 and ammonia production. 72 <lb/>Le alone, fossil fuel industries are likely to carry on a large <lb/>amount of business as usual, interspersed with a rather gradual <lb/>response to changes they see taking decades to come to fruition. <lb/>Investment in oil and gas elds continues unabated. 73 While they <lb/>recognise that governments may reach international agreements <lb/>and enact policies to restrict fossil fuel use, their actions show <lb/>that &apos;they don&apos;t believe it will happen any time soon&apos;. The long-<lb/>standing industry discount rate (10%) 74 to assess new energy <lb/>investments is still being applied in 2023 75 despite the substan-<lb/>tial rise in interest rates over the last few years. Given that <lb/>discount rates are a combination of &apos;risk-free&apos; bond interest rates <lb/>and an industry-related &apos;risk premium&apos;, this can only imply that <lb/>they do not see increased risks from climate change policies. <lb/>What are the policy options for governments in this situation? <lb/>5.4 What policies could governments implement to <lb/>convince investors and fossil fuel companies that they are <lb/>serious about climate change? <lb/>Governments can implement several policies to convince <lb/>investors and fossil fuel companies that they are serious about <lb/>their net zero carbon targets: <lb/>(1) Clear and ambitious regulations: Governments should <lb/>establish clear and ambitious regulations that set out the <lb/>requirements and timeline for achieving net zero carbon targets. <lb/></body>

			<page>446</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>These regulations should provide a stable and predictable policy <lb/>framework, giving investors and companies the condence to <lb/>transition towards cleaner energy sources. The breadth of the <lb/>challenge is illustrated by the lengthy, comprehensive, report 76 <lb/>by the Energy Transitions Commission (ETC), which discusses <lb/>the need to cut coal use by &gt;80%, gas use by &gt;55% and oil use by <lb/>&gt;75% by 2050. ETC does not expect carbon capture or removal to <lb/>play a signicant role in reduction, and instead call for reduced <lb/>investment in fossil fuel supply. In some notable cases, 77 coun-<lb/>tries have actually announced that no further fossil fuel explo-<lb/>ration will be allowed in their territories. <lb/>(2) Carbon pricing: More governments could introduce or <lb/>strengthen carbon pricing mechanisms like the EU ETS. These <lb/>mechanisms put a price on carbon emissions, incentivizing <lb/>companies to reduce their carbon footprint and invest in <lb/>cleaner technologies. Carbon pricing provides economic signals <lb/>that align with net zero goals and encourages investors to <lb/>support low-carbon projects. <lb/>(3) Renewable energy incentives: Governments can provide <lb/>incentives and subsidies for renewable energy projects, making <lb/>them more attractive for investors. These incentives can include <lb/>tax credits, feed-in tariffs, grants, or low-interest loans. By <lb/>promoting the growth of renewable energy, governments signal <lb/>their commitment to decarbonization and create investment <lb/>opportunities in the sector. <lb/>(4) Support for research and development: Governments can <lb/>invest in research and development (R&amp;D) initiatives focused on <lb/>clean energy technologies. By funding R&amp;D projects and <lb/>offering grants or tax credits for innovation, governments can <lb/>stimulate the development of new solutions and attract private <lb/>investment in clean technologies. <lb/>(5) Green infrastructure investment: Governments can <lb/>prioritize investments in green infrastructure projects, such as <lb/>renewable energy installations, public transportation systems, <lb/>and energy-efficient buildings. By demonstrating a commit-<lb/>ment to sustainable infrastructure, governments can create <lb/>a conducive environment for investors and companies to align <lb/>their activities with net zero goals. <lb/>(6) ESG disclosure and reporting: Governments can mandate <lb/>enhanced environmental, social, and governance (ESG) disclosure <lb/>and reporting requirements for companies. This ensures that <lb/>investors have access to transparent and standardized information <lb/>about companies&apos; climate-related risks and opportunities. <lb/>Improved disclosure can facilitate informed decision-making and <lb/>encourage investors to support companies that align with net zero <lb/>targets. Investors generally welcome clear rules around ESG and <lb/>become frustrated by regulatory instability 78,79 <lb/>(7) Collaborative engagement: Governments can engage in <lb/>collaborative dialogues with investors, nancial institutions, and <lb/>fossil fuel companies to discuss the transition to a low-carbon <lb/>economy. By involving stakeholders in the policy-making <lb/>process, governments can address concerns, build consensus, <lb/>and foster cooperation towards achieving net zero goals. <lb/>(8) &apos;Just transition&apos; plans: A just transition approach helps <lb/>mitigate resistance to the transition and ensures a fair and equi-<lb/>table distribution of the benets of a low-carbon economy. A <lb/>focused example of such a plan has been promulgated in the <lb/>North Sea by employee groups working alongside environmen-<lb/>talists. 80 A much broader outline from McKinsey 81 looks at aggre-<lb/>gate shis needed for net-zero economies, on energy, land-use, <lb/>industries and individuals. It comments that cumulative spending <lb/>of about $275 trillion on physical assets would be required to <lb/>achieve this. Governments should develop comprehensive just <lb/>transition plans that support workers and communities affected <lb/>by the shi away from fossil fuels. These plans should include <lb/>measures for retraining and reskilling workers, creating alterna-<lb/>tive job opportunities, and providing support to impacted regions. <lb/>(9) Government &apos;skin in the game&apos;: Governments ask inves-<lb/>tors to make twenty-ve year investment decisions on renewable <lb/>energy or hydrogen transportation, yet reserve the right to <lb/>change their minds on policies overnight. A 2011 article about <lb/>the UK Governments then new &apos;Green Investment Bank&apos; made <lb/>the following comment &apos;Before it risks signicant investment in <lb/>policy-supported new markets, the private sector understandably <lb/>wants the government to underwrite policy and regulatory risk <lb/>which is within its control (but not within the private sectors <lb/>control). In other words, it wants the government to commit to its <lb/>own policy by putting some skin in the game&apos;. 82 <lb/>One proposal that has recently borne fruit is &apos;policy perfor-<lb/>mance bonds&apos; or &apos;sovereign sustainability-linked bonds&apos; (SSLB&apos;s). <lb/>These are nancial instruments that hold governments <lb/>accountable for achieving their policy objectives. The idea is that <lb/>governments would issue bonds tied to specic &apos;Sustainability <lb/>Performance Targets&apos; (SPTs), such as carbon emissions reduction <lb/>targets, or renewable energy deployment. These bonds would pay <lb/>a higher yield if the government successfully meets its targets, but <lb/>would incur a penalty if it fails to do so. The bonds would be <lb/>tradable in nancial markets, allowing investors to speculate on <lb/>the government&apos;s performance. The purpose of policy perfor-<lb/>mance bonds is to create nancial incentives for governments to <lb/>prioritize and actively pursue their policy objectives. 83 SPTs could <lb/>be set to address some of the factors encouraging continued <lb/>invest in fossil fuel extraction mentioned in section 5.3 above. <lb/>First promulgated (by the authors) in 2009, it took until 2022 for <lb/>the rst SSLB&apos;s to be issued by the Governments of Chile and <lb/>Uruguay 84 leading to interest from a wider range of countries and <lb/>institutions. Chile&apos;s Government has committed to targets that <lb/>include decarbonising 60% of its electricity production by 2032, <lb/>while Uruguay has set a challenging gross greenhouse gas <lb/>reduction target for 2025. The issues combined longer maturity <lb/>dates and lower interest rates than traditional bonds, yet were <lb/>immediately oversubscribed by a wide range of investors, and <lb/>achieved high credit ratings. 85 <lb/>5.5 Final comments -answers to questions from <lb/>introduction <lb/>In the introduction to this paper, the authors posed four <lb/>questions to address. <lb/>Q. Is there any evidence that the concept of &apos;unburnable <lb/>carbon&apos; has in fact lead to reduction in fossil fuel reserves? <lb/>A. Apart from &apos;Brown Coal&apos;, there is no evidence from our <lb/>results of any reserve reduction. Potential carbon emissions from <lb/>fossil fuels show a 46% rise in since 2005. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>447 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>Q. What might happen to IPCC carbon budgets, and atmo-<lb/>spheric CO 2 levels, if these reserves are in fact very &apos;burnable&apos;? <lb/>A. Current reserves consumed at current rates are sufficient to <lb/>add 3400 Gt CO 2 by 2100, taking the world a long way towards <lb/>IPCC path RCP 6.0. Atmospheric CO 2 would exceed 620 ppm v/v by <lb/>2100. <lb/>Q. Do the comments around carbon pricing at $30-60 per <lb/>tonne still apply? <lb/>A. Current expert opinion is that carbon prices around and <lb/>over $75 per tonne are required to achieve net zero by 2050. We <lb/>estimate coal to gas switching in thermal power stations would be <lb/>prompted as carbon prices approach $50 per tonne. <lb/>Q. What are the implications of the current situation for <lb/>both nancial organisations and policy makers? <lb/>A. Policy makers, helped by private and public sector investors, <lb/>need to develop laws, regulations, and incentives, that steer fossil <lb/>fuel companies away from &apos;business as usual&apos; approaches to <lb/>exploration and development. It seems unlikely that fossil fuel <lb/>companies will change direction without these incentives. <lb/>We hope this paper will promote further thoughts, both around <lb/>the reserves data discussed above, and the policy options and <lb/>constraints for governments addressing these issues. <lb/></body>
    
            <div type="annex">Appendix <lb/>Our estimates show that &apos;proven reserves&apos; of fossil fuels in 2022, <lb/>would generate an estimated 4777 Gt of CO 2 aer allowing for <lb/>non-fuel uses. This appendix gives a tabulated breakdown of <lb/>our calculations for each of the major fossil fuel types. <lb/>Calculations <lb/>Potential emissions from major fossil fuels. Using the <lb/>proven reserves for fossil fuels, and conversion factors <lb/>mentioned in Table 1 of the main document, we can directly <lb/>calculate the CO 2 emitted by combustion of those reserves <lb/>(Tables 3 and 4). <lb/>The &apos;Proven Global Reserves&apos; of coal have increased by nearly <lb/>40% since 2005, despite coal being consumed at increasing <lb/>amounts throughout the period. Global coal consumption <lb/>reached 8 billion (8.0 × 10 9 ) tonnes in 2022. 36 Proven coal <lb/>stocks of &apos;hard&apos; and &apos;brown&apos; together coal could supply over 130 <lb/>years of coal consumption at 2022 levels. <lb/>The CO 2 produced in burning all current coal reserves, is <lb/>estimated as 3192 Gigatonnes, enough to take the world past <lb/>the RCP2.6 target towards RCP4.5 (Table 5). <lb/>There is no sign of &apos;peak oil&apos; in this data, as reserves have <lb/>increased by over 40%, despite the increasing consumption of <lb/>oil. These reserves, representing about 47 years supply at <lb/>current rates of consumption, are again sufficient to take the <lb/>world past the RCP2.6 budget (Table 6). <lb/>Proven natural gas from &apos;conventional&apos; (e.g. non fracking) <lb/>reserves have increased by around 21%, again despite the <lb/>switch to gas red electricity generation in multiple countries. <lb/>Current natural gas consumption is around 4 trillion cubic <lb/>metres pa, 1 so the gas reserves above represent around 46 years <lb/>supply (Table 7). <lb/>Table 3 CO 2 emissions from proven &apos;hard coal&apos; (bituminous and <lb/>anthracite) reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Mass (coal)/metric tonnes <lb/>7.536 × 10 11 (ref. 18) 4.788 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>6.782 × 10 11 <lb/>4.070 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>2.487 × 10 12 <lb/>1.492 × 10 12 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere 4.831 × 10 -4 <lb/>3.069 × 10 -4 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>483 <lb/>307 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>322 <lb/>205 <lb/>Table 4 CO 2 emissions from proven &apos;brown coal&apos; (sub-bituminous <lb/>and lignite) reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Mass (coal)/metric tonnes <lb/>3.205 × 10 11 <lb/>4.303 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>1.923 × 10 11 <lb/>2.582 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>7.050 × 10 11 <lb/>9.467 × 10 11 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>1.370 × 10 -4 <lb/>1.84 × 10 -4 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>137 <lb/>184 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>91 <lb/>123 <lb/>Table 5 CO 2 emissions from proven oil reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Volume (oil)/barrels <lb/>1.735 × 10 12 <lb/>1.201 × 10 12 <lb/>Mass (oil)/metric tonnes <lb/>2.366 × 10 11 <lb/>1.638 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>2.011 × 10 11 <lb/>1.392 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>7.375 × 10 11 <lb/>5.104 × 10 11 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>1.433 × 10 -4 <lb/>9.915 × 10 -5 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>143 <lb/>99 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>96 <lb/>66 <lb/>Table 6 CO 2 emissions from proven natural gas reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Volume (gas/10 9 m 3 ) <lb/>1.881 × 10 5 <lb/>1.557 × 10 5 <lb/>Energy (gas)/10 12 btu <lb/>6.418 × 10 6 <lb/>5.313 × 10 6 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/kg <lb/>9.261 × 10 13 <lb/>7.666 × 10 13 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>3.396 × 10 10 <lb/>2.811 × 10 10 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>6.596 × 10 -5 <lb/>5.460 × 10 -5 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>66 <lb/>55 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>44 <lb/>36 <lb/>Table 7 CO 2 emissions from extractable oil sands reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Barrels <lb/>4.232 × 10 11 <lb/>1.80 × 10 11 <lb/>Mass (oil)/metric tonnes <lb/>5.77 × 10 10 <lb/>2.57 × 10 10 <lb/>Proportion carbon <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>5.20 × 10 10 <lb/>2.31 × 10 10 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>1.905 × 10 11 <lb/>8.486 × 10 10 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>3.49472 × 10 -5 <lb/>1.56 × 10 -5 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>35 <lb/>15.57 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>23 <lb/>11 <lb/></div>

			<page>448</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>The increasing demand for hydrocarbon fuels has led to new <lb/>resources being discovered and exploited. Proven reserves from <lb/>oil sands (sometimes termed tar sands) such as those found in <lb/>Athabasca, have increased by over 220% since 2005. This <lb/>represents an incremental 11.6 years supply of oil at current <lb/>rates of demand (Table 8). <lb/>As well as oil sands, signicant amounts of oil are now being <lb/>extracted from shale via fracking. In 2005 this was still a new <lb/>technology and no proven reserves were recorded in our anal-<lb/>ysis. 2022 reserves are similar to those for oil sands, providing an <lb/>incremental 11.5 years at current demands (Table 9). <lb/>&apos;Unconventional&apos; (e.g. from fracking) shale gas reserves have <lb/>increased by nearly 15 times since 2005. Proven reserves are <lb/>now higher than those in conventional natural gas elds, and <lb/>provide an estimated 53 years at current consumption levels. <lb/>Summary data -potential emissions from major fossil fuels. <lb/>Our estimates put the total carbon dioxide potential of 2022 <lb/>reserves at 5025 Gt, compared to 3429 Gt in 2005 (Table 10). <lb/>Except for &apos;brown coal, fossil fuel reserves have increased <lb/>since 2005, with coal overall still much the largest contributor to <lb/>potential carbon dioxide increase. Coal has decreased as <lb/>a portion of the total emissions potential, mainly due to the <lb/>notable increase from shale gas (Table 11). <lb/>Non fuel uses of hydrocarbon reserves <lb/>Not all hydrocarbon reserves end up as fuel. The US Energy <lb/>Information Administration estimates that around 7% of oil is <lb/>converted into non-fuel uses such as industrial solvents, lubricants <lb/>and bitumen. 32 For natural gas, the proportion looks to be slightly <lb/>lower (3.75%). Non-fuel applications of gas (mainly fertilizer <lb/>manufacture and methanol production) are around 150 billion <lb/>cubic metres. While coal has potential for being a rich source of <lb/>valuable chemical intermediates, this is still underexploited, <lb/>except in China for olen and glycol production. Figures from IEA <lb/>resources on non-energy uses of coal suggests these amount to <lb/>around 4.5%. 34,35 The tables on this page reect this data by <lb/>deducting the non-fuel usage (Tables 12 and 13). <lb/>Table 8 CO 2 emissions from extractable shale oil reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>V (oil)/barrels <lb/>4.189 × 10 11 <lb/>0 <lb/>m (oil)/metric tonnes <lb/>5.7 × 10 10 <lb/>0 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>4.86 × 10 10 <lb/>0 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>1.781 × 10 11 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>3.4592 × 10 -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>35 <lb/>0 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>23 <lb/>0 <lb/>Table 10 Potential CO 2 emissions from all reserves (Gt CO 2 ) <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>&apos;Hard&apos; coal <lb/>2487 <lb/>1580 <lb/>&apos;Brown&apos; coal <lb/>705 <lb/>947 <lb/>Oil <lb/>737 <lb/>510 <lb/>Natural gas <lb/>340 <lb/>281 <lb/>Oil sands <lb/>190 <lb/>85 <lb/>Shale oil <lb/>178 <lb/>0 <lb/>Shale gas <lb/>387 <lb/>26 <lb/>Total <lb/>5025 <lb/>3429 <lb/>Table 9 CO 2 emissions from extractable shale gas reserves <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>Volume (gas/m 3 ) <lb/>2.14543 × 10 14 <lb/>1.46114 × 10 13 <lb/>Energy (gas)/10 12 btu <lb/>7320435.186 <lb/>498554.0422 <lb/>Mass (carbon)/metric tonnes <lb/>1.05634 × 10 11 <lb/>7.19 × 10 9 <lb/>Mass (CO 2 )/metric tonnes <lb/>3.873 × 10 11 <lb/>2.638 × 10 10 <lb/>Fraction of CO 2 /total atmosphere <lb/>7.52378 × 10 -5 <lb/>5.124 × 10 -6 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm by wt <lb/>75 <lb/>5 <lb/>Increase of CO 2 /ppm v/v <lb/>50 <lb/>3 <lb/>Table 11 Potential increase in CO 2 concentration in atmosphere <lb/>(ppm v/v) <lb/>Parameter <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>&apos;Hard&apos; coal <lb/>322 <lb/>205 <lb/>&apos;Brown&apos; coal <lb/>91 <lb/>123 <lb/>Oil <lb/>96 <lb/>66 <lb/>Natural gas <lb/>44 <lb/>36 <lb/>Oil sands <lb/>23 <lb/>11 <lb/>Shale oil <lb/>23 <lb/>0 <lb/>Shale gas <lb/>50 <lb/>3 <lb/>Sub-totals <lb/>650 <lb/>444 <lb/>Starting concentration in each year <lb/>417 <lb/>370 <lb/>&apos;Burn it all&apos; total <lb/>1067 <lb/>814 <lb/>Table 12 Potential CO 2 emissions deducting non-fuel uses (Gt CO 2 ) <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Non fuel usage <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>&apos;Hard&apos; coal <lb/>4.5% <lb/>2375 <lb/>1509 <lb/>&apos;Brown&apos; coal <lb/>4.5% <lb/>673 <lb/>904 <lb/>Oil <lb/>7% <lb/>686 <lb/>475 <lb/>Natural gas <lb/>3.75% <lb/>327 <lb/>271 <lb/>Oil sands <lb/>7% <lb/>177 <lb/>79 <lb/>Shale oil <lb/>7% <lb/>166 <lb/>0 <lb/>Shale gas <lb/>3.75% <lb/>373 <lb/>25 <lb/>Total <lb/>4777 <lb/>3263 <lb/>Table 13 Potential increase in atmospheric CO 2 deducting non-fuel <lb/>uses (ppm v/v) <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Non fuel usage <lb/>2022 values <lb/>2005 values <lb/>&apos;Hard&apos; coal <lb/>4.5% <lb/>308 <lb/>196 <lb/>&apos;Brown&apos; coal <lb/>4.5% <lb/>87 <lb/>117 <lb/>Oil <lb/>7% <lb/>89 <lb/>62 <lb/>Natural gas <lb/>3.75% <lb/>42 <lb/>35 <lb/>Oil sands <lb/>7% <lb/>22 <lb/>10 <lb/>Shale oil <lb/>7% <lb/>21 <lb/>0 <lb/>Shale gas <lb/>3.75% <lb/>48 <lb/>3 <lb/>Sub-totals <lb/>618 <lb/>422 <lb/>Total adding starting <lb/>concentrations from <lb/>Table 11 <lb/>1035 <lb/>792 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>449 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>Calculations for 2100 -burning 77 years of reserves. The <lb/>IPCC RCP scenarios predict pathways to various radiative <lb/>forcing values in the year 2100, 77 years in the future from this <lb/>paper. In Tables 4-9 above, it can be seen that proven reserves <lb/>are already sufficient to satisfy demands of fossil fuels well <lb/>beyond 2100 at current levels of consumption. For example, <lb/>proven coal stocks could last for 130 years at current levels of <lb/>consumption. A reasonable question to ask is, therefore, &apos;What <lb/>happens if we burn 77 years of fossil fuel reserves? Results <lb/>answering this question are shown in Table 14 below. <lb/>This analysis notably reduces the contribution of coal to the <lb/>carbon budget, as a sizeable portion of coal reserves might only be <lb/>consumed aer 2100. Nonetheless, the potential emissions from <lb/>current reserves are still sufficient to exceed the IPCC RCP 2.6 and <lb/>RCP4.5 budgets, and to land within the range for RCP6.0. The last <lb/>three lines of the table calculate the potential rise in CO 2 <lb/>concentration if 77 years of fossil fuel reserves were consumed in <lb/>one fast &apos;burn it all&apos; process. They are not a prediction of what <lb/>concentrations might be like in 2100 if the reserves were <lb/>consumed steadily over the period to 2100. What, if anything, can <lb/>we say about that scenario? Table 15 addresses this question, using <lb/>the assumption that carbon sinks continue to function as they <lb/>do now. <lb/>Finally, Table 16 summarises some calculations illustrating <lb/>the reduction in carbon dioxide emission and fuel costs by <lb/>switching from a hypothetical coal power station to a natural <lb/>gas plant producing the same energy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>Author KP: formal analysis, investigation, methodology, visu-<lb/>alisation, writing -original dra, writing -review and editing. <lb/></div>

			<body>Table 15 Potential CO 2 concentrations by 2100 with functioning <lb/>carbon sinks <lb/>Year <lb/>CO 2 emissions <lb/>(tonnes) <lb/>2005 <lb/>2.96 × 10 10 <lb/>2006 <lb/>3.06 × 10 10 <lb/>2007 <lb/>3.15 × 10 10 <lb/>2008 <lb/>3.21 × 10 10 <lb/>2009 <lb/>3.16 × 10 10 <lb/>2010 <lb/>3.34 × 10 10 <lb/>2011 <lb/>3.45 × 10 10 <lb/>2012 <lb/>3.50 × 10 10 <lb/>2013 <lb/>3.53 × 10 10 <lb/>2014 <lb/>3.56 × 10 10 <lb/>2015 <lb/>3.56 × 10 10 <lb/>2016 <lb/>3.55 × 10 10 <lb/>2017 <lb/>3.61 × 10 10 <lb/>2018 <lb/>3.68 × 10 10 <lb/>2019 <lb/>3.71 × 10 10 <lb/>2020 <lb/>3.53 × 10 10 <lb/>2021 <lb/>3.71 × 10 10 <lb/>Total <lb/>5.83 × 10 11 <lb/>Potential CO 2 increase in <lb/>atmosphere 2005-21 (ppm v/v) <lb/>72.5 <lb/>Actual increase in atmosphere (ppm v/v) <lb/>38 <lb/>Proportion CO 2 absorbed by carbon sinks <lb/>47.3% <lb/>Potential increase in CO 2 2023-2100 <lb/>(from Table 14, ppm v/v) <lb/>456 <lb/>Potential increase if sinks function as now <lb/>(ppm v/v) <lb/>240 <lb/>Current CO 2 concentration in atmosphere <lb/>(ppm v/v) <lb/>417 <lb/>Potential total concentration 2100 <lb/>(ppm v/v) <lb/>657 <lb/>Table 16 Potential CO 2 emission reduction converting coal to gas <lb/>generation <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Values <lb/>Coal <lb/>Gas <lb/>Power station <lb/>1000 MW <lb/>Annual energy output at 60% <lb/>capacity factor <lb/>5256 GWh <lb/>Energy from 1 tonne (MWh) <lb/>8.33 <lb/>13.63 <lb/>Mass of fuel needed at 100% <lb/>efficiency (tonnes) <lb/>630,720 385,534 <lb/>Typical efficiency <lb/>37% <lb/>55% <lb/>Realistic mass fuel required <lb/>(tonnes) <lb/>1 704 649 700 971 <lb/>Proportion of carbon <lb/>80% <lb/>75% <lb/>Carbon emitted (tonnes) <lb/>1 363 719 525 728 <lb/>CO 2 emitted (tonnes) <lb/>5 000 303 1 927 670 <lb/>Average fuel cost 2017-2020 <lb/>$84 per <lb/>tonne <lb/>$170 per <lb/>tonne <lb/>Realistic fuel cost <lb/>$143 m $121 m <lb/>Carbon price additional cost <lb/>$20 per <lb/>tonne CO 2 <lb/>$100 m $38 m <lb/>$50 per <lb/>tonne CO 2 <lb/>$250 m $96 m <lb/>$75 per <lb/>tonne CO 2 <lb/>$375 m $144 m <lb/>Total fuel cost at $75 per tonne <lb/>$518 m $265 m <lb/>Table 14 Potential CO 2 emissions and concentration (deducting non-<lb/>fuel uses) to 2100 (Gt CO 2 ) and ppm (v/v) <lb/>Parameter <lb/>&apos;Burn it all&apos; <lb/>emissions <lb/>Years of <lb/>reserves <lb/>at current <lb/>consumption <lb/>&apos;Burn 77 years&apos; <lb/>emissions <lb/>at current <lb/>consumption) <lb/>Coal <lb/>3048 <lb/>130 <lb/>1805 <lb/>Oil <lb/>Conventional oil <lb/>686 <lb/>47 <lb/>Oil sands <lb/>177 <lb/>12 <lb/>Oil shale <lb/>166 <lb/>11 <lb/>All oil sub-total <lb/>1029 <lb/>70 <lb/>1132 <lb/>Gas <lb/>Conventional gas <lb/>327 <lb/>47 <lb/>Shale gas <lb/>373 <lb/>54 <lb/>All gas sub-total <lb/>700 <lb/>101 <lb/>504 <lb/>Total <lb/>4777 <lb/>3441 <lb/>Potential CO 2 increase <lb/>in atmosphere ppm (v/v) <lb/>619 <lb/>446 <lb/>Starting <lb/>concentration 2023 <lb/>417 <lb/>417 <lb/>Total atmospheric <lb/>concentration <lb/>1036 ppm <lb/>863 ppm <lb/></body>

			<page>450</page>

            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Author MM. conceptualization, supervision, writing (section <lb/>1.1, 5.3, 5.4) writing -review and editing. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflicts of interest <lb/>Both authors have previously worked in parts of the Oil and Gas <lb/>Industry in a variety of roles as both employees and consultants. <lb/>None of these roles has been more recent than 2006. No external <lb/>sources of funding were required for this paper. Z/Yen is <lb/>promulgating one of the policy options (SSLB&apos;s) discussed in the <lb/>report and may conceivably benet from advisory work should <lb/>these become widely adopted. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors would like to thank Kate Wills, recent graduate of <lb/>the School of Chemistry at the University of Nottingham, for her <lb/>help with the calculations and her perseverance with the <lb/>multitude of unit conversions involved. Also, Dr Andrew Mob-<lb/>berley, recent PhD graduate from Heriot-Watt University <lb/>(Edinburgh) for his help with tables and graphics. The authors <lb/>would also like to thank Professor Simon Tett, of the School of <lb/>Geosciences at the University of Edinburgh, for his general <lb/>advice and specic guidance over the various carbon budgets <lb/>published by the IPCC. The authors are grateful for the oppor-<lb/>tunity to publish this paper, and very much appreciate the help <lb/>and support of all the RSC staff and reviewers involved during <lb/>the course of its lengthy gestation. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 London Accord, https://www.longnance.net/programmes/ <lb/>sustainable-futures/london-accord/, (accessed May 2023). <lb/>2 London <lb/>Accord <lb/>2007, <lb/>https://www.longnance.net/ <lb/>programmes/sustainable-futures/london-accord/london-<lb/>accord-2007/, (accessed May 2023). <lb/>3 Carbon -Burn it all?!, https://www.zyen.com/research/ <lb/>research/sustainability/carbon-burn-it-all/, (2006, accessed <lb/>May 2023). <lb/>4 BP&apos;s Deep Water Horizon Has a Deep Impact on UK Pension <lb/>Schemes, <lb/>https://www.labaton.com/blog/bps-deep-water-<lb/>horizon-has-a-deep-impact-on-uk-pension-schemes, 2010, <lb/>accessed May 2023). <lb/>5 Unburnable Carbon -Are the World&apos;s Financial Markets <lb/>Carrying a Carbon Bubble?, https://carbontracker.org/ <lb/>reports/carbon-bubble/, 2011, accessed May 2023). <lb/>6 B. Lahn, A history of the global carbon budget, Wiley <lb/>Interdiscip. Rev. Clim. Change, 2020, 11, e636, DOI: 10.1002/ <lb/>wcc.636. <lb/>7 IPCC AR5 Summary Report for Policy Makers, https:// <lb/>www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/ <lb/>WG1AR5_SPM_FINAL.pdf. <lb/>8 Friedlingstein, et al., Global Carbon Project, Carbon Budget <lb/>and <lb/>Trends <lb/>2022, <lb/>2022, <lb/>https:// <lb/>www.globalcarbonproject.org/carbonbudget] published on <lb/>11 November 2022. (accessed May 2023). <lb/>9 Carbon Tracker Report, 2013. <lb/>10 IPCC Fih Assessment Report, 2014. <lb/>11 Decline and Fall: the Size &amp; Vulnerability of the Fossil Fuel <lb/>System, <lb/>Carbon <lb/>Tracker <lb/>Report, <lb/>2020, <lb/>https:// <lb/>carbontracker.org/reports/decline-and-fall/(accessed <lb/>May <lb/>2023). <lb/>12 Current Reserves Already Exceed Any 1.5 Degree Carbon Budget. <lb/>Fossil Fuel Registry 2021, https://fossilfuelregistry.org/ <lb/>reserves (accessed May 2023). <lb/>13 U.S. Fossil-Fuel Reserves Alone Could Put Global Climate <lb/>Targets Out of Reach, Scientic American E&amp;E News, 2022, <lb/>https://www.scienticamerican.com/article/u-s-fossil-fuel-<lb/>reserves-alone-could-put-global-climate-targets-out-of-<lb/>reach/(accessed May 2023). <lb/>14 Calculating the Temperature Potential of Fossil Fuels. <lb/>Greenstone and Stuart University, 2015 Greenstone and <lb/>Stuart University Chicago Calculations Carbon Potential in <lb/>Reserves 5520 GtCO2, 2015, (accessed May 2023) https:// <lb/>assets.aeaweb.org/asset-server/articles-attachments/jep/ <lb/>app/3001/30010117_app.pdf. <lb/>15 If We Dig Out All Our Fossil Fuels Here&apos;s How Hot We Can <lb/>Expect it to Get, M.Greenstone, University Chicago, https:// <lb/>www.nytimes.com/2015/04/09/upshot/if-we-dig-out-all-our-<lb/>fossil-fuels-heres-how-hot-we-can-expect-it-to-get.html <lb/>(accessed May 2023). <lb/>16 R. Heede and N. Oreskes, Potential emissions of CO2 and <lb/>methane from proved reserves of fossil fuels: An <lb/>alternative analysis, Glob Environ Change, 2016, 36, 12-20. <lb/>17 J. Wang, L. Feng, X. Tang, Y. Bentley and M. Hook, The <lb/>Implications of Fossil Fuel Supply Constraints on Climate <lb/>Change Projections: A Supply-Side Analysis, Futures, 2016, <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/j.futures.2016.04.007. <lb/>18 BP Statistical Review of World Energy 2022. Methodology, <lb/>https://www.bp.com/content/dam/bp/business-sites/en/ <lb/>global/corporate/pdfs/energy-economics/statistical-review/ <lb/>bp-stats-review-2022-methodology.pdf (accessed March <lb/>2023). <lb/>19 Global Energy Monitor Wiki, https://www.gem.wiki/ <lb/>Coal_reserves (accessed November 2023). <lb/>20 C. E. McGlaide, A Review of the Uncertainties in estimates of <lb/>Global Oil resources, Energy, 2012, 47(1), 262-270. https:// <lb/>www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/ <lb/>S036054421200597X#sec5. <lb/>21 P. Friedlingstein, Carbon cycle feedbacks and future climate <lb/>change, Philos. Trans. R. Soc., A, 2015, 373, DOI: 10.1098/ <lb/>rsta.2014.0421. <lb/>22 Carbon and Other Biogeochemical Cycles(a) P. Ciais, <lb/>C. Sabine, G. Bala, L. Bopp, V. Brovkin, J. Canadell, <lb/>A. Chhabra, R. DeFries, J. Galloway, M. Heimann, C. Jones, <lb/>C. Le Quéré, R. B. Myneni, S. Piao and P. Thornton, <lb/>Carbon and Other Biogeochemical Cycles Supplementary <lb/>Material, In Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science <lb/>Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fih <lb/>Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate <lb/>Change, 2013; (b) T. F. Stocker, D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. <lb/>Tignor, S. K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex <lb/>and <lb/>P. <lb/>M. <lb/>Midgley, <lb/>Available <lb/>from <lb/>https:// <lb/>www.climatechange2013.org and https://www.ipcc.ch. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>451 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>23 P. P. Tans, I. Y. Fung and T. Takahashi, Observational <lb/>constraints on the global atmospheric CO2 budget, Science, <lb/>1990, 247, 1431-1438, DOI: 10.1126/science.247.4949.1431. <lb/>24 C. Le Quéré, et al., Trends in the sources and sinks of carbon <lb/>dioxide, Nat. Geosci., 2009, 2, 831-836, DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>ngeo689. <lb/>25 C. Le Quéré, et al. The global carbon budget 1959-2011, <lb/>Earth System Science Data, 2013, 5, 165-186, DOI: 10.5194/ <lb/>essd-5-165-2013. <lb/>26 A Recommended Methodology for Estimating and Reporting the <lb/>Potential Greenhouse Gas Emissions from Fossil Fuel Reserves. <lb/>World Resources Institute Working Paper December 2016, <lb/>https://ghgprotocol.org/sites/default/les/standards/ <lb/>WRI16_WorkingPaper_FF.pdf (accessed May 2023. <lb/>27 US Energy Information Adminstration, https://www.eia.gov/ <lb/>todayinenergy/detail.php?id=35672 (accessed May 2023. <lb/>28 BP Annual Statistical Review of World Energy 2022, https:// <lb/>www.bp.com/content/dam/bp/business-sites/en/global/ <lb/>corporate/pdfs/energy-economics/statistical-review/bp-stats-<lb/>review-2022-full-report.pdf (accessed May 2023). <lb/>29 Global Registry of Fossil Fuels, https://fossilfuelregistry.org <lb/>(accessed May 2023). <lb/>30 Carbon Dioxide Now More than 50% Higher than Preindustrial <lb/>Levels. NOAA News Release June 2022, https://www.noaa.gov/ <lb/>news-release/carbon-dioxide-now-more-than-50-higher-<lb/>than-pre-industrial-levels. <lb/>31 US Energy Information Admistration, https://www.eia.gov/ <lb/>international/data/world (accessed May 2023). <lb/>32 US Energy Information Administration April 2018, About 7% <lb/>of fossil fuels are consumed for non-combustion use in the <lb/>United States https://www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php? <lb/>id=35672 (accessed May 2023). <lb/>33 IEA, Natural Gas Consumption for Non-energy Use by <lb/>Application, 2019-2025, IEA, Paris https://www.iea.org/data-<lb/>and-statistics/charts/natural-gas-consumption-for-non-<lb/>energy-use-by-application-2019-2025 , IEA. Licence: CC BY <lb/>4.0 (accessed May 2023). <lb/>34 IEA 2022 Coal Fuels and Technologies, https://www.iea.org/ <lb/>fuels-and-technologies/coal. <lb/>35 Nalbandian, IEA. CCC/236 2014, Non-Fuel Uses of Coalhttps:// <lb/>usea.org/sites/default/les/052014_Non-fuel-uses-of-<lb/>coal_ccc236.pdf (accessed May 2023). <lb/>36 IEA, Coal 2022, IEA, Paris, 2022, https://www.iea.org/reports/ <lb/>coal-2022, License: CC BY 4.0(accessed May 2023). <lb/>37 Statista Research DepartmentAugust 30 2023. https:// <lb/>www.statista.com/statistics/271823/global-crude-oil-<lb/>demand/(accessed November 2023). <lb/>38 Statista, 2021, https://www.statista.com/statistics/282717/ <lb/>global-natural-gas-consumption/#:∼:text=Worldwide-<lb/>natural-gas-consumption-has,roughly-4.04-trillion-cubic-<lb/>meters. (accessed May 2023). <lb/>39 H. Ritchie, M. Roser and P. Rosado(2020) -&quot;CO₂ and <lb/>Greenhouse Gas Emissions&quot;. Published online at <lb/>OurWorldInData.org. <lb/>Retrieved <lb/>from: <lb/>https:// <lb/>ourworldindata.org/co2-and-greenhouse-gas-emissions <lb/>(Online Resource) (accessed May 2023). <lb/>40 &apos;Revealed; The Carbon &apos;Bombs&apos; Set to Trigger Catastrophic <lb/>Climate <lb/>Breakdown&apos; <lb/>Guardian, <lb/>2022, <lb/>https:// <lb/>www.theguardian.com/environment/ng-interactive/2022/ <lb/>may/11/fossil-fuel-carbon-bombs-climate-breakdown-oil-gas <lb/>(accessed May 2023). <lb/>41 &apos;Shale Oil and Shale Gas Resources Are Globally Abundant&apos; US <lb/>EIA Report June 2013(accessed May 2023) https:// <lb/>www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php?id=11611. <lb/>42 &apos;How Oil Companies Record Oil Reserves on Their Balance <lb/>Sheets&apos; <lb/>Mora <lb/>C., <lb/>Investopedia, <lb/>2022, <lb/>https:// <lb/>www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/09/oil-company-<lb/>reserves-balance-sheet.asp (accessed May 2023). <lb/>43 Forties Oil Field, Institute of Civil Engineers, https:// <lb/>www.ice.org.uk/what-is-civil-engineering/what-do-civil-<lb/>engineers-do/forties-oil-eld (accessed May 2023). <lb/>44 J. Whaley. The First UK Giant Oil Field. Geoexpro June 2010 <lb/>https://geoexpro.com/the-rst-uk-giant-oil-eld/(accessed <lb/>May 2023). <lb/>45 Oil &amp; Gas Field Prole, Forties Conventional Field, UK. Offshore <lb/>Technology and Globaldata, 2023, https://www.offshore-<lb/>technology.com/marketdata/oil-gas-eld-prole-forties-<lb/>conventional-oil-eld-uk/(accessed May 2023). <lb/>46 M. Thomas. Forties at Forty. Hart Energy, 2015, https:// <lb/>www.hartenergy.com/ep/exclusives/forties-40-175647 <lb/>(accessed May 2023). <lb/>47 F. Champenois, L. Myllyvirta, Q. Qin, X. Zhang, Centre for <lb/>Research on Energy and Clean Air, China&apos;s New Coal Power <lb/>Spree Continues as More Provinces Jump on the Bandwagon, <lb/>2023, <lb/>https://energyandcleanair.org/publication/chinas-<lb/>new-coal-power-spree-continues-as-more-provinces-jump-<lb/>on-the-bandwagon/(accessed December 2023). <lb/>48 T. Thurber and M. Shwartz, Stanford University Reports. Why <lb/>We Continue to Use Coal for Energy, https:// <lb/>energy.stanford.edu/news/qa-stanford-expert-explains-why-<lb/>we-continue-burning-coal-energy (accessed June 2023). <lb/>49 Britannica.com, <lb/>Coal <lb/>Transportation, <lb/>https:// <lb/>www.britannica.com/technology/coal-mining/Coal-<lb/>transportation (accessed June 2023). <lb/>50 Le Monde (English edition), Despite Climate Commitments, <lb/>the EU Is Going Back to Coal, 2022, https://www.lemonde.fr/ <lb/>en/economy/article/2022/09/02/despite-climate-<lb/>commitments-the-eu-is-going-back-to-<lb/>coal_5995594_19.html (accessed June 2023). <lb/>51 L. Aramayo, US Energy Information Administration. August 5 <lb/>2020. More than 100 Coal Fired Plants Have Been Replaced <lb/>or Converted to Natural Gas since, 2011, https:// <lb/>www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php? <lb/>id=44636#:∼:text=More-than-100-coal-Dred,to-natural-<lb/>gas-since-2011 (accessed November 2023). <lb/>52 C. Lo, Mining Technology. Mothballing Mines: Weathering the <lb/>Storm, <lb/>https://www.mining-technology.com/features/ <lb/>featuremothballing-mines-weathering-the-storm-4593373/ <lb/>(accessed June 2023). <lb/>53 S. A. P. N. Arasu, India pauses plans to add new coal plants for <lb/>ve years, bets on renewables, batteries, https://apnews.com/ <lb/>article/india-coal-pause-plan-climate-renewables-<lb/>68b75402af663e4553434bc672fc9cda (accessed June 2023). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>452</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>54 B. Feng, PCI Energy Solutions Blog Post. 17 April 2023. Power <lb/>Plant Efficiency: Coal, Natural Gas, Nuclear, and More, <lb/>https://www.pcienergysolutions.com/2023/04/17/power-<lb/>plant-efficiency-coal-natural-gas-nuclear-and-more/ <lb/>#:∼:text=Coal-power-plant-efficiency-is,from-33%25-o-43% <lb/>25. (accessed November 2023). <lb/>55 Just Energy Distributor Blog, Whats the Role of Coal <lb/>Consumption in Energy Production?, 2021, https:// <lb/>justenergy.com/blog/coal-consumption-in-energy/ <lb/>#:∼:text=How-Much-Energy-0Comes-From,produce-up-to-<lb/>578-kWh. (accessed November 2023). <lb/>56 Bay-Fusion.co.uk. Blog page. STEP -How would it Work?, <lb/>https://www.bay-fusion.co.uk/step-how-would-it-work/ <lb/>(accessed November 2023). <lb/>57 W. Zhang, M. Ren, J. Kang, Y. Zhou and J. Yuan, Utilities <lb/>Policy, Estimating Stranded Assets in China&apos;s Power Sector, <lb/>Elsevier, <lb/>2022. <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/ <lb/>article/abs/pii/S0957178722000170 (accessed November <lb/>2023). <lb/>58 S. Black, I. Parry, K. Zhunussova, IMF Report 21 July 2022 <lb/>More Countries Are Pricing Carbon but Emissions Are Still <lb/>Too Cheap, https://www.imf.org/en/Blogs/Articles/2022/07/ <lb/>21/blog-more-countries-are-pricing-carbon-but-emissions-<lb/>are-still-too-cheap (Accessed December 2023). <lb/>59 P. Bhat. Reuters. October 25 2021. Carbon needs to cost at least <lb/>$100/tonne now to reach net zero by 2050: Reuters poll, https:// <lb/>www.reuters.com/business/cop/carbon-needs-cost-least-<lb/>100tonne-now-reach-net-zero-by-2050-2021-10-25/(accessed <lb/>December 2023). <lb/>60 T. Adrian, P. Bolton and A. Kleinnijenhuis, Stanford Institute <lb/>for Economic Policy Research. The Great Carbon Arbitrage: <lb/>Going Short on Coal and Long on Renewables, 2022, https:// <lb/>siepr.stanford.edu/publications/policy-brief/great-carbon-<lb/>arbitrage-going-short-coal-and-long-renewables (accessed <lb/>December 2023). <lb/>61 P. Griffin A. M. Jaffe D. Lont R. Dominguez-Faus. Energy <lb/>Econ. Volume 52, Part A, December 2015, Pages 1-12. <lb/>Science and the stock market: Investors&apos; recognition of <lb/>unburnable <lb/>carbon. <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/ <lb/>science/article/abs/pii/S0140988315002546. <lb/>62 J. Bebbington, T. Schneider, L. Stevenson and A. Fox, Fossil <lb/>Fuel Reserves and Resources Reporting and Unburnable <lb/>Carbon: Investigating Conicting Accounts, Crit. Perspect. <lb/>Account., 2020, 66, 102083 https://www.sciencedirect.com/ <lb/>science/article/pii/S1045235418300467. <lb/>63 G. Gauthier, Shutting Down Oil Wells, a Risky and Expensive <lb/>Option, Resilience.org, https://www.resilience.org/stories/ <lb/>2020-05-28/shutting-down-oil-wells-a-risky-and-expensive-<lb/>option/(accessed June 2023). <lb/>64 M. Berns, R. Fitz, C. Follette, A. Gordon, J. Webster and <lb/>Boston Consulting Group, The Last Oil Price Boom may be <lb/>in <lb/>sight, <lb/>https://www.bcg.com/publications/2021/ <lb/>preparation-for-last-oil-price-boom (Accessed June 2023). <lb/>65 See graph on this link: P. Hodges, Independent Commodity <lb/>Intelligence Services. Oil Prices Start to Reconnect with Coal <lb/>and Gas, https://www.icis.com/chemicals-and-the-economy/ <lb/>2020/06/oil-prices-start-to-reconnect-with-coal-and-gas/ <lb/>(accessed June 2023). <lb/>66 R. Nickel and N. Williams, Reuters Oil Companies Cautious <lb/>about Drilling as Energy Transition Looms, 2023, https:// <lb/>www.reuters.com/business/energy/oil-companies-cautious-<lb/>about-drilling-energy-transition-looms-2023-09-20/(accessed <lb/>November 2023). <lb/>67 G. Cortazar and E. Schwartz, Implementing a Real Option <lb/>Model for valuing an undeveloped oil eld, Int Trans Oper <lb/>Res, 1997, 4(2). https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/ <lb/>article/abs/pii/S0969601697000075. <lb/>68 L. Di Salvatore, International Institute for Sustainable <lb/>Development. Investor State Disputes in the Fossil Fuel <lb/>Industry. <lb/>https://www.iisd.org/system/les/2022-01/ <lb/>investor-state-disputes-fossil-fuel-industry.pdf <lb/>(accessed <lb/>June 2023). <lb/>69 C. Beck, D. Bellone, S. Hall, J. Kar, D. Olufon and McKinsey <lb/>Oil&amp;Gas, The Big Choices for Oil and Gas in Navigating the <lb/>Energy Transition, https://www.mckinsey.com/industries/oil-<lb/>and-gas/our-insights/the-big-choices-for-oil-and-gas-in-<lb/>navigating-the-energy-transition (accessed June 2023). <lb/>70 P. I. Forbes, The Surging Hydrogen Economy that Oil and Gas <lb/>Companies Are Tiptoeing into. https://www.forbes.com/sites/ <lb/>ianpalmer/2022/09/29/the-surging-hydrogen-economy-that-<lb/>oil-and-gas-companies-are-tiptoeing-into/? <lb/>sh=39248fc86341 (accessed June 2023. <lb/>71 S. Reed, New York Times. Oil Giants Prepare to Put Carbon <lb/>Back in the Ground, https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/08/ <lb/>business/carbon-capture-bp.html (accessed June 2023). <lb/>72 A. Tullo, ACS Chemical and Engineering News. Is Ammonia the <lb/>Fuel <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>Future?, <lb/>https://cen.acs.org/business/ <lb/>petrochemicals/ammonia-fuel-future/99/i8 (accessed June <lb/>2023). <lb/>73 D. Kavakeb, Global Witness Press Release April 12 2022. <lb/>World&apos;s Biggest Fossil Fuel Firms Projected to Spend Almost <lb/>a Trillion Dollars on New Oil and Gas Fields by 2030, https:// <lb/>www.globalwitness.org/en/press-releases/worlds-biggest-<lb/>fossil-fuel-rms-projected-to-spend-almost-a-trillion-<lb/>dollars-on-new-oil-and-gas-elds-by-2030/(accessed <lb/>November 2023). <lb/>74 J. Harden, SPE Hydrocarbon Economics and Evaluation Forum. <lb/>Discount Rate Development in Oil and Gas Valuation, 2014, <lb/>https://onepetro.org/SPEHEES/proceedings-abstract/ <lb/>14HEES/2-14HEES/D021S010R001/211427 <lb/>(accessed <lb/>September 2023). <lb/>75 International Petroleum Corporation IPC 2022 Year-End <lb/>Financial Results and 2023 Budget and Production Guidance <lb/>Blackrod 1 project &apos;NPV at 10% is estimated at $807m&apos;, 2023, <lb/>https://www.international-petroleum.com/ipc-announces-<lb/>2022-year-end-nancial-results-sanction-of-blackrod-phase-<lb/>1-canadian-ma-update-and-2023-sustained-shareholder-<lb/>return-framework/(accessed September 2023). <lb/>76 H. Liabeuf, et al(47 co-authors), Energy Transitions <lb/>Commission November 2023. Fossil Fuels in Transition: <lb/>Committing to the Phase-Down of All Fossil Fuels, https:// <lb/>www.energy-transitions.org/publications/fossil-fuels-in-<lb/>transition/#:∼:text=In-its-latest-report%2C-Fossil,2050% <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 | </note>
    
            <page>453 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>2C-with-immediate-action-imperative. (accessed November <lb/>2023). <lb/>77 R. Frost, Euronews.com. The end of Fossil Fuels. Which <lb/>countries have banned exploration and extraction?, https:// <lb/>www.euronews.com/green/2021/08/12/the-end-of-fossil-<lb/>fuels-which-countries-have-banned-exploration-and-<lb/>extraction (accessed November 2023). <lb/>78 K. Bryan, Financial Times. Asset Managers Take Aim at <lb/>&apos;Unstable&apos; EU Green Fund Rules, https://www..com/ <lb/>content/212424ce-363b-4be2-81a1-79532a08ec7c (accessed <lb/>November 2023). <lb/>79 T. Fancy, The Economist. The Failure of Green Investing and the <lb/>Need for State Action, https://www.economist.com/by-<lb/>invitation/2021/11/04/tariq-fancy-on-the-failure-of-green-<lb/>investing-and-the-need-for-state-action (accessed November <lb/>2023). <lb/>80 S. Jordan, Workers Liberty. A Workers Plan to Shut Down <lb/>Oilelds, https://www.workersliberty.org/story/2023-03-28/ <lb/>workers-plan-shut-down-oilelds (accessed June 2023). <lb/>81 M. Krishnan, et al., Mckinsey The economic transformation: <lb/>What would change in the net-zero transition, 2022, https:// <lb/>www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/sustainability/our-insights/ <lb/>the-economic-transformation-what-would-change-in-the-<lb/>net-zero-transition (accessed December 2023). <lb/>82 D. Zenghelis. London School Economics Commentary. HM <lb/>Treasury Hamstrings the Green Investment Bank, 2011, <lb/>https://www.lse.ac.uk/granthaminstitute/news/hm-treasury-<lb/>hamstrings-the-green-investment-bank/(accessed December <lb/>2023). <lb/>83 M. Mainelli, Policy Performance Bonds Z/Yen Group, 2022, <lb/>https://www.zyen.com/research/research/sustainability/ <lb/>policy-performance-bonds/(accessed June 2023). <lb/>84 D. Bouzidi and S. Mills, Emena Advisory Group. Chile Sets <lb/>a High Bar, 2022 (accessed June 2023) https:// <lb/>www.longnance.net/media/documents/ <lb/>policy_performance_bond_supplement_1.3_ <lb/>SM_220506.pdf. <lb/>85 A. Funez, J. L. Lobera, Inter-American Development Bank News <lb/>Release. Uruguay Issues Global Sustainability-Linked Bond, <lb/>with IDB Support, 2022, https://www.iadb.org/en/news/ <lb/>uruguay-issues-global-sustainability-linked-bond-idb-<lb/>support (accessed November 2023). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>454</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| Environ. Sci.: Atmos., 2024, 4, 435-454 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Environmental Science: Atmospheres <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 24 January 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 12:54:59 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online </note>


	</text>
</TEI>