<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Structural brain network organization in children with prenatal alcohol exposure</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Xiaoyun</forename>
          <surname>Liang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Claire E.</forename>
          <surname>Kelly</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Chun-Hung</forename>
          <surname>Yeh</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Thijs</forename>
          <surname>Dhollander</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Stephen</forename>
          <surname>Hearps</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Peter J.</forename>
          <surname>Anderson</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Deanne K.</forename>
          <surname>Thompson</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:54:47.290Z">11/12/2025 10:54:47 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1016$1$j.nicl.2024.103690</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.nicl.2024.103690</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Xiaoyun Liang, Claire E. Kelly, Chun-Hung Yeh, Thijs Dhollander, Stephen Hearps, Peter J. Anderson, Deanne K. Thompson. (2024). Structural brain network organization in children with prenatal alcohol exposure. NeuroImage: Clinical, 44(None), 103690. DOI: 10.1016/j.nicl.2024.103690</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T10:54:38.144517Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T10:54:38.144517Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) 101500 <lb/>Available online 28 December 2023 <lb/>2213-3984/© 2023 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of INDIACLEN. This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Factors influencing the prevalence of anaemia in female adolescents: A <lb/>population-based study of rural setting in Karanganyar, Indonesia <lb/>Fathimah Sulistyowati Sigit a,b, * , Fiyan Bahrul Ilmi c, d , Prisilla Desfiandi e , Dewantari Saputri f , <lb/>Nur Dwi Fajarini f , Ana Susianti d , Latifah Agustina Lestari g, h , Asaduddien Faras f <lb/>a Department of Public Health Nutrition, Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Indonesia, Depok, Indonesia <lb/>b Metabolic, Cardiovascular, and Aging Research Cluster, The Indonesian Medical Education and Research Institute, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>c West Tegal Community Health Center, Tegal, Indonesia <lb/>d Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Islam Sultan Agung, Semarang, Indonesia <lb/>e Faculty of Medicine, Public Health, and Nursing, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia <lb/>f Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Sebelas Maret, Surakarta, Indonesia <lb/>g Eka Hospital, South Tangerang, Indonesia <lb/>h Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Trisakti, Jakarta, Indonesia <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Anaemia <lb/>BMI <lb/>Dietary intake <lb/>Menstruation <lb/>Mid-upper arm circumference (MUAC) <lb/>Underweight <lb/>Women of reproductive age (WRA) <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Background: Anaemia among women of reproductive age (15-49 years) poses substantial public health concerns, <lb/>particularly in LMICs, due to its adverse effects during pregnancy and childbirth. Understanding its determinants <lb/>is pivotal for devising strategies to combat this condition. This study investigates the prevalence of anaemia and <lb/>its associations with anthropometric indices, dietary habits, and menstruation status among female adolescents <lb/>in Karanganyar, a rural subdistrict in Indonesia. <lb/>Methods: In this population-based cross-sectional study, a multi-stage sampling method was employed to <lb/>represent all female high-school students in Karanganyar. Participants underwent capillary haemoglobin testing, <lb/>anthropometric measurements, and completed dietary intake and menstruation status assessments. Anaemia was <lb/>defined as Hb &lt; 12.0 g/dL. Logistic regressions were performed to assess the associations between anthropo-<lb/>metric indices, dietary intake, menstruation status, and the prevalence of anaemia. <lb/>Results: Approximately 49 % of female adolescents in Karanganyar had anemia. Both BMI and Mid-Upper-Arm-<lb/>Circumference exhibited inverse associations with anaemia [AOR(95%CI): 0.87(0.79-0.95) and 0.89 <lb/>(0.81-0.99)]. Compared to individuals with BMI-for-age-Z-Score (BAZ) &gt; -2 SD, those with BAZ &lt; -2 SD had <lb/>more than double the odds of anaemia [2.43 (0.94-6.29)]. Consumption of fruits [0.32(0.10-0.98)] and vege-<lb/>tables [0.30(0.11-0.78)] were negatively associated with anaemia. No association was observed between <lb/>menstruation status (length, duration, pads/day) and anaemia. <lb/>Discussion: High prevalence of anaemia among female adolescents in Karanganyar, and potentially other rural <lb/>areas in Indonesia, underscores the need for targeted interventions. Being underweight rapidly increases the risk <lb/>of anaemia, emphasizing the importance of nutritional improvements. Consuming iron-rich fruits and vegetables <lb/>may prevent anaemia. Menstruation status did not appear to be a determinant of anaemia. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Anaemia is a medical condition characterised by low haemoglobin <lb/>levels in the erythrocytes that impairs general health. 1 Haemoglobin <lb/>plays a vital role in circulation by binding oxygen in the lungs and <lb/>transporting it to tissues throughout the body. When haemoglobin levels <lb/>are low, the delivery of oxygen to the brain, muscles, and other vital <lb/>tissues is disrupted, leading to fatigue, impaired cognitive functions, and <lb/>reduced work performance. 2 These complications in turn are detri-<lb/>mental to productivity and the quality of life of the population. 3 Glob-<lb/>ally, the World Health Organization estimated in 2019 that <lb/>approximately 30 % of women aged 15-49 years were anaemic, 1,4 with <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. Department of Public Health Nutrition, Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Indonesia, Depok, Indonesia. <lb/>E-mail address: fathimah10@ui.ac.id (F.S. Sigit). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health <lb/>journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/cegh <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cegh.2023.101500 <lb/>Received 17 September 2023; Received in revised form 7 December 2023; Accepted 21 December 2023 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>75 % of severe cases and anaemia-related mortality occurring in <lb/>South-East Asia and Africa regions, which are predominantly low-and <lb/>middle-income countries (LMICs). 4,5 <lb/>Anaemia in women, particularly those of reproductive age, poses a <lb/>serious public health threat, as it is associated with detrimental and even <lb/>life-threatening complications during pregnancy and childbirth. 2 The <lb/>complications include postpartum haemorrhage, premature-born and <lb/>low birth weight babies, all contributing to increased risks of infant and <lb/>maternal death rate and growth and development retardation. 2,6 Among <lb/>women of reproductive age, the global prevalence of anaemia was the <lb/>highest in the 15-19 years age group. 4 <lb/>Although previous studies have shown that diets lacking in essential <lb/>micronutrients (e.g., iron, folate, and vitamin B12) are risk factors for <lb/>anaemia, 7,8 other factors such as menstruation status in women of <lb/>reproductive age remain a subject of debate. 9,10 Globally, it is estimated <lb/>that up to a third of women of reproductive age experience heavy <lb/>menstrual bleeding, 3 but whether this occurs more frequently and is <lb/>associated with anaemia in female adolescents living in rural areas is <lb/>still unclear. <lb/>Moreover, micronutrient deficiencies are often undiagnosed or <lb/>overlooked, as the examination requires specific laboratory blood ex-<lb/>aminations that are not always affordable or available in remote areas. <lb/>Consequently, more general measures of undernutrition (e.g., BMI, mid-<lb/>upper arm circumference) are often the only practical methods to be <lb/>used in settings with limited facilities. Furthermore, epidemiological <lb/>studies exploring the occurrence and risk factors of anaemia with set-<lb/>tings in rural areas of LMICs are still relatively rare. A study has shown <lb/>that pregnant women in rural areas have insufficient dietary intakes of <lb/>essential nutrients, 11 and thus potentially experience an increased risk of <lb/>anaemia. <lb/>Hence, this study aims to investigate the prevalence of anaemia and <lb/>the associations of dietary intake, menstrual cycle, and anthropometric <lb/>indices with anaemia in female adolescents in Karanganyar, a rural <lb/>district in Indonesia. By identifying the possible risk factors for anaemia <lb/>in Indonesia as one of the most populous LMICs, we hope to contribute <lb/>to defining a preventive mass measure for anaemia in women living in <lb/>LMICs, especially those in rural settings. <lb/>2. Methods <lb/>2.1. Study design <lb/>This is a cross-sectional study conducted in the subdistrict of Kar-<lb/>anganyar, a rural area situated in the Pekalongan Regency, Central Java, <lb/>Indonesia. According to the Central Bureau of Statistics, 10.57 % of <lb/>households in the area lived below the national poverty line. 12 The study <lb/>area encompassed the working vicinity of the Karanganyar Community <lb/>Health Center (KCHC), the free-for-public primary healthcare facility <lb/>that is fully funded by the government. KCHC routinely has public <lb/>health programs driven by the Ministry of Health, that aim to solve <lb/>timely health issues in society. This study analyses the secondary data <lb/>from the regional surveillance program for anaemia in female adoles-<lb/>cents, which was conducted jointly by the local health office and KCHC. <lb/>2.2. Data collection <lb/>From approximately 1995 female adolescents aged 15-19 who live <lb/>in the Karanganyar subdistrict, all female high school students (n = <lb/>730), who were generally aged 16-18, were encouraged to participate in <lb/>the government-funded anaemia screening. 13,14 Healthcare personnel <lb/>from KCHC visited all three high schools in the subdistrict and tested all <lb/>female students for their haemoglobin levels using a rapid haemoglo-<lb/>binometer. Among the three high schools, the largest school with the <lb/>most populous students was visited twice, in which in the second visit all <lb/>female students were asked to complete a set of general and lifestyle <lb/>questionnaires and underwent a thorough anthropometric <lb/>measurement. For this study, we only included female students who <lb/>have complete data on the level of haemoglobin, anthropometric mea-<lb/>surement (BMI and Mid-Upper Arm Circumference), and have <lb/>completed the questionnaires, resulting in a total sample of 240 female <lb/>high school students (Supplemental Fig. 1). <lb/>2.3. Haemoglobin measurement <lb/>A mobile point-of-care test kit for haemoglobin (HemoCue® <lb/>Hemoglobinometer) was used to measure the level of haemoglobin in all <lb/>participants using a capillary blood sample. Anaemia was defined ac-<lb/>cording to the WHO criteria as haemoglobin level below 12.0 g/dL. <lb/>We further categorised the severity of anaemia according to the WHO <lb/>classification for non-pregnant women aged ≥15 years, which are Hb <lb/>11.0-11.9 g/dL for mild anaemia, 8.0-10.9 g/dL for moderate anaemia, <lb/>and &lt;8.0 g/dL for severe anaemia. 15 <lb/>2.4. Anthropometric measurements <lb/>In all respondents, body mass index (BMI) and mid-upper arm <lb/>circumference (MUAC) were measured. BMI is defined as weight in ki-<lb/>logram, divided by the square of height in meters. Weight was measured <lb/>by a digital scale to the nearest 0.1 kg, whereas height was measured <lb/>with a portable stadiometer to the nearest 0.1 cm. MUAC was measured <lb/>with a flexible tape measure to the nearest 0.1 cm, and was measured <lb/>halfway between shoulder and elbow. MUAC is used as a proxy of un-<lb/>dernutrition status, with MUAC&lt;23 cm is defined as having a chronic <lb/>energy deficiency. 16,17 <lb/>2.5. The general and lifestyle questionnaires <lb/>Participants were asked to complete a set of questionnaires to pro-<lb/>vide data on general sociodemographic information, dietary intake, <lb/>physical activity habits, and menstrual cycles. Dietary intake was <lb/>assessed using a simplified food frequency questionnaire, which <lb/>measured the frequency and quantity of consumption of common food <lb/>products. For physical activity, information on the frequency and <lb/>duration of exercise was recorded. Adequate physical activity was <lb/>defined according to the national healthy lifestyle guideline as engaging <lb/>in moderate to intense physical activity for at least 30 min per day or <lb/>150 min per week. 18,19 <lb/>While the accurate assessment of blood loss during menstrual <lb/>bleeding is challenging, with no consensus available for quantifying it, <lb/>to gain insight into the quantity of blood loss during the menstrual cycle, <lb/>the number of sanitary pads used per day during menstruation were <lb/>asked. In addition, the length, regularity, and the first occurrence <lb/>(menarche) of the menstrual cycle were also asked. <lb/>2.6. Statistical analyses <lb/>Descriptive characteristics of the population were presented as mean <lb/>(SD) or median (25th-75th percentiles) for continuous variables and <lb/>percentage (95 % CI) for categorical variables. All analyses were per-<lb/>formed using STATA™ statistical software program version 17. <lb/>Multivariable logistic regression analyses were conducted to <lb/>examine the associations of anthropometric indices (BMI, MUAC), <lb/>menstruation status, and dietary intake with anaemia. We adjusted these <lb/>associations for sociodemographic and lifestyle confounding factors, <lb/>including age, parents&apos; occupation, household size/number of family <lb/>members, physical activity, and (passive) smoking. The association be-<lb/>tween menstruation status and anaemia was additionally adjusted for <lb/>BMI, whereas the association between dietary intake and anaemia was <lb/>further mutually adjusted by each food category. The estimates were <lb/>presented as odds ratios with 95 % confidence intervals. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">F.S. Sigit et al. <lb/>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) 101500 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.7. Ethics and approval <lb/>This program is a derivation from the national anaemia prevention <lb/>and iron supplementation program by the Indonesian Ministry of Health <lb/>(PERMENKES No. 88/2014, and PERMENKES No. 51/2016). 20 One <lb/>week prior to the anaemia surveillance, an announcement letter from <lb/>KCHC was provided to all female students regarding the surveillance <lb/>plan. Although encouraged to participate, the letter also stated that <lb/>students could opt out of the study if they or their parents did not wish to <lb/>participate. In addition, one day before the survey, an oral reminder was <lb/>given via announcement from the homeroom teachers in each class-<lb/>room, and students were instructed to relay the information and discuss <lb/>their participation with their parents. <lb/>On the morning of surveillance day before data collection began, all <lb/>female adolescents were given an information session by healthcare <lb/>professionals to educate them about anaemia and its health and societal <lb/>consequences. They were given ample time and opportunities to ask <lb/>questions regarding anaemia and the study they were about to enrol in. <lb/>All participants agreed and signed informed consent. KCHC had <lb/>reviewed and given permission for their data to be used in this study <lb/>(Approval No. 156 441/893/2023). <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Descriptive characteristics of the study population <lb/>The mean (SD) age of participants was 16.2 (0.9) years. Nearly half <lb/>(49 %) of the study population had a haemoglobin level of less than 12 <lb/>g/dL, of which 2 % had severe, 21 % moderate, and 26 % mild anaemia. <lb/>Almost ten percent (9.2 %) of the population had a BMI-for-age Z-score <lb/>(BAZ) of &lt; -2 SD. <lb/>In regard to parental occupation, 7 % of participants reported that <lb/>their parents worked as government or private employees, 9 % as factory <lb/>workers, 14 % as farmers, 42 % as entrepreneurs, and 27 % as others. <lb/>Only half of the participants had three regular meals daily, and the soy-<lb/>based Tofu/Tempeh appeared to be regularly consumed by the majority <lb/>of participants. The median duration of physical activity per week was <lb/>30.0 (21.3-45.0) minutes, and 74 % of participants had at least one <lb/>member in their household smoking at home. <lb/>All participants have already menstruating, but almost a third (27 %) <lb/>have irregular cycle. A third (34 %) have cycle that are less than a <lb/>month. On average, the participants changed sanitary pads three times <lb/>[2.9 (0.8)] daily during their menstrual cycle (Table 1). <lb/>3.2. The associations of anthropometric indices, dietary intake, and <lb/>menstruation status with anaemia <lb/>BMI was inversely associated with anaemia, and the association <lb/>remained stable after adjustment for sociodemographic and lifestyle <lb/>confounding factors [adjusted Odds Ratio (95 % CI): 0.87 (0.79-0.95)]. <lb/>Similarly, an inverse association was also found in MUAC, with an <lb/>adjusted OR (95 % CI) for anaemia of 0.89 (0.81-0.99). When catego-<lb/>rising BMI into underweight (BAZ &lt; -2 SD) or not underweight (BAZ &gt; <lb/>-2 SD), those with underweight had more than double the odds of <lb/>having anaemia compared to those without, despite borderline signifi-<lb/>cant [adjusted OR (95 % CI): 2.43 (0.94-6.29)](Table 2). <lb/>While the consumption of poultry and meats was inversely associ-<lb/>ated with anaemia, all crude and adjusted odds ratios had confidence <lb/>intervals that were crossing 1 [adjusted OR (95 % CI): 0.69 (0.23-2.03)]. <lb/>Consuming fruit and vegetable were negatively associated with anaemia <lb/>[adjusted ORs (95 % CIs): 0.32 (0.10-0.98) and 0.30 (0.11-0.78)], and <lb/>these association remained stable even after additional adjustment for <lb/>BMI and other food categories. We did not observe a clear association <lb/>between menstruation status with anaemia, as all crude and adjusted <lb/>odds ratios had confidence intervals that crossed 1 (Table 2). <lb/>4. Discussion <lb/>In this study, we investigated the prevalence of anaemia, as well as <lb/>the associations of anthropometric indices, dietary intake, and <lb/>menstruation status with anaemia in female adolescent in a rural setting <lb/>in Indonesia. We observed that almost half (49 %) of the population had <lb/>anaemia. BMI and MUAC, as well as consuming fruits and vegetables, <lb/>were inversely associated with anaemia. We did not find evidence that <lb/>menstruation (menarche, bleeding quantity, duration, and regularity of <lb/>cycle) was associated with anaemia. <lb/>The high prevalence of anaemia that was observed in this study was <lb/>in line with the global and national estimated prevalence. The World <lb/>Bank estimated that more than a third of women of reproductive age, <lb/>particularly those aged 15-19 and living in LMICs, suffer from (iron <lb/>deficiency) anaemia. 5 Compared to the national prevalence, we <lb/>observed that the prevalence of anaemia in our study was higher than <lb/>that of the Indonesian National Health Survey, which was roughly 32 <lb/>%. 21 This is probably due to the national survey averaging the level of <lb/>anaemia in urban and rural areas, whereas in our study, the participants <lb/>lived entirely in rural settings. <lb/>Of all predictors, the strongest association was seen between BMI and <lb/>anaemia. In particular, we observed that compared to those with normal <lb/>weight, those who were underweight had more than double the risk of <lb/>anaemia. We also observed that MUAC, another measure of malnour-<lb/>ishment, was inversely associated with anaemia. The inverse associa-<lb/>tions between anthropometric indices (BMI and MUAC) and anaemia <lb/>may be explained by the common micronutrient deficiencies in in-<lb/>dividuals with underweight (BAZ &lt; -2 SD) and chronic energy <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Descriptive characteristics of the study population (n = 240). <lb/>Age, years (mean ± SD) <lb/>16.2 ± 0.9 <lb/>Haemoglobin, g/dL (mean ± SD) <lb/>12.0 ± 1.6 <lb/>Anaemia (%, 95 % CI) a <lb/>49 (43-55) <lb/>Mild, 11.0-11.9 g/dL (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>26 (20-31) <lb/>Moderate, 8.0-10.9 g/dL (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>21 (17-27) <lb/>Severe, &lt;8.0 g/dL (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>2 (1-5) <lb/>BMI, kg/m 2 (mean ± SD) <lb/>20.0 ± 3.2 <lb/>Mid-Upper Arm Circumference, cm (mean ± SD) <lb/>23.7 ± 2.7 <lb/>Physical Activity, minutes/week (median, 25th-75th percentile) b <lb/>30.0 (21.3-45.0) <lb/>Smoker, yes (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>0 <lb/>Passive Smoker, yes (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>74 (68-79) <lb/>Menstruation Status <lb/>Already Menstruating, yes (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>99 (97-100) <lb/>Menarche, years (mean ± SD) <lb/>12.7 ± 1.0 <lb/>Regular cycle, yes (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>72 (66-78) <lb/>Length of cycle, days (mean ± SD) <lb/>3.0 ± 1.3 <lb/>&gt;1 cycle/month, yes (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>35 (29-41) <lb/>Sanitary pads per day, pads (mean ± SD) <lb/>2.9 ± 0.8 <lb/>Dietary Intake <lb/>Having 3 regular meals per day (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>54 (47-60) <lb/>2 regular meals per day (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>42 (36-49) <lb/>Trying to lose weight (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>10 (6-14) <lb/>Poultry/Beef, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>11 (7-15) <lb/>Fish, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>10 (7-15) <lb/>Eggs, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>27 (22-33) <lb/>Soybean (Tofu/Tempeh), &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>47 (41-54) <lb/>Fruits, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>14 (10-19) <lb/>Vegetables, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>35 (29-42) <lb/>Coffee/Tea, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>18 (14-24) <lb/>Milk, or other dairy products, &gt;3 portions a week (%, 95 % CI) <lb/>18 (13-23) <lb/>Data are presented in mean (SD) or median (25th-75th percentiles) for contin-<lb/>uous variable, and in proportion (%) for categorical variable. <lb/>a Anemia is defined according to WHO criteria of Hb &lt; 12 g/dL. <lb/>b Physically active as defined by the national healthy lifestyle guideline <lb/>&apos;GERMAS&apos;: moderate to intense physical activity of more than 30 min/day or <lb/>150 min/week. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">F.S. Sigit et al. <lb/>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) 101500 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>deficiency (MUAC&lt;23 cm). In acute or chronic malnourishment, the <lb/>individuals commonly experience not only macronutrients but also <lb/>micronutrients deficiency. 7,8 Deficiencies in essential micronutrients <lb/>such as iron, vitamin B12, or folate were among the common causes of <lb/>anaemia, as these micronutrients play a vital role in the haematopoiesis, <lb/>particularly the regeneration of new erythrocytes. 22,23 <lb/>In regard to dietary intake, we observed that consuming fruits and <lb/>vegetables was protective against anaemia. Although in the present <lb/>study the types of fruits and vegetables were not recorded, previous <lb/>studies have shown that green leafy vegetables are a rich source of iron, <lb/>which supports the regeneration of haemoglobin24,25. Vitamin-C-rich <lb/>fruits and vegetables are also known to help the absorption of iron in <lb/>the gastrointestinal tract. 24,25 Nevertheless, despite being known to be <lb/>the primary source of iron, we did not find strong evidence that <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Odds ratios of anaemia in association with anthropometric indices, menstruation status, and dietary intake (n = 240). <lb/>Proportion (%) with <lb/>Anaemia <lb/>Crude Odds Ratios (95 <lb/>% CI) <lb/>Adjusted Odds Ratios (95 % CI) <lb/>Model 1 <lb/>Model 2 <lb/>Model 3 <lb/>Model 4 <lb/>Anthropometric Indices <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 , as continuous variable) <lb/>0.87 (0.79-0.95) <lb/>0.86 <lb/>(0.79-0.94) <lb/>0.87 <lb/>(0.79-0.95) <lb/>MUAC (cm, as continuous variable) <lb/>0.90 (0.81-0.99) <lb/>0.90 <lb/>(0.81-0.99) <lb/>0.89 <lb/>(0.81-0.99) <lb/>BMI-for-age Z-score <lb/>(BAZ) <lb/>(as categorical variable) <lb/>BAZ &gt; -2 SD <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>BAZ &lt; -2SD <lb/>2.44 (0.96-6.21) <lb/>2.48 <lb/>(0.97-6.34) <lb/>2.43 <lb/>(0.94-6.29) <lb/>MUAC (as categorical <lb/>variable) <lb/>MUAC &gt;23 cm <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>MUAC &lt;23 cm <lb/>1.49 (0.88-2.51) <lb/>1.46 <lb/>(0.86-2.49) <lb/>1.48 <lb/>(0.86-2.55) <lb/>Menstruation Status <lb/>Menarche (years, as continuous variables) <lb/>1.07 (0.83-1.38) <lb/>1.07 <lb/>(0.82-1.38) <lb/>1.11 <lb/>(0.85-1.44) <lb/>1.03 <lb/>(0.78-1.36) <lb/>Length of cycle (days, as continuous variable) <lb/>0.93 (0.77-1.13) <lb/>0.94 <lb/>(0.78-1.15) <lb/>0.94 <lb/>(0.77-1.14) <lb/>0.92 <lb/>(0.75-1.13) <lb/>Sanitary pads per day (pads, as continuous <lb/>variable) <lb/>0.95 (0.70-1.29) <lb/>0.95 <lb/>(0.69-1.29) <lb/>0.92 <lb/>(0.67-1.26) <lb/>0.92 <lb/>(0.66-1.27) <lb/>Irregular cycle <lb/>No <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>Yes <lb/>0.97 (0.55-1.73) <lb/>0.97 <lb/>(0.54-1.75) <lb/>0.88 <lb/>(0.48-1.61) <lb/>0.93 <lb/>(0.50-1.72) <lb/>Having &gt;1 cycle/month <lb/>No <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>Yes <lb/>1.43 (0.83-2.45) <lb/>1.45 <lb/>(0.84-2.50) <lb/>1.42 <lb/>(0.82-2.48) <lb/>1.37 <lb/>(0.78-2.43) <lb/>Dietary Intake <lb/>Poultry/Beef <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.81 (0.33-1.99) <lb/>0.73 <lb/>(0.29-1.83) <lb/>0.74 <lb/>(0.29-1.89) <lb/>0.68 <lb/>(0.26-1.78) <lb/>0.69 <lb/>(0.23-2.03) <lb/>Fish <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.90 (0.37-2.23) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>(0.40-2.48) <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(0.40-2.56) <lb/>0.91 <lb/>(0.35-2.36) <lb/>1.36 <lb/>(0.44-4.23) <lb/>Eggs <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1.15 (0.51-2.57) <lb/>1.14 <lb/>(0.51-2.57) <lb/>1.38 <lb/>(0.60-3.19) <lb/>1.24 <lb/>(0.53-2.93) <lb/>1.37 <lb/>(0.51-3.72) <lb/>Soybean (Tofu/Tempeh) <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1.44 (0.58-3.55) <lb/>1.49 <lb/>(0.60-3.71) <lb/>1.57 <lb/>(0.62-3.95) <lb/>1.56 <lb/>(0.61-4.01) <lb/>2.52 <lb/>(0.76-8.40) <lb/>Fruits <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.38 (0.16-0.90) <lb/>0.36 <lb/>(0.15-0.86) <lb/>0.34 <lb/>(0.14-0.84) <lb/>0.38 <lb/>(0.15-0.93) <lb/>0.32 <lb/>(0.10-0.98) <lb/>Vegetables <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.46 (0.22-0.96) <lb/>0.43 <lb/>(0.21-0.91) <lb/>0.45 <lb/>(0.21-0.95) <lb/>0.47 <lb/>(0.22-1.02) <lb/>0.30 <lb/>(0.11-0.78) <lb/>Coffee/Tea <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.74 (0.36-1.52) <lb/>0.76 <lb/>(0.37-1.56) <lb/>0.79 <lb/>(0.38-1.64) <lb/>0.71 <lb/>(0.34-1.50) <lb/>0.63 <lb/>(0.28-1.41) <lb/>Milk <lb/>&lt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>1 (reference) <lb/>&gt;3 portions a <lb/>week <lb/>0.60 (0.29-1.26) <lb/>0.56 <lb/>(0.27-1.20) <lb/>0.61 <lb/>(0.28-1.32) <lb/>0.57 <lb/>(0.26-1.26) <lb/>0.59 <lb/>(0.24-1.50) <lb/>Data are presented as OR (95 % CI). Model 1 is adjusted for sociodemographic confounding factors (age, household size/number of family member, and parental <lb/>occupation). Model 2 is adjusted for Model 1, plus additional adjustment for lifestyle variables (duration of physical activity and (passive) smoking. Model 3 is adjusted <lb/>for Model 2, plus additional adjustment for BMI. Model 4 is adjusted for Model 3, plus additional adjustment for all other food categories. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">F.S. Sigit et al. <lb/>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) 101500 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>consuming animal-based food products (e.g., beef, poultry, and fish) <lb/>more than three portions per week was protective against anaemia, as <lb/>the majority of confidence intervals of the associations were crossing 1, <lb/>although the effect sizes were &lt;1. <lb/>Then in regard to menstruation, we did not find evidence that <lb/>menstruation (menarche, bleeding quantity, and duration and regularity <lb/>of cycle) was associated with anaemia. These were partially in line with <lb/>previous literature, as studies investigating the associations between <lb/>menstruation and anaemia often observed conflicting results. For <lb/>example, our findings were consistent with an earlier study that <lb/>observed no association between menstruation status and anaemia. 26 <lb/>However, several other studies have shown that heavy menstrual <lb/>bleeding was associated with iron loss and, in severe cases, iron defi-<lb/>ciency anaemia. 10,27 Other studies have also observed that menstrual <lb/>length and frequency were associated with increased risks of anaemia <lb/>and decreased level of ferritin3,9,28. Thus, it is still recommended that <lb/>intervention to reduce menstrual blood loss should not be overlooked, <lb/>particularly in those experiencing heavy menstrual bleeding, 10 as up to a <lb/>third of women of reproductive age experience heavy menstrual <lb/>bleeding. 3 <lb/>4.1. Strength and limitations <lb/>The strength of the study is its ability to provide an overview of <lb/>anaemia and its determinants among female adolescents in rural <lb/>Indonesia, in which studies showing findings from this setting is quite <lb/>rare. However, there are several limitations of this study. First, the cross-<lb/>sectional study design implies that no causality can be concluded from <lb/>the associations. Additionally, due to the observational nature of the <lb/>present study, there is a possibility of residual confounding that may <lb/>distort the true exposure-outcome associations. Second, there was po-<lb/>tential social desirability bias as participants may provide socially ex-<lb/>pected answers for the self-reported questionnaires (e.g., lifestyle). <lb/>Third, as the researchers visited the high schools to collect data, the <lb/>diagnosis of anaemia was measured only with a portable haemoglo-<lb/>binometer. Hence, a microscopic blood smear or complete blood count <lb/>test could not be performed, and we could not identify the specific <lb/>causes of anaemia in each individual. Fourth, the use of the Food Fre-<lb/>quency Questionnaire (FFQ) to assess dietary intake in this study may <lb/>lead to unreliable measures of total diet, total energy intake, and <lb/>nutrient values. However, as consumption of animal-based food prod-<lb/>ucts was very low in the study population and the Indonesian population <lb/>in general, we believe that FFQ is still the most relevant instrument as <lb/>other types of practical dietary assessment (e.g., 24-h food recall) may <lb/>lead to overestimation of intake if animal-based protein sources were <lb/>mentioned in the record. <lb/>4.2. Research implications <lb/>Despite the limitations, this study lays the groundwork for further <lb/>research. To help establish the definitive causes of anaemia in each in-<lb/>dividual, we encourage further studies to incorporate more thorough <lb/>laboratory examinations, such as microscopic blood smear test to <lb/>examine the morphology of erythrocytes and the mean corpuscular <lb/>volume. Screening for anaemia-inducing infectious diseases that are <lb/>common in LMICs, such as helminth and malarial infection may be <lb/>important, particularly because these infections are associated with <lb/>blood loss and iron deficiency in the infected individuals. <lb/>The high prevalence of anaemia in this study population provides <lb/>insight into the gravity of anaemia as a public health issue in Indonesia, <lb/>particularly among female adolescents living in rural areas. As results <lb/>from this study mainly represent the area of Karanganyar and its sur-<lb/>roundings, further studies with more rural areas could better show the <lb/>severity of the problem at the national level. <lb/>4.3. Public health implications <lb/>There are several public health implications of this study. First, as we <lb/>observed a prevalence of anaemia of 49 % in the female adolescent <lb/>population, this reflects a severe public health significance based on the <lb/>WHO classification. 15 As also shown by previous studies that anaemia in <lb/>women of reproductive age is the most common in adolescents, 4 public <lb/>health policy planning should be prioritised for this target group. Sec-<lb/>ond, as we observed that anaemia in the present study was mainly <lb/>explained by measures of undernutrition (BMI and MUAC), an <lb/>improvement in nutrition status could lead to anaemia reduction. <lb/>Improving nutrition status in women of reproductive age would also <lb/>eventually benefit in preventing chronic energy deficiency, which is <lb/>unfortunately a common nutrition-related problem in pregnant women <lb/>in Indonesia. 29 As previous research indicates that iron deficiency is the <lb/>leading cause in LMICs, accounting for up to 50 % of cases globally, 4,30 <lb/>efforts such as iron supplementation or fortification in staple foods with <lb/>a blanket approach should be encouraged. <lb/>5. Conclusions <lb/>In conclusion, this study highlights the alarmingly high prevalence of <lb/>anaemia among female adolescents in Karanganyar, and potentially <lb/>other rural areas in Indonesia. BMI and MUAC were strongly inversely <lb/>associated with anaemia, and being underweight doubled the risk of <lb/>anaemia. Consuming iron-rich fruits and vegetables may offer benefits <lb/>to prevent anaemia. We did not find evidence that menstruation was <lb/>associated with anaemia. Implementing multisectoral collaboration to <lb/>eliminate anaemia is crucial, and female adolescents living in rural areas <lb/>should be prioritised for targeted anaemia intervention. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Ethical Approval statement <lb/>The ethics of this study have been reviewed and approved by The <lb/>Research and Community Engagement Ethical Committee, Faculty of <lb/>Public Health, Universitas Indonesia (No.: Ket-811/UN2.F10.D11/ <lb/>PPM.00.02/2023). <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This study receives no funding. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author contribution statement <lb/>FSS -Conceptualization, Methodology, Formal Analysis, Investiga-<lb/>tion, Resources, Data Curation, Writing -Original Draft, Visualization, <lb/>Project Administration. <lb/>FBI -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>PD -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>DS -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>NDF -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>AS -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>LAL -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/>AF -Conceptualization, Investigation, Resources, Data Curation, <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing, Project Administration. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial <lb/>interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">F.S. Sigit et al. <lb/>Clinical Epidemiology and Global Health 25 (2024) 101500 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<div type="conflict">the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement <lb/>The authors thank Dr. Suryadi, Mr. Bowo Prasetijo, SST, and all <lb/>Karanganyar Community Health Center staff for their enormous support <lb/>and valuable partnership in sharing the surveillance data that makes this <lb/>publication possible. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.cegh.2023.101500. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Anaemia in women and children [Internet]. [cited 2023 Apr 4] https://www.who.in <lb/>t/data/gho/data/themes/topics/anaemia_in_women_and_children. <lb/>2. Kinyoki D, Osgood-Zimmerman AE, Bhattacharjee NV, et al. Anemia prevalence in <lb/>women of reproductive age in low-and middle-income countries between 2000 and <lb/>2018. Nat Med. 2021 Oct 1;27(10):1761-1782. <lb/>3. Mansour D, Hofmann A, Gemzell-Danielsson K. A Review of Clinical guidelines on <lb/>the Management of iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anemia in women with <lb/>heavy menstrual bleeding. Adv Ther. 2021 Jan;38(1):201-225. <lb/>4. Safiri S, Kolahi AA, Noori M, et al. Burden of anemia and its underlying causes in <lb/>204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: results from the Global Burden of Disease <lb/>Study 2019. J Hematol Oncol. 2021 Nov 4;14(1):185. <lb/>5. The World Bank. Prevalence of anemia among women of reproductive age (% of <lb/>women ages 15-49) [Internet] https://genderdata.worldbank.org/indicators/sh <lb/>-anm-allw-zs/. <lb/>6. Singh B, Verma SP, Chauhan AS, Verma DP. Prevalence of anemia among <lb/>reproductive-age females in the Tharu tribe of the Indo-Nepal border region. J Fam <lb/>Med Prim Care. 2022 Jun;11(6):2961-2964. <lb/>7. Bailey RL, West KPJ, Black RE. The epidemiology of global micronutrient <lb/>deficiencies. Ann Nutr Metab. 2015;66(Suppl 2):22-33. <lb/>8. Han X, Ding S, Lu J, Li Y. Global, regional, and national burdens of common <lb/>micronutrient deficiencies from 1990 to 2019: a secondary trend analysis based on <lb/>the Global Burden of Disease 2019 study. EClinicalMedicine. 2022 Feb;44, 101299. <lb/>9. Clancy KBH, Nenko I, Jasienska G. Menstruation does not cause anemia: <lb/>endometrial thickness correlates positively with erythrocyte count and hemoglobin <lb/>concentration in premenopausal women. Am J Hum Biol. 2006 Oct;18(5):710-713. <lb/>10. Critchley HOD, Munro MG, Shakur-Still H, Roberts I. Menstruation should not be <lb/>overlooked in control of anaemia. Lancet. 2021 Jan 2;397(10268):26. <lb/>11. Ayensu J, Annan R, Lutterodt H, Edusei A, Peng LS. Prevalence of anaemia and low <lb/>intake of dietary nutrients in pregnant women living in rural and urban areas in the <lb/>Ashanti region of Ghana. PLoS One. 2020;15(1), e0226026. <lb/>12. BPS Kabupaten Pekalongan [Internet]. [cited 2023 May 4] https://pekalongankab. <lb/>bps.go.id/indicator/23/102/1/persen-penduduk-miskin-p0-.html. <lb/>13. Badan Pusat Statistik, Kabupaten Pekalongan. Jumlah Penduduk Kabupaten <lb/>Pekalongan Menurut Kelompok Umur dan Jenis Kelamin (Jiwa), 2020-2021 <lb/>[Internet]. Available from: https://pekalongankab.bps.go.id/indicator/12/250/1/ju <lb/>mlah-penduduk-kabupaten-pekalongan-menurut-kelompok-umur-dan-jenis-kelamin <lb/>.html. <lb/>14. Direktorat Jenderal Pendidikan Anak Usia Dini, Pendidikan Dasar dan Pendidikan <lb/>Menengah, Kementerian Pendidikan, Kebudayaan, Riset dan Teknologi. Data Pokok <lb/>Pendidikan [Internet]. Available from: https://dapo.kemdikbud.go.id/sp <lb/>/2/032600. <lb/>15. World Health Organization. Haemoglobin Concentrations for the Diagnosis of Anaemia <lb/>and Assessment of Severity. World Health Organization; 2011 [Internet] https://apps. <lb/>who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/85839/WHO_NMH_NHD_MNM_11.1_eng. <lb/>pdf. <lb/>16. Van Tonder E, Mace L, Steenkamp L, Tydeman-Edwards R, Gerber K, Friskin D. Mid-<lb/>upper arm circumference (MUAC) as a feasible tool in detecting adult malnutrition. <lb/>S Afr J Clin Nutr. 2019 Oct 2;32(4):93-98. <lb/>17. Kumar P, Sareen N, Agrawal S, Kathuria N, Yadav S, Sethi V. Screening maternal <lb/>acute malnutrition using adult mid-upper arm circumference in Resource-poor <lb/>settings. Indian J Community Med. 2018 Jun;43(2):132-134. <lb/>18. Kementerian kesehatan republik Indonesia. Buku Panduan GERMAS: Gerakan <lb/>Masyarakat Hidup Sehat [Internet]. 2016 [cited 2021 Mar 12] https://dinkes.aceh <lb/>prov.go.id/uploads/buku-panduan-germas-final.pdf. <lb/>19. Direktorat Promosi Kesehatan Kementerian Kesehatan RI [Internet]. [cited 2021 Oct <lb/>18]. GERMAS -Gerakan Masyarakat Hidup Sehat. Available from: https://promkes. <lb/>kemkes.go.id/germas. <lb/>20. Ministry of Health. Republic of Indonesia. Peraturan Menteri Kesehatan Republik <lb/>Indonesia; 2016. Nomor 51 Tahun 2016. [Internet]. Direktorat Peraturan <lb/>Perundang-undangan, Kementerian Hukum dan Hak Asasi Manusia, Republik <lb/>Indonesia http://hukor.kemkes.go.id/uploads/produk_hukum/PMK_No._51_ttg_St <lb/>andar_Produk_Suplementasi_Gizi_.pdf. <lb/>21. National Institute for Health Research and Development (NIHRD). Ministry of Health, <lb/>Republic of Indonesia. Laporan Nasional RISKESDAS 2018; 2018 [Internet] http://la <lb/>bdata.litbang.kemkes.go.id/images/download/laporan/RKD/2018/Laporan_Nasi <lb/>onal_RKD2018_FINAL.pdf. <lb/>22. Moreno Chulilla JA, Romero Colás MS, Gutiérrez Martín M. Classification of anemia <lb/>for gastroenterologists. World J Gastroenterol. 2009 Oct 7;15(37):4627-4637. <lb/>23. Cappellini MD, Motta I. Anemia in clinical practice-definition and classification: <lb/>does hemoglobin change with aging? Semin Hematol. 2015 Oct;52(4):261-269. <lb/>24. Eberl E, Li AS, Zheng ZYJ, Cunningham J, Rangan A. Temporal change in iron <lb/>content of vegetables and legumes in Australia: a scoping Review. Foods. 2021 Dec <lb/>27;11(1). <lb/>25. Welk AK, Mehlhose C, Daum D, Enneking U. Vegetables with enhanced iron <lb/>bioavailability-German consumers&apos; perceptions of a new approach to improve <lb/>dietary iron supply. Nutrients. 2023;15(10). <lb/>26. Sumarlan E, Windiastuti E, Gunardi H. Iron status, prevalence and risk factors of <lb/>iron deficiency anemia among 12-to 15-year-old adolescent girls from different <lb/>socioeconomic status in Indonesia. Makara Journal of Health Research. 2018 Apr 1; <lb/>(1):22 [Internet] https://scholarhub.ui.ac.id/mjhr/vol22/iss1/8. <lb/>27. Bernardi LA, Ghant MS, Andrade C, Recht H, Marsh EE. The association between <lb/>subjective assessment of menstrual bleeding and measures of iron deficiency anemia <lb/>in premenopausal African-American women: a cross-sectional study. BMC Wom <lb/>Health. 2016 Aug 15;16(1):50. <lb/>28. Ofojekwu MJN, Nnanna OU, Okolie CE, Odewumi LA, Isiguzoro IOU, MosesD Lugos. <lb/>Hemoglobin and serum iron concentrations in menstruating nulliparous women in <lb/>jos, Nigeria. Lab Med. 2013 May 1;44(2):121-124. <lb/>29. Lestari S, Fujiati II , Keumalasari D, Daulay M, Martina SJ, Syarifah S. The <lb/>prevalence of anemia in pregnant women and its associated risk factors in North <lb/>Sumatera, Indonesia. IOP Conf Ser Earth Environ Sci. 2018 Mar 1;125(1), 012195. <lb/>30. Gardner W, Kassebaum N. Global, regional, and national prevalence of anemia and <lb/>its causes in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019. Curr Dev Nutr. 2020 Jun 1;4 <lb/>(suppl ment_2), 830-830. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">F.S. Sigit et al. </note>


	</text>


  </TEI>