<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Information work and digital support during the perinatal period: Perspectives of mothers and healthcare professionals</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Emma</forename>
          <surname>Kemp</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
          <surname>Sillence</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lisa</forename>
          <surname>Thomas</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T10:46:38.974Z">11/13/2025 10:46:38 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pdig.0000387</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Emma Kemp, Elizabeth Sillence, Lisa Thomas. (2024). Information work and digital support during the perinatal period: Perspectives of mothers and healthcare professionals. PLOS Digital Health, 3(8), e0000387. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pdig.0000387</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T10:45:57.372761Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T10:45:57.372761Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Long-term stability and the physical and <lb/>chemical factors predictive for antimicrobial <lb/>activity in Australian honey <lb/>Kenya E. Fernandes ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Andrew Z. Dong ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Aviva Levina 2 , Nural N. Cokcetin ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>Peter Brooks 3 , Dee A. Carter 1,4 * <lb/>1 School of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia, <lb/>2 School of Chemistry, University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia, 3 School of Science, <lb/>Technology and Engineering, University of the Sunshine Coast, Maroochydore, Queensland, Australia, <lb/>4 Sydney Institute for Infectious Diseases, University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia <lb/>* dee.carter@sydney.edu.au <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The growing burden of expired medicines contributes to environmental contamination and <lb/>landfill waste accumulation. Medicinal honey, with its non-toxic nature and potentially long <lb/>shelf-life, represents a promising and underutilised therapeutic that avoids some of these <lb/>issues. However, limited knowledge on how its antimicrobial properties change over time <lb/>combined with a lack of reliable processes in the honey industry for measuring antimicrobial <lb/>potential, hinder its clinical adoption. Using a diverse selection of 30 Australian honey sam-<lb/>ples collected between 2005 and 2007, we comprehensively evaluated their antibacterial <lb/>and antifungal activity and pertinent physical and chemical properties with the aims of <lb/>assessing the effect of long-term storage on activity, pinpointing factors associated with anti-<lb/>microbial efficacy, and establishing robust assessment methods. Minimum inhibitory con-<lb/>centration (MIC) assays proved superior to the standard phenol equivalence assay in <lb/>capturing the full range of antimicrobial activity present in honey. Correlations between activ-<lb/>ity and a range of physical and chemical properties uncovered significant associations, with <lb/>hydrogen peroxide, antioxidant content, and water activity emerging as key indicators in <lb/>non-Leptospermum honey. However, the complex nature and the diverse composition of <lb/>honey samples precludes the use of high-throughput chemical tests for accurately assess-<lb/>ing this activity, and direct assessment using live microorganisms remains the most eco-<lb/>nomical and reliable method. We provide recommendations for different methods of <lb/>assaying various honey properties, taking into account their accuracy along with technical <lb/>difficulty and safety considerations. All Leptospermum and fourteen of seventeen non-Lep-<lb/>tospermum honey samples retained at least some antimicrobial properties after 15-17 <lb/>years of storage, suggesting that honey can remain active for extended periods. Overall, the <lb/>results of this study will help industry meet the growing demand for high-quality, medicinally <lb/>active honey while ensuring accurate assessment of its antimicrobial potential. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/>1 / 27 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Fernandes KE, Dong AZ, Levina A, <lb/>Cokcetin NN, Brooks P, Carter DA (2024) Long-<lb/>term stability and the physical and chemical factors <lb/>predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian <lb/>honey. PLoS ONE 19(5): e0303095. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 <lb/>Editor: Branislav T. S ˇiler, Institute for Biological <lb/>Research, University of Belgrade, SERBIA <lb/>Received: February 5, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: April 18, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 22, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Fernandes et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>information files. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>All medicines have a shelf life, and the fate of expired medicines is an area of increasing con-<lb/>cern. Despite the free returned medicine scheme available in Australia, many medicines are <lb/>disposed of inappropriately or retained in the household well beyond their expiry date [1]. <lb/>These issues are of particular concern when it comes to antimicrobials, where inappropriate <lb/>disposal can result in environmental contamination [2] and use outside of prescribed need can <lb/>lead to poor clinical outcomes and the development of antimicrobial resistance [3]. Natural <lb/>products with antimicrobial activity could mitigate such risks, with a promising option being <lb/>medicinal honey. As a non-toxic product, medicinal does not pose an environmental risk, and <lb/>it appears incapable of inducing resistance [4, 5]. Additionally, when stored correctly, honey <lb/>boasts an exceptionally long shelf life. A notable example is the discovery of edible honey in <lb/>the tomb of Egyptian king Tutankhamun, which remained preserved for over 3,000 years [6]. <lb/>Despite growing recognition of the potential therapeutic benefits of honey, there remains a <lb/>need for evidence-based data to promote its use in clinical practice. Linked to this a desire in <lb/>the medicinal honey industry to identify key factors that can determine whether a given honey <lb/>will be antimicrobial, and to devise reliable processes for measuring these factors. Honey has <lb/>an extremely complex chemical composition consisting of sugars, organic acids, enzymes, and <lb/>bioactive compounds like flavonoids and phenolic acids [7], and these can all vary substantially <lb/>with floral source, geographic location, processing methods, and colony health [8, 9]. These <lb/>components are susceptible to changes over time, with storage conditions playing an impor-<lb/>tant role in the stability of key properties [10-12]. The absence of well-defined parameters for <lb/>assessing antimicrobial activity, coupled with limited data on the impact of long-term storage <lb/>on activity, presents a substantial challenge to the honey industry and ultimately affects the <lb/>clinical uptake of honey. Addressing these knowledge gaps is essential to meet the demand for <lb/>high-quality medicinally active honey and to maximise its therapeutic potential. <lb/>Antimicrobial activity can be measured in honey using various methods, each with its <lb/>advantages and limitations [13]. In Australia, the prevalent approaches are the phenol equiva-<lb/>lence assay and the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) assay. The phenol equivalence <lb/>assay, the current Australian industry standard, is an agar diffusion assay that compares the <lb/>activity of honey against Staphylococcus aureus with a standard phenol solution [14]. The MIC <lb/>assay, a standardised research method, is a broth dilution assay that determines the minimum <lb/>concentration of honey required to inhibit microbial growth [15]. Antimicrobial activity can <lb/>also be estimated through the measurement of certain chemical properties. In honey derived <lb/>from Leptospermum nectar, most antibacterial activity is due to the presence of methylglyoxal <lb/>(MGO) and the two correlate very well, allowing a simple chemical test of MGO concentration <lb/>to replace biological testing [16]. The major antimicrobial factor in non-Leptospermum honeys <lb/>is thought to be hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) production, which can be measured in honey <lb/>using various methods including the horseradish peroxidase (HRP) assay [17] and <lb/>AmplexRed-based commercial kits [18]. However, these tend to be either technically difficult <lb/>or costly to perform and often correlate poorly with antimicrobial levels, suggesting interfer-<lb/>ence by other honey components [17, 19, 20]. <lb/>In an extensive survey of Australian honey, Irish et al. (2011) characterised 477 samples for <lb/>their antimicrobial activity using the phenol equivalence assay [12], and assessed the stability <lb/>of activity of a selected subset following short-term (8 to 22 months) storage. In this follow-up <lb/>study, we chose a diverse selection of 30 honey samples from a more restricted geographic <lb/>area, with the aim of assessing the effect of ~15 years of storage on antimicrobial activity. Find-<lb/>ing most honeys retained a useful level of antimicrobial activity, this collection then allowed us <lb/>to explore a range of parameters of interest to the honey industry, including antibacterial and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<front>Funding: Funding for this project was provided by <lb/>NSW Bushfire Industry Recovery Package Sector <lb/>Development Grant (BIP-SDG-135) to DC. The <lb/>funders had no role in study design, data collection <lb/>and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>antifungal activity, hydrogen peroxide production, phenolic and antioxidant content, methyl-<lb/>glyoxal content, and honey colour. Where possible, we compared different ways of measuring <lb/>honey properties to determine the most useful and reliable methods. Finally, we combined the <lb/>data to examine the relationships between the antimicrobial activity of honey and its physical <lb/>and chemical properties, thereby identifying the key factors that contribute to its therapeutic <lb/>potential. <lb/>Materials &amp; methods <lb/>Honey samples and preparation <lb/>Honey samples previously screened by Irish et al. between 2005 and 2007 were chosen for <lb/>analysis [12]. Since their original assessment, all honeys have been stored in plastic containers <lb/>in the dark at 4 ˚C. Fifteen paired honey samples were selected, including native, non-native, <lb/>Leptospermum, and non-Leptospermum floral sources and with no, low, medium, and high <lb/>antimicrobial activity (S1 Table). The floral source of the honey was determined by beekeepers <lb/>through a process that considered the floral resources available for nectar collection, the geo-<lb/>graphical location of the apiary, and organoleptic characteristics of the honey. Three control <lb/>honeys were included in all tests: artificial honey (1.5 g sucrose, 7.5 g maltose, 40.5 g fructose, <lb/>33.5 g glucose, 17 mL sterile water) (ART), Barnes TA 10+ Jarrah honey (JAR) with peroxide-<lb/>based activity, and Comvita UMF 18+ Manuka honey (MAN) with non-peroxide-based activ-<lb/>ity. Unless otherwise specified, all honey samples were mixed thoroughly with a spatula, incu-<lb/>bated at 35 ˚C for 15 minutes, diluted to the target concentration in sterile water, and vortexed <lb/>thoroughly before use. <lb/>Microorganisms and culture conditions <lb/>Two Gram-positive bacterial species (Staphylococcus aureus ATCC29213, Enterococcus faecalis <lb/>ATCC29212), one Gram-negative bacterium (Pseudomonas aeruginosa ATCC29883), and one <lb/>yeast (Cryptococcus deuterogattii R265) were used for antimicrobial testing. Bacterial and yeast <lb/>strains were maintained as glycerol stocks at -80 ˚C. Bacterial strains were grown on Nutrient <lb/>Agar (NA; Oxoid) and incubated at 30 ˚C for 24 hours before use. C. deuterogattii was grown <lb/>on Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA; Oxoid) and incubated at 30 ˚C for 48 hours. <lb/>Antimicrobial susceptibility testing <lb/>The phenol equivalence assay was performed based on the method outlined in Irish et al. 2011 <lb/>[12]. Antimicrobial susceptibility testing by broth microdilution was performed in accordance <lb/>with CLSI guidelines for aerobic bacteria [21] and yeasts [22] with minor modifications. <lb/>Briefly, inocula were prepared from colonies growing on agar plates to a final concentration of <lb/>2 x 10 5 -8 x 10 5 for bacteria, and 0.5 x 10 3 -2.5 x 10 3 CFU/ml for C. deuterogattii. Bacterial <lb/>strains were adjusted to an absorbance of between 0.08-0.1 at 540 nm while C. deuterogattii <lb/>cells were counted using a haemocytometer. Assays used Mueller-Hinton Broth (MHB; <lb/>Oxoid) supplemented with 20 mg Ca ++ /L and 10 mg Mg ++ /L for bacteria, and Yeast Nutrient <lb/>Broth (YNB; Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 0.165 M MOPS and 0.5% D-glucose for C. <lb/>deuterogattii. Honeys were assayed at 30, 25, 20, 15, 10, and 5% (w/w) diluted in either sterile <lb/>water or freshly prepared 5600 U/ml catalase solution, and control drugs were assayed at con-<lb/>centration ranges of 0.0039-4 μg/ml for amphotericin B (AMB) and 0.125-32 μg/ml for tetra-<lb/>cycline (TET). Plates were incubated without agitation at 35 ˚C for 18 hours (bacteria), or 48 <lb/>hours (C. deuterogattii). The MIC was determined visually and defined as the lowest drug/ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>honey concentration at which growth was completely inhibited (no visible turbidity). Three <lb/>independent repeats were performed for each honey sample. <lb/>Honey microbial content <lb/>After thorough mixing, 100 μl of undiluted honey was placed on either NA or V8-Juice Agar <lb/>(Oxoid) using a truncated P1000 pipette tip. A sterile cotton swab was used to spread the <lb/>honey evenly across the entire surface of the agar plate. Plates were incubated at 35 ˚C for 5 <lb/>days and photographed using a digital camera. Two independent replicates were performed <lb/>on different days. <lb/>Hydrogen peroxide assays (HRP, ADHP, and strip-test) <lb/>The horseradish peroxidase (HRP) assay was performed based on the method outlined in Leh-<lb/>mann et al. 2019 [17]. For the 10-acetyl-3,7-dihydroxyphenoxazine (ADHP) assay, honey sam-<lb/>ples were diluted to 25% (w/w) in sterile water. At the 2-hour timepoint, 40 μl of sample was <lb/>aliquoted into a 96-well plate, 160 μl of ADHP reagent (1 mM ADHP and 30 μg/ml HRP in <lb/>PBS) was added and absorbance was measured at 560 nm using a plate reader. For both HRP <lb/>and ADHP assays, 2-fold dilutions of H 2 O 2 standards ranging from 0.5-1024 μM were used to <lb/>generate standard curves and the resulting equations from the lines of best fit were used to cal-<lb/>culate the amount of H 2 O 2 in each honey sample. For the strip-test method, honey samples <lb/>were diluted to 25% (w/w) in sterile water. At the 2-hour timepoint, H 2 O 2 test strips were <lb/>immersed in honey samples for 1 second and the excess shaken off. Test strips were allowed to <lb/>develop for 10 seconds and compared to the colour chart provided by the manufacturer to <lb/>determine H 2 O 2 concentration. <lb/>Phenolics assays (Folin-Ciocalteu and fast blue BB) <lb/>For the Folin-Ciocalteu (FC) assay, 20 μl aliquots of 20% (w/w) honey samples were prepared <lb/>in triplicate in a 96-well plate. To each sample, 100 μl of FC reagent (1 ml Folin-Ciocalteu <lb/>reagent in 30 ml sterile water) was added with incubation in the dark for 5 min at RT. Next, <lb/>80 μl of 0.75% Na 2 CO 3 was added with incubation in the dark for 90 min at RT. Absorbance <lb/>was measured at 760 nm using a plate reader. The Fast Blue BB (FBBB) assay was performed <lb/>based on the method outlined previously in [23], with slight modifications. In a 96-well plate, <lb/>200 μl aliquots of 20% (w/w) honey samples were prepared in triplicate. To each sample, 20 μl <lb/>of 0.1% Fast Blue BB reagent was added and pipetted up and down vigorously for 30 sec. Next, <lb/>20 μl of 5% NaOH was added with incubation in the dark for 45 min at RT. Absorbance was <lb/>measured at 420 nm using a plate reader. For both assays, gallic acid standards ranging from <lb/>0.06-0.18 mg/ml were used to generate a standard curve and the resulting equation for the line <lb/>of best fit was used to calculate the phenolics content of honey samples, expressed as mg of gal-<lb/>lic acid equivalent per kg of honey (mg GAE/kg). <lb/>Antioxidant assays (FRAP &amp; DDPH) <lb/>For the ferric-reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assay, FRAP reagent was prepared freshly <lb/>from 1:1:10 (v/v/v) of 10 mM 2,4,6-Tris(2-pyridyl)-s-triazine in 40 mM HCl, 20 mM FeCl 3 , <lb/>and 300 mM pH 3.6 acetate buffer, and was warmed to 37 ˚C prior to the assay. In a 96-well <lb/>plate, 20 μl aliquots of 20% (w/w) honey samples were prepared in triplicate. To each sample, <lb/>180 μl of FRAP reagent was added with incubation for 30 min at 37 ˚C. Absorbance was mea-<lb/>sured at 594 nm using a plate reader. FeSO 4 standards ranging from 200-1200 μM, made <lb/>freshly and stored on ice until use, were used to generate a standard curve and the resulting <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>equation from the line of best fit was used to calculate FRAP value, expressed as μmol Fe 2+ /kg. <lb/>For the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) assay, 10 μl aliquots of 20% (w/w) honey sam-<lb/>ples were prepared in triplicate in a 96-well plate. To each sample, 100 μl of 100 mM pH 5.5 <lb/>acetate buffer and 250 μl of DPPH reagent (130 μM DPPH in methanol) were added with incu-<lb/>bation in the dark for 90 min at RT. Absorbance was measured at 520 nm using a plate reader <lb/>against a methanol blank. Trolox standards at pH 7 ranging from 100-600 μM were used to <lb/>generate a standard curve and the resulting equation from the line of best fit was used to calcu-<lb/>late radical scavenging activity, expressed as μmol Trolox equivalent per kg of honey (μmol <lb/>TE/kg). <lb/>Assessment of honey colour <lb/>For visual assessment, 10 ml of undiluted honey in a 15 ml Falcon tube was compared against <lb/>a Pfund colour grader chart. For spectrophotometric assessment, honey samples were diluted <lb/>to 50% (w/w) and a wave scan from 380-780 nm at 1 nm steps was taken using a UV/Vis spec-<lb/>trophotometer (Specord S600) in disposable plastic cuvettes with 10 mm optical pathlength. <lb/>Sterile water was used as a blank. Honey colour was then assessed using three methods: Pfund <lb/>value, colour intensity, and CIELAB coordinates. Pfund values were calculated using the equa-<lb/>tion developed by White in 1984 [24], Pfund (mm) = -38.70 + 371.39(A 635 ). Colour Intensity <lb/>was calculated using the equation Colour Intensity (mAU) = (A 720 -A 450 ) × 1000. CIELAB <lb/>coordinates were calculated using the method outlined in [25]. <lb/>Assessment of other physical and chemical properties <lb/>For pH measurements, 10% (w/w) honey samples were measured using a pH meter (Mettler <lb/>Toledo) at RT. Brix value was measured at 20 ˚C using a refractometer (Hanna HI96801), with <lb/>Brix value expressed as g of total sugar per 100 g of honey and water content expressed as % <lb/>(w/w). Water activity was measured at 25 ˚C using a water activity analyser (Aqualab PRE) <lb/>with a correction of ± 0.005 a w made per 0.1 ºC deviation. For determination of methylglyoxal, <lb/>dihydroxyacetone, and hydroxymethylfurfural content, honey samples were derivatised with <lb/>O-(2,3,4,5,6-pentafluorobenzyl)hydroxylamine HCl and analysed against Anisole by HPLC <lb/>with 263 nm detection, as per [26]. <lb/>Elemental content <lb/>Honey samples were digested using a previously described method [27] with modifications. <lb/>An approx. 9 M solution of HNO 3 was prepared by mixing two volumes of Milli-Q water with <lb/>three volumes of 65% HNO 3 . Honey samples were heated at 40 ˚C to increase fluidity, and <lb/>three aliquots of each sample (~0.4g, ± 0.2 mg precision) were weighted into 10 mL polypro-<lb/>pylene tubes. Samples were mixed with 4 mL of HNO 3 solution, heated up to 60 ˚C for 24 h, <lb/>cooled to room temperature, and the sample volumes brought to 5 mL with Milli-Q water. To <lb/>validate the digestion technique, selected samples were also digested using a harsher method <lb/>taken from [28]. Weighed honey aliquots (~0.5 g) were mixed with 1 mL of Milli-Q water and <lb/>dissolved by sonication at 50 ˚C. Then, 5 mL of 65% HNO 3 was added to each sample, and the <lb/>samples were heated for 1 h at 90 ˚C (caution: this results in a violent reaction with the forma-<lb/>tion of NO 2 gas). Samples were cooled, and 1 mL of 30% H 2 O 2 was added. After further heat-<lb/>ing for 30 min at 90 ˚C, the samples were cooled to room temperature and brought to 10 mL <lb/>with Milli-Q water. The elemental contents measured using both digestion techniques agreed <lb/>with 5% experimental error. Elemental analysis of the digests was performed on a Perkin-<lb/>Elmer NexION 350X ICP-MS analyser. A 24-element balanced environmental standard <lb/>(HPS-Q0109521 from High Purity Standards) was used for calibration. Typical calibration <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>ranges were 10-10,000 ppb for highly abundant elements and 0.10-100 ppb for trace metals. <lb/>Only the elements that were consistently at least twice as high in honey samples compared to <lb/>the blanks were included in the final analysis. <lb/>Statistical analysis &amp; figure preparation <lb/>Whether data were normally distributed was determined using the Shapiro-Wilk normality <lb/>test. For statistical analysis, MIC readings above the tested maximum of 30% (w/w) honey <lb/>were assigned a value of 35%. Associations between variables used Spearman&apos;s rank correla-<lb/>tions which determines the strength and direction of monotonic relationships but does not <lb/>assume linearity, or linear regressions which do assume linearity. Correlations between anti-<lb/>microbial activity and the physical and chemical properties of honey samples were visualised <lb/>using partial least squares (PLS) regression to identify the underlying relationships between <lb/>the two sets of variables. For all correlations between antimicrobial activity and the physical <lb/>and chemical properties of honey, MIC values were subtracted from 35 to reverse their direc-<lb/>tion so that variables related with increased antimicrobial activity would appear as positively <lb/>rather than negatively correlated. P values &lt;0.05 were considered significant. Data were ana-<lb/>lysed using Prism 5 (GraphPad Inc), and XLSTAT (Lumivero) software. <lb/>Results <lb/>Most honey samples retained some activity following 15-17 years of <lb/>storage <lb/>The antimicrobial activity of honey samples was first assessed using the phenol equivalence <lb/>(PE) assay and compared to the results from the original testing that took place between 2005-<lb/>2007 (Fig 1A, with 2022 results also shown in Table 1). Most honey samples retained some <lb/>level of activity after 15-17 years of storage, with fourteen out of seventeen non-Leptospermum <lb/>honeys and four out of four Leptospermum honeys remaining active. The nine honey samples <lb/>that were inactive when screened in 2005-2007 were still inactive. In the active non-Leptosper-<lb/>mum honeys, the average total activity (TA) decreased by 64% from 15.6 to 5.5 PE, with a <lb/>range of 3.5 to 25.1 PE. In the active Leptospermum honeys, the average non-peroxide activity <lb/>(NPA) decreased by 31% from 17.0 to 11.9 PE, but this ranged from a 0.4 PE increase to an 8.6 <lb/>PE decrease (Fig 1B). <lb/>The number of honey samples falling into the categories of no (&lt;5), low (5-10), medium <lb/>(10-20), and high (&gt;20) activity at both testing times are shown in Fig 1C, with the largest cat-<lb/>egory in 2005-2007 being medium (10-20) activity, and the largest category in 2022 being low <lb/>(5-10) activity. Considering non-Leptospermum honeys only, a strong correlation was seen <lb/>between the TA results from 2005-2007 and the results from 2022 (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.87, <lb/>p&lt;0.001), and considering Leptospermum honeys only, a strong correlation was seen between <lb/>NPA results (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.96, p = 0.003). This indicates that TA decreased at a similar <lb/>rate in non-Leptospermum honeys and NPA decreased at a similar rate in Leptospermum hon-<lb/>eys, though the steeper TA curve indicates a faster decrease in TA relative to NPA. <lb/>Minimum inhibitory concentration values generally aligned across species <lb/>and with phenol equivalence results <lb/>The antimicrobial activity of honey samples was further assessed using broth microdilution <lb/>methodology. Staphylococcus aureus was tested to compare results with the phenol equivalence <lb/>assay, and additional microbes were tested including another Gram-positive (Enterococcus fae-<lb/>calis), a Gram-negative (Pseudomonas aeruginosa), and a fungus (Cryptococcus deuterogattii) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>to see how consistent activity was against diverse microbes (Fig 2A and Table 1). Artificial <lb/>honey MICs showed that P. aeruginosa is more susceptible to osmolarity than the other <lb/>microbes tested with an MIC of 25% (w/w) compared to &gt;30% (w/w) for the others. Overall, <lb/>S. aureus was the most susceptible microbe to the TA of honey with an average MIC for active <lb/>non-Leptospermum honeys of 14% (w/w), followed by P. aeruginosa at 16% (w/w), C. deutero-<lb/>gattii at 22% (w/w), and E. faecalis at 26% (w/w). Considering NPA in Leptospermum honeys, <lb/>S. aureus was again the most susceptible with an average MIC of 9% (w/w), followed by E. fae-<lb/>calis at 16% (w/w), P. aeruginosa at 20% (w/w), and C. deuterogattii at 25% (w/w). Fig 2B <lb/>shows the correlations between phenol equivalence and MIC values for TA and NPA in active <lb/>honeys only for S. aureus. Considering TA, phenol equivalence and MIC values were weakly <lb/>Fig 1. Antimicrobial activity of honey samples over time measured by the phenol equivalence (PE) assay. (A) Results of the PE assay performed <lb/>in 2005-2007 (left) compared to 2022 (right) showing total activity (TA) and non-peroxide activity (NPA). (B) Box plots showing the distribution of <lb/>change in phenol equivalence values for TA and NPA between 2005-2007 and 2022. Dotted line shows the median value. (C) Bar charts showing the <lb/>number of honey samples in each activity range in 2005-2007 and 2022. (D) Correlations of TA between 2005-2007 and 2022 in non-<lb/>Leptospermum samples only (left) and NPA between 2005-2007 and 2022 in Leptospermum samples only (right). Lines of best fit, Spearman&apos;s rho, <lb/>and p-values are shown. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Floral sources and antimicrobial susceptibility testing data for honey samples 1 . <lb/>ID <lb/>Floral Source <lb/>S. aureus <lb/>E. faecalis <lb/>P. aeruginosa <lb/>C. deutero-<lb/>gattii <lb/>PE 2022 <lb/>MIC <lb/>TA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>NPA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>TA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>NPA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>TA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>NPA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>TA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>NPA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>TA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>NPA <lb/>(% w/ <lb/>w) <lb/>Non-Leptospermum Honeys <lb/>AB1 Apple Box/Red <lb/>Stringybark <lb/>9.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>15 <lb/>AB2 Apple Box <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>BA1 Banksia <lb/>7.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>BA2 Banksia <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>30 <lb/>BL1 <lb/>Blueweed/ Lucerne <lb/>6.9 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>BL2 <lb/>Blueweed/ Lucerne <lb/>6.3 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>FB1 <lb/>Feather Bush <lb/>6.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>15 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>FB2 <lb/>Feather Bush <lb/>6.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>15 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>EU1 Mixed Eucalypt <lb/>7.7 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>EU2 Mixed Eucalypt <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>IB1 <lb/>Mugga Ironbark <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>IB2 <lb/>Mugga Ironbark <lb/>5.3 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>PB1 <lb/>Paperbark <lb/>8.4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>PB2 <lb/>Paperbark <lb/>9.6 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>SB1 <lb/>Red Stringybark <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>SB2 <lb/>Red Stringybark <lb/>6.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>SJ1 <lb/>Salvation Jane <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>SJ2 <lb/>Salvation Jane <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>TT1 Tea Tree <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>TT2 Tea Tree <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>YB1 Yellow Box <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>YB2 Yellow Box <lb/>7.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>MX1 Mixed <lb/>8.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>MX2 Mixed <lb/>5.4 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>25 <lb/>Leptospermum Honeys <lb/>CL1 Crows Ash/ <lb/>Leptospermum <lb/>7.3 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>30 <lb/>CL2 Crows Ash/ <lb/>Leptospermum <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>15 <lb/>25 <lb/>25 <lb/>JB1 <lb/>Jelly Bush <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>JB2 <lb/>Jelly Bush <lb/>20.3 <lb/>16.6 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>LE1 <lb/>Leptospermum <lb/>19.4 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>25 <lb/>25 <lb/>LE2 <lb/>Leptospermum <lb/>6.5 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>Control Honeys <lb/>ART Artificial <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>25 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>JAR Jarrah <lb/>11.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>20 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>MAN Manuka <lb/>19.7 <lb/>20.1 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>1 PE 2022 = Phenol Equivalence 2022, MIC = Minimum Inhibitory Concentration, TA = Total Activity, NPA = Non-<lb/>Peroxide Activity <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>but significantly correlated (Spearman&apos;s rho = -0.55, p = &lt;0.006) indicating that honeys with <lb/>greater TA by phenol equivalence are generally also more active by MIC though the fit is not <lb/>strong. Low activity honeys (5-10 PE) by phenol equivalence had a much larger spread of <lb/>MICs (5 -&gt;30% (w/w)), and some honey samples with no activity by phenol equivalence had <lb/>activity by MIC, suggesting that the MIC tests may be detecting sensitivity to certain <lb/>Fig 2. Antimicrobial activity of honey samples measured by broth microdilution assay, and correlations with the phenol equivalence (PE) <lb/>assay. (A) Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of honey samples against bacterial pathogens S. aureus, E. faecalis, and P. aeruginosa, and <lb/>fungal pathogen C. deuterogattii. Total activity (TA) is shown as bars, and non-peroxide activity (NPA) shown as diamonds. The % (w/w) refers to <lb/>the concentration of honey diluted in sterile water (for TA) or catalase solution (for NPA). (B) Correlations between PE and MIC measures of TA <lb/>(left) and NPA (right) in active honey samples. Lines of best fit, Spearman&apos;s rho, and p-values are shown. (C) TA (left) and NPA (right) Spearman <lb/>correlation matrices showing how closely antimicrobial activity of honey samples aligns between different species. Spearman&apos;s rho values are shown <lb/>in the boxes with coloured scalebar also indicating level of correlation. * = p�0.05, ** = p�0.01, *** = p�0.001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>compounds present in some honey samples that is not picked up by the phenol equivalence <lb/>test. Considering NPA, phenol equivalence and MIC values were much more strongly corre-<lb/>lated (Spearman&apos;s rho = -0.91, p = &lt;0.022). Comparing the MIC results across species, Spear-<lb/>man&apos;s correlation matrices show that both TA and NPA were significantly positively <lb/>correlated between all four species tested (p�0.01) (Fig 2C). <lb/>Honey samples with non-peroxide activity contain lower levels of microbes <lb/>after storage <lb/>Honey samples were spread onto agar plates to see whether microbes would be present after <lb/>storage for 15-17 years, and whether this would align with antimicrobial activity. Nutrient <lb/>agar plates were chosen to allow growth of a wide range of microorganisms, while V8 juice <lb/>was chosen to provide extra nutrients for the growth of moulds. Fig 3 shows images of the <lb/>spread plates after 5 days of growth at 35 ˚C, with plate pairs outlined in colours correspond-<lb/>ing to the antimicrobial activity of the honey sample as determined by MIC for S. aureus. <lb/>Minimal growth was noted on spread plates from honeys with NPA. This is particularly dis-<lb/>tinct when comparing the active Leptospermum honeys (CL1, CL2, JB2, LE1, and LE2) to <lb/>JB1, the one Leptospermum honey with no activity, which had high levels of growth. While <lb/>all inactive honeys had medium to high levels of microbial growth, results were more varied <lb/>for honeys where the activity was dominated by peroxide-based activity, with some having <lb/>minimal growth (e.g. BL1 and FB1) and some having high levels of growth (e.g. PB2 and <lb/>SB1) that did not appear to correspond to activity levels. Organisms growing on all plates <lb/>were mostly a mix of bacteria and yeasts, with only a single mould noted on the PB1 V8 <lb/>plate, however, incubation of plates at a lower temperature (25 ˚C) may have resulted in <lb/>more mould growth. <lb/>Hydrogen peroxide production is highly variable across samples and does <lb/>not align with floral source <lb/>Hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) production was measured over 6 hours using the horseradish <lb/>peroxidase (HRP) assay (Fig 4A). All honeys except one exhibited a peak in H 2 O 2 production <lb/>and return to near zero by the end of the 6 hours. The one exception was SJ1, a salvation Jane <lb/>honey, which steadily increased in H 2 O 2 production throughout the course of the assay. The <lb/>peak H 2 O 2 concentration ranged from 30 to 86 μM in inactive non-Leptospermum honeys, <lb/>from 72 to 920 μM in active non-Leptospermum honeys, and from 70 to 250 μM in Leptosper-<lb/>mum honeys. Few honey samples from the same floral source produced similar H 2 O 2 curves <lb/>(for example, blueweed/lucerne honeys BL1 and BL2, crow&apos;s ash/Leptospermum honeys CL1 <lb/>and CL2, and Leptospermum honeys LE1 and LE2), with the majority producing markedly <lb/>different curves (for example, banksia honeys BA1 and BA2, mugga ironbark honeys IB1 <lb/>and IB2, and yellow box honeys YB1 and YB2) suggesting that factors other than floral <lb/>source are a major determinant of hydrogen peroxide production or that the major floral <lb/>source identified by beekeepers may not necessarily reflect the true complexity of samples. <lb/>Three metrics were calculated from the H 2 O 2 time course data: H 2 O 2 concentration at 2 <lb/>hours, maximum H 2 O 2 concentration reached, and area under the curve for total H 2 O 2 pro-<lb/>duced (S1 Table). H 2 O 2 concentration at 2 hours was found to strongly correlate with both <lb/>maximum H 2 O 2 concentration reached (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.94, p&lt;0.001) and area under <lb/>the curve for total H 2 O 2 produced (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.91, p&lt;0.001), and was therefore cho-<lb/>sen to use for further tests as the simplest measurement to assess. H 2 O 2 concentration at 2 <lb/>hours was subsequently measured with two additional methods: a 10-acetyl-3,7-dihydroxy-<lb/>phenoxazine (ADHP) assay which uses the same principle as the commonly used <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>commercial AmplexRed kit, and H 2 O 2 test strips (S1 Table). Spearman correlations between <lb/>H 2 O 2 concentration at 2 hours measured by the HRP assay, ADHP assay, and H 2 O 2 strips <lb/>are presented in Fig 4B, with all showing strong positive (Spearman&apos;s rho �0.82) and signifi-<lb/>cant (p�0.001) correlations. <lb/>Fig 3. Growth of microbes from honey samples kept in storage for 15-17 years. Spread plates of undiluted honey on nutrient (left) or V8-juice (right) <lb/>agar incubated at 35 ˚C for 5 days. Samples are ordered from most active starting at the top left to least active at the bottom right as determined by S. <lb/>aureus MIC, with coloured borders indicating whether honey samples had no activity (orange), peroxide-dominated activity (green), or non-peroxide <lb/>activity (red). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 4. Hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) in honey samples measured by various methods and correlations between measurements. (A) H 2 O 2 production <lb/>over 6 hours measured by the horseradish peroxidase (HRP) assay. Each box shows the H 2 O 2 production curves of two honey samples with the same <lb/>floral source, except the last box which shows the three control honeys. Coloured squares indicate whether honey samples had no activity (orange), <lb/>peroxide-dominated activity (green), or non-peroxide activity (red) shown. (B) Correlations between H 2 O 2 concentration measured at 2 hours by the <lb/>HRP and 10-acetyl-3,7-dihydroxyphenoxazine (ADHP) assays (left), the HRP assay and H 2 O 2 strips (middle), and the ADHP assay and H 2 O 2 strips <lb/>(right). Lines of best fit, Spearman&apos;s rho, and p-values are shown. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods for assaying phenolics and antioxidant content are strongly <lb/>aligned <lb/>Various other physical and chemical properties that have been linked to antimicrobial activity <lb/>were assayed in honey samples. Phenolics content was measured using the Folin-Ciocalteu <lb/>(FC) and Fast Blue BB (FBBB) assays (Fig 5A), with the correlation of both methods shown in <lb/>Fig 5B. Phenolics content ranged from 90-494 mg GAE/kg via FC and from 28-399 mg GAE/ <lb/>kg via FBBB. In both cases, the lowest phenolics content was seen in blueweed/lucerne honey <lb/>BL1, and the highest was in Leptospermum honey LE1. The results of the two assays were sig-<lb/>nificantly positively correlated (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.81, p&lt;0.001), with the FC assay producing <lb/>uniformly higher values than the FBBB assay, indicating possible interference in the latter by <lb/>non-phenolic reducing compounds. Antioxidant content was measured using the 2,2-diphe-<lb/>nyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and ferric-reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assays (Fig 5C). <lb/>Antioxidant content ranged from 1685-4672 μmol TE/kg via DPPH and from 654-5466 μmol <lb/>Fe 2+ /kg via FRAP. In both cases, the honey with the lowest antioxidant content was Banksia <lb/>honey BA2, and the honey with the highest antioxidant content was Leptospermum honey <lb/>LE1. The results of the two assays were significantly positively correlated (Fig 5D, Spearman&apos;s <lb/>rho = 0.87, p&lt;0.001). Both phenolics and antioxidant content tended to be largely similar for <lb/>honey pairs from the same floral source. <lb/>Measurements of honey colour and other physical and chemical properties <lb/>The colour of honey samples was assessed visually using a Pfund colour grader chart and com-<lb/>pared to three spectrophotometric methods of colour assessment: the Pfund method devel-<lb/>oped by White [24], mAU, and CIELAB coordinates. Images showing the spectrum of colours <lb/>seen in honey samples are shown in Fig 5E, with data for each measurement method presented <lb/>in S1 Table. Honey samples from the same floral source again tended to have similar colours <lb/>although there were notable exceptions; for example, tea tree honeys TT1 and TT2, and crow&apos;s <lb/>ash/Leptospermum honeys CL1 and CL2). By visual assessment, honey samples ranged from 2 <lb/>mm or Water White (YB2) to 96 mm or Amber (LE1). By the Pfund White method, honey <lb/>samples ranged from 44 or Extra Light Amber (BA1) to 328 or Dark Amber (LE1). By mAU, <lb/>samples ranged from 451 (BA1) to 3444 (LE2). By CIELAB, samples ranged from 26 (SJ1) to <lb/>56 (CL2). Spearman correlations between colour assessed visually and the three spectrophoto-<lb/>metric measurements are shown in Fig 5F. Pfund assessed visually had poor but significant <lb/>correlation with the Pfund White (Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.46, p = 0.007) and CIELAB (Spearman&apos;s <lb/>rho = 0.48, p = 0.005) methods, and a stronger significant correlation with the mAU method <lb/>(Spearman&apos;s rho = 0.74, p&lt;0.001). <lb/>Other physical and chemical properties measured are presented in Table 2. pH ranged from <lb/>3.46 (SJ1) to 4.12 (BA1). Sugar content ranged from 72.8 (LE2) to 79.0 ˚Brix (SB2). Water <lb/>activity ranged from 0.56 (CL2) to 0.69 (CL1). In Leptospermum honeys, methylglyoxal <lb/>(MGO) content ranged from 4 (CL2) to 805 mg/ kg (JB2) and dihydroxyacetone (DHA) con-<lb/>tent ranged from 2 (CL2) to 1386 mg/ kg (JB2). The significant levels of DHA remaining in <lb/>Leptospermum honeys shows that the conversion to MGO is incomplete, suggesting that this <lb/>chemical transformation was not occurring or occurring very slowly while the honeys were in <lb/>storage at 4 ˚C. Several non-Leptospermum honeys contained MGO and DHA, including MX2 <lb/>(101 and 276 mg/ kg, respectively) which exhibited NPA, and BA2, EU2, PB2, TT1, and TT2 <lb/>(�81 and �129 mg/ kg, respectively) which did not exhibit NPA. This suggests that these hon-<lb/>eys, although they may have been predominantly from one floral source, were likely also con-<lb/>tributed to by Leptospermum nectar. Hydroxymethylfurfural (HMF) content, an indicator of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 5. Phenolics content, antioxidant content, and colour of honey samples measured by various methods and correlations between <lb/>measurements. (A) Phenolics content measured by the Folin-Ciocalteu (FC) and fast blue BB (FBBB) assays and (B) the correlation between the two <lb/>assays. (C) Antioxidant content measured by the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and ferric-reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assays and (D) <lb/>the correlation between the two assays. (E) Images showing the spectrum of colours seen in honey samples. (F) Correlations between colour as assessed <lb/>visually using a Pfund colour grader chart and colour assessed spectrophotometrically using the Pfund method of White (left), mAU (middle), and <lb/>CIELAB (right). For all correlation charts, lines of best fit, Spearman&apos;s rho, and p-values are shown. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>heat and storage changes, ranged from 3 (BL1, IB1, YB2, MX1) to 41 mg/ kg (SJ2) with an <lb/>average of 11 mg/ kg. <lb/>The elemental content of honey samples is diverse and variable <lb/>Honey samples were assessed for their level of various common elements. A heatmap using <lb/>standardised values is shown in Fig 6A, with raw values presented in S1 Table. Overall, potas-<lb/>sium (861 μg/g) was the most prevalent element on average followed by sodium (148 ug/g), <lb/>phosphorus (39 μg/g) and magnesium (38 μg/g). Elements present at lower average quantities <lb/>were calcium (8.5 μg/g), zinc (8.3 μg/g), iron (4.4 μg/g), and manganese (3.4 μg/g). Elements <lb/>Table 2. Physical and chemical properties of honey samples. <lb/>ID <lb/>˚Brix <lb/>Water Activity (aW) <lb/>pH <lb/>MGO (mg/ kg) <lb/>DHA (mg/ kg) <lb/>HMF (mg/ kg) <lb/>Non-Leptospermum Honeys <lb/>AB1 <lb/>78.8 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>3.66 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>12 <lb/>AB2 <lb/>75.0 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>3.55 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>6 <lb/>BA1 <lb/>75.9 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>4.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>BA2 <lb/>76.4 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>3.59 <lb/>1 <lb/>25 <lb/>35 <lb/>BL1 <lb/>74.8 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>3.56 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>BL2 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>3.65 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>13 <lb/>FB1 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>FB2 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>3.80 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>11 <lb/>EU1 <lb/>77.4 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>3.84 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>EU2 <lb/>75.6 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>3.94 <lb/>14 <lb/>42 <lb/>18 <lb/>IB1 <lb/>75.7 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>3.75 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>IB2 <lb/>76.3 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>3.57 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>PB1 <lb/>76.8 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>PB2 <lb/>78.5 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.66 <lb/>81 <lb/>102 <lb/>4 <lb/>SB1 <lb/>78.7 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>11 <lb/>SB2 <lb/>79.0 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.63 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>19 <lb/>SJ1 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>14 <lb/>SJ2 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>3.61 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>41 <lb/>TT1 <lb/>73.8 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>4.05 <lb/>24 <lb/>31 <lb/>4 <lb/>TT2 <lb/>74.8 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>3.97 <lb/>68 <lb/>129 <lb/>7 <lb/>YB1 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.74 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>9 <lb/>YB2 <lb/>78.6 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.71 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>MX1 <lb/>75.9 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>3.74 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>MX2 <lb/>77.8 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>101 <lb/>276 <lb/>5 <lb/>Leptospermum Honeys <lb/>CL1 <lb/>73.4 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>3.65 <lb/>167 <lb/>136 <lb/>23 <lb/>CL2 <lb/>78.8 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>3.73 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>24 <lb/>JB1 <lb/>73.9 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>191 <lb/>232 <lb/>12 <lb/>JB2 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>3.66 <lb/>805 <lb/>1386 <lb/>14 <lb/>LE1 <lb/>74.3 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>3.56 <lb/>479 <lb/>240 <lb/>15 <lb/>LE2 <lb/>72.8 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>3.62 <lb/>250 <lb/>190 <lb/>4 <lb/>Control Honeys <lb/>ART <lb/>78.1 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>4.23 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>JAR <lb/>83.1 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>4.08 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>28 <lb/>MAN <lb/>79.4 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>3.82 <lb/>657 <lb/>280 <lb/>68 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>present at very low average quantities were copper (0.936 μg/g), strontium (0.358 μg/g), bar-<lb/>ium (0.228 μg/g), nickel (0.106 μg/g), cobalt (0.009 μg/g), and cadmium (0.002 μg/g). Fig 6B <lb/>shows the distribution of values for each measured element in honey samples. Some such as <lb/>potassium and calcium show an even distribution of values, while others such as copper and <lb/>iron are present in most honeys at very low levels with only a few samples having large <lb/>amounts. This indicates that those elements might be more prevalent in the environment in <lb/>certain areas. Large quantities of a particular element in only one honey from a floral source <lb/>pair (for example, copper in JB1 and LE2 but not JB2 or LE1) indicate that these elements are <lb/>likely not naturally present in higher quantities in these particular plants but originate from <lb/>other environmental sources. The large quantities of several elements in commercial Jarrah <lb/>honey suggests that these may be more prevalent in the Western Australian environment <lb/>where Jarrah grows. <lb/>Fig 6. Elemental content of honey samples. (A) Heatmap showing the relative elemental content of honey samples using normalised measurements. <lb/>(B) Box plots showing the distribution of values for each measured element in honey samples. Dotted lines indicate the median value. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Correlations between the antimicrobial activity of non-Leptospermum <lb/>honey and its physical and chemical properties <lb/>A Spearman correlation matrix was generated to assess the strength and direction of associa-<lb/>tions between antimicrobial activity data and physical and chemical property data, separated <lb/>by TA and NPA (Fig 7A). A partial least squares (PLS) regression biplot was additionally gen-<lb/>erated for non-Leptospermum honeys using antimicrobial activity data as the outcome vari-<lb/>ables and physical and chemical property data as the explanatory variables in order to visualise <lb/>the relationship between honey activity and other measured properties (Fig 7B). Variables <lb/>towards the outer edges of the plot indicate a strong contribution to the model, while variables <lb/>towards the centre indicate a weak contribution. Variables close together are positively corre-<lb/>lated to each other and negatively correlated to those far away and opposite them. MIC values <lb/>have been reversed for both analyses so that positive correlations indicate properties that align <lb/>with increased antimicrobial activity. Average TA and Average NPA (S1 Table) were calcu-<lb/>lated by taking the average of the reversed MIC values for S. aureus, E. faecalis, P. aeruginosa, <lb/>and C. deuterogattii for each honey sample. Correlations between MIC values for each individ-<lb/>ual species and average TA or NPA MIC values found them to be in strong alignment and thus <lb/>the average values were considered a good representation of the overall antimicrobial activity <lb/>of honey samples (data not shown). <lb/>All measures of H 2 O 2 were significantly positively correlated with TA measured via the <lb/>phenol equivalence assay (p�0.05), and TA measured via the MIC assay against S. aureus, P. <lb/>aeruginosa, and C. deuterogattii (p�0.05), but not E. faecalis, suggesting this organism is less <lb/>susceptible to H 2 O 2 . This is further seen on the biplot with S. aureus, P. aeruginosa, and C. deu-<lb/>terogattii TA clustering close to measures of H 2 O 2 production while E. faecalis TA is further <lb/>away. Other physical and chemical variables significantly correlated with antimicrobial activity <lb/>against at least two organisms via MIC were phenolics via FC and antioxidants via DPPH, <lb/>which were positively correlated (p�0.05), and water activity, which was negatively correlated <lb/>(p�0.05). No variables other than H 2 O 2 were significantly correlated with phenol equivalence <lb/>TA, indicating that it is less sensitive than the MIC assay at picking up the antimicrobial con-<lb/>tributions of other components measured in this study. For average MIC TA, all measures of <lb/>H 2 O 2 (p�0.05), as well as antioxidants via DPPH (p�0.05) were significantly correlated. <lb/>Considering NPA, MGO and DHA were significantly positively correlated (p�0.01) for all <lb/>organisms using phenol equivalence and MIC assessments. Other physical and chemical vari-<lb/>ables significantly correlated with antimicrobial activity against at least two organisms assessed <lb/>via MIC were phenolics assessed via FC and FBBB (p�0.05) and colour assessed via Pfund <lb/>Eye, mAU and CIELAB (p�0.05) which were all positively correlated. Although antioxidants <lb/>assessed via DDPH was significantly correlated with several measures of TA, it was not signifi-<lb/>cantly correlated with NPA for any organism except E. faecalis. On the biplot, E. faecalis NPA <lb/>clusters closely with measures of phenolics, antioxidants, and colour indicating that this organ-<lb/>ism is more sensitive to phenolic and antioxidant compounds. C. deuterogattii NPA appears <lb/>close to the centre of the plot indicating an overall weak contribution to the model. A signifi-<lb/>cant positive correlation was seen between C. deuterogattii NPA and HMF content (p�0.05), <lb/>however whether this is a causal relationship requires further investigation. <lb/>Linear and multiple linear regressions were used to determine which physical and chemical <lb/>properties are predictive for antimicrobial activity assessed using the phenol equivalence assay <lb/>(S. aureus only) or MIC (averaged across the four microorganisms) (Fig 8). Linear regressions <lb/>use a single independent variable, while multiple linear regression uses two or more indepen-<lb/>dent variables, to predict the outcome of a dependent variable. The actual and predicted <lb/>dependent variable values can then be compared to determine the goodness of fit and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 7. Correlations between antimicrobial activity and the physical and chemical properties of honey samples. (A) Spearman correlation <lb/>matrix showing how closely and in what direction antimicrobial activity (horizontal) aligns with physical and chemical properties (vertical). MIC <lb/>values have been reversed so that positive correlations indicate properties that align with increased antimicrobial activity. Sperman&apos;s rho values are <lb/>shown in the boxes with 1 indicating the strongest positive correlation and -1 indicating the strongest negative correlation. Statistically significant <lb/>correlations are shaded in yellow with the corresponding significance level indicated on the legend to the right. (B) Partial least squares (PLS) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>significance of the model. These models necessitate a linear relationship and are therefore <lb/>more stringent than Spearman correlations but provide a simpler and more predictive rela-<lb/>tionship. For Leptospermum honeys, MGO content correlated well with TA assessed by phenol <lb/>equivalence (R 2 = 0.81; p = 0.014) as expected, but not with average TA assessed by MIC (R 2 = <lb/>0.32; p = ns). <lb/>For non-Leptospermum honeys, H 2 O 2 production correlated poorly with TA assessed by <lb/>phenol equivalence and was not significant (R 2 = 0.13; p = ns), while the correlation with aver-<lb/>age TA assessed by MIC was still poor but reached significance (R 2 = 0.25; p = 0.016). Consid-<lb/>ering multiple factors for each individual species yielded much improved correlations with the <lb/>best combination of factors being different for each organism. For S. aureus, the best model <lb/>used H 2 O 2 , phenolics (FC), and antioxidants (DPPH) (R 2 = 0.47; p = 0.006), while for E. faeca-<lb/>lis it used H 2 O 2 , phenolics (FBBB), and antioxidants (DPPH) (R 2 = 0.41; p = 0.005) and for P. <lb/>aeruginosa it used H 2 O 2 , water activity, and antioxidants (DPPH) (R 2 = 0.60; p = &lt;0.001). <lb/>While H 2 O 2 itself was not directly correlated with antimicrobial activity against E. faecalis, it&apos;s <lb/>Fig 8. Linear regressions showing physical and chemical properties that have predictive power for antimicrobial activity. (A) For Leptospermum <lb/>honeys, methylglyoxal (MGO) correlates well with total activity assessed by phenol equivalence assay (PE), but not with MIC averaged across the 4 <lb/>species tested (Average MIC). (B) For non-Leptospermum honeys, total H 2 O 2 production (area under curve measured by HRP assay) correlates poorly <lb/>with TA assessed by phenol equivalence or average MIC. (C) Including multiple variables in the regressions substantially improves correlations for <lb/>individual species. Models that are significantly predictive of antimicrobial activity were able to be identified for the bacterial species S. aureus, E. faecalis, <lb/>and P. aeruginosa, but not for the fungal species C. deuterogattii. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g008 <lb/>regression biplot for non-Leptospermum honeys showing the relationships among all variables measured in this study and giving information <lb/>about dataset structure. PLS regression was performed using antimicrobial activity as the outcome variable, and the physical and chemical <lb/>properties of honey samples as the explanatory variables. Variables towards the outer edge of the plot indicate a strong contribution to the model, <lb/>while variables towards the centre indicate a weak contribution. Variables close together are positively correlated to each other and negatively <lb/>correlated to those further away and in opposite quadrants. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>inclusion alongside phenolics and antioxidants improved the strength of the multivariable <lb/>model, suggesting that these components may operate together synergistically. The best model <lb/>for fungal species C. deuterogattii used H 2 O 2 and water activity but was poor and did not <lb/>reach significance (R 2 = 0.19; p = ns), suggesting that there may be significant contributing <lb/>antifungal factors that have not been measured in the current study. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study set out to address key challenges to assessing the medicinal potential of honey that <lb/>limit development by the honey industry and impede clinical adoption. Our objectives were to <lb/>investigate the long-term shelf life of honey, to elucidate key factors influencing the antimicro-<lb/>bial activity of honey, and to give the honey industry practical ways to assess these. We profiled <lb/>the antimicrobial properties of a diverse collection of Australian honeys from the New South <lb/>Wales region, evaluating the effects of long-term storage on activity and analysing how various <lb/>physical and chemical traits align with antimicrobial activity against distinct microbes. <lb/>Factors useful for predicting antimicrobial activity <lb/>We utilised linear regression models to ascertain the predictive capacity of various chemical <lb/>and physical properties on antimicrobial activity. For Leptospermum honeys, our models rein-<lb/>force the established use of MGO as a key predictor of antimicrobial activity measured via the <lb/>phenol equivalence assay (R 2 = 0.81) [16]. A poor correlation was seen between MGO and <lb/>activity measured via the MIC assay, but due to the small sample size of Leptospermum honeys <lb/>it is difficult to tell whether this was due to outliers, or whether the MIC assay is more sensitive <lb/>to non-MGO based activity. Further analysis with more Leptospermum samples is required to <lb/>determine whether MGO is predictive for activity measured via the MIC assay. Non-Leptosper-<lb/>mum honeys showcased a more intricate interplay among variables, where combining various <lb/>factors including H 2 O 2 production, antioxidant content, and water activity markedly <lb/>improved predictive capabilities (R 2 = 0.41-0.60) for antibacterial activity compared to consid-<lb/>ering H 2 O 2 alone (R 2 = 0.25) but was still unable to reach very high confidence. These findings <lb/>underscore the multifaceted nature of honey bioactivity, emphasising the need for comprehen-<lb/>sive models incorporating diverse chemical constituents. In future studies, exploring potential <lb/>synergistic interactions among chemical components combined with further validation across <lb/>diverse honey samples, may enable more nuanced predictive models. However, even if these <lb/>models become substantially more robust, the high potential for significant deviation in <lb/>unique samples coupled with the need to accurately measure multiple properties suggests that <lb/>a direct measurement of antimicrobial activity will remain the superior strategy for industry in <lb/>terms of both accuracy and simplicity. <lb/>Correlations between antimicrobial activity and specific physical or <lb/>chemical properties <lb/>In our investigation of the relationship between the various physical and chemical properties <lb/>and antimicrobial activity, we found several significant correlations. H 2 O 2 production was sig-<lb/>nificantly correlated with TA against S. aureus, P. aeruginosa, and C. deuterogattii. This was <lb/>expected since H 2 O 2 is the main contributor to the antimicrobial activity of most non-Leptos-<lb/>permum honeys and these microbes have all previously been reported to be susceptible to <lb/>honey [5, 8]. Activity against E. faecalis, however, correlated with increased phenolics content, <lb/>antioxidant capacity, and honey colour but not with H 2 O 2 production. Phenolic compounds <lb/>and antioxidants are known to contribute to the antimicrobial activity of honey, interacting <lb/>with bacterial membranes and enzymes to disrupt their function and cause cell death [29]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Darker honey colour can indicate an increased presence of phenolic compounds and other <lb/>phytochemicals [30]. The clustering of measures of honey colour, phenolic and antioxidant <lb/>compounds, and MGO and DHA in Fig 7B indicates that these parameters are indeed corre-<lb/>lated in our samples. E. faecalis has a higher level of resistance to oxidative stress than other <lb/>bacteria [31], due to its ability to produce several detoxifying enzymes that can break down <lb/>reactive oxygen species. It has also been identified as a pathogen in honey bee hives [32], acting <lb/>as a secondary invader during outbreaks of European Foulbrood and resistance to H 2 O 2 -medi-<lb/>ated activity could explain its ability to opportunistically invade weakened colonies where <lb/>H 2 O 2 production provides a significant level of defence. Increased phenolics and/or antioxi-<lb/>dant content also correlated with TA and NPA against S. aureus and P. aeruginosa, suggesting <lb/>that antioxidant compounds contribute to the effects of honey against these organisms. Anti-<lb/>oxidants measured via DPPH correlated significantly with TA for S. aureus, P. aeruginosa, and <lb/>E. faecalis, and with NPA for E. faecalis alone. This suggests that E. faecalis is somewhat suscep-<lb/>tible to these antioxidant compounds on their own, while the other organisms require addi-<lb/>tional weakening from H 2 O 2 for the antioxidant compounds to be effective. <lb/>Water activity was found to be significantly correlated with the TA of P. aeruginosa and C. <lb/>deuterogattii, with decreased water activity correlating with increased honey activity. Water <lb/>activity is an important factor that affects the antimicrobial activity of undiluted honey, with a <lb/>low water activity inhibiting microbial proliferation by making water required for their growth <lb/>unavailable [33]. <lb/>However, as honey is diluted to at least 32% (w/w) in the MIC assay it is unlikely that water <lb/>activity directly contributes to its antimicrobial properties. Instead, it likely serves as an indica-<lb/>tor for other factors that may alter antimicrobial activity. Water activity decreases with the <lb/>increased bee processing, which could result in higher levels of bee enzymes and antimicrobial <lb/>peptides. Differences in nectar sources can also affect water activity, and these may introduce <lb/>other antimicrobial features. Remaining physical and chemical properties that were measured, <lb/>including pH, sugar content, and elemental content were not significantly correlated with <lb/>activity. Elemental content could theoretically influence antimicrobial properties as certain ele-<lb/>ments are vital cofactors for enzymes that synthesise phytochemicals and antioxidants [34] <lb/>and metals such as iron and copper can also enhance H 2 O 2 -based killing via Fenton reactions <lb/>[35]. However, the diverse actions of these elements and the varied floral sources of the sam-<lb/>ples in the current study, each with unique phytochemical constituents, likely hindered the <lb/>identification of specific elemental effects. To gain a more comprehensive understanding, <lb/>future studies could employ manipulative experiments involving the addition of specific ele-<lb/>ments to individual honey samples, facilitating a more nuanced exploration of their potential <lb/>contributions to antimicrobial activity. <lb/>Recommended methods for assaying honey properties <lb/>An evaluation of the pros and cons of methods trialled in this study are presented in Table 3. <lb/>Looking at antimicrobial activity, we found a significant but weak correlation between phenol <lb/>equivalence and MIC results, similar to previous work that specifically set out to compare the <lb/>two methods [15], and to a study comparing general agar diffusion and broth dilution methods <lb/>for assessing honey activity [36]. Although it is the current Australian honey industry standard, <lb/>the phenol equivalence assay has several significant drawbacks including difficulty interpreting <lb/>the results, variability between laboratories, and the use of the toxic chemical phenol [14, 15]. In <lb/>addition, the water-based agar matrix may prevent large or polar molecules from diffusing <lb/>freely, which could confound interpretation in honey samples where these contribute to activity <lb/>[13]. This may explain why we saw correlations between phenolics, antioxidants and TA via <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>MIC, but not via phenol equivalence, as the free diffusion of these compounds through the agar <lb/>matrix may be hindered. This may also explain why the range of activity was much wider when <lb/>assessed via MIC than via phenol equivalence, and why NPA was identified in some honeys by <lb/>MIC but not by phenol equivalence. The MIC assay can be readily applied to a wide variety of <lb/>microbes including bacteria, yeasts, and moulds, and is the gold standard for antimicrobial sus-<lb/>ceptibility testing [21, 22]. Although honey activity is strongly correlated across diverse organ-<lb/>isms, certain species such as E. faecalis and C. deuterogattii, exhibit distinct susceptibility and <lb/>the MIC assay can capture these nuances when in-depth analyses are desired. Overall, we argue <lb/>that the MIC assay is a superior method for testing the antimicrobial activity of honey and <lb/>where possible should replace the phenol equivalence assay as the industry standard. <lb/>Measuring H 2 O 2 production in honey using the HRP assay, we found a strong alignment <lb/>between H 2 O 2 produced at 2 hours, maximum H 2 O 2 concentration reached, and total H 2 O 2 <lb/>produced. We additionally saw strong correlations between H 2 O 2 concentration at 2 hours <lb/>measured using three independent methods. A major difficulty when screening honey samples <lb/>for H 2 O 2 is the need to conduct an entire time course assay in order to identify the timepoint <lb/>where H 2 O 2 production peaks. Our results suggest that the 2-hour time point would provide a <lb/>reliable indication of H 2 O 2 production without the need for a full assay, and this can be mea-<lb/>sured using either simple strip tests or more specific colourimetric assays, depending on the <lb/>level of granularity desired. However, a caveat is that there can be outliers, such as honey sam-<lb/>ple SJ1, where H 2 O 2 curves can occur over a much longer time frame [20]. <lb/>Table 3. Evaluation of methods for assessing honey properties. <lb/>Method <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>Difficulty <lb/>Safety <lb/>Comments <lb/>Antimicrobial Activity <lb/>Phenol Equivalence <lb/>Fair-but underestimates non-<lb/>peroxide factors in non-<lb/>Leptospermum honeys <lb/>High <lb/>Hazardous chemical-phenol; <lb/>requires PC2 facilities for S. <lb/>aureus <lb/>Only performed with the bacterial pathogen S. aureus <lb/>Minimum Inhibitory <lb/>Concentration * <lb/>Good <lb/>Medium Safe; requires PC2 facilities for <lb/>microbial pathogens <lb/>Can readily be applied to a wide variety of microbes <lb/>including bacteria, yeasts, and moulds <lb/>Hydrogen Peroxide <lb/>HRP * <lb/>Good <lb/>High <lb/>Hazardous chemical-6M <lb/>H 2 SO 4 <lb/>Cheap for bulk samples, expensive for few samples <lb/>ADHP * <lb/>Good <lb/>Medium Safe <lb/>Cheap for bulk samples, expensive for few samples <lb/>Strip Test * <lb/>Good <lb/>Low <lb/>Safe <lb/>Cheap for few samples, expensive for bulk samples <lb/>Phenolics <lb/>FC <lb/>Fair-but affected by non-phenolic <lb/>reducing compounds <lb/>Low <lb/>Safe <lb/>May have utility for comparing multiple samples, but <lb/>should not be used to determine absolute values <lb/>FBBB * <lb/>Good <lb/>Medium Safe <lb/>More accurate than FC for determining absolute values <lb/>Antioxidants <lb/>FRAP <lb/>Good <lb/>Medium Safe <lb/>Produces results in alignment with DPPH <lb/>DPPH * <lb/>Good <lb/>Medium Hazardous chemical-DPPH <lb/>Produces results in alignment with FRAP but is more <lb/>strongly associated with antimicrobial activity <lb/>Colour by Spectrophotometer <lb/>Pfund <lb/>Poor-vulnerable to turbidity and <lb/>crystallisation <lb/>Low <lb/>Safe <lb/>Very inaccurate, should be avoided <lb/>mAU * <lb/>Good <lb/>Low <lb/>Safe <lb/>Gives the best correlation with colour assessed visually <lb/>CIELAB <lb/>Poor-saturated at lower wavelengths Medium Safe <lb/>May have utility when in-depth comparison across the <lb/>colour spectrum is desired and honeys can be diluted <lb/>to avoid saturation <lb/>* Recommended method <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Evaluating phenolics content and antioxidant content, we used simple colorimetric assays <lb/>that provided an easy and rapid approximation of these properties. For phenolics content, our <lb/>results indicate that the FBBB assay is superior to the FC assay as it is less affected by non-phe-<lb/>nolic compounds. While the FC assay is used widely as a measure of total phenolics content <lb/>due to its simplicity, it is known to be affected by reducing compounds including those present <lb/>in honey such as sugars and amino acids [37]. Indeed, we saw that results from the FC assay <lb/>were universally higher than those from FBBB assay, which is based on a direct reaction with <lb/>active hydroxyl groups in phenolic compounds. The FC assay may have utility for comparing <lb/>multiple honey samples but should not be used for determining absolute values. For antioxi-<lb/>dant content, the DPPH and FRAP assays were in strong alignment with each other though <lb/>the DPPH assay was more strongly associated with antimicrobial activity, suggesting that it <lb/>may be picking up the activity of a distinct set of compounds. Therefore, while either assay is <lb/>suitable for determining the antioxidant activity of honey samples, the DPPH assay may pro-<lb/>vide slightly more in-depth information. <lb/>Finally, when evaluating honey colour, poor correlations were found between Pfund value <lb/>assessed visually and assessed spectrophotometrically using the White and CIELAB methods. <lb/>The White method relies on only a single absorbance value taken at 635 nm, making it particu-<lb/>larly vulnerable to turbidity caused by the growth of microbes or incompletely dissolved sugar <lb/>crystals. The CIELAB method uses a wave scan from 280-780 nm, but we found honey absor-<lb/>bance values at the low-end wavelengths were often saturated far past the range of accuracy. <lb/>Colour intensity measured in mAU, which uses two absorbance values taken at 450 and <lb/>720nm, gave a much better correlation with colour assessed visually. The accuracy of this <lb/>method combined with its simplicity makes it the most efficient method for assessing honey <lb/>colour via spectrophotometer. <lb/>Changes in the antimicrobial activity of honey over time <lb/>The majority of initially active honey samples retained some level of activity after 15+ years of <lb/>storage at 4 ˚C in the dark, with non-Leptospermum honeys experiencing an average of 64% <lb/>decrease in TA and Leptospermum honeys experiencing an average decrease of 31% in NPA. <lb/>The strong correlations found between the 2005-2007 and 2022 data indicate that TA and <lb/>NPA declined at a relatively consistent rate across samples. This suggests that, after accounting <lb/>for activity type, storage conditions are the biggest determinant of activity decline rather than <lb/>chemical differences in the individual samples. <lb/>Relatively few studies have directly compared the antimicrobial activity of honey samples <lb/>over long periods of time, however a general decline in activity despite storage conditions is <lb/>consistently noted. Looking at 10 samples of non-Leptospermum Australian honey from the <lb/>same original survey as the current study, Irish et al. [12] reported an average decline of 23% <lb/>after 8-22 months storage in the dark at 4 ˚C, and a follow-up study on a subset of 15 samples <lb/>found an average decline of 30% after 11-12 years storage in the dark at 4 ˚C [20]. This <lb/>decrease in activity over time is thought to be due to a combination of factors including expo-<lb/>sure to light, heat, and air, which can all cause chemical changes and a breakdown of active <lb/>components [9]. Various studies have found phenolics and antioxidant content can decrease <lb/>from 17-92% following up to one year of storage under various conditions, along with signifi-<lb/>cant changes to pH, free acidity, moisture content, HMF content and honey colour [38-40]. <lb/>Leptospermum honeys are unique in that their active component is methylglyoxal (MGO), <lb/>which is produced from the conversion of dihydroxyacetone (DHA) naturally found in Leptos-<lb/>permum nectar [41]. This chemical conversion takes place over time during the maturation of <lb/>honey and can therefore lead to an increase in antimicrobial activity over time. This was <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>previously observed by Irish et al. [12] in Leptospermum samples stored at 25 ˚C for 8-22 <lb/>months, with some increasing in NPA by up to 37% and others decreasing by up to 16%. In <lb/>the current study, a decrease in activity was observed for most of the Leptospermum honeys <lb/>and we found that several still contained a considerable amount of DHA, likely due to low <lb/>temperature storage slowing or halting the conversion to MGO. Furthermore, while MGO is <lb/>thought to be relatively insensitive to light and heat, it can react with oxygen over time to form <lb/>other compounds [42], which would lead to a decrease in antimicrobial activity, though this <lb/>would likely only apply to compounds on the surface. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Our study offers recommendations for the assessment of medicinal honey and provides fur-<lb/>ther evidence of the complex interplay between different properties of honey and its antimi-<lb/>crobial activity against various microorganisms. While MGO is a reliable predictor of activity <lb/>in Leptospermum honeys, the variability inherent in non-Leptospermum honeys limits the <lb/>development of models with predictive capabilities, and a direct assessment of antimicrobial <lb/>activity is still required to determine medicinal potential. We recommend use of the MIC <lb/>method to capture the full range of activity and to enable testing across diverse microbial path-<lb/>ogens. Furthermore, our study highlights the remarkable resilience of honey&apos;s antimicrobial <lb/>properties, as evidenced by the retention of activity even after more than 15 years of storage. <lb/>This longevity underscores the therapeutic potential of honey to offer a natural and sustainable <lb/>alternative for combatting microbial infections. However, its potential to support microbial <lb/>growth and degradation highlights the importance of proper storage and handling to maintain <lb/>its quality and optimal activity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. All data collected in this study. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors would like to thank Daniel Susantio and Bridie Stanfield for technical assistance, <lb/>Dr Nicholas Proschogo (School of Chemistry, University of Sydney) for valuable advice on <lb/>sample digestion and for performing the ICP-MS measurements, and the authors of [12] as <lb/>well as the beekeepers who provided the original samples. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Data curation: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Formal analysis: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Nural N. Cokcetin, Dee A. Carter. <lb/>Investigation: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Methodology: Kenya E. Fernandes, Andrew Z. Dong, Aviva Levina, Nural N. Cokcetin, Peter <lb/>Brooks. <lb/>Project administration: Nural N. Cokcetin. <lb/>Resources: Dee A. Carter. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Supervision: Dee A. Carter. <lb/>Visualization: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Kenya E. Fernandes. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kenya E. Fernandes, Andrew Z. Dong, Aviva Levina, Nural N. <lb/>Cokcetin, Peter Brooks, Dee A. Carter. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kelly F, McMillan S, Spinks J, Bettington E, Wheeler AJ. &quot;You don&apos;t throw these things out:&quot; an explora-<lb/>tion of medicines retention and disposal practices in Australian homes. BMC Public Health. 2018; 18. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-018-5753-6 PMID: 30119656 <lb/>2. Wilkinson JL, Boxall ABA, Kolpin DW, Leung KMY, Lai RWS, Galba ´n-Malago ´n C, et al. Pharmaceutical <lb/>pollution of the world&apos;s rivers. PNAS. 2022; 119: e2113947119. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>2113947119 PMID: 35165193 <lb/>3. Llor C, Bjerrum L. Antimicrobial resistance: Risk associated with antibiotic overuse and initiatives to <lb/>reduce the problem. Ther Adv Drug Saf. 2014. pp. 229-241. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>2042098614554919 PMID: 25436105 <lb/>4. Cooper RA, Jenkins L, Henriques AFM, Duggan RS, Burton NF. Absence of bacterial resistance to <lb/>medical-grade manuka honey. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2010; 29: 1237-1241. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s10096-010-0992-1 PMID: 20549529 <lb/>5. Blair SE, Cokcetin NN, Harry EJ, Carter DA. The unusual antibacterial activity of medical-grade Leptos-<lb/>permum honey: Antibacterial spectrum, resistance and transcriptome analysis. Eur J Clin Microbiol <lb/>Infect Dis. 2009; 28: 1199-1208. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10096-009-0763-z PMID: 19513768 <lb/>6. Darby WJ. Food: the gift of Osiris. William J., Ghalioungui P, Grivetti L, editors. Academic Press; 1977. <lb/>7. Machado De-Melo AA, de Almeida-Muradian LB, Sancho MT, Pascual-Mate ´A. Composition and prop-<lb/>erties of Apis mellifera honey: A review. J Apic Res. Taylor and Francis Ltd; 2018. pp. 5-37. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1080/00218839.2017.1338444 <lb/>8. Fernandes KE, Stanfield B, Frost EA, Shanahan ER, Susantio D, Dong AZ, et al. Low levels of hive <lb/>stress are associated with decreased honey activity and changes to the gut microbiome of resident <lb/>honey bees. Microb Spectr. 2023; 11: e00742-23. <lb/>9. Bogdanov S, Jurendic T, Sieber R, Gallmann P. Honey for nutrition and health: A review. J Am Coll <lb/>Nutr. 2008; 27: 677-689. https://doi.org/10.1080/07315724.2008.10719745 PMID: 19155427 <lb/>10. Missio da Silva P, Gonzaga LV, Biluca FC, Schulz M, Vitali L, Micke GA, et al. Stability of Brazilian Apis <lb/>mellifera L. honey during prolonged storage: Physicochemical parameters and bioactive compounds. <lb/>LWT. 2020; 129. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109521 <lb/>11. Brudzynski K, Kim L. Storage-induced chemical changes in active components of honey de-regulate its <lb/>antibacterial activity. Food Chem. 2011; 126: 1155-1163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.11. <lb/>151 <lb/>12. Irish J, Blair S, Carter DA. The antibacterial activity of honey derived from Australian flora. PLoS One. <lb/>2011; 6. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0018229 PMID: 21464891 <lb/>13. Hossain ML, Lim LY, Hammer K, Hettiarachchi D, Locher C. A review of commonly used methodologies <lb/>for assessing the antibacterial activity of honey and honey products. Antibiotics. MDPI; 2022. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics11070975 PMID: 35884229 <lb/>14. Molan P. Improvements to the UMF Assay. New Zealand Beekeepers. 2008; 16: 24-25. <lb/>15. Green KJ, Dods K, Hammer KA. Development and validation of a new microplate assay that utilises <lb/>optical density to quantify the antibacterial activity of honeys including Jarrah, Marri and Manuka. PLoS <lb/>One. 2020; 15. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0243246 PMID: 33296391 <lb/>16. Cokcetin NN, Pappalardo M, Campbell LT, Brooks P, Carter DA, Blair SE, et al. The antibacterial activ-<lb/>ity of Australian Leptospermum honey correlates with methylglyoxal levels. PLoS One. 2016; 11. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0167780 PMID: 28030589 <lb/>17. Lehmann DM, Krishnakumar K, Batres MA, Hakola-Parry A, Cokcetin N, Harry E, et al. A cost-effective <lb/>colourimetric assay for quantifying hydrogen peroxide in honey. Access Microbiol. 2019; 1. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1099/acmi.0.000065 PMID: 32974499 <lb/>18. Brudzynski K, Abubaker K, St-Martin L, Castle A. Re-examining the role of hydrogen peroxide in bacte-<lb/>riostatic and bactericidal activities of honey. Front Microbiol. 2011; 2: 213. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb. <lb/>2011.00213 PMID: 22046173 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. Brudzynski K. A current perspective on hydrogen peroxide production in honey. A review. Food Chem. <lb/>Elsevier Ltd; 2020. p. 127229. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2020.127229 PMID: 32688187 <lb/>20. Guttentag A, Krishnakumar K, Cokcetin N, Harry E, Carter D. Factors affecting the production and mea-<lb/>surement of hydrogen peroxide in honey samples. Access Microbiol. 2021; 3. https://doi.org/10.1099/ <lb/>acmi.0.000198 PMID: 34151153 <lb/>21. Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI). Antifungal susceptibility testing of bacteria that grow <lb/>aerobically M07-A9. 2012. <lb/>22. Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI). Antifungal susceptibility testing of yeasts M27-A3. <lb/>Wayne, PA: Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute; 2008. <lb/>23. Medina MB. Simple and rapid method for the analysis of phenolic compounds in beverages and grains. <lb/>J Agric Food Chem. 2011; 59: 1565-1571. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf103711c PMID: 21309564 <lb/>24. White JW, Beaty MR, Eaton WG, Hart B, Huser W, Killion E, et al. Instrumental color classification of <lb/>honey: Collaborative study. J AOAC Int. 1984; 67: 1129-1131. https://doi.org/10.1093/jaoac/67.6.1129 <lb/>25. Bodor Z, Benedek C, Urbin A ´, Szabo ´D, Sipos L. Colour of honey: can we trust the Pfund scale?-An <lb/>alternative graphical tool covering the whole visible spectra. LWT. 2021; 149: 111859. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111859 <lb/>26. Pappalardo M, Pappalardo L, Brooks P. Rapid and Reliable HPLC method for the simultaneous deter-<lb/>mination of dihydroxyacetone, methylglyoxal and 5-hydroxymethylfurfural in leptospermum honeys. <lb/>PLoS One. 2016; 11. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0167006 PMID: 27861622 <lb/>27. Devillers J, Dore ´JC, Marenco M, Poirier-Duchêne F, Galand N, Viel C. Chemometrical analysis of 18 <lb/>metallic and nonmetallic elements found in honeys sold in France. J Agric Food Chem. 2002; 50: 5998-<lb/>6007. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf020497r PMID: 12358472 <lb/>28. Chakraborti D, Das D, Chatterjee A, Jin Z, Jiang SG. Direct determination of some heavy metals in <lb/>urban air particulates by electrothermal atomic absorption spectrometry using zeeman background cor-<lb/>rection after simple acid decomposition. Part IV: Application to Calcutta air particulates. Environmental <lb/>Technology (United Kingdom). 1992; 13: 95-100. https://doi.org/10.1080/09593339209385133 <lb/>29. Nolan VC, Harrison J, Cox JAG. Dissecting the antimicrobial composition of honey. Antibiotics. MDPI <lb/>AG; 2019. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics8040251 PMID: 31817375 <lb/>30. Estevinho L, Pereira AP, Moreira L, Dias LG, Pereira E. Antioxidant and antimicrobial effects of phenolic <lb/>compounds extracts of Northeast Portugal honey. FCT. 2008; 46: 3774-3779. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>fct.2008.09.062 PMID: 18940227 <lb/>31. Baureder M, Reimann R, Hederstedt L. Contribution of catalase to hydrogen peroxide resistance in <lb/>Enterococcus faecalis. FEMS Microbiol Lett. 2012; 331: 160-164. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6968. <lb/>2012.02567.x PMID: 22486165 <lb/>32. Forsgren E. European foulbrood in honey bees. J Invertebr Pathol. 2010; 103: S5-S9. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.jip.2009.06.016 PMID: 20105559 <lb/>33. Fernandes KE, Frost EA, Remnant EJ, Schell KR, Cokcetin NN, Carter DA. The role of honey in the <lb/>ecology of the hive: Nutrition, detoxification, longevity, and protection against hive pathogens. Front <lb/>Nutr. 2022; 9: 954170. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.954170 PMID: 35958247 <lb/>34. Cannas D, Loi E, Serra M, Firinu D, Valera P, Zavattari P. Relevance of essential trace elements in <lb/>nutrition and drinking water for human health and autoimmune disease risk. Nutrients. 2020; 12: 1-22. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12072074 PMID: 32668647 <lb/>35. Brudzynski K, Lannigan R. Mechanism of honey bacteriostatic action against MRSA and VRE involves <lb/>hydroxyl radicals generated from honey&apos;s hydrogen peroxide. Front Microbiol. 2012; 3. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.3389/fmicb.2012.00036 PMID: 22347223 <lb/>36. Ose ´s SM, Pascual-Mate ´A, de la Fuente D, de Pablo A, Ferna ´ndez-Muiño MA, Sancho MT. Compari-<lb/>son of methods to determine antibacterial activity of honeys against Staphylococcus aureus. NJAS-<lb/>Wagen J Life Sc. 2016; 78: 29-33. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.njas.2015.12.005 <lb/>37. Lawag IL, Nolden ES, Schaper AAM, Lim LY, Locher C. A modified Folin-Ciocalteu assay for the deter-<lb/>mination of total phenolics content in honey. Appl Sci. 2023; 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/app13042135 <lb/>38. Saric G, Markovic K, Major N, Krpan M, Ursulin-Trstenjak N, Hruskar M, et al. Changes of antioxidant <lb/>activity and phenolic content in acacia and multifloral honey during storage. Food Technol Biotechnol. <lb/>2012; 50: 434-441. <lb/>39. Wang XH, Gheldof N, Engeseth NJ. Effect of processing and storage on antioxidant capacity of honey. <lb/>J Food Sci. 2004; 69: 96-f101. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.2004.tb15509.x <lb/>40. Zarei M, Fazlara A, Alijani N. Evaluation of the changes in physicochemical and antioxidant properties <lb/>of honey during storage. Funct Foods Health Dis. 2019; 9: 593-605. https://doi.org/10.31989/ffhd.v9i9. <lb/>616 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>41. Adams CJ, Manley-Harris M, Molan PC. The origin of methylglyoxal in New Zealand manuka (Leptos-<lb/>permum scoparium) honey. Carbohydr Res. 2009; 344: 1050-1053. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carres. <lb/>2009.03.020 PMID: 19368902 <lb/>42. Mandal MD, Mandal S. Honey: Its medicinal property and antibacterial activity. Asian Pac J Trop <lb/>Biomed. 2011; 1: 154-160. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2221-1691(11)60016-6 PMID: 23569748 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Stability and factors predictive for antimicrobial activity in Australian honey <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0303095 May 22, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 / 27 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>