<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Regional estimates of gross primary production applying the Process-Based Model 3D-CMCC-FEM vs. Remote-Sensing multiple datasets</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>D.</forename>
          <surname>Dalmonech</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>E.</forename>
          <surname>Vangi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>M.</forename>
          <surname>Chiesi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>G.</forename>
          <surname>Chirici</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>L.</forename>
          <surname>Fibbi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>F.</forename>
          <surname>Giannetti</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>G.</forename>
          <surname>Marano</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>C.</forename>
          <surname>Massari</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>A.</forename>
          <surname>Nolè</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>J.</forename>
          <surname>Xiao</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>A.</forename>
          <surname>Collalti</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T14:20:33.612Z">11/12/2025 2:20:33 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1080$1$22797254.2023.2301657</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1080/22797254.2023.2301657</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>D. Dalmonech, E. Vangi, M. Chiesi, G. Chirici, L. Fibbi, F. Giannetti, G. Marano, C. Massari, A. Nolè, J. Xiao, A. Collalti. (2024). Regional estimates of gross primary production applying the Process-Based Model 3D-CMCC-FEM vs. Remote-Sensing multiple datasets. European Journal of Remote Sensing, 57(1), None. DOI: 10.1080/22797254.2023.2301657</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T14:20:26.317939Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T14:20:26.317939Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics <lb/>ISSN: 2164-5515 (Print) 2164-554X (Online) Journal homepage: www.tandfonline.com/journals/khvi20 <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout and its <lb/>associated factors among children who received <lb/>rotavirus vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African <lb/>countries: A multilevel analysis of the recent <lb/>demographic and health survey <lb/>Belayneh Shetie Workneh, Enyew Getaneh Mekonen, Alebachew Ferede <lb/>Zegeye, Almaz Tefera Gonete, Tewodros Getaneh Alemu, Tadesse Tarik <lb/>Tamir, Berhan Tekeba, Mulugeta Wassie, Alemneh Tadesse Kassie &amp; <lb/>Mohammed Seid Ali <lb/>To cite this article: Belayneh Shetie Workneh, Enyew Getaneh Mekonen, Alebachew Ferede <lb/>Zegeye, Almaz Tefera Gonete, Tewodros Getaneh Alemu, Tadesse Tarik Tamir, Berhan <lb/>Tekeba, Mulugeta Wassie, Alemneh Tadesse Kassie &amp; Mohammed Seid Ali (2024) Rotavirus <lb/>vaccine dose-two dropout and its associated factors among children who received rotavirus <lb/>vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African countries: A multilevel analysis of the recent <lb/>demographic and health survey, Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics, 20:1, 2335730, DOI: <lb/>10.1080/21645515.2024.2335730 <lb/>To link to this article: https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2024.2335730 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published with <lb/>license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC. <lb/>Published online: 04 Apr 2024. <lb/>Submit your article to this journal <lb/>Article views: 2191 <lb/>View related articles <lb/>View Crossmark data <lb/>Citing articles: 2 View citing articles <lb/>Full Terms &amp; Conditions of access and use can be found at <lb/>https://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?journalCode=khvi20 <lb/>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout and its associated factors among children who <lb/>received rotavirus vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African countries: A multilevel <lb/>analysis of the recent demographic and health survey <lb/>Belayneh Shetie Workneh a , Enyew Getaneh Mekonen b , Alebachew Ferede Zegeye c , Almaz Tefera Gonete d , <lb/>Tewodros Getaneh Alemu d , Tadesse Tarik Tamir d , Berhan Tekeba d , Mulugeta Wassie e , Alemneh Tadesse Kassie f , <lb/>and Mohammed Seid Ali d <lb/>a <lb/>Department of Emergency and Critical Care Nursing, School of Nursing, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, <lb/>Ethiopia; b Department of Surgical Nursing, School of Nursing, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia; <lb/>c Department of Medical Nursing, School of Nursing, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia; d Department of <lb/>Pediatrics and Child Health Nursing, School of Nursing, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia; e School of <lb/>Nursing, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia; f Department of Clinical Midwifery, School of Midwifery, <lb/>College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar, Gondar, Ethiopia <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Rotavirus is the most common cause of diarrhea in children worldwide. In 2016, rotavirus infection <lb/>resulted in 258 173 300 episodes of diarrhea and 128 500 child deaths in the globe. The study aimed to <lb/>assess the magnitude of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout and associated factors among children who <lb/>received rotavirus vaccine dose-one in sub-Saharan African countries. The appended and most recent <lb/>demographic and health survey (DHS) dataset of 17 sub-Saharan African countries was used for data <lb/>analysis. A total of 73,396 weighted samples were used. Factors associated with the outcome variable <lb/>were considered significant if their p-values were ≤ .05 in the multilevel mixed-effect logistic regression <lb/>model. The overall Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts was 10.77% (95% CI 10.55%, 11.00%), which <lb/>ranged from 2.77% in Rwanda to 37.67% in Uganda. Being younger, late birth order, having difficulty <lb/>accessing health facilities, having no media exposure, having no work, having home delivery, having no <lb/>antenatal follow-up, and having no postnatal checkup were factors significantly associated with the <lb/>outcome variable. The overall Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout was higher in sub-Saharan African <lb/>countries which implies that vaccine dropout is still a great issue in the region. Special attention should <lb/>be given to those mothers who are young, who have no work, who give birth at home, who experienced <lb/>difficulty in accessing health facilities, and late birth orders. Furthermore, targeted interventions should <lb/>be considered for improving access and utilization of media, antenatal care, and postnatal care services. <lb/>ARTICLE HISTORY <lb/>Received 19 January 2024 <lb/>Revised 11 March 2024 <lb/>Accepted 25 March 2024 <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Africa; dropout; Sub-Saharan; <lb/>vaccine; Rotavirus; children <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Diarrhea is a major public health problem and the second <lb/>leading cause of mortality in children. 1 Based on recent <lb/>evidence, 2 billion diarrheal diseases and 1.9 million deaths <lb/>were reported among children under the age of five years <lb/>every year globally. 2 Rotavirus is the most common cause <lb/>of diarrhea in children worldwide. 3,4 If rotavirus-induced <lb/>diarrhea is left untreated can result in severe watery diar-<lb/>rhea, vomiting, fever, severe dehydration, and <lb/>hospitalization. 5,6 In 2016, rotavirus infection resulted in <lb/>258 173 300 episodes of diarrhea and 128 500 deaths <lb/>around the globe. 7 The majority (90%) of hospitalizations <lb/>and deaths caused by rotavirus in young children occur in <lb/>low-income nations in Asia and Africa, particularly in the <lb/>sub-Saharan region. Low-income or marginalized commu-<lb/>nities, as well as areas with limited access to safe water, <lb/>sanitation, and health care, are excessively affected by diar-<lb/>rheal diseases. 8 <lb/>One of the most efficient public health initiatives to lower <lb/>childhood morbidity and mortality is childhood vaccination. 9 <lb/>More than 28,000 deaths among children are thought to have <lb/>been prevented by vaccination, especially in sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa, about 20% of all deaths related to diarrhea can be <lb/>prevented. 7 Good personal hygiene like cleanliness and hand <lb/>washing are important but are not sufficient to prevent the <lb/>spread of the rotavirus disease. The Rotavirus vaccine is the <lb/>best way to protect children from rotavirus infection which <lb/>attributes 9 out of 10 children protection against rotavirus <lb/>disease. 6 WHO reaffirms that the use of rotavirus vaccines <lb/>should be a part of a comprehensive strategy to control diar-<lb/>rheal diseases, along with increased use of treatment packages <lb/>(which include zinc and ORS) and prevention measures (such <lb/>as encouraging early and exclusive breastfeeding, handwashing <lb/>with soap, and improved water and sanitation). 10 <lb/>The rate difference between the first and last vaccination is <lb/>known as the vaccination dropout. 11 The findings of the prior <lb/>studies revealed that the prevalence of rotavirus vaccine dose <lb/></body>

			<front>CONTACT Belayneh Shetie Workneh <lb/>belay2319@gmail.com <lb/>Department of Emergency and Critical Care Nursing, School of Nursing, College of Medicine and <lb/>Health Sciences, University of Gondar, 196, Gondar, Ethiopia. <lb/>HUMAN VACCINES &amp; IMMUNOTHERAPEUTICS <lb/>2024, VOL. 20, NO. 1, 2335730 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2024.2335730 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits <lb/>unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the <lb/>posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent. <lb/></front>

			<body>dose-two out of rotavirus vaccine dose dose-one was 1.9% to <lb/>6% in Ethiopia, 12,13 and 11.7% to 17.1%in Kenya, 14 Previous <lb/>studies revealed that distance from health institution, 12,15-21 <lb/>antenatal care, 15-17,19,22,23 place of delivery, 15,22,24,25 postnatal <lb/>care, 9,11,12 respondents working status, 17 birth order 23 and <lb/>tetanus toxoid vaccination status 11 were factors significantly <lb/>associated with Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout. <lb/>Even though, complete immunization with the rotavirus <lb/>vaccine prevents rotavirus-induced diarrheal disease and <lb/>deaths, vaccine dropout is still a great concern in sub-<lb/>Saharan African countries. Thus, this study aimed to assess <lb/>the magnitude of Rotavirus vaccine dose two dropout and <lb/>associated factors among children who received rotavirus vac-<lb/>cine dose one in sub-Saharan African countries using the <lb/>recent DHS. This could help the concerned bodies to take <lb/>appropriate measures at the country and regional levels. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Data source, study setting, period, and design <lb/>The study used the recent and appended demographic and <lb/>health survey dataset from 21 sub-Saharan African countries <lb/>conducted from 2015 to 2022. DHS is a community-based <lb/>cross-sectional study conducted every five years to examine <lb/>health and health-related indicators. <lb/>Study population, sampling technique, and analysis <lb/>The most recent (from 2015 to 2022) data set of 17 sub-<lb/>Saharan African countries (Ethiopia, Angola, Burundi, <lb/>Cameron, Kenya, Senegal, Gambia, Malawi, Liberia, Mali, <lb/>Sera Leone, Rwanda, Zimbabwe, South Africa, Tanzania, <lb/>Uganda, and Zambia) was downloaded from the <lb/>Demographic Health Survey (DHS) program website and <lb/>appended to have a single data set. Data availability and <lb/>having recent DHS data (2015 to 2022) were the selection <lb/>criteria of the study. The cleaned and recorded data were <lb/>analyzed using STATA (version 14) statistical software. <lb/>Missing data for the outcome variable were dropped. The <lb/>weighting sample (v005/1000000) was applied to address <lb/>under or over-sampling. Variance inflation factor (VIF) <lb/>was tested to check multi-collinearity between variables <lb/>with a mean VIF value of 2.56. To determine factors <lb/>associated with the outcome variable multi-level mixed-<lb/>effect logistic regression was applied. Four models model <lb/>I, model II, model III, and model IV, were used to assess <lb/>the variability of Rota vaccine dropout across the cluster, <lb/>the association of individual-level variables with the out-<lb/>come variable, the association of community-level variables <lb/>with the outcome variable, and association of both indivi-<lb/>dual and community variables with outcome variable <lb/>respectively. Variables with a p-value of &lt; .025, were candi-<lb/>dates for the multivariable analysis in univariate analysis at <lb/>95% confidence intervals and variables with a p-value <lb/>of ≤ .05 were considered as significantly associated with <lb/>the outcome variable in the final analysis. The weighted <lb/>total sample participants for the study were 73,396 <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>Study variables <lb/>Dependent variable <lb/>The outcome variable of this study was the Rotavirus vaccine <lb/>(Rotarix) dose-two dropouts, in which the child received <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose one but not Rotavirus vaccine dose <lb/>two. The RV2 dropout was calculated by the number of <lb/>children who received Rotavirus vaccine dose-one minus <lb/>the number of children who received Rotavirus vaccine <lb/>dose-two divided by the number of children who received <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-one multiplied by 100% from the <lb/>Kids Record (KR) data set; (Rotavirus vaccine dose-one -<lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-two)/Rotavirus vaccine dose-<lb/>one × 100%. <lb/>Independent variables <lb/>The independent variables of this study were individual <lb/>level (maternal age, maternal education, birth order, <lb/>household wealth, maternal working status, distance <lb/>from health institution, husband educational level, place <lb/>of delivery, media exposure, ANC follow-up, PNC <lb/>checkup, maternal tetanus toxoid injection before birth, <lb/>Table 1. Sample size for rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts in the Sub-Saharan African countries. <lb/>Country <lb/>Year of survey <lb/>Weighted sample(n) <lb/>Weighted sample (%) <lb/>Angola <lb/>2015 <lb/>3690 <lb/>5.03 <lb/>Burundi <lb/>2016/17 <lb/>6747 <lb/>9.19 <lb/>Cameron <lb/>2018 <lb/>3992 <lb/>5.44 <lb/>Ethiopia <lb/>2016 <lb/>3419 <lb/>4.66 <lb/>Gambia <lb/>2019/20 <lb/>4034 <lb/>5.50 <lb/>Kenya <lb/>2022 <lb/>8936 <lb/>12.18 <lb/>Liberia <lb/>2019/20 <lb/>2358 <lb/>3.21 <lb/>Mali <lb/>2018 <lb/>4188 <lb/>5.71 <lb/>Malawi <lb/>2015/16 <lb/>8789 <lb/>11.97 <lb/>Rwanda <lb/>2019/20 <lb/>4622 <lb/>6.30 <lb/>Sera Leon <lb/>2019 <lb/>4786 <lb/>6.52 <lb/>Senegal <lb/>2019 <lb/>3048 <lb/>4.15 <lb/>Tanzania <lb/>2022 <lb/>5535 <lb/>7.54 <lb/>Uganda <lb/>2016 <lb/>706 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>South Africa <lb/>2016 <lb/>1693 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>Zambia <lb/>2018 <lb/>5086 <lb/>6.93 <lb/>Zimbabwe <lb/>2015 <lb/>1766 <lb/>2.41 <lb/>Total <lb/>73,396 <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B. S. WORKNEH ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>child gender), and community level (residence, commu-<lb/>nity media exposure, community ANC utilization, com-<lb/>munity literacy level, and community poverty level) <lb/>variables <lb/>Result <lb/>Sociodemographic characteristics <lb/>A total of weighted samples of 73,396 participants were used <lb/>for the study. Two-thirds of 49,133 (66.94%) of the participants <lb/>were rural dwellers. More than Two-thirds 49,317 (67.19%) of <lb/>the study participants had media exposure. More than two-<lb/>thirds 50,670 (69.04%) of the respondents were married. <lb/>Nearly two-thirds 42,688 (62.61%) of the participants didn&apos;t <lb/>experience difficulty in accessing the health facility. The <lb/>majority 62,943 (94.39%) of the participants had ANC follow-<lb/>up (Table 2). <lb/>Prevalence of rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts among <lb/>children who received rotavirus vaccine dose-one in <lb/>Sub-Saharan African countries <lb/>The overall RV2 dropout among children who received rota-<lb/>virus vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African countries was <lb/>10.77% (95% CI 10.55%, 11.00%). It ranged from 2.77% in <lb/>Rwanda to 37.67% in Uganda (Figure 1). <lb/>Model fitness and random effect analysis <lb/>There was about 10.83% variability in RV2 dropout due to the <lb/>difference between communities/clusters as the ICC value <lb/>showed. The final model (model III), attributed approximately <lb/>39.78% of the variation in the likelihood of RV2 dropout to <lb/>both individual and community-level variables. The lowest <lb/>deviance, which was 33,730.16 in model III revealed that <lb/>model III was the best fit for the data (Table 3) <lb/>Table 2. Sociodemographic characteristics. <lb/>Individual level variables <lb/>Weighted frequency (n) <lb/>Percentage (%) <lb/>Maternal age <lb/>15-19 <lb/>5672 <lb/>7.73 <lb/>20-35 <lb/>52772 <lb/>71.90 <lb/>36-49 <lb/>14952 <lb/>20.37 <lb/>Maternal education <lb/>No education <lb/>19931 <lb/>27.16 <lb/>Primary <lb/>28785 <lb/>39.22 <lb/>Secondary <lb/>20718 <lb/>28.23 <lb/>Higher <lb/>3962 <lb/>5.40 <lb/>Birth order <lb/>First <lb/>18095 <lb/>24.65 <lb/>Second <lb/>15027 <lb/>20.47 <lb/>Third <lb/>12302 <lb/>16.76 <lb/>Fourth and more <lb/>27972 <lb/>38.11 <lb/>Media exposure <lb/>No <lb/>24077 <lb/>32.81 <lb/>Yes <lb/>49317 <lb/>67.19 <lb/>Household wealth <lb/>Poor <lb/>30721 <lb/>41.86 <lb/>Middle <lb/>14628 <lb/>19.93 <lb/>Rich <lb/>28047 <lb/>38.21 <lb/>Maternal marital status <lb/>Never married <lb/>6,901 <lb/>9.40 <lb/>Married <lb/>50,670 <lb/>69.04 <lb/>Ever married <lb/>15,824 <lb/>21.56 <lb/>Maternal working status <lb/>Not working <lb/>29,207 <lb/>39.79 <lb/>Working <lb/>44,189 <lb/>60.21 <lb/>Distance from the health facility <lb/>Big problem <lb/>25490 <lb/>37.39 <lb/>Not big problem <lb/>42688 <lb/>62.61 <lb/>ANC follow up <lb/>No <lb/>3,744 <lb/>5.61 <lb/>Yes <lb/>62,943 <lb/>94.39 <lb/>Husband educational level <lb/>No education <lb/>17665 <lb/>28.78 <lb/>Primary <lb/>21535 <lb/>35.09 <lb/>Secondary <lb/>16983 <lb/>27.67 <lb/>Higher <lb/>5188 <lb/>8.45 <lb/>PNC checkup <lb/>No <lb/>48,041 <lb/>65.45 <lb/>Yes <lb/>25,355 <lb/>34.55 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>Male <lb/>37093 <lb/>50.54 <lb/>Female <lb/>36302 <lb/>49.46 <lb/>Place of delivery <lb/>At home <lb/>11619 <lb/>15.83 <lb/>At health institution <lb/>61777 <lb/>84.17 <lb/>Maternal tetanus toxoid injection before birth <lb/>No <lb/>12155 <lb/>18.23 <lb/>Yes <lb/>54531 <lb/>81.77 <lb/>Community level variables <lb/>Residence <lb/>Urban <lb/>24,263 <lb/>33.06 <lb/>Rural <lb/>49,133 <lb/>66.94 <lb/>Community media exposure <lb/>Low <lb/>37063 <lb/>50.50 <lb/>High <lb/>36333 <lb/>49.50 <lb/>Community literacy level <lb/>Low <lb/>41092 <lb/>55.99 <lb/>High <lb/>32304 <lb/>44.01 <lb/>Community poverty level <lb/>Low <lb/>36,989 <lb/>50.40 <lb/>High <lb/>36,407 <lb/>49.60 <lb/>Community ANC utilization <lb/>Low <lb/>26866 <lb/>36.60 <lb/>High <lb/>46529 <lb/>63.40 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUMAN VACCINES &amp; IMMUNOTHERAPEUTICS <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Factors associated with rotavirus vaccine dose-two <lb/>dropouts in the Sub-Saharan African countries <lb/>From the overall variables, in the final fitted model of <lb/>multivariable logistic regression, being a younger mother, <lb/>having no media exposure, late birth order, having home <lb/>delivery, having no PNC checkup, having no ANC follow-<lb/>up, difficulty in accessing health facility, and had no work <lb/>were factors significantly associated with the outcome vari-<lb/>able (Table 4). <lb/>The odds of RV2 dropout were 1.23 (AOR = 1.23, 95%CI: <lb/>1.11, 1.36), 1.18 (AOR = 1.18, 95%CI: 1.06, 1.31), and 1.30 <lb/>(AOR = 1.30, 95%CI: 1.18, 1.44) times higher <lb/>among second, third, and fourth birth order respectively <lb/>as compared with first birth order. The likelihood of RV2 <lb/>dropout was 1.08 (AOR = 1.08, 95%CI: 1.02, 1.15) times <lb/>higher among mothers who experienced difficulty in acces-<lb/>sing health facilities as compared to their counterparts. <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts were 1.08 <lb/>(AOR = 1.08, 95%CI: 1.01, 1.16) times higher among <lb/>mothers who had no media exposure as compared to <lb/>those mothers who had media exposure. The odds of RV2 <lb/>dropout was 1.23 (AOR = 1.23, 95%CI: 1.16, 1.31) times <lb/>higher among mother who had worked as compared with <lb/>their counterparts. The odds of RV2 dropout was 1.43 <lb/>(AOR = 1.43, 95%CI: 1.32, 1.54) times higher among <lb/>mothers who give birth at home compared with mothers <lb/>who give birth at a health institution. Rotavirus vaccine <lb/>dose-two dropouts were 1.38 (AOR = 1.38, 95%CI: 1.23, <lb/>1.54) times higher among mothers who had no ANC fol-<lb/>low-up as compared with mothers who had ANC follow-up. <lb/>The odds of RV2 dropout was 1.25 (AOR = 1.25, 95%CI: <lb/>1.17, 1.33) times higher among mothers who had no PNC <lb/>checkup as compared with mothers who had PNC checkup. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study aimed to assess Rotavirus vaccine dropout and <lb/>associated factors among children who received the first dose <lb/>in sub-Saharan African countries. The overall Rotavirus vac-<lb/>cine dose-two dropouts among children who received rota-<lb/>virus vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African countries was <lb/>10.77% (95% CI 10.55%, 11.00%). It ranged from 2.77% in <lb/>Rwanda to 37.67% in Uganda. The finding of this study is <lb/>lower than the prior study conducted in Kenya 14 and higher <lb/>than the study conducted in Ethiopia. 12,13 The variation might <lb/>be because of the difference in sample size, study population, <lb/>study period, and socioeconomic status. The WHO and <lb/>UNICEF collaborate to estimate national immunization cover-<lb/>age for various vaccines including RotaC (Second or third dose <lb/>of rotavirus vaccine, depending on the national schedule). 26 By <lb/>comparing the dropout rates for the Rotavirus vaccine with the <lb/>WUENIC estimates, we can assess the effectiveness of vaccina-<lb/>tion programs. High dropout rates, such as the 37.67% in <lb/>Uganda, indicate challenges in ensuring complete vaccination <lb/>coverage. <lb/>33.05% <lb/>6.01% <lb/>12.57% <lb/>16.99% <lb/>7.46% 6.72% <lb/>18.74% <lb/>14.12% <lb/>7.15% <lb/>2.77% <lb/>12.98% <lb/>4.95% <lb/>6.84% <lb/>37.67% <lb/>23.50% <lb/>8.49% <lb/>14.82% <lb/>0.00% <lb/>5.00% <lb/>10.00% <lb/>15.00% <lb/>20.00% <lb/>25.00% <lb/>30.00% <lb/>35.00% <lb/>40.00% <lb/>Percentage <lb/>Country <lb/>dose-two dropout <lb/>Figure 1. Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts among children who received rotavirus vaccine dose-one in Sub-Saharan African countries. <lb/>Table 3. Model comparison and random effect analysis for rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout in the Sub-<lb/>Saharan African countries. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Null model <lb/>Model I <lb/>Model II <lb/>Model III <lb/>Random effect <lb/>Variance <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>ICC <lb/>10.83% <lb/>6.54% <lb/>10.30% <lb/>6.81% <lb/>PCV <lb/>Reference <lb/>42.39% <lb/>5.48% <lb/>39.78% <lb/>Model fitness <lb/>Deviance <lb/>49995.57 <lb/>34 267.86 <lb/>48602.36 <lb/>33730.16 <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B. S. WORKNEH ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>Being a younger mother, having no media exposure, late <lb/>birth order, having home delivery, having no PNC checkup, <lb/>having no ANC follow-up, having difficulty accessing health <lb/>facilities, and having no work were factors associated with <lb/>Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts. The study at hand <lb/>revealed that maternal age was associated with Rotavirus <lb/>vaccine dose-two dropouts. Mothers aged 35 years and above <lb/>were more likely than mothers aged 15 to 35 to vaccinate <lb/>rotavirus vaccine dose-two to their children. The findings of <lb/>this study are in agreement with the previous studies. 27-29 It <lb/>could be because youngers relied on their elder family mem-<lb/>bers&apos; decisions or approval. Furthermore, it could be because <lb/>Table 4. Multivariable multilevel logistic regression analysis of individual-level and community-level factors associated with rotavirus vaccine dose-two <lb/>dropouts in the Sub-Saharan African countries. <lb/>Individual and community level variable <lb/>Model I AOR (95% CI) <lb/>Model II AOR (95% CI) <lb/>Model III AOR (95% CI) <lb/>Media Exposure <lb/>No <lb/>1.03 (0.97, 1.10) <lb/>1.08 (1.01, 1.16) <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Maternal age <lb/>15-19 <lb/>2.31 (2.00, 2.67) <lb/>2.03 (1.76, 2.35) <lb/>20-35 <lb/>1.30 (1.20, 1.40) <lb/>1.26 (1.16, 1.36) <lb/>36-49 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Maternal educational <lb/>No education <lb/>1.14 (0.93, 1.39) <lb/>1.18 (0.96, 1.44) <lb/>Primary <lb/>1.04 (0.85,1.26) <lb/>1.12 (0.92, 1.36) <lb/>Secondary <lb/>1.14 (0.94, 1.37) <lb/>1.09 (0.90, 1.32) <lb/>Higher <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Birth order <lb/>First <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Second <lb/>1.28 (1.16, 1.41) <lb/>1.23 (1.11, 1.36) <lb/>Third <lb/>1.26 (1.13, 1.40) <lb/>1.18 (1.06, 1.31) <lb/>Fourth and above <lb/>1.43 (1.29, 1.58) <lb/>1.30 (1.18, 1.44) <lb/>Household wealth <lb/>Poor <lb/>1.07 (0.99, 1.15) <lb/>1.04 (0.96, 1.13) <lb/>Middle <lb/>1.10 (1.01, 1.20) <lb/>1.03 (0.95, 1.13) <lb/>Rich <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Maternal working status <lb/>Not working <lb/>1.17 (1.10, 1.24) <lb/>1.23 (1.16, 1.31) <lb/>Working <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Distance from health institution <lb/>Big problem <lb/>1.09 (1.02, 1.15) <lb/>1.08 (1.02, 1.15) <lb/>No problem <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Husband educational level <lb/>No education <lb/>1.00 (0.86, 1.15) <lb/>0.99 (0.85, 1.15) <lb/>Primary <lb/>0.80 (0.69, 0.93) <lb/>0.87 (0.75, 1.01) <lb/>Secondary <lb/>1.05 (0.92, 1.21) <lb/>1.00 (0.87, 1.15) <lb/>Higher <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Place of delivery <lb/>At home <lb/>1.60 (1.49, 1.72) <lb/>1.43 (1.32, 1.54) <lb/>At health institution <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>ANC follow up <lb/>No <lb/>1.49 (1.33, 1.66) <lb/>1.38 (1.23, 1.54) <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>PNC checkup <lb/>No <lb/>1.23 (1.16, 1.31) <lb/>1.25 (1.17, 1.33) <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Maternal tetanus toxoid injection before birth <lb/>No <lb/>1.00 (0.93, 1.08) <lb/>1.05 (0.97, 1.14) <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>Female <lb/>1.01 (0.96, 1.07) <lb/>1.02 (0.96, 1.08) <lb/>Male <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Community level Variables <lb/>Residence <lb/>Urban <lb/>1 <lb/>Rural <lb/>1.09 (1.04, 1.15) <lb/>0.97 (0.89, 1.05 <lb/>Community media exposure <lb/>Low <lb/>1.11 (1.04, 1.18) <lb/>1.06 (0.99, 1.13) <lb/>High <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Community ANC Utilization <lb/>Low <lb/>1.05 (0.99, 1.12) <lb/>1.05 (0.99, 1.13) <lb/>Higher <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Community literacy level <lb/>Low <lb/>1.08 (1.02, 1.15) <lb/>1.03 (0.96, 1.11) <lb/>Higher <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Community poverty level <lb/>Low <lb/>0.95 (0.89, 1.01) <lb/>0.96 (0.89, 1.03) <lb/>Higher <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUMAN VACCINES &amp; IMMUNOTHERAPEUTICS <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>of improvements in maternal and child health care services like <lb/>ANC follow-up, giving birth at health facilities, and PNC <lb/>checkups as the maternal age rises. <lb/>The odds of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts were <lb/>higher among mothers who had no PNC checkup as compared <lb/>with those who had the PNC checkup. This finding is consis-<lb/>tent with the previous studies. 9,11,12 It could be because of <lb/>a lack of access to medical advice from health professionals <lb/>during the postnatal period. Furthermore, it could be due to <lb/>the loss of the entry point for child vaccination which is PNC <lb/>checkup. The odds of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts <lb/>were higher among mother who had no ANC follow-up as <lb/>compared with their counterparts. The finding of this study is <lb/>supported by the previous studies. 15-17,19,22,23 It could be <lb/>because attending antenatal care may enable them to acquire <lb/>health and health-related information including complete <lb/>child immunization from health professionals. As a result, <lb/>the tendency to vaccinate the child completely increases. <lb/>According to the findings of our study, place of delivery is <lb/>another significant factor for the Rotavirus vaccine dose-two <lb/>dropouts. The likelihood of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two drop-<lb/>outs was higher among mothers who give birth at home as <lb/>compared with those mothers who give birth at health institu-<lb/>tions. This finding is consistent with earlier studies. 15,22,24,25 The <lb/>possible justification might be that mothers who give birth at <lb/>home may not have information about immunization schedules. <lb/>The characteristics of the children are another predicting <lb/>factor for the Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts. The like-<lb/>lihood of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts was higher <lb/>among late birth orders as compared with the first birth <lb/>order. This finding is supported by the previous <lb/>studies. 23,30,31 It could be because of the mother&apos;s diminished <lb/>interest in immunization uptake for late birth orders. <lb/>Furthermore, it could be as the number of children in the <lb/>family increases, family resources, including attention and <lb/>time, are shared among the children which in turn results in <lb/>vaccine dropout. <lb/>The odds of vaccine dropout were higher among mothers <lb/>who experienced difficulty in accessing health facilities nearby <lb/>their districts. One of the biggest obstacles to completing <lb/>a child&apos;s immunizations is the geographical inaccessibility of <lb/>healthcare facilities in rural areas. 32 This finding is consistent <lb/>with the prior studies. 12,15-21 It could be because mothers who <lb/>didn&apos;t access the health institution nearby their district, may <lb/>cost their time and money. As a result, they may lost their <lb/>interest in bringing their child to health institutions for <lb/>immunization. <lb/>Media exposure is another factor associated with the out-<lb/>come variable of the study. Rotavirus vaccine dose-two drop-<lb/>outs were lower among mothers who had media exposure as <lb/>compared to those mothers who had no media exposure. The <lb/>finding of this study is supported by the previous study. 15 It <lb/>could be because mass media has the potential to share mes-<lb/>sages from the concerned bodies for the target population. <lb/>Thus, it helps the mother to acquire health-related knowledge <lb/>including immunization schedules. <lb/>The study also revealed that having no work was associated <lb/>with higher odds of Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropouts. This <lb/>is in agreement with the previous study. 17 This could be <lb/>because women who had work exhibit higher levels of financial <lb/>independence and tend to go to the health facility, which in <lb/>turn can minimize vaccine dropout. <lb/>This study uses nationally representative data from mul-<lb/>tiple sub-Saharan countries and appropriate statistical ana-<lb/>lysis which is multilevel analysis. Hence policymakers and <lb/>the international community can use it as evidence to <lb/>undertake necessary measures. However, the study has <lb/>limitations, important factors that could have a big impact <lb/>on vaccine dropout, like behavior, beliefs, and social <lb/>norms, are not included in the dataset. Additionally, to <lb/>measure the vaccine dropout a recall and response bias <lb/>may have been present. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The overall Rotavirus vaccine dose-two dropout was higher <lb/>in sub-Saharan African countries which implies that vac-<lb/>cine dropout is still a great issue in sub-Saharan African <lb/>countries. Being a younger mother, having no media expo-<lb/>sure, late birth order, giving birth at home, having no PNC <lb/>checkup, having no ANC follow-up, having difficulty in <lb/>accessing health facilities, and having no work were factors <lb/>significantly associated with the outcome variable. <lb/>Therefore, special attention should be given to those <lb/>mothers who are young, who have no work, who give <lb/>birth at home, who experienced difficulty in accessing <lb/>health facilities, and late birth orders. Furthermore, tar-<lb/>geted interventions should be considered for improving <lb/>access and utilization of media, antenatal care, and post-<lb/>natal care service <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors of the study are grateful to DHS programs for letting us to use <lb/>the relevant data. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Disclosure statement <lb/>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s). <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) reported there is no funding associated with the work <lb/>featured in this article. <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID <lb/>Belayneh Shetie Workneh <lb/>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9780-4109 <lb/></front>

			<div type="contribution">Author&apos;s contribution <lb/>Belayneh Shetie Workneh: involved in designing the study, data extrac-<lb/>tion, data analysis, interpretation, report writing, and manuscript writ-<lb/>ing. Enyew Getaneh Mekonen: involved in data curation, and <lb/>methodology. Alebachew Ferede Zegeye: involved in designing the <lb/>study, interpretation, analysis, report, and manuscript writing. Almaz <lb/>Tefera Gonete: involved in software, supervision, and data validation. <lb/>Tewodros Getaneh Alemu: involved in conceptualization and valida-<lb/>tion. Tadesse Tarik Tamir: involved in review and editing, validation, <lb/></div>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B. S. WORKNEH ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">and visualization. Berhan Tekeba: involved in conceptualization and <lb/>methodology. Mulugeta Wassie: involved in software and validation. <lb/>Alemneh Tadesse Kassie: involved in conceptualization, validation, and <lb/>writing the original draft. Mohammed Seid Ali: involved in interpreta-<lb/>tion and manuscript writing. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>The datasets generated and/or analyzed during the current study are <lb/>available in the most recent data of the Demographic and Health Survey <lb/>and it is publicly available online at (https://www.dhsprogram.com). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethical approval and consent to participate <lb/>This study was based on an analysis of existing survey datasets in the <lb/>public domain that are freely available online with all the identifier <lb/>information anonymized, no ethical approval was required. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. WHO. Diarrhoeal disease fact sheet; 2017 May 2. https://www. <lb/>who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/diarrhoeal-disease . <lb/>2. Taylor C. Diarrhea: causes, treatment, and symptom; 2023 Nov 30. <lb/>https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/158634 . <lb/>3. Vesikari T, Matson DO, Dennehy P, Van Damme P, <lb/>Santosham M, Rodriguez Z, Dallas MJ, Heyse JF, Goveia MG, <lb/>Black SB, et al. Safety and efficacy of a pentavalent human-bovine <lb/>(WC3) reassortant rotavirus vaccine. N Engl J Med. 2006;354 <lb/>(1):23-33. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa052664 . <lb/>4. Tate JE, Burton AH, Boschi-Pinto C, Parashar UD, Network <lb/>WHOCGRS. Global, regional, and national estimates of rotavirus <lb/>mortality in children&lt; 5 years of age, 2000-2013. Clin Infect Dis. <lb/>2016;62(suppl_2):96-105. doi:10.1093/cid/civ1013 . <lb/>5. Ansari SA, Springthorpe VS, Sattar SA. Survival and vehicular <lb/>spread of human rotaviruses: possible relation to seasonality of <lb/>outbreaks. Rev Infect Dis. 1991;13(3):448-461. doi:10.1093/clin <lb/>ids/13.3.448 . <lb/>6. CDC. Rotavirus vaccination; 2018 July 25. https://www.cdc.gov/ <lb/>vaccines/vpd/rotavirus/index.html . <lb/>7. Troeger C, Khalil IA, Rao PC, Cao S, Blacker BF, Ahmed T, <lb/>Armah G, Bines JE, Brewer TG, Colombara DV, et al. Rotavirus <lb/>vaccination and the global burden of rotavirus diarrhea among <lb/>children younger than 5 years. JAMA Pediatr. 2018;172 <lb/>(10):958-965. doi:10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.1960 . <lb/>8. Troeger C, Blacker BF, Khalil IA, Rao PC, Cao S, Zimsen SR, <lb/>Albertson SB, Stanaway JD, Deshpande A, Abebe Z, et al. <lb/>Estimates of the global, regional, and national morbidity, mortal-<lb/>ity, and aetiologies of diarrhoea in 195 countries: a systematic <lb/>analysis for the global burden of disease study 2016. Lancet <lb/>Infect Dis. 2018;18(11):1211-1228. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(18) <lb/>30362-1 . <lb/>9. Elizabeth K, George K, Raphael N, Moses E. Factors influencing <lb/>low immunization coverage among children between 12-23 <lb/>months in East Pokot, Baringo Country, Kenya. Int J Vaccines. <lb/>2015;1(2):00012. doi:10.15406/ijvv.2015.01.00012 . <lb/>10. WHO. Immunization, vaccines and biologicals; 2021 July 16. <lb/>https://www.who.int/teams/immunization-vaccines-and-<lb/>biologicals/diseases/rotavirus . <lb/>11. Chanie MG, Ewunetie GE, Molla A, Muche A, Spradley FT. <lb/>Determinants of vaccination dropout among children 12-23 <lb/>months age in north Gondar zone, northwest Ethiopia, 2019. <lb/>PLoS One. 2021;16(2):e0246018. doi:10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0246018 . <lb/>12. Derso T, Kebede A, Wolde HF, Atnafu A, Dellie E. Rotavirus <lb/>vaccine coverage and associated factors among a rural population: <lb/>findings from a primary health-care project in two Northwest <lb/>Ethiopia districts. Pediatric Health Med Ther. 2020;11:429-435. <lb/>doi:10.2147/PHMT.S276037 . <lb/>13. Aliyo A. Rotavirus prevalence and vaccine coverage among chil-<lb/>dren in Ethiopia: study review. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2022;10 <lb/>(2):58-63. doi:10.11648/j.ejpm.20221002.11 . <lb/>14. Wandera EA, Mohammad S, Ouko JO, Yatitch J, Taniguchi K, <lb/>Ichinose Y. Variation in rotavirus vaccine coverage by <lb/>sub-counties in Kenya. Trop Med Health. 2017;45(1):1-5. doi:10. <lb/>1186/s41182-017-0051-z . <lb/>15. Adedokun ST, Uthman OA, Adekanmbi VT, Wiysonge CS. <lb/>Incomplete childhood immunization in Nigeria: a multilevel ana-<lb/>lysis of individual and contextual factors. BMC Public Health. <lb/>2017;17(1):236. doi:10.1186/s12889-017-4137-7 . <lb/>16. Yehualashet SS, Nigussie YD, Yilema TD, Mengiste ST, Alemu YT. <lb/>Vaccine dropout rate and associated factors among childeren age <lb/>12-23 month in Shewa Robit Town, North Shewa zone, Amahra <lb/>region, Ethiopia, a community based cross-sectional study design; <lb/>2019. <lb/>17. Thapa K, Adhikary P, Faruquee MH, Suwal BR, Cho WC. <lb/>Associated factors for dropout of first vs third doses of diphtheria <lb/>tetanus pertussis (DPT) vaccination in Nepal. Adv Prev Med. <lb/>2021;2021:1-9. doi:10.1155/2021/1319090 . <lb/>18. Mekonnen AG, Bayleyegn AD, Ayele ET. Immunization coverage <lb/>of 12-23 months old children and its associated factors in Minjar-<lb/>Shenkora district, Ethiopia: a community-based study. BMC <lb/>Pediatr. 2019;19(1):1-8. doi:10.1186/s12887-019-1575-7 . <lb/>19. Gualu T, Dilie A. Vaccination coverage and associated factors <lb/>among children aged 12-23 months in debre markos town, <lb/>Amhara regional state, Ethiopia. Adv Public Health. <lb/>2017;2017:1-6. doi:10.1155/2017/5352847 . <lb/>20. Muluye M, Oljira L, Eyeberu A, Getachew T, Debella A, Deressa A, <lb/>Dheresa M. Partial vaccination and associated factors among chil-<lb/>dren aged 12-23 months in eastern Ethiopia. BMC Pediatr. <lb/>2022;22(1):268. doi:10.1186/s12887-022-03320-3 . <lb/>21. Haji A, Lowther S, Ngan&apos;ga Z, Gura Z, Tabu C, Sandhu H, <lb/>Arvelo W. Reducing routine vaccination dropout rates: evaluating <lb/>two interventions in three Kenyan districts, 2014. BMC Public <lb/>Health. 2016;16(1):1-8. doi:10.1186/s12889-016-2823-5 . <lb/>22. Tesfaye TD, Temesgen WA, Kasa AS. Vaccination coverage and <lb/>associated factors among children aged 12-23 months in <lb/>Northwest Ethiopia. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2018;14 <lb/>(10):2348-2354. doi:10.1080/21645515.2018.1502528 . <lb/>23. Hailu C, Fisseha G, Gebreyesus A. Determinants of measles vacci-<lb/>nation dropout among 12-23 months aged children in pastoralist <lb/>community of Afar, Ethiopia. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):1-9. <lb/>doi:10.1186/s12879-022-07350-1 . <lb/>24. Mezen MK, Lemlem GA, Biru YB, Yimer AM. Association of war <lb/>with vaccination dropout among children younger than 2 years in <lb/>the North Wollo Zone, Ethiopia. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(2): <lb/>e2255098. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.55098 . <lb/>25. Imran W, Abbas F, Javed S. What is causing high polio vaccine <lb/>dropout among Pakistani children? Public Health. <lb/>2018;164:16-25. doi:10.1016/j.puhe.2018.07.008 . <lb/>26. WHO. WHO/UNICEF estimates of national immunization <lb/>coverage; 2023 July 17. https://www.who.int/teams/immuniza <lb/>tion-vaccines-and-biologicals/immunization-analysis-and-<lb/>insights/global-monitoring/immunization-coverage/who-unicef-<lb/>estimates-of-national-immunization-coverage . <lb/>27. Tesfa GA, Yehualashet DE, Getnet A, Bimer KB, Seboka BT, <lb/>Heyi DZ. Spatial distribution of complete basic childhood vacci-<lb/>nation and associated factors among children aged 12-23 months <lb/>in Ethiopia. A spatial and multilevel analysis. PLoS One. 2023;18 <lb/>(1):e0279399. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0279399 . <lb/>28. Tesema GA, Tessema ZT, Tamirat KS, Teshale AB. Complete basic <lb/>childhood vaccination and associated factors among children aged <lb/>12-23 months in East Africa: a multilevel analysis of recent demo-<lb/>graphic and health surveys. BMC Public Health. 2020;20(1):1-14. <lb/>doi:10.1186/s12889-020-09965-y . <lb/>29. Wiysonge CS, Uthman OA, Ndumbe PM, Hussey GD, <lb/>Moormann AM. Individual and contextual factors associated <lb/>with low childhood immunisation coverage in Sub-Saharan <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HUMAN VACCINES &amp; IMMUNOTHERAPEUTICS <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Africa: a multilevel analysis. PLoS One. 2012;7(5):e37905. doi:10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0037905 . <lb/>30. Barata RB, de Almeida Ribeiro MCS, de Moraes JC, Flannery B, <lb/>Group VCS. Socioeconomic inequalities and vaccination coverage: <lb/>results of an immunisation coverage survey in 27 Brazilian capi-<lb/>tals, 2007-2008. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2012;66 <lb/>(10):934-941. doi:10.1136/jech-2011-200341 . <lb/>31. Mathew JL. Inequity in childhood immunization in India: <lb/>a systematic review. Indian Pediatr. 2012;49(3):203-223. doi:10. <lb/>1007/s13312-012-0063-z . <lb/>32. Albers AN, Thaker J, Newcomer SR. Barriers to and facilitators of <lb/>early childhood immunization in rural areas of the United States: <lb/>a systematic review of the literature. Prev Med Rep. <lb/>2022;27:101804. doi:10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101804. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B. S. WORKNEH ET AL. </note>


	</text>


  </TEI>