<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T10:10:19.202Z">11/14/2025 10:10:19 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T10:10:05.454140Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T10:10:05.454140Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s inhibits <lb/>proliferation and invasion while increasing <lb/>apoptosis in murine ovarian cancer cells <lb/>Resh Carter, Jim J. Petrik, Roger A. Moorehead ID * <lb/>Department of Biomedical Sciences, Ontario Veterinary College, University of Guelph, Guelph, ON, Canada <lb/>* rmoorehe@uoguelph.ca <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Women diagnosed with ovarian cancer frequently have a poor prognosis as their cancer is <lb/>often diagnosed at more advanced stages when the cancer has metastasized. At this point <lb/>surgery cannot remove all the tumor cells and while ovarian cancer cells often initially <lb/>respond to chemotherapeutic agents like carboplatin and paclitaxel, resistance to these <lb/>agents frequently occurs. Thus, novel therapies are required for the treatment of advanced <lb/>stage ovarian cancer. One therapeutic option being explored is the regulation of non-coding <lb/>RNAs such as microRNAs. An advantage of microRNAs is that they can regulate tens, hun-<lb/>dreds and sometimes thousands of mRNAs in cells and thus may be more effective than <lb/>chemotherapeutic agents or targeted therapies. To investigate the therapeutic potential of <lb/>miR-200s in ovarian cancer, lentiviral vectors were used to overexpress both miR-200 clus-<lb/>ters in two murine ovarian cancer cell lines, ID8 and 28-2. Overexpression of miR-200s <lb/>reduced the expression of several mesenchymal genes and proteins, significantly inhibited <lb/>proliferation as assessed by BrdU flow cytometry and significantly reduced invasion through <lb/>Matrigel coated transwell inserts in both cell lines. Overexpression of miR-200s also <lb/>increased basal apoptosis approximately 3-fold in both cell lines as determined by annexin <lb/>V flow cytometry. Pathway analysis of RNA sequencing of control and miR-200 overexpres-<lb/>sing ovarian cancer cells revealed that genes regulated by miR-200s were involved in pro-<lb/>cesses like epithelial mesenchymal transition (EMT) and cell migration. Therefore, miR-<lb/>200s can inhibit proliferation and increase apoptosis while suppressing tumor cell invasion <lb/>and thus simultaneously target three key cancer pathways. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Globally, ovarian cancer is the most lethal gynecological cancer with over 300,000 cases and <lb/>over 200,000 deaths in 2020 [1]. There are 5 main ovarian cancer subtypes, high grade serous <lb/>ovarian cancer (HGSOC), endometrioid carcinoma (EC), clear cell carcinoma (CCC), mucin-<lb/>ous carcinoma (MC) and low grade serous ovarian cancer (LGSOC) with HGSOC being the <lb/>most prevalent form [2]. The lack of specific symptoms associated with ovarian cancer (i.e. <lb/>bloating, pain, nausea) means that ovarian cancer is typically diagnosed at later disease stages <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/>1 / 17 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Carter R, Petrik JJ, Moorehead RA (2024) <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s inhibits proliferation <lb/>and invasion while increasing apoptosis in murine <lb/>ovarian cancer cells. PLoS ONE 19(7): e0307178. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 <lb/>Editor: Yi-Hsien Hsieh, Chung Shan Medical <lb/>University, TAIWAN <lb/>Received: April 11, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: July 1, 2024 <lb/>Published: July 19, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Carter et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Our data is publicly <lb/>available at NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus as <lb/>accession number GSE250195. <lb/>Funding: CIHR project grant PJT-162218 awarded <lb/>to Roger Moorehead. The funders had no role in <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>Abbreviations: ba429, miR-200b/200a/429 cluster; <lb/>BrdU, bromodeoxyuridine; c141, miR-200c/141 <lb/></front>

	<body>where the five year survival rate is approximately 29% [3]. There are several risk factors includ-<lb/>ing an increased number of ovulatory cycles, endometriosis, polycystic ovarian syndrome, and <lb/>genetic factors like BRCA1/BRCA2 mutations [3]. Treatment of ovarian cancer typically <lb/>involves debulking surgery followed by chemotherapy with platinum-based chemotherapies <lb/>like cisplatin or carboplatin in combination with paclitaxel [4]. For ovarian cancer patients <lb/>with defects in homologous DNA repair, such as those with BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations, Poly <lb/>(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitors like olaparib and niraparib have shown survival <lb/>benefits in several clinical trials [5-9]. As most ovarian cancers eventually become resistant to <lb/>available therapies, alternative targets like non-coding RNAs, such as microRNAs (miRNAs), <lb/>are being investigated for their therapeutic potential. <lb/>miRNAs are small, non-coding RNAs that bind to mRNA and prevent mRNA translation. <lb/>One highly conserved family of miRNAs is the miR-200 family [10]. The miR-200 family con-<lb/>sists of 5 members, miR-141, miR-200a, miR-200b, miR-200c and miR-429 organized into two <lb/>clusters (miR-200c/141 and miR-200b/200a/429) [11-13]. The seed sequence, the region of the <lb/>miRNA predicted to bind to the 3&apos;-UTR of mRNAs, is the same in miR-200b, miR-200c, and <lb/>miR-429 while miR-200a and miR-141 share the same seed sequence [10]. Therefore, both <lb/>miR-200 clusters express miRNAs with both miR-200 seed sequences and thus are predicted <lb/>to share mRNA targets. The best characterized function of the miR-200 family is the regulation <lb/>of epithelial and mesenchymal phenotypes. miR-200 family members negatively regulate mes-<lb/>enchymal transcription factors like Zeb1/2, Twist1/2, Snai1/2, to maintain epithelial features <lb/>[13-18]. Therefore, high levels of miR-200s inhibit epithelial mesenchymal transition (EMT) <lb/>and are associated with reduced migration and invasion of cancer cells [19]. <lb/>The role of the miR-200 family in ovarian cancer is unclear as conflicting results have been <lb/>reported. Elevated expression of miR-200s have been associated late stage, high grade disease, <lb/>poor prognosis or increased tumor growth and metastasis [20-29], however, studies have also <lb/>associated a decrease in miR-200 expression with late stage disease, poor prognosis or <lb/>decreased tumor growth and metastasis [30-38]. Of the studies that have manipulated miR-<lb/>200 expression in ovarian cancer cells, three studies found that miR-200 overexpression inhib-<lb/>ited ovarian cancer proliferation and migration. In these studies, transfection of mimics of <lb/>miR-200b and miR-200c [39] or the miR-200b/200a/429 cluster [39, 40] in ovarian cancer cells <lb/>inhibited proliferation and migration in vitro. However, studies have also associated elevated <lb/>miR-200 levels with increased proliferation and migration. Guan et al [29] found that overex-<lb/>pression of miR-200b/200a/429 in the non-transformed ovarian epithelial cell line, T80, stimu-<lb/>lated proliferation and promoted growth in soft agar while Suo et al [41] showed that <lb/>overexpression of miR-200a in OVCAR3 and A2780 ovarian cancer cells increased migration <lb/>It should be noted that several of these studies only regulated the expression of one miR-200 <lb/>family member. As mentioned above, miR-200s are expressed as clusters in cells with each <lb/>cluster expressing at least two miR-200 family members and combined, these two members <lb/>contain both miR-200 seed sequences. Therefore, studies manipulating miR-200s should alter <lb/>the expression of entire miR-200 clusters, or both miR-200 clusters, to better represent the <lb/>physiologic expression of miR-200s in cells. <lb/>In this study, we have manipulated both miR-200 clusters in two murine ovarian cancer cell <lb/>lines (ID8 and 28-2). We found that overexpression of miR-200s reduced the expression of <lb/>several mesenchymal genes, significantly inhibited proliferation and invasion while increasing <lb/>apoptosis. Pathway analysis of differentially expressed genes in control and miR-200 overex-<lb/>pressing murine ovarian cancer cells indicated that miR-200s influenced EMT and cell migra-<lb/>tion. This study represents the first publication of miR-200 manipulation in murine ovarian <lb/>cancer cells and our findings support the previously published studies that suggest miR-200s <lb/>inhibit human ovarian cancer progression. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<front>cluster; CCC, clear cell carcinoma; EC, <lb/>endometrioid carcinoma; EMT, epithelial <lb/>mesenchymal transition; EV, empty vector; FDR, <lb/>false discovery rate; HGSOC, high grade serous <lb/>ovarian cancer; LGSOC, low grade serous ovarian <lb/>cancer; MC, mucinous carcinoma; miRNA, <lb/>microRNA; PARP, poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase; <lb/>PRC2, polycomb repressor complex 2; UTR, <lb/>untranslated region. <lb/></front>

	<body>Materials and methods <lb/>Cell lines <lb/>ID8 and 28-2 cells have previously been described [42]. All cells were maintained in DMEM <lb/>media (GIBCO, Burlington, ON) supplemented with 10% FBS, 2% glutamine, 1% sodium <lb/>pyruvate, 1% 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piper-azineethanesulfonic acid (HEPES), and 1% antibi-<lb/>otic/antimycotic. To generate empty vector control cells (ID8EV and 28-2EV), ID8 or 28-2 <lb/>cells were infected with lentiviral particles containing the pLV[Exp]-EGFP:T2A:Puro-<lb/>EF1A&gt;mCherry (vector ID: VB160109-10005, VectorBuilder Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). ID8EV <lb/>and 28-2EV cells were maintained in media supplemented with 30μg/ml puromycin (Invivo-<lb/>Gen, San Diego, CA). ID8c141 and 28-2c141 cells were created by infecting ID8 or 28-2 cells <lb/>with lentiviral particles containing pLV[Exp]-mCherry:T2A:Hygro-CMV&gt;[Ex_miR200c-<lb/>141]. The miR-200c/141 cluster was synthesized by VectorBuilder and incorporated into the <lb/>lentiviral vector. ID8c141 cells and 28-2c141 cells maintained in media containing 100μg/ml <lb/>and 600μg/ml hygromycin (InvivoGen, San Diego, CA) respectively. Lentiviral particles con-<lb/>taining pLV[Exp]-GFP:T2A:Puro-CMV&gt;[Ex_miR200b-200a-429] were created from the <lb/>pLenti 4.1 Ex_miR200b-200a-429 plasmid [43] obtained from Addgene (cat #35533;) and was <lb/>packaged into a lentiviral vector by VectorBuilder (Chicago, IL). ID8 and 28-2 cells were <lb/>infected with this vector to create ID8ba429 and 28-2ba429 cells and these cells were main-<lb/>tained in media containing 30μg/ml or 60μg/ml of puromycin, respectively. ID8-200f and 28-<lb/>2-200f cells were created by infecting ID8 or 28-2 cells with lentiviral particles containing pLV <lb/>[Exp]-mCherry:T2A:Hygro-CMV&gt;[Ex_miR200c-141] and lentiviral particles containing pLV <lb/>[Exp]-GFP:T2A:Puro-CMV&gt;[Ex_miR200b-200a-429]. ID8-200f cells were maintained in <lb/>media containing 40μg/ml puromycin + 50μg/ml hygromycin while 28-2-200f cells were <lb/>maintained in media containing 60μg/ml puromycin + 1000μg/ml hygromycin. <lb/>RNA extraction, taqman qRT-PCR for microRNA expression and <lb/>qRT-PCR for gene expression <lb/>RNA extraction was perform using a mirVana miRNA Isolation kit (ThermoFisher Scientific, Bur-<lb/>lington, ON). For the analysis of miRNA expression, the TaqMan microRNA reverse transcription <lb/>kit (ThermoFisher Scientific, Burlington, ON) was used to reverse transcript 100 ng of total RNA <lb/>into cDNA following the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. Detailed description of these protocols have <lb/>been previously described in [44]. All miR-200 Taqman probes were obtained from ThermoFisher <lb/>Scientific (Waltham, MA). miR-200 expression was normalized to sno202 and sno234. All gene <lb/>primers were obtained from Bio-Rad Laboratories (Mississauga, ON), Cdh1 (qMmuCID0005843), <lb/>Hprt(qMmuCED0045738), Snai1 (qMmuCID0024342), Snai2 (qMmuCED0046072), Twist1 <lb/>(qMmuCED0004065), Twist2 (qMmuCID0009652) Vim (qMmuCID0005527), Zeb1 (qMmu-<lb/>CID0009095), and Zeb2 (qMmuCID0014662). Hprt was used as the housekeeping gene. <lb/>Protein isolation and western blotting <lb/>Proteins were isolated and western blotting performed as previously described [45]. Primary <lb/>antibody for Zeb1(cat#70512) was obtained from New England Biolabs Ltd., Whitby, ON, <lb/>CAN) and was used at a 1:1,000 dilution. Protein bands were visualized using Western ECL <lb/>substrate (Bio-Rad CAN, Mississauga, ON, CAN) and imaged using the ChemiDocTMXRS <lb/>+ System (Bio-Rad CAN, Mississauga, ON, CAN). Blots were subsequently normalized with <lb/>an HRP-linked anti-rabbit β-actin antibody (cat# 5125S; New England Biolabs Ltd., Whitby, <lb/>ON, CAN) and quantified through the Image Lab software (Bio-Rad CAN, Mississauga, ON, <lb/>CAN). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Flow cytometry <lb/>BrdU and Annexin V flow cytometry were performed as previously described [46]. Briefly, an <lb/>APC BrdU flow kit (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, cat #552,598) was used following the manu-<lb/>facturer&apos;s protocol for proliferation while the BD Pharminogen APC Annexin V kit (BD Bio-<lb/>sciences, San Jose, CA, USA, cat #550475) was used for apoptosis. Analysis was performed <lb/>using an Accuri C6 cytometer (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA) using a flow rate of 35 μl/min <lb/>and 25,000 events were collected. <lb/>Transwell invasion assay <lb/>Transwell invasion assays were performed using Matrigel coated inserts from the BioCoat <lb/>Matrigel Invasion Chamber kit (Corning, NY) were used as previously described [47]. 75,000 <lb/>cells for each cell line were seeded in the upper chamber in serum-free media and the lower <lb/>chamber was filled with media containing 10% FBS. Invasion was assessed after 24 hours. <lb/>RNA sequencing <lb/>RNA sequencing was performed by Novogene Corporation Inc. (Sacramento, CA, USA) using <lb/>total RNA extracted with the miRVana miRNA isolation kit (ThermoFisher Scientific, Burling-<lb/>ton, ON, Canada) as previously described [48]. Three independent samples were sequenced for <lb/>cell line. Fastq files were processed using Genialis software v3.0 (Genialis Inc, Houston, TX, <lb/>USA) following the standard RNA-seq pipeline which uses BBDuk to remove adapters and trim <lb/>reads, STAR to align the reads, and featureCounts to generate gene-level counts. Heatmap anal-<lb/>ysis was performed using Genialis software v3.0 (Genialis Inc., Houston, TX, USA), and path-<lb/>way analysis was performed using Enrichr software v3.0 [49, 50]. The RNA sequencing data <lb/>have been uploaded to the GEO database as accession number GSE250195. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis for miR-200 expression was determined using an ANOVA followed by a <lb/>Dunnett&apos;s test while all other comparisons used an unpaired t-test using GraphPad Prism 10 <lb/>(GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). Values were considered statistically significant <lb/>when p &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Results <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s in ID8 and 28-2 cells <lb/>To evaluate the impact of miR-200s in ovarian cancer, murine ID8 and 28-2 cells were <lb/>infected with lentiviral constructs containing an empty vector (EV), the miR-200b/200a/429 <lb/>cluster (ba429), the miR-200c/141 cluster (c141) or both clusters (200f). As shown in Fig 1 re-<lb/>expression of the ba429 cluster significantly increased the expression of miR-200b (Fig 1A), <lb/>miR-200a (Fig 1B), and miR-429 (Fig 1C) in ID8 cells. Interestingly, re-expression of the miR-<lb/>200b/200a/429 cluster also significantly increased the expression of miR-200c (Fig 1D) but not <lb/>miR-141 (Fig 1E). Re-expression of the miR-200c/141 cluster in ID8 cells significantly <lb/>increased the expression of miR-200c (Fig 1D) and miR-141 (Fig 1E). Our attempt to overex-<lb/>press both clusters in the ID8 cells led to a significant increase in miR-200b (Fig 1A), miR-<lb/>200a (Fig 1B), and miR-200c (Fig 1D) but not miR-429 (Fig 1C) or miR-141 (Fig 1E). <lb/>For the 28-2 cells, expression of the miR-200b/200a/429 cluster resulted in a significant <lb/>increase in miR-200a (Fig 1G) but not miR-200b (Fig 1F) or miR-429 (Fig 1H) while expres-<lb/>sion of the miR-200c/141 cluster did not significantly increase the expression of miR-200c <lb/>(Fig 1I) or miR-141 (Fig 1J). Expression of both clusters lead to a significant increase in all five <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>miR-200 family members (Fig 1F-1H). It should be noted that miR-429 and miR-141 are <lb/>expressed at considerably lower levels than miR-200a, miR-200b and miR-200c in both cell <lb/>lines. Therefore, miR-200a, miR-200b and miR-200c are likely the main miR-200s driving the <lb/>effects observed in ID8-200f and 28-2-200f cells. <lb/>The impact of miR-200 overexpression on epithelial and mesenchymal <lb/>gene expression <lb/>For all subsequent experiments, we focused on the empty vector samples (ID8EV and 28-2EV) <lb/>compared to the cell line expressing both miR-200 clusters (ID8-200f and 28-2-200f). In the <lb/>ID8-200f cells, there was a significant reduction in Vim (Fig 2B), Twist1 (Fig 2E), and Twist2 <lb/>(Fig 1F) with no significant change in Cdh1 (Fig 2A), Snai1, (Fig 2C) Zeb1 (Fig 2G), Zeb2 (Fig <lb/>2H) compared to ID8EV cells. There was also a significant increase in Snai2 (Fig 2D) in the <lb/>ID8-200f cells compared to ID8EV cells. For the 28-2-200f cells, there was a significant reduc-<lb/>tion in Vim (Fig 2J), Snai1 (Fig 2K), Twist2 (Fig 2N), Zeb1 (Fig 2O), and Zeb2 (Fig 2P) <lb/>Fig 1. Taqman RT-PCR for miR-200 family members in (A-E) ID8 or (F-J) 28-2 cells infected with an empty vector (EV) lentivirus, a lentivirus expressing the <lb/>miR-200b/200a/429 cluster (ba429), a lentivirus expressing the miR-200c/141 cluster (c141) or both clusters (200f). miR-200 expression was normalized to <lb/>Sno202 and Sno234 and is presented as the mean (horizonal line) and standard error (error bars). Four biological replicates were used for each cell line. <lb/>*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001, ****p &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. Quantitative RT-PCR for (A,I) Cdh1, (B,J) Vim, (C,K) Snai1, (D,L) Snai2, (E,M) Twist1, (F,N) Twist2, (G,O) Zeb1, and (H,P) Zeb2 <lb/>in (A-H) ID8EV and ID8-200f cells or (I-P) 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells. All genes were normalized to HPRT and the horizontal lines <lb/>represent the means and the error bars represent the standard error. Four biological replicates were used for each cell line. *p &lt; 0.05, <lb/>**p &lt; 0.01, ****p &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>compared to 28-2EV cells. There were no significant changes in Cdh1 (Fig 2I), Snai2 (Fig 2L), <lb/>or Twist1 (Fig 2M) between 28-2EV and 28-200f cells. <lb/>Since miR-200s may impair mRNA translation rather than mRNA expression, a known tar-<lb/>get of miR-200s, Zeb1, was evaluated at the protein level to confirm we have altered miR-200 <lb/>function. As shown in Fig 3, Zeb1 protein levels were reduced in ID8-200f and 28-2-200f cells <lb/>compared to their respective controls confirming that elevated levels of miR-200 functionally <lb/>reduced the levels of mesenchymal proteins. <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s reduce proliferation and invasion while <lb/>increasing apoptosis <lb/>Proliferation and apoptosis were assessed using BrdU and Annexin V flow cytometry, respec-<lb/>tively. Proliferation was significantly reduced more that 2-fold in both ID8-200f and 28-2-200f <lb/>cells compared to their respective controls (Fig 4A-4D)). Along with the reduced proliferation, <lb/>basal apoptotic rates were significantly increased approximately 3-fold in both ID8-200f and <lb/>28-2-200f cells compared to their respective controls. Cell invasion was assessed using a Matri-<lb/>gel coated transwell assay. As shown in Fig 4E-4J, overexpression of miR-200s in ID8 and 28-<lb/>2 cells significantly reduced invasion in both cell lines. <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s regulate the expression of genes related to <lb/>EMT and cell migration <lb/>RNA sequencing was performed on ID8EV, ID8-200f, 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells. Using a <lb/>cut-off of logFC &gt; 1 or logFC &lt;-1 and false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01, there were 1011 <lb/>genes differentially expressed between ID8EV and ID8-200f cells. 243 genes were upregulated, <lb/>and 786 genes were downregulated in ID8-200f cells compared to ID8EV cells. The top 10 dif-<lb/>ferentially expressed genes based on FDR are listed in S1 Table. Using Enrichr to analyze these <lb/>1011 differentially expressed genes, the top ENCODE and ChEA Consensus TFs from ChIP-X <lb/>was SUZ12 and the top MSigDB Hallmark 2020 was Epithelial Mesenchymal Transition (S2 <lb/>Table). The top ontologies were Regulation of Cell Migration (GO Biological Process 2023), <lb/>Collagen-Containing Extracellular Matrix (GO Cellular Component 2023), and Transmem-<lb/>brane Receptor Protein Kinase Activity (GO Molecular Function 2023) (S2 Table). <lb/>Fig 3. Representative western blot of Zeb1 in ID8EV, ID8-200f, 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells. β-actin was used as a <lb/>loading control. This western was repeated using a second set of samples to confirm the results. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>RNA sequencing was also performed to identify genes altered by the miR-200 family in 28-<lb/>2 cells. Using a cut-off of logFC &gt; 1 or logFC &lt;-1 and false discovery rate (FDR) &lt; 0.01, there <lb/>were 753 genes differentially expressed between 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells. 377 genes were <lb/>upregulated, and 376 genes were downregulated in 28-2-200f cells compared to 28-2EV cells. <lb/>The top 10 differentially expressed genes based on FDR are listed in S3 Table. Using Enrichr to <lb/>analyze these 753 differentially expressed genes, the top ENCODE and ChEA Consensus TFs <lb/>from ChIP-X was SUZ12, the top MSigDB Hallmark 2020 was Epithelial Mesenchymal Transi-<lb/>tion (S4 Table). The top ontologies were Regulation of Cell Migration (GO Biological Process <lb/>2023), Collagen-Containing Extracellular Matrix (GO Cellular Component 2023), and GTPase <lb/>Regulator Activity (GO Molecular Function 2023) (S4 Table). <lb/>Of the 1011 differentially expressed genes in the ID8EV vs ID8-200f comparison and 753 <lb/>genes in the 28-2EV vs 28-2-200f comparison, 291 genes were shared (Fig 5A). Analyzing the <lb/>shared genes with Enrichr, the top ENCODE and ChEA Consensus TFs from ChIP-X was <lb/>Fig 4. Percent BrdU positive cells for (A) ID8EV and ID8-200f and (B) 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells (B) as determined by flow cytometry. Percent annexin V <lb/>positive cells for (C) ID8EV and ID8-200f and (D) 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells as determined by flow cytometry. Representative transwell images for (E) <lb/>ID8EV, (F) ID8-200f, (H) 28-2EV, and (I) 28-2-200f cells. Quantification of the average percent of the transwell insert covered by invaded cells for (G) ID8EV <lb/>and ID8-200f and (J) 28-2EV and 28-2-200f cells. Three biological replicates were used for BrdU and the invasion assay while five or six biological replicates <lb/>were used for annexin V. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 5. (A) Venn diagram showing the number of unique and shared genes as determined by RNA sequencing in ID8EV vs ID8-200f and 28-2EV <lb/>vs 28-2-200f. Heatmap of (B) shared genes implicated in EMT and (C) shared genes implicated in cell migration. Three biological replicates were <lb/>sequenced for each cell line. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>SUZ12, the top MSigDB Hallmark 2020 was Epithelial Mesenchymal Transition (S5 Table). <lb/>The top ontologies were Regulation of Cell Migration (GO Biological Process 2023), Endoplas-<lb/>mic Reticulum Lumen (GO Cellular Component 2023), and Glutathione Transferase Activity <lb/>(GO Molecular Function 2023) (S5 Table). <lb/>Since miR-200s are known to regulate EMT and the top MSigDB Hallmark was EMT, the <lb/>shared genes were analyzed for genes that were attributed to EMT. Nineteen shared genes <lb/>were found that regulate EMT and these genes were Sh3rf2, Pdgfra, Ctsh, Flt1, Csf1, Twist2, <lb/>Col1a1, Sema5a, Sema3b, F2rl1, Flt4, Tiam1, Tnc, Dock10, Plxnd1, Emilin1, Mitf, Osgin1, and <lb/>Wnt5b (Fig 5B). Furthermore, as our results showed that miR-200s significantly reduced inva-<lb/>sion in both cell lines, the shared genes were analyzed for genes that were attributed to cell <lb/>migration. Seventeen genes were found that regulate migration and these genes were Aplp1, <lb/>Areg, Col16a1, Col1a1, Col3a1, Col5a1, Col6a2, Fbln5, Fstl1, Igfbp3, Igfbp4, Matn2, Sfrp4, Spp1, <lb/>Tgm2, Tnc, and Vcan (Fig 5C). <lb/>Of the 36 shared genes that contribute to EMT and migration, 20 of the genes were deter-<lb/>mined to be direct targets of members of the miR-200 family, using the miRNA prediction <lb/>software miRWalk [51]. These genes were Aplp1, Col16a1, Col1a1, Col3a1, Csf1, Ctsh, Dock10, <lb/>Emilin1, Flt4, Fstl1, Igbfbp3, Mitf, Pdgfra, Sema3b, Sema5a, Sh3rf2, Tgm2, Tiam1, Tnc, and <lb/>Vcan. Additionally, since the top ENCODE and ChEA Consensus TF from ChIP-X was <lb/>SUZ12, Harmonizome 3.0 (Rouillard et al., 2016) was used to detect genes that were targets of <lb/>SUZ12. Of the 291 shared genes from ID8EV vs ID8-200f and 28-2EV vs 28-2-200f, 122 of <lb/>these shared genes (~42%) were targets of SUZ12. In addition, 20 of the 36 genes (~56%) <lb/>related to EMT and migration were found to be target genes of SUZ12. These genes were Areg, <lb/>Col16a1, Col5a1, Fbln5, Fstl1, Igfbp3, Igfbp4, Vcan, Pdgfra, Ctsh, Flt1, Csf1, Twist2, Sema5a, <lb/>Sema3b, Flt4, Flt1, Dock10, Plxnd1, and Wnt5b. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we successfully increased the expression of both miR-200 seed sequences in two <lb/>murine ovarian cancer cell lines, ID8 and 28-2. There were a few surprising findings including <lb/>the significant increase in miR-429 in the ID8c141 cells and the significant increase in miR-<lb/>200c in ID8ba429 cells. We have also observed this phenomenon in the human breast cancer <lb/>cell line MDA-MB-231 where overexpression of the miR-200c/141 cluster induced a signifi-<lb/>cant increase in miR-200b [52]. It remains unclear whether miR-200 clusters can, under some <lb/>circumstances, regulate each other&apos;s expression or whether certain conditions allow primers <lb/>specific for one miR-200 family member to bind to and amplify a different miR-200 family <lb/>member as the sequences of some of the miR-200s are highly similar. For example, the <lb/>sequence for mmu-miR-200b-3p is UAAUACUGCCUGGUAAUGAUGA while the sequence for <lb/>mmu-miR-200c-3p is UAAUACUGCCGGGUAAUGAUGGA. <lb/>Overexpression of miR-200s in ID8 and 28-2 cells significantly reduced proliferation and <lb/>invasion while increasing apoptosis in both cell lines. These findings are consistent with several <lb/>previous papers that showed increasing one or more miR-200 family members in human ovar-<lb/>ian cancer cell lines could inhibit proliferation [39, 53, 54], or migration/invasion [39, 54-59] <lb/>and increase apoptosis [53]. However, several studies found that miR-200s had the opposite <lb/>effect to those observed in this study. Guan et al [29] transiently transfected miR-200a, miR-<lb/>200b and miR-429 mimics in the non-tumorigenic human ovarian epithelial cell line T80 and <lb/>showed that increasing miR-200 levels promoted proliferation, soft agar growth and xenograft <lb/>tumor formation. In another study, transfection of ES2 or SKOV3 cells with a miR-200a-3p <lb/>mimic was shown to increase proliferation, colony formation and invasion [60]. Liu et al [61] <lb/>showed that overexpression of miR-200a in OVCAR3 cells promoted proliferation while Suo <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>et al [41] found that overexpression of a miR-200a mimic increased, while a miR-200a inhibi-<lb/>tor decreased, invasion of OVCAR3 cells. Finally, in a study by Ibrahim et al [62], it was found <lb/>that a miR-200c mimic increased proliferation but decreased invasion of CAOV3 and SKOV3 <lb/>cells. <lb/>The reason behind these divergent results remains unclear but one variable is that most of <lb/>the studies only altered the expression of an individual miR-200 and in some cases, only the 3p <lb/>or 5p sequence of an individual miR-200. While the regulation of individual miR-200s is useful <lb/>for identifying mRNAs targeted by specific miR-200s, the physiological relevance is less clear. <lb/>Since miR-200s are expressed as clusters in cells, at a minimum a whole miR-200 cluster <lb/>should be altered to represent a physiologically relevant change in miR-200 expression. <lb/>Expressing an individual cluster or both clusters ensure that both miR-200 seed sequences are <lb/>expressed. <lb/>Only one published study used lentiviral vectors to stably elevate the expression of the miR-<lb/>200b/200a/429 cluster, the miR-200c/141 cluster or both clusters and this was performed in a <lb/>spontaneously immortalized human ovarian surface epithelial cell line OSE7. Overexpression <lb/>of the individual clusters or co-overexpression of both clusters in OSE7 cells significantly <lb/>reduced proliferation [63]. Apoptosis and invasion were not evaluated in this study. <lb/>Of the studies that evaluated the expression of epithelial and mesenchymal genes, elevated <lb/>expression of miR-200s increased the expression of epithelial genes like Cdh1 and decreased <lb/>the expression of mesenchymal genes such as Zeb1 and Zeb2 [54, 57-59, 64-67] and thus were <lb/>consistent with our findings. The maintenance of epithelial identity by miR-200s is one of the <lb/>best characterized functions of the miR-200 family [14-16]. Since EMT is thought to enhance <lb/>metastasis, it is somewhat surprising that miR-200s were consistently observed to downregu-<lb/>late mesenchymal genes or upregulate epithelial genes in ovarian cancer cells yet some studies <lb/>found that elevated levels of miR-200s promoted migration or invasion [41, 60]. It should be <lb/>noted that only four papers were found that evaluated both EMT gene expression and migra-<lb/>tion or invasion [54, 57, 58, 63]. In all four of these publications, miR-200 overexpression <lb/>decreased mesenchymal gene expression and/or increased epithelial gene expression and <lb/>inhibited migration and/or invasion. The role of miR-200s in EMT was also supported by our <lb/>RNA-sequencing. Pathway analysis of genes altered by miR-200s identified EMT as a pathway <lb/>affected in both ID8-200f and 28-2-200f compared to their respective control lines. Two previ-<lb/>ous studies performed microarrays following miR-200 overexpression in human ovarian cells <lb/>and these studies also found EMT to be one of the top regulated pathways [63, 65]. Therefore, <lb/>most of studies on human ovarian cell lines agree with our findings in murine ovarian cancer <lb/>cells that miR-200s reduce mesenchymal gene expression and invasion. <lb/>Another interesting finding in the pathway analysis was that the top ENCODE and ChEA <lb/>Consensus TF from ChIP-X was SUZ12. This is consistent with our studies that overexpressed <lb/>miR-200s in murine and human mammary tumor cell lines [48]. Suppressor of zeste 12 <lb/>(SUZ12) is a key component of the polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2). The PRC2 is <lb/>responsible for mono, di-and tri-methylating histone H3 on lysine 27 (H3K27). Methylation <lb/>of H3K27 is associated with repression of gene expression [68]. Exactly how miR-200s regulate <lb/>PRC2 activity remains to be determined but this pathway would provide an additional mecha-<lb/>nism that miR-200s could employ to regulate gene expression. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>This is the first study to stably overexpress miR-200s in murine ovarian cancer cells and show <lb/>that miR-200s decrease mesenchymal gene expression, inhibit proliferation and invasion and <lb/>increase apoptosis. These cells should be useful for furthering our understanding of miR-200s <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>in human ovarian cancer since miR-200s have been shown to suppress mesenchymal gene <lb/>expression and reduce migration and invasion in human ovarian cancer. In addition, the <lb/>mature sequences of miR-141, miR-200a, miR-200b and miR-200c are identical in mice and <lb/>humans and thus should target similar genes in murine and human cells. Moreover, we have <lb/>previously shown that injection of ID-8 or 28-2 cells into the ovaries of syngeneic C57Bl/6 <lb/>mice replicate human ovarian cancer progression including ascites formation and metastasis <lb/>[42]. Therefore, the cells characterized in this study can be used to model the impact of ele-<lb/>vated miR-200 levels on ovarian cancer progression in an in vivo model with an intact immune <lb/>system. These future studies will determine whether miR-200s impair primary tumor growth <lb/>and or metastasis in vivo and thus represent a potential therapeutic strategy for ovarian <lb/>cancer. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. Top 10 differentially expressed genes, based on false discovery rate (FDR) in <lb/>ID8-200f cells compared to ID8EV cells. Genes with negative log fold change are downregu-<lb/>lated in ID8-200f cells compared to ID8EV cells. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Table. Top transcription factors and pathways identified by Enrichr from the differen-<lb/>tially expressed genes in ID8-200f cells compared to ID8EV cells. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Table. Top 10 differentially expressed genes, based on false discovery rate (FDR) in 28-<lb/>2-200f cells compared to 28-2EV cells. Genes with negative log fold change are downregu-<lb/>lated in 28-2-200f cells compared to 28-2EV cells. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Table. Top transcription factors and pathways identified by Enrichr from the differen-<lb/>tially expressed genes in 28-2-200f cells compared to 28-2EV cells. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Table. Top transcription factors and pathways identified by Enrichr from the shared <lb/>differentially expressed genes in the ID8-200f cells compared ID8EV cells and 28-2-200f <lb/>cells compared to 28-2EV cells. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Raw image. Western blot showing the entire gel for (A) Zeb1 and (B) Hprt. Fig 3 was <lb/>adapted from this western blot. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Jim J. Petrik, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Data curation: Resh Carter. <lb/>Formal analysis: Resh Carter. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Investigation: Resh Carter, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Methodology: Resh Carter, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Project administration: Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Supervision: Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Validation: Resh Carter, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Visualization: Resh Carter, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Resh Carter, Jim J. Petrik, Roger A. Moorehead. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, et al. Global Cancer Statistics <lb/>2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries. <lb/>CA Cancer J Clin. 2021; 71(3):209-49. Epub 2021/02/05. https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21660 PMID: <lb/>33538338. <lb/>2. Fasoulakis Z, Psarommati MZ, Papapanagiotou A, Pergialiotis V, Koutras A, Douligeris A, et al. Micro-<lb/>RNAs Can Influence Ovarian Cancer Progression by Dysregulating Integrin Activity. Cancers (Basel). <lb/>2023; 15(18). Epub 2023/09/28. https://doi.org/10.3390/cancers15184449 PMID: 37760437; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMC10526761. <lb/>3. Lheureux S, Gourley C, Vergote I, Oza AM. Epithelial ovarian cancer. Lancet. 2019; 393(10177):1240-<lb/>53. Epub 2019/03/27. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32552-2 PMID: 30910306. <lb/>4. Karam A, Ledermann JA, Kim JW, Sehouli J, Lu K, Gourley C, et al. Fifth Ovarian Cancer Consensus <lb/>Conference of the Gynecologic Cancer InterGroup: first-line interventions. Ann Oncol. 2017; 28 <lb/>(4):711-7. Epub 2017/03/23. https://doi.org/10.1093/annonc/mdx011 PMID: 28327917. <lb/>5. Bustos MA, Yokoe T, Shoji Y, Kobayashi Y, Mizuno S, Murakami T, et al. MiR-181a targets STING to <lb/>drive PARP inhibitor resistance in BRCA-mutated triple-negative breast cancer and ovarian cancer. <lb/>Cell Biosci. 2023; 13(1):200. Epub 2023/11/07. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13578-023-01151-y PMID: <lb/>37932806. <lb/>6. Wang SSY, Jie YE, Cheng SW, Ling GL, Ming HVY. PARP Inhibitors in Breast and Ovarian Cancer. <lb/>Cancers (Basel). 2023; 15(8). Epub 2023/05/16. https://doi.org/10.3390/cancers15082357 PMID: <lb/>37190285; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC10137187. <lb/>7. Gonzalez-Martin A, Pothuri B, Vergote I, DePont Christensen R, Graybill W, Mirza MR, et al. Niraparib <lb/>in Patients with Newly Diagnosed Advanced Ovarian Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2019; 381(25):2391-402. <lb/>Epub 2019/09/29. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1910962 PMID: 31562799. <lb/>8. Banerjee S, Moore KN, Colombo N, Scambia G, Kim BG, Oaknin A, et al. Maintenance olaparib for <lb/>patients with newly diagnosed advanced ovarian cancer and a BRCA mutation (SOLO1/GOG 3004): 5-<lb/>year follow-up of a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2021; 22 <lb/>(12):1721-31. Epub 2021/10/30. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00531-3 PMID: 34715071. <lb/>9. Penson RT, Valencia RV, Cibula D, Colombo N, Leath CA 3rd, Bidzinski M, et al. Olaparib Versus Non-<lb/>platinum Chemotherapy in Patients With Platinum-Sensitive Relapsed Ovarian Cancer and a Germline <lb/>BRCA1/2 Mutation (SOLO3): A Randomized Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2020; 38(11):1164-74. Epub <lb/>2020/02/20. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.19.02745 PMID: 32073956; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC7145583. <lb/>10. Trumbach D, Prakash N. The conserved miR-8/miR-200 microRNA family and their role in invertebrate <lb/>and vertebrate neurogenesis. Cell Tissue Res. 2015; 359(1):161-77. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00441-<lb/>014-1911-z PMID: 24875007. <lb/>11. Saini HK, Enright AJ, Griffiths-Jones S. Annotation of mammalian primary microRNAs. BMC genomics. <lb/>2008; 9:564. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-9-564 PMID: 19038026; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC2632650. <lb/>12. Park SM, Gaur AB, Lengyel E, Peter ME. The miR-200 family determines the epithelial phenotype of <lb/>cancer cells by targeting the E-cadherin repressors ZEB1 and ZEB2. Genes Dev. 2008; 22(7):894-907. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/gad.1640608 [pii] PMID: 18381893 <lb/>13. Hill L, Browne G, Tulchinsky E. ZEB/miR-200 feedback loop: At the crossroads of signal transduction in <lb/>cancer. IntJCancer. 2012. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijc.27708 PMID: 22753312 <lb/>14. Howe EN, Cochrane DR, Richer JK. The miR-200 and miR-221/222 microRNA families: opposing <lb/>effects on epithelial identity. JMammaryGlandBiolNeoplasia. 2012; 17(1):65-77. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s10911-012-9244-6 PMID: 22350980 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>15. Radisky DC. miR-200c at the nexus of epithelial-mesenchymal transition, resistance to apoptosis, and <lb/>the breast cancer stem cell phenotype. Breast Cancer Res. 2011; 13(3):110. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>bcr2885 [pii]. PMID: 21682933 <lb/>16. Bracken CP, Gregory PA, Kolesnikoff N, Bert AG, Wang J, Shannon MF, et al. A double-negative feed-<lb/>back loop between ZEB1-SIP1 and the microRNA-200 family regulates epithelial-mesenchymal transi-<lb/>tion. Cancer Res. 2008; 68(19):7846-54. https://doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-1942 PMID: <lb/>18829540 <lb/>17. Peinado H, Olmeda D, Cano A. Snail, Zeb and bHLH factors in tumour progression: an alliance against <lb/>the epithelial phenotype? NatRevCancer. 2007; 7(6):415-28. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrc2131 PMID: <lb/>17508028 <lb/>18. Yang J, Weinberg RA. Epithelial-mesenchymal transition: at the crossroads of development and tumor <lb/>metastasis. DevCell. 2008; 14(6):818-29. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2008.05.009 PMID: <lb/>18539112 <lb/>19. Klicka K, Grzywa TM, Mielniczuk A, Klinke A, Wlodarski PK. The role of miR-200 family in the regulation <lb/>of hallmarks of cancer. Front Oncol. 2022; 12:965231. Epub 2022/09/27. https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc. <lb/>2022.965231 PMID: 36158660; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9492973. <lb/>20. Yang H, Kong W, He L, Zhao JJ, O&apos;Donnell JD, Wang J, et al. MicroRNA expression profiling in human <lb/>ovarian cancer: miR-214 induces cell survival and cisplatin resistance by targeting PTEN. Cancer Res. <lb/>2008; 68(2):425-33. Epub 2008/01/18. https://doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-2488 PMID: <lb/>18199536. <lb/>21. Nam EJ, Yoon H, Kim SW, Kim H, Kim YT, Kim JH, et al. MicroRNA expression profiles in serous ovar-<lb/>ian carcinoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2008; 14(9):2690-5. Epub 2008/05/03. https://doi.org/10.1158/1078-<lb/>0432.CCR-07-1731 PMID: 18451233. <lb/>22. Mateescu B, Batista L, Cardon M, Gruosso T, de Feraudy Y, Mariani O, et al. miR-141 and miR-200a <lb/>act on ovarian tumorigenesis by controlling oxidative stress response. Nat Med. 2011; 17(12):1627-35. <lb/>Epub 2011/11/22. https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.2512 PMID: 22101765. <lb/>23. Vilming Elgaaen B, Olstad OK, Haug KB, Brusletto B, Sandvik L, Staff AC, et al. Global miRNA expres-<lb/>sion analysis of serous and clear cell ovarian carcinomas identifies differentially expressed miRNAs <lb/>including miR-200c-3p as a prognostic marker. BMC Cancer. 2014; 14:80. Epub 2014/02/12. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1186/1471-2407-14-80 PMID: 24512620; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3928323. <lb/>24. Cao Q, Lu K, Dai S, Hu Y, Fan W. Clinicopathological and prognostic implications of the miR-200 family <lb/>in patients with epithelial ovarian cancer. Int J Clin Exp Pathol. 2014; 7(5):2392-401. Epub 2014/06/27. <lb/>PMID: 24966949; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4069884. <lb/>25. Zuberi M, Mir R, Das J, Ahmad I, Javid J, Yadav P, et al. Expression of serum miR-200a, miR-200b, <lb/>and miR-200c as candidate biomarkers in epithelial ovarian cancer and their association with clinico-<lb/>pathological features. Clin Transl Oncol. 2015; 17(10):779-87. Epub 2015/06/13. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s12094-015-1303-1 PMID: 26063644. <lb/>26. Meng X, Muller V, Milde-Langosch K, Trillsch F, Pantel K, Schwarzenbach H. Diagnostic and prognostic <lb/>relevance of circulating exosomal miR-373, miR-200a, miR-200b and miR-200c in patients with epithe-<lb/>lial ovarian cancer. Oncotarget. 2016; 7(13):16923-35. Epub 2016/03/05. https://doi.org/10.18632/ <lb/>oncotarget.7850 PMID: 26943577; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4941360. <lb/>27. Mhatre A, Koroth J, Manjunath M, Kumar SS, Gawari R, Choudhary B. Multi-omics analysis of the <lb/>Indian ovarian cancer cohort revealed histotype-specific mutation and gene expression patterns. Front <lb/>Genet. 2023; 14:1102114. Epub 2023/04/24. https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2023.1102114 PMID: <lb/>37091785; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC10117685. <lb/>28. Gumusoglu-Acar E, Gunel T, Hosseini MK, Dogan B, Tekarslan EE, Gurdamar B, et al. Metabolic path-<lb/>ways of potential miRNA biomarkers derived from liquid biopsy in epithelial ovarian cancer. Oncol Lett. <lb/>2023; 25(4):142. Epub 2023/03/14. https://doi.org/10.3892/ol.2023.13728 PMID: 36909377; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMC9996378. <lb/>29. Guan W, Cui H, Huang P, Chun WJ, Lee JW, Kim H, et al. miR-200b/200a/429 Cluster Stimulates Ovar-<lb/>ian Cancer Development by Targeting ING5. J Oncol. 2020; 2020:3404059. Epub 2020/05/08. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1155/2020/3404059 PMID: 32377191; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7193301. <lb/>30. Hu X, Macdonald DM, Huettner PC, Feng Z, El Naqa IM, Schwarz JK, et al. A miR-200 microRNA clus-<lb/>ter as prognostic marker in advanced ovarian cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2009; 114(3):457-64. Epub <lb/>2009/06/09. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2009.05.022 PMID: 19501389. <lb/>31. Leskela S, Leandro-Garcia LJ, Mendiola M, Barriuso J, Inglada-Perez L, Munoz I, et al. The miR-200 <lb/>family controls beta-tubulin III expression and is associated with paclitaxel-based treatment response <lb/>and progression-free survival in ovarian cancer patients. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2011; 18(1):85-95. <lb/>Epub 2010/11/06. https://doi.org/10.1677/ERC-10-0148 PMID: 21051560. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>32. Marchini S, Cavalieri D, Fruscio R, Calura E, Garavaglia D, Fuso Nerini I, et al. Association between <lb/>miR-200c and the survival of patients with stage I epithelial ovarian cancer: a retrospective study of two <lb/>independent tumour tissue collections. Lancet Oncol. 2011; 12(3):273-85. Epub 2011/02/25. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70012-2 PMID: 21345725. <lb/>33. Cittelly DM, Dimitrova I, Howe EN, Cochrane DR, Jean A, Spoelstra NS, et al. Restoration of miR-200c <lb/>to ovarian cancer reduces tumor burden and increases sensitivity to paclitaxel. Mol Cancer Ther. 2012; <lb/>11(12):2556-65. Epub 2012/10/18. https://doi.org/10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-12-0463 PMID: 23074172; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3519949. <lb/>34. Prislei S, Martinelli E, Mariani M, Raspaglio G, Sieber S, Ferrandina G, et al. MiR-200c and HuR in ovar-<lb/>ian cancer. BMC Cancer. 2013; 13:72. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2407-13-72 PMID: 23394580; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3576328. <lb/>35. Pecot CV, Rupaimoole R, Yang D, Akbani R, Ivan C, Lu C, et al. Tumour angiogenesis regulation by the <lb/>miR-200 family. Nat Commun. 2013; 4:2427. https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms3427 PMID: 24018975; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3904438. <lb/>36. Wang L, Wang B, Fang M, Guo F, Cui M. Identification of microRNAs and target genes involved in <lb/>serous ovarian carcinoma and their influence on survival. Eur J Gynaecol Oncol. 2014; 35(6):655-61. <lb/>Epub 2015/01/06. PMID: 25556270. <lb/>37. Xu S, Xu P, Wu W, Ou Y, Xu J, Zhang G, et al. The biphasic expression pattern of miR-200a and E-cad-<lb/>herin in epithelial ovarian cancer and its correlation with clinicopathological features. Curr Pharm Des. <lb/>2014; 20(11):1888-95. Epub 2013/07/31. https://doi.org/10.2174/13816128113199990523 PMID: <lb/>23888941. <lb/>38. Bagnoli M, Canevari S, Califano D, Losito S, Maio MD, Raspagliesi F, et al. Development and validation <lb/>of a microRNA-based signature (MiROvaR) to predict early relapse or progression of epithelial ovarian <lb/>cancer: a cohort study. Lancet Oncol. 2016; 17(8):1137-46. Epub 2016/07/13. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S1470-2045(16)30108-5 PMID: 27402147. <lb/>39. Huang X, Yan Y, Gui A, Zhu S, Qiu S, Chen F, et al. A Regulatory Loop Involving miR-200c and NF-kap-<lb/>paB Modulates Mortalin Expression and Increases Cisplatin Sensitivity in an Ovarian Cancer Cell Line <lb/>Model. Int J Mol Sci. 2022; 23(23). Epub 2022/12/12. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms232315300 PMID: <lb/>36499626; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9737914. <lb/>40. Bi Y, Guo S, Xu X, Kong P, Cui H, Yan T, et al. Decreased ZNF750 promotes angiogenesis in a para-<lb/>crine manner via activating DANCR/miR-4707-3p/FOXC2 axis in esophageal squamous cell carci-<lb/>noma. Cell Death Dis. 2020; 11(4):296. Epub 2020/04/29. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41419-020-2492-2 <lb/>PMID: 32341351; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7186230. <lb/>41. Suo HB, Zhang KC, Zhao J. MiR-200a promotes cell invasion and migration of ovarian carcinoma by <lb/>targeting PTEN. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2018; 22(13):4080-9. Epub 2018/07/20. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.26355/eurrev_201807_15398 PMID: 30024595. <lb/>42. Greenaway J, Moorehead R, Shaw P, Petrik J. Epithelial-stromal interaction increases cell proliferation, <lb/>survival and tumorigenicity in a mouse model of human epithelial ovarian cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2008; <lb/>108(2):385-94. Epub 2007/11/27. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2007.10.035 PMID: 18036641. <lb/>43. Gregory PA, Bert AG, Paterson EL, Barry SC, Tsykin A, Farshid G, et al. The miR-200 family and miR-<lb/>205 regulate epithelial to mesenchymal transition by targeting ZEB1 and SIP1. NatCell Biol. 2008; 10 <lb/>(5):593-601. https://doi.org/10.1038/ncb1722 PMID: 18376396 <lb/>44. Jones R, Watson K, Bruce A, Nersesian S, Kitz J, Moorehead R. Re-expression of miR-200c sup-<lb/>presses proliferation, colony formation and in vivo tumor growth of murine claudin-low mammary tumor <lb/>cells. Oncotarget. 2017; 8(14):23727-49. Epub 2017/04/21. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.15829 <lb/>PMID: 28423599; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5410340. <lb/>45. Jones RA, Campbell CI, Gunther EJ, Chodosh LA, Petrik JJ, Khokha R, et al. Transgenic overexpres-<lb/>sion of IGF-IR disrupts mammary ductal morphogenesis and induces tumor formation. Oncogene. <lb/>2007; 26(11):1636-44. Epub 2006/09/06. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc.1209955 PMID: 16953219. <lb/>46. Simpson KE, Staikos CA, Watson KL, Moorehead RA. Loss of MXRA8 Delays Mammary Tumor Devel-<lb/>opment and Impairs Metastasis. Int J Mol Sci. 2023; 24(18). Epub 2023/09/28. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>ijms241813730 PMID: 37762032. <lb/>47. Watson KL, Jones RA, Bruce A, Moorehead RA. The miR-200b/200a/429 cluster prevents metastasis <lb/>and induces dormancy in a murine claudin-low mammary tumor cell line. Exp Cell Res. 2018; 369 <lb/>(1):17-26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yexcr.2018.04.024 PMID: 29702103. <lb/>48. Simpson K, Conquer-van Heumen G, Watson KL, Roth M, Martin CJ, Moorehead RA. Re-expression of <lb/>miR-200s in claudin-low mammary tumor cells alters cell shape and reduces proliferation and invasion <lb/>potentially through modulating other miRNAs and SUZ12 regulated genes. Cancer Cell Int. 2021; 21 <lb/>(1):89. Epub 2021/02/06. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12935-021-01784-4 PMID: 33541373; PubMed Cen-<lb/>tral PMCID: PMC7863273. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>49. Chen EY, Tan CM, Kou Y, Duan Q, Wang Z, Meirelles GV, et al. Enrichr: interactive and collaborative <lb/>HTML5 gene list enrichment analysis tool. BMC Bioinformatics. 2013; 14:128. Epub 2013/04/17. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-14-128 PMID: 23586463; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3637064. <lb/>50. Kuleshov MV, Jones MR, Rouillard AD, Fernandez NF, Duan Q, Wang Z, et al. Enrichr: a comprehen-<lb/>sive gene set enrichment analysis web server 2016 update. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016; 44(W1):W90-7. <lb/>Epub 2016/05/05. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw377 PMID: 27141961; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC4987924. <lb/>51. Sticht C, De La Torre C, Parveen A, Gretz N. miRWalk: An online resource for prediction of microRNA <lb/>binding sites. PLoS One. 2018; 13(10):e0206239. Epub 2018/10/20. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0206239 PMID: 30335862; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6193719. <lb/>52. Simpson K, Conquer-Van Heumen G, Watson K.L., Roth M., Martin C.J., Moorehead R.A. Re-expres-<lb/>sion of miR-200s in claudin-low mammary tumor cells alters cell shape and reduces proliferation and <lb/>invasion potentially through modulating other miRNAs and SUZ12 regulated genes. Cancer Cell Inter-<lb/>national. 2021;(accepted). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12935-021-01784-4 PMID: 33541373 <lb/>53. Wang AQ, Lv M, Xu YH, Xie PM, Dong YY. MiR-200b-5p inhibits proliferation of ovarian cancer cells by <lb/>targeting ATAD2 and regulating PI3K/AKT signaling pathway. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2020; 24 <lb/>(19):9860-8. Epub 2020/10/23. https://doi.org/10.26355/eurrev_202010_23196 PMID: 33090389. <lb/>54. Chen D, Zhang Y, Wang J, Chen J, Yang C, Cai K, et al. MicroRNA-200c overexpression inhibits tumor-<lb/>igenicity and metastasis of CD117+CD44+ ovarian cancer stem cells by regulating epithelial-mesen-<lb/>chymal transition. J Ovarian Res. 2013; 6(1):50. Epub 2013/07/12. https://doi.org/10.1186/1757-2215-<lb/>6-50 PMID: 23842108; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3729499. <lb/>55. Wahab NA, Othman Z, Nasri NWM, Mokhtar MH, Ibrahim SF, Hamid AA, et al. Inhibition of miR-141 <lb/>and miR-200a Increase DLC-1 and ZEB2 Expression, Enhance Migration and Invasion in Metastatic <lb/>Serous Ovarian Cancer. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020; 17(8). Epub 2020/04/23. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.3390/ijerph17082766 PMID: 32316405; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7215320. <lb/>56. Yang C, Li H, Zhang T, Chu Y, Chen D, Zuo J. miR-200c overexpression inhibits the invasion and <lb/>tumorigenicity of epithelial ovarian cancer cells by suppressing lncRNA HOTAIR in mice. J Cell Bio-<lb/>chem. 2020; 121(2):1514-23. Epub 2019/09/20. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcb.29387 PMID: 31535411. <lb/>57. Lu YM, Shang C, Ou YL, Yin D, Li YN, Li X, et al. miR-200c modulates ovarian cancer cell metastasis <lb/>potential by targeting zinc finger E-box-binding homeobox 2 (ZEB2) expression. Med Oncol. 2014; 31 <lb/>(8):134. Epub 2014/07/24. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12032-014-0134-1 PMID: 25052237. <lb/>58. Wu Q, Guo R, Lin M, Zhou B, Wang Y. MicroRNA-200a inhibits CD133/1+ ovarian cancer stem cells <lb/>migration and invasion by targeting E-cadherin repressor ZEB2. Gynecol Oncol. 2011; 122(1):149-54. <lb/>Epub 2011/05/03. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2011.03.026 PMID: 21529905. <lb/>59. Guo QY, Song JN, Chen YM, Yuan HN, Xue WS, Sun Y, et al. IL-6 regulates epithelial ovarian cancer <lb/>EMT, invasion, and metastasis by modulating Let-7c and miR-200c through the STAT3/HIF-1alpha <lb/>pathway. Med Oncol. 2024; 41(6):155. Epub 2024/05/15. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12032-024-02328-2 <lb/>PMID: 38744773. <lb/>60. Shi C, Yang Y, Zhang L, Yu J, Qin S, Xu H, et al. MiR-200a-3p promoted the malignant behaviors of <lb/>ovarian cancer cells through regulating PCDH9. Onco Targets Ther. 2019; 12:8329-38. Epub 2019/10/ <lb/>22. https://doi.org/10.2147/OTT.S220339 PMID: 31632082; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6790212. <lb/>61. Liu N, Zhong L, Zeng J, Zhang X, Yang Q, Liao D, et al. Upregulation of microRNA-200a associates <lb/>with tumor proliferation, CSCs phenotype and chemosensitivity in ovarian cancer. Neoplasma. 2015; 62 <lb/>(4):550-9. Epub 2015/05/23. https://doi.org/10.4149/neo_2015_066 PMID: 25997962. <lb/>62. Ibrahim FF, Jamal R, Syafruddin SE, Ab Mutalib NS, Saidin S, MdZin RR, et al. MicroRNA-200c and <lb/>microRNA-31 regulate proliferation, colony formation, migration and invasion in serous ovarian cancer. <lb/>J Ovarian Res. 2015; 8:56. Epub 2015/08/12. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13048-015-0186-7 PMID: <lb/>26260454; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4531514. <lb/>63. Choi PW, So WW, Yang J, Liu S, Tong KK, Kwan KM, et al. MicroRNA-200 family governs ovarian <lb/>inclusion cyst formation and mode of ovarian cancer spread. Oncogene. 2020; 39(20):4045-60. Epub <lb/>2020/03/28. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41388-020-1264-x PMID: 32214198. <lb/>64. Ankasha SJ, Shafiee MN, Abdul Wahab N, Raja Ali RA, Mokhtar NM. Oncogenic Role of miR-200c-3p <lb/>in High-Grade Serous Ovarian Cancer Progression via Targeting the 3&apos;-Untranslated Region of DLC1. <lb/>Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021; 18(11). Epub 2021/06/03. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>ijerph18115741 PMID: 34071861; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8198916. <lb/>65. Lili LN, Huang AD, Zhang M, Wang L, McDonald LD, Matyunina LV, et al. Time-course analysis of <lb/>microRNA-induced mesenchymal-to-epithelial transition underscores the complexity of the underlying <lb/>molecular processes. Cancer Lett. 2018; 428:184-91. Epub 2018/05/08. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>canlet.2018.05.001 PMID: 29733963. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>66. Zhang M, Jabbari N, Satpathy M, Matyunina LV, Wang Y, McDonald LD, et al. Sequence diverse miR-<lb/>NAs converge to induce mesenchymal-to-epithelial transition in ovarian cancer cells through direct and <lb/>indirect regulatory controls. Cancer Lett. 2019; 459:168-75. Epub 2019/06/05. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>canlet.2019.05.039 PMID: 31163194. <lb/>67. Chen J, Wang L, Matyunina LV, Hill CG, McDonald JF. Overexpression of miR-429 induces mesenchy-<lb/>mal-to-epithelial transition (MET) in metastatic ovarian cancer cells. Gynecol Oncol. 2011; 121(1):200-<lb/>5. Epub 2011/02/01. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2010.12.339 PMID: 21277012. <lb/>68. Martin CJ, Moorehead RA. Polycomb repressor complex 2 function in breast cancer (Review). Int J <lb/>Oncol. 2020; 57(5):1085-94. Epub 2021/01/26. https://doi.org/10.3892/ijo.2020.5122 PMID: <lb/>33491744; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7549536. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>miR-200s inhibit proliferation and invasion in ovarian cancer cells <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0307178 July 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 17 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>