<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Risk of Self-Reported Penicillin Allergy Despite Removal of Penicillin Allergy Label</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ana Maria</forename>
          <surname>Copaescu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sara</forename>
          <surname>Vogrin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Abby</forename>
          <surname>Douglas</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Nicholas A.</forename>
          <surname>Turner</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Elizabeth J.</forename>
          <surname>Phillips</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Natasha E.</forename>
          <surname>Holmes</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jason A.</forename>
          <surname>Trubiano</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T10:42:05.448Z">11/12/2025 10:42:05 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1001$1$jamanetworkopen.2024.29621</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.29621</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Ana Maria Copaescu, Sara Vogrin, Abby Douglas, Nicholas A. Turner, Elizabeth J. Phillips, Natasha E. Holmes, Jason A. Trubiano. (2024). Risk of Self-Reported Penicillin Allergy Despite Removal of Penicillin Allergy Label. JAMA Network Open, 7(8), e2429621. DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.29621</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T10:41:58.326854Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T10:41:58.326854Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Original Investigation | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Epidemiology and Outcomes of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/>Jennifer A. Flemming, MD, MAS; Maya Djerboua, MSc; Orli Chapman, MD; Oyedeji Ayonrinde, MD, MBA; Norah A. Terrault, MD, MPH <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IMPORTANCE Alcohol-associated hepatitis (AH) has high mortality, and rates are increasing among <lb/>adolescents and young adults (AYAs). <lb/>OBJECTIVE To define the sex-specific epidemiology of AH in AYAs and the association between <lb/>female sex and liver-related outcomes after a first presentation of AH. <lb/>DESIGN, SETTING, AND PARTICIPANTS A retrospective, population-based cohort study of <lb/>routinely collected health care data held at ICES from Ontario, Canada, was conducted. Data on AYAs <lb/>(age, 13-39 years) with first presentation of AH without a history of cirrhosis and/or decompensation <lb/>from January 1 to December 31, 2022, were included in the analysis. <lb/>EXPOSURES Study year and female sex. <lb/>MAIN OUTCOME AND MEASURES Overall and sex-specific yearly rates of AH were compared using <lb/>Poisson regression and rate ratios (RRs). Associations between female sex and incident cirrhosis <lb/>and/or decompensation were evaluated using competing risks regression, and liver-related mortality <lb/>by sex was evaluated with cumulative incidence functions. <lb/>RESULTS A total of 3340 AYAs with AH were identified. Median age was 33 (IQR, 28-36) years, and <lb/>the population included 1190 (36%) females and 2150 (64%) males. Rates of AH increased by 8% <lb/>per year (RR, 1.08; 95% CI, 1.07-1.09), with yearly rates increasing faster among females (RR, 1.11; <lb/>95% CI, 1.09-1.12) than males (RR, 1.07; 95% CI, 1.06-1.07). A total of 2374 individuals (71%) were alive <lb/>without cirrhosis 6 months after AH presentation. Of those, 527 (22%) developed incident cirrhosis <lb/>and/or decompensation after a median follow-up of 4 (IQR, 2-9) years (37% females vs 29% males; <lb/>P &lt; .001). After adjustment, female sex was associated with a 47% higher subhazard of cirrhosis <lb/>and/or decompensation compared with male sex (38%) (subhazard, 1.47; 95% CI, 1.23-1.76; <lb/>P &lt; .001). The cumulative incidence of liver-related mortality at 10 years was higher among females <lb/>(11.0%; 95% CI, 8.3%-14.2%) than males (6.9%; 95% CI, 5.4%-8.6%) (P = .01). <lb/>CONCLUSIONS AND RELEVANCE Over the past 2 decades, the rates of AH among AYAs increased <lb/>significantly, with the greatest increase observed among females. The findings of this study suggest <lb/>sex-specific interventions to prevent the development of AH and the progression to cirrhosis after <lb/>an episode of AH are needed. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 <lb/>Key Points <lb/>Question Is sex associated with long-<lb/>term liver-related outcomes among <lb/>adolescents and young adults after first <lb/>presentation of alcohol-associated <lb/>hepatitis? <lb/>Findings In a cohort study of 3340 <lb/>adolescents and young adults from <lb/>Ontario, Canada, female sex was <lb/>associated with a 50% higher risk of <lb/>developing cirrhosis compared with <lb/>male sex. The rate of liver-related <lb/>mortality also was higher <lb/>among females. <lb/>Meaning The findings of this study <lb/>suggest that sex-specific interventions <lb/>for alcohol-associated hepatitis among <lb/>adolescents and young adults are <lb/>urgently needed. <lb/>+ Supplemental content <lb/>Author affiliations and article information are <lb/>listed at the end of this article. <lb/>Open Access. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. <lb/>JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/>1/11 <lb/>Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Worldwide, alcohol is responsible for 13.5% of deaths among individuals aged 20 to 39 years. 1 <lb/>Alcohol-associated liver disease (ALD) is a spectrum from reversible hepatic steatosis to cirrhosis and <lb/>liver failure with the most severe acute form of ALD being alcohol-associated hepatitis (AH). 2 <lb/>Alcohol-associated hepatitis has a 30-day mortality rate ranging from 30% to 50% for those with <lb/>severe disease, and historic studies have shown AH is associated with a high risk of progression to <lb/>cirrhosis in those who survive. 3 <lb/>Recent studies have consistently shown rates of AH are increasing. 4,5 The reasons for these <lb/>trends are not clear but hypothesized to be strongly correlated with governmental alcohol policies. 6 <lb/>Of most concern, adolescents and young adults (AYAs) (age, 13-39 years) have developed <lb/>disproportionate increases in AH-related harms. 7 The COVID-19 pandemic further exacerbated these <lb/>trends with recent data both from the US 5 and Canada 8 showing increases in hospitalizations for AH, <lb/>especially in young females. <lb/>Given the surging rates of AH among AYAs, there is an urgent need to identify risk groups and <lb/>short-and long-term outcomes to facilitate targeted interventions and chronic disease management <lb/>plans. Furthermore, sex-specific low-risk alcohol consumption guidelines recognize that, for the <lb/>same amount of alcohol consumption, females are at higher risk of ALD compared with males 9 due <lb/>to biologic, 10 cultural, and social factors. However, the influence of sex on the development of major <lb/>liver-related outcomes, such as cirrhosis and decompensation, among AYAs with AH is understudied. <lb/>Our objectives were to define the epidemiology and demographic characteristics of AYAs after an <lb/>initial presentation of AH and evaluate the possible association between sex and long-term liver-<lb/>related outcomes after an initial presentation of AH. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study Design and Data Sources <lb/>We conducted a population-based retrospective cohort study in Ontario, Canada, from January 1 to <lb/>December 31, 2022. This study used data from ICES, an independent, nonprofit research institute <lb/>that houses a large electronic repository of datasets for all Ontario residents who are eligible for the <lb/>province&apos;s single-payer health care system (Ontario Health Insurance Plan). 11 Due to the retrospective <lb/>nature of this study, a waiver of informed consent was obtained from the Queen&apos;s University Health <lb/>Sciences Research Ethics Board. This study used multiple administrative datasets (eTable 1 in <lb/>Supplement 1), and these datasets were linked using unique encoded identifiers and analyzed at <lb/>ICES. The study protocol received ethics approval from the Queen&apos;s University Health Sciences <lb/>Research Ethics Board and was conducted in accordance with the Strengthening the Reporting of <lb/>Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) reporting guideline for observational studies. <lb/>Study Populations <lb/>Adolescents and young adults aged 13 to 39 years with an incident diagnosis of AH were identified <lb/>through inpatient hospital admissions and emergency department (ED) records. We used the <lb/>International Classification of Diseases, 9th Revision (ICD-9) and International Statistical Classification <lb/>of Diseases and Related Health Problems, 10th Revision (ICD-10) to identify AH as the main or most <lb/>responsible diagnosis for the hospital admission or ED visit (ICD-9 code 571.1; ICD-10 code K70.1) <lb/>associated with a positive predictive value for AH of 90%. 12 If individuals had multiple AH <lb/>presentations, the index event was used. Incident diagnoses were captured from January 1, 2002, to <lb/>December 31, 2021, with a lookback window to the earliest available data and follow-up was until <lb/>December 31, 2022. The type of AH presentation was defined as diagnosis and discharge from the ED <lb/>vs hospital admission. <lb/>We excluded those who had our outcomes before the first AH presentation (cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation using validated definitions in ICES data; history of liver transplant (LT) identified <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>through billing claims (eTable 2 in Supplement 1) and those with an invalid health card number and no <lb/>Ontario Health Insurance Plan eligibility. We also identified a cohort at risk of outcomes if they <lb/>survived their first presentation of AH by further excluding individuals who died or developed <lb/>cirrhosis and/or decompensation during their initial AH presentation or within 6 months after ED or <lb/>hospital discharge to exclude prevalent disease. <lb/>Exposures, Outcomes, Demographics, and Covariates <lb/>Full details of definitions for exposures, outcomes, demographic characteristics, and covariates are <lb/>in eTable 2 and the eMethods in Supplement 1. Sex was the primary exposure obtained from the <lb/>Registered Persons Database. The outcomes of interest included all-cause mortality with death date <lb/>obtained from the Registered Persons Database (up to December 31, 2022). Incident cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation (including ascites, variceal bleeding, encephalopathy, and hepatorenal syndrome) <lb/>were defined using validated definitions. 13 Liver transplant was identified using billing codes. Cause-<lb/>specific mortality was defined to the end of 2018 using linkage to the Office of the Registrar General <lb/>Death database (liver-related, external, mental health/behavioral, and other) (eTable 2 in <lb/>Supplement 1). <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>Baseline characteristics were stratified by sex and type of presentation (hospital admission vs ED <lb/>only). A denominator of AYAs in Ontario from 2002 to 2021 was built from the Registered Persons <lb/>Database and used to calculate the overall and sex-stratified yearly incidence rates of AH with 95% <lb/>CIs. Patients were considered at risk for incident AH until diagnosis of cirrhosis, receipt of LT, death, <lb/>40th birthday, loss of Ontario Health Insurance Plan coverage, and maximum study date (December <lb/>31, 2022). Poisson regression was used to evaluate the overall and sex-specific yearly changes of <lb/>rates of AH over the study period using rate ratios (RRs). <lb/>Fine and Gray competing risk analysis was performed to assess the association of sex with each <lb/>outcome as follows: all-cause mortality with LT as a competing event, and cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation with mortality and LT as competing events. For the competing risk analysis for <lb/>overall mortality, follow-up started at the date of AH presentation and was adjusted a priori for age, <lb/>type of presentation (inpatient vs ED only), cirrhosis during index AH presentation, Elixhauser <lb/>comorbidity index, rural residence, immigrant or refugee status, and income quintile. For the <lb/>competing risk analysis of the outcome of incident cirrhosis, follow-up started 6 months after the <lb/>index and was adjusted for the same covariates except cirrhosis. Subdistribution hazard ratios (sHRs) <lb/>with 95% CIs were computed to quantify the association between sex and outcomes. <lb/>Nonparametric competing risk regression was performed to estimate the overall and <lb/>sex-stratified cumulative incidence function plots for liver-related mortality (with LT and non-liver <lb/>deaths as competing events) in addition to all-cause mortality and cirrhosis. The Gray test was <lb/>conducted to test for statistical differences between the sex-stratified cumulative incidences. 14 <lb/>All statistical findings were evaluated at a significance level of P &lt; .05 with 2-sided, unpaired <lb/>testing. All data were analyzed using SAS Enterprise Guide, version 7.1 (SAS Institute Inc). <lb/>Results <lb/>Study Population <lb/>Overall, 3340 AYAs were identified with first presentation of AH during the study and who did not <lb/>have a history of cirrhosis or decompensation (Figure 1, Table 1). The median follow-up was 5 (IQR, <lb/>2-10) years and most required hospitalization (2423 [74%]) with a median length of stay of 4 (IQR, <lb/>3-8) days. The median age was 33 (IQR, 28-36) years, 1190 (36%) were female, 2150 (64%) were <lb/>male, and 434 (13%) were immigrants or refugees with a median time from arrival in Ontario to AH of <lb/>14 (IQR, 9-21) years. Most resided in neighborhoods of the lowest income quintile (32%) and highest <lb/>quintiles for material deprivation (27%) and residential instability (30%). Within 2 years before AH <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>presentation, most (2365 [71%]) had ED or inpatient health care encounters related to the <lb/>consequences of alcohol not due to AH, 1136 (34%) had encounters for other substance use, and <lb/>over half (1912 [57%]) had encounters for mental health. Viral hepatitis was present in 8% (n = 282) <lb/>and HIV in 0.6% (n = 19) of the AYAs. When stratified by sex, females vs males were more likely to <lb/>reside in a rural location (22% vs 15%; P &lt; .001) and have mental health encounters within 2 years of <lb/>the index presentation (64% vs 53%; P &lt; .001). More males were immigrants or refugees (16% vs <lb/>7%; P &lt; .001) and resided in the most ethnically diverse neighborhoods (26% vs 17%; P &lt; .001). <lb/>At the time of AH, 624 individuals (19%) received diagnoses of cirrhosis or decompensation and <lb/>a further 261 (7%) developed these conditions within 6 months, representing prevalent disease. <lb/>Thus, 885 AYAs (26%) were considered to have cirrhosis or decompensation at index AH <lb/>presentation. In those with available laboratory data within up to 7 days before or 7 days after AH <lb/>presentation (1079 [32%]), the median model for end-stage liver disease (MELD-Na) score was 15 <lb/>(IQR, 9-21), and 321 individuals (30%) had a MELD-Na score of 21 or higher, consistent with severe <lb/>AH. The median MELD-Na score was higher among those hospitalized compared with those <lb/>discharged from the ED (16 [IQR, 10-23] vs 9 [IQR, 7-13]). During follow-up, 25% AYAs died (n = 844) <lb/>and less than 1% (n = 23) received LT. <lb/>Figure 1. Development of a Cohort of Adolescents and Young Adults (AYAs) (Age, 13-39 Years) <lb/>With Incident Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis (AH) From 2002-2021 <lb/>3806 AYAs with first presentation of AH, 2002-2001 <lb/>3340 With first presentation of AH without cirrhosis a <lb/>2374 AYAs alive at 6 mo postdischarge for <lb/>first presentation of AH at risk for cirrhosis b <lb/>917 Discharged from ED (26%) <lb/>2423 Hospital admissions (74%) <lb/>13 Excluded <lb/>8 No OHIP eligibility <lb/>2 Non-Ontario resident <lb/>2 History of liver transplant <lb/>1 Invalid identifier <lb/>650 Excluded <lb/>624 Cirrhosis and/or decompensation <lb/>during ED visit or admission <lb/>25 Died during hospitalization <lb/>1 Loss of OHIP <lb/>316 Excluded within 6 mo of discharge <lb/>261 Cirrhosis and/or decompensation <lb/>46 Died <lb/>9 Loss of OHIP eligibility <lb/>453 Excluded (history of cirrhosis <lb/>and/or decompensation before <lb/>AH presentation) <lb/>3793 With first presentation of AH <lb/>2690 AYAs who survived first presentation of AH <lb/>without cirrhosis and/or decompensation or LT <lb/>ED indicates emergency department; LT, liver <lb/>transplant; OHIP, Ontario Health Insurance Plan. <lb/>a Cohort used for overall and liver-related mortality <lb/>outcomes. <lb/>b Cohort used for cirrhosis and/or decompensation <lb/>outcomes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Individuals in Ontario Aged 13 to 39 Years With First Presentation of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>Without Known History of Cirrhosis, Decompensation, or LT: 2002-2021 <lb/>Variable <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>Overall (N = 3340) Females (n = 1190) Males (n = 2150) <lb/>Age at presentation, median (IQR), y <lb/>33 (28-36) <lb/>32 (27-36) <lb/>33 (28-37) <lb/>Rural residence a <lb/>584 (18) <lb/>257 (22) <lb/>327 (15) <lb/>Missing <lb/>16 (0.5) <lb/>&lt;6 (&lt;0.5) <lb/>12 (0.5) <lb/>Recent immigrant/refugee b <lb/>434 (13) <lb/>86 (7) <lb/>348 (16) <lb/>History of ED visit/inpatient admission for alcohol c <lb/>2365 (71) <lb/>856 (72) <lb/>1509 (70) <lb/>History of mental illness c <lb/>1912 (57) <lb/>763 (64) <lb/>1149 (53) <lb/>History of substance use c <lb/>1136 (34) <lb/>416 (35) <lb/>720 (34) <lb/>Viral hepatitis <lb/>282 (8) <lb/>121 (10) <lb/>161 (7) <lb/>ECI <lb/>0-2 <lb/>3072 (92) <lb/>1084 (91) <lb/>1989 (93) <lb/>3-5 <lb/>243 (7) <lb/>98 (8) <lb/>145 (7) <lb/>≥ 6 <lb/>24 (1) <lb/>8 (1) <lb/>16 (1) <lb/>MELD-Na, median (IQR) d <lb/>15 (9-21) <lb/>14 (9-20) <lb/>15 (9-22) <lb/>&lt;10 <lb/>319 (30) <lb/>123 (29) <lb/>196 (30) <lb/>10-20 <lb/>439 (40) <lb/>180 (43) <lb/>259 (39) <lb/>&gt;20 <lb/>321 (30) <lb/>114 (27) <lb/>207 (31) <lb/>Income quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>1080 (32) <lb/>436 (37) <lb/>644 (30) <lb/>2 <lb/>667 (20) <lb/>211 (18) <lb/>456 (21) <lb/>3 <lb/>553 (17) <lb/>195 (16) <lb/>358 (17) <lb/>4 <lb/>537 (16) <lb/>181 (15) <lb/>356 (17) <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>462 (14) <lb/>154 (13) <lb/>308 (14) <lb/>Missing <lb/>41 (1) <lb/>13 (1) <lb/>28 (1) <lb/>Material deprivation quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>479 (14) <lb/>167 (14) <lb/>312 (15) <lb/>2 <lb/>481 (14) <lb/>158 (13) <lb/>323 (15) <lb/>3 <lb/>547 (16) <lb/>169 (14) <lb/>378 (18) <lb/>4 <lb/>663 (20) <lb/>228 (19) <lb/>435 (20) <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>906 (27) <lb/>348 (29) <lb/>558 (26) <lb/>Missing <lb/>264 (8) <lb/>120 (10) <lb/>144 (7) <lb/>Ethnic diversity quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>565 (17) <lb/>203 (17) <lb/>362 (17) <lb/>2 <lb/>531 (16) <lb/>215 (18) <lb/>316 (15) <lb/>3 <lb/>616 (19) <lb/>227 (19) <lb/>389 (18) <lb/>4 <lb/>597 (18) <lb/>223 (19) <lb/>374 (17) <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>767 (23) <lb/>202 (17) <lb/>565 (26) <lb/>Missing <lb/>264 (8) <lb/>120 (10) <lb/>144 (7) <lb/>Residential instability quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>454 (14) <lb/>120 (10) <lb/>334 (16) <lb/>2 <lb/>448 (13) <lb/>137 (12) <lb/>311 (15) <lb/>3 <lb/>539 (16) <lb/>202 (17) <lb/>337 (16) <lb/>4 <lb/>618 (19) <lb/>246 (21) <lb/>372 (17) <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>1017 (30) <lb/>365 (31) <lb/>652 (30) <lb/>Missing <lb/>264 (8) <lb/>120 (10) <lb/>144 (7) <lb/>Follow-up time, median (IQR), y <lb/>5 (2-10) <lb/>5 (2-9) <lb/>5 (2-10) <lb/>Died anytime during follow-up <lb/>844 (25) <lb/>299 (25) <lb/>545 (25) <lb/>Liver transplant <lb/>23 (&lt;1) <lb/>&lt;6 (&lt;1) <lb/>17-22 (&lt;1) <lb/>Abbreviations: ECI, Elixhauser comorbidity index; ED, <lb/>emergency department; LT, liver transplant; MELD-Na, <lb/>model for end-stage liver disease. <lb/>a Rural defined as location with less than 10 000 <lb/>inhabitants. <lb/>b Immigrant or refugee who entered Canada <lb/>after 1985. <lb/>c History within 2 years of alcohol-associated hepatitis <lb/>presentation. <lb/>d MELD-Na if available up to 7 days before or after <lb/>presentation; missing values for 2261 <lb/>individuals (68%). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Epidemiology of AH in AYAs <lb/>The annual incidence rate of first presentation of AH in AYAs increased from 2.43 per 100 000 <lb/>person-years in 2002 to 6.82 per 100 000 person-years in 2021, corresponding to a yearly increase <lb/>of 8% (RR, 1.08; 95% CI, 1.07-1.09; P &lt; .001). We next stratified by sex over eras (Figure 2A), with <lb/>rates increasing faster among females (RR, 1.11; 95% CI, 1.09-1.12) than males (RR, 1.07; 95% CI, 1.06-<lb/>1.07). When stratified by hospitalization status (Figure 2B; eTable 3 in Supplement 1), rates of AH <lb/>requiring hospitalization (RR, 1.09; 95% CI, 1.08-1.10) increased over the study period more than the <lb/>rates of presentation to the ED only (RR, 1.05; 95% CI, 1.04-1.06). <lb/>Overall and Liver-Associated Mortality Outcomes <lb/>The cumulative incidence of death at 1 year was 6.9% (95% CI, 6.2%-7.9%), 18.9% at 5 years (95% CI, <lb/>17.4%-20.3%), 29.4% at 10 years (95% CI, 27.5%-31.4%), and 47.7% at 20 years (95% CI, <lb/>43.5%-51.8%). When stratified by sex, there was no association with overall mortality (eFigure 1 in <lb/>Supplement 1). Furthermore, in competing risks regression (Table 2), there was no association <lb/>between female sex and overall mortality (sHR, 1.10; 95% CI, 0.95-1.27). Factors associated with <lb/>mortality included older age (sHR per year, 1.03; 95% CI, 1.02-1.05), rural location (sHR, 0.81; 95% CI, <lb/>0.67-0.97), higher comorbidity (sHR, 1.99; 95% CI, 1.62-2.44), hospitalization at AH index (sHR, 1.40; <lb/>95% CI, 1.19-1.65), and cirrhosis during index AH presentation (sHR, 1.75; 95% CI, 1.48-2.07). <lb/>Among those with available cause of death (to end 2018; n = 461 [55%]) (eFigure 2A in <lb/>Supplement 1), the most common causes were liver-related (149 [32%]), followed by external causes <lb/>(113 [25%], including trauma, accidents, poisoning, and suicide), and mental health/behavioral <lb/>disorders (77 [17%]). Similar proportions of females vs males developed a liver-related death (38% <lb/>vs 29%; P = .07), death from an external cause (26% vs 22%; P = .32), and mental health/behavioral <lb/>disorders (16% vs 18%; P = .53). However, after considering the competing events of LT and <lb/>non-liver-related deaths, the cumulative incidence of liver-related mortality at 10 years was 8.2% <lb/>(95% CI, 6.9%-9.7%) and was higher among females (11.0%; 95% CI, 8.3%-14.2%) compared with <lb/>males (6.9%; 95% CI, 5.4%-8.6%) (P = .01) (eFigure 2B in Supplement 1). <lb/>Association Between Sex and Development of Cirrhosis and Decompensation <lb/>in AYAs With AH <lb/>After excluding AYAs who received a diagnosis of cirrhosis or decompensation, received LT, died, or <lb/>lost Ontario Health Insurance Plan coverage during the index ED visit or admission (650 [19%]), a <lb/>further 9% (n = 316) developed these outcomes within 6 months post index (Figure 1). Therefore, <lb/>71% (n = 2374) of the cohort was alive and at risk of cirrhosis and decompensation during follow-up <lb/>Figure 2. Incidence Rates of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis Among Adolescents and Young Adults in Ontario <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Incidence rate per 100 000 person-years <lb/>Year of presentation <lb/>Stratified by sex <lb/>A <lb/>2022 <lb/>2002 2004 2006 2008 2010 2012 2014 2016 2018 2020 <lb/>Males yearly incidence rate <lb/>Females yearly incidence rate <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Incidence rate per 100 000 person-years <lb/>Year of presentation <lb/>Stratified by hospitalization status <lb/>B <lb/>2022 <lb/>2002 2004 2006 2008 2010 2012 2014 2016 2018 2020 <lb/>Hospitalized yearly incidence rate <lb/>ED-only yearly incidence rate <lb/>Incidence rates stratified by sex (A) and hospitalization status (B). Shaded areas indicate 95% CIs. ED indicates emergency department; RR, rate ratio. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>(eTable 4 in Supplement 1) and were followed up for a median of 4 (IQR, 2-9) years. Among those, <lb/>22% (n = 527) received a diagnosis of cirrhosis after a median of 24 (IQR, 9-50) months, with 42% <lb/>(n = 220) presenting with decompensation. The most common decompensation events were ascites <lb/>(88 [40%]) and variceal bleeding (66 [30%]). The cumulative incidence of cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation at 20 years was 32.5% (95% CI, 29.6%-35.4%), with most developing cirrhosis <lb/>within the first 5 years after the initial AH presentation (20.5%; 95% CI, 18.8%-22.4%). <lb/>When stratified by sex, females were more likely to be diagnosed with cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation vs males (37% vs 28%; P &lt; .001). Of those with cirrhosis, females were more likely <lb/>to present with decompensation vs males (47% vs 38%; P &lt; .001). The cumulative incidence of <lb/>cirrhosis and/or decompensation at 5 years was 24.7% among females (95% CI, 21.4%-28.1%) vs <lb/>18.6% among males (95% CI, 16.5%-20.7%) (P &lt; .001) (eFigure 3 in Supplement 1). After multivariate <lb/>competing risks regression accounting for death and LT as competing events (Table 3), female sex <lb/>was independently associated with a 47% higher subhazard of cirrhosis and/or decompensation <lb/>(sHR, 1.47; 95% CI, 1.23-1.76; P &lt; .001). Other factors associated with cirrhosis and/or <lb/>decompensation included residing in the lowest income neighborhoods (sHR, 1.37; 95% CI, 1.01-1.87), <lb/>older age (per year sHR, 1.04; 95% CI, 1.03-1.06), more comorbidities (sHR, 1.36; 95% CI, 1.01-1.82), <lb/>and residing in an urban location (sHR, 1.29; 95% CI, 1.02-1.65). The need for hospitalization at index <lb/>was not associated with the development of liver-related events (sHR, 1.17; 95% CI, 0.91-1.50). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this population-based study of 3340 AYAs with AH, we observed that in the general population, <lb/>the rates of AH have been increasing rapidly, especially among females. Additionally, we highlight a <lb/>striking sex disparity. Although in absolute numbers more males are affected by AH than females, <lb/>females have higher rates of liver-related mortality and are at an approximately 50% higher risk of <lb/>developing cirrhosis than their male counterparts. These data highlight the evolving epidemic of ALD <lb/>among AYAs occurring in Canada and have broader relevance, given the global nature of increasing <lb/>harms from alcohol use. <lb/>The reasons for increasing prevalence of AH among AYAs are not known; however, we <lb/>hypothesize several factors may be contributing. Changes to alcohol policy that expand alcohol <lb/>Table 2. Competing Risk Regression Analysis Evaluating the Association Between Sex and Overall Mortality <lb/>Among 3340 Adolescents and Young Adults After First Presentation of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>Variable <lb/>Unadjusted <lb/>Adjusted <lb/>sHR (95% CI) <lb/>P value <lb/>sHR (95% CI) <lb/>P value <lb/>Female vs male sex <lb/>1.13 (0.98-1.31) <lb/>.08 <lb/>1.10 (0.95-1.27) <lb/>.21 <lb/>Age, y <lb/>1.04 (1.03-1.05) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.03 (1.02-1.05) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Type of presentation <lb/>ED only <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>Hospital admission <lb/>1.62 (1.38-1.91) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.40 (1.19-1.65) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Cirrhosis at index <lb/>1.92 (1.64-2.26) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.75 (1.48-2.07) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>ECI <lb/>0-2 <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>≥3 <lb/>2.06 (1.69-2.52) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.99 (1.62-2.44) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Rural location <lb/>0.88 (0.74-1.04) <lb/>.14 <lb/>0.81 (0.67-0.97) <lb/>.02 <lb/>Recent immigrant/refugee <lb/>0.94 (1.64-2.26) <lb/>.52 <lb/>0.91 (0.74-1.12) <lb/>.37 <lb/>Income quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>1.12 (0.90-1.40) <lb/>.45 <lb/>1.09 (0.87-1.36) <lb/>.45 <lb/>2 <lb/>1.06 (0.84-1.34) <lb/>.67 <lb/>1.05 (0.83-1.33) <lb/>.67 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.98 (0.76-1.26) <lb/>.87 <lb/>0.98 (0.76-1.26) <lb/>.87 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.91 (0.70-1.18) <lb/>.30 <lb/>0.87 (0.67-1.13) <lb/>.30 <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>Abbreviations: ECI, Elixhauser comorbidity index; ED, <lb/>emergency department; NA, not applicable; sHR, <lb/>subdistribution hazard ratio. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>access are known to be associated with increased harm. 15,16 During our study, the Ontario <lb/>government implemented policies that expanded alcohol access. 17,18 The presence of underlying <lb/>cofactors for liver disease that have been shown to be associated with a higher risk of AH are <lb/>increasing among Canadian AYAs, including obesity, 19 diabetes, 20 and viral hepatitis. 21 In our cohort, <lb/>8% had viral hepatitis and the incidence was higher among females (10%) than males (7%) while <lb/>diabetes was present in 6%, which is much higher than the less than 1% prevalence of both viral <lb/>hepatitis and diabetes in individuals younger than 40 years in the general population. 21 Changes in <lb/>the types of alcohol consumed by AYAs may also be a factor. In both the US and Canada, 22 sales for <lb/>single-serve flavored beverages, such as ciders and coolers, that contain high amounts of both <lb/>alcohol and sugar have more than tripled over the past decade. In the US, data suggest that the <lb/>highest consumers of these beverages are those born after 1980. 23 Most data on the risk of ALD are <lb/>based on consumption of either beer, wine, or spirits, all of which have relatively low sugar content. <lb/>Yet, data have suggested that high fructose consumption also increases the risk of ALD. 24 Whether <lb/>the combination of high alcohol and sugar together influence the natural history of ALD is unknown <lb/>but should be evaluated in future studies, including the impact of comorbid obesity, diabetes, and <lb/>viral hepatitis. <lb/>To our knowledge, there are no data regarding the development of liver-related complications <lb/>among AYAs after an episode of AH. Most studies evaluating the progression from AH to cirrhosis are <lb/>from historic, small, older, predominately male cohorts from the 1970s and 1980s with study designs <lb/>at risk of selection bias and loss to follow-up. In the AYAs cohort in our study, the 5-year overall <lb/>mortality after AH is approximately 25%, with liver-related causes of death most common, followed <lb/>by external injury and mental health conditions. It is noteworthy that more than 50% of this cohort <lb/>had previously contacted health care for mental health conditions, about one-third had presented <lb/>with substance use within the 2 years before AH presentation, and more than two-thirds had health <lb/>care encounters related to alcohol that were not AH within the 2 years before AH presentation. This <lb/>suggests that there are likely missed opportunities to identify those with alcohol use disorder and <lb/>harmful alcohol use before they progress to AH. Additionally, these results support the need for <lb/>comprehensive care for managing treatment of patients with AH inclusive of support for liver <lb/>disease, addictions, and mental health. <lb/>Table 3. Competing Risk Regression Analysis Evaluating the Association Between Sex and Cirrhosis <lb/>and/or Decompensation Among 2374 Adolescents and Young Adults After First Presentation <lb/>of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>Variable <lb/>Unadjusted <lb/>Adjusted <lb/>sHR (95% CI) <lb/>P value <lb/>sHR (95% CI) <lb/>P value <lb/>Female vs male sex <lb/>1.35 (1.13-1.61) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.47 (1.23-1.76) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Age, y <lb/>1.04 (1.03-1.06) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>1.04 (1.03-1.06) <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Type of presentation <lb/>ED only <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>Hospital admission <lb/>1.09 (0.92-1.31) <lb/>.32 <lb/>1.03 (0.86-1.24) <lb/>.73 <lb/>ECI <lb/>0-2 <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>≥3 <lb/>1.49 (1.12-1.98) <lb/>.007 <lb/>1.36 (1.01-1.82) <lb/>.04 <lb/>Urban location <lb/>1.32 (1.05-1.68) <lb/>.02 <lb/>1.29 (1.02-1.65) <lb/>.04 <lb/>Recent immigrant/refugee <lb/>1.23 (0.97-1.56) <lb/>.10 <lb/>1.17 (0.91-1.50) <lb/>.21 <lb/>Income quintile <lb/>1 (Lowest) <lb/>1.39 (1.03-1.87) <lb/>.03 <lb/>1.37 (1.01-1.87) <lb/>.04 <lb/>2 <lb/>1.32 (0.96-1.83) <lb/>.09 <lb/>1.26 (0.91-1.75) <lb/>.16 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.45 (1.04-2.02) <lb/>.03 <lb/>1.4 (1.00-1.96) <lb/>.05 <lb/>4 <lb/>1.29 (0.92-1.81) <lb/>.15 <lb/>1.28 (0.91-1.81) <lb/>.15 <lb/>5 (Highest) <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>1 [Reference] <lb/>NA <lb/>Abbreviations: ECI, Elixhauser comorbidity index; ED, <lb/>emergency department; NA, not applicable; sHR, <lb/>subdistribution hazard ratio. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Our study provides insights into at-risk populations. We uncovered sex-specific differences in <lb/>sociodemographic and social determinants of health. Females presenting with AH were more likely <lb/>to live rurally, in neighborhoods of the lowest income quintile, and have a history of mental health <lb/>conditions, while males were more likely to be an immigrant or refugee and live in ethnically diverse <lb/>neighborhoods. These observations emphasize the importance of understanding the social and <lb/>cultural factors of the population in need of intervention, as these are key for the development and <lb/>delivery of behavioral therapy for alcohol use disorder programs. The findings also highlight the need <lb/>to ensure protocols are in place to aid in the recruitment of diverse patient populations into clinical <lb/>trials for alcohol use disorder and AH that reflect the population&apos;s diversity. <lb/>Strengths and Limitations <lb/>Our study has many strengths, including the use of population-level data comprising a diverse <lb/>population in a contemporary era with longitudinal follow-up and use of validated algorithms to define <lb/>important liver-related outcomes. However, some limitations should be considered. First, our definition <lb/>of AH was based on ICD codes if listed as the primary diagnosis. Although this has been validated in other <lb/>data, it has not been validated in ICES. Second, we do not have access to data on treatments for AH, <lb/>specifically the use of steroids, and therefore how treatment impacts outcomes in this cohort is <lb/>unknown. However, since steroids for treatment of severe AH are only associated with a short-term <lb/>mortality benefit, 25 this is unlikely to affect our results on incident cirrhosis given the follow-up time for <lb/>this outcome started 6 months after the index presentation to exclude prevalent cirrhosis. Cause-<lb/>specific mortality data were only available to the end of 2018, including 55% of overall deaths. Therefore, <lb/>it is unclear whether sex-specific causes of death from 2019 to 2022 remained similar during the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic. Third, ICES does not contain data related to the treatment of alcohol use disorder, <lb/>quantity of alcohol consumption, obesity, race and ethnicity, marital status, or social supports, which may <lb/>also be associated with the development of AH and our outcomes. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this cohort study, rates of AH were observed to increase at concerning rates among AYAs, with females <lb/>most at risk for liver-related outcomes and death. These data support the need to develop early identifi-<lb/>cation and treatment for those at risk for AH and multidisciplinary management after their first presenta-<lb/>tion. Furthermore, the increase of AH among AYAs highlights the need to develop clinical trials and ob-<lb/>servational studies with a sex or gender approach to best support this younger vulnerable population. <lb/></body>

			<front>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Accepted for Publication: October 25, 2024. <lb/>Published: December 27, 2024. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 <lb/>Open Access: This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License. © 2024 Flemming <lb/>JA et al. JAMA Network Open. <lb/>Corresponding Author: Jennifer A. Flemming, MD, MAS, Departments of Medicine and Public Health Sciences, <lb/>Queen&apos;s University, Kingston Health Sciences Centre, 166 Brock St, Kingston, ON, Canada K7L 5G2 (jennifer.flemming2 <lb/>@kingstonhsc.ca). <lb/>Author Affiliations: Department of Medicine, Queen&apos;s University Ontario, Ontario, Canada (Flemming, Chapman); <lb/>Department of Public Health Sciences, Queen&apos;s University Ontario, Ontario, Canada (Flemming); ICES-Queen&apos;s, <lb/>Ontario, Canada (Flemming, Djerboua); Department of Psychiatry, Queen&apos;s University Ontario, Ontario, Canada <lb/>(Ayonrinde); Department of Medicine, University of Southern California, Los Angeles (Terrault). <lb/></front>
    
            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Dr Flemming had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the <lb/>integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. <lb/>Concept and design: All authors. <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Flemming, Djerboua. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">Drafting of the manuscript: Flemming, Djerboua. <lb/>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Djerboua, Chapman, Ayonrinde, Terrault. <lb/>Statistical analysis: Djerboua. <lb/>Obtained funding: Flemming, Ayonrinde. <lb/>Supervision: Flemming. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest Disclosures: Dr Ayonrinde reported receiving grants from the Canadian Institutes for Health <lb/>Research (CIHR) during the conduct of the study. Dr Terrault reported receiving institutional grant support from <lb/>Durect Corporation for a clinical trial for treatment of alcohol-associated hepatitis. No other disclosures were <lb/>reported. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding/Support: This study was funded by the CIHR. This study was supported by ICES, which is funded by an <lb/>annual grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health and the Ministry of Long-Term Care. This study also received <lb/>funding from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research. <lb/>Role of the Funder/Sponsor: The funding organizations had no role in the design and conduct of the study; <lb/>collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the <lb/>manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication. <lb/>Disclaimer: Parts of this material are based on data and/or information compiled and provided by the MOH, the <lb/>Canadian Institute for Health Information, the Ontario Registrar General (ORG) information on deaths (the original <lb/>source of which is ServiceOntario), and Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC) current to <lb/>September 2020. The analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not reflect those of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="availability">Data Sharing Statement: See Supplement 2. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Additional Information: This document used data adapted from the Statistics Canada Postal CodeOM Conversion <lb/>File, which is based on data licensed from Canada Post Corporation, and/or data adapted from the Ontario Ministry <lb/>of Health Postal Code Conversion File, which contains data copied under license from Canada Post Corporation <lb/>and Statistics Canada. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. World Health Organization. Alcohol. Accessed June 9, 2024. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/ <lb/>detail/alcohol <lb/>2. Singal AK, Mathurin P. Diagnosis and treatment of alcohol-associated liver disease: a review. JAMA. 2021;326 <lb/>(2):165-176. doi:10.1001/jama.2021.7683 <lb/>3. Saunders JB, Walters JR, Davies AP, Paton A. A 20-year prospective study of cirrhosis. BMJ (Clin Res Ed). 1981; <lb/>282(6260):263-266. doi:10.1136/bmj.282.6260.263 <lb/>4. Ahn JC, Wi CI, Buryska S, et al. Disproportionate increases in alcohol-associated hepatitis incidence in women <lb/>and individuals of low socioeconomic status: a population-based study using the Rochester Epidemiology Project <lb/>database. Hepatol Commun. 2023;7(6):e0160. doi:10.1097/HC9.0000000000000160 <lb/>5. Sohal A, Khalid S, Green V, et al. Soaring rates of alcohol-related hepatitis in the latter phase of the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic: a new normal? JGH Open. 2023;7(2):148-151. doi:10.1002/jgh3.12864 <lb/>6. Díaz LA, Fuentes-López E, Idalsoaga F, et al. Association between public health policies on alcohol and <lb/>worldwide cancer, liver disease and cardiovascular disease outcomes. J Hepatol. 2024;80(3):409-418. doi:10. <lb/>1016/j.jhep.2023.11.006 <lb/>7. Philip G, Hookey L, Richardson H, Flemming JA. Alcohol-associated liver disease is now the most common <lb/>indication for liver transplant waitlisting among young American adults. Transplantation. 2022;106(10): <lb/>2000-2005. doi:10.1097/TP.0000000000004202 <lb/>8. Shaheen AA, Kong K, Ma C, et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospitalizations for alcoholic hepatitis or <lb/>cirrhosis in Alberta, Canada. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2022;20(5):e1170-e1179. doi:10.1016/j.cgh.2021.10.030 <lb/>9. Roerecke M, Vafaei A, Hasan OSM, et al. Alcohol consumption and risk of liver cirrhosis: a systematic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. Am J Gastroenterol. 2019;114(10):1574-1586. doi:10.14309/ajg.0000000000000340 <lb/>10. Frezza M, di Padova C, Pozzato G, Terpin M, Baraona E, Lieber CS. High blood alcohol levels in women: the role <lb/>of decreased gastric alcohol dehydrogenase activity and first-pass metabolism. N Engl J Med. 1990;322(2):95-99. <lb/>doi:10.1056/NEJM199001113220205 <lb/>11. ICES. Accessed November 15, 2024. http://www.ices.on.ca <lb/>12. Jepsen P, Vilstrup H, Sørensen HT. Alcoholic cirrhosis in Denmark-population-based incidence, prevalence, <lb/>and hospitalization rates between 1988 and 2005: a descriptive cohort study. BMC Gastroenterol. 2008;8(8):3. <lb/>doi:10.1186/1471-230X-8-3 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>13. Lapointe-Shaw L, Georgie F, Carlone D, et al. Identifying cirrhosis, decompensated cirrhosis and hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma in health administrative data: A validation study. PLoS One. 2018;13(8):e0201120. doi:10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0201120 <lb/>14. Gray R. A class of K-sample tests for comparing the cumulative incidence of a competing risk. Ann Statistics. <lb/>1998;16(3):1141-1154. <lb/>15. Wyper GMA, Giles L, Beeston C, Shivaji T. Recent estimates of alcohol specific deaths support alcohol minimum <lb/>unit pricing. BMJ. 2024;384:q765. doi:10.1136/bmj.q765 <lb/>16. Wyper GMA, Mackay DF, Fraser C, et al. Evaluating the impact of alcohol minimum unit pricing on deaths and <lb/>hospitalisations in Scotland: a controlled interrupted time series study. Lancet. 2023;401(10385):1361-1370. doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00497-X <lb/>17. Alcohol and Gaming Commission of Ontario. Further extension of permitted sale hours for retail alcohol. April <lb/>27, 2020. Accessed November 18, 2024. https://www.agco.ca/en/news/further-extension-permitted-sale-hours-<lb/>retail-alcohol <lb/>18. Alcohol and Gaming Commission of Ontario. Information for liquor sales licensees selling liquor for takeout or <lb/>delivery along with food. May 28, 2020. Accessed November 18, 2024. https://www.agco.ca/en/news/information-<lb/>liquor-sales-licensees-selling-liquor-takeout-or-delivery-along-food <lb/>19. Lytvyak E, Straube S, Modi R, Lee KK. Trends in obesity across Canada from 2005 to 2018: a consecutive <lb/>cross-sectional population-based study. CMAJ Open. 2022;10(2):E439-E449. doi:10.9778/cmajo.20210205 <lb/>20. O&apos;Connor S, Robert P, Leclerc J, et al. Evolution of the burden of diabetes among adults and children in <lb/>Québec, Canada, from 2001 to 2019: a population-based longitudinal surveillance study. Diabetes Epidemiol <lb/>Manag. 2024;13:100177. doi:10.1016/j.deman.2023.100177 <lb/>21. Lourenço L, Kelly M, Tarasuk J, et al. The hepatitis C epidemic in Canada: an overview of recent trends in <lb/>surveillance, injection drug use, harm reduction and treatment. Can Commun Dis Rep. 2021;47(12):561-570. doi: <lb/>10.14745/ccdr.v47i12a01 <lb/>22. Statistics Canada. Cider dollar sales in Canada from FY 2012 to FY 2023. March 7, 2024. Accessed November <lb/>18, 2024. https://www.statista.com/statistics/557952/cider-dollar-sales-canada/ <lb/>23. Yenerall J, Jensen K, Hughes DW, Trejo-Pech C, DeLong KL. Demographics, alcoholic beverage purchase <lb/>patterns, and attitudes driving hard cider expenditures. J Food Prod Mark. 2022;28(5):228-241. doi:10.1080/ <lb/>10454446.2022.2096423 <lb/>24. Song M, Chen T, Prough RA, Cave MC, McClain CJ. Chronic alcohol consumption causes liver injury in high-<lb/>fructose-fed male mice through enhanced hepatic inflammatory response. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. 2016;40(3): <lb/>518-528. doi:10.1111/acer.12994 <lb/>25. Singh S, Murad MH, Chandar AK, et al. Comparative effectiveness of pharmacological interventions for severe <lb/>alcoholic hepatitis: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Gastroenterology. 2015;149(4):958-70.e12. <lb/>doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2015.06.006 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENT 1. <lb/>eTable 1. List and Description of ICES Databases Used <lb/>eTable 2. Codes and Definitions for Variables and Outcomes Used in Study <lb/>eTable 3. Individuals in Ontario Aged 13-39 Years With First Presentation of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis Without <lb/>Known History of Cirrhosis, Decompensation, or LT <lb/>eTable 4. Individuals in Ontario Aged 13-39 Years Without History of Cirrhosis, Decompensation, or LT Within 6 <lb/>Months of First Presentation of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>eFigure 1. Cumulative Incidence of Overall Mortality Among Adolescents and Young Adults With First Presentation <lb/>of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>eFigure 2. Cause-Specific Mortality Among Adolescents and Young Adults After First Presentation of Alcohol-<lb/>Associated Hepatitis <lb/>eFigure 3. Cumulative Incidence of Cirrhosis +/-Decompensation Among At-Risk Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/>After First Presentation of Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis <lb/>eMethods. Demographics and Covariates <lb/>eReferences <lb/>SUPPLEMENT 2. <lb/>Data Sharing Statement <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">JAMA Network Open | Gastroenterology and Hepatology <lb/>Alcohol-Associated Hepatitis in Adolescents and Young Adults <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">JAMA Network Open. 2024;7(12):e2452459. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.52459 (Reprinted) <lb/>December 27, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from jamanetwork.com by guest on 09/08/2025 </note>


	</text>


  </TEI>