<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T13:09:32.441Z">11/13/2025 1:09:32 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T13:09:14.576553Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T13:09:14.576553Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of <lb/>health facilities for chronic non-<lb/>communicable diseases: Evidence from the <lb/>Ethiopian national surveys <lb/>Atkure Defar 1,2 , Girum Taye Zeleke 1 , Della Berhanu 1,3 , Ephrem Tekle Lemango 4 , <lb/>Abebe Bekele 1 , Kassahun Alemu 2 , Sibhatu Biadgilign ID <lb/>5 <lb/>* <lb/>1 Ethiopian Public Health Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 2 College of Medicine and Health Science, <lb/>Institute of Public Health, Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of Gondar, Gondar, <lb/>Ethiopia, 3 London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom, 4 Maternal, Child <lb/>Health and Nutrition Directorate, Ministry of Health, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 5 Independent Public Health <lb/>Analyst and Research Consultant, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia <lb/>* sibhatu2010@gmail.com <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Non-communicable diseases (NCDs) currently cause more deaths than all other causes of <lb/>deaths. Cardiovascular disease, diabetes, cancer, and chronic respiratory diseases-<lb/>threaten the health and economies of individuals and populations worldwide. This study <lb/>aimed to assess the availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communi-<lb/>cable diseases (NCDs) and describe the changes of service availability for common NCDs <lb/>in Ethiopia. <lb/>Methods <lb/>We used data from the 2014 Ethiopia Service Provision Assessment Plus (ESPA +) and <lb/>2016 and 2018 Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA) surveys, which <lb/>were cross-sectional health facility-based studies. A total of 873 health facilities in 2014, 547 <lb/>in 2016, 632 in 2018 were included in the analysis. (ESPA+) and SARA surveys are con-<lb/>ducted as a census or a nationally/sub-nationally representative sample of health facilities. <lb/>Proportion of facilities that offered the service for diabetes, cardiovascular disease, chronic <lb/>respiratory disease, cancer diseases, mental illness, and chronic renal diseases was calcu-<lb/>lated to measure health service availability. The health facility service readiness was mea-<lb/>sured using the mean availably of tracer items that are required to offer the service. Thus, <lb/>13 tracer items for diabetes disease, 12 for cardiovascular disease, 11 for chronic respira-<lb/>tory disease and 11 cervical cancer services were used. <lb/>Results <lb/>The services available for diagnosis and management did not show improvement between <lb/>2014, 2016 and 2018 for diabetes (59%, 22% and 36%); for cardiovascular diseases (73%, <lb/>41% and 49%); chronic respiratory diseases (76%, 45% and 53%). Similarly, at the national <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/>1 / 15 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Defar A, Zeleke GT, Berhanu D, Lemango <lb/>ET, Bekele A, Alemu K, et al. (2024) Health <lb/>system&apos;s availability and readiness of health <lb/>facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases: <lb/>Evidence from the Ethiopian national surveys. <lb/>PLoS ONE 19(2): e0297622. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 <lb/>Editor: Charu C. Garg, Institute for Human <lb/>Development, INDIA <lb/>Received: February 4, 2022 <lb/>Accepted: January 9, 2024 <lb/>Published: February 23, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Defar et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The data belong to <lb/>the National Data Management Center (NDMC) at <lb/>the Ethiopian Public Health Institute (EPHI). <lb/>level, the mean availability of tracer items between 2014, 2016 and 2018 for diabetes (37%, <lb/>53% and 48%); cardiovascular diseases (36%, 41% and 42%); chronic respiratory diseases <lb/>(26%, 27% and 27%); and cancer diseases (6%, 72% and 51%). However, in 2014 survey <lb/>year, the mean availability of tracer items was 7% each for mental illness and chronic renal <lb/>diseases, respectively. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The majority of the health facilities have low and gradual decrement in the availability to pro-<lb/>vide NCDs services in Ethiopia. There is a need to increase NCD service availability and <lb/>readiness at primary hospitals and health centers, and private and rural health facilities <lb/>where majority of the population need the services. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>According to the World Health Organization (WHO) each year the deaths of 40 million people <lb/>were reported from non-communicable diseases (NCDs), which is equivalent to 70% of all <lb/>deaths globally [1]. In Ethiopia, NCDs cause 42% of deaths, of which 27% are premature <lb/>deaths before 70 years of age [2]. The Disability Adjusted Life Years (DALYs) increased from <lb/>below 20% in 1990 to 69% in 2015 [3] and there is a rapidly increasing burden of NCDs in <lb/>Ethiopia [2, 4-9]. Furthermore, while the annual number of deaths due to infectious diseases <lb/>is projected to decline, the total annual number of NCD deaths is projected to increase to 52 <lb/>million by 2030 [10-12]. <lb/>The main types of NCDs are cardiovascular diseases (such as heart attack and stroke), can-<lb/>cers, chronic respiratory diseases (CRDs) (such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and <lb/>asthma) and diabetes [1]. Cardiovascular diseases (CVDs) account for most of the annual <lb/>NCD deaths (17.7 million), followed by cancers (8.8 million), respiratory diseases (3.9 million), <lb/>and diabetes (1.6 million) [1]. A study of the prevalence of raised blood glucose and diabetes in <lb/>Ethiopia was 6% and raised blood pressure (SBP &gt; 140 and/or DBP &gt; 90 mmHg) was 15.6%, <lb/>[13].The overall death rates of NCDs causes has shown a decline by 40% from 1990 to 2015. <lb/>However, the crude all-cause mortality rate in 2015 was 680.9 per 100,000 people (95% UI: <lb/>505.1-913.9), of which 286.9 (95% UI: 188.1-423.0) per 100,000 were due to NCDs [14]. <lb/>NCDs threaten the progress towards the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, which <lb/>includes a target of reducing NCD related premature deaths by one-third. In order to attain <lb/>this target, each country should prioritize and implement cost-effective policies and interven-<lb/>tions and provide health services which tackle the rapid surges of this silent epidemic. In low <lb/>and middle income countries (LMICs), several interacting factors have been associated with <lb/>high burden of NCDs, including few preventative and early detection services, low availability <lb/>of essential treatments, and suboptimal organization in the delivery of care [15]. The assess-<lb/>ment of the capacity of countries&apos; to prevent and control NCDs conducted by WHO in 2015 <lb/>also showed major gaps in health system capacity in many LMICs [16]. The absence of evi-<lb/>dence-based policies and program with inadequate response at primary care level perpetuates <lb/>the problem. With limited data from LMICs on NCD service readiness, availability and utiliza-<lb/>tion in primary care facilities, the situation will become worse with time unless the situation is <lb/>actively addressed at a critical time [17]. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <front>National health and health related data have their <lb/>own data governance system and shall be <lb/>managing under the national data sharing policy. <lb/>Anyone interested to use the data sets could <lb/>communicate to the Ethiopian Public Health <lb/>institute, National Data Management Centrer using <lb/>the following link: https://rtds.ephi.gov.et/public/ <lb/>showdetail/94#step-1. The data can be accessed <lb/>using following URLs: ESPA+ 2014 (https://rtds. <lb/>ephi.gov.et/public/showdetail/76), SARA 2016 <lb/>(https://rtds.ephi.gov.et/public/showdetail/93) and <lb/>SARA 2018 (https://rtds.ephi.gov.et/public/ <lb/>showdetail/94). <lb/>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>In Ethiopia, there are a few studies conducted on service availability and readiness for <lb/>NCDs. These studies, however, are limited as they focus on a particular or selected set of <lb/>NCDs [18-20]. In the country, the health facilities lack essential logistics and have major ser-<lb/>vice provision bottlenecks including non-functionality of the existing district coordination <lb/>body and technical committees, training gaps, staff shortage, high staff turnover resulting from <lb/>work related burden, fatigue and poor motivation among service providers [21]. The overall <lb/>aim of the current study was to assess the availability and readiness of services for common <lb/>NCDs using Ethiopian Service Provision Assessment (ESPA+) and Service Availability and <lb/>Readiness Assessment (SARA) surveys in health facilities of Ethiopia. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Data source and study setting <lb/>This study used and analyzed data from the 2014 Ethiopia Service Provision Assessment Plus <lb/>(ESPA+), and 2016 and 2018 Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA) surveys. <lb/>(ESPA+) and SARA surveys are conducted as census or as a nationally/sub-nationally repre-<lb/>sentative sample of health facilities that can guide the health sector policy and planning. The <lb/>surveys were conducted using similar survey methodologies for adapting the questionnaires, <lb/>training, and pre-testing and data collection. ESPA+ and SARA questionnaires contain infor-<lb/>mation on general and specific service availability and readiness (e.g., types of services offered, <lb/>basic amenities, equipment, medicines and commodities, diagnostics, trained staff and prac-<lb/>tice guidelines). The data were collected from all nine regions of Ethiopia namely: Tigray, <lb/>Afar, Amhara, Oromia, Somali, Benishangul-gumuz, Southern Nations Nationalities and <lb/>Peopple (SNNP), Gambella, and Harari. The survey also included the two city administrations, <lb/>Addis Ababa and Dire Dawa. The Ethiopian health system has primary, secondary and tertiary <lb/>levels of care. Five health posts, their referral health center and primary hospital comprise the <lb/>primary health care unit [22]. <lb/>Study design <lb/>A cross-sectional health facilities-based study was employed in the surveys. The surveys used <lb/>the SARA methodology that was developed through a joint WHO and the United States <lb/>Agency for International Development (USAID) collaboration. The method considers, among <lb/>other thing, the service availability mapping (SAM) tool developed by WHO, and the ESPA <lb/>+ tool developed by ICF International under the USAID-funded MEASURE DHS (monitoring <lb/>and evaluation to assess and use results, demographic and health surveys) project [23]. <lb/>Sampling of health facilities <lb/>For ESPA+ 2014, the survey used a stratified random sampling designed to provide representa-<lb/>tive samples of: health facility types, management authorities, regions, and city administra-<lb/>tions. A list of health facilities obtained from each regional health office was used as a sampling <lb/>frame. This sampling method yielded a total of 1,327 health facilities to be surveyed, which <lb/>comprised of 223 hospitals, 298 health centers and 321 health posts and 485 private clinics. In <lb/>2014 sampling, all hospitals were included and a representative sample of health centers, health <lb/>posts and clinics were included. While, in 2016 sampling, all hospitals were included and a rep-<lb/>resentative sample of health centers, health posts and clinics were included and in 2018 sam-<lb/>pling, all hospitals were included and a representative sample of health centers, health posts <lb/>and clinics were included. Briefly, the sampling method for SARA 2016 and 2018 was also a <lb/>nationally representative sample stratified by health facility type and managing authority. All <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>health facilities that were in 2016 SARA were selected for the SARA 2018 survey. In the 2016 <lb/>SARA survey, 705 health facilities were included, with all hospitals (228), 165 health centers, <lb/>173 clinics, and 139 health posts. Similarly, in the 2018 SARA survey, a total of 764 health facil-<lb/>ities were assessed, which included 303 hospitals, 164 health centers, 165 clinics and 132 health <lb/>posts. The 2018 SARA survey also included new hospitals that were established after the 2016 <lb/>SARA survey [23-25]. <lb/>Data collection tool and procedure <lb/>An adapted version of the MEASURE DHS project SPA questionnaire with some additional <lb/>country specific questions and World Bank service delivery indicator (SDI) were used to col-<lb/>lect data on facility characteristics, staff contingents, service availability, referral systems, drugs <lb/>and equipment, laboratory services, reporting systems, and monitoring and supervision [26]. <lb/>To obtain this information, we interviewed heads of facilities or their delegates or heads of spe-<lb/>cific sections that were believed to be knowledgeable about the service provision. Inventory <lb/>and inspection of the guidelines, reports, equipment, drugs and laboratory supplies were also <lb/>done. <lb/>The survey data were collected using Computer-Assisted Personal Interviewing (CAPI) <lb/>programed using the Census and Survey Processing System (CSPro) 6.3 software. Data were <lb/>transferred daily to the Ethiopian Public Health Institute server. Feedback was provided to the <lb/>field team before they moved to the next selected health facility. The Ethiopian Public Health <lb/>Institute (EPHI) organized the fieldwork, monitored the data transfer system and carried out <lb/>extensive supervision over the duration of the fieldwork. Regional coordinators engaged in <lb/>supervision and actively solved problems faced by the field team. <lb/>Data management <lb/>The survey data were collected focusing on service readiness and availability for all NCDs in <lb/>the ESPA+, including diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, chronic respiratory diseases and can-<lb/>cer. To calculate the readiness score, 13 tracer items for diabetes, 12 for cardiovascular diseases, <lb/>11 for chronic respiratory diseases and 11 cervical cancer services were used. The availability <lb/>of the services and readiness of health facilities for diabetes, cardiovascular, and chronic respi-<lb/>ratory diseases were investigated in the ESPA+ 2014, and the two recent (2016 and 2018) <lb/>SARA surveys [23-25]. The service was considered to be available if a facility manages, diagno-<lb/>ses, treats or prescribes a patient coming to the facility for common NCDs. The facility readi-<lb/>ness was estimated based on the availability of tracer items that are necessary to provide the <lb/>services [27]. <lb/>Measurement of variables <lb/>The outcome variables in this study were the &quot;availability score&quot; and &quot;readiness score&quot; of the <lb/>health facilities for common NCDs. We defined facility &apos;&apos;availability&quot; as the percentage of facili-<lb/>ties in the sample that said they offered the service in question, which considered whether the <lb/>diagnosis and/or management services were available. Facility &quot;readiness&quot; was a composite <lb/>measure and was restricted to the subset of facilities that offered the service. The component <lb/>&quot;domains&quot; that make up the readiness score included trained staff, guideline, equipment/sup-<lb/>plies; medicines and commodities, and diagnostics capacities. For each domain, we calculated <lb/>an index as the mean score of items expressed as a percentage. A readiness score of 50 signifies <lb/>that, on average, half of the facilities that offered the service had each of the requisite inputs for <lb/>delivering that service. The calculated indices were compared to an agreed cutoff point of 50%. <lb/>A facility index that was below 50% was considered as &apos;not ready&apos; to manage NCDs. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>Statistical analysis <lb/>Data were cleaned and analyzed using Stata 15 (StataCorp, College Station, TX). A descriptive <lb/>analysis was carried out to summarize results using percentages and proportions, which were <lb/>then presented in the form of tables and graphs. Percentages in the tables were weighted to <lb/>make sampling adjustment for disproportional sampling and non-response rate at regional <lb/>level and by facility type, but the sample size presented in the tables are not weighted. This is a <lb/>guiding principle for the analysis of SPA data. The analysis for availability and readiness has <lb/>been done considering the WHO service availably and readiness estimation method [1]. In <lb/>this study, Fisher&apos;s exact test was used to assess the difference in the mean availability of tracer <lb/>items for various NCDs and across survey years. Further statistical analyses were done by <lb/>using chi-squared tests. Statistical significance was accepted at the 5% level (p&lt;0.05). The anal-<lb/>ysis did not include health posts since, they do not have standards for NCDs, nor are they sup-<lb/>posed to provide curative services for NCDs. The &apos;Strengthening the Reporting of <lb/>Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement&apos; to write the manuscript (online <lb/>S1 Checklist) was followed. <lb/>Quality assurance <lb/>Quality assurance involved multiple steps along a continuum of training, data collection in the <lb/>field, and data processing at the central level. Quality assurance began with the recruitment of <lb/>data collectors and team leaders with a health background. Team leaders played a critical role <lb/>in the correct completion of the data collection tools as they reviewed all the questionnaires. <lb/>The regional coordinators visited and communicated with teams regularly to provide support <lb/>and help when difficulties arose at individual facilities. The central coordinators at EPHI and <lb/>members of the Technical Working Group supervised the teams in the field to ensure consis-<lb/>tency and quality. When needed, the central data managers telephoned facilities for clarifica-<lb/>tion and to ensure quality. <lb/>Ethics approval and consideration <lb/>The current study was conducted based on a secondary analysis of existing data sets from the <lb/>three-waves of data collection (2014, 2016, and 2018). Ethical clearance was obtained from the <lb/>Scientific Ethical Review Committee (SERC) of the Ethiopian Public Health Institute (EPHI) <lb/>with reference number of EPHI 6.13/966. Informed verbal consent was obtained from all <lb/>health facilities&apos; in-charge and health workers responsible for client services who were present <lb/>at the facility. The participant recruitment date for SPA 2014 was from March to July, 2014; for <lb/>SARA 2016 from February to April 2016 and for SARA 2018 from October to December, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Result <lb/>Characteristics of health facilities <lb/>In this comprehensive study, a total of 873 health facilities in 2014, 547 in 2016, and 632 in <lb/>2018 were included in the analysis. The results are stratified by facility type, managing author-<lb/>ity, region, and residence (Table 1). <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Availability of important components for the management of NCDs <lb/>The services available for the diagnosis and/or management of diabetes did not show improve-<lb/>ment between the periods of 2014 to 2018. The availability for diagnosis and/or management <lb/>services for diabetes was 59%, 22%, and 36% in 2014, 2016, and 2018, respectively. Similarly, <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>the availability for diagnosis and/or management services for cardiovascular disease was 73%, <lb/>41%, 49% in 2014, 2016, and 2018, respectively and 76% in 2014, 45% in 2016 and 53% in 2018 <lb/>for chronic respiratory disease. Mostly, the availability of essential guidelines, trained human <lb/>power and materials and equipment for the management of NCDs services varied across the <lb/>survey years. Detail description is illustrated in Table 1. <lb/>Health facility readiness for the management of NCDs <lb/>Service readiness was measured generally by the availability of selected tracer items. In all cate-<lb/>gories of diseases, the readiness was checked by the availability of guideline and at least 1 <lb/>trained staff as necessary tracer items to provide the service. Additionally, the analysis consid-<lb/>ered the availability items listed in Table 2. The general service readiness for cancer diseases, <lb/>mental illness, and chronic renal diseases were measured based on the availability of guidelines <lb/>and at least 1 trained staff as a common tracer item. <lb/>Service readiness was estimated among those who offered the services by assessing four <lb/>domains: staff and guidelines, equipment, diagnostics, and medicines and commodities. The <lb/>bar graph shows the trend on overall readiness using the availability of tracer items for three of <lb/>the selected NCDs (diabetes, cardiovascular, cervical cancer and chronic respiratory diseases), <lb/>which showed an improvement across different periods. We used 12 tracer items that are <lb/>Table 1. Weighted percent of health facilities offering services for non-communicable diseases, by background characteristics, Ethiopia. <lb/>Background <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>Cardiovascular diseases <lb/>Chronic respiratory <lb/>diseases <lb/>Cancer <lb/>Number of surveyed <lb/>facilities(unweighted)* <lb/>Cancer <lb/>diseases <lb/>Cervical Cancer <lb/>SPA <lb/>+ <lb/>2014 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2016 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2018 <lb/>SPA <lb/>+ <lb/>2014 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2016 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2018 <lb/>SPA <lb/>+ <lb/>2014 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2016 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2018 <lb/>SPA+ <lb/>2014 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2016 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2018 <lb/>SPA <lb/>+ <lb/>2014 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2016 <lb/>SARA <lb/>2018 <lb/>Facility type <lb/>Referral Hospital 97 <lb/>91 <lb/>97 <lb/>84 <lb/>97 <lb/>97 <lb/>91 <lb/>97 <lb/>69 <lb/>56 <lb/>77 <lb/>31 <lb/>32 <lb/>31 <lb/>General Hospital 97 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>92 <lb/>97 <lb/>96 <lb/>92 <lb/>95 <lb/>66 <lb/>38 <lb/>64 <lb/>132 117 <lb/>116 <lb/>Primary Hospital 98 <lb/>89 <lb/>100 89 <lb/>94 <lb/>100 89 <lb/>96 <lb/>65 <lb/>10 <lb/>42 <lb/>48 <lb/>61 <lb/>156 <lb/>Health Center <lb/>63 <lb/>16 <lb/>82 <lb/>50 <lb/>66 <lb/>88 <lb/>55 <lb/>70 <lb/>28 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>291 165 <lb/>164 <lb/>Higher clinic <lb/>89 <lb/>69 <lb/>87 <lb/>61 <lb/>48 <lb/>88 <lb/>69 <lb/>48 <lb/>60 <lb/>4 <lb/>29 <lb/>58 <lb/>23 <lb/>19 <lb/>Medium clinic <lb/>96 <lb/>65 <lb/>93 <lb/>71 <lb/>79 <lb/>93 <lb/>76 <lb/>82 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>135 64 <lb/>74 <lb/>Lower Clinic <lb/>34 <lb/>5 <lb/>49 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>49 <lb/>11 <lb/>13 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>178 85 <lb/>72 <lb/>Managing <lb/>authority <lb/>Government/ <lb/>Public <lb/>64 <lb/>19 <lb/>83 <lb/>51 <lb/>68 <lb/>88 <lb/>56 <lb/>71 <lb/>29 <lb/>3 <lb/>8 <lb/>441 320 <lb/>410 <lb/>Others** <lb/>228 26 <lb/>223 30 <lb/>29 <lb/>208 33 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>432 227 <lb/>222 <lb/>Location of health <lb/>facilities <lb/>Urban <lb/>72 <lb/>34 <lb/>78 <lb/>43 <lb/>53 <lb/>82 <lb/>45 <lb/>57 <lb/>28 <lb/>4 <lb/>14 <lb/>536 431 <lb/>494 <lb/>Rural <lb/>49 <lb/>5 <lb/>70 <lb/>38 <lb/>41 <lb/>72 <lb/>45 <lb/>47 <lb/>19 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>337 116 <lb/>138 <lb/>Total <lb/>59 <lb/>22 <lb/>73 <lb/>41 <lb/>49 <lb/>76 <lb/>45 <lb/>53 <lb/>23 <lb/>2 <lb/>9 <lb/>873 547 <lb/>632 <lb/>*considering the numbers of health facilities of each type and national and regional levels are weighted/ adjusted, so that the distribution of facilities by type&apos;s <lb/>contribution to the total is proportionate to reflect the actual distribution or total number of health facilities in Ethiopia. We use weighted, for the percentages and <lb/>unweighted for the sample size estimation. <lb/>**Others: Governmental (military, prison, federal police), private for-profit and NGO (mission/faith-based, nonprofit) <lb/>SPA: Service Provision Assessment; SARA: Service Availability and Readiness Assessment <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 2. Percentage of health facilities having guideline, trained staff, and equipment, diagnostic capacity and essential medicines for non-communicable diseases <lb/>by year, Ethiopia. <lb/>Indicators by disease <lb/>SPA+2014 <lb/>SARA 2016 <lb/>SARA 2018 <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>Guideline** <lb/>12 <lb/>16 <lb/>15 <lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>6 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>Blood Pressure apparatus <lb/>93 <lb/>100 <lb/>96 <lb/>Adult weighing scale <lb/>76 <lb/>97 <lb/>93 <lb/>Height board/stadiometer <lb/>49 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blood glucose <lb/>40 <lb/>66 <lb/>66 <lb/>Urine protein <lb/>56 <lb/>89 <lb/>78 <lb/>Urine glucose <lb/>52 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Metformin <lb/>11 <lb/>31 <lb/>20 <lb/>Glibenclamide <lb/>28 <lb/>31 <lb/>22 <lb/>Injectable insulin <lb/>9 <lb/>18 <lb/>17 <lb/>Injectable glucose <lb/>15 <lb/>62 <lb/>57 <lb/>Measuring Tape <lb/>-<lb/>71 <lb/>69 <lb/>Urine dipstick ketones <lb/>-<lb/>89 <lb/>78 <lb/>Gliclazide/glipizide tablet <lb/>-<lb/>4 <lb/>7 <lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>37 <lb/>53 <lb/>48 <lb/>Cardiovascular disease <lb/>Guideline <lb/>11 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>Stethoscope <lb/>97 <lb/>100 <lb/>97 <lb/>B. Pressure apparatus <lb/>92 <lb/>100 <lb/>95 <lb/>Adult scale <lb/>74 <lb/>88 <lb/>90 <lb/>ACE inhibitors (Enalapril) <lb/>15 <lb/>25 <lb/>34 <lb/>Thiazide <lb/>25 <lb/>20 <lb/>-<lb/>Beta-blockers (Atenolol) <lb/>6 <lb/>15 <lb/>17 <lb/>Calcium channel blockers <lb/>26 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>Oxygen <lb/>9 <lb/>17 <lb/>13 <lb/>Hydrochlorothiazide tablet <lb/>-<lb/>37 <lb/>47 <lb/>Metformin <lb/>-<lb/>19 <lb/>16 <lb/>Asprin <lb/>-<lb/>53 <lb/>42 <lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>36 <lb/>41 <lb/>42 <lb/>Chronic respiratory disease <lb/>Guideline <lb/>15 <lb/>13 <lb/>10 <lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>Stethoscope <lb/>99 <lb/>100 <lb/>96 <lb/>Peak flow meter <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>Spacers for inhalers <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Salbutamol inhaler or tablets <lb/>43 <lb/>23 <lb/>39 <lb/>Beclomethasone inhaler <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>6 <lb/>Prednisolone <lb/>44 <lb/>44 <lb/>47 <lb/>Hydrocortisone injection <lb/>14 <lb/>24 <lb/>30 <lb/>Injectable epinephrine <lb/>51 <lb/>54 <lb/>39 <lb/>Oxygen <lb/>9 <lb/>15 <lb/>13 <lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>26 <lb/>27 <lb/>27 <lb/>Cancer diseases <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 2. (Continued) <lb/>Indicators by disease <lb/>SPA+2014 <lb/>SARA 2016 <lb/>SARA 2018 <lb/>Guideline <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>4 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>6 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mental illness <lb/>Guideline <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>5 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Chronic renal diseases <lb/>Guideline <lb/>11 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Cervical cancer <lb/>Guideline <lb/>-<lb/>53 <lb/>At least 1 trained staff <lb/>-<lb/>61 <lb/>Speculum <lb/>-<lb/>96 <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>-<lb/>77 <lb/>Mean availability of tracer items <lb/>-<lb/>72 <lb/>**Guideline is referring to a national guideline that the health worker should consider while treating patients for each particular diseases according to the standard set <lb/>by the federal ministry of health <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622.t002 <lb/>Fig 1. Mean availability of tracer items among facilities that offer diabetes, cardiovascular diseases and chronic respiratory disease <lb/>services; Ethiopia, SPA+ 2014, SARA 2016 and SARA 2018. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>necessary to provide diabetes services in 2014, whereas 13 tracer items were used for both 2016 <lb/>and 2018 surveys. On average, for each survey years, facilities had 4, 6, and 6 tracer items with <lb/>overall readiness score of 37%, 53%, and 48%, respectively. This showed improvement over <lb/>the period between 2014 and 2016. The overall readiness for cardiovascular diseases (of the <lb/>total 12) did not show improvement over time; it was 36%, 41%, and 42% during, 2014 (10 <lb/>tracer items), 2016 (of 12 tracer items), and 2018 (12 tracer items), respectively (Fig 1). <lb/>Of the 11 tracer items that are necessary to provide diabetes service, on average facilities <lb/>had 3 tracer items with an overall readiness score of 26%. There were no changes over time <lb/>2016 (27%) and 2018 (27%), with the mean tracer item availability of 3 out of 11 items. At the <lb/>national level, the mean availability of tracer items for diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, <lb/>chronic respiratory diseases, cancer diseases, mental illness, and chronic renal diseases were <lb/>37%, 36%, 26%, 6%, 7% and 7%, respectively in 2014. In 2016, the mean availability of tracer <lb/>items for diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, chronic respiratory diseases and cervical cancer <lb/>were 53%, 41%, 27% and 72%, respectively. Similarly, the mean availability of tracer items for <lb/>diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, chronic respiratory diseases, and cervical cancer were 48%, <lb/>42%, 27% and 51%, respectively in 2018 (Table 2). <lb/>Changes in preparedness for common non-communicable diseases <lb/>Table 3 shows the differences in the mean availability of tracer item in percent for NCDs ser-<lb/>vice availability between assessment years at the national level. In this study, there was an <lb/>improvement from 2014 to 2016 in terms of the availability of tracer items with 16% for diabe-<lb/>tes (p&lt; 0.001), 5% cardiovascular diseases, and 1% chronic respiratory diseases. However, <lb/>from 2016 to 2018 survey year, there was a decrease for diabetes with 5% and 21% for cervical <lb/>cancer (p&lt; 0.001) and showed almost no change for cardiovascular and chronic respiratory <lb/>diseases (See Table 3). The change in mental health and chronic renal diseases service readi-<lb/>ness were not assessed since we have only one-time data for the 2014. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The study highlighted and revealed that service availability and readiness of health facilities for <lb/>common NCDs services were compromised in Ethiopia across various periods. The services <lb/>available for diagnosis and management did not show improvement between 2014, 2016 and <lb/>2018 for diabetes (59%, 22% and 36%); for cardiovascular disease (73%, 41% and 49%); and <lb/>chronic respiratory diseases (76%, 45% and 53%). Similarly, at the national level, the mean <lb/>availability of tracer items between 2014, 2016 and 2018 was 37%, 53% and 48% for diabetes; <lb/>was 36%, 41% and 42% for cardiovascular disease; was 26%, 27% and 27% for chronic respira-<lb/>tory diseases; and was 6%, 72% and 51% for cancer diseases. However, in 2014 survey year, the <lb/>mean availability of tracer items was 7% each for mental illness and chronic renal diseases, <lb/>Table 3. Health facilities mean availability of tracer items difference in percent for non-communicable diseases service between assessment years at national level, <lb/>Ethiopia. <lb/>Non-communicable diseases <lb/>SPA+2014 to SARA 2016 <lb/>SARA 2016 to 2018 <lb/>Difference <lb/>P-value <lb/>Difference <lb/>P-value <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>16 <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Cardiovascular disease <lb/>5 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>Chronic respiratory disease <lb/>1 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Cervical Cancer <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>-21 <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>* Not applicable <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622.t003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>respectively. Similar findings have been documented in South Africa in 2014, which identified <lb/>the need to improve availability of NCD-trained nurses, functional equipment, and medica-<lb/>tion [28]. Based on 2013 Ugandan study, none of the facilities included met the WHO package <lb/>of essential non-communicable (PEN) standards for essential tools and medicines to imple-<lb/>ment effective NCD interventions [29]. <lb/>In 2008 in Ethiopia that the overall prevalence of chronic NCDs was documented to be <lb/>8.9% and the specific prevalence were 0.5% for diabetes mellitus, 2.6% for hypertension, 3.0% <lb/>for cardiovascular diseases, 1.5% for asthma and 2.7% for mental illness [30]. National cardio-<lb/>vascular disease prevalence was 15%, cancer and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease preva-<lb/>lence was 4% each, and diabetes mellitus prevalence was 2% [31]. <lb/>Health facilities included in this study were not well equipped to provide services for diabe-<lb/>tes, cardiovascular diseases, and chronic respiratory diseases. The trend was similar across the <lb/>survey years. Diabetes had the lowest service availability, but the highest readiness score to pro-<lb/>vide service among the common NCDs. The availability of guidelines and at least one trained <lb/>staff is minimal to deliver the management of diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, cervical cancer, <lb/>and chronic respiratory disease services. According to the 2020 WHO report on the health <lb/>care capacity for NCD management, evidence-based guidelines for the management of NCDs <lb/>need to be developed and broadly implemented to ensure appropriate diagnosis, referral and <lb/>treatment. Also reported was that, globally, only 48% of countries reported having evidence-<lb/>based guidelines, protocols or standards for the management of all four NCDs through a pri-<lb/>mary care approach. Contrary to our study, the report revealed that guidelines for diabetes <lb/>were most widely available (84%), followed by CVDs (77%), cancer (70%) and chronic respira-<lb/>tory diseases(CRDs) (64%). Correspondingly, countries were most likely to have guidelines for <lb/>diabetes that included referral criteria and were utilized in at least 50% of health care facilities, <lb/>with 80% of countries in upper-middle-income countries reporting having such guidelines <lb/>[32]. The decline in the trends of service availability and readiness could be the fact that the <lb/>skilled staff turnover is high form the rural to urban areas. Also, the primary health care system <lb/>might not be ready in terms of infrastructure, staffing and medicine and commodities which is <lb/>supposed to provide the service, and its inclusion increases the denominator when calculating <lb/>readiness. <lb/>Our study is consistent with the study conducted in Uganda in 2012. Less than a half (46%) <lb/>of the health facilities had hypertension guidelines with significant differences observed across <lb/>health facility levels [33], which is one of the core aspects of the management of the chronic <lb/>diseases. Similarly, a study done in Tanzania showed that in many health facilities, guidelines, <lb/>diagnostic equipment, and first-line drug therapy for the primary care of NCDs were inade-<lb/>quate, and management, training, and reporting systems were weak [17]. Likewise, in the <lb/>recent Tanzanian national survey, out of 725 health facilities involved in the study, only 28% of <lb/>the assessed facilities were considered prepared for the outpatient primary care of hyperten-<lb/>sion. About 9% and 42% of the assessed facilities reported to have at least one trained staff and <lb/>guidelines for hypertension, respectively [34]. In a Ghanaian study, the findings highlight the <lb/>unavailability of essential medicines required for adequate management of NCDs reflected in <lb/>the limited capacity at the various levels of care [35]. More importantly, there are challenges <lb/>for healthcare delivery system: first the double burden of communicable diseases and non-<lb/>communicable diseases such as diabetes and cardiovascular disease; the burden that chronic <lb/>conditions impose on health systems and multiple chronic conditions; and lastly burden on <lb/>the primary healthcare [36]. According to the WHO recommendations, training of the health <lb/>workforce and strengthening the capacity of the health systems, particularly at primary care <lb/>level and policy options to address the prevention and control of NCDs are all priorities [37]. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>From our findings, trained human resources were inadequate for addressing and managing <lb/>NCDs in Ethiopia. Consistent result was documented in Tanzanian health facilities for outpa-<lb/>tient primary care study, in which trained health workers for NCDs were inadequate, and <lb/>management, training, and reporting systems were weak. Only one of the 24 health facilities <lb/>surveyed reported any training in the past year for hypertension or diabetes [17]. According to <lb/>the national survey in Tanzania, about 26% and 13% of health facilities had guidelines and <lb/>trained staff for NCDs, respectively [38]. Coupled with this, in a Ghanaian study, inadequate <lb/>staffing was a major impediment for the capacity of primary healthcare facilities to serve <lb/>NCD-related health needs [35]. The capacity of the primary care system in Vietnam was inade-<lb/>quate to serve the NCD-related health needs of the population [39]. Similarly, a study docu-<lb/>mented in Ethiopia showed that encouraging actions and results on NCDs in terms of political <lb/>commitment, however, there was a gap as shown by the limited availability of resources for <lb/>NCDs prevention and treatment services at the primary health care level. Shortage of essential <lb/>NCD drugs and diagnostic facilities and lack of treatment guidelines are major challenges [2]. <lb/>This study showed that the majority of the services for chronic disease management <lb/>occurred in a referral hospital, general hospital, and primary hospital, unlike the primary <lb/>health care facilities. Although, people with, or at risk of developing, NCDs require long-term <lb/>care that is proactive, patient-centered, community-based and sustainable. Such care can be <lb/>delivered equitably only through robust health systems founded on strong primary health care <lb/>towards the attainment of universal health coverage [32]. This is also the case in a 2013 survey <lb/>from Uganda in that showed that limiting supply of anti-hypertensive medicines to higher-<lb/>level health facilities was incongruent with the provision of high quality, chronic care for per-<lb/>sons with hypertension in lower health facilities. <lb/>In the same way, lower-level health facilities, where the population is expected to receive <lb/>primary health care, should be expected to stock essential medicines for treating non-commu-<lb/>nicable diseases [40]. A similar finding was also documented in Zambia where nearly all pri-<lb/>mary health facilities studied did not meet the minimum threshold to manage NCDs [41] <lb/>according to the WHO recommendations [37]. <lb/>The temporal trend identified for the common non-communicable disease service availabil-<lb/>ity observed from 2014 to 2018 should be used to prioritize health care programs and scaling <lb/>up interventions for NCDs in Ethiopia and other developing countries. Health system policy <lb/>should give due attention to NCDs service availability. In addition, the government has to <lb/>focus the attention towards prioritizing each specific disease. In addition, the government has <lb/>to focus the attention towards prioritizing each specific disease (chronic respiratory diseases, <lb/>cardiovascular diseases and diabetes) in accordance of disease burden while providing and <lb/>expanding the NCDs service provision in government/public health facilities as well as focus-<lb/>ing on rural area and primary health care services, where the majority of the community mem-<lb/>bers are served. <lb/>Similarly, it will add value on the existing NCDs prevention strategies that would be <lb/>strengthened through updating the priority disease that need further attention and <lb/>implication. <lb/>Our study has some limitations. Firstly, the sampling frames used in the surveys was limited <lb/>to health centers/health posts included in the country master health facility list and some other <lb/>health facilities, especially those recently constructed, might not be included. Secondly, the <lb/>cross-sectional nature of the study limits its value to explain the relative importance of some of <lb/>the factors to be considered. At the same time, such kind of surveys can sometimes oversample <lb/>hospitals and governmental and urban health facilities. Thirdly, another potential concern is <lb/>the variations in the availability and management of NCDs across the regions of the country. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <body>Lastly, p-values estimation should be regarded as exploratory rather than for testing <lb/>hypothesis. <lb/>Despite the above limitations, our study has several strengths. First, this study was under-<lb/>taken in a representative sample of health facilities, so it might be generalisable to all facilities <lb/>in the country. Secondly, the survey tools used standardized WHO-recommended and vali-<lb/>dated data collection instrument, training. Furthermore, pre-testing of the tools was rigours in <lb/>nature. The involvement and approval of policymakers and health programme managers sup-<lb/>ports the endorsement of the findings of the study for improving quality and management of <lb/>NCDs carried out in the health facilities. In addition to this, the wealth of data allowed for <lb/>looking at the temporal pattern across the years, which demonstrated the real situation of the <lb/>health system&apos;s availability and readiness to provide NCD services in Ethiopia. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The majority of the health facilities have low and gradual decrement in the availability of <lb/>resources to provide NCD services in Ethiopia. However, there was stability and some increase <lb/>in the readiness score across the some NCDs. However, more attention is needed on facility <lb/>readiness to provide cervical cancer, mental illness, and chronic renal diseases services. There <lb/>is a need to increase NCD service availability and readiness at the primary health care system, <lb/>giving special attention to the primary hospitals and health centers, and private and rural <lb/>health facilities where the majority of the population receive services. Basic diagnostic equip-<lb/>ment and medication also need to be made available. Management of NCDs can also be <lb/>improved by providing continuous training for primary health care workers. Opportunities <lb/>for providing integrated care for NCDs should receive strong consideration, allowing for effi-<lb/>cient use of the available resources at primary health care in low-income countries such as <lb/>Ethiopia. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. STROBE statement-checklist of items that should be included in reports of <lb/>cross-sectional studies. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/></div>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We acknowledged to the Ministry of Health and the Ethiopian Public Health Institute for pro-<lb/>viding the data. As well, we are highly indebted to appreciate the contribution of study partici-<lb/>pants as well as data collectors. The surveys were undertaken by the Ethiopian Public Health <lb/>Institute (EPHI), which is the research arm of the Ethiopian Ministry of Health (FMoH). They <lb/>were also done in collaboration with various organizations. We would like to thank, For ICF <lb/>International provided technical assistance, the United States Agency for International Devel-<lb/>opment (USAID), World Bank, Irish Aid, WHO and UNICEF for their support during the <lb/>2014 ESPA+. World Health Organization, World Bank and Global Fund for their support dur-<lb/>ing the 2016 and 2018 surveys. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Ephrem Tekle <lb/>Lemango, Kassahun Alemu, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Data curation: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Formal analysis: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Ephrem Tekle Lemango, <lb/>Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Investigation: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Ephrem Tekle Lemango, Abebe Bekele, Kas-<lb/>sahun Alemu, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Methodology: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Project administration: Atkure Defar. <lb/>Resources: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Ephrem Tekle Lemango, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Software: Girum Taye Zeleke. <lb/>Supervision: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Ephrem Tekle Lemango, <lb/>Abebe Bekele, Kassahun Alemu. <lb/>Validation: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Ephrem Tekle Lemango, Abebe <lb/>Bekele, Kassahun Alemu, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Visualization: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Atkure Defar, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Atkure Defar, Girum Taye Zeleke, Della Berhanu, Ephrem Tekle <lb/>Lemango, Abebe Bekele, Kassahun Alemu, Sibhatu Biadgilign. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. WHO. Key facts on noncommunicable diseases. World Health Organization(WHO) (Available at <lb/>https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases; accessed at January <lb/>30, 2019) 2018. <lb/>2. Shiferaw F, Letebo M, Misganaw A, Feleke Y, Gelibo T, Getachew T, et al. Non-communicable Dis-<lb/>eases in Ethiopia: Disease burden, gaps in health care delivery and strategic directions. Ethiop J Health <lb/>Dev 2018; 32(3):00-000. <lb/>3. Yosef T. Prevalence and associated factors of chronic non-communicable diseases among cross-coun-<lb/>try truck drivers in Ethiopia. BMC public health. 2020; 20(1):1564. Epub 2020/10/19. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1186/s12889-020-09646-w PMID: 33069207; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7568414. <lb/>4. Demilew YM, Firew BS. Factors associated with noncommunicable disease among adults in Mecha dis-<lb/>trict, Ethiopia: A case control study. PloS one. 2019; 14(5):e0216446. Epub 2019/05/30. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0216446 PMID: 31141502; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6542246. <lb/>5. Abebe SM, Andargie G, Shimeka A, Alemu K, Kebede Y, Wubeshet M, et al. The prevalence of non-<lb/>communicable diseases in northwest Ethiopia: survey of Dabat Health and Demographic Surveillance <lb/>System. BMJ open. 2017; 7(10):e015496. Epub 2017/10/25. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2016-<lb/>015496 PMID: 29061601; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5665308. <lb/>6. Prevett M. Chronic non-communicable diseases in Ethiopia-a hidden burden. Ethiopian journal of health <lb/>sciences. 2012; 22(Spec Iss):1. PMID: 23319834 <lb/>7. Giday A, Wolde M, Yihdego D. Hypertension, obesity and central obesity in diabetics and non diabetics <lb/>in Southern Ethiopia. Ethiopian Journal of Health Development. 2010; 24(2). <lb/>8. Abebe SM, Berhane Y, Worku A, Getachew A. Prevalence and associated factors of hypertension: a <lb/>crossectional community based study in northwest ethiopia. PloS one. 2015; 10(4):e0125210. Epub <lb/>2015/04/25. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0125210 PMID: 25909382; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC4409323. <lb/>9. Girum T, Mesfin D, Bedewi J, Shewangizaw M. The burden of noncommunicable diseases in Ethiopia, <lb/>2000-2016: analysis of evidence from global burden of disease study 2016 and global health estimates <lb/>2016. International journal of chronic diseases. 2020;2020. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/3679528 <lb/>PMID: 32149073 <lb/>10. UNDESA. World Population Prospects: The 2012 Revision, Key Findings and Advance Tables. United <lb/>Nations, Department of Economic and Social Affairs Population Division(UNDESA). Working Paper No. <lb/>ESA/P/WP.227 2013. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>11. Mathers CD, Loncar D. Projections of global mortality and burden of disease from 2002 to 2030. PLoS <lb/>medicine. 2006; 3(11):e442. Epub 2006/11/30. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030442 PMID: <lb/>17132052; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1664601. <lb/>12. WHO. World Health Organization. Projections of mortality and causes of death, 2015 and 2030 (http:// <lb/>www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/projections/en/, http://www.who.int/gho/ncd/mortality_ <lb/>morbidity/en/, accessed 8, January 2019) 2014. <lb/>13. EPHI. Summary Report On Ethiopia Steps Survey On Risk Factors For Chronic Noncommunicable Dis-<lb/>eases And Prevalence Of Selected NCDs. Ethiopian Public Health Institute (EPHI) and Ministry of <lb/>Health (MOH) 2016. <lb/>14. Misganaw A, Haregu TN, Deribe K, Tessema GA, Deribew A, Melaku YA, et al. National mortality bur-<lb/>den due to communicable, non-communicable, and other diseases in Ethiopia, 1990-2015: findings <lb/>from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. Population health metrics. 2017; 15:29. Epub 2017/07/ <lb/>25. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12963-017-0145-1 PMID: 28736507; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC5521057. <lb/>15. Ali MK, Rabadan-Diehl C, Flanigan J, Blanchard C, Narayan KM, Engelgau M. Systems and capacity to <lb/>address noncommunicable diseases in low-and middle-income countries. Science translational medi-<lb/>cine. 2013; 5(181):181cm4. Epub 2013/04/19. https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.3005121 PMID: <lb/>23596201. <lb/>16. WHO. Assessing national capacity for the prevention and control of noncommunicable diseases: report <lb/>of the 2017 global survey. Geneva: World Health Organization(WHO). Licence: CC BYNC-SA 3.0 IGO. <lb/>2018. <lb/>17. Peck R, Mghamba J, Vanobberghen F, Kavishe B, Rugarabamu V, Smeeth L, et al. Preparedness of <lb/>Tanzanian health facilities for outpatient primary care of hypertension and diabetes: a cross-sectional <lb/>survey. The Lancet Global health. 2014; 2(5):e285-92. Epub 2014/05/13. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S2214-109X(14)70033-6 PMID: 24818084; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4013553. <lb/>18. Getachew T, Bekele A, Amenu K, Defar A, Teklie H, Taye G, et al. Service availability and readiness for <lb/>major noncommunicable diseases at health facilities in Ethiopia Ethiop J Health Dev 2017 31((Special <lb/>Issue)):384-90. <lb/>19. Bekele A, Getachew T, Amenu K, Defar A, Teklie H, Gelibo T, et al. Service availability and readiness <lb/>for diabetes care at health facilities in Ethiopia. Ethiop J Health Dev 2017; 31(2):110-8. <lb/>20. Gelibo T, Getachew T, Bekele A, Defar A, Amenu K, Taddesse M, et al. Availability and readiness of <lb/>services for cancer care at health facilities in Ethiopia: Implication for action. Ethiop J Health Dev. 2017; <lb/>31((Special Issue)):391-6. <lb/>21. Fenta EH, Endris BS, Mengistu YG, Sadamo FE, Gelan EH, Beyene TG, et al. Landscape analysis of <lb/>nutrition services at Primary Health Care Units (PHCUs) in four districts of Ethiopia. PloS one. 2020; 15 <lb/>(12):e0243240. Epub 2020/12/04. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0243240 PMID: 33270764; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7714176. <lb/>22. FMoH. Health Sector Transformation Plan: 2015/16-2019/20. Addis Ababa: Ethiopia. Federal Demo-<lb/>cratic Republic of Ethiopia Ministry of Health (FMoH) 2015. <lb/>23. EPHI. Ethiopia Service Provision Assessment Plus (ESPA+) Survey 2014. Ethiopian Public Health <lb/>Institute (EPHI) and Ethiopian Ministry of Health (MOH) 2014. <lb/>24. EPHI. Ethiopia Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA) 2016 Summary Report. Ethio-<lb/>pian Public Health Institute (EPHI) and Ministry of Health (MOH) 2017 <lb/>25. EPHI. Ethiopia Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA) 2018 Final Report. Ethiopian <lb/>Public Health Institute (EPHI) and Ministry of Health (MOH) 2018. <lb/>26. WHO) WHO. Service availability and readiness assessment (SARA): an annual monitoring system for <lb/>service delivery: reference manual. No. WHO/HIS/HSI/RME/2013/1. World Health Organization World <lb/>Health Organization, 2015. <lb/>27. WHO. Service Availability and Readiness Assessment (SARA). An annual monitoring system for ser-<lb/>vice delivery Reference Manual. Version 2.1 September 2013. World Health Organization (WHO) <lb/>WHO/HIS/HSI/RME/2013/1 2013. <lb/>28. Maimela E, Alberts M, Bastiaens H, Fraeyman J, Meulemans H, Wens J, et al. Interventions for improv-<lb/>ing management of chronic non-communicable diseases in Dikgale, a rural area in Limpopo Province, <lb/>South Africa. BMC health services research. 2018; 18(1):331. Epub 2018/05/08. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1186/s12913-018-3085-y PMID: 29728147; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5935929. <lb/>29. Rogers HE, Akiteng AR, Mutungi G, Ettinger AS, Schwartz JI. Capacity of Ugandan public sector health <lb/>facilities to prevent and control non-communicable diseases: an assessment based upon WHO-PEN <lb/>standards. BMC health services research. 2018; 18(1):606. Epub 2018/08/08. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s12913-018-3426-x PMID: 30081898; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6080524. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 15 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>30. Muluneh AT, Haileamlak A, Tessema F, Alemseged F, Woldemichael K, Asefa M, et al. Population <lb/>based survey of chronic non-communicable diseases at gilgel gibe field research center, southwest <lb/>ethiopia. Ethiopian journal of health sciences. 2012; 22(S):7-18. Epub 2013/01/16. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1001/jama.289.18.2363 PMID: 23319836; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3542738. <lb/>31. WHO. Noncommunicable diseases country profiles 2011. Geneva: World Health Organization(WHO); <lb/>2011. p. 207 p. 2011. <lb/>32. WHO. Health system capacity for noncommunicable diseases management a global snapshot 2020. <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO) 23 August. 2020. <lb/>33. Musinguzi G, Bastiaens H, Wanyenze RK, Mukose A, Van Geertruyden JP, Nuwaha F. Capacity of <lb/>Health Facilities to Manage Hypertension in Mukono and Buikwe Districts in Uganda: Challenges and <lb/>Recommendations. PloS one. 2015; 10(11):e0142312. Epub 2015/11/13. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pone.0142312 PMID: 26560131; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4641641. <lb/>34. Bintabara D, Mpondo BCT. Preparedness of lower-level health facilities and the associated factors for <lb/>the outpatient primary care of hypertension: Evidence from Tanzanian national survey. PloS one. 2018; <lb/>13(2):e0192942. Epub 2018/02/16. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0192942 PMID: 29447231; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5814020. <lb/>35. Nyarko KM, Ameme DK, Ocansey D, Commeh E, Markwei MT, Ohene SA. Capacity assessment of <lb/>selected health care facilities for the pilot implementation of Package for Essential Non-communicable <lb/>Diseases (PEN) intervention in Ghana. The Pan African medical journal. 2016; 25(Suppl 1):16. Epub <lb/>2017/02/06. https://doi.org/10.11604/pamj.supp.2016.25.1.6252 PMID: 28149441; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC5257011. <lb/>36. Bischoff A, Ekoe T, Perone N, Slama S, Loutan L. Chronic disease management in Sub-Saharan Africa: <lb/>whose business is it? International journal of environmental research and public health. 2009; 6 <lb/>(8):2258-70. Epub 2009/09/11. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph6082258 PMID: 19742159; PubMed Cen-<lb/>tral PMCID: PMC2738886. <lb/>37. WHO. Global action plan for the prevention and control of noncommunicable diseases 2013-2020. <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO). ISBN 978 92 4 150623 6 2013. <lb/>38. Shayo FK, Bintabara D. Are Tanzanian health facilities ready to provide management of chronic respira-<lb/>tory diseases? An analysis of national survey for policy implications. PloS one. 2019; 14(1):e0210350. <lb/>Epub 2019/01/08. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210350 PMID: 30615663; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC6322729. <lb/>39. Van Minh H, Do YK, Bautista MA, Tuan Anh T. Describing the primary care system capacity for the pre-<lb/>vention and management of non-communicable diseases in rural Vietnam. The International journal of <lb/>health planning and management. 2014; 29(2):e159-73. Epub 2013/04/05. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>hpm.2179 PMID: 23553675. <lb/>40. Armstrong-Hough M, Kishore SP, Byakika S, Mutungi G, Nunez-Smith M, Schwartz JI. Disparities in <lb/>availability of essential medicines to treat non-communicable diseases in Uganda: A Poisson analysis <lb/>using the Service Availability and Readiness Assessment. PloS one. 2018; 13(2):e0192332. Epub <lb/>2018/02/09. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0192332 PMID: 29420640; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC5805288. <lb/>41. Mutale W, Bosomprah S, Shankalala P, Mweemba O, Chilengi R, Kapambwe S, et al. Assessing <lb/>capacity and readiness to manage NCDs in primary care setting: Gaps and opportunities based on <lb/>adapted WHO PEN tool in Zambia. PloS one. 2018; 13(8):e0200994. Epub 2018/08/24. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0200994 PMID: 30138318; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6107121. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Health system&apos;s availability and readiness of health facilities for chronic non-communicable diseases <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297622 February 23, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 15 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>