<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">An innovative model for an enhanced dual intrusion detection system using LZ‐JC‐DBSCAN, EPRC‐RPOA and EG‐GELU‐GRU</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jeyavim Sherin</forename>
          <surname>R. C.</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Parkavi</forename>
          <surname>K.</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T14:10:39.776Z">11/12/2025 2:10:39 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1049$1$cmu2.12831</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Institution of Engineering and Technology (IET)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1049/cmu2.12831</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Jeyavim Sherin R. C., Parkavi K.. (2024). An innovative model for an enhanced dual intrusion detection system using LZ‐JC‐DBSCAN, EPRC‐RPOA and EG‐GELU‐GRU. IET Communications, 18(18), 1300-1318. DOI: 10.1049/cmu2.12831</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T14:10:31.890714Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T14:10:31.890714Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Received: 19 July 2023 <lb/>Revised: 5 March 2024 <lb/>Accepted: 29 April 2024 <lb/>IET Renewable Power Generation <lb/>DOI: 10.1049/rpg2.13014 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Experimental investigation of BIPV/T application in winter <lb/>season under Şanlıurfa&apos;s meteorological conditions <lb/>Yusuf Can Demir 1 <lb/>Mehmet Azmi Aktacir 2 <lb/>1 Construction Works and Technical Department, <lb/>Kocaeli University, Umuttepe Campus, İzmit, Turkey <lb/>2 Department of Mechanical Engineering, <lb/>Engineering Faculty, Harran University, Osmanbey <lb/>Campus, Haliliye, Turkey <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Yusuf Can Demir, Construction Works and <lb/>Technical Department, Kocaeli University, <lb/>Umuttepe Campus, İzmit, 41001, Turkey. <lb/>Email: yusufcan.demir@kocaeli.edu.tr; <lb/>yusuf.91@hotmail.com <lb/>Funding information <lb/>Scientific Research Projects unit of Harran <lb/>University, Grant/Award Number: 22187; Kocaeli <lb/>University, TUBITAK ULAKBIM <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Considering that nearly 39% of the total CO 2 emission released into the atmosphere <lb/>today are thought to be due to the energy consumed by buildings, the importance of <lb/>taking measures through buildings to combat global warming is evident. Therefore, the <lb/>concept of nearly zero-energy buildings (NZEB) is come to the forefront. Building inte-<lb/>grated photovoltaic thermal (BIPV/T) systems are used to enable buildings to generate <lb/>their own energy. However, buildings have limited facade and roof areas required for <lb/>BIPV/T systems. Therefore, in this study, various configurations of bifacial (double-sided) <lb/>and monofacial (single-sided) panels were compared to investigate ways to enhance the <lb/>efficiency of BIPV/T systems. Different air flow velocities and varying air gap distances <lb/>were tested for both panel types. By placing a reflective surface on the wall behind the bifa-<lb/>cial panel, the electrical efficiency of the bifacial panel was increased and proven through <lb/>PVsyst analysis. Both panels provided maximum heat efficiency at the shortest air gap dis-<lb/>tance under high air flow conditions. In addition, it was shown in both the experimental <lb/>setup and Comsol CFD analysis that it provides significant benefit in the thermal energy <lb/>load of the building when heating the interior environment in winter. In terms of electrical <lb/>power production surplus, the bifacial panel outperformed the monofacial panel in all con-<lb/>figurations, with a minimum advantage of 8.33% and a maximum of 12.73%. Additionally, <lb/>the maximum electrical efficiency was obtained from the bifacial panel in configurations <lb/>with the longest air gap distance. Using the bifacial panel in the BIPV/T system with the <lb/>shortest air gap distance during the heating season and the longest air gap distance during <lb/>other seasons can provide the highest efficiency for the building throughout the year. <lb/>1 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>1.1 <lb/>Background <lb/>Due to the use of fossil fuels, the increasing greenhouse gas <lb/>emissions are causing global warming to rise day by day [1]. <lb/>It is known that in developing or emerging countries, nearly <lb/>40% of total energy consumption is consumed by buildings <lb/>[2]. Therefore, there is an increasing trend towards renew-<lb/>able energy sources and nearly zero-energy buildings (NZEB). <lb/>Among renewable energy sources, solar energy was one of the <lb/>most heavily invested sources in recent years [3]. Therefore, <lb/>there is a growing interest in building integrated photovoltaic <lb/>thermal (BIPV/T) systems in industrial and residential buildings <lb/>[4]. <lb/></body>

			<front>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited. <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). IET Renewable Power Generation published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Institution of Engineering and Technology. <lb/></front>

			<body>Solar radiation absorbed by PV cells but not converted into <lb/>electricity increases the temperature of the PV cells, which in <lb/>turn reduces their efficiency [5]. To overcome this problem, <lb/>air or water is used as a cooling fluid in PV panels [6]. Cooling <lb/>fluids are delivered to the panels through the integration of <lb/>thermal collectors with various designs. When the heated panel <lb/>comes into contact with the cooling fluid inside the thermal <lb/>collector, heat transfer occurs from the panel to the fluid. As <lb/>a result, cooling the panel increases its electrical efficiency, and <lb/>at the same time, hot air or water is obtained from its waste <lb/>heat. These systems are called Photovoltaic Thermal (PV/T) <lb/>systems [7]. Globally, in 2023, the PV/T collector area reached <lb/>1.5 million m 2 , equivalent to a thermal capacity of 789 MW and <lb/>an electrical capacity of 276 MWp [8]. This PV/T system, when <lb/>integrated into buildings and used by the building for both <lb/></body>

			<front>1626 <lb/>wileyonlinelibrary.com/iet-rpg <lb/>IET Renew. Power Gener. 2024;18:1626-1645. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1627 <lb/></page>

			<body>electricity and thermal energy, is referred to as the BIPV/T <lb/>system [9]. Due to being relatively new emerging systems <lb/>worldwide, the use of BIPV and BIPV/T systems continues <lb/>to increase annually. In terms of energy, globally, solar thermal <lb/>systems provided approximately a total of 440 TWh of heat <lb/>in 2022, while photovoltaic systems supplied 1312 TWh of <lb/>electricity [8]. <lb/>BIPV/T is a high-efficiency solar energy system with the <lb/>capability of producing hot air/water and electricity, aimed at <lb/>effectively meeting the energy demand of the building [10]. It <lb/>supports the electricity consumption needed in buildings. In <lb/>BIPV/T systems, the cooling fluid is used not only for cool-<lb/>ing the PV panel but also for the purpose of heat collection. <lb/>Especially in winter, it is used for heating the indoor spaces of <lb/>buildings, and in summer, it is used for hot water supply and <lb/>drying processes [11]. In addition, passive heating and lighting <lb/>of the interior using semi-transparent panels are among the pri-<lb/>mary benefits of the BIPV/T system. Thus, it minimizes the <lb/>utility bills for both electricity and building heating, leading to <lb/>economic savings. <lb/>Since BIPV/T systems utilize energy from the sun, they <lb/>can be used continuously. In addition, while producing energy, <lb/>it does not emit any gases to the environment like fossil <lb/>fuels, making it environmentally friendly. The CO 2 emissions <lb/>resulting from the energy consumed by buildings make up <lb/>approximately 39% of the total emissions [12]. When consider-<lb/>ing such a high rate of CO 2 emissions in buildings, the transition <lb/>to safe and sustainable energy production systems like BIPV/T <lb/>is being encouraged [13]. <lb/>BIPV/T systems can make significant contributions to envi-<lb/>ronmental considerations in the context of sustainable energy <lb/>solutions. By producing clean and renewable energy, it reduces <lb/>dependency on fossil fuel-based energy production and it can <lb/>reduce greenhouse gas emissions by up to 1/3 in both devel-<lb/>oped and developing countries. Additionally, up to 40% of <lb/>the global energy demand in these countries can be met with <lb/>BIPV/T. This can lead to reducing the carbon footprint orig-<lb/>inating from buildings to 0 [2]. BIPV/T panels might have a <lb/>lower environmental impact compared to other types of solar <lb/>panels. Because they are integrated into building structural ele-<lb/>ments, there&apos;s no need for additional land coverage, and they <lb/>contribute to the preservation of soil resources [14]. Since <lb/>BIPV/T systems can be integrated into the facades or roofs <lb/>of buildings, they can enhance the aesthetics of the buildings. <lb/>It allows buildings to meet their own energy needs, offering <lb/>the opportunity for on-site energy production. For this rea-<lb/>son, it reduces the need for long energy transmission lines <lb/>and encourages the more efficient use of energy resources <lb/>[15]. In conclusion, BIPV/T systems significantly support envi-<lb/>ronmental considerations in the context of sustainable energy <lb/>solutions. However, factors such as material selection, produc-<lb/>tion processes, waste management, and operation/maintenance <lb/>practices need to be taken into consideration. In this way, <lb/>these systems can both enhance energy efficiency and support <lb/>environmental sustainability [16]. <lb/>BIPV/T systems provide on-site electricity and heat energy <lb/>to buildings. However, they are typically mounted on the facade <lb/>or roof of the building, so they do not cover a large area. It is <lb/>essential for them to provide high energy efficiency in a small <lb/>area. Especially in locations where there are plenty of sunny <lb/>days, particularly during the winter season, higher efficiencies <lb/>can be achieved annually from this system. The aim of this <lb/>study was to investigate the parameters influencing the design <lb/>for increasing the energy production per unit area of BIPV/T <lb/>systems. <lb/>1.2 <lb/>Literature review <lb/>In the literature, various methods have been employed to <lb/>increase the efficiency of PV/T and BIPV/T systems. Among <lb/>these methods are the use of air or water at different flow <lb/>rates, variable panel transparencies, different air gap depths, <lb/>installation under various climate conditions, and different panel <lb/>technologies. Pantic et al. [17] indicated that with the increase <lb/>of fan speed, electrical energy also increases, and suggested an <lb/>optimal fan speed. According to the study, when wind speed <lb/>increased from 1 to 7 m/s, electrical efficiency increased by <lb/>1%, while thermal efficiency decreased by 6%. In their study, <lb/>Gül and Akyüz [18] found that in air-based PV/T (photo-<lb/>voltaic/thermal) systems with cooling applied, there was a <lb/>12.9% increase in electricity production compared to the case <lb/>without cooling. Teo et al. [19] demonstrated that the cooling <lb/>effect of an air-based PV/T system was enhanced by attach-<lb/>ing fins to the back of the PV panel, resulting in improved <lb/>PV performance. In another similar study, conducted by Saygın <lb/>et al. [20], the size of the air channel and airflow rate used to <lb/>cool the panel surface were optimized to increase the electrical <lb/>efficiency. Mojumder et al. [21] found the highest thermal effi-<lb/>ciency of 56.19% in a high-fin arrangement under maximum <lb/>flow and irradiance settings. It was shown by M. Hajji et al. <lb/>[22] that in the PVT system, the panel temperature decreases <lb/>and its performance increases with an increasing water flow <lb/>rate. According to the research conducted by Tina et al. [23], <lb/>the BIPV system using ventilated bifacial panels provided 2.9% <lb/>more power compared to the ventilated conventional BIPV sys-<lb/>tem, and 4.4% more power compared to the non-ventilated <lb/>conventional BIPV system. In the study conducted by Wajs <lb/>et al. [24], it was observed that by passing air behind the PV <lb/>panel mounted on a tile frame, there was an increase of 9.5% <lb/>in electrical efficiency and 18.3% in thermal efficiency. In the <lb/>study conducted by Kabul and Duran [25], it was found that <lb/>the maximum electrical power in the PV/T panel, where water <lb/>is passed as the fluid for cooling, is 35% higher compared <lb/>to the panel where no cooling is applied. In the experiment <lb/>conducted by Cuce and Cuce [26], it was determined using <lb/>fluent CFD that the PV power output increased with cooling <lb/>applications, and the most effective PV cooling configuration <lb/>was found to be at an air velocity of 1 m/s and 15 • C air <lb/>temperature. <lb/>Another parameter that increases electrical efficiency is the <lb/>transparency of the panel material. Kamthania et al. [27] com-<lb/>pared opaque and semi-transparent panels in a double-pass <lb/>BIPV/T system and found that due to the heat retention <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1628 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>property of opaque panels, semi-transparent panels have a <lb/>higher electrical performance. Yang and Athienitis [28] studied <lb/>BIPV/T systems with opaque and semi-transparent PV panels <lb/>and found that the thermal efficiency of the semi-transparent <lb/>panel was 7.6% higher. <lb/>Among the factors that affect electrical and thermal effi-<lb/>ciency, the depth of the channel distance from the back surface <lb/>of the panel to the other surface also plays a significant role. <lb/>Xu et al. [10] found that in cases with 57 and 25 mm channel <lb/>depths of PVs, the inlet and outlet air temperature difference <lb/>was formed in the case with a maximum channel depth of <lb/>25 mm, and the thermal efficiency increased as the channel <lb/>depth decreased. In the study conducted by Kaiser et al. [29], <lb/>it was found that in a natural ventilation scenario of an air-based <lb/>PV/T system, the cell temperature reaches its minimum when <lb/>the channel depth/channel length ratio is 0.11. In addition, a <lb/>19% increase in power output was observed at air velocities <lb/>ranging from 0.5 to 6 m/s. In their study, Kim et al. [30] exam-<lb/>ined the effect of air flow rate and channel size on the thermal <lb/>efficiency of a PV/T panel. The study showed that along with a <lb/>22% thermal efficiency of the system, there was a 5 • C increase <lb/>in air temperature. <lb/>The efficiencies of BIPV/T systems can vary depending on <lb/>climatic conditions. For example, Bot et al. [31] demonstrated <lb/>that a BIPV/T system exposed to the temperate environment <lb/>in Portugal had a thermal efficiency ranging from 3.3% to <lb/>4% and an electrical efficiency of 15.1%. In addition, in the <lb/>BIPV/T study conducted by Xu et al. [10] in Beijing, Hefei, <lb/>and Xining, the annual total energy savings in the three cities <lb/>were measured as 2661.8, 1908.4, and 2412.3 kWh, respectively. <lb/>Kamel and Fung [32] combined an air-source heat pump with <lb/>a BIPV/T system to create a highly efficient heating system <lb/>for Canada&apos;s cold climate and achieved an annual savings of <lb/>500 dollars. Luo et al. [33] found that in China, the PV/T-air-<lb/>water facade system had an average daily efficiency of 7.8% <lb/>for the PV/T-water mode during the summer months, with a <lb/>total energy production of 973 kJ. During the transition period, <lb/>the efficiency increased to 11.6%, resulting in 3226.4 kJ of <lb/>total energy production. The system&apos;s energy production and <lb/>efficiency increased from summer to winter. Shao et al. [34] <lb/>demonstrated that in the city of Dalian, China, the summer <lb/>maximum electrical, thermal, and overall efficiencies of the mul-<lb/>ticrystalline silicon hybrid BIPV/T system were 11.22%, 111%, <lb/>and 86%, respectively. In winter, these efficiencies decreased to <lb/>10.58%, 81%, and 58%, respectively. <lb/>PV panel technology is one of the parameters that affect <lb/>the efficiencies of BIPV/T systems. Aaditya et al. [35] stud-<lb/>ied amorphous silicon (a-Si) and mono-crystalline silicon (m-Si) <lb/>for the BIPV/T system. According to the analyses, while a-Si <lb/>exhibited better performance, m-Si provided higher electrical <lb/>efficiency. Urbanetz et al. [36] compared a BIPV with a-Si <lb/>technology to a curved PV system and noted that a-Si has a <lb/>higher annual energy gain. In the study by Pereira and Aelenei <lb/>[6], phase-changing gypsum board material was added to the <lb/>wall part of the BIPV/T system, and this system was analysed. <lb/>Up to 64% maximum thermal efficiency was achieved in win-<lb/>ter tests, while up to 32% efficiency was obtained in summer <lb/>tests. <lb/>1.3 <lb/>Contribution of the research <lb/>In the current literature, it was observed that there are more <lb/>studies on PV/T systems compared to those on BIPV/T <lb/>systems. This indicates potential research gaps for BIPV/T sys-<lb/>tems and presents opportunities for future research [37]. In <lb/>the literature, monofacial (single-sided) panels are generally pre-<lb/>ferred to increase the thermal and electrical efficiencies of PV/T <lb/>and BIPV/T systems. No BIPV/T study comparing bifacial and <lb/>monofacial panels under the same conditions were encountered <lb/>in the literature. <lb/>This study offers an innovative perspective by exploring the <lb/>potential of bifacial panels to meet the thermal and electrical <lb/>energy needs of buildings in Şanlıurfa, Turkey, under cold cli-<lb/>mate conditions. The innovation in the study is the comparison <lb/>of monofacial and bifacial panels with the same electrical pro-<lb/>duction capacity under equal conditions in the BIPV/T system. <lb/>The most notable innovation of the study is placed a reflective <lb/>surface on the building wall behind the bifacial panel to enhance <lb/>production from its rear side. In addition, different air gap dis-<lb/>tances and air speeds were used for both panels. Given that the <lb/>study was conducted on the experimental building setup during <lb/>winter conditions, another innovation of the research is deter-<lb/>mining the degree of improvement in the indoor temperature <lb/>compared to the outdoor temperature. <lb/>This study provides valuable insights into the potential <lb/>advantages of bifacial panels for residential and industrial build-<lb/>ings in Şanlıurfa by comparing the performance of a single-sided <lb/>PV panel with that of a bifacial PV panel under the same <lb/>conditions. <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Structure of the paper <lb/>BIPV/T system was installed on the southern facade of the <lb/>examined building, and the effectiveness of structural and <lb/>physical parameters such as panel surface temperature, air tem-<lb/>perature, panel technology, ventilation, which have an impact <lb/>on the electrical and thermal performance of photovoltaic pan-<lb/>els, was experimentally investigated. In the experiment, both <lb/>bifacial and monofacial photovoltaic panels were tested. An alu-<lb/>minium foil was placed as a reflector on the surface of the <lb/>wall behind the bifacial glass-glass photovoltaic panel. Energy <lb/>efficiency is compared with the monofacial PV panel with <lb/>the same potential placed next to this panel. In addition, the <lb/>effect of air cooling by passing airflow through the intervals <lb/>between the wall and the panel using a fan was determined <lb/>on energy efficiency. The effectiveness of using this airflow <lb/>in space heating was determined in terms of its impact on <lb/>the efficiency of the heating system. The experimental setup <lb/>was compared with real data by simulating it in the PVSYST <lb/>program [38]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1629 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 1 (a) Exterior view of BIPV/T system design. (b) Interior view. BIPV/T, Building integrated photovoltaic thermal <lb/>TABLE 1 Container specifications and dimensions. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Length, width, height, thickness: <lb/>1.98 m, 2.96 m, 2.45 m, 5 cm <lb/>Material <lb/>EPS-filled sandwich panel. <lb/>Wall insulation <lb/>Thermal insulated polystyrene foam with <lb/>a density of 14 kg/m 3 <lb/>Roof insulation <lb/>Thermal insulated foam with a density of <lb/>14 kg/m 3 and a thickness of 110 mm <lb/>Exterior door <lb/>Metal-framed PVC window profile with a <lb/>40 mm sandwich panel <lb/>Window <lb/>Single casement PVC window with a <lb/>4 + 12 + 4 mm double-glazed unit <lb/>2 <lb/>MATERIAL AND METHODS <lb/>2.1 <lb/>Experimental design and setup <lb/>The aim of this study was to investigate the BIPV/T appli-<lb/>cation under the meteorological conditions of Şanlıurfa. For <lb/>this purpose, the experimental setup was established at Harran <lb/>University GAP-YENEV Research and Application Center. In <lb/>this study, the container shown in Figure 1a,b was used. Vari-<lb/>ous characteristics of this structure are provided in Table 1. A <lb/>BIPV/T system was created by placing one bifacial and one <lb/>monofacial PV panel on the southern facade of this structure <lb/>(Figure 1a). The position of the fans that provide air movement <lb/>inside and the air vents are shown in Figure 1b. <lb/>The technical characteristics of the monofacial and bifacial <lb/>panels used in the experimental setup are presented in Table 2. <lb/>EPS, Expanded polistyren foam. PVC Polyvinyl chloride. <lb/>The cross-sectional view of the experimental BIPV/T model <lb/>examined in this study is illustrated in Figure 2. The front <lb/>surfaces of the panels were mounted vertically relative to the <lb/>ground and facing south on the wall of the container. The inci-<lb/>dent solar radiation on the front surface will generate electrical <lb/>energy from the PV panels and increase the surface tempera-<lb/>ture. The air taken from the indoor environment is directed to <lb/>the back of the PV panel with the help of a fan, and the heated <lb/>air is then expelled back into the indoor environment through <lb/>the upper air vent. The back wall of the bifacial BIPV/T sys-<lb/>TABLE 2 Bifacial and monofacial panel features. <lb/>Properties <lb/>Bifacial panel <lb/>Monofacial panel <lb/>Max Power (1000 W/m 2 ) <lb/>335 W <lb/>335 W <lb/>Maximum power voltage (V mp ) 34.56 V <lb/>34.97 V <lb/>Maximum power current (I mp ) <lb/>9.7 A <lb/>9.63 A <lb/>Open-circuit voltage V oc (V) <lb/>40.65 V <lb/>42.33 V <lb/>Short-circuit current I sc (A) <lb/>10.69 A <lb/>10.18 A <lb/>Performance (%) <lb/>20.05% <lb/>20.07% <lb/>Temperature coefficient P MAX <lb/>-0.38%/K <lb/>-0.37%/K <lb/>Temperature coefficient V OC <lb/>-0.29%/K <lb/>-0.28%/K <lb/>Temperature coefficient I SC <lb/>0.04%/K <lb/>0.048%/K <lb/>Nominal operating temperature 46 o C <lb/>4 5 ± 2 o C <lb/>Transparency <lb/>Translucent <lb/>Opaque <lb/>Front cover <lb/>2 mm low iron <lb/>tempered solar <lb/>glass <lb/>Glass <lb/>Cell matrix <lb/>60 cells (6 × 10) <lb/>60 cells (6 × 10) <lb/>Module dimensions <lb/>1670 mm x <lb/>1000 mm <lb/>1665 mm x 1002 mm <lb/>Weight <lb/>20.1 kg <lb/>19 kg <lb/>tem is covered with aluminium foil, which enhances its reflective <lb/>properties. An interval is left between the PV panel and the <lb/>back wall, and a transparent tarpaulin is installed between the <lb/>PV panel and the wall to prevent air leakage. <lb/>Three different intervals, measuring 5.5, 8.5, and 11.5 cm, are <lb/>left between the wall and the PV panel. Thus, in the BIPV/T <lb/>application, three different intervals were achieved using the <lb/>sliding mechanism shown in Figure 3. <lb/>The energy generated by the panels used in the BIPV/T <lb/>application is sent to the micro inverter used in the system. The <lb/>connection was made with the wiring shown in green colour in <lb/>Figure 4. The direct current (DC) reaching the micro inverter <lb/>was converted to alternating current (AC) and connected to the <lb/>grid through the electrical cable (shown in orange colour in the <lb/>diagram). The energy generated by the PV panel is being mea-<lb/>sured instantly in the micro inverter. The data flow from the <lb/>micro inverter is transferred to the cloud system every 15 min <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1630 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 2 Cross-sectional representation of the BIPV/T system design for the bifacial and monofacial panel. BIPV/T, Building integrated photovoltaic <lb/>thermal. <lb/>FIGURE 3 Demonstration of the design of the sliding mechanism <lb/>apparatus drawn in SolidWorks. <lb/>as watts through the data transfer unit (DTU). Access to this <lb/>information is possible through the application provided by <lb/>the manufacturer of the inverter, either via mobile devices or <lb/>web-based platforms. The technical specifications of the micro <lb/>inverter and DTU are provided in Table 3. <lb/>The points measured in the experimental study are schemat-<lb/>ically shown in Figure 4. Here, the ends of the thermocouple <lb/>cables, which are placed at ten different points for tempera-<lb/>ture measurement, are indicated in yellow colour. Data logger <lb/>connections were made with the thermocouples, and measure-<lb/>ments were taken every 10 min. In addition, the solar radiation <lb/>intensity was measured using a pyranometer placed on the south <lb/>facade and recorded every 10 min on data logger. The techni-<lb/>cal specifications of the pyranometer and data logger device are <lb/>provided in Table 4. <lb/>To obtain temperature measurements from various points of <lb/>the container, 10 T-type thermocouple cables were used. The <lb/>temperature of the air entering the air duct from the indoor <lb/>environment was measured using thermocouple cables num-<lb/>bered 1 and 2, located in the lower part of the air channels <lb/>on the southern facade. For temperature measurements num-<lb/>bered 3 and 4, the cables were mounted respectively on the <lb/>exit side of the air channels of bifacial and monofacial pho-<lb/>tovoltaic panels. The objective at these points is to determine <lb/>the temperature difference by measuring the temperature of the <lb/>air entering the lower channel with cables numbered 1 and 2 <lb/>and the temperature of the air when it enters the indoor envi-<lb/>ronment after being heated in the channel. The 5th and 6th <lb/>temperature measurement points are, respectively, the bifacial <lb/>panel and the monofacial panel. Termocouple cables for tem-<lb/>perature measurements on the panels were attached to the back <lb/>of the panels using special adhesive tape. The seventh and eighth <lb/>temperature measurements were attached to the walls behind <lb/>the bifacial panel and the monofacial panel, respectively, in order <lb/>to measure the temperatures of the walls (Figure 4). <lb/>At points 9 and 10, the temperatures of the outdoor and <lb/>indoor environments were measured. The temperature of the <lb/>indoor environment was measured using a thermocouple cable <lb/>placed on the inner ceiling of the container. In order to measure <lb/>the outdoor temperature accurately and from a location shielded <lb/>from direct sunlight, the thermocouple probe was placed inside <lb/>a shade apparatus (Figure 5). <lb/>The holes with a diameter of 15.2 cm were punched into the <lb/>walls corresponding to the bottom and top sections of the pan-<lb/>els in order to prepare the air channels. The 15 cm diameter flex <lb/>pipes were connected to the lower holes by applying silicone, <lb/>forming a seal. A fan is connected to each of the other ends of <lb/>the flex pipes to ensure air circulation (Figure 1b). The power <lb/>consumed by the fans was measured using a wattmeter. When <lb/>the fans were operating at low speed, the average air velocity <lb/>was measured as 9.8 m/s, the average volumetric flow rate was <lb/>found to be 278 m 3 /h, and the power consumption was mea-<lb/>sured as 32 W. When the fans were operating at high speed, <lb/>the average air velocity was measured as 12.9 m/s, the aver-<lb/>age volumetric flow rate was found to be 366 m 3 /h, and the <lb/>power consumption was measured as 57 W. Figure 6 shows a <lb/>photograph of the experimental setup used in this study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1631 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE 3 Technical specifications of micro inverter and DTU device. DTU, Data transfer unit. <lb/>Hoymiles Micro inverter technical specifications Model: <lb/>MI-1500 (up to 4 × 470 W panels) <lb/>Hoymiles DTU technical specifications model: DTU-Pro <lb/>Max input voltage <lb/>60 V D.C. <lb/>Signal to communicate with cloud <lb/>WLAN (802.11b/g/n)*1/ Ethernet <lb/>Range of peak power MPPT Voltage <lb/>36-48 V D.C. <lb/>Saving contact information to the <lb/>cloud <lb/>Every 15 min <lb/>Range of input operating Voltage <lb/>16-60 V D.C. <lb/>Communication signal with S-miles <lb/>cloud <lb/>2.4 GHz <lb/>Start-up voltage <lb/>22 V D.C. <lb/>Maximum distance signal with S-miles <lb/>cloud <lb/>200 m <lb/>Max continuous input current <lb/>4*11.5 A D.C. <lb/>Total number of solar panels that can <lb/>be measured <lb/>99 panel <lb/>Max input short circuit current <lb/>4*15 A D.C. <lb/>Informational LED lights <lb/>4 Led: run, cloud, internet, warning <lb/>Max continuous output power <lb/>1500 W <lb/>Power source type <lb/>External power supply (mains <lb/>power) <lb/>Max continuous output current <lb/>7.5 A A.C. <lb/>Power supply input voltage/frequency <lb/>240 V/AC / 50 or 60 Hz <lb/>Nominal output voltage <lb/>220/230/240 V A.C. <lb/>Power supply output voltage/current <lb/>5 V / 2 A <lb/>Nominal output frequency <lb/>50/60 Hz <lb/>Power consumption <lb/>2.5 W (nom), 5 W (max) <lb/>Peak conversion efficiency <lb/>96.6 % <lb/>Working environment temperature <lb/>range <lb/>-20 • C / +55 • C <lb/>Output power factor <lb/>&gt;0.99 <lb/>Dimensions <lb/>200/101/29 mm (except antenna) <lb/>Type of enclosure <lb/>IP67 <lb/>Weight <lb/>0.28 kg <lb/>Over voltage category <lb/>PV:II, Mains:III <lb/>Mounting options <lb/>Wall/table mount <lb/>Operating ambient temp. <lb/>-40 ̴ + 65 o C <lb/>TABLE 4 Technical specifications of pyranometer and sdata logger device. <lb/>EKO pyranometer technical specifications model: MS-602 <lb/>Hioki data logger technical specifications model: LR8402-20 <lb/>ISO 9060 class <lb/>Second class <lb/>Number of channels <lb/>30 standard channels <lb/>Response time (%95) (s) <lb/>&lt; 17 <lb/>Voltage <lb/>±10 mV to ± 100 V, 1-5 V fs Max. <lb/>resolution: 500 nV, <lb/>Fine-tuning (zero offset) Thermal <lb/>radiation (200 W/m 2 ) <lb/>+ 10 W/m 2 <lb/>Thermocouple temperature range <lb/>-200 to 2000 • C Max. resolution 0.01 • C <lb/>Fine-tuning (zero offset) <lb/>Temperature change (5K/hr) <lb/>&lt;6 W/m 2 <lb/>Uyumlu termokupl türleri <lb/>(K, J, E, T, N, R, S, B, W) <lb/>Non-stability (change / year) <lb/>&lt;1.7% <lb/>Pt 100, JPt 100 sensor temperature range <lb/>-200 to 800 • C Max. resolution 0.01 • C <lb/>Non-linearity (1000 W/m 2 ) <lb/>&lt;1.5% <lb/>Resistance <lb/>0 Ω to 200 Ω fs Max. resolution 0.5 mΩ <lb/>Directional response (1000 W/m 2 ) <lb/>&lt;25 W/m 2 <lb/>Humidity <lb/>%5.0-95.0 Relative humidity <lb/>Spectral selectivity (0.35 -1.5 µm) <lb/>&lt;1% <lb/>Max. nominal voltage between isolated input <lb/>channels <lb/>300 V DC <lb/>Temperature response (50 • C) <lb/>&lt;2% <lb/>Max. allowed entry <lb/>±100 V DC <lb/>Tilt response (1000 W/m 2 ) <lb/>&lt;2% <lb/>Max. rated voltage from isolated terminals to <lb/>ground <lb/>300 V AC, DC <lb/>Rated sensitivity (µV/W/m 2 ) <lb/>7 <lb/>Power supply type <lb/>Mains and battery <lb/>Rated impedance (ohm) <lb/>20-140 <lb/>Memory <lb/>USB or CF card <lb/>Operating temperature, o C <lb/>-40 ∼ 80 o C between <lb/>Screen <lb/>5.7 inch TFT colour display <lb/>Wavelength range (permeability <lb/>more than 50%) <lb/>305-2800 nm between <lb/>USB interface <lb/>USB 2.0 high-speed capable, serial mini-B <lb/>socket <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1632 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE Design of measurement points and measurement instruments. <lb/>FIGURE The ninth measurement point was placed inside the shade <lb/>apparatus for measuring the outdoor temperature. <lb/>FIGURE External appearance of the installed BIPV/T system. <lb/>TABLE 5 Experimental study plan. <lb/>BIPV/T <lb/>configuration <lb/>PV-wall range <lb/>(cm) <lb/>Fan speed <lb/>(m/s) <lb/>Date of the <lb/>experiment <lb/>1. Configuration <lb/>5.5 (1. Distance) <lb/>High speed <lb/>16 February 2023 <lb/>2. Configuration <lb/>8.5 (2. Distance) <lb/>High speed <lb/>17 February 2023 <lb/>3. Configuration <lb/>11.5 (3. Distance) <lb/>High speed <lb/>20 February 2023 <lb/>4. Configuration <lb/>5.5 (1. Distance) <lb/>Low speed <lb/>21 February 2023 <lb/>5. Configuration <lb/>8.5 (2. Distance) <lb/>Low speed <lb/>22 February 2023 <lb/>6. Configuration <lb/>11.5 (3. Distance) <lb/>Low speed <lb/>23 February 2023 <lb/>7. Configuration <lb/>5.5 (1. Distance) <lb/>Fanless <lb/>24 February 2023 <lb/>8. Configuration <lb/>8.5 (2. Distance) <lb/>Fanless <lb/>25 February 2023 <lb/>9. Configuration <lb/>11.5 (3. Distance) <lb/>Fanless <lb/>26 February 2023 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>Conducting the experiment <lb/>This study covers experiments conducted over a total of 9 days <lb/>in February 2023, from 9:00 in the morning to 17:00 in the <lb/>evening, to determine the effectiveness of BIPV/T application <lb/>during the heating season (winter) under the meteorological <lb/>conditions of Şanlıurfa. To better demonstrate the effective-<lb/>ness of the BIPV/T system and to increase indoor temperature <lb/>during the winter season, experiments were conducted on the <lb/>following sunny days as specified below. <lb/>In the experimental setup, the photovoltaic panels used were <lb/>tested on a sliding system at three different intervals from the <lb/>wall and under three different air velocities. The fan speeds were <lb/>0.4 m/s (natural air flow), 9.8 m/s (low fan speed), and 12.9 m/s <lb/>(high fan speed). <lb/>The BIPV/T configuration and experimental parameters <lb/>investigated in this study are presented in Table 5. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1633 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 7 Flowchart of equations used in calculation methods. <lb/>2.3 <lb/>Calculation method <lb/>In this section, the calculation procedures related to the data <lb/>obtained from the experimental measurements were described. <lb/>Here, calculations related to the thermal energy and efficiency <lb/>as well as electrical energy and efficiency of the BIPV/T system <lb/>are given. <lb/>To determine the heat energy transferred to the indoor envi-<lb/>ronment, it is necessary to find the mass flow rate of the air 𝑚 <lb/>(kg/s) and Q˙a ir (kJ/s) values. For this, the formula for the volu-<lb/>metric flow rate of air was given in Equation (1) on the flowchart <lb/>in Figure 7. In the experimental setup, the volumetric flow rates <lb/>measured with an anemometer are 0.101 m 3 /s when the fans <lb/>are operating at high speed, 0.077 m 3 /s when the fans are oper-<lb/>ating at low speed, and 0.00314 m 3 /s in the fanless condition <lb/>[39]. In Equation (2,) the ρ value represents the density of air, <lb/>and it has been taken as 1.1839 kg/m 3 in this study. The val-<lb/>ues V (m/s) and A (m 2 ) represent the air velocity and the air <lb/>hole area, respectively. Their multiplication gives the previously <lb/>calculated volumetric flow rate. The product of the volumetric <lb/>flow rate Ʋ (m 3 /s) and the density ρ (kg/s) equals the mass flow <lb/>rate <lb/>. <lb/>m (kg/s) [39]. <lb/>After calculating the mass flow rate of the air, the equations <lb/>given in (3) and (4) were used to determine the thermal power <lb/>and energy gained from the air, respectively. <lb/>Equation (3) is used to calculate the thermal energy gained by <lb/>the air inside the air duct (refer to Figure 2). In this equation, T o <lb/>( • C) represents the temperature of the air entering the channel <lb/>cavity of the photovoltaic panel from the lower hole. T 1 ( • C) <lb/>represents the temperature of the air entering the indoor envi-<lb/>ronment from the upper hole, which increases as a result of the <lb/>solar radiation in the channel cavity. Another parameter used in <lb/>this equation is c p (kJ/kg • C), which represents the specific heat <lb/>capacity of air at constant pressure. This value is c p = 1,0057 <lb/>(kJ/(kg • C)), is valid for air between -100 • C and +100 • C <lb/>[39]. These calculations were made for both photovoltaic <lb/>panels. <lb/>In addition to the thermal power determined by Equation <lb/>(3), the total energy produced in various timeframes such as <lb/>daily, monthly, etc., is calculated in kWh using Equation (4) in <lb/>the study. The h value in Equation (4) represents the duration of <lb/>the operation in hours (Figure 7). <lb/>In general, the thermal efficiency (𝜂 t ) of photovoltaic pan-<lb/>els is calculated using Equation (5). The Q˙(kW) value here is <lb/>the thermal power calculated in Equation (3). I T is the average <lb/>amount of solar radiation per day per unit area and is the unit <lb/>W/m 2 . A represents the panel area, and its unit is m 2 . Both <lb/>panel areas are approximately 1.67 m 2 . <lb/>In determining the electrical power of photovoltaic pan-<lb/>els, the product of the instantaneous current (in amperes) <lb/>and voltage (in volts) gives the power value (P) in watts <lb/>(W). In this study, the power values are directly measured <lb/>using microinverters. Similarly, the electrical energy values <lb/>(kWh) for the operating durations are also determined using <lb/>Equation (6). <lb/>In Equations (6) and (7), the P (kW) value represents the <lb/>electrical power. The electrical power is measured by the micro <lb/>inverter in the experimental setup and converted to energy unit. <lb/>Equation (7) is used to determine the electrical efficiency. I T is <lb/>the average daily amount of solar radiation per unit area and is <lb/>the unit W/m 2 . A represents the panel area, and its unit is m 2 <lb/>(Figure 7). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1634 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 8 Experimental setup installation in PVsyst program. PVsyst, Photovoltaic software. <lb/>2.4 <lb/>PVsyst simulation study and Comsol <lb/>CFD analysis <lb/>In this study, the investigated BIPV/T model was created in the <lb/>PVsyst program, as shown in Figure 8, and a 1-year simulation <lb/>was conducted. <lb/>The photovoltaic panels selected for this study are monofa-<lb/>cial and bifacial panels with a power rating of 335 W. The area <lb/>where the panels are placed was drawn in the program based <lb/>on the dimensions of the container, leaving ≈9 cm interval <lb/>between the panel and the container wall. In order to simulate <lb/>the meteorological conditions specific to Şanlıurfa, the map of <lb/>the program was marked with the location of the experimen-<lb/>tal study at Harran University GAPYENEV Center. Hoymiles <lb/>brand MI-500 microinverters with a power rating of 500 W <lb/>were selected for each panel. Both panels were set to have a tilt <lb/>angle of 90 • and an azimuth angle of 0 • , ensuring that they face <lb/>directly south. Since the panels are positioned vertically, their <lb/>surfaces do not accumulate dust. Therefore, a pollution rate of <lb/>0% was assumed in the program. <lb/>The monthly and annual production values obtained from <lb/>the program were compared with the results obtained in the <lb/>experimental study to analyse and compare the production <lb/>values. <lb/>In addition to the analysis of electrical energy with PVsyst, <lb/>the temperature distribution of the configuration conducted on <lb/>February 24th has been thoroughly examined using the Com-<lb/>sol CFD simulation program. The study was conducted as <lb/>three-dimensional modelling. Therefore, the upper part of the <lb/>structure (+z axis) was defined with sunlight, reflecting the con-<lb/>tinuously changing weather conditions as it occurs in the real <lb/>world. The sun was set to rise and set between the -x and +x <lb/>axes, from east to west. The Comsol mesh module was preferred <lb/>for mesh distribution, and a total of 118,504 tetrahedral meshes <lb/>were generated (Figure 9). The PARDISO solver was utilized <lb/>as a solution method for high performance, robustness, multi-<lb/>processor memory, and efficient utilization (Sogukpinar, 2019; <lb/>Pardiso, 2022). To eliminate the domain size effect on the com-<lb/>putational results, the computational domain size was simulated <lb/>by expending the air portion by ten times the length of each <lb/>edge of the model. <lb/>3 <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Figure 10 presents the experimental results obtained on Febru-<lb/>ary 16th. The experiment was conducted at a distance of first <lb/>(5.5 cm) with the fans operating at high speed. The solar radia-<lb/>tion intensity was 509 W/m 2 at 9:00 am and reached its peak at <lb/>12:00 am with a value of 827 W/m 2 . With this increase, the tem-<lb/>perature of the panels, panel walls, and indoor environment also <lb/>increased. However, the maximum temperature was obtained <lb/>at the highest air temperature points. While the air tempera-<lb/>ture was 8.14 • C at 13:40, the temperature of the bifacial panel <lb/>was 37.1 • C and the temperature of the monofacial panel was <lb/>41.1 • C. Although the temperature of the monofacial panel is <lb/>higher, the temperature of its back wall is lower compared to <lb/>the temperature of the back wall behind the bifacial panel. Due <lb/>to the bifacial panel&apos;s glass-glass and transparent construction, <lb/>it allows for easier transfer of the temperature formed on its sur-<lb/>face to its backside. Consequently, it was observed that the use <lb/>of glass-glass bifacial panels in BIPV/T systems reduces electri-<lb/>cal efficiency losses due to temperature compared to monofacial <lb/>panels. In addition, the external temperature was measured as <lb/>8.14 • C while the internal temperature was measured as 26 • C. <lb/>When the fans were operating at high speed during the time <lb/>when the internal and external temperatures were at their high-<lb/>est, an approximate temperature gain of 18 • C was achieved in <lb/>the internal environment. This indicates that the BIPV/T sys-<lb/>tem is a suitable heating system for buildings and can result in <lb/>fuel cost savings during winter. <lb/>Measurements were taken for nine different configura-<lb/>tions as detailed in Table 5 in the experimental setup. <lb/>In Figure 11, daily average radiation and daily average <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1635 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 9 Mesh distribution on the container structure. <lb/>FIGURE 10 Radiation and temperature data obtained during the experimental setup on 16 February 2023. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1636 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 11 Data of daily irradiance and temperature averages taken in nine different configurations. <lb/>temperature values for all experimental configurations are <lb/>provided. <lb/>The daily average temperature distribution obtained from the <lb/>indoor ambient temperature during the days of the experiments <lb/>was determined to range between 20.5 and 33 • C. The daily aver-<lb/>age outdoor temperature during the same period varies between <lb/>6.7 and 18 • C. The temperature difference between the indoor <lb/>and outdoor temperatures was found to be between 12 and <lb/>15 • C. As previously mentioned, this showed that the BIPV/T <lb/>system can support the heating system. <lb/>In the experiments conducted on February 16, 17 and 20, in <lb/>which the fan worked at high speed, the amount of radiation <lb/>decreased day by day respectively. Despite this, the tempera-<lb/>tures in the two panels and their walls gradually increased toward <lb/>February 20. As the panels moved away from the wall, the circu-<lb/>lated air reduced the cooling effect on the panel. The panel was <lb/>found to achieve the best cooling when it was positioned at a <lb/>distance of 5.5 cm from the wall. In addition, it was determined <lb/>that the cooling performance is best when the mass flow rate of <lb/>the air is 0.1196 kg/s, which corresponds to the fan operating at <lb/>high speed. As a result, it can be concluded that the amount of <lb/>heat energy supplied to the indoor environment is most effec-<lb/>tive when the panels are positioned at a distance of 5.5 cm. In <lb/>the experiment conducted by Sopian et al. [40], it was found that <lb/>in an air-based double-pass PV/T system with a 5 cm air inter-<lb/>val, increasing the flow rate between 0.018-0.04 kg/s resulted <lb/>in an increase in both electrical and thermal efficiency. Fur-<lb/>thermore, Sopian&apos;s study found that increasing the mass flow <lb/>rate significantly contributed to the cooling of the panel. On <lb/>February 21, 22, and 23 (Figure 11), similarly, despite a decrease <lb/>in solar radiation intensity, the panel temperatures decreased <lb/>to a lesser extent. During the mentioned dates, when the fans <lb/>were operating at low speed (0.0912 kg/s), the panels were best <lb/>cooled when the distance between the panels and the wall was <lb/>5.5 cm. As the distance of the air interval increased, the cooling <lb/>effect of the panels by the air decreased. <lb/>On February 24, 25, and 26, when the panels were cooled <lb/>with natural air flow (0.0037 kg/s) without fans, the panel <lb/>temperature increased significantly compared to the parame-<lb/>ters with forced convection. In the study conducted by Cuce <lb/>and Cuce [26], it was mentioned that the temperature of the <lb/>PV cell decreased with increasing air velocity at a constant <lb/>air temperature. As shown in Figure 12, the increase in the <lb/>temperature of the PV panel has slightly reduced the electric-<lb/>ity generation compared to the incident solar radiation. In the <lb/>BIPV/T study conducted by Wajs et al. [41], under a solar radi-<lb/>ation equal to 900 W/m 2 , the maximum operating temperature <lb/>of the PV panel reached 79.6 • C. With cooling, the tempera-<lb/>ture was reduced to 72.2 • C. Approximately 9% more power <lb/>was obtained from the PV panel compared to the uncooled <lb/>condition. In our BIPV/T study, it was observed that, in the <lb/>case of high fan speed, the bifacial panel and the monofacial <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1637 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 12 Data on daily radiation and power generation averages taken in nine configurations. <lb/>panel achieved 7.8% and 6.9% higher efficiency, respectively, <lb/>compared to the situation without cooling. <lb/>During the natural convection (fanless) configuration, espe-<lb/>cially the temperature of the bifacial panel was observed to <lb/>be higher than that of the monofacial panel (Figure 11). In <lb/>cases where cooling is performed by forced convection, tem-<lb/>peratures of monofacial panel have exceeded temperatures of <lb/>bifacial panel. Due to the fact that bifacial panels are made <lb/>of glass-glass and are semitransparent, sunlight passes to their <lb/>backside. In the absence of cooling, the solar radiation pass-<lb/>ing to behind the panel heats the panel from both sides. This <lb/>also causes the bifacial panel to heat up more than the non-<lb/>translucent monofacial panel. In addition, it was observed that <lb/>the thermal transmittance of the glass-glass panel (0.78 W/mK) <lb/>is higher compared to the monofacial panel with polyethylene <lb/>terephthalate (0.29 W/mK). Therefore, as a result of increased <lb/>air velocity, it was found that the cooling effect on the bifacial <lb/>panel is greater compared to the monofacial panel (Figure 11). <lb/>As seen in Table 7, an increase in wind speed at the 1st distance <lb/>has resulted in a greater improvement in both thermal and elec-<lb/>trical efficiency in the bifacial panel compared to the monofacial <lb/>panel. The use of materials with high thermal conductivity in <lb/>BIPV/T systems ensures an increase in efficiency. <lb/>The indoor and outdoor air temperatures generally changed <lb/>proportionally to each other, as observed in Figure 11. On <lb/>February 26th, while the external air temperature averaged <lb/>18 • C, the internal temperature, on average, was measured at <lb/>33 • C, which was the highest indoor temperature recorded dur-<lb/>ing the experiment. Since the internal volume of the container <lb/>is 11.3 m 3 and the container is covered with heat-insulated <lb/>polystyrene foam with a density of 14 kg/m 3 and a thickness of <lb/>5 cm, it can be said that the indoor temperatures in the experi-<lb/>ment are high in terms of human comfort. However, when this <lb/>thermal gain is installed in larger offices or rooms, it is thought <lb/>that the indoor temperature may be at a level suitable for human <lb/>comfort. On February 16th, the average outdoor temperature <lb/>was 6.7 • C, while the average indoor temperature was found <lb/>to be 20.6 • C. It shows that the BIPV/T system will provide <lb/>a significant gain in heating load in winter for indoor heating. <lb/>As seen in Figure 11, the temperature differences between the <lb/>temperature of the air entering the air duct from the bottom and <lb/>the air leaving the top are at the lowest level when the fans are <lb/>operating at high speed. As the air interval distance increases, <lb/>the temperature difference between the upper and lower air <lb/>ducts decreases in general. Thanks to the fan, the air sent from <lb/>the lower hole absorbs a certain amount of heat from the panel <lb/>and increases its temperature by passing from the upper side to <lb/>the indoor environment. However, the faster the air rises, the <lb/>smaller the temperature difference was observed. The highest <lb/>temperature difference was observed when the fans were not in <lb/>operation, as indicated by the graph. Because the air slowly heats <lb/>up and rises, it has the opportunity to absorb heat over time. In <lb/>addition, since there is no forced convection, the temperature <lb/>of the panel increases more significantly. However, this thermal <lb/>gain in natural convection cannot immediately heat sudden air <lb/>cooling in the room. In the case of opening any door or win-<lb/>dow, when the fans are operational, they are able to restore the <lb/>indoor temperature to its previous level within a few seconds. <lb/>When examining the days on which the experiments were <lb/>conducted, it can be observed that the amount of incoming radi-<lb/>ation is directly proportional to the generated power (Figure 12). <lb/>The most important result here is that the amount of power <lb/>produced by the bifacial panel is higher than the monofacial <lb/>panel. <lb/>In Table 6, the amount of extra power produced by the bifa-<lb/>cial panel compared to the monofacial panel, according to the <lb/>days of the experiments, is shown as a percentage. The bifa-<lb/>cial panel, overall, achieved higher production compared to the <lb/>monofacial panel. The semitransparent nature of the bifacial <lb/>panel allowed the sunlight to pass through to the backside, <lb/>resulting in the reflection from the aluminium foil. This further <lb/>increased the electricity generation on the back surface of the <lb/>panel. As the panels moved away from the wall, the production <lb/>rate of the bifacial panel increases more than the monofacial <lb/>panel. As the panels move away from the wall, the increase in <lb/>the radiation entering from the transparent tarpaulin next to <lb/>the panels and the effect of the semi-transparency of the bifa-<lb/>cial panel caused the bifacial panel to produce better electrical <lb/>energy than the monofacial panel. When evaluated compara-<lb/>tively, it was observed that in the configuration where the panels <lb/>are positioned farthest from the wall and the fans are operat-<lb/>ing at high speed, the bifacial panel achieved the best electricity <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1638 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 13 The I-V curves of configurations 1, 2, and 3. <lb/>TABLE 6 Comparison of the daily average amount of power produced by <lb/>the bifacial and the monofacial panel. <lb/>Daily averages-9:00/17:00 <lb/>Bifacial <lb/>panel <lb/>power <lb/>(kW) <lb/>Monofacial <lb/>panel power <lb/>(kW) <lb/>Percentage <lb/>gain rate of <lb/>bifacial <lb/>panel (%) <lb/>16.02.2023-1. Distance, High speed 196.50 <lb/>179.70 <lb/>9.35% <lb/>17.02.2023-2. Distance, High speed 183.71 <lb/>167.35 <lb/>9.77% <lb/>20.02.2023-3. Distance, High speed 165.18 <lb/>146.53 <lb/>12.73% <lb/>21.02.2023-1. Distance, Low speed 178.38 <lb/>162.83 <lb/>9.55% <lb/>22.02.2023-2. Distance, Low speed 155.25 <lb/>141.42 <lb/>9.79% <lb/>23.02.2023-3. Distance, Low speed 145.71 <lb/>130.31 <lb/>11.82% <lb/>24.02.2023-1. Distance, Fanless <lb/>169.81 <lb/>156.74 <lb/>8.33% <lb/>25.02.2023-2. Distance, Fanless <lb/>158.86 <lb/>144.60 <lb/>9.86% <lb/>26.02.2023-3. Distance, Fanless <lb/>157.83 <lb/>141.22 <lb/>11.77% <lb/>generation with a rate of 12.73% compared to the monofacial <lb/>panel. The parameter that resulted in the lowest production was <lb/>achieved with a rate of 8.33% in the configuration performed <lb/>on February 24th. The use of the new technology of glass-<lb/>glass bifacial panels in Building integrated photovoltaic/thermal <lb/>(BIPV/T) systems was found to be significantly better in terms <lb/>of electrical energy efficiency compared to traditional panels. <lb/>In Figures 13, 14, and 15, current-voltage (I-V) curves for all <lb/>configurations conducted in the experimental setup were gener-<lb/>ated using data obtained from the data transfer unit (DTU). In <lb/>all configurations measured from 9:00 AM to 5:00 PM, the volt-<lb/>age values of the panels connected to the same micro-inverter <lb/>were found to be nearly identical. Table 6 compares the power <lb/>output of bifacial panels to monofacial panels, demonstrating <lb/>that bifacial panels produce a higher amount of power. The <lb/>reason for the higher power output of bifacial panels is the <lb/>differentiation in current values. In Figures 13-15, the current <lb/>values of the green curve representing the bifacial panel were <lb/>found to be higher in each configuration compared to the blue <lb/>curve representing the monofacial panel. This situation indi-<lb/>cates that the use of the back surface of the bifacial panel has not <lb/>affected the voltage values. In each configuration, it was found <lb/>that the reason for the higher power output of the bifacial panel <lb/>compared to the monofacial panel is due to the higher current <lb/>values. <lb/>Furthermore, it was observed that the current and volt-<lb/>age values are inversely proportional when examining the I-V <lb/>graphs of each of the nine configurations. Current values tend <lb/>to increase during times of strong solar radiation and decrease <lb/>during weak solar radiation, while voltage values tend to rise. <lb/>As shown in Table 7, the electrical and thermal efficiencies of <lb/>PV panels vary depending on the air velocity and the distance of <lb/>the panel from the wall. In general, it was observed that when <lb/>the fans are operating at high speed, the panels achieve higher <lb/>electrical energy efficiency compared to the situation where the <lb/>fans are operating at low speed, at the same distance from the <lb/>panels. The decrease in the temperature of PV panels results in <lb/>an increase in their electrical efficiency. In the air-based BIPV/T <lb/>experiment conducted by Pantic et al. [17], it was found that <lb/>increasing the air velocity resulted in an increase in electricity <lb/>generation. Teo et al. [19] tried to cool an air-based PVT sys-<lb/>tem by installing fins. In this study, with a temperature of 70 • C, <lb/>the electrical efficiency was 9%. Electrical efficiency increased <lb/>to 13% when the panel temperature was reduced to 35 • C by <lb/>means of air and fins. <lb/>When examining Table 7, it was found that the electrical effi-<lb/>ciency of the bifacial panel increases as it moves away from the <lb/>wall. Thanks to the reflective surface behind the bifacial panel, <lb/>it was observed that the rear surface is more effectively utilized <lb/>as it moves away from the wall. The thermal efficiency is higher <lb/>when the gap distance between the panel and the wall decreases, <lb/>as this allows for better contact of the passing air with the sur-<lb/>face and increases heat transfer. As the air gap distance between <lb/>the panel and the wall widens, both panels showed a tendency <lb/>of decreasing thermal efficiency. In addition, it was determined <lb/>that in fanless configurations, the thermal efficiency of mono-<lb/>facial panels is higher compared to bifacial panels. The absence <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1639 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 14 The I-V curves of configurations 4, 5, and 6. <lb/>FIGURE 15 The I-V curves of configurations 7, 8, and 9. <lb/>TABLE 7 Thermal and electrical energy production efficiency of bifacial panel and monofacial panel. <lb/>Thermal efficiency <lb/>Electrical efficiency <lb/>Total efficiency <lb/>Daily Averages-9:00/17:00 <lb/>Bifacial <lb/>Monofacial <lb/>Bifacial <lb/>Monofacial <lb/>Bifacial <lb/>Monofacial <lb/>16.02.2023-1. Distance, High speed <lb/>33.09% <lb/>29.29% <lb/>18.4% <lb/>16.8% <lb/>51.4% <lb/>46.1% <lb/>17.02.2023-2. Distance, High speed <lb/>22.25% <lb/>28.92% <lb/>18.5% <lb/>16.8% <lb/>40.7% <lb/>45.8% <lb/>20.02.2023-3. Distance, High speed <lb/>20.64% <lb/>28.57% <lb/>19.6% <lb/>17.4% <lb/>40.2% <lb/>45.9% <lb/>21.02.2023-1. Distance, Low speed <lb/>30.49% <lb/>26.56% <lb/>17.8% <lb/>16.2% <lb/>48.2% <lb/>42.8% <lb/>22.02.2023-2. Distance, Low speed <lb/>23.85% <lb/>25.95% <lb/>18.1% <lb/>16.5% <lb/>42.0% <lb/>42.4% <lb/>23.02.2023-3. Distance, Low speed <lb/>20.74% <lb/>24.74% <lb/>19.3% <lb/>17.2% <lb/>40.0% <lb/>42.0% <lb/>24.02.2023-1. Distance, Fanless <lb/>7.18% <lb/>7.86% <lb/>16.9% <lb/>15.6% <lb/>24.0% <lb/>23.4% <lb/>25.02.2023-2. Distance, Fanless <lb/>7.84% <lb/>8.38% <lb/>17.5% <lb/>16.0% <lb/>25.4% <lb/>24.3% <lb/>26.02.2023-3. Distance, Fanless <lb/>7.92% <lb/>8.56% <lb/>18.0% <lb/>16.1% <lb/>25.9% <lb/>24.7% <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1640 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 16 The amount of energy produced by the bifacial panel and <lb/>the monofacial panel, respectively, in February (data from DTU). DTU, Data <lb/>transfer unit. <lb/>of a fast airflow resulted in the glass-glass bifacial panel retain-<lb/>ing more heat. This situation can be substantiated by the graph <lb/>in Figure 11, where it is observed that the temperature of the <lb/>bifacial panel is higher than that of the monofacial panel. <lb/>According to the study of Karthich and Catherine [42], it was <lb/>observed that PVT lowered the panel temperature compared to <lb/>PV and increased the efficiency of the whole system. Compared <lb/>to this study, both thermal efficiency and electrical efficiency <lb/>were found to be lower in both panels in Table 5 in all fanless <lb/>configurations than in forced convection configurations. Sim-<lb/>ilar to the aforementioned study, both thermal efficiency and <lb/>electrical efficiency were found to be lower in both panels in <lb/>all fanless configurations in Table 7 than in forced convection <lb/>configurations. <lb/>Based on the data obtained from the experimental setup, <lb/>in February, the bifacial panel produced 35.75 kWh of energy, <lb/>while the monofacial panel produced 32.20 kWh (Figure 16). In <lb/>addition to daily average values, when examining monthly elec-<lb/>trical energy productions, the bifacial panel has approximately <lb/>11% more production than the monofacial panel. <lb/>To see the monthly and yearly electrical energy gain of the <lb/>bifacial panel compared to the monofacial panel, and to vali-<lb/>date the February production from the experimental setup, the <lb/>PVsyst analysis results was provided in Table 8. In the experi-<lb/>mental setup, the electricity production value for the monofacial <lb/>panel was found to be 32.2 kWh in February. When com-<lb/>pared with experimental data, there is a margin of error of <lb/>0.9% in monofacial panel values in Pvsyst. The results were <lb/>found to be consistent with each other. This result demonstrates <lb/>the accuracy of the model used in the simulation compared <lb/>to the experimental outcomes. In addition, an analysis of the <lb/>bifacial panel was conducted using the PVsyst program. How-<lb/>ever, due to limitations in the simulation program, it was not <lb/>possible to define the reflective surface placed on the wall <lb/>behind the bifacial panel in the experimental setup, and as a <lb/>result, the use of the reflective surface was not incorporated in <lb/>the analyses. Therefore, in the energy production comparisons <lb/>between the experimental data and the simulation for the bifa-<lb/>cial panel in February, it was found that the experimental data <lb/>was 7.5% higher. Thus, by comparing the experimental setup <lb/>with the PVsyst analysis, the reflective surface is proven to be <lb/>an important parameter. <lb/>In addition to this, in the PVsyst analysis, the bifacial <lb/>panel produced 3.6% more electrical energy than the mono-<lb/>facial panel in February. However, in the experimental setup <lb/>for February, the bifacial panel has an 11% advantage over <lb/>the monofacial panel (Figure 16). From this perspective, it <lb/>was observed that, similarly, the reflective surface used in the <lb/>experimental setup enhances the efficiency of the bifacial panel. <lb/>When examining the annual total energy production in the <lb/>PVsyst analysis, it is observed that the bifacial panel pro-<lb/>duced 421 kWh of energy, while the monofacial panel produced <lb/>401.88 kWh. According to the PVsyst analysis, the bifacial panel <lb/>generated an additional 4.76% electrical energy annually com-<lb/>pared to the monofacial panel. Based on this, when looking <lb/>at the electrical energy values produced by the panels for all <lb/>months, the superiority of the bifacial panel is proven each time. <lb/>In addition, it is estimated that the bifacial panel will produce <lb/>approximately 446 kWh of electrical energy annually when using <lb/>a reflective surface. <lb/>In the PVsyst analysis, as can be seen from the graphic <lb/>results in Figure 17, the total loss of monthly electrical energy <lb/>was higher in the monofacial panel than in the bifacial panel. <lb/>The total loss rates shown in purple on the graph are lower <lb/>on a monthly basis due to the higher efficiency of the bifa-<lb/>cial panel. In addition, the usable energy ratio generated each <lb/>month (brown bar graph) is also higher in the bifacial panel. <lb/>The reason for the high system losses of the bifacial panel is <lb/>related to its energy production rate. The bifacial panel, which <lb/>shares the same infrastructure system as the monofacial panel, <lb/>has higher energy production, and as a result, its system losses <lb/>are also higher. <lb/>CFD analysis results were given to enable the comparison <lb/>of the temperature distribution on the container structure for <lb/>the configuration conducted on February 24th. The surface <lb/>temperature distribution of the container structure is given in <lb/>Figure 18. The temperature range varies between 15 and 55 • C. <lb/>When examining the temperature distribution, it is observed <lb/>that the highest temperatures are in the PV panels. This situation <lb/>has proven the extraction of thermal energy from the panels in <lb/>the BIPV/T system during winter. <lb/>Under the realistic radiation value of 749 W/m 2 given at <lb/>12:00, the temperature distribution of the container structure <lb/>varies between 10 and 55 • C, as shown in Figure 19b. Addition-<lb/>ally, when the time-dependent temperature graph in Figure 19a <lb/>is examined, it can be observed that there is a similarity between <lb/>experimental and numerical results. This situation indicates that <lb/>the measurements obtained from experimental data are consis-<lb/>tent with the results of numerical simulation, confirming the <lb/>mutual validation of both methods. <lb/>The temperature distributions of monofacial and bifacial <lb/>panels at 12:00 under 749 W/m 2 solar irradiance are pro-<lb/>vided in Figures 20b and 21b, respectively. It is observed <lb/>that at this time, the surface temperature of the monofacial <lb/>panel varies between 52 and 54 • C, while the surface tem-<lb/>perature of the bifacial panel varies between 52 and 55.5 • C. <lb/>The fact that the bifacial panel has a higher panel tempera-<lb/>ture than the monofacial panel in the fanless condition is also <lb/>substantiated by the average temperature graph provided in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1641 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE 8 Results of PVsyst analysis. PVsyst, Photovoltaic software. <lb/>Panel type <lb/>Global <lb/>horizontal <lb/>irradiation <lb/>(kWh/m 2 ) <lb/>Horizontal <lb/>diffuse <lb/>irradiation <lb/>(kWh/m 2 ) <lb/>Ambient <lb/>temp. ( • C) <lb/>Global <lb/>incident in <lb/>coll. plane <lb/>(kWh/m 2 ) <lb/>Effective global, <lb/>corr. for IAM <lb/>and shadings <lb/>(kWh/m 2 ) <lb/>Effective <lb/>energy at the <lb/>output of the <lb/>array (kWh) <lb/>Energy <lb/>injected <lb/>into grid <lb/>(kWh) <lb/>Performance <lb/>ratio <lb/>January <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 77.5 <lb/>28.30 <lb/>6.13 <lb/>128.2 <lb/>126.7 <lb/>43.45 <lb/>41.86 <lb/>0.988 <lb/>125.7 <lb/>42.27 <lb/>40.77 <lb/>0.948 <lb/>February <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 86.7 <lb/>42.02 <lb/>7.90 <lb/>101.9 <lb/>99.7 <lb/>34.31 <lb/>33.06 <lb/>0.983 <lb/>98.8 <lb/>33.06 <lb/>31.91 <lb/>0.934 <lb/>March <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 142.6 <lb/>55.15 <lb/>12.56 <lb/>125.8 <lb/>120.1 <lb/>40.64 <lb/>39.18 <lb/>0.944 <lb/>119.3 <lb/>39.27 <lb/>37.92 <lb/>0.900 <lb/>April <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 177.0 <lb/>68.11 <lb/>17.61 <lb/>103.6 <lb/>95.1 <lb/>31.99 <lb/>30.78 <lb/>0.901 <lb/>95.4 <lb/>30.74 <lb/>29.63 <lb/>0.854 <lb/>May <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 208.3 <lb/>73.72 <lb/>24.0 <lb/>85.5 <lb/>75.6 <lb/>26.18 <lb/>25.17 <lb/>0.892 <lb/>76.8 <lb/>23.94 <lb/>23.05 <lb/>0.805 <lb/>June <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 243.9 <lb/>55.32 <lb/>30.23 <lb/>77.1 <lb/>65.9 <lb/>23.72 <lb/>22.77 <lb/>0.894 <lb/>67.6 <lb/>20.41 <lb/>19.58 <lb/>0.758 <lb/>July <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 249.2 <lb/>52.31 <lb/>34.83 <lb/>84.5 <lb/>72.8 <lb/>25.05 <lb/>24.08 <lb/>0.864 <lb/>74.5 <lb/>22.06 <lb/>21.23 <lb/>0.750 <lb/>August <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 226.3 <lb/>47.86 <lb/>33.86 <lb/>110.8 <lb/>99.0 <lb/>31.32 <lb/>30.14 <lb/>0.824 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>29.82 <lb/>28.74 <lb/>0.774 <lb/>September Bifacial monofacial 182.9 <lb/>38.80 <lb/>28.29 <lb/>142.1 <lb/>133.1 <lb/>41.76 <lb/>40.25 <lb/>0.858 <lb/>132.7 <lb/>40.55 <lb/>39.17 <lb/>0.823 <lb/>October <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 130.3 <lb/>42.08 <lb/>22.11 <lb/>149.2 <lb/>145.1 <lb/>46.81 <lb/>45.15 <lb/>0.917 <lb/>143.7 <lb/>45.24 <lb/>43.70 <lb/>0.874 <lb/>November Bifacial monofacial 89.2 <lb/>31.01 <lb/>13.70 <lb/>140.9 <lb/>138.8 <lb/>46.09 <lb/>44.43 <lb/>0.956 <lb/>137.6 <lb/>44.72 <lb/>43.17 <lb/>0.915 <lb/>December Bifacial monofacial 74.3 <lb/>26.79 <lb/>7.93 <lb/>136.2 <lb/>134.7 <lb/>45.77 <lb/>44.12 <lb/>0.982 <lb/>133.6 <lb/>44.57 <lb/>43.02 <lb/>0.943 <lb/>Year total <lb/>Bifacial monofacial 1888.2 <lb/>561.47 <lb/>20.01 <lb/>1386.1 <lb/>1306.5 <lb/>437.10 <lb/>421.00 <lb/>0.920 <lb/>1305.7 <lb/>416.66 <lb/>401.88 <lb/>0.866 <lb/>FIGURE 17 Monthly usable energy production and total loss rates of bifacial and monofacial panel in PVsyst program. PVsyst, Photovoltaic software. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1642 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 18 Temperature distribution of the container structure in the <lb/>CFD simulation program. CFD, Computational fluid dynamics. <lb/>Figure 11 above. When examining the time-dependent tempera-<lb/>ture graph in Figure 20a, it is observed that the numerical results <lb/>are higher in the morning, lower around noon, and closer to <lb/>the experimental results in the afternoon. This situation illus-<lb/>trates the variation in the panel&apos;s performance throughout the <lb/>day. The numerical model demonstrated an accurate simula-<lb/>tion of the panel&apos;s behaviour, especially during the afternoon <lb/>hours. <lb/>When examining the temperature graph in Figure 21a, <lb/>it is observed that the numerical results are closer to the <lb/>experimental results in the morning and around noon, but <lb/>lower in the afternoon. This situation demonstrates that the <lb/>numerical model successfully simulates the temperature varia-<lb/>tion of the photovoltaic (PV) panel, especially during specific <lb/>time intervals. When the experimental data is compared with <lb/>the CFD analysis results for both panels, it is generally <lb/>observed that they are compatible with each other, as shown in <lb/>Figures 19-21. <lb/>FIGURE 19 (a) Time-dependent experimental and numerical results of the internal environment of the container structure. (b) The temperature distribution <lb/>of the internal environment at 12:00. <lb/>4 <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>In this study, the BIPV/T system was made more efficient with <lb/>new technologies and various parameters. The electrical effi-<lb/>ciency of the bifacial panel was found to be higher in every <lb/>configuration compared to the monofacial panel. In the exper-<lb/>imental setup, the placement of a reflective surface on the wall <lb/>behind the bifacial panel was resulted in higher electrical pro-<lb/>duction compared to a traditional bifacial panel. This situation <lb/>was substantiated by comparing the results of the experimental <lb/>setup and PVsyst analysis. In the winter, there was not a con-<lb/>sistent advantage in the thermal efficiency of the bifacial panel <lb/>in different configurations. However, when we consider that <lb/>we do not use thermal energy in buildings during the winter <lb/>months, the superiority of the bifacial panel over the monofa-<lb/>cial panel in total energy throughout the year is indisputable. <lb/>Furthermore, increasing the gap distance between the wall and <lb/>the bifacial panel to enhance the albedo effect allows the bifa-<lb/>cial panel to achieve a higher production rate. It enables higher <lb/>efficiency per unit area to be achieved from limited spaces on <lb/>building facades. Thus, it provides more support in meeting the <lb/>building&apos;s energy load. The costs are nearly the same as mono-<lb/>facial panels. Therefore, the payback period is also shorter. In <lb/>addition, when transparent glass-glass bifacial panels are used <lb/>in buildings, savings can also be achieved in lighting expenses. <lb/>At night, electric power can be generated as a result of the <lb/>reflection of indoor lighting used on the back of the bifacial <lb/>panel. <lb/>As seen from the findings in the experimental setup, it is <lb/>evident that the thermal and electrical efficiency of the bifa-<lb/>cial panel in BIPV/T systems has been increased by adding <lb/>a reflective surface and using forced convection (fan-assisted <lb/>heat transfer). It was observed that the thermal efficiency of <lb/>the bifacial panel reaches significantly higher levels when placed <lb/>closest to the wall with forced convection. Furthermore, it <lb/>was observed that the electrical efficiency of the bifacial panel <lb/>reaches high levels when it is placed at the farthest distance <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1643 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 20 (a) Time-dependent experimental and numerical results of the monofacial panel. (b) Temperature distribution of the monofacial panel at 12:00. <lb/>FIGURE 21 (a) Time-dependent experimental and numerical results of the bifacial panel. (b) Temperature distribution of the bifacial panel at 12:00. <lb/>from the wall. Therefore, during the heating season, maintain-<lb/>ing a short air gap distance in the BIPV/T system for the <lb/>bifacial panel and increasing it during other seasons can sup-<lb/>port an approach aimed at maximizing energy intake from the <lb/>panel throughout the year. Taking this factor into account in <lb/>building designs can help reduce the building&apos;s energy load and <lb/>contribute to achieving nearly zero-energy buildings (NZEB). <lb/>Analysing the building&apos;s energy consumption requirements can <lb/>help determine the areas where the BIPV/T system will be <lb/>effective. In building designs, it is essential to first measure <lb/>the solar energy potential of the region using simulation tools. <lb/>BIPV/T systems can be integrated as part of the building, cov-<lb/>ering the roof or facade with the most extended exposure to <lb/>sunlight. The generated electrical energy should be integrated <lb/>into the building&apos;s electrical system. An energy management sys-<lb/>tem can be used to reduce unnecessary electricity consumption. <lb/>Alternatively, electricity generated by the BIPV/T system can <lb/>be sold to generate income using a bidirectional meter. For the <lb/>efficient utilization of the heat energy produced by the BIPV/T <lb/>system, it can be integrated into the automation system to work <lb/>in commutative with the building&apos;s heating system. During the <lb/>day, when the panels reach a certain temperature, the automa-<lb/>tion system can automatically shut off the building&apos;s heating <lb/>system. Under the control of the automation system, the heat <lb/>generated by the BIPV/T system can be directed to the indoor <lb/>space using fans, thus saving energy from the building&apos;s heating <lb/>system. The initial investment cost of the BIPV/T system can <lb/>be recovered in the long term with the right energy management <lb/>strategies. <lb/>Both BIPV/T systems, which can be utilized in both residen-<lb/>tial and industrial sectors, and the evolving panel technology are <lb/>regarded as a significant step towards reducing the consump-<lb/>tion of fossil fuels and attaining a sustainable environment by <lb/>mitigating the threat of greenhouse gases to the world. <lb/></body>
	  
	        <div type="contribution">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Yusuf Can Demir: Data curation; formal analysis; inves-<lb/>tigation; software; visualization; writing-original draft; <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1644 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">writing-review and editing. Mehmet Azmi Aktacir: Con-<lb/>ceptualization; funding acquisition; methodology; project <lb/>administration; resources; supervision; validation. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>Thanks to everyone who contributed to the editorial board <lb/>of IET Renewable Power Generation journal. Thanks to <lb/>Aykut GÜZEL for their assistance with CFD simulation. The <lb/>experimental setup in this study was supported by the Sci-<lb/>entific Research Projects unit of Harran University. (Project <lb/>no: 22187). Institution/Funder Name: Kocaeli University, <lb/>TUBITAK ULAKBIM. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT <lb/>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT <lb/>Data available on request from the authors <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID <lb/>Yusuf Can Demir https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0713-2244 <lb/>Mehmet Azmi Aktacir https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2345-<lb/>7815 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Agarwal, R., Hussain, I., Singh, B.: Three-phase grid-tied single-stage solar <lb/>energy conversion system using LLMS control algorithm. IET Renewable <lb/>Power Gener. 10(10), 1638-1646 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1049/iet-rpg. <lb/>2016.0061, <lb/>2. Khaki, M., Shahsavar, A., Khanmohammadi, S., Salmanzadeh, M.: Energy <lb/>and exergy analysis and multi-objective optimization of an air based build-<lb/>ing integrated photovoltaic/thermal (BIPV/T) system. Sol. Energy 158, <lb/>380-395 (2017). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.solener.2017.09.056 <lb/>3. Goiroodbari, S.Z.M., Dewaal, A.C., van Sark, W.: Proof of concept for <lb/>a novel and smart shade resilient photovoltaic modüle. IET Renewable <lb/>Power Gener. 13(12), 2184-2194 (2019). https://doi.org/10.1049/iet-rpg. <lb/>2018.6127 <lb/>4. Mathew, D., Naidu, R.C., Wang, Y., Busawon, K.: Single-stage microin-<lb/>verter with current sensorless control for BIPV system. IET Renewable <lb/>Power Gener. 15(11), 2468-2479 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1049/rpg2. <lb/>12177 <lb/>5. Khelife, A., Touafek, K., Moussa, H.B.: Approach for the modelling of <lb/>hybrid photovoltaic-thermal solar collector. IET Renewable Power Gener. <lb/>9(3), 207-217 (2015). https://doi.org/10.1049/iet-rpg.2014.0076 <lb/>6. Pereira, R., Aelenei, L.: Optimization assessment of the energy perfor-<lb/>mance of a BIPV/T-PCM system using genetic algorithms. Renewable <lb/>Energy 137, 157-166 (2019). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.renene.2018.06. <lb/>118 <lb/>7. Guo, J., Jin, Y., Li, Z., Li, M.: A quantitative analysis on key factors affect-<lb/>ing the thermal performance of the hybrid air-based BIPV/T system. <lb/>Buildings 12(8), 1135 (2022). https://doi.org/10.3390/buildings12081135 <lb/>8. Weiss, W., Spörk-Dür, M., Austria, SOLAR HEAT WORLDWIDE. <lb/>Global Market Development and Trends 2022 Detailed Market Figures <lb/>2021. https://www.iea-shc.org/Data/Sites/1/publications/Solar-Heat-<lb/>Worldwide-20231.pdf. Accessed 2 March 2024. <lb/>9. Rajendiran, G., Kuppusamy, V.B., Shanmugasundaram, S.: Experimental <lb/>investigation of the effects of sonication time and volume concentration <lb/>on the performance of PVT solar collector. IET Renewable Power Gener. <lb/>12(12), 1375-1381 (2018). https://doi.org/10.1049/iet-rpg.2018.5283 <lb/>10. Xu, L., Ji, J., Luo, K., Li, Z., Xu, R., Huang, S.: Annual analysis of a multi-<lb/>functional BIPV/T solar wall system in typical cities of China. Energy 197, <lb/>117098 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.energy.2020.117098 <lb/>11. Baljit, S.S.S., Chan, H., Sopian, K.: Review of building integrated appli-<lb/>cations of photovoltaic and solar thermal systems. J. Cleaner Prod. 137, <lb/>677-689 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2016.07.150 <lb/>12. Lops, C., Di Loreto, S., Pierantozzi, M., Montelpare, S.: Double-skin <lb/>facades for building retrofitting and climate change: A case study in <lb/>central Italy. Appl. Sci. 13(13), 7629 (2023). https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>app13137629 <lb/>13. Shrivastava, A., Sharma, R., Saxena, M.K., Shanmugasundaram, V., Rivana, <lb/>M.L., Ankit,: Solar energy capacity assessment and performance evaluation <lb/>of a standalone pv system using PVSYST. Mater. Today: Proc. 80(3), 3385-<lb/>3392 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matpr.2021.07.258 <lb/>14. Shukla, A.K., Sudhakar, K., Baredar, P., Mamat, R.: BIPV based sustain-<lb/>able building in South Asian countries. Sol. Energy 170, 1162-1170 (2018). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.solener.2018.06.026 <lb/>15. Syafaruddin Sari, Y.A., Said, S.M.: A review of building integrated <lb/>photovoltaic-thermal (BIPV/T) Systems: Current and potential technol-<lb/>ogy development. J. Eng. Sci. Technol. Rev. 14(4), 197-206 (2021). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.25103/jestr.144.24 <lb/>16. Maghrabie, H.M., Elsaid, K., Sayed, E.T., Abdelkareem, A., Wilberforce, <lb/>T., Olabi, A.G.: Building-integrated photovoltaic/thermal (BIPVT) sys-<lb/>tems: Applications and challenges. Sustainable Energy Technol. Assess. 45, <lb/>101151 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seta.2021.101151 <lb/>17. Pantic, S., Candanedo, L., Athienitis, A.K.: Modeling of energy per-<lb/>formance of a house with three configurations of building-integrated <lb/>photovoltaic/thermal systems. Energy Build. 42, 1779-1789 (2010). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enbuild.2010.05.014 <lb/>18. Gül, M., ve Akyüz, E.: Performance investigation of a hybrid photovoltaic-<lb/>thermal (PV/T) system. J. BAUN Inst. Sci. Technol. 21(1), 444-458 (2019). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.25092/baunfbed.548728 <lb/>19. Teo, H.G., Lee, P.S., Hawlader, M.N.A.: An active cooling system for pho-<lb/>tovoltaic modules. Appl. Energy 90(1), 309-315 (2012). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.apenergy.2011.01.017 <lb/>20. Saygin, H., Nowzari, R., Mirzaei, N., Aldabbagh, L.B.Y.: Performance eval-<lb/>uation of a modified PV/T solar collector: A case study in design and <lb/>analysis of experiment. Sol. Energy 141, 210-221 (2017). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.solener.2016.11.048 <lb/>21. Mojumder, J.C., Chong, W.T., Ong, H.C., Leong, K.Y., Abdullah-Al-<lb/>mamoon,: An experimental investigation on performance analysis of air <lb/>type photovoltaic thermal collector system integrated with cooling fins <lb/>design. Energy Build. 130, 272-285 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>enbuild.2016.08.040 <lb/>22. Hajji, M., Naimi, S.E., Hajji, B., el Mehdi, A., el Hafyani, M.L.: Perfor-<lb/>mance analysis of hybrid photovoltaic/thermal (PV/T) collector. In: Third <lb/>International Renewable and Sustainable Energy Conference (IRSEC), <lb/>pp. 10-13. IEEE, Piscataway, NJ (2015). https://doi.org/10.1109/IRSEC. <lb/>2015.7455048 <lb/>23. Tina, G.M., Scavo, F.B., Aneli, S., Gagliano, A.: Assessment of the electri-<lb/>cal and thermal performances of building integrated bifacial photovoltaic <lb/>modules. J. Cleaner Prod. 313, 127906 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jclepro.2021.127906 <lb/>24. Wajs, J., Galabek, A., Bochniak, R., Mikilewich, D.: Air-cooled photovoltaic <lb/>roof tile as an example of the BIPVT system an experimental study on the <lb/>energy and exergy performance. Energy 197, 117255 (2020). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.energy.2020.117255 <lb/>25. Kabul, A., ve Duran, F.: Photovoltaic/thermal (pv/t) hybrid system per-<lb/>formance analysis in isparta province. SDU Int. Technol. Sci. 6(1), 31-43 <lb/>(2014) <lb/>26. Cuce, E., Cuce, P.M.: Improving thermodynamic performance parameters <lb/>of silicon photovoltaic cells via air cooling. Int. J. Ambient Energy 35(4), <lb/>193-199 (2014). https://doi.org/10.1080/01430750.2013.793481 <lb/>27. Kamthania, D., Nayak, S., Tiwari, G.N.: Performance evaluation of a hybrid <lb/>photovoltaic thermal double pass facade for space heating. Energy Build. <lb/>43, 2274-2281 (2011). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enbuild.2011.05.007 <lb/>28. Yang, T., Athienitis, A.K.: Experimental investigation of a two-inlet air-<lb/>based building integrated photovoltaic/thermal (BIPV/T) system. Appl. <lb/>Energy 159, 70-79 (2015). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2015.08. <lb/>048 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/>DEMIR and AKTACIR <lb/></note>

			<page>1645 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>29. Kaiser, A.S., Zamora, B., Mazon, R., Garcia, J.R., Vera, F.: Experimental <lb/>study of cooling BIPV modules by forced convection in the air chan-<lb/>nel. Appl. Energy 135, 88-97 (2014). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy. <lb/>2014.08.079 <lb/>30. Kim, J.H., Park, S.H., Kim, J.T.: Experimental performance of a <lb/>photovoltaic-thermal air collector. Energy Proc. 48, 888-894 (2014). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.egypro.2014.02.102 <lb/>31. Bot, K., Aelenei, L., Gomes, M.G., Silva, C.S.: Performance assessment <lb/>of a building integrated photovoltaic thermal system in mediterranean <lb/>climate-A numerical simulation approach. Energies 13(11), 2887 (2020). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/en13112887 <lb/>32. Kamel, R.S., Fung, A.S.: Modeling, simulation and feasibility analysis of <lb/>residential BIPV/T+ASHP system in cold climated-Canada. Energy Build. <lb/>82, 758-770 (2014). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enbuild.2014.07.081 <lb/>33. Luo, K., Ji, J., Xu, L., Li, Z.: Seasonal experimental study of a hybrid <lb/>photovoltaic-water/air solar wall system. Appl. Therm. Eng. 169, 114853 <lb/>(2020). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2019.114853 <lb/>34. Shao, N., Ma, L., Zhang, J.: Experimental investigation on the performance <lb/>of direct-expansion roof-PV/T heat pump system. Energy 195, 11959 <lb/>(2020). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.energy.2020.116959 <lb/>35. Aaditya, G., Pillai, R., Mani, M.: An insight into real-time performance <lb/>assessment of a building integrated photovoltaic (BIPV) installation in <lb/>Bangalore (India). Energy Sustain. Dev. 17(5), 431-437 (2013). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.esd.2013.04.007 <lb/>36. Urbanetz, J., Zomer, C.D., Ruther, R.: Compromises between form and <lb/>function in grid-connected, building-integrated photovoltaics (BIPV) at <lb/>low-latitude sites. Build. Environ. 46, 2107-2113 (2011). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.buildenv.2011.04.024 <lb/>37. Şirin, C., Goggins, J., Hajdukiewicz, M.: A review on building-integrated <lb/>photovoltaic/thermal systems for green buildings. Appl. Therm. Eng. 229, <lb/>120607 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.applthermaleng.2023.120607 <lb/>38. de la Maison, R., Switzerland, PVSYST TUTOR İAL. Stand Alone Tuto-<lb/>rial. https://www.pvsyst.com/wp-content/pdf-tutorials/pvsyst-tutorial-<lb/>v7-standalone-en.pdf. Accessed 1 July 2023 <lb/>39. Çengel, Y.A., ve Boles, M.A.: Thermodynamics, 7th ed. Palme Publishing, <lb/>Turkey (2020) <lb/>40. Sopian, K., Liu, H.T., Kakac, S., Veziroglu, T.N.: Performance of a dou-<lb/>ble pass photovoltaic thermal solar collector suitable for solar drying <lb/>systems. Energy Conv. Manage. 41, 353-365 (2000). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/S0196-8904(99)00115-6 <lb/>41. Wajs, J., Golabek, A., Bochniak, R.: Photovoltaic roof tiles: The influence <lb/>of heat recovery on overall performance. Energies 12(21), 4097 (2019). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/en12214097 <lb/>42. Karthick, S.P., Catherine, H.: Modelling and anaysis of solar photovoltaic <lb/>thermal collector. Int. J. Adv. Res. in Electr. Electron. Instrum. Eng. 3(4), <lb/>8467-8474 (2014) <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>How to cite this article: Demir, Y.C., Aktacir, M.A.: <lb/>Experimental investigation of BIPV/T application in <lb/>winter season under Şanlıurfa&apos;s meteorological <lb/>conditions. IET Renew. Power Gener. 18, 1626-1645 <lb/>(2024). https://doi.org/10.1049/rpg2.13014 <lb/>17521424, 2024, 9-10, Downloaded from https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/rpg2.13014 by Cochrane Portugal, Wiley Online Library on [08/09/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License </front>


	</text>


  </TEI>