<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-18T16:56:12.476Z">11/18/2025 4:56:12 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T16:56:01.523599Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-18T16:56:01.523599Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Retinoic acid signaling regulates <lb/>spatiotemporal specification of human green <lb/>and red cones <lb/>Sarah E. Hadyniak 1 , Joanna F. D. Hagen 1☯ , Kiara C. Eldred 1,2☯ , Boris Brenerman 1 , <lb/>Katarzyna A. Hussey 1 , Rajiv C. McCoy 1 , Michael E. G. Sauria 1 , James A. Kuchenbecker 3 , <lb/>Thomas Reh 2 , Ian Glass 2 , Maureen Neitz 3 , Jay Neitz 3 , James Taylor 1 † , Robert J. Johnston, <lb/>JrID 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Biology, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, United States, 2 Department of <lb/>Biological Structure, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington State, United States, 3 Department of <lb/>Ophthalmology, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington State, United States <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> † Deceased. <lb/>* robertjohnston@jhu.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Trichromacy is unique to primates among placental mammals, enabled by blue (short/S), <lb/>green (medium/M), and red (long/L) cones. In humans, great apes, and Old World monkeys, <lb/>cones make a poorly understood choice between M and L cone subtype fates. To determine <lb/>mechanisms specifying M and L cones, we developed an approach to visualize expression <lb/>of the highly similar M-and L-opsin mRNAs. M-opsin was observed before L-opsin expres-<lb/>sion during early human eye development, suggesting that M cones are generated before L <lb/>cones. In adult human tissue, the early-developing central retina contained a mix of M and L <lb/>cones compared to the late-developing peripheral region, which contained a high proportion <lb/>of L cones. Retinoic acid (RA)-synthesizing enzymes are highly expressed early in retinal <lb/>development. High RA signaling early was sufficient to promote M cone fate and suppress L <lb/>cone fate in retinal organoids. Across a human population sample, natural variation in the <lb/>ratios of M and L cone subtypes was associated with a noncoding polymorphism in the <lb/>NR2F2 gene, a mediator of RA signaling. Our data suggest that RA promotes M cone fate <lb/>early in development to generate the pattern of M and L cones across the human retina. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Trichromacy in humans is enabled by three subtypes of cone photoreceptors that express <lb/>opsin photopigments sensitive to short (S), medium (M), or long (L) wavelengths of light. <lb/>Among placental mammals, only humans, great apes, Old World primates, and some New <lb/>World monkeys possess M and L cones [1-3]. The only known difference between M and L <lb/>cones is the expression of their opsin photopigment, OPN1MW (M-opsin), or OPN1LW (L-<lb/>opsin) [4]. M and L cones have been technically challenging to distinguish due to the high <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/>1 / 28 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Hadyniak SE, Hagen JFD, Eldred KC, <lb/>Brenerman B, Hussey KA, McCoy RC, et al. (2024) <lb/>Retinoic acid signaling regulates spatiotemporal <lb/>specification of human green and red cones. PLoS <lb/>Biol 22(1): e3002464. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pbio.3002464 <lb/>Academic Editor: Tom Baden, University of <lb/>Sussex, UNITED KINGDOM <lb/>Received: February 4, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 6, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 11, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Hadyniak et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Bulk organoid, WERI-<lb/>Rb-1 RNA sequencing, and association study <lb/>sequencing and genotype data are available upon <lb/>request from Johns Hopkins University Data <lb/></front>

	<body>sequence and structural similarity between the M-and L-opsin mRNA transcripts and pro-<lb/>teins, and thus, the mechanisms underlying this fate decision have proven elusive. <lb/>In humans, the OPN1LW (L-opsin) and OPN1MW (M-opsin) genes lie in a tandem array <lb/>on the X chromosome under the control of a shared regulatory DNA element called a locus <lb/>control region (LCR) [5-8]. Though the number and ordering of OPN1LW and OPN1MW <lb/>genes varies among individuals, the LCR is most commonly found upstream of OPN1LW, fol-<lb/>lowed by two copies of OPN1MW [9]. Regardless of the arrangement, only the first two opsin <lb/>genes in the array are expressed [4,5]. <lb/>Two nonexclusive models for M and L cone fate specification have been proposed. The sto-<lb/>chastic model, which suggests that cones randomly choose M or L cone fate, is based on trans-<lb/>gene reporter experiments in mice [6,10]. The temporal model, supported by functional <lb/>microspectrophotometry, multifocal electroretinograms (ERGs), and qPCR-based expression <lb/>studies, suggests that the late-born retinal periphery is enriched for L cones compared to the <lb/>early-born central retina [11-13]. In this study, we examined human retinas and manipulated <lb/>human retinal organoids to assess these mechanisms. <lb/>Organoids are powerful systems to investigate the molecular mechanisms controlling cell <lb/>fate specification during human development [14]. We previously showed that thyroid hor-<lb/>mone regulates the S versus M/L cone fate decision in human retinal organoids [15]. Here, we <lb/>studied the development of human retinas and organoids and conducted an association study <lb/>to understand the M versus L cone fate decision. Our data suggest that retinoic acid (RA) sig-<lb/>naling controls the spatiotemporal patterning of M and L cones in the developing human <lb/>retina. <lb/>Results <lb/>Visualization of M-and L-opsin expression <lb/>To distinguish M versus L cone fates, we developed a method to visualize M-and L-opsin <lb/>mRNA expression. The opsin protein sequences are approximately 96% identical and the <lb/>mRNA sequences are approximately 98% identical, complicating expression analysis. To <lb/>directly visualize M-and L-opsin expression, we generated a 40-nucleotide probe for M-opsin <lb/>and a 42-nucleotide probe for L-opsin with partial overlap that target a region with 8 differen-<lb/>tial nucleotides (Fig 1A and 1B). We utilized colorimetric in situ hybridization to visualize M-<lb/>opsin in blue and L-opsin in pink. <lb/>We tested the specificity of this approach to distinguish M-and L-opsin mRNA by transfect-<lb/>ing plasmids driving M-opsin and/or L-opsin and visualizing expression in HEK293 cells. We <lb/>scored the total number of transfected cells that expressed M-opsin mRNA (Fig 1C, &quot;M&quot;), L-<lb/>opsin mRNA (Fig 1C, &quot;L&quot;), or both M-opsin and L-opsin mRNA (Fig 1C, &quot;M+L&quot;) for each <lb/>experiment. HEK293 cells transfected with no plasmid showed almost no signal (Fig 1C and <lb/>1D). Cells transfected with a plasmid driving M-opsin showed expression of M-opsin but not <lb/>L-opsin (Fig 1C and 1E), while cells transfected with a plasmid driving L-opsin displayed <lb/>expression of L-opsin but not M-opsin (Fig 1C and 1F). Cells transfected with either a plasmid <lb/>driving M-opsin or a plasmid driving L-opsin and then mixed, showed expression of M-opsin <lb/>only or L-opsin only in individual cells (Fig 1C and 1G). Finally, cells co-transfected with both <lb/>a plasmid driving M-opsin and a plasmid driving L-opsin displayed co-expression of M-and L-<lb/>opsin (Fig 1C and 1H). In this experiment, cells expressing M-opsin or L-opsin only were also <lb/>observed, due to variation in transfection of the two plasmids (Fig 1C). Thus, this in situ <lb/>hybridization method distinguishes between the highly similar M-and L-opsin mRNAs. <lb/>We next related expression of opsin mRNA and protein. Due to the high sequence similar-<lb/>ity of the M-opsin and L-opsin proteins, available antibodies detect both proteins. We <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<front>Services (dataservices@jhu.edu). These data have <lb/>not been deposited to a publicly available <lb/>repository because patients involved in the <lb/>association study did not consent to include the <lb/>release of raw sequencing or genotype data. The <lb/>pipeline to analyze the M-versus L-opsin pileups is <lb/>available at https://github.com/bbrener1/johnston_ <lb/>retina. The pipeline to analyze the association data <lb/>is available at https://github.com/bxlab/2018.09. <lb/>01_Eldred_GWAS/releases/tag/v1.0. All other <lb/>relevant data are within the paper and its <lb/>Supporting Information files. All reagents are <lb/>available upon request to the authors which can be <lb/>directed to Robert Johnston Jr. <lb/>(robertjohnston@jhu.edu). There are restrictions to <lb/>the availability of cell lines listed in Table 1 due to <lb/>Material Transfer Agreement (MTA). <lb/>Funding: S.E.H. was an F31 Ruth L. Kirschstein <lb/>NRSA Fellow and supported by the National Eye <lb/>Institute under grant 5F31EY029157-02. J.F.D.H <lb/>was supported by the EMBO Postdoctoral <lb/>Fellowship ALTF 318-2021. K.C.E. was supported <lb/>by the HHMI Gilliam Fellowship, the National <lb/>Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship <lb/>Program under grant 174689, the Damon Runyon <lb/>Cancer Research Foundation (DRG-# 32-20), and <lb/>the Hanna H. Gray Fellows Program Award from <lb/>the HHMI (GT15994). K.A.H. was supported by the <lb/>National Science Foundation Graduate Research <lb/>Fellowship Program under grant 1746891. R.C.M. <lb/>was supported by R35GM133747 from NIH/ <lb/>NIGMS. M.N. and J.N. were supported by NEI <lb/>grants R01EY021242 and P30EY001730, and <lb/>unrestricted funds from Research to Prevent <lb/>Blindness to ophthalmology at UW. R.J.J. was <lb/>supported by the National Eye Institute <lb/>R01EY030872, the BrightFocus foundation <lb/>G2019300, and MSCRF 140841. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/>Abbreviations: ALDH, aldehyde dehydrogenase; <lb/>ATRA, all-trans retinoic acid; CPM, counts per <lb/>million; ERG, electroretinogram; FP-ERG, flicker-<lb/>photometric electroretinogram; LCR, locus control <lb/>region; LD, linkage disequilibrium; NDRI, National <lb/>Disease Research Interchange; NRL, neural retina <lb/>leucine; ONL, outer nuclear layer; RA, retinoic acid; <lb/>SEM, standard error of the mean; THRB, thyroid <lb/>hormone receptor beta; TPM, transcripts per <lb/>million. <lb/></front>

	<body>Fig 1. An in situ hybridization approach distinguishes M-opsin and L-opsin mRNA. (A) Alignment of human M-opsin and L-opsin <lb/>mRNA. Green bar = nucleotide difference. Horizontal pink and blue lines = location of in situ hybridization probes. (B) Alignment of <lb/>portions of exon 5 from M-and L-opsin. In situ hybridization probes target mRNA sequences, indicated by blue (M-opsin) and pink (L-opsin) <lb/>boxes. Green arrowheads indicate 8 nucleotide differences. Dots indicate nucleotide alignment between the opsins. (C-H) HEK293 cells <lb/>probed for M-opsin mRNA (blue) and L-opsin mRNA (pink). Insets = schematic of transfected plasmid. Cells that did not express M-opsin <lb/>mRNA or L-opsin mRNA were not quantified. (C) Quantification of transfected HEK293 cells expressing M-opsin mRNA only, L-opsin <lb/>mRNA only, or M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA for the conditions in (D-H). (D-H) Brightfield images of cells with: (D) No plasmid <lb/>transfected. (E) Transfection of a plasmid driving M-opsin. (F) Transfection of a plasmid driving L-opsin. (G) Transfection of either a <lb/>plasmid driving M-opsin or a plasmid driving L-opsin independently and then the cells were mixed. (H) Transfection of both a plasmid <lb/>driving M-opsin and a plasmid driving L-opsin. (I) Visualization of M-opsin mRNA, L-opsin mRNA, and M-/L-opsin protein (black) in <lb/>HEK293 cells transfected with both a plasmid driving M-opsin and a plasmid driving L-opsin. M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink). Blue arrow <lb/>indicates a cell expressing M-opsin mRNA only. Pink arrows indicate cells expressing L-opsin mRNA only. Purple arrow indicates a cell <lb/>expressing both M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA. Black arrow indicates an untransfected cell. Cells were identified based on nuclear <lb/>Hoechst staining (S1A Fig). With this combined RNA in situ hybridization/immunohistochemistry approach, the mRNA signal was <lb/>reduced, when compared to the mRNA signal observed when RNA in situ hybridization was conducted alone (Fig 1H). (J) Quantification of <lb/>M-/L-opsin mRNA and M/L-opsin protein expression in transfected HEK293 cells (I). Original data sets are in S1 Data. (K) Quantification of <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>transfected HEK293 cells with both a plasmid driving M-opsin and a plasmid driving L-opsin <lb/>and observed cells that expressed M-opsin only, L-opsin only, or both M-opsin and L-opsin (Fig <lb/>1I), like our previous experiment (Fig 1C and 1H). We examined protein expression using <lb/>immunohistochemistry with an M-/L-opsin antibody and observed expression of M-/L-opsin <lb/>protein in nearly all cells that expressed M-opsin alone, L-opsin alone, or both M-opsin and L-<lb/>opsin (Figs 1I, 1J, S1A, and S1C), showing that opsin mRNA-expressing cells identified by <lb/>this method also express opsin protein. <lb/>We next tested this assay in adult human retinas. We identified cells that exclusively <lb/>expressed M-opsin or L-opsin (Fig 1K). M-/L-opsin protein was observed in nearly all cells <lb/>that expressed M-opsin or L-opsin mRNA (Figs 1K, 1L, S1B, and S1C), suggesting that this <lb/>method identifies opsin-expressing M and L cones. <lb/>Together, we conclude that this in situ hybridization method distinguishes between M-and <lb/>L-opsin mRNAs and reliably identifies M cones and L cones in adult human retinas. <lb/>M-opsin is expressed before L-opsin during development <lb/>To assess the timing of M and L cone specification during development, we evaluated M-opsin <lb/>or L-opsin mRNA in a 122-day-old human fetal retina and a 130-day-old human fetal retina. <lb/>We predicted two main, alternate outcomes: (1) a mix of cones expressing either M-opsin or L-<lb/>opsin if the decision was stochastic; or (2) a majority of cones expressing M-opsin or L-opsin <lb/>only if the decision was temporal and one cone subtype was generated first. In the 122-day-old <lb/>retina, we observed M-opsin and no L-opsin (100% M-opsin only cells, n &gt; 500 cells) (Fig 2A <lb/>and 2B). This retina displayed M-/L-opsin protein in the ONL (S2A Fig), suggesting that <lb/>these cells were terminally differentiating M cones. This retina also displayed Ki67 expression <lb/>(S2A Fig), suggesting that there are proliferating cells, ongoing development, and generation <lb/>of additional neurons at this time point in this region of the fetal retina. In the 130-day-old ret-<lb/>ina, we observed &gt;99% M-opsin only cells with sparse L-opsin only cells (Fig 2A and 2B). <lb/>Opsin expression occurred within the outer nuclear layer (ONL, S2I Fig) and spanned an <lb/>approximately 3 mm wide central region of the retina (approximately 38% of the total width of <lb/>the globe), skewed towards the temporal side, between 1.6 and 4.5 mm from the most temporal <lb/>edge (S2C-S2H Fig). The highest number of M-opsin expressing cells were detected in the <lb/>center of this range, approximately 3 mm from the temporal edge (S2H Fig), consistent with <lb/>observations indicating that the human retina develops from the center to the periphery [2]. <lb/>Together, these data suggested that M cones are generated before L cones during human reti-<lb/>nal development. <lb/>We next quantified M-and L-opsin expression in RNA-seq data sets by comparing counts <lb/>of aligned sequencing reads for M-or L-opsin based on 20 nucleotide differences that distin-<lb/>guish these genes (Fig 1A), normalizing by the total number of aligned reads per sample (&quot;nor-<lb/>malized pileup count&quot;). For these experiments, each point represents the normalized value for <lb/>an individual nucleotide difference between M-opsin mRNA or L-opsin mRNA in an individ-<lb/>ual sample. We validated this approach in the WERI-Rb-1 retinoblastoma cell line, which <lb/>expresses both M-opsin and L-opsin upon addition of thyroid hormone (T3) (S2B Fig). <lb/>We evaluated expression in 12 prenatal samples from day 52/54 through day 136 postcon-<lb/>ception from published RNA-seq data sets [16]. M-opsin expression was observed from day <lb/>M-/L-opsin mRNA and M/L-opsin protein expression in adult human retina (L). Original data sets are in S1 Data. (L) Visualization of M-<lb/>opsin mRNA, L-opsin mRNA, and M-/L-opsin protein in cone cells in an adult human retina. M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink). No cones <lb/>co-expressed M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA. ONL, outer nuclear layer; OPL, outer plexiform layer; INL, inner nuclear layer. Cell <lb/>boundaries were determined by identifying layers from a nuclear Hoechst stain (S1B Fig) and analyzing opsin protein <lb/>immunohistochemistry signal from the ONL to the OPL. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. Expression of M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA in fetal and adult human retinas. (A) 20 μm sections of 122-day-old and 130-day-old human fetal <lb/>retinas. M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink). White arrow indicates L-opsin-expressing cell. (B) Quantification of % M and L cones in 122-day-old and 130-day-<lb/>old human fetal retinas. (C-F) M-and L-opsin mRNA expression in developing human fetal retinas and adult retinas. Values indicate total pileup count, <lb/>normalized to total read count. Each data point indicates detection of M-or L-opsin mRNAs, based an individual nucleotide difference. N = 1 for each time <lb/>point, except 94-2 where N = 2. 52/54 = exact date is unclear. Analyzed from [16,17]. Original data sets are in S2 Data. (C) M-opsin mRNA in fetal retinas. (D) <lb/>L-opsin mRNA in fetal retinas. (E) M-opsin mRNA in adult retinas. (F) L-opsin mRNA in adult retinas. (G) Schematic of adult human retina with regions <lb/>isolated using a 5 mm biopsy punch. White circle = optic nerve. Red lines = blood vessels. Yellow circle = macular pigment. (H-J) 20 μm sections were probed <lb/>for M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink) mRNA. (K) Average ratios of M and L cones as percent of M/L total cones across 3 individuals. One-way ANOVA with <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>115 through day 136 (Fig 2C). M-opsin expression increased in retinas from day 115 through <lb/>132. M-opsin expression was present but lower on day 136 (Fig 2C). As these expression analy-<lb/>ses were conducted on single human fetal retinal samples [16], the decrease is likely due to bio-<lb/>logical variability between samples. In contrast, L-opsin expression was minimally detected <lb/>during this time (Fig 2D). We analyzed opsin expression from three independent adult <lb/>human retinas from published data sets [17] and observed expression of both M-and L-opsin <lb/>(Fig 2E and 2F). These data suggested that M-opsin is expressed before L-opsin during human <lb/>development. <lb/>To assess cone distributions in the adult human retina, we dissected three retinas, used a <lb/>biopsy punch to isolate 5 mm wide regions of tissue from the center, middle, and peripheral <lb/>retina (Figs 2G and S3A), sectioned the tissue, and performed our in situ hybridization strat-<lb/>egy. For each retina, we analyzed one punch from the center region, three middle regions, and <lb/>three peripheral regions (S3A Fig). We manually quantified cells expressing M-opsin mRNA <lb/>or L-opsin mRNA and validated our approach using semi-automated image analysis software <lb/>(S3B-S3E Fig). The center and middle had significantly higher proportions of M cones com-<lb/>pared to the periphery (Figs 2H-2K and S3F-S3H). As cone specification occurs from the <lb/>center to the periphery during development [18,19], the higher proportions of M cones in the <lb/>earlier-specified center and middle regions are consistent with the generation of M cones <lb/>before L cones. <lb/>Early retinoic acid signaling promotes M cones and suppresses L cones in <lb/>human retinal organoids <lb/>We next sought to identify a mechanism that regulates M and L cone specification. RA signaling <lb/>controls expression of an independently evolved opsin gene array in zebrafish [20-22]. We hypoth-<lb/>esized that RA may play a role in the regulation of the M/L-opsin gene array in the developing <lb/>human retina. We assessed expression of RA pathway regulatory genes in 12 prenatal samples <lb/>from day 52/54 through day 136 postconception from published RNA-seq data sets [16]. Specific <lb/>aldehyde dehydrogenases (ALDHs) convert retinaldehyde to RA. ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 are <lb/>expressed early in retinal development and decrease over time, whereas ALDH1A2 is expressed at <lb/>very low levels throughout gestation (Fig 3A). Similar to ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 in humans <lb/>(Fig 3A), ALDH orthologs in mouse [23], zebrafish [24], and chicken [25], are expressed highly <lb/>early and decrease during development. Cytochrome p450 family 26 (CYP26) enzymes catalyze <lb/>the degradation of RA. CYP26A1 is steadily expressed at low levels, whereas CYP26B1 and <lb/>CYP26C1 are not expressed (S4A Fig). The high expression of 2 RA-synthesizing enzymes early <lb/>suggested that RA signaling is high early and decreases during development. <lb/>We next assessed spatiotemporal expression of RA pathway regulatory genes in samples <lb/>taken from the center or periphery through fetal development from published RNA-seq data <lb/>sets [16]. ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 were expressed highest in the center on day 59 and <lb/>decreased on days 96 and 132 (Fig 3B). ALDH1A2 was not expressed in the center (Fig 3B). In <lb/>the periphery, ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 were expressed highest on day 59 (Fig 3B and 3C), <lb/>with decreases on days 73, 96, and 132 (Fig 3C). ALDH1A2 was not expressed in the periphery <lb/>(Fig 3C). CYP26A1 was steadily expressed in the center and periphery and CYP26B1 and <lb/>CYP26C1 were not expressed (S4B and S4C Fig). Together, these data are consistent with (1) <lb/>the overall decreases in ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 expression during human fetal retinal devel-<lb/>opment (Fig 3A); and (2) high RA signaling early and decreasing during development. <lb/>Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test: Center L versus Middle L = no significance; Center L versus Periphery L p &lt; 0.01; Middle L versus Periphery L p &lt; 0.01. ** <lb/>Indicates p &lt; 0.01. Original data sets are in S2 Data. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>As M-opsin is expressed before L-opsin and the temporal dynamics of ALDH1A1 and <lb/>ALDH1A3 suggest high RA signaling early, we hypothesized that high RA signaling early pro-<lb/>motes M cone fate and suppresses L cone fate. We tested this hypothesis using human retinal <lb/>organoids. Differentiation of human retinal organoids involves addition of 1.0 μm RA on days <lb/>20 to 43 to promote early retinal patterning (S4D Fig). Organoids were grown in media with-<lb/>out exogenous RA from day 43 to day 200, from the end of primitive retina differentiation <lb/>through early cell fate specification (13% M, 87% L, 0.1% co-expressing M+L; Fig 3D-3F, &quot;No <lb/>Fig 3. RA signaling induces M-opsin and inhibits L-opsin early in human retinal organoids. (A-C) Expression of ALDH1A1, <lb/>ALDH1A2, and ALDH1A3 in fetal human retinas by day of gestation and retinal region. CPM, log counts per million. Analyzed from <lb/>[16]. Error bars for the 2 samples from fetal day 94 indicate SEM. Original data sets are in S3 Data. (A) Whole retina. (B) Central <lb/>retina. (C) Periphery. (D) Black bars indicate temporal windows of 1.0 μm RA addition during retinal organoid culture. (E) <lb/>Quantification of M and L cone ratios for RA treatments. For &quot;No RA,&quot; N = 3; for &quot;RA to day 60,&quot; N = 6; for &quot;RA to day 130,&quot; N = 3; <lb/>and for &quot;Late RA,&quot; N = 5. One-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test: &quot;No RA&quot; L-opsin versus &quot;RA to day 60&quot; L-<lb/>opsin, p &lt; 0.05; &quot;No RA&quot; L-opsin versus &quot;RA to day 130&quot; L-opsin p &lt; 0.005; &quot;No RA&quot; L-opsin versus &quot;Late RA&quot; L-opsin p = 0.9635. <lb/>Error bars indicate SEM. * Indicates p &lt; 0.05; *** indicates p &lt; 0.005. (F-I) M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink) expression in <lb/>organoids grown in different RA conditions (D), quantified in (E). White dotted outlines indicate M-or L-opsin-expressing cells. <lb/>White lines indicate the edge of the organoid. (F) No RA. (G) RA to day 60. (H) RA to day 130. (I) Late RA. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>RA&quot;). These organoids displayed a mix of M cones and L cones (Fig 3E and 3F), similar to <lb/>adult human retinas (Fig 2H-2K). <lb/>To test whether RA was sufficient to promote M cone specification in retinal organoids, we <lb/>added 1.0 μm RA over different timeframes and assessed M and L cone ratios at day 200 (Fig <lb/>3D). We previously examined gene expression at multiple time points during organoid devel-<lb/>opment using bulk RNA-seq [15]. We analyzed this data and found that expression of thyroid <lb/>hormone receptor beta (THRB), a marker of cone fate, stabilizes on day 70 (S4E Fig), suggest-<lb/>ing that the generation of new cones ends around this time point. In contrast, expression of <lb/>neural retina leucine zipper (NRL), a marker of later-born rod photoreceptors, stabilizes <lb/>around day 160 (S4E Fig). Opsin expression was first observed at day 130 [15], suggesting that <lb/>terminal differentiation of cones begins at this time point. We defined three main timeframes <lb/>of cone development: immature cone generation through day 70, maturation from days 70 to <lb/>130, and terminal differentiation from day 130 onwards. <lb/>Addition of RA early through cone maturation from days 43 to 130 yielded organoids with <lb/>almost exclusively M cones at day 200 (98% M, 2% L, 0% co-expressing M+L; Fig 3E and 3H; <lb/>&quot;RA to day 130&quot;), suggesting that addition of RA through the beginning of M-and L-opsin <lb/>expression was sufficient to promote M cone fate. To determine whether RA could promote M <lb/>cone fate in immature cones, we added RA through day 60, before the end of immature cone <lb/>generation and well before terminal differentiation and M-and L-opsin expression on day 130. <lb/>In this condition, organoids were enriched for M cones (74% M, 26% L, 0% co-expressing M <lb/>+L; Fig 3E and 3G; &quot;RA to day 60&quot;), suggesting that RA was sufficient to promote M cone fate <lb/>in immature cones. Addition of RA late in development during terminal differentiation from <lb/>days 130 to 200 yielded L cone-enriched organoids at day 200 (6% M, 93% L, 1% co-express-<lb/>ing; Fig 3E and 3I; &quot;Late RA&quot;), similar to &quot;No RA&quot; control organoids (Fig 3E and 3F), sug-<lb/>gesting that RA was not sufficient to convert L cones to M cone fate. <lb/>For most experimental conditions, we observed minimal differences between densities of <lb/>M and L cones (S4F Fig), suggesting that the changes in M to L cone ratios were primarily due <lb/>to changes in cell fate specification, rather than dramatic loss or gain of M or L cone subtypes. <lb/>As the &quot;Late RA&quot; condition did not affect M versus L cone subtype ratios (Fig 3E and 3I), but <lb/>did increase cone density observed on day 200 (S4F Fig), addition of RA late in organoid <lb/>development likely improves cone survival but does not affect fate specification. Addition of <lb/>RA throughout development prevented normal development and observation of M or L cones <lb/>at day 200, suggesting that continuous high RA is detrimental to overall cone or organoid <lb/>health. Alternatively, as high RA early (Fig 3E and 3H) yields organoids enriched for M cones, <lb/>late RA may specifically impair M cone survival. <lb/>Based on M-and L-opsin expression, cones were identified near the surface of all organoids <lb/>in the presumptive ONL (Fig 3F-3I). During dissection and sectioning, the irregular shapes of <lb/>organoids (S3G-S3H Fig) can result in a mix of cross and tangential sections, likely leading to <lb/>the dispersed patterns of cones observed in some sections. <lb/>Together, these data suggest that RA is sufficient to induce M cones and suppress L cones <lb/>early in retinal organoid development, but not at later time points when cones are already <lb/>specified. <lb/>Natural variation in cone ratios is associated with sequence divergence in <lb/>RA signaling regulators <lb/>In parallel, we evaluated natural variation in the ratios of M and L cones in a human population <lb/>sample. M and L cone ratios vary widely among people with normal color vision [11,26-29]. <lb/>We quantified cone ratios using flicker-photometric electroretinogram (FP-ERG), which <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>measures and analyzes spectral sensitivities to 35 degrees of eccentricity [26], in 738 males with <lb/>normal color vision. We studied males because variation at the X-linked L/M-opsin gene locus <lb/>is a primary site for mutations causing red-green color blindness, and an increase in variation <lb/>could be revealed in hemizygous conditions [30-32]. We observed a range of L cone ratios <lb/>(mean = 59.1%; SD = 16.9%; Fig 4A). The association between FP-ERG and % L is nonlinear <lb/>and as 100% is approached, very small changes in measured spectral sensitivities are associated <lb/>with relatively large changes in estimates of % L, leading to some values that exceeded 100% <lb/>upon normalization (Fig 4A). This extensive variation in the L and M cone ratios is in sharp <lb/>contrast with the modest variation observed in the S cone ratio (8% to 12%) [33-39]. <lb/>To identify a potential genetic basis of this variation in L and M cone ratios, we used a tar-<lb/>geted sequencing approach to test for associations between cone cell ratios and genetic varia-<lb/>tion in mechanistic regulators of cone specification. Our sequencing targeted 21 gene regions, <lb/>including the L/M-opsin gene locus (OPN1LW/MW), the S-opsin gene (OPN1SW), three RA <lb/>regulatory genes (RARA, NR2F2/COUP-TFII, CYP26A1/C1), and 16 other genes with putative <lb/>photoreceptor specification roles (DIO1, DIO2, DIO3, PIAS3, RXRG, RORB, NR2F1/ <lb/>COUP-TFI, OTX1, NEUROD1, THRB, NRL, OTX2, ONECUT1, NR2E3, ONECUT2, SALL3) <lb/>(S5 Fig). We generated custom-designed oligos and used a solution-based capture method for <lb/>target enrichment. We barcoded and pooled samples, which we sequenced with 125 bp paired-<lb/>end reads. We mapped the reads, genotyped the samples, and evaluated associations with L <lb/>cone ratios (Fig 4D). In this Manhattan plot (Fig 4D), the position of each variant along the y-<lb/>axis represents the significance of the association with the variation in L cone ratio and the <lb/>position along the x-axis represents the genomic position at each locus. <lb/>After alignment and genotyping, we scanned for associations between variants in these <lb/>genes and L cone ratios (Fig 4D). We identified a significant association between SNP <lb/>rs372754794 ( b = -18.54, p-value = 1.67 × 10 -5 ) and variation in the L cone ratio (Fig 4B-<lb/>4D). Individuals with the T/G genotype displayed a lower % L cone ratio than individuals with <lb/>the T/T genotype (Fig 4B and 4C). <lb/>The SNP rs372754794, which occurs within the targeted sequence spanning NR2F2/ <lb/>COUP-TFII, lies in an intron in a noncoding RNA (NR2F2-AS1) immediately upstream of <lb/>NR2F2 (Fig 4E and 4F). The minor (G) allele, which is associated with reduced L cone ratio, <lb/>was nearly exclusive to African American and African subjects within our sample <lb/>(MAF = 0.0359; Fig 4G) and exhibited similar patterns of frequency differentiation in external <lb/>data from the 1000 Genomes Project [40]. The association with L cone ratio was robust even <lb/>when restricting analysis to African American subjects ( b = -14.45, p-value = 1.44 × 10 -4 ) (Fig <lb/>4H). Within African American populations from the 1000 Genomes Project, rs372754794 <lb/>exhibited only modest linkage disequilibrium (LD) with other nearby variants (Fig 4F), such <lb/>that the associated haplotype is confined to the NR2F2-AS1 transcript. <lb/>NR2F2 is a nuclear receptor that mediates RA signaling [41]. NR2F2 and the upstream <lb/>NR2F2-AS1 are expressed in human retinas and retinal organoids during development (S6A <lb/>and S6B Fig) [16]. The associated SNP lies in a region of high transcription factor binding <lb/>identified as a putative enhancer (S6C Fig) that is predicted to interact and regulate the pro-<lb/>moters of NR2F2 and/or NR2F2-AS1 (S6D Fig). Alternatively, as part of an lncRNA transcript, <lb/>the SNP could affect NR2F2-AS1-mediated regulation of NR2F2 or other genes. The observed <lb/>association at NR2F2 is consistent with a role for RA signaling in M versus L cone subtype <lb/>specification. <lb/>The second strongest associated SNP (rs36102671) approached but did not achieve statisti-<lb/>cal significance upon multiple testing correction (Bonferroni correction p-value <lb/>threshold = 1.73 × 10 -5 ). This SNP lies within the first intron of the RARA gene, which encodes <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 4. Natural variation in cone ratios is associated with RA signaling regulation. (A) Histogram of the ratios of % L from 738 human <lb/>males with normal color vision. (B) L cone ratios for SNP rs372754794 genotypes. Original data sets are in S4 Data. (C) SNP rs372754794 <lb/>genotype frequencies for L cone ratio deciles. Original data sets are in S4 Data. (D) Manhattan plot of the genetic variant p-values. Dots <lb/>represent genetic variants in genes. Genetic variants above the gray line (Bonferroni corrected threshold) are significant (p &lt; 0.05). The dots <lb/>for each gene locus are presented in the same color (ex: DIO1 = dark blue; PIAS3 = orange). Along the X axis, the dots are spaced to scale as <lb/>they occur in the genome. As OPN1LW and OPN1MW are nearby each other in the genome, the variants are represented together at the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>a receptor for RA (Fig 4D). The minor (A) allele, which segregates at low allele frequencies in <lb/>globally diverse populations, is associated with decreased L cone ratios ( b = -15.95, p-<lb/>value = 6.54 × 10 -5 ) (S7A Fig). Within European populations, LD at this locus extends over an <lb/>approximately 200 kb region of chromosome 17, including RARA and 7 other genes (R 2 &gt; <lb/>0.7). The SNP exhibits an association with altered splicing of RARA based on RNA sequencing <lb/>of whole blood (S7B Fig) [42], suggesting that the haplotype modulates RARA function. <lb/>While validation and further dissection of these association results require investigation in <lb/>a larger cohort, the association of RA-related candidates with changes in M and L cone ratios <lb/>is consistent with a role for RA signaling in the specification of M and L cone subtypes in <lb/>humans. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We found that M-opsin, but not L-opsin, is expressed in early developing fetal retinas. In <lb/>adults, the earlier-born central and middle regions have higher proportions of M cones com-<lb/>pared to the later-born periphery. RA-synthesizing ALDHs are highly expressed early in retinal <lb/>development and decrease over time, suggesting that RA signaling is high during early devel-<lb/>opment. RA is sufficient to promote M cone fate and suppress L cone fate in immature cones. <lb/>Together, we propose that RA signaling is high early in human retinal development to pro-<lb/>mote the generation of M cones and low later to yield the generation of L cones (Fig 5). <lb/>Our observations suggest that RA signaling influences cone fate in immature cones. In <lb/>human fetal retinas, M-opsin mRNA expression is readily observed on day 115, whereas <lb/>expression of RA synthesis genes (i.e., ALDHs) is highest on day approximately 55 and then <lb/>decreases. In human retinal organoids, addition of RA before day 60, well before opsin mRNA <lb/>expression, induces M cones and suppresses L cones. RA signaling may act at the gene locus to <lb/>regulate opsin expression directly or function upstream to influence M and L cone fates. <lb/>As (1) M-opsin or L-opsin were exclusively expressed in cones in fetal and adult retinas; and <lb/>(2) RA promoted M cone fate early but did not convert L cones into M cones late, M cones <lb/>and L cones likely arise directly from immature cones and do not undergo hybrid states. An <lb/>OPN1LW/MW locus in the same dark blue color. Due to the highly similar sequences of OPN1LW and OPN1MW, many reads could not be <lb/>mapped, resulting in the gap in the variants at the OPN1LW/MW locus. Original data sets are in S4 Data. (E) Location of SNP rs372754794 <lb/>upstream at the NR2F2 gene locus. NR2F2 gene (blue); NR2F2 antisense RNA (pink). Yellow arrow denotes the location of the SNP. (F) Local <lb/>LD plot for rs37275494 based on data from an African American (ASW) population from the 1000 Genomes Project. Top indicates variants. <lb/>Bottom indicates gene predictions. (G) Minor (G) allele ratio at rs37275494 by ancestry. Original data sets are in S4 Data. (H) Association of <lb/>L:M ratio and rs372754794 stratified by self-reported ancestry. Original data sets are in S4 Data. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.g004 <lb/>Fig 5. Model-RA regulates the spatiotemporal patterning of M and L cones in the human retina. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>alternative is that all cones initially express M-opsin and then a subset switch and express L-<lb/>opsin, perhaps undergoing a period of co-expression during late fetal development, a time <lb/>point which was experimentally inaccessible. Though these details require further interro-<lb/>gation, our data clearly support temporal generation of M and L cones in the human retina. <lb/>ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 expression was observed in the central and peripheral retina on day <lb/>59 and decreased at later time points in both regions. ALDH1A1 and ALDH1A3 expression <lb/>decreases to very low levels earlier in the central retina than periphery, reflecting the regionalized <lb/>timing of retinal development, with the central region developing earlier than the periphery. <lb/>The arrangement of the LCR regulatory element and the L-and M-opsin genes in humans <lb/>resembles an independently evolved gene array in zebrafish [20]. In zebrafish, long wavelength <lb/>opsin expression is controlled by RA, which promotes expression of the proximal opsin gene <lb/>late in development [21]. This contrasts with our findings that RA signaling promotes expres-<lb/>sion of the distal opsin early in humans. These observations suggest differences in the evolu-<lb/>tion of the regulation of RA signaling and the cis-regulatory logic controlling opsin expression, <lb/>consistent with the independent origin of these opsin gene clusters. <lb/>RA appears to play multiple roles in human photoreceptor specification. In addition to its <lb/>role in M versus L cone specification, RA regulates rod generation in human retinal organoids <lb/>[43-45]. How RA coordinates the specification of cone and rod fate features is a key question <lb/>for future studies. <lb/>Studying human development poses specific challenges including limited access to tis-<lb/>sue, a lack of a controlled genetic background, and an inability to experimentally manipu-<lb/>late developing tissue. Vertebrate model organisms provided numerous insights into cell <lb/>fate specification during retinal development. However, differences between these species <lb/>and humans prevented interrogation of questions that can only be addressed in developing <lb/>human tissue. Our studies show that human retinal organoids are a powerful model system <lb/>to investigate developmental processes that are unique to humans, great apes, and Old <lb/>World monkeys. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Cell lines <lb/>Cell lines used in this study are in Table 1. <lb/>HEK293 cell line maintenance <lb/>HEK293 cells were maintained in DMEM 4.5 g/L D-glucose, L-glutamine (11965084, Gibco) <lb/>+ 10% fetal bovine serum (16140071, Gibco) + 1× Penicillin-Streptomycin (30-002-CI, Corn-<lb/>ing) at 37˚C in a HERAcell 150i or 160i 5% CO 2 incubator (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Cells <lb/>were split 1:4 to 1:10 every 2 to 3 days when approximately 80% confluent and kept in 6-well <lb/>dishes or uncoated flasks using Trypsin (0.25%)-EDTA (0.02%) in HBSS (118-093-721, Qual-<lb/>ity Biological). <lb/>Table 1. Genotypes of cell lines. <lb/>Cell line <lb/>Sex <lb/>Source <lb/>Figures <lb/>HEK293 <lb/>Female <lb/>Kuruvilla lab, Johns Hopkins <lb/>1C-1J, S1A, S1C <lb/>WERI-Rb-1 <lb/>Female <lb/>ATCC <lb/>S2B <lb/>H7 ESC <lb/>Female <lb/>WA07, WiCell <lb/>3E-3I, S4F-S4H <lb/>H7 iCas9 ESC <lb/>Female <lb/>Zack lab, Johns Hopkins <lb/>3E-3I, S4F-S4H <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>Transfection of opsin cDNA into HEK293 cells <lb/>HEK293 cells were passaged 24 h prior to be &lt;60% confluent on the day of transfection. <lb/>Transfection was done with the Lipofectamine 3000 transfection kit (L3000001, Invitrogen). <lb/>For a 10 cm dish, 7.5 μl lipofectamine 3000 was mixed with 125 μl Opti-MEM (31985062, <lb/>Thermo Fisher Scientific) at room temperature (RT) for 5 min, and 5 μl of P3000, 0.5-1 μg <lb/>DNA (Table 2), and 125 μl Opti-MEM was mixed at RT for 5 min as per manufacturer <lb/>instruction. The 2 solutions were mixed and incubated at RT for 10 min. Media was aspirated <lb/>from HEK293 cells and replaced with 8 mL of pre-warmed Opti-MEM. Lipofectamine mixture <lb/>was added to cells and incubated at 37˚C in a HERAcell 150i or 160i 5% CO 2 incubator for 4 <lb/>to 6 h. Transfection media was aspirated and replaced with HEK293 maintenance media <lb/>(DMEM/10% FBS/1× Penn/Strep) and cells were allowed to recover overnight. Cells were <lb/>adhered to slides coated with 10% Poly-L-lysine solution (0.1% w/v in H 2 O) (P8920, Sigma) <lb/>for 1 to 3 h at 37˚C in a HERAcell 150i or 160i 5% CO 2 incubator (Thermo Fisher Scientific). <lb/>Cells were washed in 1× PBS and fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) <lb/>for 30 min. Slides were either used immediately or ethanol dehydrated and stored at -80˚C. <lb/>BaseScope RNA in situ hybridization <lb/>BaseScope RNA in situ hybridization was performed according to manufacturer&apos;s instructions <lb/>(Advanced Cell Diagnostics) and modified with several changes. Adherent tissue culture cells <lb/>or sections of human, fetal, or organoid tissue were allowed to come to RT from storage at <lb/>-80˚C and rehydrated in 1× PBS. Samples were pretreated according to manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions: 10 min in RNAscope Hydrogen Peroxide followed by a wash in dH 2 O and then 2 <lb/>washes in 1× PBS. The following step is an RNAscope Protease step which varies depending <lb/>on tissue type. For HEK293 cells, RNAscope Protease III was applied at a 1:15 dilution in 1× <lb/>PBS for 15 min in a humid chamber. For organoids and human eye samples, RNAscope Prote-<lb/>ase IV was applied for 20 min in a humid chamber. Samples were then washed in 1× PBS <lb/>twice. Probes were added (Table 3) at the manufacturer suggested concentration to samples in <lb/>the HybEZ Humidity Control rack with lid and inserted into the HybEZ oven for 2 h at 40˚C. <lb/>Samples were washed twice in 1× RNAscope wash buffer for 2 min. Amplification and devel-<lb/>opment washes were done with the manufacturer reagents at the recommended concentra-<lb/>tions. All washes were done in the HybEZ Humidity Control rack with lid and insert, either at <lb/>RT or at 40˚C in the HybEZ oven at the temperatures and time lengths according to Table 4, <lb/>with 2× 2 min washes in 1× RNAScope Buffer conducted between each reagent wash. <lb/>Table 3. BaseScope in situ probes. <lb/>Reagent type <lb/>Reagent <lb/>Source <lb/>Identifier <lb/>Additional information <lb/>BaseScope probe <lb/>BA-Hs-OPN1MW-1zz-st1 <lb/>Advanced Cell Diagnostics <lb/>714201 <lb/>bp 902-941 <lb/>NM_000513.2 <lb/>BaseScope probe <lb/>BA-Hs-OPN1LW-1zz-st-C2-<lb/>Advanced Cell Diagnostics <lb/>716081-C2 <lb/>bp 880-921 <lb/>NM_020061.5 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t003 <lb/>Table 2. Opsin cDNA plasmids. <lb/>Plasmid <lb/>Source <lb/>Figures <lb/>OPN1MW NM_000513.2 <lb/>GenScript <lb/>1C-1J, S1A, S1C <lb/>OPN1LW NM_020061.5 <lb/>GenScript <lb/>1C-1J, S1A, S1C <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>Slides were baked for a minimum of 30 min at 65˚C in the HybEZ oven or until dry. Sam-<lb/>ples were preserved with VectaMount (Vector Laboratories, H-5000) mounting media and a <lb/>sealed 1.5 coverslip. <lb/>Imaging HEK293 RNA in situ hybridization <lb/>HEK293 cells were imaged using an EVOS XL Core Cell imaging system on brightfield with a <lb/>20× objective (Thermo Fisher). <lb/>M/L-opsin immunohistochemistry and BaseScope in situ hybridization on <lb/>HEK293 cells and adult human retina sections <lb/>HEK293 cells transfected with M-and/or L-opsin cDNA were allowed to come to RT after stor-<lb/>age in 100% EtOH at 4˚C. Adult sections were allowed to come to RT from storage at -80˚C <lb/>and dehydrated in a stepwise ethanol dehydration from 50%, 70%, and 100% EtOH. Samples <lb/>were pretreated according to ACD Biotechne manufacturer&apos;s instructions: 10 min of RNA-<lb/>scope Hydrogen Peroxide at RT, followed by a wash in dH2O and then 2 washes in 1× PBS. <lb/>Slides were then acclimatized for 10 s in 99˚C dH 2 0, and then transferred to 99˚C RNAscope <lb/>1× Target Retrieval Reagent for 15 min using the Oster Double Tiered Food Steamer Warmer <lb/>5712. Slides were then transferred into dH 2 0 for 15 s, and then transferred to 0.1% TWEEN <lb/>(Sigma P7949). A primary antibody targeting both OPN1MW and OPN1LW (anti-rabbit <lb/>Millipore ab5405 #3823289) was diluted 1:200 in Co-detection Antibody Diluent and added to <lb/>the slides. All slides were incubated overnight in a humidity-controlled tray at 4˚C. Primary <lb/>antibodies were washed off with 2 washes of 0.1% TWEEN for 2 min, and then postfixed by <lb/>submerging in 10% neutral buffered formalin for 30 min at RT. Fixative was removed with 4 <lb/>washes of 0.1% TWEEN for 2 min each. For HEK293 cells, RNAscope Protease III was applied <lb/>at a 1:15 dilution in 1× PBS for 15 min in a humid chamber. For retina sections, RNAscope <lb/>Protease IV was applied for 20 min in a humid chamber. Samples were washed in 1× PBS <lb/>twice. Slides were washed twice in RNAscope 1× wash buffer for 2 min each. Co-Detection <lb/>Blocker was applied to the slides and incubated for 15 min at 40˚C. Slides were then washed <lb/>twice in RNAscope wash buffer for 2 min each, and then washed in 0.1% TWEEN for 2 min. <lb/>Donkey anti-rabbit 647 secondary antibody (Invitrogen Thermo Fisher Scientific A31573 <lb/>Table 4. BaseScope assay reagent washes. <lb/>Reagent <lb/>Temperature (˚C) <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>AMP 1 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 2 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 3 <lb/>40 <lb/>15 <lb/>AMP 4 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 5 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 6 <lb/>40 <lb/>15 <lb/>AMP 7 <lb/>RT <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 8 <lb/>RT <lb/>15 <lb/>RED-A/B <lb/>RT <lb/>10 <lb/>AMP 9 <lb/>40 <lb/>15 <lb/>AMP 10 <lb/>40 <lb/>15 <lb/>AMP 11 <lb/>RT <lb/>30 <lb/>AMP 12 <lb/>RT <lb/>15 <lb/>GREEN-A/B <lb/>RT <lb/>10 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>#2181018) was diluted 1:400 in Co-detection Antibody Diluent and applied to the samples <lb/>overnight in a humidity control tray at 4˚C. Slides were then washed twice in 0.1% TWEEN <lb/>for 2 min each, and co-stained in Hoechst 33342 (Biotium 40046 #10H0212, diluted 1:2,000 in <lb/>1× PBS). <lb/>Imaging of M/L-opsin IHC and ISH <lb/>Slides were mounted in 1× PBS and the IHC staining was imaged the next day using either a <lb/>Zeiss LSM 980 inverted microscope with an Axiocam 506 color camera system and a C Apo <lb/>40×/1.2 W DICIII lens or an Olympus IX81 inverted microscope equipped with a Hamamatsu <lb/>Orca 4.0 v3 monochrome camera. <lb/>ISH BaseScope of M and L-opsin in human adult retina and HEK293 cells <lb/>Coverslips from previous IHC assay were removed by soaking for 10 min in 5× SSC (Invitro-<lb/>gen by Thermo Fisher Scientific AM9763). BaseScope probes were then applied and amplified <lb/>using the aforementioned protocol (&quot;BaseScope RNA in situ hybridization&quot;). Nuclei were <lb/>stained using Hoechst 33342 (Biotium 40046 #10H0212, diluted 1:2,000 in 1× PBS). <lb/>Imaging of ISH BaseScope M-and L-opsin in human adult retina and <lb/>HEK293 cells <lb/>ISH BaseScope colorimetric staining was then imaged the day after protocol completion in <lb/>brightfield using either a Zeiss LSM 980 inverted microscope with an Axiocam 506 color cam-<lb/>era system and a C Apo 40×/1.2 W DICIII lens, or an Olympus IX81 inverted microscope <lb/>equipped with a Hamamatsu Orca 4.0 v3 monochrome camera. A Cambridge Research &amp; <lb/>Instrumentation, Inc. (CRi) Micro*Color tunable RGB filter was inserted in the light path to <lb/>allow fast sequential acquisition of red, green, and blue images, which were merged to form <lb/>the final RGB data set. <lb/>Semi-automated quantification of M-and L-opsin in adult retina <lb/>Representative pictures of M-and L-opsin in situ hybridization colorimetric staining from cen-<lb/>tral, middle, and peripheral regions of the adult retina were deconvoluted in HALO Image <lb/>Analysis Platform 3.5.3577 (Indica Labs) [46]. To visualize the chromogenic stain, we used the <lb/>Deconvolution v1.1.7 module of the HALO Image Analysis Platform (Indica Labs) to separate <lb/>out the colorimetric stains of the RGB images. Specifically, average RGB values from 9 to 16 <lb/>pixels of each chromogenic stain were input into the brightfield algorithm to generate decon-<lb/>voluted images. The chromogenic RED-A/B signal (generated by alkaline phosphatase against <lb/>the BA-Hs-OPN1LW-1zz-st-C2 probe) was assigned red pseudo color and GREEN-A/B signal <lb/>(generated by horseradish peroxidase against the BA-Hs-OPN1MW-1zz-st1 probe) was <lb/>assigned green pseudo color. If retinal pigmented epithelium was present, this was assigned <lb/>orange pseudo color. The deconvoluted staining was then used to count the number of M-and <lb/>L-opsin-expressing foci using the Object Colocalization FL v2.1.4 module. <lb/>Human adult retina tissue <lb/>Donor samples were acquired from the National Disease Research Interchange (NDRI) <lb/>between 12.5 and 15.5 h postmortem and were flash frozen on dry ice after enucleation and <lb/>stored at -80˚C. A human eye was allowed to come to RT in 1× PBS. <lb/>The anterior portion of the eye (cornea, iris, and lens) was removed. The posterior pole of <lb/>the eye was butterflied in a petri dish, with 4 to 5 cuts made from the anterior ciliary body to <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>midway to the posterior, such that the retina and other tissue laid flat on the dish. A 5 mm <lb/>punch biopsy tool (RBP-50, Robbins Instruments) was placed over the macula based on the <lb/>presence of macular pigment in combination with presence of an avascular region to remove <lb/>the central retina. Punches were taken immediately adjacent for the middle retina and imme-<lb/>diately adjacent for the periphery. A total of 1 central punch, 3 middle punches, and 3 periph-<lb/>eral punches were taken from each eye (S3A Fig). Retinal punches were fixed for 45 min in <lb/>10% neutral buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) and washed in 1× PBS. The subsections of <lb/>retina were mounted in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. compound (4583, Sakura), placed on dry ice to <lb/>freeze, and stored at -80˚C. The retinal regions were cryosectioned in 20 μm sections. Slides <lb/>were air dried for 6 h to overnight followed by a postfixation step of 15 min in 10% neutral <lb/>buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) and washed in 1× PBS after drying. Slides were dried <lb/>and stored at -80˚C for no more than 3 months before use. <lb/>Imaging human adult RNA in situ hybridization <lb/>Samples were imaged in brightfield using a Zeiss LSM 980 inverted microscope with an Axio-<lb/>cam 506 color camera system using a C Apo 40×/1.2 W DICIII lens or an EVOS XL Core Cell <lb/>imaging system on brightfield with a 20× air objective (Thermo Fisher). <lb/>Human fetal retina tissue <lb/>Day 122 fetal retina (sex and left/right eye information unknown) and day 130 fetal eye (sex <lb/>and left/right eye information unknown) were enucleated and flash frozen on dry ice and <lb/>stored at -80˚C. The fetal eye was allowed to come to RT in 1× PBS. The anterior portion of <lb/>the eye (lens, cornea, and iris) was removed with scissors. The posterior portion of the eye was <lb/>fixed overnight in 10% neutral buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) and washed in 1× PBS. <lb/>The whole posterior eye was mounted in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. compound (4583, Sakura), placed <lb/>on dry ice to freeze, and stored at -80˚C. The eye was cryosectioned in 20 μm sections starting <lb/>from the anterior side to the posterior, such that each section contains the nasal/temporal and <lb/>dorsal/ventral information at each position along the anterior/posterior axis. For the day 130 <lb/>fetal eye, sections were collected at 100 μm intervals, moving in a temporal to nasal direction. <lb/>Sections were postfixed for 15 min in 10% neutral buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) and <lb/>washed in 1× PBS, then air dried overnight. Slides were stored at -80˚C and used within 6 <lb/>months. <lb/>Imaging human fetal RNA in situ hybridization <lb/>Samples were imaged as overlapping tile regions in brightfield using a Zeiss LSM 980 inverted <lb/>microscope with an Axiocam 506 color camera system using a C Apo 20×/1.2 W DICIII lens <lb/>or C Apo 40×/1.2 W DICIII lens. Maximum intensity projections of z-stacks (4 to 8 optical <lb/>sections, 2 μm step size) were rendered within Zen Blue Image Processing software. <lb/>Orientation of RNA in situ hybridization staining within human fetal <lb/>retinal tissue <lb/>To orient the chromogenic staining in the context of the developing retinal tissue, we counter-<lb/>stained a subset of fetal retina slides in Hoechst 33342 (Biotium 40046 #10H0212, diluted <lb/>1:2,000 in 1× PBS) for 10 min following the drying step of the BaseScope RNA in situ hybrid-<lb/>ization protocol. Slides were mounted in 1× PBS and immediately imaged on an EVOS M5000 <lb/>imaging system using a 405 fluorescent LED light cube and an RGB channel with a 20× air <lb/>objective (Thermo Scientific Invitrogen). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>To visualize the nuclear counterstain alongside the Basescope chromogenic stain, we used <lb/>the Indica Labs-Deconvolution v1.1.7 module of the HALO Image Analysis Platform version <lb/>3.5.3577 (Indica Labs) to separate the chromogenic stains of the RGB images. Specifically, <lb/>average RGB values from 9 to 16 pixels of each chromogenic stain were input into the bright-<lb/>field algorithm to generate deconvoluted images. The chromogenic RED-A/B signal (gener-<lb/>ated by alkaline phosphatase against the BA-Hs-OPN1LW-1zz-st-C2 probe) was assigned red <lb/>pseudo color, GREEN-A/B signal (generated by horseradish peroxidase against the BA-Hs-<lb/>OPN1MW-1zz-st1 probe) was assigned green pseudo color. If retinal pigmented epithelium <lb/>was present, this was assigned orange pseudo color. Deconvoluted chromogenic images were <lb/>then merged with nuclear counterstains in ImageJ software. <lb/>IHC of fetal human retina sections <lb/>Day 122 human fetal retina sections were stained using the above IHC staining protocol (&quot;M/ <lb/>L-opsin IHC and ISH BaseScope on HEK293 cells and adult human retina sections&quot;) with the <lb/>following adjustments: In addition to OPN1MW and OPN1LW, primary antibodies targeting <lb/>Ki67 (anti-mouse Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-23900 #A1520) were applied to the fetal <lb/>human retina sections. The following secondaries were used: donkey anti-rabbit 647 (Invitro-<lb/>gen Thermo Fisher Scientific A31573 #2181018), donkey anti-mouse 555 secondary antibody <lb/>(Invitrogen Thermo Fisher Scientific A31570 #204536), and donkey anti-chick 488 secondary <lb/>antibody (703-545-155 #156558 Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories) was diluted 1:400 in <lb/>Co-detection Antibody Diluent. Nuclei were counter stained using Hoescht 33342 (Biotium <lb/>40046 #10H0212, diluted 1:2,000 in 1× PBS). Samples were imaged with a laser scanning con-<lb/>focal Zeiss LSM 980 inverted microscope using a C Apo 40×/1.2 W DICIII lens. <lb/>WERI-Rb-1 cell line maintenance <lb/>WERI-Rb-1 retinoblastoma cells were maintained in RPMI 1640 Medium (11875135, Gibco) <lb/>+ 10% fetal bovine serum (16140071, Gibco) + 1× Penicillin-Streptomycin (30-002-CI, Corn-<lb/>ing) at 37˚C in a HERAcell 150i or 160i 5% CO 2 incubator (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Cells <lb/>were passaged every 4 days at approximately 1 × 10 5 to 2 × 10 6 cells/mL in uncoated flasks by <lb/>pelleting at 150 g for 5 min and resuspending in fresh media. <lb/>Bulk RNA sequencing samples <lb/>Fetal retina bulk RNA sequencing data were analyzed from Hoshino and colleagues [16]. <lb/>Adult retina sequencing data were analyzed from Pinelli and colleagues [17]. WERI-Rb-1 sam-<lb/>ples were grown in control media or T3-treated media (100 nM T3 (T6397, Sigma) in RPMI <lb/>+ supplement media) for 4 days (N = 1). RNA from individual samples was extracted using the <lb/>Zymo Direct-zol RNA Microprep Kit (R2062, Zymo Research) according to manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Libraries were prepared using the Illumina TruSeq stranded mRNA kit and <lb/>sequenced on an Illumina NextSeq 500 with single 75 bp reads. EP1 iPSC-derived organoids <lb/>were previously grown and analyzed for Eldred and colleagues at time points ranging from <lb/>day 10 to day 250 of differentiation [15]. <lb/>Bulk RNA sequencing analysis <lb/>Quantification of opsin expression in human fetal retina samples from [16,17] using code depos-<lb/>ited https://github.com/bbrener1/johnston_retina: Expression of opsin genes was directly quanti-<lb/>fied from FASTQ files using Kallisto 0.44.0. The kallisto index was generated from the Gencode <lb/>V27 human transcriptome, with the default kmer setting of 31. Reads were quantified in single-<lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>ended mode with a specified length of 75 and standard deviation of 10. Quantification of opsin <lb/>expression in organoid data: Organoid data was previously quantified and described in [15]. <lb/>Expression levels were quantified using Kallisto (version 0.34.1) with the following parameters: <lb/>&quot;-b 100 -l 200 -s 10 -t 20 -single&quot;. The Gencode release 28 comprehensive annotation was used as <lb/>the reference transcriptome [47]. For the analysis of opsin pileups, to examine the reads mapped <lb/>to each opsin directly, reads were aligned to the opsin transcripts using Bowtie 2.3.4.3, and aligned <lb/>files were processed with samtools 1.7 to produce pileups around selected locations in the tran-<lb/>scripts. Pileups are a text-based format that quantifies base calls of aligned reads to a reference <lb/>genome. For the quantification of human samples, a Bowtie2 index was generated from sequences <lb/>ENST00000595290.5 and ENST00000369951.8 using the default settings. Pileups were generated <lb/>for transcript positions given in Table 5. <lb/>Stem cell line maintenance <lb/>H7 ESC (WA07, WiCell) and episomal-derived EP1.1 iPSC (Zack lab, Hopkins) were used for <lb/>retinal organoid differentiation. Pluripotency of EP1.1 cells was evaluated previously with anti-<lb/>bodies for NANOG, OCT4, SOX2, and SSEA2 [48]. Stem cells were maintained in mTeSR1 <lb/>(85857, Stem Cell Technologies) on 1% (v/v) Matrigel-GFR (354230, BD Biosciences) coated <lb/>dishes and grown at 37˚C in a HERAcell 150i or 160i 10% CO 2 and 5% O 2 incubator (Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientific). Cells were passaged every 4 to 5 days according to confluence as in [48]. <lb/>Cells were passaged with Accutase (SCR005, Sigma) for 7 to 12 min to be dissociated to single <lb/>cells. Cells in Accutase were added 1:2 to mTeSR1 plus 5 μm Blebbistatin (Bleb, B0560, Sigma), <lb/>pelleted at 150 g for 5 min, and suspended in mTeSR1 plus Bleb and plated at 5,000 to 15,000 <lb/>cells per well in a 6-well plate. Media was replaced with mTeSR1 48 h following passage and <lb/>every 24 h until passaged again. To minimize cell stress, no antibiotics were used. <lb/>Table 5. Transcript positions for pileup analyses. <lb/>Exon <lb/>Base <lb/>Transcript position <lb/>Exon position <lb/>Absolute position on chrX <lb/>(GRCh38) <lb/>LW <lb/>MW <lb/>LW <lb/>MW <lb/>LW <lb/>MW <lb/>2 <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>254 <lb/>276 <lb/>81 <lb/>154150737 <lb/>154187851 <lb/>A <lb/>G <lb/>360 <lb/>382 <lb/>187 <lb/>154150843 <lb/>154187957 <lb/>A <lb/>G <lb/>391 <lb/>413 <lb/>218 <lb/>154150874 <lb/>154187988 <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/>407 <lb/>429 <lb/>234 <lb/>154150890 <lb/>154188004 <lb/>4 <lb/>T <lb/>C <lb/>749 <lb/>771 <lb/>110 <lb/>154154684 <lb/>154191798 <lb/>G <lb/>A <lb/>757 <lb/>779 <lb/>118 <lb/>154154692 <lb/>154191806 <lb/>C <lb/>G <lb/>758 <lb/>780 <lb/>119 <lb/>154154693 <lb/>154191807 <lb/>T <lb/>C <lb/>759 <lb/>781 <lb/>120 <lb/>154154694 <lb/>154191808 <lb/>A <lb/>G <lb/>766 <lb/>788 <lb/>127 <lb/>154154701 <lb/>154191815 <lb/>5 <lb/>A <lb/>G <lb/>880 <lb/>902 <lb/>75 <lb/>154156369 <lb/>154193483 <lb/>T <lb/>C <lb/>883 <lb/>905 <lb/>78 <lb/>154156372 <lb/>154193486 <lb/>T <lb/>G <lb/>885 <lb/>907 <lb/>80 <lb/>154156374 <lb/>154193488 <lb/>G <lb/>A <lb/>888 <lb/>910 <lb/>83 <lb/>154156377 <lb/>154193491 <lb/>A <lb/>T <lb/>890 <lb/>912 <lb/>85 <lb/>154156379 <lb/>154193493 <lb/>G <lb/>T <lb/>895 <lb/>917 <lb/>90 <lb/>154156384 <lb/>154193498 <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/>901 <lb/>931 <lb/>104 <lb/>154156398 <lb/>154193512 <lb/>A <lb/>G <lb/>905 <lb/>935 <lb/>108 <lb/>154156402 <lb/>154193516 <lb/>T <lb/>C <lb/>940 <lb/>970 <lb/>143 <lb/>154156437 <lb/>154193551 <lb/>G <lb/>C <lb/>944 <lb/>974 <lb/>147 <lb/>154156441 <lb/>154193555 <lb/>A <lb/>T <lb/>978 <lb/>1008 <lb/>181 <lb/>154156475 <lb/>154193589 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>Organoid media <lb/>E6 supplement: 970 μg/mL Insulin (11376497001, Roche), 535 μg/mL holo-transferrin (T0665, <lb/>Sigma), 3.20 mg/mL L-ascorbic acid (A8960, Sigma), 0.7 μg/mL sodium selenite (S5261, <lb/>Sigma). <lb/>BE6.2 media for early retinal differentiation: 2.5% E6 supplement (above), 2% B27 Supple-<lb/>ment (50×) minus Vitamin A (12587010, Gibco), 1% Glutamax (35050061, Gibco), 1% NEAA <lb/>(11140050, Gibco), 1 mM Sodium Pyruvate (11360070, Gibco), and 0.87 mg/mL NaCl in <lb/>DMEM (11885084, Gibco). <lb/>LTR (Long-Term Retina) media: 25% F12 (11765062, Gibco) with 2% B27 Supplement <lb/>(50×) (17504044, Gibco), 10% heat inactivated FBS (16140071, Gibco), 1 mM Sodium Pyru-<lb/>vate, 1% NEAA, 1% Glutamax, and 1 mM taurine (T-8691, Sigma) in DMEM (11885084, <lb/>Gibco). <lb/>Retinoic acid treatments <lb/>For organoids, 1.04 μm all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA; R2625; Sigma) was thawed fresh in LTR <lb/>media every 2 days, protected from light, and never freeze-thawed. <lb/>Organoid differentiation and maintenance <lb/>Organoids were differentiated from H7 ESCs, H7iCas9 ESCs, or EP1.1 iPSCs (Table 6) as <lb/>described in Eldred and colleagues with minor variations (S4D Fig) [15]. On day 0, pluripo-<lb/>tent and well-maintained stem cells with minimal to no spontaneous differentiation were used <lb/>for organoid aggregation. To aggregate, cells were passaged in Accutase (SCR005, Sigma) at <lb/>37˚C for 12 min to ensure complete dissociation. Cells were seeded in 50 μls of mTeSR1 <lb/>(85857, Stem Cell Technologies) at 3,000 cells/well into 96-well ultra-low adhesion round bot-<lb/>tom Lipidure-coated plates (51011610, NOF) or ultra-low attachment microplate (7007, Corn-<lb/>ing). Corning plates were used upon the discontinuation of Lipidure plates. Cells were placed <lb/>in hypoxic conditions (10% CO 2 and 5% O 2 ) for 24 h to enhance survival. Cells naturally <lb/>aggregated by gravity over 24 h. On day 1, cells were moved to normoxic conditions (5% <lb/>CO 2 ). On days 1 to 3, 50 μls of BE6.2 media containing 3 μm Wnt inhibitor (IWR1e: 681669, <lb/>EMD Millipore) and 1% (v/v) Matrigel (354230, BD Biosciences) were added to each well. On <lb/>days 4 to 9, 100 μl of media were removed from each well, and 100 μl of media were added. On <lb/>days 4 and 5, BE6.2 media containing 3 μm Wnt inhibitor and 1% Matrigel was added. On <lb/>days 6 and 7, BE6.2 media containing 1% Matrigel was added. On days 8 and 9, BE6.2 media <lb/>containing 1% Matrigel and 100 nM Smoothened agonist (SAG: 566660, EMD Millipore) was <lb/>added. On day 10, aggregates were transferred to 15 ml tubes, rinsed 3× in 5 ml DMEM <lb/>(11885084, Gibco), and resuspended in BE6.2 with 100 nM SAG in untreated 10 cm polysty-<lb/>rene Petri dishes in a total of 12 ml of media. From this point on, media was changed every <lb/>other day. Aggregates were monitored and manually separated if stuck together or to the bot-<lb/>tom of the plate. On days 13 to 16, LTR media with 100 nM SAG was added. On day 16, retinal <lb/>vesicles were manually dissected using sharpened tungsten needles, with cuts made to <lb/>Table 6. Organoid replicates and cell lines. <lb/>Organoid treatment <lb/>Cell line <lb/>Replicates <lb/>No RA <lb/>H7 ESC <lb/>N = 6 <lb/>RA to day 60 <lb/>H7 ESC <lb/>N = 6 <lb/>RA to day 130 <lb/>H7 ESC, H7iCas9 ESC <lb/>H7 ESC (N = 1), H7 iCas9 ESC (N = 2) <lb/>Late RA <lb/>H7iCas9 ESC <lb/>N = 5 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464.t006 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>maximize the number of vesicles per organoid. On average, 1 to 2 cuts were made per orga-<lb/>noid. After dissection, cells were transferred into 15 ml tubes and washed 3× with 5 ml DMEM <lb/>(11885084, Gibco). On days 16 to 20, cells were maintained in LTR and washed 2× with 5 ml <lb/>DMEM (11885084, Gibco), to remove dead cells, before being transferred to new plates. To <lb/>increase survival and differentiation, 1.04 μm ATRA (R2625; Sigma) was added to LTR <lb/>medium from days 20 to 43. Additional time windows of 1.04 μm were added depending on <lb/>experimental conditions; 10 μm gamma-secretase inhibitor (DAPT, 565770, EMD Millipore) <lb/>was added to LTR from days 28 to 42. Organoids were grown at low density (10 to 20 per 10 <lb/>cm dish) to reduce aggregation. Periodically, organoids were culled from the plate based on <lb/>absence of clear laminal structure indicating proper retinal organoid growth. <lb/>Organoid preparation and cryosectioning <lb/>Organoids were fixed for 45 min in 10% neutral buffered formalin (HT501128, Sigma) and <lb/>washed in 1× PBS. Organoids were placed in 25% sucrose in 0.1 M phosphate buffer solution <lb/>overnight, and then mounted in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. compound (4583, Sakura), placed on dry <lb/>ice to freeze, and stored at -80˚C. Organoids were cryosectioned in 10 μm sections. Slides <lb/>were air dried for 6 h to overnight, then postfixated for 15 min in 10% neutral buffered forma-<lb/>lin (HT501128, Sigma) and washed in 1× PBS. Slides were dried and stored at -80˚C and used <lb/>within 3 months. <lb/>Imaging organoid RNA in situ hybridization <lb/>Samples were imaged in brightfield using a Zeiss LSM 980 inverted microscope with an Axio-<lb/>cam 506 color camera system using a C Apo 40×/1.2 W DICIII lens or an EVOS XL Core Cell <lb/>imaging system on brightfield with a 20× air objective (Thermo Fisher). <lb/>Association study subjects <lb/>All experiments involving human subjects were conformed to the principles expressed in the <lb/>Declaration of Helsinki and were approved by the University of Washington Human Subjects <lb/>Review Committee. Subjects were 738 males who had previously passed several standard tests <lb/>for color vision deficiency, including Ishihara&apos;s 24-plate test, Richmond HRR 2002 edition, <lb/>and the Neitz Test of Color Vision. Subjects identified themselves as being either of African or <lb/>African American ancestry (N = 147), Asian ancestry (N = 108), Caucasian ancestry (N = 362), <lb/>Latino ancestry (N = 23), Mixed (N = 62), Native American ancestry (N = 13), South Asian <lb/>ancestry (N = 9), or Other/Not Specified (N = 14). Subjects were dropped from the study if <lb/>adequate quantity/quality of DNA or sequencing depth was not achieved. <lb/>The protocol for this human subject study was approved by the IRB at the University of <lb/>Washington (IRB #41457). Written consent was obtained for all procedures for all subjects. <lb/>Flicker-photometric electroretinogram (FP-ERG) <lb/>The proportion of L cones, expressed as the percentage of L plus M cones that were L, were <lb/>determined for each subject from a combination of genetic analysis and the FP-ERG as <lb/>described in [26,29]. Briefly, the spectral sensitivity of the individual was measured using con-<lb/>trol and test lights of specific wavelengths to illuminate a small portion of the retina. These <lb/>conditions were designed to eliminate rod and S-cone contributions. While the test lights were <lb/>flickered on and off, electrodes recorded the ERG neuronal responses to the stimulus. The <lb/>spectral sensitivity was determined by adjusting the intensity of the test light until the ERG sig-<lb/>nal produced exactly matched that produced by the fixed intensity reference light. A correction <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>20 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>factor was applied to the estimated proportion of L cones to account for the 1.5 times greater <lb/>contribution to the FP-ERG signal for each M cone compared to each L cone [28]. The associa-<lb/>tion between FP-ERG and % L is nonlinear and as 100% is approached, very small changes in <lb/>measured spectral sensitivities are associated with relatively large changes in estimates of % L. <lb/>Thus, near 100%, small experimental errors led to some values that exceeded 100% upon nor-<lb/>malization. These data combined with genetic analysis of the L and M cone genes to determine <lb/>the spectral sensitivity of each opsin allowed for the determination of the % L cone proportion. <lb/>Association study DNA preparation, pull-down, and sequencing <lb/>For each of these gene regions, we isolated DNA by targeting sequence intervals delineated by <lb/>the end coordinate of the neighboring upstream gene to the start coordinate of the neighboring <lb/>downstream gene using an oligo-based pull-down method (S5 Fig). If the neighboring <lb/>upstream or downstream genes were less than 100 kb from the gene of interest, we expanded <lb/>the pulled down region to include at least 100 kb of upstream and downstream sequence (S5 <lb/>Fig). DNA was isolated from buccal swabs or whole blood using PureGene DNA extraction kits <lb/>as described in [49]. DNA was then diluted to 10 ng/μl in low ETDA (USB Corporation, <lb/>#75793). DNA was sheared to an average length of 250 bps using the Bioruptor Pico (Diage-<lb/>node). Samples were stored on ice for 10 to 15 min prior to sonication. Sonication was per-<lb/>formed for 7 cycles of on for 15 s, off for 90 s. After 3 cycles, the samples were briefly <lb/>centrifuged before continuing with sonication for the remaining 4 cycles. Library preparation <lb/>and hybridization pull-downs were performed according to the SeqCap EZ HyperCap Work-<lb/>flow User&apos;s Guide, version 2.0 following all recommended instructions. Libraries were created <lb/>using the KAPA Hyper Prep Kit (KAPA Biosystems, #KK8504), using the KAPA Dual-Indexed <lb/>Adapter Set (15 mM, KAPA Biosystems/Roche, #08 278 555 702). Probes for the pull-down <lb/>were designed according to the Roche Nimble Design software, targeting the gene regions listed <lb/>in (S5 Fig). Samples were sequenced on a Nova-seq, high-output, with 125 bp paired-end reads. <lb/>Association study analysis <lb/>Paired-end reads for 738 samples were aligned to the human genome (build hg38) using BWA <lb/>mem (v0.7.15) with default parameters. Duplicate reads were marked using Picard (v2.9.2). <lb/>Each region was subdivided into nonoverlapping 1 kb windows starting at the upstream <lb/>boundary using bedtools (v2.29.2). Mapped reads were genotyped on a region-by-region basis <lb/>using Freebayes-parallel (v1.2.0), the argument &quot;-use-best-n-alleles 4&quot;, and, for the region on <lb/>chromosome X, &quot;-p 1&quot;. Variant calls were filtered for quality greater than 10 times the number <lb/>of additional observations, at least 1 alternative allele read on each strand, and at least 2 reads <lb/>supporting the alternate allele balanced up-and downstream using vcflib (v1.0.0). Duplicate <lb/>variants were then removed. Variants were filtered with PLINK (v1.90b6.12) for a minor allele <lb/>frequency of at least 3.5% and a per-variant genotyping rate of at least 90%. Variants were <lb/>pruned using LDAK (v5.0) with an LD cutoff of R 2 &lt; 0.75 within 100 kb windows. A kinship <lb/>matrix was calculated from the pruned variant set using LDAK, ignoring weights and a power <lb/>of -1. P-values were calculated in LDAK from the pruned variant set, using the first 5 genotype <lb/>eigenvectors as covariates to control for potential population stratification. Significant variants <lb/>were defined using an alpha of 0.05 after Bonferroni correction. <lb/>Quantification and statistical analysis <lb/>HEK293 in situ hybridization quantification. Images were tile scanned and all individ-<lb/>ual cells inside the region were manually counted using the Adobe Photoshop count tool. Cells <lb/>were delineated by presence of pink, blue, or purple signal with a boundary drawn around the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>21 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<body>signal. Images were contrasted to determine brightfield boundaries as needed. Non-expressing <lb/>cells were not counted. <lb/>Human adult retina in situ hybridization quantification. For adult retinas, all serially <lb/>sectioned punches of human retinas were imaged and counted manually and identified by <lb/>presence of pink, blue, or purple signal using the Adobe Photoshop count tool. Exclusive <lb/>expression of M-opsin or L-opsin was observed in cones. Co-expression of M-opsin and L-<lb/>opsin was never observed in human retinas (purple signal). Cells were delineated by presence <lb/>of pink, blue, or purple signal with a boundary drawn around the signal. Images were con-<lb/>trasted to determine brightfield boundaries. Average ratios were compared using a one-way <lb/>ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test. Graphs and statistical tests were done in <lb/>GraphPad Prism version 9.3.1 for Mac, GraphPad Software, San Diego, California, United <lb/>States of America; www.graphpad.com. All error bars represent standard error of the mean <lb/>(SEM). <lb/>Quantification of IHC and ISH BaseScope of M-and L-opsin stained HEK293 cells and <lb/>adult fetal retina sections. IHC and ISH BaseScope images were manually aligned in Adobe <lb/>Photoshop using the Hoescht nuclei stains. Images of the ISH BaseScope stain were used to <lb/>count cells positive for M-opsin mRNA, L-opsin mRNA or both using the count tool. By over-<lb/>laying the IHC stain, we determined which of these cells are also co-stained for M and L-opsin <lb/>protein. Graphs and statistical tests were done in GraphPad Prism. <lb/>Human opsin transcript pileups. Transcripts per million (TPM) values were then used <lb/>to generate graphs in GraphPad Prism. <lb/>RNA sequencing graphs. All graphs and statistical tests were generated using GraphPad <lb/>Prism. <lb/>Organoid quantification. All sectioned organoids were imaged and counted manually <lb/>using the Adobe Photoshop count tool. Organoids that had fewer than 150 cones (n �150) <lb/>were removed from analysis. A one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test <lb/>was used to determine significance. All error bars represent SEM. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. In situ hybridization strategy to visualize M-opsin and L-opsin mRNA. (A) Identifi-<lb/>cation of HEK293 cells using Hoechst (light gray) in the experiment in Fig 1I and 1J. M-opsin <lb/>(blue) and L-opsin (pink). Blue arrow indicates a cell expressing M-opsin mRNA only. Pink <lb/>arrows indicate cells expressing L-opsin mRNA only. Purple arrow indicates a cell expressing <lb/>both M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA. Black arrow indicates an untransfected cell. Note <lb/>that the Hoechst signal is reduced in cells that express M-opsin mRNA and/or L-opsin mRNA, <lb/>likely due to the colorimetric signal blocking the fluorescent signal. (B) Identification of retinal <lb/>layers using Hoechst (light gray) in the experiment in Fig 1K and 1L. M-opsin (blue) and L-<lb/>opsin (pink). No cones co-expressed M-opsin mRNA and L-opsin mRNA. ONL, outer nuclear <lb/>layer; OPL, outer plexiform layer; INL, inner nuclear layer. (C) Quantification of M-opsin <lb/>mRNA-expressing, L-opsin mRNA-expressing, or M+L-opsin mRNA-expressing cells that <lb/>express M/L-opsin protein for the experiments conducted in HEK293 cells in Fig 1I and 1J <lb/>and adult human retina in Fig 1K and 1L. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Fig. M-opsin and L-opsin expression in fetal retinas and WERI-RB-1 cells. (A) 20 μm <lb/>section of a fetal day 122 retina with expression of M-/L-opsin protein (magenta), Ki67 (cyan), <lb/>and Hoechst/nuclei (white). M-/L-opsin protein is observed in the ONL. Ki67 expression indi-<lb/>cates proliferating cells. (B) M-and L-opsin expression in control-and T3-treated WERI-Rb-1 <lb/>retinoblastoma cells (N = 1 experiment). The WERI-Rb-1 retinoblastoma cell line expresses <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>22 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">M-and L-opsin at low levels [50]. T3, the active form of thyroid hormone, induces M-and L-<lb/>opsin expression in WERI-Rb-1 cells [15,51]. Values indicate total pileup count normalized to <lb/>total read count. Each data point indicates 1 nucleotide difference in M-or L-opsin. Original <lb/>data sets are in S5 Data. (C-I) Analysis of M-and L-opsin mRNA expression in 130-day-old <lb/>human fetal retina. (C) Example of M-and L-opsin mRNA expression in 130-day-old human <lb/>fetal retina section. Anterior = left, posterior = right. Dorsal/ventral orientation is unknown. <lb/>Colored boxes indicate regions shown in (D-G) zoomed in regions from (C). The central <lb/>region in (F) expressed opsin mRNA. The more peripheral regions in (D), (E), and (G) show <lb/>no expression of opsin mRNA. (H) Quantification of cones expressing M-and L-opsin mRNA <lb/>from the temporal to nasal sides of the globe. (I) Identification of retinal layers using Hoechst <lb/>(light gray) in the experiment in (S2C-S2H Fig). M-opsin (blue), L-opsin (pink), and retinal <lb/>pigmented epithelial (RPE, dark brown) colorimetric signals were deconvoluted to generate <lb/>pseudo fluorescent images. These were overlaid with Hoechst nuclear counterstains to visual-<lb/>ize retinal layers. ONL, outer nuclear layer; OPL, outer plexiform layer; INL, inner nuclear <lb/>layer. Original data sets are in S5 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Quantification of cells expressing M-opsin or L-opsin mRNA in adult retinas and <lb/>validation. (A) Schematic of retina with regions isolated using a 5 mm biopsy punch (as in Fig <lb/>2G with additional detail). White circle = optic nerve. Red lines = blood vessels. Yellow <lb/>circle = macular pigment. (B-E) Validation of quantification of % of cells expressing M-opsin <lb/>or L-opsin with HALO semi-automated image analysis software. (B) Images from 20 μm sec-<lb/>tions were probed for M-opsin (blue) and L-opsin (pink) mRNA. Images as in Fig 2H-2J. (C) <lb/>HALO software deconvoluted the colorimetric M-opsin or L-opsin mRNA signals to generate <lb/>pseudo fluorescent images (from Fig S3B). (D) Manually counted average ratios of M and L <lb/>cones as percent of M/L total cones across 3 individuals. One-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s mul-<lb/>tiple comparisons test: Center L versus Middle L = no significance; Center L versus Periphery <lb/>L p &lt; 0.01; Middle L versus Periphery L p &lt; 0.01; ** indicates p &lt; 0.01. Data as in Fig 2K for <lb/>comparison to Fig S3E. (E) HALO semi-automated software analysis of single deconvoluted <lb/>representative images from the center, middle, and periphery regions (Fig S3C), showed simi-<lb/>lar ratios of M and L cones as manually scored retinas (Fig 2K). (F-H) Ratios of M and L <lb/>cones as percent of M/L total cones for each individual; n &gt; 850 cones for each region for each <lb/>individual. Averages ratios are shown in Fig 2K. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Fig. CYP26A1/B1/C1 expression during fetal retinal development and organoid differ-<lb/>entiation experiments. (A-C) Expression of CYP26A1, CYP26B1, and CYP26C1 in fetal <lb/>human retinas by day of gestation and retinal region. CPM, log counts per million. Analyzed <lb/>from [16]. Error bars for the 2 samples from fetal day 94 indicate SEM. Original data sets are <lb/>in S3 Data. (A) Whole retina. (B) Central retina. (C) Periphery. (D) Protocol for human retinal <lb/>organoid differentiation, adapted from [15]. (E) Expression of THRB (cone marker) and NRL <lb/>(rod marker) during retinal organoid development. TPM, transcripts per million. Analyzed <lb/>from [15]. Original data sets are in S6 Data. (F) No significant differences in overall densities <lb/>of M + L cones at day 200 in early RA treatment conditions (as in Fig 3F-3H) (Dunnett&apos;s mul-<lb/>tiple comparison&apos;s test, against &quot;No RA&quot; control: &quot;RA to day 60&quot; p = 0.98, &quot;RA to day 130&quot; <lb/>p = 0.32). Significant difference between &quot;No RA&quot; and &quot;Late RA&quot; conditions (Dunnett&apos;s multi-<lb/>ple comparison&apos;s test, * indicates p &lt; 0.05) (as in Fig 3I). Error bars indicate SEM. Individual <lb/>circles represent individual organoids. Original data sets are in S3 Data. (G) Representative <lb/>brightfield image of a retinal organoid in &quot;RA to day 130&quot; conditions. (H) Representative <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>23 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">brightfield image of a retinal organoid in &quot;Late RA&quot; conditions. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Fig. Genes tested in association study. Gene names and corresponding chromosome coor-<lb/>dinates for human genome assembly GRCh38. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S6 Fig. Expression of NR2F2 and NR2F2-AS1 during development. The rs372754794 SNP <lb/>at the NR2F2/NR2F2-AS1 locus lies in a putative regulatory region. (A) Expression of <lb/>NR2F2 and NR2F2-AS1 in human fetal retinas, analyzed from [16]. Original data sets are in S3 <lb/>Data. (B) Expression of NR2F2 and NR2F2-AS1 in human retinal organoids, analyzed from <lb/>[15]. Original data sets are in S6 Data. (C) ReMap ChIP-seq database [52] shows that the <lb/>rs372754794 SNP lies in an enhancer based on transcription factor binding. Each colored line <lb/>indicates ChIP-seq binding data for a different transcriptional regulator. The ReMap density <lb/>shows the density of the peaks overlap. (D) GeneHancer database [53] shows that the <lb/>rs372754794 SNP neighbors a region predicted to physically interact and regulate NR2F2 and/ <lb/>or NR2F2-AS1. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S7 Fig. The rs36102671 SNP at the RARA locus is associated with differences in cone ratio. <lb/>(A) Association of L:M ratio and rs36102671 stratified by self-reported ancestry. Original data <lb/>sets are in S7 Data. (B) rs36102671 association with altered splicing of RARA in whole blood <lb/>from the Genotype Tissue Expression Project (GTEx). Original data sets are in S7 Data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Data. Data that underlies Fig 1J, 1K. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S2 Data. Data that underlies Figs 2C-2F and 2K, and S3D-S3H. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S3 Data. Data that underlies Figs 3A-3C and 3E, S4A-S4C, S4F, and S6A. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S4 Data. Data that underlies Fig 4A-4D and 4G, and 4H. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S5 Data. Data that underlies S2B and S2H Fig. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S6 Data. Data that underlies S4E and S6B Figs. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S7 Data. Data that underlies S7A and S7B Fig. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We dedicate this work to the memory of James Taylor, a great scientist and an even better <lb/>person. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Sarah E. Hadyniak, Kiara C. Eldred, James Taylor, Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>24 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Data curation: Boris Brenerman, Rajiv C. McCoy, Michael E. G. Sauria, James Taylor. <lb/>Formal analysis: Boris Brenerman. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/>Investigation: Sarah E. Hadyniak, Joanna F. D. Hagen, Kiara C. Eldred, Katarzyna A. Hussey, <lb/>Rajiv C. McCoy, James A. Kuchenbecker, Maureen Neitz. <lb/>Methodology: Sarah E. Hadyniak, Joanna F. D. Hagen, Kiara C. Eldred, Katarzyna A. Hussey, <lb/>Ian Glass, Maureen Neitz. <lb/>Project administration: Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/>Supervision: Thomas Reh, Jay Neitz, James Taylor, Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/>Visualization: Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Sarah E. Hadyniak, Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Sarah E. Hadyniak, Kiara C. Eldred, Robert J. Johnston, Jr. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Baden T, Osorio D. The Retinal Basis of Vertebrate Color Vision. Annu Rev Vis Sci. 2019; 5:177-200. <lb/>Epub 2019/06/22. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-vision-091718-014926 PMID: 31226010. <lb/>2. Hussey KA, Hadyniak SE, Johnston RJ Jr. Patterning and Development of Photoreceptors in the <lb/>Human Retina. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2022; 10:878350. Epub 2022/05/03. https://doi.org/10.3389/fcell. <lb/>2022.878350 PMID: 35493094; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC9049932. <lb/>3. Nathans J, Thomas D, Hogness DS. Molecular genetics of human color vision: the genes encoding <lb/>blue, green, and red pigments. Science. 1986; 232(4747):193-202. https://doi.org/10.1126/science. <lb/>2937147 PMID: 2937147. <lb/>4. Yamaguchi T, Motulsky AG, Deeb SS. Visual pigment gene structure and expression in human retinae. <lb/>Hum Mol Genet. 1997; 6(7):981-90. Epub 1997/07/01. https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/6.7.981 PMID: <lb/>9215665. <lb/>5. Winderickx J, Battisti L, Motulsky AG, Deeb SS. Selective expression of human X chromosome-linked <lb/>green opsin genes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1992; 89(20):9710-4. Epub 1992/10/15. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1073/pnas.89.20.9710 PMID: 1409688; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC50202. <lb/>6. Smallwood PM, Wang Y, Nathans J. Role of a locus control region in the mutually exclusive expression <lb/>of human red and green cone pigment genes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2002; 99(2):1008-1011. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.022629799 PMID: 11773636; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC117421. <lb/>7. Wang Y, Macke JP, Merbs SL, Zack DJ, Klaunberg B, Bennett J, et al. A locus control region adjacent <lb/>to the human red and green visual pigment genes. Neuron. 1992; 9(3):429-40. Epub 1992/09/01. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0896-6273(92)90181-c PMID: 1524826. <lb/>8. Peng GH, Chen S. Active opsin loci adopt intrachromosomal loops that depend on the photoreceptor <lb/>transcription factor network. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011; 108(43):17821-6. Epub 2011/10/19. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1109209108 PMID: 22006320; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3203788. <lb/>9. Drummond-Borg M, Deeb SS, Motulsky AG. Molecular patterns of X chromosome-linked color vision <lb/>genes among 134 men of European ancestry. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1989; 86(3):983-7. Epub <lb/>1989/02/01. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.86.3.983 PMID: 2915991; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC286603. <lb/>10. Wang Y, Smallwood PM, Cowan M, Blesh D, Lawler A, Nathans J. Mutually exclusive expression of <lb/>human red and green visual pigment-reporter transgenes occurs at high frequency in murine cone pho-<lb/>toreceptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999; 96(9):5251-5256. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.96.9.5251 <lb/>PMID: 10220452; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC21850. <lb/>11. Hagstrom SA, Neitz J, Neitz M. Variations in cone populations for red-green color vision examined by <lb/>analysis of mRNA. Neuroreport. 1998; 9(9):1963-7. Epub 1998/07/23. https://doi.org/10.1097/ <lb/>00001756-199806220-00009 PMID: 9674575. <lb/>12. Kuchenbecker JA, Sahay M, Tait DM, Neitz M, Neitz J. Topography of the long-to middle-wavelength <lb/>sensitive cone ratio in the human retina assessed with a wide-field color multifocal electroretinogram. <lb/>Vis Neurosci. 2008; 25(3):301-6. Epub 2008/07/05. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0952523808080474 <lb/>PMID: 18598401; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3044242. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>25 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>13. Bowmaker J, Parry J, Mollon J. The Arrangement of Land M Cones in Human and a Primate Retina. <lb/>Normal and Defective Colour Vision. 2003. https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198525301.003. <lb/>0005 <lb/>14. Nakano T, Ando S, Takata N, Kawada M, Muguruma K, Sekiguchi K, et al. Self-formation of optic cups <lb/>and storable stratified neural retina from human ESCs. Cell Stem Cell. 2012; 10(6):771-85. Epub 2012/ <lb/>06/19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stem.2012.05.009 PMID: 22704518. <lb/>15. Eldred KC, Hadyniak SE, Hussey KA, Brenerman B, Zhang PW, Chamling X, et al. Thyroid hormone <lb/>signaling specifies cone subtypes in human retinal organoids. Science. 2018; 362(6411). Epub 2018/ <lb/>10/13. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aau6348 PMID: 30309916; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC6249681. <lb/>16. Hoshino A, Ratnapriya R, Brooks MJ, Chaitankar V, Wilken MS, Zhang C, et al. Molecular Anatomy of <lb/>the Developing Human Retina. Dev Cell. 2017; 43(6):763-79 e4. Epub 2017/12/14. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.devcel.2017.10.029 PMID: 29233477; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5776731. <lb/>17. Pinelli M, Carissimo A, Cutillo L, Lai CH, Mutarelli M, Moretti MN, et al. An atlas of gene expression and <lb/>gene co-regulation in the human retina. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016; 44(12):5773-84. Epub 2016/05/29. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw486 PMID: 27235414; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4937338. <lb/>18. Xiao M, Hendrickson A. Spatial and temporal expression of short, long/medium, or both opsins in <lb/>human fetal cones. J Comp Neurol. 2000; 425(4):545-59. Epub 2000/09/07. PMID: 10975879. <lb/>19. Hendrickson A. Development of Retinal Layers in Prenatal Human Retina. Am J Ophthalmol. 2016; <lb/>161:29-35 e1. Epub 2015/09/28. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajo.2015.09.023 PMID: 26410132; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMC5538359. <lb/>20. Chinen A, Hamaoka T, Yamada Y, Kawamura S. Gene duplication and spectral diversification of cone <lb/>visual pigments of zebrafish. Genetics. 2003; 163(2):663-75. Epub 2003/03/06. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1093/genetics/163.2.663 PMID: 12618404; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1462461. <lb/>21. Mitchell DM, Stevens CB, Frey RA, Hunter SS, Ashino R, Kawamura S, et al. Retinoic Acid Signaling <lb/>Regulates Differential Expression of the Tandemly-Duplicated Long Wavelength-Sensitive Cone Opsin <lb/>Genes in Zebrafish. PLoS Genet. 2015; 11(8):e1005483. Epub 2015/08/22. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pgen.1005483 PMID: 26296154; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4546582. <lb/>22. Tsujimura T, Hosoya T, Kawamura S. A single enhancer regulating the differential expression of dupli-<lb/>cated red-sensitive opsin genes in zebrafish. PLoS Genet. 2010; 6(12):e1001245. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pgen.1001245 PMID: 21187910; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3002997. <lb/>23. McCaffery P, Tempst P, Lara G, Drager UC. Aldehyde dehydrogenase is a positional marker in the ret-<lb/>ina. Development. 1991; 112(3):693-702. Epub 1991/07/01. https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.112.3.693 <lb/>PMID: 1935685. <lb/>24. Marsh-Armstrong N, McCaffery P, Gilbert W, Dowling JE, Drager UC. Retinoic acid is necessary for <lb/>development of the ventral retina in zebrafish. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1994; 91(15):7286-90. Epub <lb/>1994/07/19. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.91.15.7286 PMID: 8041782; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC44384. <lb/>25. Mey J, McCaffery P, Drager UC. Retinoic acid synthesis in the developing chick retina. J Neurosci. <lb/>1997; 17(19):7441-9. Epub 1997/09/20. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.17-19-07441.1997 <lb/>PMID: 9295390; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6573435. <lb/>26. Carroll J, Neitz J, Neitz M. Estimates of L:M cone ratio from ERG flicker photometry and genetics. J Vis. <lb/>2002; 2(8):531-42. Epub 2003/04/08. https://doi.org/10.1167/2.8.1 PMID: 12678637. <lb/>27. Roorda A, Williams DR. The arrangement of the three cone classes in the living human eye. Nature. <lb/>1999; 397(6719):520-2. Epub 1999/02/24. https://doi.org/10.1038/17383 PMID: 10028967. <lb/>28. Hofer H, Carroll J, Neitz J, Neitz M, Williams DR. Organization of the human trichromatic cone mosaic. <lb/>J Neurosci. 2005; 25(42):9669-79. Epub 2005/10/21. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2414-05. <lb/>2005 PMID: 16237171. <lb/>29. McMahon C, Carroll J, Awua S, Neitz J, Neitz M. The L:M cone ratio in males of African descent with <lb/>normal color vision. J Vis. 2008; 8(2):5 1-9. Epub 2008/03/06. https://doi.org/10.1167/8.2.5 PMID: <lb/>18318631; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2431169. <lb/>30. Neitz J, Jacobs GH. Polymorphism of the long-wavelength cone in normal human colour vision. Nature. <lb/>1986; 323(6089):623-5. Epub 1986/10/16. https://doi.org/10.1038/323623a0 PMID: 3773989. <lb/>31. Nathans J, Davenport CM, Maumenee IH, Lewis RA, Hejtmancik JF, Litt M, et al. Molecular genetics of <lb/>human blue cone monochromacy. Science. 1989; 245(4920):831-8. Epub 1989/08/25. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1126/science.2788922 PMID: 2788922. <lb/>32. Nathans J, Piantanida TP, Eddy RL, Shows TB, Hogness DS. Molecular genetics of inherited variation <lb/>in human color vision. Science. 1986; 232(4747):203-10. Epub 1986/04/11. https://doi.org/10.1126/ <lb/>science.3485310 PMID: 3485310. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>26 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>33. Nork TM, McCormick SA, Chao GM, Odom JV. Distribution of carbonic anhydrase among human pho-<lb/>toreceptors. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1990; 31(8):1451-8. Epub 1990/08/01. PMID: 2117597. <lb/>34. Lerea CL, Bunt-Milam AH, Hurley JB. Alpha transducin is present in blue-, green-, and red-sensitive <lb/>cone photoreceptors in the human retina. Neuron. 1989; 3(3):367-76. Epub 1989/09/01. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/0896-6273(89)90261-4 PMID: 2534964. <lb/>35. Curcio CA, Allen KA, Sloan KR, Lerea CL, Hurley JB, Klock IB, et al. Distribution and morphology of <lb/>human cone photoreceptors stained with anti-blue opsin. J Comp Neurol. 1991; 312(4):610-24. Epub <lb/>1991/10/22. https://doi.org/10.1002/cne.903120411 PMID: 1722224. <lb/>36. Szel A, Diamantstein T, Rohlich P. Identification of the blue-sensitive cones in the mammalian retina by <lb/>anti-visual pigment antibody. J Comp Neurol. 1988; 273(4):593-602. Epub 1988/07/22. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/cne.902730413 PMID: 3209737. <lb/>37. Ahnelt PK, Kolb H, Pflug R. Identification of a subtype of cone photoreceptor, likely to be blue sensitive, <lb/>in the human retina. J Comp Neurol. 1987; 255(1):18-34. Epub 1987/01/01. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>cne.902550103 PMID: 2434534. <lb/>38. Ahnelt P, Keri C, Kolb H. Identification of pedicles of putative blue-sensitive cones in the human retina. J <lb/>Comp Neurol. 1990; 293(1):39-53. Epub 1990/03/01. https://doi.org/10.1002/cne.902930104 PMID: <lb/>2312791. <lb/>39. de Monasterio FM, McCrane EP, Newlander JK, Schein SJ. Density profile of blue-sensitive cones <lb/>along the horizontal meridian of macaque retina. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1985; 26(3):289-302. Epub <lb/>1985/03/01. PMID: 2579042. <lb/>40. Genomes Project C, Auton A, Brooks LD, Durbin RM, Garrison EP, Kang HM, et al. A global reference <lb/>for human genetic variation. Nature. 2015; 526(7571):68-74. Epub 2015/10/04. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nature15393 PMID: 26432245; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4750478. <lb/>41. Zhang R, Wang Y, Li R, Chen G. Transcriptional Factors Mediating Retinoic Acid Signals in the Control <lb/>of Energy Metabolism. Int J Mol Sci. 2015; 16(6):14210-44. Epub 2015/06/26. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>ijms160614210 PMID: 26110391; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4490549. <lb/>42. Consortium GT. The GTEx Consortium atlas of genetic regulatory effects across human tissues. Sci-<lb/>ence. 2020; 369(6509):1318-30. Epub 2020/09/12. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aaz1776 PMID: <lb/>32913098; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7737656. <lb/>43. Kaya KD, Chen HY, Brooks MJ, Kelley RA, Shimada H, Nagashima K, et al. Transcriptome-based <lb/>molecular staging of human stem cell-derived retinal organoids uncovers accelerated photoreceptor dif-<lb/>ferentiation by 9-cis retinal. Mol Vis. 2019; 25:663-78. Epub 2019/12/10. PMID: 31814692; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMC6857775. <lb/>44. Zerti D, Dorgau B, Felemban M, Ghareeb AE, Yu M, Ding Y, et al. Developing a simple method to <lb/>enhance the generation of cone and rod photoreceptors in pluripotent stem cell-derived retinal orga-<lb/>noids. Stem Cells. 2020; 38(1):45-51. Epub 2019/11/02. https://doi.org/10.1002/stem.3082 PMID: <lb/>31670434; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7004057. <lb/>45. Kelley RA, Chen HY, Swaroop A, Li T. Accelerated Development of Rod Photoreceptors in Retinal <lb/>Organoids Derived from Human Pluripotent Stem Cells by Supplementation with 9-cis Retinal. STAR <lb/>Protoc. 2020; 1(1). Epub 2020/07/31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xpro.2020.100033 PMID: 32728670; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC7388645. <lb/>46. HALO Image Analysis Platform [Computer Software]. 3.5.3577. Albuquerque, NM: Indica Labs, Inc.; <lb/>2023. <lb/>47. Harrow J, Frankish A, Gonzalez JM, Tapanari E, Diekhans M, Kokocinski F, et al. GENCODE: the refer-<lb/>ence human genome annotation for The ENCODE Project. Genome Res. 2012; 22(9):1760-74. Epub <lb/>2012/09/08. https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.135350.111 PMID: 22955987; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC3431492. <lb/>48. Wahlin KJ, Maruotti JA, Sripathi SR, Ball J, Angueyra JM, Kim C, et al. Photoreceptor Outer Segment-<lb/>like Structures in Long-Term 3D Retinas from Human Pluripotent Stem Cells. Sci Rep. 2017; 7(1):766. <lb/>Epub 2017/04/12. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-00774-9 PMID: 28396597; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC5429674. <lb/>49. Gunther KL, Neitz J, Neitz M. Nucleotide polymorphisms upstream of the X-chromosome opsin gene <lb/>array tune L:M cone ratio. Vis Neurosci. 2008; 25(3):265-71. https://doi.org/10.1017/ <lb/>S0952523808080280 PMID: 18598397; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2999001. <lb/>50. Shaaban SA, Deeb SS. Functional analysis of the promoters of the human red and green visual pigment <lb/>genes. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1998; 39(6):885-96. PMID: 9579468. <lb/>51. Liu Y, Fu L, Chen DG, Deeb SS. Identification of novel retinal target genes of thyroid hormone in the <lb/>human WERI cells by expression microarray analysis. Vision Res. 2007; 47(17):2314-26. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.visres.2007.04.023 PMID: 17655910; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2932699. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>27 / 28 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>52. Hammal F, de Langen P, Bergon A, Lopez F, Ballester B. ReMap 2022: a database of Human, Mouse, <lb/>Drosophila and Arabidopsis regulatory regions from an integrative analysis of DNA-binding sequencing <lb/>experiments. Nucleic Acids Res. 2022; 50(D1):D316-D25. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkab996 PMID: <lb/>34751401; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC8728178. <lb/>53. Fishilevich S, Nudel R, Rappaport N, Hadar R, Plaschkes I, Iny Stein T, et al. GeneHancer: genome-<lb/>wide integration of enhancers and target genes in GeneCards. Database (Oxford). 2017;2017. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1093/database/bax028 PMID: 28605766; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC5467550. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS BIOLOGY <lb/>Spatiotemporal specification of human green and red cones <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002464 January 11, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>28 / 28 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>