<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T15:13:34.565Z">11/14/2025 3:13:34 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T15:13:23.915671Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T15:13:23.915671Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors <lb/>to the orthopedic and trauma admissions at <lb/>the Kenyatta National Hospital: A qualitative <lb/>assessment <lb/>Maxwell Philip Omondi ID <lb/>1☯ <lb/>*, Joseph Chege Mwangi 1☯ , Fred Chuma Sitati 1☯ , <lb/>Herbert Onga&apos;ngo 2☯ <lb/>1 Department of Surgery, Thematic Unit-Orthopedic Surgery, University of Nairobi, Nairobi, Kenya, <lb/>2 Department of Orthopedics, Kenyatta National Hospital, Nairobi, Kenya <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* maxwellomondi@gmail.com <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Inappropriate utilization of higher-level health facilities and ineffective management of the <lb/>referral processes in resource-limited settings is increasingly becoming a concern in health <lb/>care management in developing countries. This is characterized by self-referrals and fre-<lb/>quent bypassing of nearest health facilities coupled with low formal referral mechanisms. <lb/>This scenario lends itself to a situation where uncomplicated medical conditions are unnec-<lb/>essarily managed in a high-cost health facility. This situation compromises the ability and <lb/>capacity of Kenyatta National Hospital (KNH) to function as a tertiary referral health facility <lb/>as envisioned by Kenya Health Sector Referral Implementation Guidelines of 2014, Kenya <lb/>201 constitution and KNH legal statue of 1987. The study objective was to assess the pat-<lb/>terns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admissions at the <lb/>KNH. This was a descriptive qualitative study design. The study was conducted amongst <lb/>the orthopaedic and trauma admission caseload for 2021. Data collection was done through <lb/>a) data abstraction from 905 patients charts admitted during February to December 2021 <lb/>and b) 10 (ten) semi-structured interviews with 10 major health facilities that refer to KNH to <lb/>understand the reasons for referral to KNH. Quantitative data was analysed using Statistical <lb/>Package for Social Science version 21.0 to calculate the frequency distribution. Qualitative <lb/>data from the data abstraction and transcripts from the KIIs were analysed using NVivo ver-<lb/>sion 12. The major facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admis-<lb/>sions at KNH were inadequate human resource capacity and availability (42.7%), financial <lb/>constraints (23.3%), inadequate Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s and implants availability (20.0%) <lb/>and inadequate health facility infrastructure (6.3%) while the major patient related factor <lb/>was patient&apos;s preference (23.4%). In conclusion, to decongest KNH requires that the lower-<lb/>level health facilities need to be better equipped and resourced to handle essential ortho-<lb/>paedic and trauma care. <lb/>PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/>1 / 14 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Omondi MP, Mwangi JC, Sitati FC, <lb/>Onga&apos;ngo H (2024) Patterns of facility and patient <lb/>related factors to the orthopedic and trauma <lb/>admissions at the Kenyatta National Hospital: A <lb/>qualitative assessment. PLOS Glob Public Health <lb/>4(1): e0002323. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pgph.0002323 <lb/>Editor: Hani Mowafi, Yale University School of <lb/>Medicine, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: August 1, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 5, 2024 <lb/>Published: January 25, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Omondi et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its Supporting Information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: This study was partially funded by <lb/>Kenyatta National Hospital. MPO received the <lb/>partial funding from KNH on data collection and <lb/>data analysis. No authors received salary from the <lb/>funder. The funders had no role in study design, <lb/>data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>The types of admission need to reflect the level of health facility with tertiary facilities expected <lb/>to handle more complex cases while lower-level health facilities should focus on the lesser-<lb/>complicated cases due to the presence of limited equipment, physical infrastructure, and <lb/>human resources. The reason for bypassing nearest health facilities seems to be multifactorial: <lb/>patients&apos; perception of high quality of health care and resource availability at referral hospitals <lb/>play a role [1, 2]. Tertiary hospitals in resource-limited countries treat not only patients <lb/>referred but also act as the first level of care for the vast majority of patients [3]. <lb/>One of the challenges in health care delivery in resource-limited settings is inappropriate <lb/>utilization of tertiary health facilities that results in patients&apos; congestion in referral hospitals <lb/>with simple conditions that can be effectively managed at the lower peripheral health facilities. <lb/>The majority of these patients are self-referred, bypassing lower-level health facilities in the <lb/>process [1, 4-6]. The net result is lesser medical conditions end up being managed in high-cost <lb/>referral health facilities leading to overcrowding, long waiting times, and scarce staff time con-<lb/>sumed by lesser medical conditions at the expense of complex medical conditions [3, 7]. <lb/>Orthopaedic wards in KNH have consistently recorded the highest bed occupancy percent <lb/>for the last couple of years. In 2018, 2019 and 2020 it recorded bed occupancy percent of <lb/>142.2%, 138.2% and 116.5% respectively against the KNH bed occupancy percent of 106.2%, <lb/>113.4% and 91.5% respectively [8]. The consequence of this is the low nurse-patient ratio of <lb/>1:10 that compromises not only the quality of nursing care given to patients but also compro-<lb/>mises the ability of KNH to effectively perform its statutory obligations. <lb/>However, there is paucity of local data regarding the facility and patient related factors to <lb/>the orthopaedic and trauma admissions in developing countries and particularly sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa. Understanding the patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic <lb/>and trauma admissions at the KNH is important for patient planning and management and in <lb/>a university facility, this is also critical in planning for quality training. The purpose of this <lb/>study was to assess the patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and <lb/>trauma admissions at the KNH. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Ethical considerations <lb/>University of Nairobi/Kenyatta National Hospital Ethics and Research Committee granted <lb/>ethical approval (ERC No: P852/10/2021). Administrative approval was also granted by KNH <lb/>Medical Research Department and KNH Orthopaedics Department. <lb/>Study design <lb/>This was descriptive qualitative study design. <lb/>Study area <lb/>KNH Orthopaedic Wards. KNH is the national teaching and referral hospital based in Upper-<lb/>hill, Nairobi, the Capital city of Kenya. <lb/>Data collection <lb/>Data collection was done through chart abstractions and Key Informant Interviews (KIIs). <lb/>a) Chart abstractions. Study period. Data was abstracted from patients&apos; charts covering 1 st <lb/>February to 31 st December 2021. The data abstraction was done from 1 st January to 31 st March <lb/>2022 during the data collection period. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<front>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>Study population. KNH Orthopaedic inpatient caseload admitted from 1 st February to 31 st <lb/>December 2021. <lb/>Sample size. 905 chart reviews. A systematic sampling technique was used. This was part of <lb/>a study that sought to determine the patterns of orthopaedic and trauma admissions at Ken-<lb/>yatta National Hospital. <lb/>Pilot testing. Pilot testing was done to assess the feasibility and appropriateness of the data <lb/>abstraction tool to collect the data required to answer the study objective. <lb/>Data collection procedures. Data abstraction form was used to extract data from the patient <lb/>files. Three (3) research assistants (2 females and 1 male) were recruited, trained on data <lb/>abstraction process from the patients&apos; charts. The data collection was done at KNH Health <lb/>Information Office. The principal investigator did data quality checks for all the abstracted <lb/>data before and after data entry. <lb/>Data management, analysis. Quantitative data was analysed using Statistical Package for <lb/>Social Sciences (SPSS) version 21.0 using frequencies. The qualitative data obtained from the <lb/>chart abstractions were entered into excel spreadsheets and were subjected to thematic analysis <lb/>using NVIVO 12 Pro. The research questions and responses from excel spreadsheets were <lb/>reviewed for the identification of themes and patterns and a coding framework was developed. <lb/>The coding framework and excel spreadsheet were then imported directly into NVIVO for <lb/>coding. The coding process entailed going through the texts on the excel spreadsheet, dragging <lb/>and dropping into correct nodes. Some codes were modified and new ones created as they <lb/>came up while reviewing more spreadsheets entries. By analyzing the content of each code to <lb/>check if they are correctly placed, those related to the objective of the study were noted down <lb/>for summary report. <lb/>b) Key Informant Interviews (KIIs). Study period. Key Informant Interviews were done in <lb/>January 2022 and the respondents shared their experiences and observations dating back from <lb/>1 st February to 31 st December 2021 period. <lb/>Study population. Key Orthopaedic and trauma staff from the 10 (ten) health facilities <lb/>namely KNH, Mama Lucy Kibaki Hospital, Mbagathi Hospital, Machakos County Hospital, <lb/>Mwingi County Hospital, Thika Level 5 Hospital, Ngong Sub-County Hospital, St Peters <lb/>Orthopaedic Specialist Hospital, St Francis Community Hospital and Arthi River Shalom <lb/>Community Hospital. <lb/>Sample size. 10 (ten) KIIs were conducted. These were purposively sampled. These were the <lb/>health facilities that referred majority of patients to KNH during the study period. <lb/>Pilot testing. Pilot testing was done to assess the feasibility and appropriateness of the KII <lb/>guide to collect the data required to answer the study objective. <lb/>Data collection procedures. The interviewees were medical officers and orthopaedic consul-<lb/>tants responsible for patient orthopaedic and trauma referrals at the sampled health facilities. <lb/>The interviews were interviewer-administered. The Principal Investigator (male) who is an <lb/>orthopaedic surgeon conducted the interviews. The interviewees were briefed on the purpose <lb/>of the study. They reviewed the participant information consent form prior to giving their <lb/>written informed consent to participate in the study. The interviews were done at the sampled <lb/>health facilities referral office/desk. KII interview guide was used to guide the Key Informant <lb/>Interviews. The focus of the interviews was on common orthopaedic and trauma referrals to <lb/>KNH, reasons for referrals to KNH, challenges, lessons learnt and their recommendations <lb/>with a focus to improve orthopaedic and trauma care at their respective health facilities. The <lb/>interviews lasted about 30 to 45 mins. Audio recordings were taken for each interview session <lb/>and later transcribed into transcripts by one transcriber. The principal investigator went <lb/>through the 10 audio recordings and the transcripts to ensure they were in verbatim and veri-<lb/>fied the accuracy of the transcription process. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>Data management, analysis <lb/>Audio recordings were transcribed and subjected to content analysis using NVIVO 12 Pro. <lb/>The research questions and responses from transcripts were reviewed for the identification of <lb/>themes and patterns and a coding framework was developed. The coding framework and tran-<lb/>scripts were then imported directly into NVIVO for coding. The coding process entailed going <lb/>through the texts on the transcripts, dragging and dropping into correct nodes. Some codes <lb/>were modified and new ones created as they came up while reviewing more transcripts. By <lb/>analyzing the content of each code to check if they are correctly placed, those related to the <lb/>objective of the study were noted down for summary report. <lb/>Study limitations <lb/>a. Incomplete and missing records-this was addressed by making phone calls to patients to <lb/>access the required data; <lb/>b. All admissions were reviewed and therefore not necessarily focussing on admissions appro-<lb/>priate to KNH as a national referral health facility. <lb/>c. Recall bias-the interviewees were to recall the reasons for referrals to KNH during the <lb/>review period, February to December, 2022. <lb/>Results <lb/>Sample characteristics <lb/>The mean age was 33.8 years (SD 16.5) with range of 1-93 years. Majority 600 (66.3%) were <lb/>between 25-64 years with those above 65 years being 40 (4.4%). About 453 (50.1%) were facil-<lb/>ity referrals while 452 (49.9%) were walk-ins. Majority of orthopaedic and traumatic admis-<lb/>sions were through Accident and Emergency Department 707 (78.1%) followed by Corporate <lb/>Outpatient Centre 135 (14.9%) and Orthopaedic Clinic 63 (7.0%). Of the 905 admissions 712 <lb/>(78.7%) were emergency admissions while 188 (20.8%) were elective admissions (Table 1). <lb/>About 405 (44.8%) were casual workers, 183 (20.2%) unemployed. With regard to educa-<lb/>tion level 308 (34.0%) had primary education, 317 (35.0%) had secondary education (Table 1). <lb/>The facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admissions at the <lb/>KNH included human resource capacity and availability, health facility infrastructure, Ortho-<lb/>paedic equipment&apos;s and implants availability, patient&apos;s preference, unaccompanied patients <lb/>and financial considerations among others (Table 2). <lb/>1. Human resource capacity and availability. Human resource capacity and availability was <lb/>the most frequently cited reason for bypassing the nearby health facilities at 42.7%. Chart reviews <lb/>showed that most orthopaedic and trauma admissions to KNH were due to perceived or real inad-<lb/>equate human resource capacity and availability from the peripheral health facilities, both public <lb/>and private health facilities. KNH is believed to have highly specialized personnel to manage diverse <lb/>orthopaedic and associated conditions like plastic surgeons and neurosurgeons. Some health facili-<lb/>ties with orthopaedic surgeons still refer polytrauma orthopaedic cases due to luck of other special-<lb/>ist personnel/care like neurosurgeons, Intensive Care Units or High Dependency Units care <lb/>(Hospital 7 KII, Hospital 1 KII, Hospital 3 KII, Hospital 4 KII, Hospital 5 KII, Hospital 6 KII). <lb/>&quot;. . .. patient was taken to Kangundo hospital but there was not specialist to attend to the <lb/>patient. . ..&quot; Walk-in patient from Machakos county. <lb/>&quot;. . .. went to Thika level 5 hospital then they were transferred to KNH since they lacked a <lb/>spine specialist. . ..&quot; Facility referral from Thika Level 5 Hospital <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>There are those patients who were referred from the health facility due to the fact that there <lb/>was no orthopaedic surgeon at the time of emergency at the referring health facility. <lb/>&quot;. . .. . .there was no orthopaedic surgeon at that particular night so they decided to refer the <lb/>patient to KNH to get assistance. . ..&quot; Facility referral from Mama Lucy Kibaki Hospital <lb/>&quot;. . .he needed an orthopaedic doctor for treatment of his condition, and Machakos did not <lb/>have one at that moment. . ..&quot; Facility Referral from Machakos Level 5 Hospital <lb/>&quot;. . .I would say maybe especially at night, we refer Kenyatta because of the visiting consultants <lb/>are not available at night. . .&quot; Hospital 6 KII <lb/>2. Patients&apos; preference. Patients&apos; preference was the second most frequently cited reason <lb/>for bypassing the nearby health facilities at 23.4%. Chart reviews from admission files revealed <lb/>that some patients, their families, relatives and friends opted to go to KNH or be referred to <lb/>Table 2. Table showing the frequency distribution of the major facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admissions at the KNH. <lb/>Sample size <lb/>(n) <lb/>Human resource capacity and <lb/>availability <lb/>Patients&apos; <lb/>preference <lb/>Financial <lb/>constraints&apos; <lb/>Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s and Implant <lb/>availability <lb/>Health facility <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>905 <lb/>386 (42.7%) <lb/>212 (23.4%) <lb/>211 (23.3%) <lb/>181 (20.0%) <lb/>57 (6.3%) <lb/>This was a cumulative tally of the facility and patient related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admissions at the KNH as a proportion of the sample size (n). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323.t002 <lb/>Table 1. Sample characteristics (N = 905). <lb/>Variable <lb/>Category <lb/>Frequency n (%) <lb/>Age <lb/>0-14 years <lb/>(10.9%) <lb/>15-24 years <lb/>(18.3%) <lb/>25-64 years <lb/>(66.3%) <lb/>Above 65 years <lb/>(4.4%) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>(21.9%) <lb/>Male <lb/>(77.7%) <lb/>Missing <lb/>Occupation <lb/>Businessman/woman <lb/>(12.4%) <lb/>Casual <lb/>(44.8%) <lb/>Employed <lb/>(14.9%) <lb/>Other <lb/>(6.5%) <lb/>unemployed <lb/>(20.2%) <lb/>Missing <lb/>Education <lb/>None <lb/>(6.1%) <lb/>Pre-school <lb/>(2.4%) <lb/>Primary <lb/>(34.0%) <lb/>Secondary <lb/>(35.0%) <lb/>Tertiary <lb/>(20.1%) <lb/>Missing <lb/>Mode of payment <lb/>Cash <lb/>(68.6%) <lb/>Insurance <lb/>(31.0%) <lb/>Missing <lb/>Frequency distribution of key socio-demographic characteristics. Missing variables varied from 3 to 11 but they were <lb/>excluded from proportional analysis for the variables concerned. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>KNH from other health facilities due to personal reasons and preferences. For some patients, <lb/>either themselves or their relatives have been treated at KNH before and had good experience <lb/>and outcome and ended by encouraging their loved ones and friends to seek services at KNH. <lb/>This was triangulated with KII findings that revealed orthopaedic patients ask for referrals or <lb/>decide on their own volition to present themselves to KNH for treatment based on their previ-<lb/>ous experience and perception of better quality of care (Hospital 4 KII, Hospital 3 KII, Hospital <lb/>2 KII). <lb/>&quot;. . .Patient prefers KNH since family members have been treated there and fully recovered&quot;, <lb/>Walk-in from Westlands <lb/>&quot;. . .. his family wanted him to come closer to where they are since the father is a doctor at <lb/>KNH. . ..&quot; Facility Referral, Tenri Embu Children Hospital. <lb/>3. Financial constraints. Financial constraints were the third most frequently cited reason <lb/>for bypassing the nearby health facilities at 23.3%. According to significant number of ortho-<lb/>paedic admissions, the referral was done because of financial constraints since they could ill <lb/>afford the private health facilities, they were in. Most of the private health facilities were not <lb/>accepting the government National Health Insurance Fund cover for orthopaedic and trauma <lb/>admissions. This was triangulated with KII findings that revealed the most common reason for <lb/>referral from private health facilities to KNH was financial constraints. Majority of admissions <lb/>to KNH are from low socio-economic status with no insurance cover and therefore could not <lb/>afford to meet the cost of private health facilities (Hospital 1 KII, Hospital 2 KII, Hospital 4 <lb/>KII, Hospital 5 KII). <lb/>&quot;. . .she couldn&apos;t afford to pay at Nairobi South hospital so her doctor requested for the surgery <lb/>to be done at KNH since the doctor was also from KNH. . .&quot; Facility Referral from Nairobi <lb/>South Hospital <lb/>&quot;. . .Metropolitan Hospital was too expensive for the patient thus opting for KNH. . ..&quot; Facility <lb/>Referral from Metropolitan Hospital <lb/>&quot;. . .we mainly refer due to cost. . ..&quot; Hospital 9 KII <lb/>4. Orthopaedic equipment and implants availability. Orthopaedic equipment and <lb/>implants availability was the fourth most frequently cited reason for bypassing the nearby <lb/>health facilities at 20.0%. Chart reviews showed that most health facilities and patients believed <lb/>KNH had better orthopaedic equipment&apos;s and implants to manage diverse and complicated <lb/>orthopaedic and trauma conditions for example Computed Tomography (CT) scans, Mag-<lb/>netic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and X-rays for diagnosis and patient management compared <lb/>to the peripheral health facilities. These were triangulated with findings from KIIs done with <lb/>the main referring public health facilities that revealed most of these public hospitals lack <lb/>imaging equipment&apos;s like X-rays, CT scan and MRI and for those who have, the machines are <lb/>sometimes faulty and in a sorry state. Patients then end up being referred to KNH for imaging <lb/>studies (Hospital 1 KII, Hospital 3 KII, Hospital 2 KII, Hospital 4 KII, Hospital 6 KII, Hospital <lb/>5 KII) <lb/>&quot;. . .Kenyatta is better equipped. . .&quot; Walk-in patient <lb/>&quot;. . .Sinai Hospital lacked machines to do X-rays. . .&quot; Facility Referral from Sinai Hospital, <lb/>Rongai <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>&quot;Mama Lucy Hospital lacked the metals that were supposed to be put on the leg. . . ..&quot; Facility <lb/>Referral from Mama Lucy Kibaki Hospital <lb/>In addition, some health facilities had non-functioning imaging machines and so they had <lb/>to refer them to KNH where they believed machines were available and in good working <lb/>condition. <lb/>&quot;. . .X-rays machines were not working at that particular time. . .&quot; Facility Referral from <lb/>Mbagathi DH <lb/>&quot;. . .. machines were not working at Mama Lucy&quot; Facility Referral from Mama Lucy Kibaki <lb/>Hospital <lb/>Orthopaedic implants and sets are not available in most of these public and private periph-<lb/>eral health facilities. Most of these implants are outsourced and this requires that have to pay <lb/>for them in advance before they implant can be procured. Those patients with no insurance <lb/>cover, low socio-economic status and therefore cannot afford to pay for the implants, end up <lb/>being referred to KNH (Hospital 10 KII, Hospital 8 KII). <lb/>5. Health facility infrastructure. Health facility infrastructure was one of the less fre-<lb/>quently cited reason for bypassing the nearby health facilities at 6.3%. From chart reviews, a <lb/>number of patients were referred to KNH because of the unavailability of infrastructure and <lb/>better facilities to handle and perform orthopaedic operations. KNH is considered to have <lb/>superior and capacious infrastructure to handle complex orthopaedic complications. <lb/>&quot;. . .. KNH had better structure and facilities to help in his condition. . .&quot; Facility referral from <lb/>Mama Lucy Kibaki Hospital <lb/>&quot;. . .there was no bed space in Mama Lucy. . .&quot; Facility Referral from Mama Lucy Kibaki <lb/>Hospital <lb/>This was triangulated with KII findings that revealed there was no enough infrastructure in <lb/>some public hospitals with some lacking operation rooms while others health facilities have to <lb/>share the theatre space making it hard for orthopaedic procedures to be done when required. <lb/>Some public hospitals have no ICU or have few ICU beds. Some health facilities simply have <lb/>inadequate bed capacity for orthopaedic admissions and have to refer to KNH when their <lb/>capacity gets exceeded (Hospital 1 KII, Hospital 8 KII, Hospital 2 KII, Hospital 7 KII, Hospital <lb/>4 KII). <lb/>&quot;. . .because we have two theatres, but there is one specifically for maternity. This other one we <lb/>use for Obs and gynae, general surgery, ENT. So, we have one day each for each <lb/>department. . .&quot; Hospital 4 KII <lb/>6. Quality of health services. Quality of health services also came up as one of the factors <lb/>affecting orthopaedic and trauma admission to KNH. Chart reviews showed some patients <lb/>preferred to be referred to KNH because of the poor health care and services they got from <lb/>other peripheral health facilities like nurses being rude, unprofessional conduct. Some of these <lb/>patients had received unfavourable commendations about peripheral health facilities with <lb/>regard to the poor quality of health care provision. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>&quot;. . .i opted for KNH after getting advice from several people who had attended Mama Lucy <lb/>Hospital. . .&quot; Walk in from Mathare North <lb/>&quot;. . .nurses at Mama Lucy are rude unlike Kenyatta where they are friendly. . .&quot; Walk-in from <lb/>Embakasi West <lb/>7. Proximity to KNH. Chart reviews showed that some patients were either brought or <lb/>came to KNH because it was the nearest facility from their residence or from the scene of the <lb/>accident. Triangulated findings from KII revealed that referrals to KNH was convenient <lb/>because it was near. The patients preferred being referred to KNH for convenience&apos;s sake <lb/>(Hospital 1 KII, Hospital 7 KII). <lb/>&quot;. . .was rushed by an ambulance to KNH as it was the nearest from the scene&quot; Walk-in from <lb/>Mavoko <lb/>&quot;. . .area of accident was closer to KNH than any other health facility. . .&quot; Walk-in from <lb/>Ruiru, Kiambu county <lb/>8. Unaccompanied. From the data abstractions, some admissions were unconscious and <lb/>just found themselves at KNH when they woke up not knowing how they got there. For others, <lb/>it was the ambulance, good Samaritans or police officers that brought them direct to KNH <lb/>from the accident scene. Some paramedics thought it wise to bring them to KNH given the <lb/>perceived severity of their injuries. <lb/>&quot;. . .the people who were present at the area of accident opted for KNH&quot;, Walk-in from Emba-<lb/>kasi South <lb/>&quot;. . .he was unconscious and was picked by an ambulance and decided to bring to KNH. . .&quot; <lb/>Walk-in from Embakasi Central <lb/>&quot;. . .the patient was brought in to KNH by police. . ..&quot; Walk-in from Starehe <lb/>Discussions <lb/>1. Human resource capacity and availability <lb/>Human resource for health is a critical pillar in WHO health system strengthening and a key <lb/>component in access to health care. Quantity and quality of human resource for health deter-<lb/>mines the quality of care received. This study showed that most of the admissions to KNH <lb/>were due to need for specialized orthopaedic and trauma surgeons to handle orthopaedic <lb/>(spine and pelvic injuries) and other injuries including polytrauma patients. This compares <lb/>with studies done on reasons for inter-hospital transfer of trauma patients that revealed that <lb/>severely injured trauma patients and those with pelvic injuries are likely to be transferred to <lb/>advanced trauma centres for management and for better outcomes [9-12]. The advanced cen-<lb/>tres are presumed to have well trained personnel with relevant experience to handle compli-<lb/>cated cases. This reinforces studies that revealed limited staff capacity at the peripheral <lb/>facilities necessitates surgical referrals in low-and middle-income countries [13-18]. Most of <lb/>these polytrauma patients require multidisciplinary team for effective management and this is <lb/>usually not available at the peripheral facilities. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>2. Patients&apos; preferences <lb/>Patients&apos; preferences refer to patients&apos; values, beliefs, expectations and health goals that influ-<lb/>ences their health choices and health facility choices as well. This study did reveal the role of <lb/>family, friends and the society at large in health seeking behaviour of orthopaedic admissions. <lb/>The study did show that some patients, their families, relatives and friends opted to go to <lb/>KNH or be referred to KNH from other health facilities due to personal reasons, and prefer-<lb/>ences. For some patients, either themselves or their relatives have been treated at KNH before <lb/>and had good experience and outcome and ended up encouraging their loved ones and friends <lb/>to seek services at KNH. This compares favourably with a study done in Israel indicated that <lb/>about 33% of patients seek second opinion on recommendation of a relative and/or friend [18, <lb/>19]. However, this contradicts a review done in Northern Tanzania that showed patients pref-<lb/>erence accounts for about 1% of surgical patient&apos;s referral to a Tertiary health facility [18]. A <lb/>systematic review of factors patients consider in choice of a surgeon reveal that hospital reputa-<lb/>tion, rather than surgeon&apos;s reputation, was of primary importance and most patients relied on <lb/>word-on-mouth and physician preference to decide the hospital of choice [20]. <lb/>3. Financial constraints <lb/>Personal finance is key factor in the choice of a hospital with patients of high socio-economic <lb/>status and with insurance cover opting for high -end private health facilities while patients of <lb/>low-socio-economic status and mostly with no insurance cover opting to seek services in gov-<lb/>ernment health facilities. <lb/>This study did show that for a significant number of admissions, the referral was done <lb/>because of financial constraints since they could ill afford the private health facilities, they were <lb/>in. In addition, most of the private health facilities would require additional financial top ups <lb/>in addition to the NHIF cover while others would outrightly reject the NHIF cover due to its <lb/>low financial allocations for orthopaedic procedures. A number of private orthopaedic patients <lb/>were advised by their doctors to seek care at KNH because of their relative affordability and <lb/>ability to make use of the NHIF cover to sort their medical bills, given that most of the admis-<lb/>sions are not well-endowed financially. <lb/>4. Orthopaedic equipment and implants availability <lb/>Equipments, supplies are another WHO building block for effective health service delivery. <lb/>Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s, sets and implants are generally costly and require significant capital <lb/>outlays. Availability of Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s, sets and implants are key to management of <lb/>orthopaedic patients. Given the level and the nature of health care financing in Kenya, most <lb/>health facilities-both government and private-are not able to acquire and maintain these <lb/>equipment&apos;s. <lb/>KNH being a premier referral facility in the country is believed to be well resourced and <lb/>therefore best equipped in this regard including CT scans, MRI and X-rays to manage diverse <lb/>and complicated orthopaedic conditions compared to the peripheral health facilities. This <lb/>compares with a qualitative study done in Uganda that revealed unavailability, non-functional <lb/>or intermittent functioning of imaging facilities like CT scan, MRI that hindered surgical ser-<lb/>vice provision [14, 18]. This also compares with a study done in Muhimbili National Hospital <lb/>in Tanzania that revealed lack of equipment as the main reason for referral to the Tertiary <lb/>facility [21]. Similar studies done in Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Rwanda and Ghana revealed <lb/>infrastructure gap at the peripheral health facilities necessitated referrals to tertiary health facil-<lb/>ities [22]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>5. Health infrastructure <lb/>Health Infrastructure is one of the WHO pillars of health system strengthening and provides <lb/>the structural framework for provision of health care. It refers to availability of health ameni-<lb/>ties, adequate ward, theatre rooms, physiotherapy, occupational therapy spaces for Orthopae-<lb/>dic and Trauma and Rehabilitation service provisions. Poor infrastructure means <lb/>compromised health service delivery. <lb/>Orthopaedic patients were also referred or self-referred to KNH because of the unavailabil-<lb/>ity of bed space and poor facilities to handle and perform orthopaedic operations. This com-<lb/>pares with a prospective study done in Aga Khan University Hospital in Kenya that revealed <lb/>bed availability was one of the commonest reasons cited for referral [23]. Similar studies in <lb/>Uganda, Rwanda have shown inadequate health infrastructure with limited ward and theatre <lb/>capacity hinders provision and access to surgical services [14-16, 18]. The operating rooms are <lb/>shared by other surgical specialities and most often overburdened by urgent obstetric cases <lb/>that often lead to planned orthopaedic operations delayed or postponed due to the urgent <lb/>obstetric procedures. This effectively means reduced operative capacity for orthopaedic proce-<lb/>dures. Some of these public health facilities in addition to limited operative capacities also <lb/>lacked ICU or HDU capacities to handle polytrauma patients with neurosurgical <lb/>complications. <lb/>6. Quality of health services. Quality of health service delivery is one of the WHO pillars <lb/>of health care strengthening and it requires provision of quality health care. This study did <lb/>show that some patients preferred to be referred or self-referred to KNH because of either per-<lb/>ceived or real poor health care services they got from other peripheral health facilities like the <lb/>nurses being rude or unprofessional conduct. The unfavourable commendations about periph-<lb/>eral health facilities with regard to the poor quality of health care provision influenced their <lb/>decision to seek services at KNH. This compares favourably with a number of studies have <lb/>shown that quality of service influences the choice of a health facility with hospitals with high <lb/>quality of care being hospitals of choice [24, 25]. <lb/>7. Proximity to KNH <lb/>Geographical distance is a key consideration for choice of a hospital. Long distance travel has <lb/>financial implications but also it is not convenient for friends, relatives and family of the <lb/>patients who seek to visit and take care of them seek ones. <lb/>A number of admissions were either brought or came to KNH because it was the nearest <lb/>facility from their residence or from the scene of the accident; the paramedics decided to rush <lb/>them to KNH being the nearest government hospital that&apos;s is affordable. For some, they had <lb/>relatives in Nairobi and so it was easier for the relatives to monitor them. This compares <lb/>favourably with a systematic review of factors patients consider in choice of health provider <lb/>that revealed hospital distance was of primary importance in choosing facility of choice [20, <lb/>24]. <lb/>8. Unaccompanied <lb/>Unaccompanied means that these are admissions that were brought in by good Samaritans or <lb/>police officers and not relatives as unconscious and not much was known about them at the <lb/>time of admission. They were victims of road traffic accidents, assaults or mentally ill patients <lb/>that sustained orthopaedic related injuries. The polices officers, the good Samaritans are nor-<lb/>mally the first responders at the scene of accident and most of them make the decision to refer <lb/>the patients to KNH either due to financial considerations given KNH is a government facility <lb/>or due to proximity to KNH given that majority of the RTAs occur within Nairobi County. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>The unaccompanied and unconscious patients at the scene of accident are deemed to have <lb/>serious injuries. This compares with studies that showed Police officers are usually the first <lb/>responders at the scene of accident [26, 27]. Similarly a study done on post-crash emergency <lb/>care in India showed good Samaritans and police officers referred about 90% post-crash vic-<lb/>tims to government hospitals as the first contact health facility [28]. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The patient and facility related factors to the orthopaedic and trauma admissions at the KNH <lb/>included inadequate human resource capacity and availability, inadequate health facility infra-<lb/>structure, inadequate Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s and implants availability, patient&apos;s preference, <lb/>unaccompanied patients and financial constraints. <lb/>Recommendations <lb/>6.2.1 Recommendations to County Government <lb/>1. Ensure availability of accessible and high-quality orthopedic and trauma health services at <lb/>the lower tier health facilities; <lb/>2. Provide regular supportive supervision and capacity building of county health facilities on <lb/>the referral system; <lb/>3. Allocate more resources to human resource for health for recruitment of more orthopaedic <lb/>and trauma surgeons and also fund training for more specialized orthopaedic speciality <lb/>including pelvic and spine specialities; <lb/>4. Improve the health infrastructure and operative capacity of peripheral facilities to be able to <lb/>handle orthopaedic and trauma cases; <lb/>5. The high cost of Orthopaedic sets and implants is an impediment to orthopaedic care. The <lb/>government to consider subsiding the cost of orthopaedic equipment&apos;s, sets and implants to <lb/>reduce the overall cost of orthopaedic procedures and make it more affordable and <lb/>accessible; <lb/>6.2.2 Recommendations to KNH. <lb/>1. Regular training of staff at the referral coordination Unit to ensure adherence to the referral <lb/>guidelines; <lb/>2. Educate and sensitize the public, the police force as to the role of KNH as a premier <lb/>National Teaching and Referral facility that is mandated to manage complex referrals and <lb/>should not be the first point of contact for patients seeking orthopaedic care; <lb/>3. Have a written standard operating procedure on orthopaedic and trauma referrals to KNH. <lb/>This referral guideline should be reviewed and updated as necessary; <lb/>4. Consider providing outreaches/mentorship to high volume peripheral facilities on a regular <lb/>basis in management of pelvic and spine injuries as part of mentorship and capacity <lb/>building; <lb/>5. Offer fellowships and short-courses on targeted themes on orthopaedic and trauma care <lb/>namely spine, pelvic/acetabular management, polytrauma management to improve capacity <lb/>for the referring health facilities; <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<body>6.2.3 Recommendations to health facilities. <lb/>1. Human resource capacity building for Orthopaedic surgeons and fund subspeciality train-<lb/>ings in orthopaedics to handle complex orthopaedic cases like spine, pelvic and hand <lb/>injuries; <lb/>2. Need to address the culture of Ministry of Health staff with regards to unavailability/ absen-<lb/>teeism at work to avoid unnecessary referrals of patients and also for timely management of <lb/>orthopaedic patients; <lb/>3. Improvement in health infrastructure and this includes increasing the operative capacity of <lb/>the major health facilities bed capacity, imaging equipment&apos;s like CT scan, MRI, X-rays to <lb/>reduce on unnecessary referrals; <lb/>4. Strengthen the maintenance department to ensure that facilities with imaging equipment&apos;s, <lb/>theatre equipment&apos;s are serviced on a timely manner to minimize on frequent breakages <lb/>and non-functioning equipment&apos;s that impede effective and timely service provision; <lb/>5. Fund the procurement of basic Orthopaedic equipment&apos;s, sets and implants for basic ortho-<lb/>paedic procedures that can be handled by resident orthopaedic surgeons; <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Checklist. STROBE statement-checklist of items that should be included in reports of <lb/>cross-sectional studies. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S2 Checklist. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative studies (COREQ): 32-item <lb/>checklist. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Data. Dataset SPSS. <lb/>(SAV) <lb/>S2 Data. Spreadsheet database. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S1 Text. Health facility keys. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 File. Key informant interviews TRANSCRIPTS. <lb/>(ZIP) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>I would like to express my sincere gratitude to Brian Omondi and Micah J. Kipkemei for their <lb/>tireless work and exemplary commitment in data collection process. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati, Her-<lb/>bert Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Data curation: Maxwell Philip Omondi. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Formal analysis: Maxwell Philip Omondi. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Maxwell Philip Omondi. <lb/>Investigation: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Fred Chuma Sitati. <lb/>Methodology: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati, Herbert <lb/>Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Project administration: Maxwell Philip Omondi. <lb/>Resources: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Herbert Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Software: Maxwell Philip Omondi. <lb/>Supervision: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati, Herbert <lb/>Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Validation: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati. <lb/>Visualization: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati, Herbert <lb/>Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma Sitati, <lb/>Herbert Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Maxwell Philip Omondi, Joseph Chege Mwangi, Fred Chuma <lb/>Sitati, Herbert Onga&apos;ngo. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. London L, Bachmann OM. Paediatric utilisation of a teaching hospital and a community health centre. <lb/>Predictors of level of care used by children from Khayelitsha, Cape Town. S Afr Med J. 1997 Jan; 87 <lb/>(1):31-6. PMID: 9063310 <lb/>2. Nolan T, Angos P, Cunha AJ, Muhe L, Qazi S, Simoes EA, et al. Quality of hospital care for seriously ill <lb/>children in less-developed countries. Lancet. 2001 Jan 13; 357(9250):106-10. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S0140-6736(00)03542-X PMID: 11197397 <lb/>3. Hensher M, Price M, Adomakoh S. Referral Hospitals. 2006. <lb/>4. Holdsworth G, Garner PA, Harphan T. Crowded outpatient departments in city hospitals of developing <lb/>countries: a case study from Lesotho. Int J Health Plann Manage. 1993 Oct-Dec; 8(4):315-24. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1002/hpm.4740080407 PMID: 10134933 <lb/>5. Ohara K, Melendez V, Uehara N, Ohi G. Study of a patient referral system in the Republic of Honduras. <lb/>Health Policy Plan. 1998 Dec; 13(4):433-45. https://doi.org/10.1093/heapol/13.4.433 PMID: 10346035 <lb/>6. Sanders D, Kravitz J, Lewin S, McKee M. Zimbabwe&apos;s hospital referral system: does it work? Health <lb/>Policy Plan. 1998 Dec; 13(4):359-70. https://doi.org/10.1093/heapol/13.4.359 PMID: 10346028 <lb/>7. Akande T. Referral system in Nigeria: Study of a tertiary health facility. Annals of African Medicine. <lb/>2004; 3(3):130-3. <lb/>8. KNH IN-PATIENT STATISTICS REPORT 2018, 2019 &amp; 2020 [Unpublished Reports]. [cited June <lb/>2020]. <lb/>9. Viel IL, Moura BRS, Martuchi SD, de Souza Nogueira L. Factors Associated With Interhospital Transfer <lb/>of Trauma Victims. J Trauma Nurs. 2019 Sep/Oct; 26(5):257-62. https://doi.org/10.1097/JTN. <lb/>0000000000000452 PMID: 31503199 <lb/>10. Garwe T, Cowan LD, Neas B, Cathey T, Danford BC, Greenawalt P. Survival benefit of transfer to ter-<lb/>tiary trauma centers for major trauma patients initially presenting to nontertiary trauma centers. Acad <lb/>Emerg Med. 2010 Nov; 17(11):1223-32. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1553-2712.2010.00918.x PMID: <lb/>21175521 <lb/>11. Newgard CD, McConnell KJ, Hedges JR, Mullins RJ. The benefit of higher level of care transfer of <lb/>injured patients from nontertiary hospital emergency departments. J Trauma. 2007 Nov; 63(5):965-71. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1097/TA.0b013e31803c5665 PMID: 17993937 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 14 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>12. Pittalis C, Brugha R, Gajewski J. Surgical referral systems in low-and middle-income countries: A <lb/>review of the evidence. PLoS One. 2019; 14(9):e0223328. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0223328 PMID: 31560716 <lb/>13. Meara JG, Leather AJ, Hagander L, Alkire BC, Alonso N, Ameh EA, et al. Global Surgery 2030: evi-<lb/>dence and solutions for achieving health, welfare, and economic development. Lancet. 2015 Aug 8; 386 <lb/>(9993):569-624. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60160-X PMID: 25924834 <lb/>14. Albutt K, Yorlets RR, Punchak M, Kayima P, Namanya DB, Anderson GA, et al. You pray to your God: <lb/>A qualitative analysis of challenges in the provision of safe, timely, and affordable surgical care in <lb/>Uganda. PLoS One. 2018; 13(4):e0195986. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195986 PMID: <lb/>29664956 <lb/>15. Nkurunziza T, Toma G, Odhiambo J, Maine R, Riviello R, Gupta N, et al. Referral patterns and predic-<lb/>tors of referral delays for patients with traumatic injuries in rural Rwanda. Surgery. 2016 Dec; 160 <lb/>(6):1636-44. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.surg.2016.08.006 PMID: 27743716 <lb/>16. Kruk ME, Wladis A, Mbembati N, Ndao-Brumblay SK, Hsia RY, Galukande M, et al. Human resource <lb/>and funding constraints for essential surgery in district hospitals in Africa: a retrospective cross-sec-<lb/>tional survey. PLoS Med. 2010 Mar 9; 7(3):e1000242. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000242 <lb/>PMID: 20231869 <lb/>17. Sani R, Nameoua B, Yahaya A, Hassane I, Adamou R, Hsia RY, et al. The impact of launching surgery <lb/>at the district level in Niger. World J Surg. 2009 Oct; 33(10):2063-8. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00268-<lb/>009-0160-x PMID: 19653031 <lb/>18. Jumbam DT, Menon G, Lama TN, Lodge Ii W, Maongezi S, Kapologwe NA, et al. Surgical referrals in <lb/>Northern Tanzania: a prospective assessment of rates, preventability, reasons and patterns. BMC <lb/>Health Serv Res. 2020 Aug 8; 20(1):725. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-020-05559-x PMID: <lb/>32771008 <lb/>19. Shmueli L, Davidovitch N, Pliskin JS, Balicer RD, Hekselman I, Greenfield G. Seeking a second medical <lb/>opinion: composition, reasons and perceived outcomes in Israel. Isr J Health Policy Res. 2017 Dec 8; 6 <lb/>(1):67. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13584-017-0191-y PMID: 29221461 <lb/>20. Yahanda AT, Lafaro KJ, Spolverato G, Pawlik TM. A Systematic Review of the Factors that Patients <lb/>Use to Choose their Surgeon. World J Surg. 2016 Jan; 40(1):45-55. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00268-<lb/>015-3246-7 PMID: 26362880 <lb/>21. Simba DO, Mbembati NA, Museru LM, Lema LE. Referral pattern of patients received at the national <lb/>referral hospital: challenges in low income countries. East Afr J Public Health. 2008 Apr; 5(1):6-9. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4314/eajph.v5i1.38969 PMID: 18669115 <lb/>22. Hsia RY, Mbembati NA, Macfarlane S, Kruk ME. Access to emergency and surgical care in sub-Saha-<lb/>ran Africa: the infrastructure gap. Health Policy Plan. 2012 May; 27(3):234-44. https://doi.org/10.1093/ <lb/>heapol/czr023 PMID: 21441566 <lb/>23. Khan S, Zafar H, Zafar SN, Haroon N. Inter-facility transfer of surgical emergencies in a developing <lb/>country: effects on management and surgical outcomes. World J Surg. 2014 Feb; 38(2):281-6. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s00268-013-2308-y PMID: 24178181 <lb/>24. Luft HS, Garnick DW, Mark DH, Peltzman DJ, Phibbs CS, Lichtenberg E, et al. Does quality influence <lb/>choice of hospital? JAMA. 1990 Jun 6; 263(21):2899-906. PMID: 2110985 <lb/>25. Bahadori M, Teymourzadeh E, Ravangard R, Nasiri A, Raadabadi M, Alimohammadzadeh K. Factors <lb/>contributing towards patient&apos;s choice of a hospital clinic from the patients&apos; and managers&apos; perspective. <lb/>Electron Physician. 2016 May; 8(5):2378-87. https://doi.org/10.19082/2378 PMID: 27382448 <lb/>26. Lukumay GG, Outwater AH, Mkoka DA, Ndile ML, Saveman BI. Traffic police officers&apos; experience of <lb/>post-crash care to road traffic injury victims: a qualitative study in Tanzania. BMC Emerg Med. 2019 Oct <lb/>11; 19(1):51. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12873-019-0274-x PMID: 31601171 <lb/>27. Chokotho L, Mulwafu W, Singini I, Njalale Y, Maliwichi-Senganimalunje L, Jacobsen KH. First Respond-<lb/>ers and Prehospital Care for Road Traffic Injuries in Malawi. Prehosp Disaster Med. 2017 Feb; 32 <lb/>(1):14-9. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1049023X16001175 PMID: 27923422 <lb/>28. Urfi, Khalique N, Ahmad A, Ahmad ST. Post-crash emergency care: Availability and utilization pattern <lb/>of existing facilities in Aligarh, Uttar Pradesh. J Family Med Prim Care. 2020 May; 9(5):2313-8. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_1251_19 PMID: 32754494 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Patterns of facility and patient related factors to the orthopedic and trauma admissions <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002323 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 14 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>