<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Electrochemical performance enhancement of MnO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowires through silver incorporation for next-generation supercapacitors</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Muhammad Usman</forename>
          <surname>Khalid</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sonia</forename>
          <surname>Zulfiqar</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>M. Naziruddin</forename>
          <surname>Khan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Imran</forename>
          <surname>Shakir</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Muhammad Farooq</forename>
          <surname>Warsi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eric W.</forename>
          <surname>Cochran</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T11:12:37.803Z">11/12/2025 11:12:37 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1039$1$d4ma00118d</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1039/d4ma00118d</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Muhammad Usman Khalid, Sonia Zulfiqar, M. Naziruddin Khan, Imran Shakir, Muhammad Farooq Warsi, Eric W. Cochran. (2024). Electrochemical performance enhancement of MnO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowires through silver incorporation for next-generation supercapacitors. Materials Advances, 5(15), 6170-6184. DOI: 10.1039/d4ma00118d</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T11:06:09.514828Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T11:06:09.514828Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>The role of aldehydes on sulfur based-new particle <lb/>formation: a theoretical study † <lb/>Guohua Zhang, ‡ a Min Liu, ‡ b Yaning Han, b Zhongteng Wang, b Wei Liu, b <lb/>Ying Zhang * a and Jing Xu * b <lb/>Aldehydes play a crucial role in the formation of atmospheric particles, attracting significant attention due to <lb/>their environmental impact. However, the microscopic mechanisms underlying the formation of aldehyde-<lb/>involved particles remain uncertain. In this study, through quantum chemical calculations and molecular <lb/>dynamics (MD) simulations, we investigate the microscopic formation mechanisms of binary and ternary <lb/>systems composed of three representative aldehydes, two sulfur-based acids, water, and two bases. Our <lb/>research findings reveal that the most stable structures of acid-aldehyde clusters involve the connection <lb/>of acids and aldehyde compounds through hydrogen bonds without involving proton transfer reactions, <lb/>indicating relatively poor cluster stability. However, with the introduction of a third component, the <lb/>stability of 18 clusters significantly increase. Among these, in ten systems, acids act as catalysts, <lb/>facilitating reactions between aldehyde compounds and water or alkaline substances to generate glycols <lb/>and amino alcohols. However, according to MD simulations conducted at 300 K, these acids readily <lb/>dissociate from the resulting products. In the remaining eight systems, the most stable structural feature <lb/>involves ion pairs formed by proton transfer reactions between acids and aldehyde compounds. These <lb/>clusters exhibit remarkable thermodynamic stability. Furthermore, the acidity of the acid, the nature of <lb/>nucleophilic agents, and the type of aldehyde all play significant roles in cluster stability and reactivity, <lb/>and they have synergistic effects on the nucleation process. This study offers microscopic insights into <lb/>the processes of new particle formation involving aldehydes, contributing to a deeper understanding of <lb/>atmospheric chemistry at the molecular level. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>New particle formation (NPF) is a key process in the generation <lb/>of atmospheric secondary organic aerosols (SOA) within the <lb/>troposphere. 1-4 It has garnered attention for its signicant <lb/>implications on climate and human health. 5-7 NPF involves the <lb/>initial formation of stabilized clusters from small molecules, <lb/>which then grow into larger particles. 8 Despite its importance, <lb/>the chemical identity and signicance of vapors, especially in <lb/>the formation of small nucleated particles (&lt;1 nm), remain <lb/>uncertain due to technological constraints. <lb/>Early experiments at the CLOUD chamber demonstrated <lb/>NPF from sulfuric acid (H 2 SO 4 , SA) and bases like ammonia <lb/>(NH 3 , A), methylamine (CH 3 NH 2 , MA), and dimethylamine <lb/>((CH 3 ) 2 NH, DMA). 9-15 However, their concentrations proved <lb/>insufficient to fully elucidate particle nucleation rates and <lb/>growth rates under atmospheric conditions. 8,16,17 Further <lb/>research indicates that volatile organic compounds (VOCs) are <lb/>crucial in both particle formation and growth phases. 18-23 <lb/>Among VOCs, aldehydes such as formaldehyde (FA) and a-<lb/>dicarbonyls like glyoxal (GL) and methylglyoxal (MG) are <lb/>signicant contributors to atmospheric chemistry, with <lb/>concentrations in the ppb range and an annual production <lb/>exceeding 185 Tg yr-1. These compounds, primarily generated <lb/>through oxidative combustion of organic substances, have <lb/>diverse sources that include urban emissions and biogenic <lb/>processes. 24-28 In the atmosphere, aldehydes contribute to the <lb/>formation of free radicals (e.g., HO x ), ozone (O 3 ), and perox-<lb/>ycarboxylic nitric anhydride (PAN), 29-31 and play a pivotal role in <lb/>particles formation. 32-39 For example, laboratory studies have <lb/>shown that gaseous GL can lead to signicant particle growth <lb/>rates, 40 contributing notably to SOA formation in various global <lb/>locations. 41,42 Model results from the GEOS-chem model suggest <lb/>that GL and MG are expected to contribute approximately 11 Tg <lb/>yr-1 to global particles production through irreversible uptake. 43 <lb/>Additionally, GL and FA have been identied in cloud and fog <lb/>water, indicating their role in aqueous-phase reactions that <lb/>contribute to particles formation. 44 <lb/></body>

			<front>a Jinhua Advanced Research Institute, Jinhua, Zhejiang, 321013, P. R. China. E-mail: <lb/>yzhang1981@sina.com <lb/>b Department of Optical Engineering, College of Optical, Mechanical and Electrical <lb/>Engineering, Zhejiang A&amp;F University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 311300, P. R. China. <lb/>E-mail: jingxu@zafu.edu.cn <lb/> † Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available. See DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1039/d4ra00952e <lb/> ‡ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Cite this: RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321 <lb/>Received 6th February 2024 <lb/>Accepted 17th April 2024 <lb/>DOI: 10.1039/d4ra00952e <lb/>rsc.li/rsc-advances <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | 13321 <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>PAPER <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/>View Journal | View Issue <lb/></front>

			<body>SA and methanesulfonic acid (CH 3 SO 3 OH, MSA) are signi-<lb/>cant products of Earth&apos;s sulfur cycle with high gas-phase <lb/>concentrations and active atmospheric participation, and have <lb/>been identied as important drivers of atmospheric particle <lb/>nucleation. 45-65 Aldehydes and sulfur-containing compounds <lb/>play a signicant role in NPF at the atmosphere-biosphere and <lb/>atmosphere-hydrosphere interfaces. These compounds signif-<lb/>icantly inuence cloud formation processes and further have <lb/>implications for global climate patterns. 66 Recent experimental <lb/>studies indicate that sulfur-based acids can enhance the yield of <lb/>aldehydes to form particles. 67-71 Yet, there are studies indicating <lb/>that the combined product of aldehydes and acids alone does <lb/>not adequately account for the observed particle yields, and <lb/>kinetic simulations propose that the cluster formation <lb/>involving aldehyde and acid is almost negligible in terms of <lb/>growth and formation. 72 Water and basic molecules, like <lb/>ammonia and small alkyl organic amines, which are prevalent <lb/>in both gaseous and particulate phases, have been demon-<lb/>strated to facilitate new particle formation (NPF) through acid-<lb/>base reactions or oxidation reactions with hydroxyl, ozone, and <lb/>nitrate. 51,52,54-56,73-79 It is noteworthy that the carbonyl group in <lb/>aldehydes, characterized by a sp 2 hybridized carbon-oxygen <lb/>double bond, is particularly susceptible to nucleophilic attack. <lb/>This interaction can result in the displacement of electrons in <lb/>the p bond to the more electronegative oxygen atom, 80,81 inu-<lb/>encing the mechanism of new particle formation. Given this, <lb/>nucleophilic agents like water and basic molecules emerge as <lb/>potential intrinsic drivers in the reaction dynamics of aldehydes <lb/>and acids. However, the understanding of atmospheric nucle-<lb/>ation processes involving aldehydes and acids, particularly in <lb/>the presence of water or basic molecules, remains limited. <lb/>Therefore, a comprehensive investigation into NPF driven by <lb/>aldehydes, acids, water, or basic precursors is imperative to fully <lb/>elucidate the underlying molecular mechanisms of such <lb/>nucleation. <lb/>In this study, the role of aldehydes in sulfur-based NPF are <lb/>investigated at a microscopic level. We focus on two types of <lb/>acids (SA and MSA), three aldehydes (FA, GL, and MG), two <lb/>bases (A and MA), and water (W). The structures, energies, <lb/>thermodynamic and dynamic stabilities, and interactions of the <lb/>most stable structures formed by these components were <lb/>examined. Furthermore, the mechanism of proton transfer <lb/>process and the impact of each component on NPF were <lb/>analyzed. This work contributes to a deeper understanding of <lb/>the nucleation mechanism of NPF at the molecular level. <lb/>2. Theoretical methods <lb/>2.1 Clusters structural calculations <lb/>In this study, the target systems consist of six binary systems <lb/>and eighteen ternary systems, incorporating two kinds of acids, <lb/>three kinds of aldehydes, two kinds of bases, and water. To <lb/>comprehensively obtain potential initial structures, we <lb/>employed the ABCluster soware 82,83 with the articial bee <lb/>colony algorithm 84 to explore local minima on the potential <lb/>energy surface of each cluster. ABCluster, in combination with <lb/>quantum chemical calculations, has been successfully used to <lb/>obtain the local minima in atmospheric studies. 87-89 Here, each <lb/>reactant gas was randomly placed in a 4 × 4 × 4 box to generate <lb/>1000 initial structures for each system. Due to the huge amount <lb/>of computation (24 × 1000), we implemented an economic <lb/>calculation strategy: initially, 1000 initial structures generated <lb/>by ABCluster for each system underwent optimization using the <lb/>PM7 semi-empirical method. 85,86 Subsequently, from the ob-<lb/>tained 1000 initial congurations, we selected up to 100 <lb/>minimal structures within DE &lt; 10 kcal mol -1 (at PM7 level) for <lb/>further optimization at the B3LYP/3-21G level. 90-92 Following <lb/>this, up to 20 lowest-energy isomers were reselected for opti-<lb/>mization and vibrational frequency calculations, utilizing the <lb/>B3LYP functional with Grimme&apos;s dispersion correction 93 and <lb/>a 6-31G(d) basis set. Finally, up to 10 local-minimum structures <lb/>were chosen for accurate single-point energy and frequency <lb/>calculations at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p) level, 94-96 and the isomers <lb/>with the lowest Gibbs free energy (298.15 K) obtained at this <lb/>level were conrmed as the most stable structures. The nal <lb/>Gibbs free energy (G) was determined using the following <lb/>approach: <lb/>G = E MP 2 + DG thermal <lb/>(1) <lb/>Here, E MP2 represents the single-point energy obtained at the <lb/>MP2/6-311+G(d, p) level, and DG thermal accounts for thermal <lb/>corrections to Gibbs free energy, incorporating both entropic <lb/>and enthalpic contributions at the specied temperature <lb/>(298.15 K). <lb/>To validate the reliability of the relative Gibbs free energies <lb/>(DG) at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level, we <lb/>used B3LYP-D3/aug-cc-pVTZ, MP2/aug-cc-pVTZ//B3LYP-D3/6-<lb/>31G(d) and MP2/6-311+G(d, p) as references for our test calcu-<lb/>lations on the FA-SA-A system. The test results demonstrated <lb/>that the isomers predicted to have the lowest Gibbs free ener-<lb/>gies are consistent across all four methods (see Table S1 †). <lb/>Therefore, considering the balance between computational <lb/>cost-effectiveness and complexity, the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)// <lb/>B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level is sufficient for qualitatively predict-<lb/>ing the lowest-energy ground state structure of each system in <lb/>this study. Frequency calculations conrmed positive vibra-<lb/>tional frequencies for all stable minima. Natural bond orbital <lb/>(NBO) analysis 97,98 was employed to obtain partial charges (d). <lb/>All density functional theory (DFT) geometry optimizations and <lb/>vibrational frequency calculations were performed using the <lb/>Gaussian 16 program. 99 <lb/>2.2 Molecular dynamic simulations and intermolecular <lb/>interactions analysis <lb/>To assess the thermodynamic stabilities of the obtained clus-<lb/>ters, molecular dynamics (MD) simulations were conducted <lb/>with semi-empirical quantum chemical potentials (PM6) 100-102 <lb/>using the CP2K package. 103 MD simulations can enrich our <lb/>understanding by depicting the behavior of clusters in dynamic <lb/>environments, offering insights beyond static calculations. This <lb/>method illuminates the role of temperature and molecular <lb/>interactions in determining stability, providing a more nuanced <lb/>view of the thermodynamic properties. The simulations were <lb/></body>

			<page>13322</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>performed in the gas-phase NVT canonical ensemble with <lb/>Nose-Hover thermostats. 104,105 For validation, we optimized all <lb/>the lowest-energy structures at the PM6 level, conrming close <lb/>agreement with geometries obtained by density functional <lb/>theory. Each simulation comprised ve trajectories, each <lb/>propagated for 100 picoseconds (ps) with a time step of 1 <lb/>femtosecond (fs), and the temperature was maintained at T = <lb/>300 K. <lb/>To explore molecular interactions in the clusters, we con-<lb/>ducted noncovalent interaction (NCI) analysis. 106 NCI analysis <lb/>describes the relationship between electron density r(r) and <lb/>reduced density gradient (RDG). RDG(s) is calculated by eqn (2) <lb/>to demonstrate the deviation from the homogeneous distribu-<lb/>tion of electrons. <lb/>s ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>2ð3p 2 Þ 1=3 <lb/>jVrj <lb/>r 4=3 <lb/>(2) <lb/>where r is the electron density based on MP2/6-311+G(d, p)// <lb/>B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d), V is the gradient operator, and jVrj is the <lb/>electronic density gradient mode. Multiwfn 107 and VMD 108,109 <lb/>programs were utilized for RDG-sign(l 2 )r scatter plots and <lb/>bonding isosurface plots, respectively, visualizing the location, <lb/>strength, and type of weak interactions in the structure. The <lb/>strength of the interaction was judged by the value of sign(l 2 )r, <lb/>with values close to zero indicating weak interactions, such as <lb/>van der Waals forces. Negative sign(l 2 )r values corresponded to <lb/>hydrogen bonds (HB), while positive values indicated steric <lb/>hindrance. <lb/>3. Results and discussions <lb/>In this study, two types of acids (SA and MSA), three aldehydes <lb/>(FA, GL, and MG), two bases (A and MA), and water (W) are <lb/>involved, with investigations focusing on acid-aldehyde <lb/>systems, both with and without the presence of a base or <lb/>water. To facilitate comparison across these systems, a simpli-<lb/>ed naming convention was adopted: X-Y denotes binary <lb/>systems, and X-Y-Z indicates ternary systems. Here, X repre-<lb/>sents an aldehyde, Y signies an acid, and Z corresponds to <lb/>water or a base. Note that the naming convention used merely <lb/>reects the reactants involved and is not indicative of the <lb/>composition of the resulting products. For instance, the binary <lb/>system FA-SA is composed of FA and SA as reactants. Similarly, <lb/>the ternary system FA-SA-W includes FA, SA, and water mole-<lb/>cules as reactants. It is worth mentioning that for three-<lb/>component reactions, all three gas molecules are introduced <lb/>as reactants simultaneously. <lb/>3.1 Acid-aldehyde <lb/>To microscopically reveal the role of aldehydes in sulfur-based <lb/>NPF, three representative aldehydes-mono-carbonyl aldehyde <lb/>FA, and di-carbonyl aldehydes GL and MG-as well as two <lb/>representative sulfur-based acids, namely SA and MSA, were <lb/>considered in this work. The most stable structures identied <lb/>for different aldehydes and sulfur-based acids in a 1 : 1 ratio at <lb/>the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level are presented <lb/>in Fig. 1, with additional high-energy isomers shown in Fig. S1 <lb/>and S2. † For these most stable acid-aldehyde clusters, the <lb/>oxygen atoms on the carbonyl groups of all aldehydes form <lb/>OH/O hydrogen bonds with the hydroxyl hydrogen atoms on <lb/>the SA or MSA molecules, and no proton transfer was observed <lb/>in any of the systems. The bond length of hydrogen bonds <lb/>ranges from 1.70 to 1.78 Å. Notably, SA systems exhibit slightly <lb/>shorter hydrogen bond lengths than MSA systems. NBO analysis <lb/>reveals that acidic molecules in all acid-aldehyde clusters have <lb/>a small negative partial charge (d), while aldehydes have <lb/>a positive partial charge, indicating a very weak donor-acceptor <lb/>interaction. <lb/>To explore the intermolecular interactions of these acid-<lb/>aldehyde clusters, NCI analysis was performed on the global <lb/>Fig. 1 The most stable structures of X-Y (X = FA/GL/MG; Y = SA/MSA) systems at the level of MP2/6-311+G (2d, 2p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d). <lb/>Yellow, red, green and white spheres represent sulfur, oxygen, carbon and hydrogen atoms, respectively. <lb/></body>
    
            <note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13323 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>minima of these clusters. Fig. 2 illustrates the scatter plot of <lb/>RDG(s) vs. sign(l 2 )r, along with corresponding bonding iso-<lb/>surfaces. The results indicate that all hydrogen-bonded acid-<lb/>aldehyde clusters exhibit negative sign(l 2 )r values, signifying <lb/>the presence of hydrogen bonds (HBs). The OH/O hydrogen <lb/>bond positions of all clusters can be identied from the <lb/>bonding isosurfaces in the blue region. Additionally, van der <lb/>Waals forces (sign(l 2 )r ∼ 0) and steric hindrance (sign(l 2 )r &gt; 0) <lb/>are observed in each cluster. As the molecular weight of the <lb/>system increases, the van der Waals effect and steric hindrance <lb/>effect within the composite structure are enhanced. Impor-<lb/>tantly, the value of sign(l 2 )r corresponding to the spike in the <lb/>SA-based cluster is smaller than that in the MSA-based cluster, <lb/>indicating a stronger hydrogen bonding attraction formed by <lb/>aldehyde and SA. These results are further supported by the <lb/>visual bonding isosurfaces, with all hydrogen bonds corre-<lb/>sponding to the structures in Fig. 1 through the disc-like iso-<lb/>surface. MG-involved systems exhibit more pronounced van der <lb/>Waals and steric hindrance effects. It is noteworthy that SA <lb/>systems display shorter hydrogen bond lengths, more <lb/>pronounced negative partial charges, and sign(l 2 )r values in <lb/>comparison to MSA systems. These ndings collectively imply <lb/>a stronger interaction in binding aldehydes within SA systems <lb/>than in MSA systems. <lb/>The stability of acid-aldehyde clusters was further assessed <lb/>through thermodynamic analysis and MD simulations. First, <lb/>dissociation energies of these clusters were calculated at the <lb/>MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level. The binding <lb/>energies (DE), electron energies with zero-point correction (DE + <lb/>ZPE), and corresponding free energies (DG) at 298.15 K were <lb/>listed in Table 1, and dissociation energies were calculated <lb/>using eqn (3). <lb/>DG = <lb/>P G(product) -<lb/>P <lb/>G(reactant) = <lb/>P <lb/>n B G(B) -G(global minima) <lb/>(3) <lb/>As shown in Table 1, the calculated results indicate that FA-<lb/>SA exhibits a small positive D DG value (0.39 kcal mol -1 ), while <lb/>the remaining systems have negative values ranging from -0.21 <lb/>to -1.63 kcal mol -1 . These negative D DG values mean that these <lb/>clusters tend to dissociate and are thermodynamically unstable. <lb/>The order of thermodynamic stability is FA &gt; MG &gt; GL for the SA <lb/>system, while FA &gt; GL &gt; MG for the MSA system. Additionally, <lb/>most SA systems exhibit smaller dissociation energies than the <lb/>corresponding values for MSA, aligning with the observed <lb/>shorter hydrogen bonds and stronger interactions in SA. Next, <lb/>MD simulations for the six clusters were conducted at 300 K. <lb/>The MD results reveal that the OH/O hydrogen bond breaks in <lb/>a very short time, approximately 10 ps for SA and 3 ps for MSA, <lb/>leading to complete separation of the aldehyde and acid <lb/>components (see Fig. S3 †). The change in energy following <lb/>hydrogen bond dissociation is predominantly attributed to the <lb/>contribution of the hydrogen bonds. This indicates that clusters <lb/>are prone to dissociation to monomers, demonstrating insta-<lb/>bility at room temperature. <lb/>Based on the obtained results, the acid-aldehyde clusters are <lb/>characterized by a single hydrogen bond between the hydroxyl <lb/>group on the acid and the oxygen atom in the aldehyde carbonyl <lb/>group, with no proton transfer process observed. These clusters <lb/>Fig. 2 The plots of RDG versus sign(l 2 )r function and the visualized bonding isosurfaces for the most stable acid-aldehyde clusters. <lb/></body>

			<page>13324</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>exhibit poor thermodynamic stability, consistent with previous <lb/>studies. Aldehydes exhibit stronger interactions with SA than <lb/>with MSA, resulting in shorter hydrogen bonds, smaller disso-<lb/>ciation free energies, and shorter separation times. This <lb/>behavior may be attributed to the stronger acidic nature of SA. <lb/>3.2 Acid-aldehyde with water or base <lb/>Continuing from the analysis of unstable acid-aldehyde clus-<lb/>ters, we further investigated ternary X-Y-Z systems, and <lb/>revealed the role of each component within them. In this <lb/>context, the third component Z included water (W) and two <lb/>different alkaline bases NH 3 (A) and MA. <lb/>3.2.1 Structure. First, when Z is water, the most stable <lb/>structures of FA/GL/MG-SA/MSA-W systems are depicted in <lb/>Fig. 3, with additional structures of higher energy shown in <lb/>Fig. S4 and S5. † These most stable clusters exhibit an eight-<lb/>membered ring structure where two fragments are connected <lb/>by two hydrogen bonds. One fragment comprises the acid, while <lb/>the other consists of the geminal-diol. The two hydrogen bonds <lb/>connect the two hydroxyl groups in the geminal-diol with the <lb/>oxygen atom and the hydroxyl hydrogen atom on the acid, with <lb/>bond lengths ranging from 1.83 to 1.90 Å and 1.59 to 1.66 Å, <lb/>respectively. Similar to the acid-aldehyde systems, no proton <lb/>transfer occurs between the acid and aldehyde here, supported <lb/>by small d values (-0.02 ∼ -0.05) in SA or MSA. The geminal-<lb/>diol is formed by the reaction of aldehyde and water, where <lb/>water loses one proton to form an alcohol group. Because FA/ <lb/>GL/MG have a carbon end of the carbonyl double bond that is <lb/>electrophilic due to bond polarity created by resonance, when <lb/>directly attacked by a nucleophile, the p bond is broken to form <lb/>an alkoxide intermediate, which is then protonated to yield the <lb/>alcohol derivative. 80,81 However, water is a weak nucleophile, <lb/>and the carbonyl carbon usually needs to be activated. Previous <lb/>studies have shown that the carbonyl group is protonated under <lb/>acidic conditions, increasing the polarity of the carbonyl bond <lb/>and making the carbon more electrophilic. 110 Hence, in the <lb/>presence of water, SA/MSA acts as a catalyst to activate the <lb/>carbonyl carbon, facilitating the formation of geminal-diol. The <lb/>mechanism of geminal-diol formation and the specic proton <lb/>transfer situations are detailed below. <lb/>Next, we discuss the systems when the third component Z is <lb/>either A or MA. Previous studies have demonstrated that basic <lb/>molecules such as ammonia or small alkylamines not only form <lb/>Table 1 Dissociation energies (in kcal mol -1 ) of the acid-aldehyde clusters calculated from the binding energies (D DE ), electron energies with <lb/>zero-point corrected (D DE+ZPE ), and corresponding free energies (D DG ) at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level of theory. Positive <lb/>values mean endothermic and negative values mean exothermic <lb/>Dissociation paths <lb/>D DE <lb/>D DE+ZEP <lb/>D DG <lb/>Proton transfer <lb/>Types of proton <lb/>transfer <lb/>FA-SA / 1*FA +1*SA <lb/>10.12 <lb/>9.64 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>MG-SA / 1*MG +1*SA <lb/>10.72 <lb/>10.03 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>GL-SA / 1*GL +1*SA <lb/>9.20 <lb/>8.36 <lb/>-0.63 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>FA-MSA / 1*FA +1*MSA <lb/>9.02 <lb/>8.57 <lb/>-0.72 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>GL-MSA / 1*GL +1*MSA <lb/>8.40 <lb/>7.60 <lb/>-1.55 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>MG-MSA / 1*MG +1*MSA <lb/>10.01 <lb/>9.37 <lb/>-1.63 <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Fig. 3 The most stable structures of X-Y-Z (X = FA/GL/MG; Y = SA/MSA; Z = W) systems at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level. <lb/>Yellow, red, green and white spheres represent sulfur, oxygen, carbon and hydrogen atoms, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13325 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>atmospheric clusters with higher stability and nucleation rates <lb/>with SA or MSA but also act as nucleophiles attacking the <lb/>carbonyl functional groups in aldehydes. Fig. 4 illustrates the <lb/>geometry of the most stable clusters formed by the reaction of <lb/>three aldehydes with SA or MSA and basic nucleophilic compo-<lb/>nents, including A and MA molecules, with other high-energy <lb/>structures displayed in Fig. S6-S9. † These 12 clusters exhibit <lb/>global minimum structures with an eight-ring-like conguration <lb/>and two hydrogen bonds. When SA is the acid, a proton is <lb/>transferred from SA to the aldehyde carbonyl, resulting in an ion <lb/>pair. As a result, SA with a lost proton exhibits high partial charge <lb/>values, d = -0.87 to -0.88. For A or MA, nitrogen of base forms <lb/>a C-N bond with the aldehyde carbonyl, and the hydrogen on <lb/>nitrogen forms an O/H-N hydrogen bond with the acid. Clearly, <lb/>when SA is present, the carbonyl group is protonated, increasing <lb/>the polarity of the carbon-oxygen double bond and making it <lb/>more electrophilic. Notably, hydrogen bonds in basic systems are <lb/>shorter than those in water-based clusters, indicating stronger <lb/>interactions in base-based systems. When MSA is the acid, two <lb/>different scenarios exist. Only for FA-MSA-MA and MG-MSA-<lb/>MA, MSA systems exhibit the same bonding mode as SA systems, <lb/>with evident proton transfer occurring between the acid and <lb/>aldehyde. For the remaining four systems (GL-MSA-MA and FA/ <lb/>GL/MG-MSA-A), the bonding mode is similar to that in the <lb/>presence of water, where MSA, acting as a catalyst, does not <lb/>undergo changes, while the base loses a proton and forms an <lb/>aminoalcohol with the aldehyde. Regardless of whether the <lb/>nucleophile is water or a base, for clusters in which no proton <lb/>transfer occurs between the acid and aldehyde, SA or MSA still <lb/>possesses small negative d values. <lb/>To gain a deeper understanding of the formation of <lb/>compounds in which no proton transfer occurs, further <lb/>Fig. 4 The most stable structures of X-Y-Z (X = FA/GL/MG; Y = SA/MSA; Z = A/MA) systems at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) <lb/>level. Yellow, red, blue, green and white spheres represent sulfur, oxygen, nitrogen, carbon and hydrogen atoms, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<page>13326</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>investigation into the mechanism of such reactions was con-<lb/>ducted. Using 1FA-1MSA-1A as a representative system, tran-<lb/>sition state calculations for trimolecular reactions were <lb/>performed, and a complete reaction pathway was constructed. <lb/>Fig. 5 presents the Gibbs free energy change diagram for the <lb/>transition among four isomers in the FA-MSA-A system. It also <lb/>includes the geometric parameters of the corresponding struc-<lb/>tures, featuring four isomers (iso-1, iso-2, iso-3, iso-4) and two <lb/>transition states (TS-1, TS-2). From this pathway diagram, it can <lb/>be seen that in the reactants of the trimolecular reaction, <lb/>a hydrogen bond interaction with a bond length of 1.53 Å is <lb/>involved between FA and MSA molecules, while the A molecule <lb/>is only weakly linked to MSA and FA through a van der Waals <lb/>interaction. With an activation energy barrier of 2.59 kcal mol -1 <lb/>reaching transition state TS1, it can be observed that the <lb/>hydrogen atom H c of MSA is transferred to the oxygen atom O b <lb/>of FA, while ammonia is added to the carbon atom C a in <lb/>formaldehyde. This results in the formation of an eight-<lb/>membered ring product (iso-2) containing a stable ion pair. <lb/>The bond distances are H c O d = 1.72 Å, C a N h = 1.54 Å, and H i O j <lb/>= 1.51 Å, respectively. Subsequently, this product easily <lb/>undergoes a barrier-free reaction, involving a second proton <lb/>transfer via iso-2, TS2, and iso-1 in the current eight-ring model. <lb/>In this process, the hydrogen atom H i on the base A migrates to <lb/>MSA, ultimately forming the global minimum structure iso-1 <lb/>with the lowest relative energy (DG). This product involves two <lb/>hydrogen bond interactions, with bond distances of H c O d = <lb/>1.86 Å and N h H i = 1.48 Å, respectively. <lb/>According to reaction potential energy surface, we conclude <lb/>the following reaction mechanism for X-Y-Z systems in which <lb/>no proton transfer occurs, and the detailed process is shown in <lb/>Fig. 5: (1) SA/MSA protonates the carbonyl oxygen, making the <lb/>carbonyl carbon more electrophilic. Aer protonation, the <lb/>oxygen becomes positively charged, representing another reso-<lb/>nance form of carbocation. (2) Under acidic conditions, W/A/ <lb/>MA acts as a nucleophile and forms a single bond with the <lb/>electrophilic carbon. This pushes the two electrons in the <lb/>carbonyl p bond onto the electronegative oxygen. The oxygen <lb/>from the carbonyl becomes neutral, while the oxygen/nitrogen <lb/>from W/A/MA nucleophile becomes positively charged. (3) <lb/>HSO 4 <lb/>-or CH 3 SO 3 <lb/>-acts as a base to extract a proton from the <lb/>neutrally charged W/A/MA, thereby regenerating SA/MSA. <lb/>Hence, SA/MSA ultimately acts as a catalyst throughout the <lb/>entire reaction. In fact, for systems in which proton transfer <lb/>between the acid and aldehyde does occur (FA/GL/MG-SA-A/ <lb/>MA), the reaction is similar to that of TS-1, generating iso-2. <lb/>SA-based and MSA-based reactions differ in the subsequent <lb/>step, which may be attributed to the stronger basicity of <lb/>CH 3 SO 3 <lb/>-compared to HSO 4 <lb/>-. CH 3 SO 3 <lb/>-is more effective in <lb/>deprotonating the nitrogen atom in A or MA to form a positively <lb/>charged ammonolysis product. <lb/>3.2.2 Intermolecular interactions. The intermolecular <lb/>interactions within the most stable clusters of X-Y-Z systems <lb/>were further examined through NCI analysis. In all systems, the <lb/>positions of spikes on the scatter plot (RDG vs. sign(l 2 )r func-<lb/>tion) and the bonding isosurfaces visualized on the cluster <lb/>structures perfectly match in color. Taking six systems con-<lb/>taining FA as an example, we illustrate NCI analysis in Fig. 6. It <lb/>is evident that all systems exhibit two different types of <lb/>hydrogen bonds, corresponding to two negative sign(l 2 )r peaks <lb/>Fig. 5 The Gibbs free energy change diagram for the transition among four isomers in the FA-MSA-A system at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-<lb/>D3/6-31G(d) level of theory (in kcal mol -1 ). The values in parentheses represent the relative Gibbs free energy values of the isomers or transition <lb/>states relative to the zero point. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13327 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>on the scatter plot. Additionally, van der Waals forces (sign(l 2 )r <lb/>∼ 0) and steric hindrance (sign(l 2 )r &gt; 0) are also present in these <lb/>eight-ring-like ternary systems. Similar patterns are observed <lb/>for the di-carbonyl aldehydes GL and MG (see Fig. S10 and <lb/>S11 †). These results are also supported by visual bonding iso-<lb/>surfaces, with all hydrogen bonds corresponding to the struc-<lb/>tures in Fig. 3 and 4 through disk-shaped isosurfaces. <lb/>Comparing the interaction positions in the clusters containing <lb/>mono-and di-carbonyl aldehydes, we observed that only in the <lb/>GL and MG-based clusters, there are elliptical isosurfaces in <lb/>half-green and half-orange-red between the attacked carbonyl <lb/>carbon atom and the free carbonyl functional group. These <lb/>elliptical isosurfaces correspond to the dual impact of van der <lb/>Waals effects and mutual exclusion effects. This phenomenon <lb/>may be attributed to the presence of strong electron-<lb/>withdrawing groups such as -CHO and -COR in the complex <lb/>product of GL and MG. In summary, the NCI analysis reveals the <lb/>presence of various intermolecular interactions within the <lb/>clusters, including hydrogen bonds, van der Waals forces, and <lb/>steric hindrance. These interactions play a crucial role in <lb/>stabilizing the these clusters and inuencing their properties <lb/>and behavior. <lb/>3.2.3 Stability. The above results have indicated that acid-<lb/>aldehyde clusters have poor stability, however, in the presence <lb/>of nucleophilic molecules such as water or bases, aldehydes can <lb/>be protonated by the acid or nucleophilic molecules, forming <lb/>more stable eight-membered ring structures. To conrm the <lb/>stability of the most stable structures in the X-Y-Z systems, we <lb/>investigated the dissociation process of the obtained 18 clusters <lb/>and calculated their dissociation energies and the correspond-<lb/>ing proton transfer reactions. <lb/>As shown in Table 2, it is observed that, except for FA-MSA-<lb/>W (-0.31 kcal mol -1 ), the D DG values of the dissociation path-<lb/>ways for all other systems are positive (ranging from 0.1 to <lb/>15.59 kcal mol -1 ), indicating that these clusters are not prone to <lb/>dissociation reactions thermodynamically. Clearly, the third <lb/>component can effectively improve the stability of acid-<lb/>aldehyde clusters. This enhanced stability can be attributed to <lb/>several factors: (1) protonation of aldehydes: in X-Y-Z systems, <lb/>the carbonyl functional group of aldehydes is protonated by SA <lb/>or MSA, making the carbon atoms more electrophilic and thus <lb/>more prone to addition reactions with nucleophilic molecules. <lb/>(2) Contribution of water or alkali molecules: the presence of <lb/>water or alkali molecules is crucial for stabilizing the X-Y-Z <lb/>system. They can form stable hydrolysis or ammonolysis prod-<lb/>ucts with aldehydes and provide an additional pair of hydrogen <lb/>bonds with SA or MSA, enhancing the intermolecular interac-<lb/>tions within the cluster. <lb/>Furthermore, the effects of different components on D DG <lb/>were analyzed systematically: (1) aldehydes: clusters composed <lb/>of di-carbonyl aldehydes (GL and MG) exhibited larger D DG <lb/>values than those of mono-carbonyl aldehyde (FA), indicating <lb/>that the complexes generated by hydrolysis or ammonolysis <lb/>were more stable. Di-carbonyl aldehydes have strong electron-<lb/>withdrawing groups, which increase the electrophilicity of the <lb/>carbonyl carbon atom and enhance their ability to accept <lb/>Fig. 6 The plots of RDG versus sign(l 2 )r function and the visualized bonding isosurfaces for the most stable structures of X-Y-Z (X = FA) <lb/>clusters. <lb/></body>

			<page>13328</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<body>nucleophiles. (2) Nucleophiles: the D DG values of the clusters <lb/>formed by different nucleophiles attacking carbonyl carboca-<lb/>tions are consistent with their nucleophilicity, with the stability <lb/>in descending order: D DG (MA-based) &gt; D DG (A-based) &gt; D DG (W-<lb/>based). This suggests that the stability of the clusters formed by <lb/>aldehydes under the action of SA or MSA is closely related to the <lb/>nucleophilicity of the nucleophile. (3) Acid effect: the DG values <lb/>of all SA-based clusters (including X-Y and X-Y-Z systems) are <lb/>higher than those of the corresponding MSA-based clusters, <lb/>indicating that SA-based clusters are more thermodynamically <lb/>stable. This is mainly because SA has a higher acid strength and <lb/>can better stabilize the partial negative charge of the oxygen <lb/>atom on the C]O in the aldehyde. <lb/>Additionally, MD simulations were performed for all X-Y-Z <lb/>clusters to evaluate their stability at room temperature (300 K), <lb/>and the results are shown in Fig. S12-S14. † In systems where no <lb/>proton transfer occurs between acid and aldehyde in the most <lb/>stable structures, the acid tends to dissociate from the structure <lb/>rapidly. Conversely, systems that experienced proton transfer <lb/>from acid to aldehyde demonstrated enhanced stability, charac-<lb/>terized by minimal energy uctuations and intact components. <lb/>In summary, for the three-component reaction, both the acid <lb/>and nucleophilic reagents play synergistic roles in the reaction with <lb/>aldehydes, and the acidity of the acid, strength of the nucleophile, <lb/>and type of aldehyde all contribute to the stability and reactivity of <lb/>the clusters. Crucially, proton transfer between acid and aldehyde <lb/>emerges as a vital factor for evaluating cluster stability. <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>Utilizing quantum chemical calculations and MD simulations, <lb/>we systematically investigated NPF involving three types of <lb/>aldehydes, two acids, and two bases or water. Our study reveals <lb/>that acid-aldehyde (X-Y) clusters are merely linked by hydrogen <lb/>bonds between the acids and aldehydes, without any proton <lb/>transfer. Calculations of dissociation energy and MD suggest that <lb/>these clusters are less thermodynamically stable. The order of <lb/>thermodynamic stability for SA system is formaldehyde (FA) &gt; <lb/>methylglyoxal (MG) &gt; glyoxal (GL), while for MSA system, it is FA <lb/>&gt; GL &gt; MG. When a third component Z (water and base) is <lb/>present, the most stable structure forms an eight-membered ring <lb/>via two hydrogen bonds, with X-Y-Z systems exhibiting <lb/>improved stability compared to X-Y systems. Among them, ten <lb/>systems (FA/GL/MG-SA/MSA-W, FA/GL/MG-MSA-A, GL-MSA-<lb/>MA) occur twice proton transfer, i.e., MSA / aldehyde and water <lb/>or base / MSA, resulting in MSA as a catalyst in this process. For <lb/>the remaining eight clusters (FA/GL/MG-SA-A/MA, FA/MG-MSA-<lb/>MA), the most stable structures are ion pairs formed by proton <lb/>transfer from the acids to aldehydes, i.e., acid / aldehyde. These <lb/>clusters maintain excellent thermodynamic stability. Addition-<lb/>ally, under acidic conditions, the electrophilicity of carbon atoms <lb/>in FA, GL, and MG is progressively enhanced, along with the <lb/>increasing stability of the formed cluster. With the increase of <lb/>the acidity of acid and the basicity of the nucleophile, stabilities <lb/>of products formed in the aldehyde-involved reactions also <lb/>increase. In summary, this study provides valuable insights into <lb/>NPF. Proton transfer between acids and aldehydes and the <lb/>involvement of water/base molecules are crucial for nucleophilic <lb/>reactions leading to stable nucleated clusters. Additionally, the <lb/>acidity of the acid, the nature of nucleophilic agents, and the type <lb/>of aldehyde all play signicant roles in cluster stability and <lb/>reactivity, and they have synergistic effects on the nucleation <lb/>process. This research not only advances our understanding of <lb/>aldehydes-based NPF processes but also offers useful guidance <lb/>for future related studies. <lb/></body>

			<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>GZ: investigation, methodology, visualization, formal analysis, <lb/>and writing -original dra. ML: formal analysis, investigation, <lb/></div>

			<body>Table 2 Dissociation energies (in kcal mol -1 ) of the most stable clusters in X-Y-Z systems calculated from the binding energies (D DE ), electron <lb/>energies with zero-point corrected (D DE+ZPE ), and corresponding free energies (D DG ) at the MP2/6-311+G(d, p)//B3LYP-D3/6-31G(d) level of <lb/>theory, and the details of proton transfer in each cluster. Positive values mean endothermic and negative values mean exothermic <lb/>Dissociation paths <lb/>D DE <lb/>D DE+ZEP <lb/>D DG <lb/>Proton transfer <lb/>Types of proton transfer <lb/>MG-SA-MA / 1*MG + 1*SA + 1*MA <lb/>40.31 <lb/>40.34 <lb/>15.59 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / MG <lb/>GL-SA-MA / 1*GL + 1*SA + 1*MA <lb/>38.54 <lb/>38.71 <lb/>14.69 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / GL <lb/>FA-SA-MA / 1*FA + 1*SA + 1*MA <lb/>30.01 <lb/>43.61 <lb/>13.94 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / FA <lb/>MG-MSA-MA / 1*MG + 1*MSA + 1*MA <lb/>29.52 <lb/>47.44 <lb/>13.24 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / MG <lb/>GL-MSA-MA / 1*GL + 1*MSA + 1*MA <lb/>29.71 <lb/>45.58 <lb/>12.61 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / GL <lb/>MA / MSA <lb/>FA-MSA-MA / 1*FA + 1*MSA + 1*MA <lb/>34.29 <lb/>34.89 <lb/>10.94 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / FA <lb/>MG-SA-A / 1*MG + 1*SA + 1*A <lb/>30.55 <lb/>31.16 <lb/>7.96 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / MG <lb/>GL-SA-A / 1*GL + 1*SA + 1*A <lb/>29.25 <lb/>29.94 <lb/>7.48 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / GL <lb/>MG-MSA-A / 1*MG + 1*MSA + 1*A <lb/>23.06 <lb/>39.56 <lb/>7.12 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / MG <lb/>A / MSA <lb/>GL-MSA-A / 1*GL + 1*MSA + 1*A <lb/>21.92 <lb/>36.99 <lb/>6.63 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / GL <lb/>A / MSA <lb/>FA-SA-A / 1*FA + 1*SA + 1*A <lb/>27.35 <lb/>28.38 <lb/>6.33 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / FA <lb/>FA-MSA-A / 1*FA + 1*MSA + 1*A <lb/>20.11 <lb/>33.42 <lb/>5.74 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / FA <lb/>A / MSA <lb/>MG-SA-W / 1*MG + 1*SA + 1*W <lb/>15.01 <lb/>31.15 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / MG <lb/>W / SA <lb/>FA-SA-W / 1*FA + 1*SA + 1*W <lb/>15.45 <lb/>27.79 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / FA <lb/>W / SA <lb/>GL-SA-W / 1*GL + 1*SA + 1*W <lb/>14.88 <lb/>29.27 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SA / GL <lb/>W / SA <lb/>MG-MSA-W / 1*MG + 1*MSA + 1*W <lb/>14.01 <lb/>30.99 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / MG <lb/>W / MSA <lb/>GL-MSA-W / 1*GL + 1*MSA + 1*W <lb/>21.49 <lb/>22.16 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / GL <lb/>W / MSA <lb/>FA-MSA-W / 1*FA + 1*MSA + 1*W <lb/>20.39 <lb/>21.41 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>Yes <lb/>MSA / FA <lb/>W / MSA <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13329 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<div type="contribution">methodology, and writing -original dra. YH: methodology, <lb/>data curation. ZW: visualization. WL: funding acquisition. YZ: <lb/>conceptualization, funding acquisition, investigation, project <lb/>administration, resources, supervision, validation, and writing <lb/>-review and editing. All authors contributed to the article and <lb/>approved the submitted version. JX: conceptualization, funding <lb/>acquisition, investigation, project administration, resources, <lb/>supervision, and writing -review and editing. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflicts of interest <lb/>There are no conicts to declare. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported by the National Natural Science <lb/>Foundation of China (No. 12075211 and 11975206) and Scien-<lb/>tic Research Project of Jinhua Advanced Research Institute <lb/>(G202202). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 J. L. Jimenez, M. R. Canagaratna, N. M. Donahue, A. Prevot <lb/>and Q. Zhang, Evolution of organic aerosols in the <lb/>atmosphere, Science, 2009, 326, 1525-1529, DOI: 10.1126/ <lb/>science.1180353. <lb/>2 S. Guo, M. Hu, M. L. Zamora, J. Peng and R. Zhang, <lb/>Elucidating severe urban haze formation in china, Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., 2014, 111(49), 17373, DOI: <lb/>10.1073/pnas.1419604111. <lb/>3 C. L. Heald, D. J. Jacob, R. J. Park, L. M. Russell, <lb/>B. J. Huebert, J. H. Seinfeld, H. Liao and R. J. Weber, A <lb/>large organic aerosol source in the free troposphere <lb/>missing from current models, Geophys. Res. Lett., 2005, <lb/>32, L18809, DOI: 10.1029/2005GL023831. <lb/>4 M. Shrivastava, C. D. Cappa, J. Fan, A. H. Goldstein, <lb/>A. B. Guenther, J. L. Jimenez, C. Kuang, A. Laskin, <lb/>S. T. Martin, N. L. Ng, T. Petaja, J. R. Pierce, P. J. Rasch, <lb/>P. Roldin, J. H. Seinfeld, J. Shilling, J. N. Smith, <lb/>J. A. Thornton, R. Volkamer, J. Wang, D. R. Worsnop, <lb/>R. A. Zaveri, A. Zelenyuk and Q. Zhang, Recent advances <lb/>in understanding secondary organic aerosol: implications <lb/>for global climate forcing, Rev. Geophys., 2017, 55(2), 509-<lb/>559, DOI: 10.1002/2016RG000540. <lb/>5 S. Solomon, D. Qin, M. Manning, Z. Chen, M. Marquis, <lb/>K. Averyt, M. Tignor and H. Miller Climate Change 2007: <lb/>the Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I <lb/>to the Fourth 16 Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental <lb/>Panel on Climate Change; Contribution of Working Group I <lb/>to the Fourth Assesment Report of the Intergovernmental <lb/>Panel on Climate Change, Climate Change 2007: the Physical <lb/>Science Basis, 2013. <lb/>6 R. Zhang, G. Li, J. Fan, D. L. Wu and M. J. Molina, <lb/>Intensication of pacic storm track linked to asian <lb/>pollution, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., 2007, 104(13), <lb/>5295-5299, DOI: 10.1073/pnas.0700618104. <lb/>7 J. Fan, R. Zhang, W.-K. Tao and K. I. Mohr, Effects of aerosol <lb/>optical properties on deep convective clouds and radiative <lb/>forcing, J. Geophys. Res., 2008, 113(D8), D08209, DOI: <lb/>10.1029/2007JD009257. <lb/>8 R. Zhang, A. Khalizov, L. Wang, M. Hu and W. Xu, <lb/>Nucleation and growth of nanoparticles in the <lb/>atmosphere, Chem. Rev., 2012, 112(3), 1957-2011, DOI: <lb/>10.1021/cr2001756. <lb/>9 H. Henschel, T. Kurtén and H. Vehkamäki, Computational <lb/>study on the effect of hydration on new particle formation <lb/>in the sulfuric acid/ammonia and sulfuric acid/ <lb/>dimethylamine systems, J. Phys. Chem. A, 2016, 120(11), <lb/>1886-1896, DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpca.5b11366. <lb/>10 D. R. Hanson and F. L. Eisele, Measurement of <lb/>prenucleation molecular clusters in the NH 3 , H 2 SO 4 , H 2 O <lb/>system, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., 2002, 107(D12), 4158, DOI: <lb/>10.1029/2001JD001100. <lb/>11 J. Zhao, J. N. Smith, F. L. Eisele, M. Chen, C. Kuang and <lb/>P. H. McMurry, Observation of neutral sulfuric acid-<lb/>amine containing clusters in laboratory and ambient <lb/>measurements, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2011, 11(21), 10823-<lb/>10836, DOI: 10.5194/acp-11-10823-2011. <lb/>12 L. J. Larson, A. Largent and F.-M. Tao, Structure of the <lb/>sulfuric acid-ammonia system and the effect of water <lb/>molecules in the gas phase, J. Phys. Chem. A, 1999, <lb/>103(34), 6786-6792, DOI: 10.1021/jp991529p. <lb/>13 W. A. Glasoe, K. Volz, B. Panta, N. Freshour, R. Bachman, <lb/>D. R. Hanson, P. H. McMurry and C. Jen, Sulfuric acid <lb/>nucleation: an experimental study of the effect of seven <lb/>bases, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., 2015, 120(5), 1933-1950, <lb/>DOI: 10.1002/2014JD022730. <lb/>14 J. H. Zollner, W. A. Glasoe, B. Panta, K. K. Carlson, <lb/>P. H. McMurry and D. R. Hanson, Sulfuric acid <lb/>nucleation: power dependencies, variation with relative <lb/>humidity, and effect of bases, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2012, <lb/>12(10), 4399-4411, DOI: 10.5194/acp-12-4399-2012. <lb/>15 A. Kürten, S. Münch, L. Rondo, F. Bianchi, J. Duplissy, <lb/>T. Jokinen, H. Junninen, N. Sarnela, S. Schobesberger, <lb/>M. Simon, M. Sipilä, J. Almeida, A. Amorim, J. Dommen, <lb/>N. M. Donahue, E. M. Dunne, R. C. Flagan, A. Franchin, <lb/>J. Kirkby, A. Kupc, V. Makhmutov, T. Petäjä, A. P. Praplan, <lb/>F. Riccobono, G. Steiner, A. Tomé, G. Tsagkogeorgas, <lb/>P. E. Wagner, D. Wimmer, U. Baltensperger, M. Kulmala, <lb/>D. R. Worsnop and J. Curtius, Thermodynamics of the <lb/>formation of sulfuric acid dimers in the binary (H 2 SO 4 -<lb/>H 2 O) and ternary (H 2 SO 4 -H 2 O-NH 3 ) system, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 2015, 15(18), 10701-10721, DOI: 10.5194/acp-15-<lb/>10701-2015. <lb/>16 C. Kuang, M. Chen, J. Zhao, J. Smith, P. H. McMurry and <lb/>J. Wang, Size and time-resolved growth rate <lb/>measurements of 1 to 5 nm freshly formed atmospheric <lb/>nuclei, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2012, 12(7), 3573-3589, DOI: <lb/>10.5194/acp-12-3573-2012. <lb/>17 J. Tröstl, K. Chuang, H. Gordon, M. Heinritzi, C. Yan, <lb/>U. Molteni, L. Ahlm, C. Frege, F. Bianchi, M. Simon, <lb/>K. Lehtipalo, C. Williamson, S. Craven, J. Duplissy, <lb/>A. <lb/>Adamov, <lb/>J. <lb/>Almeida, <lb/>A.-K. <lb/>Bernhammer, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13330</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>M. Breitenlechner, S. Brilke, A. Dias, S. Ehrhart, C. Flagan, <lb/>A. Franchin, C. Fuchs, R. Guida, M. Gysel, A. Hansel, <lb/>R. Hoyle, T. Jokinen, H. Junninen, J. Kangasluoma, <lb/>H. Keskinen, J. Kim, M. Krapf, A. Kürten, A. Laaksonen, <lb/>M. Lawler, M. Leiminger, S. Mathot, O. Möhler, <lb/>T. Nieminen, A. Onnela, T. Petäjä, M. Piel, P. Miettinen, <lb/>P. Rissanen, L. Rondo, N. Sarnela, S. Schobesberger, <lb/>K. Sengupta, M. Sipilä, N. Smith, G. Steiner, A. Tomè, <lb/>A. Virtanen, C. Wagner, E. Weingartner, D. Wimmer, <lb/>M. Winkler, P. Ye, S. Carslaw, J. Curtius, J. Dommen, <lb/>J. Kirkby, M. Kulmala, I. Riipinen, R. Worsnop, <lb/>M. Donahue and U. Baltensperger, The role of low-<lb/>volatility organic compounds in initial particle growth in <lb/>the atmosphere, Nature, 2015, 527-531. <lb/>18 A. Metzger, B. Verheggen, J. Dommen, J. Duplissy, <lb/>A. S. H. Prevot, E. Weingartner, I. Riipinen, M. Kulmala, <lb/>D. V. Spracklen, K. S. Carslaw and U. Baltensperger, <lb/>Evidence for the role of organics in aerosol particle <lb/>formation under atmospheric conditions, Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. U. S. A., 2010, 107(15), 6646-6651, DOI: 10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.0911330107. <lb/>19 J. Elm, Clusteromics i: principles, protocols, and <lb/>applications to sulfuric acid-base cluster formation, ACS <lb/>Omega, 2021, 6(11), 7804-7814, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acsomega.1c00306. <lb/>20 Y. Ling, Y. Wang, J. Duan, X. Xie, Y. Liu, Y. Peng, L. Qiao, <lb/>T. Cheng, S. Lou, H. Wang, X. Li and X. Xing, Long-term <lb/>aerosol size distributions and the potential role of volatile <lb/>organic compounds (VOCs) in new particle formation <lb/>events in shanghai, Atmos. Environ., 2019, 202, 345-356, <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2019.01.018. <lb/>21 M. J. Apsokardu and M. V. Johnston, Nanoparticle growth <lb/>by particle-phase chemistry, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2018, <lb/>18(3), 1895-1907, DOI: 10.5194/acp-18-1895-2018. <lb/>22 X. Fang, M. Hu, D. Shang, R. Tang, L. Shi, T. Olenius, <lb/>Y. Wang, H. Wang, Z. Zhang, S. Chen, X. Yu, W. Zhu, <lb/>S. Lou, Y. Ma, X. Li, L. Zeng, Z. Wu, J. Zheng and S. Guo, <lb/>Observational evidence for the involvement of <lb/>dicarboxylic acids in particle nucleation, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol. Lett., 2020, 7(6), 388-394, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acs.estlett.0c00270. <lb/>23 P. Roldin, M. Ehn, T. Kurtén, T. Olenius, M. P. Rissanen, <lb/>N. Sarnela, J. Elm, P. Rantala, L. Hao, N. Hyttinen, <lb/>L. Heikkinen, D. R. Worsnop, L. Pichelstorfer, C. Xavier, <lb/>P. Clusius, E. Öström, T. Petäjä, M. Kulmala, <lb/>H. Vehkamäki, A. Virtanen, I. Riipinen and M. Boy, The <lb/>role of highly oxygenated organic molecules in the boreal <lb/>aerosol-cloud-climate system, Nat. Commun., 2019, 10(1), <lb/>4370, DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-12338-8. <lb/>24 H. B. Singh Composition Chemistry, and Climate of the <lb/>Atmosphere, 1995. <lb/>25 A. P. Altshuller, Review: natural volatile organic substances <lb/>and their effect on air quality in the United States, Atmos. <lb/>Environ., 1983, 17(11), 2131-2165, DOI: 10.1016/0004-<lb/>6981(83)90211-1. <lb/>26 N. Barbara, B. Ian and B. Karl-Heinz, Product study and <lb/>mechanisms of the reactions of a-pinene and of <lb/>pinonaldehyde with oh radicals, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., <lb/>1999, 104(D19), 23645-23656, DOI: 10.1029/1999jd900778. <lb/>27 R. Kamens, M. Jang, C. J. Chien and K. Leach, Aerosol <lb/>formation from the reaction of a-pinene and ozone using <lb/>a gas-phase kinetics-aerosol partitioning model, Environ. <lb/>Sci. Technol., 1999, 33(9), 1430-1438, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>es980725r. <lb/>28 M. Jang and R. M. Kamens, Characterization of secondary <lb/>aerosol from the photooxidation of toluene in the <lb/>presence of NO x and 1-propene, Environ. Sci. Technol., <lb/>2001, 35(18), 3626-3639, DOI: 10.1021/es010676+. <lb/>29 P. Carlier, H. Hannachi and G. Mouvier, The chemistry of <lb/>carbonyl compounds in the atmosphere-a review -<lb/>ScienceDirect, Atmos. Environ., 1986, 20(11), 2079-2099, <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/0004-6981(86)90304-5. <lb/>30 W. Carter, A. M. Winer and J. N. Pitts, Effect of peroxyacetyl <lb/>nitrate on the initiation of photochemical smog, Environ. <lb/>Sci. Technol., 1981, 15(7), 831-834, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>es00089a010. <lb/>31 D. Grosjean, E. L. Williams and E. Grosjean, Atmospheric <lb/>chemistry of isoprene and of its carbonyl products, <lb/>Environ. Sci. Technol., 1993, 27(5), 830-840, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>es00042a004. <lb/>32 Y. Ji, Q. Shi, Y. Li, T. An, J. Zheng, J. Peng, Y. Gao, J. Chen, <lb/>G. Li, Y. Wang, F. Zhang, A. L. Zhang, J. Zhao, M. J. Molina <lb/>and R. Zhang, Carbenium ion-mediated oligomerization of <lb/>methylglyoxal for secondary organic aerosol formation, <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., 2020, 117(24), 13294-13299, <lb/>DOI: 10.1073/pnas.1912235117. <lb/>33 Y. Li, Y. Ji, J. Zhao, Y. Wang, Q. Shi, J. Peng, Y. Wang, <lb/>C. Wang, F. Zhang, Y. Wang, J. H. Seinfeld and R. Zhang, <lb/>Unexpected oligomerization of small a-dicarbonyls for <lb/>secondary organic aerosol and brown carbon formation, <lb/>Environ. Sci. Technol., 2021, 55(8), 4430-4439, DOI: <lb/>10.1021/acs.est.0c08066. <lb/>34 C. Wang, X. Chen, Y. Liu, T. Huang and S. Jiang, Theoretical <lb/>study of the gas-phase hydrolysis of formaldehyde to <lb/>produce methanediol and its implication to new particle <lb/>formation, ACS Omega, 2023, 8(17), 15467-15478, DOI: <lb/>10.1021/acsomega.3c00770. <lb/>35 K. Shashikala, P. M. Niha, J. Aswathi, J. Sharanya and <lb/>D. Janardanan, Theoretical exploration of new particle <lb/>formation from glycol aldehyde in the atmosphere -<lb/>a temperature-dependent study, Comput. Theor. Chem., <lb/>2023, 1222, 114057, DOI: 10.1016/j.comptc.2023.114057. <lb/>36 F.-Y. Bai, T.-X. Chi, X.-H. Liu, T.-T. Meng, S. Ni and Z. Zhao, <lb/>Metal-free catalysis on the reactions of nitric acid with <lb/>aliphatic aldehydes: a new potential source of organic <lb/>nitrates, Atmos. Environ., 2023, 299, 119673, DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.atmosenv.2023.119673. <lb/>37 X. Shi, R. Zhang, Y. Sun, F. Xu, Q. Zhang and W. Wang, A <lb/>Density functional theory study of aldehydes and their <lb/>atmospheric products participating in nucleation, Phys. <lb/>Chem. Chem. Phys., 2018, 20(2), 1005-1011, DOI: 10.1039/ <lb/>C7CP06226E. <lb/>38 C.-Y. Wang, S. Jiang, Z.-Q. Wang, Y.-R. Liu, H. Wen, <lb/>T. Huang, Y.-J. Han and W. Huang, Can formaldehyde <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13331 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>contribute to atmospheric new particle formation from <lb/>sulfuric acid and water?, Atmos. Environ., 2019, 201, 323-<lb/>333, DOI: 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2018.12.057. <lb/>39 B. Long, Y. Xia and D. G. Truhlar, Quantitative Kinetics of <lb/>HO 2 reactions with aldehydes in the atmosphere: high-<lb/>order dynamic correlation, anharmonicity, and falloff <lb/>effects are all important, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2022, 144(43), <lb/>19910-19920, DOI: 10.1021/jacs.2c07994. <lb/>40 J. Liggio, Reactive uptake of glyoxal by particulate matter, J. <lb/>Geophys. Res., 2005, 110(D10), D10304, DOI: 10.1029/ <lb/>2004JD005113. <lb/>41 R. Volkamer, F. San Martini, L. T. Molina, D. Salcedo, <lb/>J. L. Jimenez and M. J. Molina, A missing sink for gas-<lb/>phase glyoxal in mexico city: formation of secondary <lb/>organic aerosol, Geophys. Res. Lett., 2007, 34(19), L19807, <lb/>DOI: 10.1029/2007GL030752. <lb/>42 R. Volkamer, P. J. Ziemann and M. J. Molina, Secondary <lb/>organic aerosol formation from acetylene (C 2 H 2 ): seed <lb/>effect on SOA yields due to organic photochemistry in the <lb/>aerosol aqueous phase, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2009, 9(6), <lb/>1907-1928. <lb/>43 T.-M. Fu, D. J. Jacob, F. Wittrock, J. P. Burrows, <lb/>M. Vrekoussis and D. K. Henze, Global budgets of <lb/>atmospheric glyoxal and methylglyoxal, and implications <lb/>for formation of secondary organic aerosols, J. Geophys. <lb/>Res., 2008, 113(D15), D15303, DOI: 10.1029/2007JD009505. <lb/>44 J. D. Blando and B. J. Turpin, Secondary organic aerosol <lb/>formation in cloud and fog droplets: a literature <lb/>evaluation of plausibility, Atmos. Environ., 2000, 34(10), <lb/>1623-1632, DOI: 10.1016/S1352-2310(99)00392-1. <lb/>45 M. Sipila, T. Berndt, T. Petaja, D. Brus, J. Vanhanen, <lb/>F. Stratmann, J. Patokoski, R. L. Mauldin, A.-P. Hyvarinen, <lb/>H. Lihavainen and M. Kulmala, The role of sulfuric acid <lb/>in atmospheric nucleation, Science, 2010, 327(5970), 1243-<lb/>1246, DOI: 10.1126/science.1180315. <lb/>46 J. Kirkby, J. Curtius, J. Almeida, E. Dunne, J. Duplissy, <lb/>S. Ehrhart, A. Franchin, S. Gagné, L. Ickes, A. Kürten, <lb/>A. Kupc, A. Metzger, F. Riccobono, L. Rondo, <lb/>S. Schobesberger, G. Tsagkogeorgas, D. Wimmer, <lb/>A. Amorim, F. Bianchi, M. Breitenlechner, A. David, <lb/>J. Dommen, A. Downard, M. Ehn, R. C. Flagan, S. Haider, <lb/>A. Hansel, D. Hauser, W. Jud, H. Junninen, F. Kreissl, <lb/>A. Kvashin, A. Laaksonen, K. Lehtipalo, J. Lima, <lb/>E. R. Lovejoy, V. Makhmutov, S. Mathot, J. Mikkilä, <lb/>P. Minginette, S. Mogo, T. Nieminen, A. Onnela, <lb/>P. Pereira, T. Petäjä, R. Schnitzhofer, J. H. Seinfeld, <lb/>M. Sipilä, Y. Stozhkov, F. Stratmann, A. Tomé, <lb/>J. Vanhanen, Y. Viisanen, A. Vrtala, P. E. Wagner, <lb/>H. Walther, E. Weingartner, H. Wex, P. M. Winkler, <lb/>K. S. Carslaw, D. R. Worsnop, U. Baltensperger and <lb/>M. Kulmala, Role of sulphuric acid, ammonia and <lb/>galactic cosmic rays in atmospheric aerosol nucleation, <lb/>Nature, 2011, 476(7361), 429-433, DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>nature10343. <lb/>47 M. Kulmala, J. Kontkanen, H. Junninen, K. Lehtipalo, <lb/>H. E. Manninen, T. Nieminen, T. Petaja, M. Sipila, <lb/>S. Schobesberger, P. Rantala, A. Franchin, T. Jokinen, <lb/>E. Jarvinen, M. Aijala, J. Kangasluoma, J. Hakala, <lb/>P. P. Aalto, P. Paasonen, J. Mikkila, J. Vanhanen, J. Aalto, <lb/>H. Hakola, U. Makkonen, T. Ruuskanen, R. L. Mauldin, <lb/>J. Duplissy, H. Vehkamaki, J. Back, A. Kortelainen, <lb/>I. Riipinen, T. Kurten, M. V. Johnston, J. N. Smith, <lb/>M. Ehn, T. F. Mentel, K. E. J. Lehtinen, A. Laaksonen, <lb/>V.-M. Kerminen and D. R. Worsnop, Direct Observations <lb/>of atmospheric aerosol nucleation, Science, 2013, <lb/>339(6122), 943-946, DOI: 10.1126/science.1227385. <lb/>48 X. Ma, Y. Sun, Z. Huang, Q. Zhang and W. Wang, A density <lb/>functional theory study of the molecular interactions <lb/>between a series of amides and sulfuric acid, <lb/>Chemosphere, 2019, 214, 781-790, DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.chemosphere.2018.08.152. <lb/>49 H. Bardouki, H. Berresheim, M. Vrekoussis, J. Sciare, <lb/>G. Kouvarakis, K. Oikonomou, J. Schneider and <lb/>N. Mihalopoulos, Gaseous (DMS, MSA, SO 2 , H 2 SO 4 and <lb/>DMSO) and particulate (sulfate and methanesulfonate) <lb/>sulfur species over the northeastern coast of crete, Atmos. <lb/>Chem. Phys., 2003, 3, 1871-1886. <lb/>50 C. J. Gaston, R. A. Pratt, X. Qin and K. A. Prather, Real-time <lb/>detection and mixing state of methanesulfonate in single <lb/>particles at an inland urban location during <lb/>a phytoplankton bloom, Environ. Sci. Technol., 2010, 44(5), <lb/>1566-1572, DOI: 10.1021/es902069d. <lb/>51 M. L. Dawson, M. E. Varner, V. Perraud, M. J. Ezell, <lb/>R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, Simplied <lb/>mechanism <lb/>for <lb/>new <lb/>particle <lb/>formation <lb/>from <lb/>methanesulfonic acid, amines, and water via experiments <lb/>and ab initio calculations, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., <lb/>2012, <lb/>109(46), <lb/>18719-18724, <lb/>DOI: <lb/>10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.1211878109. <lb/>52 M. L. Dawson, M. E. Varner, V. Perraud, M. J. Ezell, <lb/>J. Wilson, A. Zelenyuk, R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-<lb/>Pitts, <lb/>Amine-amine <lb/>exchange <lb/>in <lb/>aminium-<lb/>methanesulfonate aerosols, J. Phys. Chem. C, 2014, <lb/>118(50), 29431-29440, DOI: 10.1021/jp506560w. <lb/>53 M. J. Ezell, H. Chen, K. D. Arquero and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, <lb/>Aerosol fast ow reactor for laboratory studies of new <lb/>particle formation, J. Aerosol Sci., 2014, 78, 30-40, DOI: <lb/>10.1016/j.jaerosci.2014.08.009. <lb/>54 N. Nishino, K. D. Arquero, M. L. Dawson and B. J. Finlayson-<lb/>Pitts, Infrared studies of the reaction of methanesulfonic <lb/>acid with trimethylamine on surfaces, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 2014, 48(1), 323-330, DOI: 10.1021/es403845b. <lb/>55 H. Chen, M. E. Varner, R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, <lb/>Reactions of methanesulfonic acid with amines and <lb/>ammonia as a source of new particles in air, J. Phys. <lb/>Chem. B, 2016, 120(8), 1526-1536, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acs.jpcb.5b07433. <lb/>56 H. Chen, M. J. Ezell, K. D. Arquero, M. E. Varner, <lb/>M. L. Dawson, R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, New <lb/>particle formation and growth from methanesulfonic <lb/>acid, trimethylamine and water, Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys., <lb/>2015, 17(20), 13699-13709, DOI: 10.1039/C5CP00838G. <lb/>57 Y. Hu, S. Chen, S. Ye, S. Wei, B. Chu, R. Wang, H. Li and <lb/>T. Zhang, The role of triuoroacetic acid in new particle <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13332</page>

            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>formation from methanesulfonic acid-methylamine, Atmos. <lb/>Environ., <lb/>2023, <lb/>311, <lb/>120001, <lb/>DOI: <lb/>10.1016/ <lb/>j.atmosenv.2023.120001. <lb/>58 K. D. Arquero, R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, The <lb/>role of oxalic acid in new particle formation from <lb/>methanesulfonic acid, methylamine, and water, Environ. <lb/>Sci. Technol., 2017, 51(4), 2124-2130, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acs.est.6b05056. <lb/>59 J. S. Johnson and C. N. Jen, Role of methanesulfonic acid in <lb/>sulfuric acid-amine and ammonia new particle formation, <lb/>ACS Earth Space Chem., 2023, 7(3), 653-660, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acsearthspacechem.3c00017. <lb/>60 N. Tsona Tchinda, L. Du, L. Liu and X. Zhang, Pyruvic acid, <lb/>an efficient catalyst in SO 3 hydrolysis and effective <lb/>clustering agent in sulfuric-acid-based new particle <lb/>formation, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2022, 22(3), 1951-1963, <lb/>DOI: 10.5194/acp-22-1951-2022. <lb/>61 S.-H. Lee, H. Gordon, H. Yu, K. Lehtipalo, R. Haley, Y. Li <lb/>and R. Zhang, New particle formation in the atmosphere: <lb/>from molecular clusters to global climate, J. Geophys. Res. <lb/>Atmos., 2019, 124(13), 7098-7146, DOI: 10.1029/ <lb/>2018JD029356. <lb/>62 M. Kulmala, T. Petäjä, M. Ehn, J. Thornton, M. Sipilä, <lb/>D. R. Worsnop and V.-M. Kerminen, Chemistry of <lb/>atmospheric nucleation: on the recent advances on <lb/>precursor characterization and atmospheric cluster <lb/>composition in connection with atmospheric new particle <lb/>formation, Annu. Rev. Phys. Chem., 2014, 65, 21-37, DOI: <lb/>10.1146/annurev-physchem-040412-110014. <lb/>63 M. Peltola, C. Rose, J. V. Trueblood, S. Gray, M. Harvey and <lb/>K. Sellegri, Chemical precursors of new particle formation <lb/>in coastal New Zealand, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2023, 23(7), <lb/>3955-3983, DOI: 10.5194/acp-23-3955-2023. <lb/>64 R. Cai, C. Yan, D. R. Worsnop, F. Bianchi, V.-M. Kerminen, <lb/>Y. Liu, L. Wang, J. Zheng, M. Kulmala and J. Jiang, An <lb/>Indicator for sulfuric acid-amine nucleation in <lb/>atmospheric environments, Aerosol Sci. Technol., 2021, <lb/>55(9), 1059-1069, DOI: 10.1080/02786826.2021.1922598. <lb/>65 A. Ning, H. Zhang, X. Zhang, Z. Li, Y. Zhang, Y. Xu and <lb/>M. Ge, A molecular-scale study on the role of <lb/>methanesulnic acid in marine new particle formation, <lb/>Atmos. Environ., 2020, 227, 117378, DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.atmosenv.2020.117378. <lb/>66 E. Dovrou, K. H. Bates, J. M. Moch, L. J. Mickley, D. J. Jacob <lb/>and F. N. Keutsch, Catalytic role of formaldehyde in <lb/>particulate matter formation, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., <lb/>2022, 119(6), e2113265119, DOI: 10.1073/pnas.2113265119. <lb/>67 M. Jang and R. M. Kamens, Atmospheric secondary aerosol <lb/>formation by heterogeneous reactions of aldehydes in the <lb/>presence of a sulfuric acid aerosol catalyst, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 2001, 35(24), 4758-4766, DOI: 10.1021/es010790s. <lb/>68 M. Jang, N. M. Czoschke, S. Lee and R. M. Kamens, <lb/>Heterogeneous atmospheric aerosol production by acid-<lb/>catalyzed particle-phase reactions, Science, 2002, <lb/>298(5594), 814-817, DOI: 10.1126/science.1075798. <lb/>69 M. Jang, B. Carroll, B. Chandramouli and R. M. Kamens, <lb/>Particle growth by acid-catalyzed heterogeneous reactions <lb/>of organic carbonyls on preexisting aerosols, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 2003, 37(17), 3828-3837, DOI: 10.1021/es021005u. <lb/>70 J. Zhao, N. P. Levitt, R. Zhang and J. Chen, Heterogeneous <lb/>reactions of methylglyoxal in acidic media: implications <lb/>for secondary organic aerosol formation, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 2006, 40(24), 7682-7687, DOI: 10.1021/es060610k. <lb/>71 M. E. Gomez, Y. Lin, S. Guo and R. Zhang, Heterogeneous <lb/>chemistry of glyoxal on acidic solutions. an <lb/>oligomerization pathway for secondary organic aerosol <lb/>formation, J. Phys. Chem. A, 2015, 119(19), 4457-4463, <lb/>DOI: 10.1021/jp509916r. <lb/>72 C.-Y. Wang, S. Jiang, Z.-Q. Wang, Y.-R. Liu, H. Wen, <lb/>T. Huang, Y.-J. Han and W. Huang, Can formaldehyde <lb/>contribute to atmospheric new particle formation from <lb/>sulfuric acid and water?, Atmos. Environ., 2019, 201, 323-<lb/>333, DOI: 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2018.12.057. <lb/>73 R. J. Weber, P. H. McMurry, F. L. Eisele and D. J. Tanner, <lb/>Measurement of expected nucleation precursor species <lb/>and 3-500-Nm diameter particles at mauna loa <lb/>observatory, Hawaii, J. Atmos. Sci., 1995, 52(12), 2242-<lb/>2257, <lb/>DOI: <lb/>10.1175/1520-0469(1995) <lb/>052&lt;2242:MOENPS&gt;2.0.CO;2. <lb/>74 J. Merikanto, J. Duplissy, A. Määttänen, H. Henschel, <lb/>N. M. Donahue, D. Brus, S. Schobesberger, M. Kulmala <lb/>and H. Vehkamäki, Effect of ions on sulfuric acid-water <lb/>binary particle formation: 1. theory for kinetic-and <lb/>nucleation-type particle formation and atmospheric <lb/>implications: binary particle formation theory, J. Geophys. <lb/>Res. Atmos., 2016, 121(4), 1736-1751, DOI: 10.1002/ <lb/>2015JD023538. <lb/>75 J. Kirkby, J. Curtius, J. Almeida, E. Dunne, J. Duplissy, <lb/>S. Ehrhart, A. Franchin, S. Gagné, L. Ickes, A. Kürten, <lb/>A. Kupc, A. Metzger, F. Riccobono, L. Rondo, <lb/>S. Schobesberger, G. Tsagkogeorgas, D. Wimmer, <lb/>A. Amorim, F. Bianchi, M. Breitenlechner, A. David, <lb/>J. Dommen, A. Downard, M. Ehn, R. C. Flagan, S. Haider, <lb/>A. Hansel, D. Hauser, W. Jud, H. Junninen, F. Kreissl, <lb/>A. Kvashin, A. Laaksonen, K. Lehtipalo, J. Lima, <lb/>E. R. Lovejoy, V. Makhmutov, S. Mathot, J. Mikkilä, <lb/>P. Minginette, S. Mogo, T. Nieminen, A. Onnela, <lb/>P. Pereira, T. Petäjä, R. Schnitzhofer, J. H. Seinfeld, <lb/>M. Sipilä, Y. Stozhkov, F. Stratmann, A. Tomé, <lb/>J. Vanhanen, Y. Viisanen, A. Vrtala, P. E. Wagner, <lb/>H. Walther, E. Weingartner, H. Wex, P. M. Winkler, <lb/>K. S. Carslaw, D. R. Worsnop, U. Baltensperger and <lb/>M. Kulmala, Role of sulphuric acid, ammonia and <lb/>galactic cosmic rays in atmospheric aerosol nucleation, <lb/>Nature, 2011, 476(7361), 429-433, DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>nature10343. <lb/>76 J. Almeida, S. Schobesberger, A. Kürten, I. K. Ortega, <lb/>O. Kupiainen-Määttä, A. P. Praplan, A. Adamov, <lb/>A. Amorim, F. Bianchi, M. Breitenlechner, A. David, <lb/>J. Dommen, N. M. Donahue, A. Downard, E. Dunne, <lb/>J. Duplissy, S. Ehrhart, R. C. Flagan, A. Franchin, <lb/>R. Guida, J. Hakala, A. Hansel, M. Heinritzi, H. Henschel, <lb/>T. Jokinen, H. Junninen, M. Kajos, J. Kangasluoma, <lb/>H. Keskinen, A. Kupc, T. Kurtén, A. N. Kvashin, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13333 <lb/></page>
    
            <note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>A. Laaksonen, K. Lehtipalo, M. Leiminger, J. Leppä, <lb/>V. Loukonen, V. Makhmutov, S. Mathot, M. J. McGrath, <lb/>T. Nieminen, T. Olenius, A. Onnela, T. Petäjä, <lb/>F. Riccobono, I. Riipinen, M. Rissanen, L. Rondo, <lb/>T. Ruuskanen, F. D. Santos, N. Sarnela, S. Schallhart, <lb/>R. Schnitzhofer, J. H. Seinfeld, M. Simon, M. Sipilä, <lb/>Y. Stozhkov, F. Stratmann, A. Tomé, J. Tröstl, <lb/>G. Tsagkogeorgas, P. Vaattovaara, Y. Viisanen, <lb/>A. Virtanen, A. Vrtala, P. E. Wagner, E. Weingartner, <lb/>H. Wex, C. Williamson, D. Wimmer, P. Ye, T. Yli-Juuti, <lb/>K. S. Carslaw, M. Kulmala, J. Curtius, U. Baltensperger, <lb/>D. R. Worsnop, H. Vehkamäki and J. Kirkby, Molecular <lb/>understanding of sulphuric acid-amine particle <lb/>nucleation in the atmosphere, Nature, 2013, 502(7471), <lb/>359-363, DOI: 10.1038/nature12663. <lb/>77 O. Kupiainen, I. K. Ortega, T. Kurtén and H. Vehkamäki, <lb/>Amine substitution into sulfuric acid -ammonia clusters, <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 2012, 12(8), 3591-3599, DOI: 10.5194/ <lb/>acp-12-3591-2012. <lb/>78 M. Liu, N. Myllys, Y. Han, Z. Wang, L. Chen, W. Liu and <lb/>J. Xu, Microscopic insights into the formation of <lb/>methanesulfonic acid-methylamine-ammonia particles <lb/>under acid-rich conditions, Front. Ecol. Evol., 2022, 10, <lb/>875585, DOI: 10.3389/fevo.2022.875585/full. <lb/>79 V. Perraud, J. Xu, R. B. Gerber and B. J. Finlayson-Pitts, <lb/>Integrated experimental and theoretical approach to <lb/>probe the synergistic effect of ammonia in <lb/>methanesulfonic acid reactions with small alkylamines, <lb/>Environ. Sci.: Processes Impacts, 2020, 22(2), 305-328, DOI: <lb/>10.1039/C9EM00431A. <lb/>80 Nucleophilic Addition Reaction -General Mechanism, <lb/>Examples. <lb/>https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/ <lb/>Introductory_Chemistry/ <lb/>Introduction_to_Organic_and_Biochemistry_(Malik)/04% <lb/>3A_Organic_reactions/4.06% <lb/>3A_Nucleophilic_Addition_Reactions#:∼:text=The% <lb/>20addition%20of%20alcohol%20(R,as%20in%20the% <lb/>20following%20example. <lb/>81 19.4: Nucleophilic Addition Reactions of Aldehydes and <lb/>Ketones. Chemistry LibreTexts. https://chem.libretexts.org/ <lb/>Bookshelves/Organic_Chemistry/ <lb/>Organic_Chemistry_(McMurry)/19% <lb/>3A_Aldehydes_and_Ketones-<lb/>_Nucleophilic_Addition_Reactions/19.04% <lb/>3A_Nucleophilic_Addition_Reactions_of_ <lb/>Aldehydes_and_Ketones. <lb/>82 J. Zhang and M. Dolg, ABCluster: the articial bee colony <lb/>algorithm for cluster global optimization, Phys. Chem. <lb/>Chem. Phys., 2015, 17, 24173-24181, DOI: 10.1039/ <lb/>c5cp04060d. <lb/>83 J. Zhang and M. Dolg, Global optimization of clusters of <lb/>rigid molecules using the articial bee colony algorithm, <lb/>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys., 2016, 18, 3003-3010, DOI: <lb/>10.1039/c5cp04060d. <lb/>84 D. Karaboga, An Idea Based on Honey Bee Swarm for <lb/>Numerical Optimization, 2005. <lb/>85 J. Stewart, Optimization of parameters for semiempirical <lb/>methods v: modication of NDDO approximations and <lb/>application to 70 elements, J. Mol. Model., 2007, 13(12), <lb/>1173-1213, DOI: 10.1007/s00894-007-0233-4. <lb/>86 J. Hostaš, J. Řezáč and P. Hobza, On the performance of the <lb/>semiempirical quantum mechanical PM6 and PM7 <lb/>methods for noncovalent interactions, Chem. Phys. Lett., <lb/>2013, 568-569, 161-166, DOI: 10.1016/j.cplett.2013.02.069. <lb/>87 A. Ning and X. Zhang, The synergistic effects of <lb/>methanesulfonic acid (MSA) and methanesulnic acid <lb/>(MSIA) on marine new particle formation, Atmos. Environ., <lb/>2022, 269, 118826, DOI: 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2021.118826. <lb/>88 D. Chen, W. Wang, D. Li and W. Wang, Atmospheric <lb/>implication of synergy in methanesulfonic acid-base <lb/>trimers: a theoretical investigation, RSC Adv., 2020, 10(9), <lb/>5173-5182, DOI: 10.1039/C9RA08760E. <lb/>89 N. Myllys, D. Myers, S. Chee and J. N. Smith, Molecular <lb/>properties affecting the hydration of acid-base clusters, <lb/>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys., 2021, 23(23), 13106-13114, DOI: <lb/>10.1039/D1CP01704G. <lb/>90 J. P. Perdew, J. A. Chevary, S. H. Vosko, K. A. Jackson, <lb/>M. R. Pederson, D. J. Singh and C. Fiolhais, Atoms, <lb/>molecules, solids, and surfaces: applications of the <lb/>generalized gradient approximation for exchange and <lb/>correlation, Phys. Rev. B: Condens. Matter Mater. Phys., <lb/>1992, 46(11), 6671-6687, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevB.46.6671. <lb/>91 R. G. Parr and Y. Weitao, Density-Functional Theory of Atoms <lb/>and Molecules, Oxford University Press, 1995. DOI: 10.1093/ <lb/>oso/9780195092769.001.0001. <lb/>92 A. D. Becke, Density-functional thermochemistry. III. The <lb/>role of exact exchange, J. Chem. Phys., 1993, 98(7), 5648-<lb/>5652, DOI: 10.1063/1.464913. <lb/>93 S. Grimme, J. Antony, S. Ehrlich and H. Krieg, A consistent <lb/>and accurate ab initio parametrization of density functional <lb/>dispersion correction (DFT-D) for the 94 elements H-Pu, J. <lb/>Chem. Phys., 2010, 132(15), 154104, DOI: 10.1063/ <lb/>1.3382344. <lb/>94 M. J. Frisch, M. Head-Gordon and J. A. Pople, A direct MP2 <lb/>gradient method, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1990, 166(3), 275-280, <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/0009-2614(90)80029-D. <lb/>95 M. Head-Gordon, J. A. Pople and M. J. Frisch, MP2 energy <lb/>evaluation by direct methods, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1988, <lb/>153(6), 503-506, DOI: 10.1016/0009-2614(88)85250-3. <lb/>96 M. J. Frisch, M. Head-Gordon and J. A. Pople, Semi-direct <lb/>algorithms for the MP2 energy and gradient, Chem. Phys. <lb/>Lett., 1990, 166(3), 281-289, DOI: 10.1016/0009-2614(90) <lb/>80030-H. <lb/>97 J. P. Foster and F. Weinhold, Natural hybrid orbitals, J. Am. <lb/>Chem. Soc., 1980, 102(24), 7211-7218, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>ja00544a007. <lb/>98 A. E. Reed and F. Weinhold, Natural bond orbital analysis <lb/>of near-hartree-fock water dimer, J. Chem. Phys., 1983, <lb/>78(6), 4066-4073, DOI: 10.1063/1.445134. <lb/>99 M. J. Frisch, G. W. Trucks, H. B. Schlegel, G. E. Scuseria, <lb/>M. A. Robb, and J. R. Cheeseman. Gaussian 16, Revision <lb/>A.03, <lb/>Gaussian, <lb/>Inc, <lb/>Wallingford, <lb/>CT, <lb/>https:// <lb/>gaussian.com/citation_a03/, accessed 21 January 2022. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13334</page>
    
            <note place="footnote">| RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">RSC Advances <lb/>Paper <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>100 T. Takayanagi, T. Yoshikawa, A. Kakizaki, M. Shiga and <lb/>M. Tachikawa, Molecular dynamics simulations of small <lb/>glycine-(H 2 O) n (N=2-7) clusters on semiempirical PM6 <lb/>potential energy surfaces, J. Mol. Struct. Theochem, 2008, <lb/>869(1-3), 29-36, DOI: 10.1016/j.theochem.2008.08.016. <lb/>101 R. D. Tosso, S. A. Andujar, L. Gutierrez, E. Angelina, <lb/>R. Rodríguez, M. Nogueras, H. Baldoni, F. D. Suvire, <lb/>J. Cobo and R. D. Enriz, Molecular modeling study of <lb/>dihydrofolate reductase inhibitors. molecular dynamics <lb/>simulations, quantum mechanical calculations, and <lb/>experimental corroboration, J. Chem. Inf. Model., 2013, <lb/>53(8), 2018-2032, DOI: 10.1021/ci400178h. <lb/>102 M. Wang, Y. Mei and U. Ryde, Host-guest relative binding <lb/>affinities at density-functional theory level from <lb/>semiempirical molecular dynamics simulations, J. Chem. <lb/>Theory Comput., 2019, 15(4), 2659-2671, DOI: 10.1021/ <lb/>acs.jctc.8b01280. <lb/>103 J. VandeVondele, M. Krack, F. Mohamed, M. Parrinello, <lb/>T. Chassaing and J. Hutter, Quickstep: fast and accurate <lb/>density functional calculations using a mixed Gaussian <lb/>and plane waves approach, Comput. Phys. Commun., 2005, <lb/>167(2), 103-128, DOI: 10.1016/j.cpc.2004.12.014. <lb/>104 S. Nosé, A unied formulation of the constant temperature <lb/>molecular dynamics methods, J. Chem. Phys., 1984, 81(1), <lb/>511-519, DOI: 10.1063/1.447334. <lb/>105 W. G. Hoover, Canonical dynamics: equilibrium phase-<lb/>space distributions, Phys. Rev. A: At., Mol., Opt. Phys., <lb/>1985, 31(3), 1695-1697, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.31.1695. <lb/>106 E. R. Johnson, S. Keinan, P. Mori-Sanchez, J. Contreras-<lb/>Garcia, A. J. Cohen and W. Yang, Revealing noncovalent <lb/>interactions, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2010, 132(18), 6498, DOI: <lb/>10.1021/ja100936w. <lb/>107 E. R. Johnson, S. Keinan, P. Mori-Sánchez, J. Contreras-<lb/>García, A. J. Cohen and W. Yang, Revealing noncovalent <lb/>interactions, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2010, 132(18), 6498-6506, <lb/>DOI: 10.1021/ja100936w. <lb/>108 W. Humphrey, A. Dalke and K. Schulten, VMD: visual <lb/>molecular dynamics, J. Mol. Graphics, 1996, 14(1), 33-38, <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/0263-7855(96)00018-5. <lb/>109 University of Illinois, Visual Molecular Dynamics, 2014. <lb/>110 19.5: Nucleophilic Addition of Water -Hydration. Chemistry <lb/>LibreTexts, <lb/>https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/ <lb/>Organic_Chemistry/Organic_Chemistry_(McMurry)/19% <lb/>3A_Aldehydes_and_Ketones-<lb/>_Nucleophilic_Addition_Reactions/19.05% <lb/>3A_Nucleophilic_Addition_of_Water-_Hydration. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Author(s). Published by the Royal Society of Chemistry <lb/>RSC Adv., 2024, 14, 13321-13335 | </note>
    
            <page>13335 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Paper <lb/>RSC Advances <lb/>Open Access Article. Published on 01 May 2024. Downloaded on 9/8/2025 2:35:31 PM. <lb/>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported Licence. <lb/>View Article Online </note>

	</text>
</TEI>