<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-14T11:48:41.211Z">11/14/2025 11:48:41 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.1371_journal.pone.0293484</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-14T11:48:26.026496Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-14T11:48:26.026496Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Transformation of cereal grains: Botanical and <lb/>chemical analysis of food residues encrusted <lb/>on pottery from the Funnel Beaker settlement <lb/>of Oldenburg LA 77, northern Germany <lb/>Lucy Kubiak-Martens ID <lb/>1☯ <lb/>*, Tania F. M. Oudemans 2☯ , Jan Piet Brozio 3 ‡ , <lb/>Dragana Filipović ID <lb/>3 ‡ , Johannes Mu ¨ller 3 , Wiebke Kirleis 3 ‡ <lb/>1 BIAX Biological Archaeology &amp; Environmental Reconstruction, Zaandam, The Netherlands, 2 Kenaz <lb/>Consult &amp; Laboratory, Berlin, Germany, 3 Institute for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Archaeology, Kiel <lb/>University, Kiel, Germany <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> ‡ JPB, DF and WK also contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* kubiak@biax.nl <lb/>Abstract <lb/>An integrated botanical and chemical approach is used to study surface residues on Funnel <lb/>Beaker ceramics from the site of Oldenburg LA 77, in northern Germany. Organic residues <lb/>were discovered adhering to fragments of thick-walled, undecorated ceramic vessels (n = 19) <lb/>and ceramic discs (n = 2). The surface residues were studied using scanning electron micros-<lb/>copy (SEM), to examine remains of cereals and other plant tissues that survived food prepara-<lb/>tion and cooking, and using attenuated total reflectance Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy <lb/>(ATR-FTIR) and direct time-resolved mass spectrometry (DTMS), to chemically identify specific <lb/>food components. The SEM results show a reoccurring presence of cereal grain (emmer and <lb/>barley) and one case of co-occurrence of emmer and fat-hen seeds. The SEM evidence for the <lb/>use of sprouted emmer grain and milk-ripe barley from the Oldenburg residues greatly <lb/>enhances our understanding of Neolithic foodways in northwestern Europe. The ATR-FTIR <lb/>results showed that roughly a third of the surface residues contain traces of the original foods <lb/>prepared or processed and DTMS results confirm that most of the residues primarily contain <lb/>polysaccharides and a minimal amount of plant protein and that they lack lipids. Only one resi-<lb/>due presents minor indications for a (partly) animal origin. The ceramic vessels were thus used <lb/>almost exclusively for the processing or cooking of cereal grains. This study offers an intimate <lb/>view of the cuisine and cooking practices (and in some cases their seasonal timing) in an early <lb/>agricultural village located in a marginal farming region on the south coast of the Baltic Sea. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The subsistence economy of the first farmers in northern Europe, the Funnel Beaker groups, <lb/>has been intensively studied during the past two decades [1-14]. It is well known, which culti-<lb/>vated plants and domestic animals were used and regional variations have been identified. <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/>1 / 38 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Kubiak-Martens L, Oudemans TFM, <lb/>Brozio JP, Filipović D, Mu ¨ller J, Kirleis W (2024) <lb/>Transformation of cereal grains: Botanical and <lb/>chemical analysis of food residues encrusted on <lb/>pottery from the Funnel Beaker settlement of <lb/>Oldenburg LA 77, northern Germany. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(1): e0296986. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0296986 <lb/>Editor: John P. Hart, New York State Museum, <lb/>UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: June 7, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 22, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 19, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Kubiak-Martens et al. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/>Funding: The authors Johannes Mu ¨ller (JM) and <lb/>Wiebke Kirleis (WK) were both supported through <lb/>funds by the German Research Foundation <lb/>(Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG) within <lb/>the two programs: A) Collaborative Research <lb/>Centre 1266 &apos;Scales of Transformation -Human-<lb/></front>

			<body>Although the study of stable isotopes has provided knowledge about cultivation practices [10-<lb/>12], animal mobility [13], and food pathways [14], less is known about what items found their <lb/>way into cooking vessels and how daily meals were prepared. The first efforts to look into <lb/>cooking vessels with Baltic provenience were undertaken on sherds from the Mesolithic-Neo-<lb/>lithic (Ertebølle-Funnel Beaker) transitional sites of Neustadt, in Holstein, and Aakonge and <lb/>Stenø, in Denmark [15-17]. <lb/>Recent developments in the application of high-resolution microscopy applied in archaeo-<lb/>botany have brought additional advances in analysis of the actual remains of processed food or <lb/>cooked meals from charred objects and food residues encrusted on the surface of ceramic ves-<lb/>sels [18-21]. These applications, especially when combined with the chemical analysis of sur-<lb/>face residues, redress the imbalance that resulted from the method-driven focus in biomarker <lb/>research on animal lipids, to reveal the importance of the plant component in ancient cuisine. <lb/>In this study, surface residues are analysed using an integrated botanical and chemical <lb/>approach to understand how meals were prepared in the cooking vessels recovered from the <lb/>Middle Neolithic settlement of Oldenburg LA 77, which is one of several Neolithic sites located <lb/>in the Oldenburger Graben microregion in northeastern Schleswig-Holstein, Germany (Fig <lb/>1). The site is attributed to the Funnel Beaker (German: Trichterbecher, or TRB) groups and <lb/>dates to 3270-2920 cal. BCE. With the agglomeration of people in c. 40 houses at the peak of <lb/>its occupation, it is one of the oldest villages in Schleswig-Holstein and illustrates the transfor-<lb/>mation of social life in the Middle Neolithic, from single farmsteads to a village community. <lb/>Oldenburg LA 77 was a fully agrarian settlement, with a typical Funnel Beaker economy, <lb/>Fig 1. Map showing the location of Oldenburg LA 77 within the Oldenburger Graben area. Figure: J.P. Brozio. <lb/>Edited by D. Filipović from [24] under the CC BY license 4.0, with permission from the authors. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<front>Environmental Interaction in Prehistoric and <lb/>Archaic Societies&apos;, Project number 290391021 -<lb/>SFB 1266) and B) Cluster of Excellence &apos;ROOTS -<lb/>Social, Environmental, and Cultural Connectivity in <lb/>Past Societies&apos; (project ref. 390870439-EXC <lb/>2150). The funders had no role in study design, <lb/>data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or <lb/>preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>comprising distinctive cultivation practices for cereals, such as emmer (Triticum dicoccum) <lb/>and naked barley (Hordeum vulgare var. nudum); the tending of livestock; hunting; fishing; <lb/>and the gathering of wild plants [1, 6, 10]. <lb/>An earlier study of absorbed lipids that were preserved inside the ceramic matrix of a num-<lb/>ber of sherds from Oldenburg LA 77 gave a first insight into cooking practices at Oldenburg <lb/>LA 77 [22]. Weber and colleagues combined biomarker analysis and isotope ratio information <lb/>to conclude that dairy products and plant oils had been prepared in the vessels studied. This <lb/>paper focuses on residues encrusted on the surface of ceramic vessels because they can provide <lb/>more detailed and more direct information about the vessel use than the study of lipids <lb/>absorbed into the ceramic matrix which tends to show an overrepresentation of animal fat and <lb/>often miss the plant element. The first benefit of surface crusts over absorbed lipids is that sur-<lb/>face residues represent the last, or one of the last, use-phases of the vessel, whereas absorbed <lb/>lipids represent the cumulative deposition over the entire use-life of a vessel. The second bene-<lb/>fit is that surface residues can be studied for a full range of food components (e.g., proteins, lip-<lb/>ids, and polysaccharides such as starches and sugars), as well as for any remaining small <lb/>fragments of plant and or animal tissue, thus yielding much more detailed information about <lb/>food sources. The third benefit is that the range of detectable food components is not limited <lb/>to those containing lipids, making many plant sources more visible. <lb/>In the case of crops, food preparation practices represent the culmination of the long and <lb/>laborious production process that transforms the sown grain into a desired meal. This trans-<lb/>formation is largely elusive in the archaeological record and is usually reconstructed based on <lb/>indirect evidence, such as food processing tools. Studying food crusts can provide valuable <lb/>information about the original vessel contents. Because they are found firmly attached to either <lb/>the interior or the exterior surface of ceramics, they form a direct source of information about <lb/>food choices, the preparation and processing of food before cooking, the mixing of foods, and <lb/>even the use of different types of pots for similar or, indeed, different purposes. <lb/>The application of an integrated botanical and chemical approach to surface residue studies <lb/>has been proven to render a more complete understanding of the cooking practices and food <lb/>sources used in prehistoric times [20, 21, 23]. The use of scanning electron microscopy (SEM) <lb/>enables the observation and identification of various plant particles, and some animal remains <lb/>that survived the processes of food preparation and cooking. The high-resolution microscopic <lb/>analysis also enables the taxonomic identification of these remains. The plant particles are <lb/>often minute fragments of grain tissue (e.g., pericarp or aleurone); cereal light chaff (including <lb/>fragments of palleas, lemmas, and glumes); remains of seeds; and vegetative plant parts, <lb/>whereas the animal remains are often small bone fragments or fish scales. The chemical <lb/>approach combines two types of analysis: attenuated total reflection-Fourier-transform infra-<lb/>red spectroscopy (ATR-FTIR), for a first general identification of the nature of the residues <lb/>and their state of preservation, with direct time-resolved mass spectrometry (DTMS), a tech-<lb/>nique that makes it possible to further characterise the entire organic composition of the <lb/>charred residue without prior treatment, including volatile, extractable compounds and solid, <lb/>non-extractable compounds. <lb/>The detection of any organic amorphous remains -that cannot be analysed by other means <lb/>-helps identify the natural origin of the surviving residues and explain their presence in terms <lb/>of human behavior in the past. <lb/>The site and its economy <lb/>The Funnel Beaker settlement site of Oldenburg LA 77. The settlement site of Olden-<lb/>burg LA 77, dated to 3270-2920 cal BCE, is situated on a dune-like peninsula of ca. 3 ha in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>western part of a low-lying wetland area on the southern Baltic coast, the so-called Oldenbur-<lb/>ger Graben (Fig 1). Initially a fjord, the area transformed into a lagoon at the turn of the 4th to <lb/>the 3rd millennium BCE [1, 24-26]. The settlement was part of a larger settlement system that <lb/>used (former) islands and peninsulae as residential areas and land along the boundaries of the <lb/>wetlands as agricultural land. Associated burial sites are located on the adjacent moraine ridges <lb/>to the south and north of the Oldenburger Graben [1, 2, 24-27]. <lb/>The archaeological features in the excavated parts of the site indicate the presence of five <lb/>&apos;houses&apos; and several &apos;huts&apos; [1]. Although the houses cluster on higher terrain, remains of <lb/>domestic origin in various states of preservation have been found in a cultural layer extending <lb/>into the wetlands at the south shore of the Neolithic settlement. Some of these artefacts and <lb/>ecofacts are secondary deposits. Extensive 14 C AMS dating of the site, in combination with the <lb/>seriation of ceramics following the domestic pottery typology in the southern range of the Fun-<lb/>nel Beaker North Group for the period 3270-2920 cal BCE [1, 27], distinguished four occupa-<lb/>tion phases: Oldenburg 1: 3270-3110 cal BCE; Oldenburg 2: 3110-3020 cal BCE; Oldenburg <lb/>3A: 3020-2990 cal BCE; and Oldenburg 3B: 2990-2920 cal BCE. <lb/>Evidence of plant use at the Funnel Beaker settlement site of Oldenburg LA 77. Previ-<lb/>ous insights into plant use at Oldenburg LA 77 came from two classes of archaeological materi-<lb/>als: macro-and microbotanical remains. Trenches 1, 8, and 10 (Fig 2) yielded large amounts of <lb/>well-preserved macroscopic plant remains, and these have been studied in detail [1, 6]. The <lb/>vast majority of this material was charred or partially charred. Uncharred (in this case water-<lb/>logged) plant remains were primarily found in the cultural deposits in the wetland area at the <lb/>southern edge of the peninsula. <lb/>Fig 2. The reconstructed settlement area (dark grey shading) of Oldenburg LA 77, showing the location of the trenches excavated in 2009-<lb/>2012 (white rectangular areas). Trenches 1 and 2 extended into the wetland area (light grey shading) at the southern edge of the peninsula. <lb/>Figure: K. Winter; map base: DGM ©LVermGeo SH. Reprinted from [1, Abb. 13], with permission from the copyright holders; original © 2016 by <lb/>Institute for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Archaeology, Kiel University and author. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Archaeobotanical analysis revealed the presence of cultivated and wild taxa that are com-<lb/>monly part of the plant assemblage from Funnel Beaker sites. The crop plants primarily consist <lb/>of two cereals, namely naked barley and emmer. Einkorn (T. monococcum) and free-threshing <lb/>wheat (T. aestivum/durum/turgidum) are present in minute amounts. Stable isotopic analysis <lb/>on some of the charred grains revealed distinct cultivation strategies for the different cereals <lb/>[10]. Single seeds of flax (Linum usitatissimum) and opium poppy (Papaver somniferum) were <lb/>also identified, as were remains of edible wild plants, not only nuts and fruits from common <lb/>gathered plants, such as crab apple and hazel but also fat-hen, small-seeded grasses and sedges <lb/>[1, 4, 6, 10]. <lb/>Evidence of animal use at the Funnel Beaker settlement site of Oldenburg LA77. <lb/>Zooarchaeological analysis has so far revealed a dominance of the remains of domestic ani-<lb/>mals, with cattle and pig more frequent than sheep, goat and dog. The remains of wild animals <lb/>show the presence of large and small mammals (deer, elk, hare), fish and birds [1, 2]. The ratios <lb/>of domestic to wild animals, as well as the ratios among the varied species of domestic animals, <lb/>remain constant throughout the duration of the settlement, pointing to continuity in animal <lb/>husbandry. The ratios of individual species of wild animals, however, vary slightly among dif-<lb/>ferent phases of occupation, possibly indicating changes in their availability. The presence of <lb/>remains of large animals -cattle, deer, elk -suggests that the butchering and consumption <lb/>were practiced on-site and perhaps by a larger group of people [1, 2]. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Potsherds with food crusts <lb/>After excavation, the ceramics from the site had been air-dried and then placed in plastic bags. <lb/>Following visual inspection of the pottery assemblage, 21 pottery fragments with residues <lb/>encrusted on their surface were selected for the present study (Table 1 and S1 Fig). The sherds <lb/>come mainly from undecorated vessels with a conical top (OLD 03, 16 and 21) or cylindrical <lb/>rim (OLD 02, 07 and 10). All vessel sherds originate from large vessels, with thick walls, made <lb/>of coarse to very coarse clay mixed with crushed granite. The range of colours suggests differ-<lb/>ent firing conditions (possibly including secondary burning) and different clay types. Two <lb/>fragments (OLD 08 and 15) were originally part of ceramic discs (Tonscheiben) and have deco-<lb/>ration in the form of a row of fingertip and fingernail impressions along their edges (S1 Fig). <lb/>The function of these ceramic discs has not been resolved, even though they are regularly <lb/>recovered from prehistoric sites in Europe [27]. One suggested use for these ceramic discs is <lb/>the baking of flatbread; hence they are also referred to in German as Backteller (baking plates). <lb/>They are also thought to have served as lids and serving plates [27, 28]. <lb/>Most of the analysed potsherds (OLD 01-07, 09, 11, 12, 15, 16 and 18-20) come from the <lb/>deposits in the southernmost parts of trenches 1 and 2 (Fig 3), the formerly submerged zone <lb/>where cultural detritus accumulated during the entire timespan of the settlement, that is, ca. <lb/>3270-2920 BCE (there are also traces of younger depositions in the colluvium). It is, therefore, <lb/>difficult to associate these fragments with a specific settlement phase. The two ceramic disc <lb/>fragments (OLD 08 and 15) can be typo-chronologically assigned to the Nordic Middle Neo-<lb/>lithic I-V, that is, 3300-2800 BCE. Two of the vessel sherds (OLD 14 and 17) were found in <lb/>the use-horizon and another (OLD 13) was found in a posthole; neither context can be dated <lb/>more precisely than the general period of settlement occupation, that is, 3270-2920 cal BCE. <lb/>Sherd OLD 10 was discovered in a pit assigned to a group of features most probably originat-<lb/>ing from the Oldenburg 2/3A phase, that is, 3110-2990 cal BCE. <lb/>Subsamples of food crust removed from three of the potsherds recovered from the collu-<lb/>vium (OLD 04, 06 and 11) were submitted for radiocarbon dating. The results, as well as those <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Details of Oldenburg LA 77 ceramic fragments from which samples of surface residue were taken for botanical and chemical analyses. frag. = fragment; <lb/>undecor. = undecorated. <lb/>Sample <lb/>Identifier <lb/>ALSH <lb/>Inventory <lb/>Number <lb/>Find <lb/>Number <lb/>Find Context Type of Ceramic <lb/>Object <lb/>Sampling <lb/>Location <lb/>Residue Description <lb/>SEM FTIR DTMS Date Range Fig <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3082 <lb/>232 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, medium <lb/>layer, 1-2 mm thick, multiple <lb/>patches subsampled <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3087 <lb/>309 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Cylindrical rim <lb/>frag. of undecor. <lb/>vessel <lb/>Exterior <lb/>rim <lb/>Black, thin residue, thin/ <lb/>medium layer, &lt;1 mm thick <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3096 <lb/>423 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Conical top frag. <lb/>of undecorated <lb/>vessel <lb/>Exterior <lb/>rim <lb/>Black residue, medium/thick <lb/>layer, 1-2 mm thick <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3099 <lb/>154 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Black residue, medium layer, <lb/>1-2 mm thick <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3340-2937 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>(AMS-date <lb/>on food <lb/>crust) <lb/>4 <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.3093 <lb/>382 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Exterior <lb/>rim <lb/>Black residue, 1-2 mm thick <lb/>layer <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>7 <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3101 <lb/>546 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Black residue, medium layer, <lb/>1-2 mm thick <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3321-2914 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>(AMS-date <lb/>on food <lb/>crust) <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3094 <lb/>197 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Cylindrical rim <lb/>frag. of undecor. <lb/>vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>rim <lb/>Thin brown and white spots, <lb/>thin/medium layer, &lt;1 mm <lb/>thick <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3328-2098 <lb/>cal BCE; <lb/>median 3067 <lb/>cal BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7915 <lb/>2001 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Ceramic disk <lb/>(Tonscheibe) <lb/>On top of <lb/>disc <lb/>Thin/fine black residue, &lt;1 mm <lb/>thick (sherd sampled earlier for <lb/>absorbed residue analysis) <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7907 <lb/>2158 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, thick <lb/>layer, 3 mm <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>12 <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8108 <lb/>Ge-112 <lb/>Pit <lb/>Cylindrical rim <lb/>frag. of undecor. <lb/>vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>rim and <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, thick <lb/>layer, 3-4 mm <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>16 <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8096 <lb/>2109-01 Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, thick <lb/>layer, 3-4 mm <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3337-2935 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>(AMS-date <lb/>on food <lb/>crust) <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8096 <lb/>2109-02 Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, thick <lb/>layer, 3-4 mm <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3073 <lb/>5007 <lb/>Posthole <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Black residue, thin layer, 1 mm no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3083 <lb/>147 <lb/>Occupation <lb/>horizon/layer <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Exterior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, medium <lb/>layer, 1-2 mm thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3092 <lb/>308 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Ceramic disk <lb/>(Tonscheibe) <lb/>On top of <lb/>disc <lb/>Brown and white residue, less <lb/>than 1 mm thick (sherd sampled <lb/>earlier for absorbed residue <lb/>analysis) <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>yes <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3100 <lb/>334 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Undecor. vessel <lb/>with conical top <lb/>Exterior <lb/>rim <lb/>Thin brown-black residue, <lb/>shiny, &lt;1mm thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>for two emmer grains recovered from the occupation layer within trench 1, are presented in S2 <lb/>Fig and S1 Table. <lb/>Sample selection, pre-treatment and analyses <lb/>The ceramic assemblage was first examined with the naked eye to identify sherds with adher-<lb/>ing residues. This visual scan yielded 21 sherds, with residues on the interior (n = 13) or exte-<lb/>rior surface (n = 6) of the sherds or on the top surface (i.e. the face of sherd with fewer signs of <lb/>fire exposure) of the ceramic discs (n = 2). The surface residues on these 21 ceramic fragments <lb/>were then examined using a Leica microscope with incident light and a magnification range of <lb/>6-50× to describe the macroscopic characteristics of the residues and to determine the poten-<lb/>tial for further analyses. Some of the residues displayed exceptionally good preservation (see <lb/>examples in Figs 4 and 5). The residues varied in thickness from thin (c. 1 mm or less) to <lb/>medium (c. 2 mm) and (in most cases) thick (2-3 mm); in colour from black to brown; and <lb/>texture from solid to porous or spongy (see Table 1). <lb/>SEM analysis was performed on the residues from 10 of the 21 sherds (see Table 1) using <lb/>the JEOL JSM-6480L instrument at the Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden, the Nether-<lb/>lands. Multiple subsamples were taken from various parts of each surface residue, to ensure <lb/>wide coverage and account for potential variation in composition within the crust. Portions of <lb/>the residue were detached from each sherd and mounted on the SEM stubs using double-sided <lb/>carbon tape strips. The samples were sputter-coated with a layer of platinum-palladium <lb/>approximately 20 μm thick. The SEM images were captured at 30-750× magnification. The <lb/>analysis centered mainly on the lower surface of the residues, i.e., the surface that had been <lb/>attached to the pot, and on their interior; in several cases, the upper surface of the residues was <lb/>also examined. <lb/>Chemical analysis was performed on the residues from all 21 sherds (see Table 1). A combi-<lb/>nation of ATR-FTIR and DTMS was applied. FTIR is a rapid analytical technique that is useful <lb/>for the initial screening of solid samples, without necessitating further preparation. DTMS is a <lb/>more powerful technique, employed for detailed analysis of very small samples of complex <lb/>solid organic materials. DTMS makes it possible to characterise the complete organic composi-<lb/>tion of the material, including volatile, extractable compounds and solid, non-extractable <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Sample <lb/>Identifier <lb/>ALSH <lb/>Inventory <lb/>Number <lb/>Find <lb/>Number <lb/>Find Context Type of Ceramic <lb/>Object <lb/>Sampling <lb/>Location <lb/>Residue Description <lb/>SEM FTIR DTMS Date Range Fig <lb/>OLD 17 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3102 <lb/>95 <lb/>Occupation <lb/>horizon/layer <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>base <lb/>Light brown residue, &lt;1 mm <lb/>thick (sherd sampled earlier for <lb/>absorbed residue analysis) <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD 18 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7908 <lb/>2361 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Thin brown-black residue, &lt; 1 <lb/>mm thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD 19 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7908 <lb/>2361 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Exterior <lb/>wall <lb/>Black residue, medium layer, 2 <lb/>mm thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD 20 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7910 <lb/>2440 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Body frag. of <lb/>undecor. vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>wall <lb/>Brown-black residue, 2 mm <lb/>thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>OLD 21 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7912 <lb/>2088 <lb/>Submerged <lb/>zone, cultural <lb/>detritus <lb/>Conical top frag. <lb/>of undecorated <lb/>vessel <lb/>Interior <lb/>rim <lb/>Thin brown residue, &lt;1 mm <lb/>thick <lb/>no <lb/>yes <lb/>no <lb/>3270-2920 <lb/>cal. BCE <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>compounds. DTMS results provide information about a broad range of compounds, such as <lb/>lipids; waxes; terpenoids; saccharides; small peptides and protein fragments; and a broad range <lb/>of thermally stable, more or less condensed polymeric components (commonly called &apos;chars&apos; <lb/>or &apos;carbonised material&apos;). <lb/>Best practice involves taking samples after the removal of the outer surface of the residue, in <lb/>order to limit impregnation with soil material or possible post-excavation contamination. <lb/>However, due to the limited amount of residue present, it was not feasible to remove the outer <lb/>surface of all of the residues before sampling (see Table 1). <lb/>Instrumental conditions were as follows. In preparation for the FTIR measurements, ca. <lb/>10 μg from each sample was applied to the diamond window and flattened using the pressure <lb/>arm of the ATR unit. FTIR analysis was performed in the ATR modus of the Fourier-trans-<lb/>form infrared spectrometer (Thermo Scientific Nicolet iS05 equipped with an iD7 ATR unit). <lb/>The spectral resolution was 4 cm -1 and the spectral range was 4000-550 cm -1 . A total of 64 <lb/>scans were collected per measurement, and the scans were analysed using the OMNIS soft-<lb/>ware. The spectra were transformed using the functions &quot;ATR correct&quot;, &quot;Automatic baseline <lb/>Fig 3. Find location of the sampled potsherds in trenches 1 and 2 at Oldenburg LA 77. All sherds originate from the wetland area at the southern edge of the settlement. <lb/>Most come from a cultural layer, possibly as secondary deposits. One sherd originates from a posthole (OLD 13) and one from a settlement pit (OLD 10). Modified by J.P. <lb/>Brozio from [1, Abb. 13], with permission from the copyright holders; original © 2016 by Institute for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Archaeology, Kiel University and <lb/>author. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 4. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 04, binocular microscope images of the surface of the food crust, showing the upper <lb/>face of the surface residue (left) and detail of the area indicated by the white square in the left photo, showing grain particles <lb/>embedded in the residue matrix (right). Images: BIAX/W. van der Meer. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>correct&quot; and &quot;Transmission&quot; to result in the depicted spectra. Prior to the DTMS analysis, ca. <lb/>50 μg of each sample was suspended in 5 μL of DCM/methanol (1:1 vol.) and homogenised. A <lb/>small amount of the suspension was applied to the filament of the mass spectrometer, dried and <lb/>subsequently analysed. DTMS was performed using a ISQ 7000 Thermo Scientific single quad-<lb/>rupole mass spectrometer equipped with a Direct Exposure Probe (DEP) and combined with a <lb/>Thermo Scientific direct probe controller. Source temperature was 250˚C, the temperature pro-<lb/>grammed initial current was 0 mA (5 seconds) ramping to 1000 mA (with 10 mA/s) and held at <lb/>1000 mA for an additional 20 seconds. The following MS conditions were applied: the electron <lb/>ionisation energy was 18eV, the scanning range was m/z 45-100 and the scanning speed was 5 <lb/>scans per second. The data were collected and processed using the Xcalibur software. <lb/>Fig 5. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 06, binocular microscope images of the upper face of the surface residue, <lb/>showing overview (left) and detail of patches of cereal grain particles embedded in the residue matrix (right). Images: <lb/>BIAX/M. van Waijjen. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>The results on the analyses of the organic residues adhering to potsherds from undecorated <lb/>Funnel Beaker ceramic vessels from Oldenburg LA 77 are presented starting with the SEM <lb/>analysis, followed by the FTIR and DTMS analyses. <lb/>SEM analysis <lb/>Food crusts with emmer. The SEM analysis revealed the presence of emmer grain parti-<lb/>cles in five residues (OLD 01, 04, 06, 11 and 12 as illustrated in Figs 6-8), one of which also <lb/>Fig 6. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 04, SEM images of the internal microstructure of the food crust, showing grain <lb/>fragments with single-layered aleurone and starchy fused grain endosperm (in transverse view) (left) and single-<lb/>layered aleurone in top view (right), both indicating Triticum (here most likely emmer). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>contained fragments of fat-hen seeds (OLD 06 as illustrated in Fig 9). The most frequently <lb/>observed grain tissue was single-layered aleurone tissue. In cereal grains, aleurone is the outer-<lb/>most layer of the starchy endosperm, and it stores the main protein content [29]. It is notewor-<lb/>thy that single-layered aleurone is present in all of the cultivated cereals except for barley, <lb/>which develops multiple aleurone layers [30, 31]. In the food crusts from Oldenburg LA 77, <lb/>the single-layered aleurone was often accompanied by pericarp tissue. The characteristic pat-<lb/>tern of the transverse cells, in some cases accompanied by longitudinal cells (Fig 8 left), and <lb/>their association with the single-layered aleurone, narrowed the taxonomic identity down to <lb/>Triticum, most likely emmer grain. <lb/>Fig 7. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 01, SEM images of the internal microstructure of the food crust, showing single-<lb/>layered aleurone and pericarp tissue (left) and single-layered aleurone separated from the other grain tissues (right), <lb/>indicating Triticum (here most likely emmer). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>The absence of emmer chaff in the residues is noteworthy. In previous studies of food crusts <lb/>from various Neolithic sites in the Netherlands, emmer light chaff particles (most likely of the <lb/>lemma or palea) were frequently discovered in residues, suggesting that emmer must have <lb/>been used in cooking. The presence of light chaff in the food crusts was attributed to the fact <lb/>that despite dehusking of emmer, some light chaff would inevitably find its way into cooking <lb/>pots [21, 32, 33]. <lb/>The aleurone cells of the emmer grain particles in Oldenburg residues have conspicuously <lb/>thin walls. To determine the thickness of these cell walls, the R-STUDIO software was used to <lb/>manually measure the shortest distance connecting two adjacent aleurone cell lumina in the <lb/>Fig 8. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 06, SEM images of grain fragments embedded in residue matrix, showing <lb/>pericarp tissue (left) and single-layered aleurone accompanied by solid/fused (due to charring) grain starchy <lb/>endosperm (in transverse view, right) of Triticum (here most likely emmer). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>SEM images. The aleurone cell wall thickness in the residues was compared with that of 10 <lb/>emmer grains recovered from the settlement layer, one of which showed morphological evi-<lb/>dence for sprouting (Fig 10). The raw measurements are provided in S2 and S3 Tables; the <lb/>mean and median measurements are given in Table 2 and Fig 11. The mean and median values <lb/>for the aleurone cell wall thickness in emmer grains retrieved from the Oldenburg food crusts <lb/>are on average 1 μm (usually between 0.4 and 1.4 μm; in a few cases, a maximum thickness of <lb/>about 1.6 μm was noted). Similar measurements were obtained for emmer grains from the <lb/>occupation layer, which also display aleurone cell wall thinning. They show a mean and <lb/>median thickness of approximately 1 μm and a maximum thickness of 1.5 μm. In contrast, the <lb/>Fig 9. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 06, SEM images showing Chenopodium album seed fragments embedded in <lb/>residue matrix (left) and Chenopodium album seed fragment isolated from the matrix for SEM photography (right). <lb/>Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g009 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>aleurone cell walls from archaeological emmer grains obtained from prehistoric sites, which <lb/>are here used as a reference, show a thickness of c. 2 μm and, as such, do not display any mark-<lb/>ers for aleurone cell wall thinning [21]. The measurements obtained for aleurone cell wall <lb/>thickness from both the crusts and the grains from Oldenburg correspond well with those <lb/>reported for what are argued to be sprouted barley and emmer grains in earlier archaeobotani-<lb/>cal studies, in particular, those conducted by Heiss and colleagues in which they suggested a <lb/>threshold value for sprouted grains within the range of a mean/median of 1 μm for double cell <lb/>wall thickness, and maximum value not exceeding 1.5 μm [34]. <lb/>Several additional factors may affect the thickness of aleurone cell walls in archaeological <lb/>finds of grains, including infestation by mycelia fungi, endogenous enzyme activity, and <lb/>Fig 10. Oldenburg LA 77, charred emmer grain from the occupation layer, showing sprouted embryo <lb/>(LA77-SED28-sp1) (left) and single-layered aleurone (LA77-SED27-sp6) with thinned aleurone cell walls in grain with <lb/>no morphological evidence for sprouting (right). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g010 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>thermal degradation [34]. However, in the case of the Oldenburg specimens, there was no evi-<lb/>dence of a fungal infestation, such as the presence of hyphae or perforated cell walls. Further-<lb/>more, many of the aleurone cells retained their cell content, which was intact, thus showing no <lb/>evidence of endogenous enzyme activity. Extensive thermal degradation is also unlikely, as this <lb/>would require cooking or charring temperatures exceeding 300˚C [34], and in this study, the <lb/>good preservation of polysaccharides points to heating or cooking at relatively low tempera-<lb/>tures (see Chemical analyses section below). <lb/>Food crust with milk-ripe barley <lb/>The SEM analysis of two of the surface residues, from OLD 09 (Fig 12) and OLD 10 (Fig 13), <lb/>has revealed the presence of unripe or milk-ripe barley grains. The taxonomic identification <lb/>Table 2. Oldenburg LA 77, mean and median values for aleurone double cell wall thickness in food crusts (identifiers starting with &apos;OLD&apos;) and two emmer grains <lb/>from the settlement layer (identifiers starting with &apos;LA77&apos;). Data provided by BIAX/W. van der Meer. SD = standard deviation. <lb/>Sample Identifier <lb/>Mean (μm) <lb/>Median (μm) <lb/>SD <lb/>Number of Measurements <lb/>Tangential (top view) <lb/>OLD 04 (Find 154) <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>75 <lb/>OLD 06 (Find 546) <lb/>1.08 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>5 <lb/>OLD 09 (Find 2158) <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>397 <lb/>OLD 11 (Find 2109-1) <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>45 <lb/>OLD 12 (Find 2109-2) <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>174 <lb/>LA77-SED27-sp3 <lb/>0.89 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>119 <lb/>LA77-SED28-sp1 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>235 <lb/>Transverse (side view) <lb/>OLD 04 (Find 154) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>57 <lb/>OLD 06 (Find 546) <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>17 <lb/>LA77-SED28-sp2 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>14 <lb/>LA77-SED27-sp5 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>20 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.t002 <lb/>Fig 11. Oldenburg LA 77, aleurone double cell wall thicknesses in emmer grains (in μm) measured in food crusts, compared with the archaeological finds of <lb/>charred emmer grains used in this study as reference material. Figure: BIAX/W. van der Meer. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g011 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>process proved to be somewhat challenging due to the grains&apos; small dimensions, of approxi-<lb/>mately 4 mm x 1.4-1.8 mm (Figs 12 right and 14). However, the presence of multi-layered <lb/>aleurone has been taken as the definitive diagnostic feature for the determination of their taxo-<lb/>nomic identity (Figs 15-17). In residue OLD 10, as many as three distinct cell layers of the <lb/>aleurone tissue can be observed (Fig 17 right), clearly pointing to domesticated barley (Hor-<lb/>deum vulgare), which regularly develops a multi-layered aleurone, usually consisting of three <lb/>layers of cuboidal cells [35]. <lb/>In addition to the small size of the barley grains, the presence of chaff, most likely lemma or <lb/>palea, attached to the grains also suggests that they were harvested while the grain was not yet <lb/>fully ripe (Fig 16 right). In the naked barley documented among the archaeobotanical remains <lb/>from Oldenburg LA 77, the fully ripe grains had been freed from the chaff by threshing. But in <lb/>the Oldenburg surface residues, light barley chaff was still attached to the grains, thus indicat-<lb/>ing the use of immature, green grains. Immature grains contain higher levels of moisture and <lb/>Fig 12. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 09, binocular microscope image of food crust in top view (left) and of a detail of the food crust with multiple <lb/>immature barley grains (ca. 4 mm x 1.4-1.8 mm in size) embedded in the matrix (right). Images: Institute for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Archaeology, <lb/>Kiel University. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g012 <lb/>Fig 13. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 10 with food crust, overview (left), and detail showing immature barley grains embedded in the residue matrix <lb/>(right). Images: Institute for Prehistoric and Protohistoric Archaeology, Kiel University. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g013 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>lower levels of starch than mature grains. The endosperm portion of the unripe barley grains <lb/>in OLD 10 has collapsed (Fig 17 left), likely during cooking or charring and likely due to the <lb/>grains&apos; high moisture content. In contrast, the endosperm portion of the emmer grains discov-<lb/>ered in the SEM analyses in this study is more solid and starchy, which is typical for cooked <lb/>mature grains. <lb/>Chemical analyses <lb/>ATR-FTIR results. All residues (n = 21) were measured in triplicate, and the samples <lb/>showed fairly homogeneous chemistry. The results of the ATR-FTIR analyses are shown in <lb/>Fig 14. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 09, immature barley grains isolated from the crust for SEM photography, <lb/>transverse view (left), and side view (right), showing partially preserved seed coat and pericarp. Images: L. Kubiak-<lb/>Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g014 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>detail in S4 Table and illustrated with FTIR spectra in Fig 18, while a summary can also be <lb/>found in Table 3. Identification is based on earlier FTIR examination of heated and charred <lb/>food remains [36-39] and relevant studies in archaeology and art conservation [40, 41]. It is <lb/>important to keep in mind that ATR-FTIR is a screening method and the analysis of complex <lb/>organic materials only shows characteristics of components that form 5% or more of the vol-<lb/>ume of the mixture. Compounds that are present in very small proportions may not be <lb/>detected. <lb/>Information about the original vessel contents could be obtained from 7 of the 21 residues <lb/>(33%). In six cases, these residues were situated on the interior vessel wall and in one case, on <lb/>Fig 15. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 09, SEM images showing multicellular aleurone layer as observed in barley, <lb/>accompanied by pericarp tissues, top view (left), and multicellular aleurone layer as observed in barley, transverse view <lb/>(right). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g015 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>the exterior vessel wall. Most prominent are the indications for the presence of well-preserved <lb/>or slightly charred polysaccharides and the lack of significant amounts of lipids or proteins. <lb/>While some residues contain minor amounts of proteins (in varying degrees of thermal degra-<lb/>dation), polysaccharides form the main surviving class of compounds. <lb/>These 7 well-preserved residues can be grouped according to decreasing organic content <lb/>and increasing thermal exposure. Three residues (OLD 02, situated on an exterior surface, and <lb/>OLD 04 and 06, situated on interior surfaces) have high organic content and clearly show the <lb/>presence of polysaccharides, identifiable by three peaks between 1000 and 1100 cm -1 (i.e., <lb/>1017, 1043, and 1080 cm -1 ) and in a single peak at 1151 cm -1 . Significant aliphatic peaks at <lb/>Fig 17. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 10, SEM images showing the outline of immature barley grain (left) and the <lb/>multicellular aleurone characteristic of barley (right). The endosperm has collapsed during cooking or charring, due to <lb/>the high moisture content of the immature grains. Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g017 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>2930 and 2850 cm -1 , typical for aliphatic hydrocarbons in polysaccharides, are also present. <lb/>The spectra show no characteristics of lipids or proteins; moreover, the lack of aromatic com-<lb/>pounds indicates that the residues were barely carbonised (or charred). Three other residues <lb/>(OLD 09, 10 and 11, all from the interior surfaces of a vessel) show a lower organic content, <lb/>primarily polysaccharides, and, in the case of OLD 09, a minor amount of proteins. Here, the <lb/>polysaccharides are well preserved, but the aliphatic signals are reduced and some aromatic <lb/>compounds occur, indicating that the residues in this group have been exposed to more ther-<lb/>mal degradation. In OLD 01, originally adhering to the interior surface of a vessel, even fewer <lb/>organics could be detected. Very few aliphatic elements and only traces of polysaccharides are <lb/>Fig 16. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 09, SEM images showing multicellular aleurone layer as observed in barley, <lb/>accompanied by pericarp tissues, top view (left) and the edge of a barley grain fragment, revealing multicellular <lb/>aleurone layer, pericarp tissues, and likely chaff attached to the pericarp (right). Images: L. Kubiak-Martens. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g016 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>visible. This sample is of an aromatic nature, showing that the degree of thermal degradation is <lb/>higher than in the other food crusts (Fig 18). <lb/>The presence of well-preserved polysaccharides and the absence of any significant amount <lb/>of lipids or proteins is remarkable. When mixed foods are exposed to heat (e.g., during cook-<lb/>ing), it is the polysaccharides that are the first to lose their unique characteristics. This is due to <lb/>them being the most susceptible to thermal degradation, followed by proteins and then lipids. <lb/>In 8 of the 21 residues (38%), the FTIR spectra showed a good resolution, indicating that <lb/>these samples contained enough material for an adequate ATR-FTIR analysis. Nevertheless, <lb/>the analysis did not provide information about the original contents of the vessels. The resi-<lb/>dues (OLD 07, 08, 13, 14, 16 and 18-20) displayed low aliphatic signatures and a series of indi-<lb/>cations for various kinds of degradation and contamination from soil compounds. First, salts <lb/>of carboxylic acids (identified by two wide bands, at 1595 cm -1 and 1395 cm -1 ) were found in <lb/>some samples. These non-informative salts may originate from degraded lipids in the residue <lb/>or the soil matrix. Second, some residues contain silicates (originating from sand or clay in the <lb/>soil) and/or lignins (probably originating from modern roots or other plant material). The <lb/>presence of these compounds indicates contamination from the soil substrate making these <lb/>samples unsuitable for further analysis. Even though some of the residues in this group showed <lb/>markers for polysaccharides (especially the residue on the fragment of disc OLD 08), identifi-<lb/>cation of the original vessel contents was not possible due to the high degree of contamination <lb/>(Fig 19). <lb/>Of the 21 residues, 6 (29%) yielded no organic compounds; instead, their spectra exhibit the <lb/>presence of sulfates. These 6 are OLD 03 and 05 (from the exterior surface); OLD 12, 17 and <lb/>21 (from the interior surface); and OLD 15 (from the surface of one of the ceramic discs) (Fig <lb/>20). Calcium sulfates are identified in the FTIR spectra by a combination of two wide bands, at <lb/>3526 and 3402 cm -1 ; a narrow band at 3242 cm -1 ; two narrow, sharp bands, at 1683 and 1620 <lb/>cm -1 ; a broad band at 1445 cm -1 ; and a main band at 1108 cm -1 (see S4 Table). Sulfates regu-<lb/>larly occur in marine clay deposits. They can be formed by sulfur/sulfate-reducing bacteria, or <lb/>Fig 18. FTIR spectra, from top to bottom: OLD 01, 02, 09 and 15, showing the relative transmissions (in %) against the wave number (from <lb/>4000-550 cm -1 ). The first three spectra show characteristics typical of polysaccharides; the last spectrum is typical of calcium sulfate. Graph: T.F. <lb/>M. Oudemans. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g018 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. Summary of combined FTIR and DTMS results. The relative intensity of various characteristics is indicated in five categories (-: absent, +/-: minimal, +: average, ++: strong, and +++: very <lb/>strong). Organic signal = cumulative intensity of the measurement, where XH = extra High (&gt;300 x blank measurement), H = high (300-100 x), M = medium (100-40 x), L/M = low to medium (40-20 <lb/>x) and L = low (&lt;20x blank measurement). <lb/>Sample <lb/>OLD 01 OLD <lb/>02 <lb/>OLD <lb/>03 <lb/>OLD <lb/>04 <lb/>OLD <lb/>05 <lb/>OLD <lb/>06 <lb/>OLD <lb/>07 <lb/>OLD <lb/>08 <lb/>OLD <lb/>09 <lb/>OLD <lb/>10 <lb/>OLD <lb/>11 <lb/>OLD <lb/>12 <lb/>OLD <lb/>13 <lb/>OLD <lb/>14 <lb/>OLD <lb/>15 <lb/>OLD <lb/>16 <lb/>OLD <lb/>17 <lb/>OLD 18 OLD 19 OLD 20 OLD <lb/>21 <lb/>Sampled Location <lb/>in <lb/>ex <lb/>ex <lb/>in <lb/>ex <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>top <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>ex <lb/>top <lb/>ex <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>ex <lb/>in <lb/>in <lb/>FTIR Results <lb/>Aliphatic <lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>Aromatics <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Polysaccharides <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>Proteins <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Lipids <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Sulfates <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>+++ + <lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>Salts <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>Lignin <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Silica <lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+++ <lb/>DTMS Results <lb/>Organic signal <lb/>M-L <lb/>XH <lb/>H <lb/>M <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>L <lb/>TIC (in min.) <lb/>0.88 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.92 0.98 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>Aliphatic compounds +/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+/-<lb/>Lipids <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>Polysaccharides <lb/>+++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>-<lb/>Polysaccharide char <lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>Protein <lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>Protein char <lb/>-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>+/-<lb/>-<lb/>Soil: Sulfates <lb/>+++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+++ ++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>due to the presence of sulfate-containing minerals (e.g. gypsum), or leaching at slightly acidic <lb/>pH levels. They are present in most of the residues from Oldenburg LA 77 in varying amounts <lb/>and can be considered contamination resulting from the local soil conditions. <lb/>In summary, roughly one-third (33%) of the analysed residues contain well-preserved <lb/>remains of the original foods cooked in the vessels, while two-thirds (67%) are clearly too con-<lb/>taminated with soil components to be indicative of the vessel contents. The 7 well-preserved <lb/>residues primarily contain polysaccharides, demonstrating that the food consisted principally <lb/>of starches and/or sugars. The origin of the polysaccharides cannot be determined in more <lb/>detail, because the FTIR spectra of complex materials give only a general picture of the nature <lb/>Fig 19. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 08: images show the bottom surface with signs of fire exposure (top left), and the top surface with residue (top <lb/>right) as well as a detail of the sampled residue (bottom). White rectangles mark the sampled location. Images: T.F.M. Oudemans. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g019 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the material. But since lipids are absent, a plant origin is considered the most likely. The <lb/>composition of modern wholewheat grain shows similarities with some of the archaeological <lb/>residues (S4 Table). All well-preserved residues are situated on the surface of vessels: one is sit-<lb/>uated on the exterior of a vessel (14%) and the other six are internal residues on vessels (85%). <lb/>Neither of the two residues from the ceramic discs displayed identifiable organic compounds <lb/>in the FTIR analysis. <lb/>DTMS results. A total of 7 residues, originally situated on the interior (n = 4) or exterior <lb/>(n = 1) surface of vessels or the top surface of ceramic discs (n = 2), were measured using <lb/>DTMS (see Table 3). These residues exhibit different levels of thermal exposure. Even though <lb/>the FTIR showed that the residues from ceramic discs are less promising for chemical analysis, <lb/>they were included because the DTMS might help elucidate the function of these objects that <lb/>has thus far remained unresolved. The results of each DTMS analysis form a series of mass <lb/>spectra (see Fig 21), in which specific masses (or combinations of masses) represent known <lb/>fragments of particular organic components or biomarkers in archaeological residues [38]. <lb/>This makes it possible to score the presence or absence of various groups of organic molecules <lb/>per residue (Table 3). <lb/>Fig 20. Oldenburg LA 77, sherd OLD 15: images show the bottom surface with signs of fire exposure (top left), and the top surface with residue (top <lb/>right) as well as a detail of the sampled residue (bottom). White rectangles mark the sampled location. Images: T.F.M. Oudemans. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g020 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 21. DTMS results for residue OLD 02 including: The TIC or total ion current (top right) showing one peak at 1.03 minutes; the DTMS spectrum for <lb/>the evaporation phase (area A, 0.4-0.76 minutes) (A); the DTMS spectrum for early pyrolysis phase (area B, 0.76-0.86 minutes) (B) and the DTMS <lb/>spectrum for later pyrolysis phase (area C, 0.86-1.20 minutes) (C). Markers for component classes are indicated with symbols: psi = intact <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Six residues provided information on the original vessel contents; residue OLD 15, from <lb/>one of the ceramic discs, contained too little organic material for a reliable interpretation as <lb/>demonstrated by the cumulative intensity of the DTMS measurement, which is indicative of <lb/>the organic content of the sample. For OLD 15 this response was only 9 times higher than the <lb/>measurement without a sample where the common cut-off is at 20× the value. The DTMS <lb/>results for the six samples confirm the findings of the FTIR analysis (Table 3): the samples con-<lb/>tain polysaccharides, some better preserved than others. The DTMS analysis offered some <lb/>additional information, in that it detected the presence of small amounts of partially charred <lb/>proteins (in OLD 02, 08, 09 and 11) and a small amount of lipids in the form of free fatty acids <lb/>(in OLD 11). Contamination with sulfur-containing compounds is also clearly visible in the <lb/>DTMS analysis (see, for instance, the results for residue OLD 15). Further details on the <lb/>DTMS results for the individual samples are given below. <lb/>Residue OLD 02 is rich in organic components and shows a high organic signal (Fig 21). <lb/>The organic signal of OLD 02 is 547× higher than a measurement without sample. The total <lb/>ion current (TIC) shows one, medium-wide, peak at an average temperature (maximum at <lb/>1.03 minutes), indicating a relatively homogeneous material of medium condensation, sug-<lb/>gesting that some, but not much, thermal degradation had taken place (Fig 21). The desorption <lb/>phase of OLD 02 (area A, 0.40-0.75 minutes) is dominated by markers for elementary sulfur <lb/>(S 2 ) that is liberated from the material during the measurement and originates from the sulfur-<lb/>containing compounds in the sample. A very small amount of polysaccharides is also visible <lb/>(Fig 21). Volatile components, such as lipids, normally visible in this part of the analysis, are <lb/>not seen in OLD 02. As the temperature is increased during the early pyrolysis phase (area B, <lb/>0.76-0.85 minutes) a clear polysaccharide profile is visible, showing many intact polysaccha-<lb/>rides as well as the remaining sulfur signal. Some markers for intact proteins are also visible. <lb/>The later pyrolysis phase (area C, 0.87-1.20 minutes) shows primarily markers of thermally <lb/>degraded polysaccharides, in combination with some minor compounds for charred proteins. <lb/>Markers such as alkylphenols and alkylbenzenes (m/z 91, 92, 94, 105, 107, 108, 131) and nitro-<lb/>gen-containing compounds (m/z 117, 131, 147) indicate some thermal degradation of pro-<lb/>teins. Residue OLD 02 consists mostly of polysaccharides and is a good example of the limited <lb/>thermal degradation in the residues. Polysaccharides usually originate from plant sources, but <lb/>dairy products can also contain polysaccharides (in the form of milk sugars). However, since <lb/>no lipids were detected, it can be concluded that the polysaccharides are of plant origin. The <lb/>small amount of proteins visible in the sample are most likely part of the original, starch-rich <lb/>plant material. <lb/>Residue OLD 01 is not very different from OLD 02, except for the fact that it contains less <lb/>organic material. The TIC peak is much narrower and lies at lower temperatures, at 0.88 min-<lb/>utes, which indicates a very homogeneous material that is less condensed and thus less ther-<lb/>mally degraded. The general composition is comparable to that of OLD 02, although it <lb/>contains no protein fragments. However, due to the low organic content, it is possible that the <lb/>protein fragments fall below the signal-to-noise ratio. <lb/>Residues OLD 06, 08 and 09 are similar to OLD 02 but contain less organic material. The <lb/>narrow TIC peaks lie at lower temperatures, indicating relatively homogeneous materials of a <lb/>less condensed nature and pointing to a lower degree of thermal degradation. The general <lb/>composition is comparable to that of OLD 02, with some minor differences in the amount of <lb/>(lightly charred) protein markers. <lb/>polysaccharides; psc = thermally degraded and charred polysaccharides; pri = intact proteins; prc = charred proteins; S = elementary sulfur; <lb/>C = contamination). Figure: T.F.M. Oudemans. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.g021 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>One of the residues from the ceramic discs (OLD 08) contained polysaccharides and no lip-<lb/>ids, showing that the crust is probably of plant origin. Residue OLD 11 differs somewhat from <lb/>the other residues, even though it contains a similar amount of organic material and the TIC <lb/>peak lies around the same temperature (0.92 minutes). The general composition corresponds <lb/>well to that of the other residues, but the sample contains a small amount of lipids, in the form <lb/>of saturated free fatty acids. Although the lipid quantities are not significantly higher than the <lb/>signal-to-noise ratio, minute traces of cholesterol indicate that a (partly) animal origin cannot <lb/>be excluded. <lb/>In summary, all but one of the residues analysed with DTMS contained sufficient organic <lb/>material for a reliable interpretation and thus yielded evidence of the original foods prepared <lb/>or processed in the ceramic item. Of the 6 successful residues, 5 (83%) contain abundant poly-<lb/>saccharides and a minimal amount of proteins and lack lipids. The polysaccharides and pro-<lb/>teins originate from starch-rich plant material. Only one residue (OLD 11) contained a small <lb/>amount of lipids, which may indicate a (partly) animal origin. Five of the residues were found <lb/>on the surface of a vessel (one situated on the exterior and the other situated on the interior of <lb/>a vessel). One of the residues from a ceramic disc showed identifiable polysaccharides. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Cooking with cereals <lb/>The results of the combined SEM, FTIR and DTMS analyses of surface residues from Olden-<lb/>burg LA 77 (presented in Table 4) provide a significant contribution to the existing knowledge <lb/>on prehistoric food processing and preparation techniques in northwestern Europe. Our study <lb/>is the first of this kind both for northern Germany and for the Funnel Beaker groups. <lb/>The picture emerging for Oldenburg LA 77 shows that cereals (specifically emmer and bar-<lb/>ley) formed the major ingredient of the dishes cooked in coarse-fabric vessels with thick walls. <lb/>SEM analysis shows that these were apparently the only ingredients in all but one instance con-<lb/>sidered in this study. The exception is the combination of emmer and fat-hen seeds (in OLD <lb/>06). The addition of edible, protein-rich fat-hen seeds to the cereal-based meal is proposed to <lb/>be deliberate rather than accidental. Further, the solid, or fused, appearance of the emmer <lb/>grain endosperm in the Oldenburg LA 77 organic residues indicates that liquid, most likely <lb/>water, was used in the cooking/heating process. <lb/>The FTIR analysis shows that one-third of the analysed surface residues contain traces of <lb/>the original foods prepared or processed and that the residues are characterised primarily by <lb/>polysaccharides (starches or sugars). The DTMS analysis confirmed the presence of relatively <lb/>well-preserved polysaccharides but also provided the additional information, that most of the <lb/>residues contain traces of proteins and that the residues contain no or only minute amounts of <lb/>lipids (the latter in only one residue, OLD 11). The vast predominance of polysaccharides and <lb/>the near absence of lipids make a plant origin the most likely for these residues. Whole cereal <lb/>grains contain fair amounts (5-20%) of protein, and they are the most likely source of the pro-<lb/>teins detected in the residues. The sample taken from the top surface of the fragment of one of <lb/>the ceramic discs (OLD 08) revealed the presence of polysaccharides, suggesting that this <lb/>object may indeed have been used to heat food containing cereal grains. <lb/>The presence of unripe barley grains in some of the residues is a peculiar aspect of Olden-<lb/>burg food preparations. These would have been naked barley grains, as indicated by the analy-<lb/>sis of archaeobotanical remains from the site. Ears of barley were probably harvested when <lb/>they were still green. Due to the limited shelf life of green ears [42], they would need to have <lb/>been processed and used soon after the harvest. The green barley harvest may have taken place <lb/>in mid-or late summer (depending on whether sowing was done in winter or spring); <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. Overview of combined botanical and chemical results from Oldenburg LA 77 organic residues. <lb/>Sample <lb/>identifier <lb/>ALSH <lb/>inventory <lb/>number <lb/>Find <lb/>number <lb/>SEM results <lb/>FTIR results <lb/>all samples contain <lb/>sulfates unless <lb/>otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>DTMS results <lb/>all samples <lb/>contain sulfates <lb/>unless otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>Interpretation of <lb/>food crust <lb/>OLD 01 <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3082 <lb/>232 <lb/>emmer grain <lb/>fragments <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix, <lb/>exposed aleurone <lb/>&amp; pericarp tissue <lb/>strong <lb/>polysaccharide <lb/>signal, minimal <lb/>aliphatics, no <lb/>proteins or lipids <lb/>medium to low in <lb/>organics: mostly <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), no lipids <lb/>or proteins <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>emmer grain, <lb/>likely in water <lb/>OLD 02 <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3087 <lb/>309 <lb/>vegetative <lb/>parenchyma, no <lb/>further <lb/>determination <lb/>strong <lb/>polysaccharide <lb/>signal, strong <lb/>aliphatic signal, <lb/>minimal proteins <lb/>very high in <lb/>organics: mostly <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), minor <lb/>amount of proteins <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), no lipids <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>starch-or sugar-<lb/>rich plant <lb/>material <lb/>OLD 03 <lb/>2010-<lb/>663.3096 <lb/>423 <lb/>possible cereal <lb/>grain endosperm <lb/>matrix <lb/>polysaccharides, no <lb/>aliphatics, no <lb/>proteins or lipids, <lb/>minimal silicate <lb/>signal <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>possible <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>cereal grain <lb/>OLD 04 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3099 <lb/>154 <lb/>emmer grain <lb/>fragments <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix, <lb/>exposed aleurone <lb/>&amp; pericarp tissue <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal, no proteins <lb/>or lipids <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>emmer grain, <lb/>likely in water <lb/>OLD 05 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.3093 <lb/>382 <lb/>cf. bone fragment strong <lb/>polysaccharide <lb/>signal, no <lb/>aliphatics, minimal <lb/>proteins <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>starch-or sugar-<lb/>rich plant <lb/>material <lb/>OLD 06 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3101 <lb/>546 <lb/>emmer grain <lb/>fragments, <lb/>exposed aleurone <lb/>&amp; pericarp tissue; <lb/>also seed testa of <lb/>fat-hen <lb/>(Chenopodium <lb/>album) <lb/>strong <lb/>polysaccharide <lb/>signal, strong <lb/>aliphatic signal, <lb/>minimal proteins <lb/>high in organics: <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), no <lb/>proteins or lipids <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>emmer grain <lb/>with fat-hen <lb/>seeds, likely in <lb/>water <lb/>OLD 07 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3094 <lb/>197 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal and silicates <lb/>present <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>residue with <lb/>some <lb/>contamination <lb/>with soil material <lb/>OLD 08 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7915 <lb/>2001 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>alphatics, minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>minimal proteins <lb/>medium in <lb/>organics: <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), minor <lb/>amount of proteins <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), no lipids <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>starch-or sugar-<lb/>rich plant <lb/>material <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Sample <lb/>identifier <lb/>ALSH <lb/>inventory <lb/>number <lb/>Find <lb/>number <lb/>SEM results <lb/>FTIR results <lb/>all samples contain <lb/>sulfates unless <lb/>otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>DTMS results <lb/>all samples <lb/>contain sulfates <lb/>unless otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>Interpretation of <lb/>food crust <lb/>OLD 09 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7907 <lb/>2158 <lb/>barley grains <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal <lb/>high in organics: <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), minor <lb/>amount of proteins <lb/>(intact and <lb/>charred), no lipids <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>unripe or milk-<lb/>ripe barley grain, <lb/>likely in water <lb/>OLD 10 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8108 <lb/>Ge-112 barley grains <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>unripe or milk-<lb/>ripe barley grain, <lb/>likely in water <lb/>OLD 11 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8096 <lb/>2109-01 emmer grain <lb/>fragments <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix, <lb/>exposed aleurone <lb/>&amp; pericarp tissue <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal, minimal <lb/>proteins <lb/>high in organics: <lb/>mostly intact <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>(some charred), <lb/>minor amount of <lb/>proteins (intact <lb/>and charred), <lb/>some lipids <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>emmer grain, <lb/>likely in water or <lb/>milk <lb/>OLD 12 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.8096 <lb/>2109-02 emmer grain <lb/>fragments <lb/>embedded in <lb/>residue matrix, <lb/>expose aleurone <lb/>&amp; pericarp tissue <lb/>no polysaccharides, <lb/>some aliphatics, <lb/>strong signal for <lb/>salts of organic <lb/>acids (degraded <lb/>lipids) <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>strongly <lb/>degraded residue <lb/>of cooking/ <lb/>heating emmer <lb/>grain, likely in <lb/>water <lb/>OLD 13 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3073 <lb/>5007 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>and alphatics, some <lb/>salts of organic <lb/>acids (degraded <lb/>lipids) <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>degraded residue <lb/>OLD 14 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3083 <lb/>147 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal, minimal <lb/>proteins <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>cooking/heating <lb/>starch-or sugar-<lb/>rich plant <lb/>material <lb/>OLD 15 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3092 <lb/>308 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, no <lb/>aliphatics, strong <lb/>sulfate signal, <lb/>contamination <lb/>with silicates <lb/>low in organics: <lb/>minimal aliphatics, <lb/>major sulfate <lb/>contamination <lb/>soil material <lb/>OLD 16 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3100 <lb/>334 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>strong aliphatic <lb/>signal, no lipids or <lb/>proteins <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>residue <lb/>OLD 17 <lb/>2010-<lb/>633.3102 <lb/>95 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>minimal aliphatics, <lb/>minimal proteins, <lb/>strong signal for <lb/>salts of organic <lb/>acids (degraded <lb/>lipids) <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>degraded residue <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>assuming that the green barley was used soon after harvesting, these particular food remains <lb/>may originate from late summer or early autumn cooking events. <lb/>The harvesting and consumption of green, unripe grains, primarily wheat and occasionally <lb/>barley, are well documented ethnographically and described in publications by, for instance <lb/>[43-45]. However, there is only one published study that investigates different stages of matu-<lb/>rity of cereal grains, more specifically spelt wheat grains (Triticum spelta), recovered from an <lb/>archaeological site at Vaihingen in Germany, dating to the early La Tène period [42]. There-<lb/>fore, the presence of immature barley grains in food crusts from Oldenburg represents direct <lb/>evidence of a previously unrecorded culinary practice in Neolithic Europe. <lb/>The results presented here paint a different picture than that obtained from earlier studies <lb/>of European Neolithic assemblages of food residues encrusted on pottery. The remarkably <lb/>well-preserved food crusts on ceramic vessels from the Late Neolithic site of Pestenaker (3496-<lb/>3410 BCE) in southern Bavaria contained evidence of the processing of mixed dishes and the <lb/>cooking of combinations of cereals and dairy products [21]. A wide range of food sources <lb/>(both plant and animal) were identified in mixed residues from the large ceramic assemblages <lb/>from the Late Neolithic Corded Ware sites in the Netherlands (c. 2800-2400 BCE). At the site <lb/>of Keinsmerbrug, for example, emmer was cooked with the addition of animal fat, while at the <lb/>sites of Mienakker and Zeewijk, dishes comprised a mixture of foods [32, 33, 46]. <lb/>Consistent with an earlier study [47], we have proven that terrestrial foods were cooked in <lb/>pots in this early farming village. However, the vast predominance of polysaccharides and the <lb/>near absence of lipids from the surface residues stand in contradiction with the findings from <lb/>the earlier work. Weber and colleagues extracted lipids from the pottery fabric of potsherds <lb/>(n = 18) from Oldenburg LA 77 and argued that the absorbed lipids represent the dishes <lb/>cooked in these vessels. They found that some of the sherds contain indicators for food of <lb/>plant origin (n = 9), milk or dairy products (n = 5), and food of meat origin (n = 2); two sherds <lb/>contained no significant amount of lipids. The discrepancy between this and the results of our <lb/>study is significant: because lipids are much more heat-resistant and less soluble than <lb/>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Sample <lb/>identifier <lb/>ALSH <lb/>inventory <lb/>number <lb/>Find <lb/>number <lb/>SEM results <lb/>FTIR results <lb/>all samples contain <lb/>sulfates unless <lb/>otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>DTMS results <lb/>all samples <lb/>contain sulfates <lb/>unless otherwise <lb/>indicated <lb/>Interpretation of <lb/>food crust <lb/>OLD 18 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7908 <lb/>2361 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>minimal aliphatics, <lb/>no lipids or <lb/>proteins <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>residue <lb/>OLD 19 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7908 <lb/>2361 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>polysaccharides <lb/>and aliphatics, no <lb/>lipids or proteins <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>residue <lb/>OLD 20 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7910 <lb/>2440 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>minimal <lb/>polysaccharides, <lb/>aliphatics, strong <lb/>signal for salts of <lb/>organic acids <lb/>(degraded lipids) <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>unknown <lb/>degraded residue <lb/>OLD 21 <lb/>2011-<lb/>432.7912 <lb/>2088 <lb/>no SEM <lb/>no polysaccharides, <lb/>minimal aliphatics, <lb/>significant silicate <lb/>signal <lb/>no DTMS <lb/>soil material <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>31 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>polysaccharides, lipids would have been detected in the surface residues if they had been pres-<lb/>ent in the dishes cooked in the vessels that we analysed. In both studies, a similar set of heavily <lb/>fragmented and undecorated ceramic sherds were analysed, originating from vessels thought <lb/>to have been in regular, everyday use [1, 2]. The discrepancy could perhaps be explained by a <lb/>possibility that the lipids discovered in the ceramic matrix were the result of a post-firing <lb/>waterproofing technique, involving the use of milk, dairy products, or plant oil, intended to <lb/>make the pottery less permeable-the practice documented ethnographically and successfully <lb/>tested experimentally [48, 49]. <lb/>Processing and preparation: Sprouting and dehusking of emmer <lb/>The absence of emmer chaff from the emmer-containing food crusts from Oldenburg points <lb/>to thorough processing-dehusking, sieving, and winnowing-prior to food preparation. The <lb/>archaeobotanical assemblage includes abundant remains of emmer chaff and, thus, indirectly, <lb/>evidence for emmer having been stored in spikelets and for the final stages of cleaning having <lb/>been done on-site. Parching of spikelets is often cited as a method applied to ease the removal <lb/>of chaff, but the presence of sprouted emmer grains in Oldenburg LA 77 food crusts and the <lb/>lack of chaff in food preparations may reflect an alternative or additional strategy, such as <lb/>soaking emmer spikelets before dehusking. <lb/>Dampening of spikelets softens the chaff and, during pounding, facilitates the release of the <lb/>grain and removal (literally shredding) of the chaff through rubbing of the spikelets against <lb/>each other and the dehusking device, without causing (excessive) damage to the grains. Experi-<lb/>mental work and archaeobotanical evidence suggest that mortars and pestles could have been <lb/>used in this procedure [50, 51]. Soaking in water before dehusking, followed by either sun-dry-<lb/>ing or artificial drying or roasting in ovens, is also attested ethnographically [52] and refer-<lb/>ences therein]. The result is a damp mass consisting of shredded fine and coarse glume wheat <lb/>chaff and clean grain, which can be separated by sieving. Long periods of dampening, however, <lb/>can lead to sprouting of the grain, and this scenario seems to have played out at Oldenburg. <lb/>Moreover, sprouting seems to have been a desired outcome, given that the dampening <lb/>occurred prior to dehusking-the logic being that pounding or grinding of dry emmer spike-<lb/>lets, which are hard and have chaff tightly enclosing the grain, would have damaged the <lb/>embryo, which was needed for germination, however, in this case, the embryo was clearly <lb/>intact enough to have been able to sprout. Soaking emmer spikelets would thus have served a <lb/>dual purpose, namely, to facilitate the dehusking process and to induce germination. Analysis <lb/>of the morphology of archaeological sprouted emmer grains from the New Kingdom site at <lb/>Amarna in Egypt has shown that the chaff had been in place during the germination [50, 51]. <lb/>In Oldenburg LA 77, the soaking of spikelets likely occurred in a controlled environment, <lb/>such as ceramic vessels, in low-light conditions. The soaking water would have been drained <lb/>off after some time and the spikelets left wet. If the length of sprouts observed on some germi-<lb/>nated ancient grains can be used as an indicator, then emmer grains may have sprouted within <lb/>six to eight days [50-53]. Once free of chaff, the sprouted emmer grains at Oldenburg LA 77 <lb/>would have been processed further before cooking, possibly by being crushed or ground, <lb/>which would account for the presence of grain fragments embedded in otherwise featureless <lb/>residue matrices in some of the food residues (OLD 01, 04, 11 and 12). <lb/>Sprouting is a natural biochemical process activated when seeds and grains are exposed to <lb/>moisture and warmth, and sprouted grain has several advantages over unsprouted grain for <lb/>humans. It triggers enzymes to break down stored nutrients-complex carbohydrates into <lb/>simple sugars, proteins into amino acids, and fats into fatty acids-making the grains easier to <lb/>digest. Sprouted grains may also have higher levels of vitamins and minerals, including vitamin <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>32 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>C and iron. Overall, sprouting significantly increases the nutritional value of the grains, which <lb/>is crucial for the growth of a new plant and beneficial for humans [54, 55]. Sprouting also <lb/>enhances the flavour of the grain. Foods prepared from sprouted grains have a distinctly sweet <lb/>and nutty flavour compared with those made from unsprouted grains, most likely due to the <lb/>conversion of starches into simpler sugars during the sprouting process. Finally, grain germi-<lb/>nation is a key step in the preparation of malt, which is an essential ingredient in brewing beer. <lb/>The Neolithic inhabitants of Oldenburg LA 77 may have recognised some of the advantages <lb/>of inducing germination of emmer grains and the consumption of such grains, perhaps in the <lb/>form of porridge or a malt-containing drink. Maybe some of the encrusted residues represent <lb/>emmer mash intended for the production of fermented drinks. The generally low degree of <lb/>thermal degradation of the organic materials in several of the Oldenburg LA77 residues, as <lb/>indicated by the DTMS results, may signal exposure to low heating temperatures, which would <lb/>be a desirable quality in the production of malted drinks. <lb/>The use of sprouted cereal grains has been reported for Late Neolithic lakeshore settlements <lb/>in central Europe, including Hornstaad-Ho ¨rnle IA and Sipplingen-Osthafen, on Lake Con-<lb/>stance, in southern Germany, and Zu ¨rich-Parkhaus Ope ´ra, on Lake Zu ¨rich, in Switzerland. At <lb/>all three settlements, sprouted grains were subjected to cooking or heating, resulting in either a <lb/>malt-containing liquid (Hornstaad-Ho ¨rnle IA) or an ingredient that was in either liquid or <lb/>solid food that contained malt (Sipplingen-Osthafen and Zu ¨rich-Parkhaus Ope ´ra) [34]. These <lb/>findings demonstrate that the processing of malted grain was practiced as part of various food <lb/>production sequences during the 4th millennium BCE in central Europe. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The combination of complementary high-resolution techniques-SEM analysis of the mor-<lb/>phology and anatomy of plant remains and ATR-FTIR and DTMS for the identification of <lb/>organic components-not only identified remains of food in surface residues on ceramics <lb/>from the Funnel Beaker Neolithic in northern Germany, but also revealed some previously <lb/>unknown aspects of food processing and preparation, and their timing, in the prehistory of <lb/>northwestern Europe. <lb/>SEM study of the residues provided detailed insight into the ingredients and their state, <lb/>identifying previously unknown ways in which cereal-based foods were processed and pre-<lb/>pared for consumption, including the use of unripe barley grains, sprouted emmer grains, and <lb/>a combination of cereals and wild plants in cooked meals. The chemical analyses demonstrated <lb/>the presence of polysaccharides in combination with small amounts of proteins, and the <lb/>absence of lipids indicating starch-or sugar-rich plant-derived foods as the main constituent <lb/>of the residues. The abundance and chemical preservation of the polysaccharides indicates that <lb/>these foods have only been heated at low temperatures. <lb/>The entire chaîne opératoire associated with Neolithic cereal production and consumption <lb/>at Oldenburg LA 77 can now be traced-from managing the arable field, harvesting, and pre-<lb/>paring the grain for storage, to preparing food in cooking pots or on baking plates. The time <lb/>around 3100 BCE was the time when agricultural production in the region was being consoli-<lb/>dated and people were beginning to group in villages, here exemplified by the Funnel Beaker <lb/>community of the settlement at Oldenburg LA77. The inhabitants directed great attention to <lb/>the plant food economy, not only in working and maintaining the arable land and tending to <lb/>staple crops but also in processing and cooking the resulting grain. <lb/>Earlier studies of archaeological food remains had already demonstrated that prehistoric <lb/>food and drink preparation and cooking were as complex and diverse as the evidence they left <lb/>behind. This work has expanded the existing knowledge geographically and temporally and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>33 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>demonstrated the research potential of the multi-method approach. Most significantly, it has <lb/>enabled us to get a glimpse of the final stages of the long process of transformation of food <lb/>plants, from sowing to consumption. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Examples of thick-walled, undecorated pottery sherds from Oldenburg LA 77. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Radiocarbon AMS dates and their calibrated values for three samples of food crusts <lb/>(OLD 04, 06, and 11) and two charred emmer grains (SED 27 and 28) (S2 by D. Filipović). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Radiocarbon AMS dates and their calibrated values for three samples of food <lb/>crusts (OLD 04, 06, and 11) and two charred emmer grains (SED 27 and 28) (S2 by D. Fili-<lb/>pović). <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. Aleurone double cell wall thickness measurements on tangential (top view). <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S3 Table. Aleurone double cell wall thickness measurements on transverse (side view). <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S4 Table. ATR-FTIR results. The relative intensity of the FTIR transmission bands is indi-<lb/>cated in five categories (-: absent, +/-: minimal, +: average, ++: strong and +++: very strong). <lb/>The origin of the bands is indicated as Mi = minerals; PS = polysaccharides; Pr = proteins; <lb/>Al = aliphatic hydrocarbons; Ar = aromatic compounds; Lig = lignins; S = sulfates and <lb/>Si = silicates. The type of transmission band is given as: s. = stretch; b. = bend; vibr. = vibration <lb/>[such as rocking, scissoring, wagging, or twisting]; def. = deformation; skel. = skeletal; asym. = <lb/>asymmetrical. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>LK-M expresses her gratitude to the Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden, the Netherlands, <lb/>where she carried out the scanning electron microscope analysis using the JEOL JSM-6480L <lb/>device. The ATR-FTIR measurements were performed at the Kenaz Consult &amp; Laboratory in <lb/>Berlin. We are indebted to Ester S.B. Ferreira (Cologne Institute of Conservation Sciences, <lb/>University of Applied Sciences in Cologne) for providing DTMS accessibility; Andreas G. <lb/>Heiss (O ¨sterreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, O ¨sterreichisches Archa ¨ologisches Insti-<lb/>tut, Vienna) for his valuable thoughts concerning the taxonomic determination of immature <lb/>barley grains; and Wouter van der Meer (BIAX Consult, Zaandam, the Netherlands) for mea-<lb/>suring the thickness of the aleurone cell walls in emmer remains with the use of R-STUDIO <lb/>software and producing the diagrams. We thank Agnes Heitmann and Karin Winter (Graph-<lb/>ics Department of the Institute for Pre-and Protohistory, Kiel University) and Daniel Knitter <lb/>(OEKO-LOG field research) for their help with photography and illustration, and Suzanne <lb/>Needs-Howarth (Toronto) for copy-editing. We are grateful to the editors and reviewers for <lb/>the careful reading of our manuscript and useful suggestions. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>34 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Data curation: Lucy Kubiak-Martens, Tania F. M. Oudemans, Jan Piet Brozio. <lb/>Formal analysis: Lucy Kubiak-Martens, Tania F. M. Oudemans. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Johannes Mu ¨ller, Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/>Methodology: Lucy Kubiak-Martens, Tania F. M. Oudemans. <lb/>Project administration: Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/>Resources: Johannes Mu ¨ller, Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/>Supervision: Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Lucy Kubiak-Martens, Tania F. M. Oudemans, Jan Piet Brozio, Dra-<lb/>gana Filipović, Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Lucy Kubiak-Martens, Tania F. M. Oudemans, Jan Piet Brozio, <lb/>Dragana Filipović, Johannes Mu ¨ller, Wiebke Kirleis. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Brozio J-P. Megalithanlagen und Siedlungsmuster im trichterbecherzeitlichen Ostholstein, Fru ¨he Monu-<lb/>mentalita ¨t und soziale Differenzierung. Bonn: Verlag Dr. Rudolf Habelt GmbH; 2016. <lb/>2. Brozio J-P, Filipović D, Schmo ¨lcke U, Kirleis W, Mu ¨ller J. Mittel-bis jungneolithische Siedlungshinterlas-<lb/>senschaften zwischen 3300-2600 v. Chr. Der Fundplatz Oldenburg LA 232 im Oldenburger Graben, <lb/>Ostholstein. 2019a; 93(2):185-224. https://doi.org/10.1515/pz-2018-0007 <lb/>3. Hinz M From Hunting to Herding? Aspects of the Social and Animal Landscape during the Southern <lb/>Scandinavian Neolithic. In: Haug A, Ka ¨ppel L, Mu ¨ller J, editors. Past Landscapes The Dynamics of <lb/>Interaction Between Society, Landscape, and Culture. Leiden: Sidestone Press; 2018:207-234. <lb/>4. Kirleis W, Klooß S, Kroll H, Mu ¨ller J. Crop growing and gathering in the northern German Neolithic: a <lb/>review supplemented by new results. Vegetation History and Archaeobotany. 2012; 21(3):221-242. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00334-011-0328-9 <lb/>5. Kirleis W, Fischer E. Neolithic cultivation of tetraploid free threshing wheat in Denmark and Northern <lb/>Germany: implications for crop diversity and societal dynamics of the Funnel Beaker Culture. Vegeta-<lb/>tion History and Archaeobotany. 2014; 23(S1):81-96. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00334-014-0440-8 <lb/>6. Kirleis W. Atlas of Neolithic plant remains from northern central Europe. Groningen: Barkhuis; 2019. <lb/>7. Kirleis W. Subsistence change? Diversification of plant economy during the Neolithic in northern Ger-<lb/>many. In: Klimscha F, Heumu ¨ller M, Ramaekers D, Peeters H, Terberger T, editors. Stone Age border-<lb/>land experience: Neolithic and Late Mesolithic parallel societies in the North European plain. Rahden/ <lb/>Westfalen: Marie Leidorf GmbH; 2022:432-449. <lb/>8. Nowak M, Litynska-Zajac M, Moskal-del Hoyo M, Mueller-Bieniek A, Kapcia M, Kotynia K. Plants of the <lb/>funnel Beaker culture in Poland. In: Wlodarczak P, editor. Sprawozdania Archeologiczne. 72/1. Kra-<lb/>kow: Archaeological Reports; 2020:87-114. <lb/>9. Sørensen L, Karg S. The expansion of agrarian societies towards the north -new evidence for agricul-<lb/>ture during the Mesolithic/Neolithic transition in Southern Scandinavia. Journal of Archaeological Sci-<lb/>ence. 2014; 51:98-114. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2012.08.042 <lb/>10. Filipović D, Brozio JP, Ditchfield P, Klooß S, Mu ¨ller J, Kirleis W. Middle-Neolithic agricultural practices in <lb/>the Oldenburger Graben wetlands, northern Germany: First results of the analysis of arable weeds and <lb/>stable isotopes. The Holocene. 2019:1587-95. https://doi.org/10.1177/0959683619857224 <lb/>11. Gron KJ, Gro ¨cke DR, Larsson M, Sørensen L, Larsson L, Rowley-Conwy P, et al. Nitrogen isotope evi-<lb/>dence for manuring of early Neolithic Funnel Beaker Culture cereals from Stensborg, Sweden. Journal <lb/>of Archaeological Science: Reports. 2017; 14:575-579. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2017.06.042 <lb/>12. Kanstrup M, Holst MK, Jensen PM, Thomsen IK, Christensen BT. Searching for long-term trends in pre-<lb/>historic manuring practice. δ15N analyses of charred cereal grains from the 4th to the 1st millennium <lb/>BC. Journal of Archaeological Science. 2014; 51:115-125. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2013.04.018 <lb/>13. Gron KJ, Montgomery J, Nielsen PO, Nowell GM, Peterkin JL, Sørensen L, et al. Strontium isotope evi-<lb/>dence of early Funnel Beaker Culture movement of cattle. Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports. <lb/>2016; 6:248-251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2016.02.015 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>35 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Terberger T, Burger J, Lu ¨th F, Mu ¨ller J, Piezonka H. Step by step -The neolithisation of Northern Cen-<lb/>tral Europe in the light of stable isotope analyses. Journal of Archaeological Science. 2018; 99:66-86. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2018.08.004 <lb/>15. Craig OE, Steele VJ, Fischer A, Hartz S, Andersen SH, Donohoe P, et al. Ancient lipids reveal continuity <lb/>in culinary practices across the transition to agriculture in Northern Europe. PNAS. 2011; 108 <lb/>(44):17910-5. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1107202108 PMID: 22025697 <lb/>16. Saul H, Wilson J, Heron CP, Glykou A, Hartz S, Craig OE. A systematic approach to the recovery and <lb/>identification of starches from carbonised deposits on ceramic vessels. Journal of Archaeological Sci-<lb/>ence. 2012; 39(12):3483-92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2012.05.033 <lb/>17. Saul H, Madella M, Fischer A, Glykou A, Hartz S, Craig OE. Phytoliths in pottery reveal the use of spice <lb/>in European prehistoric cuisine. PLoS One. 2013; 8(8):e70583. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0070583 PMID: 23990910; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3749173. <lb/>18. Heiss AG, Antolı ´n F, Bleicher N, Harb C, Jacomet S, Ku ¨hn M, et al. State of the (t)art. Analytical <lb/>approaches in the investigation of components and production traits of archaeological bread-like <lb/>objects, applied to two finds from the Neolithic lakeshore settlement Parkhaus Ope ´ra (Zu ¨rich, Switzer-<lb/>land). PLoS One. 2017; 12(8):e0182401. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0182401 PMID: <lb/>28771539 <lb/>19. Heiss AG, Antolin F, Berihuete Azorin M, Biederer B, Erlach R, Gail N, et al. The Hoard of the Rings. <lb/>&quot;Odd&quot; annular bread-like objects as a case study for cereal-product diversity at the Late Bronze Age hill-<lb/>fort site of Stillfried (Lower Austria). PLoS One. 2019; 14(6):e0216907. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0216907 PMID: 31166950; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6550392. <lb/>20. Kubiak-Martens L, Brinkkemper O, Oudemans T. What&apos;s for dinner? Processed food in the coastal area <lb/>of the northern Netherlands in the Late Neolithic. Vegetation History and Archaeobotany. 2015; 24:47-<lb/>62. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00334-014-0485-8 <lb/>21. Oudemans T, Kubiak-Martens L, Limmer B, Kooistra L. Cooking in Pestenacker -Evidence from <lb/>Organic Residues in Vessels from one Household in a Late Neolithic Wetland Settlement in Bavaria <lb/>(3496-3410 BC). 2019; 49:19-40. <lb/>22. Weber J, Brozio JP, Mu ¨ller J, Schwark L. Grave gifts manifest the ritual status of cattle in Neolithic soci-<lb/>eties of northern Germany. Journal of Archaeological Science. 2020; 117:105122. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jas.2020.105122 <lb/>23. Raemaekers D, Kubiak-Martens L, Oudemans T. New food in old pots -charred organic residues in <lb/>Early Neolithic ceramic vessels from Swifterbant, the Netherlands (4300-4000 cal BC). Archaologisches <lb/>Korrespondenzblatt. 2013; 43:315-334. <lb/>24. Knitter D, Brozio JP, Hamer W, Duttmann R, Mu ¨ller J, Nakoinz O. Transformations and Site Locations <lb/>from a Landscape Archaeological Perspective: The Case of Neolithic Wagrien, Schleswig-Holstein, <lb/>Germany. Land. 2019; 8(4):68. https://doi.org/10.3390/land8040068 <lb/>25. Feeser I, Do ¨rfler W. Land-use and environmental history at the Middle Neolithic settlement site Olden-<lb/>burg-Dannau LA 77. Journal of Neolithic Archaeology. 2019; 2019(21):157-207. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>12766/jna.2019.8 <lb/>26. Knitter D, Brozio JP, Do ¨rfler W, Duttmann R, Feeser I, Hamer W, et al. Transforming landscapes: <lb/>Modeling land-use patterns of environmental borderlands. The Holocene. 2019:1572-1586. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1177/0959683619857233 <lb/>27. Dibbern H. Das trichterbecherzeitliche Westholstein. Eine Studie zur neolithischen Entwicklung von <lb/>Landschaft und Gesellschaft. Mu ¨ller J, editor. Bonn: Dr. Rudolf Habelt GmbH; 2016. <lb/>28. Behrens H. Tonscheiben (&quot;Backteller&quot;) aus dem mitteldeutschen Neolithikum. Jahresschr Mitteldt Vor-<lb/>gesch. 1963; 47:127-144. <lb/>29. Hands P, Kourmpetli S, Sharples D, Harris RG, Drea S. Analysis of grain characters in temperate <lb/>grasses reveals distinctive patterns of endosperm organization associated with grain shape. Journal of <lb/>Experimental Botany. 2012; 63(17). https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/ers281 PMID: 23081982 <lb/>30. Dickson C. The identification of cereals from ancient bran fragments. Circaea. 1987; 4(2):95-102. <lb/>31. Ko ¨rber-Grohne U, Piening U. Microstructure of the Surfaces of Carbonized and Non-Carbonized Grains <lb/>of Cereals as Observed in Scanning Electron and Light Microscopes as an Additional Aid in Determining <lb/>Prehistoric Findings. Flora. 1980; 170(3):189-228. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0367-2530(17)31207-0 <lb/>32. Oudemans TFM, Kubiak-Martens L. Broad-spectrum cooking: botanical and chemical evidence in Late <lb/>Neolithic Pottery. In: Kleijne JP, Brinkkemper O, Lauwerier RCGM, Smit BI, Theunissen EM (eds), A <lb/>Matter of Life and Death at Mienakker (the Netherlands), Late Neolithic Behavioural Variability in a <lb/>Dynamic Landscape, Amersfoort, Nederlandse Archeologische Rapporten; 2013; 45:119-146. <lb/>33. Oudemans TFM, Kubiak-Martens L. Mixed food dishes in ceramic vessels. Botanical and chemical <lb/>characterization of charred organic residues. In: Theunissen EM, Brinkkemper O, Lauwerier RCGM, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>36 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Smit BI&amp; van der Jagt I.M.M. (eds), Zones of craft and subsistence at Zeewijk (the Netherlands), Late <lb/>Neolithic behavioral variability in a dynamic landscape. Amersfoort, Nederlandse Archeologische Rap-<lb/>porten 2014; 47:143-165. <lb/>34. Heiss AG, Berihuete-Azorı ´n M, Antolı ´n F, Kubiak-Martens L, Marinova E, Arendt EK, et al. Mashes to <lb/>Mashes, Crust to Crust. Presenting a novel microstructural marker for malting in the archaeological <lb/>record. PLOS ONE. 2020; 15(5):e0231696. Epub 07.05.2020. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0231696 PMID: 32379784 <lb/>35. Brown RC, Lemmon BE, Olsen O-A. Endosperm Development in Barley: Microtubule lnvolvement in <lb/>the Morphogenetic Pathway. The Plant Cell, 1994; 6:1241-1252. <lb/>36. Braadbaart F, Boon J, Veld H, David P, Bergen PF. Laboratory simulations of the transformation of <lb/>peas as a result of heat treatment: Changes of the physical and chemical properties. Journal of Archae-<lb/>ological Science. 2004; 31:821-833. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2003.12.001 <lb/>37. Braadbaart F, Bakels C, Boon J, Bergen P. Heating experiments under anoxic conditions on varieties of <lb/>wheat. Archaeometry. 2005; 47:103-114. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1475-4754.2005.00190.x <lb/>38. Oudemans T, Eijkel G, Boon J. Identifying biomolecular origins of solid organic residues preserved in <lb/>Iron Age Pottery using DTMS and MVA. Journal of Archaeological Science. 2007; 34:173-93. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2006.04.007 <lb/>39. Pastorova I, Botto R, Arisz P, Boon J. Cellulose char structure: a combined analytical Py-GC-MS, FTIR, <lb/>and NMR study. Carbohydrate Research. 1994; 262:27-47. https://doi.org/10.1016/0008-6215(94) <lb/>84003-2 <lb/>40. Derrick MR, Stulik D, Landry JM. Infrared spectroscopy in conservation science. Los Angeles: Getty <lb/>Conservation Institute; 1999. <lb/>41. Vahur S, Teearu A, Peets P, Joosu L, Leito I. ATR-FT-IR spectral collection of conservation materials in <lb/>the extended region of 4000-80 cm-1. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry. 2016; 408(13):3373-<lb/>3379. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216-016-9411-5 PMID: 26968569 <lb/>42. Berihuete-Azorı ´n M, Stika H-P, Hallama M, Valamoti SM. Distinguishing ripe spelt from processed <lb/>green spelt (Gru ¨nkern) grains: Methodological aspects and the case of early La Tène Hochdorf (Vaihin-<lb/>gen a.d. Enz, Germany). Journal of Archaeological Science. 2020;118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas. <lb/>2020.105143 <lb/>43. Al-Azm A. 2009. The importance and antiquity of frikkeh: a simple snack or a socio-economic indicator <lb/>of decline and prosperity in the ancient Near East? In: Fairbairn A.S., Weiss E. (Eds.), From Foragers to <lb/>Farmers. Papers in Honour of Gordon C. Hillman. Oxbow Books, Oxford 2020:112-116. <lb/>44. Miedaner T, Longin F. Unterscha ¨tzte Getreidearten: Einkorn, Emmer, Dinkel &amp; Co. Clenze: AgriMedia; <lb/>2016:168. <lb/>45. Cappers RTJ. Digital Atlas of traditional food made from cereals and milk. Eelde: Barkhuis; 2018. <lb/>46. Oudemans T.F.M., Kubiak-Martens L. 2012. Botanical and chemical characterisation of charred organic <lb/>residues in ceramics. In: Smit BI, Brinkkemper O, Kleijne JP, Lauwerier RCGM, Theunissen EM (eds), <lb/>A kaleidoscope of gathering at Keinsmerbrug (the Netherlands) Late Neolithic Behavioural Variability in <lb/>a Dynamic Landscape, Amersfoort, Nederlandse Archeologische Rapporten 2012; 43:107-130. <lb/>47. Weber J, Brozio JP, Mu ¨ller J, Schwark L. Grave gifts manifest the ritual status of cattle in Neolithic soci-<lb/>eties of northern Germany. Journal of Archaeological Science. 2020; 117:105122. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jas.2020.105122 <lb/>48. Kenney J, Lynch F, Davidson A. A Welsh Landscape through Time: Excavations at Parc Cybi, Holy <lb/>Island, Anglesey; 2021. <lb/>49. Drieu L, Lepère C, Regert M. The Missing Step of Pottery chaı ˆne ope ´ratoire: Considering Post-firing <lb/>Treatments on Ceramic Vessels Using Macro-and Microscopic Observation and Molecular Analysis. <lb/>Journal of Archaeological Method and Theory. 2020; 27:1-25. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10816-019-<lb/>09428-8 <lb/>50. Samuel D. A new look at old bread: Ancient Egyptian baking. Archaeol Internat (London);1999/ <lb/>2000:28-31. <lb/>51. Brewing Samuel D. and baking. In: Nicholson PT, Shaw I, editors. Ancient Egyptian materials and tech-<lb/>nology. Cambridge 2000:537-576. <lb/>52. Peña-Chocarro L, Zapata L. Post-harvest processing of hulled wheats. An ethnoarchaeological <lb/>approach. In: Anderson PC, Cummings LS, Schippers TK, Simonel B, editors. Le traitement des <lb/>Re ´coltes: Un regard sur la Diversite ´, du ne ´olithique au pre ´sent. Antibes 2003:99-113. <lb/>53. Nesbitt M, Samuel D. From staple crop to extinction? The archaeology and history of the hulled wheats. <lb/>In: Padulosi S, Hammer K, Heller J, editors. Hulled Wheat. Promoting the conservation and use of <lb/>underutilized and neglected crops. Gatersleben/Rome: IPK/IPGRI; 1996:40-99. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>37 / 38 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>54. Benincasa P, Falcinelli B, Lutts S, Stagnari F, Galieni A. Sprouted Grains: A Comprehensive Review. <lb/>Nutrients. 2019; 11:421. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu11020421 PMID: 30781547 <lb/>55. Lemmen E, Moroni AV, Pagand J, Heirbaut P, Ritala A, Karlen Y, et al. Impact of Cereal Seed Sprouting <lb/>on Its Nutritional and Technological Properties: A Critical Review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Sci-<lb/>ence and Food Safety 2019; 18:2019. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.12414 PMID: 33337026 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Transformation of Neolithic cereal grains <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296986 January 19, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>38 / 38 </page>


	</text>


  </TEI>