<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T15:15:40.110Z">11/13/2025 3:15:40 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T15:15:26.976009Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T15:15:26.976009Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Disentangling associations between pubertal <lb/>development, healthy activity behaviors, and <lb/>sex in adolescent social networks <lb/>Mark C. Pachucki ID <lb/>1,2 <lb/>*, Lindsay Till Hoyt 3 , Li Niu 3☯ , Richard Carbonaro ID <lb/>1☯ <lb/>, Hsin <lb/>Fei Tu 1☯ , John R. Sirard 4 , Genevieve Chandler 5 <lb/>1 Department of Sociology, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of <lb/>America, 2 UMass Computational Social Science Institute, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, <lb/>Massachusetts, United States of America, 3 Department of Applied Developmental Psychology, Fordham <lb/>University, Bronx, New York, United States of America, 4 School of Public Health &amp; Health Sciences, <lb/>University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America, 5 Elaine Marieb <lb/>College of Nursing, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, Massachusetts, United States of America <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* mpachucki@umass.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>With the onset of puberty, youth begin to choose their social environments and develop <lb/>health-promoting habits, making it a vital period to study social and biological factors contex-<lb/>tually. An important question is how pubertal development and behaviors such as physical <lb/>activity and sleep may be differentially linked with youths&apos; friendships. Cross-sectional statis-<lb/>tical network models that account for interpersonal dependence were used to estimate <lb/>associations between three measures of pubertal development and youth friendships at two <lb/>large US schools drawn from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health. <lb/>Whole-network models suggest that friendships are more likely between youth with similar <lb/>levels of pubertal development, physical activity, and sleep. Sex-stratified models suggest <lb/>that girls&apos; friendships are more likely given a similar age at menarche. Attention to similar <lb/>pubertal timing within friendship groups may offer inclusive opportunities for tailored devel-<lb/>opmental puberty education in ways that reduce stigma and improve health behaviors. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Certain stages of the life-course can have disproportionate influences on future social develop-<lb/>ment and health [1-3]. With the onset of puberty and adolescence, youth begin to choose their <lb/>own social relationships, environments, and develop activity patterns [4], making it a vital <lb/>period to study how social and biological factors are intertwined. During this time, scholars <lb/>have noted that certain key physical behaviors change significantly: physical activity levels <lb/>decline, and older adolescents go to bed later and sleep less than younger adolescents in ways <lb/>that vary by sex and race/ethnicity [5-8]. Adequate physical activity has decreased for boys <lb/>and remains low for girls [9], and adolescent sleep has declined considerably from 1991 to <lb/>2012 [10]. Importantly, it has also been established that during adolescence, patterns of social <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/>1 / 25 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Pachucki MC, Hoyt LT, Niu L, Carbonaro <lb/>R, Tu HF, Sirard JR, et al. (2024) Disentangling <lb/>associations between pubertal development, <lb/>healthy activity behaviors, and sex in adolescent <lb/>social networks. PLoS ONE 19(5): e0300715. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 <lb/>Editor: Yasas Chandra Tanguturi, University of <lb/>Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, UNITED <lb/>STATES <lb/>Received: November 15, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: March 3, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 16, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Pachucki et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: This research uses <lb/>third party data from the National Longitudinal <lb/>Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health). <lb/></front>

			<body>relationships are associated with these same activity behaviors [11-15]. Pubertal development <lb/>is also associated with activity behaviors [16-18], with some evidence of pubertal development <lb/>being correlated among friends [19, 20]. <lb/>Yet it remains an outstanding question how pubertal development and these related physi-<lb/>cal behaviors (physical activity and sleep) may be differentially associated with youth socializa-<lb/>tion, because these factors tend to be studied in isolation. Why might puberty and activity <lb/>behaviors be associated with an adolescent&apos;s friendship networks, and why should we pay <lb/>attention to these associations? One response to these questions has to do with homophilic <lb/>selection processes-the idea that youth may choose to become friends with others who enjoy <lb/>similar activities, come from similar backgrounds, or have similar development status. Net-<lb/>work analysis is positioned to address this analytic challenge of disentangling these selection <lb/>processes by modeling the complex patterns of relationship dependence between individuals <lb/>[21, 22]. As such, the goals of this study are to: (1) determine the extent to which pubertal <lb/>development and activity behaviors (physical activity and sleep) may independently be associ-<lb/>ated with social relationships among friends using exponential random graph modeling, a <lb/>form of network analysis which is able to account for correlated observations between individ-<lb/>uals, and (2) to discern how these associations may vary by sex. The idea that pubertal develop-<lb/>ment and activity behaviors may be patterned within adolescent friendship networks is <lb/>supported by a small but growing body of evidence from the landmark U.S.-based National <lb/>Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health) study [23], as well as interna-<lb/>tional cohort studies [19, 24]. Knowing of similar pubertal timing within friendship groups <lb/>may offer inclusive opportunities for tailored developmental puberty education in ways that <lb/>reduce stigma by normalizing conversations about physical and physiological changes during <lb/>adolescence with trusted adults. <lb/>Puberty and friendship group dynamics <lb/>Puberty is often a time of mismatch in social and biological development. During this period <lb/>of transition, emotional and cognitive maturity can be temporarily out of sync with behavioral <lb/>expectations for individuals of a given age. Being off-time from peers is thought to be stressful, <lb/>as newfound physical distinction can elicit different reactions from both adults and peers. <lb/>Maturing earlier than peers (i.e. early timing) is theorized to be associated with an abbreviated <lb/>timespan in which to develop a strong sense of self-identity and find accepting friends [25, 26]. <lb/>In the case that puberty begins when expected, youth can anticipate, prepare, and learn how to <lb/>cope with their changing situation in community with their peers, whereas youth who begin <lb/>developing before (or after) their peers may face insecurity and heightened stress. <lb/>In one of the only large-scale studies to date to directly focus on the network distribution of <lb/>pubertal development within peer friendship groups [20], Kretsch and colleagues explored <lb/>multiple measures of development: one measure based upon an adolescent&apos;s perception of <lb/>themselves relative to peers (i.e., relative pubertal timing), and another of stage-normative <lb/>physical development based upon more traditional physical indicators of puberty (i.e. in boys, <lb/>voice change and body hair; in girls, breast development, menarche, body curviness). The <lb/>investigators examined a cross-section of more than 2800 participants (middle to late adoles-<lb/>cence) in the Add Health sample during 1994-95, using partial correlation analysis of pubertal <lb/>development measures pooled across 16 schools, intra-class correlations to assess between-<lb/>school variation in these measures, and sex-stratified mixed-effects models predicting different <lb/>pubertal timing measures to account for between-school pubertal timing clustering. The <lb/>authors found that for boys, stage-normative pubertal development was positively associated <lb/>with that of their nominated (male) friends, and that for girls, relative pubertal timing was <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<front>Information on how to obtain the Add Health data <lb/>files is available on the Add Health website (http:// <lb/>www.cpc.unc.edu/addhealth). To apply for these <lb/>data, the researcher must request access and <lb/>download a contract application from the UNC <lb/>Carolina Population Center Data Portal (https:// <lb/>data.cpc.unc.edu/projects/2/view). Once <lb/>completed, researchers must submit their <lb/>application through the portal. Data used in the <lb/>current study were not collected by the study <lb/>authors and therefore we do not have the <lb/>permission to share the data. The data used are <lb/>restricted use data from the Add Health study. <lb/>Researchers who wish to gain access to this data <lb/>must apply for access using the information <lb/>specified above. The authors did not have any <lb/>special access privileges to the data and confirm <lb/>that the data was obtained in the same manner <lb/>outlined above. Relevant codes for replicating <lb/>analyses are within the Supporting information files <lb/>of this manuscript. <lb/>Funding: Research reported in this study was <lb/>supported by the National Institute of Nursing <lb/>Research under Award Number R21NR017154 to <lb/>Co-PIs Mark C. Pachucki and Lindsay T. Hoyt. This <lb/>research uses data from the National Longitudinal <lb/>Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health). <lb/>Add Health is directed by Robert A. Hummer and <lb/>funded by the National Institute on Aging <lb/>cooperative agreements U01 AG071448 (Hummer) <lb/>and U01AG071450 (Allison E. Aiello and Hummer) <lb/>at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. <lb/>Waves I-V data are from the Add Health Program <lb/>Project, grant P01 HD319121 (Harris) was directed <lb/>by Kathleen Mullan Harris and designed by J. <lb/>Richard Udry, Peter S. Bearman, and Kathleen <lb/>Mullan Harris at the University of North Carolina at <lb/>Chapel Hill, and funded by Grant P01-HD31921 <lb/>from the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute <lb/>of Child Health and Human Development, with <lb/>cooperative funding from 23 other federal agencies <lb/>and foundations. No direct support was received <lb/>from grant P01-HD31921 for this analysis. The <lb/>funders had no role in study design, data collection <lb/>and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>similar to nominated (female) friends. The authors also examined whether this apparent clus-<lb/>tering differed by school, finding between-school differences in boys&apos; stage-normative pubertal <lb/>development after adjusting for mean school age and percentages of Black and Hispanic stu-<lb/>dents at each school, given racial/ethnic differences in pubertal onset. <lb/>Several takeaways are that even with relatively rough network measures of peer pubertal <lb/>development (relying upon an average of nominated friends&apos; development measures), the <lb/>authors document associations within friend groups. These associations vary by sex, and <lb/>importantly, these associations also differ by local school environment. However, the design of <lb/>this study only focused on same-sex friendships, precluding analysis of pubertal development <lb/>and cross-sex social ties. Perhaps more importantly, what this or any type of analysis con-<lb/>ducted in a regression framework cannot do is account for the statistical dependencies between <lb/>youth-that two individuals nominated as friends by a given youth may themselves be con-<lb/>nected as friends. These types of endogenous network properties are critical to consider. <lb/>A separate body of work has shown that variation in pubertal development is also related to <lb/>risky behaviors, such as various forms of delinquency and age of sexual debut, which are also <lb/>associated with friendship dynamics [27, 28]. Most relevant to the questions motivating this <lb/>study, Franken et al. [19] performed a statistically rigorous longitudinal network-behavior <lb/>study of friendship formation and externalizing behaviors (delinquency, smoking, drinking) <lb/>among early adolescents in two different schools in the Netherlands over the course of a year <lb/>(μ = 12.7 years of age, equivalent to 7 th -8 th grade in the US). The study design was able to <lb/>account for endogenous network properties in contrast to previous regression-based research. <lb/>The authors found that youth who had similar physical development were more likely to form <lb/>friendships with one another, and that physically more advanced were more likely to retain <lb/>friendships with students who engaged in similar externalizing behaviors. A separate longitu-<lb/>dinal three year network-behavior study of Taiwanese youths&apos; substance use and network <lb/>change (grades 7 to 9, age μ = 12.3) gathered information on the Pubertal Development Scale <lb/>to ascertain whether youth were on-time, early, or late relative to peers [24]. The authors did <lb/>not observe either selection or network influence effects on pubertal development. However, <lb/>whether this tendency towards friendship among similar-development youth applies in the <lb/>United States (US) context, and whether it holds for physical behaviors (vs. externalizing risk <lb/>behaviors) remain open questions. Speculatively, given sociocultural norms between the Neth-<lb/>erlands (more Western social context) and Taiwan (more collectivistic), we might expect a <lb/>closer fit with findings from the Dutch youth study. <lb/>Physical behaviors and networks <lb/>While some prior research concerning pubertal development and health behaviors focuses on <lb/>risk behaviors related to delinquency, drug use, and sexual activity, another subset of research <lb/>treats youths&apos; physical behaviors as different types of risk critical to cardiometabolic health <lb/>[29-32]. Network research has shown that adolescent physical activity (PA) and sleep behav-<lb/>iors are correlated within youth social networks [for reviews, see 12, 33, 34]. For instance, <lb/>among a cohort of Australian early adolescents (roughly ages 13 to 14), cross-sectional expo-<lb/>nential graph models at two different schools revealed that same-sex friends were similar in <lb/>terms of organized physical activity behaviors [35]. Sirard and colleagues [36] investigated <lb/>moderate-to-vigorous PA among nearly 2,800 students from 20 public schools in Minneapolis <lb/>&amp; St. Paul, Minnesota, finding that PA levels were similar among socially-connected friends, <lb/>with slightly stronger associations for girls. <lb/>More rigorous longitudinal network research designs, however, have attempted to discern <lb/>reasons for similarity in physical activity (e.g. selection or social influence mechanisms). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Drawing upon participants in two of the largest schools in the Add Health parent study (&apos;Sun-<lb/>shine High&apos;, a pseudonym for a suburban public high school in the western US; and &apos;Jefferson <lb/>High&apos;, a public high school in the rural Midwest), Shoham and colleagues found that in both <lb/>schools, adolescents selected one another, in part, based on the volume of active sports they <lb/>engaged in [37]. There was also evidence of social influence on changes in active sport levels. A <lb/>separate team advanced an elaborated model specification by simultaneously modeling physi-<lb/>cal activity and weight change as behaviors that jointly co-evolve with friendship formation, <lb/>including different weight-related confounders and interactions in models. This study found <lb/>that at both schools, adolescents select one another for friendships partially because of shared <lb/>PA levels and body-mass index (BMI), but that ties to friends also influence changes in PA and <lb/>BMI over time [13]. <lb/>While studies documenting causes for adolescent sleep decline are clear that electronically-<lb/>mediated interactions with friends are associated [38, 39], there has been a limited amount of <lb/>network research on sleep. Two exceptions are a longitudinal study based upon more than <lb/>8,000 participants in Add Health at Waves I &amp; II, in which the authors used generalized esti-<lb/>mating equation regression models and found an increased risk of poor sleep if one&apos;s friends <lb/>previously reported sleeping poorly, adjusting for one&apos;s own baseline sleep and other covari-<lb/>ates [15]. A more recent Add Health study restricted to students in Sunshine High and Jeffer-<lb/>son High (n = 2,550 participants) used linear regression analyses to find that sleep <lb/>insufficiency was associated with network popularity (a greater amount of friendship nomina-<lb/>tions) among girls [40]. Finally, one recent study relying upon data from Waves I-IV of Add <lb/>Health investigated the relationships between pubertal timing and risk/health promotion <lb/>behaviors, including sleep health, in the full sample. Though this study did not examine social <lb/>networks, earlier pubertal timing put girls at risk for less sleep during adolescence. However, <lb/>there was also some evidence that later timing is associated with health promoting (e.g., more <lb/>sleep) activity behaviors [41]. Specifically, for both boys and girls, later adolescent physical <lb/>development was prospectively associated with reporting more sleep nightly as young adults. <lb/>Hypotheses <lb/>To briefly review, prior research on puberty and networks has suggested some correlation <lb/>among friends&apos; pubertal development using cross-sectional regression-based methods: one <lb/>study in a US secondary school context (Add Health) pooled respondents across more than a <lb/>dozen schools, while two separate studies based on a Netherlands sample and Taiwan sample <lb/>of youth, respectively, both used stochastic actor-oriented models, finding in the Dutch case <lb/>that youth selected one another for friendships, in part, based on pubertal development. Sepa-<lb/>rately, prior actor-oriented research has demonstrated evidence of both social influence and <lb/>friendship selection mechanisms associated with adolescents&apos; physical activity among students <lb/>in Add Health, and prior regression-based studies have shown sleep to be associated with <lb/>friendship patterns as well. <lb/>While these studies have been illuminating, they were also not designed to provide answers <lb/>to the central question of this study: How are pubertal development and important physical <lb/>behaviors associated with an adolescent&apos;s patterns of friendships? On one hand, the prior use <lb/>of regression-based methods for US adolescent data pose difficulties in accounting for network <lb/>dependencies among youth who know one another and the associated endogenous network <lb/>processes that play into friendship formation. On the other hand, prior network studies that <lb/>account for statistical dependence and that integrate puberty measures into analyses have, to <lb/>date, only been conducted in countries outside the US. Thus, an appropriate starting point for <lb/>analysis of our research question is to use a statistical network approach, exponential random <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>graph models (ERGMs), that can appropriately handle dependence concerns. While we ini-<lb/>tially considered a longitudinal network-behavior framework such as SAOMs (and indeed, <lb/>some earlier Add Health network studies have used SAOMs), we felt that given our relatively <lb/>narrow research question it would be more conservative to use ERGMs, especially given that <lb/>model developers have recommended the use of more than two waves of network behavior <lb/>data for best model fit [42]. <lb/>Given prior research with the Add Health cohort, it is important to first conceptually repli-<lb/>cate the same patterns of PA and sleep homophily among friends using an ERGM framework <lb/>that others have observed using different methods. This will enable better contextualization of <lb/>results with earlier efforts. Beyond this, however, we test two novel hypotheses, first, that ado-<lb/>lescents&apos; pubertal development will be associated with a greater likelihood of friendship forma-<lb/>tion with them (Hypothesis 1). Prior network research does not lead us to clearly predict a <lb/>direction for this association, though developmental research gives some guidance. On one <lb/>hand, it is plausible that youth who report being significantly earlier developmentally than <lb/>peers will have a lower odds of friendship formation due to the stress of being more physically <lb/>advanced than one&apos;s peers-being more physically developed than peers can be a social asset <lb/>though also stigmatizing. Alternatively, being significantly later than peers might lead individ-<lb/>uals to simply join younger (or younger-looking) friendship groups, though this seems less <lb/>likely given how school grades are largely age-tracked. On balance, it is likely that being more <lb/>developed-even if earlier than peers-will be associated with more friendships. <lb/>Further, prior research on concordance in pubertal status among nominated friends [20] <lb/>suggests that pubertal development among socially-tied friends will also vary by sex (Hypothe-<lb/>sis 2), though, given lack of prior network research in this area, it is difficult to predict whether <lb/>specific measures of pubertal development will be associated with social ties among boys or <lb/>girls. Given that girls develop earlier than boys, it is likely that we will observe these associa-<lb/>tions more clearly for girls. Last, given that individual schools have different sizes, demo-<lb/>graphic compositions, climate and cultures, and organizational differentiation-what <lb/>McFarland and colleagues [43] describe as &apos;network ecology&apos;-we do not expect a consistent <lb/>magnitude of effect sizes between schools, though we do have a minimum expectation of a <lb/>similar direction for associations between pubertal development and friendship ties. <lb/>H1: Adolescents&apos; pubertal development will be associated with a greater likelihood of friend-<lb/>ship formation with them. <lb/>H2: Pubertal development among socially-tied friends will vary by sex, with pubertal timing <lb/>homophily more apparent among girls than boys. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>To test these hypotheses, analyses draw from the initial wave (1994-95) of the National Longi-<lb/>tudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health (Add Health). In the original parent study, high <lb/>schools (n = 80) and feeder middle schools (n = 52) were selected from a stratified nationally <lb/>representative sample of all public and private schools in the U.S. In-home interviews were <lb/>conducted with 20,745 students and families. From these schools, 16 were selected for inspec-<lb/>tion (commonly called &quot;saturation schools&quot;, because they represented an above-average <lb/>attempt at increased recruitment by study investigators and have more complete data). Given <lb/>the range of confounders that were necessary to account for, we chose to focus on the two larg-<lb/>est of these sixteen schools. These schools are referred to in prior research by their pseudo-<lb/>nyms, &quot;Sunshine High&quot; (n = 1721), and &quot;Jefferson High&quot; (n = 832). After excluding <lb/>participants who did not have valid grade-level information, the sample size decreased slightly <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Sunshine n = 1658; Jefferson n = 806). After excluding participants who did not have com-<lb/>plete covariate data, the sample size decreased further (Sunshine n = 1568; Jefferson n = 775). <lb/>Missing covariate proportions at Sunshine High were parent education (3.4%), relative <lb/>puberty (1.15%), physical development (1.6%), race (0.54%), ethnicity (0.36%), screen time <lb/>(0.18%), sleep duration (0.18%). sleep sufficiency (0.18%). Missing at Jefferson High were par-<lb/>ent education (1.6%), relative puberty (1.12%), physical development (1.6%), screen time <lb/>(0.12%), sleep duration (0.12%). <lb/>After excluding participants who did not make any valid in-school friend nominations, we <lb/>arrived at the final analytic sample (Sunshine n = 1408; Jefferson n = 762). We did not impute <lb/>missing data due to strong assumptions required to do so in a network context, where data <lb/>may be missing on both individuals&apos; attributes as well as missing on possible social ties <lb/>between them [44]. While research on network imputation has advanced in recent years [45-<lb/>47] the complexities of model-based imputation strategies are not yet easily implemented on <lb/>large and sparse (decentralized) networks such as the ones we focus on in this study. This <lb/>study used de-identified secondary data from human participants, accessed March 2023, in <lb/>accordance with the ethical standards of the University of Massachusetts under human sub-<lb/>jects protocol #1059. <lb/>Measures <lb/>Friendship relations. Social ties (Wave I) were identified by asking participants to name <lb/>up to 10 friends (5 male, 5 female) during interviews. Crucially, because nominated friends <lb/>were also study participants, their respective pubertal development, physical behaviors, and <lb/>other attributes are informative in analyses. We constructed networks based upon directed <lb/>social tie information, but because of the difficulties of estimating large models using directed <lb/>ties, chose to symmetrize networks such that a tie linking participant i À ! j or participant j <lb/>À ! i results in an undirected tie between i and j. Nominations to friends outside a given <lb/>school were discarded. <lb/>Pubertal development. Three measures of puberty were assessed. The first was a measure <lb/>of physical development derived from selected questions about intra-individual changes based <lb/>on the Pubertal Development Scale (PDS), the most widely used self-report [48]. These ques-<lb/>tions focus on bodily changes that become evident in mid-to-late puberty (e.g. body hair for <lb/>boys, breast development for girls). Respondents were asked to answer about these bodily <lb/>changes relative to &quot;when I was in grade school&quot; as an anchor. We then coded responses to <lb/>these measures into a continuous scale that ranged from 1 (least developed/very little change) <lb/>to 5 (most developed/a lot of change) by taking the mean of responses to three questions for <lb/>boys (i.e., facial hair, body hair, and voice change) and two questions for girls (i.e., breast devel-<lb/>opment and body curviness) and combining them into a single scale. A second measure of <lb/>puberty was perceived inter-individual development, or peer-relative pubertal timing. This <lb/>measure was assessed with the question, &quot;How advanced is your physical development com-<lb/>pared to other boys/girls your age?&quot; Responses could range from &quot;1: I look younger than most&quot;, <lb/>&quot;2: I look younger than some &quot;, &quot;3: I look about average&quot;, &quot;4: I look older than some&quot;, and &quot;5: I <lb/>look older than most&quot;. The third measure was age of menarche, for girls, and across the schools <lb/>it ranged from 7 to 16 years. Although menarche was also included in the original PDS, sepa-<lb/>rating it from our measure of physical development allows for the remaining items to contrib-<lb/>ute to a common development measure across boys and girls, and allows for evaluating <lb/>menarche as a distinct contributor to friendship in girls-only models. <lb/>Physical behaviors. Self-reported physical activity (PA) was assessed by summing ques-<lb/>tions on activity type and frequency. Previous work has used these questions to measure <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>environmental determinants of PA [49], adolescent to adult behavior patterns [50, 51] associa-<lb/>tions between future expectations and health behaviors [52], and the link between family rela-<lb/>tionships and PA [53]. In terms of PA, following exemplars [13, 52], we summed the three <lb/>available measures of past-week activity to provide a holistic measure: the frequency of skat-<lb/>ing/biking, the frequency of playing an active sport, and the frequency of exercising. <lb/>Several Add Health questions have been used to measure sleep, including a question about <lb/>typical sleep duration (hours) and whether or not participants felt they got sufficient sleep in <lb/>an average night [7, 54]. We use both sleep duration and sleep sufficiency measures because of <lb/>individual differences in need for sleep. <lb/>Confounders. Information was gathered on participant sex (Male/Female-no gender <lb/>identity information was available); age (based on date of birth); race (White; Black; Asian <lb/>American /Pacific Islander, AAPI; Native American; Other race); Hispanic ethnicity; and <lb/>highest parent education (&lt;HS, HS graduate/GED, some college, college graduate, post-col-<lb/>lege education). In addition, models adjust for participant grade. Because pubertal develop-<lb/>ment, activity behaviors, and socialization are often related to weight status, we also include an <lb/>indicator for &quot;overweight or obese&quot; derived from self-report of height and weight using Cen-<lb/>ters for Disease Control sex and age-specific thresholds for children implemented in the Stata <lb/>&apos;zanthro&apos; package [55]. To measure screen time as a confounder of primary physical behaviors <lb/>(PA and sleep), we summed three measures: TV hours (per week), video hours, and screen <lb/>games [49]. How youth make use of screens in the modern era (screens as a two-way medium) <lb/>is drastically different than how youth in the mid-1990s made use of screens (a one-way <lb/>medium). While we would have liked to analyze youth screen time as a primary activity behav-<lb/>ior (given its links to both physical activity and sleep), we were convinced by helpful reviewers <lb/>that doing so would primarily be of historical interest rather than generalizable to today&apos;s <lb/>youth. Last, because of a programming irregularity in the parent study, not all participants <lb/>were afforded a chance to nominate the full list of 5 female and 5 male friends. Those who <lb/>were restricted to one best friend of either sex were denoted with an indicator variable <lb/>(&quot;restricted nomination&quot;); this affected approximately 4% of Sunshine participants, and 5% of <lb/>Jefferson participants. <lb/>Considerations regarding modern adolescent socialization, pubertal <lb/>development, and activities <lb/>It is important to note that how adolescents socialize in today&apos;s smartphone era differs consid-<lb/>erably from the 1990s, and today, offline and online interactions need to be considered care-<lb/>fully [56-58]. Screens are now ubiquitous in a way that is qualitatively different from youth <lb/>experiences with visual media in the 1990s. Yet because these friendship data were collected <lb/>nearly 30 years ago, they enjoy the now-rare advantage of avoiding measurement complica-<lb/>tions between online and offline ties. Today&apos;s youth are broadly similar in many ways as well. <lb/>Then, as now, physical proximity, or propinquity, remains a dominant driver of friendship in <lb/>schools. Physical activity measures, while lacking the precision of contemporary measures like <lb/>GPS-enabled accelerometry, are still quite informative about variation in common youth activ-<lb/>ities. While greater precision of sleep measurement is also now possible with wearable moni-<lb/>tors, self-reported sleep sufficiency and sleep duration measures are still widely used. In terms <lb/>of pubertal development, the onset of puberty has rapidly declined since the industrial revolu-<lb/>tion [59] and has continued to decline (albeit more slowly) during the past several decades [60, <lb/>61]. Thus, if, as we hypothesize, similarity in pubertal development and physical behaviors are <lb/>associated with greater likelihood of friendship ties, we would predict such estimates to repre-<lb/>sent a relatively conservative snapshot of a patterned social phenomenon that is likely to be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>even more stark today. In sum, we take the position that these analyses can be informative to <lb/>the current era and not simply historical analysis, a point we return to in our conclusions. <lb/>Analytic approach <lb/>Social network analysis (SNA) is a field of inquiry that seeks to explain the causes and conse-<lb/>quences of patterned social relationships among humans; a wealth of useful guides are readily <lb/>accessible [e.g. 62-64]. A key feature of SNA is a practical and statistical concern not just for <lb/>individual attributes and qualities, but also a concern with quantities and qualities of ties <lb/>between individuals and how-together-individuals and their social ties are connected with a <lb/>given phenomenon. One type of SNA, exponential random graph models (ERGMs), were <lb/>used to test study hypotheses and estimate determinants of friendship formation separately <lb/>within each school using the software package R [65]. Briefly, ERGMs are simulation-based <lb/>statistical models designed to estimate the patterns of tie formation and dyadic dependencies <lb/>in relational data [66, 67]. In this model framework, the outcome of interest is the probability <lb/>that an adolescent will become a friend with another adolescent. In this framework, ERGMs <lb/>predict the probability of tie formation incorporating both network attributes and covariates <lb/>pertaining to adolescents as well as explicitly accounting for interpersonal ties among them. <lb/>We use ERGMs to model the network as a function of network structure, individual and <lb/>dyadic covariates [65, 68] as follows: <lb/>Pr Y ¼ y <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>k <lb/>� � <lb/>exp <lb/>X <lb/>A ZAgA y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>In Eq 1, the probability of tie formation with another youth (Y) is conditional on the matrix <lb/>of covariates, while ηA are coefficients of covariates and gA are network statistics [65, 69, 70]. <lb/>κ represents a normalizing quantity for the distribution [65]. <lb/>There are three types of covariates included in models: structural (endogenous) network <lb/>effects, individual-level covariates, and dyadic covariates, and with limited exceptions (race <lb/>and ethnicity covariates, discussed below), we sought to estimate the same model specification <lb/>across both schools. For structural network effects, we adjust for the general rate of tie forma-<lb/>tion (&quot;edges&quot;) in the network, for geometrically-weighted degree in the network (a measure of <lb/>an individual&apos;s network size), and for geometrically-weighted edgewise shared partners (a <lb/>measure of triadic closure). Individual covariates include three measures of pubertal develop-<lb/>ment (physical development, peer-relative timing, and age of menarche for girls), physical <lb/>behaviors (weekly PA, sleep duration, and sleep sufficiency), sex, school grade, age, parent&apos;s <lb/>highest education level, and race and ethnicity (at Sunshine only, as there was minimal varia-<lb/>tion at Jefferson). <lb/>The dyadic covariates in this paper measure different forms of homophily in the network, <lb/>the tendency for ties to form between two linked adolescents with the same attributes. Here, <lb/>we measure same-grade (within each grade), same-race (within each category), same-ethnicity, <lb/>same-physical development, same-peer-relative-timing, same-PA, same-sleep duration, and <lb/>same-sleep sufficiency. For continuous variables (PA, sleep duration, physical development, <lb/>peer-relative timing, menarche age for girls), we use a term to measure the absolute difference <lb/>in values between any two individuals on that covariate [71]. A negative coefficient on contin-<lb/>uous similarity (&quot;absdiff&quot;) indicates stronger homophily (since absolute differences in a value <lb/>decrease as values trend towards being more similar). The remaining dyadic similarity vari-<lb/>ables are dichotomous (1 = same, 0 = different), and use a &quot;nodematch&quot; term to calculate cate-<lb/>gorical similarity (a positive coefficient indicates greater friendship likelihood, a negative <lb/>coefficient lower). To address questions about sex differences in determinants of tie formation, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>we take a network stratification approach, following de la Haye and colleagues [35] and gener-<lb/>ate a male-only network and female-only network in each school, as they did. To exhaustively <lb/>capture all ties, we also construct a residual subnetwork which is solely comprised of cross-sex <lb/>social ties (male-female). <lb/>Results <lb/>Table 1 summarizes the sample characteristics of participants at both schools. The broad con-<lb/>tours of the social and demographic characteristics of students at these schools are well-<lb/>known, and given that the analytic sample is largely similar to other published work [13, 20, <lb/>40] we do not go into great descriptive detail. However, with regard to both pubertal develop-<lb/>ment measures, participants at Jefferson High report being slightly more developmentally <lb/>mature than those at Sunshine (both in terms of physical development, as well as perceptions <lb/>of pubertal development relative to same-sex peers), which is curious given the younger aver-<lb/>age age of Jefferson participants (μ = 16.9 and SD = 1.2, relative to μ = 17.3 and SD = 1.0 at <lb/>Sunshine). It is already known that given the smaller school size of Jefferson and greater net-<lb/>work density, participants report a greater number of friends than at Sunshine. Jefferson stu-<lb/>dents tend to have slightly healthier behaviors (more PA, a greater amount of sleep and sleep <lb/>sufficiency, less screen time), and are less overweight/obese. <lb/>Correlates of friendship formation <lb/>Table 2 reports on estimates of stepwise models across both schools. On the whole, model <lb/>diagnostics indicated adequate VIF metrics, adequate degree parameters, suboptimal edgewise <lb/>shared partners at segments of the distribution, relatively poor geodesic distance (expected <lb/>given large schools) and appropriate MCMC algorithm convergence, though Sunshine was on <lb/>the whole better-fit than Jefferson. GOF and MCMC plots for both schools&apos; models are avail-<lb/>able in the S1 File. The base model includes key endogenous network terms, the second adds <lb/>puberty predictors, the third adds activity behaviors and confounders, and the last adds dyadic <lb/>homophily terms. At both schools, as others have shown, there is a tendency towards larger <lb/>network size being associated with tie formation (greater degree), and a higher likelihood of <lb/>friendship based upon having friends in common (geometrically-weighted edgewise shared <lb/>partners). In addition, tendencies towards same-race, same-sex, and same-grade social ties <lb/>among youth have been well-established among youth across multiple schools [66]. Youth at <lb/>both schools with more PA tend to have more friendships, and at Sunshine, youth reporting <lb/>longer sleep tend to have fewer friendships. There is also a tendency for older and higher-SES <lb/>youth to form more friendships. At Sunshine High, where there is greater racial and ethnic <lb/>diversity, Black and AAPI youth are less likely to form friendships relative to White non-His-<lb/>panic students, while those classified as &apos;Other non-Hispanic&apos; race are more likely to form <lb/>friendships. <lb/>The set of dyadic terms included in the model indicate a tendency towards same-sex, same-<lb/>grade, and same-weight status friendships (at both schools), and same-race and same-ethnicity <lb/>friendships (at Sunshine High, which has sufficient racial diversity to test for this association). <lb/>In terms of the key dyadic terms of interest (pubertal development and activity behaviors), <lb/>youth with similar PA levels at both schools tended to form ties (Sunshine High, b = -0.024, <lb/>p = &lt;0.001, Jefferson High, b = -0.020, p = 0.0002). Youth at Sunshine High with similar rela-<lb/>tive pubertal timing (b = -0.040, p = 0.032) tended to be friends. Youth at Jefferson who had <lb/>similar sleep duration also tended to be friends (b = -0.032, p = 0.02). Again, for interpretation <lb/>purposes, we reiterate that negative dyadic homophily coefficients indicate greater similarity <lb/>because the model term is based upon absolute difference. Having the same sleep sufficiency <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>status was not significantly associated with tie formation at either school below p&lt;0.05, though <lb/>at both schools there are indications of a trend in this direction of similar size. Because inter-<lb/>preting unadjusted coefficients in ERGMs is not necessarily straightforward for readers unfa-<lb/>miliar with this statistical approach, we contextualize that the magnitude of these dyadic <lb/>Table 1. Participant characteristics (Baseline, 1994-95). <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>School 1 (&quot;Sunshine High&quot;) <lb/>School 2 (&quot;Jefferson High&quot;) <lb/>n = <lb/>μ / % <lb/>SD <lb/>Range <lb/>n = <lb/>μ / % <lb/>SD <lb/>Range <lb/>Pubertal timing <lb/>Physical development <lb/>1,408 <lb/>2.70 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>762 <lb/>3.07 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>Peer-relative pubertal timing <lb/>1,408 <lb/>2.97 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>762 <lb/>3.36 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>Age at menarche (Girls only) <lb/>632 <lb/>12.21 <lb/>1.39 <lb/>8 <lb/>-<lb/>16 <lb/>343 <lb/>12.29 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>16 <lb/>Activity Behaviors <lb/>Physical activity, times/wk <lb/>1,408 <lb/>6.24 <lb/>3.96 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>18 <lb/>762 <lb/>6.78 <lb/>4.19 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>18 <lb/>Sleep duration, avg hours/wk <lb/>1408 <lb/>7.35 <lb/>1.26 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>12 <lb/>762 <lb/>7.59 <lb/>1.39 <lb/>4 <lb/>-<lb/>14 <lb/>Sufficient sleep <lb/>No <lb/>524 <lb/>37.2% <lb/>232 <lb/>30.4% <lb/>Yes <lb/>884 <lb/>62.8% <lb/>530 <lb/>69.6% <lb/>Socio-demographic covariates <lb/>Gender <lb/>Female <lb/>679 <lb/>48.2% <lb/>352 <lb/>46.2% <lb/>Male <lb/>729 <lb/>51.8% <lb/>410 <lb/>53.8% <lb/>Grade <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>223 <lb/>29.3% <lb/>10 <lb/>489 <lb/>34.7% <lb/>218 <lb/>28.6% <lb/>11 <lb/>494 <lb/>35.1% <lb/>174 <lb/>22.8% <lb/>12 <lb/>425 <lb/>30.2% <lb/>147 <lb/>19.3% <lb/>Age <lb/>1408 <lb/>17.3 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>15 <lb/>-<lb/>21 <lb/>762 <lb/>16.9 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>15 <lb/>-<lb/>20 <lb/>Race <lb/>White <lb/>283 <lb/>20.1% <lb/>742 <lb/>97.4% <lb/>Black <lb/>321 <lb/>22.8% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Asian <lb/>477 <lb/>33.9% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Other <lb/>327 <lb/>23.2% <lb/>20 <lb/>2.6% <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>555 <lb/>39.4% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Parent&apos;s highest education <lb/>&lt;HS grad <lb/>337 <lb/>23.9% <lb/>46 <lb/>6.0% <lb/>HS grad/GED <lb/>325 <lb/>23.1% <lb/>296 <lb/>38.8% <lb/>Some college <lb/>286 <lb/>20.3% <lb/>183 <lb/>24.0% <lb/>College grad <lb/>338 <lb/>24.0% <lb/>168 <lb/>22.0% <lb/>Post-college <lb/>122 <lb/>8.7% <lb/>69 <lb/>9.1% <lb/>Overweight/Obese <lb/>No <lb/>982 <lb/>69.7% <lb/>578 <lb/>75.9% <lb/>Yes <lb/>426 <lb/>30.3% <lb/>184 <lb/>24.1% <lb/>Screen time scale, hours/wk <lb/>1,408 <lb/>22.10 <lb/>17.99 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>115 <lb/>762 <lb/>18.77 <lb/>18.67 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>175 <lb/>Restricted friend nominations <lb/>No <lb/>1,355 <lb/>96.2% <lb/>723 <lb/>94.9% <lb/>Yes <lb/>53 <lb/>3.8% <lb/>39 <lb/>5.1% <lb/>Network attributes <lb/>Degree (mean) <lb/>1,408 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>762 <lb/>6.62 <lb/>3.54 <lb/>Edges <lb/>2717 <lb/>2521 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Tie formation models, two large schools. <lb/>School 1 (&quot;Sunshine High&quot;) <lb/>School 2 (&quot;Jefferson High&quot;) <lb/>Puberty <lb/>+ Confounds <lb/>+ Dyadic terms <lb/>Puberty <lb/>+ Confounds <lb/>+ Dyadic terms <lb/>Edges <lb/>-6.858*** <lb/>-5.001*** <lb/>-6.327*** <lb/>-5.897*** <lb/>-4.888*** <lb/>-6.567*** <lb/>(0.096) <lb/>(0.504) <lb/>(0.900) <lb/>(0.094) <lb/>(0.367) <lb/>(0.563) <lb/>GW Degree (0.2) a <lb/>1.057*** <lb/>1.404*** <lb/>1.494*** <lb/>0.433 <lb/>0.614* <lb/>0.610* <lb/>(0.154) <lb/>(0.169) <lb/>(0.171) <lb/>(0.282) <lb/>(0.284) <lb/>(0.290) <lb/>GW ESP (0.2) a <lb/>1.948*** <lb/>1.930*** <lb/>1.669*** <lb/>1.681*** <lb/>1.670*** <lb/>1.536*** <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.032) <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>(0.035) <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>Pub: Physical dev <lb/>0.011 <lb/>0.017 <lb/>0.017 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.013 <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>Pub: Relative timing <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>-0.006 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>Physical activity, times/week <lb/>0.008** <lb/>0.011*** <lb/>0.006** <lb/>0.008*** <lb/>(0.003) <lb/>(0.003) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>Sleep hours, avg/night <lb/>-0.037*** <lb/>-0.033** <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.008) <lb/>(0.008) <lb/>Sufficient sleep <lb/>-0.010 <lb/>-0.032 <lb/>0.013 <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>(0.023) <lb/>(0.028) <lb/>Overweight/Obese <lb/>-0.084** <lb/>0.014 <lb/>-0.089*** <lb/>0.035 <lb/>(0.027) <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>Screen time scale, hours/week <lb/>-0.001 † <lb/>-0.001 † <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>Male <lb/>-0.016 <lb/>-0.017 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>(0.022) <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>Grade <lb/>0.036 <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.058* <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.041) <lb/>(0.018) <lb/>(0.027) <lb/>Age <lb/>-0.074*** <lb/>-0.074*** <lb/>-0.046** <lb/>-0.041** <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>Parent highest education <lb/>0.032** <lb/>0.034** <lb/>0.025** <lb/>0.025** <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.009) <lb/>(0.009) <lb/>Nomination error flag <lb/>-0.340*** <lb/>-0.300*** <lb/>-0.101 † <lb/>-0.118* <lb/>(0.085) <lb/>(0.084) <lb/>(0.052) <lb/>(0.053) <lb/>Black NH a (Ref: White NH) <lb/>-0.116* <lb/>-1.157*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.055) <lb/>(0.107) <lb/>AsAm/PI NH a <lb/>0.212*** <lb/>-0.776*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.049) <lb/>(0.098) <lb/>Other NH <lb/>0.116** <lb/>0.348*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.038) <lb/>(0.105) <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>0.091 † <lb/>0.013 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.049) <lb/>(0.061) <lb/>Dyadic homophily terms <lb/>Same, Male <lb/>0.404*** <lb/>0.251*** <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>(0.037) <lb/>Same, White NH <lb/>0.406** <lb/>-<lb/>(0.131) <lb/>Same, Black NH <lb/>2.823*** <lb/>-<lb/>(0.156) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>coefficients is relatively small. For instance, exponentiating the coefficient for similar relative <lb/>pubertal timing among students at Sunshine High is equivalent to a 1.04 times greater likeli-<lb/>hood of those individuals being friends, and similar sleep duration at Jefferson equivalent to a <lb/>1.03 times greater likelihood of friendship, compared with the 1.5 times greater likelihood of <lb/>friendship among two students of the same sex. <lb/>Correlates of tie formation by sex <lb/>Table 3 (&quot;Sunshine High&quot;) and Table 4 (&quot;Jefferson High&quot;) report on correlates of tie formation <lb/>by sex by decomposing the whole-school network into single-sex networks to give focus to <lb/>Table 2. (Continued) <lb/>School 1 (&quot;Sunshine High&quot;) <lb/>School 2 (&quot;Jefferson High&quot;) <lb/>Puberty <lb/>+ Confounds <lb/>+ Dyadic terms <lb/>Puberty <lb/>+ Confounds <lb/>+ Dyadic terms <lb/>Same, AsAm/PI NH <lb/>2.018*** <lb/>-<lb/>(0.122) <lb/>Same, Other NH <lb/>-0.224 † <lb/>-<lb/>(0.123) <lb/>Same, Hispanic <lb/>0.743*** <lb/>-<lb/>(0.059) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Phys Dev) <lb/>-0.006 <lb/>-0.024 <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Relative Timing) <lb/>-0.040* <lb/>-0.008 <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>(0.018) <lb/>Similarity, Physical activity <lb/>-0.024*** <lb/>-0.020*** <lb/>(0.006) <lb/>(0.005) <lb/>Similarity, Sleep duration <lb/>-0.026 † <lb/>-0.032* <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>(0.014) <lb/>Same, Sufficient sleep <lb/>0.071 † <lb/>0.090 † <lb/>(0.040) <lb/>(0.046) <lb/>Same, Overweight/Obese <lb/>0.211*** <lb/>0.215*** <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>(0.053) <lb/>Same, 9th grade <lb/>-<lb/>1.338*** <lb/>(0.074) <lb/>Same, 10th grade <lb/>1.140*** <lb/>1.236*** <lb/>(0.081) <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>Same, 11th grade <lb/>1.106*** <lb/>1.345*** <lb/>(0.042) <lb/>(0.050) <lb/>Same, 12th grade <lb/>1.223*** <lb/>1.395*** <lb/>(0.086) <lb/>(0.087) <lb/>Akaike Inf. Crit. <lb/>33,916 <lb/>33,703 <lb/>29,972 <lb/>25,910 <lb/>25,850 <lb/>24,159 <lb/>Bayesian Inf. Crit. <lb/>33,975 <lb/>33,928 <lb/>30,373 <lb/>25,963 <lb/>26,009 <lb/>24,434 <lb/>Note: <lb/> † p&lt;0.1; <lb/>* p&lt;0.05; <lb/>** p&lt;0.01; <lb/>*** p&lt;0.001 <lb/>a GW = geometrically-weighted; ESP = edgewise shared partners; AsAm/PI = Asian American Pacific Islander; NH = Non-Hispanic. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. Characteristics associated with friendship formation, stratified by sex, school 1 (&quot;Sunshine High&quot;). <lb/>Whole network <lb/>Network decomposition models <lb/>1.Girls <lb/>1.Girls +Menarche <lb/>2.Boys <lb/>3.Mixed Gender <lb/>n = 1408 <lb/>n = 680 <lb/>n = 633 <lb/>n = 731 <lb/>n = 942 <lb/>Edges <lb/>-6.327*** <lb/>-5.153** <lb/>-4.002 † <lb/>-6.080*** <lb/>-6.611*** <lb/>(0.900) <lb/>(1.928) <lb/>(2.166) <lb/>(1.608) <lb/>(1.388) <lb/>GW Degree (0.2) a <lb/>1.494*** <lb/>1.614*** <lb/>1.404*** <lb/>1.365*** <lb/>0.548*** <lb/>(0.171) <lb/>(0.158) <lb/>(0.151) <lb/>(0.150) <lb/>(0.121) <lb/>GW ESP (0.2) a <lb/>1.669*** <lb/>1.928*** <lb/>1.929*** <lb/>1.870*** <lb/>1.481*** <lb/>(0.032) <lb/>(0.065) <lb/>(0.071) <lb/>(0.060) <lb/>(0.049) <lb/>Pub: Physical dev <lb/>0.017 <lb/>0.053* <lb/>0.049* <lb/>-0.007 <lb/>0.011 <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.025) <lb/>(0.025) <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>Pub: Relative timing <lb/>0.005 <lb/>-0.021 <lb/>-0.025 <lb/>0.034 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>(0.022) <lb/>(0.018) <lb/>Pub: Age of menarche <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-0.010 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.019) <lb/>Physical activity <lb/>0.011*** <lb/>0.014* <lb/>0.016* <lb/>0.009 <lb/>0.011* <lb/>(0.003) <lb/>(0.007) <lb/>(0.007) <lb/>(0.006) <lb/>(0.005) <lb/>Sleep hours, avg/night <lb/>-0.033** <lb/>-0.04 † <lb/>-0.031 <lb/>-0.008 <lb/>-0.027 <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.022) <lb/>(0.023) <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>(0.017) <lb/>Sleep enough <lb/>-0.032 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>0.055 <lb/>-0.035 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>(0.054) <lb/>(0.056) <lb/>(0.057) <lb/>(0.042) <lb/>Overweight/Obese <lb/>0.014 <lb/>0.117 † <lb/>0.081 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.044 <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>(0.066) <lb/>(0.074) <lb/>(0.052) <lb/>(0.046) <lb/>Screen time <lb/>-0.001 † <lb/>-0.001 <lb/>-0.001 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>-0.002 † <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>Male <lb/>-0.017 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.020) <lb/>Grade <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>-0.066 <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.059 <lb/>(0.041) <lb/>(0.087) <lb/>(0.098) <lb/>(0.072) <lb/>(0.063) <lb/>Age <lb/>-0.074*** <lb/>-0.114** <lb/>-0.097* <lb/>-0.043 <lb/>-0.061* <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>(0.043) <lb/>(0.046) <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>Parent highest education <lb/>0.034** <lb/>0.051* <lb/>0.064** <lb/>0.023 <lb/>0.034* <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>(0.023) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.022) <lb/>(0.017) <lb/>Nomination error flag <lb/>-0.300*** <lb/>-0.345* <lb/>-0.251 † <lb/>-0.325 † <lb/>-0.445** <lb/>(0.084) <lb/>(0.153) <lb/>(0.147) <lb/>(0.172) <lb/>(0.137) <lb/>Black NH a (Ref: White NH) <lb/>-1.157*** <lb/>-1.166*** <lb/>-1.108*** <lb/>-1.710*** <lb/>-1.190*** <lb/>(0.107) <lb/>(0.230) <lb/>(0.239) <lb/>(0.201) <lb/>(0.167) <lb/>AsAm/PI NH a <lb/>-0.776*** <lb/>-0.828*** <lb/>-0.702** <lb/>-0.908*** <lb/>-0.939*** <lb/>(0.098) <lb/>(0.209) <lb/>(0.219) <lb/>(0.171) <lb/>(0.159) <lb/>Other NH <lb/>0.348*** <lb/>0.495* <lb/>0.553* <lb/>0.119 <lb/>0.233 <lb/>(0.105) <lb/>(0.228) <lb/>(0.240) <lb/>(0.182) <lb/>(0.166) <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.100 <lb/>-0.121 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>(0.061) <lb/>(0.125) <lb/>(0.133) <lb/>(0.105) <lb/>(0.093) <lb/>Dyadic Similarity terms <lb/>Same, Male <lb/>0.404*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.036) <lb/>Same, White NH <lb/>0.406** <lb/>0.606* <lb/>0.759** <lb/>0.245 <lb/>0.353 † <lb/>(0.131) <lb/>(0.261) <lb/>(0.275) <lb/>(0.224) <lb/>(0.204) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>friendships between same-sex students. The first column is identical to the final model in <lb/>Table 2 to allow for ease of comparison. The table also includes two models for girls: one (1. <lb/>Girls) that includes two measures of pubertal development (physical development, peer-<lb/>relative timing), and an alternate model that allows for the inclusion of age of menarche (1. <lb/>Girls+Menarche); this is followed by a subnetwork model that includes boys only (2.Boys). We <lb/>Table 3. (Continued) <lb/>Whole network <lb/>Network decomposition models <lb/>1.Girls <lb/>1.Girls +Menarche <lb/>2.Boys <lb/>3.Mixed Gender <lb/>n = 1408 <lb/>n = 680 <lb/>n = 633 <lb/>n = 731 <lb/>n = 942 <lb/>Same, Black NH <lb/>2.823*** <lb/>2.940*** <lb/>2.969*** <lb/>3.399*** <lb/>2.761*** <lb/>(0.156) <lb/>(0.320) <lb/>(0.333) <lb/>(0.311) <lb/>(0.237) <lb/>Same, AsAm/PI NH <lb/>2.018*** <lb/>2.370*** <lb/>2.269*** <lb/>1.870*** <lb/>2.282*** <lb/>(0.122) <lb/>(0.259) <lb/>(0.271) <lb/>(0.212) <lb/>(0.197) <lb/>Same, Other NH <lb/>-0.224 † <lb/>-0.345 <lb/>-0.399 <lb/>0.098 <lb/>-0.085 <lb/>(0.123) <lb/>(0.253) <lb/>(0.210) <lb/>(0.214) <lb/>(0.198) <lb/>Same, Hispanic <lb/>0.743*** <lb/>1.028*** <lb/>1.003*** <lb/>0.697*** <lb/>0.888*** <lb/>(0.059) <lb/>(0.121) <lb/>(0.128) <lb/>(0.103) <lb/>(0.094) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Phys Dev) <lb/>-0.006 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>-0.052 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>(0.038) <lb/>(0.041) <lb/>(0.040) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Relative Timing) <lb/>-0.040* <lb/>-0.034 <lb/>-0.038 <lb/>-0.055 <lb/>-0.021 <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>(0.037) <lb/>(0.040) <lb/>(0.035) <lb/>(0.029) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Age of Menarche) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.008 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.031) <lb/>Similarity, Physical activity <lb/>-0.024*** <lb/>-0.034** <lb/>-0.034** <lb/>-0.036*** <lb/>-0.033*** <lb/>(0.006) <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.012) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.009) <lb/>Similarity, Sleep duration <lb/>-0.026 † <lb/>-0.004 <lb/>-0.001 <lb/>-0.063* <lb/>-0.05 † <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.034) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.026) <lb/>Same, Sufficient sleep <lb/>0.071 † <lb/>0.026 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>0.103 <lb/>0.051 <lb/>(0.040) <lb/>(0.072) <lb/>(0.079) <lb/>(0.076) <lb/>(0.061) <lb/>Same, Ovwght/Obese <lb/>0.211*** <lb/>0.356*** <lb/>0.335** <lb/>0.103** <lb/>0.302*** <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>(0.087) <lb/>(0.098) <lb/>(0.076) <lb/>(0.068) <lb/>Same, 10th grade <lb/>1.140*** <lb/>1.294*** <lb/>1.226*** <lb/>1.031*** <lb/>1.258*** <lb/>(0.081) <lb/>(0.162) <lb/>(0.175) <lb/>(0.143) <lb/>(0.129) <lb/>Same, 11th grade <lb/>1.106*** <lb/>1.358*** <lb/>1.406*** <lb/>1.054*** <lb/>1.178*** <lb/>(0.042) <lb/>(0.087) <lb/>(0.095) <lb/>(0.080) <lb/>(0.065) <lb/>Same, 12th grade <lb/>1.223*** <lb/>1.545*** <lb/>1.788*** <lb/>1.175*** <lb/>1.223*** <lb/>(0.086) <lb/>(0.183) <lb/>(0.211) <lb/>(0.152) <lb/>(0.134) <lb/>Akaike Inf. Crit. <lb/>29,972 <lb/>8,039 <lb/>7,013 <lb/>9,277 <lb/>13,555 <lb/>Bayesian Inf. Crit. <lb/>30,373 <lb/>8,370 <lb/>7,360 <lb/>9,613 <lb/>13,907 <lb/>Notes: <lb/> † p&lt;0.1; <lb/>* p&lt;0.05; <lb/>** p&lt;0.01; <lb/>*** p&lt;0.001; <lb/>20% White; 54% male; Public; West, Suburb; Grades 10-12; gender and gender homophily terms not included in Models 2-5. <lb/>a GW = geometrically-weighted; ESP = edgewise shared partners; AsAm/PI = Asian American Pacific Islander; NH = Non-Hispanic. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. Factors associated with friendship formation, stratified by sex, school 2 (&quot;Jefferson High&quot;). <lb/>Whole network <lb/>Network decomposition models <lb/>1.Girls <lb/>1.Girls +Menarche <lb/>2.Boys <lb/>3.Mixed Gender <lb/>n = 762 <lb/>n = 352 <lb/>n = 343 <lb/>n = 411 <lb/>n = 465 <lb/>Edges <lb/>-6.567*** <lb/>-7.608*** <lb/>-8.110*** <lb/>-5.561*** <lb/>-6.631*** <lb/>(0.563) <lb/>(1.390) <lb/>(1.474) <lb/>(1.213) <lb/>(0.682) <lb/>GW Degree (0.2) a <lb/>0.610* <lb/>2.584*** <lb/>2.118*** <lb/>1.171*** <lb/>0.469 † <lb/>(0.290) <lb/>(0.439) <lb/>(0.360) <lb/>(0.253) <lb/>(0.251) <lb/>GW ESP (0.2) a <lb/>1.536*** <lb/>1.662*** <lb/>1.659*** <lb/>1.690*** <lb/>1.470*** <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>(0.072) <lb/>(0.074) <lb/>(0.065) <lb/>(0.040) <lb/>Pub: Physical dev <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>Pub: Relative timing <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>-0.042 <lb/>-0.024 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>(0.027) <lb/>(0.029) <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>Pub: Age of menarche <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.039 † <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.022) <lb/>Physical activity <lb/>0.008*** <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.010* <lb/>0.006* <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.007) <lb/>(0.007) <lb/>(0.005) <lb/>(0.003) <lb/>Sleep hours, avg/night <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>(0.008) <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>(0.017) <lb/>(0.010) <lb/>Sleep sufficiency <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>-0.066 <lb/>-0.061 <lb/>-0.036 <lb/>-0.017 <lb/>(0.028) <lb/>(0.056) <lb/>(0.058) <lb/>(0.058) <lb/>(0.034) <lb/>Overweight or Obese <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.085 <lb/>0.113 <lb/>0.119* <lb/>0.036 <lb/>(0.036) <lb/>(0.070) <lb/>(0.073) <lb/>(0.057) <lb/>(0.041) <lb/>Screen time <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>-0.001 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.002) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>(0.001) <lb/>Male <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.021) <lb/>Grade <lb/>0.058* <lb/>0.203** <lb/>0.214** <lb/>-0.043 <lb/>0.078* <lb/>(0.027) <lb/>(0.070) <lb/>(0.071) <lb/>(0.055) <lb/>(0.032) <lb/>Age <lb/>-0.041** <lb/>-0.109* <lb/>-0.126** <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>-0.048* <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>(0.043) <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>(0.031) <lb/>(0.020) <lb/>Parent highest education <lb/>0.025** <lb/>0.045 † <lb/>0.030 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.034** <lb/>(0.009) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>(0.019) <lb/>(0.011) <lb/>Restricted nominations <lb/>-0.118* <lb/>-0.298* <lb/>-0.305* <lb/>-0.094 <lb/>-0.219** <lb/>(0.053) <lb/>(0.140) <lb/>(0.139) <lb/>(0.114) <lb/>(0.072) <lb/>Dyadic Similarity terms <lb/>Same, Male <lb/>0.251*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.037) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Phys dev) <lb/>-0.024 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.039 <lb/>-0.076 <lb/>-0.027 <lb/>(0.021) <lb/>(0.047) <lb/>(0.048) <lb/>(0.047) <lb/>(0.024) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Relative timing) <lb/>-0.008 <lb/>-0.033 <lb/>-0.033 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>(0.018) <lb/>(0.042) <lb/>(0.045) <lb/>(0.034) <lb/>(0.022) <lb/>Similarity, Pub (Age of menarche) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-0.068 † <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(0.035) <lb/>Similarity, Physical activity <lb/>-0.020*** <lb/>-0.017 <lb/>-0.016 <lb/>-0.039*** <lb/>-0.020** <lb/>(0.005) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>(0.013) <lb/>(0.009) <lb/>(0.006) <lb/>Similarity, Sleep duration <lb/>-0.032* <lb/>-0.056 † <lb/>-0.059* <lb/>-0.061* <lb/>-0.041* <lb/>(0.014) <lb/>(0.029) <lb/>(0.030) <lb/>(0.029) <lb/>(0.016) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>treat the final model (3.Mixed sex) as a residual category that omits same-sex ties. Comments <lb/>below focus on the presence of sex variation. <lb/>At Sunshine High (Table 3), endogenous network terms are largely similar across subnet-<lb/>works. Interestingly, although in the whole network there was no significant association <lb/>between physical development and tie formation, examination of the network decomposed by <lb/>sex revealed that at least some youth with advanced physical development are more likely to <lb/>form friendships. More specifically, more physically developed girls tend to have more friend-<lb/>ships (b = 0.053, p = 0.026). In addition, girls who are more physically active tend to form <lb/>more friendships, with a coefficient size roughly the same (b = 0.014, p = 0.032) as the residual <lb/>mixed-sex subnetwork (b = 0.016, p = 0.026); PA levels are not correlated with friendship <lb/>among boys at this school. An inverse relationship among girls indicating older girls have <lb/>fewer friendships (b = -0.11, p = 0.008) is not observed for boys. In terms of dyadic homophily, <lb/>across all models, youth with similar levels of PA tend to be friends, while boys with similar <lb/>amounts of sleep tend to form friendships (b = -0.063, p = 0.04). <lb/>At Jefferson High (Table 4), similar effects for endogenous network tendencies hold across <lb/>subnetworks. Inspecting the menarche model, girls&apos; ties were marginally more likely if they <lb/>had a more advanced age of menarche (b = 0.039, p = 0.08) or in higher grades (b = 0.214, <lb/>p = 0.003), though less likely if girls were older (b = -0.126, p = 0.004). Dyadically, friendships <lb/>were more likely for girls with similar sleep duration (b = -0.059, p = 0.046), the same sleep suf-<lb/>ficiency status (b = 0.182, p = 0.032), and marginally more likely for girls with similar age of <lb/>menarche (b = -0.068, p = 0.055). Among boys, friendships were more likely for those who <lb/>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Whole network <lb/>Network decomposition models <lb/>1.Girls <lb/>1.Girls +Menarche <lb/>2.Boys <lb/>3.Mixed Gender <lb/>n = 762 <lb/>n = 352 <lb/>n = 343 <lb/>n = 411 <lb/>n = 465 <lb/>Same, Sufficient sleep <lb/>0.090 † <lb/>0.187* <lb/>0.182* <lb/>0.109 <lb/>0.077 <lb/>(0.046) <lb/>(0.082) <lb/>(0.085) <lb/>(0.086) <lb/>(0.054) <lb/>Same, Overweight or Obese <lb/>0.215*** <lb/>0.351*** <lb/>0.332*** <lb/>0.287** <lb/>0.198** <lb/>(0.053) <lb/>(0.097) <lb/>(0.102) <lb/>(0.086) <lb/>(0.063) <lb/>Same, 9th grade <lb/>1.338*** <lb/>1.837*** <lb/>1.775*** <lb/>1.405*** <lb/>1.409*** <lb/>(0.074) <lb/>(0.186) <lb/>(0.186) <lb/>(0.144) <lb/>(0.089) <lb/>Same, 10th grade <lb/>1.236*** <lb/>1.728*** <lb/>1.738*** <lb/>1.334*** <lb/>1.272*** <lb/>(0.044) <lb/>(0.110) <lb/>(0.110) <lb/>(0.082) <lb/>(0.054) <lb/>Same, 11th grade <lb/>1.345*** <lb/>1.465*** <lb/>1.449*** <lb/>1.687*** <lb/>1.350*** <lb/>(0.050) <lb/>(0.124) <lb/>(0.126) <lb/>(0.104) <lb/>(0.059) <lb/>Same, 12th grade <lb/>1.395*** <lb/>1.341*** <lb/>1.422*** <lb/>1.905*** <lb/>1.420*** <lb/>(0.087) <lb/>(0.192) <lb/>(0.201) <lb/>(0.183) <lb/>(0.101) <lb/>Akaike Inf. Crit. <lb/>24,159 <lb/>5,662 <lb/>5,419 <lb/>7,355 <lb/>17,572 <lb/>Bayesian Inf. Crit. <lb/>24,434 <lb/>5,879 <lb/>5,652 <lb/>7,579 <lb/>17,817 <lb/>Notes: <lb/> † p&lt;0.1; <lb/>* p&lt;0.05; <lb/>** p&lt;0.01; <lb/>*** p&lt;0.001; <lb/>97.3% White; Public; Midwest; Rural; Grades 9-12; Gender and gender homophily terms not included in Models 2-5. <lb/>a GW = geometrically-weighted; ESP = edgewise shared partners; AsAm/PI = Asian American Pacific Islander; NH = Non-Hispanic. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>were more physically active (b = 0.010, p = 0.04), or who were overweight/obese (b = 0.118, <lb/>p = 0.036). Additionally, friendships were more likely among boys with similar PA levels (b = <lb/>-0.039, p = &lt;0.001) and similar sleep duration (b = -0.061, p = 0.036). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study is the first to analyze how pubertal development, physical activity, and sleep-which <lb/>are often studied separately-are independently correlated with friendship tie formation using <lb/>a rigorous network analytic approach that accounts for statistical dependencies between par-<lb/>ticipants and important contextual confounders. As expected from prior research using differ-<lb/>ent methods, we conceptually replicated the finding that physical activity levels were <lb/>correlated among youth who considered each other friends. Given that ERGMs share concep-<lb/>tual foundations with the stochastic actor-oriented model (SAOM) approach that Shoham and <lb/>colleagues [37] and Simpkins et al. [13] used in these same two schools, this was not at all sur-<lb/>prising. But we also replicated regression modeling-based trends towards youth with similar <lb/>sleep duration [15] and, to a lesser extent, sleep sufficiency [40] selecting one another as friends <lb/>with a more precise modeling technique that accounts for interpersonal statistical dependence. <lb/>This makes sense intuitively, both in cases where friends are socializing in-person at night in <lb/>ways that lead to a common shared bedtime, as well as cases where they are not together, given <lb/>bedtime norms and the likelihood of youth engaging in similar evening behaviors, such as <lb/>watching similar TV shows or talking on the phone. Taken together, these findings reinforce <lb/>that a network perspective in sleep research continues to show promise. <lb/>We found qualified support for our first hypothesis, that adolescents&apos; pubertal development <lb/>would be associated with a greater likelihood of tie formation. In particular, we found that in <lb/>the context of all relationships at Sunshine High (which had a high degree of SES and racial/ <lb/>ethnic diversity), youth with similar levels of peer-relative pubertal timing had a slight ten-<lb/>dency to form more friendships with one another (although the effect size was small). Substan-<lb/>tively, this means that if one student answered, &quot;I look older than most&quot;, that student was <lb/>more likely to be friends with another student who also reported more advanced development. <lb/>Turning to the very different demographic composition of Jefferson High, we did not observe <lb/>any relationships between pubertal development and social ties in the whole-network model. <lb/>It is possible that visible markers of pubertal development &quot;stick out&quot; to peers more in school <lb/>settings like Sunshine with a great deal of socioeconomic and racial/ethnic variation in the stu-<lb/>dent population, making friendships on the basis of perceived relative pubertal timing more <lb/>likely. <lb/>Next, we gained additional insight by stratifying network models by sex, in order to isolate <lb/>how pubertal development and activity behaviors may be correlated within same-sex and <lb/>opposite-sex relationships (to test Hypothesis 2). We found that in one of the schools (Jeffer-<lb/>son), girls with similar age of menarche were nearly 7% more likely to be friends, though this <lb/>association was only marginally significant. We did not observe homophily on physical devel-<lb/>opment or peer-relative pubertal timing among girls, and there were no significant associa-<lb/>tions for any pubertal development measure among boys. In the larger, more diverse school <lb/>(Sunshine), boys with similar amounts of sleep were more likely to be friends, and girls with <lb/>more advanced physical development were more likely to have more friendships with other <lb/>girls (regardless of those girls&apos; pubertal development). Interpreting this association is compli-<lb/>cated by the way the survey question was asked. As previously noted, respondents were <lb/>prompted to note bodily changes related to pubertal development and gauge the extent of <lb/>change since grade school. We then used multiple indicators of bodily change to construct a <lb/>scale indexing very little development (1), to a great deal of development (5). For example, if a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>girl&apos;s index responses indicated that she was &quot;much more advanced&quot; than she was in grade <lb/>school, it could mean that she was, indeed, more physically developed (in an absolute sense), <lb/>but it could also mean that she was a late developer (relative to peers). Unfortunately, survey <lb/>responses given do not allow us to probe pubertal tempo. <lb/>At a minimum this association provides suggestive evidence that there is variation for girls <lb/>between physical development and tie formation that we do not observe for boys. It may be <lb/>that physical development is a more salient predictor of friendship for adolescent girls, with <lb/>potential implications for health and well-being disparities. Early work (focused on girls) sug-<lb/>gests that adolescents who develop earlier than their peers may select friends with similar phys-<lb/>ical development over chronological age [26, 72]. They may also spend more time with boys, <lb/>which can be stressful for early developing girls who are not socially or cognitively prepared <lb/>for the social stressors associated with mixed-sex peer interactions [73, 74]. These social pat-<lb/>terns may put early developing girls at higher risk for poor developmental outcomes including <lb/>aggressive and delinquent behaviors and adolescent dating abuse [28, 75-77]. On the other <lb/>hand, it may also be the case that we did not observe these same associations between pubertal <lb/>development and friendship for boys because boys develop later than girls. Analysis of an ado-<lb/>lescent cohort with an average age two years older than ours may give more insight into this <lb/>question. Our efforts build on the work of Kretsch and colleagues [20], who were the first to <lb/>study homophily in pubertal development among socially-connected boys and girls using a <lb/>regression-based approach. We extend their efforts with a more precise statistical social net-<lb/>work approach able to analyze cross-gender relationships and health behavior confounders <lb/>while accounting for statistical dependence between linked observations. Our work also com-<lb/>ports more closely with the statistical network research of Franken and colleagues [19] who <lb/>found that Dutch youth with similar pubertal development tended to be friends, rather than <lb/>that of Lee and colleagues [24] who found no support for friendship based on pubertal devel-<lb/>opment similarity among Taiwan youth. We would speculate that US-based youths&apos; affinities <lb/>with the Dutch case might owe more to youth socialization and friendship norms in Western <lb/>societies rather than intercultural differences in pubertal timing, though more research is <lb/>needed to assess this. <lb/>There are a host of modeling choices that warrant discussion in interpreting results. A <lb/>perennial observational research concern is reciprocal causation (i.e. whether friendship <lb/>changes cause behavioral shifts, or whether behaviors lead to friendship). Without more gran-<lb/>ular longitudinal information on behavior and friendship changes to establish temporal order-<lb/>ing, a cross-section of yearly data can provide insight into associations, but cannot provide <lb/>causally informative evidence of statistical relationships. Participants&apos; self-report behavior <lb/>measures also reflect the era in which they were gathered (1994-95), prior to both the wide-<lb/>spread dissemination of devices to measure PA and sleep, and prior to the emergence of porta-<lb/>ble devices with screens. While activity type and frequency are less precise than current <lb/>standards, these measures have been widely scrutinized [49-51, 78] and are similar to those in <lb/>U.S. surveillance data, such as NHANES [79]. Although we are limited in what we can infer <lb/>from the self-reported measures of puberty (e.g. Add Health does not include physician-<lb/>administered Tanner staging or hormone samples) and we have no information on pubertal <lb/>tempo (which requires repeated puberty assessment starting in childhood), the pubertal devel-<lb/>opment measures have adequate variation, and these measures have been examined in high-<lb/>quality analyses exploring pubertal development [20, 27, 54]. <lb/>Future research may productively extend our approach here to test how secular changes in <lb/>screen use and changes in puberty timing since the mid-1990s may have both independent <lb/>and interactive effects on contemporary friendship formation and maintenance. Given that <lb/>the causes and consequences of how we interact on-line versus offline are not yet well-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>understood [56], it is possible that connecting to friends in person in addition to online <lb/>enriches relationships, though we can envision social connection being in some ways &quot;thinner&quot; <lb/>and diminishing high-quality friendships in some ways. Separately but related, given that the <lb/>age of puberty onset continues to decline, depending on whether it does so uniformly or not <lb/>across biological sex and other population racial and ethnic subgroups, it is plausible that this <lb/>leads to either no change in friendship stability, or more friendship turnover owing to widen-<lb/>ing gaps between physical and psychosocial maturity [59, 80]. <lb/>As with all panel studies, it is not possible to adjust for unmeasured cofounders that occur <lb/>between waves. However, by asking participants about their details of pubertal development <lb/>during adolescence, Add Health improves upon early chronic disease research that previously <lb/>relied on adults&apos; retrospective reporting of puberty and health during their own youth [81-83]. <lb/>In addition to the value that a network-based analytic framework that accounts for interper-<lb/>sonal dependencies offers, another key strength of the study was the use of three different mea-<lb/>sures of pubertal development (i.e., physical development and peer-relative timing <lb/>standardized across boys and girls, age of menarche for girls), and a comparative framework <lb/>across two very different schools (demographically as well as geographically). Yet it would be <lb/>inappropriate to claim that our findings generalize to all schools. Given differences in school <lb/>types, sizes, student composition, and cultures, care and thoughtfulness are warranted in <lb/>applying these findings to school settings beyond the two types studied here. As McFarland <lb/>and colleagues [43] point out in relational analyses of multiple school environments, giving <lb/>attention to specific network ecologies of different schools is critical in considering how inter-<lb/>ventions might be implemented most successfully. Our study follows suit, demonstrating that <lb/>it is important for the study of pubertal development to account for the network context of <lb/>other physical health-promoting behaviors (PA, sleep) and risk factors (ST, weight status) that <lb/>may independently shape, as well as confound, puberty&apos;s relationship with friendship forma-<lb/>tion. Future network research on puberty would benefit from more careful attention to puber-<lb/>tal timing and tempo, as well as how individuals of different sexes, genders, and ethnicities <lb/>think about pubertal development differently. For instance, current studies that provide far <lb/>more refined measurement of pubertal development and related neurobiological processes <lb/>[84-86] could be augmented with high-quality dyadic friendship data [e.g., 87-89] to provide <lb/>an opportunity to build upon what we have done here. <lb/>Conclusions and practical applications <lb/>So what might we do with the insight that friendships are more likely between youth with simi-<lb/>lar relative pubertal timing, and possibly between girls with similar age at menarche? Although <lb/>this study was conducted using data from youth in the mid-1990s, we believe the results can <lb/>still inform current dialogues about child development and socialization. Despite differences <lb/>in how peers socialize between then and now, many aspects of peer influence (e.g., social com-<lb/>parison, social desirability, popularity) transcend digital spaces, shaping young people&apos;s behav-<lb/>iors, attitudes, and self-perceptions. In particular, social media may encourage youth to <lb/>compare their appearance to others even more than they did a few decades ago. There is a <lb/>clear link between social media use and body dissatisfaction [90-92]. Additionally, exacerbated <lb/>by AI-driven beauty filters, social media images can also reinforce biases (e.g., sexism, racism) <lb/>and facilitate misinformation and deception [93]. At the same time, there is also some evidence <lb/>that social media can provide a platform for body positivity and support [94]. Either way, the <lb/>heightened attention to both positive and negative body messaging underscores how social <lb/>media may exacerbate attention to physical features that change across development (e.g., <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<body>skin/acne, body shape, hair growth). Indeed, our associational findings are likely to be conser-<lb/>vative relative to today&apos;s youth. <lb/>Further, our research also offers important insights into other developmental contexts that <lb/>remain highly relevant today. For example, we found differences by gender and school-based <lb/>demographic composition. Specifically, pubertal timing appeared to be a more salient aspect <lb/>of friendship selection for girls compared to boys, and in the school that had a high degree of <lb/>SES and racial/ethnic diversity, versus a more homogenous school setting. These findings <lb/>highlight the need for tailored interventions that not only take into account one&apos;s social iden-<lb/>tity, but also how one&apos;s identity maps onto the demographic composition of the school. Over-<lb/>all, our hope is that this study can provide a roadmap for one way to study the associations <lb/>(and hopefully, prospective associations in a longitudinal framework) between physical devel-<lb/>opment and friendships) across diverse contexts. <lb/>From one perspective, these findings complement the value of having conversations about <lb/>physical and physiological changes during adolescence with trusted adults. For instance, fur-<lb/>ther research could illuminate whether such discussions are more usefully structured not just <lb/>in age or grade-matched groups (as is commonly done in school-based settings at present), but <lb/>possibly in developmentally-matched groups, or further, within small groups of developmen-<lb/>tally-matched friends. However, while it is possible that pubertal timing and tempo may be <lb/>shifted at the population level through social ecological intervention (e.g., nutrition, obesity <lb/>prevention), for the most part individuals cannot choose to change their pubertal development <lb/>status, nor is this what we would advocate. Instead, this study reinforces that caregivers, teach-<lb/>ers, and health professionals should continue to be educated about pubertal development, <lb/>including our findings that physical development and timing may play a role in how youth <lb/>socially connect with one another-even if these youth may not always be aware of phenotypic <lb/>differences being at all responsible for friendships in question. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 File. Please see separate supporting information file for this manuscript, which <lb/>describes data preparation and sample model code (Part 1) and goodness of fit model diag-<lb/>nostics (Part 2) in the same file. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We appreciate input on earlier versions of this study from seminar participants at the Duke <lb/>Network Analysis Center and the Dartmouth Interdisciplinary Network Research Group. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt, John R. Sirard, Genevieve <lb/>Chandler. <lb/>Data curation: Mark C. Pachucki. <lb/>Formal analysis: Mark C. Pachucki, Li Niu, Richard Carbonaro, Hsin Fei Tu. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt, John R. Sirard, Genevieve <lb/>Chandler. <lb/>Investigation: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt. <lb/>Methodology: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Project administration: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt. <lb/>Resources: Mark C. Pachucki. <lb/>Supervision: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Mark C. Pachucki, Lindsay Till Hoyt, Li Niu, Richard Carbonaro, <lb/>Hsin Fei Tu, John R. Sirard, Genevieve Chandler. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bronfenbrenner U. Human development, bioecological theory of. In: Baltes NSB, editor. International <lb/>Encyclopedia of the Social and Behavioral Sciences 2001. p. 6963-70. <lb/>2. Halfon N, Larson K, Lu M, Tullis E, Russ S. Lifecourse health development: Past, present, and future. <lb/>Journal of Maternal and Child Health. 2014; 18(2):344-65. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10995-013-1346-2 <lb/>PMID: 23975451. <lb/>3. Johnson MK, Crosnoe R, Elder G. Insights on adolescence from a life course perspective. J Res Ado-<lb/>lescence. 2011; 21(1):273-80. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1532-7795.2010.00728.x PMID: 21483644. <lb/>4. Harris KM. An integrative approach to health. Demography. 2010; 47(1):1-22. https://doi.org/10.1353/ <lb/>dem.0.0091 PMID: 20355681. <lb/>5. Bauman AE, Sallis JF, Dzewaltowski DA, Owen N. Toward a better understanding of the influences on <lb/>physical activity: The role of determinants, correlates, causal variables, mediators, moderators, and <lb/>confounders. Am J Prev Med. 2002; 23(2):5-14. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0749-3797(02)00469-5 <lb/>PMID: 12133733. <lb/>6. Kimm SY, Glynn NW, Kriska AM, Barton BA, Kronsberg SS, Daniels SR, et al. Decline in physical activ-<lb/>ity in black girls and white girls during adolescence. New England Journal of Medicine. 2002; 347 <lb/>(10):709-15. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa003277 PMID: 12213941. <lb/>7. Maslowsky J, Ozer EJ. Developmental trends in sleep duration in adolescence and young adulthood: <lb/>evidence from a national United States sample. J Adolescent Health. 2014; 54(6):691-7. Epub <lb/>20131218. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.10.201 PMID: 24361237. <lb/>8. Gordon-Larsen P, Nelson MC, Page P, Popkin BM. Inequality in the built environment underlies key <lb/>health disparities in physical activity and obesity. Pediatrics. 2006; 117(2):417-24. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1542/peds.2005-0058 PMID: 16452361. <lb/>9. Kalman M, Inchley J, Sigmundova D, Iannotti RJ, Tynjala JA, Hamrik Z, et al. Secular trends in moder-<lb/>ate-to-vigorous physical activity in 32 countries from 2002 to 2010: a cross-national perspective. Eur J <lb/>Public Health. 2015; 25:37-40. https://doi.org/10.1093/eurpub/ckv024 PMID: 25805785 <lb/>10. Keyes KM, Maslowsky J, Hamilton A, Schulenberg J. The great sleep recession: changes in sleep dura-<lb/>tion among US adolescents, 1991-2012. Pediatrics. 2015; 135(3):peds. 2014-707. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1542/peds.2014-2707 PMID: 25687142 <lb/>11. Gesell SB, Tesdahl E, Ruchman E. The distribution of physical activity in an after-school friendship net-<lb/>work. Pediatrics. 2012; 129(6):1064-71. Epub 2012/05/30. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2011-2567 <lb/>PMID: 22641755. <lb/>12. Maturo CC, Cunningham SA. Influence of Friends on Children&apos;s Physical Activity: A Review. Am J Pub-<lb/>lic Health. 2013; 103(7):e23-e38. Epub 20130516. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2013.301366 PMID: <lb/>23678914. <lb/>13. Simpkins SD, Schaefer DR, Price CD, Vest AE. Adolescent friendships, BMI, and physical activity: <lb/>Untangling selection and influence through longitudinal social network analysis. J Res Adolescence. <lb/>2013; 23(3):537-49. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1532-7795.2012.00836.x PMID: 24222971 <lb/>14. Sirard JR, Laska MN, Patnode CD, Farbakhsh K, Lytle LA. Adolescent physical activity and screen <lb/>time: associations with the physical home environment. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition <lb/>and Physical Activity. 2010; 7:82. Epub 20101115. https://doi.org/10.1186/1479-5868-7-82 PMID: <lb/>21078167. <lb/>15. Mednick SC, Christakis NA, Fowler JH. The spread of sleep loss influences drug use in adolescent <lb/>social networks. Plos One. 2010; 5(3):e9775. Epub 20100319. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0009775 PMID: 20333306. <lb/>16. Rogol AD, Clark PA, Roemmich JN. Growth and pubertal development in children and adolescents: <lb/>effects of diet and physical activity. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition. 2000; 72(2 Suppl):521S-8S. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/72.2.521S PMID: 10919954. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>17. Baker BL, Birch LL, Trost SG, Davison KK. Advanced pubertal status at age 11 and lower physical activ-<lb/>ity in adolescent girls. The Journal of Pediatrics. 2007; 151(5):488-93. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpeds. <lb/>2007.04.017 PMID: 17961691 <lb/>18. Davison KK, Werder JL, Trost SG, Baker BL, Birch LL. Why are early maturing girls less active? Links <lb/>between pubertal development, psychological well-being, and physical activity among girls at ages 11 <lb/>and 13. Soc Sci Med. 2007; 64(12):2391-404. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2007.02.033 PMID: <lb/>17451855 <lb/>19. Franken A, Prinstein MJ, Dijkstra JK, Steglich CEG, Harakeh Z, Vollebergh WAM. Early Adolescent <lb/>Friendship Selection Based on Externalizing Behavior: the Moderating Role of Pubertal Development. <lb/>The SNARE Study. J Abnorm Child Psych. 2016; 44(8):1647-57. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10802-016-<lb/>0134-z PMID: 26897629 <lb/>20. Kretsch N, Mendle J, Cance JD, Harden KP. Peer Group Similarity in Perceptions of Pubertal Timing. J <lb/>Youth Adolescence. 2016; 45(8):1696-710. Epub 20150404. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10964-015-<lb/>0275-3 PMID: 25840777. <lb/>21. Li JS, Barnett TA, Goodman E, Wasserman RC, Kemper AR. Approaches to the prevention and man-<lb/>agement of childhood obesity: the role of social networks and the use of social media and related elec-<lb/>tronic technologies: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2013; 127 <lb/>(2):260-7. Epub 2012/12/06. https://doi.org/10.1161/CIR.0b013e3182756d8e PMID: 23212719. <lb/>22. Pachucki MC, Goodman E. Social relationships and obesity: Benefits of incorporating a lifecourse per-<lb/>spective. Current Obesity Reports. 2015; 4(2):1-7. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13679-015-0145-z PMID: <lb/>26213644. <lb/>23. Harris KM. The Add Health Study: Design and Accomplishments. 2013. <lb/>24. Lee CT, Chen TW, Yu YF, Strong C, Lin CY, Chang YH, et al. Reciprocal Peer Network Processes on <lb/>Substance Use and Delinquent Behavior in Adolescence: Analysis from a Longitudinal Youth Cohort <lb/>Study. Int J Ment Health Ad. 2022. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-022-00904-z <lb/>25. Brooks-Gunn J, Petersen AC, Eichorn D. The study of maturational timing effects in adolescence. Jour-<lb/>nal of youth &amp; adolescence. 1985; 14(3):149-61. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02090316 PMID: 24301174 <lb/>26. Caspi A, Moffitt TE. Individual-Differences Are Accentuated during Periods of Social-Change-the <lb/>Sample Case of Girls at Puberty. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology. 1991; 61(1):157-68. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1037//0022-3514.61.1.157 PMID: 1890586 <lb/>27. Cavanagh SE. The sexual debut of girls in early adolescence: The intersection of race, pubertal timing, <lb/>and friendship group characteristics. J Res Adolescence. 2004; 14(3):285-312. https://doi.org/10.1111/ <lb/>j.1532-7795.2004.00076.x <lb/>28. Haynie DL. Contexts of risk? Explaining the link between girls&apos; pubertal development and their delin-<lb/>quency involvement. Soc Forces. 2003; 82(1):355-97. https://doi.org/10.1353/sof.2003.0093 <lb/>29. Tirosh A, Shai I, Afek A, Dubnov-Raz G, Ayalon N, Gordon B, et al. Adolescent BMI trajectory and risk <lb/>of diabetes versus coronary disease. N Engl J Med. 2011; 364(14):1315-25. https://doi.org/10.1056/ <lb/>NEJMoa1006992 PMID: 21470009. <lb/>30. Ahmed HM, Blaha MJ, Nasir K, Rivera JJ, Blumenthal RS. Effects of physical activity on cardiovascular <lb/>disease. Am J Cardiol. 2012; 109(2):288-95. Epub 20111018. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amjcard.2011. <lb/>08.042 PMID: 22011559. <lb/>31. Murray CJ, Atkinson C, Bhalla K, Birbeck G, Burstein R, Chou D, et al. The state of US health, 1990-<lb/>2010: burden of diseases, injuries, and risk factors. JAMA. 2013; 310(6):591-608. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1001/jama.2013.13805 PMID: 23842577. <lb/>32. Shay CM, Ning H, Daniels SR, Rooks CR, Gidding SS, Lloyd-Jones DM. Status of Cardiovascular <lb/>Health in US Adolescents Prevalence Estimates From the National Health and Nutrition Examination <lb/>Surveys (NHANES) 2005-2010. Circulation. 2013; 127(13):1369-76. Epub 20130401. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.001559 PMID: 23547177. <lb/>33. Salvy SJ, de la Haye K, Bowker JC, Hermans RC. Influence of peers and friends on children&apos;s and ado-<lb/>lescents&apos; eating and activity behaviors. Physiol Behav. 2012; 106(3):369-78. Epub 2012/04/07. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2012.03.022 PMID: 22480733. <lb/>34. Macdonald-Wallis K, Jago R, Sterne JA. Social network analysis of childhood and youth physical activ-<lb/>ity: a systematic review. Am J Prev Med. 2012; 43(6):636-42. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2012. <lb/>08.021 PMID: 23159259. <lb/>35. de la Haye K, Robins G, Mohr P, Wilson C. Obesity-related behaviors in adolescent friendship net-<lb/>works. Soc Networks. 2010; 32(3):161-7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.09.001 <lb/>36. Sirard JR, Bruening M, Wall MM, Eisenberg ME, Kim SK, Neumark-Sztainer D. Physical activity and <lb/>screen time in adolescents and their friends. Am J Prev Med. 2013; 44(1):48-55. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.amepre.2012.09.054 PMID: 23253649 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>37. Shoham DA, Tong L, Lamberson PJ, Auchincloss AH, Zhang J, Dugas L, et al. An actor-based model <lb/>of social network influence on adolescent body size, screen time, and playing sports. Plos One. 2012; 7 <lb/>(6):e39795. Epub 20120629. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0039795 PMID: 22768124. <lb/>38. Owens J, Adolescent Sleep Working Group; Committee on Adolescence. Insufficient sleep in adoles-<lb/>cents and young adults: an update on causes and consequences. Pediatrics. 2014; 134(3):e921-32. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2014-1696 PMID: 25157012. <lb/>39. Hale L, Guan S. Screen time and sleep among school-aged children and adolescents: a systematic lit-<lb/>erature review. Sleep medicine reviews. 2015; 21:50-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2014.07.007 <lb/>PMID: 25193149 <lb/>40. Li X, Kawachi I, Buxton OM, Haneuse S, Onnela JP. Social network analysis of group position, popular-<lb/>ity, and sleep behaviors among U.S. adolescents. Soc Sci Med. 2019; 232:417-26. Epub 2019/06/09. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2019.05.026 PMID: 31176079. <lb/>41. Hoyt LT, Niu L, Pachucki MC, Chaku N. Timing of puberty in boys and girls: Implications for population <lb/>health. SSM Popul Health. 2020; 10:100549. Epub 2020/02/27. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssmph.2020. <lb/>100549 PMID: 32099893. <lb/>42. Snijders TA, Van de Bunt GG, Steglich CE. Introduction to stochastic actor-based models for network <lb/>dynamics. Soc Networks. 2010; 32(1):44-60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2009.02.004 <lb/>43. McFarland DA, Moody J, Diehl D, Smith JA, Thomas RJ. Network Ecology and Adolescent Social Struc-<lb/>ture. Am Sociol Rev. 2014; 79(6):1088-121. https://doi.org/10.1177/0003122414554001 PMID: <lb/>25535409 <lb/>44. Kossinets G. Effects of missing data in social networks. Soc Networks. 2006; 28(3):247-68. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.socnet.2005.07.002 <lb/>45. Hipp JR, Wang C, Butts CT, Jose R, Lakon CM. Research note: The consequences of different meth-<lb/>ods for handling missing network data in stochastic actor based models. Soc Networks. 2015; 41:56-<lb/>71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2014.12.004 PMID: 25745276 <lb/>46. Smith JA, Morgan JH, Moody J. Network sampling coverage III: Imputation of missing network data <lb/>under different network and missing data conditions. Soc Networks. 2022; 68:148-78. Epub 20210618. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.05.002 PMID: 34305297 <lb/>47. Wang C, Butts CT, Hipp JR, Jose R, Lakon CM. Multiple imputation for missing edge data: A predictive <lb/>evaluation method with application to Add Health. Soc Networks. 2016; 45:89-98. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.socnet.2015.12.003 PMID: 26858508 <lb/>48. Petersen AC, Crockett L, Richards M, Boxer A. A self-report measure of pubertal status: Reliability, <lb/>validity, and initial norms. J Youth Adolescence. 1988; 17(2):117-33. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>BF01537962 PMID: 24277579. <lb/>49. Gordon-Larsen P, McMurray RG, Popkin BM. Determinants of adolescent physical activity and inactiv-<lb/>ity patterns. Pediatrics. 2000; 105(6):E83. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.105.6.e83 PMID: 10835096. <lb/>50. Gordon-Larsen P, Nelson MC, Popkin BM. Longitudinal physical activity and sedentary behavior trends: <lb/>adolescence to adulthood. Am J Prev Med. 2004; 27(4):277-83. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2004. <lb/>07.006 PMID: 15488356. <lb/>51. Nelson MC, Gordon-Larsen P, Adair LS, Popkin BM. Adolescent physical activity and sedentary behav-<lb/>ior: patterning and long-term maintenance. Am J Prev Med. 2005; 28(3):259-66. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.amepre.2004.12.006 PMID: 15766613. <lb/>52. McDade TW, Chyu L, Duncan GJ, Hoyt LT, Doane LD, Adam EK. Adolescents&apos; expectations for the <lb/>future predict health behaviors in early adulthood. Soc Sci Med. 2011; 73(3):391-8. Epub 20110628. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.06.005 PMID: 21764487. <lb/>53. Ornelas IJ, Perreira KM, Ayala GX. Parental influences on adolescent physical activity: a longitudinal <lb/>study. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity. 2007; 4(1):3. Epub 20070202. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1479-5868-4-3 PMID: 17274822. <lb/>54. Knutson KL. The association between pubertal status and sleep duration and quality among a nationally <lb/>representative sample of US adolescents. American Journal of Human Biology. 2005; 17(4):418-24. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ajhb.20405 PMID: 15981178 <lb/>55. Vidmar SI, Cole TJ, Pan H. Standardizing anthropometric measures in children and adolescents with <lb/>functions for egen: Update. The Stata Journal. 2013; 13(2):366-78. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>1536867x1301300211 <lb/>56. Lewis K. Digital networks: Elements of a theoretical framework. Soc Networks. 2021. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.socnet.2021.12.002 <lb/>57. Bond RM, Fariss CJ, Jones JJ, Kramer AD, Marlow C, Settle JE, et al. A 61-million-person experiment <lb/>in social influence and political mobilization. Nature. 2012; 489(7415):295-8. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nature11421 PMID: 22972300 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>58. Dunbar RI, Arnaboldi V, Conti M, Passarella A. The structure of online social networks mirrors those in <lb/>the offline world. Soc Networks. 2015; 43:39-47. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2015.04.005 <lb/>59. Patton GC, Viner R. Pubertal transitions in health. The Lancet. 2007; 369(9567):1130-9. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60366-3 PMID: 17398312 <lb/>60. Eckert-Lind C, Busch AS, Petersen JH, Biro FM, Butler G, Bra ¨uner EV, et al. Worldwide Secular Trends <lb/>in Age at Pubertal Onset Assessed by Breast Development Among Girls A Systematic Review and <lb/>Meta-analysis. Jama Pediatrics. 2020; 174(4). ARTN e195881. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics. <lb/>2019.5881 PMID: 32040143 <lb/>61. Parent A-S, Teilmann G, Juul A, Skakkebaek NE, Toppari J, Bourguignon J-P. The timing of normal <lb/>puberty and the age limits of sexual precocity: variations around the world, secular trends, and changes <lb/>after migration. Endocrine Reviews. 2003; 24(5):668-93. https://doi.org/10.1210/er.2002-0019 PMID: <lb/>14570750 <lb/>62. Adams J. Gathering social network data. 1 Edition. ed. Thousand Oaks: SAGE Publications; 2019. <lb/>xv, 147 pages p. <lb/>63. Carrington PJ, Scott J, Wasserman S. Models and methods in social network analysis. Cambridge; <lb/>New York: Cambridge University Press; 2005. xiv, 328 p. p. <lb/>64. Cranmer SJ, Desmarais BA, Morgan JW. Inferential network analysis: Cambridge University Press; <lb/>2020. <lb/>65. Robins G, Pattison P, Kalish Y, Lusher D. An introduction to exponential random graph (p*) models for <lb/>social networks. Soc Networks. 2007; 29(2):173-91. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.002 <lb/>66. Goodreau SM, Kitts JA, Morris M. Birds of a Feather, or Friend of a Friend? Using Exponential Random <lb/>Graph Models to Investigate Adolescent Social Networks. Demography. 2009; 46(1):103-25. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1353/dem.0.0045 PMID: 19348111 <lb/>67. Pattison P, Wasserman S. Logit models and logistic regressions for social networks: II. Multivariate rela-<lb/>tions. Brit J Math Stat Psy. 1999; 52:169-93. https://doi.org/10.1348/000711099159053 PMID: 10613111 <lb/>68. Wasserman S, Pattison P. Logit models and logistic regressions for social networks.1. An introduction <lb/>to Markov graphs and p*. Psychometrika. 1996; 61(3):401-25. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02294547 <lb/>69. Handcock MS, Hunter DR, Butts CT, Goodreau SM, Morris M. statnet: Software tools for the represen-<lb/>tation, visualization, analysis and simulation of network data. Journal of statistical software. 2008; 24 <lb/>(1):1548. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v024.i01 PMID: 18618019. <lb/>70. Hunter DR, Handcock MS, Butts CT, Goodreau SM, Morris M. ergm: A package to fit, simulate and <lb/>diagnose exponential-family models for networks. Journal of statistical software. 2008; 24(3): <lb/>nihpa54860. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v024.i03 PMID: 19756229. <lb/>71. Morris M, Handcock MS, Hunter DR. Specification of Exponential-Family Random Graph Models: <lb/>Terms and Computational Aspects. J Stat Softw. 2008; 24(4):1548-7660. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss. <lb/>v024.i04 PMID: 18650964. <lb/>72. Stattin H, Magnusson D. Pubertal maturation in female development: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, <lb/>Inc; 1990. <lb/>73. Carter R, Williams S. Self-perceptions of of pubertal timing and patterns of peer group activities and dat-<lb/>ing behavior among heterosexual adolescent girls. J Adolescence. 2016; 47:71-80. Epub 20160112. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.adolescence.2015.12.006 PMID: 26775189 <lb/>74. Ge X, Natsuaki MN. In search of explanations for early pubertal timing effects on developmental psy-<lb/>chopathology. Curr Dir Psychol Sci. 2009; 18(6):327-31. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8721.2009. <lb/>01661.x <lb/>75. Chen FR, Rothman EF, Jaffee SR. Early Puberty, Friendship Group Characteristics, and Dating Abuse <lb/>in US Girls. Pediatrics. 2017; 139(6). Epub 2017/06/01. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2016-2847 PMID: <lb/>28562261. <lb/>76. Mrug S, Elliott MN, Davies S, Tortolero SR, Cuccaro P, Schuster MA. Early puberty, negative peer influ-<lb/>ence, and problem behaviors in adolescent girls. Pediatrics. 2014; 133(1):7-14. Epub 2013/12/11. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2013-0628 PMID: 24324002. <lb/>77. Mendle J, Turkheimer E, Emery R. Detrimental psychological outcomes associated with early pubertal <lb/>timing in adolescent girls. Developmental Review. 2007; 27(2):151-71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dr. <lb/>2006.11.001 PMID: 20740062. <lb/>78. Nelson MC, Gordon-Larsen P. Physical activity and sedentary behavior patterns are associated with <lb/>selected adolescent health risk behaviors. Pediatrics. 2006; 117(4):1281-90. https://doi.org/10.1542/ <lb/>peds.2005-1692 PMID: 16585325. <lb/>79. Song M, Carroll DD, Fulton JE. Meeting the 2008 physical activity guidelines for Americans among US <lb/>youth. Am J Prev Med. 2013; 44(3):216-22. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2012.11.016 PMID: <lb/>23415117 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>80. Dahl RE. Adolescent brain development: a period of vulnerabilities and opportunities. Keynote address. <lb/>Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2004; 1021:1-22. Epub 2004/07/15. https://doi.org/10.1196/annals.1308.001 PMID: <lb/>15251869. <lb/>81. Jacobsen B, Oda K, Knutsen S, Fraser G. Age at menarche, total mortality and mortality from ischaemic <lb/>heart disease and stroke: The Adventist Health Study, 1976-88. Int J Epidemiol. 2009; 38(1):245-52. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyn251 PMID: 19188208 <lb/>82. Jacobsen B, Heuch I, Kvale G. Association of low age at menarche with increased all-cause mortality: a <lb/>37-year follow-up of 61,319 Norwegian women. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2007; 166 <lb/>(12):1431-7. https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwm237 PMID: 17875585 <lb/>83. Lakshman R, Forouhi NG, Sharp SJ, Luben R, Bingham SA, Khaw KT, et al. Early age at menarche <lb/>associated with cardiovascular disease and mortality. Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism. <lb/>2009; 94(12):4953-60. https://doi.org/10.1210/jc.2009-1789 PMID: 19880785 <lb/>84. Cheng TW, Magis-Weinberg L, Williamson VG, Ladouceur CD, Whittle SL, Herting MM, et al. A <lb/>Researcher&apos;s Guide to the Measurement and Modeling of Puberty in the ABCD Study ® at Baseline. <lb/>Front Endocrinol. 2021; 12. ARTN 608575. https://doi.org/10.3389/fendo.2021.608575 PMID: <lb/>34025573 <lb/>85. Goddings AL, Beltz A, Peper JS, Crone EA, Braams BR. Understanding the Role of Puberty in Struc-<lb/>tural and Functional Development of the Adolescent Brain. J Res Adolescence. 2019; 29(1):32-53. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/jora.12408 PMID: 30869842 <lb/>86. Pham HT, Beltz AM, Corley RP, Berenbaum SA. Twin studies of puberty and behavior. Twin Research <lb/>for Everyone: Elsevier; 2022. p. 457-74. <lb/>87. Kitts JA, Leal DF. What is(n&apos;t) a friend? Dimensions of the friendship concept among adolescents. Soc <lb/>Networks. 2021; 66:161-70. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2021.01.004 PMID: 34012218 <lb/>88. Liu SY, Nolin DA, Kitts JA. Name order effects in measuring adolescent social networks using rosters. <lb/>Soc Networks. 2024; 76:68-78. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2023.07.002 PMID: 37840904 <lb/>89. Paluck EL, Shepherd H, Aronow PM. Changing climates of conflict: A social network experiment in 56 <lb/>schools. P Natl Acad Sci USA. 2016; 113(3):566-71. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1514483113 PMID: <lb/>26729884 <lb/>90. Fardouly J, Vartanian LR. Social Media and Body Image Concerns: Current Research and Future Direc-<lb/>tions. Curr Opin Psychol. 2016; 9:1-5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2015.09.005 <lb/>91. Ryding FC, Kuss DJ. The Use of Social Networking Sites, Body Image Dissatisfaction, and Body Dys-<lb/>morphic Disorder: A Systematic Review of Psychological Research. Psychol Pop Media. 2020; 9 <lb/>(4):412-35. https://doi.org/10.1037/ppm0000264 <lb/>92. Saiphoo AN, Vahedi Z. A meta-analytic review of the relationship between social media use and body <lb/>image disturbance. Comput Hum Behav. 2019; 101:259-75. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2019.07.028 <lb/>93. Naderer B, Peter C, Karsay K. This picture does not portray reality: developing and testing a disclaimer <lb/>for digitally enhanced pictures on social media appropriate for Austrian tweens and teens. Journal of <lb/>Children and Media. 2022; 16(2):149-67. <lb/>94. Rodgers RF, Wertheim EH, Paxton SJ, Tylka TL, Harriger JA. #Bopo: Enhancing body image through <lb/>body positive social media-evidence to date and research directions. Body Image. 2022; 41:367-74. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bodyim.2022.03.008 PMID: 35525155 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Disentangling developmental characteristics in adolescent social networks <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0300715 May 16, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 25 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>