<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-19T17:10:56.631Z">11/19/2025 5:10:56 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-19T17:10:46.851539Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-19T17:10:46.851539Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Detection of driver mutations and genomic <lb/>signatures in endometrial cancers using <lb/>artificial intelligence algorithms <lb/>Anda Stan 1☯ , Korey Bosart 1☯ , Mehak Kaur 1☯ , Martin Vo 2 , Wilber Escorcia 2 , Ryan J. Yoder 3 , <lb/>Renee A. BouleyID 3 *, Ruben C. PetreacaID 4,5 * <lb/>1 Biology Program, The Ohio State University, Marion, Ohio, United States of America, 2 Biology <lb/>Department, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio, United States of America, 3 Department of Chemistry and <lb/>Biochemistry, The Ohio State University, Marion, Ohio, United States of America, 4 Department of Molecular <lb/>Genetics, The Ohio State University, Marion, Ohio, United States of America, 5 James Comprehensive <lb/>Cancer Center, The Ohio State University Columbus, Columbus, Ohio, United States of America <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* bouley.8@osu.edu (RAB); petreaca.1@osu.edu (RCB) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Analyzed endometrial cancer (EC) genomes have allowed for the identification of molecular <lb/>signatures, which enable the classification, and sometimes prognostication, of these can-<lb/>cers. Artificial intelligence algorithms have facilitated the partitioning of mutations into driver <lb/>and passenger based on a variety of parameters, including gene function and frequency of <lb/>mutation. Here, we undertook an evaluation of EC cancer genomes deposited on the Cata-<lb/>logue of Somatic Mutations in Cancers (COSMIC), with the goal to classify all mutations as <lb/>either driver or passenger. Our analysis showed that approximately 2.5% of all mutations are <lb/>driver and cause cellular transformation and immortalization. We also characterized nucleo-<lb/>tide level mutation signatures, gross chromosomal re-arrangements, and gene expression <lb/>profiles. We observed that endometrial cancers show distinct nucleotide substitution and <lb/>chromosomal re-arrangement signatures compared to other cancers. We also identified high <lb/>expression levels of the CLDN18 claudin gene, which is involved in growth, survival, metasta-<lb/>sis and proliferation. We then used in silico protein structure analysis to examine the effect of <lb/>certain previously uncharacterized driver mutations on protein structure. We found that cer-<lb/>tain mutations in CTNNB1 and TP53 increase protein stability, which may contribute to cellu-<lb/>lar transformation. While our analysis retrieved previously classified mutations and genomic <lb/>alterations, which is to be expected, this study also identified new signatures. Additionally, <lb/>we show that artificial intelligence algorithms can be effectively leveraged to accurately pre-<lb/>dict key drivers of cancer. This analysis will expand our understanding of ECs and improve <lb/>the molecular toolbox for classification, diagnosis, or potential treatment of these cancers. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>Cancers of the female reproductive organs can be generally classified into ovarian, uterine, cer-<lb/>vical, vulvar, fallopian, and vaginal [1]. These cancers can occur in women of all ages but are <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/>1 / 19 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Stan A, Bosart K, Kaur M, Vo M, Escorcia <lb/>W, Yoder RJ, et al. (2024) Detection of driver <lb/>mutations and genomic signatures in endometrial <lb/>cancers using artificial intelligence algorithms. <lb/>PLoS ONE 19(2): e0299114. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 <lb/>Editor: Nandini Dey, Avera Research Institute, <lb/>UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: October 16, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: February 5, 2024 <lb/>Published: February 26, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Stan et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All data can be found <lb/>at COSMIC: https://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cosmic <lb/>cBioPortal: https://www.cbioportal.org/. <lb/>Funding: Ohio State University Comprehensive <lb/>Cancer Center -Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital <lb/>and Richard J. Solove Research Institute. There is <lb/>no grant number. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>more prevalent in older and post-menopausal women [2, 3]. Uterine cancers can be subdi-<lb/>vided into endometrial cancers arising from the lining of the uterus and uterine sarcoma from <lb/>uterine muscles [4]. Endometrial cancers (ECs) are the most common uterine cancers, are <lb/>more aggressive than sarcoma, and have higher mortality [5]. <lb/>ECs have historically been classified by estrogen status: Type I cancers are estrogen driven <lb/>and occur in younger women, while Type II cancers are not driven by estrogen and occur in <lb/>older women [6]. Type II cancers also tend to be more aggressive. Recent advances in genome <lb/>sequencing and genetic characterization of cancer genomes driven primarily by The Cancer <lb/>Genome Atlas (TCGA) has enabled classification of ECs by molecular status [7-9]. Four differ-<lb/>ent EC molecular types are recognized: 1) POLE-mutant (ultra-mutated) showing mutations <lb/>in the proofreading region of polymerase epsilon, one of the major replicative polymerases, 2) <lb/>microsatellite instability (MSI+) characterized by mutations in mismatch repair genes, 3) <lb/>microsatellite stable, and 4) copy number high/serous-like [10-13]. The latter two types are <lb/>characterized by low mutation rates. Regardless of classification, all four types are distin-<lb/>guished by mutations of PTEN, PIK3CA, ARID1A, TP53, and KRAS genes, as well as other <lb/>signal transduction, chromatin remodeling factors and histones being highly represented [11, <lb/>14-17]. <lb/>The Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancers (COSMIC) deposits analyzed cancer <lb/>genomes data from both TCGA as well as other independent studies into a database [18]. <lb/>Building on previous EC molecular data, we used rigorous artificial intelligence algorithms to <lb/>classify all occurring mutations as either driver or passenger. In silico protein structure/func-<lb/>tion analyses were then employed to investigate how high frequency driver mutations affect <lb/>protein structure and function. We also analyzed nucleotide substitution signatures, chromo-<lb/>somal re-arrangements, gene expression patterns, as well as other parameters with the goal to <lb/>extract a more comprehensive genetic and genomic map for ECs. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Genetic analysis <lb/>Complete mutation and chromosomal structural variation files were downloaded from COS-<lb/>MIC in Excel format. Gene expression data normalized as Z-values were also downloaded for <lb/>TCGA samples. <lb/>S1B Table shows a listing between the percentages of total base pair mutations of the speci-<lb/>fied type among all types and the integer number of base pair mutations of the specified type. <lb/>To compare nucleotide changes in endometrial vs. all cancers, additional data were extracted <lb/>from COSMIC for all cancer tissues. Approximately 1200 genes were analyzed but only the <lb/>nucleotide changes in the top 100 most mutated genes in endometrial cancers are shown in <lb/>S1A Table. There are twelve different nucleotide substitution mutation possibilities: A&gt;C, <lb/>A&gt;G, A&gt;T, C&gt;A, C&gt;T, C&gt;G, G&gt;A, G&gt;C, G&gt;T, T&gt;A, T&gt;C, T&gt;G. The percentages for <lb/>every case of the twelve cases of base pair mutations were recorded. Twelve columns were cre-<lb/>ated for the added-up integer values in the categories for all twelve nucleotide substitution <lb/>mutation possibilities. Next an Independent Samples T-test was performed to compute signifi-<lb/>cant probabilities (shown in red in S1C Table). <lb/>Descriptions for the functions of the most mutated genes in endometrial cancers were <lb/>extracted from NCBI (S3 Table). <lb/>The STRING database (https://string-db.org/) was used to identify connections between <lb/>genes and proteins. The database mines other databases and extracts validated connections (both <lb/>physical and genetic) and makes computational predictions about the strength of connections <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>and provides a score. The higher the score, the higher the likelihood that a meaningful connec-<lb/>tion exists. S1F Table only shows those pathways with a strength score of 0.1 or higher. <lb/>Driver and passenger mutations were classified using the OpenCRAVAT CHASM tool [19, <lb/>20]. To create valid input files from the COSMIC database to be used in OpenCRAVAT, <lb/>Python was used to write a code that took an input.csv file containing genomic mutation data <lb/>and processed it into a format suitable for analysis by the OpenCRAVAT tool. First, the.csv <lb/>was converted into a tab separated.tsv file (csv_2_tsv), which provided an intermediate file for <lb/>parsing. Next, the TSV file was filtered to extract only the HGVSG column containing the vari-<lb/>ant annotations (tsv_2_HGVSG). The HGVSG strings were parsed via regular expressions to <lb/>pull out key details-chromosome, position, reference base, alternate base-into variables <lb/>(HGVSG_2_CRAVAT). These components were written line-by-line into a new.tsv file in the <lb/>specific columns required by OpenCRAVAT. By automating these sequential steps of file con-<lb/>version, parsing, and reformatting, the original CSV data was transformed into the proper for-<lb/>mat for computational mutation analysis by OpenCRAVAT. The full pipeline was executed by <lb/>calling csv_2_CRAVAT. This provided an efficient methodology for preparing large genomics <lb/>datasets for downstream research applications. Link to the GitHub can be found here: https:// <lb/>github.com/dhakxls/cosmic-parser. <lb/>Gene expression analysis <lb/>COSMIC reports gene expression levels for certain TCGA studies obtained either from micro-<lb/>array analysis or RNA-seq as a Z-value with values above Z = 2 considered over-expressed and <lb/>under Z = -2 under-expressed while a value between -2 and 2 is interpreted as normal expres-<lb/>sion [21, 22]. We extracted gene expression data for all TCGA samples and computed the aver-<lb/>age Z-value expression change (S2 Table). S2 Fig shows those genes with a Z change greater <lb/>than than 2. There were no changes with a score lower than -2. <lb/>Effect of driver mutations on protein structure <lb/>The PDB files of the wild-type PPP2R1A (PDB ID: 1B3U) [23], PTEN (PDB ID: 1D5R) [24], <lb/>PIK3CA (PDB ID: 2RD0) [25], CTNNB1 (PDB ID: 6M90) [26], and TP53 (PDB ID: 8F2I) [27] <lb/>human protein 3D structures were downloaded from the Protein Data Bank. There was not a <lb/>published crystal structure for human FGFR2 protein available on the Protein Databank web-<lb/>site, so an AlphaFold [28, 29] model was downloaded instead. Amino acid mutations were <lb/>made computationally using the mutagenesis function in the PyMOL Molecular Graphics Sys-<lb/>tem, Version 2.5.5 Schro ¨dinger, LLC. Side chain polar interactions in a 4 Å radius were <lb/>selected using PyMOL for the wild-type and mutant residue. All six protein PDB wild-type <lb/>(WT) files were uploaded to the BRENDA Enzyme Database website and the stability of point <lb/>mutations in comparison to WT were calculated using BRENDA&apos;s CUPSAT calculation tool <lb/>[30]. To analyze the electrostatic surface potential maps of the selected driver mutations, the <lb/>PyMOL program with the APBS electrostatics plugin was used to visualize change between <lb/>WT protein and driver mutated protein [31]. The localized area of the target mutation <lb/>sequence was used as the center point for all observation and analysis. <lb/>All figures were made in Photoshop or PowerPoint. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>Mutation distribution in endometrial cancers <lb/>Genetic mutation can occur in coding regions (translated into proteins) and non-coding <lb/>regions (untranslated). COSMIC reports both coding and non-coding mutations with the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>caveat that non-coding represents only 5&apos; and 3&apos; UTRs and intronic rather than all &quot;junk&quot; <lb/>DNA. About 65% of observed mutations are reported in coding regions with the remaining <lb/>approximately 35% in non-coding regions (Fig 1A). Both coding and non-coding mutations <lb/>have the potential to drive cellular transformation and immortalization. Coding mutations can <lb/>directly affect protein/enzyme function while non-coding mutations can affect gene expression <lb/>or splicing. When we characterized all forms of EC histology, we observed that most coding <lb/>mutations occur in carcinoma (Fig 1B, S1 Fig). <lb/>Not all mutations affect gene function equally. For example, non-silent mutations introduce <lb/>a direct change in amino acid sequence (e.g., missense, non-sense, InDel) and are predicted to <lb/>have a higher impact on gene function than silent mutations. However, certain non-silent <lb/>mutations have a more profound effect on gene function than others. For example, a missense <lb/>mutation in the active site of an enzyme would be predicted to have a greater effect on gene <lb/>function than a mutation elsewhere in its sequence. To understand which mutations are most <lb/>likely to drive ECs, we used two &apos;gold standard&apos; artificial intelligence algorithms: Cancer-Spe-<lb/>cific High-Throughput Annotation of Somatic Mutations (CHASMplus) [20] and the Variant <lb/>Effect Scoring Tool (VEST4) [32]. CHASM can classify missense mutations as driver or pas-<lb/>senger while VEST4 predicts the probability that they are pathogenic. The algorithm computes <lb/>a score and p-value. A p-value below 0.05 is considered statistically significant (e.g. mutation is <lb/>driver). Using this approach, we distilled all EC mutations to only those predicted to have a <lb/>major role in transformation and immortalization. This analysis shows that only about 2.5% of <lb/>all coding mutations are predicted to be driver and about 4% pathogenic, while fewer than <lb/>0.5% of all non-coding mutations are likely to be either driver or pathogenic (Fig 1C, S1A <lb/>Table). This indicates that most mutations in ECs are probably passenger mutations and may <lb/>play minor roles in cellular transformation or immortalization. <lb/>We next examined the type of point mutations arising in ECs (Fig 1D, S1B Table). A previ-<lb/>ous report has investigated mutation signatures in endometrial adenocarcinoma and found <lb/>that A:T&gt;T:A and G:C&gt;C:G are increased in proficient MMR cancers compared with defi-<lb/>cient MMR [33]. Here, we analyzed each transversion and transition independently and com-<lb/>pared the frequency of each nucleotide change in ECs to the frequency in other cancers <lb/>(independent samples t-test). The goal was to understand whether EC mutations show a pat-<lb/>tern different from other cancers. All comparisons produced significant p-values suggesting <lb/>that ECs have unique mutation signatures than other cancers (S1C Table). As expected, G&gt;A <lb/>and C&gt;T mutations occur at a higher frequency than the other mutations [33]. However, five <lb/>mutation types (C&gt;G, G&gt;C, G&gt;T, T&gt;A, T&gt;C) show a statistically significant higher fre-<lb/>quency compared to other cancers. Of these, the C&gt;G and G&gt;C transversions are statistically <lb/>more represented in ECs than other cancers (p = 1.3E -14 and p = 7.8E -24 , respectively). The sig-<lb/>nificance of this is not immediately obvious but the high levels of both changes suggests that <lb/>they are replication rather than transcription driven (e.g., they occur on both DNA strands). <lb/>Additionally, this cannot be due to MMR status because 1) previous findings showed that defi-<lb/>cient MMR ECs have fewer G:C&gt;C:G mutations [33] and 2) most cancers used for this com-<lb/>parison are not MMR unstable. Thus, the increase in the G:C&gt;C:G signature is unique to ECs. <lb/>Conversely, there is a higher level of G&gt;T than C&gt;A changes which indicates a strand bias. <lb/>When these data are integrated with previous studies, there appears to be a unique mutational <lb/>signature in ECs. <lb/>We next interrogated global chromosomal re-arrangements in ECs (Fig 1E and 1F, S1D <lb/>Table). Chromosomal inversions account for almost 70% of all re-arrangements with deletions <lb/>coming in second (about 20%) and translocations third (about 10%). When the data were par-<lb/>titioned by chromosome number, the longer chromosomes (e.g., 1-10) showed a higher level <lb/>of inter-chromosomal re-arrangements (translocations) than the shorter chromosomes, which <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 1. Mutation distribution in endometrial cancers. A. Percent coding and non-coding mutations in endometrial cancers. B. Distribution of <lb/>coding mutations by endometrial cancer histology. C. Percent coding driver (CHASM) and pathogenic (VEST4) mutations out of total <lb/>mutations in A in endometrial cancers. D. Distribution of nucleotide substitutions in coding endometrial mutations (blue) compared with <lb/>coding mutations in other cancers (red). Significant p values between the two samples are shown (t-test: independent samples, unequal variance, <lb/>two tails). E. Chromosomal re-arrangements in endometrial cancers. Data extracted using the CONNAN function on COSMIC. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>have a higher level of intra-chromosomal re-arrangements (e.g., deletions). The only five chro-<lb/>mosomes not following this pattern are chromosomes 4, 9, 10, 16 and 19. Chromosomes 4 and <lb/>9 generally have low levels of re-arrangements and a decreased frequency of translocations. <lb/>Conversely, chromosomes 10 and 16 have increased levels of translocations while chromo-<lb/>some 19 has a higher level of deletions. These data show that genome wide re-arrangements <lb/>are not uniform on every chromosome, suggesting that re-arrangements on certain chromo-<lb/>somes are selected because they drive EC cellular transformation and immortalization. <lb/>Gene expression changes in endometrial cancers <lb/>We also analyzed gene expression changes in endometrial samples. However, this analysis was <lb/>somewhat restricted because gene expression was only available for TCGA samples and <lb/>reported as a Z-score (please see Materials and methods). We identified a few genes with a ten-<lb/>dency to be overexpressed (S2 Table, S2 Fig). Of note is the CLDN18 claudin gene which <lb/>showed a generally high level of over-expression. High CLDN18 expression was recently <lb/>reported in certain cervical adenocarcinomas [34]. Here, we show that it is generally over-<lb/>expressed in all endometrial cancers, which agrees with previous conclusions [34] that it could <lb/>serve as a molecular marker for ECs. <lb/>CLDN18 over-expression has been observed in several other tumors [35, 36], primarily gas-<lb/>tric [37]. Two CLDN18 isoforms have been identified [38]. Claudiximab (also known as zolbe-<lb/>tuximab) is an anti-CLDN18 antibody specific for isoform CLDN18.2 (isoform 2) [39]. The <lb/>antibody is effective in promoting antibody-and complement-dependent cytotoxicity as <lb/>reported in recent phase II clinical studies [39, 40]. CLDN18 isoform 2 CAR T-cell immuno-<lb/>therapy is another promising therapy for gastric cancers and also in clinical studies [41]. The <lb/>finding that CLDN18 is also over-expressed in endometrial cancers highlight the importance <lb/>of this gene and should be considered for similar targeted therapeutics. <lb/>Genes and pathways affected by endometrial cancer driver mutations <lb/>Several previous publications have identified signature mutations in the endometrium (both <lb/>normal and tumor) [11, 12, 17, 42-56]. Our goal here was to understand the significance of <lb/>each mutation and to classify them as either driver or passenger (e.g., how likely are they to <lb/>cause cellular transformation or immortalization). These driver mutations affect certain key <lb/>pathways involved in cell proliferation, migration, and survival (Fig 5). We ran all mutations <lb/>reported on COSMIC through two artificial intelligence algorithms: CHASM, which classifies <lb/>mutations as either driver or passenger, and VEST4, which classifies mutations as pathogenic <lb/>[20, 32]. We queried 3213 patients and identified driver mutations in 66 genes that occurred <lb/>with higher frequency (at least 100 patients had the mutation) (Fig 2A, S1E Table). These <lb/>mutations affect a variety of cellular pathways (Fig 2B, S1F Table) but DNA damage repair and <lb/>checkpoint pathways were the most represented (S3 Fig, S3 Table). <lb/>Of the 66 genes identified, only 8 genes have a high level of driver mutations (30% or higher <lb/>of total analyzed samples) (Fig 2A, S4 Table). Over 77% of residues mutated in five of these <lb/>genes (PTEN, PIK3CA, CTNNB1, TP53 and KRAS) were characterized as driver and over <lb/>30% of mutated residues in three other genes (PPP2R1A, FGFR2, BCOR) were also character-<lb/>ized as driverSeveral others show a lower percentage of driver mutations (Fig 2C, S4 Table). <lb/>Note that most of the EC mutated genes were not identified to harbor driver or pathogenic <lb/>mutations indicating that they probably do not significantly contribute to cellular <lb/>transformation. <lb/>We next mapped all driver mutations on domain diagrams of the genes and indicated how <lb/>many times each mutation was reported (Fig 3). A comprehensive literature search was also <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 2. Genes and pathways affected by endometrial cancer mutations. A. Highly mutated genes detected in endometrial cancer patients. Shown <lb/>are only those genes that are mutated in at least 100 patients out of 3213 (66 genes). For each of the 66 genes, we computed their occurrence in <lb/>endometrial cancers compared with occurrence in all other cancers (expressed as percent). Red stars represent those genes with highest frequency <lb/>of driver mutations. Complete data in S2 and S4 Tables. B. Biological processes affected by most frequent mutations in endometrial cancers. Only <lb/>those processes with a string score above 0.1 are shown. C. Percent driver and passenger mutations for genes in A as determined by the CHASM <lb/>algorithm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Fig 3. Driver mutations and copy number variations of most significantly altered genes. A. Domain diagrams of genes with location of <lb/>driver mutations shown. Only driver mutations identified from CHASM are mapped onto these diagrams and the high frequency ones are <lb/>indicated in red. The number of incidences of a certain mutation is shown in parentheses. All gene maps were made based on previous <lb/>reports: PPP2R1A [58, 85-88], FGFR2 [73, 89], PTEN [90-94], PIK3CA [95, 96], CTNNB1 [68, 70, 97, 98], TP53 [99, 100], and BCOR [101]. <lb/>B. Copy number variations of most significantly altered genes. Each dot represents one sample where high copy number was detected. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>performed for each driver mutation to determine if these mutations have been previously <lb/>identified and studied. In several cases, driver mutations identified from this study have been <lb/>previously validated, which supports the ability of CHASM to correctly make predictions. A <lb/>summary of previously published mutations is presented in S5 Table. <lb/>Copy number variations and gene fusions <lb/>We also investigated copy number variations in the key driver genes (PTEN, PIK3CA, <lb/>CTNNB1, TP53, PP2R1A, FGFR2, BCOR, KRAS, CLDN18)(Fig 3B). Not unexpectedly, we <lb/>found that oncogenes (e.g. PIK3CA, KRAS) are characterized by high copy number in certain <lb/>patients whereas tumor suppressor genes are generally low copy number. We also identified <lb/>five patients with high copy numbers of the CLDN18 gene (three with 5 copies and two with 9 <lb/>copies). This suggests that the high expression profiles for CLDN18 in certain patients may be <lb/>due to allele duplication. COSMIC also reported one recurrent gene fusion, JAZF1-SUZ12, <lb/>which has been previously identified and characterized [57]. <lb/>Effect of driver mutations on protein structure <lb/>Protein structural analysis was performed for all identified driver mutations that had not been <lb/>previously studied in a similar way. Four mutations in PPP2R1A (P179R, R183W, S256F, and <lb/>S256Y) had already been identified and analyzed in detail [58]. Two mutations in FGFR2, <lb/>(N550K and N550H) were mapped onto a partial crystal structure [59]. Six mutations in <lb/>PIK3CA were previously studied: R88Q [60], E545K and H1074R [61], and M1043I, M1043T, <lb/>and M1043V [62]. Six mutations from PTEN (R130G, R130L, R130Q, R173H, and R173C) <lb/>were computationally modeled and analyzed in detail [63]. Once the previously published <lb/>driver mutations were removed, the 45 mutations that remained were modeled computation-<lb/>ally using PyMOL with wild-type protein structures obtained from the Protein Data Bank [24-<lb/>27, 64-66] or AlphaFold [65]. To study how these 45 mutations affect protein structure, a <lb/>three-pronged approach was used in which side-chain tertiary interactions were analyzed, pro-<lb/>tein stability was predicted, and electrostatic surface potentials were calculated (S6 Table). <lb/>Polar contacts with the side chain of the WT and mutant residues were analyzed using <lb/>PyMOL for all driver mutations. Mutations that reduced the number of polar contacts in com-<lb/>parison to WT were identified. There were 8 mutations out of 45 that reduced polar interac-<lb/>tions (hydrogen bonds, dipole-dipole, and salt bridges) relative to WT (S4 Fig). <lb/>All mutations were also analyzed using CUPSAT to determine if they would affect protein <lb/>stability, as determined by a ΔΔG value [30]. The ΔΔG is the difference in the ΔG of unfolding <lb/>for the mutant protein and the WT protein, in which a negative value indicates destabilization <lb/>of the protein structure, and a positive value indicates stabilization. The 10 mutations with the <lb/>largest negative ΔΔG values, representing the most destabilizing mutations, and the 10 with <lb/>the largest positive ΔΔG values, representing the most stabilizing mutations, were selected <lb/>(Table 1). The protein that displayed the most mutations within this list of 20 was the <lb/>CTNNB1 protein with 11 mutations (Table 1, S6 Table). CTNNB1 encodes the beta-catenin <lb/>protein involved in the Wnt-signaling pathway with pleiotropic functions including cell prolif-<lb/>eration and migration [67, 68]. Protein stability is regulated by GSK3-beta phosphorylation of <lb/>several N-terminal residues (S33, S37, T41) which targets CTNNB1 for degradation (Fig 5) <lb/>[69, 70]. CK1 also phosphorylates CTNNB1 at S45 and this posttranslational mark is also <lb/>required for degradation. Not unexpectedly, mutations at these phosphorylated residues affect <lb/>stability of the protein. Two other highly mutated residues in the N-terminus of the protein <lb/>are D32 and G34 [71, 72]. Both residues are also required for CTNNB1 ubiquitination and <lb/>mutations increase protein stability [72]. Remarkably, D32 and G34 decrease ubiquitination <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>and degradation without affecting the phosphorylation status of S33, S37 and T41 [71]. Our <lb/>analysis shows that the D32 and G34 mutations also affect general protein stability which may <lb/>alter the function of the protein. <lb/>FGFR2 is a receptor tyrosine kinase with pleiotropic functions including cell proliferation <lb/>(Fig 5)[73]. The most destabilizing mutation was S252W, with a ΔΔG value of -12.66 kcal/mol. <lb/>This is likely due to the significant change that takes place when mutating serine, which is a <lb/>small polar residue, to tryptophan, a bulky aromatic hydrophobic residue. The S252 residue <lb/>promotes ligand affinity and specificity [74]. The two most frequent mutations identified in <lb/>endometrial cancers are FGFR2 S252W and N550K, which are both activating mutations [75, <lb/>76]. Our analysis shows that the S252W mutation also decreases protein stability. <lb/>The most stabilizing mutation was the TP53 R273C mutation with a ΔΔG of +17.86 kcal/ <lb/>mol. Mutation of R273 also displays oncogenic phenotypes [77] with various variants showing <lb/>different oncogenic potential. Among all variants, the R273C mutation weakens DNA interac-<lb/>tions and significantly affects TP53 function [78]. Our analysis shows that this change has a <lb/>stabilizing effect on the TP53 protein, which may suggest that even in a heterozygous configu-<lb/>ration, non-functional TP53 proteins with longer half-lives may outcompete functional ones. <lb/>Interestingly, every TP53 driver mutation was identified as a stabilizing with a positive ΔΔG <lb/>value. Every mutation of TP53 was also found to be in the top 20 mutations selected for their <lb/>significance. Given that TP53 forms a tetrameric complex, stable non-functional alleles may <lb/>outcompete functional alleles to form poorly functional complexes. No mutations within the <lb/>PIK3CA protein nor the PPP2R1A were identified within either top 10 stabilizing or destabi-<lb/>lizing mutations in Table 1. <lb/>Finally, electrostatic surface potential calculations were performed for the 12 mutations <lb/>located on the exterior of the protein that were predicted to affect the pK a or surface area <lb/>based on the chemical properties of the amino acid side chains (S5 Fig). Mutations that were <lb/>lectrostatically mapped were visually analyzed for observation of any color changes, which <lb/>would indicate alterations in the local pK a , and for observation of any change in shape or size <lb/>of the protein surface, which would indicate surface area alterations. The electrostatic change <lb/>that occurred most often was the neutralization of a basic WT amino acid. This change is <lb/>observationally recognized by a change from a blue electrostatic surface coloration into a <lb/>Table 1. Top 10 stabilizing or destabilizing mutations predicted to affect protein stability via CUPSAT organized by gene. <lb/>Gene/Protein <lb/>Mutation <lb/>Predicted ΔΔG (kcal/mol) <lb/>Predicted Effect <lb/>FGFR2 <lb/>S252W <lb/>-12.66 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>PTEN <lb/>C136R <lb/>-3.93 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>Y1021H <lb/>-1.66 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>D32N <lb/>4.38 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>D32H <lb/>-4.68 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>D32Y <lb/>-2.69 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>G34V <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>G34E <lb/>-8.24 <lb/>Destabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R248G <lb/>1.71 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R248Q <lb/>2.3 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R248W <lb/>4.65 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273L <lb/>5.41 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273C <lb/>17.86 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273H <lb/>3.2 <lb/>Stabilizing <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>white surface coloration. This neutralization of a basic environment occurred in 4 of the 12 <lb/>total mutations. From the 12 mutations that were mapped, 5 mutations were selected that <lb/>showed the most significant changes in surface coloration and/or by their alteration of WT <lb/>surface area following mutation (Fig 4). The top 5 electrostatically altering mutations were <lb/>scattered across PPP2R1A, PTEN, PIK3CA, and CTNNB1 proteins. <lb/>Fig 4. Top five driver mutations that alter protein electrostatic surface potential. Surface rendering of the protein <lb/>structure is shown with basic or positive surface potential colored blue, acidic or negative colored red, and neutral <lb/>colored white. The WT or mutant residue location is identified by a black or white circle. A. PPP2R1A WT R183 <lb/>residue compared to B. PPP2R1A mutant Q183 residue. C. PTEN WT R130 residue with a tartrate molecule shown in <lb/>yellow sticks compared to D. PTEN mutant P130 residue. E. PIK3CA WT E545 residue compared to F. PIK3CA <lb/>mutant A545 residue. G. CTNNB1 WT D32 residue compared to H. CTNNB1 mutant H32 residue. I. CTNNB1 WT <lb/>G34 residue compared to J. CTNNB1 mutant E34 residue. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>Using all the protein structure analysis data compiled, it was possible to identify which <lb/>driver mutations can be classified as significantly affecting protein structure. This was per-<lb/>formed by looking for overlapping mutations from the 8 mutations that reduced polar interac-<lb/>tions, the top 10 stabilizing and top 10 destabilizing mutations with the largest change in ΔΔG <lb/>value, and the 12 mutations that changed the electrostatic surface potential. Using this down-<lb/>selection the total list of 45 studied driver mutations was narrowed down to 10 mutations <lb/>(Table 2). All 10 of these mutations affected the electrostatic surface potential of the protein. <lb/>Six of these 10 mutations reduced polar tertiary structure interactions as compared to WT. <lb/>Seven of these 10 mutations were also identified in the either 20 mutations predicted to signifi-<lb/>cantly affect protein stability (stabilizing or destabilizing) via CUPSAT. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Here, we analyzed genetic alterations in ECS. We employed gold standard artificial intelligence <lb/>algorithms to characterize driver and passenger mutations. Our data agrees with previous find-<lb/>ings, but we identified certain novel key mutation signatures in ECs that are distinct from <lb/>other cancers. Of the 45 driver mutations analyzed using protein computational modeling, 10 <lb/>mutations were identified as significantly effecting protein structure: FGFR2 (S252W), PTEN <lb/>(R130P), PIK3CA (E545A, E545G), CTNNB1 (D32H, G34E, S37Y), and TP53 (R273H, <lb/>R273C, R273L). Interestingly, the multiple mutations that were deemed significant in PIK3CA <lb/>and TP53 were located at the same place in the primary sequence in each respective gene. The <lb/>FGFR2 S252W mutation has been previously studied biochemically and shown to impact <lb/>ligand binding and specificity [74]. The R130 residue in PTEN is located within the active site <lb/>pocket and mutation of this residue has been implicated in various diseases and cancers [63, <lb/>79, 80]. Mutation of the PIK3CA E535 residue, specifically E535A, has been identified a pre-<lb/>dictive marker in breast cancer [81]. The S37 residue in CTNNB1 is a phosphorylation site and <lb/>mutations have been found in colon cancers and melanoma [82, 83]. Finally, TP53 R273 vari-<lb/>ants generally show a loss of wild-type protein function [84]. <lb/>The major molecular pathways affected by driver mutations in endometrial cancers are <lb/>summarized in Fig 5. All pathways that were identified affect cellular proliferation and trans-<lb/>formation. Mutations in CTNNB1 prevent its degradation and leads to formation of a stable <lb/>transcriptional complex and activation of cMYC and Cyclin D1. The PIK3CA signal trans-<lb/>duction pathway is one of the major pathways activated in endometrial cancers. PIK3CA can <lb/>receive signals from both FGFR2 and EGFR, which results in activation of proliferation and <lb/>cell cycle genes. In addition to activating mutations in FGFR2, EGFR and PIK3CA, loss of <lb/>function mutations in the two phosphatases, PTEN and PP2A, leads to constitutive <lb/>Table 2. Mutations identified to significantly affect protein structure. <lb/>Protein <lb/>Mutation <lb/>Observed Electrostatic Change <lb/>Reduces Polar Interactions? <lb/>Predicted ΔΔG (kcal/mol) <lb/>FGFR2 <lb/>S252W <lb/>Neutral to Neutral <lb/>No <lb/>-12.66 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>R130P <lb/>Basic to Less Basic <lb/>Yes <lb/>-0.46 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>E545A <lb/>Acidic to Neutral <lb/>Yes <lb/>-0.49 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>E545G <lb/>Acidic to Neutral <lb/>Yes <lb/>-0.69 <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>D32H <lb/>Acidic to Neutral <lb/>No <lb/>-4.68 <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>G34E <lb/>Neutral to Acidic <lb/>No <lb/>-8.24 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273H <lb/>Basic to Neutral <lb/>Yes <lb/>3.2 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273C <lb/>Basic to Neutral <lb/>Yes <lb/>17.86 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>R273L <lb/>Basic to Less Basic <lb/>Yes <lb/>5.41 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.t002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<body>activation of this oncogenic pathway. Both FGFR2 and EGFR are key receptors that signal <lb/>through PIK3CA as well as JAK-STAT and the MAPK pathways, respectively. Mutations in <lb/>the BCOR transcriptional repressor activates pluripotency and cell fate genes. Loss of TP53 <lb/>function has been well documented and is not unexpected because this gene is mutated in <lb/>over 40% of cancers. An interesting finding is the over-expression of CLDN18 which has <lb/>been demonstrated to activate metastasis and proliferation for other cancers but not endo-<lb/>metrial cancers. <lb/>While many of the mutations investigated in this study have been previously published, <lb/>our analysis sheds light on how these critical mutations impact protein structure. In addition, <lb/>this study demonstrates that CHASM, which uses artificial intelligence, correctly predicts <lb/>many driver mutations that have been experimentally validated. The data presented here <lb/>could be used to refine ECs molecular signatures. These recurrent mutations and genomic <lb/>alterations could be used as molecular markers for diagnosis and staging of ECs. Addition-<lb/>ally, a comprehensive classification of driver mutations can aid in development of molecular <lb/>therapies to target those genes and pathways that are key in EC cellular transformation and <lb/>immortalization. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Distribution of coding mutations in all EC histology types. Shown is frequency of all <lb/>EC mutations by cancer histology. Endometrial carcinoma is the most represented histology <lb/>in these data. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

	<body>Fig 5. Major molecular pathways affected by driver mutations in endometrial cancers. Please see text for details and discussion. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">S2 Fig. Over-expressed genes in endometrial cancers. Shown is a graph of average Z-values <lb/>computed for all TCGA samples (from S2 Table). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Network interaction analysis of genes from Fig 2A. A map of network interactions <lb/>using STRING database. Please see Materials and methods for this analysis. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Fig. Comparison of WT and mutant structures where a reduction in tertiary polar <lb/>interactions was observed. Protein structures are shown with the mutated residue shown in <lb/>orange. Interacting residues or small molecules are shown in yellow sticks. Polar interactions <lb/>(salt bridge, hydrogen bond, or dipole-dipole) are shown as magenta dashed lines. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Fig. Mutations observed to change the electrostatic surface potential. Surface rendering <lb/>of the protein structure is shown with basic or positive surface potential colored blue, acidic or <lb/>negative colored red, and neutral colored white. The WT or mutant residue location is identi-<lb/>fied by a black or white circle. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Table. Gene and nucleotide level analysis in endometrial cancers. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S2 Table. Z scores for all endometrial TCGA samples. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S3 Table. Functions of most frequently mutated genes. Descriptions from NCBI. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S4 Table. Driver and passenger mutation analysis. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S5 Table. Previously reported high frequency driver mutations. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Table. Polar and electrostatic analysis of selected mutations. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors thank The Ohio State Marion Campus for supporting undergraduate student <lb/>research. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Data curation: Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Formal analysis: Anda Stan, Korey Bosart, Mehak Kaur, Ryan J. Yoder, Renee A. Bouley, <lb/>Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Investigation: Anda Stan, Korey Bosart, Mehak Kaur, Ryan J. Yoder, Renee A. Bouley, Ruben <lb/>C. Petreaca. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Methodology: Anda Stan, Korey Bosart, Mehak Kaur, Wilber Escorcia, Ryan J. Yoder, Renee <lb/>A. Bouley. <lb/>Project administration: Wilber Escorcia, Ryan J. Yoder, Renee A. Bouley, Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Resources: Martin Vo, Wilber Escorcia, Ryan J. Yoder, Renee A. Bouley, Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Software: Anda Stan, Martin Vo, Wilber Escorcia, Ryan J. Yoder. <lb/>Supervision: Ryan J. Yoder, Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/>Validation: Anda Stan, Korey Bosart, Mehak Kaur. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Ryan J. Yoder, Renee A. Bouley, Ruben C. Petreaca. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2023). Gynecological Cancers. https://www.cdc.gov/ <lb/>cancer/gynecologic/index.htm. <lb/>2. Einstein M.H., Levine N.F., and Nevadunsky N.S., Menopause and Cancers. Endocrinol Metab Clin <lb/>North Am, 2015. 44(3): p. 603-17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecl.2015.05.012 PMID: 26316246 <lb/>3. Wu Y., et al., Age at Menopause and Risk of Developing Endometrial Cancer: A Meta-Analysis. <lb/>Biomed Res Int, 2019. 2019: p. 8584130. https://doi.org/10.1155/2019/8584130 PMID: 31275987 <lb/>4. Chelmow D., et al., Executive Summary of the Uterine Cancer Evidence Review Conference. Obstet <lb/>Gynecol, 2022. 139(4): p. 626-643. https://doi.org/10.1097/AOG.0000000000004711 PMID: <lb/>35272316 <lb/>5. Siegel R.L., Miller K.D., and Jemal A., Cancer statistics, 2020. CA Cancer J Clin, 2020. 70(1): p. 7-30. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21590 PMID: 31912902 <lb/>6. Guha P., et al., Estrogen receptors as potential therapeutic target in endometrial cancer. J Recept Sig-<lb/>nal Transduct Res, 2023. 43(1): p. 19-26. https://doi.org/10.1080/10799893.2023.2187643 PMID: <lb/>36883690 <lb/>7. Leon-Castillo A., Update in the molecular classification of endometrial carcinoma. Int J Gynecol Can-<lb/>cer, 2023. 33(3): p. 333-342. https://doi.org/10.1136/ijgc-2022-003772 PMID: 36878561 <lb/>8. Cancer Genome Atlas Research, N., et al., Integrated genomic characterization of endometrial carci-<lb/>noma. Nature, 2013. 497(7447): p. 67-73. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12113 PMID: 23636398 <lb/>9. Talhouk A., et al., A clinically applicable molecular-based classification for endometrial cancers. Br J <lb/>Cancer, 2015. 113(2): p. 299-310. https://doi.org/10.1038/bjc.2015.190 PMID: 26172027 <lb/>10. Vermij L., et al., Incorporation of molecular characteristics into endometrial cancer management. His-<lb/>topathology, 2020. 76(1): p. 52-63. https://doi.org/10.1111/his.14015 PMID: 31846532 <lb/>11. Hong B., Le Gallo M., and Bell D.W., The mutational landscape of endometrial cancer. Curr Opin <lb/>Genet Dev, 2015. 30: p. 25-31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gde.2014.12.004 PMID: 25622247 <lb/>12. Temko D., et al., Somatic POLE exonuclease domain mutations are early events in sporadic endome-<lb/>trial and colorectal carcinogenesis, determining driver mutational landscape, clonal neoantigen burden <lb/>and immune response. J Pathol, 2018. 245(3): p. 283-296. https://doi.org/10.1002/path.5081 PMID: <lb/>29604063 <lb/>13. Kim T.M., Laird P.W., and Park P.J., The landscape of microsatellite instability in colorectal and endo-<lb/>metrial cancer genomes. Cell, 2013. 155(4): p. 858-68. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.10.015 <lb/>PMID: 24209623 <lb/>14. O&apos;Hara A.J. and Bell D.W., The genomics and genetics of endometrial cancer. Adv Genomics Genet, <lb/>2012. 2012(2): p. 33-47. https://doi.org/10.2147/AGG.S28953 PMID: 22888282 <lb/>15. Kuhn E., et al., Identification of molecular pathway aberrations in uterine serous carcinoma by <lb/>genome-wide analyses. J Natl Cancer Inst, 2012. 104(19): p. 1503-13. https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/ <lb/>djs345 PMID: 22923510 <lb/>16. Zhao S., et al., Mutational landscape of uterine and ovarian carcinosarcomas implicates histone genes <lb/>in epithelial-mesenchymal transition. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 2016. 113(43): p. 12238-12243. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1614120113 PMID: 27791010 <lb/>17. Momeni-Boroujeni A., et al., Landscape of chromatin remodeling gene alterations in endometrial carci-<lb/>noma. Gynecol Oncol, 2023. 172: p. 54-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2023.03.010 PMID: <lb/>36958196 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>18. Tate J.G., et al., COSMIC: the Catalogue Of Somatic Mutations In Cancer. Nucleic Acids Res, 2019. <lb/>47(D1): p. D941-D947. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky1015 PMID: 30371878 <lb/>19. Pagel K.A., et al., Integrated Informatics Analysis of Cancer-Related Variants. JCO Clin Cancer <lb/>Inform, 2020. 4: p. 310-317. https://doi.org/10.1200/CCI.19.00132 PMID: 32228266 <lb/>20. Tokheim C. and Karchin R., CHASMplus Reveals the Scope of Somatic Missense Mutations Driving <lb/>Human Cancers. Cell Syst, 2019. 9(1): p. 9-23 e8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cels.2019.05.005 PMID: <lb/>31202631 <lb/>21. Cheadle C., et al., Analysis of microarray data using Z score transformation. J Mol Diagn, 2003. 5(2): <lb/>p. 73-81. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1525-1578(10)60455-2 PMID: 12707371 <lb/>22. Guo Y., et al., Large scale comparison of gene expression levels by microarrays and RNAseq using <lb/>TCGA data. PLoS One, 2013. 8(8): p. e71462. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0071462 PMID: <lb/>23977046 <lb/>23. Groves M.R., et al., The structure of the protein phosphatase 2A PR65/A subunit reveals the confor-<lb/>mation of its 15 tandemly repeated HEAT motifs. Cell, 1999. 96(1): p. 99-110. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>s0092-8674(00)80963-0 PMID: 9989501 <lb/>24. Lee J.O., et al., Crystal structure of the PTEN tumor suppressor: implications for its phosphoinositide <lb/>phosphatase activity and membrane association. Cell, 1999. 99(3): p. 323-34. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/s0092-8674(00)81663-3 PMID: 10555148 <lb/>25. Huang C.H., et al., The structure of a human p110alpha/p85alpha complex elucidates the effects of <lb/>oncogenic PI3Kalpha mutations. Science, 2007. 318(5857): p. 1744-8. https://doi.org/10.1126/ <lb/>science.1150799 PMID: 18079394 <lb/>26. Simonetta K.R., et al., Prospective discovery of small molecule enhancers of an E3 ligase-substrate <lb/>interaction. Nat Commun, 2019. 10(1): p. 1402. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-09358-9 PMID: <lb/>30926793 <lb/>27. Solares M.J., et al., High-Resolution Imaging of Human Cancer Proteins Using Microprocessor Materi-<lb/>als. Chembiochem, 2022. 23(17): p. e202200310. https://doi.org/10.1002/cbic.202200310 PMID: <lb/>35789183 <lb/>28. Kaboli Kafshgiri S., Farkhondeh T., and Miri-Moghaddam E., Glyphosate effects on the female repro-<lb/>ductive systems: a systematic review. Rev Environ Health, 2022. 37(4): p. 487-500. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1515/reveh-2021-0029 PMID: 34265884 <lb/>29. Varadi M., et al., AlphaFold Protein Structure Database: massively expanding the structural coverage <lb/>of protein-sequence space with high-accuracy models. Nucleic Acids Res, 2022. 50(D1): p. D439-<lb/>D444. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkab1061 PMID: 34791371 <lb/>30. Parthiban V., Gromiha M.M., and Schomburg D., CUPSAT: prediction of protein stability upon point <lb/>mutations. Nucleic Acids Res, 2006. 34(Web Server issue): p. W239-42. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/ <lb/>gkl190 PMID: 16845001 <lb/>31. Jurrus E., et al., Improvements to the APBS biomolecular solvation software suite. Protein Sci, 2018. <lb/>27(1): p. 112-128. https://doi.org/10.1002/pro.3280 PMID: 28836357 <lb/>32. Douville C., et al., Assessing the Pathogenicity of Insertion and Deletion Variants with the Variant <lb/>Effect Scoring Tool (VEST-Indel). Hum Mutat, 2016. 37(1): p. 28-35. https://doi.org/10.1002/humu. <lb/>22911 PMID: 26442818 <lb/>33. Lee P.J., et al., Clinical Targeted Next-Generation Sequencing Shows Increased Mutational Load in <lb/>Endometrioid-type Endometrial Adenocarcinoma With Deficient DNA Mismatch Repair. Int J Gyne-<lb/>col Pathol, 2018. 37(6): p. 581-589. https://doi.org/10.1097/PGP.0000000000000459 PMID: <lb/>29084048 <lb/>34. Du X., et al., Membranous and nuclear staining of CLDN18 in HPV-independent and HPV-associated <lb/>endocervical adenocarcinomas. Cancer Med, 2023. 12(2): p. 1441-1450. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>cam4.5029 PMID: 35861118 <lb/>35. Cao W., et al., Claudin18.2 is a novel molecular biomarker for tumor-targeted immunotherapy. Bio-<lb/>mark Res, 2022. 10(1): p. 38. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40364-022-00385-1 PMID: 35642043 <lb/>36. Kyuno D., et al., Claudin-18.2 as a therapeutic target in cancers: cumulative findings from basic <lb/>research and clinical trials. Tissue Barriers, 2022. 10(1): p. 1967080. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>21688370.2021.1967080 PMID: 34486479 <lb/>37. Depotte L., et al., New developments and standard of care in the management of advanced gastric <lb/>cancer. Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol, 2023. 48(1): p. 102245. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clinre.2023. <lb/>102245 PMID: 37952913 <lb/>38. Tureci O., et al., Claudin-18 gene structure, regulation, and expression is evolutionary conserved in <lb/>mammals. Gene, 2011. 481(2): p. 83-92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2011.04.007 PMID: <lb/>21571049 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>39. Sahin U., et al., FAST: a randomised phase II study of zolbetuximab (IMAB362) plus EOX versus EOX <lb/>alone for first-line treatment of advanced CLDN18.2-positive gastric and gastro-oesophageal adeno-<lb/>carcinoma. Ann Oncol, 2021. 32(5): p. 609-619. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.annonc.2021.02.005 PMID: <lb/>33610734 <lb/>40. Singh P., Toom S., and Huang Y., Anti-claudin 18.2 antibody as new targeted therapy for advanced <lb/>gastric cancer. J Hematol Oncol, 2017. 10(1): p. 105. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13045-017-0473-4 <lb/>PMID: 28494772 <lb/>41. Grizzi G., et al., Anti-Claudin Treatments in Gastroesophageal Adenocarcinoma: Mainstream and <lb/>Upcoming Strategies. J Clin Med, 2023. 12(8). https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm12082973 PMID: <lb/>37109309 <lb/>42. Anglesio M.S., et al., Cancer-Associated Mutations in Endometriosis without Cancer. N Engl J Med, <lb/>2017. 376(19): p. 1835-1848. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1614814 PMID: 28489996 <lb/>43. Li X., et al., Whole-exome sequencing of endometriosis identifies frequent alterations in genes <lb/>involved in cell adhesion and chromatin-remodeling complexes. Hum Mol Genet, 2014. 23(22): p. <lb/>6008-21. https://doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddu330 PMID: 24969084 <lb/>44. Moore L., et al., The mutational landscape of normal human endometrial epithelium. Nature, 2020. <lb/>580(7805): p. 640-646. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2214-z PMID: 32350471 <lb/>45. Jamieson A. and McAlpine J.N., Molecular Profiling of Endometrial Cancer From TCGA to Clinical <lb/>Practice. J Natl Compr Canc Netw, 2023. 21(2): p. 210-216. https://doi.org/10.6004/jnccn.2022.7096 <lb/>PMID: 36791751 <lb/>46. Momeni-Boroujeni A., et al., Genomic landscape of endometrial carcinomas of no specific molecular <lb/>profile. Mod Pathol, 2022. 35(9): p. 1269-1278. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41379-022-01066-y PMID: <lb/>35365770 <lb/>47. Hong J.H., et al., Genomic landscape of advanced endometrial cancer analyzed by targeted next-gen-<lb/>eration sequencing and the cancer genome atlas (TCGA) dataset. J Gynecol Oncol, 2022. 33(3): p. <lb/>e29. https://doi.org/10.3802/jgo.2022.33.e29 PMID: 35128859 <lb/>48. Choi J., et al., Distinct Genomic Landscapes in Early-Onset and Late-Onset Endometrial Cancer. JCO <lb/>Precis Oncol, 2022. 6: p. e2100401. https://doi.org/10.1200/PO.21.00401 PMID: 35108035 <lb/>49. Li L., et al., Genome-wide mutation analysis in precancerous lesions of endometrial carcinoma. J <lb/>Pathol, 2021. 253(1): p. 119-128. https://doi.org/10.1002/path.5566 PMID: 33016334 <lb/>50. Kyo S., Sato S., and Nakayama K., Cancer-associated mutations in normal human endometrium: Sur-<lb/>prise or expected? Cancer Sci, 2020. 111(10): p. 3458-3467. https://doi.org/10.1111/cas.14571 <lb/>PMID: 32654393 <lb/>51. Dou Y., et al., Proteogenomic Characterization of Endometrial Carcinoma. Cell, 2020. 180(4): p. 729-<lb/>748 e26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2020.01.026 PMID: 32059776 <lb/>52. DeLair D.F., et al., The genetic landscape of endometrial clear cell carcinomas. J Pathol, 2017. 243 <lb/>(2): p. 230-241. https://doi.org/10.1002/path.4947 PMID: 28718916 <lb/>53. Chang Y.S., et al., Identification of novel mutations in endometrial cancer patients by whole-exome <lb/>sequencing. Int J Oncol, 2017. 50(5): p. 1778-1784. https://doi.org/10.3892/ijo.2017.3919 PMID: <lb/>28339086 <lb/>54. Jones N.L., et al., Distinct molecular landscapes between endometrioid and nonendometrioid uterine <lb/>carcinomas. Int J Cancer, 2017. 140(6): p. 1396-1404. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijc.30537 PMID: <lb/>27905110 <lb/>55. Chang Y.S., et al., Genetic alterations in endometrial cancer by targeted next-generation sequenc-<lb/>ing. Exp Mol Pathol, 2016. 100(1): p. 8-12. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yexmp.2015.11.026 PMID: <lb/>26626801 <lb/>56. Choi Y.J., et al., Genomic landscape of endometrial stromal sarcoma of uterus. Oncotarget, 2015. 6 <lb/>(32): p. 33319-28. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.5384 PMID: 26429873 <lb/>57. Hrzenjak A., JAZF1/SUZ12 gene fusion in endometrial stromal sarcomas. Orphanet J Rare Dis, 2016. <lb/>11: p. 15. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13023-016-0400-8 PMID: 26879382 <lb/>58. Taylor S.E., et al., The Highly Recurrent PP2A Aalpha-Subunit Mutation P179R Alters Protein Struc-<lb/>ture and Impairs PP2A Enzyme Function to Promote Endometrial Tumorigenesis. Cancer Res, 2019. <lb/>79(16): p. 4242-4257. <lb/>59. Dixit A. and Verkhivker G.M., Structure-functional prediction and analysis of cancer mutation effects in <lb/>protein kinases. Comput Math Methods Med, 2014. 2014: p. 653487. https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/ <lb/>653487 PMID: 24817905 <lb/>60. Jin N., et al., Therapeutic implications of activating noncanonical PIK3CA mutations in head and neck <lb/>squamous cell carcinoma. J Clin Invest, 2021. 131(22). https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI150335 PMID: <lb/>34779417 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>61. Miller M.S., et al., Structural basis of nSH2 regulation and lipid binding in PI3Kalpha. Oncotarget, <lb/>2014. 5(14): p. 5198-208. <lb/>62. Gymnopoulos M., Elsliger M.A., and Vogt P.K., Rare cancer-specific mutations in PIK3CA show gain <lb/>of function. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 2007. 104(13): p. 5569-74. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>0701005104 PMID: 17376864 <lb/>63. Smith I.N. and Briggs J.M., Structural mutation analysis of PTEN and its genotype-phenotype correla-<lb/>tions in endometriosis and cancer. Proteins, 2016. 84(11): p. 1625-1643. https://doi.org/10.1002/prot. <lb/>25105 PMID: 27481051 <lb/>64. Ponomarenko S., Volfson I., and Strotmann H., Proton gradient-induced changes of the interaction <lb/>between CF0 and CF1 related to activation of the chloroplast ATP synthase. FEBS Lett, 1999. 443(2): <lb/>p. 136-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0014-5793(98)01681-0 PMID: 9989591 <lb/>65. Jumper J., et al., Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold. Nature, 2021. 596 <lb/>(7873): p. 583-589. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03819-2 PMID: 34265844 <lb/>66. Wu W., et al., The influence of natural weathering on the behavior of heavy metals in small basaltic <lb/>watersheds: A comparative study from different regions in China. Chemosphere, 2021. 262: p. <lb/>127897. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127897 PMID: 32791371 <lb/>67. Pai S.G., et al., Wnt/beta-catenin pathway: modulating anticancer immune response. J Hematol <lb/>Oncol, 2017. 10(1): p. 101. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13045-017-0471-6 PMID: 28476164 <lb/>68. Gottardi C.J. and Gumbiner B.M., Adhesion signaling: how beta-catenin interacts with its partners. <lb/>Curr Biol, 2001. 11(19): p. R792-4. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0960-9822(01)00473-0 PMID: 11591340 <lb/>69. Li H., Pamukcu R., and Thompson W.J., beta-Catenin signaling: therapeutic strategies in oncology. <lb/>Cancer Biol Ther, 2002. 1(6): p. 621-5. https://doi.org/10.4161/cbt.309 PMID: 12642683 <lb/>70. Ledinek Z., Sobocan M., and Knez J., The Role of CTNNB1 in Endometrial Cancer. Dis Markers, <lb/>2022. 2022: p. 1442441. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/1442441 PMID: 35531470 <lb/>71. Provost E., et al., Functional correlates of mutation of the Asp32 and Gly34 residues of beta-catenin. <lb/>Oncogene, 2005. 24(16): p. 2667-76. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc.1208346 PMID: 15829978 <lb/>72. Al-Fageeh M., et al., Phosphorylation and ubiquitination of oncogenic mutants of beta-catenin contain-<lb/>ing substitutions at Asp32. Oncogene, 2004. 23(28): p. 4839-46. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc. <lb/>1207634 PMID: 15064718 <lb/>73. Gatius S., et al., FGFR2 alterations in endometrial carcinoma. Mod Pathol, 2011. 24(11): p. 1500-10. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/modpathol.2011.110 PMID: 21725289 <lb/>74. Willie D., et al., Cleft Palate in Apert Syndrome. J Dev Biol, 2022. 10(3). https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>jdb10030033 PMID: 35997397 <lb/>75. Pollock P.M., et al., Frequent activating FGFR2 mutations in endometrial carcinomas parallel germline <lb/>mutations associated with craniosynostosis and skeletal dysplasia syndromes. Oncogene, 2007. 26 <lb/>(50): p. 7158-62. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc.1210529 PMID: 17525745 <lb/>76. Dutt A., et al., Drug-sensitive FGFR2 mutations in endometrial carcinoma. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, <lb/>2008. 105(25): p. 8713-7. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0803379105 PMID: 18552176 <lb/>77. Garg A., et al., Variable Mutations at the p53-R273 Oncogenic Hotspot Position Leads to Altered Prop-<lb/>erties. Biophys J, 2020. 118(3): p. 720-728. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2019.12.015 PMID: <lb/>31952808 <lb/>78. Li J., et al., Mutants TP53 p.R273H and p.R273C but not p.R273G enhance cancer cell malignancy. <lb/>Hum Mutat, 2014. 35(5): p. 575-84. https://doi.org/10.1002/humu.22528 PMID: 24677579 <lb/>79. Chi A.S., et al., Prospective, high-throughput molecular profiling of human gliomas. J Neurooncol, <lb/>2012. 110(1): p. 89-98. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11060-012-0938-9 PMID: 22821383 <lb/>80. Wang S.I., et al., Somatic mutations of PTEN in glioblastoma multiforme. Cancer Res, 1997. 57(19): <lb/>p. 4183-6. PMID: 9331071 <lb/>81. Desriani and Al-Ahwani F., The sensitivity and efficacy method of PIK3CA exon 9 E545A as a high <lb/>diagnostic accuracy in breast cancer. J Genet Eng Biotechnol, 2018. 16(1): p. 71-76. <lb/>82. de La Coste A., et al., Somatic mutations of the beta-catenin gene are frequent in mouse and human <lb/>hepatocellular carcinomas. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 1998. 95(15): p. 8847-51. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1073/pnas.95.15.8847 PMID: 9671767 <lb/>83. Morin P.J., et al., Activation of beta-catenin-Tcf signaling in colon cancer by mutations in beta-catenin <lb/>or APC. Science, 1997. 275(5307): p. 1787-90. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.275.5307.1787 <lb/>PMID: 9065402 <lb/>84. Irshaid L., et al., Endometrial Carcinoma as the Presenting Malignancy in a Teenager With a Patho-<lb/>genic TP53 Germline Mutation: A Case Report and Literature Review. Int J Gynecol Pathol, 2022. 41 <lb/>(3): p. 258-267. https://doi.org/10.1097/PGP.0000000000000792 PMID: 33990091 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 19 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>85. Remmerie M. and Janssens V., PP2A: A Promising Biomarker and Therapeutic Target in Endometrial <lb/>Cancer. Front Oncol, 2019. 9: p. 462. https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2019.00462 PMID: 31214504 <lb/>86. Kauko O. and Westermarck J., Non-genomic mechanisms of protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) regula-<lb/>tion in cancer. Int J Biochem Cell Biol, 2018. 96: p. 157-164. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocel.2018.01. <lb/>005 PMID: 29355757 <lb/>87. Jeong A.L., et al., Patient derived mutation W257G of PPP2R1A enhances cancer cell migration <lb/>through SRC-JNK-c-Jun pathway. Sci Rep, 2016. 6: p. 27391. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep27391 <lb/>PMID: 27272709 <lb/>88. Shih Ie M., et al., Somatic mutations of PPP2R1A in ovarian and uterine carcinomas. Am J Pathol, <lb/>2011. 178(4): p. 1442-7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.01.009 PMID: 21435433 <lb/>89. Stehbens S.J., et al., FGFR2-activating mutations disrupt cell polarity to potentiate migration and inva-<lb/>sion in endometrial cancer cell models. J Cell Sci, 2018. 131(15). https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.213678 <lb/>PMID: 30002137 <lb/>90. Molinari F. and Frattini M., Functions and Regulation of the PTEN Gene in Colorectal Cancer. Front <lb/>Oncol, 2013. 3: p. 326. https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2013.00326 PMID: 24475377 <lb/>91. Wang X. and Jiang X., PTEN: a default gate-keeping tumor suppressor with a versatile tail. Cell Res, <lb/>2008. 18(8): p. 807-16. https://doi.org/10.1038/cr.2008.83 PMID: 18626510 <lb/>92. Bell D.W. and Ellenson L.H., Molecular Genetics of Endometrial Carcinoma. Annu Rev Pathol, 2019. <lb/>14: p. 339-367. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-pathol-020117-043609 PMID: 30332563 <lb/>93. Markowska A., et al., Signalling pathways in endometrial cancer. Contemp Oncol (Pozn), 2014. 18(3): <lb/>p. 143-8. https://doi.org/10.5114/wo.2014.43154 PMID: 25520571 <lb/>94. Wu Y., et al., Significance of a PTEN Mutational Status-Associated Gene Signature in the Progression <lb/>and Prognosis of Endometrial Carcinoma. Oxid Med Cell Longev, 2022. 2022: p. 5130648. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1155/2022/5130648 PMID: 35251475 <lb/>95. Samuels Y., et al., High frequency of mutations of the PIK3CA gene in human cancers. Science, 2004. <lb/>304(5670): p. 554. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1096502 PMID: 15016963 <lb/>96. Saal L.H., et al., PIK3CA mutations correlate with hormone receptors, node metastasis, and ERBB2, <lb/>and are mutually exclusive with PTEN loss in human breast carcinoma. Cancer Res, 2005. 65(7): p. <lb/>2554-9. https://doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472-CAN-04-3913 PMID: 15805248 <lb/>97. Parrish M.L., Broaddus R.R., and Gladden A.B., Mechanisms of mutant beta-catenin in endometrial <lb/>cancer progression. Front Oncol, 2022. 12: p. 1009345. <lb/>98. Travaglino A., et al., Prognostic significance of CTNNB1 mutation in early stage endometrial carci-<lb/>noma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Gynecol Obstet, 2022. 306(2): p. 423-431. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00404-021-06385-0 PMID: 35034160 <lb/>99. Tanaka T., Watanabe M., and Yamashita K., Potential therapeutic targets of TP53 gene in the context <lb/>of its classically canonical functions and its latest non-canonical functions in human cancer. Oncotar-<lb/>get, 2018. 9(22): p. 16234-16247. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.24611 PMID: 29662640 <lb/>100. Mirzayans R., et al., New insights into p53 signaling and cancer cell response to DNA damage: implica-<lb/>tions for cancer therapy. J Biomed Biotechnol, 2012. 2012: p. 170325. https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/ <lb/>170325 PMID: 22911014 <lb/>101. Astolfi A., et al., BCOR involvement in cancer. Epigenomics, 2019. 11(7): p. 835-855. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.2217/epi-2018-0195 PMID: 31150281 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Endometrial cancer mutations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299114 February 26, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>19 / 19 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>