<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-16T11:07:07.081Z">11/16/2025 11:07:07 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-16T11:06:53.877462Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-16T11:06:53.877462Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Effects of partial demand uncertainty <lb/>reduction on private equity financing in small <lb/>and medium-sized enterprises: A supply chain <lb/>perspective <lb/>Jie Deng ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Li Yao 2 , Mengyi Chen 2 , Qingsong He ID <lb/>3 * <lb/>1 School of Accountancy, Chongqing Technology and Business University, Chongqing, China, 2 School of <lb/>Business Administration, Chongqing Technology and Business University, Chongqing, China, 3 School of <lb/>Economics and Management, Harbin Institute of Technology (Weihai), Weihai, China <lb/>* he_qingsong@126.com <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The effect of demand uncertainty reduction (DUR) on supply chain management has <lb/>received tremendous attention. From a financial perspective, studying the impact of DUR is <lb/>equally significant. This study explores the relationship between DUR and private equity <lb/>(PE) financing in retail enterprises within a supply chain, which comprises a dominant sup-<lb/>plier and a subordinate retailer. This article establishes decision models for a retailer backed <lb/>by PE under three market demand conditions: range, mean, and range with mean. The <lb/>study further investigates the impact of partial demand uncertainty reduction (PDUR) on the <lb/>retailer and PE through comparative analysis of these scenarios. To address incomplete <lb/>market demand information during the decision-making process, the study employs the <lb/>minimax regret criterion to construct and solve the model. An intriguing finding of this study <lb/>is that contrary to intuition, PDUR not only fails to promote PE but also reduces the retailer&apos;s <lb/>willingness to finance and decreases the asset size for both the retailer and PE. In addition, <lb/>the better the growth potential for the retail enterprise, the more severe the negative impact <lb/>brought about by PDUR. Moreover, the impact of PDUR on supplier and supply chain per-<lb/>formance is two-fold. PDUR based on range information has a negative impact on the <lb/>expected profit of the supplier and the supply chain, while PDUR based on mean information <lb/>has a positive impact on their expected profit. <lb/></front>

    <body>1. Introduction <lb/>In the past few decades, with the continuous development of the global economy and the <lb/>emergence of innovative technologies, private equity and venture capital (PE/VC) have <lb/>become an important way for small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) to obtain funding. <lb/>According to the &quot;McKinsey Global Private Markets Review 2023&quot; report released by McKin-<lb/>sey &amp; Company, the global private markets fundraising reached $1.2 trillion in 2022, and as of <lb/>June 30th, 2022, the assets under management of private markets reached $11.7 trillion. <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/>1 / 20 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Deng J, Yao L, Chen M, He Q (2024) <lb/>Effects of partial demand uncertainty reduction on <lb/>private equity financing in small and medium-sized <lb/>enterprises: A supply chain perspective. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(3): e0295713. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0295713 <lb/>Editor: Jianhua Zhu, Harbin Institute of <lb/>Technology, CHINA <lb/>Received: October 12, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: November 23, 2023 <lb/>Published: March 28, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Deng et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and Supporting information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: This research was supported by the <lb/>Chongqing Social Science Planning Fund (Grant <lb/>No. 2022NDQN42)(URL https://www.cqskl.com/ <lb/>ch/singlenews_detail.html?articleId=d9e14836-<lb/>a789-48b5-b0c9-af1901072a9c), the Science and <lb/>Technology Research Program of Chongqing <lb/>Municipal Education Commission (Grant No. <lb/>KJQN202300848)(URL http://jw.cq.gov.cn/zwxx_ <lb/></front>

    <body>Compared to traditional bank loans or bonds, PE/VC financing is more flexible and innova-<lb/>tive, and can support SMEs in multiple areas including funding, management, and market. <lb/>They play an immensely crucial role in the financial system and have a decisive impact on <lb/>both national economy and enterprise development [1]. <lb/>However, the benefits of PE/VC are often accompanied by various uncertainties [2], such <lb/>as demand uncertainty [3], valuation uncertainty [4], policy uncertainty [5] and corporate <lb/>environmental uncertainty [6], among others. These uncertainties may have an impact on the <lb/>decision-making, investment returns and exit strategies of PE/VC investments. Li et al. [7] dis-<lb/>covered that uncertainty not only directly restricts corporate investment but also indirectly <lb/>reduces it by increasing financing constraints. As a result, underinvested corporate investment <lb/>may decrease and investment efficiency may worsen. This negative effect is especially pro-<lb/>nounced in small and medium-sized enterprises. <lb/>Among these uncertainties, demand uncertainty often has a more direct impact on a com-<lb/>pany&apos;s financing and operational decisions, as well as its financial performance. CB Insights, <lb/>an American technology market research company, conducted a survey analyzing the failures <lb/>of 101 technology startups, and identified the top 20 reasons for their high-growth companies&apos; <lb/>collapse. Among these reasons, the primary cause of failure was found to be &quot;no market <lb/>demand.&quot; The survey found that a staggering 42% of failed startups had experienced this prob-<lb/>lem. Management becomes fixated on developing new ideas and overlooks the potential harm <lb/>that can result from a lack of market information. According to Pezza&apos;s [8] research, demand <lb/>uncertainty places both internal and external pressures on a company&apos;s operations. Internally, <lb/>more inventory investment is required to buffer against shortages, while externally, uncertain <lb/>sales revenues make it more difficult for a company to sustain its financial feasibility. There-<lb/>fore, demand uncertainty has the greatest impact on a company&apos;s financial performance, espe-<lb/>cially its cash position. Wang et al.&apos;s [9] research further suggests that an increase in demand <lb/>uncertainty may prompt lenders to charge higher interest rates, which could further impact <lb/>the decisions and performance of supply chain and lending market participants. <lb/>Uncertainty reduction theory suggested that people will use various sources when collecting <lb/>information to reduce their uncertainty [10]. Gomm [11] noted that reducing uncertainty can <lb/>reduce investment risk and capital costs, improve financial decision-making, and optimize <lb/>financing. The effect of demand uncertainty reduction (DUR) on supply chain management <lb/>has received tremendous attention by researchers. DUR will help firms to reduce the mismatch <lb/>between supply and demand, thus improving their operational and inventory decisions. <lb/>Unfortunately, from the financial perspective, the importance of DUR has not received suffi-<lb/>cient attention that it deserves [12], especially in terms of how DUR affects equity investment <lb/>and financing decisions, investment return and exit strategies, and so on, which have not been <lb/>addressed in the literature. <lb/>To illustrate the impact of DUR on equity financing, this study focuses on a typical financial <lb/>issue in which a capital-constrained retailer seeks access to private equity (PE). This study <lb/>explores the intersection between operations management and finance, and the analysis is con-<lb/>ducted in a supply chain that includes two self-interested members (a supplier and a retailer), <lb/>engaging in a non-cooperative strategic game. Given that businesses typically spend a great <lb/>deal of time, effort, and resources to acquire complete information, this often results in a con-<lb/>flict between acquiring information and effectively utilizing time. To address this issue, schol-<lb/>ars have explored the concept of partial uncertainty reduction, which involves reducing <lb/>uncertainty in specific aspects of a situation or problem rather than trying to eliminate all <lb/>uncertainty. This article primarily examines the effect of partial demand uncertainty reduction <lb/>(PDUR) on equity financing. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <front>209/gggs/202307/t20230703_12113880.html), <lb/>and the Humanities and Social Science Fund of <lb/>Ministry of Education of China (Grant No. <lb/>23YJA630018)(URL http://www.moe.gov.cn/s78/ <lb/>A13/tongzhi/202310/t20231019_1086367.html). <lb/>All grant were awarded to JD. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>To explore the impact of PDUR on equity financing, this paper constructed three decision <lb/>models based on the reference to Shi et al.&apos;s [13] method of using range to indicate the level of <lb/>uncertainty. These models respectively explore the relevant decisions of retailers under situa-<lb/>tions where the demand range, mean, and both range and mean are known. The situation <lb/>where both demand mean and range are known can be regarded as a partial reduction in <lb/>demand uncertainty for the cases where only the demand range or mean is known. By com-<lb/>paring the performance of supplier, retailer, and private equity under these three models, this <lb/>paper examines: <lb/>1. How does the partial reduction of demand uncertainty affect the expected profits of various <lb/>stakeholders in the context of private equity financing? <lb/>2. Does partially reducing the uncertainty of market demand information help to enhance the <lb/>willingness and efficiency of equity financing? <lb/>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 presents a review of the rele-<lb/>vant literature. In Section 3, we provided a description of the problem and related assump-<lb/>tions, and presented a benchmark model. In Section 4, we constructed and solved the three <lb/>main models, and conducted preliminary and brief analysis of the results obtained. In Section <lb/>5, numerical studies are conducted to present and compare the effects of PDUR on private <lb/>equity financing. We conclude the paper in Section 6, and our proofs are provided in the S1 <lb/>Appendix. <lb/>2. Literature review <lb/>There is currently a wealth of academic research on DUR, and closely related research fields to <lb/>this article include: the impact of DUR on operations management, the impact of DUR on <lb/>financial, and research related to partial uncertainty reduction. <lb/>Researches on the impact of DUR on operations management usually focuses on the opera-<lb/>tional decisions and performance of supply chain players, and assumes that these players are <lb/>free of any capital constraint [12, 14, 15]. For example, Miyaoka and Hausman [16] examined <lb/>the impact of DUR on expected profits of supply chain members in a decentralized supply <lb/>chain consisting of a supplier and a manufacturer. They found that when the manufacturer <lb/>sets the wholesale price, the supplier&apos;s expected profit increases with the reduction of demand <lb/>uncertainty, while the expected profits of the manufacturer and the supply chain vary with <lb/>changes in cost parameters. Li [17] studied the impact of DUR on competitive retailers and <lb/>found that with the reduction of demand uncertainty for a retailer, its own equilibrium profit <lb/>increases while the equilibrium profit of its competitors decreases. In particular, Begen et al. <lb/>[18] compared the impacts of demand uncertainty reduction and supply uncertainty reduction <lb/>on production quantity and cost in the supply chain, and found that relative to exerting supply <lb/>uncertainty reduction effort, exerting demand uncertainty reduction effort leads to producing <lb/>more units and lower system cost. Unfortunately, reducing demand uncertainty does not <lb/>always lead to positive outcomes. According to Li and Petruzzi [19], there are cases where <lb/>demand uncertainty reduction (DUR) can produce mutually beneficial or unilaterally benefi-<lb/>cial outcomes, as well as cases where it can lead to unfavorable outcomes for both parties in a <lb/>bilateral decentralized supply chain, even if the cost of reducing demand uncertainty is zero. <lb/>Another important aspect regarding DUR is how it can influence the decision-making of <lb/>capital-constrained firms in resolving financial issues. These studies generally assume that cap-<lb/>ital-constrained supply chains may have multiple sources of financing (primarily debt financ-<lb/>ing), such as bank credit financing (BCF) and trade credit financing (TCF) [12]. This type of <lb/>research mainly focuses on two areas. The first area focuses on the impact of DUR on the <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>operational decisions of capital-constrained enterprises [20-22]. For example, under the set-<lb/>ting of a price-dependent stochastic market demand, Shi et al. [13] studied how demand <lb/>uncertainty and capital constraint affect retailers&apos; integrated ordering and pricing policies <lb/>towards seasonal products. When faced with relatively low levels of demand uncertainty, a <lb/>retailer deal with such uncertainty typically sets a lower price than the risk-free retailer. In situ-<lb/>ations of high demand uncertainty, the retailer will typically order more than the risk-free <lb/>counterpart. Zhai et al. [23] considered a supply chain consisting of a capital-constrained sup-<lb/>plier who can finance with bank credit and a retailer who can place orders before or after the <lb/>supplier&apos;s production. Their research revealed that the optimal decisions and expected profits <lb/>of both the supplier and retailer vary based on the degree of demand uncertainty reduction, as <lb/>well as the differences in exogenously determined wholesale prices. <lb/>The second area focuses on the impact of DUR on the effectiveness of BCF and TCF [24-<lb/>26]. Jing et al. [27] demonstrated the impact of demand uncertainty on the selection of BCF <lb/>and TCF for a capital-constrained retailer through a set of numerical experiments. When <lb/>demand uncertainty is low, selecting TCF significantly improves supply chain efficiency, while <lb/>BCF is more efficient when demand uncertainty is high. Chen et al. [28] also found similar <lb/>findings that for a retailer with no initial capital, TCF is typically the best option at all levels of <lb/>demand variability. However, as demand uncertainty increases, the incentives for the manu-<lb/>facturer to offer TCF decrease significantly. Additionally, Deng et al. [29] studied the impact of <lb/>TCF on competition between retailers in a supply chain with two competing retailers under <lb/>different levels of demand uncertainty. They found that when both retailers are in financial <lb/>distress, trade credit exacerbates downstream competition when demand uncertainty is high, <lb/>while it mitigates competition when demand uncertainty is low. <lb/>Balancing the need for decision-making information without being overwhelmed is a diffi-<lb/>cult task. Additionally, acquiring comprehensive demand information can be both challenging <lb/>and economically difficult [30]. Langley [31] also suggests that too much information can lead <lb/>to information overload and analysis paralysis. As a result, scholars have begun to focus on <lb/>partial uncertainty reduction. In fact, optimizing the allocation of investments to partially <lb/>reduce parameter uncertainty within a limited budget has always been an important topic in <lb/>engineering design [32]. In the field of supply chain management, partial uncertainty reduc-<lb/>tion is usually modeled through a Bayesian approach using observations of demand/supply to <lb/>reduce the corresponding uncertainty, especially in multi-period newsboy frameworks [33]. <lb/>For single-period supply chain models, the level of partial uncertainty reduction can also be <lb/>characterized by the size of the intervals to which uncertain variables belong [13]. <lb/>This paper is unique compared to existing literature in two main aspects. Firstly, focusing <lb/>on the impact of partial demand uncertainty reduction on equity financing of capital-con-<lb/>strained firms brings important insights into the decision-making process of such firms. Spe-<lb/>cifically, decision-making under partial demand information sometimes better aligns with the <lb/>economic benefit principle of firms. By reducing partial uncertainty, firms are able to make <lb/>more informed and effective decisions, which in turn can lead to better financial performance <lb/>and attract more investment. Secondly, prior research on DUR in the field of finance has pri-<lb/>marily focused on debt financing. However, as Ferrary and Granovetter [34] noted, uncer-<lb/>tainty factors reduce the possibility of obtaining traditional financing resources. Therefore, <lb/>equity financing often becomes the primary way for firms to raise funds when facing signifi-<lb/>cant uncertainty. It is crucial to understand the impact of partial demand uncertainty reduc-<lb/>tion on equity financing. By expanding the scope of DUR research to equity financing, we can <lb/>obtain a more comprehensive understanding of how partial demand uncertainty reduction <lb/>affects the financing decisions of these firms and how to better support their financial goals. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>Table 1 presents a comparison of the themes explored in this research with those addressed in <lb/>related papers. <lb/>3. Problem description and benchmark model <lb/>3.1 Problem description and assumptions <lb/>Considering a two-echelon supply chain, comprising only a single supplier and retailer, the <lb/>supplier provides goods to the retailer at a wholesale price w, while the supplier itself incurs a <lb/>unit cost of c. The retailer, which operates in an emerging market, is a growing enterprise that <lb/>faces unpredictable market demand, characterized by ξ. Due to the highly uncertain external <lb/>market environment, the retailer can only obtain limited information about the distribution of <lb/>market demand. The retailer&apos;s selling price is p. Under the supplier-led Stackelberg game, the <lb/>retailer needs to decide the quantity q of goods to be purchased from the supplier, while the <lb/>supplier needs to decide its optimal wholesale price w. This article draws on Shi et al.&apos;s [12] <lb/>approach, which uses the precision of market demand information to indicate the level of <lb/>demand uncertainty. For example, at the beginning, the retailer only has information about <lb/>the mean (range) of demand, and after obtaining further information about the range (mean) <lb/>of demand, the level of demand uncertainty can be considered reduced. <lb/>This article further assumes that the retailer currently faces good market opportunities, and <lb/>can expand its market and increase market demand through efforts. According to Taylor [35], <lb/>the new market demand can be represented by D = ξ + βe, where e &gt; 0 represents the effort <lb/>level that the retailer puts into market development, and β &gt; 0 represents the demand incre-<lb/>ment brought by each unit of effort level, which is called the growth factor of the enterprise. <lb/>Let V(e) be the effort cost function, which is monotonically increasing with respect to effort <lb/>level and satisfies the law of increasing marginal cost, and also meets V(0) = 0. Without loss of <lb/>generality, this article assumes V(e) = 0.5se 2 , where s &gt; 0 represents the cost coefficient of <lb/>effort. For growing small and medium-sized enterprises, financial constraints are the main <lb/>limiting factor for development, often resulting in the company being &quot;conservative and insuf-<lb/>ficiently enterprising.&quot; Assuming that the retailer is unable to bear the cost of market develop-<lb/>ment due to its own financial constraints, in order to seize market opportunities and achieve <lb/>rapid development, the retailer introduces private equity investment institutions (PE) through <lb/>equity financing. The above process can be represented by the Fig 1. <lb/>Table 1. Differences between this paper and related literature. <lb/>Author <lb/>DUR Partial information <lb/>Capital-constrained <lb/>Equity financing <lb/>Endogenous wholesale price <lb/>Minimax regret criteria <lb/>[12] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>[13] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>[16] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>[17] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>[18] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>[19] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>[21] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>[22] <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>[23] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>[29] <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>[30] <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/>p <lb/>× <lb/>This study <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>Assuming that the PE values the enterprise based on the price-to-book ratio during financ-<lb/>ing. In fact, among various common valuation methods, the price-to-book ratio valuation <lb/>method is suitable for supply chain enterprises with a large amount of physical assets and has <lb/>the advantages of easy access to net asset data that is not easily manipulated. Supposing that <lb/>after financing, the operational decisions of the retail enterprise are still made by the original <lb/>shareholders, i.e. the retailers, and their decision-making objective is to maximize their own <lb/>asset ownership. This article does not take into account the financing costs and taxes, and <lb/>assumes that the retailer&apos;s expansion of the market will not change the selling price of the prod-<lb/>uct. For the convenience of analysis, other assumptions are added to this article, taking into <lb/>account the real cases of enterprises such as Gome, JD.com&apos;s deferred payment, Uber, and <lb/>Touch media, which use all of the financing amount for market development: <lb/>1. The product residual value is 0, and the cost of goodwill loss caused by the retailer&apos;s out-of-<lb/>stock is not considered. <lb/>2. The equity financing fund B of the retailer is used entirely for market development, that is <lb/>B = 0.5se 2 , and the amount of financing determines the extent of the retailer&apos;s market <lb/>expansion. Other parameter settings of this article are shown in Table 2. <lb/>Table 2. The list of notations. <lb/>Notations <lb/>Explanation <lb/>A <lb/>Fixed assets of the retailer before financing <lb/>η <lb/>Retailer&apos;s own funds before financing <lb/>α <lb/>Valuation multiple for the retailer <lb/>θ 1 <lb/>Retailer&apos;s shareholding after equity financing <lb/>θ 2 <lb/>PE&apos;s shareholding after equity financing <lb/>F <lb/>The cumulative distribution function of demand <lb/>Γ <lb/>The set of all non-negative distribution sets that meet certain conditions <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.t002 <lb/>Fig 1. Supply chain operation process. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>3.2 Benchmark model <lb/>In the case of incomplete market demand information, decision-makers often adopt a conser-<lb/>vative and cautious behavior to develop strategies, which we call robust behavior. Currently, <lb/>the research methods of this behavior in academia are collectively referred to as robust optimi-<lb/>zation methods. Among them, the max-min criterion [36] and the minimax regret criterion <lb/>[37] are two common branches. The former considers profit in the worst-case scenario, which <lb/>often leads to overly conservative ordering decisions or even non-ordering decisions. Accord-<lb/>ing to Perakis and Roels [37], the minimax regret criterion is a less conservative approach. <lb/>Therefore, this article uses this method to make optimal ordering decisions under incomplete <lb/>market demand information. <lb/>This section considers the development of ordering strategies for retailers without market <lb/>expansion, i.e., the case where there is no PE participation and e = 0 in Fig 1. The unit cost and <lb/>sales price of the retailer are given by w and p, respectively. In the minimax regret criterion, <lb/>&quot;regret&quot; is defined as the difference between the profit that a retailer could have earned with <lb/>complete information and the profit under incomplete information, which is represented by <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>E F p y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F p q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� in formula. π(q) represents the retailer&apos;s profit. Regret can be seen as <lb/>the loss caused by incomplete information. Maximum regret is defined as <lb/>r q <lb/>ð Þ :¼ max <lb/>F2G <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>E F p y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F p q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>, which can be understood as the maximum cost a <lb/>retailer has to pay to obtain accurate demand distribution information. Therefore, the mini-<lb/>max regret criterion is to consider the problem of minimizing the maximized regret value as <lb/>follows: <lb/>r * ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>r q <lb/>ð Þ ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>max <lb/>F2G <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>E F p y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F p q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>: <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>Perakis and Roels [37] provided the corresponding results on the minimax regret order <lb/>quantity under three market demand situations (range, mean, and range with mean). Further-<lb/>more, if the supplier and retailer engage in a supplier-dominant Stackelberg game, the supplier <lb/>should make the optimal wholesale price decision to maximize its profit, which needs to con-<lb/>sider the maximization problem: max <lb/>w�0 <lb/>w À c <lb/>ð <lb/>Þq. Based on Perakis and Roels [37], we can <lb/>obtain the following lemma: <lb/>Lemma 1. If the demand distribution is non-negative, the optimal wholesale price and <lb/>minimax regret order quantity under three market demand scenarios can be represented in <lb/>Table 3. <lb/>4. Supply chain operational decisions under different market <lb/>demand types <lb/>According to the previous assumption, a growing retailer can expand its market and increase <lb/>market demand by making efforts when facing good market opportunities. The new market <lb/>Table 3. The optimal decision for the benchmark supply chain under three market demand scenarios. <lb/>Optimal decision <lb/>Demand scenarios <lb/>Range <lb/>Mean <lb/>Range &amp; mean <lb/>Optimal wholesale price <lb/>c <lb/>2 þ pr <lb/>2 rÀ l <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>pþc <lb/>2 <lb/>c <lb/>2 þ pm <lb/>2 mÀ l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>Minimax regret order quantity <lb/>1 À c <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>r <lb/>2 þ cl <lb/>2p <lb/>1 À c <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>1 À c <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>m <lb/>2 þ cl <lb/>2p <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.t003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>demand is represented as D = ξ + βe, and the retailer&apos;s order quantity is obviously q � βe. Due <lb/>to a lack of funds, the retailer cannot expand the market on their own and therefore introduces <lb/>a private equity investment institution to increase capital and expand shares, providing all the <lb/>necessary funds for market expansion. After equity financing, the stake percentage of the <lb/>retailer in the retail industry can be estimated using the price-to-book ratio valuation method, <lb/>as y 1 ¼ a AþZ <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>a AþZ <lb/>ð <lb/>ÞþB <lb/>, while the stake percentage of the private equity investor is θ 2 = 1 -θ 1 . Accord-<lb/>ing to assumption B = 0.5se 2 , it can be inferred that e ¼ <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>, and then the net assets of the <lb/>retailer at the end of the sales period can be represented as: <lb/>TA R q <lb/>ð Þ ¼ y 1 A þ Z þ B þ p min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À wq À B <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>: <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>The net assets of the private equity investor is: <lb/>TA PE ¼ y 2 A þ Z þ B þ p min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À wq À B <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>À B: <lb/>ð3Þ <lb/>Similar to the benchmark model, we examine the optimal decisions of the retailer and the <lb/>supplier under three types of market demand. The retailer needs to determine the optimal <lb/>order quantity to minimize the maximum regret value when demand information is incom-<lb/>plete. In other words, the retailer needs to consider the following minimax regret problem: <lb/>r * ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>r q <lb/>ð Þ ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>max <lb/>F2G <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>E F TA R y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F TA R q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>: <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>The supplier needs to make the optimal wholesale price decision to maximize its profit, <lb/>with its objective function being: <lb/>max <lb/>w <lb/>p s w <lb/>ð Þ ¼ max <lb/>w <lb/>w À c <lb/>ð <lb/>Þq: <lb/>ð5Þ <lb/>The order of maximization in formula (4) can be rearranged as follows: <lb/>r * ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>r q <lb/>ð Þ ¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>max <lb/>F2G <lb/>E F TA R y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F TA R q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>¼ min <lb/>q�0 <lb/>max <lb/>y�0 <lb/>y 1 p max <lb/>F2G <lb/>Z þ1 <lb/>0 <lb/>min y; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>À min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>( <lb/>) ! <lb/>dF x <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>þ y 1 w q À y <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ: <lb/>ð6Þ <lb/>Since the retailer has at most the mean of demand, i.e., the first moment information, the <lb/>maximization problem of the inner layer concerning the distribution function in formula (6) <lb/>can be redefined as follows: <lb/>max <lb/>F2G <lb/>Z þ1 <lb/>0 <lb/>min y; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>dF x <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>s:t: <lb/>Z þ1 <lb/>0 <lb/>dF x <lb/>ð Þ ¼ 1; <lb/>R þ1 <lb/>0 <lb/>xdF x <lb/>ð Þ ¼ m; <lb/>dF x <lb/>ð Þ � 0: <lb/>8 <lb/>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; <lb/>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : <lb/>ð7Þ <lb/>It should be noted that Γ will vary depending on the specific demand information. When <lb/>only the demand range information is available, Γ represents the non-negative distribution for <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>all ranges between [l, r]. When only the demand mean information is available, Γ represents <lb/>the non-negative distribution with a mean of μ, and so on. <lb/>The optimization problem (7) can be regarded as a linear programming problem with finite <lb/>constraints and infinite variables. Since the strong duality of linear programming problems <lb/>always holds, the optimal value of (7) is equivalent to the optimal value of the following dual <lb/>problem: <lb/>min <lb/>a 0 ;a 1 <lb/>a 0 þ ma 1 <lb/>s:t: a 0 þ xa 1 � min y; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>; 8x � 0: <lb/>ð8Þ <lb/>Assuming F* is the distribution that maximizes problem (7), according to strong duality, <lb/>we obtain the following complementary slackness conditions: <lb/>Z þ1 <lb/>0 <lb/>a 0 þ xa 1 À min y; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>h <lb/>i <lb/>dF * x <lb/>ð Þ ¼ 0: ð9Þ <lb/>Therefore, the necessary and sufficient condition for problem (7) to have a non-zero solu-<lb/>tion (i.e., demand has a non-zero distribution) is: <lb/>a 0 þ xa 1 ¼ min y; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>À min q; x þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>: <lb/>ð10Þ <lb/>Let G y; q <lb/>ð Þ :¼ max <lb/>F2G <lb/>E F TA R y <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� À E F TA R q <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>f <lb/>g. Similar to Perakis and Roels [37], we can <lb/>obtain the following proposition. <lb/>Proposition 1. (a) Function G(y; q) is concave on interval y 2 [0, q] and interval y 2 [q, <lb/>+1), but not necessarily globally concave. <lb/>(b) Function ρ(q) is convex, and the optimal order quantity q* = arg min ρ(q) for the retailer <lb/>satisfies the following equation: <lb/>max <lb/>y2 0;q * <lb/>½ <lb/>� <lb/>G y; q * <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ ¼ max <lb/>y2 q * ;þ1 <lb/>½ <lb/>Þ <lb/>G y; q * <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ: <lb/>ð11Þ <lb/>Proof. See Appendix 1 in S1 Appendix. <lb/>Proposition 1 indicates that when seeking the maximum regret value with respect to y, it is <lb/>necessary to consider two cases: y � q and y � q. Since function G(y; q) does not have global <lb/>concavity, the maximum regret value cannot be directly obtained by finding its extreme points. <lb/>The order quantity that minimizes the maximum regret value should satisfy the following con-<lb/>dition: the maximum regret value in the case of insufficient orders is equal to the maximum <lb/>regret value in the case of excessive orders. <lb/>4.1 Operational decision-making based on range information <lb/>We first assume that the retailer only knows the range [l, r] of the demand distribution, which <lb/>can be viewed as &quot;uncertainty budget&quot; [38]. By limiting the uncertain demand to a certain <lb/>interval, the retailer can to some extent have more precise control over the order quantity. In <lb/>this case, the equality constraints of problem (7) do not involve the first moment. Through the <lb/>previous dual process and leveraging the conclusion of Proposition 1, we can obtain the fol-<lb/>lowing proposition. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>Proposition 2. If the demand distribution is non-negative and only the range [l, r] is <lb/>known, the optimal order quantity under minimax regret is <lb/>q * ¼ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>þ <lb/>w <lb/>p <lb/>l þ <lb/>p À w <lb/>p <lb/>r: <lb/>ð12Þ <lb/>Proof. Refer to Appendix 2 in S1 Appendix. <lb/>From Eq (12), it can be seen that the retailer&apos;s optimal ordering quantity is a monotonically <lb/>decreasing function of the wholesale price. Further, substituting Eq (12) into the supplier&apos;s <lb/>profit function yields the supplier&apos;s optimal wholesale pricing decision and the corresponding <lb/>optimal ordering decision for the retailer. <lb/>Proposition 3. If the distribution of random demand is non-negative and only the range [l, <lb/>r] is known, under the minimax regret decision of the retailer, the optimal wholesale price for <lb/>the supplier is w * ¼ c <lb/>2 þ <lb/>p rþb <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>À <lb/>� <lb/>2 rÀ l <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>, and the corresponding optimal order quantity for the <lb/>retailer is q * ¼ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi <lb/>B <lb/>2s <lb/>p <lb/>þ r <lb/>2 À c rÀ l <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>2p . <lb/>Proof. By substituting Eq (12) into the objective function (5) of the supplier, we can obtain <lb/>this conclusion. <lb/>Comparison Lemma 1 and Proposition 3 indicate that after equity financing, the retailer <lb/>will increase its ordering level, but correspondingly, the supplier will sell goods at a higher <lb/>wholesale price. This indicates that in a supplier-dominated supply chain, the overly dominant <lb/>position of the supplier leads to an imbalance in the bargaining power of both the supplier and <lb/>the retailer, which may be detrimental to the development of the supply chain. Specifically, if <lb/>the wholesale price is limited to the level in the benchmark model, it will significantly increase <lb/>the retailer&apos;s ordering quantity to q * ¼ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>q <lb/>þ r <lb/>2 À c rÀ l <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>2p . <lb/>4.2 Operational decision-making based on range and mean information <lb/>In this section, we assume that in addition to the range, the retailer can also obtain the mean μ <lb/>of market demand to partially reduce the uncertainty of demand. Then, the ordering quantities <lb/>y and q under both complete information and partial information, which appeared in the defi-<lb/>nition of &quot;regret&quot; in the previous text, should both satisfy y; q 2 l þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>; r þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>h <lb/>i <lb/>. <lb/>Through the previous duality process, we can obtain the following proposition. <lb/>Proposition 4. If the demand distribution is non-negative, has a mean of μ, and a demand <lb/>range of [l, r], then the retailer&apos;s minimax regret order quantity is <lb/>q * ¼ <lb/>m þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>À <lb/>w <lb/>p <lb/>m À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ; <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>� <lb/>w <lb/>p <lb/>; <lb/>l þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>þ <lb/>p m À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>4w <lb/>; <lb/>m À l <lb/>2 r À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>� <lb/>w <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>; <lb/>r þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>2B <lb/>s <lb/>r <lb/>À <lb/>w r À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>2 <lb/>p m À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>; <lb/>w <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>m À l <lb/>2 r À l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>: <lb/>8 <lb/>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; <lb/>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : <lb/>ð13Þ <lb/>Proof. See Appendix 3 in S1 Appendix. <lb/>Similarly, substituting Eq (13) into the supplier&apos;s profit function yields the following <lb/>proposition. <lb/>Proposition 5. If the demand distribution is non-negative, has a mean of μ, and a demand <lb/>range of [l, r], under the retailer&apos;s minimax regret decision, the supplier&apos;s optimal wholesale <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>price is w * ¼ c <lb/>2 þ p <lb/>2 mÀ l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ m þ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>, and the retailer&apos;s optimal order quantity at this whole-<lb/>sale price is q * ¼ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi <lb/>B <lb/>2s <lb/>p <lb/>þ m <lb/>2 À c mÀ l <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>2p . <lb/>Proof. By substituting Eq (13) into the objective function (5) of the supplier, we can obtain <lb/>this conclusion. <lb/>Comparing Propositions 3 and 5, it can be concluded that the partially reduction of demand <lb/>uncertainty has an impact on the decision-making of supply chain members in the case of the <lb/>retailer&apos;s equity financing. Consequently, Corollary 1 can be established. <lb/>Corollary 1. Compared with the case where the retailer only has demand range informa-<lb/>tion, when the retailer obtains additional information about the market demand mean and <lb/>partially reduces demand uncertainty, the supplier will increase the wholesale price, and the <lb/>retailer&apos;s order quantity will decrease. <lb/>Corollary 1 shows that in a decentralized supply chain, the improvement in information <lb/>accuracy brought by PDUR enables suppliers to adjust their wholesale prices based on a better <lb/>understanding of market demand. However, such adjustments may damage the profit and effi-<lb/>ciency of the supply chain, and the specific situation needs to be examined through numerical <lb/>simulation. <lb/>Specifically, we consider a particular case: l ! 0 and r ! +1, which is equivalent to the <lb/>retailer having only the mean information of market demand. In this case, the conclusion of <lb/>Proposition 3 takes the following form. <lb/>Corollary 2. If the demand distribution is non-negative with a mean of μ, under the retail-<lb/>er&apos;s minimax regret decision, the supplier&apos;s optimal wholesale price is w * ¼ pþc <lb/>2 þ <lb/>pb <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>2B=s <lb/>p <lb/>2m <lb/>, and <lb/>the retailer&apos;s optimal order quantity at this wholesale price is q * ¼ b <lb/>ffi ffi ffi <lb/>B <lb/>2s <lb/>p <lb/>þ 1 À c <lb/>p <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>m <lb/>2 . <lb/>Comparing Proposition 3, Proposition 5, and Corollary 2, it can be found that the partially <lb/>reduction of demand uncertainty always leads to the supplier setting a higher wholesale price. <lb/>However, it needs to be noted that this does not necessarily mean that the supplier will obtain <lb/>higher profits. In addition, the impact of the partially reduction of demand uncertainty on the <lb/>expected profits of supply chain participants and equity financing varies with specific supply <lb/>chain structures and different interests among participants. Therefore, it is necessary to simu-<lb/>late and explore the impact and changing trends under different conditions through numerical <lb/>simulation. <lb/>5. Numerical analysis <lb/>In the previous section, we presented the optimal decision-making of a supply chain member <lb/>under three types of market demand information when a retailer engages in equity financing <lb/>through a theoretical model. Further, we identified some of the salient features of PDUR in <lb/>equity financing supply chains by comparing them. In this section, we aim to investigate <lb/>through numerical simulation: (1) how PDUR impacts equity investment and financing, and <lb/>(2) how PDUR affects the performance of all participants. Without loss of generality, this <lb/>paper adopts the method proposed by Andersson et al. [39], and randomly generates a discrete <lb/>demand distribution within interval [l, r]. The specific process is as follows: <lb/>1. Randomly generate n values in the interval [l, r], and arrange them in ascending order to <lb/>form sequence d 1 , d 2 , . . ., d n ; <lb/>2. Randomly select n points s 1 , s 2 , . . ., s n from the interval [0,1] and normalize them using for-<lb/>mula r i ¼ <lb/>s i <lb/>X n <lb/>i¼1 s i <lb/>. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>By following the above process, we obtain a discrete random distribution with values in d 1 , <lb/>d 2 , . . ., d n and corresponding probabilities in ρ 1 , ρ 2 , . . ., ρ n . Let m ¼ <lb/>X n <lb/>i¼1 <lb/>d i r i , and we can <lb/>obtain the mean of market demand. According to Andersson et al. [39], if n is too large, it is <lb/>easy to obtain a uniform distribution, while a too small value of n leads to a too specific distri-<lb/>bution. After considering the trade-off, we set n = 10 in this paper. After obtaining the random <lb/>demand distribution, we can substitute it into the optimal solution obtained in the previous <lb/>section and obtain the performance of each participant under different parameter settings. To <lb/>avoid extreme cases caused by a single random process, we repeat the above process 10,000 <lb/>times and take the average as the final reference value for comparison. In the following simula-<lb/>tion, we use PE to represent equity investors, R to represent retailers, and S to represent suppli-<lb/>ers. All parameter units are set to &quot;1&quot;, and the default parameter settings for the simulation are <lb/>shown in Table 4 unless otherwise specified. <lb/>From the previous result, the main parameters that affect the optimal decision are the <lb/>financing amount B and the growth factor β of the retail company. Therefore, we mainly focus <lb/>on comparing the results under changes in these two parameters. <lb/>Firstly, we will examine the comparison of the optimal decisions of the supplier and the <lb/>retailer under the three information scenarios. From Figs 2 and 3, it can be seen that when the <lb/>supplier has both demand range and mean information, it will set a higher wholesale price. <lb/>Therefore, PDUR may increase the ordering cost for the retailer and may have a negative <lb/>impact on its development. Regarding the order quantity, the impact of PDUR is more compli-<lb/>cated. If only demand range information is available, PDUR will improve the retailer&apos;s order-<lb/>ing level, but if only mean information is available, PDUR will slightly reduce the retailer&apos;s <lb/>order quantity. <lb/>Secondly, we examined the comparison of net assets between the retailer and the PE under <lb/>the three information scenarios. Based on the results presented in Fig 4, neither the retailer <lb/>nor the PE has enough incentive to acquire more market demand information. Regardless of <lb/>the form of demand uncertainty reduction, PDUR always harms the interests of the retailer <lb/>and the PE. Furthermore, Panel (b) shows that companies with higher growth potential are <lb/>more severely affected by the adverse impact brought by PDUR. In particular, Panel (a) indi-<lb/>cates that when only demand range or mean information is available, the optimal financing <lb/>amount of the retailer is higher. However, PDUR will reduce the optimal financing amount of <lb/>the retailer instead, which means that PDUR lowers the retailer&apos;s willingness to finance. In <lb/>real-world situations, we can also observe similar occurrences, for instance: Tesla, an Ameri-<lb/>can electric vehicle manufacturer, encountered the challenge of uncertain demand in the early <lb/>stages of the electric vehicle market. As market demand became clearer, Tesla&apos;s willingness to <lb/>seek financing decreased, and the company began to rely on internal accumulation and debt <lb/>financing to meet its funding needs. JD.com, a major e-commerce platform in China, also <lb/>experiences similar situations. <lb/>Thirdly, we conducted an analysis of how PDUR affects the supply chain and presented the <lb/>relevant results in Figs 5 and 6. It can be found that, unlike the negative effects that PDUR <lb/>always brings to the retailer, although reducing uncertainty from only the range information <lb/>to the situation where both range and mean information are available will harm the interests <lb/>Table 4. Default parameter table for simulation. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>η <lb/>p <lb/>c <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>s <lb/>l <lb/>r <lb/>2000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>1000 <lb/>50 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>100 <lb/>2000 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.t004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>of the supplier, reducing uncertainty from only the mean to the situation where both mean <lb/>and range information are available is beneficial to the supplier. From the perspective of the <lb/>entire supply chain, PDUR greatly reduces the efficiency of the supply chain based on the exist-<lb/>ing range information. However, in the presence of existing mean information, PDUR will <lb/>slightly enhance the efficiency of the supply chain. The impact of PDUR on the supply chain <lb/>shows both positive and negative effects. <lb/>Fig 2. The optimal wholesale price and order quantity (B 2 [100, 10000]). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g002 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>Through our simulations, we found that PDUR has different impacts on different partici-<lb/>pants. Even for the same participant, different forms of PDUR can lead to opposite results. It is <lb/>worth noting that when obtaining the range and mean information of market demand, the <lb/>asset size of both the retailer and PE is lower than that of separately obtaining only range or <lb/>mean information. This phenomenon may be due to the information symmetry and the <lb/>Fig 3. The optimal wholesale price and order quantity (β 2 [1, 20]). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>14 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>dominant position of the supplier in the supply chain structure. In this case, the supplier can <lb/>obtain any market demand information that the retailer obtains, and then, relying on its domi-<lb/>nant position in the supply chain, set new wholesale prices that maximize its interests. It is evi-<lb/>dent that this power structure will lead to a decrease in supply chain efficiency and severely <lb/>weaken or even alter the value-enhancing role of information in the supply chain. Therefore, <lb/>in order to achieve higher supply chain efficiency and value for supply chain members and <lb/>equity investors, the supplier must make appropriate concessions and share benefits. <lb/>Fig 4. The net assets of the retailer and PE ((a): B 2 [100, 10000]; (b): β 2 [1, 20]). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>15 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>6. Discussion and conclusions <lb/>Equity financing is an important way for small and medium-sized enterprises to obtain finan-<lb/>cial support, but it is vulnerable to the impact of demand uncertainty. This article examines <lb/>the impact of partial demand uncertainty reduction (PDUR) on equity financing and supply <lb/>Fig 5. The expected profit of the supplier and the retailer ((a): B 2 [100, 10000]; (b): β 2 [1, 20]). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g005 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>16 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>chain participants&apos; operations in a decentralized supply chain consisting of a single supplier <lb/>and a capital-constrained retailer. The main findings of the study are as follows: <lb/>Firstly, the impact of PDUR on the decisions of a supplier and a retailer is different. Com-<lb/>pared to the similar work conducted by Miyaoka and Hausman [16], this work arrived at the <lb/>same conclusion that in a decentralized supply chain, the expected performance of the retailer <lb/>always decreases with the reduction of demand uncertainty. However, the difference between <lb/>Fig 6. The expected profit of the entire supply chain ((a): B 2 [100, 10000]; (b): β 2 [1, 20]). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713.g006 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>17 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <body>this paper and existing literature lies in the fact that the impact of PDUR on the expected prof-<lb/>its of the supplier and the supply chain varies depending on the way in which the demand <lb/>uncertainty reduces. If PDUR is based on demand range information, the expected profits of <lb/>both the supplier and the supply chain will decrease significantly; if PDUR is based on demand <lb/>mean information, the expected profits of the supplier and the supply chain will increase. <lb/>Secondly, PDUR reduces the willingness of the retailer to finance, which is detrimental to the <lb/>cooperation and development between the retailer and PE. Different from the study conducted <lb/>by Shi et al. [12], which focused on the impact of DUR on the choice of debt financing, this paper <lb/>focuses on the impact of partial DUR on the willingness of enterprises to raise equity financing. <lb/>The results indicate that when the retailer has demand range or mean information, the optimal <lb/>equity financing amount for the retailer is higher than the case where they have both range and <lb/>mean information, and the retailer and PE also have higher net assets in this case. Therefore, <lb/>PDUR has a negative impact on equity financing for companies facing capital constraints, and <lb/>the higher the growth potential of the company, the more severe this negative impact will be. <lb/>Thirdly, PDUR has a two-sided impact on the overall performance of the supplier and the <lb/>supply chain. Conducting PDUR based on range information significantly reduces the <lb/>expected profits of the supplier and the supply chain, while conducting PDUR based on mean <lb/>information slightly increases the expected profits of the supplier and the supply chain. Over-<lb/>all, when it comes to equity financing for a retailer, it is more advantageous for the overall <lb/>development of the supply chain to appropriately reduce the dominant position of the supplier <lb/>in a decentralized supply chain. <lb/>Specifically, the above results reflect a phenomenon where the range information of market <lb/>demand is always the most advantageous information for the retailer and supplier. This pro-<lb/>vides a reference direction for companies facing uncertain demand markets to conduct market <lb/>demand information research during equity financing. <lb/>Although this article focuses on the impact of PDUR on equity financing and the operation <lb/>of the supply chain, providing effective references for the retailer&apos;s information selection in <lb/>obtaining equity financing and rapid growth, it further expands the theoretical research scope <lb/>of supply chain finance. However, this article did not consider the mutual influence between <lb/>the effort level of the financed company and equity financing behavior. Moreover, the risks <lb/>faced by the company during rapid growth are not only demand risks but also high growth <lb/>risks, mainly manifested as the randomness of the demand increment brought by the efforts <lb/>made by the company. Blind optimism will occur if the high growth risk of the company is <lb/>ignored. Therefore, it is very important to take a cautious attitude towards risks and make rea-<lb/>sonable decisions when a company conducts equity financing. On the other hand, how to <lb/>achieve the coordination of the supply chain and improve the efficiency of the supply chain <lb/>through appropriate supply chain contracts is also a research topic worth paying attention to <lb/>in PDUR research, and further research is needed to expand it. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Appendix. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S1 File. Numerical simulation source code. <lb/>(RAR) <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Jie Deng. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>18 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Data curation: Jie Deng, Li Yao. <lb/>Formal analysis: Qingsong He. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Jie Deng. <lb/>Investigation: Li Yao. <lb/>Methodology: Jie Deng, Qingsong He. <lb/>Project administration: Jie Deng. <lb/>Resources: Jie Deng. <lb/>Software: Jie Deng. <lb/>Supervision: Jie Deng, Mengyi Chen. <lb/>Validation: Jie Deng. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Jie Deng, Mengyi Chen. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Li Yao. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Tykvova ´T. Venture capital and private equity financing: an overview of recent literature and an agenda <lb/>for future research. Journal of Business Economics. 2018; 88(3-4): 325-362. <lb/>2. Huang Y S, Wu J, Guo F. Venture capital staging under economic policy uncertainty. International <lb/>Review of Economics &amp; Finance. 2022; 78: 572-596. <lb/>3. Shuwaikh F, Hughes M, Brinette S, Khemiri S. Investment decisions under uncertainty: Corporate ven-<lb/>ture capital as a real option. International Journal of Finance &amp; Economics. [Preprint]. 2023 [cited 2023 <lb/>Nov 13]: [20 p.]. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijfe.2794 <lb/>4. Adams M, Kastrinaki Z. Why are private equity transactions insured? A neo-institutional theory perspec-<lb/>tive. Academy of Management Perspectives. 2022; 36(4): 968-983. <lb/>5. Kellard NM, Kontonikas A, Lamla M, Maiani S. Deal or no deal? Modelling the impact of Brexit uncer-<lb/>tainty on UK private equity activity. British Journal of Management. 2022; 33(1): 46-68. <lb/>6. Uddin M, Chowdhury A. Private equity exit strategies and profitability during the global pandemic: evi-<lb/>dence from around the world. British Journal of Management. 2021; 32(4): 1302-1337. <lb/>7. Li K, Xia B, Chen Y, Ding N, Wang J. Environmental uncertainty, financing constraints and corporate <lb/>investment: Evidence from China. Pacific-Basin Finance Journal. 2021; 70: 101665. <lb/>8. Pezza S. Supply chain finance: Gaining control in the face of uncertainty. Technical report, Aberdeen <lb/>Group, Waltham, MA, 2011. www.aberdeen.com <lb/>9. Wang F, Yang X, Zhuo XP, Xiong MH. Joint logistics and financial services by a 3PL firm: Effects of risk <lb/>preference and demand volatility. Transportation Research Part E: Logistics and Transportation <lb/>Review. 2019; 130: 312-328. <lb/>10. Hwang J, Youn S. From brick-and-mortar to livestream shopping: product information acquisition from <lb/>the uncertainty reduction perspective. Fashion and Textiles. 2023; 10: 1-21. <lb/>11. Gomm M L. Supply chain finance: applying finance theory to supply chain management to enhance <lb/>finance in supply chains. International Journal of Logistics: Research and Applications. 2010; 13(2): <lb/>133-142. <lb/>12. Shi J, Li Q, Chu LK, Shi Y. Effects of demand uncertainty reduction on the selection of financing <lb/>approach in a capital-constrained supply chain. Transportation Research Part E: Logistics and Trans-<lb/>portation Review. 2021; 148: 102266. <lb/>13. Shi J, Fung R Y K, Guo J. Optimal ordering and pricing policies for seasonal products: impacts of <lb/>demand uncertainty and capital constraint. Discrete Dynamics in Nature and Society. 2016; (2016): <lb/>1801658. <lb/>14. Lu B, Chen Z. Live streaming commerce and consumers&apos; purchase intention: An uncertainty reduction <lb/>perspective. Information &amp; Management. 2021; 58(7): 103509. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.im.2021. <lb/>103509 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>19 / 20 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>15. Liu X, Kou Y, Shockley J, Smith JS. How does supplier CSR performance help to expand exchange <lb/>relationships with major buyers? The moderating role of supply-side and demand-driven uncertainty. <lb/>Decision Sciences. 2023; 54(3): 334-357. <lb/>16. Miyaoka J, Hausman W H. How improved forecasts can degrade decentralized supply chains. <lb/>Manufacturing &amp; Service Operations Management. 2008; 10(3): 547-562. <lb/>17. Li M. Demand uncertainty reduction among competing retailers. Production and Operations Manage-<lb/>ment. 2023; 32(6): 1994-2001. <lb/>18. Begen M A, Pun H, Yan X. Supply and demand uncertainty reduction efforts and cost comparison. Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Production Economics. 2016; 180: 125-134. <lb/>19. Li M, Petruzzi N C. Demand uncertainty reduction in decentralized supply chains. Production and Oper-<lb/>ations Management. 2017; 26(1): 156-161. <lb/>20. Choi T M, Luo S. Data quality challenges for sustainable fashion supply chain operations in emerging <lb/>markets: Roles of blockchain, government sponsors and environment taxes. Transportation Research <lb/>Part E: Logistics and Transportation Review. 2019; 131: 139-152. <lb/>21. Pei H, Li H, Liu Y. Optimizing a robust capital-constrained dual-channel supply chain under demand dis-<lb/>tribution uncertainty. Expert Systems with Applications. 2022; 204: 117546. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>eswa.2022.117546 <lb/>22. Zhao Y, Zhou H, Leus R. Recovery from demand disruption: Two-stage financing strategy for a capital-<lb/>constrained supply chain under uncertainty. European Journal of Operational Research. 2022; 303(2): <lb/>699-718. <lb/>23. Zhai Y, Xue W, Ma L. Commitment decisions with demand information updating and a capital-con-<lb/>strained supplier. International Transactions in Operational Research. 2020; 27(5): 2294-2316. <lb/>24. Valencia F. Aggregate uncertainty and the supply of credit. Journal of Banking &amp; Finance. 2017; 81: <lb/>150-165. <lb/>25. Xia B, Fung R Y K, Guo J. Quality Investing and Pricing Strategies by Startups: Impacts of Demand <lb/>Uncertainties and Capital Constraint. Discrete Dynamics in Nature and Society. 2018; 8302645. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1155/2018/8302645 <lb/>26. de Ve ´ricourt F, Gromb D. Financing capacity investment under demand uncertainty: An optimal con-<lb/>tracting approach. Manufacturing &amp; Service Operations Management. 2018; 20(1): 85-96. <lb/>27. Jing B, Chen X, Cai G. Equilibrium financing in a distribution channel with capital constraint. Production <lb/>and Operations Management. 2012; 21(6): 1090-1101. <lb/>28. Chen X. A model of trade credit in a capital-constrained distribution channel. International Journal of <lb/>Production Economics. 2015; 159: 347-357. <lb/>29. Deng SJ, Fu K, Xu JY, Zhu KJ. The supply chain effects of trade credit under uncertain demands. <lb/>Omega. 2021; 98: 102113. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omega.2019.102113 <lb/>30. Yu H, Deng J. A partial robust optimization approach to inventory management for the offline-to-online <lb/>problem under different selling prices. Journal of Systems Science and Systems Engineering. 2017; <lb/>26: 774-803. <lb/>31. Langley A. Between &quot;paralysis by analysis&quot; and &quot;extinction by instinct&quot;. MIT Sloan Management Review. <lb/>1995; 36(3): 63-76. <lb/>32. Li M, Williams N, Azarm S. Interval uncertainty reduction and single-disciplinary sensitivity analysis with <lb/>multi-objective optimization. Journal of Mechanical Design. 2009; 131(3): 031007. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1115/1.3066736 <lb/>33. Ampountolas A. Forecasting hotel demand uncertainty using time series Bayesian VAR models. Tour-<lb/>ism Economics. 2019; 25(5): 734-756. <lb/>34. Ferrary M, Granovetter M. The role of venture capital firms in Silicon Valley&apos;s complex innovation net-<lb/>work. Economy and society. 2009; 38(2): 326-359. <lb/>35. Taylor T A. Supply chain coordination under channel rebates with sales effort effects. Management Sci-<lb/>ence. 2002; 48(8): 992-1007. <lb/>36. Scarf H. A min-max solution of an inventory problem. Studies in the Mathematical Theory of Inventory <lb/>and Production. 1958, 10(2): 201-209. <lb/>37. Perakis G, Roels G. Regret in the newsvendor model with partial information. Operations Research. <lb/>2008; 56(1): 188-203. <lb/>38. Bertsimas D, Sim M. The price of robustness. Operations Research. 2004; 52(1): 35-53. <lb/>39. Andersson J, Jo ¨rnsten K, Nonås SL, Sandal L, Ubøe J. A maximum entropy approach to the newsven-<lb/>dor problem with partial information. European Journal of Operational Research. 2013; 228(1): 190-<lb/>200. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Partial demand uncertainty reduction and private equity financing <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0295713 March 28, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>20 / 20 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>