<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Association of niacin intake and metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease: findings from National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jing</forename>
          <surname>Zhou</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jun</forename>
          <surname>Han</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T17:33:08.932Z">11/12/2025 5:33:08 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12889-024-20161-0</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Jing Zhou, Jun Han. (2024). Association of niacin intake and metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease: findings from National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey. BMC Public Health, 24(1), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12889-024-20161-0</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T17:33:00.434424Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T17:33:00.434424Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>1 <lb/>Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 <lb/>| https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>Optimizing vitiligo diagnosis <lb/>with ResNet and Swin <lb/>transformer deep learning <lb/>models: a study on performance <lb/>and interpretability <lb/>Fan Zhong 1 , Kaiqiao He 2 , Mengqi Ji 1 , Jianru Chen 2 , Tianwen Gao 2 , Shuli Li 2 , <lb/>Junpeng Zhang 1* &amp; Chunying Li 2* <lb/>Vitiligo is a hypopigmented skin disease characterized by the loss of melanin. The progressive nature <lb/>and widespread incidence of vitiligo necessitate timely and accurate detection. Usually, a single <lb/>diagnostic test often falls short of providing definitive confirmation of the condition, necessitating <lb/>the assessment by dermatologists who specialize in vitiligo. However, the current scarcity of such <lb/>specialized medical professionals presents a significant challenge. To mitigate this issue and enhance <lb/>diagnostic accuracy, it is essential to build deep learning models that can support and expedite the <lb/>detection process. This study endeavors to establish a deep learning framework to enhance the <lb/>diagnostic accuracy of vitiligo. To this end, a comparative analysis of five models including ResNet <lb/>(ResNet34, ResNet50, and ResNet101 models) and Swin Transformer series (Swin Transformer <lb/>Base, and Swin Transformer Large models), were conducted under the uniform condition to identify <lb/>the model with superior classification capabilities. Moreover, the study sought to augment the <lb/>interpretability of these models by selecting one that not only provides accurate diagnostic outcomes <lb/>but also offers visual cues highlighting the regions pertinent to vitiligo. The empirical findings reveal <lb/>that the Swin Transformer Large model achieved the best performance in classification, whose AUC, <lb/>accuracy, sensitivity, and specificity are 0.94, 93.82%, 94.02%, and 93.5%, respectively. In terms <lb/>of interpretability, the highlighted regions in the class activation map correspond to the lesion <lb/>regions of the vitiligo images, which shows that it effectively indicates the specific category regions <lb/>associated with the decision-making of dermatological diagnosis. Additionally, the visualization of <lb/>feature maps generated in the middle layer of the deep learning model provides insights into the <lb/>internal mechanisms of the model, which is valuable for improving the interpretability of the model, <lb/>tuning performance, and enhancing clinical applicability. The outcomes of this study underscore <lb/>the significant potential of deep learning models to revolutionize medical diagnosis by improving <lb/>diagnostic accuracy and operational efficiency. The research highlights the necessity for ongoing <lb/>exploration in this domain to fully leverage the capabilities of deep learning technologies in medical <lb/>diagnostics. <lb/>Keywords Vitiligo, Swin transformer, Dermoscopic images, Class activation mapping <lb/>Skin diseases present a substantial healthcare challenge worldwide, with vitiligo standing out as one of the <lb/>prevalent conditions. It is a dermatological condition characterized by the progressive loss of melanocytes, <lb/>resulting in depigmentation of the skin. The progressive nature of vitiligo can profoundly impact patients&apos; physical <lb/>and psychological well-being 1 . Consequently, prompt and accurate diagnosis is pivotal for facilitating effective <lb/>treatment interventions. <lb/>OPEN <lb/>1 <lb/>College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China. 2 Department of Dermatology, Xijing <lb/>Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi&apos;an, China. * email: junpeng.zhang@gmail.com; lichying@ <lb/>fmmu.edu.cn <lb/></front>

    <page>2 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Various diagnostic methods, including dermoscopy, wood lamp examination, skin CT scans, and skin <lb/>biopsies, are utilized in the diagnosis of skin conditions. Dermoscopy, in particular, affords comprehensive <lb/>insights into the status of melanocytes and the distinctive characteristics of vitiligo patches 2,3 . By recognizing the <lb/>pigment cell loss or reduction and identifying structural changes within areas of depigmentation, it contributes <lb/>to the diagnosis of vitiligo. Apart from this, skin biopsy and histological examination can also be employed to <lb/>evaluate the condition of pigment cells and confirm the presence of vitiligo. Nevertheless, since skin biopsy is <lb/>invasive, it is not used for routine diagnosis. Typically, the clinical diagnosis of vitiligo relies on a combination <lb/>of physical examination, dermoscopy, and wood lamp examination. There is no single diagnostic test that <lb/>conclusively confirms vitiligo, which requires the involvement of a dermatologist with expertise in vitiligo. <lb/>Unfortunately, there is a shortage of dermatologists and an unequal distribution of medical resources. In <lb/>some remote areas, even non-dermatologists have to undertake the diagnosis and treatment of vitiligo due to <lb/>medical resource constraints, despite their limited knowledge and training in this field. Although dermatology <lb/>textbooks can be used as reference material, accurate identification and diagnosis is still the main challenge for <lb/>these laypersons. As a result, rates of misdiagnosis and underdiagnosis remain high, and diagnostic accuracy <lb/>ranges from 24 to 70% 4-7 . Therefore, the development of accurate and efficient Artificial Intelligence (AI) -assisted <lb/>diagnostic tools is crucial for analyzing vitiligo dermoscopy images. The AI-assisted diagnostic tools hold the <lb/>potential to furnish dermatologists with precise classification results, thereby contributing to the accuracy of <lb/>vitiligo diagnosis. This technology also serves to mitigate potential errors stemming from limited expertise, <lb/>especially in the context of non-dermatologists. <lb/>The major attention of AI-assisted diagnostic tools is to achieve more accurate classification of medical images. <lb/>As early as 1959, AI-assisted diagnostic tools have been used in medicine. Initially, some traditional machine <lb/>learning models are widely used for dermatological classification problems, such as Support Vector Machines <lb/>(SVM) 8 , K-nearest neighbor (KNN) 9 , and Naive Bayes 10 . Unfortunately, these machine learning models are <lb/>heavily reliant on the quality of manual feature extraction, which poses challenges in simultaneously achieving <lb/>more precise classification results and lower system complexity. Furthermore, the utilization of hand-crafted <lb/>features 11 in these models significantly hampers both the performance and generalisability 12 of the models when <lb/>applied to dermoscopic images. <lb/>In contrast to traditional machine learning methods, deep learning has shown superior performance and <lb/>has attracted more attention. Its effectiveness has been prominently demonstrated in various medical image-<lb/>processing applications 13-15 . The adoption of automatic feature extraction has made it becoming more and more <lb/>popular in the dermatological image classification field 16-18 . As early as 2017, deep learning architectures have <lb/>been proposed and utilized in the ISIC 2017 Dermoscopy Image Segmentation Challenge for dermatological <lb/>classification, segmentation, and detection tasks 19-21 . Notably, ResGANet has exhibited outstanding performance <lb/>in medical image classification tasks in comparison to state-of-the-art backbone models 22 . Moreover, ResGANet <lb/>has demonstrated the ability to enhance performance in medical image segmentation tasks by combining it with <lb/>various segmentation networks. Therefore, deep learning-based methods can effectively overcome the limitations <lb/>associated with traditional machine learning methods. <lb/>However, it is crucial to acknowledge the notable challenge known as the &quot;black box&quot; problem in deep <lb/>learning methods. Despite the relative simplicity of the mathematical theory, the output mechanism is difficult <lb/>to understand. In the field of medical image processing, the interpretability of classification results is crucial. <lb/>However, the existence of the &quot;black box&quot; problem prevents physicians and researchers from understanding the <lb/>logic and mechanisms of implementing these methods 23 . This lack of interpretability undermines the reliability of <lb/>deep learning methods, thus limiting their use in clinical practice. To break through this constraint, visualization <lb/>tools and techniques can be used to increase the transparency of the model and enhance interpretability. <lb/>Several researchers have explored the application of weakly supervised semantic segmentation. This method <lb/>utilizes image-level labeling information, such as identifying the presence or absence of a lesion, to infer the <lb/>segmentation results of the lesion region. This method significantly improves the interpretability of medical <lb/>image classification results 24-26 , since the segmented lesion regions correspond to the visual observations of <lb/>the physician. Generally, this methodology is acknowledged for its capacity to obviate the requirement for <lb/>manual processing of segmentation masks employed as training labels, resulting in substantial time and effort <lb/>conservation 27 . Nevertheless, the delineation of ground truth remains imperative during the training of the <lb/>segmentation network, necessitating manual creation by domain experts. <lb/>This paper focuses on a AI-assisted diagnostic system based on deep learning methods, using dermoscopic <lb/>images for the detection and assessment of vitiligo. The objective of the system is to provide a diagnostic outcome <lb/>of vitiligo and a visual diagnostic report that highlights potential areas associated with the disease. For this <lb/>purpose, a set of networks has been trained, and the top five deep learning models with the most favorable <lb/>results were ultimately selected for comparison. These models belong to the Residual Network (ResNet) and Swin <lb/>Transformer network series. The results reveal that the Swin Transformer, which is a series of image classification <lb/>models based on Transformer architecture, attains the highest accuracy in vitiligo classification. This model <lb/>effectively handles global dependencies in images through hierarchical attention mechanisms and cross-stage <lb/>connectivity mechanisms. Diverging from conventional semantic segmentation techniques prevalent in medical <lb/>image processing and weakly supervised semantic segmentation methods, the deep learning models used in <lb/>this paper were exclusively trained by using disease category labels. With the overall training process, the deep <lb/>learning-based method achieves unsupervised learning for the regions of interest(ROI). <lb/></body>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Materials and methods <lb/>A. Materials <lb/>The study obtained approval from the Ethics Committee at the Fourth Military Medical University, following the <lb/>principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. The dermoscopic image dataset utilized for both model train-<lb/>ing and testing was sourced from the Department of Dermatology at Xijing Hospital, affiliated with the Fourth <lb/>Military Medical University. In accordance with confidentiality regulations and exclusions, no additional clinical <lb/>data from patients were collected. The dataset consisted of a total of 4320 dermoscopic images, representing eight <lb/>distinct hypopigmented skin diseases. Among these, 2678 images were specifically associated with vitiligo, while <lb/>the remaining 1642 images represented seven other pigmented skin diseases distinct from vitiligo. These seven <lb/>hypopigmented dermatoses were identified as pityriasis alba, pityriasis versicolor, marshall white syndrome, <lb/>anemic nevus, idiopathic guttate hypomelanosis, amelanotic nevus, and hypomelanosis of Ito. Considering that <lb/>the primary objective of this study was to distinguish vitiligo through dermoscopic images, which constitutes a <lb/>dichotomous problem, the other seven pigmented dermatoses were collectively grouped. To enhance the assess-<lb/>ment of the model, the dataset was divided into training and test sets in a 7:3 ratio. Within the training dataset, <lb/>there are 1875 images depicting cases of vitiligo and 1150 images of non-vitiligo cases. As for the test dataset, it <lb/>comprises 803 images representing vitiligo cases and 492 images non-vitiligo cases. All images were captured <lb/>in the RGB color space and resized to a standardized dimension of 1280*960 pixels for both model training <lb/>and testing. Considering the bias of the dataset on vitiligo conditions, an attention mechanism is introduced in <lb/>the model to focus more on the features of non-vitiligo images, thus balancing the bias in the training process. <lb/>B. Data preprocessing and data enhancement <lb/>In order to improve the richness of the data during the subsequent training of the network, and thus improve the <lb/>anti-interference ability and generalization of the model, conventional preprocessing methods such as filtering, <lb/>segmentation, hair removal, etc., are not applied to the raw data. Considering that the lighting conditions may be <lb/>different at the time of data acquisition, color constancy processing is used in this study to attenuate this effect. <lb/>The goal of color constancy is to transform the image acquired under an unknown light source so that the <lb/>processed image is close to the image acquired under a standard light source. Typically, color constancy process-<lb/>ing can be accomplished in two separate steps. First, the estimation of the light source in RGB space is accom-<lb/>plished. The estimated light source is then used to transform the image to minimize the effect of the light source. <lb/>The Shades of Gray method, which is the most commonly used method for dermatoscopic image processing, <lb/>employs Minkowski&apos;s paradigm for light source estimation. It uses Minkowski&apos;s paradigm to estimate the light <lb/>source. The value of P can be changed automatically, and when P = 1, the method degenerates to the GrayWorld <lb/>algorithm. When P = ∞, the equation is equivalent to finding the maximum value of f(x), which is equivalent <lb/>to the MaxRGB method. In this study, the value of P is set as 6. The steps of the calculation and the Minkowski <lb/>paradigm used are shown below: <lb/>(1) Substitute the data of each channel into the Minkowski paradigm to find the Min distance of each channel; <lb/>(2) Substitute the data of the whole image into the Minkowski paradigm to find the Min distance of the whole; <lb/>(3) Calculate the ratio of the correction according to the distance of the whole and the distance of each chan-<lb/>nel; (4) Perform the correction of the ratio of each channel, and check whether there is any value exceeding the <lb/>threshold value, and set it as 255 for the ones exceeding the threshold value of 255. All images are preprocessed <lb/>to replace the original images, and by reading the label file, the images can be mapped to the corresponding <lb/>dermatologic category. <lb/>After the preprocessing was completed, to further improve the model performance and results, we used a <lb/>data augmentation technique in each training iteration to make some minor changes to the data as a preliminary <lb/>step before batch sampling. This data augmentation strategy employed in this study encompassed four distinct <lb/>methods, namely random rotation, random brightness, random contrast, and random saturation. Additionally, to <lb/>maintain the original image dimensions, any empty spaces resulting from the data augmentation procedures were <lb/>filled with black pixels. Visual illustrations of the input images following the application of the data augmentation <lb/>procedures are presented in Fig. 1. <lb/>( <lb/>(f (X) P dX) <lb/>dX <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>p = ke <lb/>Figure 1. Three sample images following data augmentation procedures. <lb/></body>

    <page>4 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>C. Overview of the ResNet networks <lb/>The ResNet network architecture includes preprocessing layers, and residual units, as well as a fully connected <lb/>layer and a Softmax layer. The key innovation of ResNet resides in its incorporation of residual connectivity, which <lb/>effectively addresses the challenges of gradient vanishing and exploding encountered during the training of deep <lb/>networks, by establishing direct interconnections between layers. In conventional deep networks, the increase <lb/>in the number of layers results in a degradation of the gradient, thereby creating challenges in network training. <lb/>In order to enhance the network&apos;s interpretability and visual comprehension, a Class activation mapping (CAM) <lb/>module is incorporated into the ResNet architecture (as depicted in Fig. 2). The CAM module plays a crucial role <lb/>in comprehending how the network allocates attention to different categories and identifies significant image <lb/>regions. This network architecture facilitates both image classification and the generation of category activation <lb/>maps simultaneously. This capability allows the network not only to predict the input image&apos;s category but also <lb/>to provide visual interpretations of the classification outcomes. To enhance the analysis and comprehension <lb/>of the feature extraction process within the network, as well as to support research and applications in feature <lb/>visualization and analysis, the hook technique is utilized in conjunction with ResNet. This technique involves the <lb/>extraction of feature output maps from intermediate layers of the neural network by registering hook functions <lb/>during the forward propagation process. Through the implementation of the hook technique, the feature outputs <lb/>of the middle layer can be acquired, thus enabling thorough exploration and analysis of the network&apos;s feature <lb/>extraction capabilities. <lb/>D. Overview of the Swin transformer networks <lb/>Swin Transformer 28 has been proposed by Microsoft Research in 2021 as a deep neural network model based <lb/>on the Transformer architecture. Its primary objective is to extend the application of the Transformer model <lb/>into the realm of image processing by incorporating a layered window attention mechanism. In contrast to <lb/>traditional Transformers, the Swin Transformer employs a Shifted-Window-based Multi-head Self-Attention <lb/>(SW-MSA) module. This module is instrumental in modeling images at various granularities, contributing to the <lb/>model&apos;s enhanced performance in capturing diverse features within the image data. This design allows the Swin <lb/>Transformer to effectively process large-sized images while maintaining computational complexity low during <lb/>inference. Furthermore, the Swin Transformer consists of multiple Transformer layers, forming a deep network <lb/>structure. To improve the model&apos;s local perception, an interaction layer is introduced. This layer facilitates the <lb/>information exchange and interaction between different windows. <lb/>Figure 2. A brief overview of the ResNet framework with the addition of the CAM module. <lb/></body>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>In comparison to the Vision Transformer (VIT), the Swin Transformer introduces a hierarchical structure <lb/>reminiscent of a convolutional neural network (CNN), marking a significant enhancement over VIT. Another <lb/>notable improvement involves replacing the multi-headed self-attention (MSA) module with a SW-MSA mod-<lb/>ule. Summarizing these two improvements as hierarchical feature mapping and SW-MSA. Hierarchical feature <lb/>mapping requires the work of downsampling, which is commonly used in image recognition before pooling <lb/>operations. Instead of traditional pooling, the Swin Transformer employs Patch Merging for downsampling, <lb/>reducing both height (H) and width (W) by half, and channels (C) by four times. These modifications effectively <lb/>address VIT&apos;s challenges in fine-grained tasks and excessive complexity, respectively. In terms of the skeleton, <lb/>the structural skeleton of VIT is still used for the design and continues to process input image data using the <lb/>same patched. <lb/>In terms of scale, the Swin Transformer provides various model specifications tailored to different tasks and <lb/>resource constraints. The three main types of Swin Transformers are Base, Large, and Tiny, and the two specific <lb/>scales used in this study are Base and Large. <lb/>E. Swin transformer attention module <lb/>The attention mechanism serves as a computational model designed to identify and assign weights to relevant <lb/>elements within a sequence or set. This process involves computing an attention weight by learning the relation-<lb/>ship between a query (Q), a key (K), and a value (V). Subsequently, this weight is applied to the corresponding <lb/>value to produce a weighted representation. In practical applications, the Self-Attention mechanism has found <lb/>extensive use. The MSA is an extended version of the self-attentive mechanism, aiming to enhance the repre-<lb/>sentation capability of the model. It applies the attention mechanism to multiple attention heads (i.e., multiple <lb/>Q, K, and V). Each attention head within the MSA mechanism is capable of learning distinct weights, allowing <lb/>it to focus on different information within the input sequence. Finally, the outputs from these multiple attention <lb/>heads are combined or aggregated to produce the final representation vector. MSA is extensively employed in <lb/>Transformer models to capture global dependencies present in the input sequence. And the Swin Transformer <lb/>mainly contains Window-Based Multiple Self-Attention (W-MSA) and SW-MSA. <lb/>The input features are partitioned into multiple equally sized, non-overlapping windows in W-MSA, each <lb/>treated as an individual attention head. In this way, the number of windows directly corresponds to the number <lb/>of attention heads. For each window, W-MSA utilizes self-attention to compute dependencies between various <lb/>positions within the window. This involves calculating the similarity between Q and K (usually using dot product <lb/>attention or scaled dot product attention). Consequently, the attention weights for different positions within the <lb/>window are determined, and the aggregation of values within the window is weighted using these attentional <lb/>weights. This process produces the feature representation within the window. Its main objective is to tackle the <lb/>problem of excessive memory usage linked to VIT&apos;s Self-Attention mechanism. The computational complexity <lb/>of the self-attention mechanism is illustrated in Fig. 3 for both MSA and W-MSA. W-MSA effectively reduces <lb/>Figure 3. Computational complexity of self-attention mechanisms for MSA and W-MSA. <lb/></body>

    <page>6 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>the complexity of MSA from O(n 2 ) to O(n) , alleviating the memory footprint constraints associated with VIT. <lb/>Nonetheless, W-MSA has its limitations, and confining attention to the window introduces the challenge of <lb/>global attention loss. To address this problem, the Swin Transformer integrates the SW-MSA module following <lb/>the W-MSA module. This window-shifting approach introduces essential inter-window connections, thereby <lb/>improving the network&apos;s overall performance. The SW-MSA module splits the image into non-overlapping blocks <lb/>and computes the attention of each block with the neighboring blocks, which enables the model to pay more <lb/>attention to the local information of the image. In order to solve the problem of mismatched attention due to <lb/>interactive movement between windows, a mask matrix is added. For each window, a mask matrix is designed <lb/>separately, in which the mask matrix is assigned to -100 for the part that should not be computed, so that after <lb/>subsequent Softmax computation, it will eventually become 0, which is equivalent to playing a filtering role. In <lb/>addition, the SW-MSA module can establish long-distance dependencies between different locations through <lb/>the multi-head self-attention mechanism, which helps to capture the correlation information between different <lb/>locations in the image and improves the model&apos;s ability to perceive the global information of the image. <lb/>F. Class activation mapping module <lb/>To visualize the classification results, a CAM module is incorporated before the final output layer, comprising a <lb/>global average pooling (GAP) layer and a dense layer. For instance, as depicted in Fig. 4, the CAM module takes <lb/>the output feature map of the last residual module as input. It then applies GAP to the feature map, resulting in a <lb/>fixed-length vector. This vector undergoes dot-product computation with the weights in the final fully connected <lb/>layer, yielding activation values for each category. These activation values can be interpreted as the significance <lb/>of the region associated with a particular category within the input image. By weighting and summing the input <lb/>feature mapping values of the last layer of the residual unit, the CAM can be obtained. In the calculation, it is <lb/>assumed that f k (x, y) represents the activation of the spatial position coordinate point (x, y) in the last residual <lb/>cell of channel k . With channel k , the result of the GAP that has been performed is denoted as F k , and F k is <lb/>1 <lb/>H * W <lb/>x,y f k (x, y) . Hence, given the category c , the result of classifier S c is: <lb/>where w c <lb/>k represents the weight of the model for channel k in the final dense layer corresponding to category <lb/>c . It follows that w c <lb/>k is important for the final class judgment, and each position element in CAM is defined in <lb/>category c is: <lb/>In the case where the input image is classified as target class c , the CAM identifies the significance of each <lb/>location pixel (x, y) on feature map&apos;s spatial grid. Up-sampling the CAM to match the size of the original input <lb/>image, the most relevant region to the target category c can be identified. <lb/>G. Intermediate layer feature map output module <lb/>Applying the Hook technique to ResNet enables the extraction of feature output maps from the intermediate <lb/>layers of the neural network, facilitating a deeper analysis of the network&apos;s feature extraction process. The Hook <lb/>function is applied by registering it on a specific layer or module within ResNet. This Hook function is a custom <lb/>callback function. During the forward propagation of the input image through ResNet, the registered Hook <lb/>function is triggered, capturing the output feature maps of the specified layer or module in accordance with <lb/>(1) <lb/>S c = <lb/>k <lb/>w c <lb/>k F k = <lb/>k <lb/>w c <lb/>k <lb/>1 <lb/>H * W x,y <lb/>f k (x, y) = <lb/>1 <lb/>H * W x,y k <lb/>w c <lb/>k f k (x, y) <lb/>(2) <lb/>CAM c (x, y) = <lb/>k <lb/>w c <lb/>k f k (x, y) <lb/>Figure 4. Graphical diagram of the CAM module mechanism. <lb/></body>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>the specified instructions. These feature maps can then be employed for subsequent analysis, visualization, or <lb/>further processing. <lb/>Informed consent <lb/>Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study. <lb/>Results <lb/>In this section, all five proposed deep learning models are evaluated for their performance on a real pathology <lb/>image set. Our experiments are structured into three parts: first, we conduct training and testing of these five deep <lb/>learning models on the target dataset to identify the most effective model for vitiligo classification. Second, we <lb/>analyze the visual interpretation to determine if the internal weighting parameters will provide valuable informa-<lb/>tion for vitiligo diagnosis. Finally, we visualize the output feature maps for the intermediate layers of ResNet, Swin <lb/>Transformer Base, and Swin Transformer Large. This visualization enables us to observe the response regions of <lb/>neurons and the important features during the feature extraction process. <lb/>The classification performance was evaluated based on accuracy (ACC), sensitivity (SEN), specificity (SPE), <lb/>precision (PRE), and F1-score with vitiligo considered as the positive example. These metrics were computed <lb/>using True Positive (TP), True Negative (TN), False Positive (FP), and False Negative (FN) respectively. ACC <lb/>serves as a measure of the overall correctness of predictions, irrespective of whether they pertain to positive <lb/>or negative samples. It reflects the ratio of correct predictions to the total predictions made. SEN represents <lb/>the proportion of tests that accurately detect true instances of disease, essentially capturing the true positive <lb/>rate. On the other hand, SPE denotes the proportion of tests that accurately identify non-diseased individuals, <lb/>constituting the true negative rate. PRE represents the proportion of samples with a positive prediction that is <lb/>actually positive. F1-score is a weighted average of PRE and Recall. PRE reflects the model&apos;s ability to discriminate <lb/>between negative samples, and the higher the PRE, the better the model&apos;s ability to distinguish between negative <lb/>samples; Recall reflects the model&apos;s ability to recognize positive samples, the higher the Recall, the better the <lb/>model&apos;s ability to recognize positive samples. The F1-score is a combination of the two, with higher F1-scores <lb/>indicating a more robust model. <lb/>In addition to these quantitative metrics, we generated receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves for <lb/>these five models. These curves are employed for a binary categorization task to distinguish between vitiligo and <lb/>non-vitiligo skin diseases. <lb/>A. Performance of five models <lb/>The ROC curves of the five models used in this research were analyzed, and the final results of the test set are <lb/>presented in Fig. 5. Notably, in the case of AUC, the Swin Transformer Large model outperforms the other <lb/>models, achieving a value of 94%. AUC is a significant performance metric, indicating the reliability of prediction <lb/>outcomes, especially for binary classifiers. Furthermore, to provide a more detailed assessment, a confusion <lb/>matrix was utilized to quantify and visualize the performance of five models (Fig. 6). The rows and columns of <lb/>the matrix correspond to the predicted and actual classes, respectively, where 1 represents vitiligo and 0 represents <lb/>other skin diseases that are not vitiligo. It is noteworthy that the Swin Transformer Large model exhibited the <lb/>highest sensitivity at 94.02%%, and also a commendable specificity at 93.5%. Conversely, the Swin Transformer <lb/>Base model demonstrated a slight reduction in its ability to accurately classify both negative and positive samples, <lb/>with specificity and sensitivity values of 93.09% and 92.53%, respectively. Among the networks in the ResNet <lb/>series, ResNet34 emerged as the top performer with a classification accuracy of 89.26%. After assessing the <lb/>performance of five models, it was evident that the Swin Transformer Large model had the highest accuracy of <lb/>93.82% (as indicated in Table 1). Consequently, among the five models, Swin Transformer Large stands out as <lb/>the preferred choice for the diagnosis of vitiligo based on dermatoscopic images. <lb/>Furthermore, to ensure easy replication and validation of the research methodology, we analyze the proposed <lb/>methodology in comparison with some state-of-the-art (SOTA) methods that have performed well 29,30 . Consid-<lb/>ering that most of the recent advances in the use of dermoscopic images have been aimed at bridging the gap <lb/>between clinical and dermoscopic images 31,32 . Both 29,30 used datasets of clinical images. <lb/>(3) <lb/>ACC = <lb/>TP + TN <lb/>TP + FP + TN + FN <lb/>(4) <lb/>SEN = Recall = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FN <lb/>(5) <lb/>SPE = <lb/>TN <lb/>TN + FP <lb/>(6) <lb/>PRE = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FP <lb/>(7) <lb/>F1-score = 2 × <lb/>Pr ecision × Recall <lb/>Pr ecision + Recall <lb/></body>

    <page>8 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>The comparative analysis results, as presented in Table 2, reveal that the model introduced in this paper <lb/>exhibits inferior performance when compared to the method proposed in 29 concerning the public dataset. <lb/>Notably, the observed maximum accuracy difference is approximately 4%. This discrepancy could be attributed <lb/>to variations in dataset characteristics. Specifically, the public dataset predominantly comprises skin images <lb/>from non-smooth regions such as arms, whereas the dermoscopic images utilized in our study predominantly <lb/>feature smoother regions. This dissimilarity in dataset composition emerges as a potential contributing factor <lb/>to the discerned algorithmic differences. <lb/>Moreover, it is noteworthy that the proposed method demonstrates a marginally superior performance on the <lb/>personal dataset compared to the method in 30 . This nuanced improvement could be indicative of the adaptability <lb/>and efficacy of our proposed approach in handling the specific attributes inherent to the personal dataset. Further <lb/>analysis and exploration of these dataset-specific intricacies are warranted to comprehensively understand the <lb/>observed performance variations between the proposed method and existing methods. In summation, our mod-<lb/>els obtain good results on several types of datasets, which validate the stability and generalization of the models. <lb/>B. Interpretive visuals generated by the CAM module <lb/>There are some instances of visual interpretation that are extracted from ResNet&apos;s CAM module (Fig. 7). The <lb/>original images corresponding to these results are also included for further analysis. In these visualizations, red <lb/>areas indicate regions where the network is activated, while blue areas signify regions with no activation. The <lb/>darker red color indicates that the region has a higher contribution value to the model discrimination. Notably, <lb/>the activation is concentrated in areas associated with skin lesions, from the figure, it can be seen that there are <lb/>two bases of discrimination when the model makes judgments: one is based on whether the area of the white <lb/>spots is large and continuous and combined with the edge characteristics of the lesion area, and the other is <lb/>based on the color difference for differentiation, i.e., the difference in pigmentation between the lesion area and <lb/>the other normal skin areas. According to the comprehensive analysis conducted by experienced dermatologists, <lb/>the model captures the two bases and features of clinical diagnosis, i.e. edge and pigmentation, in the judgment. <lb/>The interpretability of the class activation map cues is in great agreement with the physician&apos;s clinical experience. <lb/>This suggest that the CAM-generated heat maps are capable of highlighting category-specific areas of interest <lb/>at critical diagnostic points. When analyzing the class activation maps, we observed that activations were not <lb/>presented in all regions associated with vitiligo. The distribution density of activations did not exactly correspond <lb/>to the features of vitiligo. This may due to the fact that the activation layers selected when generating the class <lb/>activation maps may not provide enough information to accurately reflect the key features of vitiligo. Different <lb/>levels of activation may highlight different image features. This results in failure to capture features associated <lb/>with vitiligo at specific levels. <lb/>However, despite these limitations, we would like to acknowledge and emphasize the insights provided by <lb/>class activation maps in terms of visual interpretation. By localizing key regions for classification, we can guide <lb/>vitiligo diagnostic decisions. Although the distribution of activations may not exactly match the reality of the <lb/>lesion, this analysis still provides us with information about which regions of the image the model is focusing <lb/>on, thus providing a strong guide to diagnosis. <lb/>C. Visual explanations from feature maps <lb/>By utilizing Hooks to access feature maps from the neural network&apos;s intermediate layer, the convolutional <lb/>layers are intercepted to obtain feature representations of the different layers. These feature maps serve multiple <lb/>purposes, including visual interpretation, analysis, and enhancing the interpretability of deep learning models. In <lb/>Figure 5. ROC curves of five models. <lb/></body>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Fig. 8a, the ResNet middle layer feature output image is displayed, with each grid in different layouts representing <lb/>a feature map. In Fig. 8b, the feature layer output images of Swin Transformer Large and Swin Transformer <lb/>Base are showcased. Due to the depth and complexity of the models, each convolutional layer extracts features <lb/>at different levels and abstraction. As a result, the feature maps output from multiple intermediate layers can <lb/>synthetically represent various visual information within the input image. This aids in better understanding the <lb/>decision-making process and performance of the deep learning model. <lb/>Figure 6. Confusion matrixes of five models on test set: (a) ResNet34; (b) ResNet50; (c) ResNet101; (d) Swin <lb/>Transformer Base; (e) Swin Transformer Large. <lb/></body>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Institutional review board statement <lb/>Written informed consent for the use of identifying images was obtained from all patients. The study was <lb/>approved by the Ethics Committee of the Fourth Military Medical University in accordance to the Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki Principles. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Recently, there has been a notable surge in interest surrounding the application of deep learning in medi-<lb/>cal diagnostics. Particularly, deep learning has demonstrated exceptional capabilities in tasks associated with <lb/>image classification, with its application extending into the field of dermatology 33 . Seung et al. proposed a clas-<lb/>sification of clinical images encompassing 12 skin diseases using a deep learning algorithm, achieving a final <lb/>average classification accuracy of 90% 34 . Andre et al. employed CNNs for skin cancer classification, achieving <lb/>results comparable to the expertise of all evaluated experts and demonstrating a similar level of competence as <lb/>dermatologists 35 . However, this is only the effect observed in experimental studies. In real-world settings, the <lb/>results of models compared to experts need to be revisited and explored 36 . Furthermore, several studies have <lb/>demonstrated the remarkable diagnostic and classification abilities of deep learning in tasks related to melanoma <lb/>image analysis 37-39 . Which further promotes the development of deep learning in the field of dermatology. <lb/>Up to now, only a limited number of studies have delved into the application of deep learning in the context <lb/>of vitiligo, and most of them have relied on publicly available datasets 40 . For example, Guo, L. et al. developed <lb/>and validated a hybrid artificial intelligence (AI) model utilizing deep learning for the objective measurement <lb/>and color analysis of vitiligo lesions. The accuracy achieved in detecting vitiligo lesions using the YOLO v3 <lb/>architecture was reported at 85.02% 41 . Another study proposed an effective intelligent classification system for <lb/>vitiligo, which generated high-resolution vitiligo images under the wood lamp and demonstrated high precision <lb/>in classifying these images, achieving a classification accuracy of 85.69% 42 . In comparison to other skin diseases, <lb/>the research on extensively trained vitiligo image datasets and high-precision diagnostic systems is still in its <lb/>early stages. In this study, an accurate diagnostic system with interpretable vitiligo dermoscopic images was <lb/>developed based on a deep learning model. <lb/>Five deep learning models were selected for comparison in this study, primarily comprising two network <lb/>structures ResNet and Swin Transformer, along with their variants, ResNet34, ResNet50, ResNet101, Swin <lb/>Table 1. Performance of five models on test set. <lb/>Models <lb/>ACC (%) SEN (%) SPE (%) AUC PRE (%) F1-score (%) <lb/>ResNet34 <lb/>89.26 <lb/>90.04 <lb/>88.01 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>92.46 <lb/>91.23 <lb/>ResNet50 <lb/>88.49 <lb/>88.54 <lb/>88.41 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>92.58 <lb/>90.51 <lb/>ResNet101 <lb/>87.18 <lb/>87.92 <lb/>85.98 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>91.10 <lb/>89.48 <lb/>Swin transformer base <lb/>92.74 <lb/>92.53 <lb/>93.09 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>95.62 <lb/>93.75 <lb/>Swin transformer large <lb/>93.82 <lb/>94.02 <lb/>93.50 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>95.93 <lb/>94.97 <lb/>Table 2. Performance of proposed models and other SOTA methods on different dataset. <lb/>Dataset <lb/>Models <lb/>ACC <lb/>SEN <lb/>SPE <lb/>PRE <lb/>F1-score <lb/>Public dataset collected from seven public dermatology atlas websites: DermNet, DermNet NZ, <lb/>AtlasDerm, DermIS, SD-260, Kaggle, and DanDerm <lb/>(a) Proposed models <lb/>ResNet34 <lb/>84.43% 84.97% 83.60% 85.38% 85.17% <lb/>ResNet50 <lb/>85.32% 85.45% 85.19% 86.67% 86.06% <lb/>ResNet101 <lb/>86.82% 87.79% 85.71% 87.38% 87.58% <lb/>Swin Transformer Base <lb/>90.80% 90.61% 91.01% 91.90% 91.25% <lb/>Swin Transformer Large 92.78% 92.96% 92.59% 93.40% 93.18% <lb/>(b) Reference 29 <lb/>VGG <lb/>96.77% 97.20% 96.30% 96.73% 96.80% <lb/>ResNet <lb/>95.27% 95.10% 95.60% 96.19% 95.80% <lb/>DenseNet <lb/>96.27% 96.20% 96.10% 96.70% 96.20% <lb/>Person dataset provided by Department of Cosmetic Laser Surgery in the Hospital for Skin Disease <lb/>and Institute of Dermatology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (CAMS) &amp; Peking Union <lb/>Medical College <lb/>(a) Proposed models <lb/>ResNet34 <lb/>81.65% 82.04% 81.00% 87.72% 84.78% <lb/>ResNet50 <lb/>82.40% 82.63% 82.00% 88.46% 85.45% <lb/>ResNet101 <lb/>83.52% 84.43% 82.00% 88.68% 86.96% <lb/>Swin Transformer Base <lb/>86.89% 87.43% 86.00% 91.82% 89.57% <lb/>Swin Transformer Large 87.64% 88.02% 87.00% 91.88% 89.91% <lb/>(b) Reference 30 <lb/>YOLO V3 <lb/>85.02% 92.91% 72.00% 84.70% 88.62% <lb/></body>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Transformer Large, and Swin Transformer Base. It is noteworthy that Swin Transformer is a relatively new <lb/>network. In previous studies, ResNets have been used widely for dermatological image segmentation and <lb/>classification and have demonstrated excellent performance 43-45 . Swin Transformer is a deep learning model based <lb/>on Transformer architecture. It has found extensive applications in the field of medical image processing and has <lb/>achieved remarkable results in computer vision tasks. Consequently, we chose to investigate the performance <lb/>of these two widely used and innovative deep learning networks in the specific context of vitiligo diagnosis. The <lb/>experimental results indicate that among the ResNets, ResNet34 performs slightly better than ResNet50, while <lb/>ResNet101 exhibits the least favorable results. Generally, with an increase in network depth, the performance <lb/>of ResNet gradually improves, as deeper structures tend to capture finer details and features in images more <lb/>effectively. However, it&apos;s noteworthy that on specific datasets or tasks, ResNet34 may outperform ResNet50 46 , and <lb/>ResNet34 with fewer parameters could also be more robust and better generalized, particularly on smaller datasets <lb/>where the data size is limited. It&apos;s important to acknowledge that performance comparisons are influenced by <lb/>various factors, and different studies may reach slightly different conclusions 47 . Swin Transformer, proposed as a <lb/>novel model for computer vision in 2021, has demonstrated wide applicability in various tasks, including image <lb/>segmentation, restoration, and reconstruction 48-50 . Swin Transformer has been used in medical image processing <lb/>through its hierarchical structure and self-attention mechanism, which demonstrates a robust capability for <lb/>feature extraction and modeling. This presents promising opportunities for innovation in medical image analysis <lb/>and diagnosis. Currently, there have been limited studies reporting the utilization of Swin Transformer in the <lb/>context of medical images 51-53 . As far as we are aware, our study stands out as one of the relatively few instances <lb/>Figure 7. Examples of visual interpretation. <lb/></body>

    <page>12 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>where the Swin Transformer has been applied to the analysis of dermoscopic images. As the optimal model in <lb/>our task, Swin Transformer achieved an accuracy of 93.82% and 92.74% for both specifications, respectively. This <lb/>indicates the potential of Swin Transformer in medical applications, warranting further research and exploration <lb/>in the field of medicine. <lb/>Figure 8. Examples of feature maps for different channels extracted from: (a) ResNet; (b) Swin Transformer. <lb/></body>

    <page>13 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <body>Conclusion <lb/>Vitiligo is a common hypopigmentation disease, and its final diagnosis usually requires a combination of <lb/>professional doctors&apos; experience and test results from specialized instruments. With the help of computer <lb/>vision and deep learning technology, it can provide an auxiliary means to help doctors diagnose vitiligo more <lb/>accurately. The objective of this study is to evaluate the performance of multiple deep learning models using <lb/>vitiligo image samples and subsequently identify five models with optimal diagnostic performance, including <lb/>ResNet34, ResNet50, ResNet101, Swin Transformer Base, and Swin Transformer Large. These models were then <lb/>utilized to develop a vitiligo diagnostic system that not only provides a disease label but also generates a visual <lb/>diagnostic report displaying the possible regions associated with the disease. The outcomes produced by the CAM <lb/>module effectively emphasize specific areas relevant to each class within diagnostic points, thereby assisting in <lb/>decision-making during the diagnosis of skin conditions. Additionally, the use of feature output maps from the <lb/>middle layer of the neural network enhances the understanding of how the model processes input images for <lb/>tasks such as classification or localization. This integrated visual and informational output helps to improve the <lb/>interpretability of the system, providing physicians with more comprehensive and in-depth insights that enhance <lb/>confidence and decision-making during the diagnostic process. <lb/>The results of this study demonstrate that deep learning techniques have achieved significant accuracy gains <lb/>in vitiligo diagnosis and provide comprehensive visual and informative outputs for diagnostic results. This not <lb/>only emphasizes the excellence of deep learning models in vitiligo diagnosis but also suggests the potential value <lb/>of their application in a broader diagnostic setting covering a wide range of dermatological conditions. This <lb/>finding highlights the great potential of deep learning techniques in the field of dermatological imaging and <lb/>also emphasizes the urgency of delving deeper into this area in the future. These encouraging results not only <lb/>provide more reliable diagnostic support for patients with vitiligo but also lay a solid foundation for advancing <lb/>the diffusion of deep learning techniques in real-world dermatologic diagnostic applications. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>The data presented in this study are available on request from the corresponding author. The data are not publicly <lb/>available due to privacy or ethical concerns. <lb/></div>

    <front>Received: 18 September 2023; Accepted: 10 April 2024 <lb/></front>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Boniface, K., Seneschal, J., Picardo, M. &amp; Taïeb, A. Vitiligo: focus on clinical aspects, immunopathogenesis, and therapy. Clin. Rev. <lb/>Allergy Immunol. 54, 52-67. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s12016-017-8622-7 (2018). <lb/>2. Thatte, S. S. &amp; Khopkar, U. S. The utility of dermoscopy in the diagnosis of evolving lesions of vitiligo. Indian J. Dermatol. Venereol. <lb/>Leprol. 80, 505-508. https:// doi. org/ 10. 4103/ 0378-6323. 144144 (2014). <lb/>3. Kumar Jha, A., Sonthalia, S., Lallas, A. &amp; Chaudhary, R. K. P. Dermoscopy in vitiligo: Diagnosis and beyond. Int. J. Dermatol. 57, <lb/>50-54. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1111/ ijd. 13795 (2018). <lb/>4. Federman, D. G., Concato, J. &amp; Kirsner, R. S. Comparison of dermatologic diagnoses by primary care practitioners and <lb/>dermatologists. A review of the literature. Arch. Fam. Med. 8, 170-172. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1001/ archf ami.8. 2. 170 (1999). <lb/>5. Moreno, G., Tran, H., Chia, A. L. K., Lim, A. &amp; Shumack, S. Prospective study to assess general practitioners&apos; dermatological <lb/>diagnostic skills in a referral setting. Australas. J. Dermatol. 48, 77-82. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1111/j. 1440-0960. 2007. 00340.x (2007). <lb/>6. Tran, H., Chen, K., Lim, A. C., Jabbour, J. &amp; Shumack, S. Assessing diagnostic skill in dermatology: A comparison between general <lb/>practitioners and dermatologists. Australas. J. Dermatol. 46, 230-234. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1111/j. 1440-0960. 2005. 00189.x (2005). <lb/>7. Federman, D. G. &amp; Kirsner, R. S. The abilities of primary care physicians in dermatology: Implications for quality of care. Am. J. <lb/>Manag. Care 3, 1487-1492 (1997). <lb/>8. Wu, W.-J., Lin, S.-W. &amp; Moon, W. K. An artificial immune system-based support vector machine approach for classifying ultrasound <lb/>breast tumor images. J. Digit Imaging 28, 576-585. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10278-014-9757-1 (2015). <lb/>9. Uddin, S., Haque, I., Lu, H., Moni, M. A. &amp; Gide, E. Comparative performance analysis of K-nearest neighbour (KNN) algorithm <lb/>and its different variants for disease prediction. Sci. Rep. 12, 6256. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ s41598-022-10358-x (2022). <lb/>10. Fesharaki, N.J., Pourghassem, H., 2012. Medical X-ray Images Classification Based on Shape Features and Bayesian Rule, in: <lb/>2012 Fourth International Conference on Computational Intelligence and Communication Networks. Presented at the 2012 4th <lb/>International Conference on Computational Intelligence and Communication Networks (CICN), IEEE, Mathura, Uttar Pradesh, <lb/>India, pp. 369-373. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1109/ CICN. 2012. 145. <lb/>11. Celebi, M. E. et al. A methodological approach to the classification of dermoscopy images. Computerized Med. Imaging Gr. 31, <lb/>362-373. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. compm edimag. 2007. 01. 003 (2007). <lb/>12. Jeong, H. K., Park, C., Henao, R. &amp; Kheterpal, M. Deep learning in dermatology: A systematic review of current approaches, <lb/>outcomes, and limitations. JID Innovations 3, 100150. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. xjidi. 2022. 100150 (2023). <lb/>13. Alwakid, G., Gouda, W., Humayun, M. &amp; Sama, N. U. Melanoma detection using deep learning-based classifications. Healthcare <lb/>10, 2481. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ healt hcare 10122 481 (2022). <lb/>14. Jalali, Y., Fateh, M., Rezvani, M., Abolghasemi, V. &amp; Anisi, M. H. ResBCDU-Net: A deep learning framework for lung CT image <lb/>segmentation. Sensors 21, 268. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ s2101 0268 (2021). <lb/>15. Hasan, Md. M., Islam, M. U., Sadeq, M. J., Fung, W.-K. &amp; Uddin, J. Review on the evaluation and development of artificial <lb/>intelligence for COVID-19 containment. Sensors 23, 527. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ s2301 0527 (2023). <lb/>16. Li, Y. et al. Deep learning radiomic analysis of DCE-MRI combined with clinical characteristics predicts pathological complete <lb/>response to neoadjuvant chemotherapy in breast cancer. Front. Oncol. 12, 1041142. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3389/ fonc. 2022. 10411 42 <lb/>(2023). <lb/>17. Tschandl, P. et al. Expert-level diagnosis of nonpigmented skin cancer by combined convolutional neural networks. JAMA Dermatol <lb/>155, 58. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1001/ jamad ermat ol. 2018. 4378 (2019). <lb/>18. Ravi, V. Attention cost-sensitive deep learning-based approach for skin cancer detection and classification. Cancers 14, 5872. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ cance rs142 35872 (2022). <lb/>19. Kaur, R., GholamHosseini, H., Sinha, R. &amp; Lindén, M. Melanoma classification using a novel deep convolutional neural network <lb/>with dermoscopic images. Sensors 22, 1134. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ s2203 1134 (2022). <lb/>20. Tushar, F. I. Automatic skin lesion segmentation using grabcut in hsv colour space. arXiv preprint. 29. https:// doi. org/ 10. 48550/ <lb/>arXiv. 1810. 00871 (2018). <lb/></listBibl>

    <page>14 <lb/></page>

    Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>21. Ruan, J., Xiang, S., Xie, M., Liu, T., Fu, Y. MALUNet: A Multi-Attention and Light-weight UNet for Skin Lesion Segmentation. 2022 <lb/>IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine, 1150-1156. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1109/ BIBM5 5620. 2022. 99950 40 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>22. Zhao, Z., Zeng, Z., Xu, K., Chen, C. &amp; Guan, C. DSAL: Deeply supervised active learning from strong and weak labelers for <lb/>biomedical image segmentation. IEEE J. Biomed. Health Inform. 25, 3744-3751. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1109/ JBHI. 2021. 30523 20 (2021). <lb/>23. Cheng, J. et al. ResGANet: Residual group attention network for medical image classification and segmentation. Med. Image Anal. <lb/>76, 102313. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. media. 2021. 102313 (2022). <lb/>24. Razzak, M. I., Naz, S. &amp; Zaib, A. Deep learning for medical image processing: Overview, challenges and the future. Classification <lb/>BioApps: Autom. Decis. Mak. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ 978-3-319-65981-7_ 12 (2018). <lb/>25. Hassan, H. et al. Supervised and weakly supervised deep learning models for COVID-19 CT diagnosis: A systematic review. <lb/>Comput. Method. Progr. Biomed. 218, 106731. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. cmpb. 2022. 106731 (2022). <lb/>26. Wang, R. et al. Medical Image segmentation using deep learning: A survey. IET Image Process. 16, 1243-1267. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1049/ ipr2. 12419 (2022). <lb/>27. Kumar, A. et al. Adapting content-based image retrieval techniques for the semantic annotation of medical images. Comput. Med. <lb/>Imaging Graph. 49, 37-45. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. compm edimag. 2016. 01. 001 (2016). <lb/>28. Liu Z, Lin Y, Cao Y, et al. Swin transformer: Hierarchical vision transformer using shifted windows. Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF <lb/>International Conference on Computer Vision. 2021: 10012-10022. <lb/>29. Zhang, L. et al. Design and assessment of convolutional neural network based methods for vitiligo diagnosis. Front. Med. 8, 754202 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>30. Guo, L. et al. A deep learning-based hybrid artificial intelligence model for the detection and severity assessment of vitiligo lesions. <lb/>Ann. Transl. Med. https:// doi. org/ 10. 21037/ atm-22-1738 (2022). <lb/>31. Kroemer, S. et al. Mobile teledermatology for skin tumour screening: Diagnostic accuracy of clinical and dermoscopic image <lb/>tele-evaluation using cellular phones. Br. J. Dermatol. 164(5), 973-979 (2011). <lb/>32. Reiter, O. et al. The differences in clinical and dermoscopic features between in situ and invasive nevus-associated melanomas and <lb/>de novo melanomas. J. Eur. Acad. Dermatol. Venereol. 35(5), 1111-1118 (2021). <lb/>33. Li, L.-F. et al. Deep learning in skin disease image recognition: A review. IEEE Access 8, 208264-208280. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1109/ <lb/>ACCESS. 2020. 30372 58 (2020). <lb/>34. Han, S. S. et al. Classification of the clinical images for benign and malignant cutaneous tumors using a deep learning algorithm. <lb/>J. Investigative Dermatol. 138, 1529-1538. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. jid. 2018. 01. 028 (2018). <lb/>35. Esteva, A. et al. Dermatologist-level classification of skin cancer with deep neural networks. Nature 542, 115-118. https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1038/ natur e21056 (2017). <lb/>36. Menzies, S. W. et al. Comparison of humans versus mobile phone-powered artificial intelligence for the diagnosis and management <lb/>of pigmented skin cancer in secondary care: a multicentre, prospective, diagnostic, clinical trial. The Lancet Digital Health, 5(10), <lb/>e679-e691. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/ S2589-7500(23) 00130-9 (2023). <lb/>37. Haenssle, H. A. et al. Man against machine: Diagnostic performance of a deep learning convolutional neural network for <lb/>dermoscopic melanoma recognition in comparison to 58 dermatologists. Ann. Oncol. 29, 1836-1842. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ <lb/>annonc/ mdy166 (2018). <lb/>38. Codella, N.C.F. et al., 2018. Skin lesion analysis toward melanoma detection: A challenge at the 2017 International symposium <lb/>on biomedical imaging (ISBI), hosted by the international skin imaging collaboration (ISIC), in: 2018 IEEE 15th International <lb/>Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (ISBI 2018). Presented at the 2018 IEEE 15th International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging <lb/>(ISBI 2018), IEEE, Washington, DC, pp. 168-172. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1109/ ISBI. 2018. 83635 47. <lb/>39. Brinker, T. J. et al. Deep learning outperformed 136 of 157 dermatologists in a head-to-head dermoscopic melanoma image <lb/>classification task. Eur. J. Cancer 113, 47-54. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. ejca. 2019. 04. 001 (2019). <lb/>40. Hillmer, D. et al. Evaluation of facial vitiligo severity with a mixed clinical and artificial intelligence approach. J. Investigative <lb/>Dermatol. 144(2), 351-357 (2024). <lb/>41. Guo, L. et al. A deep learning-based hybrid artificial intelligence model for the detection and severity assessment of vitiligo lesions. <lb/>Ann. Transl. Med. 10, 590. https:// doi. org/ 10. 21037/ atm-22-1738 (2022). <lb/>42. Luo, W., Liu, J., Huang, Y. &amp; Zhao, N. An effective vitiligo intelligent classification system. J. Ambient. Intell. Human Comput. 14, <lb/>5479-5488. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s12652-020-02357-5 (2023). <lb/>43. S, K., Inbarani, H.H., 2022. Ensemble Pre-Trained Deep Convolutional Neural Network Model for Classifying Medical Image <lb/>Datasets, in: 2022 International Conference on Augmented Intelligence and Sustainable Systems (ICAISS). Presented at the 2022 <lb/>International Conference on Augmented Intelligence and Sustainable Systems (ICAISS), IEEE, Trichy, India, pp. 121-128. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1109/ ICAIS S55157. 2022. 10011 089. <lb/>44. Al-masni, M. A., Kim, D.-H. &amp; Kim, T.-S. Multiple skin lesions diagnostics via integrated deep convolutional networks for <lb/>segmentation and classification. Comput. Method. Progr. Biomed. 190, 105351. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. cmpb. 2020. 105351 (2020). <lb/>45. Mayall, F. G. et al. Artificial intelligence-based triage of large bowel biopsies can improve workflow. J. Pathol. Inform. 14, 100181. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. jpi. 2022. 100181 (2023). <lb/>46. Huang, G., Liu, Z., Van Der Maaten, L., &amp; Weinberger, K. Q. Densely connected convolutional networks. IEEE conference on <lb/>computer vision and pattern recognition, 4700-4708. https:// doi. org/ 10. 48550/ ARXIV. 1608. 06993 (2023). <lb/>47. PMLR.Tan, M., Le, Q.V. EfficientNet: Rethinking Model Scaling for Convolutional Neural Networks. International conference on <lb/>machine learning, 6105-6114. https:// doi. org/ 10. 48550/ ARXIV. 1905. 11946 (2019). <lb/>48. Liang, J., Cao, J., Sun, G., Zhang, K., Van Gool, L., Timofte, R. SwinIR: Image Restoration Using Swin Transformer. IEEE/CVF <lb/>international conference on computer vision. 1833-1844. https:// doi. org/ 10. 48550/ ARXIV. 2108. 10257 (2021). <lb/>49. Cao, H. et al. Swin-Unet: Unet-Like Pure Transformer for Medical Image Segmentation. In: Computer Vision -ECCV 2022 <lb/>Workshops. ECCV 2022. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, (eds Karlinsky, L., Michaeli, T. &amp; Nishino, K.) 13803, 205-218. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1007/ 978-3-031-25066-8_9 (2022). <lb/>50. Huang, J. et al. Swin transformer for fast MRI. Neurocomputing. 493, 281-304. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. neucom. 2022. 04. 051 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>51. Peng, L. et al. Analysis of CT scan images for COVID-19 pneumonia based on a deep ensemble framework with DenseNet, Swin <lb/>transformer, and RegNet. Front. Microbiol. 13, 995323. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3389/ fmicb. 2022. 995323 (2022). <lb/>52. Chi, J. et al. CT image super-resolution reconstruction based on global hybrid attention. Comput. Biol. Med. 150, 106112. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. compb iomed. 2022. 106112 (2022). <lb/>53. Liu, L. et al. An intelligent diagnostic model for melasma based on deep learning and multimode image input. Dermatol. Ther. 13, <lb/>569-579. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s13555-022-00874-z (2023). <lb/></listBibl>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>Conceptualization, C.-Y.L. and J.-P.Z.; methodology, F.Z., J.-P.Z. and K.-Q.H.; software, M.-Q.J.; validation, C.-<lb/>Y.L., J.-P.Z. and K.-Q.H.; formal analysis, F.Z. and J.-R.C.; investigation, T.-W.G. and F.Z.; resources, C.-Y.L. and <lb/>J.-P.Z.; data curation, S.-L.L. and J.-R.C.; writing-original draft preparation, F.Z.; writing-review and editing, <lb/></div>

    <page>15 <lb/></page>

    Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

    <note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2024) 14:9127 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-59436-2 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">C.-Y.L. and J.-P.Z.; visualization, M.-Q.J. and T.-W.G.; supervision, J.-P.Z.; project administration, C.-Y.L. and <lb/>J.-P.Z.; funding acquisition, C.-Y.L. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China&apos;s Mathematics Tianyuan <lb/>Foundation (12126606) and the R&amp;D project of Pazhou Lab (Huangpu) (2023K0605). <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

    <front>Additional information <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to J.Z. or C.L. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the <lb/>Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from <lb/>the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024 </front>

  </text>

</TEI>