<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-17T16:37:44.093Z">11/17/2025 4:37:44 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-17T16:37:28.082689Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-17T16:37:28.082689Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak <lb/>(Quercus humboldtii Bonpl.) populations: The <lb/>importance of intraspecific variation <lb/>Diana Bonilla 1 , Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n1 , Adriana Corrales 1 , Ana M. Aldana 2 , Julieth <lb/>V. Ca ´rdenas 3 , Adriana SanchezID 1 * <lb/>1 Biology Department, Faculty of Natural Sciences, Universidad del Rosario, Bogota ´, D.C., Colombia, <lb/>2 Departamento de Ciencias Biolo ´gicas, Universidad de Los Andes, Bogota ´, D.C., Colombia, 3 Santuario de <lb/>Fauna y Flora Guanenta ´Alto Rı ´o Fonce, Parques Nacionales Naturales de Colombia, Bogota ´, D.C., <lb/>Colombia <lb/>* adriana.sanchez@urosario.edu.co <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Monodominant tree communities can have phenotypic trait variation (intraspecific variation) <lb/>as extreme as the trait variation across a forest with higher species diversity. An example of <lb/>such forests is those composed of Quercus, an important genus of woody angiosperms in <lb/>the montane neotropical forest. The Andean oak, or Quercus humboldtii Bonpl., is the sole <lb/>member of this genus in South America and a characteristic component of montane ecosys-<lb/>tems. Although there are several studies on the ecology and genetic structure of this spe-<lb/>cies, there are few studies on the functional trait diversity among populations. <lb/>Understanding functional traits can improve our comprehension of how organisms respond <lb/>to various environmental conditions. In this study, we aimed to evaluate differences in six <lb/>functional traits in individuals of the Andean oak, in two ontogenetic stages (juveniles and <lb/>adults) from three populations with contrasting environmental conditions. Additionally, using <lb/>T-statistics, we assessed the impact of external filters (e.g., climate, resource availability, <lb/>large-scale biotic interactions) on population assembly. We found a remarkable level of <lb/>functional differentiation among Andean oak forests, with all traits differing between popula-<lb/>tions and five traits differing between ontogenetic stages. External filters had a stronger <lb/>influence in populations with more extreme environmental conditions. These findings <lb/>emphasize the dynamic and context-dependent nature of functional traits in this species. <lb/>However, given the limited exploration of functional diversity in Andean oak populations, fur-<lb/>ther studies are needed to inform conservation efforts. <lb/></front>

	<body>Introduction <lb/>When thinking about tropical ecosystems, rainforests with highly diverse plant communities <lb/>and low relative abundance typically come to mind. However, exceptions to this general pat-<lb/>tern exist throughout the tropics, where a single tree species can account for more than 60% of <lb/>the total abundance [1, 2]. While monodominant forests are rare, their community-level <lb/></body>

	<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/>1 / 18 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Bonilla D, Castañeda-Leo ´n V, Corrales A, <lb/>Aldana AM, Ca ´rdenas JV, Sanchez A (2024) <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak <lb/>(Quercus humboldtii Bonpl.) populations: The <lb/>importance of intraspecific variation. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(3): e0299645. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0299645 <lb/>Editor: Francesco Boscutti, University of Udine: <lb/>Universita degli Studi di Udine, ITALY <lb/>Received: June 15, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: February 12, 2024 <lb/>Published: March 13, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Bonilla et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/>Funding: This research was funded by the <lb/>Universidad del Rosario, through funds awarded <lb/>by the Research and Innovation Center (Adriana <lb/>Sanchez) and the Faculty of Natural Sciences <lb/>(Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n). The funders had no <lb/>role in the study design, data collection and <lb/></front>

	<body>phenotypic variation can be as extreme as that observed in forests with higher species diversity <lb/>[3]. As a result, intraspecific variation within these forests may be as crucial as variation <lb/>among species for community structure and ecosystem function [4, 5]. <lb/>An example of such monodominant forests is those composed by Quercus L. Quercus is a <lb/>remarkable group of woody flowering plants in the Neotropics, ranging from central Mexico to <lb/>the northern Andes [6]. The highest species diversity for this genus in the Americas is found in <lb/>the mountains of southern Mexico [7]. However, as we move towards Central America, there is <lb/>a gradual decrease in species diversity to the extent that only one oak species, Q. humboldtii <lb/>Bonpl. (1805), exists in Colombia. Although Q. humboldtii is a relatively recent migrant in this <lb/>country [8], it remains a distinctive element of its montane ecosystems [9]. This species forms <lb/>monodominant forests [10] that span the three branches (Eastern, Central, and Western Cordil-<lb/>lera) of the Colombian Andes, occurring at elevations between 750 and 3450 meters [11, 12]. <lb/>Despite their monodominance, Andean oak forests harbor significant levels of biodiversity <lb/>and serve as refuge and critical habitat for various species of plants, animals, and fungi [13]. <lb/>These forests, known as &quot;robledales&quot; in Spanish, are part of the Andes biodiversity hotspot [14] <lb/>and provide essential ecological services, including habitat protection, water provision, and cli-<lb/>mate regulation [15]. However, despite all these benefits, they remain poorly known among <lb/>the population and have been subjected to high rates of deforestation due to timber extraction <lb/>and expansion of agricultural activities [16]. Therefore, studying this species and understand-<lb/>ing the factors that determine the assemblage of its communities is crucial. <lb/>An interesting aspect of this species is its wide altitudinal distribution, which implies a <lb/>broad climatic adaptation [8, 9]. The altitudinal gradient inhabited by Q. humboldtii encom-<lb/>passes temperatures ranging from 9.3 to 27.9˚C, with a mean temperature of approximately <lb/>20˚C, and precipitation varying from around 788 mm/year in dry environments to 2681 mm/ <lb/>year in very humid regions. Although several studies have been conducted on this species, few <lb/>have attempted to explain its wide climatic adaptation from a functional perspective [e.g., 17, <lb/>18], which could be key to understanding their ample distribution. Plant functional traits are <lb/>well-defined heritable characteristics that influence fitness [19], encompassing morphological, <lb/>physiological, or phenological features. These traits have been widely used to investigate spe-<lb/>cies-environment relationships and are linked to factors such as temperature and precipitation <lb/>[19-21]. Therefore, we hypothesize that, as a strategy to adapt to a wide range of climatic con-<lb/>ditions, Q. humboldtii may exhibit broad functional differentiation driven by local conditions. <lb/>This hypothesis of functional traits differentiation could be supported by previous studies, <lb/>including the high genetic diversity identified by Zorrilla-Azcue ´et al. [9] in Q. humboldtii pop-<lb/>ulations, as well as the historical controversy surrounding the number of Quercus species in <lb/>Colombia, with up to six different candidate species [8]. <lb/>In a climatic gradient, we can expect distinct patterns in plant functional traits. In regions <lb/>with higher precipitation and favorable temperature conditions, traits such as leaf area (LA), <lb/>specific leaf area (SLA), and specific root length (SRL) are likely to increase [20, 22]. This <lb/>reflects a strategy of maximizing resource acquisition and growth in environments with abun-<lb/>dant water and suitable temperatures [19]. Conversely, in areas with lower precipitation and <lb/>extreme temperature conditions, traits such as leaf thickness (LT), leaf dry matter content <lb/>(LDMC), and wood density (WD) are expected to increase [23, 24]. These traits indicate an <lb/>adaptation towards water conservation and structural integrity in environments where water <lb/>availability is limited, and temperature stress is prevalent [19]. However, it is important to note <lb/>that these trait patterns are generalizations and that other factors such as soil conditions, facili-<lb/>tation or trade-offs between traits may modify plant trait responses [25]. <lb/>Ontogeny is another potential factor underlying the functional differentiation in plants. <lb/>While conspecific individuals are commonly considered ecologically equivalent, evidence <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<front>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

	<body>suggests there is significant variation in specialization among populations, carrying important <lb/>ecological, evolutionary, and conservation implications [26]. Specifically, in the context of <lb/>Andean oak forests, the coexistence of functionally distinct adult and juvenile individuals <lb/>could favor climatic adaptation through temporal niche partitioning, known as the storage <lb/>effect [27, 28]. This mechanism would optimize resource utilization and improve the ability of <lb/>Q. humboldtii to thrive in diverse environmental conditions. However, to our knowledge, this <lb/>hypothesis remains unexplored. <lb/>In addition to examining plant functional trait patterns, it is crucial to assess the influence <lb/>of climate and other factors on community assembly processes. In this regard, the framework <lb/>proposed by Violle et al. [29] offers a unique approach that focuses on individual-level, rather <lb/>than species-level analysis, which is particularly valuable when studying monodominant for-<lb/>ests. By adopting this framework, we can investigate the impact of external filters on the traits <lb/>of Q. humboldtii and the composition of its populations. External filters encompass a range of <lb/>environmental factors and processes that operate at scales larger than the community, includ-<lb/>ing climatic conditions, soil characteristics, disturbances, and biotic interactions. These filters <lb/>exert selective pressures that can either facilitate or constrain specific traits, resulting in non-<lb/>random trait distributions within communities. Within the specific context of Q. humboldtii, <lb/>we hypothesize that populations inhabiting more extreme climatic conditions, such as those <lb/>characterized by cold or drought, will experience an amplified influence of external filters. <lb/>Moreover, we anticipate that the magnitude of this influence will differ significantly between <lb/>the adult and juvenile stages of the species, reflecting variations in their respective adaptive <lb/>strategies and responses to environmental constraints. <lb/>In summary, the objective of this study is to understand how functional traits of the Andean <lb/>oak, Quercus humboldtii, change between populations and two ontogenetic stages (juvenile <lb/>and adult). We expect intraspecific trait variability to be different between populations with <lb/>contrasting environments (Hypothesis 1; H1) and between ontogenetic stages in the same pop-<lb/>ulation (adults different from juveniles; Hypothesis 2; H2). Moreover, we aim to explore the <lb/>role of external filters, such as climate, in determining the population composition of Q. hum-<lb/>boldtii along the climatic gradient. We hypothesize that, consistent with the expected func-<lb/>tional differentiation between populations and ontogenetic stages, the strength of the filters <lb/>will also change, with more pronounced effects on populations living in more extreme climatic <lb/>conditions (Hypothesis 3; H3). <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Study area <lb/>This study was conducted in three different populations of Q. humboldtii along a climatic gra-<lb/>dient in the Cordillera of the Eastern Andes of Colombia (Fig 1). The first population is situ-<lb/>ated in the municipality of Arcabuco, in the Madre Monte natural reserve (5˚46´9&quot; N, 73˚25 <lb/>´28&quot; W). The average temperature of the reserve is 14˚C and annual precipitation is between <lb/>1,000 and 1,900 mm [30]. Sampling at this site was conducted in an area of approximately 1.5 <lb/>ha. The second population is located in the Parque Natural Chicaque (4˚37&apos;3&quot; N, 74˚18&apos;49&quot; W) <lb/>within the municipality of San Antonio del Tequendama, Department of Cundinamarca. The <lb/>average temperature at this site is 14.5˚C and the annual precipitation is 2,500 mm [31]. The <lb/>sampling at this site covered an area of approximately 1 ha. The third population, situated in <lb/>the Department of Santander, is found in the Guanenta ´Alto Rı ´o Fonce Flora and Fauna Sanc-<lb/>tuary (SFF GARF), near the municipality of Encino (6˚01&apos;09&quot; N, 73˚07&apos;08&quot; W). This site has an <lb/>average annual temperature of 18˚C and annual rainfall between 2,500 to 3,000 mm [32]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>Sampling at this site was conducted in an approximate area of 1.5 ha. All sampled Andean oak <lb/>forests were in altitudes between 2,250 and 2,700 m. <lb/>Functional trait sampling and measurement <lb/>During the wet season of November 2021 and March 2022, six functional traits related to plant <lb/>growth and survival were recorded following standardized protocols [35]. A total of 20 adult <lb/>and 20 juvenile individuals were sampled from each population. The six traits analyzed were <lb/>leaf area (LA), specific leaf area (SLA), leaf thickness (LT), leaf dry matter content (LDMC), <lb/>wood density (WD), and specific root length (SRL). A more in depth description of these func-<lb/>tional traits and the associated function is in S1 Table. <lb/>For leaf traits, three healthy leaves per individual (excluding the petiole) were measured. All <lb/>leaf measurements were conducted in the same light environment (shade) to maintain consis-<lb/>tent conditions for both juveniles and adults. Leaf area (LA, cm 2 ) was calculated by scanning <lb/>fresh leaves and using ImageJ digital image processing software [36]. Specific leaf area (SLA, <lb/>cm 2 g -1 ) was then determined by dividing LA by the leaf dry weight. Leaf dry weight was <lb/>obtained by drying the leaves in an oven at 70˚C for 72 h and weighing them immediately after <lb/>removal from the oven. Leaf thickness (LT, mm) was measured at the sampling site using a <lb/>digital Vernier caliper, with three measurements averaged for each leaf (always consistent in <lb/>Fig 1. Study site distribution in three different populations of Q. humboldtii (Arcabuco, Chicaque, and Encino) along the Eastern Andean Cordillera of <lb/>Colombia. The Colombian and South American layers used were downloaded from [33, 34], respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.g001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>the different individuals). Wood density (WD, g cm -3 ) was determined by sampling wood <lb/>from three branches per individual and storing them in silica gel. To calculate WD, the fresh <lb/>volume of the wood was estimated by immersing the samples in water and rehydrating them <lb/>for 24 h. The volume was determined using the water displacement method [37]. The wood <lb/>samples were then dried in an oven at 70˚C for 72 h and weighed immediately after removal <lb/>from the oven [37]. Finally, for specific root length (SRL, cm g -1 ), fine roots from the same <lb/>individuals were sampled, stored in plastic bags, and refrigerated. The roots were cleaned with <lb/>tap water and scanned using an Epson Perfection V19 scanner. Subsequently, the root samples <lb/>were dried at 70˚C for 48 h and weighed immediately after removal from the oven. The Rhizo-<lb/>Vision Explorer software [38] was utilized to estimate SRL. <lb/>Environmental variables <lb/>Data analysis was carried out in R v4.0.3 [39]. To better understand the climatic gradient in the <lb/>study area, we performed a principal component analysis (PCA) using the FactoMineR v2.4 <lb/>[40] and factoextra v1.0.7 packages [41]. We included seven environmental variables: Max Tem-<lb/>perature of Warmest Month (Tmax), Min Temperature of Coldest Month (Tmin), Tempera-<lb/>ture Seasonality (TS), Precipitation of Wettest Month (Pmax), Precipitation of Driest Month <lb/>(Pmin), Precipitation Seasonality (PS), and Elevation (Elev). The bioclimatic and elevation data <lb/>were obtained from WorldClim [42] with a spatial resolution of 30 seconds (~1 km 2 ). <lb/>Functional traits analysis <lb/>We also created separate PCAs for adult and juvenile functional trait data to visualize the dif-<lb/>ferences in each ontogenetic stage and in each population. To assess the differences between <lb/>populations (H1), we performed an analysis of variance (ANOVA) for each trait at each onto-<lb/>genetic stage (adult and juvenile), after checking for normality assumptions and log-trans-<lb/>forming the data when necessary (S2 Table). Additionally, we conducted t-tests to compare <lb/>traits between adults and juveniles within each population (Arcabuco, Chicaque, and Encino; <lb/>H2). In the few cases where data transformation was not sufficient to meet the assumptions of <lb/>t-tests, we employed a nonparametric test (S3 Table). <lb/>As a post-hoc analysis, we conducted a linear model assessment using the R function &quot;lm&quot; <lb/>incorporating two categorical factors, ontogeny and population, and their interaction. In han-<lb/>dling categorical variables, R employed dummy coding, which generates k-1 binary variables <lb/>with values of zero and one to represent essential group membership information for a cate-<lb/>gorical variable with k levels [43]. This allows the categories to serve as distinct predictor vari-<lb/>ables in the model. The coefficients associated with the dummy variables indicate how each <lb/>category affects the response variable compared to the reference group (represented as 0 in all <lb/>dummy variables). In this case, the reference category was set to the juveniles of Arcabuco. <lb/>The assigned factor values can be found in Table 1. <lb/>The Estimated Regression Eq (1) for all models is as follows: <lb/>EðTraitÞ ¼ b 0 þ b 1 X 1 þ b 2 X 2 þ b 3 X 3 þ b 4 X 1 X 2 þ b 5 X 1 X 3 <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>Where β0 represents the mean value of the reference group, X1 represents the value of Juve-<lb/>niles, X2 represents the value of Chicaque, and X3 represents the value of Encino. The coeffi-<lb/>cients β1, β2, and β3 represent the difference between β0 and the mean value of the groups <lb/>coded 1 in each reference group. β4 and β5 represent the additive effects of X1 with X2 and <lb/>X3, respectively. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>External filtering analysis <lb/>In order to understand the influence of external filters on the assemblage of Q. humboldtii <lb/>populations (H3), we followed the T statistics approach of Violle et al. [29], which is based <lb/>on the comparison of variances between different organizational levels. In this approach, <lb/>three statistics are calculated to assess the strength of both internal and external filters on <lb/>community assembly: T_IP.IC reflects the impact of internal filters by comparing popula-<lb/>tions variance to total community variance at the intraspecific level; T_IC.IR indicates the <lb/>influence of external filters by contrasting communities variance with total regional pool <lb/>variance at the intraspecific level; and T_PC.PR demonstrates the influence of external fil-<lb/>ters by comparing communities variance to total regional pool variance at the interspecific <lb/>level. However, given our study&apos;s focus on a single species forming monodominant forests, <lb/>with more than 80% of the abundance, we excluded the calculation of T_IP.IC and T_PC. <lb/>PR. Instead, we adapted T_IC.IR to assess the influence of external filters at the intraspecific <lb/>level on the population assembly, rather than the community assembly (referred to as T_IP. <lb/>IR). T_IP.IR was determined as the ratio between the population&apos;s variance and the total <lb/>regional pool&apos;s variance at the individual level. We defined a population as all sampled indi-<lb/>viduals from a specific location (Arcabuco, Chicaque or Encino), and the regional pool as <lb/>the aggregate of individuals from all three populations. This approach allows us to evaluate <lb/>the influence of external filters on Q. humboldtii individuals for each functional trait at both <lb/>ontogenetic stages (H3). <lb/>To estimate the influence of external filters on Andean oak forest, we further examined <lb/>whether the different Q. humboldtii populations are random subsets. To do so, we compared <lb/>the observed values of T_IP_IR with simulated populations (n = 1000 randomizations) by cal-<lb/>culating the standardized effect size (SES), Eq (2). <lb/>SES ¼ <lb/>I obs À I sim <lb/>s sim <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>where I obs represents the mean value of the observed values, while I sim and σ sim correspond to <lb/>the mean value and standard deviation of the random values, respectively. The standardized <lb/>effect size (SES) quantifies the deviation between observed and simulated populations. When <lb/>compared to random expectations, negative or positive SES values indicate lower or higher <lb/>T_IP.IR values, respectively. The significance of the SES was determined using two one-sided <lb/>tests (lower and upper bound) with a significance level of 5%. This analysis was conducted <lb/>using the R package cati v.099.4 [44]. <lb/>Table 1. Factor&apos;s values assigned in the multiple linear regression models. <lb/>Variables <lb/>Value <lb/>LT <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>LA <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>SLA <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>LDMC <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>WD <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>SRL <lb/>log transformed value <lb/>Juvenile <lb/>0 = no, 1 = yes <lb/>Chicaque <lb/>0 = no, 1 = yes <lb/>Encino <lb/>0 = no, 1 = yes <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.t001 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>Results <lb/>Environmental gradient <lb/>The principal component analysis (PCA) of the seven environmental variables yielded a first <lb/>principal component (PC1) that accounted for 77% of the total variation. PC1 exhibited signif-<lb/>icant correlations with Tmin, Elev, Tmax, Pmin, TS, and Pmax (Fig 2). Arcabuco, positioned <lb/>on the left side of the axis, exhibited higher altitudes, pronounced temperature seasonality, and <lb/>lower temperature and precipitation values. Conversely, Encino was situated on the right side <lb/>of the axis and Chicaque occupied an intermediate position along the gradient. The second <lb/>principal component (PC2) explained approximately 14% of the variation and showed a strong <lb/>correlation with PS (Fig 2). Overall, the ordination analysis illustrated a dominant gradient <lb/>represented by PC1, reflecting distinct variations in elevation, temperature, and precipitation <lb/>among the three sites, with Arcabuco and Encino situated at opposite ends of the gradient. <lb/>Functional trait differentiation across populations and ontogeny <lb/>PCA analyses for the functional traits of Q. humboldtii revealed distinct distributions between <lb/>adults and juveniles (Fig 3). The adult PCA resulted in two principal components (PC1 and <lb/>Fig 2. Principal component analysis (PCA) showing the relationships between seven environmental variables and three localities: Arcabuco (represented <lb/>by blue circles), Chicaque (depicted by yellow triangles), and Encino (shown as orange squares). The environmental variables include Tmax (Max <lb/>Temperature of Warmest Month), Tmin (Min Temperature of Coldest Month), TS (Temperature Seasonality), Pmax (Precipitation of Wettest Month), Pmin <lb/>(Precipitation of Driest Month), PS (Precipitation Seasonality), and Elev (Elevation). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.g002 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>PC2) that explain approximately 33% and 28% of the total variation, respectively. PC1 was <lb/>mainly influenced by LDMC, SRL, and WD, while PC2 exhibited stronger associations with <lb/>LA and SLA (Fig 3). Although there is some overlap among the functional traits across the <lb/>three adult populations, there are differences particularly between Encino and the other popu-<lb/>lations. Encino, positioned on the right side of the axis, displayed higher values for LDMC, <lb/>SRL, and WD, while Arcabuco and Chicaque have relatively lower values for these traits. Nota-<lb/>bly, Arcabuco exhibited a more confined trait distribution and overlapped with Chicaque. <lb/>In contrast, the PCA analysis of juveniles resulted in PC1 explaining 35.5% of the variation <lb/>and PC2 explaining 24.6% of the variation. PC1 demonstrated strong associations with <lb/>LDMC, SLA, and LT, while PC2 showed closer relationships with SRL and WD (Fig 3). Simi-<lb/>larly to the adult analysis, the three populations exhibited some overlap in their trait distribu-<lb/>tions. However, unlike the adult PCA, Chicaque differentiated from the other populations. In <lb/>PC1, Chicaque had lower values of LDMC and higher values of SLA and LT, while Encino and <lb/>Fig 3. Principal Component Analysis (PCA) illustrating the relationship between the six functional traits values and three distinct populations in adults (upper <lb/>panel) and juveniles (lower panel) of Q. humboldtii. Each data point corresponds to an individual sampled from the population, with different colors and <lb/>shapes representing the respective populations. The functional traits include leaf thickness (LT), leaf area (LA), specific leaf area (SLA), leaf dry matter content <lb/>(LDMC), wood density (WD), and specific root length (SRL). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.g003 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>Arcabuco had higher values of LDMC. Despite the substantial overlap between Encino and <lb/>Arcabuco, it is noteworthy that Encino displayed a more restricted distribution pattern. <lb/>Significant differences were observed in most functional traits when analyzing them indi-<lb/>vidually. Among adult populations (H1), all traits showed significant differences except for leaf <lb/>thickness (LT) (p&gt;0.05) (Fig 4; S2 Table). Similarly, when comparing juvenile populations, all <lb/>traits exhibited significant differences (p&lt;0.05) (Fig 4; S2 Table). There were also significant <lb/>differences (p&lt;0.01) between adults and juveniles within populations, in most of the func-<lb/>tional traits (H2). While Chicaque and Encino displayed significant differences in five out of <lb/>the six analyzed traits, Arcabuco showed significant differences in three traits (S3 Table). <lb/>The regression models yielded significant results for all traits (9.21 � F � 12.99, but <lb/>F = 215.80 for LDMC; p&lt;0.001; S4-S9 Tables), explaining between 26% and 32% of the trait <lb/>variation in most cases (0.26 � R2 � 0.33; S4-S9 Tables). The model for LDMC demonstrated <lb/>a high explanatory power, accounting for 89% of the variation (R2 = 0.89; S7 Table). Ontogeny <lb/>showed a significant effect on four out of the six traits (LT, LA, SLA, and WD), while popula-<lb/>tion exerted a significant effect on all traits, except LT (S4-S9 Tables). The interaction effect <lb/>between the two factors was significant only for LT, LDMC, and SRL (S4-S9 Tables). <lb/>Influence of external filters on Quercus humboldtii populations <lb/>The relationship between the SES of T_IP.IR for each functional trait and the simulated null <lb/>expectation is depicted in Fig 5, with corresponding p-values in S10 Table (H3). In the juvenile <lb/>stage, significant differences (p&lt;0.05) were observed in four out of the six traits for Arcabuco <lb/>(LA, SLA, LDMC, and SRL); three for Encino (LT, SLA, LDMC); and two for Chicaque <lb/>Fig 4. Functional traits within and between populations for adults and juveniles. Significant differences are indicated by asterisks: * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** <lb/>denotes p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. The functional traits analyzed include leaf thickness (LT), leaf area (LA), specific leaf area (SLA), leaf dry matter <lb/>content (LDMC), wood density (WD), and specific root length (SRL). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.g004 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>(LDMC, WD). In adults, Chicaque only exhibited significant differences in LDMC, whereas <lb/>Encino showed significant differences in SLA. Arcabuco, on the other hand, had significant <lb/>differences in LA, LDMC, WD and SRL. In all cases where significant differences were found, <lb/>the SES values were negative. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>According to our findings, there is a remarkable level of functional differentiation among pop-<lb/>ulations of Q. humboldtii, consistent with our first hypothesis (H1; Figs 3 and 4; Table). Our <lb/>analyses also revealed significant differences in multiple traits between adult and juvenile indi-<lb/>viduals within each population, in line with our second hypothesis (H2; S3 Table). These find-<lb/>ings provide strong support for our hypothesis that local differences play a crucial role in <lb/>driving functional differentiation and facilitating the broad climatic adaptation of Q. humbold-<lb/>tii. However, it is important to note that local differences alone do not fully account for the <lb/>observed functional variations in this species. While population differences explained varia-<lb/>tions in five out of the six analyzed traits, ontogeny accounted for differences in four traits <lb/>(S4-S9 Tables; S1 Fig). Moreover, consistent with our last hypothesis (H3), we observed a <lb/>greater impact of external filters on individuals from Arcabuco compared to those from Chica-<lb/>que and Encino, with a tendency for these filters to have a stronger effect on juveniles than on <lb/>adults (Fig 5). <lb/>Functional trait variation in Andean oak forests <lb/>Considering our results, Andean oak populations in the Colombian Andes differ in several <lb/>plant functional traits. These traits may provide information to understand the broad climatic <lb/>adaptation of these species. Previous studies on functional traits of Q. humboldtii have also <lb/>Fig 5. Standardized effect size (SES) of the T_IP.IR for the six functional traits studied. Solid circles represent the SES values for each population (Arcabuco <lb/>in blue, Chicaque in yellow, and Encino in red). Crossed circles and associated line segments represent the mean and standard deviation of the SES values. The <lb/>boxes delimit the confidence interval of each null model. If the SES of each population (solid circles) or the mean SES (crossed circles) are significantly different <lb/>from the random distribution, these differences are denoted with asterisks (see S10 Table for p-values). The functional traits represented include leaf thickness <lb/>(LT), leaf area (LA), specific leaf area (SLA), leaf dry matter content (LDMC), wood density (WD), and specific root length (SRL). The T_IP.IR statistic is the <lb/>observed ratio between the population&apos;s variance and the total regional pool variance at the individual level (individuals-populations/regional pool). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645.g005 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>shown that traits, such as SLA and WD, separate between sites as well, especially in an eleva-<lb/>tional gradient [18]. <lb/>Based on the overall trait patterns [19, 20], we expected that individuals from populations <lb/>with more extreme conditions would exhibit traits indicative of a more conservative life strat-<lb/>egy (H1). This was the case for Arcabuco, which is characterized by a more pronounced tem-<lb/>perature and precipitation seasonality (Fig 2), compared to Chicaque and Encino. Our <lb/>findings supported this hypothesis, particularly for juveniles. In the juvenile stage, traits such <lb/>as LA, SLA, and SRL showed significantly lower values in Arcabuco compared to Chicaque or <lb/>Encino, while LDMC values were higher (Figs 3 and 4). These trait combinations suggest a <lb/>resource conservation strategy that could confer advantages in resource-limited or challenging <lb/>environments [19]. <lb/>The observed reductions in LA and SLA, along with the corresponding increase in LDMC, <lb/>enable Arcabuco juveniles to minimize water loss through transpiration and provide protec-<lb/>tion against low temperatures and wind by having smaller-sized leaves with a higher concen-<lb/>tration of dry matter [23, 24]. Furthermore, the lower SRL values observed in Arcabuco <lb/>indicate the presence of longer and thicker roots, facilitating an extensive exploration of the <lb/>soil to extract scarce water resources [22] and supporting ectomycorrhizal symbiosis [45, 46]. <lb/>By contrast, in the populations of Chicaque and Encino, high values of LA and SLA, sometimes <lb/>coupled with low LDMC or high SRL (Fig 4), suggest strategic adaptations aimed at optimizing <lb/>resource acquisition, promoting rapid growth, and facilitating efficient nutrient turnover [19, <lb/>22]. This is beneficial in environments characterized by abundant resources and favorable cli-<lb/>matic conditions. <lb/>In adults, individuals from Arcabuco exhibit significantly lower LDMC and WD values <lb/>compared to the other two populations, indicating a more acquisitive strategy (Fig 4; S2 <lb/>Table). This finding is unexpected, as it is typically associated with plants thriving in resource-<lb/>rich environments [19]. The contrasting trend in the adults could be attributed to nutrient <lb/>availability influenced by mycorrhizal associations [46]. In Arcabuco, mycorrhizal associations <lb/>may enable juveniles and adults to maintain a similar functional strategy, with relatively stable <lb/>LDMC and WD traits between the two stages. In contrast, Chicaque and Encino show a transi-<lb/>tion from efficient resource acquisition in juveniles to a conservative strategy emphasizing <lb/>resource conservation and long-term persistence in adults (S3 Table). The occurrence of onto-<lb/>genetic shifts in ecological strategies has been documented in previous studies [47], and sup-<lb/>port the results obtained in this study (H2). These shifts are usually associated with higher <lb/>growth rates in juveniles, which in turn increase the probability of individuals reaching a func-<lb/>tionally specialized stage that is more resilient to disturbances [48]. Other studies have also <lb/>emphasized the significance of environmental factors and ontogeny in shaping functional <lb/>traits at the intraspecific level [47, 49]. <lb/>Influence of external filtering on population assembly in Andean oak forest <lb/>The analysis of external filters&apos; influence on Andean oak forests revealed a stronger effect in <lb/>Arcabuco compared to the other populations (Fig 5), supporting our hypothesis that popula-<lb/>tions facing higher environmental stress would undergo greater external filtering. Chicaque <lb/>and Encino populations, benefiting from more favorable climatic conditions, exhibited a <lb/>diminished impact of external filters, resulting in a more stochastic distribution of traits <lb/>(Fig 5). This pattern was particularly evident among adult individuals, as both Arcabuco and <lb/>Encino juveniles experienced stronger external filtering compared to Chicaque (Fig 5). Con-<lb/>trary to previous studies [46, 48], we found a stronger influence of environmental filtering on <lb/>juveniles rather than adults, particularly in traits such as LDMC and SLA (Fig 5). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>These findings suggest that external filters are differentially influencing population assem-<lb/>bly processes in Andean oak forests, ultimately resulting in distinct trait distributions among <lb/>populations and ontogenetic stages (Figs 3 and 4). In Chicaque and Encino, where external fil-<lb/>tering is less influential and allows for greater functional differentiation between individuals, <lb/>we propose that the storage effect plays a pivotal role. The ontogeny-dependent functional <lb/>transition within these populations may give rise to temporal niche differentiations, offering <lb/>several advantages [27, 50]. First, it would decrease intraspecific competition by creating favor-<lb/>able conditions for efficient resource access and utilization, resulting in enhanced survival, <lb/>growth, and reproduction. Second, it would contribute to population stability by buffering Q. <lb/>humboldtii against resource fluctuations, ensuring its persistence even during periods of scar-<lb/>city. This stability would foster the long-term success and dominance of Q. humboldtii within <lb/>the community. Lastly, it would promote the coexistence of Q. humboldtii with other species <lb/>by creating niches and opportunities for diverse resource requirements, thereby fostering a <lb/>resilient and diverse ecosystem. <lb/>Conversely, in Arcabuco, where external filtering exerts a stronger influence and constrains <lb/>trait variability, population assembly dynamics may be influenced by facilitation and other <lb/>associated processes, thereby enabling the maintenance of a functional strategy in adults that <lb/>resembles the one observed in juveniles (S3 Table). Research has shown that plants with higher <lb/>LDMC and lower SLA and SRL values (i.e., Arcabuco) tend to exhibit higher rates of coloniza-<lb/>tion by ectomycorrhizal fungi (ECM) [46]. This symbiotic association with mycorrhizal fungi <lb/>provides a significant advantage to plants in resource-limited environments by expanding the <lb/>absorption area of plant roots through external fungal mycelium, enhancing water and nutri-<lb/>ent uptake. In contrast, plants with high SLA and SRL values (i.e., Chicaque and Encino) are <lb/>likely adapted to resource-abundant environments, where they can acquire resources directly <lb/>at a lower cost, without relying heavily on fungal symbiosis [46]. Although the role of facilita-<lb/>tion in the studied communities remains to be evaluated, the importance of Q. humboldtii as <lb/>an ECM reservoir has already been emphasized [51]. <lb/>Evolutionary history can explain intraspecific variation <lb/>The population differences between Q. humboldtii raise questions regarding their connectivity <lb/>and the genetic structure of its populations. Hooghiemstra and Flantua [52] reported that the <lb/>upper limit of the forest reached an altitude of 2,000 m during the last glacial maxima (21 ka <lb/>BP to ca. 14 ka BP). The upper mountain forest was compressed by about 400 m and displaced <lb/>to lower elevations compared to the current altitudes. The lower mountain forest was also dis-<lb/>placed altitudinally to lower altitudes. The demography and genetics of Q. humboldtii in the <lb/>Andean montane forests were affected in various ways by these variations. In particular, paly-<lb/>nological and floristic investigations have suggested migration routes that allowed the coloni-<lb/>zation of different mountain ranges [12]. This would imply, that the Andean oak forests may <lb/>have remained connected over time and that populations of Q. humboldtii would have main-<lb/>tained gene flow [9]. <lb/>A recent study by Zorrilla-Azcue ´et al. [9], demonstrates that this species has a lack of <lb/>genetic structure and considerable genetic diversity. They found eight genetic clusters distrib-<lb/>uted along the three cordilleras (Western, Central, and Eastern). Two of their study sites corre-<lb/>spond to sampled sites in this study (Encino and Arcabuco) and both are in two different <lb/>genetic clusters (Fig 1). These findings show that although the Andean oak may be acclimating <lb/>to their environment, there could also be differences responding to their genetic diversity and <lb/>evolutionary history (and thus, adaptation). Evolutionary history, in addition to environmen-<lb/>tal factors, can be affecting trait values and could explain the functional trait differences <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>between the three populations studied (Figs 3-5). Within the Quercus genus, the influence of <lb/>the environment has been proposed to surpass that of genetic relationships [53]. The question <lb/>remains as to how the functional traits of these populations will change in the future, as frag-<lb/>mentation increases and there are more restrictions to gene flow. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Quercus humboldtii displays significant variation in functional traits among populations in the <lb/>Eastern cordillera of the Colombian Andes. The wide intraspecific trait variation observed in <lb/>this species likely contributes to its adaptability to diverse climates and environments. These <lb/>results underscore the intricate interplay between environmental conditions, ontogenetic <lb/>stage, and trait variation, highlighting the dynamic and context-dependent nature of func-<lb/>tional traits within Andean oak forests. Additionally, the observed functional differences may <lb/>be influenced by the species&apos; evolutionary history and genetic differentiation among popula-<lb/>tions. Thus, it is crucial to consider environmental, evolutionary, and developmental factors <lb/>when investigating intraspecific variation in functional traits. By integrating these factors into <lb/>future research approaches, a more comprehensive understanding of the dynamic interactions <lb/>between organisms and their environment can be achieved, enhancing our knowledge of eco-<lb/>logical patterns and processes. <lb/></body>

	<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Predictor effect plot showing the influence of two predictor variables (population <lb/>and ontogeny) on six functional traits. Asterisks indicate a significant effect of the indepen-<lb/>dent variables included in the multiple linear models: ontogeny (o), population (p), and their <lb/>interaction (i). Significant differences are indicated by asterisks: ** denotes p&lt;0.01 and <lb/>***denotes p&lt;0.001. LT = leaf thickness; LA = leaf area; SLA = specific leaf area; LDMC = leaf <lb/>dry matter content; WD = wood density; SRL = specific root length. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Table. General description of the functional traits included in this study, which details <lb/>the acronyms, units of measurement and the associated function. Trait information is based <lb/>on Pe ´rez-Harguindeguy et al. 2013 and Garnier et al. 2015. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. Summary table of the population values and tests for adults and juveniles. It <lb/>includes mean values and standard deviations, p-values of the tests used to assess normality <lb/>(Shapiro-wilk and Levene&apos;s test), as well as the p-values of the ANOVAs. When we obtained <lb/>p&lt;0.05 in Levene&apos;s tests, we performed Welch&apos;s ANOVA. LT = leaf thickness; LA = leaf area; <lb/>SLA = specific leaf area; LDMC = leaf dry matter content; WD = wood density; SRL = specific <lb/>root length. Significant differences are indicated by asterisks: * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** denotes <lb/>p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Table. Summary table of adult and juvenile values and tests for each population. In <lb/>includes mean values and standard deviations, p-values of the tests used to assess normality <lb/>(Shapiro-wilk and Levene&apos;s test), as well as p-values of the t-test or Mann Whitney U-test. <lb/>When we obtained p&lt;0.05 in the Levene&apos;s tests, we performed a Welch&apos;s t-test. LT = leaf thick-<lb/>ness; LA = leaf area; SLA = specific leaf area; LDMC = leaf dry matter content; WD = wood <lb/>density; SRL = specific root length. Significant differences are indicated by asterisks: * denotes <lb/>p&lt;0.05, ** denotes p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">S4 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on leaf thickness (LT). As <lb/>the two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the reference <lb/>group was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in the depen-<lb/>dent variable (the trait) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to the reference <lb/>category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the coefficient esti-<lb/>mates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while the associated <lb/>p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** denotes p&lt;0.01, and <lb/>*** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent variable when all pre-<lb/>dictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indicates the proportion <lb/>of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its associated p-value test the <lb/>overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S5 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on leaf area (LA). As the <lb/>two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the reference group <lb/>was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in the dependent <lb/>variable (the outcome) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to the reference <lb/>category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the coefficient esti-<lb/>mates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while the associated <lb/>p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** denotes p&lt;0.01, and <lb/>*** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent variable when all pre-<lb/>dictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indicates the proportion <lb/>of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its associated p-value test the <lb/>overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on specific leaf area (SLA). <lb/>As the two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the reference <lb/>group was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in the depen-<lb/>dent variable (the outcome) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to the refer-<lb/>ence category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the <lb/>coefficient estimates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while <lb/>the associated p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** <lb/>denotes p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent <lb/>variable when all predictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indi-<lb/>cates the proportion of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its associ-<lb/>ated p-value test the overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S7 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on leaf dry matter content <lb/>(LDMC). As the two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the <lb/>reference group was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in <lb/>the dependent variable (the outcome) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to <lb/>the reference category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the <lb/>coefficient estimates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while <lb/>the associated p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** <lb/>denotes p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent <lb/>variable when all predictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indi-<lb/>cates the proportion of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">associated p-value test the overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S8 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on wood density (WD). As <lb/>the two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the reference <lb/>group was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in the depen-<lb/>dent variable (the outcome) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to the refer-<lb/>ence category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the <lb/>coefficient estimates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while <lb/>the associated p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** <lb/>denotes p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent <lb/>variable when all predictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indi-<lb/>cates the proportion of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its associ-<lb/>ated p-value test the overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S9 Table. Effect of ontogeny, population, and their interaction on specific root length <lb/>(SRL). As the two independent variables are categorical, they were dummy coded, and the ref-<lb/>erence group was set to the adults of Arcabuco. The coefficients (β) represent the change in the <lb/>dependent variable (the outcome) for each category of the dummy variable, compared to the <lb/>reference category. The standard errors (SE) quantify the variability or uncertainty of the coef-<lb/>ficient estimates. The t-values (t) assess the significance of each coefficient estimate, while the <lb/>associated p-values (P) determine their statistical significance. * denotes p&lt;0.05, ** denotes <lb/>p&lt;0.01, and *** denotes p&lt;0.001. The constant represents the value of the dependent variable <lb/>when all predictor variables are at their reference level. The R-squared (R2) value indicates the <lb/>proportion of variance explained by the predictors, while the F-statistic and its associated p-<lb/>value test the overall significance of the regression model. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S10 Table. P-values of the two one-sided statistical tests performed (lower and upper <lb/>limit) to compare T_IP.IR from each population with random expectations. LT = leaf <lb/>thickness; LA = leaf area; SLA = specific leaf area; LDMC = leaf dry matter content; <lb/>WD = wood density; SRL = specific root length. Bold indicates significant differences <lb/>(p &lt; 0.05). <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors thank the Nature Reserves Madre Monte and Chicaque, as well as the National <lb/>Park Santuario de Fauna y Flora Guanenta ´Alto Rı ´o Fonce, for logistical support and for allow-<lb/>ing fieldwork in the field sites. The authors also thank the Laboratory of Functional and Eco-<lb/>systemic Ecology of the Universidad del Rosario. Valeria Vargas, Mauricio Salamanca, Yessica <lb/>Hoyos, Juan David Sanchez and Antony Ortiz are thanked for their support in the field and <lb/>for their help with the sample processing. Marius Bottin for advice in the data analysis. All <lb/>field trips and collections are under ANLA permits 0530-2014 and 0061-2016, and the <lb/>research permit # 20222000002783 (for the National Park). <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n, Ana M. Aldana, Adriana Sanchez. <lb/>Data curation: Diana Bonilla, Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n, Adriana Corrales, Adriana Sanchez. <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Formal analysis: Diana Bonilla, Julieth V. Ca ´rdenas, Adriana Sanchez. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n, Adriana Sanchez. <lb/>Methodology: Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n, Adriana Sanchez. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Diana Bonilla, Valentina Castañeda-Leo ´n, Ana M. Aldana, Adriana <lb/>Sanchez. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Diana Bonilla, Adriana Corrales, Julieth V. Ca ´rdenas, Adriana <lb/>Sanchez. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Hart TB, Hart JA, Murphy PG. Monodominant and species-rich forests of the humid tropics: Causes for <lb/>their co-occurrence. Am Nat. 1989; 133(5):613-33. https://doi.org/10.1086/284941 <lb/>2. Corrales A, Mangan SA, Turner BL, Dalling JW. An ectomycorrhizal nitrogen economy facilitates mono-<lb/>dominance in a neotropical forest. Ecol Lett. 2016; 19(4):383-92. https://doi.org/10.1111/ele.12570 <lb/>PMID: 26833573 <lb/>3. Albert CH, Thuiller W, Yoccoz NG, Douzet R, Aubert S, Lavorel S. A multi-trait approach reveals the <lb/>structure and the relative importance of intra-vs. interspecific variability in plant traits: Intra-vs. interspe-<lb/>cific variability in plant traits. Funct Ecol. 2010; 24(6):1192-201. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2435. <lb/>2010.01727.x <lb/>4. Crutsinger GM, Sanders NJ, Classen AT. Comparing intra-and inter-specific effects on litter decompo-<lb/>sition in an old-field ecosystem. Basic Appl Ecol. 2009; 10(6):535-43. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.baae. <lb/>2008.10.011 <lb/>5. Des Roches S, Post DM, Turley NE, Bailey JK, Hendry AP, Kinnison MT, et al. The ecological impor-<lb/>tance of intraspecific variation. Nat Ecol Evol. 2017; 2(1):57-64. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-017-<lb/>0402-5 PMID: 29203921 <lb/>6. Kappelle M, editor. Ecology and conservation of neotropical Montane oak forests. New York, NY: <lb/>Springer; 2008. <lb/>7. Nixon KC. Global and neotropical distribution and diversity of oak (genus Quercus) and oak forests. In: <lb/>Ecology and Conservation of Neotropical Montane Oak Forests. Berlin/Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag; <lb/>2006. p. 3-13. <lb/>8. Pulido MT, Cavelier J, Corte ´s-S SP. Structure and composition of Colombian Montane oak forests. In: <lb/>Ecology and Conservation of Neotropical Montane Oak Forests. Berlin/Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag; <lb/>2006. p. 141-51. <lb/>9. Zorrilla-Azcue ´S, Gonza ´lez-Rodrı ´guez A, Oyama K, Gonza ´lez MA, Rodrı ´guez-Correa H. The DNA his-<lb/>tory of a lonely oak: Quercus humboldtii phylogeography in the Colombian Andes. Ecol Evol. 2021; 11 <lb/>(11):6814-28. https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.7529 PMID: 34141258 <lb/>10. Corrales A, Henkel TW, Smith ME. Ectomycorrhizal associations in the tropics-biogeography, diversity <lb/>patterns and ecosystem roles. New Phytol. 2018; 220(4):1076-91. https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.15151 <lb/>PMID: 29689121 <lb/>11. Avella MA, Torres S, Ca ´rdenas Camacho L, Royo A. Restoration of oak forests (Quercus humboldtii) in <lb/>the Colombian Andes: A case study of landscape-scale ecological restoration initiatives in the guacha <lb/>river watershed. In: Santurf JA, editor. Restoration of Boreal and Temperate Forests. CRC Press; <lb/>2015. p. 444-59. <lb/>12. JO Rangel Ch., Avella A. Oak forests of Quercus humboldtii in the Caribbean region and distribution <lb/>patterns related with environmental factors in Colombia. Plant Biosyst. 2011; 145(sup1):186-198. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/11263504.2011.602727 <lb/>13. A ´vila FA, Patricia A ´ngel SP, Lo ´pez C R. Diversidad y estructura de un robledal en la reserva biolo ´gica <lb/>Cachalu ´, Encino (Santander¬Colombia). Colomb For. 2004; 13(1):87. https://doi.org/10.14483/ <lb/>udistrital.jour.colomb.for.2010.1.a04 <lb/>14. Salazar N, Meza MC, Espelta JM, Armenteras D. Post-fire responses of Quercus humboldtii mediated <lb/>by some functional traits in the forests of the tropical Andes. Glob Ecol Conserv. 2020; 22(e01021): <lb/>e01021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2020.e01021 <lb/>15. Bubb P, May I, Miles L, Sayer J. Cloud Forest Agenda. Nairobi, Kenya: UNEP; 2003. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>16. Garavito NT, A ´lvarez E, Caro SA, Murakami AA, Blundo C, Espinoza TEB, et al. Evaluacio ´n del estado <lb/>de conservacio ´n de los bosques montanos en los Andes tropicales. Ecosistemas, 21(1-2).; 2012. <lb/>17. Herna ´ndez AMM, Lozano AHM, Ve ´lez LCA, Gonza ´lez LLS. Evaluacio ´n de rasgos funcionales de Quer-<lb/>cus humboldtii Bonpl. en bosque natural y arbolado urbano. Boletı ´n Semillas Ambientales. 2020; <lb/>14:39-51. <lb/>18. Lo ´pez Camacho R, Quintero A, Bossa R. Intraspecific variation in functional traits of wood and leaf of <lb/>the Colombian Oak, Quercus humboldtii in an altitudinal gradient. Fundacion Universitaria Los Liberta-<lb/>dores; 2020. <lb/>19. Garnier E, Navas M-L, Grigulis K. Plant Functional Diversity: Organism traits, community structure, and <lb/>ecosystem properties. London, England: Oxford University Press; 2015. <lb/>20. Maynard DS, Bialic-Murphy L, Zohner CM, Averill C, van den Hoogen J, Ma H, et al. Global relation-<lb/>ships in tree functional traits. Nat Commun. 2022; 13(1):3185. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-<lb/>30888-2 PMID: 35676261 <lb/>21. Heilmeier H. Functional traits explaining plant responses to past and future climate changes. Flora. <lb/>2019; 254:1-11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.flora.2019.04.004 <lb/>22. Hogan JA, Valverde-Barrantes OJ, Ding Q, Xu H, Baraloto C. Morphological variation of fine root sys-<lb/>tems and leaves in primary and secondary tropical forests of Hainan Island, China. Ann For Sci. 2020; <lb/>77(3). https://doi.org/10.1007/s13595-020-00977-7 <lb/>23. Pescador DS, de Bello F, Valladares F, Escudero A. Plant trait variation along an altitudinal gradient in <lb/>Mediterranean high mountain grasslands: Controlling the species turnover effect. PLoS One. 2015; 10 <lb/>(3):e0118876. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0118876 PMID: 25774532 <lb/>24. Llerena-Zambrano M, Ordoñez JC, Llambı ´LD, van der Sande M, Pinto E, Salazar L, et al. Minimum <lb/>temperature drives community leaf trait variation in secondary montane forests along a 3000-m eleva-<lb/>tion gradient in the tropical Andes. Plant Ecol Divers. 2021; 14(1-2):47-63. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>17550874.2021.1903604 <lb/>25. Reich PB. The world-wide &apos;fast-slow&apos; plant economics spectrum: a traits manifesto. J Ecol. 2014; 102 <lb/>(2):275-301. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12211 <lb/>26. Bolnick DI, Amarasekare P, Arau ´jo MS, Bu ¨rger R, Levine JM, Novak M, et al. Why intraspecific trait vari-<lb/>ation matters in community ecology. Trends Ecol Evol. 2011; 26(4):183-92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>tree.2011.01.009 PMID: 21367482 <lb/>27. Chesson P. Mechanisms of maintenance of species diversity. Annu Rev Ecol Syst. 2000; 31(1):343-<lb/>66. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.31.1.343 <lb/>28. Angert AL, Huxman TE, Chesson P, Venable DL. Functional tradeoffs determine species coexistence <lb/>via the storage effect. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009; 106(28):11641-5. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>0904512106 PMID: 19571002 <lb/>29. Violle C, Enquist BJ, McGill BJ, Jiang L, Albert CH, Hulshof C, et al. The return of the variance: intraspe-<lb/>cific variability in community ecology. Trends Ecol Evol. 2012; 27(4):244-52. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>tree.2011.11.014 PMID: 22244797 <lb/>30. Salazar Largo D. Informe final en la modalidad de pasantı ´a desarrollada Secretaria de Planeacio ´n e <lb/>infraestructura-Alcaldı ´a del municipio de Arcabuco. 2020. <lb/>31. Colparques. Organizacio ´n Colparques. Chicaque. 2017. Available in: http://www.colparques.net/ <lb/>CHICAQUE. <lb/>32. Monroy Castro LY, Lizarazo Forero LM. Identificacio ´n De Hongos Fitopato ´genos Asociados Al Roble <lb/>(Quercus Humboldtii Bonpl.), En Los Municipios De Encino (Santander), Arcabuco, Y Tipacoque (Boy-<lb/>aca ´). Colomb For. 2010; 13(2):347. https://doi.org/10.14483/udistrital.jour.colomb.for.2010.2.a10 <lb/>33. Porto Tapique ´n, C. E. Capa de los Paı ´ses de Sudame ´rica. Geografı ´a, SIG y Cartografı ´a Digital. Valen-<lb/>cia, España, 2020. http://www.efrainmaps.es <lb/>34. DANE (Departamento Administrativo Nacional de Estadı ´stica). Capa de Colombia-Versio <lb/>´n <lb/>MGN2022-Nivel Departamento. Geoportal. Marco Geoestadı ´stico Nacional-MGN. 2022. https://www. <lb/>dane.gov.co/ <lb/>35. Pe ´rez-Harguindeguy N, Dı ´az S, Garnier E, Lavorel S, Poorter H, Jaureguiberry P, et al. New handbook <lb/>for standardised measurement of plant functional traits worldwide. Aust J Bot. 2013; 61(3):167. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1071/bt12225 <lb/>36. Schneider CA, Rasband WS, Eliceiri KW. NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis. Nat Meth-<lb/>ods. 2012; 9(7):671-5. https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2089 PMID: 22930834 <lb/>37. Negret B, Pulido Rodriguez E, Cabrera M, Osorio C, Paz H, Lo ´pez Ordo ´ñez J, et al. La Ecologı ´a Funcio-<lb/>nal Como Aproximacio ´n al Estudio, Manejo y Conservacio ´n de La Biodiversidad: Protocolos y Aplica-<lb/>ciones. Bogota: Instituto de Investigacio ´n Alexander von Humboldt. 2016. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 / 18 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>38. Seethepalli A, Dhakal K, Griffiths M, Guo H, Freschet GT, York LM. RhizoVision Explorer: open-source <lb/>software for root image analysis and measurement standardization. AoB Plants. 2021; 13(6):lab056. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/aobpla/plab056 PMID: 34804466 <lb/>39. R Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical <lb/>Computing, Vienna, Austria. 2022. https://www.R-project.org/. <lb/>40. Lê S, Josse J, Husson F. FactoMineR: AnRPackage for Multivariate Analysis. J Stat Softw. 2008; 25 <lb/>(1). https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v025.i01 <lb/>41. Kassambara A., &amp; Mundt F. Factoextra: Extract and Visualize the Results of Multivariate Data Analy-<lb/>ses. 2020. R Package Version 1.0.7. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=factoextra. <lb/>42. Fick SE, Hijmans RJ. WorldClim 2: new 1-km spatial resolution climate surfaces for global land areas: <lb/>NEW CLIMATE SURFACES FOR GLOBAL LAND AREAS. Int J Climatol. 2017; 37(12):4302-15. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.5086 <lb/>43. Alkharusi H. Categorical variables in regression analysis: A comparison of dummy and effect coding. Int <lb/>J Educ. 2012; 4(2):202. https://doi.org/10.5296/ije.v4i2.1962 <lb/>44. Taudiere A, Violle C. cati: an R package using functional traits to detect and quantify multi-level commu-<lb/>nity assembly processes. Ecography (Cop). 2016; 39(7):699-708. https://doi.org/10.1111/ecog.01433 <lb/>45. Bergmann J, Weigelt A, van der Plas F, Laughlin DC, Kuyper TW, Guerrero-Ramirez N, et al. The fun-<lb/>gal collaboration gradient dominates the root economics space in plants. Sci Adv. 2020; 6(27). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aba3756 PMID: 32937432 <lb/>46. Navarro-Ferna ´ndez CM, Pe ´rez-Ramos IM, de la Riva EG, Vera JR, Roumet C, Villar R, et al. Functional <lb/>responses of Mediterranean plant communities to soil resource heterogeneity: a mycorrhizal trait-based <lb/>approach. J Veg Sci. 2016; 27(6):1243-53. https://doi.org/10.1111/jvs.12446 <lb/>47. Dayrell RLC, Arruda AJ, Pierce S, Negreiros D, Meyer PB, Lambers H, et al. Ontogenetic shifts in plant <lb/>ecological strategies. Funct Ecol. 2018; 32(12):2730-41. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.13221 <lb/>48. Bond BJ. Age-related changes in photosynthesis of woody plants. Trends Plant Sci. 2000; 5(8):349-53. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1360-1385(00)01691-5 PMID: 10908880 <lb/>49. Henn JJ, Damschen EI. Plant age affects intraspecific variation in functional traits. Plant Ecol. 2021; <lb/>222(6):669-80. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11258-021-01136-2 <lb/>50. Emery NC, La Rosa RJ. The effects of temporal variation on fitness, functional traits, and species distri-<lb/>bution patterns. Integr Comp Biol. 2019; 59(3):503-16. https://doi.org/10.1093/icb/icz113 PMID: <lb/>31270548 <lb/>51. Tello JD. How Ectomycorrhizal Communities Vary from Natural to Urban Ecosystems: Quercus Hum-<lb/>boldtii as a Study Case in the Tropical Andes. Bachelor Thesis, Universidad del Rosario, 2021. <lb/>52. Hooghiemstra H. &amp; Flantua S.G.A. 2019. Colombia in the Quaternary: An overview of environmental <lb/>and climatic change. In: Go ´mez J. &amp; Pinilla-Pachon A.O. (editors), The Geology of Colombia, Volume 4 <lb/>Quaternary. Servicio Geolo ´gico Colombiano, Publicaciones Geolo ´gicas Especiales 38, p. 43-95. <lb/>Bogota ´. https://doi.org/10.32685/pub.esp.38.2019.02 <lb/>53. Chai Y, Zhang X, Yue M, Liu X, Li Q, Shang H, et al. Leaf traits suggest different ecological strategies <lb/>for two Quercus species along an altitudinal gradient in the Qin ling Mountains. J Forest Res. 2015; 20 <lb/>(6):501-13. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10310-015-0496-z <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Functional differences between Andean oak populations <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0299645 March 13, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>18 / 18 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>