<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Tracking cryptic SARS-CoV-2 hospital outbreak through quasispecies analysis</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Serena</forename>
          <surname>Messali</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Marta</forename>
          <surname>Giovanetti</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Alessandro</forename>
          <surname>Rondina</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Marta</forename>
          <surname>Bertelli</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Melissa</forename>
          <surname>Duheric</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Francesca</forename>
          <surname>Caccuri</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Massimo</forename>
          <surname>Ciccozzi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Arnaldo</forename>
          <surname>Caruso</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T17:43:25.891Z">11/12/2025 5:43:25 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12985-024-02609-2</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Serena Messali, Marta Giovanetti, Alessandro Rondina, Marta Bertelli, Melissa Duheric, Francesca Caccuri, Massimo Ciccozzi, Arnaldo Caruso. (2024). Tracking cryptic SARS-CoV-2 hospital outbreak through quasispecies analysis. Virology Journal, 21(1), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12985-024-02609-2</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T17:43:18.241359Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T17:43:18.241359Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Review began 04/02/2024 <lb/>Review ended 04/11/2024 <lb/>Published 04/14/2024 <lb/>© Copyright 2024 <lb/>Pedemonte-Parramón et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution, and reproduction in any <lb/>medium, provided the original author and <lb/>source are credited. <lb/>Acute Haematogenous Revision Total Knee <lb/>Arthroplasty Infection by Streptococcus canis <lb/>Treated by Debridement, Antibiotics, and Implant <lb/>Retention: A Case Report <lb/>Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón , Esteban Reynaga , Sònia Molinos , Vicente López-Pérez , <lb/>José A Hernández-Hermoso <lb/>1. Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, Badalona, ESP 2. <lb/>Department of Infectious Diseases, Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, Badalona, ESP 3. Department of <lb/>Microbiology, Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, Badalona, ESP 4. Department of Surgery, Faculty of <lb/>Medicine, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, ESP <lb/>Corresponding author: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, gpedemonte5@gmail.com <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Prosthetic joint infections (PJIs) are one of the most feared complications by orthopaedic surgeons. <lb/>Haematogenous PJI represents an important part of PJI cases. Streptococcus canis is an extremely rare cause <lb/>of haematogenous PJI and its medical and surgical treatment and prognosis are not well established. <lb/>We present a 79-year-old female patient who had a revision total knee arthroplasty (rTKA) surgery three <lb/>years before. She was admitted to the hospital referring to three days of knee pain, restricted range of <lb/>motion, and fever. Blood tests demonstrated leukocyte and C-reactive protein elevation. Joint fluid <lb/>aspiration showed elevated white blood cell count with a high neutrophil differential and its conventional <lb/>culture was positive for Streptococcus canis. She did not have pets but she took care of her daughter&apos;s dog. An <lb/>acute haematogenous infection of the rTKA was diagnosed and treated with debridement, antibiotics (eight <lb/>weeks of IV ceftriaxone), and implant retention (DAIR). After one year, the patient remains clinically <lb/>asymptomatic without changes on X-rays and with normal serum levels of inflammatory blood markers. <lb/>Streptococcus canis has to be kept in mind as a possible cause of haematogenous TKA infection in patients <lb/>who have contact with domestic pets and patients should be asked for this contact. We recommend DAIR as a <lb/>viable treatment option for this type of infection, which may show excellent results. <lb/>Categories: Infectious Disease, Orthopedics, Trauma <lb/>Keywords: ceftriaxone, implant retention, debridement, c-reactive protein, streptococcus canis, haematogenous <lb/>infection, total knee arthroplasty, prosthetic joint infection <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is one of the most performed orthopaedic surgical procedures [1]. <lb/>Nonetheless, it is not free of complications, being one of the most feared prosthetic joint infections (PJIs) <lb/>[2,3], which is associated with high morbidity [1,4] and a non-negligible mortality [1,4]. <lb/>The incidence of primary prosthetic knee infections ranges between 1% and 2% but increases up to 5-6% in <lb/>revision surgeries [5]. Prosthetic infections are typically classified according to the Tsukayama classification <lb/>into four types: immediate post-surgery, chronic, haematogenous, and positive intraoperative cultures [6]. <lb/>The haematogenous PJI type represents up to 20-35% [7]. The most common causative microorganisms of <lb/>haematogenous TKA infections are Staphylococcus aureus and Streptococcus spp [7,8]. <lb/>PJI due to commensal microorganisms in animals, such as Streptococcus canis, are rare. There are only two <lb/>well-described cases of Streptococcus canis PJI in the literature [9]. The first one was a patient with <lb/>a haematogenous TKA infection associated with systemic illness, who was treated with two-stage <lb/>replacement surgery and six weeks of intravenous vancomycin [10]. The second was a patient with a <lb/>postoperative acute hip PJI, who was treated by one-stage revision surgery, followed by six weeks of IV <lb/>cefazolin [4]. Both cases were ultimately linked to close regular contact with their pet dog. No <lb/>Streptococcus canis PJI of haematogenous origin treated by debridement, antibiotics, and implant retention <lb/>(DAIR) has been reported in the literature. <lb/>Depending on the time of onset and the status of implant fixation, the recommended surgical treatments in <lb/>PJI of haematogenous spread are DAIR and one-or two-stage revision surgery [3,11,12]. DAIR has a non-<lb/>negligible risk of failure, depending on the causative microorganism [11,12]. Staphylococcus aureus is a <lb/>microorganism with a higher risk of failure [11-13]. Nevertheless, Streptococcus spp are also associated with <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1, 4 <lb/></body>

    <front>Open Access Case <lb/>Report <lb/>DOI: 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/>How to cite this article <lb/>Pedemonte-Parramón G, Reynaga E, Molinos S, et al. (April 14, 2024) Acute Haematogenous Revision Total Knee Arthroplasty Infection by <lb/>Streptococcus canis Treated by Debridement, Antibiotics, and Implant Retention: A Case Report. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI <lb/>10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></front>

    <body>worse results with DAIR, with up to 50% of failures [11,12]. However, the presence of Streptococcus canis in <lb/>these series is practically null, so it is unknown if it will follow the same behaviour. <lb/>Our objective is to describe the clinical presentation, the approach, and the treatment and result of an <lb/>unusual clinical case of a Streptococcus canis haematogenous infection of a revision TKA treated with DAIR. <lb/>Case Presentation <lb/>A 79-year-old Spanish female, with a medical history of hypertension, atrial fibrillation, chronic bronchitis, <lb/>obstructive sleep apnoea, and obesity class III [14], on chronic treatment with enalapril 5 mg/24 hours, <lb/>amiodarone 200 mg/24 hours, apixaban 5 mg/12 hours, and ipratropium bromide 20 mcg two inhales/24 <lb/>hours, went to the traumatology emergency department. She had a left total knee replacement with a <lb/>Multigen Plus® CR (LimaCorporate®, Udine, Italy) for knee osteoarthritis in 2009 (Figure 1). She received a <lb/>one-stage revision surgery with an antibiotic (2 g gentamicin) cemented NexGen® Legacy® Constrained <lb/>Condylar Knee (Zimmer Biomet®, Zug, Switzerland) with femoral and tibia stems in 2020 for aseptic <lb/>loosening of the TKA (Figures 2, 3). Intraoperative cultures and histology were negative for infection at that <lb/>time. The patient gave written consent for personal data concerning the case to be submitted for <lb/>publication. <lb/>FIGURE 1: Anteroposterior (A) and lateral (B) radiographs of the primary <lb/>total knee arthroplasty. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>FIGURE 2: Anteroposterior (A) and lateral (B) radiographs of the <lb/>revision total knee arthroplasty previous to the haematogenous <lb/>infection. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>FIGURE 3: Full weight-bearing lower leg radiograph of the revision total <lb/>knee arthroplasty previous to the haematogenous infection. <lb/>She reported continuous left knee pain, not well localized, chills, and limited knee range of motion (ROM) <lb/>that began three days ago, and since then being unable to walk. She denied previous knee pain or <lb/>inflammatory signs, and no fever or other associated symptoms were described. She denied recent urine, <lb/>respiratory, or skin infections or wounds. On physical exam, she was haemodynamically stable with a fever <lb/>up to 38°C. Warmth, redness, and swelling of the left knee were appreciated and a limited ROM of 0-30° was <lb/>noted. No radiolucent lines surrounding the prosthesis were evident and a well-alignment implant without <lb/>changes in the position over time was appreciated on X-ray. Blood cell count revealed an elevated leukocyte <lb/>count of 14,800 x109L and C-reactive protein (CRP) of 319.8 mg/L. <lb/>Blood and joint fluid aspiration cultures of the knee under aseptic conditions were ordered due to high <lb/>suspicion of PJI. Joint fluid showed cell counts of 81,250 cells/mm3 with a 94% neutrophil differential, a <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>glucose level of 10 mg/dL, a protein level of 47 g/L, and a lactate dehydrogenase of 7140 U/L. The diagnosis <lb/>of PJI was done in light of the clinical evaluation and laboratory investigations, which met the International <lb/>Consensus on Orthopedic Infections criteria for the diagnosis [15]. At 24 hours, the conventional joint fluid <lb/>cultures sent in an aerobic and anaerobic blood culture bottle (BD BACTEC™, Becton, Dickinson and <lb/>Company, Franklin Lakes, NJ) isolated a Streptococcus canis microorganism. Blood cultures were negative. <lb/>Due to the microorganism being isolated, the patient was asked for domestic animals. She did not have pets <lb/>but she took care of her daughter&apos;s dog often, and the dog repeatedly bit or licked her extremities. However, <lb/>no skin bites or scratches were evident during the physical exam at hospital admission. <lb/>Surgical treatment <lb/>Immediately after the diagnosis, we calculated the risk of DAIR failure, which in this particular patient was <lb/>low-moderate, getting 2 points in the CRIME80 score [12]. The DAIR procedure was done under general <lb/>anaesthesia and ischaemia. The tourniquet was inflated after two to three minutes of elevation of the lower <lb/>leg. An iterative anterior knee approach was performed following the previous scar. Joint fluid aspiration <lb/>was done prior to the medial arthrotomy and was sent for culture, cell count, and biochemistry test. <lb/>Polyethylene exchange, complete synovectomy, extensive debridement, including the posterior <lb/>compartment and irrigation with one litre of dilute povidone iodate 3.5% and nine litres of sterile normal <lb/>saline solution, were carried out. The superficial drape layer of the surgical field was exchanged and a new <lb/>polyethylene NexGen® Legacy® Constrained Condylar Knee (Zimmer Biomet®, Zug, Switzerland) of the <lb/>same size was implanted (14 mm), achieving correct stability. Seven intraoperative cultures samples were <lb/>taken from the more affected parts: the synovia in the suprapatellar pouch, the medial and lateral gutters, <lb/>the intercondylar notch, the Hoffa fat pad, the posterior capsule, and the last one was the sonication of the <lb/>polyethylene. The incision was closed in a layered fashion using #2 Vicryl® (90% glycolide and 10% L-<lb/>lactide) sutures for deep layers, # 2/0 for the subcutaneous layer, and staples for the skin. One intra-articular <lb/>drain was used. <lb/>Antibiotic treatment <lb/>After the culture samples were obtained, empiric antibiotic treatment with IV ceftazidime 2 g/eight hours <lb/>and vancomycin 1 g/12 hours was started using a peripherally insertable central catheter inserted previously. <lb/>The intraoperative cultures confirmed the suspected diagnosis 72 hours after the surgery, isolating <lb/>Streptococcus canis in seven of the eight cultures. The antibiotic treatment was changed to ceftriaxone IV 2 <lb/>g/24 hours. Due to the good clinical evolution, 14 days after the surgery, the IV antibiotic was discontinued <lb/>and switched to oral levofloxacin 750 mg/24 hours and rifampicin 600 mg/24 hours. After the change to oral <lb/>antibiotics, the patient presented diarrhoea. Clostridium difficile toxins and stool culture were negative, so <lb/>antibiotic intolerance was diagnosed and oral antibiotics were discontinued and switched again to IV <lb/>ceftriaxone 2 g/24 hours for six weeks. <lb/>Complications <lb/>Seven days after the hospital admission, the patient presented an episode of acute dyspnoea and blood <lb/>oxygen desaturation up to 90%. The chest X-ray showed a bilateral pleural effusion and interstitial oedema. <lb/>Acute heart failure was the diagnosis, which resolved after oxygen therapy and depletive treatment with <lb/>furosemide. Sixteen days after the hospital admission, due to diarrhoea secondary to antibiotic intolerance, <lb/>a second heart failure decompensation was diagnosed, which was resolved with the same medical treatment. <lb/>After 18 days of the hospital admission, the patient was discharged at home with a home hospitalization <lb/>service to control the intravenous antibiotic treatment and the medical condition. <lb/>Follow-up <lb/>One year after the DAIR procedure, the patient remains clinically asymptomatic. She is able to walk an <lb/>unlimited distance without technical assistance. She can walk up and down stairs with the handrail. Her <lb/>knee does not present any clinical sign of inflammation and has a ROM of 0-100º, without varus-valgus or <lb/>anteroposterior instability. No radiolucency lines or signs of implant mobilization are appreciated on the <lb/>anteroposterior and lateral knee X-rays (Figure 4). The blood test showed normal values of leukocyte cell <lb/>count (6,500x109L) and serologic inflammatory biomarkers (CRP of 4.40 mg/L and erythrocyte <lb/>sedimentation rate (ESR) of 20 mm/h) at one year postoperatively. <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>FIGURE 4: Anteroposterior (A) and lateral (B) radiographs of the <lb/>revision TKA after the DAIR procedure at one year of follow-up. <lb/>TKA: total knee arthroplasty; DAIR: debridement, antibiotics, and implant retention. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We present a case of an acute haematogenous TKA infection due to an uncommon causative microorganism <lb/>in humans, namely, Streptococcus canis. This microorganism can cause infections in humans who usually <lb/>have had contact with domestic pets [4,9,10]. This is the first reported clinical case of an acute <lb/>haematogenous revision TKA infection treated with the DAIR procedure achieving an excellent result. <lb/>PJIs are one of the most feared and serious complications for orthopaedic surgeons [2,3] due to the <lb/>associated morbidities [1,4] as well as the non-negligible risk of mortality [1,4], their incidence being up to <lb/>5-6% in revision TKA [5]. Tsukayama et al. [6] classified PJI into four types: immediate post-surgery, chronic, <lb/>haematogenous, and positive intraoperative cultures. The incidence of PJI of haematogenous origin <lb/>accounts for 20-35% of the PJIs [7]. The most frequent places of origin of the microorganisms that spread <lb/>through the vascular stream are the cardiovascular system, the skin and soft tissue, the oral cavity, and the <lb/>gastrointestinal or urogenital tracts [7,8]. Staphylococcus aureus and Streptococcus spp are the most common <lb/>isolated microorganisms [7,8]. Acute haematogenous PJI due to animal commensal microorganisms, such as <lb/>Streptococcus canis, is very rare [9,16], being &lt;1% of streptococcal PJI [4]. There are only two cases reported <lb/>in the literature [9]. <lb/>Streptococcus canis is a G beta-hemolytic species of Streptococcus first isolated in dogs. It is a commensal <lb/>microorganism of the skin and mucous membranes of the respiratory tract, the rectum, and the genital tract <lb/>of cats and dogs [9]. It can cause opportunistic infections in animals like skin infections and other severe <lb/>clinical diseases such as meningitis or myocarditis [9,16,17]. It can rarely cause infections in other mammals <lb/>and very rarely in humans [9,16]. The pathophysiology of the infection in humans is still unknown [9]. <lb/>Despite that, it is believed to be through the faecal contamination of the environment or by direct <lb/>inoculation from a pet to humans through the contamination of wounds or bites or skin scratches [9,16,17]. <lb/>This direct transmission makes Streptococcus canis to be considered as a zoonotic pathogen [9,16]. <lb/>Other reported cases of Streptococcus canis infections, as in our case, did not have a clear portal of entry for <lb/>the microorganism [4,9,10,18,19]. The possibility of Streptococcus canis colonization in pet owners is unclear <lb/>[4,9], and it has not been demonstrated as a risk factor for PJI [4]. It has to be asked for and this possibility <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <body>needs to be taken into account in pet owners because, as in our case, contact with pet dogs was present in all <lb/>reported cases [4,10]. Other risk factors have been described such as aging or immunosuppression [9,19]. <lb/>Streptococcus canis infections in humans may be associated with soft tissue ones such as cellulitis or <lb/>abscesses, and in atypical cases, they can cause bacteremia and septic emboli, pneumonia, or endocarditis <lb/>[9]. <lb/>Clinically, Streptococcus canis PJI infection can present as an acute infection post surgery [4] or it can be <lb/>haematogenous [10], with a fever over 38°C and with the patient feeling unwell and associated with a <lb/>systemic illness that can cause severe septicemia with hypotension [10]. Local signs of inflammation, such as <lb/>warmth, erythema, swelling, and pain are usually present [4,10]. Serological blood markers of infection <lb/>(leukocytes, CRP, and ESR) are normally elevated and the analyses of the joint fluid aspiration usually reveal <lb/>an elevation of nucleated cell count with a high percentage of neutrophils. So, the clinical presentation is in <lb/>agreement with the one described for acute PJI [15]. <lb/>Streptococcus canis can be identified in conventional cultures of the preoperative synovial joint fluid <lb/>aspiration, as in our patient, or the intraoperative tissue samples [4]. Nevertheless, it can be difficult to <lb/>identify with conventional cultures [10] or it can be confused with Streptococcus dysgalactiae [9,16,20], which <lb/>makes the real incidence of Streptococcus canis in humans unknown. For this reason, it is recommended to <lb/>use new diagnostic techniques such as polymerase chain reaction or next-generation sequencing [10], which <lb/>are promising methods to facilitate its identification [9,10,16]. <lb/>Acute haematogenous PJI can be treated by different surgical techniques depending on the time of <lb/>evolution, the type of microorganism, and the presence of a well-fixed or loose implant. In acute PJI, DAIR is <lb/>a well-accepted treatment and probably the most desired by surgeons since it tries to maintain a functional <lb/>and stable implant [3,11,12]. Although DAIR has shown good results in streptococcal prosthetic joint <lb/>infections [11,12], it has never been reported in Streptococcus canis acute PJI, since the previous infections <lb/>described were treated with one-[4] or two-stage [10] revision surgery. However, when a difficult-to-treat <lb/>microorganism is isolated, when a fistula is observed, or when there is an implant failure, the recommended <lb/>treatment is revision surgery, which can be done as a one-or two-stage procedure [3,11]. <lb/>DAIR failure risk is not negligible in acute infections and increases in haematogenous ones by up to 50% <lb/>[3,11,12]. To calculate preoperatively the chances of DAIR failure, different scores have been developed and <lb/>are under discussion [11], such as the KLIC (kidney, liver, index surgery, cemented prosthesis, and C-reactive <lb/>protein value) score for acute PJI [13] and the CRIME80 score for haematogenous PJI [12]. Although no other <lb/>Streptococcus canis acute PJI cases reported in the literature were treated with DAIR, we decided to perform <lb/>it because the implant was well fixed and the risk of failure in our patient was low, following the CRIME80 <lb/>score [12]. It is advisable to know the causative microorganism and their susceptibility to antibiotic <lb/>treatment to ensure the success of DAIR and any other surgical treatment [11], but this is not always possible <lb/>before the surgery due to the emergency of the treatment. Staphylococcus aureus is the one with a higher risk <lb/>of failure [11-13]. However, Streptococcus spp also can have a high risk of DAIR failure, i.e., up to 50% <lb/>depending on the cases [11,12]. The presence of Streptococcus canis in these series is practically null, so it <lb/>cannot be assured that it will follow the same behaviour. <lb/>Streptococcus canis is sensitive to common antibiotics such as penicillin or cephalosporins, clavulanic acid, <lb/>or vancomycin with which it can be treated [4,9,20]. It is still unclear which is the best route and duration of <lb/>antibiotic treatment, but recent guidelines [11] suggest good results in PJI with a six-to eight-week course <lb/>of antibiotics, being intravenously the first two weeks followed by four to six weeks of oral antibiotic. <lb/>Further, in DAIR, the use of antibiotics against biofilms, such as rifampicin in staphylococcal PJI or <lb/>fluoroquinolones in gram-negative PJI, is important [11]. Occasional resistance to gentamicin and <lb/>rifampicin has also been reported in Streptococcus canis [9]. Due to its rarity, very little is known about the <lb/>best antibiotic treatment for Streptococcus canis PJI. Good results have been reported using IV vancomycin <lb/>[10] and cefazolin [4] associated with one-[4] or two-stage [10] revision surgery in Streptococcus canis PJI. <lb/>For the first time, we report an excellent result of a revision TKA acute haematogenous infection treated <lb/>with DAIR and IV ceftriaxone for eight weeks. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Streptococcus canis has to be kept in mind as a possible cause of haematogenous TKA infection in patients <lb/>who have contact with domestic pets and patients should be asked for this contact. The DAIR procedure can <lb/>achieve excellent clinical results without infection relapse in the treatment of Streptococcus canis acute <lb/>haematogenous TKA infection. As with any PJI, the treatment must be individualized taking into account <lb/>patient risk factors and comorbidities, skin, and implant fixation status. <lb/></body>

    <div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>All authors have reviewed the final version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the <lb/>work. <lb/></div>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Concept and design: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, Esteban Reynaga, Sònia Molinos, Vicente López-Pérez, <lb/>José A Hernández-Hermoso <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, Esteban Reynaga, Sònia <lb/>Molinos, Vicente López-Pérez <lb/>Drafting of the manuscript: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, Esteban Reynaga, José A Hernández-Hermoso <lb/>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, <lb/>Esteban Reynaga, Sònia Molinos, Vicente López-Pérez, José A Hernández-Hermoso <lb/>Supervision: Gloria Pedemonte-Parramón, Esteban Reynaga, José A Hernández-Hermoso <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Disclosures <lb/>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. </div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflicts of interest: In <lb/>compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services <lb/>info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the <lb/>submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial <lb/>relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an <lb/>interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other <lb/>relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Boddapati V, Fu MC, Mayman DJ, Su EP, Sculco PK, McLawhorn AS: Revision total knee arthroplasty for <lb/>periprosthetic joint infection is associated with increased postoperative morbidity and mortality relative to <lb/>noninfectious revisions. J Arthroplasty. 2018, 33:521-6. 10.1016/j.arth.2017.09.021 <lb/>2. Musculoskeletal Infection Society: New definition for periprosthetic joint infection . J Arthroplasty. 2011, <lb/>26:1136-8. 10.1016/j.arth.2011.09.026 <lb/>3. Gehrke T, Alijanipour P, Parvizi J: The management of an infected total knee arthroplasty . Bone Joint J. <lb/>2015, 97-B:20-9. 10.1302/0301-620X.97B10.36475 <lb/>4. McGuire A, Krysa N, Mann S: Hair of the dog? Periprosthetic joint infection with Streptococcus canis . <lb/>Arthroplast Today. 2021, 8:53-6. 10.1016/j.artd.2021.01.010 <lb/>5. Naufal E, Wouthuyzen-Bakker M, Babazadeh S, Stevens J, Choong PF, Dowsey MM: Methodological <lb/>challenges in predicting periprosthetic joint infection treatment outcomes: a narrative review. Front <lb/>Rehabil Sci. 2022, 3:824281. 10.3389/fresc.2022.824281 <lb/>6. Tsukayama DT, Goldberg VM, Kyle R: Diagnosis and management of infection after total knee arthroplasty . <lb/>J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2003, 85:S75-80. 10.2106/00004623-200300001-00014 <lb/>7. Rakow A, Perka C, Trampuz A, Renz N: Origin and characteristics of haematogenous periprosthetic joint <lb/>infection. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2019, 25:845-50. 10.1016/j.cmi.2018.10.010 <lb/>8. Zeller V, Kerroumi Y, Meyssonnier V, Heym B, Metten MA, Desplaces N, Marmor S: Analysis of <lb/>postoperative and hematogenous prosthetic joint-infection microbiological patterns in a large cohort. J <lb/>Infect. 2018, 76:328-34. 10.1016/j.jinf.2017.12.016 <lb/>9. Pagnossin D, Smith A, Oravcová K, Weir W: Streptococcus canis, the underdog of the genus . Vet Microbiol. <lb/>2022, 273:109524. 10.1016/j.vetmic.2022.109524 <lb/>10. Tarabichi M, Alvand A, Shohat N, Goswami K, Parvizi J: Diagnosis of Streptococcus canis periprosthetic joint <lb/>infection: the utility of next-generation sequencing. Arthroplast Today. 2018, 4:20-3. <lb/>10.1016/j.artd.2017.08.005 <lb/>11. Argenson JN, Arndt M, Babis G, et al.: Hip and knee section, treatment, debridement and retention of <lb/>implant: Proceedings of International Consensus on Orthopedic Infections. J Arthroplasty. 2019, 34:S399-<lb/>419. 10.1016/j.arth.2018.09.025 <lb/>12. Wouthuyzen-Bakker M, Sebillotte M, Lomas J, et al.: Clinical outcome and risk factors for failure in late <lb/>acute prosthetic joint infections treated with debridement and implant retention. J Infect. 2019, 78:40-7. <lb/>10.1016/j.jinf.2018.07.014 <lb/>13. Tornero E, Morata L, Martínez-Pastor JC, et al.: KLIC-score for predicting early failure in prosthetic joint <lb/>infections treated with debridement, implant retention and antibiotics. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2015, <lb/>21:786.e9-17. 10.1016/j.cmi.2015.04.012 <lb/>14. Weir CB, Jan A: BMI Classification Percentile and Cut Off Points . StatPearls Publishing, Treasure Island, FL; <lb/>2024. <lb/>15. Shohat N, Bauer T, Buttaro M, et al.: Hip and knee section, what is the definition of a periprosthetic joint <lb/>infection (PJI) of the knee and the hip? Can the same criteria be used for both joints?: Proceedings of <lb/>International Consensus on Orthopedic Infections. J Arthroplasty. 2019, 34:S325-7. <lb/>10.1016/j.arth.2018.09.045 <lb/>16. Richards VP, Zadoks RN, Pavinski Bitar PD, et al.: Genome characterization and population genetic <lb/>structure of the zoonotic pathogen, Streptococcus canis. BMC Microbiol. 2012, 12:293. 10.1186/1471-2180-<lb/>12-293 <lb/>17. Lam MM, Clarridge JE 3rd, Young EJ, Mizuki S: The other group G Streptococcus: increased detection of <lb/>Streptococcus canis ulcer infections in dog owners. J Clin Microbiol. 2007, 45:2327-9. 10.1128/JCM.01765-<lb/>06 <lb/>18. Ohtaki H, Ohkusu K, Ohta H, et al.: A case of sepsis caused by Streptococcus canis in a dog owner: a first <lb/>case report of sepsis without dog bite in Japan. J Infect Chemother. 2013, 19:1206-9. 10.1007/s10156-013-<lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 of 9 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>0625-6 <lb/>19. Lederman Z, Leskes H, Brosh-Nissimov T: One health and Streptococcus canis in the emergency <lb/>department: a case of cellulitis and bacteremia in an immunocompromised patient treated with etanercept. <lb/>J Emerg Med. 2020, 58:e129-32. 10.1016/j.jemermed.2019.10.019 <lb/>20. Cheong BM, Lim AY: Sharing a microbe with man&apos;s best friend: a case of canine streptococcal infection in a <lb/>diabetic patient. Med J Malaysia. 2015, 70:318-9. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="footnote">2024 Pedemonte-Parramón et al. Cureus 16(4): e58247. DOI 10.7759/cureus.58247 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 of 9 </page>

  </text>

</TEI>