<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T14:56:34.425Z">11/13/2025 2:56:34 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T14:56:18.308338Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T14:56:18.308338Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/>from infancy to pre-school age, their early <lb/>predictors, and school-age outcomes <lb/>Ane Naerde ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Harald Janson ID <lb/>1 <lb/>, Mike Stoolmiller 1,2 <lb/>1 The Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral Development, Oslo, Norway, 2 Oregon Research Institute, <lb/>Eugene, Oregon, United States of America <lb/>* ane.narde@nubu.no <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This study identified latent trajectories of physical aggression (TPA) from infancy to pre-<lb/>school age and evaluated (a) effects of early parent, parenting and child predictors on TPA <lb/>as well as on social, behavioral, and academic functioning in Grade 2, and (b) TPA effects <lb/>net of early predictor effects on Grade 2 functioning. We used data from the Behavior Out-<lb/>look Norwegian Developmental Study (BONDS), which included 1,159 children (559 girls). <lb/>Parents reported on risk and protective factors, and on physical aggression from 1 to 5 <lb/>years of age; teachers reported on Grade 2 outcomes. We employed latent class growth <lb/>curve analyses and identified nine TPA. In fully adjusted models simultaneously testing all <lb/>associations among predictors, trajectories, and outcomes, maternal and paternal harsh <lb/>parenting, child gender, and sibling presence predicted TPA, which significantly predicted <lb/>externalizing and academic competence in Grade 2. Child gender had a pervasive influence <lb/>on all outcomes as well as on TPA. To our knowledge, this is the first trajectory study to <lb/>determine which predictors are most proximal, more distal, or just confounded, with their rel-<lb/>ative direct effect sizes, and to link early paternal as well as maternal harsh parenting prac-<lb/>tices with children&apos;s TPA. Our findings underscore the need to include fathers in <lb/>developmental research and early prevention and intervention efforts. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>In this study, we examined the developmental trajectories of physical aggression (TPA) during <lb/>early childhood and explored how these patterns influence social, behavioral, and academic <lb/>functioning in school aged children while simultaneously considering early individual and <lb/>contextual risk and protective factors. While physical aggression is widely considered the most <lb/>serious and socially unacceptable form of aggression, it is ontogenetically antecedent to less <lb/>&quot;serious&quot; forms such as verbal or indirect aggression [1]. It has become increasingly evident <lb/>that children&apos;s use of physical aggression is normative during certain developmental periods. <lb/>Behaviors such as kicking, hitting, and pushing originate in early childhood and have develop-<lb/>mentally salient and adaptive functions. <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/>1 / 24 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Naerde A, Janson H, Stoolmiller M (2024) <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression from <lb/>infancy to pre-school age, their early predictors, <lb/>and school-age outcomes. PLoS ONE 19(6): <lb/>e0291704. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0291704 <lb/>Editor: Umberto Simeoni, University of Lausanne: <lb/>Universite de Lausanne, SWITZERLAND <lb/>Received: September 4, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: May 16, 2024 <lb/>Published: June 3, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Naerde et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Our data is part of an <lb/>ongoing longitudinal study and contains potentially <lb/>sensitive information. The consent of the <lb/>participants of the Behavior Outlook Norwegian <lb/>Developmental Study (BONDS), as approved by <lb/>the Regional Committee for Medical and Health <lb/>Research Ethics in South-East Norway, does not <lb/>include sharing a de-identified data set on an open <lb/>server. However, upon request the dataset may be <lb/>made accessible in our secure data server to <lb/>researchers who meet the criteria for access to <lb/>confidential data, under a data processing <lb/></front>

			<body>Following previous research [2, 3], we use the term physical aggression to denote physical <lb/>acts directed against others in the form of observable behaviors such as kicking and hitting, <lb/>without consideration of intentionality. The systematic study of how physical aggression devel-<lb/>ops from early childhood onward is still recent [4], as most research has focused on aggression <lb/>beginning in toddlerhood or at preschool age [but see e.g., 5, 6]. There is compelling evidence <lb/>that (a) children start to physically aggress at an early age [7-9]; (b) such behavior typically <lb/>peaks at approximately 2-3 years of age followed by a steep decline [5, 10-12]; and (c) a small <lb/>proportion of children maintain a high and stable frequency of physical aggression during <lb/>middle childhood that is associated with a range of negative outcomes [13-19]. <lb/>Developmental TPA across early childhood <lb/>We review research applying a developmental trajectory approach, that is, the identification of <lb/>prototypic subgroup curves representing different developmental patterns of physical aggres-<lb/>sion (i.e., TPA) [e.g., 18]. We summarize key results from large-scale longitudinal studies <lb/>exploring TPA starting in toddlerhood. In a seminal paper, Tremblay [1] reviewed the state of <lb/>knowledge regarding the origins of aggressive behavior and highlighted the need to focus on <lb/>the first few years of development. He argued that infants&apos; physical aggression typically has not <lb/>been deemed developmentally significant and stated that &quot;the exciting work that needs to be <lb/>done is to study the developmental trajectories of these aggressive behaviors at the intra-indi-<lb/>vidual level during infancy and toddlerhood and their relationships with later development&quot; <lb/>[1, p. 134]. Currently, the results from several longitudinal studies mapping the early develop-<lb/>ment of physical aggression speak of the heterogeneity in this development [4, 15-16, 19, <lb/>20-22]. <lb/>Research addressing TPA has found varying numbers of trajectories. This is likely related to <lb/>sample variation, including variations in age range, sample size, risk factor composition, the <lb/>number of repeated assessments, model specification, and selection criteria [10, 23]. Studies <lb/>have typically identified three [10, 12, 19, 21], four [20, 24-28], or five trajectories [16, 22], and <lb/>some report differing numbers of trajectories for girls and boys (i.e., 3 for girls and 5 for boys <lb/>[4]). Consistent findings include at least one TPA showing stably low levels of aggression, and <lb/>one TPA distinguished by a stably high level. Less consistent findings include a declining <lb/>aggression trajectory [22, 25, 28]. No late-onset high physical aggression groups are usually <lb/>identified. Despite strong calls [1, 23] to start early (by 6 to 8 months of age [7-8]), use multiple <lb/>data sources, and include frequent observations (every 3 months [1]), existing evidence is typi-<lb/>cally based on a later start, maternal reports, and longer assessment intervals [4-5, 10, 19-20, <lb/>22, 28, but see e.g., 6, 8, 29]. <lb/>Predictors of TPA <lb/>Our focus is on environmental predictors of TPA and Labella and Mason [30] recently dis-<lb/>cussed the most salient family-based risk and protective factors for the development of aggres-<lb/>sion and violence, grouping them into parent/family factors, parenting factors, and child <lb/>factors. In addition, it is important to acknowledge that twin and related research [31, 32] sug-<lb/>gest substantial genetic or epigenetic factors [33, 34] related to TPA. <lb/>Parent/family factors. Socioeconomic status (SES) and parental psychopathology. Low SES <lb/>and parental psychopathology are persistent predictors of child maladjustment, including <lb/>physical aggression [30, 35-37]. In line with this, low household income [4, 10, 12, 20, 22], low <lb/>parental education levels [4, 10, 20, 22], single parenthood [22], early maternal childbearing <lb/>[3], and parental psychopathology [4, 12] are among the strongest predictors of belonging to <lb/>the high-stable aggression group across trajectory studies. The family stress model [38] asserts <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<front>agreement. Requests should be addressed to the <lb/>Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral <lb/>Development (NUBU), Oslo, Norway (mail: <lb/>post@nubu.no) or to the project leader Ane Naerde <lb/>(ane.narde@nubu.no). <lb/>Funding: AN received a grant from The Research <lb/>Council of Norway (Grant 283438/H20). https:// <lb/>www.forskningsradet.no/en/. The funders had no <lb/>role in study design, data collection or analysis, <lb/>decisions to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>that the stress of poverty and financial instability undermines parenting practices and affects <lb/>subsequent child functioning. <lb/>Siblings. The presence of siblings (younger or older) constitutes a major risk factor for <lb/>aggressive behavior [39-43]. Siblings represent easily accessible targets and intersibling aggres-<lb/>sion is the most prevalent form of family violence [44]. The relevant theoretical perspectives <lb/>include family systems theory, evolutionary psychology, and social learning theories [43, 44]. <lb/>For instance, Patterson [43, 45] suggested a sibling-training hypothesis wherein coercive inter-<lb/>actions set the stage for the development and escalation of aggressive behavior through direct <lb/>practice, modeling, and reinforcement. <lb/>Parenting factors. Parenting style. Less sensitive and involved maternal parenting has <lb/>been linked with higher and more stable TPA from 2 years of age to the third grade [22], and <lb/>maternal coercive parenting has been found to be predictive of TPA from 17 to 42 months of <lb/>age [12], as well as from 2 to 8 years of age [20]. Patterson&apos;s [45] coercion model asserts that <lb/>aggression develops from negative reinforcement processes between a child and important <lb/>others. This negative reinforcement for acting out is what perpetuates adverse parent-child <lb/>cycles [45, 46]. <lb/>The recurring failure to integrate fathers into developmental research, including research <lb/>on aggression, may lead to the misattribution of paternal influences to maternal influences or <lb/>leaving important sources of variation unexplained (for an exception, see Yang et al. [47]). <lb/>Cabrera et al. [48] and Cabrera [49] recently discussed why fathers are still mostly absent from <lb/>parenting research despite strong suggestions that traditional models of developmental influ-<lb/>ences are outdated; one reason includes the tendency to define mothers as the primary care-<lb/>giver and the belief that fathers do not engage in hands-on parenting. Norwegian fathers tend <lb/>to be highly involved in caregiving [50], providing a unique opportunity to assess the impor-<lb/>tance of factors related to mothers and fathers alike (e.g., parenting style and psychopathology) <lb/>in the development of aggression. <lb/>Child factors. Gender. Whereas empirical evidence suggests that boys and girls use physi-<lb/>cal force against others (e.g., pulling hair, hitting) at similar rates in infancy and early toddler-<lb/>hood [7, 51, 52], boys show significantly more physical aggression in the following few years <lb/>[5, 7, 26, 53]. Co ˆte ´et al. [20] reported that children in the high TPA from 2 to 8 years were <lb/>more likely to be boys. Multiple hypotheses for these differences have been proposed [20, 24, <lb/>51-54], including a convincing case for a developmental cascade of biological and social fac-<lb/>tors [51]. <lb/>Temperament. High negative emotionality, activity levels and reactivity, along with low <lb/>effortful control and negative mood, have all been linked to TPA [26, 29, 55, 56]. Several theo-<lb/>retical models go beyond simple associations to postulate synergistic interactions between dif-<lb/>ficult temperaments (i.e., high negative emotionality, activity level, and reactivity) and <lb/>negative parenting that influence TPA [57-59], and a recent meta-analysis provides partial <lb/>support [60] for these theories. <lb/>Outcomes of TPA <lb/>The National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Study of Early Child Care <lb/>and Youth Development [SECCYD; 15, 22] showed that both level and stability of aggression <lb/>from age 2 to 9 years of age predict middle childhood academic achievement and social func-<lb/>tioning at home, at school, and in the peer groups. In particular, Campbell et al. [15] explored <lb/>adjustment from 9 to 12 years of age as a function of five identified trajectories and found that <lb/>children in the high-and moderate-stable groups showed continuing behavioral and social <lb/>problems relative to those in the very low aggression group; the high-stable group showed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>signs of significant antisocial behavior, whereas the moderate-stable group showed symptoms <lb/>of ADHD and more minor peer problems [15, 22]. Additionally, children in the moderate <lb/>decreasing group displaying transient and age-related aggression that disappeared before <lb/>school age showed good adjustment both at the age of 9 years [22] and across the transition to <lb/>adolescence [15]. A more surprising finding was that relative to those in the very-low group, <lb/>children in the low-stable group had elevated scores on measures of problem behaviors and <lb/>poor social skills in elementary school [15]. Thus, moderate, or low-level aggression that per-<lb/>sists from toddlerhood through school entry may signal adjustment problems that will con-<lb/>tinue or emerge by middle childhood. <lb/>The present study <lb/>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study of TPA with the following combination of <lb/>characteristics: a large population-based sample, frequent repeated measures, and an age range <lb/>of 1-5 years, during which physical aggression both emerges and declines among most chil-<lb/>dren. This study also extends previous findings by (a) including father parenting and other <lb/>paternal characteristics, (b) using a North European sample, and (c) utilizing recent advances <lb/>in statistical methods when incorporating predictors and outcomes in the trajectory model <lb/>[61]. We included 20 early predictors and four school-age outcomes suggested by prior <lb/>research, enabling us to disentangle the relative importance of TPA for social, behavioral, and <lb/>academic functioning, while simultaneously considering the direct and indirect impacts of <lb/>early risk and protective factors. <lb/>Research objectives and expectations <lb/>Our specific research objectives were to: <lb/>1. Model trajectories of physical aggression (TPA) from 1 to 5 years of age; <lb/>2. Predict TPA membership from a set of 20 early predictors and predict Grade 2 outcomes <lb/>(externalizing, internalizing, social skills, and academic competence) from TPA; <lb/>3. Test all simultaneous influences in fully adjusted models, allowing us to determine predic-<lb/>tors of TPA and Grade 2 outcomes that remained significant after adjustment for other <lb/>competing predictors. <lb/>The expectations we had concerning findings with regard to our three respective objectives <lb/>were as follows: <lb/>1. Our findings would generally agree with those from previous research concerning TPA <lb/>shapes and distributions, however; due to the dataset&apos;s frequent repeated measures and the <lb/>eventful age range, our research might identify more distinct TPA compared to prior <lb/>research; <lb/>2. Previously identified early risk and protective factors, considered individually, would pre-<lb/>dict TPA and Grade 2 outcomes consistent with prior research; and <lb/>3. Fewer early predictors of TPA and Grade 2 outcomes would remain significant in the fully <lb/>adjusted models; however, TPA would remain a significant predictor of Grade 2 outcomes. <lb/>We did not have clear expectations concerning which predictors would retain direct effects <lb/>or work indirectly in predicting Grade 2 outcomes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and methods <lb/>Sample and procedures <lb/>We utilized data from the Behavior Outlook Norwegian Developmental Study (BONDS), a <lb/>population-based longitudinal study of 1,159 children (559 girls and 600 boys) from five <lb/>municipalities in southeast Norway conducted by the Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral <lb/>Development. The BONDS was approved by the Regional Committee for Medical and Health <lb/>Research Ethics and the Norwegian Social Sciences Data Services (approval numbers S-06067; <lb/>2009/224a), and all parents provided informed written consent. Participants were recruited <lb/>from 2006 to 2008 during the 5-month visit at child health clinics, which are attended almost <lb/>universally. The inclusion criteria were the child being of the appropriate age and one parent <lb/>being able to participate without an interpreter. <lb/>Statistical power considerations, including of growth mixture models, guided the determi-<lb/>nation of the sample size [62]. Families of 1,931 eligible children were informed about the proj-<lb/>ect. Of the 1,465 (76%) families who agreed to be contacted, 1,159 (79%, or 60% of the eligible <lb/>group) opted to participate [62]. Details of the BONDS sample and procedures including a <lb/>flow chart of participation have been previously published [62, 63]. <lb/>The original study comprised parental interviews, including a computerized questionnaire, <lb/>when the child was aged 6 months and 1, 2, 3, and 4 years. Whereas both parents were invited <lb/>to participate in the first interview, fathers were primarily targeted in the 1-and 3-year waves, <lb/>and mothers were targeted in the 2-and 4-year waves. At the ages of 1, 2, and 3 years, the <lb/>assessment included videotaped structured parent-child interaction tasks, in which more <lb/>fathers participated when the child was aged 1 and 3 years, and more mothers participated <lb/>when the child was aged 2 years. In addition to the yearly data collection, brief telephone inter-<lb/>views comprising a selection of items relevant to the study&apos;s key outcomes were conducted <lb/>when the child was aged 8 months, 10 months, and 1.25, 1.50, 1.75, 2.33, 2.67, and 3.5 years, as <lb/>well as before and after entry into center-based childcare. <lb/>At the age of four years, the parents of 1,027 children (88.6%) renewed their informed writ-<lb/>ten consent for participation in a continuation of the study, including parental interviews <lb/>when the child was aged 5 years and in Grades 1 and 2 and teacher-completed questionnaires <lb/>when the child was in Grades 1 and 2. <lb/>Measures <lb/>Child physical aggression. We used an original instrument developed for the BONDS, <lb/>with idiomatic wording and a selection of items widely acceptable to parents of small children, <lb/>including exclusively physical behavior directed at others covering mostly the lower range of <lb/>intensity. The items covered hitting, pushing, pulling hair, pinching, throwing things, biting, <lb/>and kicking. In questionnaires completed by parents when the child was aged 1, 2, 3, and 4 <lb/>years, a seven-point frequency response scale ranging from 1 (never/not in the past year) to 7 <lb/>(three times daily or more) was used. In telephone interviews conducted in-between the ques-<lb/>tionnaires and at 5 years of age, the response format was dichotomous (yes/no). We used all <lb/>available reports from either questionnaires or telephone interviews from 1 to 5 years of age, <lb/>with an average of twelve repeated measures per child (ranging from 1 to 21, with 90% of chil-<lb/>dren having at least ten reports). The full instrument is reproduced in S1 Appendix, along with <lb/>item-level descriptive statistics. <lb/>We employed Rasch scaling [64] to equate the questionnaire and telephone-interview <lb/>response formats, link response patterns with varying sets of completed items, and address <lb/>measurement invariance. We used Rasch person location estimates as our physical aggression <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>measure (M = -1.86; SD = 1.87). Specifics of the scaling and further statistics of the Rasch-<lb/>scaled measure are given in S2 Appendix. A simple, nonparametric regression (Loess) plot of <lb/>the repeated measures of physical aggression vs. child age is shown in S1 Fig. <lb/>Parent/family predictor measures. All early predictor variables were obtained at either <lb/>the 6-or 12-month assessments. In addition to interview self-reports of single-parent status, <lb/>for young mother/young father we used a binary indicator of young parent age (i.e., �25 <lb/>years old). <lb/>We used interview reports of parental education in six categories of total years of education. <lb/>Financial stress was measured via a binary (yes/no) parental questionnaire self-report of <lb/>having long-standing financial difficulties in the past year (e.g., rent, mortgage). <lb/>For couple relationship we used mothers&apos; questionnaire reports of the quality of the rela-<lb/>tionship with her partner on a shortened and modified 10-item version of the Relationship sat-<lb/>isfaction scale [65] answered on a 6-point Likert scale from 1 (very much agree) to 6 (very <lb/>much disagree) with Cronbach&apos;s alpha of .90 in our sample. <lb/>Information on parental depression and anxiety was obtained using the 12-item version <lb/>of the Hopkins Symptom Check List [66] self-report questionnaire, a subset of the 25-item ver-<lb/>sion [67]. Items are scored using a Likert-type scale ranging from 1 (not at all) to 4 (extremely). <lb/>Sample Cronbach&apos;s alphas for the mean scores were .88 and .87 for mothers and fathers, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>Parenting predictor measures. Parent sensitivity. Parent sensitivity was measured based <lb/>on observer ratings of videotaped parent-child structured interaction tasks when the child was <lb/>aged 1 year. We used the mean of three ratings-sensitivity/responsiveness, detachment/dis-<lb/>engagement (reversed), and positive regard for the child-from the Norwegian adaptation of <lb/>the Qualitative Ratings for Parent-Child Interactions used in the SECCYD study [68, 69]. Rat-<lb/>ings were aggregated across two separately rated segments of interaction. Each variable was <lb/>rated by trained judges on a Likert-type scale ranging from 1 to 5; interrater reliability (intra-<lb/>class correlations) ranged from .65 to .74 in the full set of rating variables [69]. Internal consis-<lb/>tency (alpha) for the composite was .88 (fathers) and .86 (mothers). The parent sensitivity <lb/>measure is detailed in S3 Appendix. <lb/>Harsh and positive parenting. When the child was aged 1 year, the parents contributed ques-<lb/>tionnaire self-reports of parenting practices on a subset of items from the Parenting scale from <lb/>the Fast Track Project; this scale was adapted from the Parental Discipline scale and Parent <lb/>Praise scales from the Pittsburgh Youth Study [70, 71]. The items were answered on a fre-<lb/>quency scale ranging from 1 (never) to 5 (almost always). We used the mean of three items on <lb/>positive parenting behavior (smiling at the child, saying something nice about the child to the <lb/>child, and giving the child a hug, pat on the back, or a kiss) in response to desirable child <lb/>behavior. We used the mean of two items on harsh parenting behavior (yelling or screaming <lb/>and slapping or hitting) in response to undesirable child behavior. Reliabilities were estimated <lb/>at .60, .58, .86, and .81 for fathers&apos; harsh, mothers&apos; harsh, fathers&apos; positive, and mothers&apos; posi-<lb/>tive parenting, respectively. <lb/>Child predictor measures. In addition to child gender and age, the presence of similar-<lb/>aged sibling(s) was a binary indicator of interview reports of the presence of a sibling with an <lb/>age difference of up to 5 years. <lb/>For child temperament we used parent questionnaire reports completed when the child was <lb/>aged 6 months including the Activity level and Distress to Limitations scales from Rothbart&apos;s <lb/>Infant Behavior Questionnaire-Revised [72], as well as the Soothability scale from the Infant <lb/>Behavior Questionnaire [73]. A modified three-point response format was used: 1 (most of the <lb/>time), 2 (sometimes), or 3 (rarely or never). Cronbach&apos;s alphas were .71, .76, and .77 for the <lb/>three scale mean scores, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Grade 2 outcome variables. Teachers completed the Social Skills Improvement System-<lb/>Rating Scales (SSIS-RS; [74]). The children were approximately 8 years old around the time of <lb/>data collection. Externalizing, internalizing, academic competence, and social skills were <lb/>evaluated using sums of 12, 7, 7, and 46 items, respectively, with sample Cronbach&apos;s alphas of <lb/>.92, .83, .96, and .96, respectively. The scales use a four-point response format ranging from 0 <lb/>(never) to 3 (almost always), except academic competence, which is rated from 1 (lowest 10%) <lb/>to 5 (highest 10%). <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>Analytic subsample and missing data. The present study used an analytic subsample of <lb/>1141 children with reports of physical aggression. Among predictor variables from 6 months <lb/>of age representing family demographics and child temperament, 1.3% missing observations <lb/>were imputed prior to the main analyses using a single imputation of missing values, as <lb/>described in more detail in Naerde et al. [11]. For the remaining early predictor variables and <lb/>Grade 2 outcomes, missingness was addressed using 420 multiple imputations in R [100] for <lb/>standard regression analyses. The imputation model included all early predictors and Grade 2 <lb/>outcomes. For all analyses involving latent classes, missingness was handled within the latent-<lb/>variable framework in Mplus as described below in the Analytic strategy subsection. <lb/>Attrition analyses revealed that the analytic subsample and the subsample of 901 children <lb/>who had Grade 2 teacher reports resembled the original study sample very closely with respect <lb/>to all early predictors (S4 Appendix). <lb/>Data transformations. To prevent potential distortions due to outliers, we trimmed non-<lb/>binary predictors at approximately the 2nd and 98th percentiles of their respective distribu-<lb/>tions. Some of the nonbinary predictors as well as the Grade 2 outcomes of externalizing and <lb/>internalizing were highly skewed, as would be expected in this population, and were square <lb/>root transformed to make the assumption of within-class normality more reasonable. Descrip-<lb/>tive statistics for predictors and outcomes, before and after transformations, are shown in <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>Analytic strategy <lb/>Number and shapes of TPA. First, we used latent class trajectory analysis (LCGA) to investigate <lb/>the number and shape of TPA. We specified TPA as a 4th-degree (quartic) polynomial growth <lb/>model, following preliminary analyses that indicated that this model fit substantially better <lb/>than 2nd-or 3rd-degree models in our sample. We used a 2-level specification for the LCGA <lb/>with the child&apos;s age in years, centered at 2.2, as the time variable to accommodate the large <lb/>number and irregular timing of the repeated growth measures within children. The basic <lb/>2-level LCGA-growth model specification included 5 child-level growth components with <lb/>freely estimated means for the 5 growth components in each class, no within-class variability <lb/>in growth components, and time-specific variability constrained to be equal across both time <lb/>and classes. The specification of no within-class variability in growth is what locates our model <lb/>in the category of LCGA (latent class growth analysis; [18]), which is considered the simplest <lb/>longitudinal mixture model [75]). Most prominent trajectory studies to date, [e.g., 10, 18, 22, <lb/>26] have employed LCGA models. <lb/>Unadjusted predictor effects on TPA membership. After selecting the optimal TPA solution, <lb/>in the following steps, for models that included latent classes and either predictors, outcomes, <lb/>or both, we used the manual 3-step procedure as recommended by Asparouhov and Muthen <lb/>[61]. In addition to the advantages given by Asparouhov and Muthen, the 3-step approach <lb/>allows a much simpler way of dealing with missing data in child-level predictors because Step <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>3 eliminates all the repeated growth measurements for a particular child and replaces them <lb/>with one child-level nominal predictor of latent class, that is, pseudo-class. <lb/>We first examined all prediction effects unadjusted for other influences. In the first of these <lb/>steps, we considered early predictors of class membership. For the overall effect of a predictor <lb/>on class membership, we used likelihood ratio tests (LRT) to compare the model with all <lb/>Table 1. Descriptive statistics. <lb/>Raw data <lb/>Transformed data <lb/>N <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>Skew <lb/>Kurt <lb/>Min <lb/>Max <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>Skew <lb/>Kurt <lb/>Min <lb/>Max <lb/>Trajectory (growth model) repeated measure <lb/>Child physical aggression <lb/>13673 <lb/>-1.86 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>-0.23 <lb/>-5.30 <lb/>5.02 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Early predictors <lb/>Maternal education a <lb/>1141 <lb/>14.29 <lb/>2.57 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-1.06 <lb/>9 <lb/>18 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>2.57 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-1.06 <lb/>-5.29 <lb/>3.71 <lb/>Paternal education a <lb/>1141 <lb/>13.84 <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>-1.09 <lb/>9 <lb/>18 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>-1.09 <lb/>-4.84 <lb/>4.17 <lb/>Young mother <lb/>1141 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>2.12 <lb/>2.49 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Young father <lb/>1141 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>12.95 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Financial stress <lb/>1096 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>2.34 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Couple relationship b <lb/>1072 <lb/>5.33 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>-1.70 <lb/>4.18 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.70 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.38 <lb/>Single parent <lb/>1141 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>4.32 <lb/>16.66 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mat&apos;l depression &amp; anxiety c <lb/>1116 <lb/>1.33 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>1.95 <lb/>5.98 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>3.75 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>-0.82 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>Pat&apos;l depression &amp; anxiety c <lb/>671 <lb/>1.27 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>2.59 <lb/>13.12 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>4.00 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>-1.11 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Maternal sensitivity d <lb/>244 <lb/>3.90 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>-0.79 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>1.83 <lb/>5.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>-0.63 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>-1.43 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>Paternal sensitivity d <lb/>717 <lb/>3.74 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>-0.45 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>1.17 <lb/>5.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>-0.32 <lb/>-0.75 <lb/>-1.41 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>Mat&apos;l harsh parenting d <lb/>377 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>7.73 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>5.00 -0.01 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>1.70 <lb/>-0.42 <lb/>1.58 <lb/>Pat&apos;l parenting d <lb/>835 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>4.00 -0.01 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>-0.28 <lb/>-0.41 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>Mat&apos;l positive parenting d <lb/>377 <lb/>4.71 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>-2.82 <lb/>13.90 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>5.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>-1.61 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>-1.38 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>Pat&apos;l positive parenting d <lb/>835 <lb/>4.53 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>-2.10 <lb/>8.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>5.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>-0.86 <lb/>-0.18 <lb/>-1.19 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>1141 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-2.00 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Similar-aged sibling <lb/>1141 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>-1.78 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Child activity level d <lb/>1141 <lb/>2.07 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>2.83 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>-0.42 <lb/>-0.54 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>Child distress to limitations d <lb/>1141 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>2.82 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>-0.56 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>Child soothability d <lb/>1141 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>-0.46 <lb/>-0.35 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>-0.30 <lb/>-0.89 <lb/>-0.63 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>Grade 2 outcomes <lb/>Externalizing e <lb/>901 <lb/>4.81 <lb/>5.26 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>3.22 <lb/>0 <lb/>35 <lb/>1.83 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>-0.36 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>5.92 <lb/>Internalizing e <lb/>901 <lb/>3.01 <lb/>2.97 <lb/>1.17 <lb/>1.49 <lb/>0 <lb/>18 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.94 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>4.24 <lb/>Academic competence <lb/>896 <lb/>25.03 <lb/>7.12 <lb/>-0.40 <lb/>-0.50 <lb/>7 <lb/>35 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Social skills <lb/>887 103.79 <lb/>19.56 <lb/>-0.43 <lb/>-0.45 <lb/>32 <lb/>137 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Note. Some variables were transformed as marked by letter subscripts. Descriptive statistics for transformed variables are displayed in the right part of the table. <lb/>Reversing and recentering are linear transformations that do not change the shape of a distribution, the rank order of observations, or the linear relations with other <lb/>variables. Trimming and square root transformations are non-linear transformations that change the shape of a distribution (make it less skewed and heavy-tailed), the <lb/>rank order of a few of the observations (only trimming and this is because it produces ties among extremes) and thus potentially alter linear relations with other <lb/>variables. <lb/>a <lb/>Centered. <lb/>b Trimmed (values smaller than the 2nd percentile or larger than the 98th percentile recoded back to the 2nd or 98th percentile values), reversed, recentered to have a <lb/>minimum score of zero and square root transformed. <lb/>c <lb/>Trimmed, recentered to have a minimum score of zero and square root transformed. <lb/>d <lb/>Centered and trimmed. <lb/>e <lb/>Square root transformed. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>possible predictor effects to the model that included the predictor but had all predictor effects <lb/>constrained to zero. We used a pseudo-R statistic [76] as the indicator of the strength of associ-<lb/>ation between predictor and class membership. We also investigated predictor effects on mem-<lb/>bership in any class versus another in multinomial logistic regressions in the context of the <lb/>3-step approach. Multinomial logistic contrast coefficients express the change in log odds of <lb/>the outcome for a 1-unit change in the predictor. In our case with 9 latent classes, the multino-<lb/>mial logistic regression produces 8 effects for each class vs. the reference class for each predic-<lb/>tor. The 8 effects can be recombined in simple linear combinations to derive any contrast <lb/>between any 2 classes. <lb/>Unadjusted effects of TPA membership on Grade 2 outcomes. Next, we evaluated the overall <lb/>effect of class membership on the distal outcomes considered singly. Similar to our approach <lb/>for comparing predictor effects, we adopted an LRT approach comparing the model with distal <lb/>outcome means freely estimated in each class to the null model with distal outcome means <lb/>forced to be equal in each class. To summarize the overall effect of latent class on outcomes, we <lb/>computed R as the square root of R 2 by computing the proportional reduction of total outcome <lb/>variance represented by the residual, within class outcome variance. For means comparisons <lb/>of outcomes among latent classes, we used standardized mean differences. <lb/>Unadjusted predictor effects on Grade 2 outcomes. Next, we examined the strength of associ-<lb/>ation between each early predictor and each Grade 2 outcome using a standardized regression <lb/>weight. <lb/>Fully adjusted models predicting each distal outcome from early predictors and TPA. Finally, <lb/>for each distal outcome, we went on to build fully adjusted models, that simultaneously consid-<lb/>ered the influence of early predictors on TPA as well as the influence of TPA and early predic-<lb/>tors on the outcome. For these analyses, we retained those early predictors that either had a <lb/>significant unadjusted effect on TPA membership or had a significant effect on any of the four <lb/>distal outcomes after adjusting for all other predictors in separate multi-predictor models. The <lb/>fully adjusted models included all possible predictor effects on latent class, all latent class <lb/>effects on the distal outcome, and all possible direct paths from the predictors to the distal out-<lb/>come. Analogous to the unadjusted-model analyses, we investigated effects using the LRT, <lb/>pseudo-R statistics, and multinomial logistic contrast coefficients. <lb/>Results <lb/>Number and shapes of TPA <lb/>We considered two-to ten trajectory solutions. We relied on information criteria, the <lb/>parametric bootstrap likelihood ratio test (BLRT), the test that has the best support mathemati-<lb/>cally [77, 78] and in simulations [79], and substantive considerations to select the number of <lb/>TPA that seemed optimal with respect to parsimony, model fit, the distinctiveness of the tra-<lb/>jectories, and the estimated proportions of the population within each trajectory. S5 Appendix <lb/>provides information criteria and BLRT for the sequence of the models. The consistent Akaike <lb/>information criterion (CAIC; [79]) was minimized by eight trajectories, the Bayesian informa-<lb/>tion criterion (BIC) was minimized by nine trajectories, and the sample size-adjusted BIC and <lb/>the Akaike information criterion (AIC) did not reach a clear minimum by ten trajectories. The <lb/>BLRT consistently rejected models with fewer than 8 trajectories, although due to the heavy <lb/>computational burden we did not attempt to test models with 9 or more trajectories against <lb/>simpler models. We selected the nine-trajectory solution over the eight because it was sug-<lb/>gested by the BIC, which is strongly recommended by methodologists as being accurate, or at <lb/>worst somewhat conservative, in this context [79], and suggested possibly distinct <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>developmental paths worthy of investigation, each representing a reasonable proportion of the <lb/>sample. Fig 1 shows the 9-class model estimated trajectories, which seemed to represent: <lb/>1. One high-stable trajectory that rises to a very high peak of physical aggression at approxi-<lb/>mately 2 years of age and stays at a high level (Trajectory 9, model-based trajectory propor-<lb/>tion 3%); <lb/>2. Three intermediate-endpoint trajectories that end up at an elevated level of physical aggres-<lb/>sion, with different early developments: one starting high and declining after a rather high <lb/>peak (Trajectory 8, 7%), another with a similar peak and decline but a low starting point <lb/>(Trajectory 7, 9%), and a third starting low with a late and flat peak (Trajectory 6, 17%); <lb/>3. Two high-start, low-endpoint trajectories that decline from an initial high level, with a late <lb/>and flat peak followed by another decline to a low level, with one trajectory following a <lb/>slightly higher-level path (Trajectory 5, 5%) than the other (Trajectory 4, 7%); <lb/>4. Two medium-peak, low-endpoint trajectories that start and end with a low level of physical <lb/>aggression, with one trajectory reaching an early peak of a somewhat high level (Trajectory <lb/>3, 16%), and one with a flatter peak at a lower level (Trajectory 2, 22%); and <lb/>5. One low-stable or &quot;no aggression&quot; trajectory that starts and stays at a low level of aggression <lb/>with just a minor rise to a very low, flat peak, and a decline back to a low level (Trajectory 1, <lb/>14%). <lb/>Details of the 9-trajectory solution are given in S6 Appendix. <lb/>Fig 1. Model predicted child physical aggression by trajectory in nine-trajectory solution (fourth-grade polynomial growth function). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unadjusted predictor effects on TPA <lb/>Overall effects of each predictor in isolation on TPA are shown in the first three data columns <lb/>of Table 2. <lb/>Eleven out of the 20 predictors had significant overall effects on TPA with pseudo-R values <lb/>ranging from .12 to .24. The presence of a similar-aged sibling and child gender were the two <lb/>strongest predictors. Maternal education level, couple relationship, depression and anxiety in <lb/>both parents, harsh parenting by both parents, and all three child-temperament variables were <lb/>also significant predictors. Trajectory predictor coefficients with pairwise contrast tests are <lb/>shown in the upper part of Table 3. In the presence of a significant overall effect, pairwise con-<lb/>trast tests may aid the interpretation of effect direction. In the absence of a significant overall <lb/>effect, the presence of any effects notable in size but limited in scope-that is, affecting only a <lb/>few classes or small classes-cannot be inferred from the displayed contrast tests alone but <lb/>must be considered in the context of the magnitude of the contrast. <lb/>Table 2. Unadjusted overall prediction effects of early predictors on trajectory and outcomes, and of trajectory on outcomes. <lb/>Predictor <lb/>Prediction to trajectory a <lb/>Prediction to Grade 2 outcomes b <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>p <lb/>Pseudo R a <lb/>Externalizing <lb/>Internalizing <lb/>Academic competence <lb/>Social skills <lb/>Maternal education <lb/>17.1 <lb/>.029 <lb/>.12* <lb/>-.13*** <lb/>-.12*** <lb/>.22*** <lb/>.18*** <lb/>Paternal education <lb/>14.5 <lb/>.070 <lb/>.11 <lb/>-.12*** <lb/>-.09** <lb/>.17*** <lb/>.15*** <lb/>Young mother <lb/>13.7 <lb/>.090 <lb/>.11 <lb/>.09** <lb/>.11** <lb/>-.01 <lb/>-.09* <lb/>Young father <lb/>5.9 <lb/>.660 <lb/>.07 <lb/>.09* <lb/>.13*** <lb/>-.05 <lb/>-.08* <lb/>Financial stress <lb/>12.2 <lb/>.144 <lb/>.10 <lb/>.16*** <lb/>.15*** <lb/>-.13*** <lb/>-.18*** <lb/>Couple relationship (reversed) <lb/>23.3 <lb/>.003 <lb/>.14** <lb/>.09* <lb/>.12*** <lb/>-.08* <lb/>-.06 <lb/>Single parent <lb/>13.9 <lb/>.086 <lb/>.11 <lb/>.16*** <lb/>.13*** <lb/>-.14*** <lb/>-.15*** <lb/>Maternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>40.8 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.19*** <lb/>.07* <lb/>.09** <lb/>-.09** <lb/>-.06 <lb/>Paternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>16.1 <lb/>.041 <lb/>.12* <lb/>.13** <lb/>.08 <lb/>.00 <lb/>-.17*** <lb/>Maternal sensitivity <lb/>4.4 <lb/>.818 <lb/>.06 <lb/>-.12 <lb/>-.13* <lb/>.11 <lb/>.09 <lb/>Paternal sensitivity <lb/>11.4 <lb/>.179 <lb/>.10 <lb/>-.12** <lb/>-.07 <lb/>.10* <lb/>.11** <lb/>Maternal harsh parenting <lb/>46.5 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.20*** <lb/>.13* <lb/>.04 <lb/>-.09 <lb/>-.09 <lb/>Paternal harsh parenting <lb/>31.7 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.17*** <lb/>.06 <lb/>.01 <lb/>-.11** <lb/>-.09* <lb/>Maternal positive parenting <lb/>6.5 <lb/>.594 <lb/>.08 <lb/>.02 <lb/>-.02 <lb/>-.06 <lb/>-.03 <lb/>Paternal positive parenting <lb/>7.5 <lb/>.485 <lb/>.08 <lb/>.03 <lb/>.04 <lb/>.04 <lb/>-.02 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>54.7 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.22*** <lb/>.30*** <lb/>.13*** <lb/>-.13*** <lb/>-.30*** <lb/>Similar-aged sibling <lb/>66.6 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.24*** <lb/>-.02 <lb/>-.07* <lb/>-.02 <lb/>.04 <lb/>Child activity level <lb/>32.3 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.17*** <lb/>.09** <lb/>.09** <lb/>-.03 <lb/>-.08* <lb/>Child distress to limitations <lb/>38.0 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.18*** <lb/>-.04 <lb/>.00 <lb/>.02 <lb/>.04 <lb/>Child soothability <lb/>29.5 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.16*** <lb/>.09** <lb/>.03 <lb/>-.07* <lb/>-.11** <lb/>Trajectory c <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>.27*** <lb/>.11 <lb/>.19*** <lb/>.19** <lb/>*p &lt; .05 <lb/>**p &lt; .01 <lb/>***p &lt; .001. <lb/>a <lb/>Overall prediction to trajectory was assessed by comparing a model with all class discrimination effects of each single predictor freely estimated to a reduced model <lb/>where all the class discrimination effects are zeroed out in an 8 degrees of freedom chi-square test; the effect size is given as pseudo-R derived from robust chi-square <lb/>estimated as the square root of Nagelkerke&apos;s pseudo R 2 , which was identical to Cohen&apos;s ω. <lb/>b Predictor-to-outcome associations are given as fully standardized regression coefficients. Coefficients were standardized by sample standard deviations (Table 1). <lb/>c <lb/>Prediction of outcomes from trajectory membership is given as R, the square root of R 2 computed as the proportional reduction in total outcome variance represented <lb/>by the residual within class variance, that is, R 2 = proportion explained variance = 1 -(residual variance/total variance). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>The contrast tests for predictors with a significant overall effect on TPA generally indi-<lb/>cated effects in the expected direction, with risk factors predicting trajectories with higher <lb/>overall levels, peaks, or endpoints and protective factors predicting in the opposite <lb/>direction. <lb/>Table 3. Trajectory predictor coefficient contrasts for unadjusted effects of early predictors on trajectory and means comparison contrasts for unadjusted effects of <lb/>trajectory on outcomes. <lb/>Variable <lb/>Overall effect a <lb/>Trajectory <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>Trajectory prediction coefficients with pairwise contrasts for effects of early predictors on trajectory b <lb/>Maternal education <lb/>.12* <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.15 489 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.27 267 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.13 489 <lb/>0.21 489 <lb/>-0.24 267 <lb/>-0.40 267 <lb/>Paternal education <lb/>.11 <lb/>0.00 9 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.03 9 <lb/>0.21 89 <lb/>-0.31 7 <lb/>-0.60 167 <lb/>Young mother <lb/>.11 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.23 67 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.29 48 <lb/>-0.30 4 <lb/>0.12 6 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>Young father <lb/>.07 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.23 9 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>0.18 6 <lb/>Financial stress <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 9 <lb/>0.04 9 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.09 9 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.46 126 <lb/>Couple relationship (reversed) <lb/>.14** <lb/>0.00 6 <lb/>-0.13 35689 <lb/>0.21 24 <lb/>-0.22 3689 <lb/>0.23 2 <lb/>0.28 124 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.24 24 <lb/>0.45 24 <lb/>Single parent <lb/>.11 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.50 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>-0.12 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>Maternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>.19*** <lb/>0.00 36789 <lb/>0.09 3789 <lb/>0.45 12 <lb/>0.30 9 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.32 19 <lb/>0.57 12 <lb/>0.63 12 <lb/>0.84 1246 <lb/>Paternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>.12* <lb/>0.00 8 <lb/>-0.35 48 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.29 2 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.47 12 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>Maternal sensitivity <lb/>.06 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>-0.11 5 <lb/>-0.09 5 <lb/>0.68 34678 -0.07 5 <lb/>-0.10 5 <lb/>-0.08 5 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>Paternal sensitivity <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.13 4 <lb/>0.57 3569 -0.22 4 <lb/>-0.24 4 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.22 4 <lb/>Maternal harsh parenting <lb/>.20*** <lb/>0.00 38 <lb/>-0.64 3456789 <lb/>0.88 12 <lb/>0.68 2 <lb/>0.72 2 <lb/>0.65 28 <lb/>0.64 2 <lb/>1.15 1269 <lb/>0.47 28 <lb/>Paternal harsh parenting <lb/>.17*** <lb/>0.00 3679 <lb/>0.23 79 <lb/>0.51 19 <lb/>0.45 9 <lb/>0.48 9 <lb/>0.54 19 <lb/>0.75 12 <lb/>0.47 9 <lb/>1.00 1234568 <lb/>Maternal positive parenting <lb/>.08 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-0.43 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.46 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.38 <lb/>-0.39 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>Paternal positive parenting <lb/>.08 <lb/>0.00 28 <lb/>-0.43 1 <lb/>-0.29 <lb/>-0.35 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-0.43 1 <lb/>-0.46 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>.22*** <lb/>0.00 23456789 <lb/>0.59 1 <lb/>0.59 1 <lb/>0.47 17 <lb/>0.73 1 <lb/>0.80 1 <lb/>0.90 14 <lb/>0.76 1 <lb/>0.98 1 <lb/>Similar-aged sibling <lb/>.24*** <lb/>0.00 356789 <lb/>0.33 789 <lb/>0.37 1789 <lb/>0.07 6789 <lb/>0.55 1 <lb/>0.53 1479 <lb/>0.90 12346 0.80 1234 <lb/>1.00 12346 <lb/>Child activity level <lb/>.17*** <lb/>0.00 4589 <lb/>-0.04 4589 <lb/>0.06 48 <lb/>0.45 1236 <lb/>0.35 126 <lb/>-0.09 4589 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.50 1236 <lb/>0.37 126 <lb/>Child distress to limitations <lb/>.18*** <lb/>0.00 3456789 <lb/>0.32 58 <lb/>0.56 1 <lb/>0.63 1 <lb/>0.75 12 <lb/>0.53 1 <lb/>0.54 1 <lb/>0.68 12 <lb/>0.67 1 <lb/>Child soothability <lb/>.16*** <lb/>0.00 23568 <lb/>-0.34 18 <lb/>-0.39 18 <lb/>-0.17 8 <lb/>-0.58 1 <lb/>-0.45 18 <lb/>-0.20 8 <lb/>-0.76 1234679 -0.29 8 <lb/>Standardized means comparisons with pairwise contrasts for effects of trajectory on distal outcomes c <lb/>Externalizing <lb/>.27*** <lb/>0.00 23456789 <lb/>0.32 167 <lb/>0.37 17 <lb/>0.47 17 <lb/>0.48 17 <lb/>0.71 12 <lb/>0.99 12345 0.63 1 <lb/>0.75 1 <lb/>Internalizing <lb/>.11 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>Academic competence <lb/>.19*** <lb/>0.00 9 <lb/>-0.19 9 <lb/>-0.24 9 <lb/>-0.11 9 <lb/>0.08 79 <lb/>-0.19 9 <lb/>-0.34 59 <lb/>-0.38 9 <lb/>-1.09 12345678 <lb/>Social skills <lb/>.19** <lb/>0.00 679 <lb/>-0.06 679 <lb/>-0.15 9 <lb/>-0.43 <lb/>-0.35 <lb/>-0.42 12 <lb/>-0.45 12 <lb/>-0.33 <lb/>-0.80 123 <lb/>*p &lt; .05 <lb/>**p &lt; .01 <lb/>***p &lt; .001 for overall effects. <lb/>a <lb/>Pseudo-R/R estimate with overall significance test from Table 2. <lb/>b Trajectory prediction contrast coefficients are fully standardized logistic regression effects on the log odds scale (the effect on the log odds of the class contrast for a <lb/>change in the predictor of one standard deviation) given relative to membership in Trajectory 1 (the &quot;no aggression&quot; trajectory). Coefficients were standardized by <lb/>sample standard deviations (Table 1). Contrast coefficients between any pair of trajectories can be derived by subtraction (i.e., for maternal education between <lb/>Trajectories 2 and 4: 0.15-[-0.27] = 0.42, which is significant at p &lt; .05 as indicated by superscripts). A contrast coefficient of 0.69 is equivalent to an odds ratio of 2.0, <lb/>and a coefficient of -0.69 is equivalent to an odds ratio of 0.5. <lb/>c <lb/>The entries are standardized mean differences relative to Trajectory 1. <lb/>123456789 <lb/>Number superscripts indicate pairwise contrast tests significant at p &lt; .05 between the indexed trajectory and the trajectory with the superscripts&apos; number; <lb/>significant contrasts are superscripted for both involved trajectories. Contrast tests are not adjusted for mass significance; the chance expected number out of 36 pairwise <lb/>contrasts at p &lt; .05 would be 1.8 per variable, or 3.6 numbered subscripts per table row, in the case of null association. In the presence of a significant overall effect, <lb/>contrast tests may aid effect direction interpretation; in the absence of a significant overall effect, significance superscripts alone should not be taken as suggesting an <lb/>effect limited to a few classes. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unadjusted effects of TPA on grade 2 outcomes <lb/>Overall effects of TPA on outcomes in isolation tested with a likelihood ratio chi-square with 8 <lb/>degrees of freedom are shown in the lowermost row of Table 2. TPA significantly predicted <lb/>externalizing (R 2 = 7.4%), academic competence (R 2 = 3.6%), and social skills (R 2 = 3.7%). <lb/>Uncorrected for mass significance, pairwise means comparisons among outcomes by TPA <lb/>with contrast tests are shown in the lower part of Table 3. Regarding externalizing, the no-<lb/>aggression trajectory (1) had the lowest mean, contrasting with all other trajectories. For aca-<lb/>demic competence, however, it was the high-stable trajectory (9) that contrasted with all other <lb/>trajectories. <lb/>Unadjusted effects of early predictors on grade 2 outcomes <lb/>When considering the effects of predictors in isolation on any of the four outcomes, 17 predic-<lb/>tors-all except maternal and paternal positive parenting and child distress to limitations-<lb/>influenced one or more of the outcomes. The effects of the significant predictors on each out-<lb/>come are shown in the rightmost four data columns of Table 2. <lb/>Fully adjusted outcome models with early predictors and TPA <lb/>For each distal outcome, we went on to build fully adjusted models for each distal outcome <lb/>estimating simultaneously all influences, we retained 14 predictors that either had a significant <lb/>unadjusted effect on TPA (Table 2) or had a significant effect on any of the four outcomes <lb/>after adjusting for all other predictors in separate multi-predictor models. Thus, paternal edu-<lb/>cation, young father, maternal and paternal sensitivity, and maternal and paternal positive par-<lb/>enting were not included in the fully adjusted models. The findings are shown in Table 4. <lb/>In these adjusted models, the number and magnitude of significant effects, as expected, gen-<lb/>erally decreased relative to the unadjusted effects (Table 2), highlighting that these adjusted <lb/>models identify the most proximal predictors of the trajectories and outcomes. <lb/>Significant adjusted overall predictors of TPA included the presence of a similar-aged sib-<lb/>ling (which did not have a direct effect on any outcome), child gender (which also had direct <lb/>effects on all outcomes), and maternal and paternal harsh parenting (with no direct effects on <lb/>outcomes). The upper part of Table 5 displays fully adjusted trajectory prediction contrast <lb/>coefficients. For the predictors with significant effects, the contrast patterns largely resembled <lb/>those in the unadjusted results. <lb/>We can thus infer that the set of predictors that were significantly related to TPA (either <lb/>overall or for some contrasts) prior to adjustment, but not after, may have potentially impor-<lb/>tant indirect or mediated effects. These predictors include paternal depression and anxiety, <lb/>maternal education level, financial stress, and young mother status. <lb/>In the adjusted models, TPA had a significant overall effect on externalizing (R 2 = 5.0%) but <lb/>not on academic competence (R 2 = 2.6%), social skills (R 2 = 1.5%) or internalizing (R 2 = 0.8%). <lb/>Adjustment for competing predictors eliminated the significant unadjusted overall effect of <lb/>trajectory on academic competence and social skills. Of the outcomes with no significant over-<lb/>all effect, for academic competence, large and significant standardized differences indicated a <lb/>difference involving Trajectory 9 (high-stable), which had the lowest mean, in contrast to Tra-<lb/>jectories 1, 3, 4, 5, and 6 (standardized differences ranging from 0.63 to 0.91 standard devia-<lb/>tions; individual p values for contrasts ranging from .036 to .003). Thus, after adjustment for <lb/>early predictors, trajectory effects remained significant and important for externalizing (over-<lb/>all) and for academic competence (high-stable in isolation contrasting with five other trajecto-<lb/>ries) but were eliminated for social skills and remained unrelated to internalizing. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>There were direct effects on one or more Grade 2 outcomes of several early predictors <lb/>including child gender (effects on all 4 outcomes), financial stress (externalizing, internalizing, <lb/>and social skills), maternal education level (academic competence and social skills), single-par-<lb/>ent status (externalizing and academic competence), couple relationship (internalizing), child <lb/>distress to limitations (three outcomes, all in unexpected direction), and soothability (two out-<lb/>comes, both in unexpected direction). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Nine latent trajectories represented the development of physical aggression from 1 to 5 years <lb/>of age. Most of the predictors in the unadjusted analyses were associated with TPA either over-<lb/>all or by significantly contrasting among single trajectories, or significantly associated with at <lb/>least one Grade 2 outcome, albeit with some notable exceptions. The significant direct effects <lb/>were fewer and smaller in the fully adjusted model, however those that remained represented <lb/>the most proximal predictors of TPA and functioning in Grade 2. <lb/>Number and shape of TPA <lb/>In contrast to our 9 trajectories, the most comparable trajectory studies have found three to <lb/>five trajectories [10, 12, 16, 19-22, 24-28]. Our study started earlier than previous research <lb/>Table 4. Fully adjusted overall prediction effects of early predictors on trajectory and outcomes, and of trajectory on outcomes. <lb/>Predictor <lb/>Prediction to trajectory a <lb/>Prediction to Grade 2 outcomes b <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>p <lb/>Pseudo R a <lb/>Externalizing <lb/>Internalizing <lb/>Academic competence <lb/>Social skills <lb/>Maternal education <lb/>8.2 <lb/>.417 <lb/>.08 <lb/>-.07 <lb/>-.04 <lb/>.18*** <lb/>.10** <lb/>Young mother <lb/>5.2 <lb/>.732 <lb/>.07 <lb/>.04 <lb/>.04 <lb/>.08 <lb/>-.01 <lb/>Financial stress <lb/>5.5 <lb/>.704 <lb/>.07 <lb/>.09* <lb/>.10* <lb/>-.07 <lb/>-.09* <lb/>Couple relationship (reversed) <lb/>7.8 <lb/>.453 <lb/>.08 <lb/>.03 <lb/>.08* <lb/>-.02 <lb/>.00 <lb/>Single parent <lb/>12.4 <lb/>.135 <lb/>.10 <lb/>.09* <lb/>.07 <lb/>-.09* <lb/>-.07 <lb/>Maternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>10.9 <lb/>.205 <lb/>.10 <lb/>.00 <lb/>.02 <lb/>-.02 <lb/>.00 <lb/>Paternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>4.2 <lb/>.834 <lb/>.06 <lb/>.03 <lb/>.00 <lb/>.00 c <lb/>-.09 <lb/>Maternal harsh parenting <lb/>27.8 <lb/>.001 <lb/>.16*** <lb/>.06 <lb/>.00 <lb/>-.10 <lb/>-.05 <lb/>Paternal harsh parenting <lb/>20.1 <lb/>.010 <lb/>.13** <lb/>.02 <lb/>-.01 <lb/>-.09 <lb/>-.05 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>49.2 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.21*** <lb/>.25*** <lb/>.11** <lb/>-.10** <lb/>-.27*** <lb/>Similar-aged sibling <lb/>90.3 <lb/>&lt; .001 <lb/>.28*** <lb/>-.06 <lb/>-.06 <lb/>.02 <lb/>.06 <lb/>Child activity level <lb/>15.2 <lb/>.055 <lb/>.12 <lb/>.05 <lb/>.06 <lb/>.03 <lb/>-.02 <lb/>Child distress to limitations <lb/>10.7 <lb/>.222 <lb/>.10 <lb/>-.10* <lb/>-.05 <lb/>.01 <lb/>.08* <lb/>Child soothability <lb/>11.5 <lb/>.174 <lb/>.10 <lb/>.10* <lb/>.04 <lb/>-.08* <lb/>-.10** <lb/>Trajectory d <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>.22*** <lb/>.09 <lb/>.16 <lb/>.12 <lb/>*p &lt; .05 <lb/>**p &lt; .01 <lb/>***p &lt; .001. <lb/>a <lb/>Comparisons are of a baseline model where all class discrimination effects of all early predictors are included to a reduced model where all the class discrimination <lb/>effects for a single early predictor are zeroed out completely; prediction to TPA is given as pseudo-R as Cohen&apos;s ω derived from robust chi square. <lb/>b Predictor-to-outcome associations are given as fully standardized regression coefficients. <lb/>c We did not allow significant predictor effects to be in the opposite direction of effects in the unadjusted results. This occurred only for the effect of paternal depression <lb/>and anxiety on academic competence (unadjusted standardized regression coefficient -0.002 [N.S.]; freely estimated fully adjusted standardized regression coefficient <lb/>0.139 [p = .018]); the final fully adjusted model for this outcome was thus re-estimated with the effect of this predictor fixed to zero. <lb/>d <lb/>Prediction of outcomes from TPA is given as R, the square root of R 2 computed as the proportional reduction in total outcome variance represented by the residual <lb/>within class variance, that is, R 2 = proportion explained variance = 1 -(residual variance/total variance). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>and encompassed the period of peak change (at approximately 2 years of age), had frequent <lb/>assessment, used a vertically (age) scaled measurement instrument, and utilized 4th-order <lb/>polynomial growth curves. Indeed, to our knowledge, this study is the only one close to Trem-<lb/>blay&apos;s recommendation [1] regarding assessment frequency. Overall, these qualities provided <lb/>the power to make finer distinctions and detect more fine-grained developmental patterns of <lb/>aggression. Nevertheless, there are also important similarities between our results and findings <lb/>from previous studies. Like other studies [17, 19, 22, 25-27], we identified one high-stable <lb/>group (Trajectory 9) with the lowest prevalence (3%) and overall poorest outcomes. <lb/>Table 5. Trajectory predictor coefficient contrasts for fully adjusted effects of early predictors on trajectory and means comparison contrasts for fully adjusted <lb/>effects of trajectory on outcomes. <lb/>Variable <lb/>Overall effect a <lb/>Trajectory <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>Trajectory prediction coefficients with pairwise contrasts for effects of early predictors on trajectory b <lb/>Maternal education <lb/>.08 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.24 <lb/>Young mother <lb/>.07 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>Financial stress <lb/>.07 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>Couple relationship (reversed) <lb/>.08 <lb/>0.00 4 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>0.06 4 <lb/>-0.40 136 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.17 4 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Single parent <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.29 7 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.34 2 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>Maternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 79 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.51 1 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.71 1 <lb/>Paternal depression &amp; anxiety <lb/>.06 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.26 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>Maternal harsh parenting <lb/>.16*** <lb/>0.00 38 <lb/>-0.66 38 <lb/>1.18 129 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>1.16 129 <lb/>0.34 38 <lb/>Paternal harsh parenting <lb/>.13** <lb/>0.00 3679 <lb/>0.20 7 <lb/>0.68 1 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.62 1 <lb/>0.76 12 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.80 1 <lb/>Child gender <lb/>.21*** <lb/>0.00 2356789 <lb/>0.64 1 <lb/>0.53 1 <lb/>0.39 79 <lb/>0.70 1 <lb/>0.80 1 <lb/>1.04 14 <lb/>0.69 1 <lb/>1.04 14 <lb/>Similar-aged sibling <lb/>.28*** <lb/>0.00 356789 <lb/>0.36 789 <lb/>0.38 1789 <lb/>0.25 789 <lb/>0.59 1 <lb/>0.49 1789 <lb/>1.03 12346 <lb/>0.97 12346 <lb/>1.03 12346 <lb/>Child activity level <lb/>.12 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.26 8 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>-0.33 8 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.20 36 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Child distress to limitations <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 356 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.48 1 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>0.53 1 <lb/>0.45 1 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>Child soothability <lb/>.10 <lb/>0.00 8 <lb/>-0.28 <lb/>-0.05 8 <lb/>0.02 8 <lb/>-0.28 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.49 134 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>Standardized means comparisons with pairwise contrasts for effects of trajectory on distal outcomes c <lb/>Externalizing <lb/>.22*** <lb/>0.00 23456789 <lb/>0.33 17 <lb/>0.35 17 <lb/>0.40 1 <lb/>0.47 1 <lb/>0.62 1 <lb/>0.88 123 <lb/>0.52 1 <lb/>0.53 1 <lb/>Internalizing <lb/>.09 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>Academic competence <lb/>.16 <lb/>0.00 9 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>-0.20 9 <lb/>-0.02 9 <lb/>0.07 9 <lb/>-0.09 9 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>-0.84 13456 <lb/>Social skills <lb/>.12 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.12 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.36 <lb/>-0.32 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>-0.55 <lb/>*p &lt; .05 <lb/>**p &lt; .01 <lb/>***p &lt; .001 for overall effects. <lb/>a <lb/>Pseudo-R/R estimate with overall significance test from Table 4. <lb/>b Trajectory prediction contrast coefficients are fully standardized logistic regression effects on the log odds scale (the effect on the log odds of the class contrast for a <lb/>change in the predictor of one standard deviation) given relative to membership in Trajectory 1 (the &quot;no aggression&quot; trajectory). Coefficients were standardized by <lb/>sample standard deviations (Table 1). Contrast coefficients between any pair of trajectories can be derived by subtraction (i.e., for couple relationship [reversed] between <lb/>Trajectories 6 and 4: 0.17-[-0.40] = 0.57, which is significant at p &lt; .05 as indicated by superscripts). A contrast coefficient of 0.69 is equivalent to an odds ratio of 2.0, <lb/>and a coefficient of -0.69 is equivalent to an odds ratio of 0.5. <lb/>c <lb/>The entries are standardized mean differences relative to Trajectory 1. <lb/>123456789 <lb/>Number superscripts indicate pairwise contrast tests significant at p &lt; .05 between the indexed trajectory and the trajectory with the superscripts&apos; number; <lb/>significant contrasts are superscripted for both involved trajectories. Contrast tests are not adjusted for mass significance; the chance expected number out of 36 pairwise <lb/>contrasts at p &lt; .05 would be 1.8 per variable, or 3.6 numbered subscripts per table row, in the case of null association. In the presence of a significant overall effect, <lb/>contrast tests may aid effect direction interpretation; in the absence of a significant overall effect, significance superscripts alone should not be taken as suggesting an <lb/>effect limited to a few classes <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>The proportion of children belonging to the high-stable trajectory, however, varies across <lb/>studies. For instance, in accordance with our findings, the SECCYD [22] found a high-stable <lb/>group from 2 to 9 years of age, constituting 3% of their sample (N = 1195), with the poorest <lb/>academic and social functioning through 12 years of age [15, 16]. Additionally, Wildeboer <lb/>et al. [19] identified a high-increasing trajectory across 1.5, 3, and 6 years of age for 3% of the <lb/>children (N = 4781). Moreover, Joussemet et al. [26] reported a high trajectory group from <lb/>kindergarten to sixth grade comprising 6% of their sample (N = 1508), whereas Tremblay et al. <lb/>[12] reported that 13.9% (N = 572) of the participants followed an increasing trajectory from <lb/>17 to 42 months of age. Finally, Co ˆte ´et al. [10] reported that as much as 16.6% (N = 10658) of <lb/>the participants followed a high-stable trajectory between 2 and 11 years of age, which <lb/>appeared to include the two highest trajectory groups (i.e., moderate and high) in the SEC-<lb/>CYD, explaining the high prevalence. <lb/>With respect to the lower end of the aggression spectrum, the SECCYD [22], found a very-<lb/>low trajectory group accounting for 45% of the children and a low trajectory group accounting <lb/>for 25%. In our sample, the low-stable or no aggression group (1), medium-peak and low end-<lb/>point groups (2, 3), and high-start and low-endpoint aggression groups (4, 5), all with low <lb/>aggression endpoints at the age of 5 years, albeit with differing developmental patterns, may <lb/>quantitatively (in all 64%) correspond to some larger very-low or low trajectories, such as <lb/>those identified in the SECCYD [22]. Such a comparison may be even more reasonable consid-<lb/>ering that the SECCYD did not start until 2 years of age, after which physical aggression <lb/>diminishes among most children, particularly those engaging in low levels of aggression. <lb/>Early predictors of TPA (unadjusted) <lb/>Our set of nine trajectories revealed more diversity in predictor-trajectory patterns than a less <lb/>fine-grained classification into fewer developmental patterns might have revealed. All child <lb/>characteristics (gender and temperament) predicted TPA in the unadjusted results, along with <lb/>sibling presence, maternal education level, couple relationship, depression and anxiety in both <lb/>parents, and harsh parenting. Exploration of the finer distinctions in predictor-trajectory effect <lb/>patterns may provide some clues for what makes children follow particular trajectories. For <lb/>example, while the intermediate-endpoint and high-stable Trajectories 6-9 shared many pre-<lb/>dictors, the predictor-trajectory contrasts seemed to suggest some possibly important effect-<lb/>pattern differences. High maternal harsh parenting and low child soothability were associated <lb/>with membership in Trajectory 8 (rather than 9, 6, or 7, the other high end point trajectories). <lb/>This might suggest that Trajectory 8 was somewhat more driven by child temperament and <lb/>heated mother-child interactions, which is in line with the established knowledge that chil-<lb/>dren&apos;s temperamental characteristics are associated with the development of externalizing <lb/>problems [60] and with the abovementioned differential susceptibility model postulating that <lb/>children with difficult temperament are more vulnerable to negative parenting behavior than <lb/>those with easy temperament [55, 57, 58]. Additionally, higher maternal and paternal educa-<lb/>tion levels were associated with membership in Trajectories 6 and 7 (rather than 8 and 9). This <lb/>may indicate that parental resourcefulness can function as a protective factor against the high-<lb/>stable aggression pattern even in the presence of other shared risk factors. <lb/>Furthermore, the prediction patterns for the two declining-aggression Trajectories 4 and 5 <lb/>are interesting to note. Higher child activity level and distress to limitations (relative to Trajec-<lb/>tory 1) and high sensitivity in one parent (relative to several other trajectories in the absence of <lb/>an overall significant predictor effect but with large magnitudes exceeding a log odds change <lb/>of 0.70 corresponding to an odds ratio of 2.1 for all significant pairwise contrasts, Table 3) pre-<lb/>dicted membership in these trajectories. This might suggest that parental sensitivity moderates <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>or mitigates aggression development in children with difficult infant temperament, which is in <lb/>accordance with the differential susceptibility model [55, 57, 58]. <lb/>Nonreplicated early predictors of TPA or grade 2 outcomes <lb/>Among predictors identified by previous research, neither being a single parent nor being a <lb/>young mother or father was significantly related to trajectory (although each had direct asso-<lb/>ciations with one or more outcomes in the unadjusted results). The reason for nonreplication <lb/>is probably the low proportion of single parents in our sample when the child was aged 1 year, <lb/>as well as the low proportion of young mothers (� 25 years old), given the low prevalence of <lb/>teenage mothers in Norway and the high mean age for primiparous women (i.e., 30.1 years in <lb/>2021 [80]). <lb/>Parental sensitivity also did not overall predict TPA. This finding merits some attention, <lb/>not least considering that self-reported harsh parenting practices for mothers and fathers alike <lb/>were among the strongest predictors of TPA. As previously noted [69], the null findings in the <lb/>present sample may be partly related to the fact that the parents displayed low levels of aversive <lb/>or negative parenting behaviors overall during the interactions since the sample was popula-<lb/>tion based (versus clinical), the interactions were short, and the tasks were not designed to <lb/>induce conflict or elicit negative parenting. Thus, limited variability in the observed parenting <lb/>behavior may have contributed to the weak associations. This contrasts with the results from <lb/>the SECCYD [22], which indicated that less sensitive and involved maternal parenting was <lb/>associated with higher and more stable TPA from toddlerhood to middle childhood. However, <lb/>that study had access to comprehensive observational data at several ages across infancy and <lb/>third grade. <lb/>Fully adjusted models <lb/>As expected, there were notably fewer significant predictor-trajectory, trajectory-outcome, <lb/>and predictor-outcome relationships in the fully adjusted set of results than in the unadjusted <lb/>set. While this may seem dramatic, it is crucial to acknowledge that the fully adjusted model, <lb/>which is the benchmark test for identifying the most proximal predictors, constituted a rigor-<lb/>ous test of all possible simultaneous effects. Importantly, net of all other effects, TPA still pre-<lb/>dicted externalizing problems and academic competence in Grade 2. Within this context, it <lb/>may be worth noting that the high-stable trajectory specifically predicted poor academic com-<lb/>petence, while the no-aggression trajectory contrasted most strongly with all other groups with <lb/>respect to low externalizing problems. Taken together, these results both support and extend <lb/>previous research strongly suggesting that early maternal and paternal harsh parenting prac-<lb/>tices, child gender, and sibling presence, consistently predict physical aggression development <lb/>from 1 to 5 years of age after adjustment for all other predictors. <lb/>The importance of harsh parenting practices in predicting children&apos;s physical aggression <lb/>corresponds with previous findings including mothers only [10, 12, 16, 26] and generally with <lb/>the mentioned theories about the development of aggression and externalizing problems, par-<lb/>ticularly Patterson&apos;s [45] coercion theory. This is the first study addressing developmental pat-<lb/>terns of physical aggression from infancy to preschool age by applying a trajectory approach to <lb/>link early paternal as well as maternal harsh parenting with the development of aggression. <lb/>Previous research [10, 12, 16, 26] has not explored this association due to a lack of data on <lb/>fathers&apos; parenting behaviors. Our results underscore the significance of fathers&apos; harsh parent-<lb/>ing behaviors in infancy for children&apos;s subsequent development of physical aggression and are <lb/>in line with a limited but growing body of literature highlighting the significance of paternal <lb/>parenting for children&apos;s and youth&apos;s development [47-48, 81]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>In line with the established knowledge that parenting behaviors typically associated with <lb/>the development of externalizing behaviors tend to coappear with parental psychopathology <lb/>[82-84], it is theoretically and empirically sound to view the pattern of predictor-trajectory <lb/>influences in our unadjusted and adjusted results from the perspective that factors such as <lb/>parental depression and anxiety, couple relationship troubles, and difficult child temperament <lb/>do not affect aggression development, unless they are associated with an increase in harsh par-<lb/>enting practices. <lb/>Regarding predictor-outcome effects, early financial stress had a consistent impact on <lb/>three Grade 2 teacher-rated outcomes (externalizing, internalizing, and social skills). This is <lb/>notable considering the crude measure used (i.e., a single-item dichotomous self-report). <lb/>Family financial stress when the child is approximately one year old may thus have long-last-<lb/>ing or continuing effects on social and behavioral functioning. Nevertheless, this may not <lb/>relate specifically to the development of physical aggression (the predictor had no significant <lb/>effect on trajectory in any set of findings). This result highlights the well-established finding <lb/>linking socioeconomic conditions to a range of child behavioral outcomes [37, 38]. At the <lb/>same time, some previous research has shown that low family income is a risk factor for <lb/>more frequent and stable use of physical aggression across early childhood and adolescence <lb/>[4, 10, 12]. We have no clear opinion as to why our results did not replicate such findings, <lb/>but possible explanations could be differences between countries/cultures with a smaller <lb/>income range and a smaller proportion of families in serious financial hardship in Scandina-<lb/>via than in North America and Canada, variations in age span, the use of financial stress as <lb/>an indicator of financial risk as opposed to low family income, and the crude nature of our <lb/>measure. <lb/>Limitations and suggestions for future research <lb/>Our study is limited in several ways, some of which are worth noting. The study design did not <lb/>permit the disentangling of genetic predispositions and we did not obtain measures of parents&apos; <lb/>aggressive or antisocial behavior when they were children or youths. The estimated reliability <lb/>of the self-reported harsh parenting practices measure was less than desirable. Additionally, <lb/>due to the study design, only subsets of fathers and mothers provided such reports at 1 year. <lb/>Under these circumstances, null findings are uninformative, whereas significant results (e.g., <lb/>prediction of TPA and distal outcomes based on harsh parenting practices) signal true effects <lb/>that are large enough to be detected with the given sample, although attenuated and less pre-<lb/>cisely estimated. <lb/>The included predictors were all time-invariant; we did not model time-varying or interme-<lb/>diate-timepoint predictor influence as the study progressed (e.g., harsh parenting, financial <lb/>stress, or new siblings). Finally, as in most previous research, we studied each outcome in isola-<lb/>tion, not addressing possible comorbidities or overlaps. However, TPA may well predict cer-<lb/>tain multivariate outcome configurations or profiles. Similarly, we did not study the effects of <lb/>profiles of predictors. <lb/>Future research should focus on the potentially intricate interplay of predictors, including <lb/>gender-moderating effects and relevant interaction effects among predictors (e.g., parental <lb/>depression, harsh parenting practices, child gender and the number of siblings). For example, <lb/>it is easy to imagine that squabbling among siblings could amplify harsh parenting practices. <lb/>Research should also address trajectory and predictor effects on profiles of outcomes rather <lb/>than single outcomes in isolation and effects of predictor profiles rather than of single <lb/>predictors. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Conclusions <lb/>Understanding common and less common developmental patterns of physical aggression, the <lb/>link with subsequent social, behavioral, and academic functioning, and markers for the various <lb/>patterns is crucial for early prevention and intervention efforts. The results of our study con-<lb/>firm and expand previous research in underscoring the importance of addressing harsh par-<lb/>enting practices as an influence on developmental pathways of physical aggression during <lb/>infancy and toddlerhood. Our findings also support the notion that fathers matter and must <lb/>be included both in research and early prevention and intervention efforts. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Appendix. Physical aggression questionnaire and telephone interview schedule. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Appendix. Scaling of the physical aggression measure. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S3 Appendix. Ratings of parent sensitivity from videotaped parent-child structured inter-<lb/>action tasks. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S4 Appendix. Attrition. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S5 Appendix. Additional comparisons of 2-10 trajectory solutions. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S6 Appendix. Details of the 9-trajectory solution. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Fig. Loess plot of average child physical aggression by child age. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Trajectory plots for 2-9 trajectory solutions. Note. Panels A-I graph 4th grade poly-<lb/>nomial solutions for the 2 to 10-trajectory solutions, respectively. Age in years centered at 2.2 <lb/>years is given on the X-axis of each panel. The Y-axis labeled eqtrfe represents the Rasch-scaled <lb/>physical aggression. The number labels of the trajectories shift as a result of random starts in <lb/>the estimations, and in the 9-class solution in Panel H the numbering of trajectories is not the <lb/>same as in the manuscript. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We are very grateful to the participating families and to the research assistants who contrib-<lb/>uted to the data collection. We thank Elisabeth Askeland and Anett Apeland for their contri-<lb/>bution to the development of the physical aggression measure. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson. <lb/>Data curation: Harald Janson, Mike Stoolmiller. <lb/>Formal analysis: Harald Janson, Mike Stoolmiller. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Funding acquisition: Ane Naerde. <lb/>Investigation: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson. <lb/>Methodology: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson, Mike Stoolmiller. <lb/>Project administration: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson. <lb/>Resources: Ane Naerde. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Ane Naerde, Harald Janson, Mike Stoolmiller. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Tremblay RE. The development of aggressive behavior during childhood: What have we learned in the <lb/>past century? International Journal of Behavioral Development. 2000; 24(2). https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>016502500383232 <lb/>2. Tremblay RE, Japel CJ, Perusse D, Mcduff P, Boivin M, Zoccolillo M, et al. The search for the age of <lb/>&quot;onset&quot; of physical aggression: Rousseau and Bandura revisited. Criminal Behaviour and Mental <lb/>Health. 1999; 9(1), 8-23. https://doi.org/10.1002/cbm.288 <lb/>3. Tremblay R. E., Nagin D. S., Se ´guin J. R., Zoccolillo M., Zelazo P. D., Boivin M, et al (2004). Physical <lb/>aggression during early childhood: Trajectories and predictors. Pediatrics, 114, 43-50. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1542/peds.114.1.e43 PMID: 15231972 <lb/>4. Teymoori A, Co ˆte ´S, Jones B, Nagin D, Boivin M, Vitaro F, et al. Risk factors associated with boys&apos; and <lb/>girls&apos; developmental trajectories of physical aggression from early childhood through early adolescence. <lb/>JAMA network open. 2018; 1(8), Article e186364. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.6364 <lb/>PMID: 30646329 <lb/>5. Alink LRA, Mesman J, Van Zeijl J, Stolk MN, Juffer F, Koot HM, et al. The early childhood aggression <lb/>curve: Development of physical aggression in 10-to 50-month-old children. Child Development. 2006; <lb/>77(4), 954-966. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8624.2006.00912.x PMID: 16942499 <lb/>6. Lorber MF, Del Vecchio T, Slep AMS. The development of individual physically aggressive behaviors <lb/>from infancy to toddlerhood. Developmental Psychology. 2018; 54(4), 601-612. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1037/dev0000450 PMID: 29154658 <lb/>7. Hay DF. The early development of human aggression. Child Development Perspectives. 2017; 11(2), <lb/>102-106. https://doi.org/10.1111/cdep.12220 <lb/>8. Lorber MF, Del Vecchio T, Slep AMS. The emergence and evolution of infant externalizing behavior. <lb/>Development and Psychopathology. 2015; 27(3), 663-680. https://doi.org/10.1017/ <lb/>S0954579414000923 PMID: 25212988 <lb/>9. Lorber MF, Del Vecchio T, Slep AM, Scholer SJ. Normative trends in physically aggressive behavior: <lb/>Age-aggression curves from 6 to 24 months. The Journal of Pediatrics. 2019; 206, 197-203. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.jpeds.2018.10.025 PMID: 30429080 <lb/>10. Co ˆte ´SM, Vaillancourt T, LeBlanc JC, Nagin DS, Tremblay RE. The development of physical aggression <lb/>from toddlerhood to pre-adolescence: A nationwide longitudinal study of Canadian children. Journal of <lb/>Abnormal Child Psychology. 2006; 34(1), 68-82. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10802-005-9001-z PMID: <lb/>16565888 <lb/>11. Naerde A, Ogden T, Janson H, Zachrisson HD. Normative development of physical aggression from 8 <lb/>to 26 months. Developmental Psychology. 2014; 50(6), 1710-1720. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0036324 <lb/>PMID: 24708457 <lb/>12. Tremblay RE, Nagin DS, Se ´guin JR, Zoccolillo M, Zelazo PD, Boivin M, et al. Physical aggression dur-<lb/>ing early childhood: Trajectories and predictors. Pediatrics. 2004; 114(1), 43-50. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1542/peds.114.1.e43 PMID: 15231972 <lb/>13. Baillargeon RH, Zoccolillo M, Keenan K, Co ˆte ´S, Pe ´russe D, Wu HX, et al. Gender differences in physi-<lb/>cal aggression: A prospective population-based survey of children before and after 2 years of age. <lb/>Developmental Psychology. 2007; 43(1), 13-26. https://doi.org/10.1037/0012-1649.43.1.13 PMID: <lb/>17201505 <lb/>14. Broidy LM, Nagin DS, Tremblay RE, Bates J, Brame B, Dodge KA, et al. Developmental trajectories of <lb/>childhood disruptive behaviors and adolescent delinquency: A six-site, cross-national study. Develop-<lb/>mental Psychology. 2003; 39(2), 222-245. https://doi.org/10.1037//0012-1649.39.2.222 PMID: <lb/>12661883 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>15. Campbell SB, Spieker S, Burchinal M, Poe MD, The NICHD Early Child Care Research Network. Tra-<lb/>jectories of aggression from toddlerhood to age 9 predict academic and social functioning through age <lb/>12. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 2006; 47(8), 791-800. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-<lb/>7610.2006.01636.x PMID: 16898993 <lb/>16. Campbell SB, Spieker S, Vandergrift N, Belsky J, Burchinal M, The NICHD Early Child Care Research <lb/>Network. Predictors and sequelae of trajectories of physical aggression in school-age boys and girls. <lb/>Development and Psychopathology. 2010; 22(1), 133-150. https://doi.org/10.1017/ <lb/>S0954579409990319 PMID: 20102652 <lb/>17. Fontaine N, Carbonnea R, Barker ED, Vitaro F, He ´bert M, Co ˆte ´SM, et al. Girls&apos; hyperactivity and physi-<lb/>cal aggression during childhood and adjustment problems in early adulthood: A 15-year longitudinal <lb/>study. Archives of General Psychiatry. 2008; 65(3), 320-328. https://doi.org/10.1001/ <lb/>archgenpsychiatry.2007.41 PMID: 18316678 <lb/>18. Nagin D, Tremblay RE. Trajectories of boys&apos; physical aggression, opposition, and hyperactivity on the <lb/>path to physically violent and nonviolent juvenile delinquency. Child Development. 1999; 70(5), 1181-<lb/>1196. https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-8624.00086 PMID: 10546339 <lb/>19. Wildeboer A, Thijssen S, Van IJzendoorn MH, Van Der Ende J, Jaddoe VW, Verhulst FC, et al. Early <lb/>childhood aggression trajectories: Associations with teacher-reported problem behaviour. International <lb/>Journal of Behavioral Development. 2015; 39(3), 221-234. https://doi.org/10.1177/0165025414562239 <lb/>20. Co ˆte ´SM, Vaillancourt T, Barker ED, Nagin D, Tremblay RE. The joint development of physical and indi-<lb/>rect aggression: Predictors of continuity and change during childhood. Development and psychopathol-<lb/>ogy. 2007; 19(1), 37-55. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954579407070034 PMID: 17241483 <lb/>21. Co ˆte ´SM, Boivin M, Nagin DS, Japel C, Xu Q, Zoccolillo M, et al. The role of maternal education and <lb/>nonmaternal care services in the prevention of children&apos;s physical aggression problems. Archives of <lb/>General Psychiatry. 2007; 64(11), 1305-1312. https://doi.org/10.1001/archpsyc.64.11.1305 PMID: <lb/>17984399 <lb/>22. NICHD Early Child Care Research Network. Trajectories of physical aggression from toddlerhood to <lb/>middle childhood: Predictors, correlates and outcomes. Monographs of the Society for Research in <lb/>Child Development. 2004; 69(4), vii-129. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0037-976x.2004.00312.x PMID: <lb/>15667346 <lb/>23. Jennings WG, Reingle JM. On the number and shape of developmental/life-course violence, aggres-<lb/>sion, and delinquency trajectories: A state-of-the-art review. Journal of Criminal Justice. 2012; 40(6), <lb/>472-489. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcrimjus.2012.07.001 <lb/>24. Archer J, Co ˆte ´S. Sex differences in aggressive behavior: a developmental and evolutionary perspec-<lb/>tive. In: Tremblay RE, Hartup WW, Archer J, editors. Developmental Origins of Aggression. New York: <lb/>Guilford Press; 2005. p. 425-43. <lb/>25. Jambon M, Madigan S, Plamondon A, Jenkins J. Developmental trajectories of physical aggression <lb/>and prosocial behavior in early childhood: Family antecedents and psychological correlates. Devel-<lb/>opmental Psychology. 2019; 55(6), 1211-1225. https://doi.org/10.1037/dev0000714 PMID: <lb/>30945885 <lb/>26. Joussemet M, Vitaro F, Barker ED, Co ˆte ´S, Nagin DS, Zoccolillo M, et al. Controlling parenting and <lb/>physical aggression during elementary school. Child Development. 2008; 79(2), 411-425. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1111/j.1467-8624.2007.01133.x PMID: 18366431 <lb/>27. Nagin DS, Tremblay RE. Parental and early childhood predictors of persistent physical aggression in <lb/>boys from kindergarten to high school. Archives of General psychiatry. 2001; 58(4), 389-394. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1001/archpsyc.58.4.389 PMID: 11296100 <lb/>28. van Adrichem DS, Huijbregts SC, van der Heijden KB, Van Goozen SH, Swaab H. The role of inhibitory <lb/>control, attention and vocabulary in physical aggression trajectories from infancy to toddlerhood. Fron-<lb/>tiers in Psychology. 2020; 11, 1079. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01079 PMID: 32528388 <lb/>29. Hay DF, Waters CS, Perra O, Swift N, Jones R, Jones I, et al. Precursors to aggressive conduct prob-<lb/>lems are evident by six months of age. Developmental Science. 2014; 17(3), 471-480. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1111/desc.12133 <lb/>30. Labella MH, Masten AS. Family influences on the development of aggression and violence. Current <lb/>Opinion in Psychology. 2018; 19, 11-16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2017.03.028 PMID: <lb/>29279207 <lb/>31. Brendgen M, Dionne G, Girard A, Boivin M, Vitaro F, Pe ´russe D. Examining genetic and environmental <lb/>effects on social aggression: A study of 6-year-old twins. Child Development. 2005; 76(4), 930-946. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8624.2005.00887.x PMID: 16026506 <lb/>32. Dionne G, Tremblay R, Boivin M, Laplante D, Pe ´russe D. Physical aggression and expressive vocabu-<lb/>lary in 19-month-old twins. Developmental Psychology. 2003; 39(2), 261-273. https://doi.org/10.1037// <lb/>0012-1649.39.2.261 PMID: 12661885 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>33. Tremblay RE, Vitaro F, Co ˆte ´SM. Developmental origins of chronic physical aggression: a bio-psycho-<lb/>social model for the next generation of preventive interventions. Annual Review of Psychology. 2018; <lb/>69(1), 383-407. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-010416-044030 PMID: 29035692 <lb/>34. Tremblay RE. Developmental origins of chronic physical aggression: An international perspective on <lb/>using singletons, twins and epigenetics. European Journal of Criminology. 2015; 12(5), 551-561. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/1477370815600617 <lb/>35. Huijbregts SC, Seguin JR, Zoccolillo M, Boivin M, Tremblay RE. Maternal prenatal smoking, parental <lb/>antisocial behavior, and early childhood physical aggression. Development and Psychopathology. <lb/>2008; 20(2), 437-453. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954579408000217 PMID: 18423088 <lb/>36. Kinge JM, Øverland S, Flatø M, Dieleman J, Røgeberg O, Magnus MC, et al. Parental income and men-<lb/>tal disorders in children and adolescents: prospective register-based study. International Journal of Epi-<lb/>demiology. 2021; 50(5), 1615-1627. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyab066 PMID: 33975355 <lb/>37. Peverill M, Dirks MA, Narvaja T, Herts KL, Comer JS, McLaughlin KA. Socioeconomic status and child <lb/>psychopathology in the United States: A meta-analysis of population-based studies. Clinical Psychol-<lb/>ogy Review. 2021; 83, 101933. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2020.101933 PMID: 33278703 <lb/>38. Masarik AS, Conger RD. Stress and child development: A review of the Family Stress Model. Current <lb/>Opinion in Psychology. 2017; 13, 85-90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2016.05.008 PMID: 28813301 <lb/>39. Dunn J, Munn P. Sibling quarrels and maternal intervention: Individual differences in understanding and <lb/>aggression. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 1986; 27(5), 583-595. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1111/j.1469-7610.1986.tb00184.x PMID: 3771676 <lb/>40. Garcia MM, Shaw DS, Winslow EB, Yaggi KE. Destructive sibling conflict and the development of con-<lb/>duct problems in young boys. Developmental Psychology. 2000; 36(1), 44-53. https://doi.org/10.1037/ <lb/>0012-1649.36.1.44 PMID: 10645743 <lb/>41. Patterson GR. Siblings: Fellow travelers in coercive family processes. In: Blanchard RJ, editor. <lb/>Advances in the study of aggression New York: Academic Press; 1984. p. 174-213. <lb/>42. Olson SL, Ip KI, Gonzalez R, Beyers-Carlson EE, Volling BL. Development of externalizing symptoms <lb/>across the toddler period: The critical role of older siblings. Journal of Family Psychology. 2020; 34(2), <lb/>165-174. https://doi.org/10.1037/fam0000581 PMID: 31403811 <lb/>43. Patterson G. R. The contribution of siblings to training for fighting: A microsocial analysis. In: Olweus D, <lb/>Block J, Radke-Yarrow M, editors. Development of antisocial and prosocial behavior: Research, theo-<lb/>ries, and issues. Orlando, Florida: Academic; 1986, p. 235-261. <lb/>44. Caspi J. Sibling aggression: Assessment and treatment. New York, NY: Springer; 2012. <lb/>45. Patterson GR. The early development of coercive family processes. In: Reid JB, Patterson GR, Snyder <lb/>J, editors. Antisocial behavior in children and adolescents: A developmental analysis and model for <lb/>intervention. American Psychological Association; 2002. p. 25-44. <lb/>46. Shaw DS, Winslow EB, Owens EB, Vondra JI, Cohn JF, Bell RQ. The development of early externaliz-<lb/>ing problems among children from low-income families: A transformational perspective. Journal of <lb/>Abnormal Child Psychology. 1998; 26(2), 95-107. https://doi.org/10.1023/a:1022665704584 PMID: <lb/>9634132 <lb/>47. Yang P, Schlomer GL, Lippold MA. Mothering versus fathering? Positive parenting versus negative par-<lb/>enting? Their relative importance in predicting adolescent aggressive behavior: A longitudinal compari-<lb/>son. Developmental psychology. 2022; 59(1), 69-83. https://doi.org/10.1037/dev0001442 PMID: <lb/>36074588 <lb/>48. Cabrera NJ, Volling BL, Barr R. Fathers are parents, too! Widening the lens on parenting for children&apos;s <lb/>development. Child Development Perspectives. 2018; 12(3), 152-157. https://doi.org/10.1111/cdep. <lb/>12275 <lb/>49. Cabrera NJ. Father involvement, father-child relationship, and attachment in the early years. Attach-<lb/>ment &amp; Human development. 2020; 22(1), 134-138. https://doi.org/10.1080/14616734.2019.1589070 <lb/>PMID: 30968742 <lb/>50. Sullivan O, Coltrane S, McAnnally L, Altintas E. Father-friendly policies and time-use data in a cross-<lb/>national context: Potential and prospects for future research. The Annals of the American Academy of <lb/>Political and Social Science, 2009; 624(1), 234-254. https://doi.org/10.1177/0002716209335138 <lb/>51. Hay DF. The gradual emergence of sex differences in aggression: alternative hypotheses. Psychologi-<lb/>cal Medicine. 2007; 37(11), 1527-1537. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291707000165 PMID: 17335642 <lb/>52. Hay DF. The beginnings of aggression in infancy. In: Tremblay RE, Hartup WW, Archer J, editors. <lb/>Developmental origins of aggression. New York: Guilford Press; 2005. p. 107-132. <lb/>53. Co ˆte ´SM. Sex differences in physical and indirect aggression: A developmental perspective. European <lb/>Journal on Criminal Policy and Research. 2007; 13(3), 183-200. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10610-007-<lb/>9046-3 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>54. Card NA, Stucky BD, Sawalani GM, Little TD. Direct and indirect aggression during childhood and ado-<lb/>lescence: A meta-analytic review of gender differences, intercorrelations, and relations to maladjust-<lb/>ment. Child Development 2008; 79(5), 1185-1229. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8624.2008.01184.x <lb/>PMID: 18826521 <lb/>55. van Zeijl J, Mesman J, Stolk MN, Alink LR, Van IJzendoorn MH, Bakermans-Kranenburg MJ, et al. Dif-<lb/>ferential susceptibility to discipline: the moderating effect of child temperament on the association <lb/>between maternal discipline and early childhood externalizing problems. Journal of Family Psychology. <lb/>2007; 21(4), 626-636. https://doi.org/10.1037/0893-3200.21.4.626 PMID: 18179334 <lb/>56. Vitaro F, Barker ED, Boivin M, Brendgen M, Tremblay RE. Do early difficult temperament and harsh par-<lb/>enting differentially predict reactive and proactive aggression? Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology. <lb/>2006; 34(5), 681-691. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10802-006-9055-6 PMID: 17048109 <lb/>57. Belsky J. Theory testing, effect-size evaluation, and differential susceptibility to rearing influence: The <lb/>case of mothering and attachment. Child Development. 1997; 68(4), 598-600. https://doi.org/10.1111/ <lb/>j.1467-8624.1997.tb04221.x PMID: 9306638 <lb/>58. Belsky J, Hsieh KH, Crnic K. Mothering, fathering, and infant negativity as antecedents of boys&apos; exter-<lb/>nalizing problems and inhibition at age 3 years: Differential susceptibility to rearing experience? Devel-<lb/>opment and Psychopathology. 1998; 10(2), 301-319. https://doi.org/10.1017/s095457949800162x <lb/>PMID: 9635226 <lb/>59. Campbell SB, Shaw DS, Gilliom M. Early externalizing behavior problems: Toddlers and preschoolers <lb/>at risk for later maladjustment. Development and Psychopathology 2000; 12(3), 467-488. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1017/s0954579400003114 PMID: 11014748 <lb/>60. Slagt M, Dubas JS, Deković M, van Aken MA. Differences in sensitivity to parenting depending on child <lb/>temperament: A meta-analysis. Psychological Bulletin. 2016; 142(10), 1068-1110. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1037/bul0000061 PMID: 27513919 <lb/>61. Asparouhov T, Muthe ´n B. Auxiliary variables in mixture modeling: Three-step approaches using Mplus. <lb/>Structural Equation Modeling. 2014; 21(3), 329-341. https://doi.org/10.1080/10705511.2014.915181 <lb/>62. Naerde A, Janson H, Ogden T. BONDS (The Behavior Outlook Norwegian Developmental Study): A <lb/>prospective longitudinal study of early development of social competence and behavior problems. Oslo: <lb/>The Norwegian Center for Child Behavioral Development; 2014. Report. ISBN 978-82-93406-00-6. <lb/>63. Janson H, Bringedal, GE, Naerde A. A flowchart of participation and collected data across 15 years of <lb/>The Behavior Outlook Norwegian Developmental Study (BONDS). Oslo, Norway: The Norwegian Cen-<lb/>ter for Child Behavioral Development; 2023. Report. https://www.nubu.no/getfile.php/1323354-<lb/>1687432522/Filer/nubu.no/Intranett/Dokumenter/Rapporter/2023%20Report%20BONDS% <lb/>20Participation.pdf <lb/>64. Bond TG, Fox CM. Applying the Rasch model: Fundamental measurement in the human sciences ( 3rd <lb/>ed.). Routledge; 2015. <lb/>65. Blum JS, Mehrabian A. Personality and temperament correlates of marital satisfaction. Journal of Per-<lb/>sonality. 1999; 67(1), 93-125. <lb/>66. Winokur A, Winokur DF, Rickels K, Cox DS. Symptoms of emotional distress in a family planning ser-<lb/>vice: Stability over a four-week period. British Journal of Psychiatry. 1984; 144(4), 395-399. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1192/bjp.144.4.395 PMID: 6722401 <lb/>67. Tambs K, Moum T. How well can a few questionnaire items indicate anxiety and depression? Acta Psy-<lb/>chiatrica Scandinavica. 1993; 87(5), 364-367. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0447.1993.tb03388.x <lb/>PMID: 8517178 <lb/>68. Cox MJ, Crnic K. Qualitative ratings for parent-child interaction at 3-12 months of age. Unpublished <lb/>manuscript. Department of Psychology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; 2003. <lb/>69. Nordahl KB. Early father-child interaction in a father-friendly context: Gender differences, child out-<lb/>comes, and predictive factors related to fathers&apos; parenting behaviors with one-year-olds [dissertation]. <lb/>University of Bergen, Norway; 2014. <lb/>70. Loeber R, Stouthamer-Loeber M, Van Kammen W, Farrington D. Initiation, escalation and desistance in <lb/>juvenile offending and their correlates. Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology. 1991; 82(1), 36-82. <lb/>71. Thornberry T, Huizinga D, Loeber R. The prevention of serious delinquency and violence: Implications <lb/>from the Program of Research on the Causes and Correlates of Delinquency. In: Howell J, Krisberg B, <lb/>Hawking D, Wilson JD, editors. Sourcebook on serious, violent and chronic juvenile offenders Sage; <lb/>1995. p. 213-327. <lb/>72. Gartstein MA, Rothbart MK. Studying infant temperament via the Revised Infant Behavior Questionnaire. <lb/>Infant Behavior &amp; Development. 2003; 26(1), 64-86. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0163-6383(02)00169-8 <lb/>73. Rothbart MK. Measurement of temperament in infancy. Child Development. 1981; 52(2), 569-578. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2307/1129176 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>74. Gresham FM, Elliott SN. Social Skills Improvement System: Rating scales. Bloomington, MN: Pearson <lb/>Assessments 2008. <lb/>75. Muthe ´n B. Latent variable hybrids: Overview of old and new models. In: Hancock GR, Samuelsen KM, <lb/>editors. Advances in latent variable mixture models. Charlotte, NC: Information Age Publishing, Inc; <lb/>2008. p. 1-24. <lb/>76. Nagelkerke NJ. A note on a general definition of the coefficient of determination. Biometrika. 1991; 78 <lb/>(3), 691-692. <lb/>77. Dziak JJ, Lanza ST, Tan X. Effect size, statistical power and sample size requirements for the bootstrap <lb/>likelihood ratio test in latent class analysis. Structural Equation Modeling. 2014; 21(4): 534-552. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1080/10705511.2014.919819 PMID: 25328371 <lb/>78. McLachlan G, Peel D. Finite Mixture Models. New York, NY: John Wiley and Sons Inc 2000. <lb/>79. Nylund K, Asparouhov T, Muthen BO. Deciding on the number of classes in latent class analysis and <lb/>growth mixture modeling: A Monte Carlo simulation study. Structural Equation Modeling. 2007; 14(4), <lb/>535-569. https://doi.org/10.1080/10705510701575396 <lb/>80. Andersen E. Økt fruktbarhet for første gang på 12 år (Increased fertility for the first time in 12 years). <lb/>Statistics Norway 2022, March 9. https://www.ssb.no/befolkning/fodte-og-dode/statistikk/fodte/artikler/ <lb/>okt-fruktbarhet-for-forste-gang-pa-12-ar. <lb/>81. Rodrigues M, Sokolovic N, Madigan S, Luo Y, Silva V, Misra S. et al. Paternal sensitivity and children&apos;s <lb/>cognitive and socioemotional outcomes: A meta-analytic review. Child Development. 2021; 92(2), 554-<lb/>577. https://doi.org/10.1111/cdev.13545 PMID: 33511634 <lb/>82. Goodman SH, Rouse MH, Connell AM, Broth MR, Hall CM, Heyward D. Maternal depression and child <lb/>psychopathology: A meta-analytic review. Clinical Child and Family Psychology Review. 2011; 14(1), <lb/>1-27. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10567-010-0080-1 PMID: 21052833 <lb/>83. Wilson S, Durbin CE. Effects of paternal depression on fathers&apos; parenting behaviors: A meta-analytic <lb/>review. Clinical Psychology Review. 2010; 30(2), 167-180. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2009.10.007 <lb/>PMID: 19926376 <lb/>84. Cheung K, Theule J. Paternal depressive symptoms and parenting behaviors: An updated meta-analy-<lb/>sis. Journal of Child and Family Studies. 2019; 28(3), 613-626. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-018-<lb/>01316-1 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>Modeling trajectories of physical aggression <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0291704 June 3, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 24 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>