<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T13:13:26.657Z">11/13/2025 1:13:26 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T13:13:17.562743Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T13:13:17.562743Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally <lb/>painful.&quot; Paramedic´s experience exercising <lb/>coercion during assignments-A qualitative <lb/>study <lb/>Anne Kristine Bergem 1 , Nina Øye Thorvaldsen 1 , Kristin Ha ¨ikio ¨ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Heming Olsen-<lb/>Bergem 2 <lb/>1 Dept of Nursing and Health Promotion, Faculty of Health Sciences, Oslo Metropolitan University, Oslo, <lb/>Norway, 2 Dept of Oral Surgery and Oral Medicine, Institute for Clinical Dentistry, Oslo University, Oslo, <lb/>Norway <lb/>* haikio@oslomet.no <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background <lb/>More than 70% of respondents in a previous survey among paramedics reported use of <lb/>coercion or physical force towards patients. Coercion outside hospital is not permitted, and <lb/>neither routines nor equipment intended for physical restraint is available in the Norwegian <lb/>ambulance services. Paramedics carry out assignments involving use of force and coercion <lb/>on unclear legal grounds, with no training in techniques or proper equipment. Attitudes and <lb/>experiences of healthcare workers regarding incidents involving coercion in mental health <lb/>care services are frequently reported in the research literature, yet little is known about para-<lb/>medics&apos; experiences, and which factors contribute to their moral stress. <lb/>Methods <lb/>In the period June-August 2021, almost 400 employees in the ambulance services in a <lb/>county in the eastern part of Norway were invited to answer a digital questionnaire. One <lb/>question had an open text field with the question &quot;Can you say something about how you <lb/>experience transporting patients where force has to be used to secure the patient during <lb/>transport?&quot;. The answers were analyzed using Graneheim and Lundman&apos;s content <lb/>analysis. <lb/>Results <lb/>We received eighty-five completed responses (response rate 21%). Force was used by 62 <lb/>paramedics. Twenty-three left the text field open. The answers showed many unique <lb/>responses. Content analysis resulted in two overarching themes; 1) lack of routines, equip-<lb/>ment, and training regarding use of coercion and force in the ambulance service, and 2) <lb/>paramedics were confronted with ethical dilemmas, alone and without support from legisla-<lb/>tion or management. <lb/>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/>1 / 10 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Bergem AK, Thorvaldsen NØ, Ha ¨ikio ¨K, <lb/>Olsen-Bergem H (2024) &quot;Some missions can be <lb/>quite emotionally painful.&quot; Paramedic´s experience <lb/>exercising coercion during assignments-A <lb/>qualitative study. PLoS ONE 19(1): e0290593. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 <lb/>Editor: Collins Atta Poku, Kwame Nkrumah <lb/>University of Science and Technology, GHANA <lb/>Received: August 16, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: December 9, 2023 <lb/>Published: January 2, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Bergem et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data cannot be <lb/>shared publicly because of the risk of recognition <lb/>of participants in qualitative data. Data are available <lb/>from the OsloMet Privacy Ombudsman (contact via <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The paramedics experienced discomfort related to the exercise of force and coercion during <lb/>ambulance assignments due to the experience of unclear legislation, lack of training, rou-<lb/>tines, and equipment in addition to frequent ethical dilemmas and the concern about lack of <lb/>support from the employer. A clearer legal basis, adapted equipment in the ambulance and <lb/>regular training, will contribute to greater security in the performance of the work, which will <lb/>provide safer and more caring treatment for the patients and less moral stress for the staff. <lb/>With established routines, the employer will be implicitly obliged, and paramedics will be <lb/>safer in the performance of their work. Ethical reflection must be offered and put into a <lb/>system. <lb/></front>

    <body>Background <lb/>The Norwegian Health and Care Services Act [1] defines coercion and force as &quot;measures <lb/>which the service user opposes, or which are so intrusive that regardless of resistance, they <lb/>must be considered as use of coercion or force&quot;. Coercion is relatively common in mental <lb/>health care internationally and at the same time considered problematic [2]. In our survey <lb/>among ambulance workers in a Norwegian county, coercion is defined as the use of physical <lb/>force. Over 70% of respondents in the survey reported to have exercised such physical force <lb/>[3]. In health services, coercion is used to ensure proper services for patients who do not have <lb/>the competence to consent, and to prevent harm to patients or staff [4-8]. In clinical practice, <lb/>the necessity of using clinical judgment will be present, as described in guidelines from the <lb/>Norwegian Directorate of Health [9, 10]. <lb/>The Health Personnel Act gives health personnel the possibility and a duty to provide <lb/>healthcare without the consent of the patient in acute situations, even if the patient objects to <lb/>the health care. The provision authorizes the use of coercion in that it states that the duty to <lb/>help also applies if the patient objects to healthcare [9]. <lb/>In the health services, the coercion that people are subjected to will be initiated and carried <lb/>out by other people, i.e., health personnel. Exercising coercion is shown to be morally stressful <lb/>for health personnel [11]. Moral stress is defined as having to make difficult choices that go <lb/>against one&apos;s own values or the experience of ethical dilemmas and is a risk factor for impaired <lb/>mental health [12-14]. <lb/>The exercise of coercion threatens health personnel&apos;s understanding of proper care and <lb/>treatment. Exercising coercion at the same time as being required to provide health care is by <lb/>Hem et al. [15] described as &quot;a moral enterprise &quot;, i.e., a demanding assignment that is experi-<lb/>enced as morally stressful [11]. The main cause of the perceived stress is the conflict linked to <lb/>the need to maintain control over a situation and the importance of a good therapeutic rela-<lb/>tionship with the patient. Although healthcare personnel experience coercion as part of their <lb/>job, coercion is also described as destructive [16]. The balance between taking care of vulnera-<lb/>ble people with a mental disorder and society&apos;s demands for protection from people with a risk <lb/>of violence linked to a mental disorder causes moral stress [17]. <lb/>Personnel in mental health care exercise physical coercion against people already admitted <lb/>for investigation or treatment of a serious mental disorder in accordance with §4 in the Nor-<lb/>wegian Mental Health Protection Act. Coercion is exercised by a legal decision, it is docu-<lb/>mented and recorded, and all coercive decisions can be appealed by the patient and next of <lb/>kin [5]. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <front>personvernombud@oslomet.no) for researchers <lb/>who meet the criteria for access to confidential <lb/>data. <lb/>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

    <body>As a general principle, physical coercion is a task reserved for law enforcement agencies. <lb/>However, if coercion or force is necessary to provide health care of vital importance, the coer-<lb/>cion is authorized in the obligation to provide emergency medical care according to Section 7 <lb/>[19] of the Norwegian Health Personnel Act. Ambulance services, being at the front of health <lb/>care, often encounter situations where use of coercion is necessary to provide healthcare. How-<lb/>ever, Norwegian regulations have not been specifically designed, developed, or discussed in <lb/>the context of the prehospital setting [3]. The Norwegian Penal Code section 17 and 18 pro-<lb/>vides for actions deemed necessary to save lives or protect others from harm [18]. If coercion <lb/>or force is necessary to provide health care, the coercion is authorized in the obligation to pro-<lb/>vide emergency medical care according to Section 7 [19] of the Norwegian Health Personnel <lb/>Act. Paramedics must therefore have in-depth knowledge of legislation, and the legal basis for <lb/>enforcement may be unclear. <lb/>In hospital wards approved for involuntary mental health care, the Norwegian Mental <lb/>Health Protection Act [5] applies. Chapter 4 discusses the use of mechanical restraints. <lb/>Although for many years there has been a strong desire to reduce the use of coercion in mental <lb/>health care [20], mechanical restraints are available in most inpatient wards. Employees in <lb/>mental health care departments receive training in the use of mechanical restraints and in <lb/>many cases have regular training on their use, and the same applies to employees in ambula-<lb/>tory emergency teams in mental health care [21, 22]. <lb/>As exercise of coercion outside hospital is not permitted, routines have not been developed <lb/>for the implementation of such measures in the ambulance service. There is no available equip-<lb/>ment intended for physical restraint in Norwegian ambulances. <lb/>Although it is stated in the description of the paramedic course &quot;As a paramedic you are the <lb/>extended arm of the hospital and work independently with sick and injured patients&quot;, the exer-<lb/>cise of coercion and force is not on the educational plans [23]. <lb/>Paramedics today must carry out assignments that involve the use of force and coercion on <lb/>unclear legal grounds, outside existing routines, with no training in techniques. Neither do <lb/>they have access to proper equipment. Together with the high incidence of coercion on ambu-<lb/>lance missions [3], it would be reasonable to believe that many paramedics in the Norwegian <lb/>ambulance service experience participation in &quot;moral enterprises &quot; [15]. <lb/>Although the attitudes and experiences of healthcare workers regarding situations involving <lb/>coercion in mental health care services are frequently reported in the research literature [24, <lb/>25], little is known about paramedics&apos; experience of exercising coercion [26], and which factors <lb/>contribute to experiencing moral stress. <lb/>Material and methods <lb/>Inclusion and exclusion criteria <lb/>Inclusion criteria: In the period June-August 2021, almost 400 employees in the ambulance <lb/>service in a county in the eastern part of Norway were invited to answer a digital questionnaire. <lb/>Included were all ambulance personnel. There were no exclusion criteria. Information letters <lb/>and requests were sent via e-mail. No information about the participants was collected, and all <lb/>who worked as paramedics were eligible participants. <lb/>Questionnaire <lb/>A digital questionnaire, Nettskjema [27] was sent as an open link to all who wanted to partici-<lb/>pate. The questions asked were about the paramedics&apos; exercise of power and coercion. One <lb/>question with an open text field read: &quot; Can you say something about how you experience <lb/>transporting patients where force has to be used to secure the patient during transport?&quot; The <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>question is not a validated one but was made based on the second author´s experience from <lb/>the ambulance service and tested out among a group of test persons by an area instructor for <lb/>paramedics in the county where the study later was performed. <lb/>Ethical considerations <lb/>Participation was voluntary, and the survey was anonymous. The Norwegian Center for <lb/>Research Data (NSD) assessed the data (ref. no. 775741). Regional committees for medical and <lb/>health-related research ethics (REK) department south-east C assessed the purpose of the <lb/>study as outside the Health Research Act (submission assessment ref. no. 270172). <lb/>Trustworthiness <lb/>The open field question answered in this study, although not validated due to the novelty of <lb/>the study topic, is open and a part of a larger survey. A test group of paramedics described the <lb/>question as easily understood. No misinterpretation was detected among the test persons or <lb/>area instructor. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>The answers in the open text fields were analyzed using Graneheim and Lundman&apos;s analysis of <lb/>qualitative content [28]. <lb/>In accordance with Graneheim and Lundman, we have identified both a manifest and a <lb/>latent content of the text. The manifest content is based on the visible, obvious, and verbatim <lb/>written by the informants. In the latent content, we interpret the underlying meaning in the <lb/>text and raise the meaning in the text to a higher level of abstraction through interpretations <lb/>and theme formation. The first and last author read through each text response several times <lb/>first separately and then together, to get an overall picture of the content. Disagreements <lb/>would have been solved by the other authors. The analysis was conducted in five steps. Step <lb/>one: In collaboration, the meaningful elements were extracted from the answers in accordance <lb/>with the purpose of the study. Meaningful elements are groupings of words that relate to the <lb/>same meaning. These elements were during step two reduced to a condensed text making <lb/>effort not to change the core of the message [28]. In step three, an abstraction was carried out, <lb/>that is, an interpretation of the condensed meaningful elements. In step four, the following <lb/>question was posed to each condensed element: &quot;What is this really about?&quot; This resulted in <lb/>several codes that were assessed against each other to find similarities and differences. The <lb/>codes are short descriptions of the content of a group of meaningful elements with approxi-<lb/>mately the same content. In step five, the codes were sorted into categories based on their <lb/>topic. The categories consist of thematically similar codes [28]. Table 1 shows an example of <lb/>the analysis process from meaningful unit to theme. <lb/>Table 1. Example of content analysis. <lb/>Meaningful elements <lb/>Condensed element of meaning <lb/>Code <lb/>Category <lb/>Theme <lb/>Experience it as insufficient both in <lb/>relation to procedural work and <lb/>available equipment. <lb/>It feels unsafe both in terms of <lb/>procedures and equipment to <lb/>exercise coercion. <lb/>Unclear <lb/>rules <lb/>Practical <lb/>problem <lb/>There are practical <lb/>problems and missing <lb/>routines for my work. <lb/>Lack of routines, equipment, and training <lb/>regarding the use of coercion and force in <lb/>the ambulance service. <lb/>When translating the quotes into English, the context for the statements was attached, as well as the interpretation made through the content analysis. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593.t001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>Results <lb/>A total of 85 completed responses from paramedics were received, which corresponds to a <lb/>response rate of 21%. Sixty-two persons (72.9%) had used force to ensure that patients were <lb/>properly secured during transport. 23 of the respondents left the text field open. In the open <lb/>text answers, we found many unique responses. Content analysis ad modum Graneheim and <lb/>Lundman, however, resulted in two overarching themes. The two themes were 1) lack of rou-<lb/>tines, equipment, and training regarding use of coercion and force in the ambulance service, <lb/>and 2) Paramedics are often faced with ethical dilemmas, alone and without support from leg-<lb/>islation or management. <lb/>The quotes are from different paramedics. Names and sex are fictive. <lb/>Lack of routines, equipment, and training regarding use of coercion and <lb/>force in the ambulance service <lb/>In many of the responses, paramedics described the practical challenges they experience. Lack <lb/>of standardized suitable equipment, such as conveyor belts, and lack of proper training, makes <lb/>it necessary to invent adaptive and individualized solutions from job to job. <lb/>Quote: I wish we had suitable equipment like the mechanical restraints used in psychiatric <lb/>wards, I feel it would make the assignments that require restraining the patient easier to man-<lb/>age. (Barry) <lb/>The respondent above, describes the coercion required as difficult to perform due to lack of <lb/>suitable mechanical equipment, and this was supported by many other participants. As the <lb/>next quote illustrates, respondents also request a plan for safe and secure transportations of <lb/>people who need restrains. <lb/>Quote: Sometimes I think that; when we know that these transports take place, why can&apos;t we <lb/>also make plans for it to be conducted in a safe and secure way with mechanical restraints in <lb/>place so that we don´t have to physically hold the patient. Can we not practice and be good at <lb/>using mechanical restraints instead of putting ourselves, the police and the patient at risk by <lb/>tumbling around in the back of an ambulance. (Greg) <lb/>This respondent highlights the challenge that arises from the fact that use of coercion in the <lb/>ambulance service only is authorized if the healthcare is of vital importance or to protect the <lb/>patient or others from harm. However, planning and training for the use of coercion regulated <lb/>by Section 17 in the Penalty Code is not permitted, even if the incidence is high. The respondent <lb/>compares his/her tasks with the tasks of health personnel in mental health care and points out <lb/>that the same work tasks are carried out under very different conditions, legally and practically. <lb/>In addition to necessary equipment and a plan for emergency situations, several partici-<lb/>pants requested more knowledge and training related to use of coercion. The next quote illus-<lb/>trates this. <lb/>Quote: I think we have too little knowledge to use coercion and force and find it unpleasant to <lb/>have to sort things out ourselves because you don&apos;t get the necessary assistance. (Paul) <lb/>In the quote above and below, several aspects of coercion are mentioned. Knowledge in this <lb/>context is interpreted as a lack of training, and the respondent, like many other respondents, <lb/>mention that the use of coercion against patients is experienced as unpleasant and with little <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>support from other resources It may also appear that the respondent not necessarily thinks <lb/>increased knowledge is needed, and instead emphasizes lack of knowledge to be compensated <lb/>with necessary assistance. <lb/>Quote: We need more practical training, around different situations that can arise in connec-<lb/>tion with this-i.e., how best to handle it. (Iris) <lb/>Several respondents call for specific training in exercising coercion. <lb/>Paramedics are often faced with ethical dilemmas, alone and without <lb/>support from legislation or management <lb/>In many replies, despair is expressed as a response to exposing people to coercion, even though <lb/>it is for their own benefit. The respondent expresses empathy with the patient, as well as con-<lb/>cern that he/she, as a paramedic, imposes new burdens on patients in situations where they <lb/>need help. This is illustrated by one of the respondents in the next quote: <lb/>Quote: Often these people are patients who have had their problems due to abuse in the past. <lb/>The fact that we use coercion feels like another trauma. (Linda) <lb/>Several respondents express the use of coercion as necessary for the ambulance mission to <lb/>be carried out. In several responses, it appears paramedics are feeling safe when the police are <lb/>present, both because the police are the ones who exercise the coercion, excusing the paramed-<lb/>ics, and because the paramedics do not have to decide whether they are allowed to exercise <lb/>coercion. <lb/>Quote: I think the police are the ones who should exercise force and all such transports should <lb/>take place in a police car. (Sam) <lb/>Several responders express concerns about having the sole responsibility and it appears that <lb/>the exercise of force and coercion is not perceived as part of what ambulance workers are edu-<lb/>cated and trained for. Several respondents do not experience the exercise of force and coercion <lb/>as a task for healthcare personnel but designates the police as the right authority, like in the <lb/>quote below. <lb/>Quote: I think it is as a mistake. It is not our job to force people. (Rob) <lb/>A few of the respondents were expressing concern about lack of support from management <lb/>if the use of coercion were to be complained about or otherwise known to the public, like in <lb/>the quote below. <lb/>Quote: Uncomfortable with doubts about the management having my back covered. (Terry) <lb/>The answer is an example of the fear of making a mistake, i.e., exercising coercion and <lb/>power without sufficient legal basis, and that the actions performed will be regarded as some-<lb/>thing the person has done without the management´s approval. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The results show that, for several reasons, paramedics experience the exercise of coercion and <lb/>force during assignments as unpleasant, even though many express the use of force as <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>necessary. The results are in accordance with experiences from personnel who work with <lb/>municipal health work and in mental health care [11, 15-17, 29]. Both practical aspects of <lb/>coercion linked to a lack of training and equipment, and the more emotional and legal aspects <lb/>are problematized by the respondents. <lb/>Although the exact extent of the exercise of force and coercion during ambulance assign-<lb/>ments is not known, and our material is limited to one region, there are many indications that <lb/>the incidence is so high that it does not make sense to talk about rarity, coincidence, or one-off <lb/>events. A national survey with the same questionnaire shows the same trend [30]. <lb/>Lack of support in legislation and management <lb/>&quot;Not our job&quot; and &quot;should take place in a police car&quot; are statements that exemplify paramedicsd <lb/>oubts about their own role in the exercise of force and coercion. The lack of a clear legal basis <lb/>in health legislation is perceived as problematic. <lb/>Paramedics must use force without being sure whether they are allowed to do so. For that <lb/>reason, paramedics ask for assistance from the police when the patient resists healthcare, even <lb/>when the paramedics are physically able to handle the patient&apos;s resistance. The police are thus <lb/>asked for assistance for missions where coercion is necessary, even if in practice police assis-<lb/>tance is unnecessary [31]. <lb/>In Poland, EMS personnel were allowed to exercise coercion in 2010. Each incident is docu-<lb/>mented in a separate record system, and it is argued that both the patients&apos; rights as well as <lb/>those of healthcare personnel have been strengthened following the change in the law [32]. <lb/>Without routines regarding documentation, there is a risk that exercised coercion is not <lb/>documented. <lb/>Routines, equipment, and training <lb/>Since training and education in healthcare must be in line with then legislation regulating the <lb/>service, one cannot train and plan for emergency use of coercion in the prehospital health care <lb/>services. In mental healthcare, routines for exercising coercion are established [20, 21]. For the <lb/>same reason, paramedics do not have suitable equipment developed for securing patients dur-<lb/>ing transport which would be preferable using bandage materials etc. which are used today [3]. <lb/>Education and training must include prevention and ethical reflections on one&apos;s own exer-<lb/>cise of force and coercion. For employees in mental health care, this is already well described <lb/>[33]. In the training manual developed for mental health care, MAP (Encounter with aggres-<lb/>sion problems), it is expressed as follows: &quot;Furthermore, the concept of care includes our view <lb/>of people and our attitudes when dealing with the individual&quot; [34]. When use of coercion in <lb/>the ambulance services is not recognized, lack of practical training as well as lack of ethical <lb/>reflections will be a consequence. <lb/>Moral enterprise-ethical dilemmas <lb/>It is beyond the scope of this article to discuss the experience of people who are subjected to <lb/>coercion and force, but as the responses in the survey show, paramedics reflect on the force <lb/>and coercion they subject other people to and recognize that it can be harmful. The recogni-<lb/>tion is necessary and important to provide good care at the same time as they reinforce the eth-<lb/>ical dilemmas for each individual paramedic. <lb/>Without support in legislation or management, handling the burden by exercising coercion <lb/>is left to each individual employee, or each pair of paramedics. <lb/>When the use of coercion and force occurs frequently, and paramedics experience discom-<lb/>fort during the execution, this means that every week there are many people who experience <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>moral stress in their normal work, and thus have an increased risk of mental health problems <lb/>[13, 14]. <lb/>A clearer legal basis will remove some uncertainty about legality. Better cooperation with <lb/>the police will create a better distribution of work and tasks, but the ethical dilemmas and the <lb/>emotional discomfort associated with exercising force and coercion will not and should not be <lb/>removed by expanding the legislation. <lb/>It is therefore crucial that employers and organizations take greater responsibility for hav-<lb/>ing better support systems and structures to reduce moral stress. Ka ¨lvemark et al. suggests <lb/>more education in ethics and forums to discuss ethically difficult situations or hospital person-<lb/>nel [14]. <lb/>Based on the findings in our study, there is a need of closer cooperation between police and <lb/>ambulance personnel both for practice and training but also regarding the development of <lb/>new guidelines. Ethical discussions regarding the use of force must be introduced as early in <lb/>education and training as possible, and psychosocial support on the work place should be <lb/>encouraged. <lb/>Strengths and weaknesses of the study <lb/>It is a strength that the survey includes many respondents, albeit from a limited geographical <lb/>area. The pilot study has been followed up by a national study, which shows the same tendency <lb/>[30]. A disadvantage is that none of the answers go in-depth. Interviews would have given the <lb/>opportunity for more in-depth answers. A strength of an open question in a form is that the <lb/>preconceptions of the authors have not influenced the answers given. The fact that the first <lb/>author is a psychiatrist herself and has known the burden of making decisions about the use of <lb/>coercion in mental health care may have influenced the interpretation of the results in the <lb/>analysis process. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Paramedics in the county we researched, experience discomfort related to the exercise of force <lb/>and coercion during ambulance assignments. The discomfort is due to the experience of <lb/>unclear legislation, lack of training, routines, and equipment in addition to frequent ethical <lb/>dilemmas and the concern about lack of support from the employer. A clearer legal basis, <lb/>more adapted equipment in the ambulance and regular training in situations where it is neces-<lb/>sary to use force, will contribute to greater security in the performance of the work, which <lb/>both provides safer and more caring treatment for the patients and less moral stress for the <lb/>staff. With established routines, the employer will be implicitly obliged, and paramedics will be <lb/>safer in the performance of their work. In addition, ethical reflection must be offered and put <lb/>into a system. <lb/></body>

    <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors acknowledge Nils Halvor Gryting for contributing to the distribution of the <lb/>survey. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Anne Kristine Bergem, Nina Øye Thorvaldsen, Kristin Ha ¨ikio <lb/>¨. <lb/>Data curation: Kristin Ha ¨ikio <lb/>¨. <lb/>Formal analysis: Anne Kristine Bergem, Heming Olsen-Bergem. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Investigation: Anne Kristine Bergem, Nina Øye Thorvaldsen. <lb/>Methodology: Anne Kristine Bergem, Nina Øye Thorvaldsen, Kristin Ha ¨ikio <lb/>¨. <lb/>Project administration: Anne Kristine Bergem, Nina Øye Thorvaldsen, Kristin Ha ¨ikio <lb/>¨. <lb/>Supervision: Kristin Ha ¨ikio ¨, Heming Olsen-Bergem. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Anne Kristine Bergem, Heming Olsen-Bergem. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Nina Øye Thorvaldsen, Kristin Ha ¨ikio ¨, Heming Olsen-Bergem. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Health and Care Services Act (Act on municipal health and care services etc.) Section 9-2. 2011. <lb/>https://lovdata.no/dokument/NL/lov/2011-06-24-30#KAPITTEL_9. <lb/>2. O&apos;Brien A,Golding C. Coercion in Mental Healthcare: The Principle of Least Coercive Care. J Psychiatr <lb/>Ment Health Nurs. 2003; 10. 167-73. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2850.2003.00571.x PMID: <lb/>12662333 <lb/>3. Thorvaldsen NØ, Bergem AK, Holst Ø, Ha ¨ikio ¨. Use of force during ambulance transport. Tidsskr Nor <lb/>Legeforen. 2022; 142(14):1424-1426. https://doi.org/10.4045/tidsskr.22.0086 <lb/>4. Patient and User Rights Act (Act on patient and user rights) Chap. 4 A. 1999. https://lovdata.no/ <lb/>dokument/NL/lov/1999-07-02-63#KAPITTEL_4. <lb/>5. Mental health care Act (Act on the establishment and implementation of mental health care). 1999. <lb/>https://lovdata.no/lov/1999-07-02-62. <lb/>6. Health and Care Services Act (Act on municipal health and care services etc.) Chapter 9. 2011. https:// <lb/>lovdata.no/lov/2011-06-24-30. <lb/>7. Health and Care Services Act (Act on municipal health and care services etc.) Chapter 10. 2011. <lb/>https://lovdata.no/lov/2011-06-24-30. <lb/>8. Health Personnel Act (Act on health personnel etc.) § 7. 1999. https://lovdata.no/lov/1999-07-02-64/ §7. <lb/>9. The Directorate of Health. Guide on coercive measures against people with drug problems under the <lb/>Health and Care Services Act chapter 10. Oslo: Health Directorate; 2016. https://www. <lb/>helsedirektoratet.no/veiledere/tvang-overfor-personner-medrusmiddelproblemer/Tvangstiltak% <lb/>20overfor%20personner%20med%20drug%20problems%20%E2%80%93%20Guide.pdf. <lb/>10. Statsforvalteren. Tvang. 2022. https://www.statsforvalteren.no/nb/portal/Helse-omsorg-og-<lb/>sosialtjenester/Tvang/. <lb/>11. Jansen TL, Hem MH, Dambolt LJ, Hanssen I. Moral distress in acute psychiatric nursing: Multifaceted <lb/>dilemmas and demands. Nurs Ethics. 2020; 27(5):1315-1326. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>0969733019877526 PMID: 31631779 <lb/>12. National Center for PTSD. Moral injury in healthcare workers. https://www.ptsd.va.gov/professional/ <lb/>treat/cooccurring/moral_injury_hcw.asp <lb/>13. McEwen C, Alisic E, Jobson L. Moral injury and mental health: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <lb/>Traumatology. 2020; 27(1):13-23. https://doi.org/10.1037/trm0000287 <lb/>14. Ka ¨lvemark S, Ho ¨glund AT, Hansson MG, Westerholm P, Arnetz B. Living with conflicts-ethical dilem-<lb/>mas and moral distress in the health care system. Soc Sci Med. 2004; 58(6):1075-1084. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/s0277-9536(03)00279-x PMID: 14723903 <lb/>15. Hem MH, Molewijk B, Pedersen R. Ethical challenges in connection with the use of coercion: a focus <lb/>group study of health care personnel in mental health care. BMC Med Ethics. 2014; 15:82. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1186/1472-6939-15-82 PMID: 25475895 <lb/>16. Bigwood S, Crowe M. &apos;It&apos;s part of the job, but it spoils the job&apos;: a phenomenological study of physical <lb/>restraint. Int J Ment Health Nurs. 2008; 17:215-222. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1447-0349.2008.00526.x <lb/>PMID: 18460083 <lb/>17. Austin W, Kagan L, Rankel M, Bergum V. The balancing act: psychiatrists&apos; experience of moral distress. <lb/>Health Care Anal. 2008; 16(1):9-26. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11019-007-9083-1 PMID: 17703374 <lb/>18. https://www.helsedirektoratet.no/rundskriv/psykisk-helsevernloven-med-komentarer/jjaemforing-av-<lb/>psykisk-helsevern/4-8-bruk-av-tvangsmidler-i-institusjon-for-dognopphold. <lb/>19. The Penal code. 2005. https://lovdata.no/lov/2005-05-20-28/ §17. <lb/>20. The Directorate of Health. https://www.helsedirektoratet.no/rundskriv/helsepersonelloven-med-<lb/>kommentarer/krav-til-helsepersonnels-yrkesutovelse/-7.oyeblikkelig-hjelp. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>21. Norwegian Health Directorate. https://www.sintef.no/globalassets/upload/helse/psykisk-helse/pdf-filer/ <lb/>tiltaksplan_for_redusert_og_kvalitetsikret_bruk_av_tvang_i_psykisk_helsevern.pdf. <lb/>22. Pwnzo T, Skaare Ø, Instefjord TB. Training for higher security. Sykepleien. 2015; 103(9):50-52. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.4220/Sykepleiens.2015.55152 <lb/>23. National training program in the prevention and handling of problems of aggression and violence. Chap-<lb/>ter 9: Manual for physical techniques. https://www.oslomet.no/studier/hv/paramedisin. <lb/>24. Laukkanen E, Vehvila ¨inen-Julkunen K, Louheranta O, Kuosmanen L. Psychiatric nursing staffs&apos; atti-<lb/>tudes towards the use of containment methods in psychiatric inpatient care: An integrative review. Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Mental Health Nursing. 2019; 28(2):390-406 https://doi.org/10.1111/inm.12574 <lb/>PMID: 30761718 <lb/>25. Doedens P, Vermeulen J, Boyette L-L, Latour C, de Haan L. Influence of nursing staff attitudes and <lb/>characteristics on the use of coercive measures in acute mental health services-A systematic review. <lb/>Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing. 2020; 27(4):446-59. https://doi.org/10.1111/jpm. <lb/>12586 PMID: 31876970 <lb/>26. Bradbury J, Hutchinson M, Hurley J, Stasa H. Lived experience of involuntary transport under mental <lb/>health legislation. International Journal of Mental Health Nursing. 2017; 26(6):580-92. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1111/inm.12284 PMID: 27897380 <lb/>27. University of Oslo. Nettskjema. https://www.uio.no/english/services/it/adm-services/nettskjema/ <lb/>28. Graneheim UH, Lundman B. Qualitative content analysis in nursing research: concepts, procedures <lb/>and measures to achieve trustworthiness. Nurse Educ Today. 2004; 24(2):105 https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>j.nedt.2003.10.001 PMID: 14769454 <lb/>29. Kinner SA, Harvey C, Hamilton B, Brophy L, Roper C, McSherry B, et al. Attitudes towards seclusion <lb/>and restraint in mental health settings: findings from a large, community-based survey of consumers, <lb/>carers and mental health professionals. Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci. 2017; 26(5):535-544. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1017/S2045796016000585 PMID: 27515597 <lb/>30. Ha ¨ikio ¨K, Bergem AK, Holst Ø, Thorvaldsen NØ. Coercion use and seat belt use by ambulance workers <lb/>in Norway. Under review in BMC Health Services Research. <lb/>31. Kucmin Tomasz, Kucmin Adriana, Małgorzata Płowaś-Goral Adam Nogalski. Rules, indications and <lb/>documentation for applying physical coercion by emergency medical services. Pol J Public Health. <lb/>2015; 125(2):83-86. https://doi.org/10.1515/pjph-2015-0029 <lb/>32. The Directorate of Health. https://www.helsedirektoratet.no/rundskriv/psykisk-helsevernloven-med-<lb/>kommentarer/gjennomforing-av-psykisk-helsevern#paragraf-4-8-bruk-av-tvangsmidler-i-institusjon-for-<lb/>dognopphold <lb/>33. The Directorate of Health. https://www.helsedirektoratet.no/faglige-rad/tvang-forebygging-av-tvang-i-<lb/>psykisk-helsevern-for-voksne/institusjonens-ansvar-og-oppgaver-ved-bruk-av-tvang/. <lb/>34. SIFER. Meeting with aggression issues. https://sifer.no/map/. <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>&quot;Some missions can be quite emotionally painful&quot; -paramedic&apos;s experiences of using coercion <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290593 January 2, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 10 </page>


  </text>

</TEI>