<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Digital assessment of cognitive-affective biases related to mental health</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sang-Eon</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jisu</forename>
          <surname>Chung</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jeonghyun</forename>
          <surname>Lee</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Minwoo JB</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jinhee</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hong Jin</forename>
          <surname>Jeon</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hyungsook</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Choongwan</forename>
          <surname>Woo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hackjin</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sang Ah</forename>
          <surname>Lee</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T11:08:17.374Z">11/13/2025 11:08:17 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pdig.0000595</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Sang-Eon Park, Jisu Chung, Jeonghyun Lee, Minwoo JB Kim, Jinhee Kim, Hong Jin Jeon, Hyungsook Kim, Choongwan Woo, Hackjin Kim, Sang Ah Lee. (2024). Digital assessment of cognitive-affective biases related to mental health. PLOS Digital Health, 3(8), e0000595. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pdig.0000595</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T11:08:08.925104Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T11:08:08.925104Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Identifying delays in healthcare seeking and <lb/>provision: The Three Delays-in-Healthcare and <lb/>mortality among infants and children aged <lb/>1-59 months <lb/>Elisa Garcia Gomez 1☯ , Kitiezo Aggrey Igunza 2☯ , Zachary J. Madewell ID <lb/>3 <lb/>, Victor Akelo 4 , <lb/>Dickens Onyango 5 , Shams El Arifeen 6 , Emily S. Gurley 7 , Mohammad Zahid Hossain ID <lb/>6 , <lb/>Md Atique Iqbal Chowdhury 6 , Kazi Munisul Islam 6 , Nega Assefa 8,9,10 , J. Anthony G. Scott 8 , <lb/>Lola Madrid 8,9,10 , Yenenesh Tilahun 9,10 , Stian Orlien ID <lb/>11,12 , Karen L. Kotloff 13 , Milagritos <lb/>D. Tapia 13 , Adama Mamby Keita 14 , Ashka Mehta 13 , Amilcar Magac ¸o15 , David Torres-<lb/>FernandezID 15,16 , Ariel Nhacolo 15 , Quique BassatID 15,16,17,18,19 , Ina ´cio Mandomando 15,16,20 , <lb/>Ikechukwu OgbuanuID 21 , Carrie Jo Cain 22 , Ronita Luke 23 , Sorie I. B. Kamara 21 , <lb/>Hailemariam LegesseID 24 , Shabir Madhi 25 , Ziyaad Dangor 25 , Sana MahtabID 25 , <lb/>Amy Wise 26 , Yasmin Adam 27 , Cynthia G. Whitney 28 , Portia C. Mutevedzi 28 , Dianna <lb/>M. BlauID 3 , Robert F. BreimanID 29 , Beth A. Tippett BarrID 30 , Chris A. ReesID 31,32 *, Child <lb/>Health and Mortality Prevention Surveillance Network ¶ <lb/>1 Emory University School of Medicine, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, <lb/>2 Kenya Medical Research Institute-Center for Global Health Research, Kisumu, Kenya, 3 Global Health <lb/>Center, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 4 Centers <lb/>for Disease Control and Prevention-Kenya, Kisumu, Kenya, 5 Kisumu County Department of Health, Kisumu, <lb/>Kenya, 6 International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research Bangladesh (icddr,b), Dhaka, Bangladesh, <lb/>7 Bloomberg School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of <lb/>America, 8 London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom, 9 College of Health <lb/>and Medical Sciences, Haramaya University, Harar, Ethiopia, 10 Hararghe Health Research, Haramaya <lb/>University, Harar, Ethiopia, 11 College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Hargeisa, Hargeisa, <lb/>Somaliland, 12 Department of Paediatrics, Vestfold Hospital Trust, Tønsberg, Norway, 13 Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Center for Vaccine Development and Global Health, University of Maryland School of Medicine, <lb/>Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America, 14 Centre pour le De ´veloppement des Vaccins-Mali, <lb/>Bamako, Mali, 15 Centro de Investigac ¸ão em Sau ´de de Manhic ¸a (CISM), Maputo, Mozambique, 16 ISGlobal <lb/>-Hospital Clı ´nic, Universitat de Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain, 17 Institucio ´Catalana de Recerca I Estudis <lb/>Avanc ¸ats (ICREA), Barcelona, Spain, 18 Pediatrics Department, Hospital Sant Joan de De ´u, Universitat de <lb/>Barcelona, Esplugues, Barcelona, Spain, 19 Consorcio de Investigacio ´n Biome ´dica en Red de <lb/>Epidemiologı ´a y Salud Pu ´blica (CIBERESP), Madrid, Spain, 20 Instituto Nacional de Sau ´de, Ministe ´rio de <lb/>Sau ´de, Maputo, Moc ¸ambique, 21 Crown Agents, Freetown, Sierra Leone, 22 World Hope International, <lb/>Freetown, Sierra Leone, 23 Ministry of Health and Sanitation, Freetown, Sierra Leone, 24 UNICEF, <lb/>Freetown, Sierra Leone, 25 South African Medical Research Council Vaccines and Infectious Diseases <lb/>Analytics Research Unit, University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa, 26 Department of <lb/>Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Rahima Mossa Mother and Child Hospital, University of the Witwatersrand, <lb/>Johannesburg, South Africa, 27 Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Chris Hani Baragwanath <lb/>Academic Hospital, University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa, 28 Global Health Institute, <lb/>Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 29 Hubert Department of Global Health, <lb/>Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 30 Nyanja <lb/>Health Research Institute, Salima, Malawi, 31 Department of Pediatrics, Emory University School of <lb/>Medicine, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America, 32 Children&apos;s Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, Georgia, <lb/>United States of America <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> ¶ Membership of the Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveillance Network is provided in the Supporting <lb/>information file in S1 Acknowledgments. <lb/>* chris.rees@emory.edu <lb/>PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/>1 / 18 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Garcia Gomez E, Igunza KA, Madewell ZJ, <lb/>Akelo V, Onyango D, El Arifeen S, et al. (2024) <lb/>Identifying delays in healthcare seeking and <lb/>provision: The Three Delays-in-Healthcare and <lb/>mortality among infants and children aged 1-59 <lb/>months. PLOS Glob Public Health 4(2): e0002494. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 <lb/>Editor: Julia Robinson, PLOS: Public Library of <lb/>Science, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: June 26, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 10, 2024 <lb/>Published: February 8, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: This is an open access article, free of all <lb/>copyright, and may be freely reproduced, <lb/>distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or <lb/>otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. <lb/>The work is made available under the Creative <lb/>Commons CC0 public domain dedication. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: CHAMPS data may <lb/>be accessed through requests at https:// <lb/>champshealth.org/data/. <lb/>Funding: CHAMPS is funded by The Bill &amp; Melinda <lb/>Gates Foundation (OPP1126780 to CGW) which <lb/>provided input into site selection decisions and <lb/>methodology and scope of CHAMPS. The funders <lb/>had no role in study design, data collection and <lb/>analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Delays in illness recognition, healthcare seeking, and in the provision of appropriate clinical <lb/>care are common in resource-limited settings. Our objective was to determine the frequency <lb/>of delays in the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot;, and factors associated with delays, among <lb/>deceased infants and children in seven countries with high childhood mortality. We con-<lb/>ducted a retrospective, descriptive study using data from verbal autopsies and medical rec-<lb/>ords for infants and children aged 1-59 months who died between December 2016 and <lb/>February 2022 in six sites in sub-Saharan Africa and one in South Asia (Bangladesh) and <lb/>were enrolled in Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveillance (CHAMPS). Delays in 1) <lb/>illness recognition in the home/decision to seek care, 2) transportation to healthcare facili-<lb/>ties, and 3) the receipt of clinical care in healthcare facilities were categorized according to <lb/>the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot;. Comparisons in factors associated with delays were <lb/>made using Chi-square testing. Information was available for 1,326 deaths among infants <lb/>and under 5 children. The majority had at least one identified delay (n = 854, 64%). Waiting <lb/>&gt;72 hours after illness recognition to seek health care (n = 422, 32%) was the most common <lb/>delay. Challenges in obtaining transportation occurred infrequently when seeking care (n = <lb/>51, 4%). In healthcare facilities, prescribed medications were sometimes unavailable (n = <lb/>102, 8%). Deceased children aged 12-59 months experienced more delay than infants <lb/>aged 1-11 months (68% vs. 61%, P = 0.018). Delays in seeking clinical care were common <lb/>among deceased infants and children. Additional study to assess the frequency of delays in <lb/>seeking clinical care and its provision among children who survive is warranted. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>In 2021, more than 5 million children died before their fifth birthday worldwide and over 80% <lb/>of these deaths occurred in sub-Saharan Africa and Southeast Asia [1]. Given the burden of <lb/>childhood mortality in these regions, emphasis has been placed on improving demand and <lb/>access to high quality clinical care. However, delayed healthcare seeking, long distances to <lb/>healthcare facilities, and limited laboratory and radiographic capabilities continue to be com-<lb/>mon in these regions and contribute to shortcomings in high-quality clinical care [2-4]. We <lb/>have previously described that many deaths among infants in children in the Child Health and <lb/>Mortality Prevention Surveillance (CHAMPS) network may have been averted through <lb/>improved health-seeking behaviors [5]. However, a detailed description of the specific aspects <lb/>of needed changes to health-seeking behavior to prevent childhood mortality is lacking. <lb/>The &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; model was developed/proposed to characterize the <lb/>delays leading to maternal mortality, with respect to the time for: 1) the decision to seek medi-<lb/>cal care, 2) traveling to and reaching a healthcare facility, and 3) receiving adequate clinical <lb/>care once in a healthcare facility [6]. Though previously utilized to understand major delays <lb/>leading to maternal mortality [6], surgical care [7, 8], and adult mortality in resource-limited <lb/>settings [9, 10], this model has been used in few instances to understand delays in healthcare <lb/>seeking and provision for children who urgently require medical treatment [11-13]. <lb/>An understanding of healthcare seeking behaviors among caregivers of deceased infants <lb/>and children is a necessary step toward developing feasible interventions to reduce childhood <lb/>deaths in high mortality regions and achieve the Sustainable Development Goal of ending pre-<lb/>ventable childhood deaths by the year 2030 [14]. Our objective was to determine the frequency <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<front>manuscript. None of the authors receive a salary <lb/>from any of the funders. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/>following competing interests: CGW received <lb/>honoraria from the University of St. Andrews for <lb/>speaking to alumni about CHAMPS and global <lb/>health work. JAGS reports receiving funding from <lb/>the Wellcome Trust, UK FCDO, European Union, <lb/>and the National Institute for Health Research. SM <lb/>has received grants from the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates <lb/>Foundation, GSK, Pfizer, Minervax, Novavax, <lb/>Providence, Gritstone, and ImmunityBio. SM has <lb/>received honoraria from GSK for lecturing. CGW <lb/>and SM report serving on data safety monitoring <lb/>boards for SPEAC (CGW) and PATH and CAPRISA <lb/>(SM). DT-F reports having received the support of <lb/>a fellowship from &quot;La Caixa&quot; Foundation (ID <lb/>100010434, &quot;LCF/BQ/DR21/11880018&quot;). All other <lb/>investigators declare no competing interests. <lb/></front>

			<body>of delays in the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot;, and factors associated with delays, among <lb/>deceased infants and children in seven countries with high childhood mortality. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Study design <lb/>We conducted a retrospective, descriptive study using data collected on deceased infants and <lb/>children aged 1-59 months who enrolled in Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveil-<lb/>lance (CHAMPS) between December 2016 and February 2022. We accessed data for the pres-<lb/>ent study on March 12, 2022. We used the &quot;Three Delays-Healthcare&quot; framework to categorize <lb/>and contextualize delays in healthcare seeking and provision [6]. The ethical review committee <lb/>of each site approved CHAMPS mortality surveillance and the use of the data used in this <lb/>study. The use of CHAMPS data has also been approved by the Institutional Review Board at <lb/>Emory University Rollins School of Public Health. <lb/>Data sources <lb/>CHAMPS has been described previously [15, 16]. In brief, CHAMPS is a multi-country net-<lb/>work that conducts prospective community and healthcare center childhood mortality surveil-<lb/>lance in regions with disproportionately high burden of mortality in children aged &lt;5 years <lb/>(i.e., Baliakandi and Faridpur, Bangladesh; Harar, Haramaya, and Kersa, Ethiopia; Kisumu <lb/>and Siaya, Kenya; Bamako, Mali; Manhic ¸a and Quelimane, Mozambique; Makeni, Sierra <lb/>Leone; Soweto, South Africa). Community health volunteers in each included community <lb/>conduct community mortality surveillance and healthcare providers and hospital staff conduct <lb/>hospital surveillance. When deceased children are identified, caregivers are approached for <lb/>potential enrollment for extensive postmortem examinations of the deceased child including <lb/>postmortem histopathological and microbiological analyses including immunohistochemistry <lb/>staining and molecular pathogen identification through extensive polymerase chain reaction <lb/>(PCR) testing for 126 different pathogens (TaqMan array; ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, <lb/>MA, USA). Stillbirths and deaths in live-born children under 5 years of age in CHAMPS catch-<lb/>ment areas were eligible for enrollment in CHAMPS (either cases that underwent minimally <lb/>invasive tissue sampling and had verbal autopsy and clinical data or cases with verbal autopsy <lb/>and clinical data alone). However, the present analysis is restricted to information from infants <lb/>and children. If caregivers consented, CHAMPS staff at each site collected demographic, verbal <lb/>autopsy, and clinical information for each enrolled death. Here, we included cases of death <lb/>that occurred both in healthcare facilities and those that occurred outside health facilities in <lb/>the community. <lb/>As part of CHAMPS routine data collection and as soon as possible following the death, <lb/>local study staff, who did not provide clinical care, comprehensively reviewed all available <lb/>medical records for clinic visits and hospital admissions prior to the infant&apos;s or child&apos;s death to <lb/>document the clinical care an infant or child received, if this information was available. These <lb/>data include information about the frequency of clinic visits and hospital admissions, clinical <lb/>care provided, and barriers to the provision of clinical care prior to death. <lb/>CHAMPS staff completed the 2016 World Health Organization (WHO) Verbal Autopsy <lb/>form with caregivers of enrolled deceased infants and children within 2-4 weeks of the death <lb/>[15, 17]. The 2016 WHO Verbal Autopsy is a validated tool for obtaining context for events <lb/>that preceded death and includes questions with discrete answers (e.g., duration of symptoms, <lb/>clinical encounters, etc.) as well as a narrative field in which caregivers describe events occur-<lb/>ring before the death [17]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Deaths identified within 24 hours of enrollment (or 72 hours if the body was refrigerated) <lb/>were eligible for specimen collection and testing. For eligible cases, a consenting team (i.e., a <lb/>staff trained in providing support and counseling to families and a health worker) was dis-<lb/>patched to the family as soon as possible to confirm eligibility and obtain written consent to all <lb/>CHAMPS procedures [15]. For these deaths, CHAMPS teams collected minimally invasive tis-<lb/>sue samples (MITS) from lungs, brain, and liver. Additionally, CHAMPS staff collected swabs <lb/>of the rectum and upper airway, blood, and cerebrospinal fluid samples. Specimens underwent <lb/>culture, polymerase chain reaction testing to identify infectious causes of death and tissues <lb/>were reviewed by pathologists. <lb/>In each site, a Determination of Cause of Death (DeCoDe) panel consisting of local physi-<lb/>cians, public health professionals, and other healthcare providers performed a standardized <lb/>process to assign causes of death for each case enrolled in CHAMPS who underwent MITS <lb/>[18]. The DeCoDe panel analyzed all available data from verbal autopsies, clinical summaries <lb/>(if available), and histopathologic and microbiologic investigations to determine the causes for <lb/>each death. CHAMPS uses the WHO International Statistical Classification of Diseases and <lb/>Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision (ICD-10) and the WHO application of ICD-10 <lb/>deaths during the perinatal period (ICD-PM) to assign causes of death [19, 20]. Multiple <lb/>causes of death are common in CHAMPS and causes are categorized as immediate, underly-<lb/>ing, and co-morbid causes of death [21]. Once causes of death were determined, CHAMPS <lb/>staff contacted caregivers to provide information about the causes of death. <lb/>Inclusion and exclusion criteria <lb/>Our analysis included all infants and children aged 1-59 months whose caregivers agreed to <lb/>enroll in CHAMPS during the study period and had verbal autopsy or clinical summary data <lb/>available. To ensure that CHAMPS includes a representative sample of deaths that occur in the <lb/>included catchment areas, prospective community and healthcare center childhood mortality <lb/>surveillance is conducted in which notifications of all deaths among children aged &lt;5 years <lb/>are targeted. We excluded stillbirths, neonates, and infants who were never discharged from <lb/>the hospital after birth as healthcare seeking differs in these populations, largely depend on <lb/>maternal healthcare seeking patterns, and warrant a detailed independent description to <lb/>inform interventions for pregnant mothers that may differ from those that cater to caregivers <lb/>of infants and children. We also excluded infants and children who had insufficient informa-<lb/>tion in their verbal autopsy or clinical summaries to describe healthcare seeking or clinical <lb/>care received. <lb/>Data extraction <lb/>We created a list of variables that corresponded to each of the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; <lb/>framework as documented in previous studies and in consultation with experienced members <lb/>of CHAMPS [7, 22, 23]. We then extracted data corresponding to these variables, including <lb/>information related to: 1) when a caregiver recognized signs or symptoms for infants and chil-<lb/>dren in the home, including time from recognition to deciding to seek care (i.e., Delay 1); 2) <lb/>potential barriers related to transportation to seek clinical care described by caregivers (i.e., <lb/>Delay 2); and 3) treatment once a child reached a facility, including the availability of health-<lb/>care providers, treatments provided including issues with their availability, and affordability of <lb/>diagnostics and therapeutics (i.e., Delay 3). <lb/>We reviewed narrative fields in verbal autopsies and clinical summaries to extract informa-<lb/>tion related to the three delays. A subset of 10% of all cases were independently reviewed by a <lb/>second reviewer to ensure reproducibility in data extraction from narrative fields. Questions <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>regarding variable classification were discussed by the first and last authors until consensus <lb/>was achieved. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>We calculated descriptive statistics for demographics and for delays in the &quot;Three Delays-in-<lb/>Healthcare&quot; framework. We compared frequencies of delays by the deceased&apos;s age (i.e., 1-11 <lb/>months vs. 12-59 months) because prior studies suggest healthcare seeking and provision <lb/>delays may be more common in older children [24-26]. Additionally, since delays in health-<lb/>care seeking may be more common for female children [2, 22, 25], we compared the frequency <lb/>of delays by participant sex [24, 27, 28]. We also compared delays by site, given anticipated var-<lb/>iability in healthcare seeking behaviors between each country. Lastly, because we postulated <lb/>that healthcare seeking may vary by the infant&apos;s or child&apos;s diagnosis, we evaluated the odds of <lb/>experiencing at least one delay between DeCoDe determined causes of death [29, 30]. P values <lb/>for the cause of death comparison were corrected for multiple comparisons using the Benja-<lb/>min-Hochberg procedure, and false discovery rate-adjusted P values (q-values) were used for <lb/>evaluating significance [31]. Statistical significance was defined as q �0.10 (i.e., controlling the <lb/>false discovery rate [FDR] at 10%). All statistical analyses were performed using R software, <lb/>version 4.1.2 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing). <lb/>Results <lb/>There were 1,454 infants and children aged 1-59 months who died during the study period. <lb/>Of those, 77 (5%) had insufficient information in their verbal autopsy or clinical summaries to <lb/>describe healthcare seeking and provision and 51 (4%) were born and died in the hospital <lb/>without discharge. The remaining 1,326 (91%) children were included in our analyses (Fig 1). <lb/>The 77 infants and children who were excluded for insufficient information did not differ <lb/>from those included in our analyses by age at death (P = 0.97) or sex (P = 0.37) but were more <lb/>commonly deaths that occurred in the community outside healthcare facilities than those who <lb/>were included (n = 54, 71.1% and n = 506, 38.2%, respectively, P&lt;0.001). <lb/>The median age at the time of death was 11.1 months (interquartile range [IQR] 5.0, 22.7); <lb/>54% (n = 712) were male and 52% were infants (Table 1). Nearly two-thirds of deaths (62%, <lb/>n = 819) occurred in healthcare facilities and 506 (38%) occurred in the community, outside <lb/>the formal healthcare system. The most common causes of death determined by DeCoDe pan-<lb/>els were lower respiratory tract infections (23%, n = 306), sepsis (20%, n = 262), and malnutri-<lb/>tion (14%, n = 187) (Table A in S1 Text). The most common immediate cause of death was <lb/>sepsis (15%, n = 194). The most common underlying cause of death was malnutrition (10%, <lb/>n = 133) and the most common comorbid conditions were lower respiratory infections (9%, <lb/>n = 114) and anemias (5%, n = 63). <lb/>Type of care sought <lb/>Nearly two-thirds of infants and children (64%, n = 851) had a hospital admission as their <lb/>highest level of clinical care during the illness that led to their death, 214 (16%) had only one <lb/>documented clinic visit prior to death, 39 (3%) only saw a traditional healer, and 133 (10%) <lb/>received no formal clinical care in the immediate period prior to their death (Fig A in S1 <lb/>Text). Among all infants and children, 31% (n = 412) sought care at both a clinic and a hospi-<lb/>tal, 7% (n = 95) sought care at a clinic, hospital, and traditional healer, and 22% (n = 290) <lb/>sought care at only a hospital (Fig B in S1 Text). There were 16% (n = 208) of patients who <lb/>only sought care at a clinic and 7% (n = 95) sought care at both a clinic and traditional healer. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>The median time from symptom onset to seeking clinical care was 2 days (IQR 1, 4 days). Of <lb/>1,326 infants and children, 12% (n = 162) were found to be dead on arrival to a healthcare facility <lb/>and 2% (n = 23) died during resuscitation shortly after arrival (Table 2). One-third (34%, <lb/>n = 447) were seen at an outpatient clinic and not referred to a hospital; of those, 84% (n = 377) <lb/>died at home without subsequent clinical encounters and 16% (n = 70) died in route to another <lb/>healthcare facility. Approximately one-third (32%, n = 427) of infants and children were referred <lb/>to a hospital after an outpatient encounter; of those, 10% (n = 41) died en route to the hospital <lb/>and 19% (n = 82) died days later without reaching the referral facility. Among all 1,326 infant <lb/>and child deaths evaluated, 739 (56%) died during hospitalization. There were 376 (28%) infants <lb/>and children who were hospitalized, discharged, and died thereafter, with 86% (n = 325/376) of <lb/>these dying in the community and 14% (n = 51/376) dying in another hospital after readmission. <lb/>The Three Delays-in-Healthcare <lb/>Overall, 854/1,326 (64%) infants and children had at least one delay in the &quot;Three Delays-<lb/>in-Healthcare&quot; framework that had been noted by families or in clinical records. However, <lb/>Fig 1. PRISMA flow diagram for case selection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>only 3% (n = 41) had a delay in all the three categories (Fig 2). In the home, caregivers com-<lb/>monly waited &gt;72 hours from symptom onset to deciding to seek clinical care (32%, <lb/>n = 422). Also in the home, the preferred initial use of traditional medicines as therapy <lb/>(21%, n = 282) and the use of over-the-counter medications (18%, n = 232) were common <lb/>(Fig 3). Delays in attempting to reach a healthcare facility were less common overall. There <lb/>were 4% (n = 51) who were turned away from a healthcare facility and 4% (n = 51) experi-<lb/>enced challenges with transportation to healthcare facilities. In healthcare facilities, pre-<lb/>scription medication unavailability (8%, n = 102), equipment unavailability or lack of bed <lb/>availability to escalate care (5%, n = 72), and challenges accessing diagnostic tests (4%, <lb/>n = 56) were most common. <lb/>A slightly greater proportion of children aged 12-59 months experienced at least one <lb/>delay compared to infants aged 1-11 months (68% vs. 61%, P = 0.018) (Fig 4). There were no <lb/>significant differences in delays by participant sex. A minimally greater proportion of infants <lb/>and children who died outside healthcare facilities experienced a delay in the decision to <lb/>seek clinical care compared to those who died in a healthcare facility (74% vs 68%, <lb/>P = 0.026). <lb/>Table 1. Demographics of infants and children who died in the Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveil-<lb/>lance network. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>n (%) <lb/>Age at Death in Months (median, IQR) (n = 1,321) a <lb/>11 (5, 23) <lb/>Age Group at Death, (n = 1,326) <lb/>1 month to less &lt;12 months old <lb/>685 (51.7) <lb/>12 months old to &lt;60 months old <lb/>641 (48.3) <lb/>Sex, (n = 1,324) b <lb/>Male <lb/>712 (53.8) <lb/>Female <lb/>612 (46.2) <lb/>Country of CHAMPS Site, (n = 1,326) <lb/>Bangladesh <lb/>78 (5.9) <lb/>Ethiopia <lb/>57 (4.3) <lb/>Kenya <lb/>287 (21.6) <lb/>Mali <lb/>235 (17.7) <lb/>Mozambique <lb/>256 (19.3) <lb/>Sierra Leone <lb/>257 (19.4) <lb/>South Africa <lb/>156 (11.8) <lb/>Site of Death, (n = 1,325) c <lb/>Healthcare Facility <lb/>819 (61.8) <lb/>Community <lb/>506 (38.2) <lb/>Number of Causes of Death Determined by Minimally Invasive Tissue Sampling d (n = 652) <lb/>Undetermined <lb/>10 (1.5) <lb/>1 <lb/>140 (21.5) <lb/>2 <lb/>207 (31.7) <lb/>3 <lb/>154 (23.6) <lb/>�4 <lb/>141 (21.7) <lb/>a <lb/>Five cases did not have an exact age at the time of death. <lb/>b Two cases did not have sex documented. <lb/>c <lb/>One case was missing a location of death. <lb/>d <lb/>Not all cases included underwent minimally invasive tissue sampling. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Clinical care received by deceased infants and children and their caregivers in the Child Health and Mor-<lb/>tality Prevention Surveillance network (N = 1,326). <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>n (%) <lb/>Received traditional healer care/medicines <lb/>(21.3) <lb/>Any time in their clinical care course <lb/>(18.3) <lb/>Without receiving medical care <lb/>(2.9) <lb/>Received over-the-counter medicine <lb/>(17.5) <lb/>Any time in their clinical care course <lb/>(14.3) <lb/>Without receiving medical care <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>Was dead on arrival to healthcare facility <lb/>(12.2) <lb/>At an outpatient facility <lb/>(4.7) <lb/>At a hospital <lb/>100 (7.5) <lb/>Died during resuscitation shortly after presentation <lb/>(1.7) <lb/>Outpatient facility <lb/>2 (0.2) <lb/>Hospital <lb/>(1.6) <lb/>Referred to hospital after outpatient visit <lb/>(32.2) <lb/>Seen at any outpatient clinic, referred, but died en route <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>Seen at any outpatient clinic, referred, but did not go to referred facility and died <lb/>(6.2) <lb/>Not referred to hospital after outpatient clinic <lb/>(33.7) <lb/>Seen at any outpatient clinic, sent home, died en route to healthcare facility <lb/>(5.3) <lb/>Seen at outpatient and died at home without subsequent visits <lb/>(28.4) <lb/>Children seen at a hospital, sent home, then died after <lb/>(28.4) <lb/>Community <lb/>(86.4) <lb/>Another hospital <lb/>51 (13.6) <lb/>Days to death after any clinical visit (median, IQR) (n = 649) <lb/>1 (0, 4) <lb/>Caregivers left clinical care against medical advice <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>During outpatient visits <lb/>2 (0.2) <lb/>During hospital admission <lb/>(1.0) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.t002 <lb/>Fig 2. Venn diagram of each type of delay among deceased infants and children (N = 1,326). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>The proportion of infants and children who experienced any delay in the &quot;Three Delays-in-<lb/>Healthcare&quot; model was highest in Bangladesh (86% n = 67/78) and Kenya (74%, n = 213/287), <lb/>and lowest in Ethiopia (49%, n = 28/57) and Mozambique (56%, n = 142/256), with some vari-<lb/>ation seen in the type of delays encountered across sites (Table B in S1 Text). Waiting &gt;72 <lb/>hours to seek care was more common in Bangladesh (65%, n = 51/78) (P&lt;0.001) than other <lb/>sites (Fig 5). The preferred initial use of traditional medicine was most common in Mali <lb/>(39.1%, n = 92/235), Kenya (37%, n = 107/287), and Bangladesh (32%, n = 25/78). Financial <lb/>challenges for transport and paying for clinical care were common in Bangladesh (26%, <lb/>n = 20/78). Deceased infants and children in Sierra Leone commonly faced challenges with <lb/>prescription medication availability (18%, n = 46/257). Delays did not vary substantially by age <lb/>in site-specific analyses (Fig C in S1 Text). <lb/>Among the 755 included cases that underwent full postmortem examinations to determine <lb/>the cause of death, those who had a chronic condition (e.g., HIV, congenital birth defects, etc.) <lb/>(69.3%, 232/335) were more likely to experience a delay in the home than those without a <lb/>chronic condition (59.5%, 250/420; P = 0.007). There were no differences in delays in transport <lb/>or receipt of clinical care between infants and children who had a chronic condition and those <lb/>who did not. Children who died from HIV (n = 82, 83%) were more likely to experience at <lb/>least one delay than those who died from meningitis/encephalitis (n = 41, 56%; P = 0.002; <lb/>q = 0.048), congenital birth defects (n = 51, 57%; P = 0.001; q = 0.048), anemias (n = 95, 65%; P <lb/>= 0.010; q = 0.092), lower respiratory infections (n = 306, 67%; P = 0.006; q = 0.086), and sepsis <lb/>(n = 261, 67%; P = 0.008; q = 0.086) (Fig D in S1 Text). Children who had anemias as a cause <lb/>of death (n = 95, 36%) encountered more delays in the provision of care compared to children <lb/>with other diagnoses (P = 0.033). <lb/>Fig 3. Proportion of deceased infants and children who experienced each delay in the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; model. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 4. Proportion of infants and children who experienced each delay in &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; framework by age group, country site, <lb/>sex, and site of death. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>Delays in healthcare seeking and provision were common among infants and children who <lb/>died in seven sites in sub-Saharan Africa and Bangladesh, highlighting one aspect of the pre-<lb/>ventability of these deaths. Nearly two-thirds of deceased infants and children had at least one <lb/>delay prior to their death. Delays in the home were more common than delays receiving <lb/>Fig 5. Proportion of delays in the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; model among deceased infants and children by country site. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>clinical care. Deceased children aged 12-59 months experienced more delays than deceased <lb/>infants aged 1-11 months. The frequency and type of delays varied by country where the infant <lb/>or child died. <lb/>Similar to prior studies that evaluated healthcare seeking patterns for febrile infants and <lb/>young children with pneumonia, caregivers frequently delayed seeking clinical care for &gt;72 <lb/>hours in our multi-site study [9, 22]. Our study extends these findings to several other condi-<lb/>tions including sepsis, diarrheal diseases, malnutrition, and others. Thus, educational interven-<lb/>tions or the use of health applications for caregivers on general warning signs and symptoms <lb/>in which waiting &gt;72 hours to seek care, or using over-the-counter medications alone, may be <lb/>dangerous, and not just disease specific signs and symptoms, may be warranted [5]. <lb/>Although delays in attempting to reach a healthcare facility were least common of the <lb/>Three Delays in our study, transportation challenges were the most common type of delay <lb/>among those under the category of delays &quot;attempting to reach a healthcare facility&quot;. This is <lb/>consistent with prior studies demonstrating that transportation barriers may be common <lb/>among both adult patients and caregivers of pediatric patients [9, 23, 32]. Thus, as health sys-<lb/>tems are strengthened in low-and middle-income countries, a focus on timely and cost-effec-<lb/>tive transportation to healthcare facilities, the provision of health care in transit (e.g., <lb/>ambulances), and community-based health volunteers is needed. This may include expanded <lb/>access to ambulances and other forms of transportation as has been done in India with the <lb/>Referral Transportation System, which created a partnership between local governments and <lb/>private vehicles by creating a centralized call center that connects patients with previously con-<lb/>tracted private vehicles and provides free transportation services for patients in need [33]. <lb/>Efforts are underway in the CHAMPS network in Mozambique to facilitate transportation to <lb/>healthcare facilities. The impact of such efforts on childhood mortality should be measured in <lb/>future work. <lb/>One-third of deceased patients were seen at an outpatient clinic and not referred to a hospi-<lb/>tal. There is previous evidence that in low-income countries, adequate triage and management <lb/>of sick children remains insufficient and diagnostic uncertainty is frequent, contributing to <lb/>raise the mortality burden [34-36]. In healthcare facilities, similar to our findings, prescription <lb/>medication unavailability has been identified in prior studies in Malawi and India [30, 37]. <lb/>Caregivers may not be aware of medication shortages in hospitals or clinics [22, 38], which <lb/>could have led to an underestimate of medication shortages in our study given our data <lb/>sources. Additionally, our finding that lack of bed availability for escalation of care and equip-<lb/>ment availability issues were common is consistent with a study by Kakembo et al. in Uganda <lb/>in which 56% of surgical patients had delayed surgery due to lack of hospital ward capacity <lb/>and equipment issues [8]. Thus, structural support in healthcare systems including, but not <lb/>limited to, transportation, road conditions, availability of skilled technicians, access to electric-<lb/>ity may be needed to ensure adequate pharmacologic resources as well as equipment resources <lb/>to improve clinical care in settings similar to those in the CHAMPS network [39, 40]. <lb/>Similar to prior studies [25, 26, 41], deceased children aged 12-59 months had more delays <lb/>than infants aged 1-11 months in our study. This may suggest greater caregiver concern for <lb/>younger infants who are unable to localize pain or describe symptoms. Alternatively, there <lb/>could be greater concern for the fragility of infants compared to older children. <lb/>We found no significant differences in healthcare seeking delays between deaths occurring <lb/>in male infants and children compared to females. Prior work evaluating healthcare seeking <lb/>delays by sex has shown mixed results with some suggesting delays are more common for <lb/>female children and others not demonstrating the same difference [24, 26-28, 42]. As these <lb/>prior studies focused on non-fatal conditions, our findings may suggest that healthcare seeking <lb/>behaviors are not different by sex for severe illness. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<body>There was a significant difference in the number and type of delays among deceased infants <lb/>and children by site. This was anticipated given the variability in resources and transportation <lb/>options between sites. Few studies have been designed to allow cross-country comparisons of <lb/>delays in healthcare seeking [8, 11, 23]. Caregivers at each site shared similar patterns in <lb/>healthcare seeking delays in the home, which points toward widespread need for improved <lb/>education on when to seek clinical care for infants and children. Culture, context, and feasibil-<lb/>ity need to be accounted for when developing such interventions. For example, in countries <lb/>with higher initial preferred use of traditional medicine, such as Mali, Kenya, and Bangladesh, <lb/>public health officials and clinicians may consider partnering with traditional healers to dis-<lb/>seminate information on when to refer to a higher level of care [43-46]. However, direct com-<lb/>parisons between countries are difficult given variability in urbanicity, resources in healthcare <lb/>facilities, and cost of clinical care. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>We could only account for delays in healthcare seeking that were described in clinical sum-<lb/>maries or shared by caregivers after their infant or child died, which may have been subject <lb/>to recall bias, particularly when discussing a distressing topic such as the death of their infant <lb/>or child. Delays not described in those narratives may still have existed (e.g., provision of <lb/>counterfeit medications, out of pocket costs or indirect costs for clinical care, distance to <lb/>healthcare facilities, or other structural factors that may impact delays in care seeking as <lb/>described in previous studies) [47, 48]. Given the retrospective nature of this study, we did <lb/>not have detailed information about distances from homes to healthcare facilities or the <lb/>socioeconomic status of families of deceased infants and children, which precluded our abil-<lb/>ity to comment on the impact of distance as a barrier to seeking healthcare or the impact of <lb/>socioeconomic barriers on healthcare seeking behaviors. We were also limited in the number <lb/>of children included in each cause of death, which resulted in small numbers in the compari-<lb/>son of delays by diagnoses. There are no traditional controls in CHAMPS so there was no <lb/>comparison to children who did not die, making it impossible to draw conclusions about <lb/>delays definitively leading to mortality among infants and children. These data were col-<lb/>lected prior to the availability of the 2022 WHO Verbal Autopsy form, which may reduce the <lb/>duration of the interview through improved question wording and flow [49]. Additional <lb/>studies may be warranted to assess delays in care seeking using the updated WHO Verbal <lb/>Autopsy form. Lastly, as caregivers and clinicians were not asked specific details about each <lb/>component of the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; framework, our findings may underesti-<lb/>mate the true frequency of these delays. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Delays in healthcare seeking and provision were common among deceased infants and chil-<lb/>dren in seven regions with high childhood mortality rates in sub-Saharan Africa and Bangla-<lb/>desh. Community-based interventions to prompt timely healthcare seeking should be <lb/>studied as a potential approach to reduce mortality among infants and children. Efforts are <lb/>needed to ensure timely, affordable, and safe transportation to healthcare facilities and to <lb/>address stock-outs and equipment maintenance, so that indicated medications and function-<lb/>ing equipment are available in healthcare facilities to ensure high-quality clinical care for <lb/>infants and children. It is imperative that solutions and interventions account for both <lb/>regional and national needs given the differences in delays experienced by children depend-<lb/>ing on their country of origin. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Text. Tables A, B and Figs A-D. Table A. Summary of DeCoDed causes of death for <lb/>infants and children aged 1-59 months who died in the CHAMPS network (N = 1,326). <lb/>Table B. Proportion of deaths that had experienced each delay in the 3 delays model by site, <lb/>sex, age group, causes of death, and site of death, N = 1,326. Fig A. Highest level of healthcare <lb/>facilities in which deceased infants and children received clinical (N = 1,326). Fig B. Venn dia-<lb/>gram representing the intersectionality of care for infants and children in the CHAMPS Net-<lb/>work between outpatient clinical visits, hospital clinical visits and traditional healing <lb/>(N = 1,326). Fig C. Proportion of delays in the &quot;Three Delays-in-Healthcare&quot; model among <lb/>deceased infants and children by country site by age. Fig D. Frequencies of delays in the 3 <lb/>delays model (A) and frequencies of specific challenges (B) for the top ten DeCoDed causes of <lb/>death anywhere in the causal chain. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Text. STROBE checklist. <lb/>(DOC) <lb/>S1 Acknowledgments. CHAMPS consortium members. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We extend our deepest gratitude to the families who enrolled in CHAMPS to understand why <lb/>their child died. We would also like to thank the CHAMPS staff in each site for their insights, <lb/>expertise, and continued commitment to ensuring that high quality data are collected in this <lb/>project and available globally for developing strategies and interventions to save lives. <lb/>Disclaimer: Several authors are employed by the US Centers for Disease Control and Pre-<lb/>vention (CDC). The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the author(s) and do <lb/>not necessarily represent the official position of the CDC. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Kitiezo Aggrey Igunza, Zachary J. Madewell, J. Anthony G. Scott, Lola <lb/>Madrid, Yenenesh Tilahun, Quique Bassat, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad <lb/>Dangor, Sana Mahtab, Cynthia G. Whitney, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Robert <lb/>F. Breiman, Beth A. Tippett Barr, Chris A. Rees. <lb/>Data curation: Elisa Garcia Gomez, Victor Akelo, Dickens Onyango, Shams El Arifeen, Emily <lb/>S. Gurley, Mohammad Zahid Hossain, Md Atique Iqbal Chowdhury, Kazi Munisul Islam, <lb/>Nega Assefa, J. Anthony G. Scott, Lola Madrid, Yenenesh Tilahun, Stian Orlien, Karen L. <lb/>Kotloff, Milagritos D. Tapia, Adama Mamby Keita, Ashka Mehta, Amilcar Magac ¸o, David <lb/>Torres-Fernandez, Ariel Nhacolo, Quique Bassat, Ina ´cio Mandomando, Carrie Jo Cain, <lb/>Ronita Luke, Sorie I. B. Kamara, Hailemariam Legesse, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad Dangor, Sana <lb/>Mahtab, Amy Wise, Yasmin Adam, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Beth A. Tippett <lb/>Barr. <lb/>Formal analysis: Elisa Garcia Gomez, Zachary J. Madewell. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Quique Bassat, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Cynthia G. Whitney, Dianna M. <lb/>Blau, Robert F. Breiman. <lb/>Investigation: Elisa Garcia Gomez, Kitiezo Aggrey Igunza, Victor Akelo, Dickens Onyango, <lb/>Shams El Arifeen, Emily S. Gurley, Mohammad Zahid Hossain, Md Atique Iqbal <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Chowdhury, Kazi Munisul Islam, Nega Assefa, J. Anthony G. Scott, Lola Madrid, Yenenesh <lb/>Tilahun, Stian Orlien, Karen L. Kotloff, Milagritos D. Tapia, Adama Mamby Keita, Ashka <lb/>Mehta, Amilcar Magac ¸o, David Torres-Fernandez, Ariel Nhacolo, Quique Bassat, Ina ´cio <lb/>Mandomando, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Carrie Jo Cain, Ronita Luke, Sorie I. B. Kamara, Hai-<lb/>lemariam Legesse, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad Dangor, Sana Mahtab, Amy Wise, Yasmin Adam, <lb/>Cynthia G. Whitney, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Robert F. Breiman, Beth A. Tip-<lb/>pett Barr, Chris A. Rees. <lb/>Methodology: Elisa Garcia Gomez, Kitiezo Aggrey Igunza, Victor Akelo, Dickens Onyango, <lb/>Shams El Arifeen, Emily S. Gurley, Mohammad Zahid Hossain, Md Atique Iqbal Chowdh-<lb/>ury, Kazi Munisul Islam, Nega Assefa, J. Anthony G. Scott, Lola Madrid, Yenenesh Tilahun, <lb/>Stian Orlien, Karen L. Kotloff, Milagritos D. Tapia, Adama Mamby Keita, Ashka Mehta, <lb/>Amilcar Magac ¸o, David Torres-Fernandez, Ariel Nhacolo, Quique Bassat, Ina ´cio Mando-<lb/>mando, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Carrie Jo Cain, Ronita Luke, Sorie I. B. Kamara, Hailemar-<lb/>iam Legesse, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad Dangor, Sana Mahtab, Amy Wise, Yasmin Adam, <lb/>Cynthia G. Whitney, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Robert F. Breiman, Beth A. Tip-<lb/>pett Barr, Chris A. Rees. <lb/>Project administration: Victor Akelo, Dickens Onyango, Shams El Arifeen, Nega Assefa, <lb/>Ashka Mehta. <lb/>Resources: Emily S. Gurley, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau. <lb/>Software: Zachary J. Madewell, Dianna M. Blau. <lb/>Supervision: Victor Akelo, Dickens Onyango, Shams El Arifeen, Nega Assefa, Karen L. Kotl-<lb/>off, Milagritos D. Tapia, Amilcar Magac ¸o, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad <lb/>Dangor, Cynthia G. Whitney, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Beth A. Tippett Barr, <lb/>Chris A. Rees. <lb/>Validation: Zachary J. Madewell. <lb/>Visualization: Elisa Garcia Gomez, Emily S. Gurley, Quique Bassat, Beth A. Tippett Barr. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Elisa Garcia Gomez. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kitiezo Aggrey Igunza, Zachary J. Madewell, Victor Akelo, Dick-<lb/>ens Onyango, Shams El Arifeen, Emily S. Gurley, Mohammad Zahid Hossain, Md Atique <lb/>Iqbal Chowdhury, Kazi Munisul Islam, Nega Assefa, J. Anthony G. Scott, Lola Madrid, <lb/>Yenenesh Tilahun, Stian Orlien, Karen L. Kotloff, Milagritos D. Tapia, Adama Mamby <lb/>Keita, Ashka Mehta, Amilcar Magac ¸o, David Torres-Fernandez, Ariel Nhacolo, Quique <lb/>Bassat, Ina ´cio Mandomando, Ikechukwu Ogbuanu, Carrie Jo Cain, Ronita Luke, Sorie I. B. <lb/>Kamara, Hailemariam Legesse, Shabir Madhi, Ziyaad Dangor, Sana Mahtab, Amy Wise, <lb/>Yasmin Adam, Cynthia G. Whitney, Portia C. Mutevedzi, Dianna M. Blau, Robert F. Brei-<lb/>man, Beth A. Tippett Barr, Chris A. Rees. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. UNICEF. Levels &amp; Trends in Child Mortality Report 2022. 2022. https://data.unicef.org/resources/ <lb/>levels-and-trends-in-child-mortality/. <lb/>2. Forde I, Tripathi V. Association of place of residence and Under-Five mortality in middle-and low-<lb/>income countries: a meta-analysis. Children (Basel). 2018; 5(4):51. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>children5040051 PMID: 29670054 <lb/>3. Kinney MV, Kerber KJ, Blac RE, Cohe B, Nkruma F, Coovadia H, et al. Sub-Saharan Africa&apos;s mothers, <lb/>newborns, and children: where and why do they die? PLoS Med. 2010; 7(6):e1000294. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pmed.1000294 PMID: 20574524 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>4. Kagabo DM, Kirk CM, Bakundukize B, Hedt-Gauthier BL, Gupta N, Hirschhorn LR, et al. Care-seeking <lb/>patterns among families that experienced under-five child mortality in rural Rwanda. PLoS One. 2018; <lb/>13(1):e0190739. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0190739 PMID: 29320556 <lb/>5. Madewell ZJ, Whitney CG, Velaphi S, Mutevedzi P, Mahtab S, Madhi SA, et al. Prioritizing Health Care <lb/>Strategies to Reduce Childhood Mortality. JAMA Netw Open. 2022; 5(10):e2237689. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.37689 PMID: 36269354 <lb/>6. Barnes-Josiah D, Myntti C, Augustin A. The &quot;three delays&quot; as a framework for examining maternal mor-<lb/>tality in Haiti. Soc Sci Med. 1998; 46(8):981-93. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0277-9536(97)10018-1 PMID: <lb/>9579750 <lb/>7. Pilkington M, Situma M, Winthrop A, Poenaru D. Quantifying delays and self-identified barriers to timely <lb/>access to pediatric surgery at Mbarara Regional Referral Hospital, Uganda. J Pediatr Surg. 2018; 53 <lb/>(5):1073-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2018.02.045 PMID: 29548493 <lb/>8. Kakembo N, Godier-Furnemont A, Nabirye A, Cheung M, Kisa P, Muzira A, et al. Barriers to Pediatric <lb/>Surgical Care in Low-Income Countries: The Three Delays&apos; Impact in Uganda. J Surg Res. 2019; <lb/>242:193-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jss.2019.03.058 PMID: 31085367 <lb/>9. Snavely ME, Maze MJ, Muiruri C, Ngowi L, Mboya F, Beamesderfer J, et al. Sociocultural and health <lb/>system factors associated with mortality among febrile inpatients in Tanzania: A prospective social <lb/>biopsy cohort study. BMJ Glob Heal. 2018; 3(1):e000507. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000507 <lb/>PMID: 29527339 <lb/>10. Papali A, McCurdy MT, Calvello EJB. A &quot;three delays&quot; model for severe sepsis in resource-limited coun-<lb/>tries. J Crit Care. 2015; 30(4):861.e9-861.e14. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcrc.2015.04.003 PMID: <lb/>25956595 <lb/>11. Mazingi D, Burnett E, Mujuru HA, Nathoo K, Tate J, Mwenda J, et al. Delays in presentation of intussus-<lb/>ception and development of gangrene in Zimbabwe. Pan Afr Med J. 2021; 39(Suppl 1):3. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.11604/pamj.supp.2021.39.1.21301 PMID: 34548895 <lb/>12. Price J, Willcox M, Dlamini V, Khosa A, Khanyile P, Seeley J, et al. Care-seeking during fatal childhood <lb/>illness in rural South Africa: A qualitative study. BMJ Open. 2021; 11(4):e043652. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1136/bmjopen-2020-043652 PMID: 33926978 <lb/>13. Keating EM, Sakita F, Mmbaga BT, Amiri I, Nkini G, Rent S, et al. Three delays model applied to pediat-<lb/>ric injury care seeking in Northern Tanzania: A mixed methods study. PLOS Glob Public Heal. 2022; 2 <lb/>(8):e0000657. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0000657 PMID: 36962759 <lb/>14. United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs. Transforming our world: The 2030 Agenda <lb/>for sustainable development. 2015. https://sdgs.un.org/2030agenda <lb/>15. Salzberg NT, Sivalogan K, Bassat Q, Taylor AW, Adedini S, El Arifeen S, et al. Mortality Surveillance <lb/>Methods to Identify and Characterize Deaths in Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveillance Net-<lb/>work Sites. Clin Infect Dis. 2019; 69(Suppl 4):S262-73. https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciz599 PMID: <lb/>31598664 <lb/>16. Taylor AW, Blau DM, Bassat Q, Onyango D, Kotloff KL, El Arifeen S, et al. Initial findings from a novel <lb/>population-based child mortality surveillance approach: a descriptive study. Lancet Glob Heal. 2020; 8 <lb/>(7):e909-19. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30205-9 PMID: 32562647 <lb/>17. World Health Organization. Manual for the training of Interviewers on the use of the 2016 WHO VA <lb/>Instrument. 2017. https://www.who.int/standards/classifications/other-classifications/verbal-autopsy-<lb/>standards-ascertaining-and-attributing-causes-of-death-tool <lb/>18. Blau DM, Caneer JP, Philipsborn RP, Madhi SA, Bassat Q, Varo R, et al. Overview and Development of <lb/>the Child Health and Mortality Prevention Surveillance Determination of Cause of Death (DeCoDe) Pro-<lb/>cess and DeCoDe Diagnosis Standards. Clin Infect Dis. 2019; 69(Suppl 4):S333-41. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1093/cid/ciz572 PMID: 31598661 <lb/>19. World Health Organization. The WHO application of ICD-10 to deaths during the perinatal period: ICD-<lb/>PM. 2016. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241549752 <lb/>20. World Health Organization. International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Prob-<lb/>lems 10th Revision. 5th ed. 2015. https://www.who.int/standards/classifications/classification-of-<lb/>diseases <lb/>21. Breiman RF, Blau DM, Mutevedzi P, Akelo V, Mandomando I, Ogbuanu IU, et al. Postmortem investiga-<lb/>tions and identification of multiple causes of child deaths: An analysis of findings from the Child Health <lb/>and Mortality Prevention Surveillance (CHAMPS) network. PLoS Med. 2021; 18(9):1-19. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1003814 PMID: 34591862 <lb/>22. Pajuelo MJ, Anticona Huaynate C, Correa M, Mayta Malpartida H, Ramal Asayag C, Seminario JR, <lb/>et al. Delays in seeking and receiving health care services for pneumonia in children under five in the <lb/>Peruvian Amazon: A mixed-methods study on caregivers&apos; perceptions. BMC Health Serv Res. 2018; 18 <lb/>(1):149. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-018-2950-z PMID: 29490643 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>23. Kodish SR, Allen BGS, Salou H, Schwendler TR, Isanaka S. Conceptualising factors impacting nutrition <lb/>services coverage of treatment for acute malnutrition in children: an application of the Three Delays <lb/>Model in Niger. Public Health Nutr. 2021; 26(5):1074-1081. https://doi.org/10.1017/ <lb/>S1368980021004286 PMID: 34620262 <lb/>24. Haque MR, Parr N, Muhidin S. Parents&apos; healthcare-seeking behavior for their children among the cli-<lb/>mate-related displaced population of rural Bangladesh. Soc Sci Med. 2019; 226:9-20. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.socscimed.2019.02.032 PMID: 30831558 <lb/>25. Lungu EA, Darker C, Biesma R. Determinants of healthcare seeking for childhood illnesses among <lb/>caregivers of under-five children in urban slums in Malawi: a population-based cross-sectional study. <lb/>BMC Pediatr. 2020; 20:20. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12887-020-1913-9 PMID: 31952484 <lb/>26. Adinan J, Damian DJ, Mosha NR, Mboya IB, Mamseri R, Msuya SE. Individual and contextual factors <lb/>associated with appropriate healthcare seeking behavior among febrile children in Tanzania. PLoS <lb/>One. 2017; 12(4):e0175446. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0175446 PMID: 28406952 <lb/>27. Budu E, Seidu A-A, Ameyaw EK, Agbaglo E, Adu C, Commey F, et al. Factors associated with health-<lb/>care seeking for childhood illnesses among mothers of children under five in Chad. Hodges MH, edi-<lb/>tor. PLoS One. 2021; 16(8):e0254885. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0254885 PMID: <lb/>34351941 <lb/>28. Chandwani H, Pandor J. Healthcare-Seeking Behaviors of Mothers regarding their Children in a Tribal <lb/>Community of Gujarat, India. Electron Physician. 2015; 7(1):990-7. https://doi.org/10.14661/2015.990-<lb/>997 PMID: 26052410 <lb/>29. Diaz T, George AS, Rao SR, Bangura PS, Baimba JB, McMahon SA, et al. Healthcare seeking for diar-<lb/>rhoea, malaria and pneumonia among children in four poor rural districts in Sierra Leone in the context <lb/>of free health care: results of a cross-sectional survey. BMC Public Health. 2013; 13:157. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1186/1471-2458-13-157 PMID: 23425576 <lb/>30. Lungu EA, Biesma R, Chirwa M, Darker C. Healthcare seeking practices and barriers to accessing <lb/>under-five child health services in urban slums in Malawi: a qualitative study. BMC Health Serv Res. <lb/>2016; 16:410. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-016-1678-x PMID: 27542836 <lb/>31. Benjamini Y, Drai D, Elmer G, Kafkafi N, Golani I. Controlling the false discovery rate in behavior genet-<lb/>ics research. Behav Brain Res. 2001; 125(1-2):279-84. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0166-4328(01)00297-<lb/>2 PMID: 11682119 <lb/>32. Ferdous F, Dil Farzana F, Ahmed S, Das SK, Malek MA, Das J, et al. Mothers&apos; Perception and Health-<lb/>care Seeking Behavior of Pneumonia Children in Rural Bangladesh. ISRN Fam Med. 2014; <lb/>2014:690315. https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/690315 PMID: 24967328 <lb/>33. Prinja S, Jeet G, Kaur M, Aggarwal AK, Manchanda N, Kumar R. Impact of referral transport system on <lb/>institutional deliveries in Haryana, India. Indian J Med Res. 2014; 139(6):883-91. PMID: 25109723 <lb/>34. Achan J, Tibenderana J, Kyabayinze D, Mawejje H, Mugizi R, Mpeka B, et al. Case management of <lb/>severe malaria-a forgotten practice: Experiences from health facilities in Uganda. PLoS One. 2011; 6 <lb/>(3):1-7. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0017053 PMID: 21390301 <lb/>35. Chang JL, Reyes R, Matte M, Ntaro M, Mulogo E, Wiens MO, et al. Who stays and who goes: Predictors <lb/>of admission among patients presenting with febrile illness and a positive malaria rapid diagnostic test <lb/>in a rural Ugandan health center. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2018; 99(4):1080-8. https://doi.org/10.4269/ <lb/>ajtmh.18-0338 PMID: 30062988 <lb/>36. Elnour FA, Alagib MEA, Bansal D, Farag EABA, Malik EM. Severe malaria management: Current situa-<lb/>tion, challenges and lessons learned from Gezira State, Sudan. Malar J. 2019; 18(1):170. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1186/s12936-019-2805-z PMID: 31088466 <lb/>37. Shah B, Krishnan N, Kodish SR, Yenokyan G, Fatema K, Burhan Uddin K, et al. Applying the Three <lb/>Delays Model to understand emergency care seeking and delivery in rural Bangladesh: a qualitative <lb/>study. BMJ Open. 2020; 10:e042690. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2020-042690 PMID: <lb/>33361169 <lb/>38. Roder-DeWan S, Gupta N, Kagabo DM, Habumugisha L, Nahimana E, Mugeni C, et al. Four delays of <lb/>child mortality in Rwanda: a mixed methods analysis of verbal social autopsies. BMJ Open. 2019; 9: <lb/>e027435. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2018-027435 PMID: 31133592 <lb/>39. Yadav H, Shah D, Sayed S, Horton S, Schroeder LF. Availability of essential diagnostics in ten low-<lb/>income and middle-income countries: results from national health facility surveys. Lancet Glob Heal. <lb/>2021; 9(11):e1553-60. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00442-3 PMID: 34626546 <lb/>40. Peeling RW, Mabey D. Point-of-care tests for diagnosing infections in the developing world. Clin Micro-<lb/>biol Infect. 2010; 16(8):1062-9. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-0691.2010.03279.x PMID: 20670288 <lb/>41. Abegaz NT, Berhe H, Gebretekle GB. Mothers/caregivers healthcare seeking behavior towards child-<lb/>hood illness in selected health centers in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia: a facility-based cross-sectional study. <lb/>BMC Pediatr. 2019; 19:220. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12887-019-1588-2 PMID: 31269920 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>42. Ahinkorah BO, Budu E, Seidu A-A, Agbaglo E, Adu C, Ameyaw EK, et al. Barriers to healthcare access <lb/>and healthcare seeking for childhood illnesses among childbearing women in sub-Saharan Africa: A <lb/>multilevel modelling of Demographic and Health Surveys. Marotta C, editor. PLoS One. 2021; 16(2): <lb/>e0244395. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0244395 PMID: 33556057 <lb/>43. World Health Organization. WHO Traditional Medicine Strategy 2014-2023. 2014. https://www.who.int/ <lb/>publications/i/item/9789241506096 <lb/>44. Sundararajan R, Langa P V., Morshed T, Manuel S. Traditional healers as client advocates in the HIV-<lb/>endemic region of Maputo, Mozambique: results from a qualitative study. SAHARA-J J Soc Asp HIV/ <lb/>AIDS. 2021; 18(1):77-85. https://doi.org/10.1080/17290376.2021.1909492 PMID: 33902401 <lb/>45. Kwame A. Integrating Traditional Medicine and Healing into the Ghanaian Mainstream Health System: <lb/>Voices From Within. Qual Health Res. 2021; 31(10):1847-60. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>10497323211008849 PMID: 33980093 <lb/>46. Mutola S, Pemunta NV, Ngo NV. Utilization of traditional medicine and its integration into the healthcare <lb/>system in Qokolweni, South Africa; prospects for enhanced universal health coverage. Complement <lb/>Ther Clin Pract. 2021; 43:101386. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctcp.2021.101386 PMID: 33895465 <lb/>47. Shaw B, Amouzou A, Miller NP, Tafesse M, Bryce J, Surkan PJ. Access to integrated community case <lb/>management of childhood illnesses services in rural Ethiopia: a qualitative study of the perspectives <lb/>and experiences of caregivers. Health Policy Plan. 2016; 31:656-66. https://doi.org/10.1093/heapol/ <lb/>czv115 PMID: 26608585 <lb/>48. Onarheim KH, Sisay MM, Gizaw M, Moland KM, Norheim OF, Miljeteig I. Selling my sheep to pay for <lb/>medicines-household priorities and coping strategies in a setting without universal health coverage. <lb/>BMC Health Serv Res. 2018; 18(1):153. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-018-2943-y PMID: 29499709 <lb/>49. World Health Organization. Revision of the 2016 WHO Verbal Autopsy Instrument. https://cdn.who.int/ <lb/>media/docs/default-source/classification/other-classifications/autopsy/2022-va-instrument/report-<lb/>revision-of-the-2016-who-va-instrument_2022.pdf?sfvrsn=743e9b74_8&amp;download=true. Accessed <lb/>September 7, 2023. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH <lb/>Three Delays in childhood mortality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Global Public Health | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0002494 February 8, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 18 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>