<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-13T13:40:38.714Z">11/13/2025 1:40:38 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T13:40:25.143034Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-13T13:40:25.143034Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>A new point mutation in the HC-Pro of potato <lb/>virus Y is involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/>Giuseppe ParrellaID 1 *, Benoit Moury 2 * <lb/>1 Institute for Sustainable Plant Protection of The National Research Council (IPSP-CNR), Portici, Italy, <lb/>2 INRAE, Pathologie Ve ´ge ´tale, Montfavet, France <lb/>* giuseppe.parrella@ipsp.cnr.it (GP); benoit.moury@inrae.fr (BM) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Tobacco vein necrosis (TVN) is a complex phenomenon regulated by different genetic <lb/>determinants mapped in the HC-Pro protein (amino acids N 330 , K 391 and E 410 ) and in two <lb/>regions of potato virus Y (PVY) genome, corresponding to the cytoplasmic inclusion (CI) <lb/>protein and the nuclear inclusion protein a-protease (NIa-Pro), respectively. A new determi-<lb/>nant of TVN was discovered in the MK isolate of PVY which, although carried the HC-Pro <lb/>determinants associated to TVN, did not induce TVN. The HC-Pro open reading frame <lb/>(ORF) of the necrotic infectious clone PVY N605 was replaced with that of the non-necrotic <lb/>MK isolate, which differed only by one amino acid at position 392 (T 392 instead of I 392 ). The <lb/>cDNA clone N605_MKHCPro inoculated in tobacco induced only weak mosaics at the sys-<lb/>temic level, demostrating that the amino acid at position 392 is a new determinant for TVN. <lb/>No significant difference in accumulation in tobacco was observed between N605 and <lb/>N605_MKHCPro. Since phylogenetic analyses showed that the loss of necrosis in tobacco <lb/>has occurred several times independently during PVY evolution, these repeated evolutions <lb/>strongly suggest that tobacco necrosis is a costly trait in PVY. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Potato virus Y (PVY) is one of the most important plant viruses with a worldwide distribution <lb/>[1] and infects a wide range of host plants comprising 495 species in 72 genera from 31 fami-<lb/>lies, including numerous economically important solanaceous crop plants, e.g. potato (Sola-<lb/>num tuberosum), pepper (Capsicum spp.), tomato (S. lycopersicum) and tobacco (Nicotiana <lb/>tabacum) [2]. <lb/>PVY belongs to the genus Potyvirus in the family Potyviridae. It has flexuous and filamen-<lb/>tous virions with a length of about 730-740 nm and a diameter of 11 nm. The 5&apos;-end of the <lb/>genome is covalently linked to a genome-linked viral protein (VPg) through a tyrosine residue <lb/>and the 3&apos;-end contains a poly(A)-tail. As in other potyviruses, its genome consist of a posi-<lb/>tive-sense and single-stranded RNA (ssRNA) molecule of about 9.7 kb that is translated into a <lb/>single polyprotein of about 3062 amino acid (aa) residues. It is transmitted at least by 70 spe-<lb/>cies of aphids in a non-persistent manner [3]. <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/>1 / 14 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Parrella G, Moury B (2024) A new point <lb/>mutation in the HC-Pro of potato virus Y is involved <lb/>in tobacco vein necrosis. PLoS ONE 19(5): <lb/>e0302692. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0302692 <lb/>Editor: Shunmugiah Veluchamy Ramesh, ICAR-<lb/>Central Plantation Crops Research Institute, INDIA <lb/>Received: March 6, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: April 8, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 9, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Parrella, Moury. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its Supporting Information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: This research was partially funded by the <lb/>Italian National Research Council (CNR) with the <lb/></front>

			<body>PVY exists in a complex of strain groups and variants. PVY classification is based on: i) <lb/>serology-determined by antibody recognition of the CP, ii) biological properties, like symp-<lb/>tomatology induced in certain hosts (e.g. tobacco) and hypersensitive response (HR) in differ-<lb/>ent potato cultivars carrying resistance genes and iii) phylogenetic relationships among <lb/>isolates based on genome sequence analyses, including number and positions of recombina-<lb/>tion junctions (RJs). Serological, molecular and biological properties of PVY strains are not <lb/>always correlating, because there are numerous PVY strains/variants that have similar serolog-<lb/>ical classification and biological properties but different molecular properties, such as the <lb/>strains inducing tobacco veinal necrosis (TVN) in N. tabacum cvs. Xanthi and Burley: PVY N , <lb/>PVY NTN , PVY NA-NTN , PVY N:O , PVY N:O-B , PVY N-W and PVY NTN-NW [4,5]. Several molecular <lb/>determinants involved in TVN have been mapped on the PVY helper component-proteinase <lb/>(HC-Pro). Based on a pioneer work by Glais et al. [6], who identified the putative TVN domain <lb/>between the 3&apos; end of the P1 gene and the 5&apos; end of the P3 gene, by reverse genetics approach, <lb/>Tribodet et al. [7] demonstrated that amino acids K 391 and E 410 in the C-terminal part of the <lb/>HC-Pro were directly involved in the TVN symptoms. Nevertheless, as reported for the L26 <lb/>strain of PVY, the genetic determinant of TVN is more complex and involves other amino <lb/>acid substitutions in the C-terminal part of the HC-Pro in addition to K 391 and E 410 [8]. In the <lb/>following, numbering of amino acid positions in the HC-Pro follows Adams et al. [9] who <lb/>determined a new position for the P1/HC-Pro cleavage site of PVY, which was 9 residues <lb/>downstream from the original position used for the numbering in Tribodet et al. [7] and sub-<lb/>sequent articles [10]. <lb/>A PVY isolate, MK, collected in Italy in 2009 from a Datura metel plant, showed unusual <lb/>biological and serological characteristics. It was identified serologically as a N or NTN type of <lb/>isolate. Nevetheless, symptoms induced in tobacco consisted in vein clearing and not in vein <lb/>necrosis as expected. <lb/>The objectives of the present work are therefore the complete characterization of the MK <lb/>isolate and the identification of the mutation(s) responsible for its unusual characteristics. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>PVY isolates and infectious clone <lb/>The MK isolate of PVY was collected in summer 2009 from a Datura metel plant showing <lb/>green mosaic (Fig 1), which grew spontaneously in the area surrounding a small farm, located <lb/>in the municipality of Alberobello (province of Bari, southern Italy). The infected plant was <lb/>collected, transplanted in a pot of 20 cm in diameter, maintained in an insect-proof green-<lb/>house and checked serologically against different viruses (cucumber mosaic virus, tomato <lb/>spotted wilt virus, parietaria mottle virus, potato leaf roll virus, potato virus X, potato virus M, <lb/>potato virus S and PVY). Only PVY was detected. Moreover, electron microscope observations <lb/>of D. metel sap extracts by dip method [11], revealed only the presence of elongated virus parti-<lb/>cles and laminates typical of a potyvirus infection [12]. <lb/>Isolate PVY-MK was maintained only in D. metel plants and checked periodically by <lb/>RT-PCR, followed by Sanger sequencing of amplicons corresponding to the HCPro open read-<lb/>ing frame (ORF), and ELISA with a panel of antisera commercially available. Original inoculum <lb/>was also stored at 5˚C as dehydrated leaves, under continuous exposure to calcium chloride. <lb/>Virus obtained from the N605 infectious clone [13] was used as a reference for the PVY N <lb/>group. In addition, isolates Sot-1 and Nit-1, belonging to PVY NTN and PVY Ob groups, respec-<lb/>tively [14,15], were used as controls for the biological and serological assays. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<front>Short Term Mobility (STM) program 2014. The <lb/>funders had no role in study design, data collection <lb/>and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>Biological and serological characterization of PVY-MK <lb/>A set of plant species including Chenopodium amaranticolor, C. quinoa, D. metel, N. tabacum <lb/>cvs. Samsun and Xanthi, N. glutinosa, N. benthamiana, N. clevelandii and S. lycopersicum <lb/>&apos;Momor&apos;was used to characterize the pathotype of the MK isolate. These plants (two replicates <lb/>per species or accession) were mechanically inoculated at the 4-6 leaf stage with sap from <lb/>PVY-MK-infected D. metel plants and with those obtained from tobacco plants infected by <lb/>Sot-1 and Nit-1, following Parrella, [16]. Inoculated plants were maintained in an insect-proof <lb/>greenhouse at 24/18˚C day/night, under natural light conditions. Every week, they were fertil-<lb/>ized by adding complete nutritive complex to the irrigation water. Symptoms were recorded <lb/>weekly up to 2 months after inoculation. <lb/>Inoculated plants and control healthy plants were tested by DAS-ELISA 15 and 30 days <lb/>post inoculation (dpi), essentially as described by Clark and Adams [17], against one poly-<lb/>clonal and two monoclonal antibodies: the &quot;PVY polyclonal&quot;, recognizing all the PVY sero-<lb/>types, the &quot;PVY monoclonal&quot; recognizing PVY Oa , PVY C , PVY N and PVY NTN , and the &quot;PVY N <lb/>monoclonal&quot; recognizing specifically PVY N and PVY NTN serotypes (Bioreba AG, Switzerland) <lb/>[15]. The assay was conducted in duplicate for each sample in polystyrene microtitre plates <lb/>(Nunc TM MicroWell TM 96-Well Microplates, Thermo Scientific TM ) according to manufactur-<lb/>er&apos;s instructions. The mean of absorbance value at 405 nm (OD 405 ) was recorded using a Titer-<lb/>tek Multiskan photometer (Thermo Scientific TM ) every 30 min, during 2h of incubation with <lb/>substrate at room temperature. Samples were considered positive if leaf extract gave an OD 405 <lb/>signal at least twice that obtained from the extract of a healthy plant. <lb/>RNA isolation, cloning and sequencing of the full-length PVY-MK genome <lb/>Total RNA was isolated from a naturally-infected D. metel plant and used to generate the com-<lb/>plete genome sequence of PVY-MK by RT-PCR with seven primer pairs defined from the <lb/>sequence of isolate PVY-12 (Acc. No. AB185833; S1 Table), since this isolate showed serologi-<lb/>cal features similar to PVY-MK [18]. The S, M4 and M4-T primers were used for the amplifi-<lb/>cation of the 5&apos; end of the genome [19], while the 3&apos; end of the genome was amplified using the <lb/>Fig 1. Original Datura metel plant showing mosaic associated to PVY MK infection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>SMARTer 1 RACE 5&apos;/3&apos; kit (Takara Bio Inc. Shiga, Japan), following manufacturer&apos;s instruc-<lb/>tions. Overlapping RT-PCR fragments of approximately 1000 to 1800 bp were cloned into the <lb/>pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega Corp., Madison, WI, U.S.A.) according to standard protocols <lb/>[20]. One to three clones per fragment were sequenced (Genome Express, Grenoble, France). <lb/>Sequence analyses <lb/>Sequences of the primers used to generate the cloned cDNA fragments were removed before <lb/>analysis. The overlapping sequence contigs were assembled with Contig Assembly Program <lb/>[21]. Amino acid sequences were then aligned and compared with the sequence of PVY-12 with <lb/>the Clustal W program [22], using default parameters on the BioEdit software package [23]. <lb/>The Maximum-likelihood method was utilized to construct phylogenetic tree of PVY iso-<lb/>lates, using 1000 bootstrap replicates and the best nucleotide substitution model selected by <lb/>MEGA software (version 7.0.26) [24]. <lb/>The RDP2 software [25] was used to detect recombination events in the PVY-MK genome <lb/>using a set of reference sequences of the N, O and C groups and default parameters for all <lb/>recombination methods implemented in the software (RDP, GENECONV, BootScan, Max-<lb/>Chi, Chimera, SiScan, 3Seq, LARD and Phylpro) [25]. <lb/>Construction of the chimeric infectious PVY clone N605_MKHCPro <lb/>The infectious cDNA clone of PVY isolate N605 was modified (i) by inserting short plant <lb/>intron sequences to increase its stability [26,27] and (ii) by including a cassette containing the <lb/>2μ yeast replication origin and a selectable marker (Trp-1 promoter and gene) as described in <lb/>Fernandez-Delmond et al. [28] and Ayme et al. [29], allowing homologous recombination in <lb/>yeast. The region coding the HC-Pro was deleted by reverse PCR from the N605 clone and a <lb/>unique NotI restriction site was introduced at the junction, yielding the acceptor shuttle vector. <lb/>The entire cDNA corresponding to the HC-Pro coding sequence of the MK isolate was <lb/>obtained with the primers SON41HCdeb (5&apos;-TATGATGCACGTTCCAAGGTTACTCAAGGCG; <lb/>positions 988-1018) and SON41HCend (5&apos;-GCATGCTCCAGGAATACCACCAACTCTATAATG; <lb/>positions 2427-2395). Yeast was co-transformed with the shuttle vector linearized with NotI <lb/>and with cDNA of the MK HC-Pro coding sequence and yielded through homologous recom-<lb/>bination the chimeric clone N605_MKHCPro. The chimeric clone was sequenced in order to <lb/>check its conformity. Infectivity of the chimeric clone was checked by DNA-coated tungsten <lb/>particle bombardments of juvenile plants (four leaf stage) of N. clevelandii and N. benthami-<lb/>ana. The N605 infectious clone was used as control. <lb/>Comparison of accumulation of PVY N605 clone and chimeric clone <lb/>N605_MKHCPro <lb/>The accumulation at the systemic level of N605 and N605_MKHCPro were compared in N. <lb/>tabacum cv. Xanthi. Inocula of both viruses were prepared separately from infected Xanthi <lb/>plants, calibrated using quantitative DAS-ELISA using curves representing OD 405 in function of <lb/>dilution factors as described in Moury and Simon [27] and used for inoculation of 20 Xanthi <lb/>plants per virus. Inoculated plants were placed in a greenhouse in a completely random design. <lb/>Quantitative DAS-ELISAs were performed to estimate the relative PVY concentration in and the <lb/>inoculated Xanthi plants at 15 and 30 dpi (10 plants per virus at each timepoint) and compari-<lb/>sons between the two PVY variants at each date were performed using Kruskal-Wallis tests [30]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>Biological and serological characterization of isolate MK <lb/>The MK isolate induced only vein clearing in tobacco cvs. Xanthi and Samsun, like symptoms <lb/>reported for non-necrotic PVY isolates, e.g. isolate N it-1 (Table 1; [14]). PVY-MK did not <lb/>induce TVN, typical of necrotic isolates, up to 60 dpi, while Sot-1 and N605 showed distinct <lb/>TVN, sometimes associated with leaf distortions, within 14-21 dpi in both Xanthi and Sam-<lb/>sun. On other hosts, symptoms were similar among the four tested PVY isolates (Table 1). <lb/>In serological tests, PVY-MK, Sot-1 and N605 were clearly detected in infected tobacco <lb/>plants by &quot;monoclonal PVY&quot;, &quot;monoclonal PVY N &quot; and &quot;polyclonal PVY&quot; antibodies, while <lb/>Nit-1 was detected only by &quot;polyclonal PVY&quot; antibody (Table 1). <lb/>Sequence analysis and phylogenetic relationships of MK isolate with PVY <lb/>reference strains based on the whole genome <lb/>The genome of isolate MK was determined to be 9702 nt long, excluding the polyA tail. The <lb/>sequence has been deposited in the GenBank database under the accession number <lb/>MF440322. Preliminary BLASTn analysis of the whole genome sequence indicated that the <lb/>closest match was for strains of the PVY NTN group. The PVY isolate closest to MK (98.5% <lb/>nucleotide identity) was isolate IUNG-4 (accession number JF927752), a tobacco isolate col-<lb/>lected in Poland in 2008. Contrary to PVY NTN isolates however, MK did not induce veinal <lb/>necrosis in tobacco after mechanical inoculation. Hence, we suspected that one or a few muta-<lb/>tions in MK were responsible for its atypical phenotype on tobacco. <lb/>Application of the RDP2 package to the analysis of genome sequence indicated that MK <lb/>had a typical PVY NTN recombination pattern with PVY O and PVY N identified as its parents. <lb/>Three recombination breakpoints were confirmed by seven of nine methods (RDP, <lb/>Table 1. Biological and serological properties of PVY isolate MK and reference isolates Sot-1 (PVYNTN), N605 (PVYN) and Nit-1 (PVYO). <lb/>PVY isolate <lb/>MK <lb/>Sot-1 <lb/>Nit-1 <lb/>N605 <lb/>Biological properties <lb/>Chenopodium amaranticolor <lb/>LLc/-a <lb/>LLc/-<lb/>LLc/-<lb/>LLc/-<lb/>C. quinoa <lb/>LLc/-<lb/>LLc/-<lb/>LLc/-<lb/>LLc/-<lb/>Datura metel <lb/>-/mo <lb/>-/mo <lb/>-/mo <lb/>-/mo <lb/>Nicotiana tabacum cv. Xanthi <lb/>-/Vc <lb/>-/VN, ds <lb/>-/Vc <lb/>-/VN <lb/>N. tabacum cv. Samsun <lb/>-/Vc <lb/>-/VN, ds <lb/>-/Vc <lb/>-/VN <lb/>N. benthamiana <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>N. clevelandii <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>-/mo, ds <lb/>Solanum lycopersicum <lb/>-/mo <lb/>-/mo <lb/>-/mo <lb/>nt <lb/>Serological properties <lb/>PVY monoclonal b <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>PVY N monoclonal c <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>PVY polyclonal d <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>a <lb/>local symptoms/ symptoms at the systemic level; LLc = chlorotic local lesions; mo = mosaic; Vc = vein clearing; VN = vein necrosis; ds = distortion; -= no symptoms; <lb/>nt = not tested. <lb/>b recognizes PVY N , PVY Oa and PVY C [15]. <lb/>c <lb/>recognizes PVY N and PVY NTN [15]. <lb/>d <lb/>recognizes PVY N , PVY NTN , PVY O and PVY C . <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>GENECONV, BootScan, MaxChi, Chimera, SiScan and 3Seq) implemented in RDP2: the first <lb/>one between nucleotide positions 2385 and 2415 (99% confidence interval -CI) at the <lb/>HC-Pro/P3 cistron junction, the second one between nucleotide positions 5769 and 5863 <lb/>(99% CI) in the VPg cistron and the third one between nucleotide positions 8547 and 8598 <lb/>(99% CI) at the NIb/CP cistron junction. This recombination pattern is highly similar to that <lb/>of the SYR-I group of PVY [31] (S1 Fig). <lb/>The sequence of the HC-Pro cistron of PVY-MK was aligned and compared with those <lb/>from other reference strains corresponding either to the &quot;N&quot; phylogenetic group (strains <lb/>N605, L26, PVY-12, SASA61 and LW) or to the &quot;O&quot; phylogenetic group (strain O139) <lb/>(Table 2). Thirteen nucleotides differed between the sequences of the HC-Pro coding regions <lb/>of the N605 clone and the MK isolate. The deduced HC-Pro sequences differed only at amino <lb/>acid position 392 with an isoleucine for the N605 clone and a threonine for isolate MK. Note <lb/>that there is one amino acid difference between the deduced HC-Pro sequences of the N605 <lb/>published sequence (GenBank accession number X97895) and the N605 cDNA clone at posi-<lb/>tion 204 (serine for the clone and asparagine for the isolate) (Table 2). Therefore, the amino <lb/>acid substitution at position 392 is a strong candidate for the lack of necrosis in tobacco of iso-<lb/>late MK. <lb/>Blastp analyses (August 5 th , 2022) with the amino acid sequence of the HC-Pro of isolate MK <lb/>revealed that (i) more than 100 PVY isolates have a sequence identical to MK except for the <lb/>I 392 T substitution and (ii) only one PVY isolate carries the I 392 T substitution in addition to MK, <lb/>isolate SASA-61 collected from potato in the UK (accession number AJ585198). Isolate SASA-<lb/>61 encodes a HC-Pro with both residues K 391 and E 410 , required for veinal necrosis in tobacco, <lb/>but does not induce veinal necrosis symptoms on infected tobacco plants, similar to PVY-MK <lb/>[32,33]. In addition, it belongs to a different group of PVY from that of MK, group NA-N (Fig <lb/>2). Consequently, the most parsimonious phylogenetic tree shows that the I 392 T substitution <lb/>was acquired at least twice during PVY evolution, once in the MK branch and once in the <lb/>SASA-61 branch and that it was both times associated to a loss of necrotic symptoms in tobacco. <lb/>Hence, it is highly probable that this mutation confers a fitness benefit to PVY. <lb/>Symptoms induced at the systemic level in tobacco cultivar Xanthi by PVY <lb/>N605 clone and chimera N605_MKHCPro <lb/>Given the frequent involvement of HC-Pro of PVY as a determinant of symptoms in tobacco <lb/>[4,7,8], we tested by reverse genetics using the N605 cDNA clone if the HC-Pro cistron of iso-<lb/>late MK was responsible for the lack of veinal necrosis in that host (Fig 3). For this, we built <lb/>the chimeric cDNA clone N605_MKHCPro, containing the HC-Pro cistron of isolate MK in <lb/>the background of the N605 clone. <lb/>Table 2. Symptoms on tobacco (Vc: vein clearing; VN: vein necrosis) and amino acid residues at critical positions of the HC-Pro of various PVY isolates. <lb/>Isolate/clone <lb/>Strain <lb/>Tobacco <lb/>aa196 <lb/>aa204 <lb/>aa330 <lb/>aa391 <lb/>aa392 <lb/>aa410 <lb/>Acc. No. <lb/>Reference <lb/>MK <lb/>NTN <lb/>Vc <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>T <lb/>E <lb/>MF440322 <lb/>This study <lb/>N605-published <lb/>N <lb/>VN <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>X97895 <lb/>[13] <lb/>N605-clone <lb/>N <lb/>VN <lb/>D <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>-<lb/>This study <lb/>L26 <lb/>NTN <lb/>Vc <lb/>G <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>FJ204165 <lb/>[8] <lb/>PVY-12 <lb/>NTN <lb/>Vc <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>AB185833 <lb/>[18] <lb/>SASA61 <lb/>N <lb/>Vc <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>T <lb/>E <lb/>AJ585198 <lb/>[32] <lb/>LW <lb/>W <lb/>Vc <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>AJ890349 <lb/>[33] <lb/>O139 <lb/>O <lb/>Vc <lb/>D <lb/>N <lb/>D <lb/>R <lb/>I <lb/>D <lb/>U09509 <lb/>[34] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>In five out of five inoculated plants of tobacco cultivar Xanthi, N605 induced veinal necrosis <lb/>but N605_MKHCPro induced only mosaic and vein clearing at the systemic level (Fig 3B). <lb/>Fig 2. Maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree obtained with software MEGA7.0.26 of full-length genome <lb/>sequences of isolate MK, isolate PVY-12 (accession number AB185833) and the 166 PVY isolates described in <lb/>Table 3 in Green et al. [35]. The nucleotide substitution model GTR+G+I (General Time Reversible with Gamma <lb/>distributed rate variation among Invariable sites) was selected. The consensus of 100 bootstrap replicates is shown and <lb/>bootstrap values higher than 70% are indicated. Group names are according to Green et al. [35] and isolates not <lb/>associated with group names are &quot;unclassified&quot; in Green et al. [35]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Accumulation of PVY N605 clone and chimeric clone N605_MKHCPro in <lb/>tobacco <lb/>We tested if the infectious chimera N605_MKHCPro would have acquired the ability to multi-<lb/>ply in tobacco better that the wild type PVY_N605, demonstrating a gain of fitness in such <lb/>host. Results obtained in quantitative ELISA clearly stated that there was no difference in virus <lb/>accumulation at 15 and 30 dpi between the wild type PVY_N605 and the chimera <lb/>N605_MKHCPro (Fig 4). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we have identified a novel PVY determinant -involved in the triggering of sys-<lb/>temic necrosis in tobacco. The MK isolate of PVY, originating from D. metel, did not induce <lb/>systemic necrosis in the Xanthi tobacco cultivar despite the presence of a lysine at amino acid <lb/>position 391 and a glutamic acid at amino acid position 410 of the HC-Pro, a combination of <lb/>amino acids that usually determines systemic necrosis in tobacco [7]. Comparison of HC-Pro <lb/>sequences of isolates MK and N605 followed by reverse genetics validated the involvement of <lb/>the HC-Pro cistron of MK in the absence of necrosis in tobacco. The absence of necrosis was <lb/>not due to a lower multiplication capacity of the N605_MKHCpro chimera, carrying the <lb/>HC-Pro cistron of isolate MK in the background of the N605 clone, since it accumulated at lev-<lb/>els similar to N605 in Xanthi (Fig 4). Since the only amino acid difference in the HC-Pro <lb/>between the MK isolate and the N605 clone corresponds to amino acid 392 (threonine for MK <lb/>and isoleucine for N605) and because all determinants of necrosis in tobacco identified so far <lb/>correspond to nonsynonymous substitutions, it is highly probable that the I 392 T substitution is <lb/>responsible for the absence of necrosis in tobacco plants infected by the MK isolate. <lb/>Systemic necrosis following PVY infection is responsible for considerable yield losses in <lb/>tobacco. These symptoms are induced mainly by the N (Necrotic) group of PVY isolates or <lb/>recombinant isolates with a HC-Pro cistron similar to that of the N group. Another PVY phy-<lb/>logenetic group, comprising pepper and tobacco isolates from Chile, also induces systemic <lb/>veinal necrosis in tobacco [36,37]. Among tobacco cultivars that do not carry any recessive <lb/>resistance gene, only a minority (10 of 162) does not exhibit necrotic symptoms upon PVY <lb/>Fig 3. Symptoms of vein necrosis observed in tobacco cultivar Xanthi after inoculation with PVY N605 infectious clone (A) and of <lb/>vein clearing after inoculation with clone N605_MKHCPro (B), compared with mock-inoculated plant (C). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>infection [38]. The NtTPN1 gene of tobacco, a homologue of Arabidopsis thaliana resistance <lb/>gene RPP8 [39], determines the expression of systemic necrosis or PVY tolerance (lack of <lb/>necrosis) [40]. Hence, it is highly probable that the necrotic phenotypic response induced by <lb/>PVY in tobacco is similar to an induced plant resistance involving a hypersensitive response, <lb/>as in the interaction between the tobacco N gene and tobacco mosaic virus (TMV) helicase <lb/>[41], but not efficient enough to restrict rapidly the virus spread into the plant. <lb/>Two nonsynonymous substitutions at codon positions 391 and 410 in PVY HC-Pro cistron <lb/>were shown to be critical in the induction of necrosis in tobacco. Indeed, mutations K 391 R or <lb/>E 410 D independently abolish the ability to induce necrosis in the context of the &quot;N&quot; type strain <lb/>N605 [7]. However, several PVY isolates described in the following encode the canonical amino <lb/>acids of necrotic strains at these two positions but do not induce systemic necroses in tobacco: <lb/>• The L26 potato isolate (belonging to group NTNa; Table 2) possesses the D 196 G HC-Pro <lb/>mutation that was shown to determine the absence of necrotic properties [8]. <lb/>• The MK and SASA-61 isolates (closely related to the SYR-I group and belonging to group <lb/>NA-N, respectively) carry the I 392 T mutation analyzed in the present article. <lb/>• The LW [33] isolate belongs to group N-Wi and no mutation responsible for the absence of <lb/>necrotic properties has been identified [4]. Several amino acid mutations in the HC-Pro dis-<lb/>tinguish isolate LW from isolates of the same group that induce vein necrosis in tobacco and <lb/>may be responsible for the absence of vein necrosis (mutations K431E, D256E and V91A). <lb/>Alternatively, mutations in regions outside the HC-Pro may also be involved as shown in [4]. <lb/>• The PVY-12 [18] isolate belongs to group NTNb and, as for the previous isolate, no mutation <lb/>responsible for this phenotype has been identified. Again, this could be due mutations in the <lb/>Fig 4. Relative accumulation of N605 and the N605_MKHCPro chimera in N. tabacum cv. Xanthi plants at 15 and <lb/>30 days post inoculation. Quantitative ELISA was performed on apical uninoculated leaves on independent sets of 10 <lb/>plants per virus per date. A Kruskal-Wallis test [30] did not reveal any significant difference between the two viruses at <lb/>each date (p-value &gt; 0.05). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>HC-Pro cistron (PVY-12 carries mutation M264V that is absent in necrotic isolates of the <lb/>same group) or elsewhere in the genome. <lb/>• Finally, several isolates of an &quot;N:O&quot; (or &quot;N:O minus&quot;) group collected in the USA in 2004 or <lb/>later carry mutations at position 330 of HC-Pro that may be involved in the lack of necrotic <lb/>properties in tobacco [4,35]. <lb/>However, some of these non-necrotic isolates do not carry any characterized candidate <lb/>HC-Pro mutation that may be responsible for this phenotype. As for LW or PVY-12, the phe-<lb/>notype could be due to other, uncharacterized HC-Pro mutations or to mutations elsewhere in <lb/>the genome. <lb/>The fact that two consecutive amino acid positions in the HC-Pro (391 and 392) are <lb/>involved in tobacco necrosis suggests that this trait depends on a change in HC-Pro local sur-<lb/>face charge and/or structure that alters its binding with a ligand in tobacco cells. However, the <lb/>nature of amino acid mutations does not clearly support this hypothesis. At position 391, the <lb/>lysine and arginine belong to the same group of positively-charged amino acids. At position <lb/>392, the isoleucine belongs to the hydrophobic group and the threonine to the polar group of <lb/>amino acids. Therefore, no general rule can be seen on the mutations at these two positions <lb/>that affect tobacco necrosis. <lb/>Phylogenetic analyses showed that the loss of necrosis in tobacco has occurred several times <lb/>independently during PVY evolution. At least four independent evolutions towards a loss of <lb/>Fig 5. Schematic phylogenetic tree of non-recombinant PVY HC-Pro coding sequences. The tree was built with the maximum-likelihood method implemented in <lb/>software MEGA7.0.26 using 157 PVY isolates described in Tab 3 in Green et al. [35] plus isolates PVY-12 (accession number AB185833) and MK (this study). The <lb/>nucleotide substitution model TN92+G (Tamura-Nei model with gamma distributed rate variation among sites) was selected. The main PVY groups based on bootstrap <lb/>values higher than 70% are indicated. Group names are according to Green et al. [35]. The N group includes the Eu-N group and several recombinant groups described in <lb/>Green et al. [35]. Isolates carrying the canonical amino acids at positions 391 and 410 of the HC-Pro of necrotic PVY isolates but that do not induce a systemic necrosis in <lb/>tobacco are indicated in red together with the mutation involved in the loss of necrosis, when identified. The asterisk correspond to isolates ME81, MI090004, MN10c_26, <lb/>MN121, MN13a_39, ND121, ND68, NY51 and WI120127 from group N:O. Three of them (ME81, MN10c_26, NY51) carry mutations N 330 K or N 330 S in the HC-Pro that <lb/>may be responsible for the lack of necrosis in tobacco [4]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>necrotic properties in tobacco are inferred: two involving mutation I 392 T for isolates MK and <lb/>SASA-61, which belong to two separate PVY clades, one involving mutation D 196 G for isolate <lb/>L26 and at least one involving other, undetermined, mutations for isolates LW, PVY-12 and <lb/>several other isolates in group N:O [35], for which the HC-Pro cistron sequence belongs to the <lb/>same PVY clade (Fig 5). <lb/>These repeated evolutions strongly suggest that tobacco necrosis is a costly trait in PVY and <lb/>that the lack of necrosis was selected for several times independently. However, the reasons for <lb/>this selection are not obvious, since we did not observe any difference in PVY accumulation at <lb/>the systemic level between N605 and the N605_MKHCPro chimera in Xanthi tobacco plants <lb/>(Fig 4). Several scenarios can be proposed and would be interesting to test further: (i) selection <lb/>of PVY mutants in tobacco cultivars other than Xanthi where the absence of necrosis induc-<lb/>tion may confer a multiplication advantage; (ii) selection of PVY mutants in other hosts for a <lb/>fitness advantage independently of virulence traits, notably in certain potato cultivars carrying <lb/>the Ny and/or Nc resistance genes which interact with the HC-Pro of PVY [42,43]; (iii) selec-<lb/>tion of PVY mutants for increased aphid transmissibility since HC-Pro is one of the two PVY <lb/>proteins with the coat protein that are directly involved in aphid transmission. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Schematic diagram of recombinant structure of the MK isolate, showing the nucle-<lb/>otide position intervals for the three putative breakpoints identified by seven out of nine <lb/>methods implemented in the RDP2 package with a 99% of confidence interval [25]. The <lb/>organization of the PVY genome (ca. 9.7-kb long) is reported on the top, where individual cis-<lb/>trons are presented as rectangles with corresponding protein names. The putative parental <lb/>sequences of PVY-MK, i.e. PVY group O in white and PVY group Eu-N in black, are shown <lb/>below the PVY genome. The recombinant structure of group SYR-I [13] is also reported to <lb/>show its similarity with that of PVY-MK. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Primers used for genome amplification and sequencing of PVY-MK. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work is dedicated to Prof. Crisostomo Vovlas (&quot;Makis&quot; for us) from the University &quot;Aldo <lb/>Moro&quot; of Bari (Italy), who gave us the symptomatic Datura metel plant analyzed in this study. <lb/>We would also like to thank Mr. Salvatore Cristadoro and Mrs. Immacolata Nunziata (IPSP-<lb/>CNR) for their administrative support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Data curation: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Formal analysis: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Investigation: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Methodology: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Project administration: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="contribution">Resources: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Software: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Supervision: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Validation: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Visualization: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Giuseppe Parrella, Benoit Moury. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Benoit Moury. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kehoe MA, Jones RAC. Improving Potato virus Y strain nomenclature: lessons from comparing isolates <lb/>obtained over a 73-year period. Plant Pathology 2016; 65:322-333. <lb/>2. Kerlan C. Potato virus Y. AAB descriptions of plant viruses no 414, 2006. (https://www.dpvweb.net/ <lb/>dpv/showdpv.php?dpvno=414). <lb/>3. Kerlan C, Moury B. Potato virus Y. In: Encyclopedia of Virology, 3rd ed.; Mahy, B.W.J., Van Regenmor-<lb/>tel, M.H.V., Eds.; Publisher: Elsevier, Oxford, UK, 2008; pp. 287-296. <lb/>4. Faurez F, Baldwin T, Tribodet M, Jacquot E. Identification of a new Potato virus Y (PVY) molecular deter-<lb/>minants for the induction of vein necrosis in tobacco. Molecular Plant Pathology, 2012; 13:948-959. <lb/>5. Rai R, Khurana SMP, Sharma SK, Baranwa VK. Genomic properties of potyviruses and their adaptation <lb/>to hosts, In: Plant RNA Viruses. Editor(s): Rajarshi Kumar Gaur, Basavaprabhu L. Patil, Ramasamy <lb/>Selvarajan, Academic Press, 2023, pages 3-37., <lb/>6. Glais L, Tribodet M, Kerlan C. Genomic variability in Potato potyvirus Y (PVY): Evidence that PVY NW <lb/>and PVY NTN variants are single to multiple recombinants between PVY O and PVY N isolates. Archives <lb/>of Virology 2002; 147: 363-378. <lb/>7. Tribodet M, Laurent G, Kerlan C, Jacquot E. Characterization of Potato virus Y (PVY) molecular deter-<lb/>minants involved in the vein necrosis symptom induced by PVY N isolates in infected Nicotiana tabacum <lb/>cv. Xanthi. Journal of General Virology 2005; 86:2101-2105. <lb/>8. Hu X, Meacham T, Ewing L, Gray SM, Karasev AV. A novel recombinant strain of Potato virus Y sug-<lb/>gests a new viral genetic determinant of vein necrosis in tobacco. Virus Research 2009; 143:68-76. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2009.03.008 PMID: 19463723 <lb/>9. Adams MJ, Antoniw JF, Beaudoin F. Overview and analysis of the polyprotein cleavage sites in the fam-<lb/>ily Potyviridae. Molecular Plant Pathology 2005; 6:471-487. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2005. <lb/>00296.x PMID: 20565672 <lb/>10. Tian Y-P, Valkonen JPT. Genetic determinants of potato virus Y required to overcome or trigger hyper-<lb/>sensitive resistance to PVY strain group O controlled by the gene Ny in potato. Molecular Plant Microbe <lb/>Interactions 2013; 26:297-305. https://doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-09-12-0219-R PMID: 23113714 <lb/>11. PM 7/126 (1) Electron microscopy in diagnosis of plant viruses. EPPO Bulletin 2015; 45:450-453. <lb/>12. Edwardson JR, Christie RG. The potyvirus. In: Florida Agricultural Experiment Station Monograph, <lb/>1991, No. 16, 1244 pp. <lb/>13. Jakab G, Droz E, Brigneti G, Baulcombe D, Malnoe ¨P. Infectious in vivo and in vitro transcripts from a <lb/>full-length cDNA clone of PVY-N605, a Swiss necrotic isolate of potato virus. Journal of General Virol-<lb/>ogy 1997; 78:3141-3145. <lb/>14. Parrella G, Nappo AG, Sorrentino R, Alioto D. Detection and characterization of PVY NTN and PVY Ob <lb/>isolates from Southern Italy. Proceeding of the 4 th Conference of the International Working Group on <lb/>Legume and Vegetable Viruses (IWGLVV), Antequera, Malaga, Spain, May 17-20, 2011, p. 106. <lb/>15. Rigotti S, Gugerli P. Quantification of Potyviruses PVY N and PVY NTN isolates in swiss potatoes by one-<lb/>step duplex RT-PCR. 12 th EAPR Virology Section Meeting, Rennes, France, 2004, p. 42. <lb/>16. Parrella G. Sources of resistance in wild Solanum germplasm (section Lycopersicon) to parietaria mot-<lb/>tle virus, an emerging virus in the Mediterranean basin. Plant Pathology 2020; 69:1018-1025. <lb/>17. Clark MF, Adams AN. Characteristics of the microplate method of enzyme-linked immunosorbent <lb/>assay for the detection of plant viruses. Journal of General Virology 1977; 34:475-483. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1099/0022-1317-34-3-475 PMID: 323416 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>18. Ali CM, Maoka T, Natsuaki KT. A point mutation changes the serotype of a potato virus Y isolate; geno-<lb/>mic determination of the serotype of PVY strains. Virus Genes 2007; 35:359-67. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/s11262-007-0115-y PMID: 17564823 <lb/>19. Chen J, Chen J, Adams MJ. A universal PCR primer to detect members of the Potyviridae and its use to <lb/>examine the taxonomic status of several members of the family. Archives of Virology 2001; 146:757-<lb/>766. https://doi.org/10.1007/s007050170144 PMID: 11402861 <lb/>20. Sambrook J, Fritsch ER, Maniatis T. In: Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual ( 2 nd ed.), Cold Spring <lb/>Harbor Laboratory Press, New York, 1989; pp. 1659. <lb/>21. Huang X. A contig assembly program based on sensitive detection of fragment overlaps. Genomics <lb/>1992; 14:18-25. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0888-7543(05)80277-0 PMID: 1427824 <lb/>22. Thompson JD, Higgins DG, Gibson TJ. CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple <lb/>sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix <lb/>choice. Nucleic Acids Research 1994; 22:4673-80. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/22.22.4673 PMID: <lb/>7984417 <lb/>23. Hall T A BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analisys. GERF Bulletin of <lb/>Bioscience 1999; 2:60-61. <lb/>24. Kumar S, Stecher G, Tamura K. MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 7.0 for big-<lb/>ger datasets. Molecular Biology and Evolution 2016; 33:1870-1874. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/ <lb/>msw054 PMID: 27004904 <lb/>25. Martin DP, Williamson C, Posada D. RDP2: recombination detection and analysis from sequence align-<lb/>ments. Bioinformatics 2005; 21:260-262. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth490 PMID: <lb/>15377507 <lb/>26. Johansen E. Intron insertion facilitates amplification of cloned virus cDNA in Escherichia coli while bio-<lb/>logical activity is reestablished after transcription in vivo. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sci-<lb/>ences 1996, 93:12400-12405. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.93.22.12400 PMID: 8901593 <lb/>27. Moury B, Simon V. dN/dS-Based Methods Detect Positive Selection Linked to Trade-Offs between Dif-<lb/>ferent Fitness Traits in the Coat Protein of Potato virus Y. Molecula Biology and Evolution 2011; <lb/>28:2707-2717. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr105 PMID: 21498601 <lb/>28. Fernandez-Delmond I, Pierrugues O, de Wispelaere M, Guilbaud L, Gaubert S, Dive ´ki Z, Godon C, <lb/>Tepfer M, Jacquemond M. A novel strategy for creating recombinant infectious RNA virus genomes. <lb/>Journal of Virological Methods 2004; 121:247-257. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2004.07.003 <lb/>PMID: 15381363 <lb/>29. Ayme V, Souche S, Caranta C, Jacquemond M, Chadoeuf J, Palloix A, Moury B. Different mutations in <lb/>the genome linked protein VPg of Potato Virus Y confer virulence on the pvr2 3 resistance in pepper. <lb/>Molecular Plant-Microbe Interaction 2006; 19:557-563. <lb/>30. Kruskal W H, Wallis WA. Use of ranks in one-criterion variance analysis. Journal of the American Statis-<lb/>tical Association 1952; 47:583-621. <lb/>31. Green KJ, Brown CJ, Karasev AV. Genetic diversity of potato virus Y (PVY): sequence analyses reveal <lb/>ten novel PVY recombinant structures. Archives of Virology 2018; 163:23-32. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s00705-017-3568-x PMID: 28940005 <lb/>32. Barker H.; McGeachy K.D.; Toplak N.; Gruden K.; Zel J.; Browning I. Comparison of Genome Sequence <lb/>of PVY Isolates with Biological Properties. American Journal of Potato Research 2009; 86:227-238. <lb/>33. Schubert J, Fomitcheva V, Sztangret-Wiśniewska J. Differentiation of Potato virus Y strains using <lb/>improved sets of diagnostic PCR-primers. Journal of Virological Methods 2007; 140:66-74. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.10.017 PMID: 17182113 <lb/>34. Singh M, Singh RP. Nucleotide sequence and genome organization of a Canadian isolate of the com-<lb/>mon strain of potato virus Y (PVY O ). Canadian Journal of Plant Pathology 1996; 18:209-214. <lb/>35. Green KJ, Brown CJ, Gray SM, Karasev AV. Phylogenetic study of recombinant strains of Potato virus <lb/>Y. Virology 2017; 507:40-52. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2017.03.018 PMID: 28399436 <lb/>36. Moury B. A new lineage sheds light on the evolutionary history of Potato virus Y. Molecular Plant Pathol-<lb/>ogy 2010; 11:161-168. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2009.00573.x PMID: 20078785 <lb/>37. Sudarsono Woloshuk SL, Xiong Z, Hellmann GM, Wernsman EA, Weissinger AK, Lommel SA. Nucleo-<lb/>tide sequence of the capsid protein cistrons from six Potato virus Y (PVY) isolates infecting tobacco. <lb/>Archives of Virology 1993; 132:161-170. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01309850 PMID: 8352655 <lb/>38. Julio E, Cotucheau J, Decorps C, Volpatti R, Sentenac C, Candresse T, Dorlhac de Borne F. A eukary-<lb/>otic translation initiation factor 4E (eIF4E) is responsible for the &quot;va&quot; tobacco recessive resistance to <lb/>potyviruses. Plant Molecular Biology Reporter 2014; 33:609-623. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>39. Cooley MB, Pathirana S, Wu HJ, Kachroo P, Klessig DF. Members of the Arabidopsis HRT/RPP8 family <lb/>of resistance genes confer resistance to both viral and oomycete pathogens. Plant Cell 2000; 12:663-<lb/>676. https://doi.org/10.1105/tpc.12.5.663 PMID: 10810142 <lb/>40. Michel V, Julio E, Candresse T, Cotucheau J, Decorps C, Volpatti R, Moury B, Glais L, Dorlhac de <lb/>Borne F, Decroocq V, German-Retana S. NtTPN1: a RPP8-like R gene required for Potato virus Y-<lb/>induced veinal necrosis in tobacco. Plant Journal 2018; 95:700-714. https://doi.org/10.1111/tpj.13980 <lb/>PMID: 29863810 <lb/>41. Abbink TEM, Tjernberg PA, Bol JF, Linthorst HJM. Tobacco Mosaic virus helicase domain induces <lb/>necrosis in N gene-carrying tobacco in the absence of virus replication. Molecular Plant Microbe Interac-<lb/>tion 1998; 11:1242-1246. <lb/>42. Moury B, Caromel B, Johansen E, Simon V, Chauvin L, Jacquot E, Kerlan C, Lefebvre V. The helper <lb/>component proteinase cistron of Potato virus Y induces hypersensitivity and resistance in potato geno-<lb/>types carrying dominant resistance genes on chromosome IV. Molecular Plant Microbe Interactions <lb/>2011; 24:787-797. https://doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-10-10-0246 PMID: 21405985 <lb/>43. Tian Y-P, Valkonen JPT. Recombination of strain O segments to HCpro-encoding sequence of strain N <lb/>of Potato virus Y modulates necrosis induced in tobacco and in potatoes carrying resistance genes Ny <lb/>or Nc. Molecular Plant Pathology 2015; 16:735-747. https://doi.org/10.1111/mpp.12231 PMID: <lb/>25557768 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>New amino acid involved in tobacco vein necrosis <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0302692 May 9, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 14 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>