<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-19T14:48:53.199Z">11/19/2025 2:48:53 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-19T14:48:44.855037Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-19T14:48:44.855037Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A novel diagnostic <lb/>tool for measuring glucose-6-phosphate <lb/>dehydrogenase (G6PD) activity and <lb/>hemoglobin concentration <lb/>Robert Harper 1 , Benedikt Ley ID <lb/>2 <lb/>, Md Alamgir Kabir 1 , Graham Matulis ID <lb/>3 , Lorenz von <lb/>Seidlein 4 , Mohammad Shafiul Alam ID <lb/>5 <lb/>, Bipin Adhikari 4 , Bernard A. Okech 6 , Alan <lb/>L. Williams ID <lb/>7 <lb/>, Ric N. Price 2,4,8 , Michael E. von Fricken ID <lb/>3,9 <lb/>* <lb/>1 In Vitro Diagnostic Solutions, Cherry Hill, New Jersey, United States of America, 2 Global and Tropical <lb/>Health Division, Menzies School of Health Research and Charles Darwin University, Darwin, Australia, <lb/>3 Department of Environmental and Global Health, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United States of <lb/>America, 4 Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol-Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Mahidol <lb/>University, Bangkok, Thailand, 5 Infectious Diseases Division, International Centre for Diarrheal Diseases <lb/>Research, Bangladesh (icddr,b), Mohakhali, Dhaka, Bangladesh, 6 Department of Preventive Medicine and <lb/>Biostatistics, F. Edward Herbert School of Medicine, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, <lb/>Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America, 7 Department of Family Medicine, Uniformed Services <lb/>University of the Health Sciences, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America, 8 Nuffield Department of <lb/>Clinical Medicine, Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, University of Oxford, Oxford, United <lb/>Kingdom, 9 One Health Center of Excellence, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United States of <lb/>America <lb/>* mvonf@ufl.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Quantitative diagnosis of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency is essen-<lb/>tial for the safe administration of 8-aminoquinoline based radical cure for the treatment of <lb/>Plasmodium vivax infections. Here, we present the PreQuine Platform (IVDS, USA), a quan-<lb/>titative biosensor that uses a dual-analyte assay for the simultaneous measurement of <lb/>Hemoglobin (Hgb) levels and G6PD enzyme activity within the same sample. The platform <lb/>relies on a downloadable mobile application. The device requires 10μl of whole blood and <lb/>works with a reflectance-based meter. Comparing the G6PD measurement normalized by <lb/>Hgb of 12 samples from the PreQuine Platform with reference measurements methods <lb/>(spectrophotometry, Pointe Scientific, USA and hemoglobin meter, HemoCue, Sweden) <lb/>showed a positive and significant agreement with a slope of 1.0091 and an intercept of <lb/>-0.0379 under laboratory conditions. Next steps will be to conduct field trials in Bangladesh, <lb/>Cambodia, and the USA to assess diagnostic performance, user friendliness and <lb/>acceptance. <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Plasmodium vivax causes between 5-14 million malaria cases each year, with over two billion <lb/>people at risk of infection [1,2], and is the predominant cause of malaria in areas outside of the <lb/></body>

    <front>PLOS ONE <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/>1 / 10 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Harper R, Ley B, Kabir MA, Matulis G, von <lb/>Seidlein L, Alam MS, et al. (2024) The PreQuine <lb/>Platform: A novel diagnostic tool for measuring <lb/>glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) <lb/>activity and hemoglobin concentration. PLoS ONE <lb/>19(5): e0297918. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0297918 <lb/>Editor: Germana Bancone, Shoklo Malaria <lb/>Research Unit, THAILAND <lb/>Received: October 4, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 15, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 10, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: This is an open access article, free of all <lb/>copyright, and may be freely reproduced, <lb/>distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or <lb/>otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. <lb/>The work is made available under the Creative <lb/>Commons CC0 public domain dedication. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript. <lb/>Funding: This project was supported by NIH SBIR <lb/>Phase I award # 1R43AI129057-01A1, Phase II <lb/>2R44AI129057-02A1 &amp; 5R44AI129057-03, and <lb/>2SB1AI129057-04. The funder had no role in the <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: I have read the journal&apos;s <lb/>policy and the authors of this manuscript have the <lb/></front>

    <body>African continent. In contrast to other malaria parasites, P. vivax (and P. ovale) can form dor-<lb/>mant liver stages (hypnozoites) which reactivate weeks to months after the initial infection <lb/>accounting for up to 80% of all cases of vivax malaria in some areas [3]. <lb/>Only one class of drugs with hypnozoitocidal properties is currently licensed. 8-aminoqui-<lb/>noline compounds (8AQ), namely primaquine (PQ) and tafenoquine (TQ), can clear hypno-<lb/>zoites, and in combination with a blood schizontocidal are referred to as radical cure [4-6]. <lb/>While well tolerated in most patients, PQ and TQ can cause hemolysis in individuals with glu-<lb/>cose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency, an enzymopathy that affects between <lb/>400 to 500 million people worldwide [7-9]. Since routine testing for G6PD deficiency is rarely <lb/>available in many endemic settings, clinicians often do not prescribe hypnozoitocidal treat-<lb/>ment due to concerns of drug induced acute hemolytic anemia in patients with unknown <lb/>G6PD deficiency. Hence, there is a critical need to Identify G6PD deficiency in patients and <lb/>monitor hemoglobin (Hgb) concentrations at point-of-care, to guide radical cure and support <lb/>overall clinical management of patients infected with P. vivax [1]. Wider use of G6PD diagnos-<lb/>tics for the safe administration of radical cure will be critical to reduce relapse and the trans-<lb/>mission of vivax malaria in high-risk populations. Scaled availability of point-of-care G6PD <lb/>diagnostic kits for rural tropical regions, which suffer the largest burden of vivax malaria, will <lb/>protect individuals vulnerable to 8-aminoquinolone drug-induced adverse events and enable <lb/>individuals with normal G6PD levels to receive curative treatment [10]. <lb/>The PreQuine Platform is a novel, point-of-care diagnostic kit developed by In Vitro Diag-<lb/>nostics Solutions (IVDS, USA) for the simultaneous, quantitative determination of G6PD <lb/>enzyme activity and Hgb concentration. We report the first findings from the device when <lb/>tested under laboratory conditions. <lb/>Methods <lb/>The PreQuine Platform <lb/>The PreQuine Platform consists of a portable reflectometer, dual-analyte test strips, blood col-<lb/>lection kits, fixed-volume, single-use pipettes, lysing buffer, and a mobile application (Fig 1). <lb/>Each lot of test strips is validated by scanning a QR code which contains information concern-<lb/>ing the lot number, expiration date, and calibration constants needed for calculating Hgb and <lb/>G6PD levels. A total of 10 μl of capillary or venous blood is added to the lysis buffer using a sin-<lb/>gle-use pipette, and the resulting suspension is mixed thoroughly. Using a second pipette, <lb/>20 μl of the blood-buffer suspension are then added to a test strip inserted into the meter cas-<lb/>sette guide. A precise formulation of enzymes, bioactive components, surfactants, and excipi-<lb/>ents immobilized within the test strip membranes produce a colorimetric signal proportional <lb/>to analyte levels in the sample. The reflectometer detects and transmits the colorimetric data to <lb/>the mobile app for display, storage, and dissemination. The mobile app also displays step-by-<lb/>step directions of use. A normalized G6PD measurement is displayed within 6 minutes, the <lb/>measurement of Hgb concentration is done within 1 minute. <lb/>Dual analyte test strip design <lb/>The design schema of the dual analyte test strip for simultaneous detection of Hgb concentra-<lb/>tion and G6PD enzyme activity is shown in Fig 2. A hydrophilic spreading layer (transport <lb/>membrane), which contains a chelating agent, helps to filter cell debris while evenly distribut-<lb/>ing the sample laterally across the underlying membrane layers. The applied sample then <lb/>migrates vertically through the Hgb and G6PD reaction layers, eventually reaching the read <lb/>zones positioned over the 570nm (for Hgb detection) and 670nm (for G6PD detection) LEDs, <lb/>which are embedded in the reflectometer. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <front>following competing interests: RH is the Founder <lb/>and CEO of In Vitro Diagnostic Solutions, MAK is a <lb/>scientist currently employed by IVDS, BL, LvS, <lb/>MSA, BA, BAO, and MEV are receiving project <lb/>funding for the field trials in the United States, <lb/>Bangladesh and Cambodia. Both MEV and BL <lb/>serve as academic editors for PLoS One. This does <lb/>not alter our adherence to PLoS ONE policies on <lb/>sharing data and materials. <lb/></front>

    <body>G6PD detection mechanism <lb/>The reaction mechanism for the G6PD measurement is shown in Fig 3A. The chemistry utilizes <lb/>a substrate β-D-glucose-6-phosphate disodium salt (G6PD substrate), NADP+, diaphorase (elec-<lb/>tron mediator), and a tetrazolium salt, which eventually produce formazan, a colored end-reac-<lb/>tion product. The chosen formazan reaction product is outside of the spectral wavelength <lb/>maxima of hemoglobin and bilirubin, reducing the potential for assay interference from these <lb/>two compounds (Fig 3B). Maleimide is also added to the membrane as a sequestering compound <lb/>to reduce the creation of secondary NADPH resulting from reactions with 6-phosphogluconate <lb/>dehydrogenase. The PreQuine Platform incorporates a Temperature Correction Factor (TCF) <lb/>for G6PD activity measurements, similar to other G6PD point-of-care quantitative devices [11], <lb/>which is critical given that the G6PD enzyme activity is temperature dependent. <lb/>Hgb detection mechanism <lb/>The reaction mechanism for Hgb detection is shown in Fig 4. Free Hgb is liberated from the <lb/>blood sample by mixing with the lysing buffer. After traversing the transport membrane, the <lb/>Fig 1. The PreQuine Platform consists of the following (1) Blood collection kits with single-use, fixed-volume <lb/>pipettes, (2) Lysis buffer, (3) Handheld reflectance-based meter, (4) Cell phone application, and (5) Test strips for <lb/>G6PD and Hgb detection. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g001 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>sample flows through a polyether sulfone (PES) membrane coated with an oxidizer and <lb/>sodium azide to convert the free Hgb to azide methemoglobin (Fig 2A, layer 5). The optical <lb/>membrane is an anisotropic PES membrane facing the LED, which collects the colored reac-<lb/>tion product and serves as the Hgb read zone. <lb/>Preparation of blood samples <lb/>A total of 10 ml of deidentified healthy donor venous blood (heparinized) were purchased <lb/>from BioIVT (USA) and aliquoted. The native G6PD enzyme activity was assayed by spectro-<lb/>photometry on a temperature-controlled Genesys 10S (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA) at <lb/>37˚C using commercially available reagents (Cat# G7583180, Pointe Scientific, Canton, MI) <lb/>and the Hgb value of the blood was determined using the HemoCue HB 201 System (Hemo-<lb/>Cue, Angelholm, Sweden). G6PD enzyme activity was adjusted via freeze/thaw cycles and/or <lb/>Fig 2. a) Exploded view of the G6PD dual analyte test strip. (1) a spreading layer (transport membrane), (2) a G6PD reagent membrane (hollow fiber <lb/>membrane with electron mediator, inhibitor, and substrate), (3) a G6PD detection membrane (mixed mesh &lt; 1 μm) facing the LED, (4) a reagent membrane <lb/>(polyether sulfone membrane containing sodium azide and sodium nitrite) and (5) an optical membrane (polyether sulfone membrane &lt; 1 μm) facing the <lb/>LED. b) Top and bottom view of the fully assembled test strip with representative color change after test strip chemical reaction (far right). c) PreQuine <lb/>Platform&apos;s reflectance-based meter shows both 570 and 670 nm LEDs that are used for the simultaneous detection of Hgb and G6PD, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g002 <lb/>Fig 3. a) G6PD assay reaction mechanism. b) PreQuine Platform&apos;s unique indicator showing free of interference with Bilirubin and Hemoglobin. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g003 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>spiking with recombinant G6PD enzyme (Cat# 078A0020, Calzyme, San Luis Obispo, CA) <lb/>while Hgb levels were adjusted through the addition and subtraction of plasma. This generated <lb/>blood samples with G6PD enzyme activity ranging from 0-300 U/dL and with Hgb values <lb/>ranging from 0-25 g/dL. Prepared samples were assayed in triplicate using the PreQuine Plat-<lb/>form and the average values were used to generate a best-fit polynomial equation relating <lb/>reflectance (%R) to Hgb (g/dL) or G6PD (U/dL). These polynomial equations were used to cal-<lb/>culate G6PD and Hgb levels from the %R data. The calculated values were then compared to <lb/>measurements obtained using reference assays (spectrophotometry with Pointe Scientific <lb/>reagents and HB 201 HemoCue). <lb/>Simultaneous G6PD and Hgb detection <lb/>G6PD enzyme activity must be normalized by Hgb concentration to provide a meaningful <lb/>reading. To evaluate the performance of the PreQuine assay, we encoded the polynomial equa-<lb/>tions relating %R to G6PD (U/dL) and %R to Hgb (g/dL) into the QR code that is scanned <lb/>using the PreQuine mobile app (the QR code also contains lot information and expiration date <lb/>of the test strips) and programmed the results output to be expressed in normalized values of <lb/>G6PD activity (U/g Hgb). We then obtained twelve de-identified blood samples with varying <lb/>levels of G6PD enzyme activity (provided by PATH, USA, as G6PD references). The samples <lb/>were assayed on the PreQuine Platform, HB 201, and using spectrophotometry to compare the <lb/>G6PD enzyme activity values as determined by the PreQuine Platform with the values <lb/>obtained from the reference assays. <lb/>Results <lb/>Performance of PreQuine system for simultaneous G6PD and Hgb <lb/>measurement <lb/>Twelve de-identified blood samples with varying G6PD enzyme activities were assayed simul-<lb/>taneously using the HemoCue HB 201, Pointe Scientific reagents, and the PreQuine system. <lb/>The linear relationship between the PreQuine Platform and combined HB 201/Pointe Scien-<lb/>tific assays is shown in Fig 5. The PreQuine Platform showed a positive and significant linear <lb/>agreement with the reference assays with a slope of 1.0091, an intercept of -0.0379, and R 2 of <lb/>0.9936. <lb/>Dose response of G6PD enzyme activity using PreQuine platform <lb/>Fig 6 shows the dose response in %R of samples across the analytical range of 0-300 U/dL <lb/>G6PD activity. Regression analysis revealed that a cubic fit polynomial described the dose <lb/>response with R 2 = 0.9638 and an average coefficient of variation of 2% (range 1-5%). The lin-<lb/>ear regression comparing the PreQuine Platform with the reference assay is shown in Fig 7. <lb/>Fig 4. Hgb assay reaction mechanism. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g004 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>The PreQuine Platform showed a positive and significant linear agreement with spectropho-<lb/>tometry, with a slope of 1.0959, an intercept of -3.7386, and R 2 of 0.9614. <lb/>Dose response of Hgb using PreQuine platform <lb/>Fig 8 shows the dose response in %R of samples across the analytical range of 0-25 g/dL Hgb. <lb/>Regression analysis revealed that a cubic fit polynomial described the dose response with R 2 = <lb/>0.9933 and an average coefficient of variation of 9% (range 3-18%). The linear regression com-<lb/>paring the PreQuine Platform with HB 201 is shown in Fig 9. The PreQuine Platform showed <lb/>a positive and significant linear agreement with the HB 201, with a slope of 1.0262, an intercept <lb/>of -0.1074, and R 2 of 0.993. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We found the PreQuine system to provide accurate measurements of G6PD activity levels up <lb/>to 300 U/dL and Hgb values up to 25 g/dL, and a good correlation based on R 2 with the corre-<lb/>sponding reference methods, but further analysis of a larger sample size is required to deter-<lb/>mine statistically significant association (spectrophotometry, Pointe Scientific, USA; <lb/>hemoglobin meter, HemoCue, Sweden). The PreQuine system is quantitative, does not require <lb/>laboratory equipment, does not require cold chain for distribution or storage, and should <lb/>remain functional at ambient tropical temperatures, but requires field validation to determine <lb/>Fig 5. The performance comparison of the PreQuine Platform to measure the activity of the G6PD enzyme <lb/>compared with the Pointe Scientific method measured by the spectrophotometer (Pointe Scientific reagents) in <lb/>U/g Hgb. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g005 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 6. 3rd order polynomial relationship between known values of G6PD/mL and percent reflectance values <lb/>(derived from PreQuine G6PD assay) for G6PD-adjusted blood samples. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g006 <lb/>Fig 7. The first order linear regression relationship between U/dL values as measured by the Spectrophotometer <lb/>(Pointe Scientifique) and as measured and derived by the PreQuine G6PD assay. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g007 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>Fig 8. 3rd order polynomial relationship between g/dL Hgb values (derived from HB 201) and percent reflectance <lb/>values (derived from PreQuine Hgb assay) for Hgb-adjusted whole blood samples. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g008 <lb/>Fig 9. The first order linear regression relationship between g/dL values as measured by the HB 201 system and as <lb/>measured and derived by the PreQuine Hgb system. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918.g009 <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <body>actual performance in vivo which will help us understand the impact of other environmental <lb/>factors like humidity. <lb/>The dual-analyte design omits the need to run two assays in parallel and removes the need <lb/>for health care providers to calculate G6PD activity. In contrast to other comparable devices <lb/>the Prequine measures product formation from G6PD activity at 670nm and thereby avoids <lb/>inference from the Hgb present in the blood sample, where Fe 2+ from Hgb can yield the same <lb/>color signal as the end reaction of the G6PD assay, resulting in an unwanted background sig-<lb/>nal. Furthermore, the chosen chemical indicator for G6PD detection has an absorbance maxi-<lb/>mum outside of the absorbance range of bilirubin. <lb/>The PreQuine Platform relies on a mobile application that connects the meter device via <lb/>Bluetooth to a mobile phone. This allows users to store patient ID, test results, and geolocation <lb/>information, while also allowing for the calculation of normalized G6PD activity in U/g Hgb. <lb/>This approach reduces the hardware costs for the end user, simplifies software updates world-<lb/>wide, and provides a real time, step-by-step guide to the user while performing a measure-<lb/>ment. The app also provides a platform for additional features that can be added on later such <lb/>as telehealth consultation, and if requested by the user uploading of test results to centralized <lb/>databases. While various assays have been developed to determine G6PD deficiency, many of <lb/>have limited utility in malaria-endemic regions, including: the need for expensive laboratory <lb/>equipment, cold chain requirements, the need of a separate assay for Hgb quantification, cost, <lb/>and inadequate assay sensitivities and specificities [12]. <lb/>The reported results were performed by trained scientists in a laboratory setting, thus far <lb/>the PreQuine Platform has not been tested under field conditions on samples from malaria <lb/>patients. It is expected that the observed correlation may differ under more realistic condi-<lb/>tions. To assess field feasibility, the PreQuine Platform will be trialed at field sites in Bangla-<lb/>desh, Cambodia, and the United States following standard procedures [13]. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Initial laboratory-based data suggest that the PreQuine device shows good correlation across <lb/>the physiological range of 0-300 U/dL G6PD activity and 0-25 g/dL Hgb, when compared to <lb/>the respective reference assays. Field studies will be critical to validate these findings, assess the <lb/>overall device performance, monitor user friendliness and acceptance, and eventually examine <lb/>PreQuine performance in comparison to other commercially available point-of-care G6PD <lb/>devices. <lb/></body>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Robert Harper, Benedikt Ley, Lorenz von Seidlein, Michael E. von <lb/>Fricken. <lb/>Data curation: Robert Harper, Md Alamgir Kabir, Graham Matulis. <lb/>Formal analysis: Robert Harper, Md Alamgir Kabir, Graham Matulis. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Robert Harper, Michael E. von Fricken. <lb/>Investigation: Robert Harper, Benedikt Ley, Lorenz von Seidlein, Mohammad Shafiul Alam, <lb/>Bipin Adhikari, Bernard A. Okech, Alan L. Williams, Ric N. Price, Michael E. von Fricken. <lb/>Methodology: Robert Harper, Benedikt Ley, Md Alamgir Kabir, Lorenz von Seidlein, Moham-<lb/>mad Shafiul Alam, Bipin Adhikari, Bernard A. Okech, Alan L. Williams, Ric N. Price, <lb/>Michael E. von Fricken. <lb/>Project administration: Robert Harper, Michael E. von Fricken. <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 / 10 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">Supervision: Md Alamgir Kabir. <lb/>Visualization: Benedikt Ley, Md Alamgir Kabir, Graham Matulis. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Robert Harper, Benedikt Ley, Graham Matulis, Michael E. von <lb/>Fricken. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Robert Harper, Lorenz von Seidlein, Mohammad Shafiul Alam, <lb/>Bipin Adhikari, Bernard A. Okech, Alan L. Williams, Ric N. Price. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. World Health Organization. WHO guidelines for malaria, 14 March 2023 [Internet]. World Health Orga-<lb/>nization; 2023 [cited 2023 Mar 30]. Report No.: WHO/UCN/GMP/2023.01. Available from: https://apps. <lb/>who.int/iris/handle/10665/366432. <lb/>2. Battle KE, Lucas TCD, Nguyen M, Howes RE, Nandi AK, Twohig KA, et al. Mapping the global endemic-<lb/>ity and clinical burden of Plasmodium vivax, 2000-17: a spatial and temporal modelling study. The Lan-<lb/>cet. 2019 Jul; 394(10195):332-43. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31096-7 PMID: 31229233 <lb/>3. Commons RJ, Simpson JA, Watson J, White NJ, Price RN. Estimating the Proportion of Plasmodium <lb/>vivax Recurrences Caused by Relapse: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Am J Trop Med Hyg. <lb/>2020 Sep; 103(3):1094-9. https://doi.org/10.4269/ajtmh.20-0186 PMID: 32524950 <lb/>4. Edgcomb JH, Arnold J, Yount EH, Alving AS, Eichelberger L, Jeffery GM, et al. Primaquine, SN 13272, <lb/>a new curative agent in vivax malaria; a preliminary report. J Natl Malar Soc. 1950 Dec; 9(4):285-92. <lb/>PMID: 14804087 <lb/>5. Taylor WRJ, Thriemer K, von Seidlein L, Yuentrakul P, Assawariyathipat T, Assefa A, et al. Short-<lb/>course primaquine for the radical cure of Plasmodium vivax malaria: a multicentre, randomised, pla-<lb/>cebo-controlled non-inferiority trial. The Lancet. 2019 Sep; 394(10202):929-38. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S0140-6736(19)31285-1 PMID: 31327563 <lb/>6. Shanks GD, Oloo AJ, Aleman GM, Ohrt C, Klotz FW, Braitman D, et al. A New Primaquine Analogue, <lb/>Tafenoquine (WR 238605), for Prophylaxis against Plasmodium falciparum Malaria. CLIN INFECT DIS. <lb/>2001 Dec 15; 33(12):1968-74. https://doi.org/10.1086/324081 PMID: 11700577 <lb/>7. Phru CS, Kibria MG, Thriemer K, Chowdhury MU, Jahan N, Aktaruzzaman MM, et al. Case Report: A <lb/>Case of Primaquine-Induced Hemoglobinuria in Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase Deficient <lb/>Malaria Patient in Southeastern Bangladesh. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. <lb/>2020 Jan 8; 102(1):156-8. https://doi.org/10.4269/ajtmh.19-0643 PMID: 31701865 <lb/>8. Chu CS, Bancone G, Nosten F, White NJ, Luzzatto L. Primaquine-induced haemolysis in females het-<lb/>erozygous for G6PD deficiency. Malar J. 2018 Dec; 17(1):101. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12936-018-<lb/>2248-y PMID: 29499733 <lb/>9. World Health Organization. Control and elimination of Plasmodium vivax malaria: a technical brief. 27 <lb/>August 2015. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023 [cited 2023 Mar 30]. Available from: https:// <lb/>www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241509244. <lb/>10. Gething PW, Elyazar IRF, Moyes CL, Smith DL, Battle KE, Guerra CA, et al. A Long Neglected World <lb/>Malaria Map: Plasmodium vivax Endemicity in 2010. Carlton JM, editor. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2012 Sep <lb/>6; 6(9):e1814. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001814 PMID: 22970336 <lb/>11. Ley B, Winasti Satyagraha A, Kibria MG, Armstrong J, Bancone G, Bei AK, et al. Repeatability and <lb/>reproducibility of a handheld quantitative G6PD diagnostic. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2022 Feb 17; 16(2): <lb/>e0010174. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0010174 PMID: 35176015 <lb/>12. Weppelmann TA, von Fricken ME, Wilfong TD, Aguenza E, Philippe TT, Okech BA. Field Trial of the <lb/>CareStart Biosensor Analyzer for the Determination of Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase Activity <lb/>in Haiti. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2017 Oct; 97(4):1262-1270. https://doi.org/10.4269/ajtmh.16-0714 PMID: <lb/>28820691 <lb/>13. Ley B, Bancone G, von Seidlein L, Thriemer K, Richards JS, Domingo GJ, et al. Methods for the field <lb/>evaluation of quantitative G6PD diagnostics: a review. Malar J. 2017 Sep 11; 16(1):361. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1186/s12936-017-2017-3 PMID: 28893237 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">PLOS ONE <lb/>The PreQuine Platform: A simple diagnostic tool for determining G6PD deficiency <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PLOS ONE https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0297918 May 10, 2024 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 / 10 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>