<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:57:00.800Z">11/20/2025 10:57:00 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:56:50.627105Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:56:50.627105Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Age-dependent molecular <lb/>variations in osteosarcoma: <lb/>implications for precision <lb/>oncology across pediatric, <lb/>adolescent, and adult patients <lb/>Changye Zou 1 † , Renxuan Huang 1 † , Tiao Lin 1 † , Yaxian Wang 2 † , <lb/>Jian Tu 1 , Liwen Zhang 2 , Bo Wang 1 , Jintao Huang 2 , <lb/>Zhiqiang Zhao 1 , Xianbiao Xie 1 , Gang Huang 1 , Kai Wang 2 , <lb/>Junqiang Yin 1 * and Jingnan Shen 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Musculoskeletal Oncology Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University, Guangzhou, China, 2 OrigiMed, Shanghai, China <lb/>Background: Osteosarcoma is a leading subtype of bone tumor affecting <lb/>adolescents and adults. Comparative molecular characterization among <lb/>different age groups, especially in pediatric, adolescents and adults, is scarce. <lb/>Methods: We collected samples from 194 osteosarcoma patients, encompassing <lb/>pediatric, adolescent, and adult cohorts. Genomic analyses were conducted to <lb/>reveal prevalent mutations and compare molecular features in pediatric, <lb/>adolescent, and adult patients. <lb/>Results: Samples from 194 osteosarcoma patients across pediatric to adult ages <lb/>were analyzed, revealing key mutations such as TP53, FLCN, NCOR1, and others. <lb/>Children and adolescents showed more gene amplifications and HRD mutations, <lb/>while adults had a greater Tumor Mutational Burden (TMB). Mutations in those <lb/>over 15 were mainly in cell cycle and PI3K/mTOR pathways, while under 15s had <lb/>more in cell cycle and angiogenesis with higher VEGFA, CCND3, TFEB mutations. <lb/>CNV patterns varied with age: VEGFA and XPO5 amplifications more in under 25s, <lb/>and CDKN2A/B deletions in over 25s. Genetic alterations in genes like MCL1 and <lb/>MYC were associated with poor prognosis, with VEGFA mutations also indicating <lb/>worse outcomes. 58% of patients had actionable mutations, suggesting <lb/>opportunities for targeted therapies. Age-specific patterns were observed, with <lb/>Multi-TKI mutations more common in younger patients and CDK4/6 inhibitor <lb/>mutations in adults, highlighting the need for personalized treatment approaches <lb/>in osteosarcoma. In a small group of patients with VEGFR amplification, <lb/>postoperative treatment with multi-kinase inhibitors resulted in a PR in 3 of 13 <lb/>cases, especially in patients under 15. A significant case involved a 13-year-old <lb/>with a notable tumor size reduction achieving PR, even with other genetic <lb/>alterations present in some patients with PD. <lb/>Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Alma D. Campos-Parra, <lb/>Universidad Veracruzana, Mexico <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Dorian Yarih Garcia-Ortega, <lb/>National Institute of Cancerology <lb/>(INCAN), Mexico <lb/>Gerardo Cuamani-Mitznahuatl, <lb/>ABC Medical Center, Mexico <lb/>Macrina Beatriz Silva Ca ´zares, <lb/>Autonomous University of San Luis <lb/>Potosı ´, Mexico <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Jingnan Shen <lb/>shenjn@mail.sysu.edu.cn <lb/>Junqiang Yin <lb/>yinjunq@mail.sysu.edu.cn <lb/> † These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work <lb/>RECEIVED 05 February 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 19 April 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 22 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Zou C, Huang R, Lin T, Wang Y, Tu J, <lb/>Zhang L, Wang B, Huang J, Zhao Z, <lb/>Xie X, Huang G, Wang K, Yin J and <lb/>Shen J (2024) Age-dependent molecular <lb/>variations in osteosarcoma: implications <lb/>for precision oncology across pediatric, <lb/>adolescent, and adult patients. <lb/>Front. Oncol. 14:1382276. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Zou, Huang, Lin, Wang, Tu, Zhang, <lb/>Wang, Huang, Zhao, Xie, Huang, Wang, Yin and <lb/>Shen. This is an open-access article distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (CC BY). The use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction in other forums <lb/>is permitted, provided the original author(s) <lb/>and the copyright owner(s) are credited and <lb/>that the original publication in this journal is <lb/>cited, in accordance with accepted academic <lb/>practice. No use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>is permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 22 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/>Conclusion: This study delineates the molecular differences among pediatric, <lb/>adolescent, and adult osteosarcoma patients at the genomic level, emphasizing <lb/>the necessity for precision diagnostics and treatment strategies, and may offer <lb/>novel prognostic biomarkers for patients with osteosarcoma. These findings <lb/>provide a significant scientific foundation for the development of individualized <lb/>treatment approaches tailored to patients of different age groups. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>osteosarcoma, pediatrics, adolescents, adults, genomic alteration, next <lb/>generation sequencing <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Osteosarcoma, a relatively uncommon malignancy, manifests a <lb/>distinct incidence pattern characterized by a significant surge <lb/>during the growth phase of adolescence. The rarity of this disease <lb/>poses substantial challenges for conducting broad research <lb/>initiatives, rendering large-scale studies especially crucial (1, 2). <lb/>Despite significant advances in limb-salvage surgery and <lb/>multimodal chemotherapy, the long-term survival for non-<lb/>metastatic osteosarcoma has stagnated around 70% for the past <lb/>few decades, while patients presenting with metastatic disease at <lb/>diagnosis have an even poorer prognosis, with survival rates <lb/>hovering around 20-30% (3, 4). Moreover, the high-dose <lb/>chemotherapeutic regimens necessary for treatment are associated <lb/>with considerable acute and long-term morbidity (5, 6). <lb/>The complexity of osteosarcoma is underscored by its clinical <lb/>and molecular heterogeneity, which poses a challenge for the <lb/>identification of prognostic markers and therapeutic targets. <lb/>Clinical prognosticators, including tumor size, site, and response <lb/>to chemotherapy, have been well-documented (7). In multivariate <lb/>analysis, proximal position within the limb was independently <lb/>associated with worse overall survival of patients with <lb/>osteosarcoma (8). Previous study showed that the prognosis of <lb/>male osteosarcoma is slightly worse than that of female patients (9). <lb/>Age is generally considered to be an independent factor of <lb/>osteosarcoma. Due to the onset characteristics of osteosarcoma, <lb/>that is, patients with osteosarcoma show a bimodal distribution <lb/>according to age, with the highest proportion of 15-19 years old, <lb/>followed by 75-79 years old, and then 25-59 years old (10). The <lb/>study found that in adolescent patients with osteosarcoma, the <lb/>younger the age, the worse the prognosis (7). However, the impact <lb/>of age on disease characteristics and outcomes has become a focal <lb/>point of recent research, with studies suggesting that older age may <lb/>correlate with a higher frequency of adverse histologic response to <lb/>chemotherapy and inferior survival (11, 12). <lb/>Advancements in high-throughput sequencing technologies <lb/>have revolutionized our understanding of osteosarcoma biology, <lb/>revealing a multitude of genetic alterations with potential <lb/>prognostic and therapeutic implications (13). Unlike other solid <lb/>tumors, osteosarcoma has a low proportion of common driver gene <lb/>mutations and depends more on the activation of signal pathways <lb/>caused by gene amplification or overexpression, such as PI3K/ <lb/>mTOR (14), IGF1 (15), VEGF (16), and PDGF (17), etc. Clinical <lb/>trials of molecular typing and targeted therapy of osteosarcoma <lb/>based on gene mutations are particularly necessary to improve the <lb/>prognosis of patients with osteosarcoma. Due to the low incidence <lb/>rate of osteosarcoma and the heterogeneity of osteosarcoma, it is <lb/>difficult to carry out large-scale clinical trials. The clinical <lb/>characteristics of osteosarcoma in young and elderly patients have <lb/>been reported to differ, along with correlations between clinical <lb/>features and prognosis (7, 18-20). A few studies have also depicted <lb/>the distinct genomic profiles of osteosarcomas in different age <lb/>groups, revealing age-specific mutation patterns and alterations in <lb/>signaling pathways (14, 15). These findings underline the <lb/>significance of age as a biological variable in osteosarcoma and <lb/>may pave the way for age-specific treatment strategies. In a glioma <lb/>study, age groups defined by 15 and 25 years -children (&lt;15 years), <lb/>adolescents (15-25 years), and adults (&gt;25 years) -were found to <lb/>have distinct molecular features, such as differences in the <lb/>proportion of IDH1,BRAF and H3G34 mutations (21). <lb/>Studies have shown that in untreated osteosarcoma, the <lb/>presence of Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor (VEGF) serves as <lb/>a prognostic indicator for the likelihood of pulmonary metastasis <lb/>and unfavorable outcomes in patients undergoing intensive therapy <lb/>(22). Additionally, a notable discovery is that patients who are very <lb/>young exhibit a substantially increased incidence of capillary <lb/>hemangioma-like histological features (10.2% compared to 2.9%; <lb/>P = 0.017) (23). These insights provide a crucial foundation for <lb/>devising therapeutic approaches that concentrate on the vascular <lb/>growth properties of osteosarcoma and may also prompt a <lb/>reconsideration of age ranges for the inclusion of subjects in <lb/>clinical trials for emerging therapeutics. <lb/>This study is designed to conduct a comprehensive analysis of <lb/>the molecular mutation characteristics in osteosarcoma patients <lb/>across various age groups, with the intent of identifying unique <lb/>molecular markers that could enable personalized treatment <lb/>approaches. By delving into the age-specific mutation patterns <lb/>and signaling pathway alterations as previously reported, and <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<body>utilizing advanced genomic data, our goal is to enhance the current <lb/>understanding of the complex molecular landscape of <lb/>osteosarcoma. Ultimately, this research aims to contribute to <lb/>precision medicine efforts, and thereby improve clinical outcomes <lb/>for osteosarcoma patients of all ages. <lb/>2 Patients and methods <lb/>2.1 Patients and samples <lb/>From June 2017 to April 2023, we have gathered a cohort of 194 <lb/>osteosarcoma patients from The First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-<lb/>sen University. These patients were selected based on their visits to <lb/>our institution for treatment, during which they also underwent <lb/>genetic testing. These patients were stratified into three age groups <lb/>for analysis: pediatric patients (under 15 years), adolescent and <lb/>young adult patients (15 -25 years), and adult patients (over 25 <lb/>years). Samples included fresh surgical/biopsy tissues or formalin-<lb/>fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor tissues, along with matched <lb/>blood samples, which were collected to detect genomic alterations <lb/>(GAs). Genomic DNA was prepared by using QIAamp DNA FFPE <lb/>Tissue Kit and QIAamp DNA Blood Midi Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, <lb/>Germany) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. The <lb/>concentration of DNA was measured and normalized to 20-50 <lb/>ng/mL. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of The <lb/>First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, and all patients <lb/>signed an informed consent form. <lb/>2.2 Genomic alterations identification <lb/>The DNA samples were detected by using the NGS-based <lb/>Yuansu 450 gene panel or whole exon sequencing (WES) <lb/>(OrigiMed, Shanghai, China). Yuansu 450gene panel covers all <lb/>the coding exons of 450 tumor-related genes, the genes were <lb/>captured and sequenced with a mean depth of 1000×. WES <lb/>libraries were prepared and captured using the SureSelect Human <lb/>All Exon V6 kit (Agilent Technologies) following manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions and sequenced with a mean coverage depth of 300X. <lb/>All these experiments were performed on Illumina Novaseq 6000 <lb/>system (Illumina, Inc., CA). Resultant sequences were further <lb/>analyzed for genomic alterations compared with normal genomic <lb/>DNA, including single nucleotide variants, short and long <lb/>insertions/deletions (indels), copy number variations, and <lb/>structural variants of gene rearrangement/fusion. The tumor <lb/>mutational burden (TMB) was estimated by analyzing somatic <lb/>mutations, including coding base substitution and INDELs, per <lb/>mega-base of the panel sequences examined. <lb/>2.3 Mutational signature analysis <lb/>According to the number of different types of point mutations <lb/>such as C &gt; A/G &gt; T, C &gt; G/G &gt; C, C &gt; T/G &gt; A, T &gt; A/A &gt; T, T &gt; C/ <lb/>A &gt; G, and T &gt; G/A &gt; C, a cluster analysis was performed in order <lb/>to observe similarity in tumor samples. Extracted mutational <lb/>features were compared with the pan-cancer catalogue for 94 <lb/>known features cited in the cancer somatic mutation catalogue <lb/>(COSMIC) database (https://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/signatures/) using <lb/>Mutational Patterns packages (3.6.0) (24). The similarity of <lb/>mutational features was assessed based on a cosine similarity &gt; <lb/>0.85, which indicated common features. <lb/>2.4 Function enrichment analyses <lb/>To explore the biological functions of somatic mutations, gene <lb/>ontology (GO) and a Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes <lb/>(KEGG) enrichment analysis were conducted using the <lb/>ClusterProfiler (v.3.10.1) in the R software. <lb/>2.5 Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was conducted using the R statistical software <lb/>package (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). <lb/>Categorical variables are expressed as in frequency and percentages; <lb/>Continuous variables was presented with medians and percentiles. <lb/>Wilcoxon rank test was used for comparing two continuous data <lb/>and Fisher&apos;s exact tests were used for comparing two categorical <lb/>data. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Characterization of <lb/>osteosarcoma patients <lb/>A total of 194 osteosarcoma patients were enrolled in this <lb/>study. There were 127 males and 67 females. The median age was <lb/>16 Years old, ranged from 5-73 years old. Osteosarcoma is <lb/>predominantly seen in adolescents, with about 75% of cases <lb/>occurring between the ages of 15 and 25. Therefore, we <lb/>categorize patients aged younger 15 as pediatric patients, those <lb/>between 15 to 25 years as adolescent &amp; young adult patients, and <lb/>those over 25 years as adult patients. Our cohort includes 81 <lb/>pediatric patients, 85 adolescent patients, and 28 adult patients. <lb/>Based on pathological staging records, there were 2 cases of Stage I <lb/>tumors, 136 cases of Stage II tumors, 2 cases of Stage III tumors, <lb/>and 43 cases of Stage IV tumors. Additionally, there were 11 cases <lb/>of pelvic and spinal bone tumors for which the AJCC staging <lb/>criteria were not applicable. Within this cohort, the YuanSu450 <lb/>gene panel and WES (Whole Exome Sequencing) (OrigiMed, <lb/>Shanghai, China) were utilized to test samples from 110 <lb/>and 84 patients, respectively. In this cohort, 177 underwent <lb/>immunohistochemistry testing for PD-L1 expression, there were <lb/>44 PD-L1 positive patients and 133 negative patients. The <lb/>majority of patients (193/194, 99.5%) were characterized as <lb/>having Microsatellite Stable (MSS) tumors (Table 1). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.2 Mutational profile of osteosarcomas <lb/>In this research, a total of 23,951 gene mutations were detected <lb/>among 194 osteosarcoma patients. Gene panel testing yielded 1,066 <lb/>mutations in 110 patients, while whole-exome sequencing (WES) <lb/>detected 22,885 mutations in 84 patients. We found that the most <lb/>prevalent mutation type in osteosarcomas was gene amplification <lb/>(71.8%), followed by substitutions/deletions (19.7%), gene fusions <lb/>(3.8%), homozygous deletions (2.6%), and truncating mutations <lb/>(2.1%) (Supplementary Figure S1). <lb/>To illustrate the genomic landscape based on a large cohort, we <lb/>integrated the results of WES and panel testing by filtering the WES <lb/>data for panel probe sites. The results revealed that the most <lb/>frequent mutations in osteosarcomas were in TP53 (39%), FLCN <lb/>(22%), NCOR1 (21%), VEGFA (16%), CCND3 (15%), RB1 (14%), <lb/>TFEB (12%), and MAP2K4 (11.8%) (Figure 1A). TP53 mutations <lb/>were predominantly of the substitution/indel type and concentrated <lb/>in the p53 protein&apos;s DNA-binding domain (Figure 1B). <lb/>3.3 Comparison of mutation characteristics <lb/>between pediatric, adolescent and adult <lb/>osteosarcoma patients <lb/>In this study, osteosarcoma patients under the age of 15 were <lb/>categorized as pediatric patients, those aged 15-25 as adolescent <lb/>patients, and those over the age of 25 as adult patients. Our findings <lb/>indicate that pediatric and then adolescent patients have a higher <lb/>frequency of gene amplification compared to adult patients, while <lb/>substitution/Indel mutation types are less frequent than in adult <lb/>osteosarcoma patients (Figure 1C). Enrichment analysis indicates <lb/>that gene mutations in patients older than 15 years are mainly <lb/>enriched in the cell cycle and PI3K/mTOR signaling pathways, while <lb/>gene mutations in patients younger than 15 years are primarily <lb/>enriched in the cell cycle and angiogenesis signaling pathways. <lb/>Additionally, we compared Homologous Recombination <lb/>Deficiency (HRD) mutated genes. The results showed that the <lb/>frequency of HRD mutations in pediatric and adolescent patients <lb/>was higher than in adult patients (17.5% vs. 16.5% vs. 7.7%) <lb/>(Figures 2A, B). We also compared the Tumor Mutational Burden <lb/>(TMB) distribution among pediatric, adolescent, and adult patients. <lb/>It was found that the TMB in adult patients was higher than in <lb/>pediatric patients, with a statistically significant difference (p = 0.04) <lb/>(Figure 2C). Compared with adult patients, the mutation frequency <lb/>of VEGFA (P &lt;0.001), CCND3 (P = 0.016) and TEEB (P = 0.0016) <lb/>were significantly higher in pediatrics and adolescents (Figure 2D). <lb/>The co-mutation analysis revealed that VEGFA, CCND3, and TEEB <lb/>are the most commonly co-mutated genes. In addition, XPO5 is <lb/>frequently co-mutated with VEGFA, CCND3, and TEEB, while <lb/>AURKB is commonly co-mutated with FLCN, NCOR1, CCND1, <lb/>TFEB, and MAP2K4 (Figure 2E). <lb/>3.4 Analysis of CNV distribution of <lb/>osteosarcoma in different age groups <lb/>In our study, we identified a total of 1,156 copy number <lb/>variation (CNV) variants across a cohort of 194 patients with <lb/>osteosarcoma. Among all CNVs, amplifications of VEGFA and <lb/>XPO5 were primarily found in patients under the age of 25, while <lb/>TABLE 1 Patient characteristics. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>Age,n(%), median(min-max) <lb/>16(5-73) <lb/>Age&lt;15 <lb/>81 (42) <lb/>15≤Age≤25 <lb/>85 (44) <lb/>Age&gt;25 <lb/>28 (14) <lb/>Gender, n (%) <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>Female <lb/>66 (34) <lb/>Male <lb/>128 (66) <lb/>Stage, n (%) <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>IA <lb/>1 (0.5) <lb/>IB <lb/>1 (0.5) <lb/>IIA <lb/>44 (23) <lb/>IIB <lb/>92 (47) <lb/>III <lb/>2 (1) <lb/>IVA <lb/>43 (22) <lb/>/ <lb/>11 (6) <lb/>Histologic subtypes <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>Parosteal osteosarcoma <lb/>3 (1.5) <lb/>Small cell osteosarcoma <lb/>1 (0.5) <lb/>Conventional osteosarcoma <lb/>190 (98) <lb/>grading <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>G1 <lb/>2 (1) <lb/>G2 <lb/>192 (99) <lb/>therapy <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>Neoadjuvant + surgery + adjuvant <lb/>164 (85) <lb/>surgery + adjuvant <lb/>30 (15) <lb/>MSI, n (%) <lb/>Total (n = 194) <lb/>MSS <lb/>193 (99) <lb/>MSI-H <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>PD-L1 (≥1=positive) <lb/>Total (n = 177) <lb/>Positive <lb/>44 (25) <lb/>Negative <lb/>133 (75) <lb/>In staging patients, the AJCC (American Joint Committee on Cancer) system is utilized. <lb/>However, it should be noted that for pelvic and spinal bone tumors (n=11), the AJCC staging <lb/>criteria are not applicable, as indicated by the &quot;/&quot; symbol, according to the Bone Cancer <lb/>NCCN Guidelines 2024, Version 2. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<body>amplifications of DAXX and DDR1 were concentrated in patients <lb/>under the age of 15. Conversely, deletions of CDKN2A and <lb/>CDKN2B were more prevalent in the age group over 25 years old <lb/>(Figure 3A). Additionally, within a subset of 75 osteosarcoma <lb/>patients who underwent whole-exome sequencing (WES), we <lb/>detected 668 CNV variants. The most frequent CNV include <lb/>17p11.2, 19q12, 6q21.1 and 12q12.1 amplification. In 31 pediatric <lb/>patients, 258 CNVs we detected including 247 amplifications and 11 <lb/>gene homozygous deletions, and the most frequent CNVs included <lb/>6p21.1 amplification, 17p12 amplification, 19q12 amplification, <lb/>16p13.3 deletion and 17p13.1 deletion; In 30 pediatric patients, <lb/>292 CNVs we detected including 277 amplifications and 15 <lb/>gene homozygous deletions, and the most frequent CNVs <lb/>included 1p36.13 amplification, 6p21.1 amplification, 12q14.1 <lb/>amplification, and 17p11.2 amplification; In 14 adult patients, 118 <lb/>CNVs were detected including 102 amplifications and 16 gene <lb/>homozygous deletions, and the most common CNVs included <lb/>8p12 deletion, 9p21.3 deletion, 13q13.3 deletion, 15q15.1 deletion, <lb/>and 16p13.3 deletion (Figure 3B). <lb/>3.5 Signature analysis <lb/>We observed similar trends across all six possible point <lb/>mutation types in the three groups. C&gt;T mutations were the <lb/>most abundant types, followed by C&gt;A and C&gt;G. Upon <lb/>conducting a comprehensive Signature analysis, underscores the <lb/>importance of age as a factor in mutational processes. <lb/>The differential signature analysis indicates that mutations <lb/>characteristic of BRCA1/2 and Aristolochic acid are more <lb/>pronounced in adults. The individual distribution of these <lb/>signatures was shown in Figure 4 and Table S1. <lb/>3.6 Prognosis analysis of <lb/>osteosarcoma patients <lb/>Based on the genomic alteration, we evaluated the prognostic <lb/>significance of specific genetic alterations in a cohort of patients. We <lb/>collected the effective overall survival (OS) information of 74 patients, <lb/>including 39 pediatric, 31 adolescents and 4 adult patients. The <lb/>overall median DFS was 24 months. Notably, mutations in the <lb/>genes MCL1, MYC, TFEB, CCND3, AURKB, and ALOX12B were <lb/>associated with a significantly worse prognosis, with p-values less <lb/>than 0.05, underscoring their potential role as markers for aggressive <lb/>disease courses. On the other hand, mutations in VEGFA were also <lb/>correlated with a poorer prognosis, with p-values approaching the <lb/>threshold of significance (near 0.05), suggesting a trend that warrants <lb/>further investigation for definitive conclusions (Figure 5 and <lb/>Table S2). <lb/>3.7 Available drug mutations <lb/>in osteosarcoma <lb/>Actionable drug mutations were detected in 58% (113 out of <lb/>194) of patients, encompassing 185 mutations across 35 target <lb/>genes, with VEGFA being the most frequently mutated gene <lb/>associated with drug responsiveness. About 25% (49/194) of <lb/>patients harbored the mutations of angiogenesis related gene <lb/>amplification, such as VEGFA, KIT, KDR, PDGFRA, ARAF, <lb/>FGFR1, VHL, and TFE3, and 18% (34/194) patients were <lb/>harbored CDK4/6 inhibition related mutations. These results <lb/>suggested the potential targeted treatment of osteosarcomas. In <lb/>pediatric adolescent patients, 86 available drug mutations from 23 <lb/>targeted genes were detected in 49 osteosarcoma patients. In <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Mutational characterization of this cohort. (A) Mutational landscape of 194 osteosarcoma patients (&lt;15, 15-25, &gt;25, respectively). (B) Distribution of TP53 <lb/>mutation sites. (C) Amplification statistics of patients in different age groups (&lt; 15, 15-25, &gt; 25, respectively). Green represents substitution/Indel mutations, <lb/>red represents gene amplification mutations, blue represents gene homozygous deletion mutations, yellow represents fusion/rearrangement mutations, and <lb/>purple represents truncation mutations. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<body>adolescent patients, 66 available drug mutations from 25 targeted <lb/>genes were detected in 49 osteosarcoma patients, and in adult <lb/>patients, 25 available drug mutations from 15 targeted genes were <lb/>detected in 15 osteosarcoma patients. The most common available <lb/>drug mutated genes include VEGFA in pediatric and adolescent <lb/>patients, CDK4 in adolescent patients, and CDKN2A, and CDKN2B <lb/>in adult patients. According to the drug type, the drug available <lb/>mutations were divided into Anti-PD-1/PD-L1 related mutations <lb/>such as CD274 and PDCD1LG2, CDK4/6 inhibitor related <lb/>mutations such as CDKN2A, CDKN2B, CCND1, and CDK4, <lb/>mTOR inhibitor related mutations such as PTEN, MTOR, <lb/>FBXW7, PIK3CA, and STK11, Multi-TKI related mutations such <lb/>as VEGFA, KIT, KDR, PDGFRA, ARAF, FGFR1, VHL, and TFE3, <lb/>VEGFA, KIT, KDR, PDGFRA, ARAF, FGFR1, VHL, and TFE3, and <lb/>PARP inhibitor related mutations such as ATM, BRCA2, and <lb/>BRCA1, and TKI related mutations such as ALK, KRAS, NRAS, <lb/>ROS1, MET, BRAF, EGFR, and MET. We found that the frequency <lb/>of Multi-TKI related mutations was significantly higher in pediatric <lb/>and adolescent patients than that in adult patients (34.57% vs <lb/>21.18% vs 10.71%, P =0.02), while the frequency of CDK4/6 <lb/>inhibitor related mutations was significantly higher in adult <lb/>patients than that of pediatric and adolescent patients (32.14% vs <lb/>18.82 vs 11.11%, P= 0.04) (Figure 6). <lb/>In the cohort of patients with VEGFR amplification, 13 <lb/>individuals underwent adjuvant therapy with multi-kinase <lb/>inhibitors post-surgery, including agents such as anlotinib, <lb/>apatinib, and recombinant human vascular endothelial inhibitors. <lb/>The median duration of follow-up was 3 months (1-20 months). <lb/>Within this subgroup, 3 patients achieved a Partial Response (PR), <lb/>all of whom were younger than 15 years. Furthermore, 4 patients <lb/>maintained Stable Disease (SD), and 6 patients experienced <lb/>Progressive Disease (PD). Notably, among the patients with PD, 4 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Comparison of mutation characteristics between osteosarcoma subgroups (pediatric, adolescent and adult). (A) Enrichment analysis of mutated pathways in <lb/>adult osteosarcoma group and adolescent osteosarcoma group. From blue to red represents the gradually decreased p value, circle size represents the <lb/>count of mutations in each pathway. (B) Enrichment differences in signaling pathways across age groups. (C) Association analysis between TMB and <lb/>osteosarcoma subgroup (pediatric, adolescent and adult). (D) Correlation analysis between genetic variation and age. (E) Co-mutation analysis of genes. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<body>exhibited additional genetic alterations: 2 cases with CDK4 <lb/>amplification, 1 with PIK3CA amplification, and 1 with a <lb/>PTEN mutation. <lb/>One notable case of PR was a 13-year-old patient diagnosed <lb/>with proximal tibial osteosarcoma, which demonstrated VEGFR <lb/>amplification. The patient underwent a successful surgical resection <lb/>of the tumor on December 18, 2018, which was classified as Stage <lb/>IIB by postoperative pathology. Between January 14, 2019, and <lb/>February 22, 2019, the patient received two cycles of adjuvant <lb/>chemotherapy using pirarubicin and cisplatin. Subsequent <lb/>treatment from April 2019 to January 2020 included the oral <lb/>VEGFR inhibitor anlotinib hydrochloride (Focilex). <lb/>To assess treatment response, a baseline imaging study was <lb/>obtained before the initiation of anlotinib, which identified multiple <lb/>lung nodules. According to RECIST criteria, target lesions were <lb/>defined, with the largest nodule in the lingular segment of the left <lb/>upper lobe measuring 10mm in diameter (considered as the target <lb/>lesion). Follow-up CT scans were performed to evaluate the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>Distribution and frequency of CNVs in osteosarcoma across different age groups. The frequency of common CNV in osteosarcoma is different in <lb/>different age groups (A). Distribution of CNVs in osteosarcoma across different age groups (B). <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 4 <lb/>Signature analysis of this cohort. (A) The most significant signatures in adolescent osteosarcoma patients. (B) The most significant signatures in adult <lb/>osteosarcoma patients. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<body>response at regular intervals. On July 1, 2019, the size of the target <lb/>lesion had decreased to 5mm, and by September 20, 2019, it had <lb/>further reduced to 4mm. Comparative imaging on December 19, <lb/>2019, showed continued reduction in the size of the target lesion as <lb/>well as non-target lesions. As of March 18, 2020, the target lesions <lb/>have further reduced in size. Based on the RECIST criteria, this <lb/>patient achieved a Partial Response (PR), with a significant <lb/>reduction in the size of the target lesion and overall tumor <lb/>burden (Figure 7). <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>With the development of molecular biology and next-<lb/>generation sequencing technology, the genomic variation <lb/>information of many cancer types has been revealed and applied <lb/>to targeted therapy. In osteosarcoma, due to the lack of <lb/>osteosarcoma samples and extensive genomic heterogeneity, the <lb/>determination of its somatic therapeutic targets is particularly <lb/>challenging. Although germline genetic variation is an important <lb/>risk factor associated with osteosarcoma, many studies are still <lb/>aiming to explore new treatments by identifying osteosarcoma <lb/>related biologically important pathways (1, 25, 26). In this study, <lb/>we collected 194 osteosarcoma patients, grouped them according to <lb/>their age, and analyzed the mutation characteristics of pediatric, <lb/>adolescent and adult osteosarcoma patients. <lb/>Previous studies have shown that the common mutant genes in <lb/>osteosarcoma include TP53, RB1, MYC (6, 7), however, there are <lb/>few studies on the mutation characteristics of osteosarcoma patients <lb/>based on large samples. Our results showed that not only identified <lb/>the high-frequency mutations of TP53 and RB1, but also revealed <lb/>high-frequency mutations in FLCN, NCOR1, VEGFA, CCND3, <lb/>TFEB, MAP2K4, and ATRX in osteosarcoma. Mutations in FLCN <lb/>gene are associated with Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome, which is <lb/>characterized by fibrofolliculomas, renal tumors, lung cysts, and <lb/>pneumothorax (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/201163). The <lb/>FIGURE 6 <lb/>Comparison of available drug mutation distribution in pediatric, adolescent and adult osteosarcoma group. * p &lt; 0.05. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 5 <lb/>Potential biomarkers related to the prognosis of osteosarcoma patients. The Kaplan-Meier curves separately depict the overall survival (OS) for <lb/>patients with and without mutations in the genes VEGFA (A), CCND3 (B), TFEB (C), MCL1 (D), AURKB (E), and MYC (F). The p-values between the risk <lb/>groups were calculated using the log-rank test. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<body>FLCN gene is commonly observed in patients diagnosed with both <lb/>primary and metastatic osteosarcoma (27), with a higher frequency <lb/>of alterations seen in pediatric cases compared to those in adults <lb/>(28). NCOR1 is a tumor suppressor gene. According to AACR <lb/>Genie cases, NCOR1 amplification is frequently occurred <lb/>proportion in osteosarcoma, which only less frequent than <lb/>leiomyosarcoma (29) (https://www.mycancergenome.org/content/ <lb/>gene/ncor1/). NCOR1 has been reported to be associated with <lb/>prognosis in many cancer type (30, 31). In bladder cancer, <lb/>NCOR1 mutation is associated with immune biomarker such as <lb/>TMB, suggesting that it may be used as biomarker for <lb/>immunotherapy (32). Therefore, NCOR1 has great potential for <lb/>clinical application. Its high frequency amplification mutation in <lb/>osteosarcoma may become a potential biomarker for guiding the <lb/>treatment. ATRX deficiency can promote tumorigenesis, including <lb/>enhanced cell movement of glioma cells and TGF in hepatoma cells-<lb/>b Activation and CDH1 (E-cadherin) down-regulation (33-35). In <lb/>osteosarcoma, ATRX deficiency also can promote tumor formation, <lb/>growth, infection and metastasis (36). In this study, there was no <lb/>significant difference in the proportion of ATRX mutations between <lb/>pediatric, adolescents and adults. <lb/>The onset characteristics of osteosarcoma are related to the age <lb/>of patients. The first peak of osteosarcoma is in adolescence, which <lb/>indicates that there is a close relationship between adolescent <lb/>growth spurt and osteosarcoma; The second peak of <lb/>osteosarcoma occurs in adults over 65 years old, which may be <lb/>related to the accumulation of mutations and the occurrence of <lb/>diseases (37). However, little is known about the mutation <lb/>characteristics of pediatric, adolescent and adult patients with <lb/>osteosarcoma. The comparison of mutation characteristics <lb/>between the three groups suggested that pediatric, adolescents are <lb/>more prone to gene amplification / deletion and fusion than adults, <lb/>and adults may accumulate more point mutations over time. The <lb/>differential signature analysis indicates that mutations characteristic <lb/>of BRCA1/2 and Aristolochic acid are more pronounced in adults, <lb/>and homologous recombination deficiency associated signature <lb/>may lead to the accumulation of DNA damage and genomic <lb/>instability (38). These results suggested the special molecular <lb/>characteristics of pediatric, adolescent and adult osteosarcoma <lb/>patients. Compared to adult patients with osteosarcoma, we <lb/>observed that the amplification frequencies of NCOR1, VEGFA, <lb/>CCND3, and TEEB were higher in pediatric and adolescent patients. <lb/>In contrast, the amplification frequencies of CDK4, TSPAN31, GLI1, <lb/>MDM2, and FRS2 were highest in adult patients with osteosarcoma, <lb/>followed by adolescents, and lowest in pediatric patients. There have <lb/>been few reports on mutations of TEEB, GLI1, MDM2, and FRS2 in <lb/>osteosarcoma. This suggests that the genetic mutation <lb/>characteristics of osteosarcoma are age-related, and the <lb/>pathogenesis of osteosarcoma may differ across various age <lb/>groups. The CCND3 encodes a highly conserved cell cycle <lb/>regulatory protein, and the expression of cyclin is characterized <lb/>by cyclicity. The fusion of KCNMB4-CCND3 was ever detected in <lb/>osteosarcoma and promoted the migration of osteosarcoma cell line <lb/>SAOS-2 (39). The overexpression of VEGFA in various human <lb/>tumors is associated with tumor cell invasion, increased vascular <lb/>density, tumor metastasis, tumor recurrence and poor prognosis <lb/>(40). The amplification of VEGFA may elevate their respective <lb/>proteins in osteosarcoma (41). In this study, we grouped <lb/>osteosarcoma patients by their age and suggested that high <lb/>frequency VEGFA and CCND3 amplification may be the <lb/>FIGURE 7 <lb/>Computed Tomography (CT) imaging changes in tumor size during patient medication regimen. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<body>molecular characteristics of adolescent osteosarcoma patients. <lb/>There has been an increasing interest in exploring the role of <lb/>TSPAN31 in cancerous diseases. Earlier studies have discovered a <lb/>significant rise in TSPAN31 levels in osteosarcoma, hinting at its <lb/>possible link to the expansion and dissemination of the tumor. It is <lb/>also important to point out that TSPAN31 acts as a natural antisense <lb/>transcript to CDK4. Investigations have demonstrated that <lb/>TSPAN31 plays a role in the advancement of tumors by <lb/>controlling the expression of CDK4, with evidence from research <lb/>on cervical and liver cancer cases (42-44). FRS2 and MDM2 are <lb/>close to each other on chromosomes and are often detected in the <lb/>form of co-amplification. Previous study had shown that the <lb/>amplification of FRS2 and MDM2 occurs frequently in low-grade <lb/>osteosarcoma (95%, 21/22), and only one of these patients is <lb/>younger than 20 years old (45). Our research underscores the <lb/>high amplification frequency of MDM2 within the adult patient <lb/>population, particularly considering MDM2&apos;s role in the negative <lb/>regulation of the p53 pathway-a pivotal aspect of tumor biology. <lb/>The amplification of MDM2 correlates with increased protein levels <lb/>capable of inhibiting p53, thereby promoting tumor progression <lb/>and potentially exerting a detrimental effect on patient outcomes. <lb/>The age-specific prevalence of MDM2 amplification identified in <lb/>our study positions it as a valuable biomarker for the diagnosis and <lb/>prognosis of adult osteosarcoma. It may also signal the need for <lb/>more aggressive therapeutic approaches in this demographic group. <lb/>Furthermore, the potential for targeted therapy against MDM2, <lb/>with inhibitors that are already undergoing clinical trials for other <lb/>cancers, presents an optimistic path for personalized treatment <lb/>strategies. Recognizing the necessity for additional validation, we <lb/>propose further research to solidify the predictive and prognostic <lb/>utility of MDM2 amplification. This would involve larger patient <lb/>cohorts and an analysis of clinical outcomes, such as treatment <lb/>response, disease progression, and survival rates. Other studies have <lb/>shown that higher TMB is more distributed in older patients (46). <lb/>Similar results have been obtained in our study. The TMB of adult <lb/>patients is higher than that of pediatric patients, which may be <lb/>related to the long-term accumulation of point mutations. This also <lb/>supports our previous conjecture to properly explain the age <lb/>characteristics of osteosarcoma patients. A significant role of NGS <lb/>in cancer precision medicine is to detect potential available targets <lb/>(47). PDGFRA and KIT mutations are common in gastrointestinal <lb/>stromal tumors (48). Our results suggest that these two mutations <lb/>are also common in patients with osteosarcoma. Sunitinib, <lb/>regorafenib, and imatinib have kinase inhibitory activities of KIT <lb/>and PDGFRA (49). Studies have shown that regorafenib is also <lb/>active in osteosarcoma (50). However, we did not find any <lb/>difference in the frequency of these gene mutations between <lb/>adolescent and adult osteosarcoma patients. <lb/>Osteosarcomas are genetically defined by significant genomic <lb/>instability, which is manifested through extensive aneuploidy, the <lb/>existence of imbalanced chromosomal rearrangements, and the <lb/>frequent amplification or deletion of various genomic segments. <lb/>Previous studies have indicated that amplifications in osteosarcoma <lb/>are commonly concentrated in specific regions such as regions <lb/>6p12-p21, 8q24, and 17p11.2-p12 (51-53). However, differences in <lb/>amplification regions among patients of varying age groups have <lb/>not yet been reported. Our genomic analysis identified a <lb/>chromosomal hotspot harboring high-frequency mutations at the <lb/>6p21 locus, particularly involving the TFEB, CCND3, and VEGFA <lb/>genes. This region is known to be critical during pediatric and <lb/>adolescence, and the presence of mutations in this area may indicate <lb/>a predisposition to certain malignancies in younger populations. <lb/>These results indicate the unique prognosis molecular indicators of <lb/>osteosarcoma patients in different age groups. <lb/>Previous studies have indicated that the loss of RB1, <lb/>amplification of MYC, and amplification of VEGFA are molecular <lb/>characteristics that can identify high-risk patients. However, these <lb/>risk factors have not been fully validated and cannot yet serve as the <lb/>basis for clinical risk stratification (54). Our research findings <lb/>suggest that in addition to MYC, mutations in the genes MCL1, <lb/>TFEB, CCND3, AURKB, and ALOX12B are also significantly <lb/>associated with poor prognosis. Additionally, mutations in the <lb/>VEGFA gene have shown a trend towards association with poor <lb/>prognosis, although the p-value is close to the significance threshold <lb/>and has not yet reached statistical significance. Given the critical <lb/>role of VEGFA in angiogenesis, this trend suggests that the gene <lb/>might play a role in vascular supply and tumor microenvironment <lb/>formation in osteosarcoma. These findings prompt us to further <lb/>investigate the specific role of VEGFA in the development of <lb/>osteosarcoma and to explore its potential as a therapeutic target. <lb/>VEGFA can bind to vascular endothelial growth factor receptor <lb/>on the surface of cell membrane, produce biological effects through <lb/>a series of signal pathways, and finally lead to angiogenesis (55), and <lb/>plays a role in regulating vascular development and is the target of <lb/>targeted drugs to inhibit angiogenesis (56). VEGF/VEGFR can be <lb/>used as a target to inhibit angiogenesis (57-59). The most common <lb/>CNV of osteosarcoma includes VEGFA, which suggested the <lb/>potential opportunity to benefit from anti-angiogenic agent (60). <lb/>In our cohort, we stratified the patients and found that 100% of <lb/>patients with VEGFA mutations belong to pediatric and adolescent <lb/>patients. The VEGFA variations correspond to Multi-TKI, and the <lb/>high proportion of VEGFA variants in pediatric and adolescents <lb/>may result in the more opportunities to benefit from Multi-TKI <lb/>treatment than adults. This also showed that it is necessary to <lb/>stratify patients with osteosarcoma according to their age and <lb/>provide accurate medical treatment. <lb/>The CDK4/6 inhibitor related gene include CDKN2A/B, CCND1, <lb/>and CDK4, and the variations frequency of these genes increase with <lb/>age (61). Research has indicated that elevated levels of CDK4 <lb/>expression and its amplification in tumors serve as predictive <lb/>biomarkers for resistance to standard chemotherapy in <lb/>osteosarcoma (OS) patients, suggesting that palbociclib holds <lb/>potential as an effective treatment option for this clinically <lb/>challenging group (62). Our study findings confirm the same trend, <lb/>with higher frequencies of CDKN2A/B, CCND1, and CDK4 gene <lb/>mutations observed in adults. This indicates that with the growth of <lb/>age, adult osteosarcoma patients are more likely to accumulate age-<lb/>related gene mutations, including CDKN2A/B, CCND1, and CDK4, <lb/>which supports that adult osteosarcoma patients may have more <lb/>opportunities to benefit from CDK4/6 inhibitors. <lb/>Additionally, our study found that the number of patients under <lb/>the age of 15 (81 cases) closely matches those aged 15-25 (85 cases), <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<body>with their molecular differences predominantly centralized in <lb/>variations in enriched signaling pathways. In patients older than <lb/>15, gene mutations are mainly enriched in the cell cycle and PI3K/ <lb/>mTOR signaling pathways. In contrast, patients younger than 15 <lb/>exhibit gene mutations largely concentrated in the cell cycle and <lb/>angiogenesis signaling pathways. CDK4 mutations are more <lb/>frequently observed in adolescent patients. Furthermore, all patients <lb/>who achieved partial remission with multitargeted kinase inhibitor <lb/>therapy were under the age of 15. There are also mutual molecular <lb/>features; mutations in VEGFA, CCND3, and TFEB are significantly <lb/>present in both children and adolescents. The amplification rates of <lb/>VEGFA and XPO5 are high in pediatric and adolescent patients as <lb/>well, whereas mutations in CDKN2A and CDKN2B are more <lb/>common in adults, underscoring the stark differences between <lb/>pediatric/adolescent and adult patients. Adolescent patients may <lb/>represent a transitional state in terms of molecular characteristics <lb/>and treatment responses, falling between children and adults. <lb/>The study examining molecular distinctions among pediatric, <lb/>adolescent, and adult patients with osteosarcoma is subject to several <lb/>limitations: It encompasses a modest patient population of 194 cases, <lb/>potentially curtailing the power to discern differences and possibly <lb/>not reflecting the wider osteosarcoma demographic. Although the <lb/>research indicates potential associations between certain mutations <lb/>and poorer outcomes, these findings do not confirm causality or <lb/>establish definitive prognostic indicators without additional <lb/>substantiation. Consequently, while the study sheds valuable light <lb/>on the molecular landscape of osteosarcoma across various age <lb/>groups, the results warrant cautious interpretation and require <lb/>corroboration via more extensive, prospective, multicentered <lb/>studies with prolonged follow-up periods and randomized clinical <lb/>trials to determine the true clinical relevance of the molecular <lb/>markers identified. Another limitation of our study is that 28 of <lb/>194 patients who were enrolled had tissue samples obtained from <lb/>needle biopsies, and tumor heterogeneity poses substantial <lb/>challenges. This heterogeneity implies that distinct molecular <lb/>profiles may be present in different tumor areas, making genetic <lb/>data interpretation complex. Biopsy samples inherently offer a limited <lb/>snapshot of the entire tumor since they are typically obtained from a <lb/>single region. This selective sampling might render an incomplete or <lb/>potentially misleading picture of the tumor&apos;s genetic makeup. The <lb/>impact of tumor heterogeneity on study outcomes is significant; it <lb/>may lead to overrepresentation of genetic alterations that are <lb/>prevalent in the sampled region but not indicative of the whole <lb/>tumor. Conversely, crucial mutations in other tumor parts may be <lb/>overlooked. Such omissions could profoundly affect our conclusions <lb/>on the correlation between genetic mutations and clinical outcomes, <lb/>as they might not accurately reflect the mutational burden of the <lb/>entire tumor. To mitigate the potential biases introduced by tumor <lb/>heterogeneity in biopsy samples, future studies should consider <lb/>incorporating multiple biopsy samples from diverse tumor regions <lb/>when possible. Additionally, the comparison of genetic data from <lb/>biopsy samples with that from complete tumor resections could yield <lb/>a more holistic view of the molecular changes in osteosarcoma. <lb/>Employing standardized methods for sample collection and DNA <lb/>sequencing, as well as including larger patient cohorts from various <lb/>demographics, is essential for future research. These steps will help <lb/>lessen the effects of heterogeneity and enhance the generalizability of <lb/>the study&apos;s findings to a broader osteosarcoma patient population. In <lb/>this study, the majority of the specimens were surgical samples <lb/>obtained after 2 to 3 cycles of neoadjuvant chemotherapy. We <lb/>acknowledge that neoadjuvant chemotherapy may impact the <lb/>genomic analysis of the surgical tissue. The potential effects include <lb/>a significant reduction in the number of detectable tumor cells, which <lb/>could affect genetic analyses that require a sufficient quantity of tumor <lb/>cells. Chemotherapy might selectively eliminate tumor cell <lb/>populations that are sensitive to the drugs, leaving behind resistant <lb/>populations, which could result in altered genetic characteristics of <lb/>the tumor. Furthermore, chemotherapy could influence the gene <lb/>expression patterns within tumor cells, leading to the upregulation or <lb/>downregulation of certain genes, thereby affecting the outcomes of <lb/>genetic testing. <lb/>In this study, we examined the molecular characteristics of <lb/>osteosarcoma across pediatric, adolescent, and adult patients, <lb/>highlighting differences in the molecular mechanisms of the disease <lb/>between adolescents and adults, and investigated biomarkers that <lb/>could specifically predict the prognosis of adolescent osteosarcoma <lb/>patients. Furthermore, we identified the importance of age in the <lb/>distribution of copy number variations (CNVs) and point mutations, <lb/>revealing age-related pathogenic differences and the potential <lb/>influence of certain genetic variations on patient outcomes. <lb/>Notably, younger patients with VEGFR-amplified osteosarcoma <lb/>who received adjuvant multi-kinase inhibitor therapy achieved <lb/>partial remission or disease stabilization, emphasizing the necessity <lb/>for personalized treatment approaches. These insights contribute to a <lb/>deeper understanding of the genetic heterogeneity in osteosarcoma <lb/>and support the development of precise diagnostic and treatment <lb/>strategies that are tailored to the individual needs of patients from <lb/>different age cohorts. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The authors acknowledge that the data presented in this study <lb/>must be deposited and made publicly available in an acceptable <lb/>repository, prior to publication. Frontiers cannot accept an article <lb/>that does not adhere to our open data policies. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by The Clinical <lb/>Research and Laboratory Animal Ethics Committee of the First <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University. The studies were <lb/>conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional <lb/>requirements. The human samples used in this study were acquired <lb/>from Tissue samples are the remaining samples for pathological <lb/>diagnosis, which will not affect the subject&apos;s diagnosis. The studies <lb/>were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and <lb/>institutional requirements. The human samples used in this study <lb/>were obtained in compliance with ethical standards. Written <lb/>informed consent for participation was not required from the <lb/>participants or the participants&apos; legal guardians/next of kin in <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<div type="annex">accordance with the national legislation and institutional <lb/>requirements. Written informed consent was obtained from the <lb/>minor(s)&apos; legal guardian/next of kin for the publication of any <lb/>potentially identifiable images or data included in this article. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>JS: Funding acquisition, Project administration, Resources, <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. CZ: Data curation, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Writing -review &amp; editing. RH: <lb/>Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Writing -<lb/>original draft. TL: Investigation, Supervision, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. YW: Formal analysis, Writing -original draft. JT: <lb/>Resources, Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. LZ: Formal <lb/>analysis, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. BW: <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Writing -review &amp; editing. JH: <lb/>Formal analysis, Methodology, Writing -review &amp; editing. ZZ: <lb/>Resources, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. XX: Resources, <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. GH: Data curation, <lb/>Resources, Writing -review &amp; editing. KW: Resources, Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing. JY: Project administration, Resources, <lb/>Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work is <lb/>supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of China (NSFC) -General Program (82072964, 81972507 <lb/>and 82273413). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors are grateful to all the study participants, patients, <lb/>and their family members for their contributions and support. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>Authors YW, LZ, JH, and KW were employed by OrigiMed. <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or <lb/>endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/>SUPPLEMENTARY FIGURE 1 <lb/>Distribution of mutation types in osteosarcoma patients. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Whelan JS, Davis LE. Osteosarcoma, chondrosarcoma, and chordoma. J Clin <lb/>Oncol. (2018) 36:188-93. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.75.1743 <lb/>2. Mirabello L, Troisi RJ, Savage SA. Osteosarcoma incidence and survival rates from <lb/>1973 to 2004: data from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program. <lb/>Cancer: Interdiscip Int J Am Cancer Soc. (2009) 115:1531-43. doi: 10.1002/cncr.24121 <lb/>3. Bielack SS, Kempf-Bielack B, Delling G, Exner GU, Flege S, Helmke K, et al. <lb/>Prognostic factors in high-grade osteosarcoma of the extremities or trunk: an analysis <lb/>of 1,702 patients treated on neoadjuvant cooperative osteosarcoma study group <lb/>protocols. J Clin Oncol. (2002) 20:776-90. doi: 10.1200/JCO.20.3.776 <lb/>4. Kager L, Zoubek A, Poütschger U, Kastner U, Flege S, Kempf-Bielack B, et al. Primary <lb/>metastatic osteosarcoma: presentation and outcome of patients treated on neoadjuvant <lb/>Cooperative Osteosarcoma Study Group protocols. J Clin Oncol. (2003) 21:2011-8. <lb/>doi: 10.1200/JCO.2003.08.132 <lb/>5. Lewis IJ, Nooij MA, Whelan J, Sydes MR, Grimer R, Hogendoorn PC, et al. <lb/>Improvement in histologic response but not survival in osteosarcoma patients treated with <lb/>intensified chemotherapy: a randomized phase III trial of the European Osteosarcoma <lb/>Intergroup. J Natl Cancer Institute. (2007) 99:112-28. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djk015 <lb/>6. Wachtel M, Schäfer BW. Targets for cancer therapy in childhood sarcomas. <lb/>Cancer Treat Rev. (2010) 36:318-27. doi: 10.1016/j.ctrv.2010.02.007 <lb/>7. Jiang Y, Wang T, Wei Z. Construction and validation of nomograms for <lb/>predicting the prognosis of juvenile osteosarcoma: a real-world analysis in the SEER <lb/>database. Technol Cancer Res Treat. (2020) 19:1533033820947718. doi: 10.1177/ <lb/>1533033820947718 <lb/>8. Morsy AM, Ahmed BM, Rezk KM, Ramadan IK, Aboelgheit AM, Eltyb HA, <lb/>et al. Age and tumor location predict survival in nonmetastatic osteosarcoma in <lb/>upper Egypt. J Pediatr Hematology/Oncology. (2020) 42:e66-78. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>MPH.0000000000001506 <lb/>9. Ding WZ, Liu K, Li Z, Chen SR. A meta-analysis of prognostic factors of <lb/>osteosarcoma. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. (2020) 24:4103-12. doi: 10.26355/ <lb/>eurrev_202004_20989 <lb/>10. Savage SA, Mirabello L. Using epidemiology and genomics to understand <lb/>osteosarcoma etiology. Sarcoma. (2011) 2011:548151. doi: 10.1155/2011/548151 <lb/>11. Ferrari S, Bielack SS, Smeland S, Longhi A, Egerer G, Sundby Hall K, et al. <lb/>EURO-BOSS: A European study on chemotherapy in bone-sarcoma patients aged over <lb/>40: Outcome in primary high-grade osteosarcoma. Tumori J. (2018) 104:30-6. <lb/>doi: 10.5301/tj.5000696 <lb/>12. Grimer RJ, Cannon SR, Taminiau AM, Bielack S, Kempf-Bielack B, Windhager <lb/>R, et al. Osteosarcoma over the age of forty. Eur J Cancer. (2003) 39:157-63. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/S0959-8049(02)00478-1 <lb/>13. Chen X, Bahrami A, Pappo A, Easton J, Dalton J, Hedlund E, et al. Recurrent <lb/>somatic structural variations contribute to tumorigenesis in pediatric osteosarcoma. <lb/>Cell Rep. (2014) 7:104-12. doi: 10.1016/j.celrep.2014.03.003 <lb/>14. Hu K, Dai HB, Qiu ZL. mTOR signaling in osteosarcoma: Oncogenesis and <lb/>therapeutic aspects. Oncol Rep. (2016) 36:1219-25. doi: 10.3892/or.2016.4922 <lb/>15. Li Y, Liu Q, He HB, Luo W. The possible role of insulin-like growth factor-1 in <lb/>osteosarcoma. Curr Problems Cancer. (2019) 43:228-35. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.currproblcancer.2018.08.008 <lb/>16. Assi T, Watson S, Samra B, Rassy E, Le Cesne A, Italiano A, et al. Targeting the <lb/>VEGF pathway in osteosarcoma. Cells. (2021) 10:1240. doi: 10.3390/cells10051240 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>17. Xu J, Xie L, Guo W. PDGF/PDGFR effects in osteosarcoma and the &quot;add-on&quot; <lb/>strategy. Clin Sarcoma Res. (2018) 8:1-9. doi: 10.1186/s13569-018-0102-1 <lb/>18. Tsuchie H, Emori M, Nagasawa H, Miyakoshi N, Murahashi Y, Shimizu J, et al. <lb/>Prognosis of primary osteosarcoma in elderly patients: a comparison between young <lb/>and elderly patients. Med Principles Pract. (2019) 28:425-31. doi: 10.1159/000500404 <lb/>19. Vasquez L, Silva J, Chavez S, Zapata A, Diaz R, Tarrillo F, et al. Prognostic <lb/>impact of diagnostic and treatment delays in children with osteosarcoma. Pediatr Blood <lb/>Cancer. (2020) 67:e28180. doi: 10.1002/pbc.28180 <lb/>20. Pan Y, Chen D, Hu T, Lv G, Dai Z. Characteristics and prognostic factors of <lb/>patients with osteosarcoma older than 60 years from the SEER database. Cancer <lb/>Control. (2019) 26:1073274819888893. doi: 10.1177/1073274819888893 <lb/>21. Roux A, Pallud J, Saffroy R, Edjlali-Goujon M, Debily MA, Boddaert N, et al. <lb/>High-grade gliomas in adolescents and young adults highlight histomolecular <lb/>differences from their adult and pediatric counterparts. Neuro-oncology. (2020) <lb/>22:1190-202. doi: 10.1093/neuonc/noaa024 <lb/>22. Kaya M, Wada T, Akatsuka T, Kawaguchi S, Nagoya S, Shindoh M, et al. <lb/>Vascular endothelial growth factor expression in untreated osteosarcoma is predictive <lb/>of pulmonary metastasis and poor prognosis. Clin Cancer Res. (2000) 6:572-7. <lb/>23. Worch J, Matthay KK, Neuhaus J, Goldsby R, DuBois SG. Osteosarcoma in <lb/>children 5 years of age or younger at initial diagnosis. Pediatr Blood Cancer. (2010) <lb/>55:285-9. doi: 10.1002/pbc.22509 <lb/>24. Blokzijl F, Janssen R, Van Boxtel R, Cuppen E. MutationalPatterns: <lb/>comprehensive genome-wide analysis of mutational processes. Genome Med. (2018) <lb/>10:1-11. doi: 10.1186/s13073-018-0539-0 <lb/>25. Friebele JC, Peck J, Pan X, Abdel-Rasoul M, Mayerson JL. Osteosarcoma: a meta-<lb/>analysis and review of the literature. Am J Orthop. (2015) 44:547-53. <lb/>26. Meyers PA, Heller G, Healey JH, Huvos A, Applewhite A, Sun M, et al. <lb/>Osteogenic sarcoma with clinically detectable metastasis at initial presentation. J Clin <lb/>Oncol. (1993) 11:449-53. doi: 10.1200/JCO.1993.11.3.449 <lb/>27. Zou C, Zhao Z, Xu M, Guo W, Huang J, Zhang X, et al. Deciphering possible <lb/>mechanisms of action in pathophysiology of osteosarcoma: PI3K-Akt/MAPK pathways <lb/>contribute to tumorigenesis versus FoxO/mTOR/HIF-1 pathways involved in <lb/>metastasis. J Clin Oncol. (2022) 40:e23515-e23515. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2022.40. <lb/>16_suppl.e23515 <lb/>28. Seeber A, Elliott A, Modiano J, Untergasser G, von Mehren M, Rosenberg AE, <lb/>et al. Age as a factor in the molecular landscape and the tumor-microenvironmental <lb/>signature of osteosarcoma. J Clin Oncol. (2022) 40. doi: 10.1200/ <lb/>JCO.2022.40.16_suppl.11525 <lb/>29. AndréF, Arnedos M, Baras AS, Baselga J, Bedard PL, Berger MF, et al. AACR <lb/>Project GENIE: powering precision medicine through an international consortium. <lb/>Cancer Discovery. (2017) 7:818-31. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.cd-17-0151 <lb/>30. Noblejas-Loṕez MM, Morcillo-Garcia S, Nieto-Jimeńez C, Nuncia-Cantarero M, <lb/>Gyorffy B, Galan-Moya EM, et al. Evaluation of transcriptionally regulated genes <lb/>identifies NCOR1 in hormone receptor negative breast tumors and lung <lb/>adenocarcinomas as a potential tumor suppressor gene. PloS One. (2018) 13: <lb/>e0207776. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0207776 <lb/>31. Tang L, Zhang L, Liu L, Dong L, Dong Y, Zhu W, et al. NCOR1 may be a <lb/>potential biomarker of a novel molecular subtype of prostate cancer. FEBS Open Bio. <lb/>(2020) 10:2678-86. doi: 10.1002/2211-5463.13004 <lb/>32. Lin A, Qiu Z, Zhang J, Luo P. Effect of NCOR1 mutations on immune <lb/>microenvironment and efficacy of immune checkpoint inhibitors in patient with <lb/>bladder cancer. Front Immunol. (2021) 12:630773. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.630773 <lb/>33. Danussi C, Bose P, Parthasarathy PT, Silberman PC, Van Arnam JS, Vitucci M, <lb/>et al. Atrx inactivation drives disease-defining phenotypes in glioma cells of origin <lb/>through global epigenomic remodeling. Nat Commun. (2018) 9:1057. doi: 10.1038/ <lb/>s41467-018-03476-6 <lb/>34. Haase S, Garcia-Fabiani MB, Carney S, Altshuler D, Nuñez FJ, Meńdez FM, et al. <lb/>Mutant ATRX: uncovering a new therapeutic target for glioma. Expert Opin Ther <lb/>Targets. (2018) 22:599-613. doi: 10.1080/14728222.2018.1487953 <lb/>35. Liang J, Liu H, Li G, Qian J, Gao R, Zhou Y, et al. Global changes in chromatin <lb/>accessibility and transcription following ATRX inactivation in human cancer cells. <lb/>FEBS Lett. (2020) 594:67-78. doi: 10.1002/1873-3468.13549 <lb/>36. DeWitt SB, Plumlee SH, Brighton HE, Sivaraj D, Martz EJ, Zand M, et al. Loss of <lb/>ATRX promotes aggressive features of osteosarcoma with increased NF-kB signaling <lb/>and integrin binding. JCI Insight. (2022) 7:e15158. doi: 10.1172/jci.insight.151583 <lb/>37. Ottaviani G, Jaffe N. The epidemiology of osteosarcoma. Pediatr Adolesc <lb/>osteosarcoma. (2010), 3-13. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdx709 <lb/>38. Hoppe MM, Sundar R, Tan DSP, Jeyasekharan AD. Biomarkers for homologous <lb/>recombination deficiency in cancer. JNCI: J Natl Cancer Institute. (2018) 110:704-13. <lb/>doi: 10.1093/jnci/djy085 <lb/>39. Yang J, Annala M, Ji P, Wang G, Zheng H, Codgell D, et al. Recurrent LRP1-<lb/>SNRNP25 and KCNMB4-CCND3 fusion genes promote tumor cell motility in human <lb/>osteosarcoma. J Hematol Oncol. (2014) 7:1-10. doi: 10.1186/s13045-014-0076-2 <lb/>40. Kerbel RS. Tumor angiogenesis. New Engl J Med. (2008) 358:2039-49. <lb/>doi: 10.1056/NEJMra0706596 <lb/>41. Yang J, Zhao L, Tian W, Liao Z, Zheng H, Wang G, et al. Correlation of WWOX, <lb/>RUNX2 and VEGFA protein expression in human osteosarcoma. BMC Med Genomics. <lb/>(2013) 6:1-8. doi: 10.1186/1755-8794-6-56 <lb/>42. Ragazzini P, Gamberi G, Pazzaglia L, Serra M, Magagnoli G, Ponticelli F, et al. <lb/>Amplification of CDK4, MDM2, SAS and GLI genes in leiomyosarcoma, alveolar and <lb/>embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma. Histol Histopathology. (2004) 19(2):401-11. <lb/>doi: 10.14670/hh-19.401 <lb/>43. Xia Y, Deng Y, Zhou Y, Li D, Sun X, Gu L, et al. TSPAN31 suppresses cell <lb/>proliferation in human cervical cancer through down-regulation of its antisense pairing <lb/>with CDK4. Cell Biochem Funct. (2020) 38:660-8. doi: 10.1002/cbf.3526 <lb/>44. Wang J, Zhou Y, Li D, Sun X, Deng Y, Zhao Q. TSPAN 31 is a critical regulator <lb/>on transduction of survival and apoptotic signals in hepatocellular carcinoma cells. <lb/>FEBS Lett. (2017) 591:2905-18. doi: 10.1002/1873-3468.12737 <lb/>45. He X, Pang Z, Zhang X, Lan T, Chen H, Chen M, et al. Consistent amplification <lb/>of FRS2 and MDM2 in low-grade osteosarcoma. Am J Surg Pathol. (2018) 42:1143-55. <lb/>doi: 10.1097/PAS.0000000000001125 <lb/>46. Wang L, Pan S, Zhu B, Yu Z, Wang W. Comprehensive analysis of tumour <lb/>mutational burden and its clinical significance in prostate cancer. BMC Urol. (2021) <lb/>21:1-10. doi: 10.1186/s12894-021-00795-7 <lb/>47. Strom SP. Current practices and guidelines for clinical next-generation sequencing <lb/>oncology testing. Cancer Biol Med. (2016) 13:3. doi: 10.20892/j.issn.2095-3941.2016.0004 <lb/>48. Lasota J, Miettinen M. KIT and PDGFRA mutations in gastrointestinal stromal <lb/>tumors (GISTs). Semin Diagn Pathol. (2006) 23:91-102. doi: 10.1053/ <lb/>j.semdp.2006.08.006 <lb/>49. Demetri GD, Reichardt P, Kang YK, Blay JY, Rutkowski P, Gelderblom H, et al. <lb/>Efficacy and safety of regorafenib for advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours after <lb/>failure of imatinib and sunitinib (GRID): an international, multicentre, randomised, <lb/>placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet. (2013) 381:295-302. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736 <lb/>(12)61857-1 <lb/>50. Davis LE, Bolejack V, Ryan CW, Ganjoo KN, Loggers ET, et al. Randomized <lb/>double-blind phase II study of regorafenib in patients with metastatic osteosarcoma. J <lb/>Clin Oncol. (2019) 37:1424. doi: 10.1200/JCO.18.02374 <lb/>51. Forus A, Weghuis DO, Smeets D, Fodstad O, Myklebost O, Geurts van Kessel A. <lb/>Comparative genomic hybridization analysis of human sarcomas: II. Identification of <lb/>novel amplicons at 6p and 17p in osteosarcomas. Genes Chromosomes Cancer. (1995) <lb/>14:15-21. doi: 10.1002/gcc.2870140104 <lb/>52. Lau CC, Harris CP, Lu XY, Perlaky L, Gogineni S, Chintagumpala M, et al. <lb/>Frequent amplification and rearrangement of chromosomal bands 6p12-p21 and <lb/>17p11. 2 in osteosarcoma. Genes Chromosomes Cancer. (2004) 39:11-21. <lb/>doi: 10.1002/gcc.10291 <lb/>53. Selvarajah S, Yoshimoto M, Ludkovski O, Park PC, Bayani J, Thorner P, et al. <lb/>Genomic signatures of chromosomal instability and osteosarcoma progression detected <lb/>by high resolution array CGH and interphase FISH. Cytogenetic Genome Res. (2008) <lb/>122:5-15. doi: 10.1159/000151310 <lb/>54. Beird HC, Bielack SS, Flanagan AM, Gill J, Heymann D, Janeway KA, et al. <lb/>Osteosarcoma. Nat Rev Dis Primers. (2022) 8:77. doi: 10.1038/s41572-022-00409-y <lb/>55. Holmes DIR, Zachary I. The vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) family: <lb/>angiogenic factors in health and disease. Genome Biol. (2005) 6(2):209. doi: 10.1186/gb-<lb/>2005-6-2-209 <lb/>56. Eswarappa SM, Fox PL. Antiangiogenic VEGF-Ax: a new participant in tumor <lb/>angiogenesis. Cancer Res. (2015) 75:2765-9. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-14-3805 <lb/>57. Cao G, Li X, Qin C, Li J. Prognostic value of VEGF in hepatocellular carcinoma <lb/>patients treated with sorafenib: a meta-analysis. Med Sci monitor: Int Med J Exp Clin <lb/>Res. (2015) 21:3144. doi: 10.12659/MSM.894617 <lb/>58. Peng H, Zhang Q, Li J, Zhang N, Hua Y, Xu L, et al. Apatinib inhibits VEGF <lb/>signaling and promotes apoptosis in intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma. Oncotarget. <lb/>(2016) 7:17220. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.v7i13 <lb/>59. Amano T, Iijima H, Shinzaki S, Tashiro T, Iwatani S, Tani M, et al. Vascular <lb/>endothelial growth factor-A is an Immunohistochemical biomarker for the efficacy of <lb/>bevacizumab-containing chemotherapy for duodenal and jejunal adenocarcinoma. <lb/>BMC Cancer. (2021) 21:978. doi: 10.1186/s12885-021-08724-5 <lb/>60. Suehara Y, Alex D, Bowman A, Middha S, Zehir A, Chakravarty D, et al. Clinical <lb/>genomic sequencing of pediatric and adult osteosarcoma reveals distinct molecular <lb/>subsets with potentially targetable alterations. Clin Cancer Res. (2019) 25:6346-56. <lb/>doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-18-4032 <lb/>61. Chatsirisupachai K, Lesluyes T, Paraoan L, Van Loo P, de Magalhães JP. An <lb/>integrative analysis of the age-associated multi-omic landscape across cancers. Nat <lb/>Commun. (2021) 12:2345. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-22560-y <lb/>62. Iwata S, Tatsumi Y, Yonemoto T, Araki A, Itami M, Kamoda H, et al. CDK4 <lb/>overexpression is a predictive biomarker for resistance to conventional chemotherapy <lb/>in patients with osteosarcoma. Oncol Rep. (2021) 46:1-11. doi: 10.3892/or <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Zou et al. <lb/>10.3389/fonc.2024.1382276 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Oncology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>13 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>