<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T14:33:31.956Z">11/21/2025 2:33:31 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T14:33:12.517248Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T14:33:12.517248Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Citation: Wei, Z.; Chen, J.; Xue, J.; Qu, <lb/>N.; Liu, Y.; Sun, L.; Xiao, Y.; Wu, B.; <lb/>Zhu, J.; Tang, H. Investigation of the <lb/>Influence of Alloy Atomic Doping on <lb/>the Properties of Cu-Sn Alloys Based <lb/>on First Principles. Metals 2024, 14, <lb/>552. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>met14050552 <lb/>Academic Editor: Alain Pasturel <lb/>Received: 19 March 2024 <lb/>Revised: 24 April 2024 <lb/>Accepted: 30 April 2024 <lb/>Published: 7 May 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 by the authors. <lb/>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. <lb/>This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and <lb/>conditions of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution (CC BY) license (https:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by/ <lb/>4.0/). <lb/>metals <lb/>Article <lb/>Investigation of the Influence of Alloy Atomic Doping on the <lb/>Properties of Cu-Sn Alloys Based on First Principles <lb/>Zongfan Wei 1 , Jiaying Chen 1 , Jingteng Xue 1 , Nan Qu 1 , Yong Liu 1, *, Ling Sun 2,3 , Yuchen Xiao 2,3 , Baoan Wu 2,3 , <lb/>Jingchuan Zhu 1, * and Huiyi Tang 2,3, * <lb/>1 <lb/>School of Materials Science and Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin 150001, China <lb/>2 <lb/>Chongqing Materials Research Institute Co., Ltd., Chongqing 400707, China <lb/>3 <lb/>National Engineering Research Center for Instrument Functional Materials, Chongqing 400707, China <lb/>* Correspondence: lyonghit@hit.edu.cn (Y.L.); fgms@hit.edu.cn (J.Z.); hytang320@163.com (H.T.) <lb/>Abstract: In order to design Cu-Sn alloys with excellent overall performance, the structural stability, <lb/>mechanical properties, and electronic structure of X-doped Cu-Sn alloys were systematically cal-<lb/>culated using first-principles calculations. The calculation results of the cohesive energy indicate <lb/>that the Cu-Sn-X structures formed by X atoms (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) doping into Cu-Sn can <lb/>stably exist. The Cu-Sn-Ni structure is the most stable, with a cohesive energy value of -3.84 eV. <lb/>Doping of X atoms leads to a decrease in the bulk modulus, Possion&apos;s ratio and B/G ratio. However, <lb/>doping Ag and Ni atoms can improve the shear modulus, Young&apos;s modulus, and strain energy of the <lb/>dislocation. The doping of Ni has the highest enhancement on shear modulus, Young&apos;s modulus, <lb/>and strain energy of the dislocation, with respective values as follows: 63.085 GPa, 163.593 GPa, and <lb/>1.689 W/J•m -1 . The analysis of electronic structure results shows that the covalent bond between Cu <lb/>and X is the reason for the performance differences in Cu-Sn-X structures. <lb/>Keywords: Cu-Sn alloy; first-principles calculations; cohesive energy; mechanical properties; <lb/>electronic structure <lb/></front>

    <body>1. Introduction <lb/>Copper alloys find extensive application in various industries including electrical, <lb/>construction, and aerospace, owing to their exceptional conductivity, thermal conductivity, <lb/>and resistance to corrosion [1-4]. However, the relatively low mechanical strength of <lb/>pure copper limits its application in high-performance scenarios. Hence, enhancing the <lb/>mechanical properties of copper alloys through alloying techniques has emerged as a <lb/>central focus in the field of material science research. The study conducted by Ma et al. [5] <lb/>reveals that doping Sc in the Cu-Cr-Zr alloy, combined with a treatment of solid solution, <lb/>rolling, and aging, results in the formation of nanoscale precipitates and subgrains within <lb/>the matrix. As a result, the mechanical properties of the Cu-Cr-Zr alloy are significantly <lb/>improved, while the electrical conductivity experiences negligible reduction. Liu et al. [6] <lb/>discovered that the incorporation of Cr, Zr, Ti, and Mg into the Cu-Ni-Si alloy leads to <lb/>grain refinement and the formation of a twinning structure. Li et al. [7] showed that the <lb/>addition of Mg in the Cu-Cr-Zr alloy, through a two-step deep cold rolling and aging <lb/>process, effectively improves both the electrical and mechanical properties of the alloy. <lb/>Huang et al. [8] discovered that the incorporation of Fe into the Cu-Ti alloy results in <lb/>increased dislocation density, tensile strength, and quantity of deformation bands after <lb/>cold rolling. Furthermore, the addition of Fe enhances the stress relaxation resistance of <lb/>the Cu-Ti alloy. Lei et al. [9] designed a Cu-9Ni-1.5Sn-0.8Si-0.1Al alloy and employed <lb/>multiple-stage deformation and heat treatment processes. As a result, the precipitation of <lb/>Ni 3 X (where X represents Sn, Si, and Al) notably enhances the tensile strength of the alloy. <lb/>In recent years, the effective utilization of first-principles calculations has guided <lb/>the design of alloy compositions and facilitated the prediction of their performance. <lb/></body>

    <front>Metals 2024, 14, 552. https://doi.org/10.3390/met14050552 <lb/>https://www.mdpi.com/journal/metals <lb/></front>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>Yang et al. [10] investigated the effect of different Al contents on the elastic properties <lb/>of Cu-Al alloy using first-principles calculations. At 0 K, with increasing the Al content, <lb/>the mechanical stability, shear modulus, bulk modulus, and Young&apos;s modulus of the alloy <lb/>all show a decreasing trend. The best wear resistance and erosion resistance of Cu-Al <lb/>alloy are achieved when the aluminum content is between 15.625 at.% and 18.750 at.% <lb/>(at.% refers to atomic percent). Yang et al. [11] examined the role of Ni in Cu-Al-Mn alloy <lb/>through a combination of first-principles calculations and experiments, showing that Ni <lb/>not only significantly improves the shape memory effect of the alloy but also suppresses the <lb/>temperature-dependent martensitic stabilization. He et al. [12] investigated the corrosion <lb/>interface and characteristics of the Cu-C alloy in liquid Ga at temperatures ranging from <lb/>100 °C to 180 °C. The application of first-principles calculations unveiled that the diffusion <lb/>of Ga atoms induces the phase transformation of Cu and initiates the formation of the corro-<lb/>sion product CuGa 2 . Dong et al. [13] investigated the intergranular precipitation behavior <lb/>of the G phase (Ni 16 Ti 6 Si 7 ) in a high-performance casting Cu-Ni-Al alloy. Moreover, the <lb/>application of first-principles calculations demonstrated that substituting Zr for Ti in the G <lb/>phase is favorable for its formation and reduces the lattice mismatch at the G phase/matrix <lb/>interface. Hideaki Iwaoka et al. [14] performed first-principles calculations to determine <lb/>the elastic properties of Cu-Zn binary metal compounds. Their findings revealed that <lb/>the Young&apos;s modulus of polycrystalline CuZn 4 aggregates is nearly equivalent to that of <lb/>Cu 5 Zn 8 aggregates, indicating low elasticity. <lb/>Cu-Sn (bronze) alloys are significant engineering structural materials with valuable <lb/>applications in various fields such as aerospace, marine, and electrical appliances [15,16]. <lb/>In the electronics industry, it is commonly used for manufacturing electronic components, <lb/>such as electronic devices and circuit boards. These alloys exhibit exceptional character-<lb/>istics, such as wear resistance, corrosion resistance, thermal conductivity, and electrical <lb/>conductivity, while also maintaining adequate strength and ductility. According to the <lb/>Cu-Sn phase diagram [17], the solid solution limit of Sn in the Cu matrix is 15.8 wt.% (the <lb/>term &quot;wt.%&quot; denotes the weight percent). Within this solid solubility limit, increasing the <lb/>Sn content can enhance the strength but may lead to a compromise in electrical conductivity <lb/>and ductility. Conversely, reducing the Sn content can maintain high electrical conductivity <lb/>and good ductility, albeit with a potential reduction in strength. The Sn content ranging <lb/>from 5 to 11 wt.% finds its primary application in various fields such as bearings, shaft <lb/>sleeves, and turbines [18]. In previous studies on Cu-Sn alloys, Cu 30 Sn 2 (Sn content of <lb/>11.08 wt.%) has demonstrated the highest Young&apos;s modulus and elastic anisotropy [19]. <lb/>Therefore, based on the structure of Cu 30 Sn 2 , this study aims to explore the effects of <lb/>replacing Sn atoms in copper alloys with atoms X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) that exhibit <lb/>higher electrical conductivity. The focus is to investigate the alterations in the properties of <lb/>the Cu-Sn-X structure and elucidate the underlying factors contributing to these changes. <lb/>The influence of six alloying atoms on the structural stability, mechanical properties, and <lb/>electronic structure of Cu-Sn alloys is explored through first-principles calculations. This <lb/>approach offers an efficient means of selecting alloying elements, thus reducing the time <lb/>and cost related to trial-and-error experimentation. Additionally, it provides a theoretical <lb/>foundation for the development of high-strength and highly conductive Cu-Sn alloys. <lb/>2. Calculation Method and Material Structure <lb/>In Cu-Sn alloys, Sn exists in the form of a solid solution. Thus, a supercell model <lb/>with Cu as the solvent and Sn as the solute is constructed. The supercell model adopts a <lb/>face-centered cubic crystal structure with a 2 × 2 × 2 size, containing a total of 32 metal <lb/>atoms. As shown in Figure 1a, Sn replaces one vertex copper atom and one face-centered <lb/>copper atom, resulting in a supercell configuration with 30 Cu atoms and 2 Sn atoms. <lb/>Figure 1b depicts the inclusion of X atoms (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) of the Cu-Sn model. <lb/>Consequently, the models consist of 30 Cu atoms, 1 Sn atom, and 1 X atom (hereafter <lb/>denoted as Cu-Sn for Cu 30 Sn 2 and Cu-Sn-X for Cu 30 Sn 1 X 1 ). <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figure 1. The structure of the Cn-Sn solid solution and the solid solution structure of Cu-Sn-X: <lb/>(a) Cu-Sn solid solution structure, (b) Cu-Sn-X solid solution structure. <lb/>First-principles calculations were performed using the Cambridge Sequential Total <lb/>Energy Package (CASTEP) software version 8.0 [20]. Periodic boundary conditions were <lb/>employed, and the structural optimization was carried out using the Broyden-Fletcher-<lb/>Goldfarb-Shanno (BFGS) method prior to each calculation. The calculation of exchange <lb/>correlation functional is based on the high-precision Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof (PBE) func-<lb/>tional form selected from the Generalized Gradient Approximation (GGA) [21,22]. Ultrasoft <lb/>pseudopotentials in reciprocal space representation were applied, with a cutoff energy set <lb/>to 360 eV. A 4 × 4 × 4 Monkhorst-Pack k-point grid was used. The total energy calculation <lb/>employed the self-consistent field (SCF) method and was accelerated by the Pulay density <lb/>mixing scheme for convergence [23]. The convergence criteria were set as follows: the <lb/>total energy was lower than 5.0 × 10 -6 eV/atom, the forces on each atom were less than <lb/>0.01 eV/atom, the displacement tolerance was lower than 5.0 × 10 -5 nm, and the stress <lb/>deviation was below 0.02 GPa. <lb/>3. Results and Discussion <lb/>3.1. Crystal Structure and Stability <lb/>The lattice constant is a fundamental parameter that reflects the crystal structure <lb/>and internal composition, serving as the basis for studying material structure. Table 1 <lb/>presents the optimized lattice constants and cohesive energy of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X. To <lb/>validate the accuracy of the computational results, the lattice constant of the pure copper <lb/>model was compared with experimental data from other sources, revealing a difference of <lb/>0.414%. Generally, the disparity in lattice constants falls within 1%, indicating a well-chosen <lb/>pseudopotential, as evidenced by the model, conditions, and parameters. The deviation <lb/>between calculated and experimental values primarily arises due to the temperature-<lb/>dependent nature of lattice parameters and the GGA process. Cohesive energy (E coh ) is <lb/>defined as the energy needed to separate the crystal cell structure into individual atoms or <lb/>the energy released when individual atoms combine to form a crystal cell [24]. In essence, <lb/>a higher value of cohesive energy indicates the greater structural stability of the material. <lb/>The calculation Equation (1) for the cohesive energy of Cu-Sn-X (where X = Ag, Ca, Cd, <lb/>Mg, Ni, Zr) is shown below [25]: <lb/>E coh Cu x Sn y X z = <lb/>E tot Cu x Sn y X z -xE atom (Cu) -yE atom (Sn) -zE atom (X) <lb/>x + y + z <lb/>(1) <lb/>In the formula, E tot denotes the total ground-state energy of the unit cell, which can be <lb/>obtained by calculating the lattice constant of the model. E atom (Cu), E atom (Sn), E atom (X) <lb/>denote the energies of the isolated Cu, Sn and X atoms, respectively; and x, y, and z are <lb/>the number of Cu, Sn, and X atoms in the supercell, respectively. Figure 2 illustrates the <lb/>cohesive energy of the Cu-Sn-X alloy. When X atoms are dissolved in the Cu-Sn alloy, they <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>can stably exist. Among them, the absolute value of the cohesive energy of Ni dissolved in <lb/>the Cu-Sn alloy is the largest, and the resulting Cu-Sn-Ni structure is the most stable. The <lb/>stability ranking for the cohesive of Cu-Sn-X structures is as follows: Cu-Sn-Ni &gt; Cu-Sn-Zr <lb/>&gt; Cu-Sn-Ag &gt; Cu-Sn-Mg &gt; Cu-Sn-Ca &gt; Cu-Sn-Cd. <lb/>Figure 2. The cohesive energy of the Cu-Sn-X alloy. <lb/>Table 1. Opimized lattice parameters and cohesive energy for Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X alloys. <lb/>Structure <lb/>Source <lb/>a (Å) <lb/>α (deg) <lb/>E coh (kJ/mol) <lb/>Cu <lb/>Exp at 25 °C [23] <lb/>3.615 <lb/>90 <lb/>-<lb/>Present <lb/>3.630 <lb/>90 <lb/>-<lb/>Error <lb/>0.414% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Cu-Sn <lb/>Present <lb/>7.229 <lb/>90 <lb/>-<lb/>Cu-Sn-Ag <lb/>Present <lb/>7.368 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.686 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ca <lb/>Present <lb/>7.453 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.639 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Cd <lb/>Present <lb/>7.389 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.617 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Mg <lb/>Present <lb/>7.360 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.657 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ni <lb/>Present <lb/>7.318 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.840 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Zr <lb/>Present <lb/>7.433 <lb/>90 <lb/>-3.830 <lb/>3.2. Mechanical Properties <lb/>It is crucial to have a comprehensive understanding of the elastic constants of mate-<lb/>rials, because they encompass many key characteristics, such as solid stability, bonding <lb/>properties, hardness, and processability. Elastic constants are quantities that establish a <lb/>relationship between strain and stress, aiding in understanding the behavior of elastic mate-<lb/>rials. The analysis of mechanical properties in crystals is commonly performed using elastic <lb/>constants. Within the Cauchy stress-strain method, the calculation of all independent <lb/>elastic constants involves solving Hooke&apos;s law, as depicted in Equation (2) [26]: <lb/>σ i = <lb/>σ <lb/>∑ <lb/>j=1 <lb/>C ij ε j , <lb/>(2) <lb/>where σ i is the strain component for the ith component; ∑ σ <lb/>j=1 is the summation over j from <lb/>1 to σ, where σ is the total number of components; C ij is the elasticity tensor between the <lb/>ith and jth components; and ε j is the strain component for the jth component. <lb/>For the cubic crystal system, there are three independent elastic constants, namely <lb/>C 11 , C 12 , and C 44 . The C 11 coefficient signifies the resistance to unidirectional compression <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>(compression along the principal directions &lt;100&gt;), while C 44 characterizes the resistance to <lb/>shear deformation across the (100) plane in the [110] direction. However, when the model <lb/>derived from the disordered modeling of supercells undergoes geometric optimization, <lb/>the number of independent elastic constants increases. This is due to the quasi-random <lb/>distribution of solute atoms, which slightly breaks the crystal structure symmetry. The <lb/>technique of symmetry-based projection (SBP) is employed to correct elastic tensors by <lb/>projecting distorted elastic tensors onto their corresponding symmetric forms, aligning <lb/>with the crystal symmetry of the material. This approach effectively eliminates symmetry-<lb/>breaking components and facilitates the derivation of more precise and physically consistent <lb/>elastic tensors. Therefore, in this study, we utilized the Symmetry-based Projection (SBP) <lb/>technique to correct the elastic tensors of Cu-Sn-X [27,28]. To obtain the elastic constants of <lb/>these quasi-random systems, we usually calculate the average values of the corresponding <lb/>elastic parameters. This relationship is described by Equation (3) : <lb/>C 11 = <lb/>(C 11 + C 22 + C 33 ) <lb/>3 <lb/>C 12 = <lb/>(C 12 + C 13 + C 23 ) <lb/>3 <lb/>C 44 = <lb/>(C 44 + C 55 + C 66 ) <lb/>3 <lb/>(3) <lb/>Average values of the relevant elastic parameters calculated for Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X <lb/>(X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) are shown in Table 2. <lb/>Table 2. Calculated values of elastic constants for Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr). <lb/>Structure <lb/>C 11 <lb/>C 22 <lb/>C 33 <lb/>C 11 <lb/>C 12 <lb/>C 13 <lb/>C 23 <lb/>C 12 <lb/>C 44 <lb/>C 55 <lb/>C 66 <lb/>C 44 <lb/>Cu-Sn <lb/>208.336 207.863 208.137 208.137 178.681 178.849 178.605 178.711 88.438 <lb/>88.432 <lb/>88.445 <lb/>88.438 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ag 187.246 187.085 187.057 187.130 104.073 104.070 104.267 104.137 77.932 <lb/>78.289 <lb/>78.278 <lb/>78.166 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ca 142.597 142.598 143.467 142.887 111.261 108.654 108.668 109.528 67.180 <lb/>67.143 <lb/>65.625 <lb/>66.650 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Cd 143.442 143.451 130.855 139.250 122.416 118.995 119.046 120.152 77.720 <lb/>77.740 <lb/>77.246 <lb/>77.569 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Mg 136.668 136.538 136.388 136.531 111.485 117.329 117.264 115.359 77.041 <lb/>77.041 <lb/>80.190 <lb/>78.091 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ni <lb/>184.447 184.461 185.989 184.966 110.125 107.830 107.844 108.560 87.363 <lb/>87.363 <lb/>90.339 <lb/>88.355 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Zr <lb/>160.133 160.0815 158.517 159.577 114.948 115.125 115.135 115.069 72.350 <lb/>72.351 <lb/>70.343 <lb/>71.681 <lb/>The stability criteria for different crystal structures are not the same. The elastic <lb/>constants C 11 , C 12 , and C 13 , as utilized in the subsequent text, all pertain to the average <lb/>values that have been corrected using SBP technology. For the cubic crystal system, the <lb/>criterion formula based on the Born stability rule is given by Equation (4): <lb/>C 11 -|C 12 | &gt; 0 <lb/>C 11 + 2C 12 &gt; 0 <lb/>C 11 &gt; 0 <lb/>C 44 &gt; 0 <lb/>(4) <lb/>Based on the calculated results of the elastic constants in Table 2, it can be observed <lb/>that when X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atoms are doped into the Cu-Sn alloy, the crystal <lb/>structure still maintains mechanical stability. As shown in Equation (5) [24], the obtained <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>three independent elastic constants can be further used to calculate the bulk modulus and <lb/>shear modulus through the Voigt-Reuss (V-R) method. <lb/>B V = B R = <lb/>(C 11 + 2C 12 ) <lb/>3 <lb/>G V = <lb/>(C 11 -C 12 + 3C 44 ) <lb/>5 <lb/>G R = <lb/>5(C 11 -C 12 )C 44 <lb/>4C 44 + 3(C 11 -C 12 ) <lb/>(5) <lb/>Using the Hill approximation, the bulk modulus (B) and shear modulus (G) can be <lb/>further calculated [24]. The calculation Equation (6) is as follows: <lb/>B = <lb/>B V + B R <lb/>2 <lb/>G = <lb/>G V + G R <lb/>2 <lb/>(6) <lb/>Utilize the bulk modulus and shear modulus for recycling purposes. As shown in <lb/>Equation (7) [29], solve for the Young&apos;s modulus (E) and Poisson&apos;s ratio (v) as follows: <lb/>E = <lb/>9BG <lb/>3B + G <lb/>v = <lb/>3B -2G <lb/>6B + 2G <lb/>(7) <lb/>The elastic modulus is a crucial indicator for characterizing the mechanical properties <lb/>of materials, which encompasses the bulk modulus, shear modulus, and Young&apos;s modulus. <lb/>Specifically, the bulk modulus is commonly employed to gauge a material&apos;s capacity to <lb/>withstand compressive deformation under stress. Generally, a larger value of bulk modulus <lb/>indicates a stronger resistance to compressive deformation, making the material more <lb/>difficult to compress. As shown in Figure 3a, when no atoms are doped, the bulk modulus <lb/>of the Cu-Sn alloy is 188.518 GPa. Compared to the Cu-Sn alloy, the structures formed after <lb/>doping X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atoms all lead to a decrease in the bulk modulus. <lb/>Among them, the largest decrease is observed when Ca atoms are doped, with a value of <lb/>120.637 GPa. <lb/>The shear modulus reflects a material&apos;s resistance to shear strain under shear stress. <lb/>A larger shear modulus indicates a stronger resistance to shear strain, indicating greater <lb/>rigidity of the material. As shown in Figure 3b, when Ag, Ni, and Zr atoms are doped into <lb/>the Cu-Sn alloy, the shear modulus increases. On the other hand, doping of Ca, Cd, and <lb/>Mg into the Cu-Sn alloy results in varying degrees of decrease in the shear modulus. The <lb/>shear modulus increases slightly when Zr atoms are doped, while the doping of Ag and Ni <lb/>atoms leads to a significant increase. <lb/>Within the elastic limit, the ratio of stress to strain is known as the Young&apos;s modulus, <lb/>which reflects the material&apos;s stiffness. As shown in Figure 3c, when no alloy atoms are <lb/>doped, the value of Young&apos;s modulus for the Cu-Sn alloy is 122.976 GPa. The doping of Ag <lb/>and Ni atoms causes an increase in the Young&apos;s modulus, while the doping of Ca, Cd, Mg, <lb/>and Zr atoms causes a decrease in the Young&apos;s modulus. After Ni doping, the maximum <lb/>value of Young&apos;s modulus is 163.593 GPa, while the minimum value of Young&apos;s modulus <lb/>during Cd doping is 96.16 GPa. <lb/>When a material is subjected to tensile or compressive forces, the absolute value of the <lb/>ratio between transverse and axial positive strains is known as the Poisson&apos;s ratio, which <lb/>typically ranges from -1 to 0.5. A larger Poisson&apos;s ratio indicates better plasticity of the <lb/>material, with values above 0.26 indicating plastic behavior. As illustrated in Figure 3d, <lb/>the Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X structures both maintain plasticity. However, doping of X (X = Ag, <lb/>Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atoms results in a decrease in the Poisson&apos;s ratio. Among them, the <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>doping of Ca, Cd, Mg, and Zr atoms causes a relatively small decrease, while the doping of <lb/>Ag and Ni atoms leads to a significant decrease in the Poisson&apos;s ratio. The ratio of the bulk <lb/>modulus to shear modulus B/G can be used to evaluate the plasticity and brittleness of a <lb/>material. The criterion value is 1.75, where a B/G ratio greater than 1.75 indicates ductility, <lb/>with larger values indicating better plasticity, while values below the criterion point to <lb/>brittleness. As shown in Figure 3e, the trends of the Poisson&apos;s ratio and B/G ratio in the <lb/>structures formed by X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atom doping are consistent. <lb/>Figure 3. Cu-Sn alloy and Cu-Sn-X alloy mechanical properties: (a) Bulk modulus, (b) Shear modulus, <lb/>(c) Young&apos;s modulus, (d) Poisson&apos;s ratio, (e) B/G ratio, (f) Dislocation strain energy. <lb/>Lattice distortion arises when X is solidly dissolved into the Cu-Sn structure, leading <lb/>to an elastic stress field that raises the crystal energy. This crystal energy is defined as the <lb/>strain energy of the dislocation [26], <lb/>W ≈ Gb 2 <lb/>(8) <lb/>where G is the shear modulus, and b is the Burgers vectors. For FCC crystals, b 2 = 0.5a 2 . <lb/>The larger the dislocation strain energy, the lower the plastic deformation ability and the <lb/>higher the tensile strength. The dislocation strain energy of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X is shown in <lb/>Figure 3f. Doping of Ag, Ni, and Zr atoms leads to an increase in dislocation energy, while <lb/>doping of Ca, Cd, and Mg atoms results in a decrease in dislocation energy. The variation <lb/>trend of dislocation energy is consistent with the variation trend of shear modulus, which <lb/>can be explained by motion theory. <lb/>In general, polycrystalline materials do not exhibit isotropic elastic properties, which <lb/>means they display direction-dependent anisotropic properties. The mechanical response <lb/>of materials to external stresses is typically controlled by the elastic anisotropy factor. <lb/>Therefore, the study and description of this factor are crucial for material manufacturing. <lb/>The Universal anisotropy factor of Cu-Sn and the Cu-Sn alloy can be examined through the <lb/>subsequent Equation [28]. <lb/>A U = 5 <lb/>G V <lb/>G R <lb/>+ <lb/>B V <lb/>B R <lb/>-6 <lb/>(9) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>The parameter A U takes into account the contributions of both the shear modulus <lb/>and bulk modulus. The deviation of A U from 0 indicates the degree of crystal anisotropy. <lb/>The computational results are shown in Table 3. The doping of Cd and Ag atoms into the <lb/>Cu-Sn alloy leads to an increase in A U , while the doping of Ag, Ca, Ni, and Zr results in a <lb/>decrease in A U . <lb/>Table 3. Cu-Sn alloy and Cu-Sn-X alloy mechanical properties. <lb/>Structure <lb/>B (GPa) <lb/>G (GPa) <lb/>E (GPa) <lb/>B/G <lb/>v <lb/>W/J•m -1 <lb/>A U <lb/>Cu-Sn <lb/>188.518 <lb/>44.192 <lb/>122.967 <lb/>4.266 <lb/>0.391 <lb/>1.155 <lb/>5.013 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ag <lb/>131.800 <lb/>60.624 <lb/>157.694 <lb/>2.174 <lb/>0.301 <lb/>1.645 <lb/>0.498 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ca <lb/>120.637 <lb/>38.438 <lb/>104.243 <lb/>3.138 <lb/>0.356 <lb/>1.068 <lb/>2.722 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Cd <lb/>125.964 <lb/>35.024 <lb/>96.160 <lb/>3.597 <lb/>0.372 <lb/>0.956 <lb/>7.799 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Mg <lb/>122.344 <lb/>36.208 <lb/>98.870 <lb/>3.379 <lb/>0.365 <lb/>0.981 <lb/>6.978 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Ni <lb/>134.054 <lb/>63.085 <lb/>163.593 <lb/>2.125 <lb/>0.297 <lb/>1.689 <lb/>0.899 <lb/>Cu-Sn-Zr <lb/>129.903 <lb/>44.928 <lb/>120.852 <lb/>2.891 <lb/>0.345 <lb/>1.241 <lb/>1.840 <lb/>In order to see the variation in the Young&apos;s modulus, we have examined the 3D <lb/>plots of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X through the Elastic POST [30]. The Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X alloys <lb/>investigated in this study belong to the cubic crystal system, and the directional dependence <lb/>of their Young&apos;s modulus can be obtained from the calculated compliance constants, which <lb/>can be expressed as [27] <lb/>1 <lb/>E <lb/>= S 11 -(2S 11 -2S 12 -S 44 ) l 2 <lb/>1 l 2 <lb/>2 + l 2 <lb/>2 l 2 <lb/>3 + l 2 <lb/>3 l 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>(10) <lb/>E represents the Young&apos;s modulus, S ij denotes the elastic flexibility coefficient, and l 1 , l 2 , <lb/>and l 3 are the directional cosines. <lb/>Figure 4 illustrates the three-dimensional projection map of the Young&apos;s modulus <lb/>anisotropy. The square represents the isotropy of the material, while any deviation from a <lb/>perfect square represents the anisotropy of the material. The outer surface of the square <lb/>has a higher Young&apos;s modulus, while the interior has a lower Young&apos;s modulus. <lb/>3.3. Electronic Structure Properties <lb/>The stability and mechanical properties of materials depend on their electronic struc-<lb/>tures. In order to further analyze the electronic structure of Cu-Sn-X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, <lb/>Ni, Zr) alloys from a microscopic perspective, the electronic density of states, occupation <lb/>numbers, and differential charge densities were calculated for Cu-Sn alloys and Cu-Sn-X <lb/>alloys. To analyze the bonding properties of Cu-Sn alloys and Cu-Sn-X alloys, the electronic <lb/>density of states was examined. Figure 5 shows the total and partial electronic density of <lb/>states for Cu-Sn alloys and Cu-Sn-X alloys, with the Fermi level represented by dashed lines. <lb/>It can be observed that both Cu-Sn alloys and Cu-Sn-X alloys exhibit significant electron <lb/>densities around the Fermi level, indicating typical metallic characteristics. Known to all, <lb/>the pseudogap is defined as the valley of the Fermi level (E f ), where there are two peaks <lb/>in the density of states (DOS) on each side of a nonzero Fermi level. The presence of the <lb/>pseudogap indicates the existence of covalent bonds. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figure 4. Three-dimensional surfaces of the Young&apos;s modulus for Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X alloys: (a) Cu-<lb/>Sn, (b) Cu-Sn-Ag, (c) Cu-Sn-Ca, (d) Cu-Sn-Cd, (e) Cu-Sn-Mg, (f) Cu-Sn-Ni, (g) Cu-Sn-Zr. <lb/>As shown in Figure 5a, the total density of states in Cu-Sn alloys is primarily con-<lb/>tributed by the d orbitals of Cu, with a sharp peak in the energy range of -10.17 eV to <lb/>-9.14 eV mainly originating from the s orbitals of Sn. Figure 5b demonstrates that when <lb/>Ag is doped into the Cu-Sn alloy to form Cu-Sn-Ag alloy, there is a sharp peak in the energy <lb/>range of -7.12 eV to -4.18 eV, mainly contributed by the d orbitals of Ag. In Figure 5c, the <lb/>overall density of states for the Cu-Sn-Ca alloy after Ca doping reveals two sharp peaks in <lb/>the energy ranges of -42.07 eV to 39.56 eV and -21.88 eV to 20.68 eV, corresponding to the <lb/>contributions from the s and p orbitals of Ca, respectively. After Cd doping, as illustrated <lb/>in Figure 5d, a sharp peak arises in the energy range of -9.93 eV to -8.63 eV due to the d <lb/>orbital contributions of Cd. Figure 5e shows that after Mg doping, a sharp peak is observed <lb/>in the energy range of -42.77 eV to -41.36 eV, contributed by the p orbitals of Mg. In the <lb/>case of Ni doping, no sharp peak is observed in the total density of states. After Zr doping, <lb/>sharp peaks emerge in the energy ranges of -50.95 eV to -48.54 eV and -27.62 eV to <lb/>-26.53 eV, corresponding to the contributions from the s and p orbitals of Zr, respectively. <lb/>In order to further characterize the strength of chemical bonds, bond lengths and <lb/>Mulliken&apos;s bond populations were calculated. Mulliken&apos;s bond populations also confirm <lb/>the presence of covalent bonds in Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X alloys. Positive bond populations <lb/>indicate bonding states between two atoms, while negative bond populations represent <lb/>anti-bonding states. In general, larger positive bond populations correspond to stronger <lb/>bonding strength. Figure 6 illustrates that the Cu-Cu bond has a shorter bond length and <lb/>a larger population value, indicating stronger bonding strength. When X (X = Ag, Ca, <lb/>Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atoms are doped into the Cu-Sn alloy, X atoms are more likely to form <lb/>bonds with Cu. As depicted in Figure 6c,f,g, when only Ca, Ni, and Zr atoms are doped, <lb/>they can bond with Sn to form Ca-Sn, Ni-Sn, and Zr-Sn bonds, but these three bonds have <lb/>smaller population value. The analogous relationship between the covalent bond strength <lb/>and phase stability of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X alloys can be obtained through bond groups. <lb/>Therefore, when Ca, Cd, and Mg atoms are doped into Cu-Sn alloys, it is found that the <lb/>Mulliken&apos;s bond populations are relatively small, resulting in weaker covalent bonds. This <lb/>is consistent with the calculated cohesive energy results. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>Figure 5. Total and partial electronic densities of states of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X: (a) Cu-Sn, (b) Cu-Sn-<lb/>Ag, (c) Cu-Sn-Ca, (d) Cu-Sn-Cd, (e) Cu-Sn-Mg, (f) Cu-Sn-Ni, (g) Cu-Sn-Zr. <lb/>Figure 6. Cu-Sn alloy and Cu-Sn-X alloy bond length and occupation numbers. (a) Cu-Sn, <lb/>(b) Cu-Sn-Ag, (c) Cu-Sn-Ca, (d) Cu-Sn-Cd, (e) Cu-Sn-Mg, (f) Cu-Sn-Ni, (g) Cu-Sn-Zr. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <body>To gain further insight into electron transfer, the distribution of differential electron <lb/>density on the (111) surface of Cu-Sn alloy and Cu-Sn-X alloys was investigated. As <lb/>depicted in Figure 7, gained electrons are represented by blue regions, while lost electrons <lb/>are indicated by red regions. The variation in charge density around the Cu atom signifies <lb/>metallic bonding in pure Cu, while the petal-shaped charge density around the Sn atom <lb/>indicates the formation of a covalent bond with Cu. Figure 7a suggests that Cu atoms tend <lb/>to lose electrons, while Sn atoms tend to gain electrons. However, with the introduction of <lb/>X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atoms into the Cu-Sn alloy, X atoms are capable of gaining <lb/>electrons, indicating a substantial electron participation in chemical bonding between X <lb/>and Cu atoms, resulting in the formation of stable bonding strength. <lb/>Figure 7. Electron density difference distribution cloud maps of Cu-Sn alloy and Cu-Sn-X alloy on <lb/>the (111) surface. (a) Cu-Sn, (b) Cu-Sn-Ag, (c) Cu-Sn-Ca, (d) Cu-Sn-Cd, (e) Cu-Sn-Mg, (f) Cu-Sn-Ni, <lb/>(g) Cu-Sn-Zr. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>In this study, first-principles method was used to investigate the Cu-Sn-X (X = Ag, <lb/>Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) alloys formed by the addition of X atoms to Cu-Sn. The geometrical <lb/>structures of Cu-Sn and Cu-Sn-X were optimized, and various properties including ther-<lb/>modynamic stability, mechanical properties, and electronic structures were calculated. The <lb/>following conclusions were obtained: <lb/>(1) The calculation results of the cohesive energy for Cu-Sn-X structures after X (X = Ag, <lb/>Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) atom doping indicate that these Cu-Sn-X structures can stably exist, <lb/>with the most stable structure being Cu-Sn-Ni. The cohesive energy value of Cu-Sn-Ni <lb/>structure is -3.84 eV. <lb/>(2) The calculation results of mechanical properties show that doping of X atoms <lb/>(X = Ag, Ca, Cd, Mg, Ni, Zr) leads to a decrease in the bulk modulus, Possion&apos;s ratio, and <lb/>B/G ratio. However, doping Ag and Ni atom can improve shear modulus, Young&apos;s modu-<lb/>lus, and strain energy of the dislocation. The doping of Ni has the highest enhancement on <lb/>the shear modulus, Young&apos;s modulus, and strain energy of the dislocation, with respective <lb/>values as follows: 63.085 GPa, 163.593 GPa, and 1.689 W/J•m -1 . <lb/>(3) An analysis of the electronic structure of Cu-Sn-X alloys with X (X = Ag, Ca, Cd, <lb/>Mg, Ni, Zr) doping reveals that the performance differences in Cu-Sn-X alloys originate <lb/>from the Mulliken&apos;s bond populations of Cu-X. The doping of Ni and Ag atoms holds <lb/>promise for achieving Cu-Sn alloys with superior overall performance. <lb/></body>

    <div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Conceptualization, Z.W. and J.C.; data curation, Z.W., J.C. and N.Q.; for-<lb/>mal analysis, Y.X.; funding acquisition, Y.L., J.Z. and H.T.; investigation, Y.L.; methodology, N.Q.; <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <div type="contribution">resources, Y.X. and B.W.; software, J.X.; supervision, Y.L.; validation, N.Q.; visualization, L.S., Y.X. <lb/>and B.W.; writing-original draft, Z.W.; writing-review &amp; editing Y.L., L.S., J.Z. and H.T. All authors <lb/>have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding: This research received no external funding. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">Data Availability Statement: The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made <lb/>available by the authors on request. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: Author Ling Sun, Yuchen Xiao, Baoan Wu, Huiyi Tang were employed by the <lb/>company China Steel Corporation. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted <lb/>in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential <lb/>conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Kuang, G.; Miao, K.; Li, X.; Wu, H.; Liu, C.; Li, R.; Fan, G. In-situ observation of microstructure and orientation evolution of the <lb/>Cu-Cr-Zr-Hf alloys. Mater. Sci. Eng. A 2023, 865, 144642. [CrossRef] <lb/>2. <lb/>Jiabin, L.; Menglian, H.; Huiya, Y.; Hongbin, X.; Chao, Y.; Jindong, Z.; Qiong, F.; Litian, W.; Liang, M.; Hongtao, W. In-situ TEM <lb/>study of the dynamic interactions between dislocations and precipitates in a Cu-Cr-Zr alloy. J. Alloys Compd. 2018, 765, 560-568. <lb/>3. <lb/>Wang, Y.D.; Wu, L.H.; Xue, P.; Zhang, H.; Ni, D.R.; Ma, Z.Y. Improved strength with good conductivity in Cu-Cr-Zr alloys: <lb/>Determinant effect of under-aging treatment before rolling and aging. Mater. Sci. Eng. A 2022, 848, 143395. [CrossRef] <lb/>4. <lb/>Lai, Z.; Mai, Y.; Song, H.; Mai, J.; Jie, X. Heterogeneous microstructure enables a synergy of strength, ductility and electrical <lb/>conductivity in copper alloys. J. Alloys Compd. 2022, 902, 163646. [CrossRef] <lb/>5. <lb/>Ma, B.; An, B.; Zhao, X.; Li, Y.; Du, J.; Wang, E. Microstructure and properties of Cu-Cr-Zr alloy by doping Sc. Mater. Lett. 2023, <lb/>336, 133917. [CrossRef] <lb/>6. <lb/>Liu, Y.; Zhou, Y.; Lu, C.; Gan, K.; Du, Y.; Liu, A.; Meng, F.; Liu, G.; Gong, Y.; Song, K.; et al. Nano-precipitates evolution and <lb/>properties improvement mechanism of Cu-Zn-Ni-Si-X alloy strip based on multi-element microalloying and thermomechanical <lb/>treatment. J. Mater. Res. Technol. 2023, 25, 107-119. [CrossRef] <lb/>7. <lb/>Li, L.; Kang, H.; Zhang, S.; Li, R.; Yang, X.; Chen, Z.; Guo, E.; Wang, T. Microstructure and properties of Cu-Cr-Zr (Mg) alloys <lb/>subjected to cryorolling and aging treatment. J. Alloys Compd. 2023, 938, 168656. [CrossRef] <lb/>8. <lb/>Huang, L.; Cui, Z.; Meng, X.; Li, X.; Sheng, X.; Lei, Q. Effect of trace alloying elements on the stress relaxation properties of high <lb/>strength Cu-Ti alloys. Mater. Sci. Eng. A 2022, 846, 143281. [CrossRef] <lb/>9. <lb/>Lei, Q.; Xiao, Z.; Hu, W.; Derby, B.; Li, Z. Phase transformation behaviors and properties of a high strength Cu-Ni-Si alloy. Mater. <lb/>Sci. Eng. A 2017, 697, 37-47. [CrossRef] <lb/>10. Yang, J.; Ouyang, P.; Liu, T.; Yun, H.; Sun, W.; Wang, Y.; Liu, J.; Zhang, S. First-principles study of the effect of aluminum content <lb/>on the elastic properties of Cu-Al alloys. Mater. Today Commun. 2022, 31, 103399. [CrossRef] <lb/>11. Yang, Q.; Yin, D.Q.; Ge, J.Q.; Chen, J.; Wang, S.L.; Peng, H.B.; Wen, Y.H. Suppressing heating rate-dependent martensitic <lb/>stabilization in ductile Cu-Al-Mn shape memory alloys by Ni addition: An experimental and first-principles study. Mater. Charact. <lb/>2018, 145, 381-388. [CrossRef] <lb/>12. He, D.; Liu, G.; Liu, J.; Xie, H.; Yue, D.; Chen, Z.; Wei, C.; Xu, X.; Xie, H. Study of effects of corrosion temperature on corrosion <lb/>resistance of Cu-C alloys to liquid Ga. Corros. Sci. 2023, 211, 110917. [CrossRef] <lb/>13. Dong, H.; Zhong, R.; Liu, L.; Wang, Z.; Yang, C.; Luo, Z.; Zhang, W. The intergranular precipitation behavior of G phase in a <lb/>high-performance complex cast Cu-Ni-Al alloy. Mater. Charact. 2023, 196, 112611. [CrossRef] <lb/>14. Iwaoka, H.; Hirosawa, S. First-principles calculation of elastic properties of Cu-Zn intermetallic compounds for improving the <lb/>stiffness of aluminum alloys. Comput. Mater. Sci. 2020, 174, 109479. [CrossRef] <lb/>15. Liu, Y.; Wang, L.; Jiang, K.; Yang, S. Electro-deposition preparation of self-standing Cu-Sn alloy anode electrode for lithium ion <lb/>battery. J. Alloys Compd. 2019, 775, 818-825. [CrossRef] <lb/>16. Singh, J.B.; Cai, W.; Bellon, P. Dry sliding of Cu-15 wt%Ni-8 wt%Sn bronze: Wear behaviour and microstructures. Wear 2007, <lb/>263, 830-841. [CrossRef] <lb/>17. Davis, J.R. ASM Specialty Handbook: Copper and Copper Alloys; ASM International: Detroit, MI, USA, 2001. <lb/>18. Yang, P.; He, D.; Shao, W.; Tan, Z.; Guo, X.; Lu, S.; Anton, K. Study of the microstructure and mechanical properties of Cu-Sn <lb/>alloys formed by selective laser melting with different Sn contents. J. Mater. Res. Technol. 2023, 24, 5476-5485. [CrossRef] <lb/>19. Zhang, L.; Li, Y.; Zhou, R.; Wang, X.; Wang, Q.; Xie, L.; Li, Z.; Xu, B. First-Principles Study of the Effect of Sn Content on the <lb/>Structural, Elastic, and Electronic Properties of Cu-Sn Alloys. Crystals 2023, 13, 1532. [CrossRef] <lb/>20. Segall, M.D.; Lindan, P.J.D.; Probert, M.J.; Pickard, C.J.; Hasnip, P.J.; Clark, S.J.; Payne, M.C. First-principles simulation: Ideas, <lb/>illustrations and the CASTEP code. J. Phys. Condens. Matter 2002, 14, 2717. [CrossRef] <lb/>21. Huang, J.; Xue, J.; Li, M.; Cheng, Y.; Lai, Z.; Hu, J.; Zhou, F.; Qu, N.; Liu, Y.; Zhu, J. First-Principles Computation of Microscopic <lb/>Mechanical Properties and Atomic Migration Behavior for Al4Si Aluminum Alloy. Metals 2023, 13, 1622. [CrossRef] <lb/>22. Djemia, P.; Benhamida, M.; Bouamama, K.; Belliard, L.; Faurie, D.; Abadias, G. Structural and elastic properties of ternary metal <lb/>nitrides TixTa1-xN alloys: First-principles calculations versus experiments. Surf. Coat. Technol. 2013, 215, 199-208. [CrossRef] <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Metals 2024, 14, 552 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 of 13 <lb/></page>

    <listBibl>23. Uesugi, T.; Higashi, K. First-principles studies on lattice constants and local lattice distortions in solid solution aluminum alloys. <lb/>Comput. Mater. Sci. 2013, 67, 1-10. [CrossRef] <lb/>24. Chong, X.; Jiang, Y.; Zhou, R.; Feng, J. Elastic properties and electronic structures of CrxBy as superhard compounds. J. Alloys <lb/>Compd. 2014, 610, 684-694. [CrossRef] <lb/>25. Zhang, X.; Wang, D.; Zhou, Y.; Chong, X.; Li, X.; Zhang, H.; Nagaumi, H. Exploring crystal structures, stability and mechanical <lb/>properties of Fe, Mn-containing intermetallics in Al-Si Alloy by experiments and first-principles calculations. J. Alloys Compd. <lb/>2021, 876, 160022. [CrossRef] <lb/>26. Ranganathan, S.I.; Ostoja-Starzewski, M. Universal Elastic Anisotropy Index. Phys. Rev. Lett. 2008, 101, 055504. [CrossRef] <lb/>[PubMed] <lb/>27. Browaeys, J.T.; Chevrot, S. Decomposition of the elastic tensor and geophysical applications. Geophys. J. Int. 2004, 159, 667-678. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>28. Moakher, M.; Norris, A.N. The Closest Elastic Tensor of Arbitrary Symmetry to an Elasticity Tensor of Lower Symmetry. J. Elast. <lb/>2006, 85, 215-263. [CrossRef] <lb/>29. Wang, G.; Jiang, Y.; Li, Z.; Chong, X.; Feng, J. Balance between strength and ductility of dilute Fe2B by high-throughput <lb/>first-principles calculations. Ceram. Int. 2021, 47, 4758-4768. [CrossRef] <lb/>30. Liao, M.; Liu, Y.; Min, L.; Lai, Z.; Han, T.; Yang, D.; Zhu, J. Alloying effect on phase stability, elastic and thermodynamic properties <lb/>of Nb-Ti-V-Zr high entropy alloy. Intermetallics 2018, 101, 152-164. [CrossRef] <lb/>Disclaimer/Publisher&apos;s Note: The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual <lb/>author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to <lb/>people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>