<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T11:12:30.980Z">11/20/2025 11:12:30 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T11:12:20.452063Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T11:12:20.452063Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>The role of green tea intake in <lb/>thromboprophylaxis of venous <lb/>thromboembolism in patients <lb/>with cancer <lb/>Qihuan Yao 1 , Hongwei Qiao 2 , Yi Cheng 3 , He Du 4 , <lb/>Yanbin Zhang 5 , Yong Luo 6 , Hongwei Wang 3 , Song Liu 3 , Mei Xu 7 <lb/>and Wei Xiong 3,8 * <lb/>1 Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Kongjiang Hospital, Shanghai, China, 2 Department of <lb/>Medical Oncology, Kongjiang Hospital, Shanghai, China, 3 Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care <lb/>Medicine, Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, China, <lb/>4 Department of Medical Oncology, Shanghai Pulmonary Hospital, Tongji, University School of <lb/>Medicine, Shanghai, China, 5 Department of TCM Dermatology, Kongjiang Hospital, Shanghai, China, <lb/>6 Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Chongming Hospital, Shanghai University of <lb/>Medicine and Health Science, Shanghai, China, 7 Department of General Practice, North Bund <lb/>Community Health Service Center, Shanghai, China, 8 Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, <lb/>Graduate School of Medicine, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan <lb/>Background: Green tea intake has been reported to improve the clinical <lb/>outcomes of patients with cardiovascular diseases or cancer. It may have a <lb/>certain role in the development of venous thromboembolism (VTE) among <lb/>cancer patients. The current study aimed to address this issue, which has been <lb/>understudied. <lb/>Methods: We carried out a retrospective study to explore the role of green <lb/>tea intake in cancer patients. Patients with and without green tea intake were <lb/>enrolled in a 1:1 ratio by using propensity scoring matching. The primary and <lb/>secondary outcomes were VTE development and mortality 1 year after cancer <lb/>diagnosis, respectively. <lb/>Results: The cancer patients with green tea intake (n = 425) had less VTE <lb/>development (10 [2.4%] vs. 23 [5.4%], p = 0.021), VTE-related death (7 [1.6%] vs. <lb/>18 [4.2%], p = 0.026), and fatal pulmonary embolism (PE) (3 [0.7%] vs. 12 [2.8%], <lb/>p = 0.019), compared with those without green tea intake (n = 425). No intake <lb/>of green tea was correlated with an increase in VTE development (multivariate <lb/>hazard ratio (HR) 1.758 [1.476-2.040], p &lt; 0.001) and VTE-related mortality (HR <lb/>1.618 [1.242-1.994], p = 0.001), compared with green tea intake. Patients with <lb/>green tea intake less than 525 mL per day had increased VTE development (area <lb/>under the curve (AUC) 0.888 [0.829-0.947], p &lt; 0.001; HR1.737 [1.286-2.188], <lb/>p = 0.001) and VTE-related mortality (AUC 0.887 [0.819-0.954], p &lt; 0.001; HR <lb/>1.561 [1.232-1.890], p = 0.016) than those with green tea intake more than <lb/>525 mL per day. Green tea intake caused a decrease in platelet (p &lt; 0.001) instead <lb/>of D-dimer (p = 0.297). The all-cause mortality rates were similar between <lb/>green tea (39 [9.2%]) and non-green tea (48 [11.3%]) intake groups (p = 0.308), <lb/>whereas the VTE-related mortality rate in the green tea intake group (7 [1.6%]) <lb/>was lower than that of the non-green tea intake group (18 [4.2%]) (p = 0.026). <lb/>The incidences of adverse events were similar between the green tea and non-<lb/>green tea intake groups. <lb/>Conclusion: In conclusion, the current study suggests that green tea intake <lb/>reduces VTE development and VTE-related mortality in cancer patients, most <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Hang Ma, <lb/>University of Rhode Island, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Huimin Xu, <lb/>Zhejiang University, China <lb/>Anca Daniela Farcas, <lb/>University of Medicine and Pharmacy Iuliu <lb/>Hatieganu, Romania <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Wei Xiong <lb/>xiongwei@xinhuamed.com.cn; <lb/>xiongw@kuhp.kyoto-u.ac.jp <lb/>RECEIVED 28 September 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 15 April 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 02 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Yao Q, Qiao H, Cheng Y, Du H, Zhang Y, <lb/>Luo Y, Wang H, Liu S, Xu M and <lb/>Xiong W (2024) The role of green tea intake in <lb/>thromboprophylaxis of venous <lb/>thromboembolism in patients with cancer. <lb/>Front. Nutr. 11:1296774. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Yao, Qiao, Cheng, Du, Zhang, Luo, <lb/>Wang, Liu, Xu and Xiong. This is an open-<lb/>access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>in other forums is permitted, provided the <lb/>original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) <lb/>are credited and that the original publication <lb/>in this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 02 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/>Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/>Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/>02 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>likely through antiplatelet mechanisms. Drinking green tea provides the efficacy <lb/>of thromboprophylaxis for cancer patients. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>green tea, venous thromboembolism, prophylaxis, cancer, antiplatelet <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>Venous thromboembolism (VTE) that comprises both <lb/>pulmonary embolism (PE) and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) affects <lb/>nearly 10 million people every year globally. The annual incidence <lb/>of acute VTE is 1-2 cases per 1,000 population. Approximately 20% <lb/>of patients with PE die within 1 year of diagnosis, mostly due to <lb/>comorbidities such as cancer rather than recurrent PE (1-4). VTE <lb/>in cancer patients (that is usually termed cancer-associated VTE) is <lb/>a common and life-threatening condition. The presence of cancer <lb/>increases the risk for VTE by approximately ninefold, especially in <lb/>cancer patients who undergo chemotherapy. VTE is the leading <lb/>cause of death in cancer patients, second only to cancer itself. The <lb/>occurrence of VTE increases the likelihood of death in cancer <lb/>patients by approximately two-to sixfold. Appropriate VTE <lb/>prophylaxis can bring about substantial benefits for cancer patients <lb/>who are at VTE risk (5, 6). <lb/>A recent research revealed an antithrombotic signature of <lb/>heat shock protein 47 (HSP47) as the most substantially reduced <lb/>protein in platelets of hibernating brown bears. The down-<lb/>regulation or ablation of HSP47 attenuates immune cell <lb/>activation and neutrophil extracellular trap formation, thereby <lb/>contributing to thromboprophylaxis in bears, paralyzed spinal <lb/>cord injury patients, and mice (7). Epigallocatechin-3-gallate <lb/>(EGCG), which is the most important component of green tea <lb/>catechins (GTC) in green tea, has been identified as a potent <lb/>inhibitor of HSP47 and is proven to be beneficial for the <lb/>treatment of PE in a murine model (8). In a two-sample <lb/>Mendelian randomization study carried out to explore whether <lb/>there is a causal association between green tea intake and arterial <lb/>embolism and thrombosis in the MRC-IEU consortium (64,949 <lb/>participants with green tea intake) and the FinnGen project (278 <lb/>cases of arterial thrombosis and 92,349 control participants), <lb/>genetically determined green tea intake was causally associated <lb/>with a lower risk of arterial embolism and thrombosis (9). Green <lb/>tea intake is also considered to have prophylactic and therapeutic <lb/>efficacy in cancer (10, 11). <lb/>Taken together, since green tea containing EGCG having <lb/>antiplatelet effect by inhibiting HSP47, thereby yielding the effect of <lb/>thromboprophylaxis, has been verified in mouse models of PE and <lb/>patients with arterial thrombosis, it was hypothesized that green tea <lb/>intake may have a prophylactic role in the development of VTE among <lb/>cancer patients. Due to the high incidence of VTE occurrence, <lb/>recurrence, and mortality, cancer patients would be benefited, <lb/>provided that it was determined that drinking green tea had certain <lb/>prophylactic efficacy on VTE development through a study. To our <lb/>best knowledge, there is no such literature to date. Therefore, the <lb/>current study was performed to address this issue. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design <lb/>We conducted a retrospective study to investigate the role of green <lb/>tea in prophylaxis in the development of VTE among cancer patients, <lb/>whose initial diagnosis was made at least 1 year prior to the current <lb/>study. Depending on whether patients drank brewed green tea or not, <lb/>all eligible patients were classified into the green tea group and <lb/>non-green tea group. Patients in the non-green tea group were defined <lb/>as those who never or only occasionally drank green tea, whereas <lb/>patients in the green tea group were defined as those who had a habit <lb/>of drinking green tea everyday (12). In the green tea group, patients <lb/>were subdivided into subgroups according to the average volume of <lb/>green tea they drank per day. Based on the previous literature (9), all <lb/>patients in the green tea group were classified into subgroup 1 <lb/>(0-250 mL per day), subgroup 2 (250-500 mL per day), and <lb/>subgroup 3 (500 mL or more per day) in the present study, according <lb/>to the self-reported average volume of green tea that they drank per <lb/>day. In China, tea brewing is typically conducted by infusing 2-3 <lb/>grams of loose tea leaves in a cup containing 100-150 mL hot water <lb/>with a temperature of 85-100°C. Only the volume of the first and <lb/>second tea infusions was counted if there was more subsequent water <lb/>refill since the GTC and EGCG for the third tea infusion in hot water <lb/>significantly declined (12-15). The minimum unit of measurement for <lb/>green tea intake was 50 mL. <lb/>In line with the recommendation in guidelines (16), VTE risk <lb/>assessment was conducted routinely every 3 months after the diagnosis <lb/>of cancer. During each VTE risk assessment, for patients with clinical <lb/>VTE symptoms or signs, or a D-dimer level of 1,000 ng/mL or more, <lb/>computed tomography pulmonary angiography (CTPA), compression <lb/>ultrasonography (CUS) of lower extremities, and/or planar <lb/>ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scan were conducted to objectively <lb/>diagnose or exclude VTE. Patients with a sudden clinical VTE <lb/>symptom or signs at the hospital or home were also instructed to <lb/>be evaluated for VTE risk and undergo VTE imaging investigation if <lb/>necessary. In general, pharmacological thromboprophylaxis was <lb/>implemented for patients in surgery, systemic anticancer treatment, <lb/>and hospitalization, unless there was a contraindication to <lb/>anticoagulation. All patients underwent anticancer treatment <lb/>according to the requirements of their condition. The specific <lb/>decisions for prophylactic anticoagulation and anticancer treatment <lb/>were at the discretion of the patients&apos; attending physicians. <lb/>The primary outcome was VTE development 1 year after the <lb/>cancer diagnosis/index date. The secondary outcome was mortality <lb/>1 year after the cancer diagnosis/index date including all-cause and <lb/>VTE-related mortality. VTE-related mortality was defined as patients <lb/>for whom the underlying cause of death was PE or VTE (17). The <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>03 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>occurrence of VTE and mortality was recorded on a monthly basis. <lb/>The overall prevalence of VTE development and all-cause and <lb/>VTE-related mortality 1 year after cancer diagnosis were compared <lb/>between green tea and non-green tea groups. Time-dependent <lb/>cumulative VTE incidence and all-cause and VTE-related mortality <lb/>rates 1 year after cancer diagnosis were compared between green tea <lb/>and non-green tea groups. The correlation between green tea intake <lb/>and outcomes was analyzed. The predictive power of volume of green <lb/>tea intake per day for outcomes in the green tea group was analyzed. <lb/>Comparisons of decrease in platelet as well as D-dimer from cancer <lb/>diagnosis to 1 year after cancer diagnosis or death within 1 year after <lb/>cancer diagnosis were conducted between green tea and non-green <lb/>tea groups. Subgroup analysis with respect to outcomes was conducted <lb/>among subgroups 1, 2, and 3 in the green tea group. We also <lb/>documented possible adverse events due to green tea intake in the <lb/>green tea group, compared with the same adverse events in the <lb/>non-green tea group. According to previous literature (14, 18), <lb/>we mainly focused on hepatotoxicity, which was defined as an increase <lb/>of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), <lb/>gamma glutamyltransferase (GGT), alkaline phosphatase (AP), or <lb/>bilirubin in the blood concentration, and gastrointestinal irritation, <lb/>which was defined as vomiting and/or diarrhea. <lb/>The present study was undertaken by medical researchers of <lb/>Shanghai Kongjiang Hospital, Shanghai Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai <lb/>Pulmonary Hospital, Chongming Hospital of Shanghai University of <lb/>Medicine and Health Science, and Shanghai North Bund Community <lb/>Health Service Center. The data required for analysis were obtained <lb/>mainly through the electronic medical record system or telephone <lb/>communication. All authors contributed more or less to the writing <lb/>of the manuscript. All authors vouch for the completeness, fidelity, and <lb/>accuracy of the data. All authors have read and approved the submitted <lb/>version of the manuscript for publication. Patients or the public were <lb/>not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination <lb/>plans of our research. This study protocol was approved by the <lb/>Institutional Review Board of each participating hospital. <lb/>Study population <lb/>We collected eligible patients according to the inclusion and <lb/>exclusion criteria. Inclusion criteria comprised the following: (1) <lb/>patients were 18 years old or older; (2) patients were objectively <lb/>diagnosed with primary active cancer (19) for the first time at least <lb/>1 year prior to the current study; (3) patients underwent VTE risk <lb/>assessment periodically, as well as VTE imaging investigation and <lb/>thromboprophylaxis if necessary. Exclusion criteria were as follows: <lb/>(1) patients already had an objectively confirmed chronic <lb/>thromboembolic disease (CTED) or acute VTE prior to the diagnosis <lb/>of cancer; (2) patients underwent a concurrent use of single or dual <lb/>antiplatelet therapies besides prophylactic anticoagulation; (3) patients <lb/>drank other kinds of tea apart from green tea concurrently; (4) <lb/>patients had more than one primary active cancer. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Propensity score matching was adopted in the present study to offset <lb/>the bias of potential confounding factors highly associated to cancer-<lb/>associated VTE. Based on the predictors in risk assessment scores of <lb/>cancer-associated VTE (5, 6, 20), we matched age, body mass index <lb/>(BMI), previous VTE, and familial and/or acquired hypercoagulability <lb/>due to reasons other than cancer, mainly including thrombophilia, active <lb/>autoimmune diseases, nephrotic syndrome, oral contraception, and <lb/>pregnancy; medical comorbidities including infection, renal disease, <lb/>pulmonary disease, congestive heart failure, or arterial thromboembolism, <lb/>primary site of cancer, performance status, and metastasis; VTE-related <lb/>anticancer therapies including major surgery, chemotherapy, <lb/>immunotherapy, protein kinase inhibitors (PKI), hormonal or <lb/>antiangiogenic therapies, central venous catheter (CVC), hospitalization, <lb/>or prolonged immobilization; and use of red cell growth factors, platelet, <lb/>hemoglobin, leukocyte, D-dimer, Khorana score, and thromboprophylaxis <lb/>between green tea and non-green tea groups. Nearest-neighbor (greedy) <lb/>matching without replacement was adopted in the propensity score <lb/>matching analysis (21). We adopted a 1:1 ratio by using a caliper width of <lb/>0.2 of pooled standard deviation of the logit of the propensity score (22) <lb/>for the number of patients between non-green tea and green tea groups. <lb/>The matching algorithm selected one patient in the green tea group first <lb/>and then selected one patient in the non-green tea group who had a linear <lb/>propensity score being closest to that of the selected one in the non-green <lb/>tea group. <lb/>Comparison of measurement data was performed by using t-test <lb/>or analysis of variance. Comparison of rates was performed by using <lb/>the chi-square test. Time-dependent cumulative incidence of VTE <lb/>development, all-cause, and VTE-related mortality rates between <lb/>green tea and non-green tea groups was explored by using Kaplan-<lb/>Meier curve analysis. The correlation between outcomes and green tea <lb/>intake as well as other risk factors of cancer-associated VTE (5, 16, 20) <lb/>including age, BMI, previous VTE, hypercoagulability, medical <lb/>comorbidities, primary site of cancer, performance status, metastasis, <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies, CVC, hospitalization or prolonged <lb/>immobilization, platelet, use of red cell growth factors, hemoglobin, <lb/>leukocyte, D-dimer, Khorana score, and thromboprophylaxis were <lb/>analyzed by using the multivariate Cox proportional hazard model. <lb/>The predictive efficiency of the volume of green tea intake per day for <lb/>VTE development was analyzed by using receiver operator <lb/>characteristic (ROC) curve analysis. We used SPSS 26 and R software <lb/>3.6.1 (R Project for Statistical Computing) for statistical analyses. A <lb/>p-value less than 0.05 denotes statistical significance. <lb/>Results <lb/>Characteristics of patients <lb/>A total of 1,521 patients from the participating hospitals between <lb/>2012 and 2022 who met the inclusion criteria were enrolled. Then, 1,312 <lb/>patients remained in the study after the exclusion of 209 patients <lb/>according to the exclusion criteria. Among these 209 patients, 25 patients <lb/>already had an objectively confirmed CTED or acute VTE prior to the <lb/>diagnosis of cancer, 74 patients underwent a concurrent use of antiplatelet <lb/>therapies besides prophylactic anticoagulation, 97 patients concurrently <lb/>drank other kinds of tea rather than green tea, and 13 patients had more <lb/>than one primary active cancer. After the following propensity score <lb/>matching, a total of 850 cancer patients entered into the final analysis, in <lb/>which the number of patients in green tea and non-green tea groups were <lb/>425 and 425, respectively. The number of patients in subgroups 1, 2, and <lb/>3 were 139, 151, and 135, respectively. The median age of all patients was <lb/>69.8 years. Among them, 422 patients were women, whereas 428 patients <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>04 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>were men. The cancer types included prostate, breast, lung, lymphoma, <lb/>gynecologic, bladder, brain, stomach, and pancreatic. The VTE-related <lb/>anticancer therapies mainly included major surgery, chemotherapy, <lb/>immunotherapy, protein kinase inhibitors (PKIs), hormonal therapies, <lb/>and antiangiogenic therapies. The agents used for thromboprophylaxis <lb/>were low molecular weight heparin (LMWH), direct oral anticoagulant <lb/>(DOAC), and warfarin. The median length of green tea drinking history <lb/>was 25.2 years in the green tea group, whereas it was 27.6, 25.8, and <lb/>22.2 years in the subgroups 1, 2, and 3, respectively. The median volume <lb/>of green tea intake per day was 336.9 mL/day in the green tea group, <lb/>whereas it was 152.6, 408.7, and 711.8 mL/day in the subgroups 1, 2, and <lb/>3, respectively. The demographics and characteristics of enrolled patients <lb/>before and after propensity score matching are demonstrated in Tables 1, <lb/>2, respectively. <lb/>TABLE 1 Demographics and characteristics of patients before propensity score matching. <lb/>Variables <lb/>Green tea (n = 609) <lb/>Non-green tea (n = 703) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age-years <lb/>67.3 ± 19.6 <lb/>70.7 ± 21.4 <lb/>0.136 <lb/>Sex (female/male)-no. (%) <lb/>303(49.8)/306(50.2) <lb/>361(51.4)/342(48.6) <lb/>0.564 <lb/>BMI-kg/m 2 <lb/>23.1 ± 6.9 <lb/>22.8 ± 5.2 <lb/>0.353 <lb/>Previous VTE (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>51(8.4)/558(91.6) <lb/>118(16.8)/585(83.2) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Hypercoagulability (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>85(14.0)/524(86.0) <lb/>185(26.3)/518(73.7) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Medical comorbidities (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>294(48.3)/315(51.7) <lb/>422(60.0)/281(40.0) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Primary site of cancer-no. (%) <lb/>Prostate <lb/>Breast <lb/>Lung <lb/>Lymphoma <lb/>Gynecologic <lb/>Bladder <lb/>Brain <lb/>Stomach <lb/>Pancreas <lb/>Others <lb/>60(9.9) <lb/>62(10.2) <lb/>89(14.6) <lb/>77(12.6) <lb/>85(14.0) <lb/>26(4.3) <lb/>27(4.4) <lb/>76(12.5) <lb/>51(8.4) <lb/>56(9.2) <lb/>99(14.1) <lb/>101(14.4) <lb/>88(12.5) <lb/>72(10.2) <lb/>80(11.4) <lb/>48(6.8) <lb/>17(2.4) <lb/>91(12.9) <lb/>55(7.8) <lb/>52(7.4) <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.022 <lb/>0.268 <lb/>0.171 <lb/>0.160 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>0.801 <lb/>0.715 <lb/>0.237 <lb/>Performance status-points <lb/>2.0 ± 1.3 <lb/>2.2 ± 1.6 <lb/>0.336 <lb/>Metastasis (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>253(41.5)/356(58.5) <lb/>401(57.0)/302(53.0) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies-no. (%) <lb/>Major surgery <lb/>Chemotherapy <lb/>Immunotherapy <lb/>Protein kinase inhibitor <lb/>Hormonal therapies <lb/>Antiangiogenic therapies <lb/>212(34.8) <lb/>406(66.7) <lb/>112(18.4) <lb/>253(41.5) <lb/>81(13.3) <lb/>97(15.9) <lb/>175(24.9) <lb/>512(72.8) <lb/>137(19.5) <lb/>316(45.0) <lb/>89(12.7) <lb/>121(17.2) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.613 <lb/>0.214 <lb/>0.730 <lb/>0.533 <lb/>CVC (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>244(40.1)/365(59.9) <lb/>301(43.2)/402(57.2) <lb/>0.313 <lb/>Hospitalization or prolonged immobilization <lb/>(Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>422(69.3)/187(30.7) <lb/>512(72.8)/191(27.2) <lb/>0.158 <lb/>Use of red cell growth factors (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>188(30.9)/421(69.1) <lb/>222(31.6)/481(68.4) <lb/>0.782 <lb/>Hemoglobin-g/L <lb/>128.2 ± 43.4 <lb/>122.3 ± 38.7 <lb/>0.561 <lb/>Platelet-× 10 9 /L <lb/>196.7 ± 108.3 <lb/>225.4 ± 119.1 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Leukocyte-× 10 9 /L <lb/>7.4 ± 3.9 <lb/>7.7 ± 4.1 <lb/>0.737 <lb/>D-dimer-mg/L <lb/>1.3 ± 1.6 <lb/>1.7 ± 1.8 <lb/>0.139 <lb/>Khorana score-points <lb/>1.2 ± 1.5 <lb/>2.1 ± 1.9 <lb/>0.036 <lb/>Thromboprophylaxis-no. (%) <lb/>Overall <lb/>LMWH <lb/>DOAC <lb/>Warfarin <lb/>500(82.1) <lb/>421(69.1) <lb/>54(8.9) <lb/>25(4.1) <lb/>610(86.8) <lb/>514(73.1) <lb/>73(10.4) <lb/>23(3.3) <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.112 <lb/>0.354 <lb/>0.423 <lb/>no., number; BMI, body mass index; kg/m 2 , kilogram/meter 2 ; Y/N, yes/no; VTE, venous thromboembolism; CVC, central venous catheterization; L, liter; g/L, gram/liter; mg/L, milligram/liter; <lb/>LMWH, low molecular weight heparin; DOAC, direct oral anticoagulant. Medical comorbidities denote infection, renal disease, pulmonary disease, congestive heart failure, or arterial <lb/>thromboembolism at the diagnosis of cancer. Since the same patient may receive multiple anticancer therapies, the sum of the various VTE-related anticancer therapies may be greater than <lb/>100%. The variables at the diagnosis of cancer were adopted for age, BMI, PS, metastasis, hemoglobin, platelet, leukocyte, D-dimer, and Khorana score. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>05 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>Primary and secondary outcomes <lb/>The overall number of patients with VTE development, all-cause <lb/>mortality, and VTE-related mortality 1 year after cancer diagnosis was <lb/>33 (3.9%), 87 (10.2%), and 25 (2.9%) in all 850 patients, respectively. <lb/>The VTE development rate in the green tea group (10 [2.4%]) was <lb/>lower than that in the non-green tea group (23 [5.4%]) (p = 0.021). The <lb/>proportion of PE (4 [0.9%] vs. 6 [1.4%], p = 0.525), DVT (3 [0.7%] vs. <lb/>8 [1.9%], p = 0.129), and PE with DVT (3 [0.7%] vs. 9 [2.1%], p = 0.081) <lb/>was similar between green tea and non-green tea groups, respectively. <lb/>The PE fatality rate in the green tea group (3 [0.7%]) was lower than <lb/>that in the non-green tea group (12 [2.8%]) (p = 0.019). The <lb/>TABLE 2 Demographics and characteristics of patients after propensity score matching. <lb/>Variables <lb/>Green tea (n = 425) <lb/>Non-green tea (n = 425) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age-years <lb/>71.2 ± 22.5 <lb/>68.4 ± 18.1 <lb/>0.512 <lb/>Sex (female/male)-no. (%) <lb/>204 (48.0)/221(52.0) <lb/>218 (51.3)/207(48.7) <lb/>0.337 <lb/>BMI-kg/m 2 <lb/>22.7 ± 5.1 <lb/>21.4 ± 4.6 <lb/>0.459 <lb/>Previous VTE (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>45(10.6)/380(89.4) <lb/>42(9.9)/383(90.1) <lb/>0.734 <lb/>Hypercoagulability (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>80(18.8)/345(81.2) <lb/>85(20.0)/340(80.0) <lb/>0.665 <lb/>Medical comorbidities (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>235(55.3)/190(44.7) <lb/>228(53.6)/197(46.4) <lb/>0.630 <lb/>Primary site of cancer-no. (%) <lb/>Prostate <lb/>Breast <lb/>Lung <lb/>Lymphoma <lb/>Gynecologic <lb/>Bladder <lb/>Brain <lb/>Stomach <lb/>Pancreas <lb/>Others <lb/>49(11.5) <lb/>52(12.2) <lb/>55(12.9) <lb/>44(10.4) <lb/>51(12.0) <lb/>22(5.2) <lb/>18(4.2) <lb/>50(11.8) <lb/>37(8.7) <lb/>47(11.1) <lb/>47(11.1) <lb/>54(12.7) <lb/>52(12.2) <lb/>43(10.1) <lb/>56(13.2) <lb/>20(4.7) <lb/>15(3.5) <lb/>48(11.3) <lb/>40(9.4) <lb/>50(11.8) <lb/>0.828 <lb/>0.836 <lb/>0.756 <lb/>0.910 <lb/>0.605 <lb/>0.752 <lb/>0.594 <lb/>0.830 <lb/>0.720 <lb/>0.746 <lb/>Performance status-points <lb/>2.1 ± 1.5 <lb/>1.9 ± 1.3 <lb/>0.549 <lb/>Metastasis (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>222(52.2)/203(47.8) <lb/>208(48.9)/217(51.1) <lb/>0.337 <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies-no. (%) <lb/>Major surgery <lb/>Chemotherapy <lb/>Immunotherapy <lb/>Protein kinase inhibitor <lb/>Hormonal therapies <lb/>Antiangiogenic therapies <lb/>140(32.9) <lb/>301(70.8) <lb/>88(20.7) <lb/>171(40.2) <lb/>60(14.1) <lb/>77(18.1) <lb/>144(33.9) <lb/>295(69.4) <lb/>85(20.0) <lb/>167(39.3) <lb/>65(15.3) <lb/>72(16.9) <lb/>0.771 <lb/>0.653 <lb/>0.798 <lb/>0.779 <lb/>0.628 <lb/>0.652 <lb/>CVC (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>198(46.6)/227(53.4) <lb/>193(45.4)/232(54.6) <lb/>0.731 <lb/>Hospitalization or prolonged immobilization <lb/>(Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>308(72.5)/117(27.5) <lb/>303(71.3)/122(28.7) <lb/>0.703 <lb/>Use of red cell growth factors (Y/N)-no. (%) <lb/>146(34.4)/279(65.6) <lb/>140(32.9)/285(67.1) <lb/>0.663 <lb/>Hemoglobin-g/L <lb/>125.3 ± 37.1 <lb/>121.8 ± 33.6 <lb/>0.906 <lb/>Platelet-× 10 9 /L <lb/>218.9 ± 96.1 <lb/>206.4 ± 107.8 <lb/>0.212 <lb/>Leukocyte-× 10 9 /L <lb/>7.7 ± 4.4 <lb/>7.2 ± 4.8 <lb/>0.972 <lb/>D-dimer-mg/L <lb/>1.6 ± 1.4 <lb/>1.4 ± 1.2 <lb/>0.162 <lb/>Khorana score-points <lb/>1.8 ± 1.7 <lb/>1.9 ± 1.5 <lb/>0.708 <lb/>Thromboprophylaxis-no. (%) <lb/>Overall <lb/>LMWH <lb/>DOAC <lb/>Warfarin <lb/>372(87.5) <lb/>310(72.9) <lb/>44(10.4) <lb/>18(4.2) <lb/>366(86.1) <lb/>304(71.5) <lb/>47(11.1) <lb/>15(3.5) <lb/>0.543 <lb/>0.646 <lb/>0.739 <lb/>0.594 <lb/>no., number; BMI, body mass index; kg/m 2 , kilogram/meter 2 ; Y/N, yes/no; VTE, venous thromboembolism; CVC, central venous catheterization; L, liter; g/L, gram/liter; mg/L, milligram/liter; <lb/>LMWH, low molecular weight heparin; DOAC, direct oral anticoagulant. Medical comorbidities denote infection, renal disease, pulmonary disease, congestive heart failure, or arterial <lb/>thromboembolism at the diagnosis of cancer. Since the same patient may receive multiple anticancer therapies, the sum of the various VTE-related anticancer therapies may be greater than <lb/>100%. The variables at the diagnosis of cancer were adopted for age, BMI, PS, metastasis, hemoglobin, platelet, leukocyte, D-dimer, and Khorana score. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>06 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>symptomatic VTE in the green tea and non-green tea groups was 6 <lb/>(1.4%) and 13 (3.1%), respectively (p = 0.104). The incidental VTE in <lb/>the green tea and non-green tea groups was 4 (0.9%) and 10 (2.4%), <lb/>respectively (p = 0.106). The between-group comparison of secondary <lb/>outcomes demonstrated that the all-cause mortality rates were similar <lb/>between green tea (39 [9.2%]) and non-green tea (48 [11.3%]) groups <lb/>(p = 0.308), whereas the VTE-related mortality in the green tea group <lb/>(7 [1.6%]) was lower than that in the non-green tea group (18 [4.2%]) <lb/>(p = 0.026). <lb/>By using a Kaplan-Meier analytical method, the time-dependent <lb/>cumulative VTE-free incidence (p = 0.007) and VTE-related survival <lb/>incidence (p = 0.023) during 1 year after cancer diagnosis in the <lb/>non-green tea group declined more dramatically than those in the <lb/>green tea group, whereas the time-to-event overall survival rates were <lb/>similar between the two groups (p = 0.283). The time-dependent <lb/>cumulative VTE development and mortality are demonstrated in <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>Correlation between green tea intake and <lb/>outcomes <lb/>After a sequential univariate and multivariate Cox regression <lb/>analysis, the green tea intake (HR 1.758 [1.476-2.040], p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>previous VTE (HR 1.737 [1.305-2.169], p = 0.001), hypercoagulability <lb/>(HR 1.824 [1.336-2.312], p &lt; 0.001), medical comorbidities (HR 1.616 <lb/>[1.317-1.915], p = 0.003), performance status (HR 1.603 [1.233-<lb/>1.973], p = 0.002), metastasis (HR 1.785 [1.416-2.154], p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies (HR 1.935 [1.410-2.460], p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>CVC (HR 1.702 [1.327-2.077], p = 0.001), platelet (HR 1.506 [1.207-<lb/>1.805], p = 0.002), D-dimer (HR 1.863 [1.453-2.273], p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>Khorana score (HR 1.645 [1.298-2.039], p = 0.001), and <lb/>thromboprophylaxis (HR 1.712 [1.227-2.197], p &lt; 0.001) were finally <lb/>correlated with VTE development. Another multivariate Cox analysis <lb/>showed that green tea intake was also correlated with VTE-related <lb/>mortality (HR 1.618 [1.242-1.994], p = 0.001). The correlation <lb/>between VTE predictors and VTE development is shown in Table 3. <lb/>Predictive efficiency of volume of green <lb/>tea intake per day for outcomes <lb/>By using an ROC curve analysis, the predictive efficiency of the <lb/>volume of green tea intake per day for VTE development in the green <lb/>tea group was explored. The sensitivity and specificity of the volume <lb/>of green tea intake per day for VTE development were 71.4 and 88.9%, <lb/>respectively. The area under the curve (AUC) was 0.888 (0.829-0.947) <lb/>(p &lt; 0.001). The cutoff value was 525 mL of green tea per day. It <lb/>indicates that, for cancer patients who drink green tea, patients with <lb/>green tea intake of more than 525 mL per day are less likely to develop <lb/>VTE than those with green tea intake of less than 525 mL per day. The <lb/>sensitivity and specificity of the volume of green tea intake per day for <lb/>VTE-related mortality were 71.1 and 85.7%, respectively. The AUC <lb/>was 0.887 (0.819-0.954) (p &lt; 0.001). The cutoff value was 525 mL of <lb/>green tea per day. It indicates that, for cancer patients who drink green <lb/>tea, patients with green tea intake of more than 525 mL per day had <lb/>less VTE-related death than those with green tea intake of less than <lb/>525 mL per day. In the green tea group, taking green tea intake of more <lb/>than 525 mL per day as 1.0, the hazard ratio for a green tea intake of <lb/>less than 525 mL per day to develop VTE and VTE-related death were <lb/>(1.737 [1.286-2.188], p = 0.001) and (1.561 [1.232-1.890], p = 0.016), <lb/>respectively. The predictive efficiency of the volume of green tea intake <lb/>per day for outcomes is demonstrated in Figure 2. <lb/>Comparison of decrease of platelets and <lb/>D-dimer between green tea and non-green <lb/>tea groups <lb/>The results of the comparison of decrease of platelets as well as <lb/>D-dimer from cancer diagnosis to 1 year after cancer diagnosis or <lb/>death within 1 year after cancer diagnosis between green tea and <lb/>non-green tea groups demonstrated that the decrease of platelets was <lb/>more in the green tea group (55.6 ± 26.3) than in the non-green tea <lb/>group (29.3 ± 13.1) (p &lt; 0.001), whereas that of D-dimer was similar <lb/>between the green tea (-0.8 ± 0.7) and non-green tea (-1.0 ± 0.8) <lb/>groups (p = 0.297). <lb/>Subgroup analysis <lb/>The overall number of patients with VTE development in the <lb/>subgroups 1 (n = 139), 2 (n = 151), and 3 (n = 135) were 7(5.0%), <lb/>2(1.3%), and 1(0.7%), respectively. The pairwise subgroup analysis <lb/>among subgroups 1, 2, and 3 revealed that the VTE incidence of <lb/>subgroup 1 was similar to that of subgroup 2 (p = 0.069), whereas it <lb/>was higher than that of subgroup 3 (p = 0.035). The VTE incidence of <lb/>subgroup 2 was similar with that of the subgroups 3 (p = 0.629). The <lb/>all-cause mortality in the subgroups 1, 2, and 3 was 16 (11.5%), 13 <lb/>(8.6%), and 10 (7.4%), respectively. The pairwise subgroup comparison <lb/>demonstrated that the all-cause mortality was similar among <lb/>subgroups 1, 2, and 3 (1vs2, p = 0.411; 1vs3, p = 0.247; 2vs3, p = 0.709). <lb/>The VTE-related mortality in the subgroups 1, 2, and 3 was 5 (3.6%), <lb/>1 (0.7%), and 1 (0.7%), respectively. The pairwise subgroup <lb/>comparison demonstrated that the VTE-related mortality was similar <lb/>among subgroups 1, 2, and 3 (1vs2, p = 0.079; 1vs3, p = 0.106; 2vs3, <lb/>p = 0.937). <lb/>The synergistic effect of the prophylactic anticoagulation was also <lb/>analyzed, although the proportion of patients who did not receive <lb/>prophylactic anticoagulation was very small. The overall VTE <lb/>incidence were 6/372 (1.6%), 16/366 (4.4%), 4/53 (7.5%), and 7/59 <lb/>(11.9%), in the patients with prophylactic anticoagulation and green <lb/>tea intake, those with prophylactic anticoagulation without green tea <lb/>intake, those with green tea intake without prophylactic <lb/>anticoagulation, and those without green tea intake or prophylactic <lb/>anticoagulation (1.6% vs. 4.4%, p = 0.028; 1.6% vs. 7.5%, p = 0.008; <lb/>1.6% vs. 11.9%, p &lt; 0.001; 4.4% vs. 7.5%, p = 0.311; 4.4% vs. 11.9%, <lb/>p = 0.018; 7.5% vs. 11.9%, p = 0.443), respectively. <lb/>Adverse events <lb/>The incidence of hepatotoxicity was 142 (33.4%) and 151 (35.5%) <lb/>in the green tea and non-green tea groups, respectively (p = 0.516). The <lb/>incidence of gastrointestinal irritation was 257 (60.5%) and 233 <lb/>(54.8%) in the green tea and non-green tea groups, respectively <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>07 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Time-dependent cumulative VTE development and mortality. VTE, venous thromboembolism. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>08 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>(p = 0.096). There was no statistical disparity either, with regard to <lb/>adverse events among subgroups 1, 2, and 3 in the green tea group. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In the current study, cancer patients with green tea intake had less <lb/>VTE development, VTE-related death, and fatal PE, compared with <lb/>those without green tea intake, despite green tea intake not affecting <lb/>all-cause mortality. No green tea intake was correlated with an <lb/>increase in VTE development, compared with green tea intake. The <lb/>volume of green tea intake per day had predictive power for VTE <lb/>development. An intake volume of less than 525 mL per day was <lb/>associated with an increase in VTE development or VTE-related <lb/>death, compared with an intake volume of more than 525 mL per day, <lb/>in the green tea group. The green tea intake caused a decrease in <lb/>platelet instead of D-dimer. Subgroup 3 had less VTE development <lb/>than subgroup 1. Adverse events were similar in patients with and <lb/>without green tea intake. To our best knowledge, the present study is <lb/>unprecedented, for no comparable studies are available. <lb/>The patient population in the present study consisted of a large <lb/>variety of cancer types, mainly including prostate and breast cancers, <lb/>being consistent with the cancer distribution in the general population <lb/>for years (23), as well as lung, lymphoma, gynecologic, bladder, brain, <lb/>stomach, and pancreatic cancers, which well-represented cancers with <lb/>high or very high thromboembolic risk (5). In other words, the <lb/>TABLE 3 Correlation between VTE development and green tea intake as well as other risk factors. <lb/>Predictors <lb/>Univariate-HR <lb/>(95%CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>Multivariate-HR <lb/>(95%CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>No green tea intake (green tea intake <lb/>as 1.0) <lb/>1.701(1.325-2.077) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.758(1.476-2.040) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Age (age &lt; 65 years old as 1.0) <lb/>1.205(1.007-1.401) <lb/>0.538 <lb/>BMI (BMI &lt; 35 kg/m 2 as 1.0) <lb/>1.218(1.016-1.420) <lb/>0.462 <lb/>Previous VTE (no previous VTE <lb/>history as 1.0) <lb/>1.669(1.347-1.991) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.737(1.305-2.169) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Hypercoagulability (no <lb/>hypercoagulability as 1.0) <lb/>1.931(1.427-2.435) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.824(1.336-2.312) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Medical comorbidities (no medical <lb/>comorbidities as 1.0) <lb/>1.552(1.234-1.870) <lb/>0.005 <lb/>1.616(1.317-1.915) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Primary site of cancer (cancer of high <lb/>VTE risk as 1.0) <lb/>1.443(1.135-1.752) <lb/>0.017 <lb/>1.229(1.038-1.421) <lb/>0.134 <lb/>PS (PS &lt; 2 points as 1.0) <lb/>1.664(1.247-2.081) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.603(1.233-1.973) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Metastasis (no metastasis as 1.0) <lb/>1.772(1.391-2.153) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.785(1.416-2.154) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies (no <lb/>VTE-related anticancer therapies as <lb/>1.0) <lb/>1.836(1.351-2.321) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.935(1.410-2.460) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>CVC (no CVC as 1.0) <lb/>1.651(1.226-2.076) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>1.702(1.327-2.077) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Hospitalization or prolonged <lb/>immobilization (no hospitalization or <lb/>prolonged immobilization as 1.0) <lb/>1.508(1.212-1.806) <lb/>0.016 <lb/>1.332(1.114-1.550) <lb/>0.075 <lb/>Platelet (platelet&lt;350 × 10 9 /L as 1.0) <lb/>1.695(1.248-2.142) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.506(1.207-1.805) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Hemoglobin (hemoglobin&gt;100 g/L as <lb/>1.0) <lb/>1.223(1.008-1.438) <lb/>0.538 <lb/>Use of red cell growth factors (no use <lb/>of red cell growth factors as 1.0) <lb/>1.447(1.159-1.735) <lb/>0.012 <lb/>1.261(1.042-1.481) <lb/>0.646 <lb/>Leukocyte (leukocyte&lt;11 × 10 9 /L as <lb/>1.0) <lb/>1.315(1.142-1.661) <lb/>0.025 <lb/>1.139(1.025-1.367) <lb/>0.773 <lb/>D-dimer (D-dimer&lt;1.44 mg/L as 1.0) <lb/>2.058(1.675-2.441) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.863(1.453-2.273) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Khorana score (Khorana score &lt; 2 as <lb/>1.0) <lb/>1.531(1.258-1.804) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>1.645(1.298-2.039) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>No thromboprophylaxis <lb/>(thromboprophylaxis as 1.0) <lb/>1.696(1.234-2.158) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.712(1.227-2.197) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>VTE, venous thromboembolism; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; BMI, body mass index; kg/m 2 , kilogram/meter 2 ; PS, performance status; CVC, central venous catheterization; L, <lb/>liter; g/L, gram/liter; mg/L, milligram/liter. Medical comorbidities denote infection, renal disease, pulmonary disease, congestive heart failure, or arterial thromboembolism at the diagnosis of <lb/>cancer. VTE-related anticancer therapies denote major surgery, chemotherapy, immunotherapy, protein kinase inhibitor, hormonal therapies, and antiangiogenic therapies. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>09 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>FIGURE 2 <lb/>Predictive efficiency of green tea intake per day for outcomes. <lb/>(A) Predictive efficiency of the volume of green tea intake per day for <lb/>VTE development in the green tea group. (B) Predictive efficiency of <lb/>the volume of green tea intake per day for VTE-related mortality in <lb/>the green tea group. <lb/>current patient population not only has a general representation of <lb/>cancer patients but also includes cancer patients who are at high risk <lb/>of VTE, thereby avoiding a selection bias. The overall VTE morbidity <lb/>in the present patient population was 3.9%, being similar to that of a <lb/>large population-based cohort study including 499,092 patients with <lb/>a first-time cancer diagnosis and 1,497,276 individuals without cancer, <lb/>in which the cumulative incidence of VTE 12 months after the cancer <lb/>diagnosis/index date was 2.3% (24). Taken together, the current <lb/>patient population makes the results of the study have an <lb/>excellent generalizability. <lb/>Despite the role of green tea intake in the development of VTE <lb/>among cancer patients being understudied, its role in cardiovascular <lb/>diseases or cancer has been thoroughly studied. In a population-<lb/>based, prospective cohort study among 40,530 Japanese adults without <lb/>history of stroke, coronary heart disease, or cancer at baseline, green <lb/>tea consumption was associated with reduced all-cause and <lb/>cardiovascular disease-related mortality, but not with reduced <lb/>mortality due to cancer (12). In a systematic review and meta-analysis <lb/>including 22 prospective studies among 856,206 individuals, increased <lb/>tea consumption was associated with reduced risk of coronary heart <lb/>disease, cardiac death, stroke, cerebral infarction, intracerebral <lb/>hemorrhage, and total mortality (25). <lb/>With respect to thrombotic diseases, it was revealed that GTC and <lb/>EGCG prevented death caused by pulmonary thrombosis for mice in <lb/>vivo in a dose-dependent manner. The modes of antithrombotic <lb/>action may be due to antiplatelet activities instead of anticoagulation <lb/>ones (26). In addition to GTC, EGCG, or EGC, CsCPI1, which is a <lb/>cysteine proteinase inhibitor (CPI) from green tea, also promotes <lb/>antithrombotic activity by inhibiting platelet aggregation (27). <lb/>Furthermore, epigallocatechin (EGC) in green tea was demonstrated <lb/>to have both significant anticoagulation and antiplatelet activities in <lb/>vivo in another research (28). In the current study, green tea intake <lb/>manifested antiplatelet efficacy instead of anticoagulation, being <lb/>consistent with the rationale mentioned in the Introduction. Since the <lb/>anticancer treatments that can cause thrombocytopenia were balanced <lb/>between the two groups, plus all patients received no antiplatelet <lb/>therapy, the significantly higher decrease in platelet among patients in <lb/>the green tea group than that in the non-green tea group suggests that <lb/>green tea may have certain antiplatelet effects. Although not the first <lb/>choice, aspirin is also considered for thromboprophylaxis in cancer <lb/>patients, justifying that the antiplatelet effect of green tea may <lb/>be beneficial to the prophylaxis of cancer-associated VTE (6, 16, 29). <lb/>By contrast, no significant difference of D-dimer change was observed <lb/>between the two groups. From the clinical perspective of the efficacy <lb/>of green tea intake on thrombotic diseases, only a study provided <lb/>causal evidence between genetically predicted green tea intake and the <lb/>prophylaxis of arterial embolism and thrombosis (9). The present <lb/>study is the first one that provides clinical evidence for the prophylactic <lb/>efficacy of green tea intake in the development of VTE among <lb/>cancer patients. <lb/>In addition to antiplatelet efficacy, whether the anticancer <lb/>efficacy of green tea may facilitate the decrease of VTE incidence <lb/>among cancer patients in the present study deserves further <lb/>discussion. Anticancer efficacy of green tea still remains relatively <lb/>controversial, despite an already academic viewpoint that green tea <lb/>has anticancer effects (10, 11). Green tea did not reduce the <lb/>mortality due to cancer in the Ohsaki Study (12). In a population-<lb/>based, prospective cohort study in Japan, no association between <lb/>green tea consumption and the risk of gastric cancer was observed <lb/>(13). In a meta-analysis, overall findings from epidemiological <lb/>studies yielded inconsistent results, thereby providing limited <lb/>evidence for the beneficial effect of green tea consumption on the <lb/>overall risk of cancer or specific cancer sites (30). Likewise, <lb/>we observed no improvement due to green tea intake in overall <lb/>outcomes of cancer patients in the present study. <lb/>Another issue is the interaction of green tea intake with other <lb/>medicine. It was reported that green tea is rich in vitamin K and thus <lb/>may antagonize the efficacy of warfarin (31). In the present study, the <lb/>VTE incidence among the patients undergoing warfarin therapy for <lb/>thromboprophylaxis was similar between the green tea and non-green <lb/>tea groups. In addition, the number of patients receiving warfarin was <lb/>considerably small (&lt;5%) in the present study, and there were no <lb/>reports of interaction of green tea intake with LMWH or DOAC in <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>previous literature. Similarly, no evidence was found that green tea <lb/>intake affected the efficacy of LMWH and DOAC in this study. <lb/>With regard to adverse events, no statistical difference was <lb/>observed between the green tea and non-green tea groups. Although <lb/>we focused on hepatotoxicity and gastrointestinal irritation which <lb/>may frequently occur in cancer patients due to chemotherapy, <lb/>immunotherapy or targeted therapy, since those anticancer treatment <lb/>have been balanced between the two groups by using propensity <lb/>score matching, green tea intake seemed to add no further impact on <lb/>the adverse events. The present study suggested that a minimum of <lb/>525 mL per day may be an optimal volume of green tea intake for the <lb/>thromboprophylaxis of VTE in cancer patients. According to the <lb/>United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) Flavonoid <lb/>Database, brewed green tea usually contains an average of 126.6 mg <lb/>total catechins and 77.8 mg EGCG per 100 mL (14). As such, the <lb/>optimal EGCG per day for VTE thromboprophylaxis in the current <lb/>study is estimated to be 408.5 mg, which is below the safe intake limit <lb/>of green tea, that is, 704 mg EGCG per day in a beverage form <lb/>(14, 32). <lb/>The clinical implications of the current results lie in some aspects. <lb/>First, clinicians could encourage cancer patients to drink green tea for <lb/>its potential VTE prophylactic efficacy as well as reduction in <lb/>VTE-related death. Second, for cancer patients with green tea intake, <lb/>525 mL green tea intake per day or more may be the optimal volume <lb/>for VTE thromboprophylaxis. Third, drinking green tea contributes <lb/>little to improvement of cancer conditions. Fourth, the prophylactic <lb/>function for VTE from green tea intake is mainly through its <lb/>antiplatelet efficacy rather than the anticoagulant one. Fifth, the <lb/>combination of prophylactic anticoagulation and green tea drinking <lb/>can provide the optimal prophylactic effect against VTE, being <lb/>superior to the isolated prophylactic anticoagulation, the isolated <lb/>green tea drinking, and neither of them, whereas only drinking green <lb/>tea without prophylactic anticoagulation may not have much benefit. <lb/>Last, drinking green tea seldom has adverse events or interaction with <lb/>other medicine. <lb/>Strengths and limitations <lb/>The current study has certain strengths. First, the introduction of <lb/>propensity score matching into the current study contributed to a <lb/>favorable comparability between the green tea and non-green tea <lb/>groups, thereby minimizing the influence of bias and confounding <lb/>factors on the results to the greatest extent. Second, we excluded <lb/>patients who concurrently drank other kinds of tea than green tea to <lb/>ensure that disparity with respect to thromboprophylaxis between the <lb/>two groups was due to isolated green tea drinking. Last, we also <lb/>observed the disparity of changes in platelets and coagulation <lb/>indicators between the two groups, which clarified the major <lb/>mechanism of thromboprophylaxis of green tea intake to a certain <lb/>extent. The result confirmed the hypothesis in the Introduction section. <lb/>Nevertheless, it is still necessary to acknowledge some limitations <lb/>in the current study. First, since it was a retrospective study, a <lb/>prospective one is warranted in the future, despite that propensity <lb/>score matching may eliminate the bias of confounding factors to some <lb/>degree. Second, the daily volume and adherence of green tea intake <lb/>were orally self-reported by the patients or their family in the green <lb/>tea group, whereas no daily green tea drinking record was <lb/>documented. Nevertheless, for patients with a fixed habit of green tea <lb/>drinking, drinking tea is their routine daily compulsory course. Third, <lb/>it was impracticable to understand the actual concentration of GTC <lb/>or EGCG in the green tea intake per day, despite the volume of green <lb/>tea intake being collected. However, the cups and volume of green tea <lb/>drinking were always adopted in the relevant studies (12, 13). In <lb/>addition, the brands of green tea varied from patient to patient. <lb/>Nevertheless, no report of difference in GTC or EGCG among <lb/>different green tea brands has been found to our best knowledge. <lb/>Fourth, the propensity score matching in the present study mainly <lb/>targeted cancer-associated VTE instead of mortality, the risk factors <lb/>of mortality may not be matched between green tea and non-green tea <lb/>groups, as well as among subgroups in the green tea group. Fifth, <lb/>we only reported hepatotoxicity and gastrointestinal irritation, which <lb/>are most frequent and critical adverse events resulted from green tea <lb/>intake in the present study. Some adverse events which are infrequent <lb/>and mild may be overlooked. Sixth, we only calculated the volume of <lb/>the first and second tea infusions for certain tea leaves since they have <lb/>the most GTC and EGCG. The results might have been different, <lb/>provided that we also calculated the volume of refill water after the <lb/>first and second infusions. Seventh, since most patients in the green <lb/>tea group had a long green tea drinking habit for dozens of years, the <lb/>results may be inapplicable to those who just started green tea <lb/>drinking. Relevant studies may be warranted in the future. Last, since <lb/>the follow-up period in the present study was 1 year after cancer <lb/>diagnosis, the current results may only be applicable to such an <lb/>interval in cancer patients. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, based on the hypothesis that green tea intake may <lb/>have certain prophylactic effect on VTE development in cancer <lb/>patients by antiplatelet mechanisms, the current study confirmed that <lb/>green tea intake did reduce the VTE development and VTE-related <lb/>mortality in cancer patients through such a mechanism, on the basis <lb/>of prophylactic anticoagulation, after the analyses of a cohort of cancer <lb/>patients for the first time. The clinical application of this finding in the <lb/>future may contribute to the reduction of VTE development and <lb/>VTE-related death, as well as further improvement of prognosis in <lb/>cancer patients. Since the current study was a retrospective one, a <lb/>randomized controlled trial is warranted in the future. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included in <lb/>the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by the Institutional <lb/>Review Boards of Shanghai Kongjiang Hospital (approval number: <lb/>LL-2020-KY-14), Shanghai Xinhua Hospital (approval number: <lb/>XHEC-QT-2021-027). The studies were conducted in accordance with <lb/>the local legislation and institutional requirements. The ethics <lb/></div>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <div type="annex">committee/institutional review board waived the requirement of <lb/>written informed consent for participation from the participants or <lb/>the participants&apos; legal guardians/next of kin because written informed <lb/>consent is waived for retrospective study according to relevant ethic <lb/>regulations in China. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>QY: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing -original <lb/>draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. HQ: Data curation, Formal analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Software, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. YC: Data curation, Formal <lb/>analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, <lb/>Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing -original draft. HD: Data <lb/>curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, <lb/>Validation, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. YZ: Data <lb/>curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, <lb/>Validation, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. YL: Data <lb/>curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, <lb/>Validation, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. HW: Data <lb/>curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, <lb/>Validation, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. SL: <lb/>Methodology, Resources, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing <lb/>-review &amp; editing, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation. MX: <lb/>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing. WX: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was <lb/>supported by the 2020 Kongjiang Hospital 5th Hospital-level Project <lb/>(Youth) (KJ20Q05), the International Talent Training Program of <lb/>Shanghai Xinhua Hospital (2023YGJRC04), and the National Natural <lb/>Science Foundation of China (Youth) (82000039). <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim <lb/>that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed <lb/>by the publisher. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Khan F, Tritschler T, Kahn SR, Rodger MA. Venous thromboembolism. Lancet. <lb/>(2021) 398:64-77. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32658-1 <lb/>2. Tritschler T, Kraaijpoel N, Le Gal G, Wells PS. Venous thromboembolism: advances <lb/>in diagnosis and treatment. JAMA. (2018) 320:1583-94. doi: 10.1001/jama.2018.14346 <lb/>3. Kahn SR, de Wit K. Pulmonary embolism. N Engl J Med. (2022) 387:45-57. doi: <lb/>10.1056/NEJMcp2116489 <lb/>4. Freund Y, Cohen-Aubart F, Bloom B. Acute pulmonary embolism: a review. JAMA. <lb/>(2022) 328:1336-45. doi: 10.1001/jama.2022.16815 <lb/>5. Streiff MB, Holmstrom B, Angelini D, Ashrani A, Elshoury A, Fanikos J, et al. <lb/>Cancer-associated venous thromboembolic disease, version 2.2021, NCCN clinical <lb/>practice guidelines in oncology. J Natl Compr Cancer Netw. (2021) 19:1181-201. doi: <lb/>10.6004/jnccn.2021.0047 <lb/>6. Farge D, Frere C, Connors JM, Khorana AA, Kakkar A, Ay C, et al. 2022 <lb/>international clinical practice guidelines for the treatment and prophylaxis of venous <lb/>thromboembolism in patients with cancer, including patients with COVID-19. Lancet <lb/>Oncol. (2022) 23:e334-47. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(22)00160-7 <lb/>7. Thienel M, Müller-Reif JB, Zhang Z, Ehreiser V, Huth J, Shchurovska K, et al. <lb/>Immobility-associated thromboprotection is conserved across mammalian species from <lb/>bear to human. Science. (2023) 380:178-87. doi: 10.1126/science.abo5044 <lb/>8. Mokra D, Adamcakova J, Mokry J. Green tea polyphenol (-)-Epigallocatechin-3-<lb/>Gallate (EGCG): a time for a new player in the treatment of respiratory diseases? <lb/>Antioxidants. (2022) 11:1566. doi: 10.3390/antiox11081566 <lb/>9. Jia L, Chen Y, Liu C, Luan Y, Jia M. Genetically predicted green tea intake and the <lb/>risk of arterial embolism and thrombosis. Front Med. (2023) 10:1156254. doi: 10.3389/ <lb/>fmed.2023.1156254 <lb/>10. Béliveau R, Gingras D. Green tea: prevention and treatment of cancer by <lb/>nutraceuticals. Lancet. (2004) 364:1021-2. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(04)17076-1 <lb/>11. Shirakami Y, Shimizu M. Possible mechanisms of green tea and its constituents <lb/>against cancer. Molecules. (2018) 23:2284. doi: 10.3390/molecules23092284 <lb/>12. Kuriyama S, Shimazu T, Ohmori K, Kikuchi N, Nakaya N, Nishino Y, et al. Green <lb/>tea consumption and mortality due to cardiovascular disease, cancer, and all causes in <lb/>Japan: the Ohsaki study. JAMA. (2006) 296:1255-65. doi: 10.1001/jama.296.10.1255 <lb/>13. Tsubono Y, Nishino Y, Komatsu S, Hsieh CC, Kanemura S, Tsuji I, et al. Green tea <lb/>and the risk of gastric cancer in Japan. N Engl J Med. (2001) 344:632-6. doi: 10.1056/ <lb/>NEJM200103013440903 <lb/>14. Hu J, Webster D, Cao J, Shao A. The safety of green tea and green tea extract <lb/>consumption in adults -results of a systematic review. Regul Toxicol Pharmacol. (2018) <lb/>95:412-33. doi: 10.1016/j.yrtph.2018.03.019 <lb/>15. Yang DJ, Hwang LS, Lin JT. Effects of different steeping methods and storage on <lb/>caffeine, catechins and gallic acid in bag tea infusions. J Chromatogr A. (2007) <lb/>1156:312-20. doi: 10.1016/j.chroma.2006.11.088 <lb/>16. Key NS, Khorana AA, Kuderer NM, Bohlke K, Lee AYY, Arcelus JI, et al. <lb/>Venous thromboembolism prophylaxis and treatment in patients with cancer: ASCO <lb/>clinical practice guideline update. J Clin Oncol. (2020) 38:496-520. doi: 10.1200/ <lb/>JCO.19.01461 <lb/>17. Barco S, Valerio L, Ageno W, Cohen AT, Goldhaber SZ, Hunt BJ, et al. Age-sex <lb/>specific pulmonary embolism-related mortality in the USA and Canada, 2000-18: <lb/>an analysis of the WHO mortality database and of the CDC multiple cause of <lb/>death database. Lancet Respir Med. (2021) 9:33-42. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>S2213-2600(20)30417-3 <lb/>18. Bedrood Z, Rameshrad M, Hosseinzadeh H. Toxicological effects of Camellia <lb/>sinensis (green tea): a review. Phytother Res. (2018) 32:1163-80. doi: 10.1002/ptr.6063 <lb/>19. Agnelli G, Becattini C, Meyer G, Muñoz A, Huisman MV, Connors JM, et al. <lb/>Apixaban for the treatment of venous thromboembolism associated with cancer. N Engl <lb/>J Med. (2020) 382:1599-607. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1915103 <lb/>20. Xiong W, Zhao Y, Du H, Wang Y, Xu M, Guo X. Optimal authoritative risk <lb/>assessment score of cancer-associated venous thromboembolism for hospitalized <lb/>medical patients with lung cancer. Thromb J. (2021) 19:95. doi: 10.1186/ <lb/>s12959-021-00339-x <lb/>21. Thomas L, Li F, Pencina M. Using propensity score methods to create target <lb/>populations in observational clinical research. JAMA. (2020) 323:466-7. doi: 10.1001/ <lb/>jama.2019.21558 <lb/>22. Son MBF, Murray N, Friedman K, Young CC, Newhams MM, Feldstein LR, et al. <lb/>Multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children -initial therapy and outcomes. N Engl <lb/>J Med. (2021) 385:23-34. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2102605 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">Yao et al. <lb/>10.3389/fnut.2024.1296774 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Nutrition <lb/></note>

    <page>12 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>23. Miller KD, Nogueira L, Mariotto AB, Rowland JH, Yabroff KR, Alfano CM, et al. <lb/>Cancer treatment and survivorship statistics, 2019. CA Cancer J Clin. (2019) 69:363-85. <lb/>doi: 10.3322/caac.21565 <lb/>24. Mulder FI, Horváth-Puhó E, van Es N, van Laarhoven HWM, Pedersen L, Moik <lb/>F, et al. Venous thromboembolism in cancer patients: a population-based cohort study. <lb/>Blood. (2021) 137:1959-69. doi: 10.1182/blood.2020007338 <lb/>25. Zhang C, Qin YY, Wei X, Yu FF, Zhou YH, He J. Tea consumption and risk of <lb/>cardiovascular outcomes and total mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of <lb/>prospective observational studies. Eur J Epidemiol. (2015) 30:103-13. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s10654-014-9960-x <lb/>26. Kang WS, Lim IH, Yuk DY, Chung KH, Park JB, Yoo HS, et al. Antithrombotic <lb/>activities of green tea catechins and (-)-epigallocatechin gallate. Thromb Res. (1999) <lb/>96:229-37. doi: 10.1016/S0049-3848(99)00104-8 <lb/>27. Fang M, Cha JH, Wang HC, Ye P, Chen B, Chen M, et al. An undefined cystatin <lb/>CsCPI1 from tea plant Camellia sinensis harbors antithrombotic activity. Biomed <lb/>Pharmacother. (2023) 159:114285. doi: 10.1016/j.biopha.2023.114285 <lb/>28. Chen XQ, Wang XB, Guan RF, Tu J, Gong ZH, Zheng N, et al. Blood <lb/>anticoagulation and antiplatelet activity of green tea (-)-epigallocatechin (EGC) in <lb/>mice. Food Funct. (2013) 4:1521-5. doi: 10.1039/c3fo60088b <lb/>29. Farge D, Debourdeau P, Beckers M, Baglin C, Bauersachs RM, Brenner B, et al. <lb/>International clinical practice guidelines for the treatment and prophylaxis of venous <lb/>thromboembolism in patients with cancer. J Thromb Haemost. (2013) 11:56-70. doi: <lb/>10.1111/jth.12070 <lb/>30. Filippini T, Malavolti M, Borrelli F, Izzo AA, Fairweather-Tait SJ, Horneber M, <lb/>et al. Green tea (Camellia sinensis) for the prevention of cancer. Cochrane Database Syst <lb/>Rev. (2021) 2021:CD005004. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD005004.pub3 <lb/>31. Tan CSS, Lee SWH. Warfarin and food, herbal or dietary supplement interactions: <lb/>a systematic review. Br J Clin Pharmacol. (2021) 87:352-74. doi: 10.1111/bcp.14404 <lb/>32. Toolsee NA, Aruoma OI, Gunness TK, Kowlessur S, Dambala V, Murad F, <lb/>et al. Effectiveness of green tea in a randomized human cohort: relevance to <lb/>diabetes and its complications. Biomed Res Int. (2013) 2013:412379:1-12. doi: <lb/>10.1155/2013/412379 </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>