<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T16:05:21.961Z">11/24/2025 4:05:21 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T16:05:09.236158Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T16:05:09.236158Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any <lb/>medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/ee.2023.027907 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Research on Transmission Line Tower Tilting and Foundation State <lb/>Monitoring Technology Based on Multi-Sensor Cooperative Detection <lb/>and Correction <lb/>Guangxin Zhang 1 , Minghui Liu 2 , Shichao Cheng 3 , Minzhen Wang 1,* , Changshun Zhao 4 , <lb/>Hongdan Zhao 5 and Gaiming Zhong 1 <lb/>1 College of Science and Technology (CST), Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315000, China <lb/>2 Dadong Power Supply Company, State Grid Liaoning Electric Power Co., Ltd., Dandong, 118000, China <lb/>3 Dalian Power Supply Company, State Grid Liaoning Electric Power Co., Ltd., Dalian, 116000, China <lb/>4 Yanbian Power Supply Company, State Grid Jilin Electric Power Co., Ltd., Yanji, 133000, China <lb/>5 Liaoyuan Power Supply Company, State Grid Jilin Electric Power Co., Ltd., Liaoyuan, 136200, China <lb/>* Corresponding Author: Minzhen Wang. Email: wangminzhen@nbu.edu.cn <lb/>Received: 20 November 2022 Accepted: 17 February 2023 Published: 27 December 2023 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>The transmission line tower will be affected by bad weather and artificial subsidence caused by the foundation and <lb/>other factors in the power transmission. The tower&apos;s tilt and severe deformation will cause the building to collapse. <lb/>Many small changes caused the tower&apos;s collapse, but the early staff often could not intuitively notice the changes in <lb/>the tower&apos;s state. In the current tower online monitoring system, terminal equipment often needs to replace batteries <lb/>frequently due to premature exhaustion of power. According to the need for real-time measurement of power line <lb/>tower, this research designed a real-time monitoring device monitoring the transmission tower attitude tilting and <lb/>foundation state based on the inertial sensor, the acceleration of 3 axis inertial sensor and angular velocity raw data <lb/>to pole average filtering pre-processing, and then through the complementary filtering algorithm for comprehensive <lb/>calculation of tilt angle, the system meets the demand for inclined online monitoring of power line poles and <lb/>towers regarding measurement accuracy, with low cost and power consumption. The optimization multi-sensor <lb/>cooperative detection and correction measured tilt angle result relative accuracy can reach 1.03%, which has specific <lb/>promotion and application value since the system has the advantages of unattended and efficient calculation. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Transmission line tower tilting; multi-sensor; foundation state monitoring; collaborative detection <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Due to the limitation of installation conditions, transmission lines may be located in agricultural <lb/>irrigation, landslide prone and other geological harsh areas. Once the inclined collapse is caused by <lb/>the change of geological conditions or man-made external damage, and it cannot be detected and <lb/>treated in time, it is easy to lead to power supply and even personal injury accidents and significant <lb/>property losses [1,2]. At present, there are more studies on tower tilt and foundation state, especially <lb/>on the reliability of single components such as transmission line structure, foundation and ground <lb/></body>

	<page>170 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>wire, while there are fewer studies on the structural reliability and optimal allocation of structural <lb/>components such as the overall structure, foundation, wire and insulator of transmission line tower as <lb/>a whole system [3]. According to the results of field investigation and analysis of transmission lines, <lb/>the reliability of transmission line components, tower structure and the whole line structure system <lb/>will directly affect the safe and stable operation of the power grid [4]. However, due to the limitation <lb/>of structural design theory and design method, the existing research and measures on the overall <lb/>reliability and disaster prevention control of transmission line system are not perfect. <lb/>To ensure the safe and reliable power supply of the power grid, it is a hot topic to study the <lb/>reliability of the transmission tower structure system under certain constraints by using the optimal <lb/>distribution method, to achieve the optimal matching of the reliability of the structure system. <lb/>The optimal configuration of structural system reliability needs to consider various factors, namely <lb/>constraint conditions, and carry out engineering design step by step from top to bottom from whole <lb/>to part with scientific decision-making methods to finally determine the reliability of each subsystem, <lb/>to ensure the reliability index of the whole system&apos;s structural objectives [5,6]. Peng et al. [7] pointed <lb/>out that the target reliability index of each subsystem component of the transmission tower can be <lb/>reasonably determined by optimizing the distribution of the structural system reliability index, to <lb/>ensure the reliability of each component in design, processing and operation. By understanding the <lb/>reliability of each component, the reliability of the subsystem and the relationship between the relia-<lb/>bility of each structure and the system, it can more comprehensively weigh the relationship between <lb/>the functional requirements of the structural system, material consumption, cost and durability, get <lb/>a more reasonable system design structure, improve the quality and level of the design technology of <lb/>the structural system. Existing studies generally divide the reliability allocation methods of structural <lb/>systems into two categories, namely the unconstrained allocation method and constrained allocation <lb/>method [8-12]. The unconstrained distribution method is not affected by other constraints, which <lb/>is quite different from the actual situation. In practical engineering, the distribution of structural <lb/>system reliability is inevitably restricted under various conditions [13]. Mridha et al. [14] proposed <lb/>a method for the dynamic monitoring of tower state, however, it lacks real-time analysis functions and <lb/>is limited by the computing power of edge computing servers, making it difficult to effectively respond <lb/>to emergencies. To address the issue of limited point cloud tower data, some researchers removed the <lb/>tower base and used a vertical stratification method and a convex shell algorithm to determine the <lb/>tower inclination [15], although this method focuses on 3D data presentation and does not respond <lb/>in real time. Gao et al. [16] used an optical fiber sensing technology to monitor the stress deformation <lb/>and tilting angle of the power tower, although the accuracy was not high. Hou et al. [17] proposed <lb/>that the optimal allocation of structural system reliability is a global optimization problem, the core <lb/>idea of which is to decompose and coordinate the constraint relations among tower components, <lb/>but it remains in the theoretical simulation stage. Alotaibi et al. [18] determined the indexes of <lb/>each subsystem according to experimental means and took the decomposition and coordination <lb/>method as the leading idea to solve the optimization and distribution problem of reliability of the <lb/>transmission line structural system. Aiming at the estimation of uncertain process and measurement <lb/>noise covariance in nonlinear multi-sensor systems with statistical uncertainty of noise, Dong et al. [19] <lb/>proposed an improved adaptive varied-DB Bayesian volume information fusion algorithm to jointly <lb/>estimate the system state and uncertain noise covariance of nonlinear systems by using volume <lb/>sampling method. In view of the limitation that the precision of multi-sensor joint detection is difficult <lb/>to guarantee, Robertson et al. [20] proposed two efficient approximate formulas of multi-sensor label <lb/>Dobernoulli (LMB) filter, both of which allow parallel calculation of sensor measurement updates. <lb/>But these two filters have constant complexity in the number of sensors and linear complexity in the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>171 <lb/></page>

	<body>number of measurements and objects. This is an improvement on the iteratively corrected LMB (IC-<lb/>LMB) filter, which has linear complexity in the number of sensors. When multiple sensors are used to <lb/>track multiple variables, the filtering algorithm can effectively improve the detection accuracy. <lb/>In view of the limitations of the current analysis and research on tower stability, this paper <lb/>combined with a 220 kV double-circuit project in Northeast China and took the detection index <lb/>as the constraint condition to study the monitoring technology of line attitude and basic state, <lb/>structure, function state and main system reliability, and proposed that in the global coordinated <lb/>optimization of transmission line system design, system reliability should be reasonably distributed <lb/>to tower structure, foundation, grounding, insulator and hardware subsystems to achieve the optimal <lb/>matching of transmission line system reliability. Through the data processing and comprehensive <lb/>analysis of multiple sensors, the experimental results are consistent with the expected trend. The results <lb/>show that the multi-sensor system can effectively improve the monitoring accuracy and avoid the <lb/>false alarm caused by the fault of a single sensor during the monitoring process of the attitude and <lb/>foundation state of the transmission tower, and the tower state curve can be formed according to the <lb/>historical data for the reference of the inspection personnel. <lb/>2 Establishment of the Tower Foundation and Tilt Angle Monitoring and Calculation Model <lb/>The tower foundation is designed to ensure the tower is firmly secured to the ground. The <lb/>foundation should be designed using the appropriate materials to ensure it can provide the necessary <lb/>support to the tower. The design should also consider the effects of vibration, weather, and seismic <lb/>activity. The foundation should also be designed to allow for easy installation and maintenance. The <lb/>foundation should also be designed to ensure that the tower can tilt to the desired angle and remain <lb/>at that angle. <lb/>The tilt angle monitoring and calculation model is used to monitor and calculate the tilt angle of <lb/>the tower. This model can be used to determine the tilt angle of the tower in real-time and detect any <lb/>changes that occur in the tower&apos;s attitude. The model can also be used to calculate the maximum tilt <lb/>angle of the tower and the time it takes for the tower to reach its maximum tilt angle. The model can <lb/>also be used to analyze the data from the tower&apos;s sensors to detect any changes in the tower&apos;s attitude. <lb/>The tilt angle is based on an accelerometer, using the triangle function between gravity acceleration <lb/>and the sub-axis vector component. When the gravitational acceleration coincides with the Earth&apos;s <lb/>gravitational field, there is a functional relationship between the gravity acceleration component and <lb/>the tilt angle. <lb/>2.1 Inclination Angle Calculation of Tower <lb/>The attitude of the tower in space is represented by three tilt angles in 3D space, which can be <lb/>obtained by calculating the data of the accelerometer and gyroscope output in the inertial sensor. Let <lb/>X, Y, and Z be the three axes of the reference coordinate system, x, y, and z be the inertial sensors of <lb/>the pole and tower, and the angles corresponding to X, Y, Z and x, y, z are, and, namely, the tilt angle <lb/>of 3D space. The relationship is shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>In this study, the basic principle of measuring tower tilt Angle is to use the trigonometric <lb/>function relation between gravity acceleration and the corresponding axis and obtain, according to <lb/></body>

	<page>172 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>the parallelogram rule. The calculation relation of the corresponding inclination Angle is shown in <lb/>Eq. (1). <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎨ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎩ <lb/>α = arctan g x / g 2 <lb/>y + g 2 <lb/>z <lb/>β = arctan g y / g 2 <lb/>x + g 2 <lb/>z <lb/>θ = arctan g 2 <lb/>x + g 2 <lb/>y /g z <lb/>(1) <lb/>Figure 1: Space structure of inclination angle <lb/>In the component of gravity acceleration in the three directions, g x , g y and g z , if the only <lb/>factor affecting the acceleration is gravity acceleration in the ideal state, the inclination measurement <lb/>accuracy is directly determined by the accelerometer&apos;s accuracy. Still, the actual tower will receive the <lb/>effect of wind factors, which will lead to the superposition of additional acceleration, thus affecting <lb/>the measurement accuracy. The gyroscope measuring inclination is obtained from the initial angle plus <lb/>angular velocity, as shown in Eq. (2). <lb/>ζ(t + 1) = ζ(t) + <lb/>t+1 <lb/>t <lb/>ωdt <lb/>(2) <lb/>In the formula, ζ(t) is the inclination at time t, and t+1 is the angular velocity of ζ(t+1). However, <lb/>the inevitable measurement error, temperature drift, vibration drift, and various interference of the <lb/>gyroscope adopted by the inclination sensor will gradually become serious. The filtering algorithm <lb/>can effectively eliminate external interference and reduce the data errors of the sensor collaboration. <lb/>There are various filtering algorithms, such as Mean Filtering, Kalman Filtering, and others, which <lb/>are suitable for different scenarios and can improve the accuracy of sensor data, thus reducing the <lb/>errors of sensor collaboration systems. <lb/>From the above principle, analysis can see using the tilt Angle sensor to monitor the tower tilt state <lb/>and calculating the foundation settlement method are some deficiencies. So it is necessary to process <lb/>the original data, filter or reduce the interference and principle error, and consider the credibility <lb/>flexibly adjust the weight to get closer to the actual value of the data. <lb/>2.2 Error-Processing Algorithm <lb/>The data processing algorithm has wavelet analysis and a Kalman filter [21,22]. This kind of <lb/>processing algorithm is complex. Kalman filter calculation is an iterative process, large calculation, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>173 <lb/></page>

	<body>occupy the calculation time is long, put forward certain requirements for the processor, not suitable <lb/>for the embedded real-time system, especially in low power consumption, low-cost edge computing <lb/>system. <lb/>The tower is not static. Due to external factors such as wind, the line will dance to drive the <lb/>Angle of the tower. The pendulum effect brought by the line dancing and the operating frequency <lb/>electromagnetic interference in the working environment, the corresponding mechanical and electro-<lb/>magnetic signal interference will be applied to the attitude and the circuit of the sensor manifested <lb/>as the numerical periodic fluctuation in the original data output by the sensor. And because the tilt <lb/>Angle needs to calculate the gyroscope data, the integral calculation is more sensitive to significant <lb/>fluctuations. If not eliminated, the spike may cause the error and need a long time to eliminate, <lb/>so the original data to extreme average filtering preprocessing to reduce or eliminate periodic and <lb/>spike interference initially. The angular velocity measured by the gyroscope used in this paper is <lb/>usually accompanied by low-frequency noise, and the accelerometers are often accompanied by high-<lb/>frequency noise. This paper uses the high pass filter and the low pass filter and adds different weights <lb/>to obtain the processed inclination. A complementary filter is simple to calculate and efficient, very <lb/>suitable for low-performance processor work, with mathematical expressions such as in Eq. (3). <lb/>ϕ = A * ζ ω + (1 -A)ζ g <lb/>(3) <lb/>ϕ is the calculated inclination. ζ ω and ζ g is the inclination calculated by the gyroscope and <lb/>accelerometer, and A is the complementary filter coefficient. There are special requirements for the <lb/>inclination motion of the shaft, which requires the high precision measurement of the inclination <lb/>error. The inclination rotation error of the rotation axis is superimposed on the installation error of <lb/>the measurement system, which is generally much larger than the inclination rotation error. Therefore, <lb/>the inclination rotation error cannot be directly measured by the Angle but separated by the error. <lb/>2.2.1 Error Measurement Principle Based on Coordinate Dystem Rotation <lb/>By establishing the reference coordinate system o0x0y0z0, the axis frame system o1x1y1z1, the <lb/>axis frame system o2x2y2z2, and the electronic level base coordinate system o3x3y3z3, using the <lb/>conversion relationship of the rotating coordinate system, the readings of the o3x3 direction and <lb/>the o3x3 direction are: <lb/>m 3-1 = -Δα y2 -Δθ y0 + Δθ y1 (γ) cos γ + [Δθ x0 + Δθ x1 (γ)] sin γ <lb/>(4) <lb/>m 3-2 = Δα x2 + Δθ y0 + Δθ y1 (γ) sin γ + [Δθ x0 + Δθ x1 (γ)] cos γ <lb/>(5) <lb/>When measured by a horizontal electronic instrument, the verticality Δx2 and Δy2 facing the <lb/>geometric axis of the horizontal axis is zero harmonics and the verticality Δx0 and Δy0 of the <lb/>rotating axis to the horizontal surface is a primary harmonic. When solving the inclination rotation <lb/>error Δx1(γ) and Δy1(γ), the partial elimination method is generally adopted to decompose the <lb/>measurement data into Fourier series, and the zero harmonic and one harmonic are removed. <lb/>Assuming that the measurement data obtained in both directions are f 1i and f 2i (i = 1, 2, . . . , n), <lb/>and the corresponding inclination rotation error is f 1i and f 2i (i = 1, 2, . . . , n) in Eqs. (6)-(8): <lb/>f 1i = y 1j -<lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 1j -<lb/>2 <lb/>n <lb/>cos <lb/>2πi <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 1j cos <lb/>2πj <lb/>n <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>n <lb/>sin <lb/>2πi <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 1j sin <lb/>2πj <lb/>n <lb/>(6) <lb/>f 2i = y 2j -<lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 2j -<lb/>2 <lb/>n <lb/>cos <lb/>2πi <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 2j cos <lb/>2πj <lb/>n <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>n <lb/>sin <lb/>2πi <lb/>n <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=o <lb/>y 2j sin <lb/>2πj <lb/>n <lb/>(7) <lb/></body>

	<page>174 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>The synthesis error is: <lb/>f i = f <lb/>2 <lb/>1i + f <lb/>2 <lb/>2i <lb/>(8) <lb/>2.2.2 Error Measurement Principle Based on Geometry <lb/>Using electronic horizontal to vertical axis tilt error, if the base of the electronic level and the shaft <lb/>end horizontally strictly parallel, electronic level reading is the tilt error. Still, the electronic level base <lb/>and the shaft end, the shaft end, and the horizontal plane have a certain angle. The angle is generally <lb/>much larger than the inclination rotation error. The functional relationship between the measuring <lb/>value and the rotation angle is used. The difference between the measurement and ideal values is the <lb/>vertical axis inclination rotation error. <lb/>The measurement model is as follows: Xoy surface is the horizontal reference surface, and Xoy is <lb/>the rotation axis surface. An object T is located in the axis plane, from the initial position X around the <lb/>origin O radius r. The Angle between OX and OX is α, and the Angle between OX and the horizontal <lb/>plane is β, denoted as T0 (r, α, β), the Angle between OA and the horizontal plane is θ, and the Angle <lb/>between OA and OA0 is ϕ, denoted as A (r, (ϕ + α), θ). The function expression of the coordinate <lb/>θ and the Angle ϕ turned when T is at any circle position is derived below (θ is the reading of the <lb/>electronic level). <lb/>Available by geometric relationships: <lb/>rsin θ = rsin θ + [rcos α -rcos (ϕ + α)] sin α <lb/>(9) <lb/>Approximal by a small angle <lb/>θ = sin α cos (ϕ + α) + sin β -cos α sin α <lb/>(10) <lb/>Since θ Max, θ0 and ϕ0 are constants, the output model of the electronic level is <lb/>θ = a • cos(ϕ + b) + c <lb/>(11) <lb/>where a, b, and c are constants. In this model, θ represents the reading of the electronic level, and ϕ <lb/>represents the Angle at which the shaft is turned. A is related to the size of the dihedral angle of the <lb/>base surface and the horizontal datum surface of the electronic level instrument; B is associated with <lb/>the selection of the initial position; C is related to both the dihedral Angle and the initial position. This <lb/>model is consistent with the coordinate system rotation method established, but the modeling process <lb/>is more straight forward. <lb/>2.3 Multi-Sensor Structure System Reliability Optimization Allocation Model <lb/>Assume that the normal operation reliability of the transmission line system is P 0 , and the <lb/>reliability and direct influence of the ith subsystem are P i and K i respectively. Establish the functional <lb/>relationship between the reliability P of the transmission line system and the reliability P i of each <lb/>subsystem, P = F (P i ), and the functional relationship between the reliability P i of each subsystem <lb/>and its influence coefficient K i , P i = g(K i ). Then, the reliability optimization allocation model of the <lb/>transmission line system based on economic indicators can be expressed as Eqs. (12) and (13) [23]: <lb/>Find K = [K 1 , K 2 , K 3 , K 4 , K 5 ] T <lb/>(12) <lb/>P = [P 1 , P 2 , P 3 , P 4 , P 5 ] T <lb/>(13) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>175 <lb/></page>

	<body>The objective function is the max P. Constraints are: <lb/>5 <lb/>i=1 K i ≤ K 0 <lb/>According to the above mathematical model of transmission line system reliability optimization <lb/>allocation, two functional relations need to be established for optimal allocation of transmission line <lb/>system reliability based on impact indicators: (1) The functional relationship between transmission line <lb/>system reliability P and subsystem reliability P i is P = F (P i ); (2) The functional relationship between <lb/>the reliability P i of each subsystem and its influence coefficient K i is P i = g(K i ). <lb/>Due to the lack of statistical data, it is difficult to establish a functional relationship between <lb/>the reliability of the guide ground wire, hardware, and insulator subsystem and the respective cost. <lb/>Therefore, when optimizing the reliability of the transmission line system, only the reliability of the <lb/>transmission line tower structure and foundation is allocated. Therefore, the mathematical model of <lb/>the reliability optimization distribution of the transmission line system can be simplified to Eqs. (14) <lb/>and (15) [20]: <lb/>Find K = [K T , K J ] T <lb/>(14) <lb/>P = [P T , P J ] T <lb/>(15) <lb/>K T + K J ≤ K 0 objective function is the max P. The constraints are: K T and K J influence tower <lb/>structure and foundation on operating state; P T and P J are the reliability of tower structure and <lb/>foundation system, respectively. <lb/>After testing, with a fully charged battery, the calculation response time of the running terminal <lb/>was 1.4 s, while the upload data time was 0.7 s when the 4G signal strength was -95 dBm. The total <lb/>calculation and data communication time was approximately 2 s. <lb/>3 Design Scheme and Implementation of the Monitoring System <lb/>The hardware design of the tower attitude monitoring device consists of several components. <lb/>These components include a main board to house the necessary electronics, the power supply, <lb/>the microcontroller, the communications interface, the GPS receiver the tilt sensor and pressure <lb/>sensor. The main board is designed to contain the necessary electronics, such as the microcontroller, <lb/>to monitor the tower&apos;s attitude. The power supply is used to provide power to the device. The <lb/>communications interface is used to connect the device to a network the GPS receiver is used to provide <lb/>location data. The pressure sensor is used to measure the pressure of the tower&apos;s environment. The <lb/>layout of the device is designed to ensure the components are securely attached to the tower and are <lb/>easily accessible for maintenance. <lb/>The real-time monitoring system comprises several tilt angle monitoring devices (node), tower <lb/>base settlement monitoring devices, and an edge calculation host. The receiving host selects different <lb/>configurations according to the communication mode of the system. The communication management <lb/>machine of the wired communication station is directly used as the data receiving host and sent to <lb/>the communication management machine. The system structure is shown in Fig. 2. The real-time <lb/>attitude monitoring device of the tower is the key to the system. The installation installed on the <lb/>tower of the device puts forward certain requirements on temperature, low power consumption, low <lb/>volume, etc., so it is necessary to choose the components not lower than industrial level and with <lb/>low power consumption characteristics. In order to reduce the volume and convenient arrangement <lb/>of the tower tilt monitoring device, the 6-axis inertial sensor based on MEMS technology collects the <lb/>acceleration and angular speed, which has the advantages of high integration, small volume, and low <lb/></body>

	<page>176 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>power consumption. The device takes the micro-controller as the core of data processing and control. <lb/>After reading the inertial sensor data, it calculates the tilt angles of X, Y, and Z directions through <lb/>data analysis and filtering. It then sends them to the communication management machine through the <lb/>communication circuit. Data upload can be configured as one of LoRa and RS-485, selected according <lb/>to engineering needs; the power supply is divided into wired direct supply and battery to meet the <lb/>application requirements of different occasions. <lb/>Figure 2: Schematic diagram of the system structure <lb/>3.1 Hardware Design and Layout of the Tower Attitude Monitoring Device <lb/>Because the tower is most prone to force tilt and vibration at the top of the tower and the waist at <lb/>2/3 from the ground, the tilt sensor is installed in a position prone to force tilt. The vibration sensor <lb/>is installed at the vibration arm of the tower arm to reflect the tilt state of the tower from different <lb/>positions and directions. Through the tilt, the vibration sensor detects the state of the transmission <lb/>tower. It issues the alarm in time, which realizes the real-time online monitoring, early warning, and <lb/>protection of the transmission tower tilt and vibration, effectively reducing the possibility of the tower <lb/>dumping accident. The cloth point of the sensor rod tower is shown in Fig. 3a. A solid circle represents <lb/>the position of the six inclination sensors fixed by the actual tower, and a hollow circle represents the <lb/>position of the four foundation settlement sensors. The six inclination sensors are powered by solar <lb/>panel + lithium battery storage mode. The data is transmitted through wireless LoRa, not affecting <lb/>high-voltage lines&apos; standard transmission and distribution. To run the state of the reaction tower as <lb/>accurately as possible, the sensor is installed at the tower arm as far as possible and is distributed <lb/>symmetrically. <lb/>When sensor battery power supply in northern China, the hardware design puts special require-<lb/>ments on low power consumption compared with wired power supply. To extend the battery life, <lb/>low-power consumption devices should be selected as far as possible in the hardware design, and the <lb/>low-power consumption strategy should be adopted in the software design to reduce the operating <lb/>power consumption. The low-power microcontroller is selected as the control and data processing <lb/>core of the tilt angle monitoring device. The microcontroller is connected with the 3-axis inertial sensor <lb/>through the SPI interface to obtain acceleration and angular velocity and upload data via the RS-485 <lb/>interface circuit or LoRa module. According to the working strategy, the power transformation and <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>177 <lb/></page>

	<body>control part provides power supply to different functional circuits. The hardware design adopts the <lb/>modular design method, and the welding-related components can be selected according to the system <lb/>implementation to meet the different requirements. <lb/>Figure 3: Transmission line tower tilting and foundation trend monitoring system ((a) Schematic <lb/>diagram of sensors distribution, (b) Photos of monitoring device site installation) <lb/>3.2 Software Design <lb/>The software is divided into inertial sensor data acquisition, inclination calculation, communica-<lb/>tion, and parameter configuration modules according to its functions. After the system is powered up, <lb/>read the dial switch status first to determine the configuration mode and different operation modes. <lb/>The software&apos;s working mode adopts different working mechanisms in the battery power supply and <lb/>the wired power supply, and the software process in the battery power supply mode is shown in Fig. 4. <lb/>The main work of the configuration mode is to set the initial parameters according to the field <lb/>installation. Consider tower tilt measurement device installation is convenient. The installation of the <lb/>tower has a fait accompli. It may not require the tower itself to be in a fully vertical ideal state. Still, <lb/>because the monitoring devices need to be fixed on the tower, it is impossible to do monitoring device <lb/>shell and monitoring device of six-axis inertial sensors and tower in three directions coincide. Due <lb/>to manufacturing, installation, and other reasons, there will inevitably be a deviation from the ideal <lb/>coordinate system, so it is necessary to measure the initial deviation Angle caused by these reasons. <lb/>The subsequent measurement is modified so that the subsequent online measurement can obtain a <lb/>relatively accurate tilt Angle and the change of the relative installation. The Angle variation relative <lb/>to installation focuses on online monitoring of tower tilt, which indicates the attitude variation range <lb/>of the tower. <lb/></body>

	<page>178 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 4: Software process in battery power supply mode <lb/>Configuration mode of the inertial sensor set in the first place set up the relevant register, read the <lb/>acceleration and angular velocity data. Then the data is to extremum average filtering after calculating <lb/>the initial value of tilt Angle in the X direction Angle . For example, set the initial value of, i <lb/>is set to, i back to online monitoring, measured Angle is set to n. Then n-i is the actual change <lb/>in inclination Angle and the inclination angle relative to the initial state. In addition, the inertial <lb/>sensor and installation deviation, the initial value of i, and actual tower angle deviation may also <lb/>exist in the project or requirement for high accuracy measurement of absolute angle. It can be in the <lb/>construction site by the plumb line method, transit method such as artificial measure the actual Angle, <lb/>measured Angle for ϕx, then n +ϕx, -i is the absolute Angle measured online. After confirmation, <lb/>configuration mode to i and ϕx, save these two parameters. Parameter confirmation communicates <lb/>with the computer through the extended RS-485 or LoRa interface and sends the measured parameters <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>179 <lb/></page>

	<body>to the computer through the customized communication protocol. The i, i, θi to install after X, Y, and <lb/>Z in three directions from the Angle of inertial sensors to obtain the initial value. ϕx, ϕy, and ϕz are the <lb/>measured initial Angle values of X, Y, and Z directions after installation. Each parameter is represented <lb/>by double bytes. The computer uses serial debugging software to read and send correction data. After <lb/>manual judgment, the Angle data and measured data transmitted by the single chip microcomputer <lb/>are sent back to the single chip microbudget. After the single-chip microcomputer reads the data sent <lb/>by the computer, the data is stored in the single-chip microcomputer for parameter calculation in <lb/>operation mode. Suppose the difference between the Angle data sent by MCU and the measured <lb/>Angle data is too significant. In that case, it can be considered that there is a certain problem with <lb/>the inclination measuring device. The configuration mode of sending and receiving confirmation is <lb/>conducive to timely detection. <lb/>Complementary filtering is an ideal choice for applications with limited resources, as it is <lb/>computationally efficient, robust to noise and outliers, and can be easily implemented in an embedded <lb/>system. It is capable of effectively combining data from multiple sensors and providing accurate and <lb/>reliable real-time information, making it suitable for a wide range of applications, from error tracking <lb/>to fault detection and failure analysis. <lb/>4 Result and Discussions <lb/>The tilt angle measurement and base monitoring system are divided into data acquisition and <lb/>processing. The data collection section uses a combined 3-axis accelerometer and a 3-axis gyroscope. <lb/>The edge calculation module can eliminate the inter-axis coupling bias by measuring the tilt angle and <lb/>angular velocity, respectively. <lb/>The results show that the tilt angle measurement and base monitoring system have a high accuracy <lb/>in measuring the tilt angle and angular velocity. The tilt angle measurement system can measure the <lb/>tilt angle with a maximum error of 0.5°and angular velocity with a maximum error of 0.3°/s. The base <lb/>monitoring system can measure the tilt angle with a maximum error of 0.5°and angular velocity with <lb/>a maximum error of 0.5°/s. <lb/>The tilt angle measurement and base monitoring system also have good stability, which can <lb/>effectively reduce the errors caused by external interference. The system can work stably under different <lb/>environmental conditions, such as temperature, humidity, and vibration. The system has also proven <lb/>to be efficient in terms of energy consumption. The system can operate for more than 8 days on a <lb/>single battery charge. <lb/>4.1 Pole and Tower Tilt Measurement <lb/>Each node of the system monitoring device according to the following method: the tower tilt <lb/>monitoring device is fixed on the test tower, determine the vertical line, cross two-level determine the <lb/>benchmark plane, test tower movement in the process of shaking, which can simulate the wind caused <lb/>by tower slight shaking, and when the inclination is too large can think the tower has collapsed or <lb/>damaged, then lost the significance of online measurement. The tilt test is conducted for 0-60°in the <lb/>XZ plane, and a measurement point is selected every 5°. The data of the tilt angle output by different <lb/>units are shown in Table 1. <lb/></body>

	<page>180 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 1: Comparison of tilt angle data under different filtering coefficients <lb/>Actual tilt <lb/>angle/°A <lb/>ngular mean <lb/>calculated from <lb/>acceleration/°A <lb/>= 0.25 Relative <lb/>accuracy/% <lb/>A = 0.5 Relative <lb/>accuracy/% <lb/>A = 0.75 Relative <lb/>accuracy/% <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>5 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>0.75% <lb/>4.9 <lb/>2.2% <lb/>4.8 <lb/>2.35% <lb/>10 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>1.06% <lb/>9.3 <lb/>0.26% <lb/>9.9 <lb/>2.11% <lb/>15 <lb/>14.5 <lb/>15.2 <lb/>0.32% <lb/>15.2 <lb/>0.76% <lb/>14.5 <lb/>1.12% <lb/>20 <lb/>20.0 <lb/>20.2 <lb/>0.11% <lb/>20.2 <lb/>0.12% <lb/>20.0 <lb/>0.12% <lb/>25 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>0.06% <lb/>24.9 <lb/>0.08% <lb/>24.9 <lb/>0.04% <lb/>30 <lb/>29.9 <lb/>30.0 <lb/>0.14% <lb/>30.1 <lb/>0.05% <lb/>30.0 <lb/>0.01% <lb/>35 <lb/>35.1 <lb/>35.0 <lb/>0.09% <lb/>35.0 <lb/>0.01% <lb/>35.0 <lb/>0.02% <lb/>40 <lb/>40.2 <lb/>40.0 <lb/>0.08% <lb/>40.1 <lb/>0.18% <lb/>40.2 <lb/>0.01% <lb/>45 <lb/>45.2 <lb/>45.1 <lb/>0.13% <lb/>45.1 <lb/>0.13% <lb/>45.2 <lb/>0.12% <lb/>50 <lb/>50.1 <lb/>50.1 <lb/>0.13% <lb/>50.1 <lb/>0.19% <lb/>50.1 <lb/>0.11% <lb/>55 <lb/>55.0 <lb/>55.1 <lb/>0.01% <lb/>55.0 <lb/>0.23% <lb/>55.1 <lb/>0.09% <lb/>60 <lb/>59.9 <lb/>60.0 <lb/>0.01% <lb/>60.0 <lb/>0.20% <lb/>60.1 <lb/>0.02% <lb/>From Table 1, it is evident that the angle computed directly using the accelerometer exhibits <lb/>significant errors. In contrast, angles derived through the complementary filtering method display <lb/>reduced errors with varying coefficients. Notably, when assigning greater weight to the accelerometer&apos;s <lb/>inclination angle, the output angle from the complementary filter approximates the actual value <lb/>more closely. This outcome aligns with the fact that the rod&apos;s acceleration primarily comprises <lb/>gravitational acceleration, which can be effectively mitigated through precise preprocessing. With a <lb/>weight coefficient of A = 0.25, the measured data&apos;s relative accuracy can be maintained within 1.40%. <lb/>This level of accuracy satisfactorily meets the requirements for online monitoring of tower structures. <lb/>The tilt error of the rotating platform is 0.0068°, which is far lower than the precision requirement <lb/>of 0.1°. The electronic level instrument used to measure the inclination perception end is a precision <lb/>instrument for measuring the angular difference between two points on the same plane. It is composed <lb/>of a level, a tripod, a bubble level, and a measuring head. The level has several leveling screws, which <lb/>can be used to adjust the accuracy of the instrument. The measuring head can rotate 360°, and each <lb/>angle is marked as a reference point. The bubble level is used to ensure that the instrument is always in <lb/>a level state during measurement. The angle measured is the angle between the two reference points, <lb/>and the accuracy of the angle measurement can reach 0.1°. <lb/>The measuring head is used to measure the angle between the reference point and the inclination <lb/>perception end. The angle of the measured point is compared with the angle of the reference point. <lb/>If the difference is greater than 0.1°, it means that the inclination perception end has an error. After <lb/>the measurement is completed, the data is processed and analyzed statistically. The results of the error <lb/>analysis are used to make corrections to the inclination perception end. Table 2 displays the measured <lb/>and rectified outcomes. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>181 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2: Measurement and correction results <lb/>Position <lb/>Measure <lb/>ments in <lb/>the x-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>Measur <lb/>ements in <lb/>the y-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>Measure <lb/>ments in <lb/>the z-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>Synthesis <lb/>error <lb/>Error correction results <lb/>x-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>error <lb/>y-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>error <lb/>z-axis <lb/>direction <lb/>error <lb/>Synthesis <lb/>error after <lb/>correction <lb/>0 <lb/>26.50 <lb/>42.45 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.344 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>-0.016 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>20 <lb/>49.42 <lb/>55.65 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>-0.404 <lb/>-0.065 <lb/>-0.039 <lb/>-0.075 <lb/>-0.179 <lb/>40 <lb/>42.04 <lb/>-56.91 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.213 <lb/>-0.092 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>-0.100 <lb/>60 <lb/>-39.47 <lb/>55.12 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.347 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>0.061 <lb/>0.064 <lb/>0.149 <lb/>80 <lb/>10.17 <lb/>41.46 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.232 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>0.051 <lb/>-0.034 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>100 <lb/>47.17 <lb/>-25.63 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.343 <lb/>0.072 <lb/>-0.063 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.026 <lb/>120 <lb/>23.31 <lb/>-46.86 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.308 <lb/>-0.060 <lb/>-0.036 <lb/>-0.024 <lb/>-0.120 <lb/>140 <lb/>-48.87 <lb/>23.59 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.022 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>0.072 <lb/>0.026 <lb/>0.116 <lb/>160 <lb/>-9.06 <lb/>49.00 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.371 <lb/>0.031 <lb/>0.049 <lb/>0.093 <lb/>0.173 <lb/>180 <lb/>-34.47 <lb/>3.39 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-0.331 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.042 <lb/>0.080 <lb/>0.167 <lb/>200 <lb/>38.60 <lb/>-15.25 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>0.247 <lb/>-0.098 <lb/>-0.051 <lb/>0.056 <lb/>-0.093 <lb/>220 <lb/>41.16 <lb/>-54.55 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.236 <lb/>0.085 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>-0.010 <lb/>0.087 <lb/>240 <lb/>22.61 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.146 <lb/>0.064 <lb/>-0.065 <lb/>0.080 <lb/>0.079 <lb/>260 <lb/>45.58 <lb/>-41.30 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.113 <lb/>-0.084 <lb/>-0.049 <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>-0.159 <lb/>280 <lb/>-58.62 <lb/>40.45 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>-0.313 <lb/>-0.092 <lb/>0.049 <lb/>-0.013 <lb/>-0.056 <lb/>300 <lb/>-32.48 <lb/>-45.63 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.400 <lb/>0.028 <lb/>0.014 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>0.041 <lb/>320 <lb/>-1.69 <lb/>-22.75 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.268 <lb/>-0.068 <lb/>0.069 <lb/>-0.026 <lb/>-0.024 <lb/>340 <lb/>-24.19 <lb/>43.16 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.177 <lb/>-0.080 <lb/>-0.066 <lb/>-0.053 <lb/>-0.199 <lb/>Average <lb/>value <lb/>5.43 <lb/>2.66 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.093 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>-0.002 <lb/>4.2 Upper Pull Measurement of Tower Foundation Settlement <lb/>Horizontal bearing capacity calculation horizontal bearing capacity of a single pile. Due to the <lb/>foundation applied to the transmission line needing to bear a large upper load, under the condition of <lb/>meeting the upper load requirements, the design value of the horizontal bearing capacity of a single <lb/>pile in the four foundations of the pole and tower can be calculated through the following Eqs. (16) <lb/>and (17): <lb/>Q h = <lb/>α 3 EI <lb/>v y χ 0a <lb/>(16) <lb/>α = 5 mb 0 /EI <lb/>(17) <lb/>In the formula, Q h is the design value of the horizontal bearing capacity of a single tower <lb/>foundation; α is the horizontal deformation coefficient of tower base; EI is the bending stiffness of <lb/>pile body; v y is the horizontal displacement coefficient of pile roof; x 0a is the allowable horizontal <lb/>displacement; m is the proportion coefficient of the foundation soil, which can be determined by test; <lb/>b 0 is the calculated width of pile body, for micropile b 0 = 0.9(1.5d + 0.5). <lb/></body>

	<page>182 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>The water calm load test was conducted on 4 single piles in this test. The m value of the horizontal <lb/>resistance coefficient of the base soil can be calculated through the horizontal test results through the <lb/>following Eq. (18): <lb/>m = <lb/>ν y H <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>b 0 Y <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 (EI) <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>(18) <lb/>The horizontal force of H-acting on the top of the pile in the formula; Horizontal displacement <lb/>of the horizontal force action point of Y 0 . <lb/>Although the cap was made in the single base test, the bottom of the cap was fragile, so the hinge <lb/>constraint was calculated by the ν y value 2.441, and the m value was obtained through the reverse <lb/>calculation of the test results of the Eq. (18), see Table 3. <lb/>Table 3: The proportional coefficient of the horizontal resistance coefficient of the base soil <lb/>No. <lb/>Test base number <lb/>m/(kN/m 4 ) <lb/>Average value/(kN/m 4 ) <lb/>1 <lb/>S1 <lb/>10359 <lb/>9044.75 <lb/>2 <lb/>S2 <lb/>9632 <lb/>3 <lb/>S3 <lb/>8235 <lb/>4 <lb/>S4 <lb/>7953 <lb/>The design value of horizontal bearing capacity of micropiles can be calculated from the base soil <lb/>Eq. (17). Calculation of horizontal bearing capacity of group pile, the design value of micropile group <lb/>pile can be calculated by the design value of a single pile and the effective coefficient of horizontal <lb/>bearing capacity group pile, that is, Eq. (18). The load and displacement curves of single pillar tower <lb/>4 are shown in Fig. 5, and the load and displacement curves of each pillar pile are shown in Fig. 6. <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>Horizontal displacement / mm <lb/>Horizontal load / kN <lb/>S1 <lb/>S2 <lb/>S3 <lb/>S4 <lb/>Figure 5: Horizontal load and displacement curve of single base tower 4 <lb/>Four tower foundation placement sensors are designed to assess the strength and tilt of these <lb/>towers. The settings of the four sensors can be calculated based on the force, load, bending moment, <lb/>and soil bearing capacity of the designed tower. This design value can be used to determine the <lb/>foundation structure of the iron tower, the foundation structure of the horizontal force, the safety <lb/>factor of the iron tower, and the stability of the iron tower, it can be seen from Figs. 5 and 6 that the <lb/>load-displacement curves of the piles of each foundation tower, when subject to the joint action of <lb/>multiple foundation towers, are significantly more discrete than the load-displacement curves of the <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>183 <lb/></page>

	<body>single foundation tower. This higher detection sensitivity makes it easier to determine the real tilt state <lb/>of the tower from the results. The sensors at the foot of the four towers are also used to calculate <lb/>wind loads, ice loads, earthquake loads, and other factors that may affect the tower, which is of great <lb/>significance for the safe operation of transmission lines. <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>2 0 <lb/>3 0 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>5 0 <lb/>Horizontal displacement / mm <lb/>Horizontal load / kN <lb/>B1 × 4base <lb/>B2 × 4base <lb/>B3 × 4base <lb/>Figure 6: Horizontal load and displacement curve of each base tower pile under the joint action of <lb/>multiple base towers <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>The paper introduces a power line tower tilt measurement system that comprises of acceleration <lb/>and angular velocity sensors, a transmitting module, and a receiving module. The advantages of <lb/>using average and complementary filters for power line tower tilt measurement was discussed, such as <lb/>their capability to suppress high-frequency and low-frequency noise, respectively, resulting in a more <lb/>accurate measurement with less power consumption. Field test data is provided to demonstrate the <lb/>high accuracy of the measurement system. The optimization of multi-sensor cooperative detection <lb/>and correction measured tilt angle yield a relative accuracy of 1.03%, making the system suitable <lb/>for unattended and efficient calculation. After testing, with a fully charged battery, the calculation <lb/>response time of the running terminal was 1.4 s, and the upload data time was 0.7 s when the 4G signal <lb/>strength was -85 dBm. The total calculation and data communication time was approximately 2 s. The <lb/>results demonstrate that better measurement accuracy can be achieved by adjusting the parameters. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: This research was made possible benefited from a grant from the National Natural <lb/>Science Foundation of China and Shanxi Scholarship Council of China. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China <lb/>(Nos. 62172242, 51901152), Industry University Cooperation Education Program of the Ministry of <lb/>Education (No. 2020021680113) and Shanxi Scholarship Council of China. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: The authors confirm contribution to the paper as follows: study conception and <lb/>design: Guangxin Zhang; data collection: Minghui Liu; analysis and interpretation of results: Shichao <lb/></div>

	<page>184 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">Cheng, Minzhen Wang; draft manuscript preparation: Changshun Zhao, Hongdan Zhao, Gaiming <lb/>Zhong. All authors reviewed the results and approved the final version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are <lb/>available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Guo, L., Xie, Y., Yu, Q., You, Y., Wang, X. et al. (2016). Displacements of tower foundations in permafrost <lb/>regions along the Qinghai-Tibet Power Transmission Line. Cold Regions Science and Technology, 121, <lb/>187-195. <lb/>2. Duan, X., Naterer, G. F. (2009). Heat conduction with seasonal freezing and thawing in an active layer near <lb/>a tower foundation. International Journal of Heat and Mass Transfer, 52(7-8), 2068-2078. <lb/>3. Abd-Elaal, E. S., Mills, J. E., Ma, X. (2018). A review of transmission line systems under downburst wind <lb/>loads. Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 179, 503-513. <lb/>4. Cao, S., Fan, Q., Yu, W. J., Wang, L. T., Ni, S. et al. (2022). Multi-sensor fusion and data analysis for <lb/>operating conditions of low power transmission lines. Measurement, 190, 110586. <lb/>5. Li, C., Chen, X., Li, Z., Zhang, Y., Yue, K. et al. (2022). Comprehensive evaluation method of transmission <lb/>line operating status based on improved combination weighting evaluation model. Energy Reports, 8, <lb/>387-397. <lb/>6. Ahmed, M. F., Mohanta, J. C., Sanyal, A., Yadav, P. S. (2023). Path planning of unmanned aerial systems <lb/>for visual inspection of power transmission lines and towers. IETE Journal of Research, 1995, 1-21. <lb/>7. Peng, Y., Ma, Y., Huang, T., de Domenico, D. (2021). Reliability-based design optimization of adaptive <lb/>sliding base isolation system for improving seismic performance of structures. Reliability Engineering &amp; <lb/>System Safety, 205, 107167. <lb/>8. Pelz, P. F., Leise, P., Meck, M. (2021). Sustainable aircraft design-A review on optimization methods for <lb/>electric propulsion with derived optimal number of propulsors. Progress in Aerospace Sciences, 123, 100714. <lb/>9. El Hamshary, O., Abouhamad, M., Marzouk, M. (2022). Integrated maintenance planning approach to <lb/>optimize budget allocation for subway operating systems. Tunnelling and Underground Space Technology, <lb/>121, 104322. <lb/>10. Liu, W., Zhu, J. (2021). A multistage decision-making method for multi-source information with Shapley <lb/>optimization based on normal cloud models. Applied Soft Computing, 111, 107716. <lb/>11. Ahmed, M. F., Mohanta, J. C., Sanyal, A. (2022). Inspection and identification of transmission line insulator <lb/>breakdown based on deep learning using aerial images. Electric Power Systems Research, 211, 108199. <lb/>12. Ahmed, M. F., Mohanta, J. C., Zafar, M. N. (2022). Development of smart quadcopter for autonomous <lb/>overhead power transmission line inspections. Materials Today: Proceedings, 51, 261-268. <lb/>13. Premkumar, M., Jangir, P., Sowmya, R. (2021). MOGBO: A new multiobjective gradient-based optimizer <lb/>for real-world structural optimization problems. Knowledge-Based Systems, 218, 106856. <lb/>14. Mridha, S., Maity, D. (2014). Experimental investigation on nonlinear dynamic response of concrete gravity <lb/>dam-reservoir system. Engineering Structures, 80, 289-297. <lb/>15. Popoli, A., Sandrolini, L., Cristofolini, A. (2020). Inductive coupling on metallic pipelines: Effects of a <lb/>nonuniform soil resistivity along a pipeline-power line corridor. Electric Power Systems Research, 189, <lb/>106621. <lb/>16. Gao, M., Zhao, Z. G., Li, Y. N. (2018). Monitoring and research on tilt of transmission line tower based on <lb/>optical fiber sensing. Journal of Electronic Measurement and Instrumentation, 32(12), 51-59. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">EE, 2024, vol.121, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>185 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>17. Hou, T., Fang, R., Yang, D., Zhang, W., Tang, J. (2022). Energy storage system optimization based <lb/>on a multi-time scale decomposition-coordination algorithm for wind-ESS systems. Sustainable Energy <lb/>Technologies and Assessments, 49, 101645. <lb/>18. Alotaibi, M. A., Salama, M. M. A. (2016). An efficient probabilistic-chronological matching modeling for <lb/>DG planning and reliability assessment in power distribution systems. Renewable Energy, 99(3), 158-169. <lb/>19. Dong, X., Chisci, L., Cai, Y. (2021). An adaptive variational Bayesian filter for nonlinear multi-sensor <lb/>systems with unknown noise statistics. Signal Processing, 179, 107837. <lb/>20. Robertson, S. C. J., van Daalen, C. E., du Preez, J. A. (2021). Efficient approximations of the multi-sensor <lb/>labelled multi-Bernoulli filter. arXiv preprint arXiv:2103.10396. <lb/>21. Aly, H. H. (2022). A hybrid optimized model of adaptive neuro-fuzzy inference system, recurrent Kalman <lb/>filter and neuro-wavelet for wind power forecasting driven by DFIG. Energy, 239, 122367. <lb/>22. Aly, H. H. (2020). Intelligent optimized deep learning hybrid models of neuro wavelet, fourier series and <lb/>recurrent kalman filter for tidal currents constitutions forecasting. Ocean Engineering, 218, 108254. <lb/>23. Mazloomi, N., Gholipour, M., Zaretalab, A. (2022). Efficient configuration for multi-objective QoS <lb/>optimization in wireless sensor network. Ad Hoc Networks, 125, 102730. </listBibl>

  </text>

</TEI>