<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:51:26.344Z">11/20/2025 10:51:26 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:51:14.376145Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:51:14.376145Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>p66Shc deficiency in CLL cells <lb/>enhances PD-L1 expression and <lb/>suppresses immune <lb/>synapse formation <lb/>Ludovica Lopresti 1 † , Nagaja Capitani 1 † , Vanessa Tatangelo 1 , <lb/>Carmela Tangredi 1 , Gioia Boncompagni 1 , Federica Frezzato 2 , <lb/>Andrea Visentin 2 , Giuseppe Marotta 3 , Sara Ciofini 4 , <lb/>Alessandro Gozzetti 4 , Monica Bocchia 4 , Livio Trentin 2 , <lb/>Cosima T. Baldari 1 * ‡ and Laura Patrussi 1 * ‡ <lb/>1 Department of Life Sciences, University of Siena, Siena, Italy, 2 Hematology and Clinical Immunology <lb/>Unit, Department of Medicine, University of Padua, Padua, Italy, 3 Stem Cell Transplant and Cellular <lb/>Therapy Unit, University Hospital, Siena, Italy, 4 Department of Medical Science, Surgery and <lb/>Neuroscience, University of Siena, Siena, Italy <lb/>Introduction: Escape from immunosurveillance is a hallmark of chronic <lb/>lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) cells. In the protective niche of lymphoid organs, <lb/>leukemic cells suppress the ability of T lymphocytes to form the immune synapse <lb/>(IS), thereby hampering T-cell mediated anti-tumoral activities. By binding its <lb/>cognate receptor PD-1 at the surface of T lymphocytes, the inhibitory ligand PD-<lb/>L1, which is overexpressed in CLL cells, mediates the T-cell suppressive activities <lb/>of CLL cells. However, the molecular mechanism underlying PD-L1 <lb/>overexpression in CLL cells remains unknown. We have previously reported a <lb/>defective expression of the pro-apoptotic and pro-oxidant adaptor p66Shc in <lb/>CLL cells, which is causally related to an impairment in intracellular reactive <lb/>oxygen species (ROS) production and to the activation of the ROS-sensitive <lb/>transcription factor NF-κB. The fact that PD-L1 expression is regulated by NF-κB <lb/>suggests a mechanistic relationship between p66Shc deficiency and PD-L1 <lb/>overexpression in CLL cells. <lb/>Methods: 62 treatment-naive CLL patients and 43 healthy donors were included <lb/>in this study. PD-L1 and p66Shc expression was quantified in B cells by flow <lb/>cytometry and qRT-PCR. IS architecture and local signaling was assessed by flow <lb/>cytometry and confocal microscopy. CD8+ cell killing activity was assessed by <lb/>flow cytometry. <lb/>Results: Here we show that residual p66Shc expression in leukemic cells isolated <lb/>both from CLL patients and from the CLL mouse model Eμ-TCL1 inversely <lb/>correlated with PD-L1 expression. We also show that the PD-L1 increase <lb/>prevented leukemic cells from forming ISs with T lymphocytes. Reconstitution <lb/>of p66Shc, but not of a ROS-defective mutant, in both CLL cells and the CLL-<lb/>derived cell line MEC-1, enhanced intracellular ROS and decreased PD-L1 <lb/>expression. Similar results were obtained following treatment of CLL cells with <lb/>H 2 O 2 as exogenous source of ROS, that normalized PD-L1 expression and <lb/>recovered IS formation. <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Lei Shi, <lb/>Lanzhou University, China <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Luca Simula, <lb/>INSERM U1016 Institut Cochin, France <lb/>Haopeng Yang, <lb/>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer <lb/>Center, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Cosima T. Baldari, <lb/>cosima.baldari@unisi.it <lb/>Laura Patrussi, <lb/>patrussi2@unisi.it <lb/> † <lb/>These authors share first authorship <lb/> ‡ These authors share last authorship <lb/>RECEIVED 19 September 2023 <lb/>ACCEPTED 08 January 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 23 January 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Lopresti L, Capitani N, Tatangelo V, Tangredi C, <lb/>Boncompagni G, Frezzato F, Visentin A, <lb/>Marotta G, Ciofini S, Gozzetti A, Bocchia M, <lb/>Trentin L, Baldari CT and Patrussi L (2024), <lb/>p66Shc deficiency in CLL cells enhances PD-L1 <lb/>expression and suppresses immune <lb/>synapse formation. <lb/>Front. Cell Dev. Biol. 12:1297116. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Lopresti, Capitani, Tatangelo, Tangredi, <lb/>Boncompagni, Frezzato, Visentin, Marotta, <lb/>Ciofini, Gozzetti, Bocchia, Trentin, Baldari and <lb/>Patrussi. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction in other forums is <lb/>permitted, provided the original author(s) and <lb/>the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic practice. <lb/>No use, distribution or reproduction is <lb/>permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/>Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>01 <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 23 January 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/>Discussion: Our data provide direct evidence that the p66Shc-deficiency-related <lb/>ROS depletion in CLL cells concurs to enhance PD-L1 expression and provides a <lb/>mechanistic basis for the suppression of T cell-mediated anti-tumoral functions in <lb/>the immunosuppressive lymphoid niche. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>PD-L1, immune checkpoint, CLL, p66Shc, immune synapse, ROS <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The efficient evasion of anti-tumor immune responses is a hallmark <lb/>of chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) cells (Capitani et al., 2021). In the <lb/>protective niche of secondary lymphoid organs and bone marrow, <lb/>leukemic cells contribute to the establishment of an <lb/>immunosuppressive microenvironment by secreting soluble factors, <lb/>such as interleukin (IL)-10, that promote regulatory T cell <lb/>development and suppression of anti-tumoral effector T cell functions <lb/>(ten Hacken and Burger, 2016; Beyer et al., 2005). Additionally, CLL cells <lb/>negatively modulate T cell activity through direct contact mediated by <lb/>inhibitory surface receptor/ligand pairs. PD-L1, which is upregulated at <lb/>the surface of CLL cells (Ramsay et al., 2012; Grzywnowicz et al., 2015), <lb/>interacts with its receptor PD-1 whose expression, transiently enhanced <lb/>during the physiological activation processes, is aberrantly upregulated <lb/>on effector T cells in the stromal CLL niche (Riches et al., 2013), thus <lb/>potentiating the PD1/PD-L1 signaling axis. PD-L1 has a major negative <lb/>impact on the assembly of a functional immune synapse (IS), the <lb/>signaling platform that T cells assemble at the interface with cognate <lb/>antigen presenting cells (APC) by triggering the polarization of receptors, <lb/>adhesion molecules, cytoskeletal components and secretory machinery <lb/>toward the T cell/APC contact area (Fooksman et al., 2010; Alarcón et al., <lb/>2011; Cassioli and Baldari, 2022). The formation of a stable IS <lb/>architecture, which is a key prerequisite for the execution of T cell <lb/>effector functions (Dustin and Choudhuri, 2016), is consistently disabled <lb/>in the CLL context. This occurs at least in part as a result of PD-L1-<lb/>dependent PD-1 triggering (Ramsay et al., 2012) which leads to the <lb/>recruitment of the phosphatase SHP-2 close to the T Cell Receptor (TCR) <lb/>(Saunders et al., 2005), thereby shutting down antigen-dependent <lb/>signaling (Arasanz et al., 2017). By reactivating anti-tumor T cell <lb/>functions, immune checkpoint inhibitor-based immunotherapies <lb/>targeting the PD-1/PD-L1 axis showed promising results in clinical <lb/>trials enrolling Hodgkin lymphoma, follicular lymphoma and diffuse <lb/>large B-cell lymphoma patients (Kline et al., 2020), witnessing to the key <lb/>role of this inhibitory signaling axis in the pathogenesis of hematological <lb/>malignancies. Of note, the modest efficacy observed for CLL patients, <lb/>which was limited to patients with the aggressive Richter transformation <lb/>who experienced increased PD-1 expression during treatment (Ding <lb/>et al., 2017; Kline et al., 2020; Ioannou et al., 2021), together with the large <lb/>variability of both PD-1 and PD-L1 expression in CLL patients, underlie <lb/>the low effectiveness of neutralizing antibody-based therapies (Brusa <lb/>et al., 2013; Ding et al., 2017) and highlight the need of alternative <lb/>therapeutic approaches to target this signaling axis in CLL. <lb/>In B lymphocytes, the adaptor protein p66Shc negatively regulates <lb/>cell survival by modulating the expression of apoptosis-regulating <lb/>proteins belonging to the Bcl-2 family and inhibiting the activation of <lb/>the pro-survival kinase Akt (Capitani et al., 2010). Additionally, it <lb/>participates in signaling pathways linking oxidative stress to apoptosis <lb/>(Migliaccio et al., 1999; Patrussi et al., 2020). By interrupting the <lb/>mitochondrial respiratory chain through cytochrome-c binding and <lb/>oxidation, p66Shc promotes ROS production and activates the <lb/>apoptotic cascade (Giorgio et al., 2005; Pellegrini et al., 2007). In CLL <lb/>cells a profound p66Shc decrease, which is most pronounced in leukemic <lb/>cells with unmutated IGHV genes (U-CLL), has been related to enhanced <lb/>leukemic cell survival and drug resistance (Capitani et al., 2010; Patrussi <lb/>et al., 2019). The resulting decrease in intracellular ROS promotes the <lb/>expression of the chemokine receptors CCR2, CXCR3 and CCR7, which <lb/>are implicated in CLL cell homing to lymphoid and non-lymphoid <lb/>organs, as a result of enhanced activity of the transcription factor NF-κB <lb/>(Capitani et al., 2012; Tatangelo et al., 2022). The p66Shc defect also <lb/>impacts on the expression of the egress receptor sphingosine-1-phosphate <lb/>receptor 1 (S1PR1) in U-CLL cells, thereby further promoting leukemic <lb/>cell entrapment in the pro-survival tumoral niche (Capitani et al., 2012). <lb/>The implication of p66Shc deficiency in CLL onset and development <lb/>is witnessed by the rapid development of an aggressive form of the <lb/>disease in Eμ-TCL1/p66Shc -/-mice, generated by introducing a null <lb/>p66Shc allele into the Eµ-TCL1 mouse model of human CLL (Bichi et al., <lb/>2002; Patrussi et al., 2019). However, the potential impact of the p66Shc <lb/>defect on immunosuppressive activities of leukemic cells remains to be <lb/>clarified. Here, we have addressed the outcome of p66Shc deficiency on <lb/>the ability of CLL cells to form ISs with T lymphocytes. We show that <lb/>p66Shc deficiency leads to enhanced expression of PD-L1, which in turn <lb/>contributes to suppress IS formation with Jurkat T cells, a defect that was <lb/>reversed by restoring p66Shc expression. Furthermore, we demonstrate <lb/>that the p66Shc defect in CLL cells impinges on PD-L1 overexpression <lb/>and IS suppression by downregulating the intracellular ROS content. <lb/>Altogether, our data provide direct evidence that ROS depletion caused <lb/>by p66Shc deficiency concurs to the formation of a T cell-suppressive <lb/>tumor microenvironment in CLL. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 CLL patients, healthy donors and mice <lb/>Peripheral blood samples were collected from 62 treatment-naive <lb/>CLL patients. CLL diagnosis and mutational IGHV status were assessed <lb/>as reported (Hallek et al., 2008; Patrussi et al., 2019; Visentin et al., <lb/>2019). Healthy B cells obtained from 43 buffy coats were used as healthy <lb/>population controls. Human B cells were purified by negative selection <lb/>using RosetteSep B-cell enrichment Cocktail (StemCell Technologies, <lb/>Vancouver, Canada) followed by density gradient centrifugation on <lb/>Lympholite (Cedarlane Laboratories, The Netherlands). <lb/>Mice included Eμ-TCL1 and Eμ-TCL1/p66Shc -/-mice (Bichi et al., <lb/>2002; Patrussi et al., 2019), and parental C57BL/6J mice. Disease <lb/>development and overt leukemia achievement were assessed as <lb/>reported (Patrussi et al., 2019). Leukemic cells were purified from <lb/>age-matched 9-12-month-old EµTCL1 or Eμ-TCL1/p66Shc -/-mice by <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>immunomagnetic activated cell-sorting (MACS, Miltenyi Biotech). <lb/>Splenic B cells were purified from C57BL/6 mice as reported <lb/>(Patrussi et al., 2018). <lb/>2.2 Cell lines and transfections <lb/>Stable transfectants generated using the CLL-derived B-cell line <lb/>MEC-1 and expressing human full-length p66Shc or the p66ShcQQ <lb/>mutant were previously described (Stacchini et al., 1999; Capitani <lb/>et al., 2012). CLL cells were transiently transfected with 5 μg <lb/>pcDNA3 or p66Shc-encoding pcDNA3 or p66ShcQQ pBabe <lb/>vectors/sample using the Human B-cell Nucleofector Kit (Amaxa <lb/>Biosystems, Cologne, Germany) as described (Patrussi et al., 2019). <lb/>Assays were carried out after 24/48 h. For NF-AT translocation <lb/>assays, Jurkat T cells were transiently transfected with the plasmid <lb/>pEGFP/NFAT-1D (Plyte et al., 2001) by electroporation. <lb/>2.3 Purification and activation of CD8 + cells <lb/>CD8 + cells were isolated from peripheral blood of healthy <lb/>donors by negative selection using the RosetteSep Human CD8 + <lb/>T Cell Enrichment Cocktail (StemCell Technologies, #15063), <lb/>following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. On the same day (day <lb/>0), cells were stimulated in RPMI-HEPES medium (1×10 6 /mL) <lb/>(Merck, #R7388) supplemented with 10% BCS (GE Healthcare <lb/>HyClone, #SH30072.03), 1% MEM nonessential amino acids <lb/>(MEM NEAA; #11140050), and 50 U/mL recombinant human <lb/>IL-2 with Dynabeads ™ Human T-activator CD3/CD28. <lb/>48 h after activation (day 2), beads were removed and CTLs were <lb/>collected. For cytotoxicity assays, CTLs were expanded in RPMI-<lb/>HEPES supplemented with 10% BCS, 1% MEM NEAA, and 50 U/ <lb/>mL recombinant human IL-2 for additional 3 days, then further <lb/>expanded for 2 days and collected at day 7 (Onnis et al., 2023). <lb/>2.4 Cell treatments, ROS measurements, <lb/>flow cytometry and immunoblot <lb/>Freshly isolated healthy and leukemic human B cells, and MEC-1 <lb/>transfectants were treated with 100 μM H 2 O 2 (Merck, #H1009). After <lb/>6 h, intracellular ROS were measured by flow cytometry in cells labeled <lb/>for 30 min at 37 °C with 5 μM CM-H 2 DCFDA (Capitani et al., 2012). <lb/>H 2 O 2 dose and treatment time were previously determined (Tatangelo <lb/>et al., 2022). Leukemic cell and MEC-1 transfectants were treated with <lb/>1 μM IT-901 (R&amp;D Systems, #5846) for 24 h. Control samples were <lb/>treated with DMSO. Phospho-NF-κB was quantified after 30 min by <lb/>flow cytometry in cells fixed and permeabilized using Fixation <lb/>(Biolegend, #420801) and Permeabilization (Biolegend, #421002) <lb/>buffers and stained with anti-human phospho-NF-κB p65 (Ser536) <lb/>(Cell Signaling Technology, #3031) and Alexa Fluor-647 anti-rabbit <lb/>secondary antibodies (Thermo Fisher Scientific, #A21236). Surface <lb/>expression of PD-L1 was assessed by flow cytometry. MEC <lb/>transfectants and B cells purified from peripheral blood of CLL <lb/>patients and healthy donors were stained with anti-PD-<lb/>L1 antibodies (Invitrogen, #PA5-23043) and Alexa Fluor 647-<lb/>labelled anti-rabbit secondary antibodies (Thermo Fisher Scientific, <lb/>#A21236). Single-cell suspensions obtained from mouse spleens were <lb/>depleted of erythrocytes by hypotonic lysis and incubated with mouse <lb/>Fc-block for 15 min at 4 °C. Murine B cells were stained as above and <lb/>subjected to flow cytometry using Guava Easy-Cyte cytometer (Merck <lb/>Millipore) as described (Patrussi et al., 2015). Antibodies and reagents <lb/>are listed in Supplementary Table S1. <lb/>Cells (2×10 6 /sample) were lysed in 1% (v/v) Triton X-100 in <lb/>20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 150 mM NaCl in the presence of Protease <lb/>Inhibitor Cocktail (Calbiochem ® , #539-134) and 0.2 mg/mL sodium <lb/>orthovanadate (Merck, #S6508), for 5 min on ice. Protein extracts <lb/>were quantified by Quantum Protein Assay Kit (Euroclone, <lb/>#EMP014500) and denatured in 4× Bolt ™ LDS Sample Buffer <lb/>(Thermo Fisher Scientific, #B0007) supplemented with 10× Bolt ™ <lb/>Sample Reducing Buffer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, #B009) for 5 min <lb/>at 100 °C. Proteins (10 μg) were resolved by SDS-PAGE (Life <lb/>Technologies, #NW04120BOX) and transferred to nitrocellulose <lb/>(GE Healthcare, #9004-70-0) as previously described (Patrussi <lb/>et al., 2018). Membranes were incubated with primary antibodies <lb/>for 3 h at room temperature or overnight at 4 °C. Immunoblots were <lb/>carried out using anti-Shc (Merck Millipore, #06-203), anti-PD-L1 <lb/>(Invitrogen, #PA5-20343) and anti-actin (Millipore, #MAB1501) <lb/>primary antibodies. Secondary peroxidase-labeled anti-mouse <lb/>(#115-035-146) and anti-rabbit (#111-035-003) antibodies were <lb/>from Jackson Immuno-Research (Supplementary Table S1). <lb/>Labeled antibodies were detected using ECL kit (SuperSignal ® West <lb/>Pico Chemiluminescent Substrate, Thermo Fisher Scientific #34578), <lb/>and immunoblots were digitally acquired and analyzed using Alliance <lb/>Q9-Atom chemiluminescence imaging system (Uvitec). <lb/>2.5 RNA purification and qRT-PCR <lb/>RNA was extracted and retrotranscribed as described (Patrussi <lb/>et al., 2018). Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed <lb/>on 96-well optical PCR plates (Sarstedt) using SsoFast ™ EvaGreen ® <lb/>Supermix (Bio-Rad, #1725204) using the CFX96 Real-Time system <lb/>(Bio-Rad Laboratories). Primers used for amplification are listed in <lb/>Supplementary Table S2. Results were processed and analyzed as <lb/>described (Patrussi et al., 2018). The relative gene transcript <lb/>abundance was determined on triplicate samples using the ddCt <lb/>method and normalized to either HPRT1 (human-derived samples) <lb/>or GAPDH (mouse-derived samples). <lb/>2.6 IS formation and immunofluorescence <lb/>Purified healthy or CLL B cells (0.4×10 6 cells/100 μL) were <lb/>loaded with 10 μg/mL staphylococcal enterotoxin E (SEE; Toxin <lb/>Technologies, #ET404) for 1 h and labelled with 10 μM Cell Tracker <lb/>Blue (Thermo Fisher Scientific, #C2110) for the last 20 min of <lb/>incubation. SEE was used for Jurkat cells that express TCR Vβ8. <lb/>For ISs with CTLs, healthy or CLL B cells (0.4×10 6 cells/100 μL) were <lb/>loaded with 10 μg/mL Staphylococcal SAg A (SEA; Toxin <lb/>Technologies, #AT101), B (SEB; Toxin Technologies, #BT202) <lb/>and E (SEE; Toxin Technologies, #ET404) for 2 h, to broadly <lb/>cover the TCR Vβ repertoire, and labelled with 10 μM Cell <lb/>Tracker Blue (Thermo Fisher Scientific, #C2110) for the last <lb/>20 min of incubation. SAgs-loaded B cells were washed twice, <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>mixed with either Jurkat cells (2:1) or CTLs (2:1) and incubated for <lb/>15 min at 37 °C. When required, 5 μg/mL anti-PD-L1 neutralizing <lb/>mAbs (EliteRmab, #10084-R639) were added to the medium during <lb/>conjugate formation. Samples were seeded on microscope slides <lb/>(Thermo Fisher Scientific, #X2XER208B) coated with poly-L-lysine <lb/>(Merck, #P1274) and allowed to adhere for 15 min at 37 °C. Then, <lb/>samples were fixed for 10 min in methanol at -20 °C (for CD3ζ and <lb/>p-Tyr staining) or for 15 min with 4% paraformaldehyde/PBS at <lb/>room temperature (for F-actin staining with phalloidin) and <lb/>permeabilized with 0.1% Triton in 1% BSA PBS. Cells were <lb/>stained with primary antibodies overnight at 4 °C, washed with <lb/>PBS, incubated for 45 min at room temperature with Alexa Fluor <lb/>488-and 555-labeled secondary antibodies and mounted with 90% <lb/>glycerol/PBS (Cassioli et al., 2021). For phospho-ERK1/ <lb/>2 quantification, Jurkat T cells were conjugated with B cell for <lb/>15 min at 37 °C, subjected to strong pipetting to disrupt conjugates, <lb/>fixed and permeabilized using Fixation (Biolegend, #420801) and <lb/>Permeabilization (Biolegend, #421002) buffers and stained with PE <lb/>anti-human CD3ε antibody (BioLegend, #317308) and anti-<lb/>phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204; Cell Signaling, #9101) <lb/>antibodies. The percentage of phospho-ERK1/2 + cells was <lb/>quantified by flow cytometry on CD3 + positive cells. For NF-AT <lb/>nuclear translocation assays, Jurkat T cells transfected with the <lb/>plasmid pEGFP/NFAT-1D (Plyte et al., 2001) were cultured at <lb/>37 °C for 24 h, then mixed with SEE-loaded B cells for 1 h at <lb/>37 °C. Jurkat T cell transfectants either unstimulated (ns) or <lb/>stimulated for 30 min at 37 °C with 1 μg/mL A23187 (A23) were <lb/>used as negative and positive controls, respectively (Pacini et al., <lb/>2004). Cells were then allowed to adhere to poly-L-lysine-coated <lb/>slides for 15 min, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde/PBS at room <lb/>temperature, permeabilized and stained with anti-GFP primary <lb/>antibodies (Invitrogen, #A11120) and Alexa Fluor 488-labeled <lb/>anti mouse secondary antibodies (Thermo Fisher Scientific, <lb/>#A11001). Confocal microscopy was carried out on a Zeiss <lb/>LSM700 (Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany) microscope using a 63×/ <lb/>1.40 oil immersion objective. Images were acquired with pinholes <lb/>opened to obtain 0.8 μm-tick sections. Images were processed with <lb/>Zen 2009 image software (Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany). <lb/>Immunofluorescence analyses were performed using ImageJ <lb/>(RRID:SCR_003070). Scoring of conjugates for accumulation <lb/>of CD3ζ, p-Tyr or F-actin at the IS was performed as reported <lb/>(Cassioli et al., 2021; Onnis et al., 2023). Antibodies used for <lb/>immunofluorescence <lb/>microscopy <lb/>are <lb/>listed <lb/>in <lb/>Supplementary Table S1. <lb/>2.7 Cytotoxicity assays <lb/>B cells (0.025×10 6 ) were pulsed with 2 μg/mL SAgs for 1 h in <lb/>serum-free AIMV medium. Unpulsed B cells were used as negative <lb/>control. CTLs collected at day 7 were stained with 1.5 μM <lb/>carboxyfluorescein diacetate succinimidyl ester (CFSE; Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientific, #C34554) for 8 min at room temperature in PBS <lb/>and then added to B cells at 1:10 B cell:CTL ratio in 50 μL AIMV <lb/>(Gibco, #12055-091) medium and incubated at 37 °C for 4 h to <lb/>evaluate target cell killing. When required, 5 μg/mL anti-PD-<lb/>L1 neutralizing mAbs were added to the medium during <lb/>conjugate formation. Cells were then diluted to 200 μL with cold <lb/>PBS and acquired using a GUAVA flow cytometer. Propidium <lb/>iodide (PI, Sigma, #537059) was added before each acquisition to <lb/>the final concentration of 20 μg/mL. Cytotoxicity (% target cell lysis) <lb/>was calculated as follows: CFSE -PI + cells-CFSE -PI + cells in <lb/>control sample) × 100. <lb/>2.8 Study approval <lb/>Written informed consent was received from CLL patients and <lb/>healthy donors prior to inclusion in the study according to the <lb/>Declaration of Helsinki. Experiments were approved by the local <lb/>Ethics Committee. <lb/>2.9 Statistical analyses <lb/>Each experiment was performed ≥3 independent times. One-<lb/>way ANOVA tests with post-hoc Tukey correction and multiple <lb/>comparisons were used to compare multiple groups. Mann-Whitney <lb/>rank-sum and Paired t tests were performed to determine the <lb/>significance of the differences between two groups. One-sample <lb/>Wilcoxon tests were used where samples were compared to a known <lb/>standard value. Power and sample size estimations were performed <lb/>using G*Power (RRID:SCR_013726). Statistical analyses were <lb/>performed using GraphPad Prism (RRID:SCR_002798). Statistical <lb/>significance was defined as: ****p ≤ 0.0001; ***p ≤ 0.001; **p ≤ 0.01; <lb/>*p ≤ 0.05. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 The p66Shc expression defect in CLL <lb/>cells impinges on their ability to form ISs <lb/>with Jurkat T cells <lb/>CLL cells have a profound defect in the expression of the pro-<lb/>apoptotic and pro-oxidant adaptor p66Shc (Capitani et al., 2010), <lb/>that progressively further decreases during disease development <lb/>(Capitani et al., 2019; Patrussi et al., 2021a). Since CLL cells <lb/>suppress the ability of T cells to form ISs (Ramsay et al., 2012), <lb/>we asked whether the p66Shc defect impinges on the IS-suppressive <lb/>abilities of CLL cells. To this end, CLL cells were purified from <lb/>peripheral blood of CLL patients and healthy donors and p66Shc <lb/>mRNA was quantified by qRT-PCR (Supplementary Figure S1A). In <lb/>agreement with previous results, the p66Shc mRNA levels were <lb/>strongly decreased in CLL cells from our patient cohort compared to <lb/>the levels detected in healthy B cells, with the lowest levels harbored <lb/>by U-CLL cells (Supplementary Figure S1A, B). Based on their <lb/>residual levels of p66Shc, CLL patients were then grouped in high <lb/>p66Shc (high-p66) and low p66Shc (low-p66) expressing patients, <lb/>according to an arbitrarily set threshold (0.25, corresponding to the <lb/>median ddCt p66Shc mRNA of all CLL patients, Figure 1A). Cells <lb/>from both high-p66 and low-p66 CLL patients, as well as B cells <lb/>purified from healthy donors (HD), were pulsed with Staphylococcal <lb/>enterotoxin E (SEE) and conjugated with Jurkat T cells. IS formation <lb/>was impaired in conjugates of Jurkat T cells with CLL cells, as shown <lb/>by the decreased frequency of conjugates displaying F-actin, and <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 1 <lb/>CLL cells with low p66Shc expression suppress the ability of Jurkat T cells to form ISs. (A). Immunofluorescence analysis of F-actin, CD3ζ and p-Tyr <lb/>in Jurkat T cells mixed with B cells purified from buffy coats of healthy donors (HD B) or peripheral blood of CLL patients with p66Shc expression above <lb/>(high-p66) or below (low-p66) threshold (0.25 median ddCt value, see Supplementary Figure S1A), pulsed with SEE and incubated for 15 min at 37 °C. Data <lb/>are expressed as % of 15-min SEE-specific conjugates harboring staining at the IS (≥50 cells/sample, n independent experiments≥3). One-way <lb/>ANOVA test; *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ 0.00001. Representative images (medial optical sections) of the Jurkat T cell/B cell conjugates are <lb/>shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. (B). Correlation between F-actin + , CD3ζ + and p-Tyr + Jurkat/B conjugates shown in (A) and mRNA levels of p66Shc in CLL cells <lb/>used in the respective IS experiments (n = 21). Simple linear regression; p ≤ 0.05 statistically significant. (C). Flow cytometric analysis of ERK1/ <lb/>2 phosphorylation in Jurkat T cells mixed with SEE-pulsed B cells purified from buffy coats of either healthy donors (HD B, n = 6) or peripheral blood of <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>tyrosine phosphoprotein (p-Tyr) staining at the Jurkat T/CLL <lb/>interface (Figure 1A). The frequency of conjugates displaying <lb/>TCR/CD3 staining at the IS, which in Jurkat cells is mainly <lb/>represented by a pool of TCR/CD3 complexes associated with <lb/>recycling endosomes which moves beneath the synaptic <lb/>membrane as a result of centrosome polarization (Soares et al., <lb/>2013; Onnis and Baldari, 2019) was also impaired (Figure 1A). <lb/>Moreover, IS formation was significantly decreased in conjugates of <lb/>Jurkat T cells with CLL cells with p66Shc expression below threshold <lb/>compared to conjugates formed with CLL cells with p66Shc <lb/>expression above threshold (Figure 1A). The frequency of <lb/>F-actin + , TCR/CD3 + and p-Tyr + conjugates significantly <lb/>correlated with the residual p66Shc expression in CLL cells <lb/>(Figure 1B), suggesting that the residual p66Shc expression in <lb/>CLL cells affects their ability to form ISs with T cells. In <lb/>agreement with their lowest p66Shc expression (Supplementary <lb/>Figure S1B) (Capitani et al., 2010; Capitani et al., 2019; Patrussi <lb/>et al., 2021a), U-CLL cells showed a significant impairment in the <lb/>frequency of F-actin + , TCR/CD3 + and p-Tyr + conjugates with Jurkat <lb/>T cells when compared to M-CLL cells (Supplementary Figure S1C). <lb/>We then assessed whether the defective ability of CLL cells to <lb/>form ISs with T cells also affects the activation state of downstream <lb/>TCR signaling mediators. Phosphorylation of the mitogen-activated <lb/>protein kinase ERK (phospho-ERK1/2) was impaired in Jurkat <lb/>T cells conjugated with CLL cells with p66Shc expression above <lb/>threshold when compared to Jurkat T cells conjugated with healthy <lb/>B cells (Figure 1C), with a significant further decrease in conjugates <lb/>of Jurkat T cells with CLL cells with p66Shc expression below <lb/>threshold (Figure 1C). A similar impairment was observed when <lb/>nuclear translocation of the transcription factor NF-AT was <lb/>quantified by immunofluorescence in Jurkat T cells transiently <lb/>transfected with a vector encoding the GFP-NF-AT fusion <lb/>protein and then conjugated with either healthy B cells or CLL <lb/>cells (Figure 1D). Our results demonstrate that the p66Shc-<lb/>dependent IS defects observed in Jurkat T cells conjugated with <lb/>CLL cells also affect downstream mediators of TCR signaling. <lb/>Defects in TCR signaling and IS formation result in impaired <lb/>cytotoxic T cell (CTL) effector functions in CLL (Riches et al., 2013). <lb/>We asked whether the p66Shc-dependent IS defects may result in <lb/>impaired CTL-mediated killing. To address this point, CD8 + cells <lb/>were immunopurified from buffy coats of healthy donors and <lb/>differentiated to CTLs (Onnis et al., 2023). Similar to Jurkat <lb/>T cells (Figure 1A), CTLs showed impaired ability to form ISs <lb/>with CLL cells, with the highest impairment observed in conjugates <lb/>formed with CLL cells with p66Shc expression below threshold <lb/>(Figure 2A). Killing activity was then quantified in CFSE-stained <lb/>CTLs incubated with SAg-pulsed leukemic or healthy B cells for 4 h, <lb/>followed by flow cytometric analysis of propidium iodide-stained <lb/>B cells. Consistent with the IS defects, CLL cells suppressed the <lb/>ability of CTLs to kill target cells, with the highest suppressive <lb/>activity harbored by CLL cells with p66Shc expression below <lb/>threshold (Figure 2B). <lb/>Taken together, our data demonstrate that leukemic cells from <lb/>patients with aggressive disease presentation and the lowest residual <lb/>p66Shc expression suppress the ability of T lymphocytes to form ISs, <lb/>to activate the TCR-dependent signaling pathway and to execute <lb/>their effector functions. <lb/>3.2 The enhanced PD-L1 expression in CLL <lb/>cells is caused at least in part by their <lb/>p66Shc defect <lb/>Multiple inhibitory ligands that are upregulated in CLL cells <lb/>have been implicated in the suppression of IS formation and <lb/>T cell effector functions, among which the PD-1 ligand PD-L1 <lb/>(Ramsay et al., 2008; Riches et al., 2013). Accordingly, leukemic <lb/>cells isolated from our CLL patient cohort express enhanced <lb/>mRNA and surface PD-L1 compared to healthy B cells <lb/>(Figure 3A). Moreover, both mRNA and surface expression of <lb/>PD-L1 inversely correlated with the ability of leukemic B cells to <lb/>form ISs with Jurkat T cells (Figure 3B, Supplementary Figure <lb/>S2). To confirm the inverse relationship between PD-L1 <lb/>expression in leukemic cells and IS formation, SEE-pulsed <lb/>CLL cells were conjugated with Jurkat T cells in the presence <lb/>of anti-PD-L1 neutralizing antibodies. PD-L1 neutralization <lb/>recovered IS formation, as shown by the enhanced frequency <lb/>of F-actin + , CD3ζ + and p-Tyr + conjugates (Figure 3C). Moreover, <lb/>PD-L1 blockade recovered the killing activity of CTLs toward <lb/>SAg-pulsed CLL cells (Figure 3D), further supporting the notion <lb/>that the suppressive activity of CLL cells relies at least in part on <lb/>their PD-L1 expression levels. <lb/>P66Shc deficiency in CLL cells impinges on the expression of a <lb/>number of CLL-critical genes, including genes encoding lymphoid <lb/>homing receptors, and cytokines such as IL-9 (Capitani et al., 2012; <lb/>Patrussi et al., 2015; Patrussi et al., 2021a; Tatangelo et al., 2022). We <lb/>asked whether it also promotes PD-L1 expression in CLL cells. Both <lb/>mRNA and surface PD-L1 were significantly enhanced in low-<lb/>p66Shc compared to high-p66Shc CLL cells (Figure 4A). <lb/>Moreover, PD-L1 expression inversely correlated with the <lb/>residual p66Shc expression in CLL cells (Figure 3B). In <lb/>agreement with their lowest p66Shc expression (Supplementary <lb/>Figure S1B) (Capitani et al., 2010; Capitani et al., 2019; Patrussi <lb/>et al., 2021a), U-CLL cells showed a significant enhancement in PD-<lb/>L1 <lb/>expression <lb/>when <lb/>compared <lb/>to <lb/>M-CLL <lb/>cells <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S3A). <lb/>FIGURE 1 (Continued) <lb/>CLL patients with p66Shc expression above (high-p66, n = 4) or below (low-p66, n = 6) threshold, incubated for 15 min at 37 °C and stained with anti-<lb/>CD3 and anti-phospho-ERK1/2 antibodies. Unstimulated Jurkat T cells (ns) were used as control. One-way ANOVA test; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ <lb/>0.00001. (D). Immunofluorescence analysis of NF-AT nuclear translocation in Jurkat T cells transiently transfected with a vector encoding GFP-NF-AT, <lb/>then mixed with either healthy B cells (HD B, n = 6) or leukemic cells from CLL patients with p66Shc expression above (high-p66, n = 6) or below <lb/>(low-p66, n = 6) threshold, incubated for 1 h at 37 °C, and stained with anti-GFP antibodies. Unstimulated Jurkat T cell transfectants either unstimulated <lb/>(ns) or stimulated for 30 min with 1 μg/mL A23187 (A23) were used as negative and positive controls, respectively. Data are expressed as % of cells with <lb/>total GFP staining in the nuclei. Representative images (medial optical sections) are shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. MFI±SD. One-way ANOVA test; **p ≤ 0.01; <lb/>***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ 0.00001. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 2 <lb/>CLL cells with low p66Shc expression suppress IS formation and killing activities of CTLs. (A). Immunofluorescence analysis of F-actin, CD3ζ and p-Tyr <lb/>in CD8 + cells purified from buffy coats (n = 2), stimulated with anti-CD3/CD28 mAb-coated beads + IL-2 for 48 h and mixed with B cells purified from buffy coats <lb/>of healthy donors (HD B, n = 4) or peripheral blood of CLL patients with p66Shc expression above (high-p66, n = 4) or below (low-p66 n = 4) threshold <lb/>(0.25 median ddCt value, see Supplementary Figure S1A), pulsed with a combination of SEA, SEB, and SEE (SAgs) and incubated for 15 min at 37 °C. Data are <lb/>expressed as % of 15-min SAg-specific conjugates harboring staining at the IS (≥50 cells/sample). One-way ANOVA test; *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001; <lb/>****p ≤ 0.00001. Representative images (medial optical sections) of the CTL/B cell conjugates are shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. (B). Flow cytometric analysis of target <lb/>cell killing by CFSE-labelled CTLs, using as targets SAg-loaded B cells purified from buffy coats of healthy donors (HD B, n = 19) or peripheral blood of CLL patients <lb/>with p66Shc expression above (high-p66, n = 5) or below (low-p66, n = 6) threshold, at a T:B cell ratio 10:1. Cells were cocultured for 4 h and stained with <lb/>propidium iodide prior to processing for flow cytometry. Analyses were carried out gating on CFSE -/PI + cells. The histogram shows the percentage (%) of target <lb/>cells lysed. One-way ANOVA test; *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ****p ≤ 0.00001. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>These results were recapitulated in the Eμ-TCL1 mouse model of <lb/>CLL (Bichi et al., 2002), where leukemic cells that accumulate in <lb/>aged mice show decreased expression of p66Shc and prolonged <lb/>survival (Patrussi et al., 2019). Both mRNA and surface PD-L1 were <lb/>enhanced in leukemic cells isolated from spleens of Eμ-TCL1 mice <lb/>compared to wild-type mice (Figure 4C), especially those with the <lb/>worst disease presentation (&gt;40% CD5 + CD19 + IgM + cells in <lb/>peripheral blood (Patrussi et al., 2019)) (Supplementary Figure <lb/>S3B), and inversely correlated to p66Shc mRNA expression <lb/>(Figure 4D). The tight correlation between p66Shc and PD-L1 <lb/>expression in Eμ-TCL1 mice is corroborated by the further <lb/>increase in the amounts of PD-L1 displayed by leukemic cells <lb/>isolated from spleens of Eμ-TCL1/p66 -/-mice (Figures 4C,D). <lb/>Hence, the p66Shc defect accounts at least in part for the <lb/>enhanced PD-L1 expression in CLL cells. <lb/>We asked whether p66Shc reconstitution in CLL cells could <lb/>normalize PD-L1 expression and IS formation. Leukemic cells <lb/>were isolated from CLL patients and transiently nucleofected <lb/>with vectors encoding p66Shc (p66). Cells transfected with <lb/>empty vector were used as control (vect) (Figure 4E). <lb/>Reconstitution of CLL cells with wild-type p66Shc decreased <lb/>PD-L1 expression compared to the empty vector control <lb/>(Figures 4E,F). Notably, p66Shc reconstitution did not affect <lb/>the expression of the inhibitory ligands CD200, CD276 and <lb/>CD270 (Supplementary Figure S4) which, similar to PD-L1, are <lb/>upregulated in CLL cells and contribute to the IS defects <lb/>observed in CLL (Ramsay et al., 2012), ruling them out as <lb/>mediators of the p66Shc-dependent IS dysfunctions. <lb/>Transfectants were then pulsed with SEE and conjugated <lb/>with Jurkat T cells. Reconstitution of CLL cells with p66Shc <lb/>significantly enhanced IS formation, as shown by the increased <lb/>frequency of conjugates displaying F-actin, TCR/CD3 and <lb/>p-Tyr staining at the Jurkat T/CLL interface (Figure 4G). <lb/>Altogether, our results support the notion that the p66Shc <lb/>defect in CLL cells contributes to their IS-suppressive <lb/>activities by modulating PD-L1 expression. <lb/>3.3 The pro-oxidant activity of p66Shc <lb/>controls PD-L1 expression in CLL cells <lb/>We have recently reported that p66Shc modulates gene <lb/>expression through its ROS-elevating activity (Tatangelo et al., <lb/>2022). To address the potential role of the pro-oxidant activity of <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>PD-L1 overexpression in CLL cells impairs IS formation with Jurkat T cells. (A) qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA (left) and flow cytometric analysis of <lb/>surface (right) expression of PD-L1 in B cells purified from buffy coats of healthy donors (HD B, n = 12) or peripheral blood of CLL patients (CLL B, n = 52). A <lb/>representative flow cytometric histogram is shown. Mann-Whitney Rank Sum test; **p ≤ 0.01; ****p ≤ 0.00001. (B). Correlation between F-actin + Jurkat/ <lb/>CLL B conjugates shown in Figure 1A and mRNA (left) and surface (right) levels of PD-L1 shown in (A) (n = 21). Simple linear regression; p ≤ <lb/>0.05 statistically significant. (C). Immunofluorescence analysis of F-actin, CD3ζ and p-Tyr in Jurkat T cells mixed with B cells purified from peripheral <lb/>blood of CLL patients, pulsed with SEE and incubated for 15 min at 37 °C either in the absence or in the presence of anti-PD-L1 neutralizing antibodies. <lb/>Data are expressed as % of 15-min SEE-specific conjugates harboring staining at the IS (≥50 cells/sample, n independent experiments = 3). Paired t-test; <lb/>*p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01. Representative images (medial optical sections) of the Jurkat T cell/B cell conjugates are shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. (D). Flow <lb/>cytometric analysis of target cell killing by CFSE-labelled healthy CTLs (n buffy coats = 3), using as targets B cells purified from peripheral blood of CLL <lb/>patients (ratio T:B cells 10:1), pulsed with SAgs either in the absence or in the presence of anti-PD-L1 neutralizing antibodies. Cells were cocultured for 4 h <lb/>and stained with propidium iodide prior to processing for flow cytometry. Analyses were carried out gating on CFSE -/PI + cells. The histogram shows the <lb/>percentage (%) of target cells lysed (n CLL patients = 6). One-way ANOVA test; ****p ≤ 0.00001. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 4 <lb/>The p66Shc defect accounts for PD-L1 overexpression in CLL cells. (A) qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA (left) and flow cytometric analysis of surface (right) <lb/>expression of PD-L1 in B cells purified from buffy coats of healthy donors (HD B, n = 12) or peripheral blood of CLL patients with p66Shc expression above (high-p66, <lb/>n = 26) or below (low-p66, n = 26) threshold (0.25 median ddCt value, see Supplementary Figure S1A). A representative flow cytometric histogram is shown. One-<lb/>way ANOVA test; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ 0.00001. (B). Correlation between mRNA (left) and surface (right) levels of PD-L1 shown in (A) and mRNA <lb/>levels of p66Shc in CLL cells (n = 21). Simple linear regression; p ≤ 0.05 statistically significant. (C). qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA (letf) and flow cytometric analysis of <lb/>surface (right) expression of PD-L1 in B cells isolated from spleens of either wild-type (n = 10), Eμ-TCL1 (n = 14) or Eμ-TCL1/p66Shc -/-(n = 13) mice. Representative <lb/>flow cytometric histograms are shown (Mann Whitney Rank Sum test). *p ≤ 0.05; ***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ 0.0001. (D). Correlation between mRNA (left) and surface <lb/>(right) levels of PD-L1 shown in C and mRNA levels of p66Shc in B cells isolated from Eμ-TCL1 mice (n = 14). Simple linear regression; p ≤ 0.05 statistically significant. <lb/>(E). qRT-PCR analysis of p66Shc mRNA in B cells purified from CLL patients and transfected with either empty (vect) or p66Shc-encoding (p66) vectors (n = 19; <lb/>paired t-test, ****p ≤ 0.0001). (F). qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA (left) and flow cytometric analysis of surface (right) expression of PD-L1 in B cells purified from CLL <lb/>patients and transfected with either empty (vect) or p66Shc-encoding (p66) vectors (n ≥ 9; paired t-test, **; p ≤ 0.01). (G). Immunofluorescence analysis of F-actin, <lb/>CD3ζ and p-Tyr in Jurkat T cells mixed with B cells purified from peripheral blood of CLL patients and transfected with either empty (vect) or p66Shc-encoding (p66) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>p66Shc in PD-L1 expression, we used MEC-1 cells, which do not <lb/>express p66Shc due to promoter methylation (Cattaneo et al., 2016), <lb/>stably transfected with either empty vector (ctr), or wild-type <lb/>p66Shc (p66), or a ROS-defective p66Shc mutant carrying E to Q <lb/>substitutions at positions 132-133 (p66QQ) (Tatangelo et al., 2022) <lb/>(Figure 5A). Flow cytometric analysis of homeostatic ROS <lb/>production in the CM-H 2 DCFDA-loaded MEC-1 transfectants <lb/>confirmed an enhanced ROS production in p66Shc-expressing <lb/>cells, but not in cells expressing p66ShcQQ, compared to control <lb/>cells (Figure 5B). PD-L1 expression was strongly decreased in the <lb/>MEC transfectant expressing wild-type p66Shc compared to the <lb/>empty vector control, as assessed by immunoblot and flow <lb/>cytometry (Figures 5C,D). Interestingly, at variance with wild-<lb/>type p66Shc, expression of the ROS-defective p66Shc mutant did <lb/>not affect PD-L1 expression (Figures 5C,D), suggesting that p66Shc <lb/>regulates PD-L1 expression through its ROS-elevating activity. <lb/>By elevating intracellular ROS, p66Shc suppresses the <lb/>transcriptional activity of NF-κB (Tatangelo et al., 2022). <lb/>Since PD-L1 expression is regulated by NF-κB (Lim et al., <lb/>2016; Antonangeli et al., 2020), we asked whether the p66Shc-<lb/>and ROS-dependent PD-L1 reduction is mediated by NF-κB. To <lb/>address this point, PD-L1 expression was quantified by flow <lb/>cytometry in MEC-1 transfectants treated for 24 h with 1 μM <lb/>IT-901, a NF-κB inhibitor that has been proven efficient in <lb/>inhibiting the transcriptional activity of NF-κB in CLL cells <lb/>(Vaisitti et al., 2017). In agreement with previous results <lb/>(Tatangelo et al., 2022), NF-κB activation, assessed by flow <lb/>cytometric analysis of transfectants using anti-phospho-NF-κB <lb/>p65 (Ser536) antibodies, was significantly impaired in the <lb/>p66 transfectant, (Supplementary Figure S5A). IT-901 reduced <lb/>NF-κB phosphorylation (SSupplementary Figure S5A) in the <lb/>control transfectant to levels similar to p66Shc-expressing cells <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S1A, B). Interestingly, NF-κB inhibition <lb/>in control cells strongly decreased PD-L1 expression <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S1B). The ROS-defective p66Shc <lb/>mutant p66QQ did not affect either NF-κB phosphorylation <lb/>or PD-L1 expression (Supplementary Figure S5A, B). Hence, <lb/>NF-κB inhibition elicited by reconstitution of wild-type p66Shc, <lb/>but not the ROS-defective p66QQ mutant, suppresses PD-L1 <lb/>expression. <lb/>To validate these findings in CLL cells, where low intracellular <lb/>ROS are causally associated to their p66Shc expression defect <lb/>(Patrussi et al., 2019; Tatangelo et al., 2022), leukemic cells <lb/>isolated from CLL patients were transiently nucleofected with <lb/>vectors encoding either wild-type p66Shc (p66) or the ROS <lb/>defective p66ShcQQ mutant (p66QQ) (Figure 5E) and PD-L1 <lb/>expression was assessed by flow cytometry 24 h after transfection. <lb/>In agreement with our previous results (Patrussi et al., 2019), <lb/>reconstitution of CLL cells with wild-type p66Shc, but not with <lb/>the p66ShcQQ mutant, enhanced intracellular ROS compared to the <lb/>empty vector control (Figure 5F). Under these conditions, PD-L1 <lb/>expression was selectively downregulated in the presence of wild-<lb/>type p66Shc (Figure 5G). <lb/>Interestingly, the NF-κB inhibitor IT-901 decreased PD-L1 <lb/>expression in CLL cells transfected with either empty vector or <lb/>vector encoding the ROS-defective p66ShcQQ mutant to levels <lb/>similar to CLL cells transfected with wild-type p66Shc <lb/>(Supplementary Figure S5C, D), supporting the notion that, by <lb/>restoring ROS production, forced p66Shc expression in CLL cells <lb/>hampers NF-κB activation, thereby lowering their abnormal PD-L1 <lb/>expression. <lb/>Our data suggest that PD-L1 overexpression in CLL cells can <lb/>be counteracted by enhancing intracellular ROS levels. To further <lb/>corroborate this notion, we measured PD-L1 in CLL cells treated <lb/>for 24 h with 100 μM H 2 O 2 as exogenous source of ROS. This <lb/>treatment reduced PD-L1 expression (Figures 5H,I) and <lb/>recovered their ability to form ISs with Jurkat T cells <lb/>(Figure 5L). Taken together, these results demonstrate that the <lb/>p66Shc-dependent decrease in intracellular ROS in CLL cells <lb/>enhances NF-κB transcriptional activity, which in turn <lb/>contributes to promote PD-L1 expression, thereby suppressing <lb/>their ability to form ISs with T lymphocytes. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>The incomplete knowledge concerning the molecular <lb/>circuitries that fuel disease progression in the tumoral <lb/>microenvironment makes the management of CLL challenging <lb/>(Arruga et al., 2020). Both direct and indirect mechanisms <lb/>implemented in the lymphoid niche converge to promote <lb/>leukemic cell survival and resistance to therapy (Burger and <lb/>Gribben, 2014; Allegra et al., 2020; Patrussi et al., 2021b; <lb/>Capitani et al., 2021). Some of them are focused on disabling <lb/>the anti-tumoral activities of T lymphocytes by hampering their <lb/>ability to form ISs with leukemic cells and to selectively kill them <lb/>in an antigen-dependent manner (Ramsay et al., 2008; Burger <lb/>and Gribben, 2014; Capitani et al., 2021). In the tumor <lb/>microenvironment of CLL both the conversion of functional <lb/>to exhausted T cells overexpressing the exhaustion marker <lb/>PD-1 (Riches et al., 2013), and PD-L1 overexpression on the <lb/>surface of leukemic cells, concur to exacerbate the physiological <lb/>PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitory axis and hamper TCR-mediated T cell <lb/>activation (Riches et al., 2013). The molecular mechanisms <lb/>underlying PD-L1 overexpression in CLL cells remain to be <lb/>clarified. Here we demonstrate that the profound defect in the <lb/>expression of the pro-apoptotic and pro-oxidant adaptor p66Shc <lb/>in CLL cells (Capitani et al., 2010) accounts at least in part for <lb/>their enhanced expression of PD-L1. The p66Shc-dependent PD-<lb/>L1 increase in CLL cells in turn prevents T lymphocytes from <lb/>FIGURE 4 (Continued) <lb/>vectors, pulsed with SEE and incubated for 15 min at 37 °C. Data are expressed as % of 15-min SEE-specific conjugates harboring staining at the IS <lb/>(≥50 cells/sample, n = 4). Paired t-test; *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01. Representative images (medial optical sections) of the Jurkat T cell/B cell conjugates are <lb/>shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 5 <lb/>The p66Shc deficiency-related impairment in homeostatic ROS contributes to the enhanced PD-L1 expression in CLL cells. (A). Immunoblot <lb/>analysis with anti-Shc antibodies of postnuclear supernatants of MEC-1 cells stably transfected with empty vector (ctr) or with a vector encoding either <lb/>wild-type (p66) or mutated (p66QQ) p66Shc. The stripped filters were reprobed with anti-actin antibodies. Molecular weights (kDa) are indicated on the <lb/>right of the panel. The quantification of three independent experiments is shown on the right. (B). Flow cytometric analysis of ROS intracellular <lb/>content in MEC-1 transfectants stained with CM-H 2 DCFDA (n independent experiments ≥5). (C). Immunoblot analysis with anti-PD-L1 antibodies of <lb/>postnuclear supernatants of MEC-1 transfectants. The stripped filters were reprobed with anti-actin antibodies. Molecular weight markers (kDa) are <lb/>indicated on the right of the panel. The quantification of three independent experiments is shown on the right. (D). Flow cytometric analysis of surface <lb/>expression of PD-L1 in MEC-1 transfectants (n ≥ 5). (E). qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA expression of p66Shc in cells purified from CLL patients and <lb/>transfected with empty vector (ctr) or with a vector encoding either wild-type (p66) or mutated (p66QQ) p66Shc (n = 4). F, (G). Flow cytometric analysis of <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<body>forming ISs with leukemic cells themselves, thereby facilitating <lb/>the evasion of leukemic cells from T cell-mediated surveillance. <lb/>Notwithstanding the fact that PD-L1 expression correlates with <lb/>disease stage and prognosis in some tumoral contexts, among which <lb/>lung adenocarcinoma, nasopharyngeal carcinoma and non-small cell <lb/>lung cancer (Nie et al., 2021; Zhou et al., 2023), the relationship between <lb/>surface PD-L1 and disease parameters remains largely unknown. Here <lb/>we demonstrated that leukemic cells from U-CLL patients, that develop <lb/>aggressive forms of the disease (Kipps et al., 2017), as well as from Eμ-<lb/>TCL1 mice with overt leukemia, express the highest surface amounts of <lb/>PD-L1 and harbor the most relevant IS-suppressive activity. These <lb/>results provide new evidence of the relationship between disease stage <lb/>and PD-L1 expression in CLL, and suggest that p66Shc deficiency in <lb/>CLL cells from patients with aggressive disease impinges in T cell <lb/>suppression by enhancing PD-L1 expression. <lb/>Genetic aberrations, such as ionizing radiation-induced double <lb/>strand breaks, have been implicated in PD-L1 overexpression in <lb/>cancer cells (Zhou et al., 2023). Moreover, pro-inflammatory stimuli <lb/>such as interferons, as well as altered oncogenic signaling pathways, <lb/>among which the Ras/mitogen activated protein kinase (MAPK) and <lb/>the Phosphatidyl inositol-3-kinase (PI3K)/Akt pathways, also promote <lb/>PD-L1 overexpression (Zhou et al., 2023). Interestingly, a complex <lb/>interplay between intracellular ROS and PD-L1 expression in cancer <lb/>cells has recently come to light (Bailly, 2020). Depending on their <lb/>targets, ROS either up-or downregulate PD-L1 expression in cancer <lb/>cells. ROS-elevating hypoxic conditions, that promote both expression, <lb/>activation and stabilization of the transcription factors HIF-1α, NF-κB <lb/>and Yes-associated protein 1 (Yap1) (Kang et al., 2020), are frequently <lb/>associated to elevated membrane expression of PD-L1 on cancer cells of <lb/>solid tumors such as pulmonary pleomorphic carcinoma (Chang et al., <lb/>2016), endometrial cancer (Tawadros and Khalafalla, 2018) and non-<lb/>small-cell lung cancer (Guo et al., 2019). However, pro-oxidant drugs <lb/>such as the biguanide compounds metformin and phenformin, that <lb/>induce oxidative stress-mediated cancer cell apoptosis (Zhao et al., <lb/>2019), attenuate PD-L1 expression via the Hippo signaling pathway in <lb/>colorectal cancer and melanoma (Zhang et al., 2019). In B lymphocytes, <lb/>p66Shc has a frank ROS-elevating activity which modulates the <lb/>expression of genes encoding trafficking receptors such as <lb/>CCR7 and S1PR1 (Capitani et al., 2012; Patrussi et al., 2019; <lb/>Patrussi et al., 2020). We have recently shown that the p66Shc <lb/>expression defect in CLL cells leads to a decrease in the intracellular <lb/>ROS levels, which in turn abnormally enhance the transcriptional <lb/>activity of the ROS-sensitive p65 subunit of NF-κB (Tatangelo et al., <lb/>2022) and promotes IL-9 release by CLL cells (Patrussi et al., 2021a), <lb/>thereby contributing to shape the tumor niche to a pro-survival one <lb/>(Patrussi et al., 2021a; Patrussi et al., 2021b). Here we demonstrate that <lb/>the p66Shc-dependent ROS defect also controls PD-L1 overexpression <lb/>in CLL cells. We moreover provide evidence that the drop in <lb/>intracellular ROS levels of CLL cells indirectly impinges on leukemic <lb/>cell survival not only by promoting their recruitment to and entrapment <lb/>in the pro-survival stromal niche (Capitani et al., 2012; Patrussi et al., <lb/>2021a; Tatangelo et al., 2022), but also by preventing T cells from <lb/>forming ISs with leukemic cells, thereby suppressing their anti-tumor <lb/>activities. Hence, therapeutical approaches able to restore intracellular <lb/>ROS might be explored to overcome PD-L1 overexpression and T cell <lb/>dysfunctions in CLL. <lb/>It is however noteworthy that ROS are highly reactive compounds <lb/>whose intracellular concentration must be tightly controlled to avoid <lb/>protein, DNA, and lipid damage. (Yu et al., 2020). Direct <lb/>pharmacological targeting of cell-intrinsic ROS-modulating enzymes <lb/>in CLL cells might therefore be hardly feasible due to uncontrolled side <lb/>effects (Wang et al., 2021). Here we demonstrate that reconstitution of <lb/>p66Shc, whose expression is profoundly impaired in CLL cells (Capitani <lb/>et al., 2010), but not of the ROS-defective p66ShcQQ mutant, leads to <lb/>an elevation in intracellular ROS and normalizes PD-L1 expression, <lb/>restoring the ability of T cells to form ISs with leukemic cells by <lb/>removing one of the most important TCR signaling blocks. <lb/>Immunotherapy with Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR)-<lb/>engineered T cells has emerged as a promising treatment option for <lb/>high-risk relapsed/refractory CLL patients (Cassioli et al., 2022). <lb/>However, as opposed to other B cell malignancies such as B-ALL <lb/>(Maude et al., 2018) and large B cell lymphoma (Locke et al., 2019), <lb/>where it has already been approved for clinical application, the <lb/>beneficial use of CAR T cells in CLL is still debated and the <lb/>number of CAR T cell-treated CLL patients who reached complete <lb/>remission in the context of clinical trials is still limited (Cassioli et al., <lb/>2022). Although the reason for this therapeutic failure remains to be <lb/>elucidated, the molecular mechanisms implemented by tumoral cells to <lb/>overexpress inhibitory ligands such as PD-L1 and to suppress IS <lb/>formation and anti-tumoral activities of T cells may contribute to <lb/>also suppress CAR T cells. An in-depth understanding of the <lb/>mechanisms exploited by CLL cells to enhance their IS-suppressive <lb/>potential and turn off T cell (and CAR T cell) anti-tumor activity is <lb/>therefore warranted to expand our treatment options. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included in <lb/>the article/Supplementary Material, further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by the Ethics <lb/>commettees of the Universities of Siena and Padua. The studies were <lb/>conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional <lb/></div>

	<body>FIGURE 5 (Continued) <lb/>ROS intracellular content (F) and surface expression of PD-L1 (G) in CLL cell transfectants (F): n = 6; (G); n = 4). (A-G): One-way ANOVA test; *p ≤ <lb/>0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001; ****p ≤ 0.00001. (H, I). Flow cytometric analysis of ROS intracellular content (H) and surface expression of PD-L1 (I) in <lb/>B cells purified from peripheral blood of CLL patients, either untreated or treated for 6 h (H); n = 6) or 24 h (I); n = 6) with 100 μM H 2 O 2 . (J). <lb/>Immunofluorescence analysis of F-actin in Jurkat T cells mixed with B cells purified from peripheral blood of CLL patients and treated for 24 h with <lb/>100 μM H 2 O 2 , pulsed with SEE and incubated for 15 min at 37 °C. Data are expressed as % of 15-min SEE-specific conjugates harboring staining at the IS <lb/>(≥50 cells/sample, n = 4). (H-J): Paired t-test; *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001. Representative images (medial optical sections) of the Jurkat T cell/B cell <lb/>conjugates are shown. Scale bar, 5 μm. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>12 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<div type="annex">requirements. The participants provided their written informed <lb/>consent to participate in this study. The animal study was <lb/>approved by Ethics commettee of the University of Siena. The <lb/>study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and <lb/>institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>LL: Investigation, Writing-original draft. NC: Investigation, <lb/>Writing-original draft. VT: Investigation, Writing-original draft. <lb/>CT: Investigation, Writing-original draft. GB: Investigation, <lb/>Writing-original draft. FF: Investigation, Resources, Writing-review <lb/>and editing. AV: Investigation, Resources, Writing-review and editing. <lb/>GM: Resources, Writing-review and editing. SC: Resources, <lb/>Writing-original draft. AG: Resources, Writing-review and editing. <lb/>MB: Resources, Writing-review and editing. LT: Resources, <lb/>Writing-review and editing. CB: Conceptualization, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Methodology, Resources, Supervision, Writing-review <lb/>and editing, Project administration. LP: Conceptualization, Data <lb/>curation, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing-review <lb/>and editing, Formal Analysis, Project administration. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received <lb/>for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this <lb/>article. The research leading to these results has received <lb/>funding from AIRC under IG 2017 -ID. 20148 -and <lb/>Regione Toscana, ID. PRECISE-CLL-to Cosima Baldari. <lb/>This work was also supported by grants from AIRC to LT <lb/>(IG-25024) and ERC Synergy (Grant Agreement ERC 951329) <lb/>to Cosima Baldari. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board <lb/>member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no <lb/>impact on the peer review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and <lb/>do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or <lb/>those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that <lb/>may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Alarcón, B., Mestre, D., and Martínez-Martín, N. (2011). The immunological synapse: <lb/>a cause or consequence of T-cell receptor triggering? Immunology 133, 420-425. doi:10. <lb/>1111/j.1365-2567.2011.03458.x <lb/>Allegra, A., Musolino, C., Tonacci, A., Pioggia, G., Casciaro, M., and Gangemi, S. <lb/>(2020). Clinico-biological implications of modified levels of cytokines in chronic <lb/>lymphocytic leukemia: a possible therapeutic role. Cancers (Basel) 12, 524. doi:10. <lb/>3390/cancers12020524 <lb/>Antonangeli, F., Natalini, A., Garassino, M. C., Sica, A., Santoni, A., and Di Rosa, F. <lb/>(2020). Regulation of PD-L1 expression by NF-κB in cancer. Front. Immunol. 11, <lb/>584626. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2020.584626 <lb/>Arasanz, H., Gato-Cañas, M., Zuazo, M., Ibañez-Vea, M., Breckpot, K., Kochan, G., <lb/>et al. (2017). PD1 signal transduction pathways in T cells. Oncotarget 8, 51936-51945. <lb/>doi:10.18632/ONCOTARGET.17232 <lb/>Arruga, F., Gyau, B. B., Iannello, A., Vitale, N., Vaisitti, T., and Deaglio, S. (2020). <lb/>Immune response dysfunction in chronic lymphocytic leukemia: dissecting molecular <lb/>mechanisms and microenvironmental conditions. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 21, 1825. doi:10.3390/ <lb/>ijms21051825 <lb/>Bailly, C. (2020). Regulation of PD-L1 expression on cancer cells with ROS-<lb/>modulating drugs. Life Sci. 246, 117403. doi:10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117403 <lb/>Beyer, M., Kochanek, M., Darabi, K., Popov, A., Jensen, M., Endl, E., et al. (2005). <lb/>Reduced frequencies and suppressive function of CD4+CD25 hi regulatory T cells in <lb/>patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia after therapy with fludarabine. Blood 106, <lb/>2018-2025. doi:10.1182/blood-2005-02-0642 <lb/>Bichi, R., Shinton, S. A., Martin, E. S., Koval, A., Calin, G. A., Cesari, R., et al. (2002). <lb/>Human chronic lymphocytic leukemia modeled in mouse by targeted TCL1 expression. <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 99, 6955-6960. doi:10.1073/pnas.102181599 <lb/>Brusa, D., Serra, S., Coscia, M., Rossi, D., D&apos;Arena, G., Laurenti, L., et al. (2013). The <lb/>PD-1/PD-L1 axis contributes to T-cell dysfunction in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. <lb/>Haematologica 98, 953-963. doi:10.3324/haematol.2012.077537 <lb/>Burger, J. A., and Gribben, J. G. (2014). The microenvironment in chronic <lb/>lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) and other B cell malignancies: insight into disease <lb/>biology and new targeted therapies. Semin. Cancer Biol. 24, 71-81. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>semcancer.2013.08.011 <lb/>Capitani, N., Lori, G., Paoli, P., Patrussi, L., Troilo, A., Baldari, C. T., et al. (2019). <lb/>LMW-PTP targeting potentiates the effects of drugs used in chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukemia therapy. Cancer Cell Int. 19, 67. doi:10.1186/s12935-019-0786-1 <lb/>Capitani, N., Lucherini, O. M., Sozzi, E., Ferro, M., Giommoni, N., Finetti, F., et al. <lb/>(2010). Impaired expression of p66Shc, a novel regulator of B-cell survival, in chronic <lb/>lymphocytic leukemia. Blood 115, 3726-3736. doi:10.1182/blood-2009-08-239244 <lb/>Capitani, N., Patrussi, L., and Baldari, C. T. (2021). Nature vs. Nurture: the two <lb/>opposing behaviors of cytotoxic t lymphocytes in the tumor microenvironment. Int. <lb/>J. Mol. Sci. 22, 11221. doi:10.3390/ijms222011221 <lb/>Capitani, N., Patrussi, L., Trentin, L., Lucherini, O. M., Cannizzaro, E., Migliaccio, E., <lb/>et al. (2012). S1P1 expression is controlled by the pro-oxidant activity of p66Shc and is <lb/>impaired in B-CLL patients with unfavorable prognosis. Blood 120, 4391-4399. doi:10. <lb/>1182/blood-2012-04-425959 <lb/>Cassioli, C., and Baldari, C. T. (2022). Lymphocyte polarization during immune <lb/>synapse assembly: centrosomal actin joins the game. Front. Immunol. 13, 830835. <lb/>doi:10.3389/fimmu.2022.830835 <lb/>Cassioli, C., Onnis, A., Finetti, F., Capitani, N., Brunetti, J., Compeer, E. B., et al. <lb/>(2021). The Bardet-Biedl syndrome complex component BBS1 controls T cell polarity <lb/>during immune synapse assembly. J. Cell Sci. 134, jcs258462. doi:10.1242/jcs.258462 <lb/>Cassioli, C., Patrussi, L., Valitutti, S., and Baldari, C. T. (2022). Learning from TCR <lb/>signaling and immunological synapse assembly to build new chimeric antigen receptors <lb/>(CARs). Int. J. Mol. Sci. 23, 14255. doi:10.3390/ijms232214255 <lb/>Cattaneo, F., Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., Frezzato, F., D&apos;Elios, M. M., Trentin, L., et al. <lb/>(2016). Expression of the p66Shc protein adaptor is regulated by the activator of <lb/>transcription STAT4 in normal and chronic lymphocytic leukemia B cells. Oncotarget 7, <lb/>57086-57098. doi:10.18632/oncotarget.10977 <lb/>Chang, Y. L., Yang, C. Y., Lin, M. W., Wu, C. T., and Yang, P. C. (2016). High co-<lb/>expression of PD-L1 and HIF-1α correlates with tumour necrosis in pulmonary <lb/>pleomorphic carcinoma. Eur. J. Cancer 60, 125-135. doi:10.1016/j.ejca.2016.03.012 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>13 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Ding, W., LaPlant, B. R., Call, T. G., Parikh, S. A., Leis, J. F., He, R., et al. (2017). <lb/>Pembrolizumab in patients with CLL and Richter transformation or with relapsed CLL. <lb/>Blood 129, 3419-3427. doi:10.1182/BLOOD-2017-02-765685 <lb/>Dustin, M. L., and Choudhuri, K. (2016). Signaling and polarized communication <lb/>across the T cell immunological synapse. Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol. 32, 303-325. doi:10. <lb/>1146/annurev-cellbio-100814-125330 <lb/>Fooksman, D. R., Vardhana, S., Vasiliver-Shamis, G., Liese, J., Blair, D. A., Waite, J., <lb/>et al. (2010). Functional anatomy of T cell activation and synapse formation. Annu. Rev. <lb/>Immunol. 28, 79-105. doi:10.1146/annurev-immunol-030409-101308 <lb/>Giorgio, M., Migliaccio, E., Orsini, F., Paolucci, D., Moroni, M., Contursi, C., et al. <lb/>(2005). Electron transfer between cytochrome c and p66Shc generates reactive oxygen <lb/>species that trigger mitochondrial apoptosis. Cell 122, 221-233. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2005. <lb/>05.011 <lb/>Grzywnowicz, M., Karczmarczyk, A., Skorka, K., Zajac, M., Zaleska, J., Chocholska, S., <lb/>et al. (2015). Expression of programmed death 1 ligand in different compartments of <lb/>chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Acta Haematol. 134, 255-262. doi:10.1159/000430980 <lb/>Guo, R., Li, Y., Wang, Z., Bai, H., Duan, J., Wang, S., et al. (2019). Hypoxia-inducible <lb/>factor-1α and nuclear factor-κB play important roles in regulating programmed cell <lb/>death ligand 1 expression by epidermal growth factor receptor mutants in non-small-<lb/>cell lung cancer cells. Cancer Sci. 110, 1665-1675. doi:10.1111/cas.13989 <lb/>Hallek, M., Cheson, B. D., Catovsky, D., Caligaris-Cappio, F., Dighiero, G., Döhner, <lb/>H., et al. (2008). Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukemia: a report from the international workshop on chronic lymphocytic leukemia <lb/>updating the national cancer institute-working group 1996 guidelines. Blood 111, <lb/>5446-5456. doi:10.1182/blood-2007-06-093906 <lb/>Ioannou, N., Hagner, P. R., Stokes, M., Gandhi, A. K., Apollonio, B., Fanous, M., et al. <lb/>(2021). Triggering interferon signaling in T cells with avadomide sensitizes CLL to anti-<lb/>PD-L1/PD-1 immunotherapy. Blood 137, 216-231. doi:10.1182/blood.2020006073 <lb/>Kang, Y. B., Eo, J., Bulutoglu, B., Yarmush, M. L., and Usta, O. B. (2020). Progressive <lb/>hypoxia-on-a-chip: an in vitro oxygen gradient model for capturing the effects of <lb/>hypoxia on primary hepatocytes in health and disease. Biotechnol. Bioeng. 117, 763-775. <lb/>doi:10.1002/bit.27225 <lb/>Kipps, T. J., Stevenson, F. K., Wu, C. J., Croce, C. M., Packham, G., Wierda, W. G., <lb/>et al. (2017). Chronic lymphocytic leukaemia. Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim. 3, 16096. doi:10.1038/ <lb/>nrdp.2016.96 <lb/>Kline, J., Godfrey, J., and Ansell, S. M. (2020). The immune landscape and response to <lb/>immune checkpoint blockade therapy in lymphoma. Blood 135, 523-533. doi:10.1182/ <lb/>blood.2019000847 <lb/>Lim, S. O., Li, C. W., Xia, W., Cha, J. H., Chan, L. C., Wu, Y., et al. (2016). <lb/>Deubiquitination and stabilization of PD-L1 by CSN5. Cancer Cell 30, 925-939. doi:10. <lb/>1016/j.ccell.2016.10.010 <lb/>Locke, F. L., Ghobadi, A., Jacobson, C. A., Miklos, D. B., Lekakis, L. J., Oluwole, O. O., <lb/>et al. (2019). Long-term safety and activity of axicabtagene ciloleucel in refractory large <lb/>B-cell lymphoma (ZUMA-1): a single-arm, multicentre, phase 1-2 trial. Lancet Oncol. <lb/>20, 31-42. doi:10.1016/S1470-2045(18)30864-7 <lb/>Maude, S. L., Laetsch, T. W., Buechner, J., Rives, S., Boyer, M., Bittencourt, H., et al. <lb/>(2018). Tisagenlecleucel in children and young adults with B-cell lymphoblastic <lb/>leukemia. N. Engl. J. Med. 378, 439-448. doi:10.1056/nejmoa1709866 <lb/>Migliaccio, E., Giorgio, M., Mele, S., Pelicci, G., Reboldi, P., Pandolfi, P. P., et al. <lb/>(1999). The p66shc adaptor protein controls oxidative stress response and life span in <lb/>mammals. Nature 402, 309-313. doi:10.1038/46311 <lb/>Nie, H., He, T., Wang, L., and Zhang, L. (2021). Expression and prognostic value of <lb/>tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes and pd-l1 in hepatocellular carcinoma. Onco Targets <lb/>Ther. 14, 1377-1385. doi:10.2147/OTT.S289720 <lb/>Onnis, A., Andreano, E., Cassioli, C., Finetti, F., Della Bella, C., Staufer, O., et al. <lb/>(2023). SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein suppresses CTL-mediated killing by inhibiting <lb/>immune synapse assembly. J. Exp. Med. 220, e20220906. doi:10.1084/JEM.20220906 <lb/>Onnis, A., and Baldari, C. T. (2019). Orchestration of immunological synapse assembly by <lb/>vesicular trafficking. Front. Cell Dev. Biol. 7, 110. doi:10.3389/fcell.2019.00110 <lb/>Pacini, S., Pellegrini, M., Migliaccio, E., Patrussi, L., Ulivieri, C., Ventura, A., et al. <lb/>(2004). p66SHC promotes apoptosis and antagonizes mitogenic signaling in T cells. <lb/>Mol. Cell Biol. 24, 1747-1757. doi:10.1128/MCB.24.4.1747-1757.2004 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., and Baldari, C. T. (2020). P66Shc: a pleiotropic regulator of <lb/>B cell trafficking and a gatekeeper in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Cancers (Basel) 12, <lb/>1006. doi:10.3390/cancers12041006 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., and Baldari, C. T. (2021b). Interleukin (IL)-9 supports the <lb/>tumor-promoting environment of chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Cancers (Basel) 13, <lb/>6301. doi:10.3390/cancers13246301 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., Cattaneo, F., Manganaro, N., Gamberucci, A., Frezzato, F., <lb/>et al. (2018). p66Shc deficiency enhances CXCR4 and CCR7 recycling in CLL B cells by <lb/>facilitating their dephosphorylation-dependent release from β-arrestin at early <lb/>endosomes. Oncogene 37, 1534-1550. doi:10.1038/s41388-017-0066-2 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., Martini, V., Pizzi, M., Trimarco, V., Frezzato, F., et al. <lb/>(2015). Enhanced chemokine receptor recycling and impaired S1P1 expression promote <lb/>leukemic cell infiltration of lymph nodes in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Cancer Res. <lb/>75, 4153-4163. doi:10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-15-0986 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Capitani, N., Ulivieri, C., Manganaro, N., Granai, M., Cattaneo, F., et al. <lb/>(2019). P66Shc deficiency in the Eμ-TCL1 mouse model of chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukemia enhances leukemogenesis by altering the chemokine receptor landscape. <lb/>Haematologica 104, 2040-2052. doi:10.3324/haematol.2018.209981 <lb/>Patrussi, L., Manganaro, N., Capitani, N., Ulivieri, C., Tatangelo, V., Libonati, F., et al. <lb/>(2021a). Enhanced IL-9 secretion by p66Shc-deficient CLL cells modulates the <lb/>chemokine landscape of the stromal microenvironment. Blood 137, 2182-2195. <lb/>doi:10.1182/blood.2020005785 <lb/>Pellegrini, M., Finetti, F., Petronilli, V., Ulivieri, C., Giusti, F., Lupetti, P., et al. <lb/>(2007). p66SHC promotes T cell apoptosis by inducing mitochondrial dysfunction <lb/>and impaired Ca2+ homeostasis. Cell Death Differ. 14, 338-347. doi:10.1038/sj. <lb/>cdd.4401997 <lb/>Plyte, S., Boncristiano, M., Fattori, E., Galvagni, F., Paccani, S. R., Majolin, M. B., et al. <lb/>(2001). Identification and characterization of a novel nuclear factor of activated T-cells-<lb/>1 isoform expressed in mouse brain. J. Biol. Chem. 276, 14350-14358. doi:10.1074/jbc. <lb/>M007854200 <lb/>Ramsay, A. G., Clear, A. J., Fatah, R., and Gribben, J. G. (2012). Multiple inhibitory <lb/>ligands induce impaired T-cell immunologic synapse function in chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukemia that can be blocked with lenalidomide: establishing a reversible immune <lb/>evasion mechanism in human cancer. Blood 120, 1412-1421. doi:10.1182/blood-2012-<lb/>02-411678 <lb/>Ramsay, A. G., Johnson, A. J., Lee, A. M., Gorgün, G., Le Dieu, R., Blum, W., et al. <lb/>(2008). Chronic lymphocytic leukemia T cells show impaired immunological synapse <lb/>formation that can be reversed with an immunomodulating drug. J. Clin. Invest. 118, <lb/>2427-2437. doi:10.1172/JCI35017 <lb/>Riches, J. C., Davies, J. K., McClanahan, F., Fatah, R., Iqbal, S., Agrawal, S., et al. <lb/>(2013). T cells from CLL patients exhibit features of T-cell exhaustion but retain <lb/>capacity for cytokine production. Blood 121, 1612-1621. doi:10.1182/blood-2012-09-<lb/>457531 <lb/>Saunders, P. A., Hendrycks, V. R., Lidinsky, W. A., and Woods, M. L. (2005). PD-L2: <lb/>PD-1 involvement in T cell proliferation, cytokine production, and integrin-mediated <lb/>adhesion. Eur. J. Immunol. 35, 3561-3569. doi:10.1002/eji.200526347 <lb/>Soares, H., Lasserre, R., and Alcover, A. (2013). Orchestrating cytoskeleton and <lb/>intracellular vesicle traffic to build functional immunological synapses. Immunol. Rev. <lb/>256, 118-132. doi:10.1111/imr.12110 <lb/>Stacchini, A., Aragno, M., Vallario, A., Alfarano, A., Circosta, P., Gottardi, D., et al. <lb/>(1999). MEC1 and MEC2: two new cell lines derived from B-chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukaemia in prolymphocytoid transformation. Leuk. Res. 23, 127-136. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>s0145-2126(98)00154-4 <lb/>Tatangelo, V., Boncompagni, G., Capitani, N., Lopresti, L., Manganaro, N., Frezzato, <lb/>F., et al. (2022). p66Shc deficiency in chronic lymphocytic leukemia promotes <lb/>chemokine receptor expression through the ROS-dependent inhibition of NF-κB. <lb/>Front. Oncol. 12, 877495. doi:10.3389/fonc.2022.877495 <lb/>Tawadros, A. I. F., and Khalafalla, M. M. M. (2018). Expression of programmed <lb/>death-ligand 1 and hypoxia-inducible factor-1α proteins in endometrial carcinoma. <lb/>J. Cancer Res. Ther. 14, S1063-S1069. doi:10.4103/0973-1482.202891 <lb/>ten Hacken, E., and Burger, J. A. (2016). Microenvironment interactions and B-cell <lb/>receptor signaling in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia: implications for disease <lb/>pathogenesis and treatment. Biochim. Biophys. Acta -Mol. Cell Res. 1863, 401-413. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbamcr.2015.07.009 <lb/>Vaisitti, T., Gaudino, F., Ouk, S., Moscvin, M., Vitale, N., Serra, S., et al. (2017). <lb/>Targeting metabolism and survival in chronic lymphocytic leukemia and richter <lb/>syndrome cells by a novel NF-κB inhibitor. Haematologica 102, 1878-1889. doi:10. <lb/>3324/haematol.2017.173419 <lb/>Visentin, A., Bonaldi, L., Rigolin, G. M., Mauro, F. R., Martines, A., Frezzato, F., et al. <lb/>(2019). The combination of complex karyotype subtypes and IGHV mutational status <lb/>identifies new prognostic and predictive groups in chronic lymphocytic leukaemia. Br. <lb/>J. Cancer 121, 150-156. doi:10.1038/s41416-019-0502-x <lb/>Wang, J., Liu, N., Jiang, H., Li, Q., and Xing, D. (2021). Reactive oxygen species in <lb/>anticancer immunity: a double-edged sword. Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 9, 784612. <lb/>doi:10.3389/fbioe.2021.784612 <lb/>Yu, Y., Gong, L., and Ye, J. (2020). The role of aberrant metabolism in cancer: insights <lb/>into the interplay between cell metabolic reprogramming, metabolic syndrome, and <lb/>cancer. Front. Oncol. 10, 942. doi:10.3389/fonc.2020.00942 <lb/>Zhang, J.-J., Zhang, Q.-S., Li, Z.-Q., Zhou, J.-W., and Du, J. (2019). Metformin <lb/>attenuates PD-L1 expression through activating Hippo signaling pathway in colorectal <lb/>cancer cells. Am. J. Transl. Res. 11, 6965-6976. <lb/>Zhao, B., Luo, J., Wang, Y., Zhou, L., Che, J., Wang, F., et al. (2019). Metformin <lb/>suppresses self-renewal ability and tumorigenicity of osteosarcoma stem cells via <lb/>reactive oxygen species-mediated apoptosis and autophagy. Oxid. Med. Cell Longev. <lb/>2019, 9290728. doi:10.1155/2019/9290728 <lb/>Zhou, Y. J., Li, G., Wang, J., Liu, M., Wang, Z., Song, Y., et al. (2023). PD-L1: <lb/>expression regulation. Blood Sci. 5, 77-91. doi:10.1097/BS9.0000000000000149 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<page>14 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">Lopresti et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcell.2024.1297116 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>