<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T15:25:55.824Z">11/24/2025 3:25:55 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T15:23:03.412427Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T15:23:03.412427Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>Computer Modeling in <lb/>Engineering &amp; Sciences <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/cmes.2023.043322 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Parametric Optimization of Wheel Spoke Structure for Drag Reduction of an <lb/>Ahmed Body <lb/>Huihui Zhai 1 , Dongqi Jiao 2 and Haichao Zhou 2,* <lb/>1 Institute of Electrical and Information Engineering, Zhenjiang College, Zhenjiang, 212028, China <lb/>2 School of Automotive and Traffic Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212013, China <lb/>*Corresponding Author: Haichao Zhou. Email: haichaozhou999@163.com <lb/>Received: 29 June 2023 Accepted: 20 September 2023 Published: 30 December 2023 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>The wheels have a considerable influence on the aerodynamic properties and can contribute up to 25% of the total <lb/>drag on modern vehicles. In this study, the effect of the wheel spoke structure on the aerodynamic performance of <lb/>the isolated wheel is investigated. Subsequently, the 35°Ahmed body with an optimized spoke structure is used <lb/>to analyze the flow behavior and the mechanism of drag reduction. The Fluent software is employed for this <lb/>investigation, with an inlet velocity of 40 m/s. The accuracy of the numerical study is validated by comparing it <lb/>with experimental results obtained from the classical Ahmed model. To gain a clearer understanding of the effects <lb/>of the wheel spoke parameters on the aerodynamics of both the wheel and Ahmed model, and five design variables <lb/>are proposed: the fillet angle α, the inside arc radius R 1 , the outside radius R 2 , and the same length of the chord <lb/>L 1 and L 2 . These variables characterize the wheel spoke structure. The Optimal Latin Hypercube design method <lb/>is utilized to conduct the experimental design. Based on the simulation results of various wheel spoke designs, the <lb/>Kriging model and the adaptive simulated annealing algorithm is selected to optimize the design parameters. The <lb/>objective is to achieve the best combination for maximum drag reduction. It is indicated that the optimized spoke <lb/>structure resulted in a maximum drag reduction of 5.7% and 4.7% for the drag coefficient of the isolated wheel and <lb/>Ahmed body, respectively. The drag reduction is primarily attributed to changes in the flow state around the wheel, <lb/>which suppressed separation bubbles. Additionally, it influenced the boundary layer thickness around the car body <lb/>and reduced the turbulent kinetic energy in the wake flow. These effects collectively contributed to the observed <lb/>drag reduction. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Ahmed body; wheel spoke design; parameter optimization; drag reduction; numerical simulation <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The automotive industry is facing rapid development and increasing customer diversification and <lb/>personalized needs, which puts immense pressure on automotive companies to optimize products <lb/>and produce high-caliber vehicles. Aerodynamics is a major concern in the automobile industry as <lb/>it directly influences safety, comfort, fuel consumption, and driving range. The need to minimize fuel <lb/>consumption in automobiles is driven by greenhouse gas CO 2 emissions. One effective measure for <lb/></body>

	<page>956 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>reducing CO 2 emissions is to decrease the vehicle&apos;s aerodynamic drag. It has been reported that the <lb/>aerodynamic drag of a mid-size car contributes up to 46% of fuel consumption at highway speeds, and <lb/>a 5% reduction in aerodynamic drag could result in a reduction of 1.5 g/km of CO 2 [1]. Therefore, <lb/>engineers and scholars have made significant efforts to improve the aerodynamic performance of <lb/>vehicles using passive and active devices [2,3]. Kim et al. argued that the classical approach to reducing <lb/>drag, such as shape modification, is not feasible in the modern world due to customers&apos; aesthetic <lb/>demands [4]. Inspired by the secondary feathers of birds, Kim et al. proposed a new automatic moving <lb/>deflector to be applied to the Ahmed body, resulting in a maximum drag reduction of 19%. Therefore, <lb/>the urgency to develop new drag reduction methods without compromising aesthetics is a growing <lb/>area of research interest. <lb/>Numerous studies have pointed out that wheels have a considerable influence on the aerodynamic <lb/>properties and can contribute up to 25% of the total drag on modern vehicles. The aerodynamic <lb/>drag has a direct relationship with the flow field around the car, and the high contribution of <lb/>wheels to drag is due to the strong interactions between the wheel wake and the vehicle underbody <lb/>through pressure modifications [5]. Hence, when body shape optimization reaches its limits, wheel <lb/>aerodynamics becomes a prominent concern in order to reduce fuel consumption. Additionally, <lb/>reducing wheel drag benefits the range of electric vehicles. Consequently, over the past two decades, <lb/>wheel aerodynamics has been the focus of numerous studies and optimization efforts in academia and <lb/>industry [6-8]. <lb/>Frackell [9] conducted the first experimental work on an isolated wheel under realistic conditions. <lb/>The results showed that the pressure distribution measured on the wheel surface highlighted two main <lb/>specificities of the flow: the wheel rotation moved the forward stagnation point approximately 15°d <lb/>own towards the front contact patch on the ground, and jetting-vortex effects appeared on either <lb/>side of the contact patch. Brandt et al. [10] designed several different types of wheels and studied <lb/>the effects of certain rim parameters on the flow field and drag using computational fluid dynamics <lb/>(CFD). The study concluded that drag has a linear relationship with the coverage area of the wheel <lb/>spoke. Fang et al. [11] investigated the influence of rim cover area on drag using wind tunnel tests and <lb/>found that the full cover wheel has the lowest drag coefficient. Fu et al. [12] studied the aerodynamic <lb/>characteristics of wheels and cars using different wheel opening areas and design locations, and it is <lb/>shown that, under the same opening area condition, increasing the number of openings can improve <lb/>the aerodynamic performance. <lb/>Despite the known potential for wheel modification to reduce drag, there is still considerable <lb/>room for improvement in understanding flow phenomena and their interaction with surrounding <lb/>parts in wheel aerodynamics. Elofsson et al. [13] presented a schematic picture of near-wake structures, <lb/>including two jetting-vortices and two vortices downstream of the upper wheel boundary separation. <lb/>Saddingtion et al. [14] analyzed the flow field around the wheel using the Laser Doppler Anemometry <lb/>(LDV) system, and the results showed that the upper vortices appeared weaker and merged with the <lb/>jetting-vortices within one diameter downstream behind the wheel axis. Computational fluid dynamics <lb/>(CFD) has provided further insight into understanding the wheel flow field and aerodynamics. <lb/>Simulations with isolated wheels have demonstrated the ability of CFD to capture specific flow features <lb/>and improve understanding of vortex dynamics and their impact on aerodynamic drag. When the <lb/>air reaches the wheel, a stagnation point occurs, and the flow divides, resulting in three main vortex <lb/>structures around the front wheel [15]. However, the wheel coverage area affects the flow field and <lb/>leads to changes in drag coefficients. A fully covered wheel blocks the air entering the wheel cavity, <lb/>reducing the vortex size and minimizing flow separation around the wheel. Furthermore, it has been <lb/>found that drag reduction from covering the rim track is more efficient than covering the center [16]. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>957 <lb/></page>

	<body>Although the effect of wheel design and the main flow features has been studied both exper-<lb/>imentally and numerically, few studies have focused on the optimization of wheel spoke design to <lb/>reduce aerodynamic drag. Therefore, the objective of this study is to investigate the influence of wheel <lb/>spoke structure parameters on the aerodynamic drag of an isolated wheel. Subsequently, the kriging <lb/>model and ASA method are employed to optimize the wheel spoke design and achieve maximum drag <lb/>reduction for the Ahmed body, as well as the drag reduction mechanism is also discussed. The paper is <lb/>organized as follows: Section 2 presents the geometry model and simulation details. Section 3 discusses <lb/>the investigation of parameters and the optimization process for the wheel spoke structure. Section 4 <lb/>reports the results and discussions, including the differences in the flow field and the drag reduction <lb/>mechanism. Finally, Section 5 provides concluding remarks. <lb/>2 Geometry Model and Simulation Details <lb/>2.1 Geometry Model <lb/>In this current study, a generic car model with the wheels and wheelhouses is used, and the <lb/>reference model chosen is the Ahmed body. The selection of this model is based on its extensive use in <lb/>previous studies for validation and benchmarking purposes in the field of road vehicle aerodynamics. <lb/>The geometry model of Ahmed body, as depicted in Fig. 1, represents a 1:4 scale model of a lower-<lb/>medium size hatchback vehicle. It features a short curved front section, followed by a long straight <lb/>middle section, and an angled rear end. Varying the rear end angle between 0°and 40°enables the <lb/>investigation of different flow characteristics and significant changes in drag coefficients [17]. The <lb/>rear angle plays a crucial role in determining drag, as approximately 85% of the aerodynamic drag is <lb/>attributed to pressure drag. Rear angles larger than 30°correspond to a low drag configuration. Based <lb/>on the findings of previous research and Strachan&apos;s test results [18], the Ahmed body with a rear angled <lb/>upper surface of 35°is selected for the present study. The detailed dimensions of the Ahmed body are <lb/>presented in Fig. 2. <lb/>Figure 1: Ahmed body of a simplified vehicle <lb/>The purpose of this investigation is to determine the sensitivity of the wheel spoke structure <lb/>parameters and identify an optimal aerodynamic shape that minimizes the drag coefficient of the <lb/>wheel. Additionally, the aim is to enhance the overall aerodynamic performance of vehicles equipped <lb/>with low drag wheels. To establish a universal design principle, an analysis is conducted on the opening <lb/>ratio of 15 popular car models currently available in the market. For instance, Fig. 3 illustrates the <lb/>investigation of a popular SUV. <lb/>The selected wheels in this study primarily exhibit an opening ratio concentrated in the range of <lb/>50%-55%, as demonstrated in Fig. 4. Therefore, the focus of this research is on a five-spoke wheel with <lb/>an opening ratio of 50%. The dimensions and features of the wheel used in this study closely resemble <lb/>those of a real car, maintaining the same proportions as the Ahmed body, as depicted in Fig. 5. To <lb/>simulate realistic conditions, four wheels are attached to the car body using cylindrical axles. The <lb/></body>

	<page>958 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>center of these cylindrical axles is positioned at a vertical height of 75 mm, as shown in Fig. 6. In order <lb/>to accurately capture the pressure peak and jetting effect at the wheel edges, following the simulation <lb/>results provided by Humimic [19], the contact patch region of the wheel is modeled as a convex plate <lb/>with a height of 0.2 mm and a length of 25 mm for computational analysis. This modeling approach <lb/>ensures the quality of the mesh and captures the airflow behavior around the wheel effectively. <lb/>Figure 2: Detail sizes of Ahmed model <lb/>Figure 3: The different car wheel structure with five spoke <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Count <lb/>Opening ratio % <lb/>Figure 4: The opening ration distribution <lb/>Figure 5: Wheel model with five spoke <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>959 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 6: Ahmed model with four wheels <lb/>2.2 Calculation Domain and Boundary Conditions <lb/>The shape and geometry of the Ahmed body are depicted in Fig. 7. The body has a length (L) of <lb/>1044 mm, a height (H) of 288 mm, and a width (W ) of 389 mm. The computational domain extends <lb/>approximately 12 times the body length (12 L), 5 times the width (5 W ), and 5 times the height (5 H). <lb/>The car body is positioned in the middle of the width direction, with a distance of 4 L from the inlet <lb/>and 7 L from the outlet. This arrangement corresponds to a blockage ratio of 4%. The inlet boundary <lb/>condition is set as a uniform inflow condition, while the outlet is configured as a pressure-outlet <lb/>condition with a pressure of 0 Pa. Frictionless boundary conditions are applied to the top and two <lb/>lateral sidewalls. The Ahmed body surface is modeled as a no-slip wall, and the floor is treated as <lb/>a zero-shear wall. As for the wheel surface, a rotating motion is considered with a specified angular <lb/>speed. To simulate the flow characteristics, the SST turbulence model is chosen, given its widespread <lb/>usage in the industry for modeling vehicle flows [20]. The SIMPLE algorithm and second-order <lb/>discretization method are employed to obtain the flow field and pressure distributions accurately. <lb/>Figure 7: Computing domain and boundary conditions <lb/>2.3 Model Validation <lb/>The numerical simulation method presented in this study is validated using the available data <lb/>of the Ahmed model in the published literature. The mesh generated around the Ahmed body is <lb/>shown in Fig. 8. The numerical study uses the same boundary conditions as the experiment, including <lb/>an incoming flow velocity of 40 m/s. The total number of elements generated using the Hypermesh <lb/>software is 11,326,856, with a minimum cell size of 0.02 m around the body surface. Two refined <lb/>regions are applied in the mesh generation, one with a cell size of 0.02 m and the other with a cell <lb/>size of 0.034 m. The maximum cell size in the outer surface of the domain is set to 0.5 m. By setting the <lb/>minimum cell size, the first layer is ensured to be at y + &lt; 10 in the present study, as shown in Fig. 9. <lb/>This choice is important for accurately capturing the near-wall flow. <lb/></body>

	<page>960 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 8: Mesh around the Ahmed body <lb/>Figure 9: The y + values around the body surface <lb/>The simulation results are compared with both experimental data and simulation results from <lb/>previous studies [21,22]. Table 1 shows that the numerical values of the drag coefficient are in good <lb/>agreement with the experimental results. Fig. 10 presents a comparison of the velocity along vertical <lb/>lines in the symmetry plane, revealing a significant separation over the rear slant zone, which is <lb/>consistent with the experimental results [23]. These validation results confirm the accuracy of the <lb/>simulation model, including the mesh work and physics model used for simulating the Ahmed model <lb/>with wheels in this study. The validation outcome further strengthens the reliability of the results <lb/>presented in this research. <lb/>Table 1: Comparisons of drag coefficient with the published results <lb/>No. <lb/>Reference <lb/>Method <lb/>Drag coefficient (C d ) <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>1 <lb/>Ahmed et al. [21] <lb/>Experimental <lb/>0.26 <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>Siddiqui et al. [22] <lb/>CFD simulation <lb/>0.271 <lb/>4.2% <lb/>3 <lb/>Present study <lb/>CFD simulation <lb/>0.261 <lb/>0.38% <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>961 <lb/></page>

	<body>-0.25 -0.20 -0.15 -0.10 -0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>CFD[Present work] <lb/>Rear body <lb/>Exp.[23] <lb/>X/m <lb/>Figure 10: Comparison of velocity distribution between simulation and experiment <lb/>2.4 Meshing <lb/>The Hypermesh software is utilized to generate a mixed mesh consisting of tetrahedral and <lb/>pentahedral cells for the Ahmed body with the wheel. Two mesh refinements are applied near the <lb/>wheel and car body surfaces using tetrahedral elements, while the pentahedral elements are generated <lb/>further away in the domain using solid mapping. Following the same mesh structure used for the <lb/>mesh validation case, three meshes, named Mesh 1, Mesh 2, and Mesh 3, are created, containing 15.02 <lb/>million, 18.51 million, and 22.46 million cells, respectively. As indicated in Table 2, the drag coefficients <lb/>decrease with an increasing number of grid cells. The C d value error for Mesh 1, Mesh 2 and Mesh 3 <lb/>is 0.002. It is worth noting that the calculation accuracy is positively correlated with the number of <lb/>cells; however, excessive cell count can reduce computational efficiency. Therefore, Mesh 2 is selected <lb/>for further research, as illustrated in Fig. 11. <lb/>Table 2: Grid independence results <lb/>Mesh <lb/>Total cells numbers C d <lb/>Mesh 1 <lb/>15.02 million <lb/>0.415 <lb/>Mesh 2 <lb/>18.51 million <lb/>0.402 <lb/>Mesh 3 <lb/>22.46 million <lb/>0.404 <lb/>3 Parameter Investigation and Optimization <lb/>3.1 Simulation of Isolated Wheel <lb/>While the wheel structure has a significant impact on the aerodynamic drag of the wheel, it is <lb/>important to note that wheel aerodynamics are independent of the overall vehicle aerodynamics. In <lb/>other words, reducing the aerodynamic drag of the wheel can have a positive effect on the vehicle drag. <lb/>This perspective has been supported by previous research [10]. <lb/></body>

	<page>962 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 11: The mesh around the car body and the front wheel <lb/>To define the computational domain, the dimensions of the isolated wheel, including length <lb/>(L W = 150 mm), width (W W = 50 mm), and height (H W = 150 mm), are taken into consideration. The <lb/>boundaries of the domain are designed to be 20 times the length of the wheel (20 L W ) in length, 10 <lb/>times the width of the wheel (10 W W ) in width, and 5 times the height of the wheel (5 H W ) in height, <lb/>as depicted in Fig. 12. The wheel is positioned at the center of the width direction, with a clearance <lb/>of 7 times the wheel length (7 L W ) from the inlet. The resulting blockage ratio is approximately 2%. <lb/>For mesh generation, the commercial software Hypermesh is employed to create the volume mesh <lb/>and boundary layer cells. A cylindrical-shaped volumetric control is applied around the wheel, while a <lb/>rectangular-shaped volumetric control is used in the wake region to accurately capture flow features in <lb/>these areas. Prism layers, triangular elements, and tetrahedral elements are utilized for meshing. The <lb/>prism layers, consisting of 5 inflation layers with a growth rate of 1.2, are employed to capture the <lb/>boundary layer flow. The wheel rotation is simulated using the moving reference frame method. To <lb/>test the grid sensitivity of the simulation, three different gird resolutions, named as the coarse, medium <lb/>and fine, are proposed, and the response Cd is shown in Table 3. The fine grid distribution around the <lb/>wheel are shown in Fig. 12b. Additionally, the fine grid ensured a y + value of less than 2, as shown in <lb/>Fig. 13. <lb/>Table 3: Comparison of the different grid resolutions <lb/>Items <lb/>Coarse <lb/>Medium <lb/>Fine <lb/>Total cells number <lb/>4.15 million <lb/>4.86 million <lb/>5.23 million <lb/>C d <lb/>0.963 <lb/>0.941 <lb/>0.934 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>963 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.2 Parameters Selection and DOE <lb/>The structure of the rim spoke plays a crucial role in aerodynamic drag as it affects the airflow. <lb/>Considering the same rim area coverage of 50% and a fixed wheel diameter of 75 mm, five design <lb/>parameters of the rim spoke are studied: the fillet angle α, inside arc radius R 1 , outside arc radius R 2 , <lb/>and the arc tangent lines L 1 and L 2 , as depicted in Fig. 14. <lb/>Figure 12: Computational domain sizes and grids <lb/>Figure 13: Y + values distribution around wheel surface <lb/></body>

	<page>964 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 14: Schematic diagram of a single spoke <lb/>In the original spoke design, the fillet angle α is set at 0.384 rad, with inside arc radius R 1 and <lb/>outside arc radius R 2 of 8 and 55 mm, respectively. The arc tangent lines L 1 and L 2 are both 35.693 mm. <lb/>To examine the influence of different spoke design parameters on wheel aerodynamic drag while <lb/>maintaining the same opening area of 5S, the parameter variables are assigned the following values: <lb/>α ∈ (0.262, 0.523) rad, R 2 ∈ (41.582, 58.679) mm while the remaining two parameters are determined <lb/>using Eqs. (1)-(3). <lb/>S = α • R 2 <lb/>2 -20.91 2 • sin (α) • cos (α) + <lb/>(π -α) <lb/>2 <lb/>• 20.91 2 • (sin (α)) <lb/>2 <lb/>(1) <lb/>R 1 = 20.91 • sin (α) <lb/>(2) <lb/>L 1 = L 2 = R 2 -20.91 • cos (α) <lb/>(3) <lb/>The Optimal Latin Hypercube design method [24,25], known for optimizing the combination <lb/>of factor levels, is employed to generate 20 sample points in this study. All 20 cases are simulated <lb/>with an inlet velocity of 40 m/s. The factors and corresponding levels, as well as the obtained results, <lb/>are summarized in Table 4. Fig. 15 showcases the designs of samples 7, 11, and 16. The impact of <lb/>parameter variables on the wheel&apos;s aerodynamic drag coefficient is depicted in Fig. 16. It is evident <lb/>that the fillet angle α has the greatest influence on the drag coefficient, followed by the outside arc <lb/>radius R 1 . Conversely, the arc tangent lines L 1 and L 2 exhibit minimal impact on the drag coefficient. <lb/>Table 4: Test schemes and calculation results <lb/>No. <lb/>L 1 (L 2 )/mm <lb/>R 1 /mm <lb/>R 2 /mm <lb/>α/Rad <lb/>C d <lb/>1 <lb/>30.606 <lb/>9.691 <lb/>42.129 <lb/>0.482 <lb/>0.957 <lb/>2 <lb/>29.405 <lb/>10.205 <lb/>47.649 <lb/>0.510 <lb/>0.951 <lb/>3 <lb/>29.965 <lb/>7.598 <lb/>58.036 <lb/>0.372 <lb/>0.960 <lb/>4 <lb/>31.705 <lb/>7.053 <lb/>60.143 <lb/>0.344 <lb/>0.959 <lb/>5 <lb/>27.124 <lb/>8.657 <lb/>52.386 <lb/>0.427 <lb/>0.891 <lb/>6 <lb/>28.434 <lb/>8.141 <lb/>54.192 <lb/>0.401 <lb/>0.919 <lb/>7 <lb/>46.827 <lb/>5.411 <lb/>67.019 <lb/>0.262 <lb/>0.940 <lb/>8 <lb/>45.186 <lb/>5.697 <lb/>65.299 <lb/>0.276 <lb/>0.943 <lb/>9 <lb/>42.400 <lb/>6.238 <lb/>62.353 <lb/>0.303 <lb/>0.956 <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>965 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4 (continued) <lb/>No. <lb/>L 1 (L 2 )/mm <lb/>R 1 /mm <lb/>R 2 /mm <lb/>α/Rad <lb/>C d <lb/>10 <lb/>31.886 <lb/>9.187 <lb/>50.664 <lb/>0.455 <lb/>0.951 <lb/>11 <lb/>34.289 <lb/>7.871 <lb/>55.193 <lb/>0.386 <lb/>0.950 <lb/>12 <lb/>41.103 <lb/>6.516 <lb/>60.966 <lb/>0.317 <lb/>0.954 <lb/>13 <lb/>34.155 <lb/>8.390 <lb/>53.303 <lb/>0.413 <lb/>0.885 <lb/>14 <lb/>32.602 <lb/>8.923 <lb/>51.507 <lb/>0.441 <lb/>0.946 <lb/>15 <lb/>37.772 <lb/>7.325 <lb/>57.352 <lb/>0.358 <lb/>0.951 <lb/>16 <lb/>28.863 <lb/>10.452 <lb/>46.967 <lb/>0.524 <lb/>0.968 <lb/>17 <lb/>39.893 <lb/>6.794 <lb/>59.663 <lb/>0.331 <lb/>0.950 <lb/>18 <lb/>43.794 <lb/>5.958 <lb/>63.832 <lb/>0.289 <lb/>0.938 <lb/>19 <lb/>29.991 <lb/>9.949 <lb/>48.376 <lb/>0.496 <lb/>0.950 <lb/>20 <lb/>31.254 <lb/>9.430 <lb/>49.911 <lb/>0.468 <lb/>0.957 <lb/>Figure 15: Geometric models of some typical Schemes <lb/>49.732 <lb/>95.876 <lb/>97.7 <lb/>98.85 <lb/>100 <lb/>α <lb/>R1 <lb/>R2 <lb/>L1 <lb/>L2 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Contributions for <lb/>C <lb/>d <lb/>Design variables <lb/>0% <lb/>20% <lb/>40% <lb/>60% <lb/>80% <lb/>100% <lb/>Figure 16: Contribution of different design variables for C d <lb/></body>

	<page>966 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>3.3 Surrogate Model and Parameters Optimization <lb/>The Kriging surrogate model, known for its effectiveness in curve interpolation and response <lb/>surface approximation, is utilized in this study for the approximate evaluation of design schemes [26]. <lb/>The correlation coefficient R 2 is selected as a measure to evaluate the accuracy of the built Kriging <lb/>surrogate model. Fig. 17 illustrates the forecast accuracy between the simulation results and predicted <lb/>results, with an R 2 value of approximately 0.98. This indicates that the established surrogate model <lb/>possesses sufficient accuracy for optimizing the parameters of the wheel spoke. <lb/>0.88 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>Simulation <lb/>C <lb/>d <lb/>Predicting C d <lb/>Figure 17: Kriging surrogate model accuracy <lb/>The adaptive simulated annealing (ASA) algorithm is chosen to obtain the global optimal <lb/>solution for the design parameters of the wheel spoke. In this algorithm, the objective function <lb/>aimed to minimize the wheel drag coefficient, while the constraint conditions are defined as α ∈ <lb/>(0.262, 0.523) rad, R 2 ∈ (41.582, 58.679) mm; R 1 ∈ (5.411, 10.452) mm, L 1 ∈ (27.125, 46.827) mm. <lb/>After 382 iterations, the optimal feasible solutions are determined and are listed in Table 5. Based on <lb/>these optimized parameters, a new wheel model is established and analyzed, resulting in a wheel drag <lb/>coefficient of 0.883. This represents a 5.7% decrease compared to the original drag coefficient of 0.934. <lb/>Table 5: Comparison of aerodynamic drag coefficients between original and optimized <lb/>L 1 (L 2 )/mm <lb/>R 1 /mm <lb/>R 2 /mm <lb/>α/rad <lb/>C d <lb/>Original wheel <lb/>35.693 <lb/>8 <lb/>55 <lb/>0.384 <lb/>0.934 <lb/>Optimized wheel <lb/>33.905 <lb/>8.473 <lb/>53.016 <lb/>0.393 <lb/>0.883 <lb/>4 Results Analysis and Discussion <lb/>4.1 Flow Field around Wheel <lb/>To investigate the impact of the optimized wheel spoke on the flow field and aerodynamic drag, <lb/>several vertical sections and a longitudinal section are analyzed to compare the flow field information <lb/>before and after optimization, as depicted in Fig. 18. This analysis aims to reveal the differences <lb/>resulting from the optimized wheel spoke design. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>967 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 18: Four different sections <lb/>The pressure drag represents the primary component of the aerodynamic drag. Fig. 19 illustrates <lb/>the pressure distribution in the Y = 0 section of the wheel. It is evident that the air pressure around the <lb/>front of the wheel remains relatively unchanged, while the pressure at the rear undergoes noticeable <lb/>changes, with increased pressure values. The observed increase in pressure magnitude indicates a <lb/>decrease in pressure drag, resulting in a reduced overall wheel drag. <lb/>Figure 19: Pressure of longitudinal plane in wheel before and after optimization <lb/>Fig. 20 illustrates the streamlines and vorticity within the wheel cavity at different Z-direction <lb/>sections. Due to the obstructive effect of the wheel, the airflow initially separates at the front edge of the <lb/>wheel, forming two streams that propagate downstream. The presence of the wheel cavity introduces <lb/>unsteady flow characteristics and generates numerous flow vortices in the low-velocity airflow. When <lb/></body>

	<page>968 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>the airflow impacts the rear edges of the wheel cavity, the airflow velocity around the inner edge <lb/>decreases while vorticity increases. Under the driving effect of high-speed airflow from the front edge, <lb/>the vorticity within the inside zone is greater than that in the outside zone. With improved ventilation <lb/>capacity of the spoke, the vorticity distribution within the cavity of the optimized wheel is smaller <lb/>compared to the original wheel. Fig. 20a demonstrates minimal changes in the flow field around the <lb/>outside zone of the wheel, while significant differences are observed in the vicinity of the inside zone. <lb/>The optimized rim design displaces the vortex core backward and reduces the vorticity in the central <lb/>region. However, the vorticity intensity within the optimized wheel cavity is higher than that of the <lb/>original wheel. Fig. 20b compares the flow field at the Z = 0 mm section. Although the flow field <lb/>behind the wheel appears similar, the optimized wheel features a wider opening that more effectively <lb/>directs the airflow into the wheel cavity, resulting in a larger region of streamline vortices near the inner <lb/>edge of the rim. Fig. 20c reveals the presence of vortex pairs behind the optimized wheel, which are <lb/>absent in the original wheel. The vortices within the optimized wheel cavity exhibit relatively uniform <lb/>magnitudes, indicating a more stable airflow and reduced flow energy losses. Moreover, the regions of <lb/>higher vorticity in the optimized wheel are smaller compared to those in the original wheel. <lb/>Figure 20: Comparison of vorticity distribution in different sections <lb/>4.2 Aerodynamic Characteristics of Ahmed Body with Wheel <lb/>Fig. 21 illustrates the comparison of the time-average pressure coefficient distributions on the <lb/>body surfaces. It can be observed that compared to the original wheel, the pressure coefficient around <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>969 <lb/></page>

	<body>the front wheel increases while it decreases around the rear wheel. This indicates that the rim spoke <lb/>structure has a direct influence on the airflow movement around the wheel. As for the back surface <lb/>of the car body, the pressure coefficient reduces on the slant rear surface, but due to changes in <lb/>airflow conditions in the under-body gap, there is a significant increase in the pressure coefficient <lb/>on the vertical rear surface. The drag coefficients are presented in Table 6. It can be seen that the <lb/>drag coefficient of the Ahmed body is reduced by 4.7%, while the front and rear wheels experience a <lb/>reduction of 16.7% and 17.1% in drag coefficient, respectively. From these findings, it can be concluded <lb/>that improving the geometric characteristics of the wheel&apos;s aerodynamic shape is an effective measure <lb/>to enhance automotive aerodynamic performance and reduce drag. <lb/>Figure 21: Comparison of surface pressure coefficients around different Ahmed body <lb/>Table 6: Before and after optimization of vehicle aerodynamic drag coefficient <lb/>C d of the car model <lb/>C d of the front wheel <lb/>C d of the rear wheel <lb/>Original model <lb/>0.402 <lb/>0.0364 <lb/>0.0246 <lb/>Optimized model <lb/>0.384 <lb/>0.0312 <lb/>0.0210 <lb/>The iso-surface of zero total pressure coefficient is selected to characterize the location, strength, <lb/>and size of flow separation, and the difference in the distribution of zero total pressure coefficient is <lb/>used to clarify the reasons for pressure drag [27]. Fig. 22 displays the iso-surface of zero total pressure <lb/>coefficient for the original wheel and optimized wheel. It is evident that the size of the zero total <lb/>pressure coefficient region is larger for the original front and rear wheels compared to the optimized <lb/>wheel. This indicates that the structural changes in the wheel spoke have a direct influence on the <lb/>airflow movements around the wheel, which also extends to the wake flow. Drag reduction relies on <lb/>pressure recovery around the car body. As depicted in Fig. 22, the separation bubbles around the front <lb/>wheel are larger than those around the rear wheel in both the original and optimized configurations. <lb/>This implies that the pressure recovery in the front wheel is slower, resulting in higher aerodynamic <lb/>drag compared to the rear wheel [5,28]. In comparison, the optimized wheel exhibits suppressed flow <lb/>separation and reduced separation bubble size based on the differences in the iso-surface of zero total <lb/>pressure coefficient. This delay in flow separation leads to a decrease in velocity fluctuations and <lb/>turbulent kinetic energy. Consequently, the aerodynamic performance of the Ahmed body with the <lb/>optimized wheel is improved. <lb/></body>

	<page>970 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 22: Iso-surface of zero total pressure coefficient for car body with different wheel model <lb/>The Q-criterion is based on the second invariant of the velocity gradient denoted as Q, which also <lb/>includes the condition that the ambient pressure should be higher than the pressure of the vortex to <lb/>separate it. The identification of vortex structures using the Q-criterion has been applied in vehicle <lb/>aerodynamics [29]. Fig. 23 illustrates the Q-criterion for the original and optimized wheel. In the <lb/>case of the front wheel, the large-scale vortical structure encompassing the five spoke appears similar <lb/>in both the original and optimized configurations. Additionally, there is a distinct horseshoe vortex <lb/>structure observed around the leeward side of the front wheel. However, in the optimized wheel, the <lb/>vortex development on the leeward side is reduced compared to the original wheel, indicating lower <lb/>fluctuations in the turbulent flow. <lb/>Figure 23: Vortex structure of front wheels before and after optimization (Q = 40000) <lb/>For the rear wheel, the original wheel model exhibits a prominent vortex structure on the windward <lb/>side, extending towards the spoke as depicted in Fig. 24. However, this large vortex is absent in the <lb/>optimized wheel, indicating effective control of flow separation on the windward side. In the optimized <lb/>wheel, the development of vortices on the leeward side of the rear wheel is reduced compared to the <lb/>original wheel. Additionally, the longitudinal vortex development is shorter and exhibits lower strength <lb/>and intensity compared to the original wheel. These differences in vortex structures imply that the <lb/>available kinetic energy for the eddies is reduced at an earlier stage. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>971 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 24: Vortex structure of rear wheel before and after optimization (Q = 40000) <lb/>The boundary layer distribution on four planes, defined by the range of velocities less than 0.99u, <lb/>is depicted in Fig. 25a. Fig. 25b presents a comparison of the boundary layer between the original <lb/>wheel and the optimized wheel. The values in the figure represent the normalized airflow velocity <lb/>using U/U in , where U in corresponds to the inlet velocity of 40 m/s. From Fig. 25b, it can be observed <lb/>that the boundary layer thickness around the wheel gradually increases along the car body, while the <lb/>velocity gradient decreases. However, there are differences in the boundary layer thickness around the <lb/>top of the car body. In plane P2, the boundary layer thickness is smaller for the original wheel, resulting <lb/>in higher viscous drag on the original car body. Conversely, in plane P4, the boundary layer thickness <lb/>is smaller for the optimized wheel, leading to higher viscous drag on the optimized car body. These <lb/>differences in the boundary layer affect the velocity field and result in variations in the iso-surface <lb/>of zero total pressure coefficient (Fig. 8). Therefore, it can be inferred that the pressure drag plays a <lb/>dominant role in the overall aerodynamic performance compared to the viscous drag. <lb/>Figure 25: (Continued) <lb/></body>

	<page>972 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 25: Locations and boundary layer distribution for the different four plane <lb/>The turbulent kinetic energy (TKE) is a crucial parameter that serves to connect the mechanisms of <lb/>drag reduction. It represents the mean kinetic energy available per unit mass of turbulent eddies. Fig. 26 <lb/>illustrates the variation in TKE for the original and optimized wheel. The TKE is predominantly <lb/>concentrated on the upper slant surface. As the distance increases in the wake region, the TKE <lb/>decreases. However, when compared to the original wheel, the TKE in the surrounding flow area <lb/>exhibits a significant decrease. This indicates that the size of the low-vortex region is larger, and the <lb/>dissipation of flow energy can be effectively controlled. Typically, lower TKE signifies more stable <lb/>velocity pulsations, which may result in larger vortices and lower base pressure. This observation aligns <lb/>with the findings from the pressure coefficient results presented in Fig. 21. <lb/>Figure 26: (Continued) <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>973 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 26: Turbulent kinetic energy at different planes in the original and optimized wheel <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>This study aimed to numerically investigate the influence of wheel spoke design on the aerody-<lb/>namics of an isolated wheel and the Ahmed model. The main conclusions are as follows: <lb/>(1) The aerodynamic characteristics of an isolated wheel are studied through numerical simulation, <lb/>focusing on four design parameters of wheel spoke: the fillet angle α, inside arc radius R 1 , outside <lb/>radius R 2 , and chord length L 1 . The drag coefficient is selected as the objective. Using the Optimal <lb/>Latin Hypercube (OLH) design, 20 sample points are generated, and their corresponding drag <lb/>coefficients are calculated. Sensitivity analysis revealed that the angle α had the greatest impact on <lb/>the drag coefficient, followed by the outside arc radius R 1 , while the arc tangent lines L 1 and L 2 had <lb/>minimal influence. <lb/>(2) By utilizing the integrated approach of the Kriging surrogate model and adaptive simulated <lb/>annealing algorithm, the optimal design parameters of the wheel spoke are obtained. Comparative <lb/>analysis of the flow fields between the original and optimized wheels demonstrated that the optimized <lb/>wheel influenced the airflow state inside the wheel cavity, reducing flow instability around the wheel. <lb/>As a result, the optimized wheel achieved a drag reduction of 5.7%. <lb/>(3) The aerodynamic drag of an Ahmed body equipped with the original and optimized wheel <lb/>is investigated, revealing a decrease of 4.7% in the drag coefficient for the Ahmed body with the <lb/>optimized wheel. Analysis of flow features indicated that the drag reduction primarily relied on <lb/>changes in the flow state around the wheel to suppress separation bubbles, as well as the influence on <lb/>boundary layer thickness around the car body and reduction of turbulent kinetic energy in the wake <lb/>flow. Further investigations can focus on developing new active or passive devices, for example the <lb/>active drag reduction of bionic non-smooth surface and the passive drag reduction of vortex generator, <lb/>to further reduce drag and enhance aerodynamic performance of the wheel and the vehicle. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: The authors are grateful for the support by the National Natural Science <lb/>Foundation of China, and Postdoctoral Foundation of China. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: The authors are pleased to acknowledge funding of the National Natural Sci-<lb/>ence Foundation of China (Nos. 52072156, 51605198), and Postdoctoral Foundation of China <lb/>(2020M682269). <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: The authors confirm contribution to the paper as follows: study conception <lb/>and design: Huihui Zhai; data collection: Dongqi Jiao; analysis and interpretation of results: Haichao <lb/></div>

	<page>974 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<div type="contribution">Zhou; draft manuscript preparation: Huihui Zhai. All authors reviewed the results and approved the <lb/>final version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: The data undering this article will be shared on reasonable request <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Huminic, A., Huminic, G. (2017). Aerodynamic study of a generic car model with wheels and underbody <lb/>diffuser. International Journal of Automotive Technology, 18, 397-404. <lb/>2. Altaf, A., Omar, A. A., Asrar, W. (2014). Passive drag reduction of square back road vehicles. Journal of <lb/>Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 134, 30-43. <lb/>3. Yang, X., Hu, Y., Gong, Z., Jian, J., Liu, Z. (2021). Numerical study of combined drag reduction bases <lb/>on vortex generators and riblets for the ahmed body using IDDES methodology. Journal of Applied Fluid <lb/>Mechanics, 15(1), 193-207. <lb/>4. Kim, D., Lee, H., Yi, W., Choi, H. (2016). A bio-inspired device for drag reduction on a three-dimensional <lb/>model vehicle. Bioinspiration &amp; Biomimetics, 11(2), 026004. <lb/>5. Yu, X., Jia, Q., Yang, Z. (2022). Comprehensive study of the aerodynamic influence of ground and wheel <lb/>states on the notchback DrivAer. JEnergies, 15(3), 1-33. <lb/>6. Zhou, H., Jiang, Z., Wang, G., Zhang, S. (2021). Aerodynamic characteristics of isolated loaded tires with <lb/>different tread patterns: Experiment and simulation. Chinese Journal of Mechanical Engineering, 34, 1-16. <lb/>7. Josefsson, E., Hobeika, T., Sebben, S. (2022). Evaluation of wind tunnel interference on numerical prediction <lb/>of wheel aerodynamics. Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 224, 104945. <lb/>8. Jiang, F., Niu, J., Li, R., Wang, Y., Zhang, Y. (2023). Computational fluid dynamics analysis of effect <lb/>of braking plate configurations on the aerodynamic behaviors of an ahmed car. Flow, Turbulence and <lb/>Combustion, 110(2), 301-323. <lb/>9. Fackrell, J. E. (1974). The aerodynamic of an isolated tire rotating in contact with ground (Ph.D. Thesis). <lb/>University of London, London. <lb/>10. Brandt, A., Berg, H., Bolzon, M., Josefsson, L. (2019). The effects of wheel design on the aerodynamic <lb/>drag of passenger vehicles. SAE International Journal of Advances and Current Practices in Mobility, 1(3), <lb/>1279-1299. <lb/>11. Fang, J., Wang, F. L. (2019). A study on CFD simulation and wind tunnel test on aerodynamic effects of <lb/>wheel rotation and drag reduction optimization. Automotive Engineering, 41(9), 1006-1012. <lb/>12. Fu, L., Hu, X., Zhang, S. (2006). Numerical simulation of influence of holes in wheel spokes on automotive <lb/>external flow-field. Nongye Jixie Xuebao (Transactions of the Chinese Society of Agricultural Machinery), <lb/>37(1), 8-11 (In Chinese). <lb/>13. Elofsson, P., Bannister, M. (2002). Drag reduction mechanisms due to moving ground and wheel rotation <lb/>in passenger cars. SAE Technical Paper, 2002-01-0531. <lb/>14. Saddington, A. J., Knowles, R. D., Knowles, K. (2007). Laser Doppler anemometry measurements in the <lb/>near-wake of an isolated formula one wheel. Experiments in Fluids, 42(5), 671-681. <lb/>15. Croner, E., Bézard, H., Sicot, C., Mothay, G. (2013). Aerodynamic characterization of the wake of an <lb/>isolated rolling wheel. International Journal of Heat and Fluid Flow, 43, 233-243. <lb/>16. Qiu, Z. (2009). Wheel aerodynamic developments by module-based prototype rims and stationary rim shields <lb/>(Ph.D. Thesis). Chalmers University of Technology, Gothenburg. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">CMES, 2024, vol.139, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>975 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>17. Strachan, R. K., Knowles, K., Lawson, N. J. (2007). The vortex structure behind an ahmed reference model <lb/>in the presence of a moving ground plane. Experiments in Fluids, 42(5), 659-669. <lb/>18. Corallo, M., Sheridan, J., Thompson, M. C. (2015). Effect of aspect ratio on the near-wake flow structure <lb/>of an ahmed body. Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 147, 95-103. <lb/>19. Diasinos, S., Barber, T. J., Doig, G. (2015). The effects of simplifications on isolated wheel aerodynamics. <lb/>Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 146, 90-101. <lb/>20. Liang, H., Sun, Y., Li, T., Zhang, J. (2022). Influence of marshalling length on aerodynamic characteristics <lb/>of urban EMUs under crosswind. Journal of Applied Fluid Mechanics, 16(1), 9-20. <lb/>21. Ahmed, S. (1984). Some salient features of the time-averaged ground vehicle wake. SAE Paper, 840300. <lb/>22. Siddiqui, N. A., Chaab, M. A. (2020). A simple passive device for the drag reduction of an ahmed body. <lb/>Journal of Applied Fluid Mechanics, 14(1), 147-164. <lb/>23. Meile, W., Brenn, G., Reppenhagen, A., Lechner, B., Fuchs, A. (2011). Experiments and numerical <lb/>simulations on the aerodynamics of the ahmed body. CFD Letters, 3(1), 32-39. <lb/>24. Montazeri, F., Tavakoli, M. R., Salimpour, M. R. (2023). Improving thermal performance of rectangular <lb/>microchannel heat sinks using porous layer: CFD simulation and optimization. Journal of Applied Fluid <lb/>Mechanics, 16(8), 1574-1586. <lb/>25. Park, J. S. (1994). Optimal latin-hypercube designs for computer experiments. Journal of Statistical Planning <lb/>and Inference, 39(1), 95-111. <lb/>26. Zhang, L., Zhou, H., Wang, G., Li, H., Wang, Q. (2022). Investigation of effects of tire contour on <lb/>aerodynamic characteristics and its optimization. Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, <lb/>Part D: Journal of Automobile Engineering, 236(12), 2756-2772. <lb/>27. McArthur, D., Burton, D., Thompson, M., Sheridan, J. (2018). An experimental characterisation of the <lb/>wake of a detailed heavy vehicle in cross-wind. Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, <lb/>175, 364-375. <lb/>28. Wang, Y., Sicot, C., Boree, J., Grandemange, M. (2020). Experimental study of wheel-vehicle aerodynamic <lb/>interactions. Journal of Wind Engineering and Industrial Aerodynamics, 198, 104062. <lb/>29. Zhou, H., Chen, Q., Qin, R., Zhang, L., Li, H. (2021). Investigation of wheelhouse shapes on the <lb/>aerodynamic characteristics of a generic car model. Advances in Mechanical Engineering, 13(12), <lb/>16878140211066842. </listBibl>

  </text>

</TEI>