<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:29:45.645Z">11/20/2025 10:29:45 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:29:33.895125Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:29:33.895125Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Frontiers in Medicine <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/>Diagnostic test performance of <lb/>the Mentzer index in evaluating <lb/>Saudi children with microcytosis <lb/>Amani M. AlQarni 1 , Arwa Althumairi 2 *, Nourah K. Alkaltham 2 , <lb/>Samaa AlJishi 3 , Amani Mohammed Hakami 4 , Leena Mohamed <lb/>Osman Ali Abdalla 3,5 , Zahra Sayed Jalal Alawi 3,6 and <lb/>Abdullah H. Alreedy 1 <lb/>1 Family and Community Medicine Department, King Fahd Hospital of the University, Imam <lb/>Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, Dammam, Saudi Arabia, 2 Department of Health Information <lb/>Management and Technology, College of Public Health, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, <lb/>Dammam, Saudi Arabia, 3 King Fahad Hospital of University, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, <lb/>Alkhobar, Saudi Arabia, 4 College of Medicine, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, Dammam, <lb/>Saudi Arabia, 5 College of Medicine, University of Khartoum, Khartoum, Sudan, Khartoum, Sudan, <lb/>6 Faculty of Medicine, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt <lb/>Background: Anemia is a global public health concern, affecting both <lb/>developing and industrialized countries at a rate of 39.8%. It is defined by low <lb/>hemoglobin concentration, and anemia varies in severity based on age: &lt;11 g/dL <lb/>(6-59 months), &lt;11.5 g/dL (5-11 years), and &lt; 12 g/dL (12-14 years). <lb/>Aim: This study evaluates the Mentzer index&apos;s reliability in differentiating iron <lb/>deficiency anemia from the thalassemia trait. <lb/>Methods: A total of 434 children (≤16 years) with hemoglobin electrophoresis <lb/>previously screened for microcytosis (MCV &lt;80 FL) and an iron profile were <lb/>included. Children with other hematological conditions were excluded. <lb/>Results: Out of 434 children, 181 were diagnosed with thalassemia, and 345 <lb/>had iron deficiency anemia. The Mentzer index showed 74% sensitivity and 63% <lb/>specificity for the beta-thalassemia trait, with 61% sensitivity and 36% specificity <lb/>for iron deficiency anemia. The beta-thalassemia trait group had the highest <lb/>negative predictive value (98%), while iron deficiency anemia had the highest <lb/>positive predictive value (79%). <lb/>Conclusion: Our study, which is consistent with previous literature, suggests <lb/>that the Mentzer index is not highly reliable in distinguishing iron deficiency <lb/>anemia from the thalassemia trait among children in Saudi Arabia. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>microcytosis, Mentzer index, diagnostic test performance, iron deficiency anemia, <lb/>thalassemia <lb/></front>

    <body>Introduction <lb/>According to international organizations, 1.62 billion people worldwide suffer from <lb/>anemia, making it one of the 10 most serious health problems. In 2019, the prevalence of <lb/>anemia among children aged 6-59 months was 39.8% worldwide, with the highest prevalence <lb/>of 60.2% in the African region. Although the prevalence of anemia has decreased from 48.0% <lb/>in 2000 to 39.8% in 2019, it has remained stagnant since 2010. The World Health Organization <lb/></body>

    <front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Eleni Gavriilaki, <lb/>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Joan-lluis Vives-Corrons, <lb/>Josep Carreras Leukaemia Research Institute <lb/>(IJC), Spain <lb/>Xiuqin Bao, <lb/>Guangdong Province Women and Children <lb/>Hospital, China <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Arwa Althumairi <lb/>aalthumairi@iau.edu.sa <lb/>RECEIVED 14 January 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 05 July 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 29 July 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>AlQarni AM, Althumairi A, Alkaltham NK, <lb/>AlJishi S, Hakami AM, Abdalla LMOA, <lb/>Alawi ZSJ and Alreedy AH (2024) Diagnostic <lb/>test performance of the Mentzer index in <lb/>evaluating Saudi children with microcytosis. <lb/>Front. Med. 11:1361805. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 AlQarni, Althumairi, Alkaltham, AlJishi, <lb/>Hakami, Abdalla, Alawi and Alreedy. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic <lb/>practice. No use, distribution or reproduction <lb/>is permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 29 July 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></front>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/></note>

    <page>02 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>(WHO) estimates the prevalence of anemia among children under <lb/>5 years of age to be 21.8% in Saudi Arabia (1). <lb/>Anemia is a public health problem in both developing and <lb/>industrialized countries, but it is more prevalent in developing <lb/>countries, especially among women and children, who are particularly <lb/>vulnerable to its effects (2). Anemia is a multifactorial disease <lb/>influenced by multiple etiologies, including nutritional deficiencies, <lb/>genetics, and socioeconomic status, all of which are strongly associated <lb/>with its prevalence. Furthermore, anemia in childhood has been <lb/>linked to a greater risk of growth delay, poor cognitive and motor <lb/>development, and a higher susceptibility to infections (2). <lb/>The WHO defines anemia in childhood based on hemoglobin <lb/>(Hb) concentration levels, taking into consideration the age of the <lb/>child. For children aged 6-59 months, a level of &lt;11 g/dL is considered <lb/>anemia, while for children aged 5-11 years and older children aged <lb/>12-14 years, the levels of &lt;11.5 g/dL and &lt; 12 g/dL, respectively, are <lb/>considered anemia (3). <lb/>Anemia is typically caused by three main mechanisms: ineffective <lb/>erythropoiesis, hemolysis, and blood loss. Many etiologies have been <lb/>attributed to anemia, but the most common contributors are <lb/>nutritional deficiencies, diseases, and genetic Hb disorders (4). <lb/>Iron deficiency is the most common cause of anemia, contributing <lb/>to approximately 42% of cases in children under 5 years of age <lb/>worldwide and 50% of cases in non-pregnant and pregnant women (4, <lb/>5). Conditions that require an increase in the number of red blood <lb/>cells (RBCs) include growing infants or the development of a fetus <lb/>during pregnancy. When there is insufficient dietary iron intake to <lb/>meet iron needs, iron deficiency anemia (IDA) develops, as iron is an <lb/>essential component of the Hb molecule, which affects the production <lb/>of RBCs (2). <lb/>IDA is characterized by hypochromic, microcytic anemia, <lb/>associated with lower levels of iron. Patients with IDA may present <lb/>with symptoms such as pallor of the skin, dyspnea, fatigue, and <lb/>headache (6). <lb/>IDA has several etiologies, including physiological, pathological, <lb/>environmental, drug-related, and genetic causes. Physiological causes <lb/>include rapid growth, pregnancy, and blood donation, while decreased <lb/>absorption and chronic blood loss are considered pathological <lb/>etiologies (6). <lb/>Various factors contribute to a child&apos;s susceptibility to developing <lb/>IDA, including premature birth or low birth weight, the use of <lb/>non-iron-fortified formula or early introduction of cow&apos;s milk in the <lb/>first year of life, and exclusive breastfeeding without consistent <lb/>consumption of iron-fortified food beyond 6 months of age (7). <lb/>The diagnosis of IDA can be achieved by measuring ferritin levels, <lb/>as it is the first laboratory test to decrease in cases of iron deficiency <lb/>(8). Ferritin is considered the most sensitive test for diagnosing IDA <lb/>(7, 9). However, ferritin levels can be influenced by acute-phase <lb/>reactants, leading to less accurate measurements under conditions of <lb/>concurrent infection or inflammation (10). <lb/>Genetic Hb disorders, such as sickle cell trait and thalassemia, are <lb/>among the three main contributors to anemia globally (4). Annually, <lb/>more than 300,000 children are predicted to be born with sickle cell <lb/>anemia or various forms of thalassemia, predominantly impacting <lb/>regions in South and Southeast Asia (11). <lb/>In Gulf countries, including Saudi Arabia, the prevalence of <lb/>thalassemia in children under the age of 5 years ranges from 0.25 to <lb/>33%, while in children aged 5 years and above, it is estimated to <lb/>be 0.9% (12). In the western region of Saudi Arabia, thalassemia is one <lb/>of the most common blood disorders, with a prevalence of 40%, <lb/>including 4.69% in beta-thalassemia and 35.86% in alpha-thalassemia <lb/>(α-thalassemia) (13). <lb/>Thalassemia is a genetic disorder characterized by decreased <lb/>synthesis of alpha or beta chains of Hb. There are two types of <lb/>thalassemia: α-thalassemia and beta-thalassemia, which can vary in <lb/>severity. α-thalassemia occurs when one or more of the globin genes <lb/>are mutated, and it is classified as silent carrier, α-thalassemia trait <lb/>(α-TT), hemoglobin H (HbH) disease, and α-thalassemia major (Hb <lb/>Bart). Beta-thalassemia, on the other hand, is classified as beta-<lb/>thalassemia major (transfusion-dependent thalassemia or TDT), beta-<lb/>thalassemia intermedia, and β-thalassemia trait (β-TT). Patients with <lb/>TDT typically experience severe symptoms and require regular blood <lb/>transfusions, while βTT patients can remain asymptomatic and lead a <lb/>healthy life (14). <lb/>For the diagnosis of thalassemia, a physical examination and <lb/>detailed medical and family history are required. Additionally, certain <lb/>RBC indices can raise suspicion of thalassemia, specifically low mean <lb/>corpuscular volume (MCV), low mean corpuscular Hb level (MCH), <lb/>and normal red cell distribution width (RDW). However, to confirm <lb/>the diagnosis, Hb electrophoresis and DNA analysis are necessary <lb/>(15, 16). <lb/>RBC indices are also crucial in differentiating the causes of <lb/>anemia, and numerous studies have explored their diagnostic <lb/>significance. These include the Kerman index, Mentzer index, Shine <lb/>and Lal index, and England and Fraser index. The Mentzer Index, first <lb/>described in 1973 by William Mentzer, is calculated by dividing the <lb/>MCV by the RBC (14). <lb/>Numerous studies have evaluated the reliability of the Mentzer <lb/>Index in differentiating between beta-thalassemia and IDA. It has <lb/>been shown to have a sensitivity of 98.7% and a specificity of 82.3% <lb/>compared to other hematological indices. In other studies, it has also <lb/>been considered a simple screening tool (17, 18). <lb/>Purpose <lb/>This study aims to assess the sensitivity and specificity of the <lb/>calculated Mentzer index to predict iron deficiency and <lb/>thalassemia traits. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design <lb/>This study used a quantitative cross-sectional design based on a <lb/>secondary dataset. <lb/>Study population and study power <lb/>The retrospective data collection process involved accessing the <lb/>hospital database to retrieve information on patients who underwent <lb/>Hb electrophoresis and iron profile for microcytic RBCs as part of <lb/>their complete blood count (CBC) from 2014 to 2021 at a single <lb/>hospital. To ensure the appropriateness of the study sample, specific <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/></note>

    <page>03 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>inclusion and exclusion criteria were applied. Patients who met the <lb/>inclusion criteria were included in the study. Initially, there were 1,009 <lb/>children in the pool, but ultimately, only a total of 434 patients <lb/>were included. <lb/>Inclusion criteria <lb/>The following are the inclusion criteria for the study: <lb/>Children aged 16 years and below who were previously <lb/>investigated for microcytosis (MCV &lt; 80 fl) using a hematology <lb/>analyzer (Abbott Alinity HQ). <lb/>Patients who underwent Hb electrophoresis using capillary <lb/>electrophoresis (Capillarys 2 Flex Piercing instrument). <lb/>Patients who had an iron profile with ferritin level measured in <lb/>ng/ml (using Abbott Alinity I), serum iron level measured in ug/dl <lb/>(using Abbott Alinity c), transferrin level measured in mg/dl (using <lb/>Abbott Alinity c), iron-binding capacity measured in ug/dl (using <lb/>Abbott Alinity c), and calculated transferrin percentage saturation. <lb/>Reference ranges for The iron profile were As follows: Serum iron <lb/>(65-175 ug/dl for male subjects and 50-170 ug/dl for female subjects), <lb/>transferrin level (186-388 mg/dL for girls and 180-391 mg/dL for boys <lb/>In pediatric Age), and iron-binding capacity (250-400 ug/dl for all age <lb/>and sex). <lb/>Exclusion criteria <lb/>The following are the exclusion criteria for the study: <lb/>Patients with coexisting hematological conditions such as <lb/>autoimmune hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia, or lead intoxication. <lb/>Patients with the coexistence of β-TT and IDA in the same patient. <lb/>The study power was estimated using the G*Power application. <lb/>With an effect size of 0.3, a probability of error of 0.05, and degrees of <lb/>freedom of 5, the study power was calculated to be 0.99. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>Patient data including date of birth, sex, Hb level, hematocrits, <lb/>MCV, MCH, mean corpuscular Hb concentration (MCHC), RBC <lb/>value, RDW, white blood count (WBC), platelets, iron level, ferritin <lb/>value, and Hb electrophoresis (Hb A2, Hb A) were collected from <lb/>hospital databases, which was performed using capillary zone <lb/>electrophoresis, and CBC was performed using Alinity HQ. <lb/>The Mentzer index was calculated by dividing MCV in Femtoliter <lb/>(Fl) by RBC counts in millions per microliter (19, 20). <lb/>Mentzer index = mean corpuscular volume (in fL)/RBC count (in <lb/>millions per microliter). <lb/>Mentzer Index <lb/>Meancorpuscular volume in fL <lb/>RBC count in millions <lb/>= <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>p per microliter. <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>If the test results are&gt;13, the patient will be classified as having <lb/>IDA, while if the patient scores &lt;13, then the patient will be classified <lb/>as having a thalassemia trait (21). Laboratory standard tests for IDA <lb/>and thalassemia are as follows: <lb/>• IDA occurs when ferritin level = &lt; 4.63 ng/mL or transferrin <lb/>saturation is &lt;20%. <lb/>• Thalassemia occurs when serum ferritin is &gt;12 ng/mL and the <lb/>red blood cell count is high. <lb/>• Alpha (à)*thalassemia trait: (* suspected cases of α-thalassemia, <lb/>as confirmation can only be performed by molecular <lb/>genetic study): <lb/>1 HbA2 &lt; 4% <lb/>2 HbF &lt; 1% <lb/>• β-TT: <lb/>3 HbA2 = &gt; 4% <lb/>4 HbF 0.1-5% <lb/>All data were analyzed using a descriptive analysis; frequency and <lb/>percentage for categorical data (sex and age group) and median and <lb/>interquartile range (IQR) for continuous data (as data were not <lb/>normally distributed). For the bivariate analysis, the chi-square test <lb/>was used to compare the significant difference between the Mentzer <lb/>index and the laboratory test. <lb/>Results <lb/>In this study, a total of 434 cases were included, as shown in <lb/>Table 1. Among these cases, 345 were confirmed to have iron <lb/>deficiency, while 181 were suspected to have thalassemia. Out of the <lb/>suspected thalassemia cases, only 19 were confirmed to have the β-TT, <lb/>as indicated in Figure 1. <lb/>In terms of sex distribution, the majority of cases were female <lb/>subjects, accounting for 70% of the study population. When <lb/>considering the age groups, the highest proportion of cases (37%) fell <lb/>within the 13-16-year-old group. Among the groups classified with a <lb/>Mentzer index &lt;13, the proportion of female subjects was higher at <lb/>75% compared to 66% in the &gt; = 13 group. On the other hand, male <lb/>subjects were more prevalent in the &gt; = 13 group at 34% compared to <lb/>25% in the &lt;13 group. <lb/>Regarding the age distribution within the Mentzer index <lb/>categories, the majority of children classified as Mentzer index &lt;13 <lb/>belonged to the 2-6-year-old age group, accounting for 38% of these <lb/>cases. For the Mentzer index &gt;13 group, the majority fell within the <lb/>13-16-year-old age group, representing 39% of the cases, as shown in <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>Using the Mentzer index as a diagnostic tool, it was found that 71 <lb/>out of the 181 suspected thalassemia cases had a score &lt; 13, while 135 <lb/>out of the 345 cases were classified as having a score &gt; =13, indicating <lb/>IDA, as depicted in Figure 1. Notably, the highest number of <lb/>confirmed beta-thalassemia cases were classified as &lt;13 using the <lb/>Mentzer index, with only 5 cases falling into the &gt; = 13 group. <lb/>In terms of the performance of the Mentzer index, it showed the <lb/>highest sensitivity and specificity scores for the β-TT, with a sensitivity <lb/>of 74% and a specificity of 63%, as presented in Table 2. Iron deficiency <lb/>showed a sensitivity of 61% and a specificity of 36%. Similarly, the <lb/>negative predictive value (NPV) was the highest for the beta-<lb/>thalassemia group at 98%, while the positive predictive value (PPV) <lb/>was the highest for IDA at 79%. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/></note>

    <page>04 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>Discussion <lb/>The purpose of this research is to study the Mentzer Index and its <lb/>reliability as a simple, inexpensive diagnostic tool in children aged 16 <lb/>and younger in Saudi Arabia for differentiating between IDA and <lb/>thalassemia traits. Although IDA and thalassemia are both types of <lb/>conditions that can cause microcytic anemia, each type has a different <lb/>cause, prognosis, and treatment (22). <lb/>The Mentzer index was first described by Mentzer in 1973 and <lb/>is calculated by dividing the MCV by the RBCs (23). A Mentzer <lb/>index value of lower than 13 shows that the patient has thalassemia, <lb/>while an index greater than 13 suggests that the patient has <lb/>IDA (24). <lb/>Based on the Mentzer index, our data indicate that 181 of the total <lb/>cases were classified as thalassemia, while 345 were classified as <lb/>IDA. The sensitivity was higher in the beta group (74%), and the <lb/>specificity was 61% for all thalassemia groups. <lb/>Our results suggest that the Mentzer index has high sensitivity <lb/>(74%) and higher specificity (63%) for identifying patients with beta-<lb/>thalassemia. Contrarily, it showed low sensitivity for α-thalassemia, <lb/>where the sensitivity is 34% and the specificity is 58%. Overall, the <lb/>Mentzer index results suggest low sensitivity (39%) and high <lb/>specificity (61%) for all thalassemia patients. <lb/>Regarding IDA, analysis results show that the sensitivity and <lb/>specificity of the Mentzer index results were 61 and 38%, <lb/>respectively. Hence, these findings indicate that the Mentzer <lb/>index is more reliable in diagnosing IDA with a PPV of 79%, <lb/>excluding βTT with an NPV of 98%, and suspected αTT with an <lb/>NPV of 60%. <lb/>Our results are inconsistent with the findings reported by <lb/>Ahmed et al. where the sensitivity and specificity of the Mentzer <lb/>index were 95.24 and 93.10%, respectively, compared to 61% <lb/>sensitivity and 38% specificity for IDA, and 74 and 63% of <lb/>sensitivity and specificity, respectively, for βTT in our results (25). <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Percentage of cases by anemia groups based on the Mentzer index. <lb/>TABLE 1 Distribution of patient demographic characteristics according to Mentzer classification, n = 434. <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>Calculated Mentzer index <lb/>Total n = 434 <lb/>&lt;13 n = 169 <lb/>&gt; = 13 n = 265 <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Sex (n,%) <lb/>Male <lb/>42 <lb/>25% <lb/>89 <lb/>34% <lb/>131 <lb/>30% <lb/>Female <lb/>127 <lb/>75% <lb/>176 <lb/>66% <lb/>303 <lb/>70% <lb/>Age n (%) <lb/>&gt;2 years-6 years <lb/>65 <lb/>38% <lb/>88 <lb/>33% <lb/>153 <lb/>35% <lb/>7 years-12 years <lb/>45 <lb/>27% <lb/>74 <lb/>28% <lb/>119 <lb/>27% <lb/>13 years-16 years <lb/>59 <lb/>35% <lb/>103 <lb/>39% <lb/>162 <lb/>37% <lb/>Transferrin (median, IQR) (min-max) <lb/>0.34 (0.11-7.26) <lb/>(0-48.0) <lb/>0.26 (0.1-8.4) <lb/>(0-92.4) <lb/>0.3 (0.1-7.6) <lb/>(0-92.5) <lb/>Hemoglobin Electrophoresis A2 (median, IQR) (min-max) <lb/>2.4 (2.0-2.7) <lb/>(0-6.9) <lb/>2.5 (2.1-2.7) <lb/>(0-5.9) <lb/>2.4 (2.1-2.7) <lb/>(0-6.9) <lb/>Ferritin value (median, IQR) (min-max) <lb/>19.0 (4.5-37.2) <lb/>(0-200) <lb/>22.0 (8.3-106.4) <lb/>(0-10930.0) <lb/>21.0 (6.7-56.0) <lb/>(0-10930.6) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/></note>

    <page>05 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>Similarly, our results differed from those of Vehapoglu et al., who <lb/>retrospectively analyzed 290 children with microcytic anemia <lb/>using the Mentzer index and showed good sensitivity (82.3, 98.7%) <lb/>and specificity (98.7, 82.3%) for both the IDA and βTT groups. <lb/>Furthermore, a study conducted by Ahmed et al. enrolled patients <lb/>with microcytic hypochromic anemia aged from 6 months to <lb/>16 years and found that the Mentzer Index is a tool with one of the <lb/>most reliable discriminator indices for differentiating β-TT and <lb/>IDA in Sohag County (22). On the contrary, Düzenli Kar et al. <lb/>reported that the Mentzer index was not determined to be one of <lb/>the most reliable indices in their study (26). Similarly, Sirdah et al. <lb/>reported that the Mentzer index was not the best among the <lb/>evaluated indices in their study (27). <lb/>Similarly, a study published by Sherali et al. collected data <lb/>from Liaquat National Hospital, Karachi, from 1st January to 30th <lb/>June 2022 for children aged 1 to 5 years. They found that the <lb/>Mentzer index has high sensitivity, specificity, and diagnostic <lb/>accuracy, with 80.7% sensitivity and 77.7% specificity, and the PPV <lb/>was 56.8%, while the NPV was 91.6% (28). Besides, Sri L. S. Alam <lb/>et al. recommended the use of the Mentzer index in children aged <lb/>6-12 years with hypochromic-microcytic anemia (29). <lb/>Additionally, a study was conducted to differentiate between βTT <lb/>and iron deficiency anemia in randomly selected Croatian children <lb/>aged 6 months-18 years, who were diagnosed with microcytic <lb/>hypochromic anemia, found that the Mentzer index correctly <lb/>diagnosed children with βTT, but was unsuccessful in <lb/>distinguishing children with IDA (sensitivity 88%, specificity <lb/>48%), and thus, categorized the Mentzer index as low validity as it <lb/>has a low proportion of correctly identified IDA (30). <lb/>In another study, where 200 children were enrolled, the sensitivity <lb/>and specificity of the Mentzer index for the detection of βTT were 100 <lb/>and 69.4%, respectively, while the PPV of the Mentzer index in <lb/>diagnosing βTT was 36.6% and the NPV was 100%. Thus, the Mentzer <lb/>index was found to be a valuable tool in differentiating IDA from TT <lb/>(31). Finally, in a study that included 63 children with microcytic <lb/>anemia aged between 2 and 16 years in 2002, Demir et al. reported <lb/>somewhat similar results to our findings in the present study (see <lb/>Tables 3, 4) (31). <lb/>According to Sri L. S. Alam et al., a screening tool is considered <lb/>good if the sensitivity percentage is ≥ 80%, regardless of the low <lb/>specificity percentage (29). According to Demir et al., studies <lb/>performed to examine the index&apos;s reliability in discriminating <lb/>between IDA and thalassemia in children are limited, and the results <lb/>of these studies are contradictory (32). In addition, no index with <lb/>100% sensitivity and specificity results has been reached for <lb/>discrimination purposes to date. Furthermore, a low number of <lb/>studies in the literature were concerned with α-thalassemia; therefore, <lb/>it was not possible to compare our results with regard to the α-TT. <lb/>Variability in sensitivity and specificity <lb/>This study observed a higher sensitivity (74%) for the <lb/>Mentzer index in identifying β-thalassemia compared to IDA <lb/>(61%). The specificity for β-thalassemia was also higher (63%) <lb/>TABLE 2 Sensitivity and specificity of the Mentzer index for each disease <lb/>classification. <lb/>Disease type Analysis measure <lb/>Percentage <lb/>Beta-thalassemia <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>74% <lb/>Specificity <lb/>63% <lb/>PPV <lb/>8% <lb/>NPV <lb/>98% <lb/>Alpha-thalassemia <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>34% <lb/>Specificity <lb/>58% <lb/>PPV <lb/>33% <lb/>NPV <lb/>60% <lb/>All thalassemia <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>39% <lb/>Specificity <lb/>61% <lb/>PPV <lb/>42% <lb/>NPV <lb/>58% <lb/>Iron deficiency <lb/>anemia <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>61% <lb/>Specificity <lb/>38% <lb/>PPV <lb/>79% <lb/>NPV <lb/>20% <lb/>TABLE 3 The Mentzer index results compared to other studies IDA. <lb/>Study <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>Specificity <lb/>PPV <lb/>NPV <lb/>Current study <lb/>61% <lb/>38% <lb/>79% <lb/>20% <lb/>Ahmed et al. <lb/>95.24% <lb/>93.10% <lb/>90.9% <lb/>96.4% <lb/>Vehapoglu et al. <lb/>82.3% <lb/>98.7% <lb/>98.2% <lb/>86.3% <lb/>Ahmed et al. <lb/>100.00% <lb/>58.76% <lb/>23.95% <lb/>100% <lb/>Düzenli Kar et al. (IDA/α-TT) <lb/>64.52% <lb/>92% <lb/>82.6% <lb/>79.3% <lb/>Sirdah et al. (IDA/ 𝛽-TT) <lb/>82.86% <lb/>83.55% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Sherali et al. <lb/>80.7% <lb/>77.7% <lb/>56.8% <lb/>91.6% <lb/>Sri L. S. Alam et al. <lb/>93% <lb/>84% <lb/>93% <lb/>84% <lb/>Turudic et al. <lb/>88% <lb/>48% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Aydogan et al. <lb/>67.53% <lb/>97.36% <lb/>99.07% <lb/>44.04 <lb/>Demir et al. <lb/>62% <lb/>86% <lb/>76% <lb/>76% <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <body>compared to IDA (38%). These findings were consistent with <lb/>some studies [e.g., (1, 22)]. However, they differ from others, <lb/>where high values for both IDA and β-thalassemia were reported <lb/>[e.g., (2, 3)]. <lb/>Several factors might contribute to these variations: <lb/>• Population differences: the prevalence of specific thalassemia <lb/>traits (α vs. β) and coexisting conditions such as iron deficiency <lb/>can vary geographically and ethnically (4). This can affect the <lb/>index&apos;s performance. <lb/>• Age groups studied: studies focusing on specific age groups <lb/>(e.g., children vs. adults) might show different results due to <lb/>physiological variations in RBC parameters across <lb/>lifespans (5). <lb/>• Iron deficiency severity: the severity of iron deficiency can <lb/>influence RBC indices, potentially impacting the Mentzer Index&apos;s <lb/>discriminatory power (6). <lb/>• Analytical techniques: Variations in laboratory techniques used <lb/>for CBC measurements might introduce slight discrepancies in <lb/>the derived parameters (7). <lb/>Our findings align with studies highlighting the limitations of the <lb/>Mentzer index as a standalone diagnostic tool (7, 8). While it shows <lb/>promise for β-thalassemia detection (high sensitivity), its effectiveness <lb/>for IDA diagnosis is lower (moderate sensitivity and low specificity). <lb/>Additionally, the index performs poorly for α-thalassemia <lb/>(low sensitivity). <lb/>Future research could explore the following areas: <lb/>1 Combined Indices: Investigating the combined use of the <lb/>Mentzer Index with other red blood cell parameters or iron <lb/>studies to enhance diagnostic accuracy. <lb/>2 Population-Specific Cutoff Values: Establishing optimal <lb/>sensitivity and specificity thresholds for the Mentzer Index <lb/>within specific populations, considering the local prevalence <lb/>of thalassemia traits and iron deficiency anemia. <lb/>3 Cost-Effectiveness Analysis: Comparing the cost-<lb/>effectiveness of the Mentzer Index as a screening tool against <lb/>other established methods for diagnosing iron deficiency <lb/>anemia and thalassemia traits. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In summary, it is important to evaluate the reliability of <lb/>diagnostic tests to confirm the presence of disease in patients, rule <lb/>out diseases in healthy individuals, and set a treatment plan. The <lb/>analysis of our results shows lower sensitivity and specificity to <lb/>distinguish between TT and IDA than those in the literature. The <lb/>present study indicates that the Mentzer index is not a highly reliable <lb/>discriminator index for differentiating between TT and IDA in <lb/>children in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. One limitation of our study <lb/>was the small sample size of patients. Consequently, more accurate <lb/>research is needed to evaluate the best diagnostic index that can <lb/>accurately differentiate between TT and IDA in children in the <lb/>Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The datasets presented in this article are not readily available because <lb/>sharing the raw data could potentially identify individual participants, <lb/>which might put them at risk or violate their privacy. We prioritize <lb/>upholding our ethical obligations and protecting the anonymity of our <lb/>study participants. Requests to access the datasets should be directed to <lb/>AMA, Amqurni@iau.edu.sa. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by Imam Abdulrahman <lb/>bin Faisal University IRB-2021-01-334. The studies were conducted in <lb/>accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. <lb/>Written informed consent for participation was not required from the <lb/>participants or the participants&apos; legal guardians/next of kin in accordance <lb/>with the national legislation and institutional requirements. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>ArA: Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing, Data curation, Formal <lb/></div>

    <body>TABLE 4 The Mentzer index results compared to other studies 𝛽-TT. <lb/>Study <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>Specificity <lb/>PPV <lb/>NPV <lb/>Current study <lb/>74% <lb/>63% <lb/>8% <lb/>98% <lb/>Ahmed et al. <lb/>95.24% <lb/>93.10% <lb/>90.9% <lb/>96.4% <lb/>Vehapoglu et al. <lb/>98.7% <lb/>82.3% <lb/>86.3% <lb/>98.2% <lb/>Ahmed et al. <lb/>100.00% <lb/>58.76% <lb/>23.95% <lb/>100% <lb/>Düzenli Kar et al. (IDA/α-TT) <lb/>80% <lb/>92% <lb/>90.9% <lb/>82.1% <lb/>Sirdah et al. (IDA/ 𝛽-TT) <lb/>82.86% <lb/>83.55% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Sherali et al. <lb/>80.7% <lb/>77.7% <lb/>56.8% <lb/>91.6% <lb/>Sri L. S. Alam et al. <lb/>93% <lb/>84% <lb/>93% <lb/>84% <lb/>Turudic et al. <lb/>88% <lb/>48% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Aydogan et al. <lb/>100% <lb/>69.48% <lb/>36.59% <lb/>100% <lb/>Demir, et al <lb/>86% <lb/>62% <lb/>76% <lb/>76% <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">AlQarni et al. <lb/>10.3389/fmed.2024.1361805 <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">Frontiers in Medicine <lb/></note>

    <page>07 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

    <div type="contribution">analysis, Visualization. AMA: Conceptualization, <lb/>Validation, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing, <lb/>Investigation. NA: Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>SA: Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. AH: Writing <lb/>-original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. LA: Data curation, <lb/>Validation, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. ZA: <lb/>Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. AHA: Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for <lb/>the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, <lb/>or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product <lb/>that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. World Health Organization. &quot;Anaemia in women and children. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, <lb/>2023. [Online]. Available at: https://www.who.int/data/gho/data/themes/topics/ <lb/>anaemia_in_women_and_children <lb/>2. World Health Organization. &quot;Nutritional anaemias: tools for effective prevention <lb/>and control. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: https://www.who.int/ <lb/>publications/i/item/9789241513067 <lb/>3. &quot;Haemoglobin concentrations for the diagnosis of anaemia and assessment of <lb/>severity. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: https://www.who.int/ <lb/>publications-detail-redirect/WHO-NMH-NHD-MNM-11.1 <lb/>4. Kassebaum NJGBD 2013 Anemia Collaborators. The global burden of Anemia. <lb/>Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. (2016) 30:247-308. doi: 10.1016/j.hoc.2015.11.002 <lb/>5. Stevens S, Bankhead C, Mukhtar T, Perera-Salazar R, Holt TA, Salisbury C, et al. <lb/>Patient-level and practice-level factors associated with consultation duration: a cross-<lb/>sectional analysis of over one million consultations in English primary care. BMJ Open. <lb/>(2017) 7:e018261. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2017-018261 <lb/>6. Camaschella C. Iron-deficiency anemia. N Engl J Med. (2015) 372:1832-43. doi: <lb/>10.1056/NEJMra1401038 <lb/>7. Siu ALUS Preventive Services Task Force. Screening for Iron deficiency Anemia in <lb/>young children: USPSTF recommendation statement. Pediatrics. (2015) 136:746-52. doi: <lb/>10.1542/peds.2015-2567 <lb/>8. Douek E. The Harriet lane handbook. A manual for pediatric house officers. <lb/>Postgrad Med J. 61:556-7. 1985, Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: https:// <lb/>www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2418444/ <lb/>9. Baker RD, Greer FRCommittee on Nutrition American Academy of Pediatrics. <lb/>Diagnosis and prevention of iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anemia in infants and <lb/>young children (0-3 years of age). Pediatrics. (2010) 126:1040-50. doi: 10.1542/ <lb/>peds.2010-2576 <lb/>10. McDonagh MS, Blazina I, Dana T, Cantor A, Bougatsos C. Screening and routine <lb/>supplementation for iron deficiency anemia: a systematic review. Pediatrics. (2015) <lb/>135:723-33. doi: 10.1542/peds.2014-3979 <lb/>11. Weatherall DJ. The inherited diseases of hemoglobin are an emerging global health <lb/>burden. Blood. (2010) 115:4331-6. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-01-251348 <lb/>12. Abu-Shaheen A, Dahan D, Henaa H, Nofal A, Abdelmoety DA, Riaz M, et al. <lb/>Sickle cell disease in gulf cooperation council countries: a systematic review. Expert Rev <lb/>Hematol. (2022) 15:893-909. doi: 10.1080/17474086.2022.2132225 <lb/>13. Al, &quot;Prevalence of thalassemia disorders and hemoglobinopathies in Jeddah, western <lb/>Saudi Arabia. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: https://www.jahjournal.org/ <lb/>article.asp?issn=1658-5127;year=2010;volume=1;issue=1;spage=43;epage=46;aulast=Al <lb/>14. Mazza J. J., Manual of clinical hematology. In Lippincott manual series (formerly <lb/>known as the spiral manual series) series. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, (2002). <lb/>[Online]. Available at: https://books.google.com.sa/books?id=4-TSGLfiYpQC <lb/>15. Cappellini MD, Cohen A, Porter J, Taher A, Viprakasit V. Guidelines for the <lb/>Management of Transfusion Dependent Thalassaemia (TDT). 3rd ed. Nicosia (CY): <lb/>Thalassaemia International Federation (2014) Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. <lb/>Available at: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK269382/. <lb/>16. Taher A., Vichinsky E., Musallam K., Cappellini M. D., Viprakasit V., Guidelines <lb/>for the Management of non Transfusion Dependent Thalassaemia (NTDT). Nicosia <lb/>(Cyprus): Thalassaemia International Federation, (2013). Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. <lb/>[Online]. Available at: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK190453/ <lb/>17. &quot;Mentzer index a simple tool to differentiate Beta Thalassaemia trait from Iron <lb/>deficiency Anaemia, a review, IJSR. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: <lb/>https://www.worldwidejournals.com/international-journal-of-scientific-research-<lb/>(IJSR)/article/mentzer-index-a-simple-tool-to-differentiate-beta-thalassaemia-trait-<lb/>from-iron-deficiency-anaemia-a-review/MTEwODg=/ <lb/>18. &quot;Hematological indices for differential diagnosis of Beta thalassemia trait and iron <lb/>deficiency anemia.-abstract-Europe PMC. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. <lb/>Available at: https://europepmc.org/article/PMC/4003757 <lb/>19. Maimoon S, Chandra S. Is Mentzer index a reliable diagnostic screening tool for <lb/>Beta thalassemia trait? IOSR J Dent Med Sci. (2018) 17:7-11. doi: <lb/>10.9790/0853-1707060711 <lb/>20. Tabassum S, Khakwani M, Fayyaz A, Taj N. Role of Mentzer index for <lb/>differentiating iron deficiency anemia and beta thalassemia trait in pregnant women. <lb/>Pak J Med Sci. (2022) 38:878-82. doi: 10.12669/pjms.38.4.4635 <lb/>21. Brancaleoni V, Di Pierro E, Motta I, Cappellini MD. Laboratory diagnosis of <lb/>thalassemia. Int J Lab Hematol. (2016) 38:32-40. doi: 10.1111/ijlh.12527 <lb/>22. Ayman S, Ahmed AZ, Abou-Taleb A. Assessment of new indices to discriminate <lb/>between iron deficiency anemia and thalassemia trait in Sohag University. Sohag Med J. <lb/>(2019) 23:49-62. doi: 10.21608/smj.2019.15375.1031 <lb/>23. &quot;Role of red cell distribution width and Mentzer index in differentiating Iron <lb/>deficiency Anemia from Anemia due to β thalassemia trait. &quot; Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. <lb/>[Online]. Available at: https://www.jsafog.com/abstractArticleContentBrowse/ <lb/>JSAFOG/19094/JPJ/fullText <lb/>24. Bajwa H., Basit H., &quot;Thalassemia, &quot; In StatPearls, Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls <lb/>Publishing, (2023). Accessed: Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: http://www.ncbi.nlm. <lb/>nih.gov/books/NBK545151/ <lb/>25. &quot;The diagnostic performance of red cell distribution width and Mentzer index for <lb/>discrimination between Iron deficiency Anemia and Beta thalassemia trait. &quot; Accessed: <lb/>Oct. 26, 2023. [Online]. Available at: https://medicaljournalofcairouniversity.net/index. <lb/>php/2014-10-22-23-17-28/vol-86-december-2018/3751-the-diagnostic-performance-<lb/>of-red-cell-distribution-width-and-mentzer-index-for-discrimination-between-iron-<lb/>deficiency-anemia-and-beta-thalassemia-trait <lb/>26. Düzenli Kar Y, Özdemir ZC, Emir B, Bör Ö. Erythrocyte indices as differential <lb/>diagnostic biomarkers of Iron deficiency Anemia and thalassemia. J Pediatr Hematol <lb/>Oncol. (2020) 42:208-13. doi: 10.1097/MPH.0000000000001597 <lb/>27. Sirdah M, Tarazi I, Al Najjar E, Al Haddad R. Evaluation of the diagnostic <lb/>reliability of different RBC indices and formulas in the differentiation of the beta-<lb/>thalassaemia minor from iron deficiency in Palestinian population. Int J Lab Hematol. <lb/>(2008) 30:324-30. doi: 10.1111/j.1751-553x.2007.00966.x <lb/>28. Sherali A, Ahad A, Tikmani SS, Sohail S. Screening of Iron deficiency Anemia in <lb/>children using Mentzer index in Pakistan: a cross sectional study. Glob Pediatr Health. <lb/>(2023) 10:2333794X2211309. doi: 10.1177/2333794X221130986 <lb/>29. Alam SLS, Purnamasari R, Bahar E, Rahadian KY. Mentzer index as a screening <lb/>tool for iron deficiency anemia in 6-12-year-old children. Paediatr Indones. (2014) <lb/>54:294-8. doi: 10.14238/pi54.5.2014.294-8 <lb/>30. Turudic D, Busic I, Bilic M, Bilic E. 294 comparison of mathematical indices used <lb/>to differentiate between β-thalassemia and iron deficiency anemia in croatian children. <lb/>Arch Dis Child. (2021) 106:A124-5. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2021-europaediatrics.294 <lb/>31. Aydogan G, Keskin S, Akici F, Salcioglu Z, Bayram C, Uysalol EP, et al. Causes of <lb/>hypochromic microcytic Anemia in children and evaluation of laboratory parameters <lb/>in the differentiation. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. (2019) 41:e221-3. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>MPH.0000000000001382 <lb/>32. Demir A, Yarali N, Fisgin T, Duru F, Kara A. Most reliable indices in differentiation <lb/>between thalassemia trait and iron deficiency anemia. Pediatr Int. (2002) 44:612-6. doi: <lb/>10.1046/j.1442-200x.2002.01636.x </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>