<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T10:25:01.818Z">11/20/2025 10:25:01 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T10:24:34.790064Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T10:24:34.790064Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Restoration of Alouatta guariba <lb/>populations: building a binational <lb/>management strategy for the <lb/>conservation of the endangered <lb/>brown howler monkey of the <lb/>Atlantic Forest <lb/>Luciana I. Oklander 1,2,3 * , Marcelo Rheingantz 4,5 , <lb/>Rafael S. Rossato 6,7 , Silvana Peker 8 , Zelinda M. B. Hirano 3,9 , <lb/>Caue ˆMonticelli 10 , Aline Naı ´ssa Dada 9 , Dante L. Di Nucci 2,11 , <lb/>Dilmar Oliveira 10 , Fabiano R. de Melo 3,12 , <lb/>Mo ˆnica M. Valenc ¸a-Montenegro 6 , Martin Kowalewski 2,3,13 <lb/>and Leandro Jerusalinsky 3,6,7,14 <lb/>1 Grupo de Investigacio ´n en Gene ´tica Aplicada (GIGA), Instituto de Biologı ´a Subtropical (IBS), Consejo <lb/>Nacional de Investigaciones Cientı ´ficas y Te ´cnicas (CONICET), Universidad Nacional de Misiones <lb/>(UNAM), Posadas, Argentina, 2 Neotropical Primate Conservation Argentina, Puerto Iguazu ´, Argentina, <lb/>3 Primate Specialist Group, Species Survival Commission, International Union for the Conservation of <lb/>Nature, Austin, TX, United States, 4 Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio <lb/>de Janeiro, Brazil, 5 Refauna, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 6 Centro Nacional de Pesquisa e Conservac ¸ão de <lb/>Primatas Brasileiros -CPB, Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservac ¸ão da Biodiversidade -ICMBio, <lb/>Cabedelo, Brazil, 7 Programa Macacos Urbanos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto <lb/>Alegre, Brazil, 8 Direccio ´n de Biodiversidad, Subsecretarı ´a de Ambiente de la Nacio ´n Argentina, Buenos <lb/>Aires, Argentina, 9 Projeto Bugio, Centro de Pesquisas Biolo ´gicas de Indaial -CEPESBI, Universidade <lb/>Regional de Blumenau -FURB, Indaial, Brazil, 10 Coordenadoria de Fauna Silvestre, Secretaria de Meio <lb/>Ambiente, Infraestrutura e Logı ´stica do Estado de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil, 11 Fundacio ´n de Historia <lb/>Natural Fe ´lix de Azara, Centro de Rescate, Rehabilitacio ´n y Recrı ´a de Fauna Silvestre Güira ´Oga, <lb/>Misiones, Puerto Iguazu ´, Argentina, 12 Depto. Eng. Florestal, Universidade Federal de Vic ¸osa, <lb/>Viçosa, Brazil, 13 Estacio ´n Biolo ´gica Corrientes (CECOAL-CONICET), Corrientes, Argentina, <lb/>14 Conservation Planning Specialist Group, Species Survival Commission, International Union for the <lb/>Conservation of Nature, Apple Valley, MN, United States <lb/>The brown howler monkey (Alouatta guariba) is endemic to the Atlantic Forest of <lb/>eastern Brazil and northeastern Argentina, threatened by extinction due to <lb/>habitat loss and fragmentation, and hunting. Its reduced and isolated <lb/>populations dramatically decreased and suffered local extinctions after recent <lb/>yellow fever outbreaks, recommending the species risk uplist from Vulnerable to <lb/>Endangered. In Brazil, the species occurs along eight states in sparse populations, <lb/>including some large protected areas, and is being uplisted to Endangered. <lb/>Following the National Action Plan for Conservation of the Atlantic Forest <lb/>Primates and the Maned-sloth, and applying the Guidelines for Reintroductions <lb/>and other Conservation Translocations (IUCN/CTSG), the Ex Situ Guidelines <lb/>(IUCN/CPSG) and the One Plan Approach (IUCN/CPSG), a workshop was held <lb/>on August 2021 to evaluate the need, requisites and roles of an integrated <lb/>Population Management Program for A. guariba. Such program was developed in <lb/>June 2022 defining the objectives of (i) restore in situ populations from ex situ <lb/>populations, prioritizing populations in higher risk to prevent local extinctions, <lb/>and (ii) establish an ex situ insurance population. This in situ -ex situ integrated <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>01 <lb/></page>

			<front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>EDITED BY <lb/>Carlos R. Ruiz-Miranda, <lb/>State University of Northern Rio de Janeiro, <lb/>Brazil <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Pedro Dias, <lb/>Universidad Veracruzana, Mexico <lb/>Helena De Godoy Bergallo, <lb/>Rio de Janeiro State University, Brazil <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Luciana I. Oklander <lb/>lulaok@gmail.com <lb/>RECEIVED 15 March 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 12 April 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 10 May 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Oklander LI, Rheingantz M, Rossato RS, <lb/>Peker S, Hirano ZMB, Monticelli C, Dada AN, <lb/>Di Nucci DL, Oliveira D, de Melo FR, Valenc ¸a-<lb/>Montenegro MM, Kowalewski M and <lb/>Jerusalinsky L (2024) Restoration of Alouatta <lb/>guariba populations: building a binational <lb/>management strategy for the conservation of <lb/>the endangered brown howler monkey of the <lb/>Atlantic Forest. <lb/>Front. Conserv. Sci. 5:1401749. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Oklander, Rheingantz, Rossato, Peker, <lb/>Hirano, Monticelli, Dada, Di Nucci, Oliveira, de <lb/>Melo, Valenc ¸a-Montenegro, Kowalewski and <lb/>Jerusalinsky. This is an open-access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction in other <lb/>forums is permitted, provided the original <lb/>author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are <lb/>credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with <lb/>accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted <lb/>which does not comply with these terms. <lb/>TYPE Policy and Practice Reviews <lb/>PUBLISHED 10 May 2024 <lb/>DOI 10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/>management program was approved by ICMBio in February 2023, with actions <lb/>recommended for all states along the species distribution. In Argentina, the <lb/>species is Critically Endangered, with a remaining population of 20-50 <lb/>individuals. Following the National Plan for Primate Conservation in <lb/>Argentina, in a process similar to that in Brazil, two workshops were held in <lb/>2022/2023 to evaluate and define management actions for the long-term <lb/>recovery of A. guariba. The priorities indicated were (i) reintroduction in ten <lb/>potential areas in Misiones -due to a lower risk when compared to <lb/>reinforcement of remaining populations, and (ii) establishing an ex situ <lb/>management program in Argentina -still non-existent. The progressive <lb/>collaboration between the initiatives of both countries is promoting the <lb/>exchange of experiences and the integration of strategies. Here we <lb/>summarize the planning and management carried out in Brazil and Argentina, <lb/>highlighting the need for integrated measures. We debate on the progress and <lb/>challenges, proposing next steps for developing and implementing a binational <lb/>population management program for the conservation of the brown <lb/>howler monkey. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>population management, conservation translocations, action plans, primates, health <lb/>sentinel, seed dispersion <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The brown howler monkey, Alouatta guariba, is endemic to the <lb/>Atlantic Forest, one of the largest primates and the one with the <lb/>widest distribution in this biome. It occurs in eight states along <lb/>eastern Brazil -Rio Grande do Sul, Santa Catarina, Parana, São <lb/>Paulo, Rio de Janeiro, Minas Gerais, Espıŕito Santo, and Bahia <lb/>(Bicca-Marques et al., 2018; Neves et al., 2018), while in Argentina it <lb/>is only present in the northeastern province of Misiones (Agostini <lb/>et al., 2019). There is a persistent controversy about the existence of <lb/>two different taxa. With a more pronounced sexual dichromatism, <lb/>being adult male reddish and adult females brown, A. g. clamitans <lb/>(Agc, Cabrera, 1940) has a larger range in the central and <lb/>southernmost part of the species distribution. With a more <lb/>uniform brown coloration in both sexes, A. g. guariba is present <lb/>in the northernmost area, occupying a more restricted and <lb/>uncertain range (Agg, Rylands et al., 2000; Neves et al., 2018). <lb/>The species is increasingly impacted by loss and modification of <lb/>its native habitat, hunting, trafficking for pet trade and diverse <lb/>threats associated with infrastructure and urbanization -injuries or <lb/>deaths due to vehicle collisions, electrocutions, and dog attacks <lb/>(Agostini et al., 2019; Jerusalinsky et al., 2021; Chaves et al., 2022). <lb/>Although howler monkeys are resilient and still present in <lb/>fragmented landscapes and small impoverished forest remnants <lb/>(Bicca-Marques et al., 2020), the indiscriminate deforestation and <lb/>destruction of forests, besides the growing exposure to other threats <lb/>in anthropized areas could severely threaten their survival in the <lb/>medium and long term (Chaves et al., 2022). <lb/>Howler monkeys are also especially susceptible to yellow fever <lb/>virus and suffer high mortality within a few days of being bitten by <lb/>the mosquitoes vectors (Rifakis et al., 2006; Fernandes et al., 2021). <lb/>Thus, they play a key role as public health sentinels, providing early <lb/>warning of the virus and allowing for increased vaccination of <lb/>surrounding human populations. Yellow fever outbreaks have <lb/>decimated many populations or caused drastic population <lb/>reduction in Argentina and southern Brazil in 2007/2009 <lb/>(Almeida et al., 2012; Moreno et al., 2015). Another outbreak <lb/>since 2017 up to date in Brazil caused thousands of monkeys&apos; <lb/>deaths (Bicca-Marques et al., 2017; Possamai et al., 2022), but has <lb/>not reached Argentina. Aggravating the situation, due to the false <lb/>information that contact or proximity with howler monkeys could <lb/>infect humans, many individuals of this species were injured and <lb/></body>

			<front>Abbreviations: APN DR NEA, Administracioń de Parques Nacionales -<lb/>Delegacioń Regional Noreste; CONICET, Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones <lb/>Cientıfcas y Tećnicas; NPC Argentina, Neotropical Primate Conservation <lb/>Argentina; EBCo-CECOAL, Estacioń Bioloǵica Corrientes -Centro de Ecologıá <lb/>Aplicada del Litoral; UNNE, Universidad Nacional de Nordeste; MEyRNR <lb/>Misiones, Ministerio de Ecologıá y Recursos Naturales Renovables Misiones; <lb/>ICMBio, Instituto Chico Mendes para la Conservacioń de la Biodiversidad; <lb/>CMAG BRASIL; IEGEBA, Instituto de Ecologıá, Genetica y Evolucioń de <lb/>Buenos Aires; FCEN-UBA, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, <lb/>Universidad de Buenos Aires; IMiBio, Instituto Misionero de Biodiversidad; <lb/>INEVH, Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Virales Humanas &quot;Dr. Julio I. <lb/>Maiztegui&quot;; MAyDS, Ministerio de Ambiente y Desarrollo Sostenible. <lb/>Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>02 <lb/></page>

			<body>killed in outbreak areas (Bicca-Marques et al., 2017, Bicca-Marques <lb/>et al., 2018). <lb/>All these threats together resulted in reduced and isolated <lb/>populations with local extinctions throughout its distribution <lb/>(Jerusalinsky et al., 2021). These local extirpations, likely taking <lb/>place simultaneously at various locations within the species&apos; range <lb/>can quickly lead to wider-spread regional extinctions if populations <lb/>are separated by distances large enough to prevent re-colonization <lb/>of empty habitats or with physical or anthropogenic barriers that <lb/>reduce both movement and survivorship of dispersing individuals <lb/>(Torres-Romero et al., 2023). <lb/>Alouatta guariba was included in the International Union for <lb/>the Conservation of Nature&apos;s (IUCN) Red List of Threatened <lb/>Species in the 1990&apos;s, being currently categorized as Vulnerable <lb/>(Jerusalinsky et al., 2021), and has been listed five times (2012-<lb/>2022) as one of the 25 most endangered primates of the world, first <lb/>at subspecies level (A. guariba guariba -Neves et al., 2017) and later <lb/>as species (Buss et al., 2019; Oklander et al., 2022a). In Argentina, <lb/>the situation is particularly alarming, with an estimated population <lb/>between 20 and 50 individuals exclusively in the province of <lb/>Misiones, and the species is categorized as Critically Endangered <lb/>(Agostini et al., 2019; Ministerio De Ambiente y Desarrollo <lb/>Sostenible de Argentina -MADySResolution 316, 2021). <lb/>In Brazil, Alouatta guariba clamitans is categorized as <lb/>Vulnerable (Bicca-Marques et al., 2018) and Alouatta guariba <lb/>guariba as Critically Endangered (Neves et al., 2018), but both <lb/>taxa were evaluated unifiedly at the species level at the technical-<lb/>scientific stages for updating the national conservation status <lb/>assessment coordinated by Instituto Chico Mendes de <lb/>Conservacão da Biodiversidade (ICMBio) and the category <lb/>Endangered was indicate for A. guariba. The same is being <lb/>followed by the IUCN Species Survival Commission&apos;s (SSC) <lb/>Primate Specialist Group, which is preparing the publication of <lb/>this updated category for the IUCN Red List. In addition, these taxa <lb/>are classified as threatened in several Brazilian states: Critically <lb/>Endangered (CR) in Minas Gerais (Agg, Deliberacão Normativa <lb/>COPAM n°147, 2010), and Bahia (Agg, Portaria n°37, 2017); <lb/>Endangered (EN) in São Paulo (Ag, Decreto Estadual N°63853, <lb/>2018) and Espıŕito Santo (Agc, Decreto Estadual No. 5.237/2022); <lb/>and Vulnerable (VU) in Rio Grande do Sul (Agc, Decreto Estadual <lb/>No. 51.797, 2014), Santa Catarina (Agc, Resolucão Consema No. <lb/>002, 2011) and Minas Gerais (Agc, Deliberacão Normativa COPAM <lb/>No. 147, 2010). In Rio de Janeiro, the species was not listed but it <lb/>was classified as Presumably Threatened (Bergallo et al., 2000), but <lb/>the assessment is outdated. Finally, in Paranáthe species is not <lb/>included in the list of threatened species. <lb/>The species have a crucial role in the regeneration and <lb/>maintenance of forests across its distribution, as they are <lb/>important seed dispersers for numerous plant species (Chaves <lb/>et al., 2018). Additionally, A. guariba, as howlers all over south <lb/>America are part of the cultural heritage of both native people and <lb/>settlers inhabiting Brazil and Argentina (Urbani and Cormier, 2015; <lb/>de Almeida and Voltolini, 2017; Alves and Barboza, 2018; <lb/>Oliveira, 2022). <lb/>Therefore, the conservation of this primate species contributes <lb/>to the regeneration of the flora of the Atlantic Forest, to preserve <lb/>cultural heritage, and to promote public health and awareness <lb/>towards biodiversity and habitat conservation. <lb/>In this context, under such level of risk and diversity of <lb/>menaces, the long-term persistence of A. guariba must depend <lb/>largely on the refined design and effective implementation of <lb/>participatory, science-based conservation strategies (Lees et al., <lb/>2021). Under the framework of the global biodiversity <lb/>conservation targets -such as in the Convention of Biological <lb/>Diversity and the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals <lb/>-both Brazil and Argentina established public policies for the <lb/>conservation of the species through National Conservation Action <lb/>Plans (ICMBio, 2018; MADyS, 2021), including population <lb/>management in the specific objectives. In the present study, we <lb/>describe the efforts to create national population management <lb/>programs in both countries and to advance towards an integrated <lb/>strategy in order to promote the conservation of A. guariba through <lb/>population restoration. Our purpose is also reflecting on the <lb/>progress and challenges to coordinate such initiatives and <lb/>effectively reestablish viable populations of the species throughout <lb/>its distribution range. <lb/>Policies and guidelines for population <lb/>management of Alouatta guariba <lb/>Brazil <lb/>In August 2018, Brazil published the National Action Plan for <lb/>the Conservation of Primates of the Atlantic Forest and the Maned-<lb/>sloth (ICMBio, 2018), with strategies for 13 threatened species, <lb/>including A. guariba. One of the six strategic goals established was <lb/>to manage populations of target species aiming at their viability. <lb/>In order to implement this goal, in August 2021, the National <lb/>Center for Research and Conservation of Brazilian Primates <lb/>(ICMBio/CPB) and the IUCN SSC Conservation Planning <lb/>Specialist Group (CPSG) held a virtual workshop using a unified <lb/>planning approach (One Plan Approach -IUCN/CPSG, Byers et al., <lb/>2013) and applying the IUCN Ex Situ Guidelines (IUCN, 2014) to <lb/>assess whether ex situ management is a suitable conservation tool <lb/>for these species, defining what roles it can play in the species&apos; <lb/>overall conservation strategy, and which ones would need specific <lb/>ex situ, in situ or integrated (i.e., in situ + ex situ) Population <lb/>Management Programs (ICMBio, 2021; Valenca-Montenegro et al., <lb/>2024). For Alouatta guariba, the decision was made to establish an <lb/>ex situ insurance population primarily to serve as a source of <lb/>individuals and groups for in situ population restoration efforts, <lb/>while also playing a supportive role in promoting ex situ research <lb/>and conservation education. Another major outcome for the species <lb/>was the recommendation of creating an integrated Population <lb/>Management Program (PMP), involving both in situ and ex situ <lb/>populations and actions (Valenca-Montenegro et al., 2024). <lb/>In June 2022, ICMBio/CPB coordinated another workshop with <lb/>24 collaborators from 21 institutions -including researchers and <lb/>managers, representatives of universities, governmental and non-<lb/>governmental institutions, environmental agencies from all eight <lb/>Brazilian states of the species&apos; distribution, and ex situ institutions, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>03 <lb/></page>

			<body>to design the Alouatta guariba Integrated Population Management <lb/>Program. Endorsing the workshop decisions, this program was <lb/>officially approved by ICMBio in February 2023, with the main goal <lb/>to &quot;develop integrated population management of Alouatta guariba, <lb/>throughout its range of occurrence, to offset the effects of threats <lb/>and restore populations in situ&quot;, with the specific goals of: i) <lb/>ordering the ex situ population; ii) restore in situ populations <lb/>using individuals from ex situ; iii) establish the ex situ insurance <lb/>population; and iv) promote education and research actions for the <lb/>conservation of the species (ICMBio, 2023). The involved <lb/>stakeholders also recommended that, to restore in situ <lb/>populations, priority be given to those populations at higher risk, <lb/>aiming to reinforce populations with significant reductions to <lb/>prevent imminent local extinctions, and to reintroduce <lb/>populations in areas where the species became extinct within its <lb/>distribution range. <lb/>It is also important to highlight that, due to the threat posed by <lb/>yellow fever outbreaks, it was decided that all animals from ex situ <lb/>populations to be released must be immunized before their release, <lb/>in addition to two specific actions being included in the Alouatta <lb/>guariba Integrated Population Management Program in relation to <lb/>this issue: i) continue research into the effectiveness of the yellow <lb/>fever vaccine for the species; and ii) establish flow and coordination <lb/>with the competent institutions to obtain immunization against <lb/>yellow fever.&quot; <lb/>For coordinating and monitoring this Integrated Population <lb/>Management Program, the Committee for Management of Alouatta <lb/>guariba (CMAG) was also formally established, constituted by <lb/>taxon specialists, in situ and ex situ managers, as well as <lb/>representatives from the Brazilian Environmental Agency <lb/>(ICMBio) and State Environmental Agencies from all the <lb/>Brazilian states within the species natural distribution. This group <lb/>evaluates and monitors population reinforcement and <lb/>reintroduction projects for the species in Brazil. Furthermore, the <lb/>Committee for Management of Alouatta guariba has the support of <lb/>specialists in different areas for specific consultations, such as <lb/>arboviruses, bacteriology, parasitology, assisted reproduction, <lb/>pathology, etc. <lb/>Argentina <lb/>In March 2019, the Argentinian Ministry of Environment and <lb/>Sustainable Development and the Argentinian Primatological <lb/>Society promoted a workshop, with support in preparing and <lb/>facilitating from CPSG and ICMBio/CPB, to design the National <lb/>Plan for the Conservation of Primates in Argentina. This plan was <lb/>officially published by the Ministry in December 2021 (RESOL-<lb/>2021-430-APN-MAD, Ministerio de Ambiente y Desarrollo <lb/>Sostenible, 2021) aiming to coordinate conservation initiatives for <lb/>the five primate species of the country. For the species at highest risk <lb/>in the country, the Critically Endangered A. guariba, the plan set a <lb/>specific objective to evaluate the recovery of the populations <lb/>through an ex situ conservation program and analyzing the <lb/>possibility of starting a breeding and reintroduction program and/ <lb/>or translocation of specimens. <lb/>Aiming to implement this specific objective, a two-stage <lb/>workshop was held. First, in December 2022, a virtual meeting was <lb/>organized as a preparatory step to gather the information needed to <lb/>evaluate the population management of A. guariba in Argentina. <lb/>Afterwards, in April 2023, an in person workshop with 47 <lb/>participants, from 25 institutions (APN -DR NEA, Ananda <lb/>Consultora, Aves Argentinas, Cambio Climatico Misiones, Cambio <lb/>Climatico Nacioń, CONICET, NPC Argentina, EBCo-CECOAL/ <lb/>CONICET-UNNE, Fundacioń Rewilding Argentina, Fundacioń <lb/>Temaikèn, MEyRNR Misiones, ICMBio/CPB, IEGEBA-CONICET, <lb/>FCEN-UBA, IMiBio, INEVH, ITAIPU BINACIONAL, Ministerio <lb/>de Ambiente y Desarrollo Sostenible de la Nacioń, Ministerio Salud <lb/>Nación, Policıá Ambiental Misiones, Programa Conservación <lb/>Inclusiva MAyDS, Projeto Bugio, Proyecto Zorro Pitoco, <lb/>Fundacioń Azara/Centro de Fauna Silvestre GüiráOga) was held <lb/>to develop and agree on management actions for the long-term <lb/>recovery of the Alouatta guariba populations in Misiones, Argentina. <lb/>This meeting counted on the participation of key members of the <lb/>Brazilian Committee for Management of Alouatta guariba, such as <lb/>the group&apos;s coordinator and the ICMBio/CPB representative, <lb/>looking for strengthening the connection among the two <lb/>initiatives. The process followed the CPSG One Plan Approach <lb/>(Byers et al., 2013), considering both the benefits and risks of <lb/>population management following the IUCN Guidelines for <lb/>Reintroductions and other Conservation Translocations (IUCN, <lb/>2013; Oklander et al., 2023a). <lb/>Coordinating committees for <lb/>population management of <lb/>Alouatta guariba <lb/>Brazil <lb/>The Brazilian Committee for Management of Alouatta guariba <lb/>has been meeting monthly, with 19 virtual meetings to date. It has <lb/>prepared, reviewed, and approved the committee&apos;s internal <lb/>regulations; prepared, tested, and used project and report <lb/>evaluation forms, project and report presentation forms, and <lb/>animal handling and release protocols. <lb/>Internal regulations were drawn up to establish the rules that <lb/>are guiding the functioning of the committee. To guide the teams <lb/>developing translocation projects, two protocols were created: <lb/>-Ex Situ Management Protocol (Hirano et al., 2023) -which <lb/>addresses: sex-age classification; sanitary management and <lb/>biosecurity; installations; nutrition; well-being; reproductive <lb/>control; management of infants and the elderly; and the <lb/>transport of animals. This protocol was prepared by the <lb/>Technical Advisory Group of the National Action Plan for <lb/>the Conservation of Primates of the Atlantic Forest and the <lb/>Maned-sloth. <lb/>-Release Protocol: addresses the management necessary for the <lb/>release of howler monkeys, including sanitary issues <lb/>(disease risk analysis, recommended laboratory tests), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>04 <lb/></page>

			<body>dietary issues (dietary transition to eat food usually eaten by <lb/>wild howlers in the target or close areas), behavioral <lb/>evaluation and also specification of acclimation enclosure, <lb/>decision tree to guide the management, and post-release <lb/>monitoring advices. This protocol is still under <lb/>construction by the Committee for Management of <lb/>Alouatta guariba with support from program specialists. <lb/>To guide proponents in presenting projects of management <lb/>actions and also the committee members in analyzing and <lb/>approving it, the following set of standard forms and documents <lb/>was prepared, which are available at: https://drive.google.com/ <lb/>drive/folders/1ft2zb4M8WSMtw6ZfOqLd70Kek1xhICBs): <lb/>-Project submission form: the form contains all the necessary <lb/>items to be presented when submitting projects, allowing <lb/>for better targeting; <lb/>-Report submission form: to be presented to the committee <lb/>after one year of project development, the form contains all <lb/>the items to be evaluated; <lb/>-Project evaluation form and report to be used by committee <lb/>members that contains all the criteria to be considered <lb/>when evaluating them. <lb/>Letter of general opinion from the committee for forwarded <lb/>projects: after analyzing each project, the committee issues an <lb/>official opinion to the proponents so that they can continue with <lb/>the process. This letter is presented by the proponent to ICMBio for <lb/>registration in the official Brazilian system for submitting, analyzing <lb/>and issuing permits for scientific activities and management actions, <lb/>in accordance with pre-established documentation flow (Sisbio -<lb/>Sistema de Autorizacão e Informacão em Biodiversidade) -The <lb/>species studbook is under construction: institutions that maintain <lb/>brown howlers in ex situ conditions were contacted requesting <lb/>information on the animals kept and forwarding documents for <lb/>officializing the participation of the institution in the Program. In <lb/>relation to the ex situ population, the species&apos; studbook has already <lb/>recorded 314 individuals in 27 different institutions. Of these, at <lb/>least 152 meet the criteria to form an insurance population and <lb/>could also be used in translocation actions (reinforcement and/or <lb/>reintroduction) if they are approved in the behavioral and health <lb/>analyses defined by the Program. These 152 individuals selected for <lb/>the insurance population were also categorized by Management <lb/>Units based on genetic differences (see description in the Binational <lb/>actions section), with 19 from the Management Unit of Rio de <lb/>Janeiro, Espıŕito Santo and Minas Gerais; 51 from São Paulo; eight <lb/>from Parana; and 74 from Santa Catarina, Rio Grande do Sul <lb/>and Argentina. <lb/>Regarding the priority areas to be considered by the Integrated <lb/>Population Management Program, 16 areas were identified as <lb/>eligible during the meeting in São Paulo, 2021, indicating <lb/>population reinforcement in areas where brown howlers still <lb/>persist or reintroduction in areas where they were extirpated <lb/>(Table 1, Figure 1). From those 16 potential areas, there are three <lb/>projects under evaluation by the Committee for Management of <lb/>Alouatta guariba. Two conservation translocation projects have <lb/>been already approved and are underway, namely: <lb/>-Population reinforcement of Alouatta guariba in the <lb/>Cantareira State Park, in the State of São Paulo; <lb/>-Reintroduction of Alouatta guariba in Florianoṕolis, in the <lb/>State of Santa Catarina. <lb/>TABLE 1 List of priority areas in the Alouatta guariba Brazilian <lb/>Management Program, including the name, size, state of the country and <lb/>the suggested management (reintroduction, reinforcement, no <lb/>management needed or to be defined) ordered by States from South to <lb/>North and by Recommended Population Management. <lb/>Name of the area <lb/>Area <lb/>size <lb/>(ha) <lb/>State Recommended <lb/>Population <lb/>Management <lb/>Espigão Alto State Park <lb/>1,332 <lb/>Rio <lb/>Grande <lb/>do Sul <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Morro Geisler, Indaial2 <lb/>40 <lb/>Santa <lb/>Catarina <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Rio Vermelho State Park <lb/>1,532 <lb/>Santa <lb/>Catarina <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>São Francisco de Assis <lb/>Municipal Natural Park2 <lb/>23 <lb/>Santa <lb/>Catarina <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Iguacu National Park <lb/>185,262 <lb/>ParanáReinforcement <lb/>Area of Relevant Ecological <lb/>Interest Mata de <lb/>Santa Genebra2 <lb/>241,55 <lb/>São <lb/>Paulo <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Serra da Cantareira State Park <lb/>7,916 <lb/>São <lb/>Paulo <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Serra do Mar State Park <lb/>315,391 <lb/>São <lb/>Paulo <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Macaéde Cima <lb/>Environmental <lb/>Protection Area <lb/>35,037 <lb/>Rio <lb/>de <lb/>Janeiro <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Tijuca National Park1 <lb/>3,953 <lb/>Rio <lb/>de <lb/>Janeiro <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Area of Relevant Ecological <lb/>Interest Floresta da Cicuta2 <lb/>131 <lb/>Rio <lb/>de <lb/>Janeiro <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Desengano State Park <lb/>21,080 <lb/>Rio <lb/>de <lb/>Janeiro <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Alto Douro Private Natural <lb/>Heritage Reserve and Serra da <lb/>Prata Private Natural <lb/>Heritage Reserve <lb/>479,05 <lb/>Minas <lb/>Gerais <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Ibitipoca State Park <lb/>and surroundings <lb/>1,418 <lb/>Minas <lb/>Gerais <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>Rio Doce State Park <lb/>35,974 <lb/>Minas <lb/>Gerais <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Serra do Brigadeiro State Park <lb/>13,210 <lb/>Minas <lb/>Gerais <lb/>To be defined <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 Continuation of the Reintroduction process; 2 Areas with less than 250 hectares of area are <lb/>contiguous to larger forest remnants. Source: ICMBio (2023). <lb/>Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/>Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>05 <lb/></page>

			<body>Another reintroduction project is underway in Tijuca National <lb/>Park, Rio de Janeiro State and, having started 10 years ago, before <lb/>the Integrated Population Management Program for A. guariba. <lb/>However, important management decisions regarding this project <lb/>have already been taken with the approval of CMAG. On the other <lb/>hand, many aspects of the Integrated Population Management <lb/>Program were inspired and informed by this pioneer experience. <lb/>The Brazilian Committee for Management of Alouatta guariba <lb/>is composed by several experts and representatives from the <lb/>different states of the species distribution range, and it receives <lb/>requests for support in the destination of animals that are at risk or <lb/>need to be transferred to another ex situ institution. These requests <lb/>come mainly from state agencies and the ICMBio/CPB itself, <lb/>considering the importance of recommendations from the <lb/>Studbook keeper in some cases. A spreadsheet to register and <lb/>control these cases was established and, to date, some type of <lb/>support has been provided for 17 cases, coming from five states <lb/>(Minas Gerais, São Paulo, Espirito Santo, Santa Catarina and Rio <lb/>Grande do Sul). <lb/>Although a plan for systematic communication and <lb/>dissemination has not yet been developed, several actions to <lb/>publicize the IPMP have already been carried out, including: two <lb/>articles in &quot;O Eco&quot; website (O Eco, 2023a, b); two articles in &quot;Jornal <lb/>O Globo&quot; (O Globo, 2023, 2024); and lectures for Biology and <lb/>Veterinary graduation courses at FURB (Blumenau Regional <lb/>University) and for State Environmental Agencies. <lb/>Regarding the actions aiming to control the impacts of yellow <lb/>fever, an intensive investigative effort supported by the Committee <lb/>for Management of Alouatta guariba is underway to verify if <lb/>vaccination could be an effective tool for preventing the disease in <lb/>Alouatta guariba. Preliminary results demonstrated that the 17DD <lb/>attenuated yellow fever vaccine was safe and immunogenic for A. <lb/>guariba (Fernandes et al., 2021). After that, other captive <lb/>populations in Brazil are receiving the 17DD attenuated yellow <lb/>fever vaccine, such as Centro de Pesquisas Bioloǵicas de Indaial and <lb/>Instituto Espaco Silvestre (Santa Catarina); Centro de Manejo e <lb/>Conservacão de Animais Silvestres and Instituto Libio (São Paulo) <lb/>and Centro de Primatologia do Rio de Janeiro (Rio de Janeiro). All <lb/>the animals involved in the Integrated Population Management <lb/>Program are being vaccinated against yellow fever and tested if they <lb/>become immunized prior to being included in reintroduction/ <lb/>reinforcement actions, following the protocol established in <lb/>this research. <lb/>Argentina <lb/>During the two-stage workshop in Argentina, we evaluated <lb/>strategies for the long-term population recovery in Misiones, <lb/>resulting in an exhaustive analysis of the existing scientific <lb/>information on the population and areas where howlers have <lb/>been recorded before and after the yellow fever outbreaks. The <lb/>analysis indicated that all four management options evaluated -<lb/>reintroduction, reinforcement, rescue and ex situ management -<lb/>can be implemented, following the list of criteria and <lb/>recommendations established for each option by the participants. <lb/>Reintroduction was considered as the first measure in specific <lb/>areas of Misiones because it entails fewer potential risks to natural <lb/>populations compared to population reinforcement. <lb/>Reintroduction was also proposed as a priority option, as a way <lb/>of improving management and translocation techniques to be <lb/>subsequently applied in the implementation of population <lb/>reinforcement actions. The simultaneous establishment of an ex <lb/>situ management program was recommended for Alouatta guariba <lb/>in Argentina as part of the comprehensive species management <lb/>program (One-plan approach) and to contribute to its recovery and <lb/>conservation. In Argentina nowadays there are no individuals of A. <lb/>guariba in captivity. <lb/>Another important output of this workshop was the creation of <lb/>a multi-sectoral Management Committee, aiming to promote the <lb/>implementation of the defined population management strategies, <lb/>thus favoring the restoration of ecological functions in the <lb/>ecosystems inhabited by these monkeys, as well as to recover <lb/>their cultural value among local communities, highlighting <lb/>their role as sentinels for public health and as seed dispersers. <lb/>This committee is composed of representatives of the <lb/>national governmental environmental entities of Argentina and <lb/>Brazil, Misiones province authorities, the IUCN SSC Primate <lb/>Specialist Group, researchers, forest rangers, NGOs and other <lb/>important stakeholders. <lb/>Ten areas were prioritized to initiate the surveys as possible <lb/>reintroduction sites, of which Esmeralda Provincial Park was <lb/>indicated as one with the greatest benefits and lowest potential <lb/>risks (Table 2). The final report of this workshop is in process to be <lb/>published, but the preprint is already available (Oklander et al., <lb/>2023b). Currently, we are working on obtaining funds in order to <lb/>develop the agreed actions. <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>Map with the potential Priority Areas for conservation translocations <lb/>of Brown Howler Monkey Alouatta guariba (red dots) selected by <lb/>Brazilian and Argentinian Management Programs inside species <lb/>distribution range (dashed blue) and Atlantic Forest limits <lb/>(light green). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>06 <lb/></page>

			<body>Binational actions and integration process <lb/>The processes in the two countries ran in parallel, following the <lb/>stakeholders&apos; agendas and the governmental directives of each one. <lb/>Although, the continuous exchange of information and experience <lb/>was crucial to qualify the proposals and evidenced the need for <lb/>integration among the two programs, since the distribution of the <lb/>species transcends political borders. The main evidence of how <lb/>crucial the binational cooperation is for recovering the brown <lb/>howler populations is that it became clear that the conservation <lb/>of the species in Argentina unequivocally depends on population <lb/>management; which in turn depends on individuals and ex situ <lb/>management experience from Brazil, since in Argentina there are <lb/>no captive brown howlers and the remnant in situ populations are <lb/>too small to serve as source for conservation translocations. <lb/>Genetic analysis including samples from across the species&apos; <lb/>distribution are key to guarantee correct ex situ management and <lb/>structuring adequate insurance populations. The description of <lb/>intraspecific conservation units, assessing the levels of genetic <lb/>diversity and gene flow of remaining populations is fundamental <lb/>to guide management decisions. Aiming to conserve the genetic <lb/>pool of Alouatta guariba, and provide conservation guidelines and <lb/>key information for management or conservation translocation <lb/>projects, five different Management Units (MU) were defined <lb/>throughout the actual geographic distribution of the brown <lb/>howler monkey during the meeting in São Paulo, in 2021. Based <lb/>on significant differences in allele frequency distributions (Oklander <lb/>et al., 2007) and significant divergence in mitochondrial and nuclear <lb/>loci, with the samples analyzed up to 2021, we grouped individuals <lb/>into three genetic clusters: 1. Misiones (Argentina), Rio Grande do <lb/>Sul and Santa Catarina (Brazil); 2. São Paulo (Brazil); 3. Rio de <lb/>Janeiro, Espıŕito Santo and Minas Gerais (Brazil). Until that <lb/>moment, there were no available samples analyzed from the <lb/>Brazilian states of Parana and Bahia, so they were designated as <lb/>two additional distinct Management Units for precautionary <lb/>measures. However, more recent analyzes suggest that at least one <lb/>population analyzed in Paranánear the province of Misiones <lb/>(Argentina) belongs to the cluster 1. These data, together with a <lb/>review of previous work on the taxonomy and phylogeography of <lb/>the species (Rylands et al., 2000; Gregorin, 2006; Povill et al., 2023) <lb/>are about to be published in an article where updated MU are <lb/>proposed (Oklander et al., in prep). <lb/>The published protocol for ex situ management (Hirano et al., <lb/>2023) and that for preparation for release (under construction), <lb/>both developed in the scope of the Brazilian Integrated Population <lb/>Management Program, counted on the advice of members from <lb/>Argentina, and is also being adapted to be used by the Argentinian <lb/>program. These protocols are essential to control and reduce the <lb/>risks involved in animal translocations and will serve as a guide for <lb/>conservationist translocations of ex situ howlers to be developed. <lb/>The first Brazilian translocations began in Santa Catarina, with the <lb/>reintroduction of three groups of howler monkeys out of a total of six <lb/>groups planned for the first half of 2024. In São Paulo, there is another <lb/>project already approved by the management program that aims to <lb/>reinforce the natural population in one of the priority areas listed for <lb/>the state and which suffered a decline in the howler monkey <lb/>population due to yellow fever outbreaks. And there is the third <lb/>reintroduction in one of the selected areas, the continuation of the <lb/>reintroduction project at Tijuca National Park, in Rio de Janeiro, with <lb/>the release of the second group, a family group with six members. In <lb/>Argentina, surveys are being prepared to select sites for reintroductions <lb/>in Misiones. Additionally, appropriate enclosures are being planned to <lb/>receive individuals/groups from Brazil and the Committee is seeking <lb/>funds to build them. Another important decision in this integration <lb/>process was that all the individuals exported from Brazil to Argentina <lb/>must be vaccinated against yellow fever. <lb/>Discussion and next steps <lb/>The brown howler monkey has been suffering from hunting, <lb/>deforestation and habitat fragmentation, in addition to the latest <lb/>epizootic events of yellow fever, which has led the species to an <lb/>increased level of extinction risk and being listed among the 25 most <lb/>endangered primates of the world (Jerusalinsky et al., 2021; <lb/>Oklander et al., 2022a). This motivated the mobilization of efforts <lb/>to develop management strategies with an integrative approach to <lb/>its ex situ and in situ populations, aiming to restore the largest <lb/>possible number of populations throughout its distribution area. <lb/>TABLE 2 List of ten priority areas in the Alouatta guariba Argentinian <lb/>Management Program, including the name, size, state of the country and <lb/>the suggested management (population reinforcement, reintroduction, <lb/>no management needed or to be defined) ordered by Recommended <lb/>Population Management. <lb/>Name of <lb/>the area <lb/>Area <lb/>size <lb/>(ha) <lb/>State Recommended <lb/>Population <lb/>Management <lb/>Caa-Yari <lb/>Provincial Park <lb/>4,783 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Cruce Caballero <lb/>Provincial Park <lb/>600 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Guarani Multiple <lb/>Use Reserve <lb/>5,343 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>Reintroduction <lb/>Esmeralda <lb/>Provincial Park <lb/>31,700 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>MoconaṔ <lb/>rovincial Park <lb/>1,000 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>Reinforcement <lb/>El Piñalito <lb/>Provincial Park3 <lb/>3,800 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Papel Misionero <lb/>Cultural <lb/>Natural Reserve4 <lb/>10,200 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Private <lb/>property Arauco2 <lb/>8700 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Private property GBM <lb/>(former Belgian <lb/>Forestry)2 <lb/>25,000 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Private property <lb/>La Mocheta1 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>Misiones <lb/>To be defined <lb/>Reasons for not defining the management this date: 1 Permanent deforestation in this area; <lb/>2 Private areas that need negotiation with the owner company; 3 Risk of hybridization by the <lb/>confirmed occurrence of A. guariba and A. caraya; 4 Presence of Guaranı́communities. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>07 <lb/></page>

			<body>Given that the species&apos; distribution includes two countries, <lb/>Argentina and Brazil, these strategies need to be developed in an <lb/>integrated manner to be more effective. We present here how the <lb/>involved teams of the two countries, following the respective <lb/>national conservation action plans, have acted both independently <lb/>and cooperatively to develop such strategies, with the step-by-step <lb/>procedures in each country and to promote integration, as well as <lb/>the achievements and difficulties in these processes. <lb/>In Brazil, the Integrated Population Management Program for A. <lb/>guariba was the first created and officially recognized following the <lb/>newest national legal framework for such programs (ICMBio, 2021, <lb/>2023). However, in its first year (2023-2024), the Committee for <lb/>Management of Alouatta guariba faced numerous difficulties to <lb/>coordinate and implement the program: 1. the need to update/ <lb/>identify populations/areas which would require management <lb/>according to the established criteria (considering distribution <lb/>extremes and management units); 2. the delay in producing a list of <lb/>dietary species consumed in the occurrence areas, according to the <lb/>forest types; 3. the need to identify other areas -in addition to those <lb/>already selected -that could be eligible for population management; 4. <lb/>the delay to consolidate/update the necessary protocols -collection and <lb/>allocation of biological samples for genetics, health research, behavioral <lb/>assessment (associated with ethograms); preparation for release in <lb/>translocations; post-release monitoring; reproductive assessment; and <lb/>5. the lack of an established decision key to evaluate and define the <lb/>destination of confiscated and ex situ individuals. <lb/>The Committee for Management of Alouatta guariba also <lb/>experienced difficulties in implementation or application of the <lb/>following actions due to the insufficiency of financial resources: 1. <lb/>executing efforts to collect biological samples for genetic analysis in <lb/>the following areas (sampling gaps): southern Bahia, southeast of <lb/>Minas Gerais, central and western the São Paulo, the whole state of <lb/>Parana, and the highlands of Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina; <lb/>2. liaise with laboratories to carry out serological tests for <lb/>arboviruses; and 3. continue research on the effectiveness of the <lb/>yellow fever vaccine for the species. Additional challenges were <lb/>faced due to the low adherence by institutions and their respective <lb/>managers in: 1. updating/identifying the individuals to be part of the <lb/>studbook -according to established criteria; 2. assembling the <lb/>studbook for Alouatta guariba; 3. making the annual <lb/>management recommendations; 4. developing the ex situ <lb/>management according to studbook recommendations; and 5. <lb/>effectively promoting the establishment of an insurance population. <lb/>In the other hand, within just one year, the Committee for <lb/>Management of Alouatta guariba was able to promote the <lb/>satisfactory implementation of several actions in Brazil, with a <lb/>continuous work in progress. This includes: 1. promoting the <lb/>integrated management for the conservation of the species; 2. <lb/>articulating to obtain serology results for arboviruses carried out <lb/>in active surveillance by the Health Departments/Research Projects; <lb/>3. establishing and implementing a communication and awareness <lb/>plan about the species and the Population Management Program; 4. <lb/>creating forms for project, report, considerations on the project and <lb/>report evaluation; and 5. evaluating projects proposing <lb/>management actions in accordance with the Integrated <lb/>Population Management Program. <lb/>In Argentina, to carry out the first reintroductions, several prior <lb/>steps are necessary such as: 1) survey the presence of brown howler <lb/>monkeys in the 10 areas prioritized as possible reintroduction sites; <lb/>2) survey the presence of black and gold howler monkeys in the <lb/>same areas, following the recommendation to avoid reintroductions <lb/>in sites with the presence of A. caraya due to the evidence of <lb/>hybridization between the two species; 3) survey the presence of <lb/>other mammal species and potential predators in that priority areas; <lb/>4) evaluate the state of habitat conservation in the 10 areas <lb/>prioritized; 5) work together with the local communities on the <lb/>importance of the brown howlers as sentinels for yellow fever, <lb/>regenerators of the forest, and cultural values previously to any <lb/>reintroduction; 6) import groups/individuals from Brazil to carry <lb/>out the reintroductions. Since the workshop, we have been working <lb/>on obtaining financing support to progress on all these steps. <lb/>So far, we have obtained financing for developing conservation <lb/>educational workshops -framed for the upcoming reintroduction of <lb/>brown howler monkeys into these areas, highlighting the importance <lb/>of the species as a seed disperser and health sentinel -in rural schools <lb/>within the prioritized areas (Primate Conservation Inc). We plan to <lb/>start these activities in May 2024 together with an information survey <lb/>with local people to comply with the scientific-technical requirements <lb/>necessary to carry out the consensual actions. We have also obtained <lb/>funding to expand the capacity of enclosures at the rescue center in <lb/>Misiones Province, complying with international standards, for the <lb/>reception of individuals imported from Brazil (International Primate <lb/>Protection League). This Rescue Center called Guira Oga (https:// <lb/>guiraoga.com.ar/) will finance the maintenance, medical attention <lb/>and supplies, and food for howlers, from reception until release. The <lb/>challenge at hand is to obtain funding to carry out the rest of the prior <lb/>steps mentioned above. Another key issue refers to obtaining the <lb/>international movement permits, which we believe will be facilitated <lb/>by the involvement of competent authorities in the process. <lb/>The current categorization of Alouatta guariba as Vulnerable, <lb/>despite the diverse and severe menaces it faces, can be largely <lb/>attributed to the species&apos; wide geographic distribution range <lb/>(Jerusalinsky et al., 2021). The consideration that all individuals <lb/>of the species (or of the currently recognized subspecies) are <lb/>homogeneous can lead to management errors and the unnoticed <lb/>loss of populations with exclusive genetic characteristics. This can <lb/>be prevented by designating intraspecific conservation units such as <lb/>Evolutionarily Significant Units (ESU) or Management Units (MU). <lb/>An example of this regrettably late detection exists in the black-and-<lb/>gold howler monkey (Alouatta caraya) where a genetic study after <lb/>the construction of dams showed that an entire genetic cluster of the <lb/>species probably became extinct due to the flooding of populations <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>08 <lb/></page>

			<body>with exclusive genetic characteristics (Oklander et al., 2022b). In <lb/>this sense, the designation of MU in Alouatta guariba has been a <lb/>very important precautionary measure. <lb/>Following the Guidelines for Reintroductions and other <lb/>Conservation Translocations (IUCN, 2013), each management <lb/>action proposed to effectively implement the present strategy, will <lb/>need to include detailed exposure of its potential risks and benefits <lb/>for ecological, social and economic interests, which will be carefully <lb/>evaluated by the corresponding coordination committee and the <lb/>competent authorities. Particular attention must be given whether <lb/>there is strong evidence that the threat(s) that caused population <lb/>reduction or local extinction have been correctly identified and <lb/>removed or sufficiently reduced, without which it should not <lb/>proceed, and alternative conservation solutions should be sought <lb/>(IUCN, 2013). In a local perspective, much of the success of such <lb/>reintroductions will depend on minimizing typical conflicts with <lb/>humans (Garcıá de la Chica et al., 2023), so working with the <lb/>community in areas where conservation translocations will be <lb/>implemented is indispensable. At another extreme of the spatial <lb/>scale, the effectiveness of this strategy must depend on the <lb/>continuous binational integration and some type of international <lb/>formalization of the initiative. <lb/>Biodiversity faces the worldwide escalation of an anthropogenic <lb/>crisis, with extensive modification of natural environments <lb/>threatening several species, impacted by habitat loss and <lb/>fragmentation, and emergent challenges to their conservation <lb/>such as climate change and diseases outbreaks (Bernard and <lb/>Marshall, 2020). This is the case for many primates, including A. <lb/>guariba (Estrada et al., 2017; Jerusalinsky et al., 2021; Oklander <lb/>et al., 2022a). Developing and implementing science-based, <lb/>participatory and integrated strategies -sharing information, <lb/>work and responsibilities among all those involved (researchers, <lb/>government agencies, NGOs, zoos and wildlife rescue centers, <lb/>protected areas and concerned citizens) -can be a decisive factor <lb/>for the conservation of species (Lees et al., 2021). Several efforts have <lb/>been made in this sense to develop conservation action plans for <lb/>primates in the last five decades, including national initiatives <lb/>(Reuter et al., 2022). A good example on the positive impacts for <lb/>primate conservation of such approach comes from another <lb/>Atlantic Forest atelid, the muriquis, which benefited from <lb/>progressive efforts in science, public policies and population <lb/>management (Strier et al., 2021). In this context, building the <lb/>present science-based, participatory and integrative strategy to <lb/>restore populations of A. guariba represents an innovative <lb/>background, and may inspire further initiatives for the <lb/>conservation of threatened species requiring population <lb/>management and pluri-national efforts. <lb/></body>

			<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>LO: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Supervision, Validation, Visualization, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. MR: Conceptualization, <lb/>Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, <lb/>Resources, Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing, Validation. RR: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal <lb/>analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Supervision, Visualization, Writing -original draft, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing, Validation. SP: Conceptualization, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Resources, Supervision, Validation, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. ZH: Conceptualization, <lb/>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>CM: Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Resources, <lb/>Validation, Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review <lb/>&amp; editing. AD: Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. DD: Investigation, <lb/>Resources, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>DO: Investigation, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. FM: Investigation, Writing -review &amp; editing. MV-M: <lb/>Investigation, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, <lb/>Methodology, Project administration, Resources, Supervision, <lb/>Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. MK: <lb/>Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Project <lb/>administration, Writing -review &amp; editing. LJ: Conceptualization, <lb/>Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, <lb/>Project administration, Resources, Supervision, Validation, <lb/>Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. The <lb/>workshop in Brazil was funded by the Instituto Chico Mendes de <lb/>Conservacão da Biodiversidade (ICMBio) with the support of the <lb/>São Paulo Zoo. The workshops in Argentina were funded by the <lb/>Primate Action Fund supported by the Margot Marsh Biodiversity <lb/>Foundation and Re:wild, Ministry of Environment and Sustainable <lb/>Development of Argentina through the UNDP Project ARG/21/ <lb/>G28 GEF (Global Environment Funds), SSC Internal Grant IUCN <lb/>and NPC Argentina. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We are especially grateful for the support of the IUCN SSC <lb/>Conservation Planning Specialist Group at different stages of this <lb/>initiative, such as designing and facilitating the One Plan Approach/ <lb/>Ex situ Guidelines virtual workshop in Brazil and the virtual and in-<lb/>person workshops held in Argentina, particularly Fabiana Lopes <lb/>Rocha, Eugenia Cordero Schmidt, Kristin Leus and Kathy Traylor-<lb/>Holzer. We are also thankful for the support of São Paulo Zoo in <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>09 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">promoting the in-person workshop in Brazil, especially to Mara <lb/>Marques, who pushed the present initiative from the start as a key <lb/>collaborator of the National Action Plan for the Conservation of <lb/>Primates of the Atlantic Forest and the Maned-sloth. We would like <lb/>to thank the National Center for Research and Conservation of <lb/>Brazilian Primates (CPB) of the Instituto Chico Mendes de <lb/>Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio), the Brazilian <lb/>Association of State Environmental Entities (ABEMA), and all the <lb/>institutions that are part of the Committee for Management of <lb/>Alouatta guariba. We also like to acknowledge the institutions and <lb/>professionals that are already sending projects to be evaluated by <lb/>this committee for starting the effective implementation of the <lb/>management program in Brazil. We would also like to thank the <lb/>Instituto Misionero de Biodiversidad (IMIBio) specially to Dr. <lb/>Emanuel Grassi and the Ministry of Ecology of Misiones, for <lb/>their essential support in promoting the workshop in Argentina <lb/>and for endorsing the development of this program. We are also <lb/>grateful to the provincial park rangers, all the participants of the <lb/>workshop, and the whole network involved in the National Primate <lb/>Conservation Action Plan of Argentina. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be <lb/>construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, <lb/>or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product <lb/>that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its <lb/>manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Agostini, I., Holzmann, I., Oklander, L., Peker, S., Pave, R., and Kowalewski, M. <lb/>(2019). &quot;Alouatta guariba,&quot; in Categorizacioń 2019 de los mamıferos de Argentina seguń <lb/>su riesgo de extincioń. Red List of mammals in Argentina. Ed. SAyDS-SAREM,. (Buenos <lb/>Aires, Argentina: SAREM). Available at: http://cma.sarem.org.ar/es/especie-nativa/ <lb/>alouatta-guariba. doi: 10.31687/SaremLR.19.117 <lb/>Almeida, M. A. B. D., Santos, E. D., Cardoso, J. D. C., Fonseca, D. F. D., Noll, C. A., Silveira, <lb/>V. R., et al. (2012). Yellow fever outbreak affecting Alouatta populations in southern Brazil <lb/>(Rio Grande do Sul State), 2008-2009. Am. J. Primatol. 74, 68-76. doi: 10.1002/ajp.21010 <lb/>Alves, R. R. N., and Barboza, R. R. D. (2018). &quot;Animals as ethnozooindicators of <lb/>weather and climate,&quot; in Ethnozoology: Animals in Our Lives. Eds. R. R. N. Alves and A. <lb/>U. Paulino (Elsevier Science &amp; Technology, Saint Louis), 383-420. <lb/>Bergallo, H. G., Rocha, C. F. D., Alves, M. A. S., and Van Sluys, M. (2000). A fauna <lb/>ameacada de extincão do Estado do Rio de Janeiro. (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: EdUERJ). <lb/>Bernard, A. B., and Marshall, A. J. (2020). Assessing the state of knowledge of contemporary <lb/>climate change and primates. Evol. Anthrop. 29, 317-331. doi: 10.1002/evan.21874 <lb/>Bicca-Marques, J. C., Alves, S. L., Ingberman, B., Buss, G., Fries, B. G., Alonso, A. C., <lb/>et al. (2018). &quot;Alouatta guariba clamitans,&quot; in Livro Vermelho da Fauna Brasileira <lb/>Ameacada de Extincão: Volume II -Mamıferos. Eds. A. B. M. MaChado, G. M. <lb/>Drummond and A. Paglia (Brasília, Brazil: Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservacão da <lb/>Biodiversidade (ICMBio). <lb/>Bicca-Marques, J. C., Calegaro Marques, C., Rylands, A., Strier, K. B., Mittermeier, R., <lb/>De Almeida, M. A., et al. (2017). Yellow fever threatens Atlantic Forest primates. <lb/>Yellow fever threatens Atlantic Forest primates. Sci. Adv. 3, e1600946/tab-e. <lb/>Bicca-Marques, J. C., Chaves, O ́. M., and Hass, G. P. (2020). Howler monkey <lb/>tolerance to habitat shrinking: lifetime warranty or death sentence? Am. J. Primatol. 82, <lb/>e23089. doi: 10.1002/ajp.23089 <lb/>Buss, G., Oklander, L. I., Bicca Marques, J. C., Hirano, Z. B., Chaves, O ́.M., Mendes, S. <lb/>L., et al. (2019). &quot;Brown howler monkey Alouatta guariba (Humboldt 1812),&quot; in <lb/>Primates in Peril: The World&apos;s 25 Most Endangered Primates 2018-2020. Eds. C. <lb/>Schwitzer, R. A. Mittermeier, A. B. Rylands, F. Chiozza, E. A. Williamson, D. Byler, <lb/>et al (IUCN SSC Primate Specialist Group, International Primatological Society, Global <lb/>Wildlife Conservation, and Bristol Zoological Society, Washington, USA). <lb/>Byers, O., Lees, C., Wilcken, J., and Schwitzer, C. (2013). The philosophy and <lb/>implementation of CBSG&apos;s approach to integrated species conservation planning. <lb/>WAZA magazine 14, 2-5. <lb/>Cabrera, A. (1940). Notas sobre carnivoros sudamericanos. Notas del Museo de La <lb/>Plata. Seccioń Zoologıá. 5 (29). <lb/>Chaves, O ́. M., Bicca-Marques, J. C., and Chapman, C. A. (2018). Quantity and <lb/>quality of seed dispersal by a large arboreal frugivore in small and large Atlantic forest <lb/>fragments. PloS One 13, e0193660. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0193660 <lb/>Chaves, O ́. M., Juńior, J. C. S., Buss, G., Hirano, Z. M. B., Jardim, M. M. A., Amaral, E. <lb/>L. S., et al. (2022). Wildlife is imperiled in peri-urban landscapes: threats to arboreal <lb/>mammals. Sci. Total Environ. 15, 152883. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.152883 <lb/>de Almeida, A. S., and Voltolini, J. C. (2017). Percepcão ambiental dos moradores do <lb/>entorno da Mata do Bugio sobre bugios-ruivos Alouatta guariba clamitans Cabrera <lb/>1940, em Taubate, SP&quot;. Rev. Biociencias 23.2, 54-64. <lb/>Estrada, A., Garber, P. A., Rylands, A. B., Roos, C., Fernandez-Duque, E., Di Fiore, <lb/>A., et al. (2017). Impending extinction crisis of the world&apos;s primates: Why primates <lb/>matter. Sci. Adv. 3, e1600946. doi: 10.1126/sciadv.1600946 <lb/>Fernandes, A. T. S., Moreira, S. B., Gaspar, L. P., Simões, M., dos Reis Albuquerque <lb/>Cajaraville, A. C., Carvalho Pereira, R., et al. (2021). Safety and immunogenicity of <lb/>17DD attenuated yellow fever vaccine in howler monkeys (Alouatta spp.). J. Med. <lb/>Primatol. 50, 36-45. doi: 10.1111/jmp.12501 <lb/>Garcıá de la Chica, A., Oklander, L. I., Kowalewski, M. M., and Fernandez-Duque, E. <lb/>(2023). Human and non-human primate coexistence in Argentina: conflicts and <lb/>solutions. Animals 13, 3331. doi: 10.3390/ani13213331 <lb/>Gregorin, R. (2006). Taxonomy and geographic variation of species of the genus <lb/>Alouatta Laceṕède (Primates,Atelidae) in Brazil. Rev. Bras. Zool. 23, 64-144. <lb/>doi: 10.1590/S0101-81752006000100005 <lb/>Hirano, Z. M. B., Francisco, S. R. S., Ludwig, G., Ansolch, M., Dada, A. N., Junglos, <lb/>A. M., et al. (2023). Protocolos de manejo ex situ de primatas do ge ̂nero Alouatta <lb/>{livro eletronico}. 2ed (Brasilia, DF: Instituto Chico Mendes -ICMBio). Available at: <lb/>https://www.gov.br/icmbio/pt-br/assuntos/programas-e-projetos/programa-de-<lb/>manejo-populacional/Protocolos_de_Manejo_ex_situ_de_primatas_do_genero_ <lb/>Alouatta.pdf. <lb/>ICMBio. (2018). Plano de Acão Nacional para a Conservacão dos Primatas da Mata <lb/>Atlantica e da Preguica-de-Coleira -PAN PPMA. Brasília: DOU de 07/08/2018. <lb/>Available online at: https://www.gov.br/icmbio/pt-br/assuntos/biodiversidade/pan/ <lb/>pan-primatas-ma-e-preguica-de-coleira#:~:text=O%20Plano%20de%20A%C3%A7% <lb/>C3%A3o%20Nacional,cinco%20anos%22%20e%20como%20vis%C3%A3o (Accessed <lb/>at April 21, 2024) <lb/>ICMBio (2021) INSTRUÇÃO NORMATIVA N°5/GABIN/ICMBIO, DE 28 DE <lb/>JUNHO DE 2021. Available online at: https://www.gov.br/icmbio/pt-br/assuntos/ <lb/>programas-e-projetos/programa-de-manejo-populacional/arquivos/in_5_de_28_de_ <lb/>junho_de_2021.pdf. <lb/>ICMBio (2023) PROGRAMA DE MANEJO POPULACIONAL DE Alouatta guariba. <lb/>Available online at: https://www.gov.br/icmbio/pt-br/assuntos/programas-e-projetos/ <lb/>programa-de-manejo-populacional/Programa_Manejo_Alouatta_guariba_com_ <lb/>anexo_publicacao_final_corrigido_especialistas.pdf. <lb/>IUCN/SSC (2013). Guidelines for Reintroductions and Other Conservation Translocations. <lb/>Version 1.0 (Gland, Switzerland: IUCN Species Survival Commission). Available at: https:// <lb/>portals.iucn.org/library/efiles/documents/2013-009.pdf. <lb/>IUCN/SSC (2014). Guidelines on the Use of Ex Situ Management for Species <lb/>Conservation. Version 2.0 (Gland, Switzerland: IUCN Species Survival Commission). <lb/>Available at: www.iucn.org/about/work/programmes/species/publications/iucn_ <lb/>guidelines_and:policy:statements/. <lb/>Jerusalinsky, L., Bicca-Marques, J. C., Neves, L. G., Alves, S. L., Ingberman, B., Buss, G., <lb/>et al. (2021). &quot;Alouatta guariba (amended version of 2020 assessment),&quot; in The IUCN Red <lb/>List of Threatened Species 2021 (Gland, Switzerland: IUCN), e.T39916A190417874. <lb/>doi: 10.2305/IUCN.UK.2021-1.RLTS.T39916A190417874.en <lb/>Lees, C. M., Rutschmann, A., Santure, A. W., and Beggs, J. R. (2021). Science-based, <lb/>stakeholder-inclusive, and participatory conservation planning helps reverse the decline of <lb/>threatened species. Biol. Conserv. 260, E109194. doi: 10.1016/j.biocon.2021.109194 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Ministerio de Ambiente y Desarollo Sostenible (2021) RESOL-2021-430-APN-MAD. <lb/>Available online at: https://www.Argentina.gob.ar/normativa/nacional/resoluci%C3% <lb/>B3n-430-2021-358740/texto (Accessed February 21, 2024). <lb/>Moreno, E. S., Agostini, I., Holzmann, I., Di Bitetti, M. S., Oklander, L. I., <lb/>Kowalewski, M., et al. (2015). Yellow fever impact on brown howler monkeys <lb/>(Alouatta guariba clamitans) in Argentina: a metamodelling approach based on <lb/>population viability analysis and epidemiological dynamics. Mem. Inst. Oswaldo <lb/>Cruz 110, 865-876. doi: 10.1590/0074-02760150075 <lb/>Neves, L. G., Jerusalinsky, L., and Melo, F. R. (2018). &quot;Alouatta guariba guariba <lb/>(Humboldt 1812),&quot; in Livro Vermelho da Fauna Brasileira Ameacada de Extincão: <lb/>Volume II -Mamıferos, Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservacão da Biodiversidade -<lb/>ICMBio (Org.) (Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservacão da Biodiversidade (ICMBio, <lb/>Brasıĺia, Brazil), 162-166. <lb/>Neves, L. G., Jerusalinsky, L., Melo, F. R., Rylands, A. B., and Talebi, M. (2017). <lb/>&quot;Northern brown howler Alouatta guariba guariba (Humboldt 1812),&quot; in Primates in <lb/>Peril -The World&apos;s 25 Most Endangered Primates 2016-2018 (Arlington, USA: IUCN <lb/>SSC Primate Specialist Group (PSG), International Primatological Society (IPS), <lb/>Conservation International (CI) and Bristol Zoological Society), 96-99. <lb/>O Eco. (2023a) Integracão: palavra-chave para salvar o bugio-ruivo. Available online at: <lb/>https://oeco.org.br/reportagens/integracao-palavra-chave-para-salvar-o-bugio-ruivo/. <lb/>O Eco. (2023b) Bugios do Brasil serão fundamentais para salvar a espećie na <lb/>Argentina. Available online at: https://oeco.org.br/noticias/bugios-do-brasil-serao-<lb/>fundamentais-para-salvar-a-especie-na-Argentina/. <lb/>O Globo. (2023) Febre amarela: vacina da Fiocruz étestada com sucesso em macacos. <lb/>Available online at: https://oglobo.globo.com/saude/vacina-e-saude/noticia/2023/04/ <lb/>febre-amarela-vacina-e-testada-com-sucesso-em-macacos-vitimados-por-epidemia-<lb/>recente-da-doenca.ghtml. <lb/>O Globo. (2024) Apoś oito anos, segundo grupo com sete macacos-bugios são <lb/>reintroduzidos no Parque Nacional da Tijuca. Available online at: https://oglobo. <lb/>globo.com/um-so-planeta/noticia/2024/01/03/apos-oito-anos-segundo-grupo-com-<lb/>sete-macacos-bugios-sao-reintroduzidos-no-parque-nacional-da-tijuca.ghtml. <lb/>Oklander, L. I., Buss, G., Bicca-Marques, J. C., Hirano, Z., Chaves, O ́., Mendes, S. L., <lb/>et al. (2022a). &quot;Brown howler monkey Alouatta guariba (Humboldt 1812) Brazil, <lb/>Argentina,&quot; in Primates in Peril. The world&apos;s 25 most endangered primates 2022-2023. <lb/>Eds. R. A. Mittermeier, K. E. Reuter, A. B. Rylands, L. Jerusalinsky, C. Schwitzer, K. B. <lb/>Strier, et al (IUCN SSC Primate Specialist Group, International Primatological Society, <lb/>Global Wildlife Conservation, and Bristol Zoological Society, Washington, USA). <lb/>Oklander, L. I., Caputo, M., Fernańdez, G. P., Jerusalinsky, L., de Oliveira, S. F., <lb/>Bonatto, S. L., et al. (2022b). Gone with the water: The loss of genetic variability in black <lb/>and gold howler monkeys (Alouatta caraya) due to dam construction. Front. Ecol. Evol. <lb/>10. doi: 10.3389/fevo.2022.768652 <lb/>Oklander, L. I., Cordero-Schmidt, E., Peker, S., Jerusalinsky, L., Kowalewski, M., <lb/>Pablo Dovico, P., et al. (2023a). Collaborative efforts for the conservation of the brown <lb/>howler monkey (Alouatta guariba) population management planning of Argentina&apos;s <lb/>most endangered primate. WAZA Magazine 2023-3, 14-15. <lb/>Oklander, L., Jerusalinsky, L., and Bonatto, S. L. (2007). Applicability of microsatellite <lb/>heterologs in Alouatta guariba and other Brazilian primates. Eds. F. R. Melo, A. Hirsch, <lb/>C. G. Costa, L. G. Dias, I. M. C. Mourthe, F. P. Tabacow, et al (Belo Horizonte, Brazil: <lb/>Resumos XII Congresso Brasileiro de Primatologia), pp: 195. <lb/>Oklander, L. I., Peker, S., Kowalewski, M., Jerusalinsky, L., Cordero, E., Lopes Rocha, <lb/>F., et al. (2023b) Evaluacioń del manejo poblacional para la conservacioń del mono <lb/>aullador rojo (Alouatta guariba) en la provincia de Misiones, Argentina. Available <lb/>online at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/378138882_Evaluacion_del_ <lb/>manejo_poblacional_para_la_conservacion_del_mono_aullador_rojo_Alouatta_ <lb/>guariba_en_la_provincia_de_Misiones_Argentina_REPORTE_FINAL?channel= <lb/>doi&amp;linkId=65c8db371bed776ae3413231&amp;showFulltext=true (Accessed February 20, <lb/>2024). <lb/>Oklander, L. I., Fernandez, G. P., Machado, S., Caputo, M., Hirano, Z. M. B., Neves, <lb/>L. G., et al. (in prep). Phylogeography of the endangered brown howler monkey, <lb/>Alouatta guariba (Primates, Atelidae), of the Atlantic Forest: evolution, taxonomy, and <lb/>conservation. Frontiers in Genetics -section Evolutionary and Population Genetic <lb/>(Research Topic Challenges and Prospects for Conservation Genetics at XXI Century). <lb/>Oliveira, L. G. D. (2022). O Bugio Ruivo (Alouatta guariba clamitans) como <lb/>instrumento cultural e ambiental no municıṕio de São Francisco de Paula-RS. (São <lb/>Francisco de Paula, Brazil: Universidade Estadual do Rio Grande do Sul). Available at: <lb/>https://repositorio.uergs.edu.br/xmlui/bitstream/handle/123456789/2364/8_o_bugio_ <lb/>ruivo.pdf?sequence=-1&amp;isAllowed=y. <lb/>Possamai, C. B., Rodrigues de Melo, F., Mendes, S. L., and Strier, K. B. (2022). <lb/>Demographic changes in an Atlantic Forest primate community following a yellow <lb/>fever outbreak. Am. J. Primatol. 84, e23425. doi: 10.1002/ajp.23425 <lb/>Povill, C., de Oliveira, M. B., de Abreu, F. V. S., de Oliveira, R. L., Perini, F. A., <lb/>Monticelli, C., et al. (2023). Genetic Diversity and Insights about Distribution of Brown <lb/>Howler Monkeys (Alouatta guariba Group) (Atelidae, Alouattinae). Int. J. Primatol. 44, <lb/>517-539. doi: 10.1007/s10764-023-00352-z <lb/>Reuter, K. E., Mittermeier, R. A., Williamson, E. A., Jerusalinsky, L., Refisch, J., <lb/>Sunderland-Groves, J., et al. (2022). Impact and lessons learned from a half-century of <lb/>primate conservation action planning. Diversity 14, 751. doi: 10.3390/d14090751 <lb/>Rifakis, P. M., Benitez, J. A., De-La-Paz-Pineda, J., and Rodriguez-Morales, A. J. <lb/>(2006). Epizootics of yellow fever in Venezuela, (2004-2005): an emerging zoonotic <lb/>disease. Ann. N Y Acad. Sci. 1081, 57-60. doi: 10.1196/annals.1373.005 <lb/>Rylands, A. B., Schneider, H., Langguth, A., Mittermeier, R. A., Groves, C. P., and <lb/>Rodrıǵuez-Luna, E. (2000). An assessment of the diversity of New World primates. <lb/>Neotrop. Primates 8, 61-93. doi: 10.62015/np.2000.v8.453 <lb/>Strier, K. B., Melo, F. R., Mendes, S. L., Valenca-Montenegro, M. M., Rylands, A. B., <lb/>Mittermeier, R. A., et al. (2021). Science, policy, and conservation management for a <lb/>critically endangered primate in the atlantic forest of Brazil. Front. Conserv. Sci. 2. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fcosc.2021.734183 <lb/>Torres-Romero, E. J., Nijman, V., Fernańdez, D., and Eppley, T. M. (2023). Human-<lb/>modified landscapes driving the global primate extinction crisis. Glob. Change Biol. 29, <lb/>5775-5787. doi: 10.1111/gcb.16902 <lb/>Urbani, B., and Cormier, L. A. (2015). &quot;The ethnoprimatology of the howler <lb/>monkeys (Alouatta spp.): from past to present,&quot; in Howler monkeys: behavior, <lb/>ecology, and conservation (New York, USA Heidelberg, Germany Dordrecht, <lb/>Netherlands, London, England: Springer), 259-280. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4939-1960-4 <lb/>Valenca-Montenegro, M. M., Azevedo, R. B., Buss, G., Cordero-Schmidt, E., <lb/>Rodrigues, K. C., Faria, A. R. G., et al. (2024). Executive Summary: Ex situ <lb/>Conservation Assessment for 15 Primates and the Maned Sloth (Brasıĺia, Brazil: <lb/>Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservacão da Biodiversidade (ICMBio), 54p. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Oklander et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcosc.2024.1401749 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Conservation Science <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>11 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>