<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T14:05:11.019Z">11/21/2025 2:05:11 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T14:05:01.658284Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T14:05:01.658284Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Citation: Choi, W.-H.; Lewe, J.-H. <lb/>Advancing Fault Detection in <lb/>Building Automation Systems <lb/>through Deep Learning. Buildings <lb/>2024, 14, 271. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.3390/buildings14010271 <lb/>Academic Editor: Yaolin Lin <lb/>Received: 14 November 2023 <lb/>Revised: 19 December 2023 <lb/>Accepted: 9 January 2024 <lb/>Published: 19 January 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 by the authors. <lb/>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. <lb/>This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and <lb/>conditions of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution (CC BY) license (https:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by/ <lb/>4.0/). <lb/>buildings <lb/>Article <lb/>Advancing Fault Detection in Building Automation Systems <lb/>through Deep Learning <lb/>Woo-Hyun Choi 1 and Jung-Ho Lewe 2, * <lb/>1 <lb/>AI Graduate School, Gwangju Institute of Science and Technology (GIST), Gwangju 61005, Republic of Korea; <lb/>woohyunchoi@gm.gist.ac.kr <lb/>2 <lb/>Aerospace Systems Design Laboratory, School of Aerospace Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, <lb/>275 Ferst Dr. NW, Atlanta, GA 30332, USA <lb/>* Correspondence: jungho.lewe@ae.gatech.edu <lb/>Abstract: This study proposes a deep learning model utilizing the BACnet (Building Automation <lb/>and Control Network) protocol for the real-time detection of mechanical faults and security vulnera-<lb/>bilities in building automation systems. Integrating various machine learning algorithms and outlier <lb/>detection techniques, this model is capable of monitoring and learning anomaly patterns in real-time. <lb/>The primary aim of this paper is to enhance the reliability and efficiency of buildings and indus-<lb/>trial facilities, offering solutions applicable across diverse industries such as manufacturing, energy <lb/>management, and smart grids. Our findings reveal that the developed algorithm detects mechanical <lb/>faults and security vulnerabilities with an accuracy of 96%, indicating its potential to significantly <lb/>improve the safety and efficiency of building automation systems. However, the full validation of the <lb/>algorithm&apos;s performance in various conditions and environments remains a challenge, and future <lb/>research will explore methodologies to address these issues and further enhance performance. This <lb/>research is expected to play a vital role in numerous fields, including productivity improvement, data <lb/>security, and the prevention of human casualties. <lb/>Keywords: ICS (industrial control system); BAS (building automation system); BACnet protocol; <lb/>cybersecurity; smart buildings; fault detection <lb/></front>

	<body>1. Introduction <lb/>In today&apos;s increasingly complex and interconnected world, the architecture of build-<lb/>ings and industrial facilities has undergone significant changes [1,2]. Not only have these <lb/>structures expanded in scale, but the systems that manage them have become very com-<lb/>plex [3,4]. This is driving the demand for sophisticated building automation and control <lb/>systems [5-7]. BACnet is an essential component among the various protocols that drive <lb/>this. It plays an indispensable role in seamlessly integrating and managing various subsys-<lb/>tems, including heating, ventilation, air conditioning (HVAC), lighting control, and safety <lb/>and security systems [8-12]. However, the complexity of these integrated systems creates <lb/>a number of problems that are difficult to overlook [13]. Among them are mechanical <lb/>anomalies and security vulnerabilities that can seriously compromise the reliability and <lb/>efficiency of the entire system [14]. These problems can have a series of serious conse-<lb/>quences, including productivity degradation, data leakage, and in extreme cases, loss of <lb/>life [15,16]. Therefore, the main objective of this study is to develop a robust algorithm <lb/>that can quickly and accurately detect mechanical anomalies and security vulnerabilities <lb/>in building automation systems using the BACnet protocol. For this purpose, we utilized <lb/>state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms and data analysis methodologies. These tools <lb/>are used to design algorithms that can be monitored in real-time by learning anomalies and <lb/>patterns of anomaly behavior. The second goal of this study is to extend the applicability <lb/>of the findings. In addition to building management, we believe that this algorithm can <lb/>be applied to various industries such as manufacturing, energy management, and smart <lb/></body>

	<front>Buildings 2024, 14, 271. https://doi.org/10.3390/buildings14010271 <lb/>https://www.mdpi.com/journal/buildings <lb/></front>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>2 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>grids [17-19]. This can greatly improve the universality of our findings. The main contri-<lb/>bution of this thesis is the development and evaluation of a deep learning model for the <lb/>real-time detection of mechanical faults in building network systems. <lb/>• <lb/>First, this research leveraged deep learning to develop a model that achieves sig-<lb/>nificantly higher accuracy and efficiency than traditional fault detection methods, <lb/>particularly through the process of adding noise to the data to improve the model&apos;s <lb/>generalization performance. <lb/>• <lb/>Second, the paper goes beyond simply detecting a single defect and presents a strategy <lb/>that can cope with many different defect situations. This allows for high performance <lb/>not only for single faults but also for complex multi-fault situations. This is of great <lb/>practical significance as it provides concrete suggestions on how to maintain high <lb/>performance in these various situations. <lb/>• Third, the model developed in this study is designed for practicality and scalability. <lb/>The model can be easily applied to real building network systems, allowing building <lb/>managers or system engineers to make faster and more accurate decisions. This is <lb/>expected to improve the reliability and efficiency of the overall building network <lb/>system. Our model is designed to operate smoothly with the addition of new HVAC <lb/>and AHU equipment to building network systems. This ensures efficient operation, <lb/>even as the complexity and size of the system increase. <lb/>This paper consists of six chapters in total. Section 1, the &apos;introduction&apos;, details the <lb/>background, necessity, and purpose of the study. In Section 2, &apos;Related Work&apos;, we review <lb/>existing studies on anomaly detection and BACnet to explain how this work provides <lb/>new value. Section 3 details the research &apos;Methodology&apos; used in this study. One can learn <lb/>more about how to collect and preprocess data, and how to design and implement the <lb/>model. Section 4 focuses on &apos;Experiments and Results&apos;. It analyzes the various experiments <lb/>conducted in this study and their results to assess whether the study objectives have been <lb/>achieved. Section 5 &apos;Discussion&apos; the limitations of the study results and the direction of <lb/>future research. Through this, we would like to recognize the limitations of this study and <lb/>suggest future research directions. Finally, Section 6 summarizes the main findings and <lb/>&apos;Conclusion and Future Work&apos; of this study. This paper proposes a new way to increase the <lb/>reliability, efficiency, and scalability of building automation and control systems through <lb/>this configuration and verifies its practical applicability. <lb/>2. Related Work <lb/>2.1. Machine Anomaly Detection Research <lb/>Machine anomaly detection continues to be a hot research topic in both industry <lb/>and academia. In its early stages, anomaly identification was primarily based on statis-<lb/>tical methodologies, analyzing simple characteristics and patterns in the data to identify <lb/>anomalies [20,21]. While these approaches were effective for detecting simple and ob-<lb/>vious anomalies, they were limited when it came to complex or unexpected anomalies. <lb/>However, with the advancement of machine learning algorithms, various techniques <lb/>such as Support Vector Machines (SVM), K-Nearest Neighbors (K-NN), and Decision <lb/>Trees began to be increasingly applied to anomaly detection [22-25]. More recently, deep <lb/>learning techniques, especially various forms of neural networks, have been excelling in <lb/>anomaly detection [26,27]. These deep learning models are highly capable of handling <lb/>high-dimensional and complex data and are also useful for real-time monitoring and pre-<lb/>diction [28]. Machine anomaly detection is being used in a wide variety of applications, <lb/>including industrial robots, manufacturing processes, and energy systems, which further <lb/>emphasizes its importance [29-33]. Furthermore, anomaly detection is also an important re-<lb/>search topic in network security and information security [34]. Initially, intrusion detection <lb/>systems (IDS) primarily used rule-based methods to detect known attack patterns based on <lb/>predefined rules [35]. While these methods performed well against known attack types, <lb/>they were vulnerable to new types of attacks or complex attack patterns. Typically, there are <lb/>&quot;Zero-Day Attacks&quot; using unknown vulnerabilities, or &quot;Multi-Vector Attacks&quot; that attempt <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>3 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>multiple attacks simultaneously. To address this, new technologies such as anomaly-based <lb/>analysis and state protocol analysis are being researched, and these approaches can identify <lb/>more diverse and complex anomaly patterns by incorporating machine learning algorithms. <lb/>These techniques, which perform well even on real-time data streams, can be utilized in a <lb/>variety of applications and systems. <lb/>2.2. Research with BACnet <lb/>BACnet is a widely used protocol for building automation and control, initially focused <lb/>on HVAC and lighting control [36]. It has since expanded to include energy management, <lb/>smart grid connectivity, and Internet of Things (IoT) integration [37,38]. Kaur et al. focus on <lb/>the BACnet protocol and list several possible attacks that can occur on BACnet networks, <lb/>such as network flooding, traffic redirection, and rerouting [39]. Holmberg aims to raise <lb/>awareness of the threats involved when connecting building control systems (especially <lb/>BACnet systems) to a wider network. He presents countermeasures to combat security <lb/>threats and provides information on current BACnet security and planned developments <lb/>to improve security. The work also provides an overview of the use of firewalls, VPNs, <lb/>intrusion detection systems, and security policies [40]. However, there is a relative lack of <lb/>research on the security and anomaly detection aspects of BACnet. Most research focuses on <lb/>the communication efficiency, compatibility, and scalability of BACnet, while the anomaly <lb/>detection and security aspects are relatively neglected. Against this background, research <lb/>on anomaly detection using BACnet is becoming increasingly important and requires the <lb/>development of new approaches and algorithms. <lb/>3. Methodology <lb/>As shown in Figure 1, this study aims to develop a model that predicts and detects <lb/>possible mechanical defects in real time within the building&apos;s automation system and <lb/>network. We focus on various types of mechanical faults that may occur in HVAC systems, <lb/>Air Handling Units (AHU), and energy management systems. These faults can have <lb/>catastrophic consequences, such as the inefficient use of energy or, in severe cases, damage <lb/>to the system, making their prevention and rapid response critical. To build the model, we <lb/>first collect health information on the building network and mechanical devices at 10 min <lb/>intervals using high-performance sensors and data collection devices. The collected data <lb/>are stored in a local database and used as the source data for further analysis. Based on this <lb/>data, data preprocessing and feature engineering are performed to transform the data into <lb/>a form that is easy to analyze. <lb/>Buildings 2024, 14, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/>3 of 18 <lb/>were vulnerable to new types of attacks or complex attack patterns. Typically, there are <lb/>&quot;Zero-Day Attacks&quot; using unknown vulnerabilities, or &quot;Multi-Vector Attacks&quot; that at-<lb/>tempt multiple attacks simultaneously. To address this, new technologies such as anomaly-<lb/>based analysis and state protocol analysis are being researched, and these approaches can <lb/>identify more diverse and complex anomaly patterns by incorporating machine learning <lb/>algorithms. These techniques, which perform well even on real-time data streams, can be <lb/>utilized in a variety of applications and systems. <lb/>2.2. Research with BACnet <lb/>BACnet is a widely used protocol for building automation and control, initially focused <lb/>on HVAC and lighting control [36]. It has since expanded to include energy manage-<lb/>ment, smart grid connectivity, and Internet of Things (IoT) integration [37,38]. Kaur et al. <lb/>focus on the BACnet protocol and list several possible attacks that can occur on BACnet <lb/>networks, such as network flooding, traffic redirection, and rerouting [39]. Holmberg <lb/>aims to raise awareness of the threats involved when connecting building control sys-<lb/>tems (especially BACnet systems) to a wider network. He presents countermeasures to <lb/>combat security threats and provides information on current BACnet security and <lb/>planned developments to improve security. The work also provides an overview of the <lb/>use of firewalls, VPNs, intrusion detection systems, and security policies [40]. However, <lb/>there is a relative lack of research on the security and anomaly detection aspects of BACnet. <lb/>Most research focuses on the communication efficiency, compatibility, and scalability of <lb/>BACnet, while the anomaly detection and security aspects are relatively neglected. Against <lb/>this background, research on anomaly detection using BACnet is becoming increasingly <lb/>important and requires the development of new approaches and algorithms. <lb/>3. Methodology <lb/>As shown in Figure 1, this study aims to develop a model that predicts and detects <lb/>possible mechanical defects in real time within the building&apos;s automation system and net-<lb/>work. We focus on various types of mechanical faults that may occur in HVAC systems, <lb/>Air Handling Units (AHU), and energy management systems. These faults can have cat-<lb/>astrophic consequences, such as the inefficient use of energy or, in severe cases, damage <lb/>to the system, making their prevention and rapid response critical. To build the model, <lb/>we first collect health information on the building network and mechanical devices at 10 <lb/>min intervals using high-performance sensors and data collection devices. The collected <lb/>data are stored in a local database and used as the source data for further analysis. Based <lb/>on this data, data preprocessing and feature engineering are performed to transform the <lb/>data into a form that is easy to analyze. <lb/>Figure 1. Research overview. <lb/>Figure 1. Research overview. <lb/>As shown in Figure 2, this study demonstrates a model design that can detect me-<lb/>chanical failures using a total of 60 min of data, and this is performed by resampling and <lb/>analyzing six consecutive data points every 10 min. The reason is that if failure occurs in <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>4 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>an actual building operation situation, the impact accumulates over a period of time, so it <lb/>is more accurate to comprehensively analyze the data over a period of time than to analyze <lb/>simple instantaneous data. Because a minimum detection time of 10 min is set for each <lb/>rule and interval A and interval B are compared, the fault lasts for a total of 60 min if the <lb/>same fault occurs in six successive intervals (three A intervals and three B intervals). The <lb/>maximum allowable time for the scenario set in this study is 1 h, and the time required to <lb/>restore the system to its original state after the failure proposed by NREL is 2 h. In this <lb/>study, we would like to use this methodology to propose a practical model for detecting <lb/>mechanical failures in building networks that are expected to have a positive effect on the <lb/>energy efficiency of buildings. <lb/></body>

	<!-- invisible text -->
	Buildings 2024, 14, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/>4 of 18 <lb/>

	<body>As shown in Figure 2, this study demonstrates a model design that can detect me-<lb/>chanical failures using a total of 60 min of data, and this is performed by resampling and <lb/>analyzing six consecutive data points every 10 min. The reason is that if failure occurs in <lb/>an actual building operation situation, the impact accumulates over a period of time, so it <lb/>is more accurate to comprehensively analyze the data over a period of time than to analyze <lb/>simple instantaneous data. Because a minimum detection time of 10 min is set for each <lb/>rule and interval A and interval B are compared, the fault lasts for a total of 60 min if the <lb/>same fault occurs in six successive intervals (three A intervals and three B intervals). The <lb/>maximum allowable time for the scenario set in this study is 1 h, and the time required to <lb/>restore the system to its original state after the failure proposed by NREL is 2 h. In this <lb/>study, we would like to use this methodology to propose a practical model for detecting <lb/>mechanical failures in building networks that are expected to have a positive effect on the <lb/>energy efficiency of buildings. <lb/>Figure 2. Anomaly detection models with resampled data. <lb/>3.1. The Dataset <lb/>In this study, a special simulation platform was used to analyze the impact of cyber-<lb/>security threats on the building&apos;s mechanical systems. The simulation is based on a refer-<lb/>ence building model from the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE), reproducing a cyberat-<lb/>tack scenario through a log device. Network data and building physical health data ob-<lb/>tained in this process provide great help in a clear understanding the real impact of <lb/>cyberattacks and their causes. &apos;A dataset of cyber-induced mechanical faults on build-<lb/>ings with network and buildings data&apos; [41] provided by NREL was first utilized. This <lb/>dataset contains various mechanical conditions and network data for the building and has <lb/>the advantage of reproducing complex real-world situations. Given these characteristics, <lb/>it was considered a suitable dataset for the purpose of this study. <lb/>The simulation was run through a tool called &apos;Alfalfa&apos;, which not only allows you to <lb/>query various pieces of state information of the building but also provides an interface <lb/>function that applies external inputs to the model. This Alfalfa tool, in conjunction with <lb/>the Building Automation System (BAS), centrally manages building health information <lb/>and delivers necessary control commands to other BACnet devices. For example, BAS re-<lb/>ceives data from Alfalfa, such as building temperature, humidity, and energy usage, and <lb/>controls BACnet devices such as air conditioners and dampers. <lb/>The dataset in this study comprehensively includes various variables and state <lb/>changes that occur during these simulations, as well as the impact of malicious attackers <lb/>on the system. Specifically, it contains detailed information about how an attacker distorts <lb/>or interferes with BAS control commands and what mechanical faults occur in the build-<lb/>ing system as a result. <lb/>Figure 2. Anomaly detection models with resampled data. <lb/>3.1. The Dataset <lb/>In this study, a special simulation platform was used to analyze the impact of cyberse-<lb/>curity threats on the building&apos;s mechanical systems. The simulation is based on a reference <lb/>building model from the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE), reproducing a cyberattack <lb/>scenario through a log device. Network data and building physical health data obtained in <lb/>this process provide great help in a clear understanding the real impact of cyberattacks and <lb/>their causes. &apos;A dataset of cyber-induced mechanical faults on buildings with network <lb/>and buildings data&apos; [41] provided by NREL was first utilized. This dataset contains var-<lb/>ious mechanical conditions and network data for the building and has the advantage of <lb/>reproducing complex real-world situations. Given these characteristics, it was considered a <lb/>suitable dataset for the purpose of this study. <lb/>The simulation was run through a tool called &apos;Alfalfa&apos;, which not only allows you to <lb/>query various pieces of state information of the building but also provides an interface <lb/>function that applies external inputs to the model. This Alfalfa tool, in conjunction with the <lb/>Building Automation System (BAS), centrally manages building health information and <lb/>delivers necessary control commands to other BACnet devices. For example, BAS receives <lb/>data from Alfalfa, such as building temperature, humidity, and energy usage, and controls <lb/>BACnet devices such as air conditioners and dampers. <lb/>The dataset in this study comprehensively includes various variables and state changes <lb/>that occur during these simulations, as well as the impact of malicious attackers on the <lb/>system. Specifically, it contains detailed information about how an attacker distorts or <lb/>interferes with BAS control commands and what mechanical faults occur in the building <lb/>system as a result. <lb/>Table 1 is the &apos;Experimental Scenario&apos; dataset provided by NREL that describes the <lb/>various failure situations that occur in a building&apos;s HVAC systems, and which includes the <lb/>following key columns. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>5 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 1. Description of columns in &apos;Experimental Scenarios&apos;. <lb/>Column Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Model <lb/>Building model name <lb/>Weather <lb/>Source of weather data <lb/>System Loop <lb/>System loop (e.g., air side) <lb/>Equipment <lb/>Related equipment (e.g., AHU) <lb/>Scenario Number <lb/>Scenario number <lb/>Scenario Name <lb/>Name of the scenario <lb/>Fault Explanation <lb/>Explanation of the fault <lb/>Fault Expression <lb/>Logical conditions to activate the fault <lb/>Required Variables <lb/>Variables required to determine the fault <lb/>Equivalent Point Name <lb/>Column name in the actual dataset corresponding to the required variables <lb/>Impact <lb/>Potential impact of the fault <lb/>Warmup <lb/>Time required to stabilize the system before applying the fault <lb/>Attack Run Time <lb/>Duration the fault lasts <lb/>Cooldown <lb/>Time required to restore the system to its original state after the fault <lb/>Scenario Season <lb/>Season in which the fault occurs <lb/>Fault Injecting Scenario <lb/>Method of injecting the fault <lb/>Expected Response <lb/>Expected system response to the fault <lb/>Attack Type <lb/>Type of attack causing the fault <lb/>Table 2 shows that &apos;Experimental Scenarios&apos; provides detailed information about <lb/>various experimental conditions and variables. First, &quot;Fault Expression&quot; according to <lb/>&quot;Scenario Name&quot; is also described in detail. Not only does this information help in a clear <lb/>understanding of the situation each scenario is trying to simulate, but it also explains why it <lb/>is important to predict the likelihood of failure conditions. Next, the item &quot;Impact&quot; analyzes <lb/>in depth the potential impact of each failure situation on the building&apos;s mechanical system. <lb/>This analysis provides a credible basis for which cyberattacks can have a catastrophic <lb/>impact on building systems. Finally, the &quot;Cool Down&quot; section specifies the time required to <lb/>stabilize the system before applying the failure. In addition to designing experiments, this <lb/>information serves as an important reference for developing effective response strategies to <lb/>real-world cyber threat situations. <lb/>Table 2. Part of the &apos;Experimental Scenarios&apos;. <lb/>Scenario Name <lb/>Impact <lb/>Cool Down <lb/>Fault Expression <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck <lb/>Closed <lb/>Insufficient cooling, <lb/>occupant thermal discomfort <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = IF outside air temp &gt; 35 <lb/>&amp; Supply air flowrate &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; Chilled water Valve Command &gt; 50 pct <lb/>&amp; (discharge air temperature <lb/>&gt; discharge air temperature setpoint + 5) <lb/>for 30 min THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/>Heat Cool Operation without <lb/>Min OA Damper <lb/>Energy waste <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = IF Supply air flowrate &gt; 0 is ON <lb/>&amp; hot water valve command &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; chilled water valve command &gt; 0) <lb/>for 15 min THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck <lb/>Open <lb/>Space over cooling, <lb/>occupant thermal discomfort, <lb/>energy waste <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = If Supply air flowrate &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; Chilled water Valve command = 0 <lb/>&amp; (discharge air temperature <lb/>&lt; discharge air temperature setpoint -5) <lb/>for 30 min THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/>OA Damper Stack Open <lb/>Energy waste <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = If unit is ON or Supply air flowrate &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; outside air damper command is CLOSED <lb/>&amp; (abs (Return air temperature <lb/>-Mixed air temperature) &gt; 5) <lb/>for 30 min THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>6 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2. Cont. <lb/>Scenario Name <lb/>Impact <lb/>Cool Down <lb/>Fault Expression <lb/>Low Supply Fan Speed <lb/>Under heating/cooling <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = If Discharge Air Flows &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; Supply fan Speed command &lt; 100% <lb/>&amp; (discharge air Static Pressure <lb/>&lt; discharge air Static pressure setpoint -0.25) <lb/>for 1 h THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/>High Supply Fan Speed <lb/>Energy waste <lb/>2 h <lb/>x = If Discharge Air Flows &gt; 0 <lb/>&amp; Supply fan Speed command = 100% <lb/>&amp; (discharge air Static Pressure <lb/>&gt; discharge air Static pressure setpoint + 0.25) <lb/>for 1 h THEN 1 ELSE 0 <lb/>3.2. Data Analysis <lb/>As you can see in Table 3, each of the six Fault Names identified through data analysis <lb/>has a different Fault Description, and they are categorized by relying on certain Variables. <lb/>These &apos;Variables&apos; are variables that are directly measured or monitored in the dataset <lb/>to analyze the nature and cause of the fault. Therefore, the accurate measurement and <lb/>monitoring of these variables plays a very important role in the correct detection and <lb/>classification of faults. Therefore, the main objective of this research is the detection of six <lb/>different &apos;Fault Names&apos;. <lb/>Table 3. Fault analysis table. <lb/>Rule_Id <lb/>Scenario_Name <lb/>Fault Description <lb/>Variables <lb/>1 <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>This fault occurs when the cooling coil valve <lb/>is closed, leading to insufficient cooling. <lb/>weaSta_reaWeaTDryBul_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yCoo_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_TSupSet_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TSup_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>2 <lb/>Heat Cool Operation without <lb/>Min OA Damper <lb/>This fault occurs when the cooling valve and <lb/>hot water valve are both open, leading to <lb/>energy waste. <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yCoo_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yHea_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yOA_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>3 <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Open <lb/>This fault occurs when the cooling coil valve <lb/>is open, leading to excessive cooling. <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yCoo_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TSup_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_TSupSet_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>4 <lb/>OA Damper Stack Open <lb/>This fault occurs when the outdoor air <lb/>damper is open, leading to energy waste. <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TMix_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yOA_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TRet_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>5 <lb/>Low Supply Fan Speed <lb/>This fault occurs when the supply fan speed <lb/>is too low, leading to insufficient airflow. <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_dpSet_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_dp_sup_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yFan_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>6 <lb/>High Supply Fan Speed <lb/>This fault occurs when the supply fan speed <lb/>is too high, leading to energy waste. <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_dpSet_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_dp_sup_y <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yFan_y <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>3.3. Variable Selection <lb/>In this study, only 13 important variables were selected from a total of 96 columns and <lb/>used for analysis. This choice was based on several key reasons. First, high-dimensional <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>7 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>data reduced the number of variables because they increased computational complexity <lb/>and increased the risk of overfitting the model. Second, to clearly interpret the analysis <lb/>results, we chose only the variables most directly related to the purpose of the analysis, <lb/>excluding non-critical variables. Third, the fewer variables selected, the shorter the model&apos;s <lb/>learning and prediction time, resulting in more computational efficiency. Finally, to increase <lb/>the reliability of the analysis, we removed unnecessary variables that could be noise. In this <lb/>way, we were able to increase the efficiency and accuracy of our research at the same time. <lb/>Table 4 lists the 13 variables required for this study and their descriptions. These <lb/>selected variables consider the building&apos;s HVAC system, weather conditions, and various <lb/>mechanical factors, and we believe they are well suited to the objectives of this study. The <lb/>variable selection process was an important step in improving the predictive performance <lb/>and computational efficiency of this study. <lb/>Table 4. Selected variables. <lb/>Variable Name <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Time <lb/>Time Stamp of the Data <lb/>weaSta_reaWeaTDryBul_y <lb/>Outside Dry Bulb Temperature from Weather Station <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>Supply Air Flow Rate from AHU (Air Handling Unit) <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yCoo_y <lb/>Cooling Command from AHU <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TSup_y <lb/>Supply Air Temperature from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_TSupSet_y <lb/>Setpoint for Supply Air Temperature from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_dpSet_y <lb/>Setpoint for Differential Pressure from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yFan_y <lb/>Fan Status from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yHea_y <lb/>Heating Command from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yOA_y <lb/>Outside Air Command from AHU <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TMix_y <lb/>Mixed Air Temperature from AHU <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TRet_y <lb/>Return Air Temperature from AHU <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_ret_y <lb/>Return Air Flow Rate from AHU <lb/>3.4. Characteristic Engineering <lb/>To determine the variables in the model, we focused on characteristic engineering. <lb/>In this step, we selected and combined existing variables based on 13 previously selected <lb/>variables. This can be valid for understanding the correlation between each variable and <lb/>for various situations and conditions in complex building systems. <lb/>Table 5 adds extra variables, focusing on characteristic engineering. For example, <lb/>we introduced a binary property that returns 1 if the value of a particular property ex-<lb/>ceeds a predefined threshold, or 0 otherwise. The new characteristics created in this way <lb/>contributed to improving the predictive performance of the model. <lb/>Table 5. Final variables. <lb/>Variable Name <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Time <lb/>Time Stamp of the Data <lb/>weaSta_reaWeaTDryBul_y <lb/>Outside Dry Bulb Temperature from Weather Station <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_V_flow_sup_y <lb/>Supply Air Flow Rate from AHU (Air Handling Unit) <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yCoo_y <lb/>Cooling Command from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yFan_y <lb/>Fan Status from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yHea_y <lb/>Heating Command from AHU <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_yOA_y <lb/>Outside Air Command from AHU <lb/>Extra_1 <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TSup_y &gt; hvac_oveAhu_TSupSet_y +5 <lb/>Extra_2 <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TSup_y &lt; hvac_oveAhu_TSupSet_y -5 <lb/>Extra_3 <lb/>hvac_reaAhu_TRet_y -hvac_reaAhu_TMix_y &gt; 5 <lb/>Extra_4 <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_dpSet_y &lt; hvac_reaAhu_dp_sup_y -0.25 <lb/>Extra_5 <lb/>hvac_oveAhu_dpSet_y &gt; hvac_reaAhu_dp_sup_y -0.25 <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>8 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.5. Poisson Distribution <lb/>We calculated the probability of occurrence of each rule using Poisson distribution. <lb/>This distribution quantitatively assessed the frequency and importance of the rules. The <lb/>parameters of the distribution were set by referring to the characteristics of the dataset. The <lb/>probability of k events in the interval, P(X = k), is expressed as follows: <lb/>P(X = k) = <lb/>λ k •e -λ <lb/>k! <lb/>(1) <lb/>where λ is the average rate of events per interval (also known as the rate parameter) and k! <lb/>is the factorial of k. <lb/>The use of the Poisson distribution in our study is particularly justified due to its <lb/>suitability in modeling the frequency of events in complex systems like building networks. <lb/>This distribution is a perfect fit for several reasons. Firstly, the Poisson distribution is ideal <lb/>for situations where events occur independently. In the context of building network systems, <lb/>this is a crucial factor since faults and vulnerabilities, such as failures of &quot;cooling coil valve <lb/>fails&quot; or &quot;outside air damper is open&quot;, usually occur without any direct correlation to one <lb/>another. The Poisson distribution captures this aspect of independence effectively, allowing <lb/>for a more accurate representation and analysis of these events. Secondly, the randomness <lb/>of event occurrences in building networks is another critical aspect well-handled by the <lb/>Poisson distribution. These systems are subject to a variety of faults and vulnerabilities <lb/>that appear at unpredictable intervals. The Poisson distribution, with its ability to model <lb/>random occurrences within a defined time frame, offers a reliable way to predict the <lb/>frequency of these events. This ability to handle randomness is especially important <lb/>for creating models that can anticipate and prepare for a wide range of potential issues. <lb/>Additionally, the Poisson distribution is beneficial in quantitatively assessing the frequency <lb/>and importance of different rules or events within the system. By setting the parameters of <lb/>the distribution based on the characteristics of the dataset, it becomes possible to obtain a <lb/>nuanced understanding of how often certain types of faults or vulnerabilities might occur. <lb/>In summary, the choice of the Poisson distribution aligns well with the nature of building <lb/>network systems, where faults and vulnerabilities occur independently and randomly. It <lb/>provides a statistically sound method to handle the complexity of these systems and offers <lb/>a way to estimate the probability of each event occurring more accurately. This makes the <lb/>Poisson distribution an invaluable tool in our analysis, enhancing the overall reliability and <lb/>effectiveness of our modeling approach. <lb/>3.6. Noise Addition <lb/>Adding noise is an important way to increase the generalization power of a machine <lb/>learning model. Generalization means that the model is not limited to the training data, <lb/>but also performs well on new data. This is very important because it determines how <lb/>useful the model will be in the real world. Preventing overfitting is one of the main goals <lb/>of adding noise. Overfitting typically results in poor performance, with new input as a <lb/>model is excessively fitted by training data, resulting in poor performance on new data. <lb/>By adding noise to prevent this, the model is forced to pay more attention to the general <lb/>characteristics of the training data. Data augmentation is also an important purpose of <lb/>adding noise. In situations where data are sparse, adding noise artificially increases the <lb/>amount of data available, allowing the model to learn different patterns. Adding noise <lb/>also has the effect of making the model more robust. Real-world data is often noisy, and <lb/>training a model with noisy data improves the model&apos;s robustness to that noise. In this <lb/>study, we added a normally distributed noise with a mean of 0.5 to the training data to add <lb/>noise similar to the distribution of the original data and a standard deviation of 0.001 to <lb/>prevent the noise from overfitting the model without significantly affecting the original <lb/>data. We also added noise by setting 5% of the total data as outliers, which allows the <lb/>model to cope well with outliers and minor noise. This strategy has multiple benefits: it <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>9 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>improves the model&apos;s generalization ability, prevents overfitting, and makes it more robust <lb/>to real-world data. <lb/>3.7. Detection Algorithm Model <lb/>As shown in Figure 3, this study contains the design of a deep learning model to <lb/>effectively detect mechanical defects. First of all, we chose the most basic and widely used <lb/>&apos;simple random segmentation&apos; method as the data segmentation method. This method <lb/>splits the entire dataset into training and test sets at random. Specifically, 80% of all data <lb/>were allocated as training data and the remaining 20% as test data. This segmentation is <lb/>known to help evaluate the generalization ability of the model by leveraging randomness <lb/>to segment datasets evenly. We selected a model that combines multilayer perceptron <lb/>(MLP), Gated Recurrent Unit (GRU), and Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) as appropriate <lb/>algorithms. This algorithm was deemed very suitable for the purpose of this study for <lb/>several reasons. First, the multilayer structure allows the model to learn even complex <lb/>patterns. This allows it to accurately model the various variables and interactions in the <lb/>building network. Second, GRU cells can reflect the characteristics of time series data well. <lb/>GRU efficiently utilizes historical information to predict current and future conditions, <lb/>so it can accurately determine the impact of historical data on current mechanical faults. <lb/>Third, enabling ReLU speeds up computation. This saves time in the training and inference <lb/>phases of the model and can be applied to real-time flaw detection systems. Finally, the <lb/>Adam optimization algorithm allows us to optimize the performance of the model quickly <lb/>and accurately. For these reasons, we chose a deep-learning model based on this algorithm. <lb/>also has the effect of making the model more robust. Real-world data is often noisy, and <lb/>training a model with noisy data improves the model&apos;s robustness to that noise. In this <lb/>study, we added a normally distributed noise with a mean of 0.5 to the training data to <lb/>add noise similar to the distribution of the original data and a standard deviation of 0.001 <lb/>to prevent the noise from overfitting the model without significantly affecting the original <lb/>data. We also added noise by setting 5% of the total data as outliers, which allows the <lb/>model to cope well with outliers and minor noise. This strategy has multiple benefits: it <lb/>improves the model&apos;s generalization ability, prevents overfitting, and makes it more ro-<lb/>bust to real-world data. <lb/>3.7. Detection Algorithm Model <lb/>As shown in Figure 3, this study contains the design of a deep learning model to <lb/>effectively detect mechanical defects. First of all, we chose the most basic and widely used <lb/>&apos;simple random segmentation&apos; method as the data segmentation method. This method <lb/>splits the entire dataset into training and test sets at random. Specifically, 80% of all data <lb/>were allocated as training data and the remaining 20% as test data. This segmentation is <lb/>known to help evaluate the generalization ability of the model by leveraging randomness <lb/>to segment datasets evenly. We selected a model that combines multilayer perceptron <lb/>(MLP), Gated Recurrent Unit (GRU), and Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) as appropriate al-<lb/>gorithms. This algorithm was deemed very suitable for the purpose of this study for sev-<lb/>eral reasons. First, the multilayer structure allows the model to learn even complex pat-<lb/>terns. This allows it to accurately model the various variables and interactions in the build-<lb/>ing network. Second, GRU cells can reflect the characteristics of time series data well. GRU <lb/>efficiently utilizes historical information to predict current and future conditions, so it can <lb/>accurately determine the impact of historical data on current mechanical faults. Third, <lb/>enabling ReLU speeds up computation. This saves time in the training and inference phases <lb/>of the model and can be applied to real-time flaw detection systems. Finally, the Adam op-<lb/>timization algorithm allows us to optimize the performance of the model quickly and accu-<lb/>rately. For these reasons, we chose a deep-learning model based on this algorithm. <lb/>Figure 3. Algorithm model. <lb/>We chose Adam as the optimizer and used &quot;categorical_crossentropy&quot; as the loss <lb/>function. The learning rate of the Adam optimizer was set to 0.005, which was deemed to <lb/>be the most appropriate for the purpose of this study, as well as previous studies. To avoid <lb/>overfitting the model and to achieve optimal performance, we also applied an early stop-<lb/>ping technique, which automatically stops learning if the model&apos;s performance does not <lb/>improve over 20 epochs. <lb/>R <lb/>e <lb/>L <lb/>U <lb/>Input <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>R <lb/>E <lb/>S <lb/>H <lb/>A <lb/>P <lb/>E <lb/>G <lb/>R <lb/>U <lb/>R <lb/>e <lb/>L <lb/>U <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>Output <lb/>Figure 3. Algorithm model. <lb/>We chose Adam as the optimizer and used &quot;categorical_crossentropy&quot; as the loss <lb/>function. The learning rate of the Adam optimizer was set to 0.005, which was deemed <lb/>to be the most appropriate for the purpose of this study, as well as previous studies. To <lb/>avoid overfitting the model and to achieve optimal performance, we also applied an early <lb/>stopping technique, which automatically stops learning if the model&apos;s performance does <lb/>not improve over 20 epochs. <lb/>3.8. Model Performance Validation Metrics <lb/>3.8.1. Confusion Matrix <lb/>Table 6 is the Confusion Matrix. A confusion matrix is a visual representation of how <lb/>well a model classifies. It is a fundamental tool for evaluating a model&apos;s performance, <lb/>providing basic elements such as True Positive, True Negative, False Positive, and False <lb/>Negative. These elements provide the foundational information needed to calculate other <lb/>performance metrics. <lb/>Table 6. Confusion Matrix. <lb/>Prediction <lb/>Positive <lb/>Negative <lb/>Actual <lb/>Positive <lb/>TP <lb/>FN <lb/>Negative <lb/>FP <lb/>TN <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>10 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>• True Positive (TP): It&apos;s Actually Positive, and the model classified it as Positive. <lb/>• True Negative (TN): Actually Negative, and the model also classified it as Negative. <lb/>• <lb/>False Positive (FP): Actually Negative, but the model classified it as Positive. <lb/>• <lb/>False Negative (FN): Actually Positive, but the model classified it as Negative <lb/>3.8.2. Performance Metrics <lb/>• Accuracy is a metric that indicates how much of the total data the model correctly <lb/>classified. This is the most intuitive metric to understand model performance, but it <lb/>requires caution as it can be misleading if there is an imbalance in the data. <lb/>Accuracy = <lb/>TP + TN <lb/>TP + TN + FP + FN <lb/>(2) <lb/>• <lb/>Precision refers to the percentage of data that the model classifies as positive that is <lb/>actually positive. This metric is useful when it is important to reduce the number of <lb/>false positives. <lb/>Precision = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FP <lb/>(3) <lb/>• <lb/>Recall indicates the percentage of data classified as positive by the model that is <lb/>actually positive. This metric is useful when reducing the number of false negatives <lb/>is important. <lb/>Recall = <lb/>TP <lb/>TP + FN <lb/>(4) <lb/>• <lb/>F1 Score is the harmonic mean of precision and recall. This metric is used in situations <lb/>where both precision and recall are important. When the two metrics are balanced, the <lb/>F1 Score is higher. <lb/>F1 Score = 2• <lb/>Precision•Recall <lb/>Precision + Recall <lb/>(5) <lb/>These performance metrics allow us to evaluate different aspects of how well our <lb/>model actually works. Especially when it comes to the problem of detecting mechanical <lb/>faults in building network systems in real time, these metrics are very useful for measuring <lb/>the reliability and efficiency of our model. <lb/>4. Experiment and Results <lb/>In this study, we developed deep learning models to detect mechanical faults in <lb/>building network systems in real-time. The experiments were based on data resampled <lb/>every 10 min and successfully detected faults from a variety of situations and data. We <lb/>used a Confusion Matrix and several Performance Metrics to evaluate and interpret the <lb/>performance of these models. <lb/>4.1. Confusion Matrix and Performance Metrics <lb/>As shown in Figure 4, the performance of the deep learning model developed in this <lb/>study for detecting mechanical faults in building network systems can be considered very <lb/>high. From the confusion matrix, we can see that all the classes were classified very well: <lb/>almost all the samples in each class were classified correctly. The performance metric also <lb/>shows very high values. The accuracy is 96.59%, which means that the model made correct <lb/>predictions in most cases. A precision score of 1 indicates that all the cases that the model <lb/>classified as positive were actually positive. The recall and F1 scores were also near perfect. <lb/>This high performance is likely due to the impact of adding noise to the data. Adding <lb/>noise can contribute to improved performance because it improves the model&apos;s ability to <lb/>generalize and prevents overfitting. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>11 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>shows very high values. The accuracy is 96.59%, which means that the model made correct <lb/>predictions in most cases. A precision score of 1 indicates that all the cases that the model <lb/>classified as positive were actually positive. The recall and F1 scores were also near per-<lb/>fect. This high performance is likely due to the impact of adding noise to the data. Adding <lb/>noise can contribute to improved performance because it improves the model&apos;s ability to <lb/>generalize and prevents overfitting. <lb/>Figure 4. Confusion matrix and performance metrics. <lb/>As can be seen from Table 7, defect detection was performed for each of the six clas-<lb/>ses, and the results confirmed the high performance of the model. Accuracy, precision, <lb/>recall, and F1 scores for each class were all high. These high-performance indicators sug-<lb/>gest that the model can effectively detect even complex defect patterns. However, partic-<lb/>ularly noteworthy is the model&apos;s performance in Class 6. In this class, precision was meas-<lb/>ured as relatively low, which makes it more likely that the model is over-detecting defects <lb/>for Class 6. In fact, the number of samples classified by the model was significantly higher <lb/>than the actual number of samples. This point indicates that the model may tend to over-<lb/>react to Class 6. In addition, when viewed through the F1 score, the model maintains a <lb/>good balance between precision and recall. This means that the model will show a stable <lb/>performance even in real-world situations. In conclusion, although the model in this study <lb/>shows high performance, it was confirmed that there is a need to improve the model in <lb/>the future due to the relatively low precision of Class 6. <lb/>Table 7. Multi-class classification performance assessment metrics. <lb/>Class <lb/>n (Truth) n (Classified) Accuracy <lb/>Precision <lb/>Recall <lb/>F1 Score <lb/>0 <lb/>204 <lb/>198 <lb/>98.89% <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>1 <lb/>209 <lb/>208 <lb/>98.81% <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>2 <lb/>212 <lb/>206 <lb/>99.52% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>3 <lb/>209 <lb/>199 <lb/>99.21% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>4 <lb/>204 <lb/>197 <lb/>99.45% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>5 <lb/>224 <lb/>254 <lb/>97.31% <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>Figure 4. Confusion matrix and performance metrics. <lb/>As can be seen from Table 7, defect detection was performed for each of the six classes, <lb/>and the results confirmed the high performance of the model. Accuracy, precision, recall, <lb/>and F1 scores for each class were all high. These high-performance indicators suggest <lb/>that the model can effectively detect even complex defect patterns. However, particularly <lb/>noteworthy is the model&apos;s performance in Class 6. In this class, precision was measured as <lb/>relatively low, which makes it more likely that the model is over-detecting defects for Class <lb/>6. In fact, the number of samples classified by the model was significantly higher than the <lb/>actual number of samples. This point indicates that the model may tend to overreact to <lb/>Class 6. In addition, when viewed through the F1 score, the model maintains a good balance <lb/>between precision and recall. This means that the model will show a stable performance <lb/>even in real-world situations. In conclusion, although the model in this study shows high <lb/>performance, it was confirmed that there is a need to improve the model in the future due <lb/>to the relatively low precision of Class 6. <lb/>Table 7. Multi-class classification performance assessment metrics. <lb/>Class <lb/>n (Truth) <lb/>n (Classified) <lb/>Accuracy <lb/>Precision <lb/>Recall <lb/>F1 Score <lb/>0 <lb/>204 <lb/>198 <lb/>98.89% <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>1 <lb/>209 <lb/>208 <lb/>98.81% <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>2 <lb/>212 <lb/>206 <lb/>99.52% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>3 <lb/>209 <lb/>199 <lb/>99.21% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>4 <lb/>204 <lb/>197 <lb/>99.45% <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>5 <lb/>224 <lb/>254 <lb/>97.31% <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>4.2. One Type of Defect Is Detected <lb/>This study is specifically designed to assume excessive situations. Specifically, while <lb/>normal conditions remain in place for 60 h (3600 min), we model scenarios in which <lb/>abnormal or malicious behavior occurs for a continuous hour (60 min). This design involves <lb/>a class imbalance problem, but it was a deliberate choice. One of the main objectives of <lb/>this study was to measure how quickly our model can detect anomalies in these excessive <lb/>and realistic situations. This approach is significant for increasing model applicability in a <lb/>variety of systems and applications where fast responsiveness in production environments <lb/>is important. <lb/>In Figure 5, models specifically designed for experiments are set to detect only certain <lb/>types of defects, and if a specific defect, such as &quot;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&quot;, is <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>12 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>detected out of a total of six rules, it means that the cooling coil valve is operating in a <lb/>closed state, which may not receive adequate cooling and therefore requires a prompt <lb/>response. Because our model sets a detection time of at least 10 min for each rule, the actual <lb/>detection time for the entire rule set is 60 min. In particular, if there are six successive <lb/>sections (section A and section B), the fault lasts for a total of 60 min. If a defect in &quot;Cooling <lb/>Coil Valve Stuck Closed&quot; is detected, &apos;0&apos; in the variable column indicates that the rule or <lb/>condition is inactive or undetected, whereas if only four columns display &apos;1&apos;, it means that <lb/>those four conditions are active or detected. <lb/>a class imbalance problem, but it was a deliberate choice. One of the main objectiv <lb/>this study was to measure how quickly our model can detect anomalies in these exce <lb/>and realistic situations. This approach is significant for increasing model applicabil <lb/>a variety of systems and applications where fast responsiveness in production env <lb/>ments is important. <lb/>In Figure 5, models specifically designed for experiments are set to detect only ce <lb/>types of defects, and if a specific defect, such as &quot;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>detected out of a total of six rules, it means that the cooling coil valve is operating <lb/>closed state, which may not receive adequate cooling and therefore requires a pro <lb/>response. Because our model sets a detection time of at least 10 min for each rule <lb/>actual detection time for the entire rule set is 60 min. In particular, if there are six su <lb/>sive sections (section A and section B), the fault lasts for a total of 60 min. If a defe <lb/>&quot;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&quot; is detected, &apos;0&apos; in the variable column indicates tha <lb/>rule or condition is inactive or undetected, whereas if only four columns display <lb/>means that those four conditions are active or detected. <lb/>Figure 5. One type of defect detected. <lb/>If you detect only one type of fault, as shown in Table 8, you can create a response <lb/>that is specific to that fault. This allows building managers or system engineers to <lb/>quicker and more accurate actions, contributing to a more reliable and efficient system <lb/>Table 8. One type of defect detection result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1] <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.99994] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>0.99993997812227112 <lb/>4.3. Multiple Defects Detected <lb/>As shown in Figure 6, the model can detect multiple faults simultaneously, inclu <lb/>&apos;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&apos;, &apos;Heat Cool Operation without Min OA Damper&apos; <lb/>&apos;OA Damper Stack Open&apos;. This experimental setup is intended to simulate a situ <lb/>where the cooling coil valve, the hot water valve, and the outside air dampe <lb/>Figure 5. One type of defect detected. <lb/>If you detect only one type of fault, as shown in Table 8, you can create a response <lb/>plan that is specific to that fault. This allows building managers or system engineers to take <lb/>quicker and more accurate actions, contributing to a more reliable and efficient system. <lb/>Table 8. One type of defect detection result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1] <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.99994] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>0.99993997812227112 <lb/>4.3. Multiple Defects Detected <lb/>As shown in Figure 6, the model can detect multiple faults simultaneously, including <lb/>&apos;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&apos;, &apos;Heat Cool Operation without Min OA Damper&apos;, and <lb/>&apos;OA Damper Stack Open&apos;. This experimental setup is intended to simulate a situation where <lb/>the cooling coil valve, the hot water valve, and the outside air damper are simultaneously <lb/>causing problems. The model can accurately detect situations in which the same fault <lb/>persists for 60 min in six successive sections with a slight lag (three A sections and three B <lb/>sections that will occur in the future). <lb/>When three faults occur simultaneously, as shown in Table 9, they can have a very <lb/>large impact on the building&apos;s HVAC system. Therefore, it is essential to detect and <lb/>analyze various faults simultaneously, especially since one fault is likely to trigger another. <lb/>Therefore, such multi-fault situations require more thorough monitoring and a faster <lb/>response, and it is important to analyze each fault independently and understand their <lb/>interaction as much as possible. To this end, the model developed in this study is designed <lb/>to provide detailed information about each fault, enabling effective responses in real-<lb/>world operations. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>13 of 17 <lb/></page>

Buildings 2024, 14, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/>

	13 of 18 <lb/>

	simultaneously causing problems. The model can accurately detect situations in which <lb/>the same fault persists for 60 min in six successive sections with a slight lag (three A sec-<lb/>tions and three B sections that will occur in the future). <lb/>Figure 6. Multiple defects detected. <lb/>When three faults occur simultaneously, as shown in Table 9, they can have a very <lb/>large impact on the building&apos;s HVAC system. Therefore, it is essential to detect and ana-<lb/>lyze various faults simultaneously, especially since one fault is likely to trigger another. <lb/>Therefore, such multi-fault situations require more thorough monitoring and a faster re-<lb/>sponse, and it is important to analyze each fault independently and understand their in-<lb/>teraction as much as possible. To this end, the model developed in this study is designed <lb/>to provide detailed information about each fault, enabling effective responses in real-<lb/>world operations. <lb/>
<!-- too much invisibile text -->
		<body>Table 9. Multiple defects detected result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1, 2, 4] <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Heat Cool Operation without Min OA Damper <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>OA Damper Stack Open <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.99997, 0.9999, 0.99996] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>2.9998300075531006 <lb/>4.4. Multiple Defects and One Insufficient Score Detected <lb/>In Figure 7, a number of defects, including &apos;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&apos;, &apos;Cool-<lb/>ing Coil Valve Stuck Open&apos;, &apos;OA Damper Stack Open&apos;, &apos;Low Supply Fan Speed&apos;, and &apos;High <lb/>Supply Fan Speed&apos;, occurred simultaneously with high probability. However, &apos;Heat Cool <lb/>Operation without Min OA Damper&apos; assumes a fault with a relatively low probability. <lb/>The model can accurately detect situations in which a number of defects except one persist <lb/>for a total of 60 min, even if the same defect occurs in six successive sections with a slight <lb/>lag (three A sections and three B sections to occur). In addition, if one fault signal occurs <lb/>during one unit of time (10 min), it can accurately detect at least six faults in 60 min. <lb/>Figure 6. Multiple defects detected. <lb/>Table 9. Multiple defects detected result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1, 2, 4] <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Heat Cool Operation without Min OA Damper <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>OA Damper Stack Open <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.99997, 0.9999, 0.99996] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>2.9998300075531006 <lb/>4.4. Multiple Defects and One Insufficient Score Detected <lb/>In Figure 7, a number of defects, including &apos;Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed&apos;, &apos;Cooling <lb/>Coil Valve Stuck Open&apos;, &apos;OA Damper Stack Open&apos;, &apos;Low Supply Fan Speed&apos;, and &apos;High <lb/>Supply Fan Speed&apos;, occurred simultaneously with high probability. However, &apos;Heat Cool <lb/>Operation without Min OA Damper&apos; assumes a fault with a relatively low probability. The <lb/>model can accurately detect situations in which a number of defects except one persist <lb/>for a total of 60 min, even if the same defect occurs in six successive sections with a slight <lb/>lag (three A sections and three B sections to occur). In addition, if one fault signal occurs <lb/>during one unit of time (10 min), it can accurately detect at least six faults in 60 min. <lb/></body>

Buildings 2024, 14, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/>

	14 of 18 <lb/>

	Figure 7. Multiple defects and one insufficient score detected. <lb/>These situations, like the one in Table 10, require particular attention. A fault detected <lb/>with a high score indicates that a clear problem is occurring within the system and may <lb/>require an immediate response. However, a fault detected with a low score, such as &quot;Heat <lb/>Cool Operation without Min OA Damper,&quot; may be easy to ignore, but it may indicate that <lb/>the cooling and hot water valves are not being regulated properly. This low score may be <lb/>Figure 7. Multiple defects and one insufficient score detected. <lb/>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>14 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>These situations, like the one in Table 10, require particular attention. A fault detected <lb/>with a high score indicates that a clear problem is occurring within the system and may <lb/>require an immediate response. However, a fault detected with a low score, such as &quot;Heat <lb/>Cool Operation without Min OA Damper&quot;, may be easy to ignore, but it may indicate that <lb/>the cooling and hot water valves are not being regulated properly. This low score may be <lb/>caused by the interaction with other faults or the influence of other system variables, which <lb/>may lead to an increasingly large impact on the overall system. Therefore, these low scores <lb/>are also significant and should be utilized in the evaluation of the overall system health. <lb/>The model developed in this study is designed to flexibly respond to these different fault <lb/>situations and score distributions. This will enable more accurate and efficient mechanical <lb/>fault detection. <lb/>Table 10. Multiple defects and one insufficient score detected result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6] <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Closed <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Heat Cool Operation without Min OA Damper <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Cooling Coil Valve Stuck Open <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>OA Damper Stack Open <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>Low Supply Fan Speed <lb/>Detected Fault <lb/>High Supply Fan Speed <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.99997, 0.71518, 0.99996, 0.99996, 0.99999, 0.99998] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>5.715039968490601 <lb/>4.5. Not Detected <lb/>For Figure 8, we assume that a number of faults are rare with low probability over <lb/>a unit of time (10 min). This can occur when the model collects data or when the equip-<lb/>ment is switched. Because of this, it is highly likely that defects will not be detected in <lb/>these situations. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

	<page>15 of 18 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 8. Not detected. <lb/>If no failures are detected, as shown in Table 11, this can mean two possibilities. The <lb/>system could be stable and fault-free. This is when the model is working correctly and has <lb/>correctly determined that there are no faults. This situation can be a good indicator of the <lb/>stability of the system. The system could be faulty but has not detected any faults. This <lb/>situation requires attention. A situation where the model fails to detect a defect can be <lb/>caused by a number of things. For example, a new type of fault might occur and the model <lb/>might not recognize it. Or the model might misjudge the fault due to noise or the influence <lb/>of other variables. Even when faults are not detected, periodic system checks and further <lb/>analysis are still required, especially to ensure that the model&apos;s performance is constantly <lb/>monitored and updated as needed to ensure that no faults are missed. <lb/>Table 11. &apos;Not detected&apos; result. <lb/>Figure 8. Not detected. <lb/>If no failures are detected, as shown in Table 11, this can mean two possibilities. The <lb/>system could be stable and fault-free. This is when the model is working correctly and <lb/>has correctly determined that there are no faults. This situation can be a good indicator <lb/>of the stability of the system. The system could be faulty but has not detected any faults. <lb/>This situation requires attention. A situation where the model fails to detect a defect can be <lb/>caused by a number of things. For example, a new type of fault might occur and the model <lb/>might not recognize it. Or the model might misjudge the fault due to noise or the influence <lb/>of other variables. Even when faults are not detected, periodic system checks and further <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>15 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<body>analysis are still required, especially to ensure that the model&apos;s performance is constantly <lb/>monitored and updated as needed to ensure that no faults are missed. <lb/>Table 11. &apos;Not detected&apos; result. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Predict_rule_id <lb/>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6] <lb/>Analysis_score <lb/>[0.0019, 0.117, 0.21459, 0.04307, 0.01659, 0.58922] <lb/>Sum_of_analysis_score <lb/>0.9823699831031263 <lb/>5. Discussion <lb/>The deep learning model developed in this study showed very high accuracy in detect-<lb/>ing mechanical defects in real time in building network systems. As a result of evaluation <lb/>based on the confusion matrix and performance indicators, the model achieved an excellent <lb/>accuracy of 96.59%. This indicates that the model performed accurate predictions in most <lb/>situations. In addition, the precision, reproducibility, and F1 scores were all almost perfect, <lb/>suggesting that the model has effectively different patterns of the data. The model <lb/>demonstrated the ability to effectively detect not only single defects but also multiple <lb/>defects. This is an important characteristic that allows us to respond quickly to complex <lb/>problems that may arise in building network systems. In particular, with a detailed analysis <lb/>by each class, the model showed excellent performance in distinguishing between different <lb/>types of defects. According to the study results, the model maintained high performance <lb/>even in the presence of noise added to the data, indicating that it could prevent overfitting <lb/>and improve generalization capabilities in real-world environments. <lb/>However, since all results were limited to specific experimental conditions and datasets, <lb/>further validation of the model&apos;s performance in various real-world environments is needed. <lb/>This study represents an important advance in the field of mechanical defect detection using <lb/>deep learning, laying the foundation for a wider range of applications and performance <lb/>improvements in the future. <lb/>6. Conclusions and Future Work <lb/>6.1. Conclusions <lb/>This study developed and evaluated a deep learning model to detect mechanical <lb/>failures quickly and accurately in building network systems. Our model demonstrates the <lb/>effectiveness of real-time defect detection with a high accuracy of 96.59% and an excellent <lb/>F1 score, and in particular, it reduced the proposed &apos;Cool-Down&apos; time by 50% compared <lb/>to 2 h in the dataset provided by NREL, enabling anomaly detection within 1 h. This <lb/>is a breakthrough that can significantly improve the efficiency of building management <lb/>systems and quickly address potential risks. These results will be useful information for <lb/>building managers. This means that shortening the failure detection process from 2 h to 1 h <lb/>by applying the proposal in the dataset provided by NREL. <lb/>6.2. Future Work <lb/>Considerations for future research directions include the following. Model general-<lb/>ization and data extension considering data diversity are needed. The robustness of the <lb/>model should be checked by verifying its performance in the real world as well as its <lb/>performance in the experimental environment. In addition, the applicability of the model <lb/>in other fields should be explored and the applicability in smart cities, manufacturing, etc., <lb/>should be investigated. We expect that these studies will increase the practicality and field <lb/>applicability of the model. <lb/></body>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Conceptualization, J.-H.L.; Methodology, W.-H.C. and J.-H.L.; Software, <lb/>W.-H.C.; Validation, W.-H.C. and J.-H.L.; Formal analysis, W.-H.C.; Investigation, W.-H.C.; Resources, <lb/>W.-H.C.; Data curation, W.-H.C.; Writing-original draft, W.-H.C.; Writing-review &amp; editing, J.-H.L.; <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>16 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">Visualization, W.-H.C.; Supervision, J.-H.L.; Project administration, J.-H.L.; Funding acquisition, <lb/>J.-H.L. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding: This research was supported by the MOTIE (Ministry of Trade, Industry, and Energy) <lb/>in Korea, under the Resource Development Program for Industrial Innovation (Global) <lb/>(P0017311) supervised by the Korea Institute for Advancement of Technology (KIAT). <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Data Availability Statement: This dataset, identified by ID 210 and accessible via DOI 10.7799/1922641, <lb/>is publicly available and was last updated on 12 December 2023. It adheres to open data principles, <lb/>ensuring transparency and availability for research and analysis purposes. The dataset is maintained <lb/>and updated regularly, reflecting the latest findings and developments related to its scope. For further <lb/>information, inquiries, or access requests, users are encouraged to refer to the dataset&apos;s DOI link or <lb/>contact the dataset&apos;s custodian. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Rivas Pellicer, M.; Tungekar, M.Y.; Carpitella, S. Where to Place Monitoring Sensors for Improving Complex Manufacturing <lb/>Systems? Discussing a Real Case in the Food Industry. Sensors 2023, 23, 3768. [CrossRef] <lb/>2. <lb/>Waqar, A.; Skrzypkowski, K.; Almujibah, H.; Zagórski, K.; Khan, M.B.; Zagórska, A.; Benjeddou, O. Success of Implementing <lb/>Cloud Computing for Smart Development in Small Construction Projects. Appl. Sci. 2023, 13, 5713. [CrossRef] <lb/>3. <lb/>Pan, Y.; Zhang, L. Integrating BIM and AI for smart construction management: Current status and future directions. Arch. Comput. <lb/>Methods Eng. 2023, 30, 1081-1110. [CrossRef] <lb/>4. <lb/>Kor, M.; Yitmen, I.; Alizadehsalehi, S. An investigation for integration of deep learning and digital twins towards Construction <lb/>4.0. Smart Sustain. Built Environ. 2023, 12, 461-487. [CrossRef] <lb/>5. <lb/>Mishra, P.; Singh, G. Energy Management Systems in Sustainable Smart Cities Based on the Internet of Energy: A Technical <lb/>Review. Energies 2023, 16, 6903. [CrossRef] <lb/>6. <lb/>Hepf, C.; Overhoff, L.; Koth, S.C.; Gabriel, M.; Briels, D.; Auer, T. Impact of a Weather Predictive Control Strategy for Inert <lb/>Building Technology on Thermal Comfort and Energy Demand. Buildings 2023, 13, 996. [CrossRef] <lb/>7. <lb/>Dzyuba, A.; Solovyeva, I.; Semikolenov, A. Raising the Resilience of Industrial Manufacturers through Implementing Natural <lb/>Gas-Fired Distributed Energy Resource Systems with Demand Response. Sustainability 2023, 15, 8241. [CrossRef] <lb/>8. <lb/>Graveto, V.; Cruz, T.; Simões, P. A Network Intrusion Detection System for Building Automation and Control Systems. IEEE <lb/>Access 2023, 11, 7968-7983. [CrossRef] <lb/>9. <lb/>Apanavičien ė, R.; Shahrabani, M.M.N. Key Factors Affecting Smart Building Integration into Smart City: Technological Aspects. <lb/>Smart Cities 2023, 6, 1832-1857. [CrossRef] <lb/>10. Márquez-Sánchez, S.; Calvo-Gallego, J.; Erbad, A.; Ibrar, M.; Fernandez, J.H.; Houchati, M.; Corchado, J.M. Enhancing Building <lb/>Energy Management: Adaptive Edge Computing for Optimized Efficiency and Inhabitant Comfort. Electronics 2023, 12, 4179. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>11. Skała, A.; Grela, J.; Lato ń, D.; Ba ńczyk, K.; Markiewicz, M.; Ozadowic ż, A. Implementation of Building a Thermal Model to <lb/>Improve Energy Efficiency of the Central Heating System-A Case Study. Energies 2023, 16, 6830. [CrossRef] <lb/>12. Almusaed, A.; Yitmen, I.; Almssad, A. Enhancing Smart Home Design with AI Models: A Case Study of Living Spaces <lb/>Implementation Review. Energies 2023, 16, 2636. [CrossRef] <lb/>13. Gao, Y.; Miyata, S.; Akashi, Y. Energy saving and indoor temperature control for an office building using tube-based robust model <lb/>predictive control. Appl. Energy 2023, 341, 121106. [CrossRef] <lb/>14. Jaramillo-Alcazar, A.; Govea, J.; Villegas-Ch, W. Anomaly Detection in a Smart Industrial Machinery Plant Using IoT and Machine <lb/>Learning. Sensors 2023, 23, 8286. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>15. Himeur, Y.; Elnour, M.; Fadli, F.; Meskin, N.; Petri, I.; Rezgui, Y.; Bensaali, F.; Amira, A. AI-big data analytics for building <lb/>automation and management systems: A survey, actual challenges and future perspectives. Artif. Intell. Rev. 2023, 56, 4929-5021. <lb/>[CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>16. El-Kady, A.H.; Halim, S.; El-Halwagi, M.M.; Khan, F. Analysis of Safety and Security Challenges and Opportunities Related to <lb/>Cyber-physical Systems. Process Saf. Environ. Prot. 2023, 173, 384-413. [CrossRef] <lb/>17. Saleem, M.U.; Shakir, M.; Usman, M.R.; Bajwa, M.H.T.; Shabbir, N.; Shams Ghahfarokhi, P.; Daniel, K. Integrating smart energy <lb/>management system with internet of things and cloud computing for efficient demand side management in smart grids. Energies <lb/>2023, 16, 4835. [CrossRef] <lb/>18. Jafari, M.; Kavousi-Fard, A.; Chen, T.; Karimi, M. A review on digital twin technology in smart grid, transportation system and <lb/>smart city: Challenges and future. IEEE Access 2023, 11, 17471-17484. [CrossRef] <lb/>19. Giglio, E.; Luzzani, G.; Terranova, V.; Trivigno, G.; Niccolai, A.; Grimaccia, F. An efficient artificial intelligence energy management <lb/>system for urban building integrating photovoltaic and storage. IEEE Access 2023, 11, 18673-18688. [CrossRef] <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Buildings 2024, 14, 271 <lb/></note>

	<page>17 of 17 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>20. Nakamura, T.; Imamura, M.; Mercer, R.; Keogh, E. Merlin: Parameter-free discovery of arbitrary length anomalies in massive <lb/>time series archives. In Proceedings of the 2020 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM), Sorrento, Italy, 17-20 <lb/>November 2020; pp. 1190-1195. <lb/>21. Hu, W.; Xiao, X.; Fu, Z.; D.; Tan, T.; Maybank, S. A system for learning statistical motion patterns. IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. <lb/>Mach. Intell. 2006, 28, 1450-1464. <lb/>22. Piciarelli, C.; Micheloni, C.; Foresti, G.L. Trajectory-based anomalous event detection. IEEE Trans. Circuits Syst. Video Technol. <lb/>2008, 18, 1544-1554. [CrossRef] <lb/>23. Akpinar, K.O.; Ozcelik, I. Analysis of machine learning methods in EtherCAT-based anomaly detection. IEEE Access 2019, 7, <lb/>184365-184374. [CrossRef] <lb/>24. Tonkal, Ö.; Polat, H.; Ba¸saran, E.; Cömert, Z.; Kocaogl ȗ, R. Machine learning approach equipped with neighbourhood component <lb/>analysis for DDoS attack detection in software-defined networking. Electronics 2021, 10, 1227. [CrossRef] <lb/>25. Olu-Ajayi, R.; Alaka, H.; Sulaimon, I.; Sunmola, F.; Ajayi, S. Building energy consumption prediction for residential buildings <lb/>using deep learning and other machine learning techniques. J. Build. Eng. 2022, 45, 103406. [CrossRef] <lb/>26. Copiaco, A.; Himeur, Y.; Amira, A.; Mansoor, W.; Fadli, F.; Atalla, S.; Sohail, S.S. An innovative deep anomaly detection of <lb/>building energy consumption using energy time-series images. Eng. Appl. Artif. Intell. 2023, 119, 105775. [CrossRef] <lb/>27. Chakraborty, D.; Elzarka, H. Advanced machine learning techniques for building performance simulation: A comparative <lb/>analysis. J. Build. Perform. Simul. 2019, 12, 193-207. [CrossRef] <lb/>28. Chung, S.H.; Ma, H.L.; Hansen, M.; Choi, T.M. Data science and analytics in aviation. Transp. Res. Part E Logist. Transp. Rev. 2020, <lb/>134, 101837. [CrossRef] <lb/>29. Aldahiri, A.; Alrashed, B.; Hussain, W. Trends in using IoT with machine learning in health prediction system. Forecasting 2021, 3, <lb/>181-206. [CrossRef] <lb/>30. Formosa, N.; Quddus, M.; Ison, S.; Abdel-Aty, M.; Yuan, J. Predicting real-time traffic conflicts using deep learning. Accid. Anal. <lb/>Prev. 2020, 136, 105429. [CrossRef] <lb/>31. Morariu, C.; Morariu, O.; Řaileanu, S.; Borangiu, T. Machine learning for predictive scheduling and resource allocation in large <lb/>scale manufacturing systems. Comput. Ind. 2020, 120, 103244. [CrossRef] <lb/>32. Castellani, A.; Schmitt, S.; Squartini, S. Real-world anomaly detection by using digital twin systems and weakly supervised <lb/>learning. IEEE Trans. Ind. Inform. 2020, 17, 4733-4742. [CrossRef] <lb/>33. Dairi, A.; Harrou, F.; Bouyeddou, B.; Senouci, S.M.; Sun, Y. Semi-supervised deep learning-driven anomaly detection schemes <lb/>for cyber-attack detection in smart grids. In Power Systems Cybersecurity: Methods, Concepts, and Best Practices; Springer: <lb/>Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany, 2023; pp. 265-295. <lb/>34. Komisarek, M.; Kozik, R.; Pawlicki, M.; Choraś, M. Towards Zero-Shot Flow-Based Cyber-Security Anomaly Detection Framework. <lb/>Appl. Sci. 2022, 12, 9636. [CrossRef] <lb/>35. Zhang, J.; Zulkernine, M.; Haque, A. Random-forests-based network intrusion detection systems. IEEE Trans. Syst. Man Cybern. <lb/>Part C (Appl. Rev.) 2008, 38, 649-659. [CrossRef] <lb/>36. Kastner, W.; Neugschwandtner, G.; Soucek, S.; Newman, H.M. Communication systems for building automation and control. <lb/>Proc. IEEE 2005, 93, 1178-1203. [CrossRef] <lb/>37. Granzer, W.; Praus, F.; Kastner, W. Security in building automation systems. IEEE Trans. Ind. Electron. 2009, 57, 3622-3630. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>38. Wetter, M. Co-simulation of building energy and control systems with the Building Controls Virtual Test Bed. J. Build. Perform. <lb/>Simul. 2011, 4, 185-203. [CrossRef] <lb/>39. di Vimercati, S.D.C.; Martinelli, F. ICT Systems Security and Privacy Protection. In Proceedings of the 32nd IFIP TC 11 International <lb/>Conference, SEC 2017, Rome, Italy, 29-31 May 2017; Springer: Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany, 2017; Volume 502. <lb/>40. Holmberg, D.G. Enemies at the gates: Securing the BACnet (R) building. ASHRAE J. 2003, 45, B24. <lb/>41. Balamurugan, S.P.; Granda, S.; Haile, S.; Petersen, A. A Dataset of Cyber-Induced Mechanical Faults on Buildings with Network 537 <lb/>and Buildings Data; Technical Report, National Renewable Energy Laboratory-Data (NREL-DATA); National Renewable Energy <lb/>Laboratory: Golden, CO, USA, 2023. <lb/>Disclaimer/Publisher&apos;s Note: The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual <lb/>author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to <lb/>people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content. </listBibl>


  </text>

</TEI>