<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-20T11:24:47.439Z">11/20/2025 11:24:47 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-20T11:24:33.934072Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-20T11:24:33.934072Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>EDITED BY <lb/>Wuqiang Zhu, <lb/>Mayo Clinic Arizona, United States <lb/>REVIEWED BY <lb/>Jingwei Xie, <lb/>University of Nebraska Medical Center, <lb/>United States <lb/>Yura Son, <lb/>Mayo Clinic Arizona, United States <lb/>*CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>Christian Devlin <lb/>c.t.devlin@emory.edu <lb/>Vahid Serpooshan <lb/>vahid.serpooshan@bme.gatech.edu <lb/> † These authors have contributed equally to <lb/>this work <lb/>RECEIVED 14 May 2024 <lb/>ACCEPTED 10 June 2024 <lb/>PUBLISHED 04 July 2024 <lb/>CITATION <lb/>Devlin C, Tomov ML, Chen H, Nama S, Ali S, <lb/>Neelakantan S, Avazmohammadi R, Dasi LP, <lb/>Bauser-Heaton HD and Serpooshan V (2024) <lb/>Patient-specific 3D in vitro modeling and fluid <lb/>dynamic analysis of primary pulmonary vein <lb/>stenosis. <lb/>Front. Cardiovasc. Med. 11:1432784. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/>COPYRIGHT <lb/>© 2024 Devlin, Tomov, Chen, Nama, Ali, <lb/>Neelakantan, Avazmohammadi, Dasi, <lb/>Bauser-Heaton and Serpooshan. This is an <lb/>open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or <lb/>reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the <lb/>copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in <lb/>accordance with accepted academic practice. <lb/>No use, distribution or reproduction is <lb/>permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/>Patient-specific 3D in vitro <lb/>modeling and fluid dynamic <lb/>analysis of primary pulmonary <lb/>vein stenosis <lb/>Christian Devlin 1 * † , Martin L. Tomov 1 , Huang Chen 1 , <lb/>Sindhu Nama 1 , Siraj Ali 1 , Sunder Neelakantan 2 , <lb/>Reza Avazmohammadi 2,3,4 , Lakshmi Prasad Dasi 1 , <lb/>Holly D. Bauser-Heaton 1,5,6,7 and Vahid Serpooshan 1,5,6 * † <lb/>1 <lb/>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Emory University School of Medicine and <lb/>Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, United States, 2 Department of Biomedical Engineering, <lb/>Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX, United States, 3 J. Mike Walker &apos;66 Department of Mechanical <lb/>Engineering, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX, United States, 4 School of Engineering Medicine, <lb/>Texas A&amp;M University, Houston, TX, United States, 5 Department of Pediatrics, Emory University School <lb/>of Medicine, Atlanta, GA, United States, 6 Children&apos;s Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, GA, United States, <lb/>7 <lb/>Sibley Heart Center, Children&apos;s Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, GA, United States <lb/>Introduction: Primary pulmonary vein stenosis (PVS) is a rare congenital heart <lb/>disease that proves to be a clinical challenge due to the rapidly progressive <lb/>disease course and high rates of treatment complications. PVS intervention is <lb/>frequently faced with in-stent restenosis and persistent disease progression <lb/>despite initial venous recanalization with balloon angioplasty or stenting. <lb/>Alterations in wall shear stress (WSS) have been previously associated with <lb/>neointimal hyperplasia and venous stenosis underlying PVS progression. Thus, <lb/>the development of patient-specific three-dimensional (3D) in vitro models is <lb/>needed to further investigate the biomechanical outcomes of endovascular <lb/>and surgical interventions. <lb/>Methods: In this study, deidentified computed tomography images from three <lb/>patients were segmented to generate perfusable phantom models of <lb/>pulmonary veins before and after catheterization. These 3D reconstructions <lb/>were 3D printed using a clear resin ink and used in a benchtop experimental <lb/>setup. Computational fluid dynamic (CFD) analysis was performed on models <lb/>in silico utilizing Doppler echocardiography data to represent the in vivo flow <lb/>conditions at the inlets. Particle image velocimetry was conducted using the <lb/>benchtop perfusion setup to analyze WSS and velocity profiles and the results <lb/>were compared with those predicted by the CFD model. <lb/>Results: Our findings indicated areas of undesirable alterations in WSS before <lb/>and after catheterization, in comparison with the published baseline levels in <lb/>the healthy in vivo tissues that may lead to regional disease progression. <lb/>Discussion: The established patient-specific 3D in vitro models and the <lb/>developed in vitro-in silico platform demonstrate great promise to refine <lb/>interventional approaches and mitigate complications in treating patients with <lb/>primary PVS. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>3D printing, pulmonary vein stenosis (PVS), flow hemodynamics, particle image <lb/>velocimetry, computational fluid dynamics, stenting, cardiac intervention <lb/>TYPE Original Research <lb/>PUBLISHED 04 July 2024 <lb/>| DOI 10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/>Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/>01 <lb/>frontiersin.org <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Primary pulmonary vein stenosis (PVS) is a pediatric disease of <lb/>the congenital pulmonary vasculature with a prognosis that remains <lb/>poor despite recent advances in endovascular and surgical techniques <lb/>(1-3). The 5-year survival rate of PVS remains below 50% due to <lb/>frequent in-stent restenosis and progression of the disease despite <lb/>intervention (4-6). Patients with congenital PVS exhibit significant <lb/>disease heterogeneity owing to the variance in the number of <lb/>occluded veins, degree of stenosis, and other comorbid conditions <lb/>that affect cardiac anatomy and hemodynamics (7). Although the <lb/>onset of primary PVS is thought to have an embryologic origin, <lb/>alterations in wall shear stress (WSS) complicated by a tortuous <lb/>anatomical course are likely an important driver of disease <lb/>progression (8). Prior studies have demonstrated that decreased <lb/>levels of WSS lead to pathological vascular changes, notably the <lb/>dedifferentiation of endothelial cells to undergo a mesenchymal <lb/>transition (9). Similar alterations in WSS have been previously <lb/>associated with coronary plaque formation and stent restenosis <lb/>(10, 11). In PVS, neointimal hyperplasia and fibrosis are primary <lb/>drivers of disease progression and have been associated with <lb/>disturbed venous WSS (12). Considering these challenges, there is a <lb/>significant need to investigate the hemodynamic and biomechanical <lb/>alterations underlying PVS in a patient-specific manner to guide <lb/>future clinical management. In this study, we developed patient-<lb/>specific, 3D printed, perfusable in vitro phantoms and in silico <lb/>models of PVS in the pre-and post-catheterization states. We <lb/>employed complementary techniques in computational fluid <lb/>dynamics (CFD) modeling and particle image velocimetry (PIV) to <lb/>analyze the hemodynamic and biomechanical outcomes of <lb/>endovascular intervention. <lb/>The etiology of primary PVS is thought to be a failed <lb/>embryologic connection of the left atrial outpouching with the <lb/>confluence of fetal pulmonary veins, resulting in significant fibrosis <lb/>or atresia of one or more pulmonary veins (7, 8, 13). Patients often <lb/>initially present in the first year of life with non-specific symptoms <lb/>of tachypnea and recurrent pulmonary infections (13). Disease <lb/>progression often leads to signs and symptoms of pulmonary <lb/>hypertension, including hemoptysis, right ventricular overload, and <lb/>cardiac murmurs (2, 14). Diagnosis and management of primary <lb/>PVS is frequently challenged by coexisting congenital cardiac <lb/>malformations, seen in up to 50% of patients with primary PVS, <lb/>which complicate disease management and interventional <lb/>approaches (8). Catheter-based interventions of PVS, including <lb/>balloon angioplasty (15) and endovascular stenting (16) in PVS, <lb/>have historically been burdened with significant rates of restenosis <lb/>and pulmonary regurgitation (5, 17). The recent increase in the use <lb/>of drug-eluting stents has shown initial promise for improving the <lb/>rates of in-stent restenosis (18); however, stent placement is not <lb/>always feasible due to severe stenosis or venous anatomy (7). <lb/>Modern surgical approaches involve resection, mobilization, <lb/>reorientation, and anastomosis of the pulmonary veins (19). Many <lb/>of these novel surgical techniques, however, also require further <lb/>investigation to understand the altered anatomy and blood flow (20). <lb/>To date, significant advances in additive manufacturing, and in <lb/>particular, 3D printing technologies, such as extrusion, <lb/>stereolithography, and digital light processing (DLP)-based printing, <lb/>have substantially improved the ability to develop highly accurate <lb/>in vitro models of various tissues and organs (21-24). 3D printed <lb/>models provide unparalleled capacity to recapitulate the highly <lb/>complex and dynamic microenvironment of various tissues and, <lb/>therefore, have found increasing applications in modeling a variety <lb/>of congenital heart disease (25-27). The creation of patient-specific <lb/>anatomical 3D models has been shown to be a greatly effective tool <lb/>in cardiac interventional planning and medical education (28). <lb/>Notably, techniques in additive manufacturing and fluid dynamic <lb/>analysis have been previously used to study pulmonary artery atresia <lb/>(PAA) and tetralogy of Fallot (TOF) with major aortopulmonary <lb/>collateral arteries (MAPCAs) by the creation of simplified perfusable <lb/>phantom models and subsequent CFD and PIV analyses (29). In <lb/>PVS, a similar approach can be employed using 3D-segmented <lb/>models from patient imaging of the congenital pulmonary veins. <lb/>Computational and experimental analyses of flow hemodynamic <lb/>parameters within the 3D congenital vasculature have been proven <lb/>to be robust tools in examining the impact of flow (alterations) on <lb/>various congenital heart diseases (30-33). CFD analyses employ <lb/>differential equations and numerical methods to predict fluid <lb/>behavior using in silico models, based on fundamental equations <lb/>that describe conservation of momentum and mass. <lb/>Computational modeling has been shown to be instrumental in <lb/>modeling various cardiovascular pathologies, including various <lb/>aortic anomalies, Norwood anatomy, single-ventricle defects, and <lb/>PAA (34-37). CFD modeling has also been shown to be useful in <lb/>interventional and surgical planning to study hemodynamic effects <lb/>of stenting and compare surgical approaches (38). Similarly and in <lb/>parallel to the in silico models, in vitro PIV methods have been <lb/>proven to be a valuable experimental technique to study flow <lb/>characteristics in cardiovascular models (29, 39, 40). Through the <lb/>use of laser or ultrasound-based approaches, PIV techniques have <lb/>enabled precise tracking of flow within the 3D geometries and <lb/>quantifying fluid flow parameters such as planar and 3D WSS and <lb/>velocity vectors, which are critical factors in the pathogenesis of <lb/>congenital pulmonary vascular disease (29, 34, 41). <lb/>2 Experimental methods <lb/>2.1 CT imaging, segmentation, and creation <lb/>of 3D perfusable models <lb/>Deidentified computed tomography (CT) angiography (CTA) <lb/>data were taken from patients with congenital PVS in the setting <lb/>of idiopathic, single ventricle, and totally anomalous pulmonary <lb/>venous return pathologies. CTA images were loaded as DICOM <lb/>files using 3D Slicer (Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital, Boston, <lb/>MA, USA) software for segmentation (42, 43). Five sets of <lb/>pulmonary veins and attached left atrium pre-and post-<lb/>catheterization data were segmented for these three patients. <lb/>Manual segmentation was performed on each geometry. Primary <lb/>anatomical branches were segmented for each pulmonary vein. <lb/>Stereolithography (STL) files were exported to Ansys SpaceClaim <lb/>(Images used courtesy of Ansys ® Inc., SpaceClaim 2022 R2, <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>02 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>Lebanon, NH, USA) for 3D model post-processing and perfusion <lb/>engineering. An outer shell with 1mm wall thickness was created <lb/>for each geometry to perform benchtop and PIV flow testing. <lb/>Perfusion inlets and outlets were created to connect to a <lb/>peristaltic pump for benchtop flow testing. Inlet barbs [2.25 mm <lb/>internal diameter (ID) × 20 mm length] were designed for each <lb/>anatomical inlet to decrease turbulence created by the inlet tubing <lb/>interface in benchtop and CFD testing. A single outlet connection <lb/>was created and attached to the left atrium to simulate the mitral <lb/>outlet (12 mm ID × 5 mm length). These computer-aided design <lb/>(CAD) models with varying degrees of stenosis were 3D printed <lb/>on the Form 3+ stereolithography 3D printer (Formlabs, <lb/>Somerville, MA, USA) using a 25 µm layer thickness. Each model <lb/>was printed using external supports and underwent recommended <lb/>post-processing. After printing, each model was washed for <lb/>60 min in 100% isopropyl alcohol to remove non-crosslinked <lb/>resin from the models and subsequently underwent a 25-min <lb/>curing stage at 60 °C UV for final processing of the resin. <lb/>2.2 Benchtop perfusion and PIV setup <lb/>2.2.1 Creation of polydimethylsiloxane constructs <lb/>and benchtop perfusion setup <lb/>To utilize laser-based PIV technique for the analysis, 3D <lb/>constructs of optically transparent polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) <lb/>(Sylgard TM 184 Silicone Elastomer Kit, Dow, CA, USA) were created <lb/>for pre-and post-catheterization models for the left lower <lb/>pulmonary vein (LLPV) from patient #1 with idiopathic PVS. <lb/>Perfusable inner-shelled resin models were created with a 0.6 mm <lb/>wall thickness and were 3D printed and used as model molds for <lb/>PDMS casting. Molding boxes were 3D printed using a filament <lb/>extrusion printer, and holes were created to allow for inlet and <lb/>outlet tubing connections. Perfusion attachments were connected to <lb/>the model inside the molding boxes, and the boxes were sealed <lb/>using 100% silicone rubber. A 10:1 ratio of PDMS to crosslinking <lb/>agent was used for curing. Vacuum aspiration was performed on <lb/>crosslinking PDMS for 30 min to remove air bubbles before <lb/>pouring. PDMS was poured into the molding boxes and was initially <lb/>cured at 80 °C for 2 h. The models were then left at room <lb/>temperature (20 °C) for 48 h to complete curing. Once cured, the <lb/>models were perfused with 100% acetone for 4 days to fully clear the <lb/>inner 3D resin models, which did not undergo a UV curing in post-<lb/>processing. The resulting PDMS block was extracted from the <lb/>molding box, and the imaging surfaces were leveled. Diameter-<lb/>matched inlet and outlet silicone tubing was used to connect the <lb/>PDMS models to a 12 V variable speed peristaltic pump (Kamoer©, <lb/>Kamoer Fluid Tech Co., Shanghai, China) set to an average flow rate <lb/>of 79 ml/min, which was calculated using the LLPV post-<lb/>catheterization average velocity from pulse-Doppler echocardiogram <lb/>data and the cross-sectional lumen area. <lb/>2.2.2 PIV experimental setup <lb/>A 2D laser PIV assay was constructed to image and quantify <lb/>flow through the LLPV PVS model using a benchtop perfusion <lb/>setup. The PDMS block was submerged in an index-matching <lb/>aqueous urea solution with a refractive index of 1.41. A water-<lb/>glycerol-urea mixture at a density of 1,130 kg/m 3 and a viscosity <lb/>of 0.0039 kg/(m s) in the range of blood viscosity was used for <lb/>the perfusion setup. We added 2 µm tracer polystyrene particles, <lb/>coated with Rhodamine 6G (LaVision 1001851), to the solution <lb/>and illuminated them during the experiments using a double-<lb/>pulse from a Nd:YLF laser (DM20-527-DH, Photonics Lasers, <lb/>Ronkonkoma, NY, USA). A Phantom VEO-E 340l (AMETEK, <lb/>Berwyn, PA, USA) camera with a high-speed sensor was used <lb/>with a Nikon (Melville, NY, USA) NIKKOR Z MC 105 mm F <lb/>2.8 VR S Macro lens for imaging flow through a mirror setup. <lb/>The laser sheet was oriented to the image along the longitudinal <lb/>plane including the stenosis/stented regions as well as a distal <lb/>region. The images were recorded for multiple peristaltic pump <lb/>cycles and velocity vectors were calculated. Vector data were <lb/>post-processed using ParaView (Kitware, Clifton Park, NY, USA). <lb/>2.3 CFD analysis of flow hemodynamics <lb/>CFD analysis was performed on the pre-and post-catheterization <lb/>idiopathic LLPV models. In Ansys SpaceClaim, the interior fluid <lb/>volumes of the perfusable models were used for CFD testing. One <lb/>outlet and two inlet boundaries were used for CFD testing. The <lb/>meshes were generated using tetrahedral mesh elements. A <lb/>transient analysis was performed on these models using Ansys <lb/>SpaceClaim, Meshing, and Fluent. Two CFD tests were performed <lb/>on each geometry, one to compare with the results of PIV and <lb/>another to best mimic in vivo conditions. Planes of interest were <lb/>chosen for the analysis. These included a plane in the distal <lb/>pulmonary vein, a plane through the stenotic and subsequently <lb/>stented region, as well as a longitudinal plane in the PIV experiments. <lb/>2.3.1 PIV simulations <lb/>For PIV comparison, a water-glycerol-urea mixture was <lb/>simulated in Fluent with a density of 1,130 kg/m 3 and a viscosity <lb/>of 0.0039 kg/(m s), which were included under a Newtonian fluid <lb/>assumption. The flow rate vs. time input function was <lb/>determined from flow measurements performed on the peristaltic <lb/>pump used in the benchtop flow setup. The same input function <lb/>was used for both inlets of the LLPV model. <lb/>2.3.2 Simulating the in vivo flow conditions <lb/>A set of CFD simulations was conducted using parameters to <lb/>best match in vivo conditions. A density of 1,060 kg/m 3 was <lb/>chosen for this analysis, and given the non-Newtonian viscosity <lb/>characteristics of blood, a Casson fluid model was chosen to <lb/>model the variable blood viscosity with respect to shear rate as <lb/>follows: <lb/>m ¼ <lb/>m 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>_ <lb/>g <lb/>þ <lb/>2m 1 N 1 <lb/>ffiffiffi <lb/>_ <lb/>g <lb/>p <lb/>þ N 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>N 1 ¼ <lb/>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi <lb/>m p (1 À Hct) À0:25 <lb/>q <lb/>m 1 ¼ <lb/>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi <lb/>0:625Hct <lb/>p <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">FDevlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>03 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>where m is the viscosity, _ <lb/>g is the shear rate, m 2 <lb/>1 is the yield stress, <lb/>N 1 is the consistency index, and Hct is the blood hematocrit. For <lb/>the blood, m p ¼ 0:00145 (Pa s) and Hct ¼ 0:4. <lb/>Pulse-Doppler echocardiogram data were obtained from pre-<lb/>and post-catheterization studies. The post-catheterization Doppler <lb/>waveforms were curve fitted and used as the velocity vs. time <lb/>profiles for the CFD analysis. Gravity was simulated on the <lb/>geometry assuming the patient was in a vertical, standing position. <lb/>The in vivo simulations were conducted over one cardiac cycle <lb/>using a fixed time step, and convergence was verified. A time point <lb/>at the systolic peak of the pulse Doppler waveform was chosen to <lb/>observe WSS and velocity levels in the PVS models. <lb/>2.3.3 CFD solution parameters <lb/>In both sets of CFD simulations, a parabolic inlet function was <lb/>described as a user-defined function to simulate fluid flow. A <lb/>pressure-based solver was chosen for the analysis. A no-slip wall <lb/>condition was applied, and a coupled Green-Gauss cell-based <lb/>solver was used for simulation. A turbulent two-equation <lb/>k-epsilon flow model was used for the analysis. The results were <lb/>generated using Ansys Fluent (Images used courtesy of Ansys ® <lb/>Inc. Fluent 2022 R2, Lebanon, NH, USA) and subsequently post-<lb/>processed using ParaView. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Creation of 3D printed, patient-specific, <lb/>perfusable phantom models <lb/>In this study, five pulmonary vein models from the <lb/>three patients were segmented and 3D printed (Figure 1). <lb/>FIGURE 1 <lb/>3D printing of patient-specific synthetic models of PVS. (A) CT scans with contrast from patient #1 with idiopathic PVS, demonstrating LLPV pre-(top) <lb/>and post-catheterization (bottom). (B) Raw segmentations of LLPV and attached left atria. (C) The CAD model of LLPV with engineered inlet and outlet <lb/>ports to reduce interface turbulence. (D) Form 3+ 3D printed resin models of patient #1 demonstrating stenosis in LLPV. (E) 3D printed resin models of <lb/>stenosis in patient #1, in the RUPV (i) and the LUPV (ii), as well as in patient #2 (LLPV, iii) and patient #3 (RUPV, iv), with total anomalous pulmonary <lb/>venous return. Scale bar in (B) shows 5 cm and that in (E-iv) shows 2 cm. Percentages of stenosis are shown for each condition in the <lb/>pre-catheterization state. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">FDevlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>04 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>Pre-catheterization lumen diameters, degree of stenosis, and <lb/>post-catheterization lumen diameters were measured using CTA <lb/>data from each patient (Supplementary Figure S1, Supplementary <lb/>Table S1). For patient #1, with idiopathic PVS, three pulmonary <lb/>veins underwent catheterization between studies. Pre-and post-<lb/>catheterization models were segmented and post-processed <lb/>using 3D Slicer and Ansys SpaceClaim for the LLPV, right <lb/>upper pulmonary vein (RUPV), and the left upper pulmonary <lb/>vein (LUPV) (Figures 1D,E-i,ii). Three branching veins were <lb/>included in the models for the RUPV and the LUPV. The LLPV <lb/>was found to only have two identifiable branches on CTA. <lb/>The LLPV, RUPV, and LUPV had 64%, 41%, and 50% <lb/>stenosis, respectively, in the pre-catheterization imaging <lb/>(Figures 1D,E-i,ii). For the second patient (patient #2) with <lb/>PVS in the setting of single-ventricle shunt pathology, the <lb/>LLPV was stented between CTA images and was chosen for the <lb/>analysis with three branching inlet veins. This patient was <lb/>found to have a high degree of stenosis of 83% (Figure 1E-iii). <lb/>For patient #3, with PVS in the setting of total anomalous <lb/>pulmonary venous return (TAPVR), the RUPV underwent <lb/>surgical correction and was also included for the analysis <lb/>with a 57% stenosis (Figure 1E-iv). Three inlet branches were <lb/>identified and included in the models. The 3D resin models <lb/>were 3D printed for all models using clear resin on the <lb/>Formlabs Form 3+. The LLPV for patient #1 was chosen for <lb/>the CFD and PIV analysis. Given such a high degree of <lb/>stenosis in the RUPV in patient #2, the stenosis region was <lb/>resolution-limited on CT imaging, so the model with the next <lb/>highest degree of stenosis with adequate resolution was chosen. <lb/>3.2 PIV analysis of flow in patient <lb/>#1-stenosis in LLPV <lb/>A 2D laser PIV analysis was performed on the LLPV PVS <lb/>model (patient #1, Figures 1A-D) using a benchtop perfusion <lb/>setup (Figures 2A-C). Average velocity and WSS as functions of <lb/>time during two flow cycles of the peristaltic pump were <lb/>acquired through stenosis and distal planes (Figures 2D,E). PIV <lb/>results in the pre-catheterization models demonstrated markedly <lb/>greater (&gt;2×) velocity and WSS values on the stenosis plane <lb/>compared with that of the distal plane. Stenting of the LLPV <lb/>resulted in a significant decrease in velocity and WSS, with <lb/>values lower than those measured in the distal plane (Figures 2D, <lb/>E, bottom). Furthermore, 3D time-averaged WSS (TAWSS) was <lb/>calculated for a peristaltic pump cycle as follows: <lb/>TAWSS ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>T <lb/>ð <lb/>T <lb/>0 <lb/>jWSSjdt <lb/>Areas of elevated TAWSS were observed in the stenosis region <lb/>with the smallest lumen diameter (Figure 2F). The oscillatory shear <lb/>index (OSI) is a frequently used parameter in cardiovascular CFD <lb/>analysis that describes local changes in the magnitude and size of <lb/>WSS. High OSI has been associated with aberrant endothelial <lb/>response (44) and is given as follows: <lb/>OSI ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 À <lb/>Ð T <lb/>0 WSS dt <lb/>Ð T <lb/>0 jWSSjdt <lb/>The highest levels of OSI were noted in the post-catheterization <lb/>model near the pulmonary venoatrial junction (Figure 2G). In <lb/>the next step, two time points during a pump cycle were <lb/>included as points of interest for the simulation. The time (1) <lb/>(=0.08 s) was chosen at the peak flow of the peristaltic pump of <lb/>158 ml/min and time (2) (=0.10 s) was at the average flow rate of <lb/>79 ml/min. Velocity vector data were generated along the <lb/>longitudinal plane at times (1) and (2) (Figure 2H). The highest <lb/>average velocities were visualized at time (1) through the stenosis <lb/>region and reached 1.0 m/s. <lb/>3.3 Computational analysis of flow in <lb/>patient #1-stenosis in LLPV <lb/>The CFD modeling results were generated using the flow and <lb/>rheological parameters consistent with those used in the PIV <lb/>experiments. The same time points during the peristaltic pump <lb/>cycle, time (1) (0.08 s) and time (2) (0.10 s), were used for the <lb/>CFD analysis, representing the peak and average flows, <lb/>respectively (Figure 3A). Further, the longitudinal planes were <lb/>chosen to match those imaged with the laser sheet in the PIV <lb/>experiments (Figures 3B,C). The average velocity and WSS were <lb/>plotted as functions of time at the stenosis and distal planes in <lb/>the pre-and post-catheterization models (Figures 3D,E). <lb/>Consistent with the experimental (PIV) measurements <lb/>(Figures 2D,E), the CFD model predicted significantly greater <lb/>(&gt;2×) levels of velocity and WSS in the stenosis plane compared <lb/>with the distal plane. The stenting of the LLPV resulted in a <lb/>drastic decrease in the velocity and WSS (Figures 3D,E, bottom). <lb/>The highest velocities were predicted at time (1), through the <lb/>stenosis region, reaching 0.98 m/s. 3D contours of TAWSS and <lb/>OSI were also calculated for pre-and post-catheterization models <lb/>(Figures 3F,G). Regions with the highest TAWSS were located in <lb/>the stenotic and bifurcation regions of the pre-catheterization <lb/>model, and regions with the highest OSI were in the distal region <lb/>of the post-catheterization model, also at the venoatrial junction. <lb/>Longitudinal planar vector fields were further constructed to <lb/>demonstrate flow profiles through the stenosis and stented <lb/>regions to match those obtained using the PIV (Figure 3H). <lb/>Consistent with the PIV results (Figure 2H), the longitudinal <lb/>vectors showed the highest velocity through the stenosis region. <lb/>Next, CFD modeling was used to analyze the in vivo flow data <lb/>in the reference LLPV PVS case (patient #1). The inlet flow rate vs. <lb/>time profiles from patient echocardiogram data were verified in <lb/>Ansys Fluent at each inlet plane (Figures 4A-C). The average <lb/>WSS was calculated at distal and stenotic regions during one <lb/>cardiac cycle. The average WSS at peak systole in the stenotic <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>05 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>region was calculated at 346 dyn/cm 2 (Figures 4D-F). In the post-<lb/>catheterization model, WSS decreased to 6 dyn/cm 2 in the stented <lb/>region (Figure 4F). The 3D contours of WSS were generated at peak <lb/>systole (Figure 4G). Regions of highest instantaneous WSS, as <lb/>expected, were noted in the pre-catheterization model at the <lb/>stenosis region with the smallest lumen size. In the post-<lb/>catheterization models, highest levels of instantaneous WSS were <lb/>also visualized at the bifurcation region. The highest levels of OSI <lb/>were seen at this distal region in the pre-catheterization LLPV <lb/>model and in the stented region of the post-catheterization <lb/>model (Figure 4H). Contours of TAWSS were generated and <lb/>scaled to an average WSS (35 dyn/cm 2 ) above which venous <lb/>neointimal hyperplasia and fibrosis have been shown to occur <lb/>(Figure 4I) (12). In patient #1, elevated regions of TAWSS were <lb/>present in the stenosis region as well as the distal and bifurcation <lb/>regions before catheterization. In the post-catheterization models, <lb/>TAWSS returned to healthy levels at the venoatrial junction; <lb/>however, distal regions in the stent continued to experience <lb/>elevated levels of TAWSS above a conservative threshold of <lb/>20 dyn/cm 2 (Figure 4I). The CFD results from patient #2 <lb/>FIGURE 2 <lb/>PIV analysis of flow hemodynamics in 3D printed models of PVS. Schematic (A) and actual (B) experimental setup used for the PIV analysis (partly <lb/>created using Biorender.com). Key experimental components included a PDMS model of the LLPV (i), a flow meter (ii), peristaltic pump (iii), and a <lb/>reservoir containing PIV fluid with particles (iv). Bottom panel in (B) shows the close-up view of the PDMS model of LLPV with two inlets and one <lb/>outlet. (C) Imaging planes used for PIV analysis, pre-catheterization (top), and post-catheterization (bottom). Average velocity (D) and WSS (E) <lb/>measured via PIV technique for two cycles of flow through the LLPV constructs pre-(top) and post-catheterization (bottom). 2D contours <lb/>of TAWSS (F) and OSI (G). (H) Velocity vectors along the longitudinal plane at time (1) = peak systole (left) and time (2) = average flow (right), <lb/>pre-(top) and post-catheterization (bottom). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>06 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>indicated elevated levels of TAWSS in the severe stenosis region as <lb/>well as in the distal branch vessels. Intervention decreased TAWSS <lb/>in the venoatrial junction, but TAWSS remained high in the stented <lb/>region. For patient #3, elevated levels of TAWSS were visualized <lb/>throughout the pre-catheterization pulmonary vein. After surgical <lb/>intervention, the levels of TAWSS were decreased in several <lb/>regions but remained high in the region of large venous <lb/>curvature. Furthermore, WSS levels remained elevated above <lb/>healthy physiologic levels in the bifurcation region after stenting. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>Recent advancements in surgical and endovascular techniques <lb/>have sought to alleviate the high mortality and morbidity rates of <lb/>primary PVS (1). Despite the increasing clinical use of these <lb/>novel therapies, patients with PVS still face high intervention <lb/>complication rates. Given the significant disease heterogeneity in <lb/>PVS and the variety of available interventional approaches, <lb/>management of this life-threatening disease should be driven in a <lb/>FIGURE 3 <lb/>CFD modeling of flow hemodynamics in 3D printed models of PVS. (A) Flow waveform measured for the peristaltic pump used in the study for <lb/>perfusion assays. This waveform was fed into the CFD model as an inlet function. (B) The setup used for the CFD analysis of flow through the <lb/>LLPV PVS model, consisting of two inlets (blue arrows) and one outlet (gray arrows). The scale bar shows 5 cm. (C) Imaging planes used for the <lb/>particle image velocimetry assay were replicated in CFD model before and after catheterization. Average velocity (D) and WSS (E) predicted via <lb/>CFD during two peristaltic pump cycles, for flow through the LLPV PVS geometry pre-(top) and post-catheterization (bottom). 2D contours of <lb/>TAWSS (F) and OSI (G). (H) Velocity vectors along the longitudinal plane, predicted at time (1) = peak systole (left) and time (2) = average flow <lb/>(right), pre-(top) and post-catheterization (bottom). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>07 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>FIGURE 4 <lb/>CFD modeling of flow hemodynamics in the clinical cases of PVS. (A) Post-catheterization Doppler echocardiography of LLPV during a single cardiac <lb/>cycle. (B) Velocity vs. time curve fit was used to determine inlet flow rate function for CFD. (C) Parabolic user-defined inlet function in Ansys Fluent. (D) <lb/>The LLPV setup used for CFD, with inlets (blue arrows) and outlet (red arrows). (E) Stenosis, stented, and distal planes in the pre-catheterization (left) <lb/>and post-catheterization (right) models. (F) Average WSS vs. time in the pre-catheterization (top) and post-catheterization (bottom) models. (G) 3D <lb/>contours of WSS at the t = systolic peak. (H) 3D contours of OSI. (I) 3D contours of TAWSS for patient #1 (anterior view), patient #2 (left view), and <lb/>patient #3 (posterior view). <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>08 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<body>patient-specific fashion. 3D modeling, 3D printing and bioprinting, <lb/>PIV, and CFD techniques address this challenge and shed light on <lb/>patient-specific factors that may better predict interventional <lb/>outcomes in PVS. In this study, we utilized these methods to <lb/>create image-reconstructed 3D models of primary PVS to study <lb/>hemodynamic changes associated with stenosis and subsequent <lb/>intervention in three patients. We demonstrated how PIV and <lb/>CFD analyses, two common experimental modalities for flow <lb/>analysis, can be instrumental for studying and quantifying <lb/>biomechanical properties associated with congenital PVS. The <lb/>velocity results from CFD analyses aligned well with the PIV <lb/>results, demonstrating the potential of the simultaneous use of <lb/>in silico and in vitro platforms for studying hemodynamic <lb/>changes associated with cardiovascular interventions. <lb/>Furthermore, we demonstrated how CFD analysis using patient-<lb/>specific in vivo parameters can be used to predict interventional <lb/>outcomes through the WSS calculations. Recently published data <lb/>indicated healthy levels of venous WSS approximated at <lb/>10 dyn/cm 2 , and neointimal hyperplasia levels are observed at <lb/>20-50 dyn/cm 2 (12). In CFD studies here, 35 dyn/cm 2 was chosen <lb/>as an average upper limit of normal for venous WSS. Our CFD <lb/>results demonstrated that TAWSS levels were above the upper limit <lb/>of normal in several locations in the pre-catheterization models for <lb/>all patients, predicting further stenosis progression. In the post-<lb/>catheterization models, TAWSS levels decreased at the venoatrial <lb/>junction; however, isolated areas of elevated TAWSS in the stent <lb/>were still observed. Notably, our results suggested that TAWSS <lb/>levels remain high at the bifurcation region, stented region, and <lb/>high curvature areas for patients #1, #2, and #3, respectively. These <lb/>results suggest that these patients may continue to have disease <lb/>progression despite endovascular intervention, as frequently <lb/>observed clinically. The outcomes from this study, therefore, <lb/>highlight the need for improved intervention practices to reach <lb/>desired WSS goals in patients with PVS. Although stent diameter is <lb/>often limited by vascular compliance, other aspects of intervention <lb/>may be altered by CFD and PIV prediction, including stent <lb/>location and need for surgical intervention. <lb/>Future opportunities exist to further study altered <lb/>hemodynamics and biomechanics of PVS using patient-specific <lb/>modeling. 3D PIV methods could be employed to better <lb/>recapitulate the hemodynamic behavior in vitro or ex vivo. <lb/>Furthermore, as previously demonstrated in PVS, PAA, and <lb/>tetralogy of Fallot with MAPCAs, 3D bioprinted models could be <lb/>developed, using hydrogel-based biomaterials and a variety of cell <lb/>types, and used to study cellular and genetic responses to venous <lb/>stenosis (29, 41, 45-47). Using 3D bioprinted models, spatial <lb/>transcriptomics and/or proteomic analyses could be highly <lb/>informative tools to study genetic implications associated with <lb/>the altered cellular microenvironment observed in primary PVS. <lb/>Several limitations and challenges exist in this study that could <lb/>be addressed in future works. The resolution of CT images was <lb/>determined to be adequate for creating 3D models; however, <lb/>models with a high degree of stenosis, as seen in patient #2 with <lb/>single-ventricle pathology, had very little contrast passthrough <lb/>and a higher subjective degree of error when segmenting. Given <lb/>the peristaltic flow profile of the pump used in the benchtop <lb/>perfusion setup, the pediatric cardiac cycle velocity vs. time <lb/>profile could not be simulated but was estimated using the <lb/>determined average flow rate. PDMS has been shown to be an <lb/>effective optically clear polymer to be used in PIV experiments; <lb/>however, it is unable to precisely replicate the biomechanical <lb/>properties of the congenital pulmonary veins. Moreover, the <lb/>ability to resolve instantaneous WSS from 2D PIV is limited, and <lb/>here, PIV results underpredict instantaneous and time-averaged <lb/>WSS results obtained from CFD. Based on the CFD results, the <lb/>velocity profile exhibits a steep slope, and the boundary layer <lb/>thickness is only 0.2 mm. Although high-resolution PIV was <lb/>employed to measure the flow, the vector spacing was <lb/>approximately 0.12 mm, resulting in only two vectors within the <lb/>boundary layer, which is insufficient to accurately capture the <lb/>high-velocity gradient. Moreover, PIV uses a finite interrogation <lb/>window, with an interrogation window of 64 pixels, ∼0.48 mm, <lb/>used in these experiments, resulting in averaged values of vectors <lb/>near the wall in the boundary layer. Consequently, the PIV <lb/>technique cannot accurately determine the WSS values in the <lb/>stenosis. Nonetheless, the inlet profile can be utilized to calibrate <lb/>CFD simulations. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>Congenital PVS is an ongoing clinical challenge for pediatric <lb/>interventional cardiologists due to significant disease <lb/>heterogeneity and progression despite intervention. 3D printing <lb/>has been shown to be a useful technique for facing the challenge <lb/>of modeling cardiovascular disease with considerable <lb/>heterogeneity. In primary PVS, disturbed WSS is suggested to <lb/>underlie disease pathogenesis through neointimal hyperplasia and <lb/>venous fibrosis. Integrated CFD-PIV techniques continue to be <lb/>an instrumental approach to model cardiovascular conditions <lb/>with hemodynamic alterations. In this paper, using patient-<lb/>specific 3D printed in vitro models we present how the CFD and <lb/>PIV modalities can be used in parallel to simulate biomechanical <lb/>changes in PVS. The obtained data can, in turn, be used to <lb/>predict regions of disease progression, hence enabling more <lb/>effective interventional procedures or therapies. Future studies <lb/>are needed to further understand potential uses of patient-<lb/>specific modeling using PIV, CFD, 3D bioprinting, and <lb/>cellularization to improve outcomes for patients with PVS. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The original contributions presented in the study are included <lb/>in the paper/Supplementary Material, further inquiries can be <lb/>directed to the corresponding authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>The studies involving humans were approved by the Emory <lb/>University Institutional Review Board. The studies were <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>09 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<div type="annex">conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional <lb/>requirements. The ethics committee/institutional review board <lb/>waived the requirement of written informed consent for <lb/>participation from the participants or the participants&apos; legal <lb/>guardians/next of kin because anonymized patient data were <lb/>used in this study. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>CD: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal Analysis, <lb/>Investigation, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, <lb/>Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. MT: <lb/>Conceptualization, Data curation, Methodology, Supervision, <lb/>Writing -original draft. HC: Data curation, Investigation, <lb/>Methodology, Validation, Writing -original draft. SiN: Data <lb/>curation, Methodology, Writing -original draft. SA: Data <lb/>curation, Writing -original draft. SuN: Methodology, Writing -<lb/>original draft, Data curation. RA: Conceptualization, <lb/>Methodology, Resources, Supervision, Validation, Writing -<lb/>original draft. LD: Methodology, Resources, Supervision, <lb/>Validation, Writing -original draft, Investigation. HB-H: <lb/>Conceptualization, <lb/>Investigation, <lb/>Resources, <lb/>Supervision, <lb/>Validation, Writing -original draft. VS: Conceptualization, <lb/>Funding acquisition, Methodology, Project administration, <lb/>Resources, Supervision, Validation, Writing -original draft, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The authors declare financial support was received for the <lb/>research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/>This research was funded by the National Institutes of Health <lb/>(NIH) grant number R01 HL131017 and the National Science <lb/>Foundation (NSF) CAREER award number 2044657 (to VS). <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors acknowledge the Cardiovascular Fluid Mechanics <lb/>Laboratory for providing access to PIV equipment and related <lb/>technical expertise. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/>The authors declared that they were an editorial board member <lb/>of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the <lb/>peer-review process and the final decision. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the <lb/>authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated <lb/>organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the <lb/>reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or <lb/>claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed <lb/>or endorsed by the publisher. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this paper can be found online <lb/>at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Feins EN, Callahan R, Baird CW. Pulmonary vein stenosis-evolving surgical <lb/>management of a challenging disease. Children (Basel). (2021) 8:631-43. doi: 10. <lb/>3390/children8080631 <lb/>2. Amin R, Kwon S, Moayedi Y, Sweezey N. Pulmonary vein stenosis: case report <lb/>and literature review. Can Respir J. (2009) 16:e77-80. doi: 10.1155/2009/791653 <lb/>3. Firouzi A, Khajali Z, Mortezaeian H, Pouraliakbar H, Mohebbi B, Alemzadeh-<lb/>Ansari MJ, et al. Current endovascular approach in adult patients with pulmonary <lb/>vein stenosis: a state-of-the-art approach. Curr Probl Cardiol. (2022) 47:100850. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2021.100850 <lb/>4. McLennan DI, Solano ECR, Handler SS, Lincoln J, Mitchell ME, Kirkpatrick EC. <lb/>Pulmonary vein stenosis: moving from past pessimism to future optimism. Front <lb/>Pediatr. (2021) 9:747812. doi: 10.3389/fped.2021.747812 <lb/>5. Almakadma AH, Sarma D, Hassett L, Miranda W, Alkhouli M, Reeder GS, et al. <lb/>Pulmonary vein stenosis-balloon angioplasty versus stenting: a systematic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. JACC Clin Electrophysiol. (2022) 8:1323-33. doi: 10.1016/j.jacep.2022. <lb/>08.008 <lb/>6. Prieto LR. The state of the art in pulmonary vein stenosis-diagnosis &amp; treatment. <lb/>J Atr Fibrillation. (2010) 2(228):27-38. doi: 10.4022/jafib.228 <lb/>7. Vanderlaan RD, Rome J, Hirsch R, Ivy D, Caldarone CA. Pulmonary vein <lb/>stenosis: treatment and challenges. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2021) 161:2169-76. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2020.05.117 <lb/>8. Pazos-Lopez P, Garcia-Rodriguez C, Guitian-Gonzalez A, Paredes-Galan E, <lb/>Alvarez-Moure MA, Rodriguez-Alvarez M, et al. Pulmonary vein stenosis: <lb/>etiology, diagnosis and management. World J Cardiol. (2016) 8:81-8. doi: 10. <lb/>4330/wjc.v8.i1.81 <lb/>9. Mahmoud MM, Serbanovic-Canic J, Feng S, Souilhol C, Xing R, Hsiao S, et al. <lb/>Shear stress induces endothelial-to-mesenchymal transition via the transcription <lb/>factor Snail. Sci Rep. (2017) 7:3375. doi: 10.1038/s41598-017-03532-z <lb/>10. Dhawan SS, Avati Nanjundappa RP, Branch JR, Taylor WR, Quyyumi AA, Jo H, <lb/>et al. Shear stress and plaque development. Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther. (2010) <lb/>8:545-56. doi: 10.1586/erc.10.28 <lb/>11. Gijsen F, Katagiri Y, Barlis P, Bourantas C, Collet C, Coskun U, et al. Expert <lb/>recommendations on the assessment of wall shear stress in human coronary <lb/>arteries: existing methodologies, technical considerations, and clinical applications. <lb/>Eur Heart J. (2019) 40:3421-33. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehz551 <lb/>12. Hammer PE, McEnaney K, Callahan R, Baird CW, Hoganson DM, Jenkins KJ. <lb/>The role of elevated wall shear stress in progression of pulmonary vein stenosis: <lb/>evidence from two case studies. Children (Basel). (2021) 8:729-40. doi: 10.3390/ <lb/>children8090729 <lb/>13. Frank DB, Levy PT, Stiver CA, Boe BA, Baird CW, Callahan RM, et al. Primary <lb/>pulmonary vein stenosis during infancy: state of the art review. J Perinatol. (2021) <lb/>41:1528-39. doi: 10.1038/s41372-021-01008-7 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>10 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>14. Rosenblum JM, Altin HF, Gillespie SE, Bauser-Heaton H, Kanter KA, Sinha R, <lb/>et al. Management outcomes of primary pulmonary vein stenosis. J Thorac Cardiovasc <lb/>Surg. (2020) 159:1029-36 e1021. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2019.08.105 <lb/>15. Ghobrial J. Drug-coated balloon angioplasty in pulmonary vein stenosis: a <lb/>promising tool. JACC Case Rep. (2023) 24:102021. doi: 10.1016/j.jaccas.2023.102021 <lb/>16. Kurita Y, Baba K, Kondo M, Eitoku T, Kasahara S, Iwasaki T, et al. Clinical outcomes <lb/>after the endovascular treatments of pulmonary vein stenosis in patients with congenital <lb/>heart disease. Cardiol Young. (2019) 29:1057-65. doi: 10.1017/S1047951119001495 <lb/>17. Yin D, Wu X, Xiang P, Zhang Y, Tian J, Lv T, et al. Outcomes of percutaneous <lb/>balloon pulmonary valvuloplasty in congenital pulmonary valve stenosis. Clin Case <lb/>Rep. (2021) 9:e04705. <lb/>18. Khan A, Qureshi AM, Justino H. Comparison of drug eluting versus bare metal <lb/>stents for pulmonary vein stenosis in childhood. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. (2019) <lb/>94:233-42. doi: 10.1002/ccd.28328 <lb/>19. Hickey EJ, Caldarone CA. Surgical management of post-repair pulmonary vein <lb/>stenosis. Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg Pediatr Card Surg Annu. (2011) 14:101-8. <lb/>doi: 10.1053/j.pcsu.2011.01.007 <lb/>20. Feins EN, Ireland C, Gauvreau K, Chavez M, Callahan R, Jenkins KJ, et al. <lb/>Pulmonary vein stenosis: anatomic considerations, surgical management, and outcomes. <lb/>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2022) 163:2198-207.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2021.10.022 <lb/>21. Salmi M. Additive manufacturing processes in medical applications. Materials <lb/>(Basel). (2021) 14:191-207. doi: 10.3390/ma14010191 <lb/>22. Helman SN, Soriano RM, Tomov ML, Serpooshan V, Levy JM, Pradilla G, et al. <lb/>Ventilated upper airway endoscopic endonasal procedure mask: surgical safety in the <lb/>COVID-19 era. Oper Neurosurg (Hagerstown). (2020) 19:271-80. doi: 10.1093/ons/ <lb/>opaa168 <lb/>23. Cetnar A, Tomov M, Theus A, Lima B, Vaidya A, Serpooshan V. &quot;3D <lb/>bioprinting in clinical cardiovascular medicine.&quot; In: Guvendiren M, editor. 3D <lb/>Bioprinting in Medicine: Technologies, Bioinks, and Applications. Cham: Springer <lb/>International Publishing (2019). p. 149-62. <lb/>24. Jin Z, Li Y, Yu K, Liu L, Fu J, Yao X, et al. 3D printing of physical organ models: <lb/>recent developments and challenges. Adv Sci (Weinh). (2021) 8:e2101394. doi: 10. <lb/>1002/advs.202101394 <lb/>25. Sun Z. Patient-specific 3D-printed models in pediatric congenital heart disease. <lb/>Children (Basel). (2023) 10:319-46. doi: 10.3390/children10020319 <lb/>26. Sun Z, Wee C. 3D printed models in cardiovascular disease: an exciting future to <lb/>deliver personalized medicine. Micromachines (Basel). (2022) 13:1575-605. doi: 10. <lb/>3390/mi13101575 <lb/>27. Anwar S, Singh GK, Miller J, Sharma M, Manning P, Billadello JJ, et al. 3D <lb/>printing is a transformative technology in congenital heart disease. JACC Basic <lb/>Transl Sci. (2018) 3:294-312. doi: 10.1016/j.jacbts.2017.10.003 <lb/>28. Grab M, Hopfner C, Gesenhues A, Konig F, Haas NA, Hagl C, et al. Development <lb/>and evaluation of 3D-printed cardiovascular phantoms for interventional planning and <lb/>training. J Vis Exp. (2021) (167):112-30. doi: 10.3791/62063 <lb/>29. Tomov ML, Perez L, Ning L, Chen H, Jing B, Mingee A, et al. A 3D bioprinted in <lb/>vitro model of pulmonary artery atresia to evaluate endothelial cell response to <lb/>microenvironment. Adv Healthc Mater. (2022) 11:e2201227. doi: 10.1002/adhm. <lb/>202201227 <lb/>30. Salman HE, Yalcin HC. Computational modeling of blood flow hemodynamics <lb/>for biomechanical investigation of cardiac development and disease. J Cardiovasc Dev <lb/>Dis. (2021) 8:14-41. doi: 10.3390/jcdd8020014 <lb/>31. Leinan PR, Gronli T, Skjetne P, Wigen MS, Urheim S, Lovstakken L, et al. <lb/>Comparison of ultrasound vector flow imaging and CFD simulations with PIV <lb/>measurements of flow in a left ventricular outflow trackt phantom-implications for <lb/>clinical use and in silico studies. Comput Biol Med. (2022) 146:105358. doi: 10. <lb/>1016/j.compbiomed.2022.105358 <lb/>32. Xu L, Yang M, Ye L, Dong Z. Computational fluid dynamics analysis and PIV <lb/>validation of a bionic vortex flow pulsatile LVAD. Technol Health Care. (2015) 23 <lb/>(Suppl 2):S443-51. doi: 10.3233/THC-150981 <lb/>33. D&apos;Avenio G, Wang G, Li Y, Rafiroiu D, De Angelis G, Grigioni M. &quot;PIV and <lb/>CFD insight into the hinge and near-hinge flow fields of bileaflet mechanical heart <lb/>valves&quot;. In: Kyriacou E, Christofides S, Pattichis CS, editors. XIV Mediterranean <lb/>Conference on Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing 2016. Cham: <lb/>Springer International Publishing (2016). p. 694-9. <lb/>34. Tomov ML, Cetnar A, Do K, Bauser-Heaton H, Serpooshan V. Patient-specific <lb/>3-dimensional-bioprinted model for in vitro analysis and treatment planning of <lb/>pulmonary artery atresia in tetralogy of Fallot and major aortopulmonary collateral <lb/>arteries. J Am Heart Assoc. (2019) 8:e014490. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.119.014490 <lb/>35. Romarowski RM, Lefieux A, Morganti S, Veneziani A, Auricchio F. Patient-<lb/>specific CFD modelling in the thoracic aorta with PC-MRI-based boundary <lb/>conditions: a least-square three-element Windkessel approach. Int J Numer Method <lb/>Biomed Eng. (2018) 34:e3134. doi: 10.1002/cnm.3134 <lb/>36. Bove EL, de Leval MR, Migliavacca F, Guadagni G, Dubini G. Computational <lb/>fluid dynamics in the evaluation of hemodynamic performance of cavopulmonary <lb/>connections after the Norwood procedure for hypoplastic left heart syndrome. <lb/>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. (2003) 126:1040-7. doi: 10.1016/s0022-5223(03)00698-6 <lb/>37. Chen L-J, Tong Z-R, Wang Q, Zhang Y-Q, Liu J-L. Feasibility of computational <lb/>fluid dynamics for evaluating the intraventricular hemodynamics in single right <lb/>ventricle based on echocardiographic images. Biomed Res Int. (2018) 2018:1042038. <lb/>doi: 10.1155/2018/1042038 <lb/>38. Gosling RC, Morris PD, Lawford PV, Hose DR, Gunn JP. Predictive <lb/>physiological modeling of percutaneous coronary intervention-is virtual treatment <lb/>planning the future? Front Physiol. (2018) 9:1107. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2018.01107 <lb/>39. Duraiswamy N, Schoephoerster RT, Moore JE Jr. Comparison of near-wall <lb/>hemodynamic parameters in stented artery models. J Biomech Eng. (2009) <lb/>131:061006. doi: 10.1115/1.3118764 <lb/>40. Cadena M, Ning L, King A, Hwang B, Jin L, Serpooshan V, et al. 3D bioprinting <lb/>of neural tissues. Adv Healthc Mater. (2020) 10:e2001600. doi: 10.1002/adhm. <lb/>202001600 <lb/>41. Ning L, Zanella S, Tomov ML, Amoli MS, Jin L, Hwang B, et al. Targeted <lb/>rapamycin delivery via magnetic nanoparticles to address stenosis in a 3D <lb/>bioprinted in vitro model of pulmonary veins. Adv Sci (Weinh). (2024):e2400476. <lb/>In press. doi: 10.1002/advs.202400476 <lb/>42. Fedorov A, Beichel R, Kalpathy-Cramer J, Finet J, Fillion-Robin JC, Pujol S, et al. <lb/>3D slicer as an image computing platform for the quantitative imaging network. Magn <lb/>Reson Imaging. (2012) 30:1323-41. doi: 10.1016/j.mri.2012.05.001 <lb/>43. Kikinis R, Pieper SD, Vosburgh KG. &quot;3D slicer: a platform for subject-specific <lb/>image analysis, visualization, and clinical support&quot;. In: Jolesz FA, editor. <lb/>Intraoperative Imaging and Image-Guided Therapy. New York, NY: Springer <lb/>New York (2014). p. 277-89. <lb/>44. Chen Z, Yu H, Shi Y, Zhu M, Wang Y, Hu X, et al. Vascular remodelling relates <lb/>to an elevated oscillatory shear index and relative residence time in spontaneously <lb/>hypertensive rats. Sci Rep. (2017) 7:2007. doi: 10.1038/s41598-017-01906-x <lb/>45. Kabirian F, Mela P, Heying R. 4D printing applications in the development of <lb/>smart cardiovascular implants. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. (2022) 10:873453. doi: 10. <lb/>3389/fbioe.2022.873453 <lb/>46. Lee S, Serpooshan V, Tong X, Venkatraman S, Lee M, Lee J, et al. Contractile <lb/>force generation by 3D hiPSC-derived cardiac tissues is enhanced by rapid <lb/>establishment of cellular interconnection in matrix with muscle-mimicking stiffness. <lb/>Biomaterials. (2017) 131:111-20. doi: 10.1016/j.biomaterials.2017.03.039 <lb/>47. Tomov ML, Gil CJ, Cetnar A, Theus AS, Lima BJ, Nish JE, et al. Engineering <lb/>functional cardiac tissues for regenerative medicine applications. Curr Cardiol Rep. <lb/>(2019) 21:105. doi: 10.1007/s11886-019-1178-9 <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">Devlin et al. <lb/>10.3389/fcvm.2024.1432784 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/></note>

	<page>11 <lb/></page>

	<note place="footnote">frontiersin.org </note>


  </text>

</TEI>