<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-24T16:00:26.487Z">11/24/2025 4:00:26 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-24T16:00:13.236573Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-24T16:00:13.236573Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>ech <lb/>T <lb/>Press <lb/>Science <lb/>DOI: 10.32604/cmc.2023.044612 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Image Inpainting Technique Incorporating Edge Prior and Attention <lb/>Mechanism <lb/>Jinxian Bai, Yao Fan * , Zhiwei Zhao and Lizhi Zheng <lb/>College of Information Engineering, Xizang Minzu University, Xianyang, 712000, China <lb/>*Corresponding Author: Yao Fan. Email: fannyaoo@xzmu.edu.cn <lb/>Received: 04 August 2023 Accepted: 24 November 2023 Published: 30 January 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Recently, deep learning-based image inpainting methods have made great strides in reconstructing damaged <lb/>regions. However, these methods often struggle to produce satisfactory results when dealing with missing images <lb/>with large holes, leading to distortions in the structure and blurring of textures. To address these problems, we <lb/>combine the advantages of transformers and convolutions to propose an image inpainting method that incorporates <lb/>edge priors and attention mechanisms. The proposed method aims to improve the results of inpainting large <lb/>holes in images by enhancing the accuracy of structure restoration and the ability to recover texture details. This <lb/>method divides the inpainting task into two phases: edge prediction and image inpainting. Specifically, in the edge <lb/>prediction phase, a transformer architecture is designed to combine axial attention with standard self-attention. <lb/>This design enhances the extraction capability of global structural features and location awareness. It also balances <lb/>the complexity of self-attention operations, resulting in accurate prediction of the edge structure in the defective <lb/>region. In the image inpainting phase, a multi-scale fusion attention module is introduced. This module makes <lb/>full use of multi-level distant features and enhances local pixel continuity, thereby significantly improving the <lb/>quality of image inpainting. To evaluate the performance of our method, comparative experiments are conducted <lb/>on several datasets, including CelebA, Places2, and Facade. Quantitative experiments show that our method <lb/>outperforms the other mainstream methods. Specifically, it improves Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR) and <lb/>Structure Similarity Index Measure (SSIM) by 1.141∼3.234 db and 0.083∼0.235, respectively. Moreover, it reduces <lb/>Learning Perceptual Image Patch Similarity (LPIPS) and Mean Absolute Error (MAE) by 0.0347∼0.1753 and <lb/>0.0104∼0.0402, respectively. Qualitative experiments reveal that our method excels at reconstructing images with <lb/>complete structural information and clear texture details. Furthermore, our model exhibits impressive performance <lb/>in terms of the number of parameters, memory cost, and testing time. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Image inpainting; transformer; edge prior; axial attention; multi-scale fusion attention <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Image inpainting is a challenging computer vision task that aims to construct visually appealing <lb/>and semantically plausible content for missing regions. It has various practical applications, including <lb/>restoring damaged photos [1], removing unwanted objects [2], and enhancing image resolution [3]. <lb/></body>

	<page>1000 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Initially, traditional diffusion-based methods [4,5] were used for image inpainting. These methods <lb/>gradually spread pixel information into the surrounding areas of damaged regions and synthesize <lb/>new textures to fill the holes. While effective for repairing small damaged areas like cracks, these <lb/>methods tend to produce blurry results as the size of the missing regions grows. Pioneering sample-<lb/>based methods were then developed for image inpainting [6,7] which synthesize texture by searching <lb/>for matching similar sample blocks in the undamaged areas of the image and copying them to the <lb/>corresponding positions in the missing regions. These approaches often produce high-quality texture <lb/>but may introduce incorrect structure and semantics in the restoration. <lb/>With the rapid advancement of deep learning in image processing tasks, researchers worldwide <lb/>have introduced various deep learning techniques to tackle these challenges. Convolutional neural <lb/>networks (CNNs) [8-10] have been widely adopted in methods that follow an encoder-decoder archi-<lb/>tecture and incorporate the adversarial idea of generative adversarial networks (GANs) [11]. These <lb/>methods aim to reconstruct missing regions by learning high-level semantic features. Nonetheless, the <lb/>localized inductive bias of convolutional operations and the limited receptive field make it difficult for <lb/>the model to learn globally consistent textures in semantics. To address these limitations, attention <lb/>mechanisms have been introduced in methods [12,13] to find the most similar feature blocks to <lb/>the masked regions in the feature space of known regions. This enables long-distance feature block <lb/>matching. However, for images with large missing regions, the attention mechanism cannot provide <lb/>sufficient information for restoration, resulting in blurred texture details and increased artifacts in <lb/>the restoration results. In comparison to CNN-based methods, transformer-based solutions [14,15] <lb/>leverage the strengths of transformers in capturing long-term correlations and extracting global <lb/>features to reconstruct low-resolution images and then provide CNN-based upsamplers to restore <lb/>texture details. Nonetheless, the above restoration scheme ignores the significance of the overall image <lb/>structure, resulting in inconsistent boundaries and a lack of semantics in the results. Moreover, there <lb/>are high computational and storage costs associated with model training and inference processes. Some <lb/>methods use edge [16], gradient [17], or semantic [18,19] information for structural restoration. For <lb/>example, Nazeri et al. [20] utilized the Canny operator to extract edge information from the defective <lb/>region. Subsequently, the refinement network utilizes the reconstructed edge maps as structural <lb/>information to guide the content repair continuously, which enhances the repair of structural details <lb/>to a certain extent. Differently, Xiong et al. [21] utilized predicted foreground contour maps to <lb/>guide image completion, ensuring the rationality of image content filling and avoiding overlap with <lb/>foreground objects. However, the above inpainting methods based on structural constraints have <lb/>certain limitations. Firstly, due to the spatial invariance and local induction priors of convolutional <lb/>neural networks, they may not perform well in understanding global structures, leading to subpar edge <lb/>prediction results. Secondly, many factors influence successful texture synthesis in image inpainting. <lb/>While focusing on structural details is important, successful texture synthesis also requires the effective <lb/>utilization of long-range features to capture rich contextual information. <lb/>To address these issues, this paper presents a two-stage image inpainting framework that combines <lb/>edge prior and attention mechanism (EPAM). Our framework uses the transformer architecture to <lb/>accurately predict the edge structure of the defect area. Then in the image inpainting stage, effective <lb/>edge structures are used to constrain the image content, so as to reconstruct visually plausible and <lb/>texture-clear images. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1001 <lb/></page>

	<body>In summary, the contributions of this paper are as follows: <lb/>(1) In the edge prediction phase, this paper proposes an efficient transformer-based edge pre-<lb/>diction (TEP) module to accurately extract edges of incomplete regions. Unlike existing CNN-based <lb/>methods, our TEP module achieves more accurate and comprehensive structural restoration. In the <lb/>TEP module, axial attention with relative position encoding is used. This improves position awareness <lb/>while significantly reducing computational complexity, ensuring a balance between performance and <lb/>efficiency. <lb/>(2) In the image inpainting phase, a multi-scale fusion attention (MFA) module is designed. This <lb/>module aggregates contextual feature information at different levels using dilated convolutions with <lb/>varying ratios. Additionally, an efficient channel attention mechanism is applied to reduce the impact <lb/>of redundant features. Furthermore, the attention transfer network is introduced to fully integrate <lb/>shallow texture details and deep semantic features, thereby avoiding unreasonable or contradictory <lb/>regions in generated images. This allows our model to accurately reconstruct texture details under the <lb/>guidance of the edge structure. <lb/>(3) Experiments are carried out by comparing the EPAM model to existing state-of-the-art <lb/>approaches. The EPAM model demonstrates superior performance in both qualitative and quanti-<lb/>tative assessments, as observed in the CelebA [22], Facade [23], and Places2 [24] datasets. <lb/>2 Related Work <lb/>In recent years, many methods have been proposed to improve the results of image inpainting <lb/>by incorporating prior knowledge of image structure. For example, Liao et al. [25] built upon the <lb/>CE [8] and introduced an edge-aware context encoder to predict the image edge structure. This <lb/>approach facilitated the learning of scene structure and context. However, the inpainted regions in <lb/>their results often suffered from significant blurring and artifacts. Cao et al. [26] utilized an encoder-<lb/>decoder structure to learn a sketch tensor space composed of edges, lines, and connection points. <lb/>They also introduced a gated convolution and attention module to enhance local details under cost-<lb/>saving conditions. However, this design is not suitable for structural restoration in facial or similar <lb/>scenes. Some methods have also attempted to incorporate both image structure and texture details <lb/>to guide image completion. For example, Liao et al. [19] designed a semantic segmentation guidance <lb/>and evaluation mechanism to interact to iteratively update semantic information and repair images. <lb/>Nonetheless, obtaining accurate semantic information for images with complex backgrounds can be <lb/>challenging. Guo et al. [16] proposed a method that shares information between the two branches <lb/>of texture generation and structure prediction. They also fused an attention module with learnable <lb/>parameters to further enhance global consistency. Nevertheless, when applied to recover natural <lb/>images with irregular defects, such coupled methods often lack explicit structural details. <lb/>Transformer [27] was originally proposed as a sequence-to-sequence model for machine trans-<lb/>lation tasks and was later improved and applied to computer vision tasks such as object detection, <lb/>video processing, and image processing [28]. Researchers have recently started exploring the use of <lb/>transformers for image restoration problems. Wan et al. [14] were among the first to use transformers <lb/>for image inpainting. They employed bi-directional attention and a masked language model objective <lb/>similar to BERT [29] to reconstruct low-resolution images with diverse appearances. Zheng et al. [30] <lb/>designed a mask-aware transformer content reasoning model, which uses a restricted convolutional <lb/>neural network module to extract tokens. In this model, the transformer encoder uses a replacement <lb/>weighted self-attention layer to capture the global context, reducing Proximity dominant effects that <lb/></body>

	<page>1002 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>give rise to semantically incoherent results. Nevertheless, this method cannot understand and imagine <lb/>high-level semantic content. <lb/>The existing image inpainting methods based on structural constraints ignore the positive influ-<lb/>ence of long-distance features when dealing with large-area irregular defects. Once the reconstructed <lb/>structure is missing or incorrect, the repair effect obviously deteriorates. It is worth noting that the <lb/>above transformer-based methods primarily focus on image reconstruction to obtain low-resolution <lb/>repaired images. However, one limitation of such methods is their long inference time, which can be a <lb/>drawback in practical applications. For the structural reconstruction problem, edge maps are preferred <lb/>over smooth or semantic images as they provide accurate structural information of images and have <lb/>stronger resistance to noise and other interference factors. This paper therefore introduces a novel <lb/>TEP module that uses the transformer to reconstruct the overall edge structure of an image. The TEP <lb/>module outperforms CNN-based methods in terms of performance. To address the issue of artifacts in <lb/>the restoration results, where texture details and inconsistent boundaries, this paper proposes the MFA <lb/>module. This module enhances the texture inference ability and independently synthesizes new content <lb/>in regions lacking structural information by mining distant features at different levels. In general, the <lb/>EPAM model performs structure prediction and texture generation for images by decoupling, which <lb/>improves the model&apos;s representational ability and ensures the consistency of the overall structure and <lb/>detailed texture of the restored images. <lb/>3 Proposed Method <lb/>This paper proposes an image inpainting model that combines structural priors and attention <lb/>mechanisms. The overall model architecture is shown in Fig. 1. The model consists of two cascaded <lb/>generative adversarial networks (GANs), where the output of the first-stage generator serves as the <lb/>input of the second-stage generator. These two-stage networks together form an end-to-end inpainting <lb/>model. In the first stage, the edge prediction network utilizes grayscale inpainted images and incom-<lb/>plete edge information to predict plausible edge contours within the defect regions. Subsequently, the <lb/>second-stage network utilizes the edge prediction map as a structural prior along with the incomplete <lb/>RGB image to synthesize suitable texture details within a locally enclosed region surrounded by edges. <lb/>This process ultimately completes the inpainting task. <lb/>In the edge prediction stage, the autoencoder serves as the generator of the edge prediction <lb/>network, while the PatchGAN architecture is the discriminator. In view of this, this paper proposes <lb/>the transformer-based edge prediction (TEP) module, which is embedded into the information <lb/>bottleneck section of the autoencoder. Notably, instead of using deeply stacked convolutional layers, <lb/>the TEP module uses a transformer-based architecture that allows all visible pixels to have equal flow <lb/>opportunities, resulting in expressive global structures. In addition, relative position encoding [31] and <lb/>axial attention blocks [32] are introduced into the TEP module, to enhance spatial relations and reduce <lb/>memory overhead. Existing attention-based models often suffer from color discrepancies, blurriness, <lb/>and boundary distortions in the inpainted images. To address these issues, the Multi-scale Fusion <lb/>Attention (MFA) module is introduced. Cascaded MFA modules are integrated after the encoder. <lb/>The MFA module captures deep features in different receptive fields by using dilated convolution with <lb/>varying expansion rates so as to better integrate global contextual information with local details. Then, <lb/>an Attention Transfer Network (ATN) [33] is constructed on feature maps at four scales to enhance <lb/>local pixel continuity and make effective use of long-distance dependencies, which notably improves <lb/>the quality of image inpainting. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1003 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 1: Overall network structure. Our proposed EPAM is made up of two sub-networks. The upper <lb/>half is the edge prediction network, and the lower half is the image inpainting network <lb/>The edge prediction network contains a generator G 1 and a discriminator D 1 . Similarly, the image <lb/>inpainting network consists of a generator G 2 and a discriminator D 2 . I t , I gs , and E t are the original <lb/>image, the corresponding grayscale map, and the edge structure map, respectively. In the binary mask <lb/>I M , the value 1 denotes the hole region pixels and the value 0 denotes the other region pixels. Then, <lb/>the incomplete image is expressed as I M <lb/>t <lb/>= I t <lb/>(1 -I M ), incomplete grayscale image as I M <lb/>gs = I gs <lb/>(1 -I M ), and the defective edges as E M <lb/>t = E t <lb/>(1 -I M ), where is element-wise product operation. <lb/>Then the edge prediction follows the following Eq. (1): <lb/>E pred = G 1 I M <lb/>gs , E M <lb/>t , I M , <lb/>E comp = E M <lb/>t + E pred <lb/>I M , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where E comp is the synthesized edge prediction map. The operation of the image generator is denoted <lb/>by G 2 (•). The following Eq. (2) represents the process of image restoration: <lb/>I pred = G 2 I M <lb/>t , E comp . <lb/>(2) <lb/>Finally, the inpainting output with the same original size is obtained by using Eq. (3). <lb/>I output = I M <lb/>t + I pred <lb/>I M . <lb/>(3) <lb/></body>

	<page>1004 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>3.1 Edge Prediction Network <lb/>3.1.1 Transformer-Based Edge Prediction Module <lb/>The transformer architecture was originally used to solve natural language processing (NLP) <lb/>tasks. This architecture is entirely based on self-attention and can directly model longer-distance <lb/>dependencies between input sequences. Recently, researchers have applied it to computer vision tasks <lb/>and achieved remarkable results. Inspired by ViT [34], this paper introduces the transformer decoder <lb/>from [27] into the TEP module and then reconstructs the edge information based on the shallow <lb/>features of the encoder&apos;s output. <lb/>In Fig. 2, the input feature of the TEP module is represented as F ∈ R H×W ×C with height H, width <lb/>W, and channels C, specifically 32 × 32 × 256. The input is reshaped using the View operation to obtain <lb/>F in <lb/>E = R C×D , (D = H × W ). The processed input F in <lb/>E is then embedded in the positional encoding PE <lb/>and fed into the Transformer Decoder. The output feature Y after position coding is defined as Eq. (4). <lb/>Figure 2: Architecture of the proposed transformer-based edge prediction (TEP) module <lb/>Y = F in <lb/>E + PE F in <lb/>E <lb/>(4) <lb/>To reduce the consumption of feature map computation and storage in the self-attention layer, <lb/>both the axial attention module and the standard attention module were introduced in the TEP <lb/>module. Axial attention modules can be implemented by reshaping tensors on the width and height <lb/>axes, which are then processed with dot-product-based self-attention, respectively. As shown in Fig. 3, <lb/>uni-directional attention only focuses on the contextual constraints before the token. Although bi-<lb/>directional attention can pay attention to all positions before and after the token, its computational <lb/>complexity up to is O n 2 . Axial attention can be the available context in the row and column directions <lb/>of the token (i.e., focus on the available information before and after the token), which makes the <lb/>model more efficient, in addition to the lower computational complexity of axial attention, which is <lb/>only O 2n <lb/>3 <lb/>2 . To ensure stable training, layer normalization [35] is applied before the features Y are <lb/>fed into the axial attention module. In addition, a learnable relative position encoding (RPE) [31] is <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1005 <lb/></page>

	<body>provided for this module to improve the spatial relationship and the accuracy and effect of inpainting. <lb/>The following Eq. (5) is the formula of the axial attention score based on the width axis and height axis. <lb/>y hi and y hj are the feature vectors of columns i and j of the height axis of Y . W wq , W wk , W hq , and W hk are <lb/>the weight matrix of queries and keys in the width and height axis; R width <lb/>i,j <lb/>is the relative position encoding <lb/>matrix between the width axis i and j; R height <lb/>i,j <lb/>is the relative position encoding matrix between the height <lb/>axis i and j. The scaling factor <lb/>√ <lb/>d is to find the gradient more stable when backward spreading. <lb/>Attention <lb/>width <lb/>i,j <lb/>= y wi W wq y wj W wk <lb/>T / <lb/>√ <lb/>d + R width <lb/>i,j <lb/>, <lb/>Attention <lb/>height <lb/>i,j <lb/>= y hi W hq y hj W hk <lb/>T / <lb/>√ <lb/>d + R height <lb/>i,j <lb/>(5) <lb/>The attention weights are obtained by Softmax operation. The output Ŷ of the axial attention <lb/>layer is given by Eq. (6). <lb/>Ŷ = softmax Attention <lb/>width <lb/>i,j <lb/>y wj W wv + softmax Attention <lb/>height <lb/>i,j <lb/>y hj W hv + Y <lb/>(6) <lb/>(a) Masked Input <lb/>(b) Uni-directional attention(c) Bi-directional attention <lb/>(d) Axial attention <lb/>Figure 3: Differences between uni-directional, bi-directional and axial attention <lb/>Then, the layer Ŷ is normalized to a standard normal distribution to speed up the training and <lb/>convergence of the model, which is then fed into the multilayer perceptron (MLP) for computation. <lb/>Additionally, residual connections are added to make the matrix operation dimension consistent while <lb/>preventing the network from degrading. In Fig. 2, LN is layer normalization. MLP consists of 2 fully <lb/>connected layers (FC), an activation function, and a residual dropout layer. The first FC converts <lb/>D-dimension features to 4D-dimension features, which are then converted to D-dimension features <lb/>by the second FC. In the middle, GELU servers a nonlinear activation function. Finally, the residual <lb/>dropout layer is regularized to prevent overfitting. This process is shown in Eq. (7). <lb/>Ŷ = MLP LN Ŷ + Ŷ <lb/>(7) <lb/>In addition, the standard attention module Attention norm is utilized to learn the global correlation, <lb/>and then repeat the process of Eq. (7) to obtain the final output Ŷ <lb/>out . The specific process is defined as <lb/>the following Eqs. (8) and (9). <lb/>Ŷ = Attention norm LN Ŷ <lb/>+ Ŷ , <lb/>(8) <lb/>Ŷ <lb/>out = MLP LN Ŷ <lb/>+ Ŷ <lb/>(9) <lb/>3.1.2 Design of Edge Generator and Discriminator <lb/>The edge generator in this paper follows a self-encoder structure to predict edges through encoder <lb/>data compression, bottleneck layer feature reconstruction, and decoder decompression for a given <lb/></body>

	<page>1006 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>image feature F 1 <lb/>in ∈ R H×W ×C . In the encoding stage, the encoder first uses a 7 × 7 convolution with <lb/>a reflective padding parameter of 3 and a stride of 1 to obtain rich features, which will adjust F 1 <lb/>in <lb/>to a size of 256 × 256 × 64. Then three consecutive 4 × 4 convolution layers with a stride of 2 are <lb/>applied to obtain a shallow feature F 1 <lb/>s with a dimension of 32 × 32 × 256. Different from patch-<lb/>based embedding methods, the above convolution operation injects a beneficial convolution inductive <lb/>bias for the TEP module. The bottleneck layer does not use the convolution-based residual block <lb/>but chooses to stack eight TEP modules based on the transformer structure to form the information <lb/>bottleneck layer to enhance the representation ability of feature information and the ability to capture <lb/>global structural information, and then complete the missing edge information. Unlike convolutions, <lb/>self-attention mechanisms can capture non-local information from the entire feature map. However, <lb/>the computational cost of the similarity calculation is quite large. To address this, the TEP module, the <lb/>alternating use of the axial attention layer and the standard attention layer is adopted. This ensures that <lb/>the generator utilizes the global context information to complete image edges that align with overall <lb/>semantics while considering the performance and parameter quantity of the transformer. In addition, <lb/>the axial attention layer can acquire multi-directional features by separately computing attention on <lb/>the height and width axis, thereby enhancing the orientation awareness of feature maps. After passing <lb/>through the bottleneck layer, a reconstructed feature with a dimension of 32 × 32 × 256 is obtained. <lb/>The features are then upsampled to 256 × 256 × 64 by using a 3-layer transposed convolution with <lb/>a convolution kernel size of 4 × 4, zero padding of 1, and a stride of 2. Subsequently, the output is <lb/>adjusted to 256 × 256 × 1 through a convolution with a convolution kernel size of 7 × 7, a reflection <lb/>filling parameter of 3, and a step size of 1, so the predicted complete edge map is obtained. In addition, <lb/>each convolutional layer of the edge generator adopts instance normalization, which speeds up the <lb/>model convergence while improving the nonlinear representation of the feature extraction module. <lb/>Additionally, a ReLU activation function is applied immediately after each convolutional layer to <lb/>reduce the gradient disappearance phenomenon. <lb/>To improve the network&apos;s attention to local details during training, the PatchGAN [36] architec-<lb/>ture is used as the basic framework of the edge discriminator. It consists of 5 layers of convolution <lb/>with strides of 2, 2, 2, 1, 1 and a kernel size of 4 × 4. Spectral normalization [37] and the Leaky-<lb/>ReLU activation function are applied after each convolutional layer. After 5 layers of convolution <lb/>operations, the input image is converted into a single-channel feature map with dimensions of 30 × <lb/>30. Ultimately, the Sigmod function is used to map the output to a scalar in the range of [0, 1], which <lb/>can effectively distinguish the authenticity of the input samples and promote the generation of high-<lb/>quality restoration results. <lb/>3.2 Image Inpainting Network <lb/>3.2.1 Multi-Scale Fusion Attention Module <lb/>In the texture synthesis stage, traditional methods often extract feature information from shallow <lb/>details to high-level semantics through convolutional layer stacking. However, this approach has <lb/>limitations. The extraction of rich spatial structural information and texture details is performed <lb/>serially with a fixed-size convolutional kernel, leading to varying degrees of feature loss. This also <lb/>exacerbates inconsistency in global contextual information and causes difficulty in capturing global <lb/>structural information from distant pixels. To address this problem, the MFA module is introduced. <lb/>It first extracts information at different scales in parallel by applying convolution operations with <lb/>different expansion factors to the input features. Then, the features at each scale are scaled and fed <lb/>into the ATN module to facilitate the transfer of information between features at different levels. This <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1007 <lb/></page>

	<body>helps the model to better understand the details and structures in the image, resulting in improved <lb/>restoration quality and accuracy. In addition, the utilization of efficient channel attention [38] and pixel <lb/>attention [39] enables the model to selectively focus on important channels and pixels, thus reducing <lb/>unnecessary computations and parametric quantities. The residual structure and skip connections help <lb/>to avoid gradient explosion and network convergence difficulties. See Fig. 4 for details. <lb/>Figure 4: Architecture of the proposed multi-scale fusion attention (MFA) module <lb/>Specifically, a 1 × 1 convolution operation is used to transform the dimension of the input feature <lb/>F in of the MFA module from 64 × 64 × 256 to 64 × 64 × 64. This paper uses f 1×1 (•) to represent the 1 × <lb/>1 convolution operation, and τ to represent the instance normalization and ReLU activation function. <lb/>The transformed input feature F is shown in Eq. (10) as follows: <lb/>F = τ (f 1×1 (F in )) <lb/>(10) <lb/>Subsequently, Parallel expansion convolution is used to extract multilevel features FRi <lb/>C with <lb/>expansion rates Ri of 8, 4, 2, and 1 (i = 1,2,3,4) and convolution size of 3 × 3. Convolution with <lb/>a smaller expansion rate can better perceive texture and position information whereas convolution <lb/>with a larger one can perceive advanced and global feature information. Then, the Efficient Channel <lb/>Attention (ECA) module is introduced, which effectively captures the information of cross-channel <lb/>interactions and reduces the effect of redundant features. The computational formula can be expressed <lb/>by the following Eq. (11): <lb/>FRi <lb/>C = ECA τ f Ri <lb/>3×3 <lb/>F <lb/>(11) <lb/>Since deep feature maps are usually more compact, scaling is applied to the features of each layer. <lb/>f Si <lb/>ds (•) is the bilinear interpolation downsampling operation with scaling factor Si. As shown in Fig. 4, <lb/></body>

	<page>1008 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>the scaling factor Si is 1/8, 1/4, 1/2, and 1 in turn. The scaling process defines the following Eq. (12). <lb/>F i <lb/>ds = f Si <lb/>ds <lb/>FRi <lb/>C <lb/>(12) <lb/>Then, Attention Transfer Network (ATN) [33] is introduced to guide the complementation of <lb/>low-level features layer by layer from high-level features, which makes the complementation content <lb/>semantically sound and texture clear. ATN (•) is the attention transfer operation, and F i <lb/>ATN is the feature <lb/>map reconstructed by the ATN of the i-th layer. The specific operation can be expressed as Eq. (13). <lb/>F i <lb/>ATN = ATN F i <lb/>ds , F i+1 <lb/>ds <lb/>(13) <lb/>Local residual connections are built on the feature map of the last ATN reconstruction to reduce <lb/>information loss. After 3 × 3 convolution, τ layer, ECA layer, and Pixel Attention (PA) layer, the <lb/>feature map F is obtained, which is defined as the following Eq. (14): <lb/>F 1 <lb/>res = PA ECA τ f 3×3 Concat FR1 <lb/>C , F <lb/>(14) <lb/>In addition, to ensure the consistency of local contextual feature information, operations such as <lb/>skip connection and 3 × 3 convolution are employed to fuse multilevel features F i <lb/>C of the same size <lb/>into a 64 × 64 × 128 feature map F 2 <lb/>res . Finally, the fused output of feature maps F 1 <lb/>res and F 2 <lb/>res is expressed <lb/>in the following Eq. (15): <lb/>F out <lb/>C = ECA τ f 3×3 Concat F 1 <lb/>res , F 2 <lb/>res <lb/>(15) <lb/>3.2.2 Design of Image Generator and Discriminator <lb/>Image generators are an improvement over autoencoders. Since the bottleneck layer does not <lb/>use the transformer structure, inputting a large-size feature map into the bottleneck layer will not <lb/>cause excessive computational complexity. In this case, the encoder only downsamples to a feature <lb/>map dimension of 64 × 64 × 256. To synthesize realistic textures in different regions, the bottleneck <lb/>layer employs stacked 4 MFA modules instead of fully connected layers. Through hierarchical atrous <lb/>convolutions and attention transfer strategies, the generator is able to synthesize semantically correct <lb/>new content independently even in the absence of local edge information. Otherwise, the image <lb/>generator has the same network structure and parameter settings as its counterpart in the edge <lb/>generator. <lb/>The image discriminator has a similar structure to the edge prediction discriminator. It uses <lb/>a 70 × 70 PatchGAN discriminator network, which consists of five layers of convolutions with a <lb/>kernel size of 4 × 4. The discriminator network performs spectral normalization and Leaky-ReLU <lb/>activation function processing after each layer of convolution operation. The output of the last <lb/>layer is a two-dimensional matrix of N × N, where each element corresponds to the true or false <lb/>value of a 70 × 70 region block. The average value of all elements is used as the output value <lb/>of the discriminator. Compared to the traditional GAN discriminator, the PatchGan discriminator <lb/>determines the authenticity of each Patch, which allows more attention to texture details and thus <lb/>improves the quality of the generated image. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1009 <lb/></page>

	<body>3.3 Loss Functions <lb/>3.3.1 Loss of Edge Prediction Network <lb/>To obtain a clear and realistic edge prediction map, the edge prediction network uses a joint loss for <lb/>model training, including adversarial loss [11] and feature matching loss [40]. Given the mathematical <lb/>expectation E, the discriminator function D 1 , the expression for the adversarial loss L 1 <lb/>adv can be written <lb/>as Eq. (16). <lb/>L 1 <lb/>adv = E Igs log 1 -D 1 E comp , I gs + E ( E t ,Igs ) log D 1 E t , I gs <lb/>(16) <lb/>The feature matching loss L fm evaluates the quality of generated edges by measuring the Euclidean <lb/>distance between the predicted edge and the original edge in the feature space. Let S denote the total <lb/>number of layers of D 1 , D k <lb/>1 denote the activation map of the k-th layer of D 1 , N k denote the number of <lb/>elements in D k <lb/>1 , and • denote the Euclidean distance. This loss can be defined as Eq. (17). <lb/>L fm = E <lb/>S <lb/>k=1 <lb/>1 <lb/>N k <lb/>D k <lb/>1 (E t ) -D k <lb/>1 E comp 1 <lb/>(17) <lb/>Let the loss weights α 1 <lb/>adv and α fm denote the weights of the adversarial loss and the feature matching <lb/>loss, respectively. The joint loss L E of the edge prediction network is expressed as the following Eq. (18): <lb/>L E = α 1 <lb/>adv L 1 <lb/>adv + α fm L fm <lb/>(18) <lb/>3.3.2 Loss of Image Inpainting Network <lb/>To ensure the image inpainting result has reasonable semantic content, consistent structure, and <lb/>clear texture, this paper uses various loss functions including adversarial loss, perceptual loss [41], style <lb/>loss [42], and reconstruction loss to train the image inpainting network. The network uses Eq. (19) to <lb/>represent the adversarial loss L 2 <lb/>adv . <lb/>L 2 <lb/>adv = E Ecomp log 1 -D 2 I pred , E comp + E ( I t ,I pred ) log D 2 I t , E comp <lb/>(19) <lb/>Next, the pre-trained VGG-19 [43] network is adopted to convert the differences between the <lb/>pixel values of the repaired image I pred and the real image I t into differences in the feature space so <lb/>as to better preserve the high-level semantic information of the images. The following Eq. (20) is the <lb/>formula of the perceptual loss L perc , where M k is the feature map size of the k-th layer, and ϕ k is the <lb/>feature representation of the k-th layer in the loss network. <lb/>L perc = E <lb/>k <lb/>1 <lb/>M k <lb/>ϕ k (I t ) -ϕ k I pred 1 , <lb/>(20) <lb/>Style loss usually uses the Gram matrix (gram) to calculate the difference of feature maps, <lb/>expressing the correlation of style features on different channels, so that the inpainted image is closer <lb/>to the reference image&apos;s style. Let G ϕ k = ϕ k <lb/>T (•) ϕ k (•) be the Gram matrix constructed by ϕ k . The style <lb/>loss L style is specifically defined as Eq. (21). <lb/>L style = E <lb/>k <lb/>G ϕ k (I t ) -G ϕ k I pred 1 , <lb/>(21) <lb/></body>

	<page>1010 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>The reconstruction loss L rec is minimized by the L 1 loss to calculate the absolute difference between <lb/>the output result I pred and the real image I t . This ensures that the overall contour of the result is roughly <lb/>consistent with the target. Its specific calculation process is shown in Eq. (22) below: <lb/>L rec = I pred -I t 1 . <lb/>(22) <lb/>The total loss L G 2 of the second-stage network is expressed by Eq. (23). <lb/>L G 2 = α 2 <lb/>adv L 2 <lb/>adv + α perc L perc + α style L style + α rec L rec . <lb/>(23) <lb/>4 Experiments <lb/>4.1 Experimental Design and Implementation <lb/>The experimental hardware configuration in this paper is a single Intel(R) Core i7-11700 CPU, <lb/>a single NVIDIA GeForce RTX 3090 24 GB GPU, 64.0 GB RAM, and the software environment is <lb/>Windows 10, Pytorch v1.7.0, CUDA v11.0. <lb/>4.1.1 Experimental Datasets <lb/>Training and evaluation were conducted on 3 publicly available datasets: CelebA [22], Facade <lb/>[23], and Places2 [24]. The CelebA dataset contains 202,599 face images of celebrities and was <lb/>commonly used in face-related computer vision experiments. The Places2 contains various unique <lb/>scene categories, such as restaurants, beaches, courtyards, valleys, etc. The Facade dataset mainly <lb/>consists of highly structured facades of cities worldwide. The distribution of the dataset in this paper <lb/>is shown in Table 1. In terms of irregular masks, the test set of the irregular mask dataset proposed <lb/>by Liu et al. [44] is adopted, which contains 12,000 masks equally divided into 6 intervals. During the <lb/>experiments, images were randomly masked using the mask test set with different scale ranges. All <lb/>images and irregular masks were resized to 256 × 256 pixels. <lb/>Table 1: Setup of the CelebA, Facade, and Places2 datasets <lb/>Dateset <lb/>Training set <lb/>Validation set <lb/>Test set <lb/>CelebA <lb/>182,599 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>Facade <lb/>556 <lb/>50 <lb/>50 <lb/>Places2 <lb/>225,000 <lb/>15,000 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>4.1.2 Parameter Settings <lb/>Referring to the parameter settings of the EC model, Both the two-stage network are trained with <lb/>Adam optimizer (β 1 = 0.0, β 2 = 0.9), the batch size is 8, and the initial learning rates of generator G 1 , <lb/>G 2 , and discriminator D 1 , D 2 are 1 × 10 -4 and 1 × 10 -5 , respectively. The experiments in this paper <lb/>learn to generate realistic samples faster by giving the generator a higher learning rate. In Table 2, this <lb/>paper conducts 5 sets of experiments on Attention head and embedding dimension. When the Multi-<lb/>Head Attention of the TEP module is set to 8 and the embedding dimension is set to 256, the model <lb/>parameter count is reasonable and the accuracy and recall are the highest. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1011 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2: Performance of edge prediction network with different combinations of hyperparameters <lb/>Heads <lb/>Embedding dims Params (M) <lb/>Precision <lb/>Recall <lb/>4 <lb/>256 <lb/>18.17 <lb/>0.3563 <lb/>0.3591 <lb/>8 <lb/>256 <lb/>18.17 <lb/>0.3635 <lb/>0.3695 <lb/>16 <lb/>256 <lb/>18.18 <lb/>0.3500 <lb/>0.3617 <lb/>8 <lb/>128 <lb/>6.08 <lb/>0.3522 <lb/>0.3646 <lb/>8 <lb/>512 <lb/>64.37 <lb/>0.3492 <lb/>0.3590 <lb/>For the weights of different loss terms in the two-stage model, this paper adjusted one weight at a <lb/>time for comparison experiments based on the parameter settings of the EC method. Specifically, <lb/>the network restarted training after adjusting the weight parameters each time. After 500 epochs, <lb/>the model ends training and is saved. Eventually, the loss weights α 1 <lb/>adv and α fm of the edge prediction <lb/>network were set to 1 and 15, respectively. The loss weights of the image restoration network were set <lb/>to α 2 <lb/>adv = 0.2, α perc = 0.1, α style = 200, and α rec = 0.5, respectively. As can be seen in Fig. 5, when α 1 <lb/>adv <lb/>is set to 0.8, there are breaks in the lines around the window. When α 1 <lb/>adv is set to 1.2, the predicted <lb/>edges look reasonable but the window in the middle of the mask is incorrectly predicted as a line. <lb/>When the weight of feature matching loss is 13.0, there are busy lines in the defective region, which <lb/>may affect the subsequent repair work. When the weight α fm is 17.0, the generation of lines beyond the <lb/>windows is unreasonable. As can be seen from Fig. 5c, according to the weights set in this article, the <lb/>model predicts lines with high local closure and consistent semantics. The experiments on the weights <lb/>for the second stage of the network were conducted with the assurance of the consistency of the edge <lb/>information used. As can be seen in Figs. 6c and 6d, too large or too small weights for adversarial <lb/>loss can adversely affect the color of the repaired windows. Other unreasonable weights also affect the <lb/>repair performance of the model. It can be seen from Fig. 6b that the weights set in this paper have <lb/>some advantages. On the one hand, the color consistency between the inside and outside of the holes <lb/>is enhanced, and on the other hand, the edges of the repair results are more visible. <lb/>Figure 5: Comparison of loss function weights of edge prediction network <lb/>4.1.3 Training Strategy <lb/>The training of the EPAM model involved three steps. First, G 1 was trained using grayscale images <lb/>and edge binary images as training samples. After the G 1 loss was balanced, the learning rate was <lb/>adjusted to 1 × 10 -5 for further training until the model converged, thereby generating a prediction <lb/>edge. Next, the complete image edge information detected by the Canny operator combined with the <lb/>damaged image was used as the input of G 2 to train G 2 separately. After the loss of the image generator <lb/>was balanced, the learning rate was lower to 1 × 10 -5 for continued training until convergence. Finally, <lb/></body>

	<page>1012 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>G 1 and G 2 were cascaded, and the edge discriminator D 1 was removed. After that, the generators G 1 <lb/>and G 2 were trained end-to-end at a learning rate of 1 × 10 -6 until the model converged. <lb/>Figure 6: Comparison of loss function weights of image inpainting network <lb/>4.1.4 Implementation Details <lb/>Fig. 7 shows the training loss plot of the proposed model on the Places2 dataset. Throughout <lb/>the training process, the loss values of the latest batch of data were recorded every 5000 iterations. <lb/>Both phases of the network underwent 2 million iterations each. Due to the large span of each loss <lb/>value in the network, the red area of the curve was enlarged for better visualization. Fig. 7a shows the <lb/>variation tendency of different loss functions during the training of the edge prediction network. The <lb/>adversarial loss of G 1 fluctuates within the range of (0.5, 1.7), and the adversarial loss of D 1 oscillates <lb/>in a smaller range of (0.45, 0.75). This indicates that G 1 and D 1 are undergoing adversarial training <lb/>and gradually approaching a balance. As the number of iterations increases, the feature matching <lb/>loss stabilizes the training by constraining the outputs of the intermediate layers of the discriminator. <lb/>As shown in Fig. 7b, the reconstruction loss, perceptual loss, and style loss gradually decline as the <lb/>training progresses. This suggests that the gap between generated samples and real samples at the <lb/>feature map or pixel level is narrowing, and the quality of generated samples is steadily improving. <lb/>4.2 Experimental Results and Analysis <lb/>To quantitatively evaluate the efficiency of the proposed EPAM model, this model is compared <lb/>with some of the advanced inpainting algorithms, including EC [20], CTSDG [16], ICT [14], MAT <lb/>[45], and PUT [46]. To reflect the generalization of the proposed method, irregular masks, center <lb/>rectangle masks, and human-labeled masks are randomly used to perform occlusion experiments on <lb/>samples for qualitative comparison. In addition, extensive quantitative comparisons, ablation studies, <lb/>and visualization analysis are conducted to demonstrate the effectiveness of TEP and MFA. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1013 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 7: Two-stage training loss line charts of the EPAM model <lb/>4.2.1 Quantitative Comparisons <lb/>Four commonly used metrics are applied to evaluate the inpainting results of the proposed method <lb/>and other methods for comparison. Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR) is a widely used objective <lb/>measurement for image quality, although its results may not align perfectly with human perception. <lb/>Structure Similarity Index Measure (SSIM) uses use three factors in line with human perception to <lb/>evaluate the similarity between images, namely brightness, contrast, and structure. The window size <lb/>used for SSIM calculation is set to 51. Learning Perceptual Image Patch Similarity (LPIPS) [47] <lb/>is a perception-based metric that quantifies the differences between images and can better reflect <lb/>human perception and understanding of images. Mean Absolute Error (MAE) refers to the average <lb/>absolute errors between two values. The evaluation scores of our method with those of state-of-the-art <lb/>approaches on datasets with irregular mask ratios of 20%-40%, 40%-60%, and random masks. <lb/>Table 3 presents the evaluation results on the CelebA dataset, where our model achieves the highest <lb/>scores in both PSNR and SSIM. However, in some cases, our model may not rank as high in terms of <lb/>LIPIPS and MAE. This discrepancy can be attributed to the use of dilated convolutions with different <lb/>expansion factors to capture multi-scale context information and long-distance feature information of <lb/>the defect image. The excessive zero-padding operation of the dilated convolution introduces certain <lb/>edge artifacts in the patched image, which may affect these indicators. Distinct from other metrics, <lb/>LPIPS compares the Euclidean distance between the repaired image and the feature representation <lb/>of the real image obtained at an intermediate layer of a deep neural network. Therefore, there may be <lb/>some similarities that cannot be captured by LPIPS, resulting in bias at the metric level. On the Facade <lb/>dataset, our algorithm outperforms other methods by a significant margin in the first two metrics. <lb/>This indicates that our algorithm is more effective in repairing fine structural details when dealing with <lb/>highly structured objects. On the Places2 dataset, even though both PUT and MAT use the transformer <lb/>architecture, our method consistently achieves superior performance across various metrics. This <lb/>demonstrates the effectiveness of the proposed transformer-based edge prediction strategy and the <lb/>multi-scale fusion attention strategy in improving the overall performance of the model. <lb/></body>

	<page>1014 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 3: Quantitative comparison results of our method with EC, CTSDG, ICT, MAT, PUT on <lb/>CelebA, Facade and Places2 datasets with different mask ratios. ↓ indicates the lower the better. ↑ <lb/>indicates higher the better. The best and second best results are in red and blue, respectively <lb/>Method Dataset <lb/>PSNR↑ <lb/>SSIM↑ <lb/>LPIPS↓ <lb/>MAE↓ <lb/>20-40% 40-60% Random <lb/>20-40% 40-60% Random <lb/>20-40% 40-60% Random <lb/>20-40% 40-60% Random <lb/>EC <lb/>CelebA <lb/>28.049 <lb/>24.800 <lb/>26.237 <lb/>0.940 <lb/>0.893 <lb/>0.916 <lb/>0.0568 <lb/>0.0882 <lb/>0.0786 <lb/>0.0195 <lb/>0.0279 <lb/>0.0232 <lb/>CTSDG <lb/>29.383 <lb/>26.836 <lb/>28.358 <lb/>0.955 <lb/>0.922 <lb/>0.941 <lb/>0.0518 <lb/>0.0846 <lb/>0.0700 <lb/>0.0144 <lb/>0.0207 <lb/>0.0165 <lb/>ICT <lb/>26.576 <lb/>24.770 <lb/>25.748 <lb/>0.914 <lb/>0.887 <lb/>0.902 <lb/>0.0663 <lb/>0.0945 <lb/>0.0820 <lb/>0.0241 <lb/>0.0292 <lb/>0.0257 <lb/>MAT <lb/>29.370 <lb/>27.096 <lb/>28.461 <lb/>0.952 <lb/>0.930 <lb/>0.945 <lb/>0.0635 <lb/>0.0770 <lb/>0.0680 <lb/>0.0176 <lb/>0.0220 <lb/>0.0183 <lb/>PUT <lb/>28.818 <lb/>26.174 <lb/>27.977 <lb/>0.946 <lb/>0.916 <lb/>0.940 <lb/>0.0468 <lb/>0.0674 <lb/>0.0549 <lb/>0.0163 <lb/>0.0222 <lb/>0.0171 <lb/>Ours <lb/>29.981 <lb/>27.722 <lb/>28.521 <lb/>0.955 <lb/>0.936 <lb/>0.945 <lb/>0.0523 <lb/>0.0760 <lb/>0.0708 <lb/>0.0159 <lb/>0.0214 <lb/>0.0190 <lb/>EC <lb/>Facade <lb/>22.282 <lb/>21.916 <lb/>21.825 <lb/>0.839 <lb/>0.783 <lb/>0.782 <lb/>0.1279 <lb/>0.1622 <lb/>0.1667 <lb/>0.0452 <lb/>0.0384 <lb/>0.0433 <lb/>CTSDG <lb/>23.586 <lb/>22.796 <lb/>23.090 <lb/>0.866 <lb/>0.808 <lb/>0.817 <lb/>0.1212 <lb/>0.1705 <lb/>0.1583 <lb/>0.0360 <lb/>0.0329 <lb/>0.0354 <lb/>ICT <lb/>23.751 <lb/>22.322 <lb/>22.729 <lb/>0.873 <lb/>0.810 <lb/>0.819 <lb/>0.0891 <lb/>0.1425 <lb/>0.1255 <lb/>0.0416 <lb/>0.0384 <lb/>0.0408 <lb/>MAT <lb/>24.332 <lb/>24.139 <lb/>23.098 <lb/>0.887 <lb/>0.856 <lb/>0.825 <lb/>0.0790 <lb/>0.0824 <lb/>0.1000 <lb/>0.0306 <lb/>0.0258 <lb/>0.0339 <lb/>PUT <lb/>23.095 <lb/>22.438 <lb/>22.372 <lb/>0.863 <lb/>0.809 <lb/>0.807 <lb/>0.0984 <lb/>0.1292 <lb/>0.1317 <lb/>0.0392 <lb/>0.0343 <lb/>0.0395 <lb/>Ours <lb/>27.023 <lb/>25.160 <lb/>26.290 <lb/>0.941 <lb/>0.895 <lb/>0.915 <lb/>0.0693 <lb/>0.0954 <lb/>0.0834 <lb/>0.0262 <lb/>0.0280 <lb/>0.0264 <lb/>EC <lb/>Places2 <lb/>21.741 <lb/>21.144 <lb/>21.424 <lb/>0.867 <lb/>0.784 <lb/>0.827 <lb/>0.1119 <lb/>0.1861 <lb/>0.1853 <lb/>0.0314 <lb/>0.0583 <lb/>0.0535 <lb/>CTSDG <lb/>23.275 <lb/>22.183 <lb/>23.052 <lb/>0.901 <lb/>0.820 <lb/>0.872 <lb/>0.1053 <lb/>0.1813 <lb/>0.1818 <lb/>0.0243 <lb/>0.0477 <lb/>0.0428 <lb/>ICT <lb/>23.213 <lb/>21.684 <lb/>21.946 <lb/>0.882 <lb/>0.815 <lb/>0.839 <lb/>0.0781 <lb/>0.1204 <lb/>0.1497 <lb/>0.0318 <lb/>0.0552 <lb/>0.0508 <lb/>MAT <lb/>25.288 <lb/>23.865 <lb/>24.206 <lb/>0.927 <lb/>0.896 <lb/>0.907 <lb/>0.1136 <lb/>0.1401 <lb/>0.1220 <lb/>0.0293 <lb/>0.0441 <lb/>0.0380 <lb/>PUT <lb/>24.118 <lb/>22.694 <lb/>23.235 <lb/>0.911 <lb/>0.858 <lb/>0.885 <lb/>0.0681 <lb/>0.1032 <lb/>0.1350 <lb/>0.0236 <lb/>0.0421 <lb/>0.0406 <lb/>Ours <lb/>25.827 <lb/>24.769 <lb/>24.379 <lb/>0.936 <lb/>0.900 <lb/>0.900 <lb/>0.0691 <lb/>0.1038 <lb/>0.1011 <lb/>0.0213 <lb/>0.0384 <lb/>0.0344 <lb/>4.2.2 Qualitative Comparisons <lb/>The EPAM model is compared with existing methods on the CelebA dataset containing face <lb/>images with similar semantics. As shown in Fig. 8, EC [20] is an inpainting method that starts with <lb/>structure and then texture. However, the structure prediction in the previous step is incomplete, which <lb/>will affect the detail restoration in the latter step. This results in blurry edges and unclear texture, <lb/>as seen in the eyes and lips of the characters in rows 1 and 5 in Fig. 8b. CTSDG attempts to balance <lb/>texture and structure generation, but it often fails to achieve a good balance, leading to local boundary <lb/>artifacts. For example, the mouth of the face image in Fig. 8c exhibits distortion and missing parts, <lb/>and the eyes do not appear natural enough. <lb/>ICT employs a transformer to reconstruct the visual prior and then uses conventional CNN to fill <lb/>in texture details. However, the large-scale downsampling in this process causes the loss of important <lb/>semantic information in the generated results. This is evident in the repaired eyes in Fig. 8d, which are <lb/>either missing or deformed. MAT addresses large missing areas using a mask perception mechanism <lb/>but falls short in dealing with small missing areas. For example, the eyes in rows 2, 4, and 5 in <lb/>Fig. 8e are asymmetrical and inconsistent in size. PUT improves image quality using a non-quantized <lb/>transformer, but it cannot fully understand the semantic features. For example, in Fig. 8f, the repaired <lb/>eyeball part does not match the face. In comparison, our method excels in understanding global <lb/>semantics and preserving more realistic texture details. It generates structurally and color-consistent <lb/>face images, as shown in Fig. 8g. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1015 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 8: Qualitative comparison results of our method with existing methods on the CelebA dataset <lb/>with irregular and artificially drawn holes <lb/>The effect of our method on the Facade dataset is visually analyzed, and the results are shown in <lb/>Fig. 9. When EC faces a large-scale rectangular defect, the windows of the building will be missing, <lb/>resulting in noticeable color discrepancies in the restoration results. The visualization results of <lb/>CTSDG demonstrate its inability to handle large holes, leading to the loss of essential components <lb/>and image distortion. While ICT recovers occluded regions at the pixel level, it fails to capture <lb/>the global structural semantics well. This can be observed in the irregularities of the windows <lb/>and their surrounding contours in rows 1 and 2 of Fig. 9d. MAT utilizes long-range context to <lb/>reconstruct structures and textures. However, the reconstructed masked regions in row 2 of Fig. 9e <lb/>exhibit incoherent colors and unreasonable semantic objects. Although the image synthesized by PUT <lb/>(Fig. 9f) appears to produce reasonable results, it is plagued by noticeable artifacts. In contrast, our <lb/>model not only infers reasonable structural-semantic information but also effectively alleviates mesh <lb/>artifacts and loss of texture information in local regions, thereby enhancing perceptual quality. For <lb/>example, in rows 1 and 2 of Fig. 9g, the window edges repaired by our method exhibit clear outlines <lb/>and visually appealing results. In addition, the small windows predicted by the mask area in row 3 are <lb/>arranged regularly and possess reasonable semantics. <lb/></body>

	<page>1016 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 9: Qualitative comparison results of our method with existing methods on the Facade dataset <lb/>with irregular, center-regular and artificially drawn holes <lb/>Our model is further evaluated on the Places2 dataset containing images with different semantics, <lb/>as shown in Fig. 10. In such challenging scenarios, the structure-texture-based methods such as EC <lb/>[20] and CTSDG [16] cannot understand the global background well, resulting in incomplete and <lb/>unreasonable restorations. In contrast, methods using the Transformer architecture (ICT, MAT, and <lb/>PUT) demonstrate improved capability in capturing global context information for complex image <lb/>inpainting tasks. Nevertheless, due to the lack of constraints on global structural information, these <lb/>methods often exhibit boundary inconsistencies and missing semantics in the inpainting results. This <lb/>can be observed in column 6 of Fig. 10, where the target structure for occluded region reconstruction <lb/>appears incoherent. In comparison to the above methods, our method incorporates a Transformer-<lb/>based structure repair module that reconstructs the semantic content accurately. Additionally, our <lb/>method employs an attention shift strategy, applied layer by layer to the MFA module, to combine <lb/>shallow detail texture information and deep structural-semantic information based on a precise <lb/>appearance prior. This strategy mitigates the loss of long-distance features in deep networks and greatly <lb/>enhances the consistency between global and local features of the image. For example, rows 1-4 in <lb/>Fig. 10g show high-quality texture and structural details in missing regions. <lb/>To further demonstrate the effectiveness of our method, the trained model is compared with <lb/>similar inpainting schemes (EC and CTSDG). Fig. 11 shows the edge prediction and image inpainting <lb/>results of EC, CTSDG, and our method on three datasets: CelebA, Facade, and Places2. Upon <lb/>closer observation of columns 2 and 3, it becomes evident that the edge priors reconstructed by these <lb/>inpainting methods fail to accurately predict semantic contours such as building windows and doors <lb/>of drum washing machines. Similarly, it can be observed in columns 5 and 6 that although the color <lb/>details are similar, the overall structure cannot show the characteristics of the original image. Overall, <lb/>both EC and CTSDG are unable to restore reasonable images such as buildings and faces based on <lb/>the biased edge prior. In contrast, our method introduces relative position coding and self-attention <lb/>mechanisms to enhance the extraction capability of edge features. This enables the restoration of <lb/>core edge information (Fig. 11d) and target boundaries that align with the scene semantics in the <lb/>central region of a wide range of masks. In addition, as shown in column 7 of Fig. 11, the inpainting <lb/>output generated by our method exhibits more detailed texture and a more realistic visual perception. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1017 <lb/></page>

	<body>Furthermore, in cases where there is insufficient priori information about local edges, the MFA module <lb/>also fuses global contextual features and shallow features to guide the model to synthesize novel <lb/>content, as shown in the square structure in the right gate in row 6 of Fig. 11g. <lb/>Figure 10: Qualitative comparison results of our method with existing methods on the Places2 dataset <lb/>with irregular and artificially drawn holes <lb/>4.2.3 Visual Analysis <lb/>To demonstrate the effectiveness of the TEP module in applying position-sensitive axial attention, <lb/>the attention weights of the axial attention layer are visualized on the CelebA dataset. As shown in <lb/>Fig. 12, block 2 of the TEP module is chosen to visualize the heat map of the 8 heads of column <lb/>(height axis) and row (width axis) attention, respectively. To better visualize the focus areas of each <lb/>head, the 32 × 32 pixel Attention Map is enlarged to 256 × 256 and overlaid on the original image, <lb/>creating a heatmap of the attention weights. It is worth noting that some heads learn to concentrate on <lb/>relatively local regions, whereas others concentrate on distant contexts. For example, in column-wise <lb/>attention, column heads 1, 5, and 6 exhibit a preference for relatively local regions of the head, while <lb/>column heads 2, 3, and 8 cover the entire image. Regarding row-wise attention, row heads 1, 2, and 3 <lb/>are associated with local semantic concepts such as eyes, mouth, and nose of faces. Row heads 4, 5, <lb/>and 7 place greater emphasis on the long-distance row-wise contextual relationships. <lb/></body>

	<page>1018 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 11: Visual comparison of the proposed method against other structure-based methods on the <lb/>CelebA, Facade, and Places2 datasets: (a) input corrupted image; (b)-(d) are the edge structures <lb/>generated by EC [20], CTSDG [16], and our method, respectively; (e)-(g) are the corresponding <lb/>inpainting effects of EC [20], CTSDG [16], and our method, respectively; and (h) Ground-Truth <lb/>Input <lb/>column head 1 column head 2 column head 3 column head 4 column head 5 column head 6 column head 7 column head 8 <lb/>row head 1 <lb/>row head 2 <lb/>row head 3 <lb/>row head 4 <lb/>row head 5 <lb/>row head 6 <lb/>row head 7 <lb/>row head 8 <lb/>Figure 12: Axial attention maps in block 2 mapped onto the original image <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1019 <lb/></page>

	<body>To verify the effectiveness of the ATN structure applied in the MFA module, the attention score <lb/>heatmaps of ATN at different scales are visualized. Specifically, ATN 8×8 <lb/>i <lb/>represents the ATN attention <lb/>score heat map with a resolution of 8 × 8 in the i-th block of the MFA module, and the visualization <lb/>result is shown in Fig. 13. Columns 2 to 4 show different attention score matrices from deep to shallow, <lb/>achieving attention from point to local, and gradually to the entire domain. This can effectively <lb/>enhance the consistency of context features and improve the network&apos;s capability to process features <lb/>of different scales. Furthermore, part of the ATN feature map of the MFA module is visualized. <lb/>Specifically, ATN 64×64 <lb/>k <lb/>represents the ATN feature map of the k-th block of the MFA module with <lb/>a size of 64 × 64. As depicted in columns 2 to 5 of Fig. 14, the MFA module obtains feature maps <lb/>with multi-level semantic information by applying the attention transfer strategy. This strategy reduces <lb/>information loss or confusion resulting from feature scale changes. Feature maps are progressively <lb/>reconstructed and optimized from the first to the fourth block. <lb/>(a) Input <lb/>(b) <lb/>8 8 <lb/>1 <lb/>Score <lb/>u <lb/>(c) <lb/>16 16 <lb/>1 <lb/>Score <lb/>u <lb/>(d) <lb/>32 32 <lb/>1 <lb/>Score <lb/>u <lb/>Figure 13: Attention score matrix of ATN at different scales <lb/>4.3 Ablation Study <lb/>Ablation experiments were conducted on the Facade dataset to analyze the qualitative and <lb/>quantitative differences between different components of our proposed model. As indicated in Fig. 15 <lb/>and Table 4, various network combinations were tested. These experiments included: (b) removing <lb/>the entire TEP module and the MFA module and replacing them with residual blocks from EC <lb/>(-TER -MFA), (c) removing the entire TEP module and replacing it with 8 residual blocks (-TER); <lb/>(d) removing only the Axial-attention in the TEP module (-AA); (e) removing the MFA module <lb/>and replacing it with 4 residual blocks (-MFA), (f) applying the complete TEP module and MFA <lb/>module (+TER+MFA), namely our network structure. As shown in column (c) of Fig. 15, the network <lb/>composed of residual blocks lacks understanding and analysis of the global structure. Consequently, <lb/>this component cannot accurately predict the edge information of the window in the central region of <lb/></body>

	<page>1020 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>the large mask. It can be observed from column (d) of Fig. 15 that in the case of large irregular masks, <lb/>only the edge prediction network of self-attention cannot explicitly encode the position information. <lb/>This restricts the model&apos;s ability to model the local structure of the image, resulting in poor repair <lb/>results. To address these issues, the image inpainting network herein introduces the MFA module. <lb/>This module helps to enhance the relevance of multi-level features, balance the attention on visual <lb/>content and generated content, and realistically restore the texture details and color information of <lb/>the damaged area. As shown in columns (e) and (f) of Fig. 15, when the edge priors are consistent, <lb/>the composite image obtained in the absence of the MFA module exhibits inconsistent wall color <lb/>information inside and outside the hole. Nonetheless, our method achieves a more natural visual effect <lb/>inside and outside the hole, with the smallest area of blurred texture. <lb/>Figure 14: ATN feature maps <lb/>Figure 15: Analysis of different configurations of the proposed method <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1021 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 4: Quantitative ablation analysis of the proposed method on Facade dataset <lb/>Models <lb/>PSNR/dB↑ SSIM↑ <lb/>LPIPS↓ <lb/>MAE↓ <lb/>-TEP -MFA <lb/>22.412 <lb/>0.805 <lb/>0.1355 <lb/>0.0378 <lb/>-TEP <lb/>23.105 <lb/>0.820 <lb/>0.1266 <lb/>0.0354 <lb/>-AA <lb/>24.040 <lb/>0.848 <lb/>0.1078 <lb/>0.0319 <lb/>-MFA <lb/>24.250 <lb/>0.879 <lb/>0.0966 <lb/>0.0309 <lb/>Proposed method <lb/>25.738 <lb/>0.903 <lb/>0.0838 <lb/>0.0262 <lb/>Table 4 presents the quantitative comparison of the models composed of different components in <lb/>terms of metrics such as PSNR, SSIM, LPIPS, and MAE. As shown in rows 3, 4, and 6, the fusion of <lb/>axial attention and self-attention significantly enhances the model&apos;s performance. Fig. 16 shows the <lb/>accuracy and precision curves with/without axial attention. The red curve, which represents the use <lb/>of axial attention, demonstrates better performance. In the inpainting network, the MFA module is <lb/>employed to learn from various levels of distant features, so as to extract the contextual information <lb/>from the input feature map. The quantitative results in row 6 of Table 4 exhibit significant improvement <lb/>compared to the residual block (row 5 of Table 4). This suggests that the MFA module assists the <lb/>image inpainting generator in learning more effective information about the image features, thereby <lb/>enhancing the model&apos;s performance in texture synthesis. <lb/>Figure 16: Accuracy and precision curves with/without Axial attention <lb/>4.4 Model Complexity Analysis <lb/>To analyze the computational complexity of the model, a comparison is made between the EPAM <lb/>model and other methods in terms of the number of total parameters, memory consumption, and <lb/>testing time. The term &quot;total parameters&quot; refers to the combined number of trainable and untrainable <lb/>parameters. &quot;Total memory&quot; means the memory space required during model testing. &quot;Runtime&quot; <lb/>represents the time taken to repair a single image. Table 5 clearly demonstrates that our model has <lb/>the fewest parameters and the lowest memory cost compared to other transformer-based methods <lb/>(ICT, MAT, and PUT). Additionally, our method is also the fastest in inpainting a single image. <lb/></body>

	<page>1022 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 5: Complexity analysis of different models, lower values are better <lb/>Method <lb/>Total params (M)↓ <lb/>Total memory (MB)↓ <lb/>Runtime (S)↓ <lb/>EC <lb/>21.54 <lb/>1745.32 <lb/>1.868 <lb/>CTSDG <lb/>52.14 <lb/>3346.94 <lb/>3.984 <lb/>ICT <lb/>121.63 <lb/>5558.47 <lb/>26.59 <lb/>MAT <lb/>60.35 <lb/>4081.67 <lb/>2.847 <lb/>PUT <lb/>96.38 <lb/>4124.00 <lb/>9.642 <lb/>Proposed <lb/>24.73 <lb/>2177.27 <lb/>2.304 <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>This paper proposes the EPAM image inpainting model which consists of two phases: edge <lb/>prediction and image restoration. The edge prediction phase incorporates an efficient transformer-<lb/>based edge prediction (TEP) module, which can better obtain the edge structure of the defect area and <lb/>reduce the computational cost. The second phase introduces a multi-scale fusion attention (MFA) <lb/>module, which can extract effective features at multiple scales and enhance the continuity of local <lb/>pixels through layer-by-layer filling from deep semantics to shallow details. According to qualitative <lb/>and quantitative comparisons on the CelebA, Facade, and Places2 datasets with irregular masks, our <lb/>method demonstrates superior performance in repairing complex and large holes. Next, our method <lb/>utilizes attention and feature visualization to observe the distribution of attention weights and judge <lb/>the rationality of the feature map. In addition, this paper conducted multiple ablation analyses to <lb/>verify the effectiveness of each component in the EPAM model from visual effects and quantitative <lb/>indicators. Finally, through complexity analysis experiments, it is intuitively shown that our proposed <lb/>method has lower complexity. <lb/>The proposed EPAM can only handle images with 256 × 256 resolution. Due to the constraint of <lb/>structural information, our model is not suitable for pluralistic image inpainting. In addition, when <lb/>dealing with complex structures and scenes, the repair results may not meet expectations. For example, <lb/>when dealing with small accessories such as earrings and necklaces around people&apos;s faces or trees <lb/>around buildings, this method still has the problem of obvious repair traces. In recent years, multi-<lb/>modal (e.g., text, depth map, and pose) guided image inpainting has been a challenging research <lb/>direction. Future research could explore how to perform joint restoration in multi-modal data to <lb/>produce novel and diverse inpainting results. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: The authors gratefully acknowledge the equipment support from the Key Labo-<lb/>ratory of Optical Information Processing and Visualization Technology at Xizang Minzu University. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Funding Statement: This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of China under Grant 62062061, author Y.F, https://www.nsfc.gov.cn/; in part by the Major Project <lb/>Cultivation Fund of Xizang Minzu University under Grant 324112300447, author Y.F, https://www. <lb/>xzmu.edu.cn/. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author Contributions: Study conception and design: J. X. Bai, Y. Fan; data collection and visualization: <lb/>Z. W. Zhao, L. Z. Zheng; analysis and interpretation of results: J. X. Bai; draft manuscript preparation: <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1023 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">J. X. Bai; supervision: Y. Fan. All authors reviewed the results and approved the final version of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

	<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials: All data generated or analysed during this study are included in <lb/>this published article. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to report regarding the <lb/>present study. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Z. Wan, B. Zhang, D. Chen, P. Zhang, D. Chen et al., &quot;Bringing old photos back to life,&quot; in Proc. of the <lb/>IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Seattle, WA, USA, pp. 2747-2757, 2020. <lb/>[2] C. Barnes, E. Shechtman, A. Finkelstein and D. B. Goldman, &quot;PatchMatch: A randomized correspondence <lb/>algorithm for structural image editing,&quot; ACM Transactions on Graphics, vol. 28, no. 3, pp. 24:1-24:11, 2009. <lb/>[3] F. Yang, H. Yang, J. Fu, H. Lu and B. Guo, &quot;Learning texture transformer network for image super-<lb/>resolution,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Seattle, WA, <lb/>USA, pp. 5791-5800, 2020. <lb/>[4] M. Bertalmio, G. Sapiro, V. Caselles and C. Ballester, &quot;Image inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the 27th Annual Conf. <lb/>on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, New York, NY, USA, pp. 417-424, 2000. <lb/>[5] T. F. Chan and J. Shen, &quot;Nontexture inpainting by curvature-driven diffusions,&quot; Journal of Visual Commu-<lb/>nication and Image Representation, vol. 12, no. 4, pp. 436-449, 2001. <lb/>[6] N. Komodakis and G. Tziritas, &quot;Image completion using efficient belief propagation via priority scheduling <lb/>and dynamic pruning,&quot; IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, vol. 16, no. 11, pp. 2649-2661, 2007. <lb/>[7] A. Criminisi, P. Pérez and K. Toyama, &quot;Region filling and object removal by exemplar-based image <lb/>inpainting,&quot; IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, vol. 13, no. 9, pp. 1200-1212, 2004. <lb/>[8] D. Pathak, P. Krahenbuhl, J. Donahue, T. Darrell and A. A. Efros, &quot;Context encoders: Feature learning by <lb/>inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Las Vegas, NV, USA, <lb/>pp. 2536-2544, 2016. <lb/>[9] S. Iizuka, E. Simo-Serra and H. Ishikawa, &quot;Globally and locally consistent image completion,&quot; ACM <lb/>Transactions on Graphics, vol. 36, no. 4, pp. 107:1-107:14, 2017. <lb/>[10] Y. Wang, X. Tao, X. Qi, X. Shen and J. Jia, &quot;Image inpainting via generative multi-column convolutional <lb/>neural networks,&quot; in Proc. of Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, Montreal, QC, Canada, <lb/>pp. 331-340, 2018. <lb/>[11] I. Goodfellow, J. Pouget-Abadie, M. Mirza, B. Xu and D. Warde-Farley, &quot;Generative adversarial nets,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, Montreal, QC, Canada, pp. 2676-2680, 2014. <lb/>[12] J. Yu, Z. Lin, J. Yang, X. Shen, X. Lu et al., &quot;Generative image inpainting with contextual attention,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of the IEEE conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Salt Lake City, UT, USA, pp. 5505-<lb/>5514, 2018. <lb/>[13] M. C. Sagong, Y. G. Shin, S. W. Kim, S. Park and S. J. Ko, &quot;PEPSI: Fast image inpainting with parallel <lb/>decoding network,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Long Beach, <lb/>CA, USA, pp. 11360-11368, 2019. <lb/>[14] Z. Wan, J. Zhang, D. Chen and J. Liao, &quot;High-fidelity pluralistic image completion with transformers,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Int. Conf. on Computer Vision, Montreal, QC, Canada, pp. 4692-4701, 2021. <lb/>[15] Y. Yu, F. Zhan, R. Wu, J. Pan and K. Cui, &quot;Diverse image inpainting with bidirectional and autoregressive <lb/>transformers,&quot; in Proc. of the 29th ACM Int. Conf. on Multimedia, Chengdu, Sichuan, China, pp. 69-78, <lb/>2021. <lb/>[16] X. Guo, H. Yang and D. Huang, &quot;Image inpainting via conditional texture and structure dual generation,&quot; <lb/>in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Int Conf on Computer Vision, Montreal, QC, Canada, pp. 14134-14143, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>1024 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>[17] J. Yang, Z. Qi and Y. Shi, &quot;Learning to incorporate structure knowledge for image inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of <lb/>the AAAI Conf. on Artificial Intelligence, New York, NY, USA, pp. 12605-12612, 2020. <lb/>[18] Y. Song, C. Yang, Y. Shen, P. Wang, Q. Huang et al., &quot;SPG-Net: Segmentation prediction and guidance <lb/>network for image inpainting,&quot; 2016. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.03356 (accessed on <lb/>05/08/2023) <lb/>[19] L. Liao, J. Xiao, Z. Wang, C. W. Lin and S. I. Satoh, &quot;Guidance and evaluation: Semantic-aware image <lb/>inpainting for mixed scenes,&quot; in Proc. of European Conf. on Computer Vision, Glasgow, Scotland, UK, pp. <lb/>683-700, 2020. <lb/>[20] K. Nazeri, E. Ng, T. Joseph, F. Z. Qureshi and M. Ebrahimi, &quot;EdgeConnect: Generative image inpainting <lb/>with adversarial edge learning,&quot; 2019. [Online]. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.00212 (accessed on <lb/>05/08/2023) <lb/>[21] W. Xiong, J. Yu, Z. Lin, J. Yang, X. Lu et al., &quot;Foreground-aware image inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the <lb/>IEEE/CVF Int. Conf. on Computer Vision, Long Beach, CA, USA, pp. 5840-5848, 2019. <lb/>[22] Z. Liu, P. Luo, X. Wang and X. Tang, &quot;Deep learning face attributes in the wild,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Int. <lb/>Conf. on Computer Vision, Santiago, Chile, pp. 3730-3738, 2015. <lb/>[23] R. Tyleček and R. Šára, &quot;Spatial pattern templates for recognition of objects with regular structure,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of German Conf. on Pattern Recognition, Saarbrücken, Germany, pp. 364-374, 2013. <lb/>[24] B. Zhou, A. Lapedriza, A. Khosla, A. Oliva and A. Torralba, &quot;Places: A 10 million image database for scene <lb/>recognition,&quot; IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, vol. 40, no. 6, pp. 1452-1464, <lb/>2018. <lb/>[25] L. Liao, R. Hu, J. Xiao and Z. Wang, &quot;Edge-aware context encoder for image inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of 2018 <lb/>IEEE Int. Conf. on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing, Calgary, AB, Canada, pp. 3156-3160, 2018. <lb/>[26] C. Cao and Y. Fu, &quot;Learning a sketch tensor space for image inpainting of man-made scenes,&quot; in Proc. of <lb/>the IEEE/CVF Int. Conf. on Computer Vision, Montreal, QC, Canada, pp. 14509-14518, 2021. <lb/>[27] A. Vaswani, N. Shazeer, N. Parmar, J. Uszkoreit, L. Jones et al., &quot;Attention is all you need,&quot; in Proc. of <lb/>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, Long Beach, CA, USA, pp. 5998-6008, 2017. <lb/>[28] H. Chen, Y. Wang, T. Guo, C. Xu, Y. Deng et al., &quot;Pre-trained image processing transformer,&quot; in Proc. of <lb/>the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Nashville, TN, USA, pp. 12299-12310, <lb/>2021. <lb/>[29] J. Devlin, M. W. Chang, K. Lee and K. Toutanova, &quot;BERT: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers <lb/>for language understanding,&quot; 2018. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.04805 (accessed on <lb/>05/08/2023) <lb/>[30] C. Zheng, T. J. Cham, J. Cai and D. Phung, &quot;Bridging global context interactions for high-fidelity image <lb/>completion,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, New Orleans, <lb/>LA, USA, pp. 11512-11522, 2022. <lb/>[31] C. Raffel, N. Shazeer, A. Roberts, K. Lee, S. Narang et al., &quot;Exploring the limits of transfer learning with a <lb/>unified text-to-text transformer,&quot; The Journal of Machine Learning Research, vol. 21, no. 1, pp. 5485-5551, <lb/>2020. <lb/>[32] J. Ho, N. Kalchbrenner, D. Weissenborn and T. Salimans, &quot;Axial attention in multidimensional transform-<lb/>ers,&quot; 2019. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.12180 (accessed on 05/08/2023) <lb/>[33] Y. Zeng, J. Fu, H. Chao and B. Guo, &quot;Learning pyramid-context encoder network for high-quality image <lb/>inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Long Beach, CA, <lb/>USA, pp. 1486-1494, 2019. <lb/>[34] A. Dosovitskiy, L. Beyer, A. Kolesnikov, D. Weissenborn, X. Zhai et al., &quot;An image is worth 16×16 words: <lb/>Transformers for image recognition at scale,&quot; 2020. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.11929 <lb/>(accessed on 05/08/2023) <lb/>[35] J. L. Ba, J. R. Kiros and G. E. Hinton, &quot;Layer normalization,&quot; 2016. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/ <lb/>abs/1607.06450 (accessed on 05/08/2023) <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">CMC, 2024, vol.78, no.1 <lb/></note>

	<page>1025 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>[36] P. Isola, J. Y. Zhu, T. Zhou and A. A. Efros, &quot;Image-to-image translation with conditional adversarial <lb/>networks,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Honolulu, HI, USA, <lb/>pp. 1125-1134, 2017. <lb/>[37] M. S. M. Sajjadi, B. Scholkopf and M. Hirsch, &quot;EnhanceNet: Single image super-resolution through <lb/>automated texture synthesis,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Int. Conf. on Computer Vision, Venice, Italy, pp. 4491-<lb/>4500, 2017. <lb/>[38] Q. Wang, B. Wu, P. Zhu, P. Li, W. Zuo et al., &quot;ECA-Net: Efficient channel attention for deep convolutional <lb/>neural networks,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Seattle, <lb/>WA, USA, pp. 11534-11542, 2020. <lb/>[39] M. Chen, S. Zang, Z. Ai, J. Chi, G. Yang et al., &quot;RFA-Net: Residual feature attention network for <lb/>fine-grained image inpainting,&quot; Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence, vol. 119, pp. 105814:1-<lb/>105814:10, 2023. <lb/>[40] T. C. Wang, M. Y. Liu, J. Y. Zhu, A. Tao, J. Kautz et al., &quot;High-resolution image synthesis and semantic <lb/>manipulation with conditional GANs,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern <lb/>Recognition, Salt Lake City, UT, USA, pp. 8798-8807, 2018. <lb/>[41] J. Johnson, A. Alahi and F. F. Li, &quot;Perceptual losses for real-time style transfer and super-resolution,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of European Conf. on Computer Vision, Amsterdam, the Netherlands, pp. 694-711, 2016. <lb/>[42] L. A. Gatys, A. S. Ecker and M. Bethge, &quot;Image style transfer using convolutional neural networks,&quot; in <lb/>Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Las Vegas, NV, USA, pp. 2414-2423, <lb/>2016. <lb/>[43] K. Simonyan and A. Zisserman, &quot;Very deep convolutional networks for large-scale image recognition,&quot; <lb/>2014. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.1556 (accessed on 05/08/2023) <lb/>[44] G. Liu, F. A. Reda, K. J. Shih, T. C. Wang, A. Tao et al., &quot;Image inpainting for irregular holes using partial <lb/>convolutions,&quot; in Proc. of European Conf. on Computer Vision, Munich, Germany, pp. 85-100, 2018. <lb/>[45] W. Li, Z. Lin, K. Zhou, L. Qi, Y. Wang et al., &quot;MAT: Mask-aware transformer for large hole image <lb/>inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, New Orleans, <lb/>LA, USA, pp. 10758-10768, 2022. <lb/>[46] Q. Liu, Z. Tan, D. Chen, Q. Chu, X. Dai et al., &quot;Reduce information loss in transformers for pluralistic <lb/>image inpainting,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE/CVF Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, New <lb/>Orleans, LA, USA, pp. 11347-11357, 2022. <lb/>[47] R. Zhang, P. Isola, A. A. Efros, E. Shechtman and O. Wang, &quot;The unreasonable effectiveness of deep <lb/>features as a perceptual metric,&quot; in Proc. of the IEEE Conf. on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, <lb/>Salt Lake City, UT, USA, pp. 586-595, 2018. </listBibl>

  </text>

</TEI>