<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T16:01:47.038Z">11/21/2025 4:01:47 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T16:01:33.800901Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T16:01:33.800901Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>A Greenland-wide empirical reconstruction of paleo ice sheet <lb/>retreat informed by ice extent markers: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/>Tancrède P. M. Leger 1 , Christopher D. Clark 1 , Carla Huynh 2 , Sharman Jones 3 , Jeremy C. Ely 1 , Sarah L. Bradley 1 , <lb/>Christiaan Diemont 1 , and Anna L. C. Hughes 4 <lb/>1 Department of Geography, University of Sheffield, Sheffield, S10 2TN, United Kingdom <lb/>2 School of GeoSciences, University of Edinburgh, Drummond Street, Edinburgh, EH8 9XP, United Kingdom <lb/>3 Geography and Earth Sciences, Aberystwyth University, Aberystwyth, SY23 3DB, United Kingdom <lb/>4 Department of Geography, School of Environment, Education and Development, The University of Manchester, <lb/>Manchester, M13 9PL, United Kingdom <lb/>Correspondence: Tancrède P. M. Leger (t.p.leger@sheffield.ac.uk, tancrede.leger@unil.ch) <lb/>Received: 28 July 2023 -Discussion started: 31 July 2023 <lb/>Revised: 29 November 2023 -Accepted: 12 February 2024 -Published: 28 March 2024 <lb/>Abstract. The Greenland Ice Sheet is a large contributor to <lb/>global sea level rise, and current mass losses are projected <lb/>to accelerate. However, model projections of future ice sheet <lb/>evolution are limited by the fact that the ice sheet is not in <lb/>equilibrium with present-day climate but is still adjusting to <lb/>past changes that occurred over thousands of years. While the <lb/>influence of such committed adjustments on future ice sheet <lb/>evolution remains unquantified, it could be addressed by cal-<lb/>ibrating numerical ice sheet models over larger timescales <lb/>and, importantly, against empirical data on ice margin posi-<lb/>tions. To enable such paleo data-model interactions, we need <lb/>Greenland-wide empirical reconstructions of past ice sheet <lb/>extent that combine geomorphological and geochronological <lb/>evidence. Despite an increasing number of field studies pro-<lb/>ducing new chronologies, such a reconstruction is currently <lb/>lacking in Greenland. Furthermore, a time slice reconstruc-<lb/>tion can help to (i) answer open questions regarding the rate <lb/>and pattern of ice margin evolution in Greenland since the <lb/>glacial maximum, (ii) develop a standardised record of em-<lb/>pirical data, and (iii) identify new sites for future field cam-<lb/>paigns. Based on these motivations, we here present Pale-<lb/>oGrIS 1.0, a new Greenland-wide isochrone reconstruction <lb/>of ice sheet extent evolution through the Late Glacial and <lb/>early-to mid-Holocene informed by both geomorphological <lb/>and geochronological markers. Our isochrones have a tem-<lb/>poral resolution of 500 years and span ∼ 7.5 kyr from ap-<lb/>proximately 14 to 6.5 kyr BP. We describe the resulting re-<lb/>construction of the shrinking ice sheet and conduct a series of <lb/>ice-sheet-wide and regional analyses to quantify retreat rates, <lb/>areal extent change, and their variability across space and <lb/>time. During the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene, <lb/>we find the Greenland Ice Sheet has lost about one-third <lb/>of its areal extent (0.89 million km 2 ). Between ∼ 14 and <lb/>∼ 8.5 kyr BP, it experienced a near-constant rate of areal ex-<lb/>tent loss of 170 ± 27 km 2 yr -1 . We find that the ice-sheet-<lb/>scale pattern of margin retreat is well correlated to atmo-<lb/>spheric and oceanic temperature variations, which implies a <lb/>high sensitivity of the ice sheet to deglacial warming. How-<lb/>ever, during the Holocene, we observe inertia in the ice sheet <lb/>system that likely caused a centennial-to millennial-scale <lb/>time lag in ice extent response. At the regional scale, we <lb/>observe highly heterogeneous deglacial responses in ice ex-<lb/>tent evident in both the magnitude and rate of retreat. We hy-<lb/>pothesise that non-climatic factors, such as the asymmetrical <lb/>nature of continental shelves and onshore bed topographies, <lb/>play important roles in determining the regional-to valley-<lb/>scale dynamics. PaleoGrIS 1.0 is an open-access database <lb/>designed to be used by both the empirical and numerical <lb/>modelling communities. It should prove a useful basis for im-<lb/>proved future versions of the reconstruction when new geo-<lb/>morphological and geochronological data become available. <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></front>

	<page>702 <lb/></page>

	<front>T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Greenland Ice Sheet holds an estimated ∼ 7.4 m of <lb/>global sea level equivalent (Morlighem et al., 2017). It is <lb/>currently experiencing mass loss at a rate of ∼ 150 Gt yr -1 <lb/>(over the 1992-2018 period; The IMBIE Team, 2019; Oto-<lb/>saka et al., 2023), making it a large contributor to cur-<lb/>rent global mean sea level rise. In a warming world, these <lb/>losses are projected to accelerate (Meredith et al., 2019), <lb/>with the latest Greenland Ice Sheet Model Intercomparison <lb/>Project (ISMIP6) estimating a contribution to global mean <lb/>sea level rise of 32 ± 17 and 90 ± 50 mm by the year 2100 <lb/>for the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP)2.6 and <lb/>RCP8.5 greenhouse gas concentrations scenarios, respec-<lb/>tively (Goelzer et al., 2020). The robustness of such projec-<lb/>tions is limited by the short time span of instrumental evi-<lb/>dence (tens to hundreds of years) used for verification and <lb/>testing (Larsen et al., 2015). This is problematic because on-<lb/>going and future ice sheet mass losses are not only exclu-<lb/>sively a consequence of contemporary and future climate but <lb/>also represent adjustments to climate variations stretching <lb/>further back in time (hundreds to thousands of years; Ro-<lb/>gozhina et al., 2011; Yang et al., 2022). As few models in-<lb/>clude the committed response to Late Quaternary environ-<lb/>mental changes, current projection simulations might effec-<lb/>tively be starting from a possibly unrealistic state, whose in-<lb/>fluence is thus far unquantified. Consequently, improved em-<lb/>pirical reconstructions of Late Quaternary ice sheet evolution <lb/>may be useful for refining future predictions of mass loss <lb/>and global sea level rise by enabling the calibration of ice <lb/>sheet models over larger timescales encompassing thousands <lb/>of years (e.g. Lecavalier et al., 2014; Albrecht et al., 2020). <lb/>The response of the ice sheet to climate change during the <lb/>Late Quaternary likely contributes to major imbalances in its <lb/>current state (Calov and Hutter, 1996), yet many key ques-<lb/>tions pertaining to this time remain unresolved. The posi-<lb/>tion, rate, and pattern of ice margin retreat during the Late <lb/>Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene periods (between ∼ 14 <lb/>and ∼ 6 kyr BP) remains heterogeneously constrained in nu-<lb/>merous regions. During that time, the ice sheet was respond-<lb/>ing to rapid and high-amplitude fluctuations in atmospheric <lb/>and oceanic boundary conditions (e.g. the Bølling-Allerød <lb/>interstadial; Buizert et al., 2018b), while also adjusting to <lb/>fast rates of relative sea level change, following the demise <lb/>of other ice sheets. Consequent changes in ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin, volume, and surface mass balance were likely associated <lb/>with modifications to the configurations of ice divides and <lb/>to the position and discharge regimes of major ice streams <lb/>(e.g. Franke et al., 2022). A key question concerns how far <lb/>the ice sheet retreated behind its contemporary margin in re-<lb/>sponse to the warming of the Holocene thermal maximum <lb/>(10-5 kyr BP; Weidick et al., 2004; Cartapanis et al., 2022), a <lb/>possible analogue to atmospheric warming expected in future <lb/>decades (Funder et al., 2011). Calibrating model simulations <lb/>against known Holocene margin positions around the full ice <lb/>sheet perimeter might help answer this latter question. <lb/>The Greenland Ice Sheet has been subject to an increasing <lb/>number of field studies reconstructing the deglacial evolu-<lb/>tion of the former ice sheet margin, both on land and off-<lb/>shore. These typically use geomorphological, sedimentolog-<lb/>ical, and geochronological dating analyses (e.g. Ten Brink <lb/>and Weidick, 1974; Hjort, 1979; England, 1985; Bennike <lb/>and Weidick, 2001; Hughes et al., 2012; Briner et al., 2014; <lb/>Larsen et al., 2014; Young et al., 2021; Garcia-Oteyza et al., <lb/>2022; Sbarra et al., 2022). This growing library of geologi-<lb/>cal evidence enables an improved understanding of the ice <lb/>sheet response to deglacial climate change at both the re-<lb/>gional and continental scale (Sinclair et al., 2016). However, <lb/>to our knowledge, it appears that a Greenland-Ice-Sheet-wide <lb/>reconstruction with an open-access, reproducible database of <lb/>geomorphological and geochronological evidence is lacking. <lb/>Such a product would prove useful to both the modelling <lb/>and empirical glaciology communities. It would enable ice-<lb/>sheet-scale analyses, help keep a standardised record of dat-<lb/>ing investigations, facilitate targeting new study regions for <lb/>future fieldwork, and provide a reconstruction for calibrat-<lb/>ing ice sheet model simulations. We note that ice-sheet-wide <lb/>summary datasets of accumulated evidence have played an <lb/>essential and enabling role in advancing the understanding <lb/>of other paleo ice sheets and in answering key glaciological <lb/>questions on former ice dynamics (e.g. Dyke, 2004; Bentley <lb/>et al., 2014; Hughes et al., 2016; Davies et al., 2020; Dalton <lb/>et al., 2020; Clark et al., 2022). <lb/>Based on motivations outlined above, we present an ice-<lb/>sheet-wide isochrone reconstruction of the Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet&apos;s Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene evolution <lb/>informed by an ice-sheet-scale dataset of geomorphologi-<lb/>cal and geochronological ice extent markers compiled in an <lb/>open-access database. This reconstruction, hereafter referred <lb/>to as PaleoGrIS 1.0, has a temporal resolution of 500 years, <lb/>and spans 7500 years, between ∼ 14 and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP, the <lb/>period bracketing most terrestrial landform evidence of ice <lb/>margin change. This reconstruction represents a first attempt <lb/>at combining both geochronological and geomorphological <lb/>records to estimate the pattern and timing of the ice sheet <lb/>deglacial retreat. In this work, we describe our methodology <lb/>in detail to make the reconstruction transparent and repro-<lb/>ducible, with the hope that improved versions of PaleoGrIS <lb/>can be produced as more empirical evidence arises. We use <lb/>our isochrone reconstruction to conduct a series of ice-sheet-<lb/>wide and regional analyses to quantify the natural variation <lb/>in retreat rates and areal extent change and to address scien-<lb/>tific questions on the nature and style of retreat dynamics in <lb/>Greenland during the Late Glacial to mid-Holocene period. <lb/>We envisage that modellers can use this reconstruction to <lb/>quantitatively compare deglacial simulations of the ice sheet <lb/>with a vast quantity of empirical evidence. For example, the <lb/>reconstruction (made available in both shapefile and NetCDF <lb/>formats) could be used to quantitatively score model simula-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>703 <lb/></page>

	<body>tions run as part of ensemble experiments and/or to narrow <lb/>down parameter spaces when conducting model sensitivity <lb/>analyses, by testing the fit with margin extent and retreat pace <lb/>(e.g. Patton et al., 2017; Ely et al., 2019; Pittard et al., 2022). <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Geomorphological reconstruction of ice retreat <lb/>patterns <lb/>Across Greenland&apos;s exposed land area there has been a rich <lb/>but sporadic field collection of landform and sedimentary ev-<lb/>idence for former ice margin positions. These studies have <lb/>been based on field investigation and mapping from aerial <lb/>photographs or satellite images (e.g. Weidick, 1968, 1971; <lb/>Ten Brink and Weidick, 1974; van Tatenhove et al., 1996; <lb/>Roberts et al., 2009; Levy et al., 2012; Young et al., 2013b) <lb/>and, more recently, using digital elevation models (DEMs; <lb/>e.g. Carrivick et al., 2017; Pearce et al., 2018). Such inves-<lb/>tigations have typically mapped individual moraines, melt-<lb/>water channels, and trimlines to define former ice margin <lb/>positions, which were then used to build local reconstruc-<lb/>tions of ice margin retreat. This information covers a small <lb/>fraction (&lt; 10 %) of the land area, leaving most of Green-<lb/>land&apos;s ice marginal history unexplored. The release of the <lb/>2 m ArcticDEM (Porter et al., 2018) for the whole of Green-<lb/>land provides a consistent dataset that has the potential to <lb/>revolutionise our understanding of Holocene ice retreat from <lb/>the Greenland coast to the present-day ice sheet margin po-<lb/>sition. Motivated by the availability of this new resource, we <lb/>devised a mapping scheme and protocol that could capture <lb/>the first-order pattern of retreat for the whole of Greenland&apos;s <lb/>terrestrial ice sheet periphery, an area of 430 500 km 2 . We did <lb/>not identify and map every ice marginal landform from the <lb/>ArcticDEM, as this would represent a decade-long task. In-<lb/>stead, we sampled the area in sufficient detail to provide the <lb/>first landform-based reconstruction. <lb/>2.1.1 Geomorphological mapping <lb/>We focussed our investigation on landforms indicating the <lb/>position and shape of former Greenland Ice Sheet margins, <lb/>paying less attention to peripheral ice caps and mountain <lb/>glaciers. To capture high-resolution details of ice marginal <lb/>retreat across the whole area and with a consistent approach <lb/>is a challenge. To accomplish this, we adopted a sampling ap-<lb/>proach in which, for some regions that we called &quot;swathes&quot;, <lb/>we investigated and mapped ice marginal landforms in detail <lb/>(e.g. Figs. 1-3). For the intervening areas between swathes, <lb/>we only identified the most prominent landforms that would <lb/>permit us to connect paleo ice margins across these areas, <lb/>joining up swathe to swathe (see Sect. 2.1.2). A total of 18 <lb/>swathes were chosen, based on presenting especially dense <lb/>and well-preserved ice marginal landforms (Fig. 1), to be po-<lb/>sitioned approximately evenly around the ice sheet perimeter <lb/>and which covered ∼ 60 % of Greenland&apos;s ice-free periphery. <lb/>Although it was beyond the scope of this continental-scale <lb/>investigation to map all ice marginal landforms identifiable <lb/>from the ArcticDEM, such an endeavour would be a valu-<lb/>able future goal. We suggest that the main focus should be <lb/>to pursue mapping efforts in between the 18 swathes, which <lb/>could contribute to updating future versions of the PaleoGrIS <lb/>database. <lb/>All geomorphological mapping was conducted using re-<lb/>motely sensed data. Identification of ice marginal landforms <lb/>was carried out using the 2 m ArcticDEM (Porter et al., <lb/>2018) and the 30 m ALOS WORLD 3D (AW3D30) DEM <lb/>(AW3D30, https://www.Eorc.jaxa.jp/ALOS/en/aw3d30/, last <lb/>access: 1 December 2022). As recommended by Smith and <lb/>Clark (2005), optimised orthogonal hillshaded relief models <lb/>of 315 and 45°azimuth angles and 45°inclination were tog-<lb/>gled between to minimise azimuth biasing and better identify <lb/>landforms of interest. Moreover, to aid us in distinguishing <lb/>glaciogenic sediments from bedrock features, Google Earth <lb/>Pro software was used for consulting three-dimensional visu-<lb/>alisations of satellite imagery (as recommended by Chandler <lb/>et al., 2018). All mapped landforms were digitised manually <lb/>as shapefiles in the WGS 84/NSIDC Sea Ice Polar Stereo-<lb/>graphic north (EPSG code 3413) reference coordinate sys-<lb/>tem. To remain consistent throughout, and to avoid introduc-<lb/>ing bias from other investigators&apos; landform interpretations, <lb/>our mapping was conducted without input from previous <lb/>mapping investigations. Furthermore, mapping was not con-<lb/>ducted at a fixed spatial scale but by zooming in or out to <lb/>enable better visualisation of the spatially variable landform <lb/>details. <lb/>The main indicators of former ice extent were terminal <lb/>and lateral moraine ridges, more expansive moraine com-<lb/>plexes, hummocks and hummocky ridges, lateral meltwa-<lb/>ter channels, and trimlines. These landforms were inter-<lb/>preted and identified based on their morphology and tex-<lb/>ture, their position in relation to the wider topographic set-<lb/>ting, and following criteria for landform interpretation as <lb/>detailed in Benn and Evans (2014), Chandler et al. (2018), <lb/>Barr and Clark (2009), Rootes and Clark (2020), and Leger <lb/>et al. (2020). The most numerous landforms were moraine <lb/>ridges, which are typically discerned on DEM hillshades as <lb/>arcuate, steep-sided, and sometimes sinuous ridges with pos-<lb/>itive relief and often displaying sharp crests (e.g. Fig. 2). <lb/>Given our aim of covering the entire landmass in a single <lb/>pass with a small number of investigators, we did not in-<lb/>dividually map and classify landforms into their respective <lb/>types (e.g. moraine ridge and meltwater channel). Instead, we <lb/>captured and summarised information from these landforms <lb/>by digitising lines all grouped into a single layer (shapefile) <lb/>called &quot;ice marginal landforms&quot; (Figs. 2, 3). Due to a lack of <lb/>pre-Last-Glacial-Maximum (LGM) ice margin chronologies <lb/>across Greenland, and following the assumption that glacio-<lb/>genic deposits relating to previous glaciations were over-<lb/>ridden during the last glaciation (Funder et al., 2011) and <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>704 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 1. Greenland geographical context, present-day ice sheet thickness (BedMachine v4; Morlighem et al., 2017), and location of 18 <lb/>regions (boxes outlined in light green), where detailed ice marginal landform mapping (displayed in purple) was conducted as part of this <lb/>study. Note that few areas were mapped in detail in the southeast due to relative lack of ice-free land. A simplified pattern of contemporary <lb/>ocean circulation is represented, after Yang et al. (2016; Fig. 1), where red and orange arrows symbolise warmer Atlantic-origin water, <lb/>while blue arrows represent colder Arctic-origin water. NAC, IC, EGC, WGC, BC, and LC stand for the North Atlantic, Irminger, east <lb/>Greenland, west Greenland, Baffin, and Labrador currents, respectively. The digital elevation model (DEM) displaying both topographic and <lb/>bathymetric data is from the General Bathymetric Chart of the Oceans (GEBCO) 2022 release (450 m resolution). Geographical extent of <lb/>Greenland periphery ice caps and glaciers (white polygons) is from BedMachine v4. The locations of main Greenland ice cores (further <lb/>mentioned in text) are shown by black stars. All data (here and in subsequent figures) are displayed projected to the WGS 84/NSIDC Sea Ice <lb/>Polar Stereographic north coordinate reference system. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>705 <lb/></page>

	<body>thus less likely to be preserved (with exceptions, see Mej-<lb/>dahl and Funder, 1994; Kelly et al., 1999), we adopt the as-<lb/>sumption that our mapped ice marginal landforms were de-<lb/>posited during the last deglaciation between ∼ 17 kyr BP and <lb/>the present. <lb/>2.1.2 Establishing an internally consistent map of <lb/>retreat pattern <lb/>The high number (n = 194 302) of ice marginal landforms <lb/>identified inhibited reconstruction at an ice-sheet-wide scale. <lb/>Thus, the landform record underwent two stages of simplifi-<lb/>cation to create a pattern of retreat, following the method em-<lb/>ployed by Clark et al. (2012). First, ice marginal fragments <lb/>were drawn to summarise the collective pattern in which ice <lb/>marginal landforms could be reasonably linked in close prox-<lb/>imity (thick black lines; Fig. 4). As a rule, ice marginal frag-<lb/>ments were mostly confined within the same valley, unless <lb/>the landform evidence was overwhelming for expanding be-<lb/>yond this scale. A further interpretive, and more speculative, <lb/>step involved joining up these ice marginal fragments with <lb/>ice marginal connectors (thick yellow lines; Fig. 4). These <lb/>lines attempt to connect nearby ice marginal fragments inter-<lb/>preted as being approximately time-synchronous. Such con-<lb/>nectors are guided by less prominent or less dense spreads of <lb/>landform evidence and by considering relationships between <lb/>topography and plausible ice dynamics. As a result, the 18 <lb/>swathes featuring more detailed mapping (Fig. 1) enable <lb/>us to connect landforms with both ice marginal fragments <lb/>and connectors, while inter-swathe areas are mostly domi-<lb/>nated by ice marginal connectors. To interpolate ice marginal <lb/>connectors across offshore areas, submarine topographic <lb/>data were obtained from the 15 arcsec spatial resolution <lb/>General Bathymetric Chart of the Oceans (GEBCO) 2022 <lb/>release (https://www.gebco.net/data_and_products/gridded_ <lb/>bathymetry_data/, last access: 1 October 2022). Together, the <lb/>ice marginal fragments and connectors depict the direction <lb/>and relative age of ice marginal recession in undated time <lb/>steps; this is the first-order pattern of ice marginal retreat <lb/>(e.g. Fig. 4). The underlying assumption behind our first-<lb/>order retreat pattern map is that retreat was generally con-<lb/>sidered to be monotonic, unless there was geomorphological <lb/>evidence for time-transgressive margins (e.g. cross-cutting <lb/>moraines). <lb/>2.2 Compiling geochronological evidence <lb/>We attempt to compile published ages relating to the Green-<lb/>land Ice Sheet grounded margin retreat from ∼ 14 kyr BP <lb/>through to the present day for the entirety of the Greenland <lb/>domain (Fig. 1). We include ages from both terrestrial cos-<lb/>mogenic nuclide (TCN) surface exposure dating and radio-<lb/>carbon dating methods. Other dating methods (e.g. lumines-<lb/>cence and lichenometry) were not included in this compila-<lb/>tion, as they have been applied much more sporadically for <lb/>the specific objective of dating the former position of the ice <lb/>sheet margin in Greenland. <lb/>2.2.1 Terrestrial cosmogenic nuclide surface exposure <lb/>ages <lb/>Compilation of ages <lb/>The geochronological component of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 <lb/>database compiles published TCN surface exposure ages, <lb/>and associated metadata, produced with the aim of dat-<lb/>ing the deglacial and Holocene ice extent fluctuations in <lb/>the Greenland Ice Sheet. Such ages estimate the timing <lb/>of moraine emplacement and stabilisation, deposition of <lb/>glacial erratics, or the abandonment of ice from exposed <lb/>bedrock surfaces, which are all relevant for constraining the <lb/>timing of ice retreat. These exposure ages were extracted <lb/>predominantly from the maintained ICE-D Greenland on-<lb/>line database (ICE-D Greenland, https://version2.ice-d.org/ <lb/>greenland/publications, last access: 1 December 2022). In <lb/>addition, a complementary review of the existing literature <lb/>was conducted to compile relevant studies not currently in-<lb/>cluded in ICE-D Greenland. Exposure ages dating the former <lb/>margin evolution of periphery ice caps and mountain glaciers <lb/>were intentionally excluded from our collection. Any new <lb/>data added to ICE-D and any new study published later than <lb/>our census date of 21 October 2022 are not included in the <lb/>PaleoGrIS 1.0 database. <lb/>Age calibration and re-calculation <lb/>All ages were re-calculated using the online calculator for-<lb/>merly known as the CRONUS-Earth online calculator ver-<lb/>sion 3 (Balco et al., 2008). We do not apply an erosion <lb/>rate correction to our exposure age calculations. We use the <lb/>LSDn scaling scheme (Lifton et al., 2014), and the 10 Be <lb/>west Greenland production rate (Young et al., 2013a) ob-<lb/>tained from the ICE-D online calibration database (http: <lb/>//calibration.ice-d.org/, last access: 1 December 2022). Fur-<lb/>thermore, no corrections were applied for post-exposure iso-<lb/>static and/or tectonic uplift or subsidence, which, given the <lb/>young nature of the ages (&lt; 14 kyr BP) and the relatively <lb/>low magnitude of surface elevation change (50-120 m) re-<lb/>lated to glacial isostatic adjustment during the Holocene, is <lb/>not thought to cause age offsets greater than analytical un-<lb/>certainties in most Greenland regions (Jones et al., 2019). <lb/>To remain consistent across the domain, no corrections were <lb/>applied for post-exposure vegetation or snow cover. Final ex-<lb/>posure ages are reported in calendar years (or thousands of <lb/>years, kyr) before present (BP), with &quot;present&quot; defined as the <lb/>year of sampling. Nuclide concentrations and sample meta-<lb/>data were retrieved from ICE-D and/or from original pub-<lb/>lications when needed. When multiple ages were described <lb/>by original publications as dating a single time-synchronous <lb/>margin, these were grouped and summarised by a &quot;summary <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>706 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 2. Comparison between DEM hillshade (light azimuth 315°; incline 45°) of the 2 m spatial resolution ArcticDEM (Porter et al., 2018) <lb/>in the left-hand panel, and the same area with our ice marginal landform mapping superimposed (right-hand panel). The area presented here <lb/>is part of J. C. Christensen Land in north Greenland, as highlighted by the red box in the inset. This region displays remarkable preservation <lb/>and spatial density of terminal and lateral moraine rides, moraine complexes, lateral meltwater channels, and trimlines. <lb/>event age&quot; (Fig. 5) and uncertainty calculated using the pop-<lb/>ulation arithmetic mean and the 1σ standard deviation, re-<lb/>spectively. No grouping of ages was applied if not clearly <lb/>described in source study as dating the same event. While <lb/>TCN exposure ages positioned on mountains can act as for-<lb/>mer ice thickness indicators (e.g. elevation dipstick models), <lb/>they are not used directly by our isochrone reconstruction <lb/>but are included in the database, as they may prove useful for <lb/>comparing with modelled ice sheet thickness predictions, for <lb/>instance. <lb/>Age filtering and quality control <lb/>Stratigraphical and/or statistical outliers were removed from <lb/>event-age calculations only when considered such in orig-<lb/>inal publications. The only exception to this is when sam-<lb/>ple coordinates provided in original publications were either <lb/>missing or erroneous (e.g. plotting offshore or within the ice <lb/>sheet). In this case, the age was considered an outlier and was <lb/>not included in summary event age calculations. For a few <lb/>more recent investigations (e.g. Søndergaard et al., 2020), in <lb/>situ cosmogenic 14 C was also measured alongside 10 Be or <lb/>26 Al. When 14 C-derived exposure ages display younger ex-<lb/>posure ages and are described by authors as presenting less <lb/>nuclide inheritance than other nuclides, they were given pri-<lb/>ority in our summary event age calculations. Our database <lb/>also includes the details of whether paired nuclide analysis <lb/>on a given sample (e.g. 26 Al / 10 Be) suggests a complex ex-<lb/>posure/burial history and thus guides us to exposure ages that <lb/>are likely too old to be considered in our Holocene retreat re-<lb/>construction. Furthermore, to help combine the geomorpho-<lb/>logical and geochronological evidence in a time slice recon-<lb/>struction of ice sheet evolution, TCN exposure ages compiled <lb/>within PaleoGrIS 1.0 are provided a quality control rating <lb/>and classified in three categories described as high-, medium-<lb/>, and low-confidence ages. The criteria list followed to apply <lb/>this quality control is presented in Table 1 and is derived from <lb/>the investigations of Hughes et al. (2016), Small et al. (2017), <lb/>and Davies et al. (2020). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>707 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 3. Examples of mapped ice marginal landforms in two distinct regions displaying high density and preservation of ice marginal <lb/>glacial deposits. The mapped landforms are displayed overlaying topographic data from the AW3D30 DEM (30 m resolution). The left-hand <lb/>panel presents mapping in a region of north Greenland (also referred to as Wulff Land), while the right-hand panel focuses on the deglaciated <lb/>region directly south of Disko Bay in central west Greenland. <lb/>2.2.2 Radiocarbon ages <lb/>Compilation of ages <lb/>The PaleoGrIS 1.0 database also features a collection of <lb/>Greenland-wide radiocarbon ages and associated metadata, <lb/>which provide minimum-limiting age estimates of organic <lb/>deposition in ice-free conditions following ice retreat dur-<lb/>ing the deglacial and Holocene periods. This collection of <lb/>radiocarbon ages was assembled by consulting former ice-<lb/>sheet-scale reviews by Bennike and Björck (2002), Dyke <lb/>(2004), Sinclair et al. (2016), and Dalton et al. (2020). Other <lb/>more regional reviews, including those by Rinterknecht et <lb/>al. (2014), Dyke et al. (2014), Larsen et al. (2014), and Young <lb/>et al. (2021), were also examined. Furthermore, a review of <lb/>the existing literature was conducted with the aim of finding <lb/>other relevant studies not included in the above. Any new ra-<lb/>diocarbon date published after 21 October 2022, our census <lb/>date, is not included in the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database. <lb/>Age calibration and re-calculation <lb/>All radiocarbon ages were consistently recalibrated using the <lb/>IntCal20 curve (Reimer et al., 2020) for terrestrial samples, <lb/>the Marine20 (Heaton et al., 2020) curve for marine samples, <lb/>and the CALIB 8.2 online calibration software (CALIB, http: <lb/>//calib.org/calib/calib.html, last access: 1 December 2022). <lb/>We report final calibrated ages and uncertainty as the mid-<lb/>point ± half of the calibrated age range at 95 % probability <lb/>(2σ ). Calibrated ages are reported in calendar years (or kyr) <lb/>before present (BP), with &quot;present&quot; defined as year 1950. <lb/>For marine samples, we apply a marine reservoir age cor-<lb/>rection protocol that attempts to consistently account for both <lb/>spatial heterogeneity in the reservoir effect itself and for <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>708 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 1. Quality control assessment criteria list for TCN and radiocarbon summary event ages compiled in the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database. <lb/>Criteria are adapted from Hughes et al. (2016), Small et al. (2017), and Davies et al. (2020) to fit the Greenland-specific context of numerical <lb/>dating of former ice sheet margin retreat. Note that AMS is for accelerator mass spectrometer; n/a is for not applicable. <lb/>Dating technique <lb/>Quality control rating Criteria <lb/>Pre-requisites for all techniques n/a <lb/>-All metadata required for age re-calculation/calibration are provided, including AMS <lb/>standards for TCN exposure ages <lb/>-Publication clearly indicates when multiple ages from a site date an event (i.e. map, <lb/>table with groups, stratigraphic age model, etc.) <lb/>-Details of geologic and stratigraphic context are provided <lb/>-Analytical errors are provided and &lt; 10 % of age <lb/>TCN exposure dating <lb/>High confidence <lb/>-Multiple (at least three) ages dating an event after outlier removal <lb/>-Exposure ages dating single event display little scatter; acceptable reduced chi-<lb/>squared statistic <lb/>-No evidence of complex exposure/burial history <lb/>-No indication of major nuclide inheritance or post-depositional disturbance signals <lb/>Medium confidence <lb/>-Only two samples dating an event but showing consistent ages (after outlier removal) <lb/>-Only one sample but for which the 14 C radionuclide was also measured, and it dis-<lb/>plays a consistent or younger exposure age than obtained with other nuclides <lb/>-Only one sample reported to date an event but located near other samples (&lt; ∼ 10 km) <lb/>displaying summary event ages consistent with stratigraphic order of events <lb/>Low confidence <lb/>-Only one geographically isolated sample dating an event (after outlier removal) <lb/>-Multiple samples but highly scattered exposure ages <lb/>-Multi-nuclide analysis shows complex exposure/burial history of sample(s) <lb/>-Coordinates reported by author plot in odd location (e.g. at sea or on ice when study <lb/>site is terrestrial), thus suggesting inaccurate geolocation measurement <lb/>Radiocarbon dating <lb/>High confidence <lb/>-One sample to date an event (after outlier removal), but terrestrial sample and species <lb/>of macrofossil/microfossil is identified and clearly reported <lb/>-Multiple (at least two) consistent samples from a single location or stratigraphic se-<lb/>quence (after outlier removal) to date an event and which include at least one terrestrial <lb/>sample <lb/>Medium confidence <lb/>-Multiple consistent ages to date an event but all marine radiocarbon ages <lb/>-Dated material is clearly reported <lb/>-One terrestrial sample to date an event but dated material is gyttja, peat, and humic <lb/>acid (soil-related) <lb/>Low confidence <lb/>-Only one terrestrial but bulk sediment sample to date an event <lb/>-Only one marine radiocarbon age to date an event <lb/>-Poor stratigraphic context with respect to studied event <lb/>-Dated material is not reported or specific enough to attribute a quality control rating <lb/>-Coordinates reported by author plot in odd location (e.g. at sea or on ice when study <lb/>site is terrestrial), thus suggesting inaccurate geolocation measurement <lb/>variability between R calibration sites. To do so, we cal-<lb/>ibrate all marine ages against the Marine20 curve using re-<lb/>gional R values obtained from the maintained online Ma-<lb/>rine Reservoir Correction Database (http://calib.org/marine/, <lb/>last access: 1 December 2022) (Reimer and Reimer, 2001). <lb/>For each sample and location, a final R value is obtained by <lb/>computing the weighted mean of the 10 nearest available R <lb/>calibration sites, as determined directly from the correction <lb/>database. The reported final uncertainty following this calcu-<lb/>lation is the maximum of the standard deviation of R and <lb/>the weighted uncertainty in mean of R (Bevington, 1969). <lb/>Following this protocol, R values in our database range <lb/>from -113 to 73 years, while R uncertainties range from <lb/>36 to 150 years. We note that these R values mostly overlap <lb/>with the newest Greenland-specific marine reservoir age cor-<lb/>rection assessment of Pearce et al. (2023), which was submit-<lb/>ted after our compiled ages were re-calculated). We acknowl-<lb/>edge that, for polar latitudes (&gt; 50°N), calibrating marine ra-<lb/>diocarbon ages against the Marine20 curve may be problem-<lb/>atic, due to greater variability in ocean ventilation and air-<lb/>sea gas exchange caused by fluctuations in sea ice extent and <lb/>wind strength, leading to increased and more time-variable <lb/>marine reservoir effects (Butzin et al., 2005; Heaton et al., <lb/>2022). However, this is more likely to be problematic during <lb/>glacial periods (Reimer et al., 2020). For polar samples dat-<lb/>ing to the Holocene (11.5-0 kyr BP), Heaton et al. (2022) rec-<lb/>ommend calibrating directly against Marine20. Since the Pa-<lb/>leoGrIS 1.0 reconstruction spans the Late Glacial and early-<lb/>to mid-Holocene (14-6.5 kyr BP) period and because 90 % <lb/>of the calibrated radiocarbon ages compiled in our database <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>709 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 4. Visual and cartographic description of methodology fol-<lb/>lowed to produce an ice-sheet-wide retreat pattern from DEM and <lb/>imagery data. Our procedure involves three main steps of data gen-<lb/>eralisation to incrementally summarise the raw topographic and im-<lb/>agery data to near-continuous ice marginal connectors interpreted as <lb/>representing time-synchronous former ice sheet margins. The latter <lb/>product is then used to inform our isochrone time slice reconstruc-<lb/>tion, which involves adding geochronological information from our <lb/>compilation of TCN and radiocarbon-derived event ages. <lb/>are younger than 11 kyr BP, we choose to treat all samples <lb/>the same, for consistency. <lb/>Age filtering and quality control <lb/>Previous reviews and published studies were systematically <lb/>filtered so that only radiocarbon dates produced with the aim <lb/>to constrain the evolution of the ice sheet margin through <lb/>time were compiled. Following this logic, only dated events <lb/>that present a clear stratigraphic link to the evolution of the <lb/>former ice sheet extent are incorporated in the database. In <lb/>Greenland, a common example of such dates are multiple <lb/>radiocarbon dates down a core of lacustrine sediments fea-<lb/>turing a clear sedimentological transition from subglacial <lb/>(e.g. till) to proglacial (e.g. silts and clays) deposits. In the <lb/>latter case, and for any deglacial chronologies presenting <lb/>multiple radiocarbon ages from a single core or single loca-<lb/>tion, the oldest age of the sequence was considered the clos-<lb/>est age estimate of ice-free conditions and organic deposition <lb/>following ice retreat and was thus retained as the summary <lb/>event age (following Hughes et al., 2016; Small et al., 2017; <lb/>Dalton et al., 2020) (Fig. 5). The data were also filtered so <lb/>that radiocarbon ages dating the evolution of Greenland pe-<lb/>riphery ice caps and mountain glaciers were not included in <lb/>this collection. Stratigraphical and/or statistical outliers were <lb/>not included in the summary event age compilation when <lb/>described as such in original publications. Samples featur-<lb/>ing missing or erroneous geographical coordinates were also <lb/>considered outliers. Radiocarbon ages compiled within Pa-<lb/>leoGrIS 1.0 are given a quality control rating and are clas-<lb/>sified in three categories described as high-, medium-, and <lb/>low-confidence ages. The criteria list followed to apply this <lb/>quality control consistently through the dataset is displayed <lb/>in Table 1. <lb/>2.2.3 The PaleoGrIS 1.0 geochronological database <lb/>format <lb/>TCN and radiocarbon ages compiled were entered into <lb/>two respective Excel (.xlsx) spreadsheets made avail-<lb/>able in the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database (data available from <lb/>https://doi.org/10.17632/nh57cz4gys.1, Leger et al., 2024). <lb/>Both spreadsheets (one for TCN and one for radiocarbon) <lb/>document sample information and source publication details <lb/>(also in Tables 2 and 3), metadata relevant to age calibra-<lb/>tion and re-calculations, all event identification and summary <lb/>event ages, and age quality control attributions. A subset of <lb/>these details including sample names, locations, source pub-<lb/>lications, summary event ages and uncertainties were used <lb/>to generate point shapefiles for use with any geographic in-<lb/>formation system software (e.g. ArcMap or QGIS). Further <lb/>details concerning the several shapefiles published alongside <lb/>this work are described in the ReadMe files provided in the <lb/>online database. <lb/>2.3 Producing Greenland-Ice-Sheet-wide isochrones <lb/>Within the context of reconstructing past ice sheet extent, <lb/>isochrones are defined as time-stamped and spatially con-<lb/>tinuous margins highlighting changes in the former spa-<lb/>tial extent of an entire ice sheet over time. Reconstructing <lb/>such continuous perimeters is a challenge, given a fragmen-<lb/>tary evidence base. Geochronological and geomorphological <lb/>data available to empirically reconstruct isochrones are either <lb/>point data (ages) or fragments of line data (e.g. moraine map-<lb/>ping). Such data are characterised by highly variable tempo-<lb/>ral and spatial densities and are associated with uncertainties <lb/>of their own. Therefore, the task of drawing time-stamped <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>710 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 5. Spatial distribution of radiocarbon-derived (a) and TCN-exposure-age-derived (b) summary event ages (after filtering and statis-<lb/>tics) used to produce the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction. Topographic and bathymetric data (GEBCO 2022 release) are overlaid <lb/>with 1000 m interval contour lines. The dashed line shows our division scheme of the ice sheet in seven main drainage regions that we refer <lb/>to throughout the paper and in associated quantitative analyses, after the drainage basin sampling scheme of Rignot and Mouginot (2012), <lb/>labelled in panel (b). Panel (b) also features lines denoting our estimations of maximum and minimum scenarios of the last full glacial <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet extent (grounded ice only), based on a review of the literature (see Sect. 2.6), and which informs the mapping of our <lb/>outermost isochrones. <lb/>and spatially continuous ice sheet perimeters involves in-<lb/>terpolating between empirical evidence and extrapolating <lb/>across blank areas of the map (e.g. Stroeven et al., 2016; <lb/>Hughes et al., 2016). The following paragraphs describe the <lb/>methods followed to produce isochrones that combine ge-<lb/>omorphological and geochronological evidence, while sep-<lb/>arately accounting for temporal and spatial uncertainties in <lb/>empirical data. <lb/>2.3.1 Isochrone time span, temporal resolution, and <lb/>uncertainty <lb/>For PaleoGrIS 1.0, we map isochrones that delineate <lb/>grounded ice only (and not floating ice fronts) (Fig. 6). <lb/>Since Greenland ice-free land areas were deglaciated mostly <lb/>during the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene peri-<lb/>ods, there is a higher density of terrestrial TCN and ra-<lb/>diocarbon dates displaying ages between 12 and 6.5 kyr BP <lb/>(Fig. 7). Following the Holocene thermal maximum, between <lb/>6.5 and 2 kyr BP, the number of available dates drop signifi-<lb/>cantly (Fig. 7). This coincides with the ice sheet reaching its <lb/>minimum Holocene extent (between ∼ 7 and ∼ 4.5 kyr BP), <lb/>which, in most Greenland regions, was either as extensive <lb/>as or more retreated than today&apos;s margin position (Larsen et <lb/>al., 2015; Briner et al., 2016). After ∼ 5-4 kyr BP, the on-<lb/>set of neoglacial cooling caused ice sheet readvances culmi-<lb/>nating in the Little Ice Age, which explains the small rela-<lb/>tive increase in the number of dates in our compilation af-<lb/>ter 2 kyr BP (Fig. 7). Consequently, the time period featuring <lb/>enough terrestrial geochronological evidence for reconstruct-<lb/>ing past retreat at the ice sheet scale currently spans only <lb/>6-7 kyr. Recent methodological and technological improve-<lb/>ments to TCN exposure and radiocarbon dating now enable <lb/>the production of Holocene ages with analytical uncertain-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>711 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2. List of publications and associated numbers of compiled ages in PaleoGrIS 1.0 for TCN surface exposure dating. <lb/>TCN exposure ages <lb/>Publication <lb/>Number of <lb/>Publication <lb/>Number of <lb/>ages compiled <lb/>ages compiled <lb/>Andersen et al. (2020) <lb/>13 <lb/>Lesnek and Briner (2018) <lb/>24 <lb/>Balter-Kennedy et al. (2021) <lb/>5 <lb/>Levy et al. (2012) <lb/>9 <lb/>Briner et al. (2013) <lb/>2 <lb/>Levy et al. (2016) <lb/>16 <lb/>Carlson et al. (2014) <lb/>29 <lb/>Levy et al. (2018) <lb/>16 <lb/>Ceperley et al. (2020) <lb/>71 <lb/>Levy et al. (2020) <lb/>41 <lb/>Corbett et al. (2011) <lb/>30 <lb/>Nelson et al. (2014) <lb/>11 <lb/>Corbett et al. (2013) <lb/>19 <lb/>Philipps et al. (2017) <lb/>6 <lb/>Corbett et al. (2015) <lb/>28 <lb/>Reusche et al. (2018) <lb/>33 <lb/>Cronauer et al. (2016) <lb/>11 <lb/>Rinterknecht et al. (2009) <lb/>12 <lb/>Dyke et al. (2014) <lb/>23 <lb/>Rinterknecht et al. (2014) <lb/>7 <lb/>Garcia-Oteyza et al. (2022) <lb/>39 <lb/>Roberts et al. (2008) <lb/>12 <lb/>Håkansson et al. (2007a) <lb/>4 <lb/>Roberts et al. (2009) <lb/>16 <lb/>Håkansson et al. (2007b) <lb/>7 <lb/>Roberts et al. (2013) <lb/>17 <lb/>Hughes et al. (2012) <lb/>12 <lb/>Skov et al. (2020) <lb/>25 <lb/>Kelley et al. (2012) <lb/>2 <lb/>Søndergaard et al. (2019) <lb/>3 <lb/>Kelley et al. (2013) <lb/>12 <lb/>Søndergaard et al. (2020) <lb/>27 <lb/>Kelley et al. (2015) <lb/>18 <lb/>Winsor et al. (2014) <lb/>17 <lb/>Lane et al. (2014) <lb/>15 <lb/>Winsor et al. (2015) <lb/>47 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2014) <lb/>47 <lb/>Young et al. (2013a) <lb/>47 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2018) <lb/>28 <lb/>Young et al. (2013b) <lb/>5 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2020) <lb/>43 <lb/>Young et al. (2020) <lb/>62 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2021) <lb/>9 <lb/>Young et al. (2021) <lb/>61 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2022) <lb/>47 <lb/>ties that can be inferior to 500 and 200 years (at 1σ ), respec-<lb/>tively. For these reasons, we chose to produce ice-sheet-wide <lb/>isochrones at 500-year temporal resolution between 12 and <lb/>6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Between 14 and 12 kyr BP, a period characterised by a <lb/>predominantly marine-terminating ice sheet constrained by <lb/>fewer empirical data, we chose to draw isochrones at a 1000-<lb/>year temporal resolution. Prior to this, between the ice sheet&apos;s <lb/>last full glacial extent and 14 kyr BP, the ice sheet is thought <lb/>to have been mostly grounded on the presently submerged <lb/>continental shelf (Funder et al., 2011). A few offshore sam-<lb/>pling studies provide geochronological constraints for the ap-<lb/>proximate location of the grounded ice margin during this <lb/>time period (e.g. Smith and Licht, 2000; Kuijpers et al., 2003; <lb/>Ó Cofaigh et al., 2013). However, we believe such studies are <lb/>currently too scarce and spatially scattered to enable tracing <lb/>ice-sheet-wide isochrones between the last full glacial ex-<lb/>tent and 14 kyr BP and hope such improvements can be made <lb/>with future versions of this reconstruction as more data from <lb/>less studied regions arise. The PaleoGrIS 1.0 reconstruction <lb/>therefore features 14 isochrones (or time slices) between 14 <lb/>and 6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>In an attempt to account for uncertainties inherent to TCN <lb/>exposure and radiocarbon dating, we chose to allocate a time <lb/>range to individual isochrones and thus to each time slice <lb/>of our reconstruction (Fig. 6). For instance, the youngest <lb/>and innermost isochrone of PaleoGrIS 1.0 is here referred <lb/>to as the 7-6.5 kyr BP isochrone. This means that we esti-<lb/>mate the former margin to have been near the location of <lb/>that isochrone line at any time between ∼ 7 and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>This line was thus drawn to connect, as much as possible, <lb/>the landforms and summary event ages comprised between <lb/>7.0 and 6.5 kyr BP when rounded to the nearest 100 years. <lb/>This approach is different from previous time slice recon-<lb/>structions that attributed a single timestamp to isochrones <lb/>and choosing to represent the dating uncertainty spatially by <lb/>differentiating minimum, maximum, and/or optimum posi-<lb/>tions for isochrones for a given time slice (e.g. Dyke and <lb/>Prest, 1987; Hughes et al., 2016; Davies et al., 2020; Dal-<lb/>ton et al., 2020; Clark et al., 2022). Contrastingly, the Pa-<lb/>leoGrIS 1.0 approach aims to more clearly distinguish and <lb/>separate the temporal from the spatial uncertainties inherent <lb/>to isochrone reconstructions. Isochrone temporal uncertainty <lb/>is exclusively associated with the analytical and calculation/-<lb/>calibration uncertainties of the numerical dates (TCN or ra-<lb/>diocarbon), while isochrone spatial uncertainty instead re-<lb/>sults from spatially variable density of geochronological and <lb/>geomorphological evidence. Here, the latter is treated by at-<lb/>tributing various confidence levels along a single isochrone <lb/>line (more details in Sect. 2.3.5). Therefore, our approach <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>712 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Table 3. List of publications and associated number of compiled ages in PaleoGrIS 1.0 for radiocarbon dating. <lb/>Radiocarbon ages <lb/>Publication <lb/>Number of <lb/>Publication <lb/>Number of <lb/>ages compiled <lb/>ages compiled <lb/>Bennike and Kelly (1987) <lb/>2 <lb/>Kelly and Bennike (1985) <lb/>1 <lb/>Bennike et al. (1994) <lb/>3 <lb/>Kelly and Bennike (1992) <lb/>7 <lb/>Bennike et al. (1999) <lb/>2 <lb/>Kelly and Funder (1974) <lb/>3 <lb/>Bennike (2000) <lb/>4 <lb/>Kelly et al. (1999) <lb/>3 <lb/>Bennike (2002) <lb/>19 <lb/>Kuijpers et al. (2003) <lb/>1 <lb/>Bennike et al. (2002) <lb/>6 <lb/>Landvik et al. (2001) <lb/>3 <lb/>Bennike (2008) <lb/>1 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2014) <lb/>15 <lb/>Bennike and Björck (2002) <lb/>7 <lb/>Larsen et al. (2021) <lb/>4 <lb/>Bennike and Wagner (2012) <lb/>1 <lb/>Levy et al. (2017) <lb/>7 <lb/>Bennike and Weidick (2001) <lb/>75 <lb/>Lloyd et al. (2005) <lb/>2 <lb/>Bick (1978) <lb/>1 <lb/>Long and Roberts (2002) <lb/>4 <lb/>Björk et al. (1994) <lb/>1 <lb/>Long and Roberts (2003) <lb/>5 <lb/>Blake (1987) <lb/>4 <lb/>Long et al. (1999) <lb/>12 <lb/>Blake (1992) <lb/>1 <lb/>Long et al. (2003) <lb/>1 <lb/>Blake et al. (1996) <lb/>1 <lb/>Long et al. (2006) <lb/>5 <lb/>Böcher and Bennike (1996) <lb/>1 <lb/>Long et al. (2008) <lb/>2 <lb/>Briner et al. (2010) <lb/>3 <lb/>Manley and Jennings (1996) <lb/>1 <lb/>Briner et al. (2013) <lb/>4 <lb/>Marienfeld (1990) <lb/>3 <lb/>Christiansen et al. (2002) <lb/>1 <lb/>McCarthy (2011) <lb/>1 <lb/>Crane and Griffin (1959) <lb/>1 <lb/>Nichols (1969) <lb/>1 <lb/>Cremer et al. (2001) <lb/>1 <lb/>Ó Cofaigh et al. (2013) <lb/>5 <lb/>Davies et al. (2022) <lb/>2 <lb/>Perner et al. (2013) <lb/>4 <lb/>Delibrias et al. (1986) <lb/>1 <lb/>Puleo et al. (2022) <lb/>1 <lb/>Donner and Junger (1975) <lb/>3 <lb/>Shotton et al. (1974) <lb/>1 <lb/>Dowdeswell et al. (1994) <lb/>1 <lb/>Simonarson (1981) <lb/>1 <lb/>Eisner et al. (1995) <lb/>1 <lb/>Smith and Licht (2000) <lb/>9 <lb/>England (1985) <lb/>5 <lb/>Søndergaard et al. (2019) <lb/>1 <lb/>Fredskild (1972) <lb/>2 <lb/>Sparrenbom et al. (2006) <lb/>3 <lb/>Fredskild (1973) <lb/>2 <lb/>Storms et al. (2012) <lb/>6 <lb/>Fredskild (1983) <lb/>7 <lb/>Sugden et al. (1972) <lb/>1 <lb/>Fredskild (1985) <lb/>2 <lb/>Tauber (1966) <lb/>1 <lb/>Fredskild (1995) <lb/>1 <lb/>Tauber (1968) <lb/>1 <lb/>Funder (1978) <lb/>2 <lb/>Ten Brink and Weidick (1974) <lb/>3 <lb/>Funder (1982) <lb/>7 <lb/>Trautman (1963) <lb/>1 <lb/>Funder (1990) <lb/>4 <lb/>Trautman and Willis (1966) <lb/>1 <lb/>Funder and Abrahamsen (1988) <lb/>2 <lb/>van Tatenhove et al. (1996) <lb/>3 <lb/>Funder and Hansen (1996) <lb/>2 <lb/>Wagner et al. (2000) <lb/>2 <lb/>Gulliksen et al. (1991) <lb/>1 <lb/>Wagner and Melles (2002) <lb/>2 <lb/>Håkansson (1974) <lb/>1 <lb/>Washburn and Stuiver (1962) <lb/>1 <lb/>Håkansson (1975) <lb/>1 <lb/>Weidick (1968) <lb/>1 <lb/>Håkansson (1976) <lb/>1 <lb/>Weidick (1972) <lb/>3 <lb/>Håkansson (1987) <lb/>1 <lb/>Weidick (1975) <lb/>4 <lb/>Hansen (2001) <lb/>4 <lb/>Weidick (1976) <lb/>22 <lb/>Hansen et al. (2022) <lb/>2 <lb/>Weidick (1977) <lb/>2 <lb/>Hjort (1979) <lb/>8 <lb/>Weidick (1978) <lb/>6 <lb/>Hjort (1981) <lb/>4 <lb/>Weidick and Bennike (2007) <lb/>10 <lb/>Hjort (1997) <lb/>2 <lb/>Weidick et al. (1990) <lb/>1 <lb/>Ingólfsson et al. (1990) <lb/>5 <lb/>Weidick et al. (1996) <lb/>1 <lb/>Ingólfsson et al. (1994) <lb/>1 <lb/>Weidick et al. (2004) <lb/>1 <lb/>Ives et al. (1964) <lb/>1 <lb/>Willemse (2000) <lb/>1 <lb/>Jennings et al. (2002) <lb/>1 <lb/>Williams (1993) <lb/>6 <lb/>Jennings et al. (2014) <lb/>1 <lb/>Williams et al. (1995) <lb/>1 <lb/>Kaufman and Williams (1992) <lb/>1 <lb/>Young et al. (2011a) <lb/>1 <lb/>Kelly (1973) <lb/>2 <lb/>Young et al. (2011b) <lb/>4 <lb/>Kelly (1979) <lb/>1 <lb/>Young et al. (2013b) <lb/>3 <lb/>Kelly (1980) <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>713 <lb/></page>

	<body>allows comparing numerical ice sheet model outputs to a <lb/>single isochrone, while enabling model time to vary within <lb/>our isochrone temporal error range and thus account for an-<lb/>alytical uncertainty in geochronological data. To help mod-<lb/>ellers use the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones in their model-data <lb/>comparison procedures, our online database includes details <lb/>(ReadMe files) on how various data formats could be used, <lb/>depending on the model resolution and the type of experi-<lb/>ment conducted. <lb/>2.3.2 Rules followed when drawing isochrones <lb/>To draw spatially continuous isochrones as consistently as <lb/>possible around the ice sheet&apos;s periphery, the following work-<lb/>flow and set of rules were applied. <lb/>-Using ArcMap 10.7.1 software, we displayed our land-<lb/>form mapping database accompanied by our synthe-<lb/>sised pattern of retreat map. <lb/>-All TCN and radiocarbon summary event ages were dis-<lb/>played rounded to 100 years and feature a traffic light <lb/>colour code relating to one of the three confidence level <lb/>categories (Table 1). <lb/>-All information was displayed on a rendition of topog-<lb/>raphy from the ALOS World 3D 30 m spatial resolution <lb/>DEM and bathymetry from the GEBCO 2022 release. <lb/>-The location of contemporary grounded ice was dis-<lb/>played at all times using the raster mask of the IceBridge <lb/>BedMachine Greenland version 4 dataset (Morlighem et <lb/>al., 2017). <lb/>-Isochrones were interpreted and mapped, working <lb/>clockwise around the full Greenland perimeter, and se-<lb/>quentially following chronological order (starting from <lb/>oldest). The process was conducted iteratively and with <lb/>numerous adjustments, as the position of an individual <lb/>isochrone might depend upon the preceding and suc-<lb/>ceeding ones. Multiple authors re-interpreted and con-<lb/>tributed to the final isochrones to try and ensure a con-<lb/>sensus view of possible alternate behaviours. <lb/>-When the ice sheet was more extensive than present <lb/>everywhere, isochrones were drawn around the whole <lb/>of Greenland. However, during younger isochrone time <lb/>slices (i.e. 10-6.5 kyr BP), paleo ice sheet margins were <lb/>likely similar to present-day positions, or in a more re-<lb/>treated position, for certain regions (Briner et al., 2010; <lb/>Larsen et al., 2015). In such cases, isochrones were not <lb/>drawn around the full ice sheet perimeter but were in-<lb/>stead interrupted where they meet the present-day mar-<lb/>gin. We do not attempt to map out the extent of ice <lb/>where it retreated inside of the present-day position, as <lb/>the position of the ice margin is largely undefined/un-<lb/>known, even within regions where it is known to have <lb/>occurred. <lb/>The precise method employed when drawing isochrone lines <lb/>varied, depending on the nature and spatiotemporal density <lb/>of empirical data available. When both mapped ice marginal <lb/>landforms and TCN or radiocarbon event ages coincided, <lb/>the line was drawn through both sets of information. When <lb/>only reliable event ages were available, the line was drawn to <lb/>connect them while considering the topography, bathymetry, <lb/>and spatial configuration of the modern ice sheet margin <lb/>(e.g. Fig. 6). On the other hand, when only mapped ice <lb/>marginal landforms were available, the line was drawn fol-<lb/>lowing the landforms and topography/bathymetry only. In <lb/>the absence of any chronological constraints, the retreat pat-<lb/>tern was assumed to be monotonic in nature, i.e. producing <lb/>a decreasing extent that is spatially and temporally consis-<lb/>tent. The resulting ice margin isochrones are thus much more <lb/>complex than a product of lines joining up geochronological <lb/>point data (Fig. 6). Instead, the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones rep-<lb/>resent a qualitative reconciliation and interpretation of topo-<lb/>graphic, geomorphological, and geochronological data. Such <lb/>a heuristic approach sometimes relies on soft knowledge of <lb/>typical interactions between ice sheet margins and topog-<lb/>raphy, including the lobate behaviour of outlet glaciers and <lb/>the dynamics of ice flow around present-day Greenland. The <lb/>isochrones therefore stand as an informed interpretation of <lb/>successive ice margin positions, well constrained in some <lb/>places and in others much less so, and which are likely to <lb/>require adjustment once further landform or geochronologi-<lb/>cal data become available. <lb/>2.3.3 Addressing periphery ice caps and glaciers <lb/>During the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene, as the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet margin receded, peripheral ice caps <lb/>and mountain glaciers became separated from the main ice <lb/>sheet body. Ideally, a full reconstruction of the ice sheet <lb/>Late Glacial and Holocene evolution would also include the <lb/>changing extent of these peripheral ice bodies. Future ver-<lb/>sions of PaleoGrIS could usefully be extended to include the <lb/>development of such peripheral ice caps, but for this first ver-<lb/>sion, we chose to exclusively reconstruct the retreat pattern of <lb/>the main body of the ice sheet. Peripheral ice caps were thus <lb/>either (i) included within the perimeter of the reconstructed <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet margin, when the latter was considered <lb/>extensive enough, or (ii) excluded from our reconstruction, <lb/>after complete separation from the ice sheet was estimated to <lb/>have occurred. <lb/>2.3.4 Connection with the Innuitian Ice Sheet <lb/>Ellesmere Island lies just 100 km to the NW of Greenland <lb/>(Fig. 1), and along with much of the rest of the Canadian Arc-<lb/>tic Archipelago, it was covered by the Innuitian Ice Sheet, <lb/>which is thought to have been connected to the Laurentide <lb/>Ice Sheet until approximately 10.5-9.5 kyr BP (England et <lb/>al., 2006). Given such a close proximity, it is deemed likely <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>714 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 6. Example maps showing the details of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones in a land-dominated region of central west Greenland (a) and <lb/>a fjord-dominated region of central east Greenland (Scoresby Sund (b)). The two examples highlight our choice of distinguishing isochrone <lb/>temporal uncertainty (shown by time ranges labelled in bold black) from isochrone spatial uncertainty (shown by the four colour-coded <lb/>confidence levels). The figure also displays the location of local event ages compiled in our database which is colour-coded here based on <lb/>our quality control assessment (Table 1). All data are displayed with the AW3D30 DEM overlaid (30 m resolution). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>715 <lb/></page>

	<body>that the Greenland and Innuitian ice sheets coalesced over <lb/>Nares Strait during glacial maxima (Dyke, 2004; Sinclair et <lb/>al., 2016; Funder et al., 2011; Georgiadis et al., 2018; Dal-<lb/>ton et al., 2020). We chose to make no inferences regarding <lb/>the pattern of retreat associated with the margins of the In-<lb/>nuitian Ice Sheet. We thus draw isochrones that are consis-<lb/>tent with the two ice sheets merging, but we interrupt them <lb/>towards the point of deepest bathymetry between Greenland <lb/>and Ellesmere Island throughout the length of Nares Strait. <lb/>The same method was applied to close polygon shapefiles <lb/>over Nares Strait when measuring the ice sheet&apos;s areal extent <lb/>and create time slice maps. <lb/>2.3.5 Isochrone confidence levels <lb/>Geochronological and geomorphological evidence are spa-<lb/>tiotemporally heterogeneous, causing each isochrone to fea-<lb/>ture spatially variable levels of reliability around its perime-<lb/>ter (e.g. Fig. 6). Given this uneven distribution of informa-<lb/>tion, our mapping procedure was adapted accordingly. We <lb/>split each isochrone line into four confidence level categories <lb/>referred to as high, medium, low, or very low confidence <lb/>isochrones, by applying the following set of rules. <lb/>-High-confidence isochrone sections. These are drawn <lb/>when empirical evidence features both mapped ice <lb/>marginal landforms and TCN or radiocarbon event ages <lb/>and deemed reliable, i.e. graded high or medium confi-<lb/>dence. <lb/>-Medium-confidence isochrone sections. These are <lb/>drawn when empirical evidence does not feature <lb/>mapped ice marginal landforms but features reliable <lb/>event ages, i.e. graded high or medium confidence. <lb/>-Low-confidence isochrone sections. These are drawn <lb/>when empirical evidence features only ice marginal <lb/>landforms or only low reliability dates, i.e. ages graded <lb/>low confidence. <lb/>-Very low-confidence isochrone sections. These are <lb/>drawn in the absence of any mapped geomorphological <lb/>or any geochronological evidence but relying on topo-<lb/>graphic and/or bathymetric information exclusively. <lb/>2.3.6 Ages that could not reasonably be reconciled to <lb/>isochrones <lb/>When building isochrones by integrating geochronological <lb/>evidence from numerous published sources and locations, <lb/>contradictory evidence can become challenging to resolve. <lb/>For instance, this can occur when nearby event ages display <lb/>high age variability while presenting similar levels of relia-<lb/>bility but also when they are found reversed relative to the <lb/>general direction of presumed ice retreat, and/or relative to <lb/>stratigraphic order of events in nearby valleys/regions. <lb/>For TCN exposure dating, misleading ages can result from <lb/>nuclide inheritance causing apparent ages that are too old, <lb/>post-depositional disturbance causing apparent ages that are <lb/>too young, or laboratory contamination/errors potentially <lb/>causing both (Dunai, 2010). Such issues are in most cases <lb/>reported in original publications, thus enabling us to eas-<lb/>ily identify outliers. In Greenland more specifically, Late <lb/>Glacial and Holocene studies generally report nuclide inher-<lb/>itance to be the dominating cause of exposure age scatter <lb/>(Larsen et al., 2021). For radiocarbon ages, delayed organic <lb/>growth following ice retreat or contamination by younger <lb/>organics (e.g. for bulk samples) can cause ages to be too <lb/>young. This challenge is common in the Arctic, where post-<lb/>deglaciation biodiversity establishment is relatively slow. For <lb/>marine ages, an erroneous estimation of the marine reservoir <lb/>effect can also cause calibrated ages to misrepresent the true <lb/>deposition age. Moreover, in Greenland, numerous radiocar-<lb/>bon ages were produced to date the marine-to-freshwater <lb/>transition of basins following isostatic uplift caused by ice re-<lb/>treat (Weidick et al., 2004). Delay in such uplift can increase <lb/>the potential for radiocarbon ages underestimating the timing <lb/>of deglaciation. The misfit between our isochrone reconstruc-<lb/>tion and a specific event age may also be due to oversights in <lb/>our age-filtering exercise. <lb/>In these challenging cases, drawing isochrones requires <lb/>subjective decisions to either favour and/or ignore certain <lb/>seemingly awkward or anomalous event ages when weighed <lb/>against our interpretation of the most representative tim-<lb/>ing of local deglaciation. Such interpretations were either <lb/>based on a review of the region-specific literature or on as-<lb/>sessing the distance separating relevant isochrones in ad-<lb/>jacent regions displaying more consistent geochronologi-<lb/>cal constraints. Summary event ages deemed challenging <lb/>and ignored were identified and gathered after the mapping <lb/>of isochrones in a separate shapefile available in the on-<lb/>line database (https://doi.org/10.17632/nh57cz4gys.1, Leger <lb/>et al., 2024). We acknowledge that decisions to ignore event <lb/>ages are necessarily subjective (see Sect. 2.3.2). <lb/>2.3.7 Limitations and uncertainties in isochrone <lb/>reconstruction <lb/>In regions of Greenland with a high quality and density of <lb/>geochronological and geomorphological constraints (e.g. the <lb/>Sisimiut and Disko Bay regions), former ice margins can <lb/>be reconstructed with reasonably high levels of confidence. <lb/>Contrastingly, our reconstruction also features crude interpo-<lb/>lations of ice margins over vast areas, due to the low den-<lb/>sity or absence of empirical evidence in numerous locations. <lb/>Thus, the heterogeneous nature of our reconstruction&apos;s un-<lb/>certainties, as depicted by our four different confidence levels <lb/>(Sect. 2.3.5), calls for caution. One must stress that the Pale-<lb/>oGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction is not intended for use at <lb/>the valley or regional scale, for which local investigations are <lb/>likely more accurate (e.g. Pearce et al., 2018), but rather at <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>716 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>continental scale. Caution should also be applied concerning <lb/>the temporal resolution of our reconstruction, which aims to <lb/>provide estimates of ice sheet margin positions every 1000-<lb/>500 years. In fact, our reconstruction should be regarded <lb/>as averaged or net retreat over such time intervals, and any <lb/>short-lived readvances or dynamic ice sheet margin response <lb/>(e.g. tens to hundreds of years) are not captured in our re-<lb/>construction. In most locations, the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones <lb/>should not be considered precise enough to accurately depict <lb/>the margin evolution of individual outlet glaciers, to predict <lb/>the formation of small proglacial lakes and spillways, or to <lb/>reconstruct past meltwater pathways, for instance. The relia-<lb/>bility of the reconstruction is, of course, dependent on the un-<lb/>derpinning evidence, an examination of which should guide <lb/>a user away from more speculative areas. The continental-<lb/>scale mapping approach can sometimes cause resulting ice <lb/>configurations to be glaciologically unrealistic and inconsis-<lb/>tent with a complex landscape at the valley scale (&lt; 5 km <lb/>spatial resolution), despite our efforts to consider the influ-<lb/>ence of local topography/bathymetry as much as possible. <lb/>Over the past 30 years, several offshore investigations have <lb/>established the approximate location of the ice margin during <lb/>initial deglaciation from its local full glacial position (∼ 17-<lb/>12 kyr BP) when the ice sheet was mostly marine-terminating <lb/>(e.g. Smith and Licht, 2000; Nørgaard-Pedersen et al., 2008; <lb/>Evans et al., 2009; Ó Cofaigh et al., 2004, 2013; Rasmussen <lb/>et al., 2022; Hansen et al., 2022; Lloyd et al., 2023). Such <lb/>studies remain scarce, and we find former grounding line <lb/>positions remain largely understudied and undated. Readers <lb/>should thus be aware that our oldest isochrones (i.e. between <lb/>∼ 14 and ∼ 12 kyr BP) are associated with crude interpola-<lb/>tions across large offshore areas, thus presenting higher lev-<lb/>els of uncertainty than we now have for the terrestrial areas. <lb/>We believe there is much scope for reducing isochrone un-<lb/>certainty in future versions of the PaleoGrIS reconstruction, <lb/>as more mapping and dating are conducted from less stud-<lb/>ied regions. We make suggestions as to which regions would <lb/>most benefit from this attention in a discussion section later <lb/>in the paper. <lb/>2.4 Estimating areal extent change in the Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet <lb/>To evaluate the former areal extent of the ice sheet (i.e. two-<lb/>dimensional surface area) between ∼ 14 and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP, <lb/>we produced a series of polygon shapefiles covering the area <lb/>delineated by each isochrone perimeter and measured their <lb/>areal extent using the ArcMap geometry calculator. To com-<lb/>pare variations regionally, we divided the ice sheet into seven <lb/>major hydrological basins, following the ice divide sampling <lb/>of Rignot and Mouginot (2012) and the IMBIE Team (2019) <lb/>(Fig. 5). Region-dividing polylines were extended towards <lb/>the outermost isochrones, following topographic/bathymet-<lb/>ric highs, while remaining as perpendicular to isochrones as <lb/>possible. Therefore, for the exclusive purpose of subdividing <lb/>the ice sheet into regions, the catchment areas were crudely <lb/>assumed to remain similar from ∼ 14 kyr BP onwards, as <lb/>their paleo configurations remain unknown. Between the 14-<lb/>13 and 10.5-10 kyr BP time slices, we consider our measure-<lb/>ments as absolute estimates of areal extent. However, for <lb/>time slices between 10-9.5 and 7-6.5 kyr BP, our measure-<lb/>ments should be regarded as maximum-limiting estimates of <lb/>ice sheet areal extent. That is because empirical evidence <lb/>suggests the ice sheet was as extensive as or smaller than <lb/>today in several regions during that time interval. In these <lb/>cases, we chose not to guess the extent of retreat behind the <lb/>current margin and merged polygons representing more ex-<lb/>tensive margins with the contemporary ice sheet extent in <lb/>data-free regions. Present-day ice sheet areal extent was com-<lb/>puted from BedMachine Greenland version 4 (Morlighem et <lb/>al., 2017) after removing peripheral glaciers. <lb/>We chose not to convert our ice sheet areal extent recon-<lb/>struction into a volume and mass estimation. The Greenland <lb/>Ice Sheet was characterised by very cold and arid condi-<lb/>tions during extensive advance and, conversely, significant <lb/>increases in accumulation occurred during deglacial margin <lb/>retreat. The relationship between areal extent and ice thick-<lb/>ness is thus complex and not necessarily positively corre-<lb/>lated across the ice sheet (Cuffey and Clow, 1997). Obtain-<lb/>ing a realistic deglacial volume reconstruction of the Green-<lb/>land Ice Sheet requires extensive modelling experiments that <lb/>take climate, surface mass balance, glacial isostatic adjust-<lb/>ment, relative sea level change, calving, and basal sliding <lb/>(e.g. Bradley et al., 2018) into account and that conduct <lb/>quantitative model-data comparisons. Our team is conduct-<lb/>ing such an experiment with the Parallel Ice Sheet Model <lb/>(Winkelmann et al., 2011) and will thus present volume re-<lb/>constructions in a separate publication. <lb/>2.5 Assessing rates of retreat and their variation <lb/>To quantitatively estimate the former retreat rates of out-<lb/>let glaciers, 72 transects emanating from present-day out-<lb/>lets were drawn. Transects were traced from the outermost <lb/>(14-13 kyr BP) to the innermost (7-6.5 kyr BP) PaleoGrIS <lb/>1.0 isochrone margins, following our estimate of the former <lb/>glacier front central position at each time step and guided by <lb/>topography. We thus follow the assumption that the approx-<lb/>imate centre of former glacier termini (or grounding lines) <lb/>was located near the point of lowest topography. Hence, such <lb/>transects should not be interpreted as supraglacial flowlines, <lb/>as these would have likely evolved through time with glacier <lb/>catchments and ice divides potentially readjusting during <lb/>deglaciation. The transects are made available in a polyline <lb/>shapefile (see the online database). Present-day outlet glacier <lb/>names (preferably new Greenlandic, otherwise Danish) were <lb/>obtained from the database of Bjørk et al. (2015), while <lb/>distances along transects were measured for each isochrone <lb/>spacing using ArcMap. As each isochrone is associated with <lb/>a temporal uncertainty (i.e. 1000 or 500 years), both min-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>717 <lb/></page>

	<body>imum and maximum retreat rates were calculated for each <lb/>time step. The reported retreat rate for each step is taken as <lb/>the midpoint ± half the range. For the purpose of evaluating <lb/>former retreat rates only, the positions of isochrones are re-<lb/>garded as definite, and the reported error is exclusively tem-<lb/>poral. For each transect, an overall retreat rate (± temporal <lb/>uncertainty) is also computed using the total distance divided <lb/>by the minimum and maximum time span between outermost <lb/>and innermost isochrones. <lb/>2.6 Where and when was Greenland&apos;s last full glacial <lb/>extent? <lb/>Although we mostly focus on the terrestrial deglaciation <lb/>from ∼ 14 kyr BP onwards, it was important for positioning <lb/>this outermost isochrone to have some knowledge of greater <lb/>ice extents and indeed the maximum achieved extent in the <lb/>last glacial. A review of Greenland&apos;s potential last full glacial <lb/>extent (thought to occur around 18-16 kyr BP; Simpson et <lb/>al., 2009) was conducted. We updated the full glacial margin <lb/>drawn by Funder et al. (2011) after consulting publications <lb/>contributing new empirical knowledge to that specific ques-<lb/>tion (Möller et al., 2010; Ó Cofaigh et al., 2013; Arndt et <lb/>al., 2017; Laberg et al., 2017; Jennings et al., 2017; Newton <lb/>et al., 2017; Seidenkrantz et al., 2019; Sbarra et al., 2022; <lb/>Couette et al., 2022; Rasmussen et al., 2022; Hansen et al., <lb/>2022). In several regions, a debate prevails regarding whether <lb/>grounded ice reached the outer continental shelf when in <lb/>the last full glacial configuration. We find that in all stud-<lb/>ied regions, apart from offshore the Northeast Greenland Ice <lb/>Stream (NEGIS; Rasmussen et al., 2022), more recent inves-<lb/>tigations tend to suggest a more extensive full glacial con-<lb/>figuration than previously proposed, with grounded ice often <lb/>argued to have reached the mid-to outer shelf. For instance, <lb/>in central west Greenland, Ó Cofaigh et al. (2013) used a <lb/>series of dated marine sediment cores and bathymetric sub-<lb/>glacial landform mapping to show that the Uummannaq and <lb/>Jakobshavn Isbrae ice streams remained grounded near the <lb/>continental shelf edge until ∼ 15 kyr BP. A similar interpre-<lb/>tation was, for instance, proposed by Hansen et al. (2022), <lb/>who argued that grounded ice in the Westwind Trough region <lb/>(northeast Greenland) was located towards the outer shelf <lb/>during last full glacial extent and prior to 13.5 kyr BP. How-<lb/>ever, near the same site (79.5°N), Rasmussen et al. (2022) <lb/>suggest that grounded ice did not reach the shelf edge during <lb/>the last glacial. Such contrasts demonstrate that the question <lb/>remains open in this region. Vast areas of the Greenland con-<lb/>tinental shelf are still data scarce for this purpose. We revise <lb/>the limit of Funder et al. (2011) by considering two scenarios, <lb/>a minimum and maximum last full glacial extent, with the <lb/>aim of highlighting spatial uncertainties in debated regions <lb/>(Fig. 5). These two full glacial extent scenarios are used to <lb/>inform the mapping of our outermost isochrones and are in-<lb/>cluded here as shapefiles (see online database). The maxi-<lb/>mum extent scenario displays an ice sheet that reaches the <lb/>Figure 7. Histogram displaying the temporal distribution of all <lb/>summary event ages calculated in the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database. <lb/>Colour-coded relative proportions of the three quality control cat-<lb/>egories are shown for each 1000-year bin. A light-blue polygon <lb/>highlights the time period covered by the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone <lb/>reconstruction. This Late Glacial to mid-Holocene period (14-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP) features the large majority (&gt; 90 %) of compiled event <lb/>ages dating the deglacial evolution of former Greenland Ice Sheet <lb/>margins. <lb/>shelf edge around the entire ice sheet perimeter. The mini-<lb/>mum extent scenario modifies the latter by following the out-<lb/>line of Funder et al. (2011) in the central east and northeast <lb/>regions, except towards the Westwind Trough, where it ac-<lb/>counts for new data by Hansen et al. (2022). The minimum <lb/>extent scenario also displays a more retreated full glacial <lb/>ice sheet in the northwest region, where little data constrain <lb/>whether a mid-shelf or outer shelf position was reached. We <lb/>suppose that the grounding line was likely highly dynamic <lb/>and that any maximum achieved last glacial extent configu-<lb/>ration between these lines is feasible. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 The PaleoGrIS 1.0 geomorphological and <lb/>geochronological database <lb/>3.1.1 Geomorphology <lb/>The PaleoGrIS 1.0 database contains a total of 194 302 ice <lb/>marginal landforms mapped over 430 500 km 2 of ice-free <lb/>land around Greenland. The distribution of landforms is rel-<lb/>atively sparse in the southeast (SE) and northwest (NW) re-<lb/>gions, where the contemporary ice sheet terminates near to <lb/>the coast. Consequently, the majority of ice marginal land-<lb/>forms mapped as part of this study are located in the south-<lb/>west (SW), central west (CW), central east (CE), northeast <lb/>(NE), and north (NO) regions of ice-free Greenland. Interest-<lb/>ingly, we find ice marginal landforms are particularly abun-<lb/>dant and well-preserved in NO Greenland, increasing our <lb/>confidence here in the retreat pattern relative to other regions. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>718 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>This abundance and pristine nature of landforms might be <lb/>due to the generally softer nature of subglacial bedrock (Ped-<lb/>ersen et al., 2013) in this region enabling greater sediment <lb/>supply for moraine-building, a drier climate that could bet-<lb/>ter promote landform preservation (Niwano et al., 2021), or <lb/>a potentially steadier and more monotonic retreat pattern of <lb/>outlet glacier margins characterised by fewer dynamic fluc-<lb/>tuations and readvances that cause erosion. <lb/>3.1.2 Geochronology <lb/>The PaleoGrIS 1.0 database features 1028 TCN exposure <lb/>ages gathered from 45 studies and contains 423 radiocar-<lb/>bon ages collected from 111 studies. Following the com-<lb/>putation of summary statistics for age groups, and the re-<lb/>moval of outliers, this collection contains 251 TCN-derived <lb/>summary event ages. This number excludes TCN exposure <lb/>ages produced as past ice sheet thickness indicators (e.g. dip-<lb/>stick models). The radiocarbon age compilation features 370 <lb/>summary event ages post age-filtering. Therefore, a total of <lb/>621 summary event ages were directly used to inform our <lb/>isochrone reconstruction. Details regarding the temporal fre-<lb/>quency distribution of summary event ages and their number <lb/>per investigation are presented in Fig. 7 and Tables 2 and <lb/>3. We here acknowledge the possibility that relevant investi-<lb/>gations and datasets may be missing from our chronological <lb/>database. It is our goal that such an oversight can be corrected <lb/>in future versions of PaleoGrIS. <lb/>In the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database, 90 % (n = 558) of the sum-<lb/>mary event ages compiled are younger than 14 kyr BP and <lb/>older than 6 kyr BP (Fig. 7). As a result, we chose to restrict <lb/>our isochrone reconstruction to this time period (more justi-<lb/>fication for this decision can be found in Sect. 2.3.2). Fol-<lb/>lowing quality control assessment of summary event ages <lb/>(Table 1), we find that high-and medium-confidence event <lb/>ages each represent a quarter of the total (26 % and 25 %, re-<lb/>spectively). Low-confidence event ages represent the largest <lb/>proportion, i.e. 49 % (Fig. 7). This is in part explained by nu-<lb/>merous event ages resulting from a single marine radiocar-<lb/>bon age, here attributed a low-confidence rating due to large <lb/>uncertainties in past marine radiocarbon reservoir effects at <lb/>high latitudes (Heaton et al., 2022) (see criteria list in Ta-<lb/>ble 1). However, we stress that event ages described as low <lb/>confidence may still closely estimate the true timing of mar-<lb/>gin retreat and are by no means excluded from our isochrone <lb/>reconstruction. Our event age quality control assessment is <lb/>merely an indicator utilised to inform challenging decisions <lb/>made when tracing isochrones. <lb/>Using our geochronological database, we analyse the spa-<lb/>tial variability in event age reliability across Greenland and <lb/>its periphery. For TCN exposure ages, we find a higher <lb/>relative concentration of medium-to low-confidence event <lb/>ages in NO Greenland, and more specifically from Inglefield <lb/>Land, Inglefield Bredning, Washington Land and around <lb/>Danmark Fjord, Hagen Fjord, Independence Fjord, and the <lb/>Centrumsø regions. Indeed, while studies that investigated <lb/>these regions sampled both bedrock and erratic surfaces and <lb/>have produced extensive datasets, their results often display <lb/>old apparent ages (Ceperley et al., 2020; Larsen et al., 2018, <lb/>2020; Søndergaard et al., 2019, 2020). It has been stated <lb/>that this abundance of overestimating exposure ages is most <lb/>likely associated with high levels of nuclide inheritance in <lb/>NO Greenland caused by insufficient subglacial erosion of <lb/>bedrock and transported clasts. Future studies producing ex-<lb/>posure ages from these regions might thus be inclined to also <lb/>measure in situ cosmogenic 14 C alongside other radionu-<lb/>clides (e.g. 10 Be, 26 Al, and 36 Cl), which may enable the <lb/>quantification of nuclide inheritance and more accurate es-<lb/>timation of Holocene deglacial exposure ages (e.g. Sønder-<lb/>gaard et al., 2020). We note that the ice-free region to the <lb/>west of the Akuliarutsip Sermia and Inuppaat Quuat glaciers <lb/>(67.3-68.3°N, 50.1-54°W), in central west Greenland, also <lb/>displays a high concentration of medium-to low-confidence <lb/>TCN event ages (Young et al., 2020). For radiocarbon ages, <lb/>however, we do not observe any clear spatial patterns in the <lb/>variability in the summary event age reliability. <lb/>3.2 Regional retreat patterns and timings <lb/>In this section, we describe the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone re-<lb/>construction and the pattern and timing of ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin retreat for selected regions, followed by a chronological <lb/>description of the main deglacial events. This section also <lb/>describes key empirical constraints that inform our recon-<lb/>struction. When found, new Greenlandic place and glacier <lb/>names are preferably used to describe the geography (e.g. af-<lb/>ter Bjørk et al., 2015). When not found, we refer to places, <lb/>features and certain glaciers using Danish or other foreign <lb/>names. <lb/>3.2.1 Ice sheet retreat in north Greenland and the <lb/>timing of Nares Strait opening <lb/>Towards the onset of the studied time period (i.e. 14-<lb/>13 kyr BP), our reconstruction portrays the Innuitian (ice <lb/>over Ellesmere Island) and Greenland ice sheets as con-<lb/>nected, with grounded ice from both ice masses merg-<lb/>ing along Nares Strait, as supported by empirical evidence <lb/>(e.g. Jennings et al., 2011; Georgiadis et al., 2018). For that <lb/>time step, we reconstruct the two connected ice sheets to <lb/>feature marginal grounding lines on both the southwestern <lb/>and northeastern ends of Nares strait, with respective mar-<lb/>gins terminating into Baffin Bay and the Lincoln Sea (Fig. 8). <lb/>Geochronological evidence of ice sheet extent suggests that <lb/>the retreat of these two grounding lines occurred somewhat <lb/>simultaneously on both ends of the strait. This is supported <lb/>by ages indicating onshore regions located closest to Nares <lb/>Strait&apos;s openings (e.g. Inglefield Fjord and Wulff Land) were <lb/>progressively deglaciated earlier than regions located to-<lb/>wards its centre, i.e. terrestrial regions adjacent to Kane <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>719 <lb/></page>

	<body>Basin, such as Washington and Inglefield lands (Fig. 8). In-<lb/>deed, TCN exposure ages suggest grounded ice had retreated <lb/>within Inglefield Fjord by around 11.5-11 kyr BP (Sønder-<lb/>gaard et al., 2019). At the same time, deglacial radiocarbon <lb/>ages (Funder, 1982; Kelly and Bennike, 1992) indicate ice <lb/>from the Ryder, Steensby, and C. H. Ostenfeld basins had re-<lb/>treated towards the outermost present-day coastline of Nye-<lb/>boe, Wulff, and Nares lands. After 11 kyr BP, we reconstruct <lb/>grounding lines that retreated further within Nares Strait <lb/>and that reached the southwestern and northeastern edges of <lb/>Kane Basin by 9-8.5 kyr BP (Fig. 8). TCN ages produced <lb/>from contemporary coastal regions of Inglefield Land (Søn-<lb/>dergaard et al., 2020) and Washington Land (Ceperley et al., <lb/>2020) suggest that regions adjacent to the Humboldt Glacier <lb/>lateral margins started deglaciating at around 8.5-8 kyr BP. <lb/>During that time, further east, evidence suggests the Peter-<lb/>mann Glacier front was located towards the fjord&apos;s mouth <lb/>(Bennike, 2002). After ∼ 8 kyr BP, in this region, we esti-<lb/>mate that the ice sheet had retreated inland beyond present-<lb/>day coastlines, except for offshore contemporary Humboldt <lb/>Glacier, where we map a grounding line that remained within <lb/>∼ 100 km outside the present-day margin. Therefore, empir-<lb/>ical data suggest that the last ice bridge connecting the In-<lb/>nuitian and Greenland ice sheets over Nares Strait survived <lb/>exclusively within the Kane Basin, and until 8.5-8 kyr BP <lb/>(although large uncertainties remain). We thus estimate the <lb/>final deglacial opening of Nares Strait to have occurred be-<lb/>tween 9 and 8 kyr BP (Fig. 8). Following this, further retreat <lb/>caused the ice sheet margin to reach its present-day extent <lb/>by 7.5-7 kyr BP on Inglefield Land, while shortly after (7-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP) on Washington Land. <lb/>In northernmost Greenland (&gt; 82.7°N), we reconstruct a <lb/>margin retreat pattern characterised by a disconnection with <lb/>glaciers and ice caps from Roosevelt Land that occurred at <lb/>around 10-9.5 kyr BP. This estimation is however uncertain <lb/>due to the low abundance of local geochronological con-<lb/>straints. Around 9-8.5 kyr BP, we estimate further retreat to <lb/>generate ice sheet separation from the large Hans Tausen Ice <lb/>Cap. Between 8.5 and 6.5 kyr BP, the relatively slow retreat <lb/>of the more-extensive-than-present ice margins was still oc-<lb/>curring on inter-fjord regions of Wulff, Adam Biering, and <lb/>J. C. Christensen lands (Larsen et al., 2020). In the same re-<lb/>gions, empirical evidence suggests outlet glaciers terminat-<lb/>ing in deep and wide fjords, such as Independence, Hagen, or <lb/>Victoria fjords, experienced faster retreat than those located <lb/>on adjacent inter-fjord regions (Larsen et al., 2020). <lb/>3.2.2 Ice sheet retreat in northeast Greenland and ice <lb/>margin evolution in the Nioghalvfjerdsfjorden and <lb/>Jøkelbugten regions <lb/>In this section, we describe the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone re-<lb/>construction in a region characterised by a ∼ 300 km long <lb/>stretch of the coast in northeast Greenland belonging to King <lb/>Frederick VIII Land and which lies between Holm Land <lb/>(79.8°N) and the Skaer Fjord (77.4°N). The largest contrib-<lb/>utor to ice flux in this region is the North East Greenland <lb/>Ice Stream (NEGIS), which currently splits into three wide <lb/>marine-terminating and fast-flowing outlet glaciers display-<lb/>ing surface velocities of &gt; 1000 m yr -1 in places (Joughin et <lb/>al., 2018). These are, from north to south, the Nioghalvfjerds-<lb/>brae (also referred to as 79N) glacier, the Zachariae Isstrøm <lb/>glacier, and the southernmost branch which splits in two sub-<lb/>outlets, the Kofoed-Hansen and Storstrømmen outlet glaciers <lb/>(Fig. 9). In this region, a debate prevails regarding whether <lb/>the grounded ice sheet advanced extensively on the wide <lb/>continental shelf during last full glacial extent or whether it <lb/>was restricted to the inner shelf (Rasmussen et al., 2022). <lb/>However, recent offshore investigations (e.g. Hansen et al., <lb/>2022), including soon-to-be-published work (Ó Cofaigh et <lb/>al., 2023), increasingly suggest a last full glacial ice sheet <lb/>margin that was more extensive than previously drawn by <lb/>Funder et al. (2011) and that likely reached the mid-to outer <lb/>continental shelf. However, whether the grounded ice sheet <lb/>remained confined to the prominent bathymetric Westwind <lb/>(north) and Norske (south) troughs or instead also flowed <lb/>eastwards over the mid-shelf bathymetric highland separat-<lb/>ing the two, the Northwind Shoal, is uncertain (Arndt et al., <lb/>2017; Pados-Dibattista et al., 2022). The large disparity be-<lb/>tween our minimum and maximum last full glacial extent <lb/>scenarios reflects this debate in the literature (Fig. 9). <lb/>To remain conservative, our reconstruction in this region <lb/>features a very low-confidence outermost isochrone (14-<lb/>13 kyr BP) located closely on board our minimum last full <lb/>glacial extent scenario, depicting a grounded ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin positioned towards the mid-shelf, while remaining con-<lb/>fined within the Westwind and Norske troughs (Fig. 9). This <lb/>14-13 kyr BP extent is constrained in the Westwind Trough <lb/>by a marine radiocarbon deglacial chronology by Hansen <lb/>et al. (2022). We then tentatively reconstruct an ice sheet <lb/>margin that had monotonically retreated ∼ 50 km westwards <lb/>along the troughs by ∼ 12-11.5 kyr BP, as suggested by off-<lb/>shore data by Davies et al. (2022). However, directly south of <lb/>Norske Trough, we reconstruct a less extensive ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin around the same time (12-11.5 kyr BP). This interpreta-<lb/>tion is based on TCN exposure ages by Larsen et al. (2018), <lb/>indicating that by 11.5 kyr BP, the grounded ice had likely re-<lb/>treated west of Kap Amélie (77.5°N), into the Skaerfjorden <lb/>embayment and had reached the Storøen and Ambolten is-<lb/>lands; this became a north-south-oriented archipelago acting <lb/>as a topographic barrier to ice flowing eastwards from the <lb/>deep Jøkelbugten basin (Fig. 9). <lb/>Based on TCN-derived event ages from Bourbon Øer <lb/>(Larsen et al., 2018) and Dove Bay (Larsen et al., 2022) <lb/>located ∼ 60 km further south, we reconstruct a margin <lb/>that had retreated to the inner shores of Skaerfjorden and <lb/>that was positioned ∼ 55 km from the present-day ice front <lb/>of Nioghalvfjerdsbrae by ∼ 11.5-11 kyr BP. Over the next <lb/>2000 years, our reconstruction suggests that the ice sheet <lb/>margin retreated relatively quickly westwards within the <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>720 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Jøkelbugten basin, through Lamberts Land, and within <lb/>Nioghalvfjerdsfjorden, with a former margin that was posi-<lb/>tioned within ∼ 15 km of the present-day ice sheet front in <lb/>most locations of the region by ∼ 10-9.5 kyr BP. We estimate <lb/>the next phase of retreat to be slower (&lt; 20 m yr -1 ), with <lb/>an ice sheet margin remaining more extensive but near the <lb/>present-day one, until ∼ 9-8.5 kyr BP. This is well supported <lb/>by coeval TCN exposure ages from Bloch Nunatakker, an <lb/>island located near Nioghalvfjerdsbrae&apos;s contemporary calv-<lb/>ing front, and from three sites situated ∼ 3 km from the mod-<lb/>ern lateral margins of Zachariae Isstrøm glacier (Larsen et al., <lb/>2018). To the south of Nioghalvfjerdsbrae, and for a 300 km <lb/>long stretch of the ice margin, we thus reconstruct an ice <lb/>sheet margin that was as or more retreated than the present by <lb/>∼ 8.5 kyr BP. This contrasts with the mountainous region di-<lb/>rectly northwest of Nioghalvfjerdsbrae, however, where the <lb/>predominantly land-terminating former ice sheet margin ap-<lb/>pears to have retreated more slowly and more steadily. This is <lb/>supported by our mapping depicting a highly regular spacing <lb/>of moraine ridges in this region. There, we reconstruct an ice <lb/>sheet margin that remained more extensive than present for <lb/>2000 years longer than further south, until ∼ 7-6.5 kyr BP, as <lb/>indicated by deglacial event ages by Bennike and Weidick <lb/>(2001) and Larsen et al. (2018, 2020). <lb/>3.2.3 Ice sheet retreat in central east Greenland and ice <lb/>margin evolution in the Scoresby Sund and <lb/>Kangerlussuaq regions <lb/>The central east (CE) region of the Greenland Ice Sheet is <lb/>characterised by two major ice drainage basins. The north-<lb/>ernmost one is composed of ice streams and outlet glaciers <lb/>flowing eastwards and into fjord systems that merge to form <lb/>Scoresby Sund. The southernmost basin comprises three ma-<lb/>jor ice streams flowing southeastwards, namely the Kanger-<lb/>lussuaq, Christian IV, and Hutchinson plateau glaciers (Rig-<lb/>not and Mouginot, 2012; Bjørk et al., 2015). We here de-<lb/>scribe the general pattern and timing of retreat in these two <lb/>key regions (Fig. 10). <lb/>The Scoresby Sund region <lb/>At ∼ 14-13 kyr BP, we reconstruct a grounded ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin positioned towards the inner continental shelf, near the <lb/>mouth of Scoresby Sund and around the location of the un-<lb/>derwater Cape Brewster moraine complex (Dowdeswell et <lb/>al., 1994; Fig. 10). The timing of this specific extent is highly <lb/>uncertain and exclusively based on a TCN-derived chronol-<lb/>ogy from Cape Brewster by Håkansson et al. (2007a). For <lb/>this time slice, we reconstruct the ice sheet as connected <lb/>with ice caps from the Liverpool Land peninsula (Fig. 10). <lb/>However, our reconstruction tentatively suggests that a dis-<lb/>connection between the two occurred shortly after, towards <lb/>∼ 13-12 kyr BP. By ∼ 12-11.5 kyr BP, deglacial radiocarbon <lb/>ages (Bennike et al., 1999) indicate that the Scoresby Sund <lb/>outlet had retreated within the fjord, with its northern lat-<lb/>eral margin resting against the southwestern slopes of Jame-<lb/>son Land. Following further glacier retreat and thinning, we <lb/>reconstruct the disconnection of ice flowing southeastwards <lb/>within Hall Bredning fjord and ice flowing northeastwards <lb/>within Gaasefjord to occur between ∼ 11.5 and ∼ 10 kyr BP, <lb/>based on radiocarbon deglacial chronologies by Marienfeld <lb/>(1990), Ingólfsson et al. (1994), and Hansen (2001). We pro-<lb/>pose that progressive westward retreat and separation into <lb/>three outlet glaciers retreating into Nordvestfjord, Harefjord, <lb/>and Fonfjord, occurred between ∼ 9.5 and ∼ 8 kyr BP. After <lb/>∼ 8 kyr BP, we estimate the grounded ice extent was similar <lb/>to or less than the present in this region (Funder, 1978). <lb/>The Kangerlussuaq glacier region <lb/>During the last full glacial configuration of the ice sheet, <lb/>outlets of the southernmost basin in CE Greenland con-<lb/>verged into one major lobe, commonly referred to as the <lb/>Kangerlussuaq outlet glacier (Dowdeswell et al., 2010). <lb/>This major outlet flowed southeastwards and is thought to <lb/>have likely reached the outer continental shelf during last <lb/>full glacial extent (Mienert et al., 1992), although this re-<lb/>mains uncertain. The deglacial pattern and timing of re-<lb/>treat of the Kangerlussuaq outlet has been studied by a <lb/>relatively large number of offshore coring (e.g. Williams, <lb/>1993, 1995; Andrews et al., 1996; Smith and Licht, 2000) <lb/>and onshore (e.g. Dyke et al., 2014) investigations. Based <lb/>on findings from these empirical studies, we reconstruct <lb/>a grounded ice margin reaching a mid-shelf position to-<lb/>wards ∼ 14-13 kyr BP in this area (Fig. 10). Between ∼ 14 <lb/>and ∼ 10 kyr BP, our reconstruction suggests the Kangerlus-<lb/>suaq outlet glacier retreated in a relatively slow and mono-<lb/>tonic manner (∼ 10 m yr -1 ). Radiocarbon-dated marine sed-<lb/>iment records (Smith and Licht, 2000) suggest that faster re-<lb/>treat between ∼ 10 and ∼ 9 kyr BP (∼ 70-40 m yr -1 ) caused <lb/>the outlet glacier to reach the Kangerlussuaq Fjord mouth <lb/>by ∼ 9 kyr BP. We estimate later retreat within the fjord to <lb/>have been relatively quick (∼ 60 m yr -1 ), and a similar or <lb/>more-retreated than present extent was likely reached before <lb/>∼ 8 kyr BP (Dyke et al., 2014). <lb/>3.2.4 Ice sheet retreat in the southeast region and ice <lb/>margin evolution of the Sermilik outlet glacier <lb/>To the south of the Kangerlussuaq Fjord and Kangerlussuaq <lb/>Trough, a 300 km long stretch of the Greenland coastline is <lb/>characterised by rugged, steep, and high-elevation mountains <lb/>displaying numerous summits reaching 2000 m a.s.l., with <lb/>some acting as contemporary nunataks. These high coastal <lb/>mountains act as orographic barriers causing snow accumu-<lb/>lations and resulting in the contemporary ice sheet reaching <lb/>the shore along the entire coastline. This results in a lack <lb/>of settlements, difficult access conditions, and thus a lack of <lb/>paleo glaciological field investigations. Moreover, in this re-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>721 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 8. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in Nares Strait region. The reconstructed ice sheet areal extent <lb/>for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying opaque white layer is the <lb/>present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone polylines, which feature <lb/>different colour schemes relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). We merge our isochrones with the reconstruction <lb/>of former ice extent over Ellesmere Island (Innuitian Ice Sheet) from Dalton et al. (2020). While no modifications were applied to the margin <lb/>extent of that dataset, the timing of Dalton et al. (2020) isochrones was in some cases modified (inferior to 1 kyr at most)to match our <lb/>reconstruction. Bottom panels also feature present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., <lb/>2018). Topography and bathymetry are from the GEBCO 2022 release. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>722 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 9. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in the Nioghalvfjerdsfjorden and Jøkelbugten regions. The recon-<lb/>structed ice sheet areal extent for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying <lb/>opaque white layer is the present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone <lb/>polylines, which feature different colour schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom <lb/>panels also feature present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and <lb/>bathymetry are from the GEBCO 2022 release. For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>723 <lb/></page>

	<body>gion, the offshore continental shelf does not yet feature pub-<lb/>lished geochronological constraints on deglacial grounded <lb/>ice margin retreat, as far as our compilation suggests. There-<lb/>fore, our ice sheet margin reconstruction along this coastline <lb/>displays only very low-confidence isochrones, and retreat is <lb/>crudely assumed to be monotonic in nature. At a distance <lb/>of 300 km further south, the next location presenting empiri-<lb/>cal constraints on past ice sheet margin evolution is the large <lb/>Sermilik fjord, in which the rapidly flowing Helheim (up to <lb/>8000 m yr -1 ; Joughin et al., 2018), Apuseerajik, and Niger-<lb/>tiip Apusiia tidewater glaciers terminate. The Sermilik fjord <lb/>is bordered on its eastern side by the large Ammassalik Island <lb/>and other peninsulas which feature steep mountains reaching <lb/>&gt; 1000 m a.s.l. (above sea level). These high topographies <lb/>act as orographic barriers to moisture supply and enable sus-<lb/>taining numerous ice caps and mountain glaciers. <lb/>Today, the deep Sermilik fjord is thus characterised by <lb/>its main tidewater glacier fronts (e.g. Helheim) terminating <lb/>more than ∼ 100 km inside the fjord, while the fjord&apos;s terres-<lb/>trial flanks remain heavily glaciated. We attempted to mimic <lb/>this characteristic ice configuration when reconstructing the <lb/>deglacial retreat of the ice sheet margin in this region. Based <lb/>on extrapolating chronological constraints from the Kanger-<lb/>lussuaq Trough, we map a very low-confidence outermost <lb/>isochrone (14-13 kyr BP) located towards the inner-to mid-<lb/>continental shelf offshore the Sermilik fjord. Soon after, by <lb/>13-12 kyr BP, we locally reconstruct an ice margin that had <lb/>quickly retreated towards the mouth of the Sermilik fjord <lb/>and onto the shore of local coastal mountains. This relatively <lb/>early retreat scenario is constrained by TCN exposure ages <lb/>from the southwestern tip of Ammassalik Island (Hughes et <lb/>al., 2012), located east of Sermilik fjord, and by exposure <lb/>ages from the end of the Torqulertivit Imiat valley (Roberts <lb/>et al., 2008), located near the western edge of the main fjord <lb/>mouth. Since deglacial radiocarbon ages from the Ammas-<lb/>salik Fjord further east (Long et al., 2008) give similar ages <lb/>to TCN exposure dates from rock surfaces located towards <lb/>the mid-to inner-Sermilik fjord sides (Hughes et al., 2012), <lb/>we reconstruct a Sermilik fjord outlet front that had retreated <lb/>∼ 30 km north by 11.5-11 kyr BP, while ice sheet margins re-<lb/>mained extensive, i.e. near the coast and towards the Johan <lb/>Petersen Fjord mouth, on the western side of Sermilik fjord. <lb/>The Sermilik outlet thus appears to have experienced a potent <lb/>state of negative mass balance during the Younger Dryas to <lb/>early-Holocene rapid warming transition (GISP2 data; Alley, <lb/>2000), while ice masses occupying the fjord-side mountains <lb/>either remained stable or retreated less and slower. Approxi-<lb/>mately 25 km further north, exposure ages from the Amanga <lb/>island (Hughes et al., 2012), situated where the fjord splits <lb/>into three, suggest the Sermilik outlet had rapidly retreated <lb/>further into the inner fjord and started to split into the three <lb/>main tidewater glaciers existing today (Helheim, Apuseera-<lb/>jik, and Nigertiip Apusiia) by approximately 11-10.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Although uncertain, this rapid retreat prompts us to recon-<lb/>struct front margins for these three outlets that were as or <lb/>more retreated than present after 10-9.5 kyr BP, which is an <lb/>early timing for this event relative to other Greenland re-<lb/>gions, we find. <lb/>3.2.5 Ice sheet retreat in southernmost Greenland <lb/>The southernmost region of Greenland is characterised by a <lb/>relatively narrow (&lt; 70 km) and shallow (typically &lt; 200 m) <lb/>continental shelf, and features high-elevation coastal moun-<lb/>tains with several summits reaching 2000 m a.s.l. The <lb/>present-day ice sheet margin is generally located within <lb/>100 km of the outer coast in this region. Compared with other <lb/>Greenland regions, little ice build-up was required for the ice <lb/>sheet to reach the continental shelf edge during the last full <lb/>glacial extent, and this scenario is considered highly likely by <lb/>previous investigations (e.g. Funder et al., 2011; Andersen et <lb/>al., 2020; Levy et al., 2020). <lb/>The relatively short distance to the continental shelf com-<lb/>bined with high local Bølling-Allerød warming and the prox-<lb/>imity to the Irminger Current enabling warm water incur-<lb/>sion are thought to have caused relatively early deglaciation <lb/>in southernmost Greenland (Levy et al., 2020). In fact, the <lb/>well-studied N14 lake record, located on the Kitsissut Is-<lb/>lands (59.98°N, -45.18°W), features the oldest radiocarbon <lb/>deglacial isolation age (∼ 13.6 kyr BP) in Greenland (Ben-<lb/>nike et al., 2002; Puleo et al., 2022). Based on these stud-<lb/>ies, southernmost Greenland is the only region in which we <lb/>map the oldest isochrone (14-13 kyr BP) onshore, towards <lb/>the present-day outer coastline (Fig. 11). TCN event ages <lb/>from Lindenows Fjord (Levy et al., 2020) suggest that the <lb/>series of fjords located east of the Qaqortoq ice cap started <lb/>deglaciating at around ∼ 12 kyr BP. Although a lack of evi-<lb/>dence makes isochrone mapping in adjacent northern fjords <lb/>highly uncertain, our reconstruction displays outlet glaciers <lb/>retreating and reaching present-day configurations earlier <lb/>than most Greenland regions by approximately 10 kyr BP. <lb/>Therefore, the ice sheet margin was as retreated as (or more <lb/>retreated) than the present for most of the Holocene in this <lb/>region. <lb/>To the west of Uummannarsuaq (also known as Cape <lb/>Farewell), in the region of the Nanortalik and Narsarsuaq set-<lb/>tlements, the timing of ice sheet retreat (from Qaqortoq bay) <lb/>is better constrained by empirical evidence. The majority of <lb/>the local ice basin is currently drained by three fast-flowing <lb/>outlet glaciers (maximum surface velocities &gt; 1000 m yr -1 ), <lb/>namely the Eqalorutsit Kangilliit Sermiat, Eqalorutsit Kil-<lb/>liit Sermiat, and Qooqqup Sermia glaciers (Bjørk et al., <lb/>2015; Joughin et al., 2018). TCN exposure ages from Win-<lb/>sor et al. (2015) indicate these outlet glacier fronts had re-<lb/>treated ∼ 20 km into local fjords by ∼ 13-12 kyr BP, while <lb/>TCN ages from Nelson et al. (2014) suggest retreat over the <lb/>next 2000 years caused the outlet glacier fronts to be within <lb/>∼ 15 km of the present day before ∼ 10 kyr BP (Fig. 11). This <lb/>scenario of retreat is also consistent with a deglacial radio-<lb/>carbon age produced by Weidick (1975) from the Bredefjord <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>724 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 10. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in the Scoresby Sund and Kangerlussuaq regions. The recon-<lb/>structed ice sheet areal extent for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying <lb/>opaque white layer is the present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone <lb/>polylines, which feature different colour schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom <lb/>panels also feature present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and <lb/>bathymetry are from the GEBCO 2022 release. For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/>(the Narssaq site). To the northwest, between Qaqortoq bay <lb/>and the large piedmont Sioqqap Sermia outlet glacier, our <lb/>compilation features no geochronological constraints over a <lb/>∼ 200 km long stretch of ice-free coastal land. We have iden-<lb/>tified this region as a possible target for future field inves-<lb/>tigations aiming to reconstruct Holocene ice margin fluctu-<lb/>ations. Along this region, low-confidence isochrones were <lb/>thus mapped solely by linking mapped ice marginal land-<lb/>forms and by extrapolating retreat timings from adjacent ar-<lb/>eas. Further north, the next site to display chronological con-<lb/>straints on ice sheet retreat is Kuannersooq fjord (61.98°N) <lb/>to the east of the Paamiut settlement, with TCN exposure <lb/>ages from Winsor et al. (2015) dating an ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin retreating to the fjord mouth by 12-11.5 kyr BP. Further-<lb/>more, in this valley, Carlson et al. (2014) sampled boulder <lb/>and bedrock surfaces shorter than 2 km from the present-day <lb/>ice sheet margin. The resulting TCN exposure ages suggest <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>725 <lb/></page>

	<body>the ice sheet had retreated towards its present-day extent by <lb/>∼ 10 kyr BP in this sector. <lb/>3.2.6 Ice sheet retreat in southwest Greenland and ice <lb/>margin evolution in the Nuuk region <lb/>The ice-free coastal region to the east and south of <lb/>Nuuk presents a complex topography with high (1500-<lb/>2000 m a.s.l.) and steep-sided mountains dissected by several <lb/>sinuous and deep fjords forming an archipelago. Upstream of <lb/>these fjords, the majority of the ice discharge is captured by <lb/>four fast-flowing outlet glaciers (maximum surface veloci-<lb/>ties 1000-2000 m yr -1 ). From south to north, these are the <lb/>Sermeq, Kangiata Nunaata Sermia, Akullersuup Sermia, and <lb/>Narsap Sermia glaciers (Bjørk et al., 2015). Due to easier <lb/>accessibility, several investigations studying the former ice <lb/>sheet evolution have taken place in this area, and the Late <lb/>Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene retreat of the ice sheet&apos;s <lb/>margin is relatively well constrained. Further north, however, <lb/>to the east of the Atammik settlement, a large ice-free re-<lb/>gion displaying flatter topographies with fewer overdeepen-<lb/>ings features fewer geomorphological and geochronological <lb/>constraints on ice margin retreat. <lb/>In the well-studied valleys, numerous TCN and radiocar-<lb/>bon dates from four parallel fjords and from three distinct <lb/>investigations (Weidick, 1976; Winsor et al., 2015; Larsen <lb/>et al., 2014) show consistent results. These constraints en-<lb/>able us to map, with good levels of confidence, an ice sheet <lb/>margin positioned towards the mouths of the Nuup Kanger-<lb/>lua, Kangerdluarsunguak, and Sermilik fjords, while posi-<lb/>tioned towards the middle of the Ameralik fjord, at ∼ 11-<lb/>10.5 kyr BP (Fig. 12). Older isochrones (14-11 kyr BP) are <lb/>less well constrained and are here reconstructed following a <lb/>low-confidence and monotonic retreat pattern from a mid-<lb/>shelf position at 14-13 kyr BP. Several extensive investiga-<lb/>tions sampling along the fjords and towards the modern ice <lb/>margin have shown that after ∼ 11-10.5 kyr BP, local outlets <lb/>flowing into the Nuuk Fjord system likely experienced very <lb/>rapid retreat, with their fronts reaching the inner fjords by <lb/>∼ 10 kyr BP (Weidick, 1972; Larsen et al., 2014; Young et <lb/>al., 2021) (Fig. 12). According to this retreat scenario, lo-<lb/>cal fjords were deglaciated in fewer than 1000 years, which <lb/>represents a retreat rate of 207 ± 69 m yr -1 for the Kangiata <lb/>Nunaata Sermia outlet glacier during that time. Out of the 72 <lb/>Greenland outlet glaciers sampled for retreat rate analysis, <lb/>this rate is the sixth-highest maximum retreat rate reached <lb/>over the reconstructed period. Therefore, this rapid retreat <lb/>of the ice sheet margin in the Nuuk region between ∼ 11 <lb/>and ∼ 10 kyr BP was likely a high-magnitude event at the ice <lb/>sheet scale. <lb/>Following this, numerous multi-nuclide TCN exposure <lb/>ages from near the contemporary margins of the Kangiata <lb/>Nunaata Sermia, Akullersuup Sermia, and Narsap Sermia <lb/>glaciers indicate local tidewater glaciers had reached an ex-<lb/>tent similar to the present by ∼ 9 kyr BP (Larsen et al., <lb/>2014; Young et al., 2021). Further north, towards a plateau <lb/>(&gt; 600 m a.s.l.) lying between the Nuup Qinngua fjord and <lb/>the Saqqap Sermia outlet glacier, younger deglacial radio-<lb/>carbon ages (∼ 7.5 kyr BP; Levy et al., 2017) suggest that the <lb/>land-terminating ice sheet margin retreated at a slower pace. <lb/>Although this hypothesis requires further evidence for vali-<lb/>dation, our reconstruction uses these data to suggest an ice <lb/>margin remaining more extensive than the present until our <lb/>youngest isochrone, i.e. 7-6.5 kyr BP (Fig. 12). <lb/>3.2.7 Ice sheet retreat in central west Greenland and ice <lb/>margin evolution in the Sisimiut, Disko Bay, and <lb/>the Uummannaq fjord regions <lb/>Sisimiut region <lb/>The coastal region here described as belonging to central <lb/>west (CW) Greenland stretches 600 km northward from the <lb/>large Maniitsoq Ice Cap (66°13 N, 52°11 W) to the Uum-<lb/>mannaq Fjord region. From the Maniitsoq Ice Cap to the <lb/>southern edge of Disko Bay (Qeqertarsuup tunua), the ice-<lb/>free coast is characterised by a relatively flat bedrock plateau <lb/>dissected by deep fjords and extending ∼ 150 km from the <lb/>outer coast to the contemporary ice margin (Fig. 13). This <lb/>region, home to the towns of Sisimiut and Kangerlussuaq, <lb/>has been the subject of numerous investigations reconstruct-<lb/>ing the evolution of the ice sheet margin during deglaciation <lb/>(e.g. Ten Brink and Weidick, 1974; Eisner et al., 1995; Ben-<lb/>nike, 2000; Roberts et al., 2009; Rinterknecht et al., 2009; <lb/>Storms et al., 2012; Winsor et al., 2015; Kelley et al., 2013, <lb/>2015; Lesnek and Briner, 2018; Briner et al., 2020; Young <lb/>et al., 2020). Moreover, ice marginal landforms are well <lb/>preserved and highly concentrated in this area. As a result, <lb/>the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene retreat of the <lb/>ice sheet margin is locally well constrained. Based on this <lb/>high density of geological evidence, we reconstruct, with <lb/>reasonable levels of confidence, an ice sheet margin that <lb/>had retreated to within 30 km (offshore or onshore depend-<lb/>ing on the valley) of the present-day outer coast by ∼ 12-<lb/>11.5 kyr BP (Fig. 13). After that time, the eastward ice sheet <lb/>margin retreat appears to have been relatively monotonic in <lb/>this region. Local outlet glaciers sampled, i.e. the south Rus-<lb/>sell, Isunnguata Sermia, Inuppaat Quuat, and Akuliarutsip <lb/>Sermia glaciers (Bjørk et al., 2015), seem to have retreated <lb/>at intermediate but steady speeds varying between 25 and <lb/>30 m yr -1 once averaged. By ∼ 9 kyr BP, we reconstruct an <lb/>ice sheet margin that was near (within 20 km) the inner end of <lb/>local fjords (e.g. Kangerlussuaq, Nassuttooq, Qasigiarssuit). <lb/>Between ∼ 9 and ∼ 7 kyr BP, empirical evidence suggests <lb/>that the ice sheet started retreating slower and was located <lb/>closer than 30 km from the present-day margin for ∼ 3 kyr <lb/>in most locations throughout this region. This slowdown in <lb/>retreat appears to have been coeval with the ice sheet margin <lb/>becoming fully land-terminating in most valleys and is thus <lb/>a potential consequence of the removal of calving-related ab-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>726 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 11. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in southernmost Greenland. The reconstructed ice sheet areal <lb/>extent for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying opaque white layer is the <lb/>present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone polylines, which feature <lb/>different colour schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom panels also feature <lb/>present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and bathymetry are <lb/>from the GEBCO 2022 release. For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/>lation. The local reconstructed retreat pattern is such that <lb/>the present-day ice sheet extent was not reached until ∼ 7-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Disko Bay <lb/>Further north, at 68.7°N, lies Disko Bay (Qeqertarsuup <lb/>tunua), formerly host to a large streaming outlet glacier (also <lb/>referred as the Jakobshavn Isbrae ice stream) that flowed to-<lb/>wards Baffin Bay. This ice stream is thought to have reached <lb/>the continental shelf break during the last full glacial extent <lb/>and likely remained near such an extent until ∼ 14 kyr BP (Ó <lb/>Cofaigh et al., 2013; Rinterknecht et al., 2014). For our out-<lb/>ermost isochrone (14-13 kyr BP), we thus reconstruct an ice <lb/>sheet margin located towards the middle-to-outer continen-<lb/>tal shelf, mostly based on data from Ó Cofaigh et al. (2013) <lb/>(Fig. 13). Data from McCarthy (2011) and Rinterknecht et <lb/>al. (2014) enable us to tentatively draw an ice sheet margin <lb/>that had retreated towards the inner continental shelf, with ice <lb/>thinning causing its lateral margin to rest against the southern <lb/>coastal mountain slopes of Disko Island. <lb/>Based on offshore data by Lloyd et al. (2005) and TCN <lb/>exposure ages by Kelley et al. (2013, 2015), we estimate that <lb/>the further retreat into Disko Bay had caused the ice mar-<lb/>gin to be positioned 30 km offshore the mouth of the Ilulis-<lb/>sat Icefjord, and towards the Akunnaaq and Qasigiannguit <lb/>settlements further south, by 10.5-10 kyr BP. The follow-<lb/>ing phase of retreat was likely characterised by local outlet <lb/>glaciers (i.e. Sermeq Kujalleq, Eqip Sermia, Saqqarliup Ser-<lb/>mia, Sermeq Avannarleq, and Akuliarutsip Sermia) retreat-<lb/>ing into fjords to the east of Disko Bay. These proglacial re-<lb/>gions have been studied extensively and are characterised by <lb/>dense mapping and numerous geochronological constraints <lb/>(e.g. Donner and Jungne, 1975; Long et al., 1999, 2006; Wei-<lb/>dick and Bennike, 2007; Briner et al., 2010; Young et al., <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>727 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 12. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in the Nuuk region. The reconstructed ice sheet areal extent for <lb/>each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying opaque white layer is the present-day <lb/>ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone polylines, which feature different colour <lb/>schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom panels also feature present-day ice <lb/>sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and bathymetry are from the GEBCO <lb/>2022 release. For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>728 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>2013b; Carlson et al., 2014; Cronauer et al., 2016; Balter-<lb/>Kennedy et al., 2021). This enables a high density of mid-<lb/>to high-confidence isochrones to be drawn. To the south of <lb/>Ilulissat Icefjord, empirical data suggest the ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin evolution was characterised by slow and steady retreat <lb/>between ∼ 10 and ∼ 7 kyr BP. At a maximum, local out-<lb/>let glacier fronts (e.g. Akuliarutsip Sermia) had retreated <lb/>∼ 20 km during that time interval, which suggest retreat rates <lb/>likely below 10 m yr -1 . Based on these observations, we re-<lb/>construct an ice margin that reached the present-day extent <lb/>by ∼ 7.5-6.5 kyr BP in this area. For the Sermeq Kujalleq <lb/>outlet glacier (also known as Jakobshavn Isbrae), extensive <lb/>empirical datasets from both sides of the Ilulissat Icefjord <lb/>enable us to constrain, with high levels of confidence, the <lb/>position of the outlet&apos;s lateral margins through time (Briner <lb/>et al., 2010; Young et al., 2013). These data indicate that be-<lb/>tween ∼ 10 and 8 kyr BP, the glacier calving front was ei-<lb/>ther stable, or slowly retreating, and remained near the fjord&apos;s <lb/>mouth, with the glacier&apos;s right lateral margins terminating on <lb/>the Ilulissat peninsula (Fig. 13). After ∼ 8 kyr BP, the calving <lb/>front likely retreated to a mid-fjord position, with lateral ice <lb/>margins retreating to within ∼ 5 km of contemporary ones by <lb/>∼ 7 kyr BP. We estimate the Sermeq Kujalleq had retreated to <lb/>a near-present-day extent between ∼ 7 and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Uummannaq Fjord <lb/>Located ∼ 250 km north from the former Jakobshavn Isbrae <lb/>ice stream, a major outlet glacier, known as the Uumman-<lb/>naq ice stream (Lane et al., 2014), also formerly advanced <lb/>towards Baffin Bay with rapid flow, causing the formation <lb/>of streamlined subglacial bedforms (Ó Cofaigh et al., 2013). <lb/>Radiocarbon ages from a marine sediment core (VC45) sug-<lb/>gest that during the last full glacial configuration, this out-<lb/>let glacier likely reached the continental shelf break and re-<lb/>mained in this position until ∼ 15-14.5 kyr BP (Ó Cofaigh <lb/>et al., 2013). Given this maximum-limiting constraint, we <lb/>draw our outermost isochrone (14-13 kyr BP -very low con-<lb/>fidence) in this area towards the middle-to-outer continen-<lb/>tal shelf and map the Uummannaq ice stream margin as <lb/>a protruding lobe (Fig. 14). A radiocarbon-derived event <lb/>age by Bennike et al. (1994) indicates the ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin had retreated from the lower slopes of Hareoen Island <lb/>prior to ∼ 12.2 kyr BP. We thus tentatively reconstruct south <lb/>and north lateral margins of the Uummannaq outlet posi-<lb/>tioned towards the outer contemporary coast between ∼ 13 <lb/>and ∼ 12 kyr BP, while mapping a protruding lobe along the <lb/>central bathymetric trough with a margin reaching a mid-<lb/>shelf position (Fig. 14). <lb/>Further east, a TCN-derived event age produced by <lb/>Roberts et al. (2013) suggest the highlands of Illorsuit is-<lb/>land were becoming ice-free by ∼ 11.5-11 kyr BP. For this <lb/>isochrone, we therefore reconstruct an ice sheet margin that <lb/>separates into two distinct glaciers, with a northern glacier <lb/>retreating northeastwards into Karrat Fjord and a south-<lb/>ern glacier retreating southeastwards into Uummannaq Fjord <lb/>(Fig. 14). Further retreat led to divisions into 12 distinct out-<lb/>lets retreating in a dendritic series of narrow fjords that are <lb/>now host to the calving fronts of several fast-flowing tide-<lb/>water glaciers, such as Salliarutsip Sermia (72.0°N), Umi-<lb/>ammakku Sermiat (71.7°N), Kangilliup Sermia (Rink Isbrae; <lb/>71.7°N), or Sermeq Kujalleq (Store Gletscher; 70.4°N). <lb/>In agreement with TCN-derived event ages by Lane et <lb/>al. (2014), our reconstruction suggests that by 10-9.5 kyr BP, <lb/>the Umiammakku Sermiat and Kangilliup Sermia glacier <lb/>fronts had retreated towards the fjord mouths, near the west-<lb/>ern edge of Karrat Island, ∼ 50-30 km from their present-day <lb/>fronts (Fig. 14). Therefore, in the northern sector of the Uum-<lb/>mannaq Fjord system (Karrat area), we estimate that rapid re-<lb/>treat of the ice sheet margin was experienced between ∼ 11.5 <lb/>and ∼ 9.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Informed by data from the Qarajaq Icefjord further south <lb/>(Simonarson, 1981; Roberts et al., 2013), our reconstruc-<lb/>tion also suggests a rapid retreat of the ice margin in <lb/>the southern Uummannaq Fjord system, between ∼ 11 and <lb/>∼ 10 kyr BP. However, after ∼ 10-9.5 kyr BP, northern out-<lb/>let glacier fronts (Karrat area) appear to have remained rela-<lb/>tively stable, with fronts staying more extensive than present <lb/>until at least 5 kyr BP and hence for significantly longer than <lb/>most other Greenland regions (Lane et al., 2014). This con-<lb/>trasts with the ice sheet margin evolution in the southern <lb/>Uummannaq sector; 60 km further south, TCN-derived event <lb/>ages from Philipps et al. (2017) suggest that the lateral mar-<lb/>gins of the Perlerfiup Sermia (71.0°N) glacier were within <lb/>5 km of the present-day margin by 10.5-10 kyr BP (Fig. 14). <lb/>This dataset further indicates that after ∼ 9.5 kyr BP, this out-<lb/>let was either as retreated as (or more retreated than) the <lb/>present-day margin. This southern sector is characterised by <lb/>lower coastal mountains, more gradual slopes, wider fjords, <lb/>and fewer mountain glaciers today than towards the north-<lb/>ern Uummannaq Fjord system. This setting may have caused <lb/>a smaller ice mass contribution from periphery mountain <lb/>glaciers acting as tributaries than further north. At a distance <lb/>of 70 km further south, our reconstruction suggests the Ser-<lb/>meq Kujalleq (Store) glacier was more extensive than the <lb/>present until ∼ 9-8 kyr BP (Roberts et al., 2013). Overall, <lb/>empirical data suggest the early-to mid-Holocene margin re-<lb/>sponse of individual outlet glaciers of the Uummannaq Fjord <lb/>system was complex and heterogenous, and we try to capture <lb/>this variability in our isochrone reconstruction. <lb/>3.2.8 Ice sheet retreat in northwest Greenland and ice <lb/>margin evolution in the Upernavik and Aappilattup <lb/>Ikera region <lb/>To the north of the Uummannaq Fjord region, the ∼ 800 km <lb/>coastline of Greenland that stretches up to Steensby Land <lb/>(77°N) is commonly described as belonging to the NW <lb/>Greenland region. This coastline is characterised by little <lb/>ice-free land as the present-day ice sheet margin reaches the <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>729 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 13. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in the Sisimiut and Disko Bay region. The reconstructed ice sheet <lb/>areal extent for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying opaque white layer <lb/>is the present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone polylines, which <lb/>feature different colour schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom panels also <lb/>feature present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and bathymetry <lb/>are from the GEBCO 2022 release. For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>730 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 14. Time slice maps of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in the Uummannaq Fjord region. The reconstructed ice sheet areal <lb/>extent for each given time slice is displayed in each subpanel as a translucent white polygon, while the underlying opaque white layer is the <lb/>present-day ice cover from BedMachine v4. The reconstructed ice sheet margins are highlighted by our isochrone polylines, which feature <lb/>different colour schemes (see Fig. 8 for key) relating to our four isochrone confidence levels (see Sect. 2.3.5). Bottom panels also feature <lb/>present-day ice sheet thickness (Morlighem et al., 2017) and surface velocity data (Joughin et al., 2018). Topography and bathymetry are <lb/>from the GEBCO 2022 release. Note that between 9-8.5 and 7-6.5 kyr BP, in this region, sections of the former ice sheet margin may have <lb/>retreated beyond its present-day extent (opaque white polygon). For a more complete figure legend, the reader is advised to consult Fig. 8. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>731 <lb/></page>

	<body>shore along most of the coastline, and this region features <lb/>relatively low-lying coastal topographies. In this sector, ac-<lb/>cording to our compilation, few studies constrain the timing <lb/>and positions of the former Greenland Ice Sheet margin. The <lb/>exception to this is the region of Upernavik, however, where <lb/>two studies (Briner et al., 2013; Corbett et al., 2013) provide <lb/>numerous TCN-exposure-age-derived time constraints on the <lb/>deglacial evolution of the Sermeq (Upernavik Isstrøm) tide-<lb/>water glacier, which drains a major catchment of the NW <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet. There, we use the deglacial TCN ex-<lb/>posure ages from westernmost Islands located 15 km off-<lb/>shore the Upernavik settlement (Corbett et al., 2013) to map <lb/>a retreated outermost isochrone (14-13 kyr BP) located to-<lb/>wards the inner continental shelf, approximately 30 km west <lb/>of the mouth of Aappilattup Ikera (the Upernavik Isfjord). <lb/>Younger TCN exposure ages and dipstick models obtained <lb/>from high topographies that lie further east along the Uper-<lb/>navik archipelago seem to indicate a relatively monotonic <lb/>and slow (∼ 15 m yr -1 ) ice sheet margin retreat pattern be-<lb/>tween 14-13 and 11.5-11 kyr BP. We thus reconstruct the <lb/>Sermeq outlet glacier front to rest towards the outer-to mid-<lb/>Aappilattup Ikera fjord by 11.5-11 kyr BP. Further inland, <lb/>TCN exposure ages from an island adjacent to the historical <lb/>ice margin (Briner et al., 2013) indicate faster retreat likely <lb/>caused the ice sheet margin to recede towards the inner fjord <lb/>by 10-9.5 kyr BP. Moreover, according to three deglacial ra-<lb/>diocarbon ages from lake cores sampled within 5 km of the <lb/>contemporary ice front (Briner et al., 2013), we reconstruct <lb/>a local ice sheet margin that reached an extent that is simi-<lb/>lar to the present-day shortly after ∼ 9.5-9 kyr BP. Along the <lb/>coastline located to the north of the Upernavik sector, our re-<lb/>construction mostly features very low-confidence isochrones <lb/>crudely depicting a retreat pattern assumed to be monotonic, <lb/>due to a lack of geochronological and land-based geomor-<lb/>phological evidence. <lb/>3.3 Analysis of changes in areal extent of the Greenland <lb/>Ice Sheet <lb/>3.3.1 Ice-sheet-wide areal extent evolution <lb/>Our reconstruction at 14-13 kyr BP suggests that the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet had an approximate areal extent of <lb/>2.61 million km 2 (Figs. 15, 16) and lost about one-third of <lb/>this areal extent (0.89 million km 2 ) as it reduced in size to <lb/>its present-day extent (1.71 million km 2 ; Morlighem et al., <lb/>2017; Fig. 16). Between 14-13 and 9-8.5 kyr BP, our recon-<lb/>struction produces a near-constant rate of ice sheet areal ex-<lb/>tent loss of 170 ± 27 km 2 yr. Later, between 9-8.5 and 7-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP, our reconstruction suggests a rate of areal ex-<lb/>tent loss that progressively decreased through time (Fig. 16). <lb/>However, as our areal extent estimates are only maximum-<lb/>limiting between 10-9.5 and 7-6.5 kyr BP (see Sect. 2.4), <lb/>this potential slow down remains hypothetical and could be a <lb/>consequence of our limited knowledge regarding how far the <lb/>ice sheet margin retreated behind the present-day position in <lb/>response to the Holocene thermal maximum. <lb/>At 7-6.5 kyr BP, we estimate the ice sheet areal extent <lb/>was 1.71 million km 2 or smaller. This suggests the Green-<lb/>land Ice Sheet extent was similar to or smaller than present <lb/>by this time. Although highly uncertain, our literature-based <lb/>maximum and minimum full glacial extent scenarios (see <lb/>Sect. 2.6) suggest that the ice sheet areal extent was likely <lb/>between ∼ 3.13 and ∼ 2.94 million km 2 during the last full <lb/>glacial configuration (Figs. 5, 16). We thus estimate that be-<lb/>fore the start of the Holocene (∼ 11.7 kyr BP), deglaciation <lb/>had caused the ice sheet to lose between ∼ 26 % and ∼ 21 % <lb/>of its full glacial extent. Therefore, we find that between <lb/>∼ 57 % and ∼ 51 % of the post-glacial areal extent loss oc-<lb/>curred before the onset of the Holocene, while a significant <lb/>proportion (∼ 49 %-43 %) still occurred during the early-to <lb/>mid-Holocene interval. <lb/>3.3.2 Region-specific areal extent change <lb/>After dividing the ice sheet into seven major drainage basins <lb/>(after Rignot and Mouginot, 2012; see Sect. 4), we analysed <lb/>regional patterns of areal extent change through time. While <lb/>all regions lost areal extent between 14-13 and 7-6.5 kyr BP, <lb/>we find the timing, rate, and magnitude of ice sheet re-<lb/>treat differs substantially between regions (Fig. 17). By 7-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP, the NO, SW, and CE regions had lost at least 40 % <lb/>of their 14-13 kyr BP areal extent. The same figure is nearly <lb/>twice as low (∼ 25 %) for the NW and SE regions. During <lb/>that time, the CW and NE regions lost at least ∼ 30 % and <lb/>∼ 35 % of their areal extent, respectively. Furthermore, our <lb/>reconstruction suggests that the rate of areal extent loss, and <lb/>its evolution through time, varied significantly between re-<lb/>gions. For instance, the SW region lost areal extent relatively <lb/>quickly from the period onset (∼ 12 % kyr -1 -8 % kyr -1 ) and <lb/>reached an extent that is similar to the present earlier than <lb/>other regions by 10-9.5 kyr BP. The NO region also lost areal <lb/>extent at a relatively quick rate (∼ 8 % kyr -1 -6 % kyr -1 ), but <lb/>such rapid loss started later (after ∼ 12-11.5 kyr BP), and an <lb/>areal extent that is similar to the present was not reached un-<lb/>til ∼ 7-6.5 kyr BP (Fig. 17). In the NE region, on the other <lb/>hand, empirical data suggest that an extent that is similar <lb/>to the present was reached by approximately 8-7.5 kyr BP. <lb/>Before that time, the rate of the percentage areal extent <lb/>loss was relatively constant and at ∼ 7 % kyr -1 -5 % kyr -1 . <lb/>In the CE region, the ice sheet areal extent loss was rela-<lb/>tively slow (∼ 7 % kyr -1 -5 % kyr -1 ) until ∼ 10-9.5 kyr BP, <lb/>prior to accelerating substantially (∼ 18 % kyr -1 -9 % kyr -1 ) <lb/>until ∼ 8.5-8 kyr BP, by which time it had reached an extent <lb/>that is similar to the present. In our reconstruction, the CE <lb/>regions thus appears to have experienced a rapid and de-<lb/>layed collapse of a significant proportion of its total areal <lb/>extent between ∼ 10 and ∼ 8 kyr BP (Fig. 17). The SE re-<lb/>gion reached an extent that is similar to the present relatively <lb/>early, by 9.5-9 kyr BP, and experienced relatively slow areal <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>732 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 15. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>733 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 15. Ice-sheet-scale map of the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction divided in two distinct panels (north Greenland and south <lb/>Greenland) for readability purposes. The individual isochrone lines mapped as part of this study, and their four respective confidence levels, <lb/>are too detailed to be visualised at this scale. Instead, we show a colour map of the areas located between isochrones. Consequently, each <lb/>colour-coded mask (or isochrone buffer) highlights the former location of the Greenland Ice Sheet margins between the timings of the outer <lb/>and inner isochrones that it is delimited by. In order to visualise the full details of the isochrone reconstruction, along with the geomorpho-<lb/>logical and geochronological data compiled, the reader is advised to download and zoom into the PaleoGrIS 1.0 poster (A0 format) provided <lb/>in the online database. Alternatively, the reader can download the PaleoGrIS 1.0 shapefile database and visualise the reconstruction at any <lb/>scale in geographic information system (GIS) software. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>734 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 16. Empirical estimation of the Greenland Ice Sheet areal extent evolution between ∼ 18 kyr BP and the present. The ice sheet extent <lb/>during last full glacial configuration (red box) is estimated here by bracketing the maximum (at continental shelf break everywhere) and <lb/>minimum extent scenarios, reconstructed after consulting the relevant literature, in an attempt to highlight the uncertainties in several debated <lb/>regions (more details in Sect. 2.6). The hypothetical timing of such full glacial extent is crudely associated with maximum atmospheric and <lb/>oceanic cooling over Greenland during Heinrich Stadial 1 (Buizert et al., 2018), but we stress that the timing of maximum extent is unknown <lb/>and could have been reached before 18 kyr BP and until Bølling-Allerød warming started after ∼ 16 kyr BP, as highlighted by our conservative <lb/>range (red box). Ice sheet areal extent estimates from the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction are shown with green circles (actual extent <lb/>estimates) and orange triangles (maximum-limiting extent pointing upwards). This differentiation is due to our isochrones not covering the <lb/>full ice sheet perimeter during the ∼ 10-6.5 kyr BP interval when some sections of the ice sheet margin are estimated to have been as retreated <lb/>as (or more retreated than) the present margins. <lb/>extent loss prior to that (∼ 7 % kyr -1 -5 % kyr -1 ). The rate <lb/>of areal extent loss in the CW region decreased progressively <lb/>through time, and an extent that is similar to the present was <lb/>reached late in this region, after ∼ 8.5 kyr BP. The NW region <lb/>follows a similar pattern but reached near-present-day ex-<lb/>tent slightly earlier, prior to ∼ 9 kyr BP (Fig. 17). Such com-<lb/>parisons should be treated with caution, as they are some-<lb/>times derived from low-or very low-confidence isochrones. <lb/>However, the data generally suggest a latitudinal signal in <lb/>the different regional retreat patterns by which southernmost <lb/>regions reached a near-present-day margin position earlier <lb/>than northern regions, which experienced a more delayed <lb/>deglaciation. <lb/>3.4 Outlet glacier retreat rates analysis <lb/>Transects were drawn across reconstructed isochrones for 72 <lb/>outlet glaciers sampled around Greenland (further methods <lb/>in Sect. 2.5) (Fig. 18). Measuring distances along these tran-<lb/>sects allows us to estimate that overall retreat rates of glacier <lb/>fronts (or of the grounding line for marine margins) ranged <lb/>between 72 and 8 m yr -1 during the ∼ 14-6.5 kyr BP time <lb/>period (mean and 1σ SD 37 ± 16 m yr -1 ) (Fig. 18). Although <lb/>the frequency distribution of overall retreat rates is scattered <lb/>and bimodal, it is such that &gt; 80 % of outlet glaciers display <lb/>retreat rates between 56 and 16 m yr -1 . Although slightly dif-<lb/>ferent in nature, these overall retreat rates are comparable to <lb/>calving front retreat rates observed by Carr et al. (2017) for <lb/>marine-terminating glaciers across Greenland for the 1992-<lb/>2000 period (mean and 1σ SD ∼ 42 ± 86 m yr -1 ). <lb/>Our reconstructed ice sheet Late Glacial and early-to mid-<lb/>Holocene retreat rates can be compared with deglacial re-<lb/>treat rates from other ice sheet reconstructions. For instance, <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet outlets retreated at paces comparable <lb/>to, or perhaps slightly faster than, terrestrial margins of the <lb/>British-Irish Ice Sheet, which is associated with retreat rates <lb/>of &lt; 50 m yr -1 for most regions during deglaciation (Clark <lb/>et al., 2022). Marine calving margins of the British-Irish <lb/>Ice Sheet, however, generally retreated faster than our sam-<lb/>pled Greenland outlets (&gt; 50 and up to 451 m yr -1 ). Green-<lb/>land outlet retreat rates also appear to be slower than fast-<lb/>retreating terrestrial margins of the Laurentide Ice Sheet, <lb/>e.g. the southwest margin, which is thought to have reached <lb/>retreat rates of 380-340 m yr -1 following separation from <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>735 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 17. The PaleoGrIS 1.0 reconstruction of percentage ice sheet areal extent loss between ∼ 14 kyr BP (0 %) and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP for each <lb/>of the seven ice sheet regions spatially divided, as displayed in the inset map, after Rignot and Mouginot (2012). The colour code of the <lb/>individual time series matches the inset map polygons. Importantly, we use a different symbol to highlight whether the percentage of areal <lb/>extent loss, for a given region, is an absolute areal extent estimate (straight line) or a minimum-limiting areal extent loss estimate (dashed <lb/>line with downward-pointing arrows). The switch from straight to dashed lines thus represents, for each region, the youngest isochrone to <lb/>feature an extent that is more extensive than the present ice sheet extent along the full region-specific ice margin. <lb/>the Cordilleran Ice Sheet (Norris et al., 2022). However, <lb/>the Labrador sector of the Laurentide Ice Sheet is believed <lb/>to have experienced retreat that is slower than and similar <lb/>to the Greenland Ice Sheet Holocene retreat, with Lowell <lb/>et al. (2021) reporting a near-constant mean retreat rate of <lb/>52 m yr -1 between ∼ 19 and ∼ 10 kyr BP in this region. We <lb/>note that our reconstructed Greenland outlet retreat rates are <lb/>net rates averaged over the distances and time separating <lb/>500-year resolution isochrones. Our reconstruction may thus <lb/>lead to smoothing of faster pulses of retreat (&gt; 200 m yr -1 ), <lb/>which therefore should not be ruled out. <lb/>Our reconstruction further suggests that, overall, outlet <lb/>glacier retreat rates varied significantly between regions <lb/>(Fig. 18). We find that outlet glaciers from the CW region <lb/>were likely the fastest retreating in Greenland between ∼ 14-<lb/>13 and 7-6.5 kyr BP, with a regional mean retreat rate of <lb/>∼ 50 ± 14 (1σ SD) m yr -1 . This region includes the Sermeq <lb/>Kujalleq (overall rate 49 ± 5 m yr -1 ), Sermeq Avannarleq <lb/>(72 ± 14 m yr -1 ) and Store (70 ± 11 m yr -1 ) glaciers, for in-<lb/>stance. Outlet glaciers from the NE and NO regions also re-<lb/>treated relatively quickly during that period, with mean re-<lb/>treat rates of 44 ± 10 and 44 ± 13 m yr -1 , respectively. The <lb/>retreat of outlet glaciers from the CE and SW regions was <lb/>intermediate in speed, with mean retreat rates of 35 ± 23 and <lb/>29 ± 12 m yr -1 , respectively. Finally, we estimate that outlet <lb/>glaciers from the SE and NW regions experienced slower re-<lb/>treat at that time relative to other regions, with mean retreat <lb/>rates of 25 ± 5 and 24 ± 15 m yr -1 , respectively (Fig. 18). <lb/>The latter contrasts with present-day retreat rates, as marine-<lb/>terminating outlet glaciers in SE and SW Greenland currently <lb/>show the third-and fourth-fastest regional mean retreat rates <lb/>(136 and 117 m yr -1 , respectively) after NO and CW Green-<lb/>land (Carr et al., 2017). Our reconstruction shows that spatial <lb/>variability in outlet glacier retreat rate over the studied period <lb/>is dominated by these regional patterns. Indeed, we find no <lb/>statistically significant correlation between individual glacier <lb/>retreat rates and their present-day front width or with the ap-<lb/>proximate width of the overdeepened troughs along which <lb/>they retreated. Moreover, we argue that confidence levels in <lb/>the ice-sheet-wide PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones are often too <lb/>low to conduct quantitative analyses at the valley or outlet <lb/>glacier scale. <lb/>Our results also indicate that for most ice sheet out-<lb/>let glaciers sampled, the rate of retreat is highly variable <lb/>throughout the reconstructed time period, i.e. between 14-13 <lb/>and 7-6.5 kyr BP. Indeed, the median retreat rate of all sam-<lb/>pled glaciers (n = 72) shows intermediate values between <lb/>∼ 14 and ∼ 12 kyr BP (20-10 m yr -1 ), increases between <lb/>∼ 11.5 and ∼ 9.5 kyr BP (30-20 m yr -1 ), and decreases to its <lb/>lowest values between ∼ 9.5 and ∼ 6.5 kyr BP (15-5 m yr -1 ) <lb/>(Fig. 19). We thus find a significant proportion of Greenland <lb/>outlet glaciers experienced acceleration in their retreat pace <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>736 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>between ∼ 11.5 and ∼ 9.5 kyr BP, when our reconstruction <lb/>suggests numerous glaciers retreated at speeds &gt; 100 m yr -1 <lb/>(Fig. 19). These faster retreat rates are not observed as much <lb/>during other time intervals of the Late Glacial and early-<lb/>to mid-Holocene. The timing of this faster retreat (∼ 11.5-<lb/>9.5 kyr BP) coincides with the highest rates of atmospheric <lb/>and oceanic warming reconstructed between the Younger <lb/>Dryas (∼ 13-11.7 kyr BP) and the end of the pre-industrial <lb/>era (Buizert et al., 2018b). Furthermore, using linear regres-<lb/>sion analyses, we find that the majority of outlet glaciers <lb/>(65 %) indicate a decelerating retreat pace over the full re-<lb/>constructed period (Fig. 19). <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>4.1 Progress towards a robust reconstruction of the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet retreat, knowledge gaps, and <lb/>opportunities for future investigations <lb/>PaleoGrIS 1.0 is the first attempt to merge both geochrono-<lb/>logical and geomorphological markers of former grounded <lb/>ice extent to produce an ice-sheet-wide isochrone reconstruc-<lb/>tion of the Late Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene evolu-<lb/>tion of the Greenland Ice Sheet margin (Fig. 15). It thus rep-<lb/>resents a significant improvement from previous ice-sheet-<lb/>wide reviews and compilations (e.g. Dyke, 2004; Funder et <lb/>al., 2011; Lecavalier et al., 2014; Sinclair et al., 2016). An-<lb/>other novelty of this work is that it aims to make the recon-<lb/>struction and empirical database as accessible and usable as <lb/>possible, whether it is to inform future empirical and model-<lb/>data comparison investigations or to provide a format suit-<lb/>able to the production of future versions of the reconstruction <lb/>(see online database). <lb/>This first version of PaleoGrIS, however, remains incom-<lb/>plete and has its limitations. As noted earlier (Sect. 2.1.1), <lb/>our mapping of ice marginal landforms was conducted <lb/>rapidly over a few years and deliberately at a reconnaissance <lb/>level to identify only the main terrestrial landforms record-<lb/>ing former ice margin positions. This was necessary to cover <lb/>the large area and permitted us to erect the ice-sheet-wide <lb/>framework we have presented. Conducting and compiling <lb/>more detailed regional studies that map a wider range of ice <lb/>marginal landforms, including those located offshore, is an <lb/>important future task. In regions displaying fewer empiri-<lb/>cal constraints (e.g. Fig. 20), our reconstruction may act as <lb/>a stimulus for such investigations and could represent a tem-<lb/>plate that will undoubtedly require revision. We believe such <lb/>revision would greatly benefit from becoming a wider com-<lb/>munity effort, enabling the gathering of newly acquired data <lb/>and knowledge on the update scenarios of local ice sheet mar-<lb/>gin history (e.g. DATED-2, Hughes et al., 2023). <lb/>To enhance confidence in the empirical record and im-<lb/>prove our ability to quantitatively compare paleo model <lb/>simulations with observations, the glaciology community <lb/>requires more field data from and around Greenland. We <lb/>here used our reconstruction to identify regions that would <lb/>most benefit from new constraints on the timing of former <lb/>grounded ice sheet retreat. To do so, we mapped terrestrial <lb/>and offshore regions displaying no or only low-confidence <lb/>event ages and thus presenting either low-or very low-<lb/>confidence isochrones in our reconstruction. The highlighted <lb/>regions are shown in Fig. 20, and shapefiles are provided <lb/>in the online database. Care should be taken, as this assess-<lb/>ment does not include ongoing research efforts, data yet to be <lb/>published, or data published after our census date (21 Octo-<lb/>ber 2022) (e.g. Weiser et al., 2023). Nonetheless, we find vast <lb/>terrestrial and offshore areas displaying low-or very low-<lb/>confidence isochrones. Offshore of present-day coastlines, <lb/>we note the majority of the Greenland continental shelf re-<lb/>mains data-scarce when compiling studies establishing the <lb/>timing and pattern of grounded ice retreat from the last full <lb/>glacial extent. For terrestrial regions, we also find numer-<lb/>ous areas displaying potential for new field data collection <lb/>around the full ice sheet perimeter, with a relatively greater <lb/>density and surface area coverage of less studied sites in the <lb/>northern half of the island&apos;s periphery (&gt; 71°N; Fig. 20). <lb/>Furthermore, a great source of uncertainty impeding a better <lb/>understanding of the deglacial dynamics originates from the <lb/>ice sheet being generally more extensive today than between <lb/>∼ 6 and ∼ 2 kyr BP when responding to the Holocene ther-<lb/>mal maximum. Obtaining empirical evidence of the ice sheet <lb/>minimum extent during that interval (e.g. as is attempted by <lb/>the ongoing GreenDrill project; Briner et al., 2021) would <lb/>thus greatly improve our capacity to reconstruct the ice sheet <lb/>deglacial evolution. <lb/>4.2 Exploring controls on the varied retreat dynamics of <lb/>the Greenland Ice Sheet <lb/>Our overarching interpretation of the reconstruction is that <lb/>the deglacial retreat pattern and rate of the Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet, and the magnitude of the resulting mass loss, are con-<lb/>trolled by a series of interacting mechanisms whose relative <lb/>importance differs, depending on the spatial and temporal <lb/>scales analysed. <lb/>4.2.1 Ice-sheet-wide response <lb/>Linear response to climate and ocean forcing <lb/>Our reconstruction shows that at a Greenland-wide scale, the <lb/>ice sheet mostly retreated in a simple radial pattern progres-<lb/>sively stepping back from the continental shelf during the <lb/>last deglaciation (Figs. 15, 16). When analysed at a 1000-<lb/>to 500-year resolution, the retreat was not found to signifi-<lb/>cantly diverge from a linear retreat pattern other than with <lb/>local offsets and complexity arising from lagged position-<lb/>ing of marine versus terrestrial margins (e.g. in and adja-<lb/>cent to outlet glacier tongues; Fig. 12) and where the main <lb/>ice sheet left residual ice caps behind. As we here focus on <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>737 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 18. Map of Greenland Ice Sheet outlet glacier transects (black lines; n = 72) drawn to conduct a retreat rate analysis (see Sect. 3.4) <lb/>using PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones, the main results of which are also shown here. Retreat rates over the full reconstruction period (∼ 14-<lb/>6.5 kyr BP) are denoted using pink circles characterised by sizes proportional to the overall retreat rate magnitudes. Our outermost isochrone <lb/>(14-13 kyr BP), which marks the outer edge of our transect mapping, is shown with its spatially variable colour-coded confidence levels. <lb/>Towards the bottom-right corner, a histogram of overall retreat rate distribution is shown to have been split into eight bins of retreat rate <lb/>magnitude. Moreover, bold black numbers indicate the regional mean overall retreat rate (±1σ SD) for each of the seven ice sheet regions <lb/>sampled. Towards the top-right corner, a doughnut diagram highlights the relative proportions of outlet glacier retreat rates indicating decel-<lb/>erating (65 %) vs. accelerating (35 %) trends over the full reconstruction period. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>738 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 19. Time series denoting the evolution of the median re-<lb/>treat rate for all outlet glaciers sampled over the full reconstruc-<lb/>tion period (14-6.5 kyr BP). The blue polygon highlights a period <lb/>of general acceleration in the Greenland Ice Sheet outlet glacier re-<lb/>treat speed (see Sect. 3.4). It is important to note that the youngest <lb/>time slices are here associated with fewer than 72 data points, as <lb/>our reconstruction features certain outlet glacier margins reaching <lb/>present-day extent before others. <lb/>the ice-sheet-wide retreat signal (heterogeneous regional be-<lb/>haviours discussed further in Sect. 4.2.2), and because event <lb/>ages are now reasonably well distributed around Greenland&apos;s <lb/>periphery, we believe that this simple retreat signal would <lb/>still arise even with the improved spatiotemporal distribution <lb/>of geochronological markers. Along with this surprisingly <lb/>straightforward retreat pattern, we observe that the ice-sheet-<lb/>wide reduction in areal extent reveals a simple (negative) lin-<lb/>ear relationship with atmospheric or sea surface temperatures <lb/>(Buizert et al., 2018b; Osman et al., 2021) during the Late <lb/>Glacial and early-to mid-Holocene (Fig. 21). These correla-<lb/>tions suggest climate and ocean forcing were the dominating <lb/>agents of former ice sheet extent change. For instance, the <lb/>overall acceleration of outlet glacier retreat that we observe <lb/>between ∼ 11.5 and ∼ 9.5 kyr BP is coeval with the potent <lb/>atmospheric warming that characterised the Younger Dryas-<lb/>early-Holocene transition in the North Atlantic and Green-<lb/>land regions (Grootes et al., 1993; Fig. 21). This faster re-<lb/>treat also coincides with significant ocean warming, with ma-<lb/>rine records indicating increasing sea surface temperatures <lb/>offshore of most Greenland regions from ∼ 16 kyr BP and <lb/>reaching maximum warmth at ∼ 10-8 kyr BP (e.g. Williams, <lb/>1993; Jennings et al., 2006, 2017; Osman et al., 2021; <lb/>Fig. 21). More particularly, offshore of the SE, SW, and CW <lb/>Greenland regions, warmer and saline sub-surface Atlantic <lb/>water ingress from the Irminger Current (Fig. 1) is thought <lb/>to have caused rapid mass loss and initial retreat of grounded <lb/>ice margins from the outer continental shelves (Knutz et al., <lb/>2011; Ó Cofaigh et al., 2013; Jennings et al., 2017). Similar <lb/>forcing is thought to have occurred in NE and CE Greenland, <lb/>with warmer and more saline Atlantic water advected south-<lb/>ward from Fram Strait, along the Greenland coast, and across <lb/>continental shelves to marine-terminating margins, with the <lb/>establishment of the west Spitsbergen, return Atlantic, and <lb/>east Greenland currents during deglaciation (Hopkins, 1991; <lb/>Hebbeln et al., 1994). Furthermore, the findings of former ice <lb/>sheet margins likely located behind present-day ones during <lb/>and following the Holocene thermal maximum (Briner et al., <lb/>2014), followed by ice margin readvances during the mid-<lb/>to late-Holocene cooling that peaked with the Little Ice Age <lb/>(∼ 1850; Kjeldsen et al., 2015), are more evidence of this <lb/>broadly linear response to climate and ocean forcing. Over-<lb/>all, these observations suggest that the Greenland Ice Sheet <lb/>was highly sensitive to atmospheric and oceanic warming. <lb/>Relative sea level change is also likely to have influ-<lb/>enced the timing and the linear nature of the ice-sheet-wide <lb/>retreat pattern during the Late Glacial and early-to mid-<lb/>Holocene periods (Figs. 15, 16). In most coastal regions, <lb/>relative sea level rose rapidly after ∼ 16 kyr BP, reaching <lb/>a spatially variable high stand of 50-120 m at around 12-<lb/>10 kyr BP (Funder and Hansen 1996; Gowan, 2023; Lecav-<lb/>alier et al., 2014; Simpson et al., 2009). The timing of this <lb/>relative sea level high stand therefore also coincides with the <lb/>observed peak in outlet glacier retreat rates (Fig. 19). More <lb/>specifically, this rapid sea level rise is thought to have pro-<lb/>moted the early deglaciation of interstream sectors of the <lb/>marine-terminating former ice sheet, which likely presented <lb/>thinner ice (&lt; 300-400 m) grounded on shallower sections <lb/>of the continental shelves and were more vulnerable to buoy-<lb/>ant lift-off-and calving-induced retreat (Roberts et al., 2009). <lb/>The importance of this mechanism has moreover been con-<lb/>firmed by modelling studies experimenting with different sea <lb/>level forcings to nudge modelled Greenland Ice Sheet extent <lb/>(e.g. Lecavalier et al., 2014; Simpson et al., 2009). <lb/>Based on the observation of such broadly linear response <lb/>in ice extent, we suggest that at a whole ice sheet scale, com-<lb/>plexities in ice dynamics are less relevant at 1000-to 500-<lb/>year timescales than is perhaps perceived when analysing <lb/>contemporary glaciological fluctuations and feedbacks. Al-<lb/>ternatively, our reconstructions are not yet sufficient in den-<lb/>sity and resolution to adequately constrain retreat and ad-<lb/>vance oscillations that might have existed. <lb/>Glaciological inertia and delay in response <lb/>Although the Greenland Ice Sheet was highly sensitive to at-<lb/>mospheric and oceanic warming, specific glaciological re-<lb/>sponses to a forcing may vary over different timescales. <lb/>Melting or calving can happen nearly instantaneously, <lb/>whereas changes to ice accumulation may take thousands <lb/>of years to work through the system. Dynamic changes to <lb/>flow geometry and the positions of ice divides, as well as re-<lb/>sponses to glacial isostatic adjustment, may take even longer <lb/>still (Rogozhina et al., 2011). Consequently, significant in-<lb/>ertia in the system may have caused delay in the ice sheet <lb/>extent response to deglacial warming. The PaleoGrIS 1.0 re-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>739 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 20. Map of offshore and onshore regions that we interpret as data-scarce for the specific purpose of mapping and dating the deglacial <lb/>evolution of the grounded Greenland Ice Sheet margin. We thus believe these regions would most benefit from new geomorphological and <lb/>geochronological data. They were identified by locating regions dominated by very low-or low-confidence isochrones in our PaleoGrIS 1.0 <lb/>reconstruction. Two polygon shapefiles associated with these highlighted regions can be found in the online database. <lb/>construction suggests that the Greenland Ice Sheet margins <lb/>remained more extensive than present in several regions un-<lb/>til 7-6.5 kyr BP. The minimum Holocene extent of the entire <lb/>ice sheet was thus not reached until later, most likely between <lb/>6.5 and 4 kyr BP, as was previously suggested by numerical <lb/>modelling experiments (e.g. Lecavalier et al., 2014). Over <lb/>Greenland, δ 18 O ice core records (e.g. Alley, 2000; Buiz-<lb/>ert et al., 2018b) and temperature reconstructions from pa-<lb/>leo climate data assimilations (e.g. Buizert et al., 2018a; Erb <lb/>et al., 2022) all suggest Holocene mean annual temperatures <lb/>reached maximum values between ∼ 9 and ∼ 6 kyr BP, fol-<lb/>lowed by gradual neoglacial cooling until the end of the pre-<lb/>industrial era (∼ 1850; Kjaer et al., 2022) (Fig. 21). There-<lb/>fore, our ice-sheet-wide empirical reconstruction agrees with <lb/>previous observations that, during the Holocene, the ice ex-<lb/>tent response of the Greenland Ice Sheet lagged the cessation <lb/>of warming, potentially by thousands of years. This delay in <lb/>turn caused a lag in the response of the ice sheet to positive <lb/>mass balances during mid-to late-Holocene cooling. Indeed, <lb/>while both summer insolation (Berger and Loutre, 1991) and <lb/>temperature proxy records (e.g. Erb et al., 2022) reveal atmo-<lb/>spheric cooling across Greenland from 8-6 kyr BP to the pre-<lb/>industrial era, significant neoglacial glacier expansion did not <lb/>occur until 2.5-1.7 kyr BP (Kjaer et al., 2022). Finally, the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet&apos;s response to anthropogenic warming <lb/>that started around 1880-1900 was also delayed by almost a <lb/>century, with the mass and ice extent loss only being of ice-<lb/>sheet-scale significance from the 1980s onward (Kjeldsen et <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>740 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>al., 2015; Yang et al., 2022). Interestingly, the latter decadal <lb/>delay was shorter than the centennial-to millennial-scale lag <lb/>in ice sheet&apos;s response to the earlier positive mass balances <lb/>associated with mid-to late-Holocene cooling, thus possibly <lb/>highlighting a positive correlation between the duration/mag-<lb/>nitude of the climate forcing and the length of the delay in <lb/>the subsequent ice extent response. However, such a lagged <lb/>response observed at the ice sheet scale was not ubiquitous <lb/>across the entire ice sheet margin, as certain more dynamic <lb/>outlet glaciers appear to be better coupled with short-lived <lb/>early-Holocene temperature changes (e.g. Jakobshavn Isbrae; <lb/>Young et al., 2013b). Centennial to millennial-scale inertia <lb/>of the Greenland Ice Sheet following warming has been pre-<lb/>viously suggested (e.g. Yang et al., 2022) and has important <lb/>implications for ongoing climate warming because it results <lb/>in committed future mass losses and thus sea level rise con-<lb/>tributions that may last for centuries to millennia (e.g. Greve <lb/>and Chambers, 2022). <lb/>4.2.2 Regional responses <lb/>Moving from ice-sheet-wide to a focus on individual regions <lb/>(the ice catchments of Rignot and Mouginot, 2012), we find <lb/>heterogeneous retreat patterns with apparent differences in <lb/>both the magnitude of regional areal extent loss and the speed <lb/>of ice margin retreat (Figs. 17, 18). Spatially variable climate <lb/>and ocean forcings (Fig. 21) may have caused some of these <lb/>differences. For instance, the saline Irminger Current trans-<lb/>porting warm Atlantic waters offshore of south Greenland <lb/>(Fig. 1) likely caused this region to experience early, more <lb/>intense oceanic and atmospheric warming (Levy et al., 2020; <lb/>Fig. 21c). The inflow of relatively warmer, more saline sub-<lb/>surface water originating from the North Atlantic current was <lb/>likely crucial in causing sub-shelf melt near the grounding <lb/>lines of marine-terminating ice sheet margins (Knutz et al., <lb/>2011; Jennings et al., 2014). It has been argued that signif-<lb/>icant leads and lags in early deglaciation across Greenland <lb/>may be partly related to the complex advection patterns of <lb/>this water mass, enabled by the Irminger and west Greenland <lb/>currents (Fig. 1) influencing ice retreat in SE, SW, and CW <lb/>Greenland. Similar mechanisms are regarded to have caused <lb/>the intermediate return Atlantic current to influence ice mar-<lb/>gin retreat across the NE and CE Greenland shelves (Hebbeln <lb/>et al., 1994; Nørgaard-Pedersen et al., 2003; Hansen et al., <lb/>2022). However, at regional to valley scales, we believe non-<lb/>climatic and oceanic factors also help explain the variability. <lb/>We discuss and hypothesise some of these mechanisms in <lb/>the following sections, with a particular focus on ice-sheet-<lb/>and sector-scale topographic heterogeneities and asymme-<lb/>tries. While numerous other non-climatic factors, such as <lb/>spatial heterogeneities in ice shelf loss and sea ice cover, for <lb/>instance, may also play roles in controlling such regional het-<lb/>erogeneities, we here only focus on what we believe to be <lb/>main or first-order drivers. <lb/>Influence of heterogeneous continental shelf <lb/>topographies <lb/>When the Greenland Ice Sheet reached its maximum extent <lb/>(between 24 and 16 kyr BP, depending on regions; Funder <lb/>et al., 2011), and when local atmospheric and, more impor-<lb/>tantly, sea surface temperatures were lowest (Grootes et al., <lb/>1993; Osman et al., 2021), the ice sheet&apos;s margins had ad-<lb/>vanced across continental shelves (e.g. CW Greenland; Ó <lb/>Cofaigh et al., 2013). Such advances were facilitated by the <lb/>soft and unlithified nature of shelf surface sediments promot-<lb/>ing shear deformation of subglacial sediments, high basal <lb/>sliding velocities, and ice streaming in some cases (Evans <lb/>et al., 2009). Certain regions have wider continental shelves <lb/>providing grounded ice with considerable distances across <lb/>which to advance during build-up phases, while other sectors <lb/>only feature a narrow shelf to traverse before the continen-<lb/>tal slope, deep ocean, and high calving losses are attained. <lb/>For example, assuming grounded ice reached the continental <lb/>shelf break in the NE, offshore of NEGIS, the ice sheet had a <lb/>distance to advance of ∼ 280-300 km relative to present-day <lb/>positions. In southernmost Greenland, however, this distance <lb/>to attain the shelf break was instead only ∼ 80-100 km. <lb/>During full glacial conditions, precipitation and ice ac-<lb/>cumulation were very low in Greenland due to cold atmo-<lb/>spheric and oceanic temperatures (Buizert et al., 2018). The <lb/>GISP2 ice core record (Cuffey and Clow, 1997) suggests <lb/>accumulations &lt; 10 cm yr -1 between 20 and 15 kyr BP, and <lb/>the latest simulations of the water isotope-enabled Commu-<lb/>nity Earth System Model (iCESM) suggest values of around <lb/>5 cm yr -1 for that location (He et al., 2021). Therefore, in <lb/>sectors experiencing larger lateral ice sheet expansion across <lb/>wider continental shelves (e.g. NE and CW regions), ice <lb/>accumulation was less likely to be able to compensate the <lb/>required mass transfer to lower elevations during extensive <lb/>margin advance. This potentially caused greater ice sheet <lb/>thinning and lower surface slopes than in other sectors expe-<lb/>riencing less expansion across the continental shelf (e.g. SW, <lb/>NW, and CE regions). <lb/>Relative to a steeper ice sheet profile, a thinner sector <lb/>of the ice sheet with a gentler surface slope should ex-<lb/>perience increased melting for a given rise in the equilib-<lb/>rium line altitude because a greater surface area is now be-<lb/>low that altitude (Edwards et al., 2014). Warm periods such <lb/>as the Bølling-Allerød and early-Holocene intervals may <lb/>therefore have had varied effects on mass balance arising <lb/>from regional differences in ice surface slope attained during <lb/>build-up across continental shelves of different widths. Hy-<lb/>pothetically, such mechanisms may have caused Greenland <lb/>sectors with wider continental shelves and more extensive <lb/>last full glacial advances (e.g. offshore CW Greenland) to <lb/>have experienced faster grounding line retreat during the ini-<lb/>tial phase of deglaciation, under still predominantly marine-<lb/>terminating conditions (e.g. Fig. 22b, scenario 2). Another <lb/>sector where such effects may have played a role is in NE <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>741 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 21. Comparison between our reconstruction of Greenland Ice Sheet areal extent evolution and past atmospheric/sea surface tem-<lb/>perature reconstructions from proxy and model data between 20 kyr BP and the present. (a) Blue curve shows the reconstruction of mean <lb/>annual near-surface temperature at the location of the Greenland Ice Sheet Project (GISP2) ice core (72.58°N, -38.48°W) by Buizert et <lb/>al. (2018a), who merged Greenland ice core temperature reconstructions (GISP2, NGRIP, and NEEM) with the Transient Climate of the Last <lb/>21 000 Years (TraCE-21ka) simulations. Red curve shows the ensemble mean reconstruction of mean annual temperature anomaly (towards <lb/>GISP2 ice core location) relative to a 5-3 kyr BP reference period, by Erb et al. (2022), who use the global Holocene paleo temperature proxy <lb/>database of Kaufman et al. (2020) to conduct data assimilation on HadCM3 and TraCE-21ka simulations. (b) The Greenland Summit δ 18 O <lb/>record (Buizert et al., 2018b) that averages the GISP2 and GRIP δ 18 O records. (c) Reconstructions of sea surface temperature at different <lb/>locations offshore Greenland, using the ensemble mean (n = 500) from the Last Glacial Maximum reanalysis (LGMR) global dataset of <lb/>Osman et al. (2021), who use a paleo climate data assimilation scheme to correct biases in climate simulations of the isotope-enabled Com-<lb/>munity Earth System Model (iCESM) (versions 1.2 and 1.3). Coordinates for time series are as follows: south (Cape Farewell) is 58.34°N, <lb/>43.25°W; CW (Davis Strait) is 64.72°N, 56.53°W; CE (Danmark Strait) is 66.64°N, 27.26°W; NE (Nordic Sea) is 72.25°N, 10.10°W; and <lb/>NW (Baffin Bay) is 73.17°N, 62.65°W. (d) Greenland Ice Sheet areal extent reconstruction from the literature review (LGM-HS1 period), <lb/>the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones (this study, ∼ 14-6.5 kyr BP), and BedMachine v4 (Morlighem et al., 2017). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>742 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Greenland, which experienced rapid and extensive deglacia-<lb/>tion of a wide continental shelf, while NW Greenland on <lb/>the opposite side of the main ice divide instead experienced <lb/>slower and more limited retreat of ice margins (Fig. 22c). <lb/>Consequently, during the Late Glacial and early-Holocene <lb/>periods, a significant ice divide migration may have occurred <lb/>in NE Greenland. The recent findings of a possible reconfig-<lb/>uration of NEGIS during the early Holocene (Franke et al., <lb/>2022) could perhaps be linked to such regional adjustments <lb/>in ice flow. Around Greenland, more generally, the ∼ 12 to <lb/>∼ 8 kyr BP window may have been critical for ice stream <lb/>readjustments, as the ice sheet margin stepped back and <lb/>thinned from mid-/inner-shelf positions into more topograph-<lb/>ically confined coastal fjords. Such confinement increased <lb/>the fixing in position and channelising of ice flow, and pre-<lb/>existing overdeepenings may have induced some stepped <lb/>behaviour in retreat. The early-Holocene interval was thus <lb/>likely associated with a stronger topographic control on ice <lb/>stream position and behaviour throughout the Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet (Roberts et al., 2009). <lb/>Influence of heterogeneous onshore bed topography <lb/>The present-day onshore Greenland topography is spatially <lb/>heterogenous, with the CE, SE, and SW regions charac-<lb/>terised by prominent coastal mountain ranges, while other re-<lb/>gions generally feature lower-lying beds, which are in some <lb/>places resting below the modern sea level, such as under-<lb/>neath NEGIS or the Jakobshavn and Humboldt ice streams, <lb/>for instance (Morlighem et al., 2017). The latter can in some <lb/>cases enhance margin retreat speed and magnitude and pro-<lb/>mote outlet glacier instability (Jamieson et al., 2012). Higher <lb/>and more rugged topographies near the coast present oro-<lb/>graphic obstacles to precipitation from offshore. They pro-<lb/>mote ice accumulations sustaining coastal glaciers which can <lb/>contribute ice flux to the main ice sheet and locally decrease <lb/>the impact of negative mass balances on ice margin retreat <lb/>during warming phases. Higher coastal topographies enable <lb/>steeper surface slopes near ice sheet margins, and smaller <lb/>accumulation area loss for a given rise in equilibrium line <lb/>altitude during warming (Fig. 22b, scenario 2). Moreover, <lb/>high coastal mountains likely promote less slippery bed con-<lb/>ditions, with a rougher bed and more bedrock areas at higher <lb/>elevations potentially enabling more cold-based conditions. <lb/>These mechanisms could together explain why the SE sec-<lb/>tor of the Greenland Ice Sheet is characterised by a mar-<lb/>gin located closer to the shore than other more deglaciated <lb/>regions, despite significantly warmer local atmospheric and <lb/>sea surface temperatures (Fig. 21; Osman et al., 2021). In-<lb/>deed, while greater ocean and atmospheric warming likely <lb/>caused this region to lose its former marine-terminating mar-<lb/>gins earlier and more rapidly than in other sectors, this high <lb/>coastal topography feedback may have caused the ice sheet <lb/>to stabilise when becoming predominantly land-terminating, <lb/>with local margins remaining near the shore throughout the <lb/>Holocene. <lb/>Generally, we observe a pattern of stabilisation of ice sheet <lb/>margins during their marine to terrestrial transition in sev-<lb/>eral regions. Indeed, an abundance of prominent moraines <lb/>and other ice marginal landforms close to present-day coasts <lb/>can often be observed where present-day topography reaches <lb/>above the marine limit. This is common in the Ilulis-<lb/>sat, Sisimiut, and Nuuk regions (e.g. the Kapisillit stade <lb/>moraines; Young et al., 2021) (Fig. 12), for example, but <lb/>also in NE Greenland, onshore of major fjords (e.g. Dan-<lb/>mark Fjord). These landforms imply stillstands of the margin <lb/>once floatation and calving fronts were lost, suggesting that <lb/>calving and sub-shelf melt caused more ablation than sub-<lb/>aerial processes in these regions during the Late Glacial to <lb/>mid-Holocene retreat of the ice sheet. Here again, the role <lb/>of bed topography is critical, as the width, depth, and length <lb/>of fjord systems control how much margin retreat is required <lb/>prior to ice becoming fully grounded. Due to the added ab-<lb/>lation effect of calving, topographic heterogeneities between <lb/>fjords and inter-fjord sectors can generate different modes <lb/>of deglaciation for adjacent outlet glaciers, as observed, for <lb/>example, in north Greenland (Larsen et al., 2020). There-<lb/>fore, the transition from marine to land-terminating margins, <lb/>which occurred at different times in different regions due to <lb/>variabilities in uplift from glacial isostatic adjustment and <lb/>thus in relative sea level change (Long et al., 2011) is an es-<lb/>sential factor influencing the dynamics of former ice sheet <lb/>margin retreat in Greenland. We note the spatial and tem-<lb/>poral uncertainties in the PaleoGrIS 1.0 reconstruction are <lb/>likely too large to assess such valley-scale feedback quan-<lb/>titatively. Moreover, while numerous regions feature robust <lb/>paleo sea level records (e.g. the Disko Bugt area; Long et al., <lb/>2006), it remains a challenge to establish an accurate, time-<lb/>dependent, and Greenland-wide map of paleo sea levels at <lb/>the valley scale (Gowan, 2023). In most Greenland regions, <lb/>our ability to test the impact of this mechanism requires <lb/>thorough modelling experiments (with a coupled glacial-<lb/>isostatic-adjustment model) that are calibrated against obser-<lb/>vations and run at high (&lt; 1 km) spatial resolutions. Finally, <lb/>we argue that when subglacial topography is asymmetrical <lb/>on opposite sides of an ice sheet, it can cause potent ice di-<lb/>vide migrations during ice sheet build-up and demise phases <lb/>(Larsen et al., 2016). In central Greenland, for instance, sig-<lb/>nificantly higher coastal topographies (up to 2500 m a.s.l.) <lb/>lie underneath and around the eastern ice sheet margin rel-<lb/>ative to the western margin, which features a wide, low-<lb/>lying subglacial drainage basin (Fig. 22). During strong cool-<lb/>ing phases and ice build-up towards full glacial extent, the <lb/>ice sheet in CE Greenland draining towards Scoresby Sund <lb/>would have required thicker ice to overflow mountains and <lb/>become unconstrained compared to CW Greenland, where <lb/>ice feeding the Jakobshavn Ice Stream faces no such obsta-<lb/>cle. This asymmetrical thickness build-up may have gener-<lb/>ated an ice sheet dome increasingly skewed towards the east <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>743 <lb/></page>

	<body>during build-up to full glacial extent, resulting in a potent <lb/>eastwards migration of the main ice divide in central Green-<lb/>land. Conversely, during deglaciation, when eastern margins <lb/>retreated towards or behind present-day positions and be-<lb/>came increasingly constrained by coastal mountains imped-<lb/>ing ice evacuation, a westward migration of the divide may <lb/>have occurred in this region (as drawn in Fig. 22). In fact, one <lb/>could argue that westward migration of the main ice divide <lb/>in central Greenland might continue and possibly accelerate <lb/>in the future as the ice sheet margin thins, retreats, and be-<lb/>comes increasingly blocked by higher topographies and re-<lb/>versed bed slopes to the east. We therefore speculate that ice <lb/>divide migrations likely play an important role in controlling <lb/>the position of ice streams and influencing ice margin retreat <lb/>dynamics as noted for other paleo ice sheets (e.g. Greenwood <lb/>and Clark, 2009). The influence of such mechanisms could <lb/>be further tested by running high-order and high-resolution <lb/>model simulations constrained by ice extent observations. <lb/>To summarise, we here raise the hypothesis that at the <lb/>regional scale, the heterogeneous and sometimes asymmet-<lb/>ric nature of Greenland&apos;s terrestrial and continental shelf to-<lb/>pographies may be responsible for the following: <lb/>-skewed ice sheet profiles in surface elevation; <lb/>-regional variability in thickness and surface slope; <lb/>-regional variability in mass balance response to warm-<lb/>ing as a consequence of the above; <lb/>-rearrangements of certain ice streams and of surface ve-<lb/>locity fields during retreat; <lb/>-spatial variability in the timing of marine to terrestrial <lb/>transitions resulting in non-synchronous margin stabili-<lb/>sations; and <lb/>-major ice divide migrations during both advance and re-<lb/>treat phases. <lb/>Together, these rearrangements may cause inter-regional <lb/>variability in the speed and magnitude of Greenland Ice Sheet <lb/>margin retreat during deglaciation. <lb/>5 Summary and conclusions <lb/>-We present PaleoGrIS 1.0, an ice-sheet-wide recon-<lb/>struction of the Late Glacial and Holocene Greenland <lb/>Ice Sheet margin evolution, documenting the deglacial <lb/>back-stepping of ice margins to the present-day ice <lb/>sheet edge. This new reconstruction is based on around <lb/>194 000 geomorphological and 1450 geochronological <lb/>markers of former ice extent. It yields ice marginal <lb/>isochrones at a temporal resolution of 500 years and <lb/>spans ∼ 7.5 kyr from approximately 14 to 6.5 kyr BP. <lb/>-This reconstruction of the ice sheet margin evolution <lb/>through time, based on our Greenland-wide mapping of <lb/>ice marginal landforms, combined with a synthesis of <lb/>published geochronological data, enables us to pinpoint <lb/>the timing and dynamics of key glaciological events, <lb/>such as the unzipping of the Innuitian and Greenland <lb/>ice sheets and subsequent opening of Nares Strait, for <lb/>example, which is here estimated to have occurred at <lb/>∼ 8.5-8 yr BP. <lb/>-The PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrones enable us to quantify <lb/>the Late Glacial and Holocene areal extent change <lb/>in the entire Greenland Ice Sheet. We find that be-<lb/>tween 14-13 kyr BP until the present day, the ice sheet <lb/>has lost approximately one-third of its areal extent <lb/>(0.89 million km 2 ). Between 14-13 and 9-8.5 kyr BP, <lb/>the ice sheet experienced a near-constant rate of areal <lb/>extent loss of 170 ± 27 km 2 yr -1 . We also find Green-<lb/>land outlet glaciers experienced faster retreat rates be-<lb/>tween ∼ 12 and ∼ 9 kyr BP, while both rates of areal ex-<lb/>tent loss and margin retreat decreased markedly after <lb/>∼ 9 kyr BP. The timing of such faster retreat coincides <lb/>with the most potent local climate warming to have oc-<lb/>curred between the Younger Dryas (∼ 13-11.7 kyr BP) <lb/>and the end of the pre-industrial era (∼ 1850). In spite <lb/>of local glaciological complexities, the deglacial evo-<lb/>lution of ice margins at the ice sheet scale is strongly <lb/>correlated to, and controlled by, changes in atmospheric <lb/>and oceanic temperatures. These results imply that the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet was highly sensitive to climate <lb/>warming in its recent history and will likely remain so <lb/>in the future. <lb/>-We find the Greenland Ice Sheet minimum Holocene <lb/>extent was reached later than ∼ 6.5 kyr BP, which is <lb/>hundreds to thousands of years after the peak warm-<lb/>ing of the Holocene thermal maximum. We conclude <lb/>that inertia in the ice sheet system (a mix of fast and <lb/>slow glaciological responses) has caused a centennial-<lb/>to millennial-scale time lag in its response to the cessa-<lb/>tion of Holocene warming. Understanding and quanti-<lb/>fying such inertia, by better calibrating numerical ice <lb/>sheet models against data, for instance, is of crucial <lb/>importance to anticipating the magnitude of committed <lb/>mass loss and the response of the ice sheet to ongoing <lb/>global warming over the next few centuries. <lb/>-When quantifying retreat in different Greenland re-<lb/>gions, we find heterogeneous responses in the magni-<lb/>tude and rate of the ice sheet areal extent loss and in <lb/>outlet glacier retreat rates. While some of this hetero-<lb/>geneity may be related to spatial variability in climate <lb/>and ocean forcing, other non-climatic factors likely play <lb/>important roles in determining the regional-to valley-<lb/>scale dynamics of deglacial ice margin retreat. In partic-<lb/>ular, we hypothesise that in certain Greenland regions, <lb/>the asymmetrical configurations of continental shelf and <lb/>onshore bed topographies on opposite sides of the ice <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>744 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 22. Schematic model describing the hypotheses raised in Sect. 4.2.2, which explore the potential roles of asymmetrical continental <lb/>shelf and coastal bed topographies on the observed inter-regional variability in ice sheet margin retreat dynamics in Greenland during <lb/>deglaciation. Perhaps these ideas help explain the regional variability in both rate and magnitude of retreat. The subglacial topography and <lb/>bathymetry data displayed in the right-hand panels are a merged product of the BedMachine v4 and GEBCO (2022 release) DEMs. <lb/>sheet may be responsible for inter-regional variability in <lb/>the magnitude and timing of margin evolution, with im-<lb/>plications for both advance and retreat phases. Ice sheet <lb/>modelling experiments could usefully explore these hy-<lb/>pothesised controls, which may continue to be relevant <lb/>regarding future ice loss and sea level rise contributions. <lb/>-Despite remarkable and accelerating efforts from the <lb/>empirical community to produce an extensive library of <lb/>ice extent markers around the periphery of the Green-<lb/>land Ice Sheet, we find vast onshore and offshore re-<lb/>gions with sparse data and which yield isochrones of <lb/>low confidence. There is therefore much potential for <lb/>improving our knowledge of deglacial Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet margin evolution by producing new robust pa-<lb/>leo glaciological investigations in less well-constrained <lb/>regions. We believe the PaleoGrIS 1.0 reconstruction <lb/>and database can prove useful for identifying important <lb/>study sites and motivating future onshore and offshore <lb/>field activities. <lb/>-PaleoGrIS 1.0 is made available as an open-access <lb/>database, which may prove useful to both the em-<lb/>pirical and ice sheet modelling communities and for <lb/>data-modelling comparison exercises. To reduce data-<lb/>processing tasks and make our database usable by both <lb/>communities, we provide isochrone-related datasets in <lb/>both GIS (GeoTIFF/shapefile) and NetCDF formats. <lb/>The database also aims to be in a format suitable to <lb/>the production of improved future versions of the re-<lb/>construction. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Data availability. The PaleoGrIS 1.0 database is available <lb/>(open-access) on the Mendeley Data online platform at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.17632/nh57cz4gys.1 (Leger et al., 2024). It <lb/>includes the geomorphological mapping dataset (shapefile format), <lb/>the geochronological data compilation (two Excel spreadsheets and <lb/>numerous shapefiles for various products, including for both raw <lb/>ages and summary event ages), an A0 poster of the reconstruction, <lb/>and the PaleoGrIS 1.0 isochrone reconstruction in both shapefile <lb/>and NetCDF formats for both the empirical and modelling commu-<lb/>nities to use. The database features several READ_ME files to ease <lb/>navigation through the various products. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions. CDC conceived and guided the study. In-<lb/>put from JCE and TPML contributed to the design of the investiga-<lb/>tion. SJ, CH, CDC, and TPML conducted geomorphological map-<lb/>ping of ice marginal landforms from remote sensing (in relative or-<lb/>der of contribution). TPML compiled and filtered the geochronol-<lb/>ogy, with input from CH&apos;s Master of Science thesis. TPML created <lb/>the isochrone reconstruction, with feedback from CDC and JCE, <lb/>and TPML conducted the subsequent quantitative analyses. TPML <lb/>wrote the paper, with feedback from CDC and JCE, primarily, and <lb/></div>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>745 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">other co-authors for subsequent drafts. TPML produced all maps, <lb/>figures, tables, and prepared/formatted the PaleoGrIS 1.0 database. <lb/>CDC, JCE, and CD helped with providing feedback and ideas for <lb/>figures, along with other co-authors but to a lesser extent. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/>Special issue statement. This article is part of the special issue <lb/>&quot;Icy landscapes of the past&quot;. It is not associated with a conference. <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. We express our gratitude towards all indi-<lb/>viduals who contributed informal ideas and feedback to this work, <lb/>including Lev Tarasov, Jason Briner, David H. Roberts, and mem-<lb/>bers of the PALGLAC team, including Remy L. J. Veness, Helen <lb/>E. Dulfer, and Benjamin M. Boyes. We thank the two reviewers for <lb/>providing insightful comments which greatly improved the paper. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Financial support. This study has benefited from the PALGLAC <lb/>team of researchers, with funding from the European Research <lb/>Council (ERC) under the European Union&apos;s Horizon 2020 research <lb/>and innovation programme to Christopher D. Clark (grant no. <lb/>787263), which supported Tancrède P. M. Leger, Sharman Jones, <lb/>Sarah L. Bradley, and Christiaan Diemont. Jeremy C. Ely has re-<lb/>ceived support from a NERC independent fellowship award (grant <lb/>no. NE/R014574/1). <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Irina Rogozhina and <lb/>reviewed by Evan Gowan and one anonymous referee. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Albrecht, T., Winkelmann, R., and Levermann, A.: Glacial-cycle <lb/>simulations of the Antarctic Ice Sheet with the Parallel Ice <lb/>Sheet Model (PISM) -Part 2: Parameter ensemble analy-<lb/>sis, The Cryosphere, 14, 633-656, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-14-<lb/>633-2020, 2020. <lb/>Alley, R. B.: The Younger Dryas cold interval as viewed <lb/>from central Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 19, 213-226, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0277-3791(99)00062-1, 2000. <lb/>Andersen, J. L., Egholm, D. L., Olsen, J., Larsen, N. K., <lb/>and Knudsen, M. F.: Topographical evolution and glacia-<lb/>tion history of South Greenland constrained by paired <lb/>26 Al/ 10 Be nuclides, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 542, 116300, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2020.116300, 2020. <lb/>Andrews, J. T., Jennings, A. E., Cooper, T., Williams, K. M., <lb/>and Mienert, J.: Late Quaternary sedimentation along a fjord <lb/>to shelf (trough) transect, East Greenland (c. 68°N), 153-166, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1144/GSL.SP.1996.111.01.10, 1996. <lb/>Arndt, J. E., Jokat, W., and Dorschel, B.: The last glaciation and <lb/>deglaciation of the Northeast Greenland continental shelf re-<lb/>vealed by hydro-acoustic data, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 160, 45-56, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2017.01.018, 2017. <lb/>Balco, G., Stone, J. O., Lifton, N. A., and Dunai, T. <lb/>J.: A complete and easily accessible means of calculat-<lb/>ing surface exposure ages or erosion rates from 10 Be <lb/>and 26 Al measurements, Quat. Geochronol., 3, 174-195, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quageo.2007.12.001, 2008. <lb/>Balter-Kennedy, A., Young, N. E., Briner, J. P., Graham, <lb/>B. L., and Schaefer, J. M.: Centennial-and Orbital-Scale <lb/>Erosion Beneath the Greenland Ice Sheet Near Jakob-<lb/>shavn Isbrae, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 126, e2021JF006429, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2021JF006429, 2021. <lb/>Barr, I. D. and Clark, C. D.: Distribution and pattern of moraines in <lb/>Far NE Russia reveal former glacial extent, J. Maps, 5, 186-193, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4113/jom.2009.1108, 2009. <lb/>Benn, D. and Evans, D. J.: Glaciers and glaciation, 2nd Edn., Rout-<lb/>ledge, ISBN 13 978-0-340-90579-1, 2014. <lb/>Bennike, O.: Palaeoecological studies of Holocene lake sediments <lb/>from west Greenland, Palaeogeogr. Palaeocl., 155, 285-304, <lb/>2000. <lb/>Bennike, O.: Late Quaternary history of Washington Land, North <lb/>Greenland, Boreas, 31, 260-272, 2002. <lb/>Bennike, O.: An early Holocene Greenland whale from <lb/>Melville Bugt, Greenland, Quaternary Res., 69, 72-76, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yqres.2007.10.004, 2008. <lb/>Bennike, O. and Björck, S.: Chronology of the last recession <lb/>of the Greenland Ice Sheet, J. Quaternary Sci., 17, 211-219, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.670, 2002. <lb/>Bennike, O. and Kelly, M.: Radiocarbon dating of sam-<lb/>ples collected during the 1984 expedition to North Green-<lb/>land, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 135, 8-10, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v135.7991, 1987. <lb/>Bennike, O. and Wagner, B.: Deglaciation chronology, <lb/>sea-level changes and environmental changes from <lb/>Holocene lake sediments of Germania Havn Sø, Sabine <lb/>Ø, northeast Greenland, Quaternary Res., 78, 103-109, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yqres.2012.03.004, 2012. <lb/>Bennike, O. and Weidick, A.: Late Quaternary history around <lb/>Nioghalvfjerdsfjorden and Jøkelbugten, North-East Greenland, <lb/>Boreas, 30, 300-9483, 2001. <lb/>Bennike, O., Hansen, K. B., Knudsen, K. L., Penney, D. N., <lb/>and Rasmussen, K. L.: Quaternary marine stratigraphy and <lb/>geochronology in central West Greenland, Boreas, 23, 194-215, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1994.tb00599.x, 1994. <lb/>Bennike, O., Björck, S., Böcher, J., Hansen, L., Heinemeier, J., and <lb/>Wohlfarth, B.: Early Holocene plant and animal remains from <lb/>North-east Greenland, J. Biogeogr., 26, 667-677, 1999. <lb/>Bennike, O., Björck, S., Böcher, J., Hansen, L., Heinemeier, J., and <lb/>Wohlfarth, B.: Early Holocene plant and animal remains from <lb/>North-east Greenland, J. Biogeogr., 26, 667-677, 1999. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>746 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Bennike, O., Björck, S., and Lambeck, K.: Estimates of <lb/>South Greenland late-glacial ice limits from a new rela-<lb/>tive sea level curve, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 197, 171-186, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0012-821X(02)00478-8, 2002. <lb/>Bentley, M. J., Ó Cofaigh, C., Anderson, J. B., Conway, H., Davies, <lb/>B., Graham, A. G. C., Hillenbrand, C.-D., Hodgson, D. A., <lb/>Jamieson, S. S. R., Larter, R. D., Mackintosh, A., Smith, J. A., <lb/>Verleyen, E., Ackert, R. P., Bart, P. J., Berg, S., Brunstein, D., <lb/>Canals, M., Colhoun, E. A., Crosta, X., Dickens, W. A., Do-<lb/>mack, E., Dowdeswell, J. A., Dunbar, R., Ehrmann, W., Evans, <lb/>J., Favier, V., Fink, D., Fogwill, C. J., Glasser, N. F., Gohl, K., <lb/>Golledge, N. R., Goodwin, I., Gore, D. B., Greenwood, S. L., <lb/>Hall, B. L., Hall, K., Hedding, D. W., Hein, A. S., Hocking, <lb/>E. P., Jakobsson, M., Johnson, J. S., Jomelli, V., Jones, R. S., <lb/>Klages, J. P., Kristoffersen, Y., Kuhn, G., Leventer, A., Licht, K., <lb/>Lilly, K., Lindow, J., Livingstone, S. J., Massé, G., McGlone, <lb/>M. S., McKay, R. M., Melles, M., Miura, H., Mulvaney, R., <lb/>Nel, W., Nitsche, F. O., O&apos;Brien, P. E., Post, A. L., Roberts, <lb/>S. J., Saunders, K. M., Selkirk, P. M., Simms, A. R., Spiegel, <lb/>C., Stolldorf, T. D., Sugden, D. E., van der Putten, N., van <lb/>Ommen, T., Verfaillie, D., Vyverman, W., Wagner, B., White, <lb/>D. A., Witus, A. E., and Zwartz, D.: A community-based geo-<lb/>logical reconstruction of Antarctic Ice Sheet deglaciation since <lb/>the Last Glacial Maximum, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 100, 1-9, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.06.025, 2014. <lb/>Berger, A. and Loutre, M. F.: Insolation values for the climate of <lb/>the last 10 million years, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 10, 297-317, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0277-3791(91)90033-Q, 1991. <lb/>Bevington, P.: Data reduction and error analysis for the physical <lb/>sciences, McGraw Hill Book Co, New York, 1969. <lb/>Bick, H.: A Postglacial Pollen Diagram From Angmagssa-<lb/>lik, East Greenland, Medd. Gr Nonoland, DNK, DA., 204, <lb/>1-22, <lb/>http://pascal-francis.inist.fr/vibad/index.php?action= <lb/>getRecordDetail&amp;idt=PASCALGEODEBRGM7920268534 <lb/>(last access: 20 March 2024), 1978. <lb/>Björck, S., Wohlfarth, B., Bennike, O., Hjort, C., and Pers-<lb/>son, T.: Revision of the early Holocene lake sediment based <lb/>chronology and event stratigraphy on Hochstetter Forland, NE <lb/>Greenland, Boreas, 23, 513-523, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-<lb/>3885.1994.tb00619.x, 1994. <lb/>Bjørk, A. A., Kruse, L. M., and Michaelsen, P. B.: Brief commu-<lb/>nication: Getting Greenland&apos;s glaciers right -a new data set of <lb/>all official Greenlandic glacier names, The Cryosphere, 9, 2215-<lb/>2218, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-9-2215-2015, 2015. <lb/>Blake, W., Ruth Jackson, H., Currie, C. G., and Jackson, J.: Seafloor <lb/>evidence for glaciation, northernmost Baffin Bay, B. Geol. Soc. <lb/>Denmark, 43, 157-168, 1996. <lb/>Blake, W. J.: Geological Survey of Canada radiocarbon dates <lb/>XXVI, Geol. Surv. Canada, 86, https://doi.org/10.4095/122368, <lb/>1987. <lb/>Blake, W. J., Boucherle, M., Fredskild, B., Janssens, J., and Smol, <lb/>J.: The geomorphological setting, glacial history and Holocene <lb/>development of Kap Inglefield Sø, Inglefield Land, North-West <lb/>Greenland, Geol. Surv. Canada, 27, 1-42, 1992. <lb/>Bradley, S. L., Reerink, T. J., van de Wal, R. S. W., and Helsen, <lb/>M. M.: Simulation of the Greenland Ice Sheet over two glacial-<lb/>interglacial cycles: investigating a sub-ice-shelf melt parame-<lb/>terization and relative sea level forcing in an ice-sheet-ice-shelf <lb/>model, Clim. Past, 14, 619-635, https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-14-<lb/>619-2018, 2018. <lb/>Briner, J., Schaefer, J., Young, N., Keisling, B., Anandakrish-<lb/>nan, S., Kuhl, T., Boeckmann, G., MacGregor, J., Deconto, <lb/>R., Morlighem, M., Winckler, G., and Walcott, C.: Introducing <lb/>GreenDrill: Retrieving sub-glacial bedrock cores in North Green-<lb/>land to test ice sheet response to interglacial warmth (and sup-<lb/>porting your research?), in: AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts, C31A-<lb/>07, 2021AGUFM.C31A..07B, 2021. <lb/>Briner, J. P., Stewart, H. A. M., Young, N. E., Philipps, W., and <lb/>Losee, S.: Using proglacial-threshold lakes to constrain fluc-<lb/>tuations of the Jakobshavn Isbrae ice margin, western Green-<lb/>land, during the Holocene, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 29, 3861-3874, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.09.005, 2010. <lb/>Briner, J. P., Håkansson, L., and Bennike, O.: The deglaciation and <lb/>neoglaciation of upernavik isstrøm, greenland, Quaternary Res., <lb/>80, 459-467, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yqres.2013.09.008, 2013. <lb/>Briner, J. P., Kaufman, D. S., Bennike, O., and Kosnik, M. A.: <lb/>Amino acid ratios in reworked marine bivalve shells constrain <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet history during the holocene, Geology, 42, <lb/>75-78, https://doi.org/10.1130/G34843.1, 2014. <lb/>Briner, J. P., McKay, N. P., Axford, Y., Bennike, O., Bradley, <lb/>R. S., de Vernal, A., Fisher, D., Francus, P., Fréchette, B., <lb/>Gajewski, K., Jennings, A., Kaufman, D. S., Miller, G., Rous-<lb/>ton, C., and Wagner, B.: Holocene climate change in Arctic <lb/>Canada and Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 147, 340-364, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2016.02.010, 2016. <lb/>Briner, J. P., Cuzzone, J. K., Badgeley, J. A., Young, N. E., Steig, E. <lb/>J., Morlighem, M., Schlegel, N. J., Hakim, G. J., Schaefer, J. M., <lb/>Johnson, J. V., Lesnek, A. J., Thomas, E. K., Allan, E., Bennike, <lb/>O., Cluett, A. A., Csatho, B., de Vernal, A., Downs, J., Larour, E., <lb/>and Nowicki, S.: Rate of mass loss from the Greenland Ice Sheet <lb/>will exceed Holocene values this century, Nature, 586, 70-74, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2742-6, 2020. <lb/>Buizert, C., Sigl, M., Severi, M., Markle, B. R., Wettstein, J. J., <lb/>McConnell, J. R., Pedro, J. B., Sodemann, H., Goto-Azuma, <lb/>K., Kawamura, K., Fujita, S., Motoyama, H., Hirabayashi, M., <lb/>Uemura, R., Stenni, B., Parrenin, F., He, F., Fudge, T. J., and <lb/>Steig, E. J.: Abrupt ice-age shifts in southern westerly winds <lb/>and Antarctic climate forced from the north, Nature volume 563, <lb/>681-685, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-018-0727-5, 2018a. <lb/>Buizert, C., Keisling, B. A., Box, J. E., He, F., Carlson, A. E., Sin-<lb/>clair, G., and DeConto, R. M.: Greenland-Wide Seasonal Tem-<lb/>peratures During the Last Deglaciation, Geophys. Res. Lett., 45, <lb/>1905-1914, https://doi.org/10.1002/2017GL075601, 2018b. <lb/>Butzin, M., Prange, M., and Lohmann, G.: Radiocarbon simulations <lb/>for the glacial ocean: The effects of wind stress, Southern Ocean <lb/>sea ice and Heinrich events, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 235, 45-61, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2005.03.003, 2005. <lb/>Calov, R. and Hutter, K.: The thermomechanical response of the <lb/>Greenland ice sheet to various climate scenarios, Clim. Dynam., <lb/>12, 243-260, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00219499, 1996. <lb/>Carlson, A. E., Winsor, K., Ullman, D. J., Brook, E. J., Rood, D. <lb/>H., Axford, Y., Legrande, A. N., Anslow, F. S., and Sinclair, <lb/>G.: Earliest Holocene south Greenland ice sheet retreat within <lb/>its late Holocene extent, Geophys. Res. Lett., 41, 5514-5521, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2014GL060800, 2014. <lb/>Carr, J. R., Stokes, C. R., and Vieli, A.: Threefold in-<lb/>crease in marine-terminating outlet glacier retreat rates across <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>747 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>the Atlantic Arctic: 1992-2010, Ann. Glaciol., 58, 72-91, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/aog.2017.3, 2017. <lb/>Carrivick, J. L., Yde, J., Russell, A. J., Quincey, D. J., <lb/>Ingeman-Nielsen, T., and Mallalieu, J.: Ice-margin and melt-<lb/>water dynamics during the mid-Holocene in the Kanger-<lb/>lussuaq area of west Greenland, Boreas, 46, 369-387, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12199, 2017. <lb/>Cartapanis, O., Jonkers, L., Moffa-Sanchez, P., Jaccard, S. L., <lb/>and de Vernal, A.: Complex spatio-temporal structure of <lb/>the Holocene Thermal Maximum, Nat. Commun., 13, 5662, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-33362-1, 2022. <lb/>Ceperley, E. G., Marcott, S. A., Reusche, M. M., Barth, A. <lb/>M., Mix, A. C., Brook, E. J., and Caffee, M.: Widespread <lb/>early Holocene deglaciation, Washington Land, north-<lb/>west Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 231, 106181, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106181, 2020. <lb/>Chandler, B. M. P., Lovell, H., Boston, C. M., Lukas, S., Barr, I. D., <lb/>Benediktsson, Í. Ö., Benn, D. I., Clark, C. D., Darvill, C. M., <lb/>Evans, D. J. A., Ewertowski, M. W., Loibl, D., Margold, M., <lb/>Otto, J. C., Roberts, D. H., Stokes, C. R., Storrar, R. D., and <lb/>Stroeven, A. P.: Glacial geomorphological mapping: A review <lb/>of approaches and frameworks for best practice, Earth-Sci. Rev., <lb/>185, 806-846, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2018.07.015, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Christiansen, H. H., Bennike, O., Böcher, J., Elberling, B., Hum-<lb/>lum, O., and Jakobsen, B. H.: Holocene environmental recon-<lb/>struction from deltaic deposits in northeast Greenland, J. Quater-<lb/>nary Sci., 17, 145-160, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.665, 2002. <lb/>Clark, C. D., Hughes, A. L. C., Greenwood, S. L., Jordan, C., <lb/>and Sejrup, H. P.: Pattern and timing of retreat of the last <lb/>British-Irish Ice Sheet, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 44, 112-146, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.07.019, 2012. <lb/>Clark, C. D., Ely, J. C., Hindmarsh, R. C. A., Bradley, S., Ignéczi, <lb/>A., Fabel, D., Ó Cofaigh, C., Chiverrell, R. C., Scourse, J., <lb/>Benetti, S., Bradwell, T., Evans, D. J. A., Roberts, D. H., Burke, <lb/>M., Callard, S. L., Medialdea, A., Saher, M., Small, D., Smed-<lb/>ley, R. K., Gasson, E., Gregoire, L., Gandy, N., Hughes, A. L. C., <lb/>Ballantyne, C., Bateman, M. D., Bigg, G. R., Doole, J., Dove, <lb/>D., Duller, G. A. T., Jenkins, G. T. H., Livingstone, S. L., Mc-<lb/>Carron, S., Moreton, S., Pollard, D., Praeg, D., Sejrup, H. P., <lb/>Van Landeghem, K. J. J., and Wilson, P.: Growth and retreat <lb/>of the last British-Irish Ice Sheet, 31 000 to 15 000 years ago: <lb/>the BRITICE-CHRONO reconstruction, Boreas, 51, 699-758, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12594, 2022. <lb/>Corbett, L. B., Young, N. E., Bierman, P. R., Briner, J. <lb/>P., Neumann, T. A., Rood, D. H., and Graly, J. A.: <lb/>Paired bedrock and boulder 10 Be concentrations resulting <lb/>from early Holocene ice retreat near Jakobshavn Isfjord, <lb/>western Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 30, 1739-1749, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2011.04.001, 2011. <lb/>Corbett, L. B., Bierman, P. R., Graly, J. A., Neumann, T. <lb/>A., and Rood, D. H.: Constraining landscape history and <lb/>glacial erosivity using paired cosmogenic nuclides in upernavik, <lb/>northwest greenland, Bull. Geol. Soc. Am., 125, 1539-1553, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1130/B30813.1, 2013. <lb/>Corbett, L. B., Bierman, P. R., Lasher, G. E., and Rood, <lb/>D. H.: Landscape chronology and glacial history in Thule, <lb/>northwest Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 109, 57-67, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.11.019, 2015. <lb/>Couette, P.-O., Lajeunesse, P., Ghienne, J.-F., Dorschel, B., <lb/>Gebhardt, C., Hebbeln, D., and Brouard, E.: Evidence for <lb/>an extensive ice shelf in northern Baffin Bay during the <lb/>Last Glacial Maximum, Commun. Earth Environ., 3, 225, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-022-00559-7, 2022. <lb/>Crane, H. R. and Griffin, J. B.: University of Michi-<lb/>gan Radiocarbon Dates IV, Radiocarbon, 1, 173-198, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200020452, 1959. <lb/>Cremer, H., Wagner, B., Melles, M., and Hubberten, H.-W.: <lb/>The postglacial environmental development of Raffles Sø, East <lb/>Greenland: inferences from a 10,000 year diatom record, J. Pale-<lb/>olimnol., 26, 67-87, https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1011179321529, <lb/>2001. <lb/>Cronauer, S. L., Briner, J. P., Kelley, S. E., Zimmerman, <lb/>S. R. H., and Morlighem, M.: 10 Be dating reveals early-<lb/>middle Holocene age of the Drygalski Moraines in cen-<lb/>tral West Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 147, 59-68, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2015.08.034, 2016. <lb/>Cuffey, K. M. and Clow, G. D.: Temperature, accumulation, <lb/>and ice sheet elevation in central Greenland through the last <lb/>deglacial transition, J. Geophys. Res.-Oceans, 102, 26383-<lb/>26396, https://doi.org/10.1029/96JC03981, 1997. <lb/>Dalton, A. S., Margold, M., Stokes, C. R., Tarasov, L., Dyke, A. <lb/>S., Adams, R. S., Allard, S., Arends, H. E., Atkinson, N., Attig, <lb/>J. W., Barnett, P. J., Barnett, R. L., Batterson, M., Bernatchez, <lb/>P., Borns, H. W., Breckenridge, A., Briner, J. P., Brouard, E., <lb/>Campbell, J. E., Carlson, A. E., Clague, J. J., Curry, B. B., <lb/>Daigneault, R. A., Dubé-Loubert, H., Easterbrook, D. J., Franzi, <lb/>D. A., Friedrich, H. G., Funder, S., Gauthier, M. S., Gowan, <lb/>A. S., Harris, K. L., Hétu, B., Hooyer, T. S., Jennings, C. E., <lb/>Johnson, M. D., Kehew, A. E., Kelley, S. E., Kerr, D., King, <lb/>E. L., Kjeldsen, K. K., Knaeble, A. R., Lajeunesse, P., Lake-<lb/>man, T. R., Lamothe, M., Larson, P., Lavoie, M., Loope, H. M., <lb/>Lowell, T. V., Lusardi, B. A., Manz, L., McMartin, I., Nixon, <lb/>F. C., Occhietti, S., Parkhill, M. A., Piper, D. J. W., Pronk, A. <lb/>G., Richard, P. J. H., Ridge, J. C., Ross, M., Roy, M., Seaman, <lb/>A., Shaw, J., Stea, R. R., Teller, J. T., Thompson, W. B., Thor-<lb/>leifson, L. H., Utting, D. J., Veillette, J. J., Ward, B. C., Wed-<lb/>dle, T. K., and Wright, H. E.: An updated radiocarbon-based ice <lb/>margin chronology for the last deglaciation of the North Amer-<lb/>ican Ice Sheet Complex, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 234, 106223, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106223, 2020. <lb/>Davies, B. J., Darvill, C. M., Lovell, H., Bendle, J. M., Dowdeswell, <lb/>J. A., Fabel, D., García, J.-L., Geiger, A., Glasser, N. F., Ghe-<lb/>orghiu, D. M., Harrison, S., Hein, A. S., Kaplan, M. R., Mar-<lb/>tin, J. R. V., Mendelova, M., Palmer, A., Pelto, M., Rodés, <lb/>Á., Sagredo, E. A., Smedley, R., Smellie, J. L., and Thorndy-<lb/>craft, V. R.: The evolution of the Patagonian Ice Sheet from <lb/>35 ka to the present day (PATICE), Earth-Sci. Rev., 204, 103152, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103152, 2020. <lb/>Davies, J., Mathiasen, A. M., Kristiansen, K., Hansen, K. <lb/>E., Wacker, L., Alstrup, A. K. O., Munk, O. L., Pearce, <lb/>C., and Seidenkrantz, M. S.: Linkages between ocean <lb/>circulation and the Northeast Greenland Ice Stream in <lb/>the Early Holocene, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 286, 107530, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2022.107530, 2022. <lb/>Delibrias, G., Guillier, M., and Labeyrie, J.: Gif Natural <lb/>Radiocarbon Measurements X, Radiocarbon, 28, 9-68, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200060008, 1986. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>748 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/>Donner, J. and Jungne, H.: Radiocarbon dating of shells from <lb/>marine Holocene deposits in the Disko Bugt area, West <lb/>Greenland, Boreas, 4, 25-45, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-<lb/>3885.1975.tb00677.x, 1975. <lb/>Dowdeswell, J. A., Uenzelmann-Neben, G., Whittington, R. J., <lb/>and Marienfeld, P.: The Late Quaternary sedimentary record <lb/>in Scoresby Sund, East Greenland, Boreas, 23, 294-310, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1994.tb00602.x, 1994. <lb/>Dowdeswell, J. A., Evans, J., and Ó Cofaigh, C.: Sub-<lb/>marine landforms and shallow acoustic stratigraphy of a <lb/>400 km-long fjord-shelf-slope transect, Kangerlussuaq mar-<lb/>gin, East Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 29, 3359-3369, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.06.006, 2010. <lb/>Dunai, T. J.: Cosmogenic nuclides: Principles, con-<lb/>cepts and applications in the earth surface sciences, <lb/>Cambridge <lb/>University <lb/>Press, <lb/>Cambridge, <lb/>1-187, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511804519, 2010. <lb/>Dyke, A. S.: An outline of North American deglaciation <lb/>with emphasis on central and northern Canada, in: Qua-<lb/>ternary Glaciations-Extent and Chronology, vol. 2, edited <lb/>by: Ehlers, J. and Gibbard, P. L., Elsevier, 373-424, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1571-0866(04)80209-4, 2004. <lb/>Dyke, A. S. and Prest, V. K.: Late Wisconsinan and Holocene his-<lb/>tory of the Laurentide Ice Sheet, Géographie Phys. Quatern., 41, <lb/>237-263, 1987. <lb/>Dyke, L. M., Hughes, A. L. C., Murray, T., Hiemstra, J. F., An-<lb/>dresen, C. S., and Rodés, Á.: Evidence for the asynchronous <lb/>retreat of large outlet glaciers in southeast Greenland at the <lb/>end of the last glaciation, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 99, 244-259, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.06.001, 2014. <lb/>Edwards, T. L., Fettweis, X., Gagliardini, O., Gillet-Chaulet, F., <lb/>Goelzer, H., Gregory, J. M., Hoffman, M., Huybrechts, P., Payne, <lb/>A. J., Perego, M., Price, S., Quiquet, A., and Ritz, C.: Probabilis-<lb/>tic parameterisation of the surface mass balance-elevation feed-<lb/>back in regional climate model simulations of the Greenland ice <lb/>sheet, The Cryosphere, 8, 181-194, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-8-<lb/>181-2014, 2014. <lb/>Eisner, W. R., Törnqvist, T. E., Koster, E. A., Bennike, O., and <lb/>van Leeuwen, J. F. N.: Paleoecological Studies of a Holocene <lb/>Lacustrine Record from the Kangerlussuaq (Søndre Strøm-<lb/>fjord) Region of West Greenland, Quaternary Res., 43, 55-66, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1006/qres.1995.1006, 1995. <lb/>Ely, J. C., Clark, C. D., Small, D., and Hindmarsh, R. C. A.: <lb/>ATAT 1.1, the Automated Timing Accordance Tool for compar-<lb/>ing ice-sheet model output with geochronological data, Geosci. <lb/>Model Dev., 12, 933-953, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-12-933-<lb/>2019, 2019. <lb/>England, J.: The late Quaternary history of Hall Land, <lb/>northwest Greenland, Can. J. Earth Sci., 22, 1394-1408, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1139/e85-147, 1985. <lb/>England, J., Atkinson, N., Bednarski, J., Dyke, A. S., Hodgson, D. <lb/>A., and Ó Cofaigh, C.: The Innuitian Ice Sheet: configuration, <lb/>dynamics and chronology, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 25, 689-703, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2005.08.007, 2006. <lb/>Erb, M. P., McKay, N. P., Steiger, N., Dee, S., Hancock, <lb/>C., Ivanovic, R. F., Gregoire, L. J., and Valdes, P.: Re-<lb/>constructing Holocene temperatures in time and space us-<lb/>ing paleoclimate data assimilation, Clim. Past, 18, 2599-2629, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-18-2599-2022, 2022. <lb/>Evans, J., Cofaigh, C. Ó., Dowdeswell, J. A., and Wad-<lb/>hams, P.: Marine geophysical evidence for former expansion <lb/>and flow of the Greenland Ice Sheet across the north-east <lb/>Greenland continental shelf, J. Quaternary Sci., 24, 279-293, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.1231, 2009. <lb/>Franke, S., Bons, P. D., Westhoff, J., Weikusat, I., Binder, T., Streng, <lb/>K., Steinhage, D., Helm, V., Eisen, O., Paden, J. D., Eagles, <lb/>G., and Jansen, D.: Holocene ice-stream shutdown and drainage <lb/>basin reconfiguration in northeast Greenland, Nat. Geosci., 15, <lb/>995-1001, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-022-01082-2, 2022. <lb/>Fredskild, B.: Palynological evidence for Holocene climatic <lb/>changes in Greenland, in: Climatic Changes in Arctic Areas Dur-<lb/>ing the Last Ten Thousand Years, Acta Universitatis Ouluensis <lb/>Series. A, 277-305, 1972. <lb/>Fredskild, B.: Studies in the vegetational history of Greenland. <lb/>Palaeobotanical investigations of some Holocene lake and bog <lb/>deposits, Meddelelser om Grönl., 198, 1-245, 1973. <lb/>Fredskild, B.: The Holocene vegetational development of the <lb/>Godthåbsfjord area, West Greenland, Medd. Om. Grønl. Geosci., <lb/>10, 1-28, 1983. <lb/>Fredskild, B.: Holocene pollen records from west Greenland: qua-<lb/>ternary environments: eastern Canadian arctic, baffin Bay and <lb/>western Greenland, Allen and Unwin, Boston, 643-681, 1985. <lb/>Fredskild, B.: Palynology and sediment slumping in <lb/>a high arctic Greenland lake, Boreas, 24, 345-354, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1995.tb00784.x, 1995. <lb/>Funder, S.: Holocene stratigraphy and vegetation history in the <lb/>Scoresby Sund area, East Greenland, Groenlands Geol. Under-<lb/>soegelse, 129, 1-76, 1978. <lb/>Funder, S.: 14 C-dating of samples collected during the 1979 expe-<lb/>dition to North Greenland, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, <lb/>110, 9-14, https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v110.7787, 1982. <lb/>Funder, S.: Late Quaternary stratigraphy and glaciology in the <lb/>Thule area, Northwest Greenland, Kommissionen Vidensk. Un-<lb/>dersøgelser i Grønl., 22, ISBN 978-87-635-1199-5, 1990. <lb/>Funder, S. and Abrahamsen, N.: Palynology in a polar <lb/>desert, eastern North Greenland, Boreas, 17, 195-207, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1988.tb00546.x, 1988. <lb/>Funder, S. and Hansen, L.: The Greenland ice sheet-a model for its <lb/>culmination and decay during and after the last glacial maximum, <lb/>Meddelelser Fra Dansk Geol. Foren., 42, 137-152, 1996. <lb/>Funder, S., Kjeldsen, K. K., Kjaer, K. H., and O Cofaigh, C.: <lb/>The Greenland Ice Sheet During the Past 300,000 Years: A <lb/>Review, Developments in Quaternary Sciences, 15, 699-713, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-444-53447-7.00050-7, 2011. <lb/>Garcia-Oteyza, J., Oliva, M., Palacios, D., Fernández-<lb/>Fernández, J. M., Schimmelpfennig, I., Andrés, N., Anto-<lb/>niades, D., Christiansen, H. H., Humlum, O., Léanni, L., <lb/>Jomelli, V., Ruiz-Fernández, J., Rinterknecht, V., Lane, <lb/>T. P., Adamson, K., Aumaître, G., Bourlès, D., and Ked-<lb/>dadouche, K.: Late Glacial deglaciation of the Zacken-<lb/>berg area, NE Greenland, Geomorphology, 401, 108125, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2022.108125, 2022. <lb/>Georgiadis, E., Giraudeau, J., Martinez, P., Lajeunesse, P., St-<lb/>Onge, G., Schmidt, S., and Massé, G.: Deglacial to post-<lb/>glacial history of Nares Strait, Northwest Greenland: a ma-<lb/>rine perspective from Kane Basin, Clim. Past, 14, 1991-2010, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-14-1991-2018, 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>749 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Goelzer, H., Nowicki, S., Payne, A., Larour, E., Seroussi, H., Lip-<lb/>scomb, W. H., Gregory, J., Abe-Ouchi, A., Shepherd, A., Si-<lb/>mon, E., Agosta, C., Alexander, P., Aschwanden, A., Barthel, A., <lb/>Calov, R., Chambers, C., Choi, Y., Cuzzone, J., Dumas, C., Ed-<lb/>wards, T., Felikson, D., Fettweis, X., Golledge, N. R., Greve, R., <lb/>Humbert, A., Huybrechts, P., Le clec&apos;h, S., Lee, V., Leguy, G., <lb/>Little, C., Lowry, D. P., Morlighem, M., Nias, I., Quiquet, A., <lb/>Rückamp, M., Schlegel, N.-J., Slater, D. A., Smith, R. S., Stra-<lb/>neo, F., Tarasov, L., van de Wal, R., and van den Broeke, M.: The <lb/>future sea-level contribution of the Greenland ice sheet: a multi-<lb/>model ensemble study of ISMIP6, The Cryosphere, 14, 3071-<lb/>3096, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-14-3071-2020, 2020. <lb/>Gowan, E. J.: Paleo sea-level indicators and proxies from Green-<lb/>land in the GAPSLIP database and comparison with modelled <lb/>sea level from the PaleoMIST ice-sheet reconstruction, GEUS <lb/>Bull., 53, 1-17, https://doi.org/10.34194/geusb.v53.8355, 2023. <lb/>Greenwood, S. L. and Clark, C. D.: Reconstructing the last Irish <lb/>Ice Sheet 2: a geomorphologically-driven model of ice sheet <lb/>growth, retreat and dynamics, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 28, 3101-<lb/>3123, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2009.09.014, 2009. <lb/>Greve, R. and Chambers, C.: Mass loss of the Greenland ice sheet <lb/>until the year 3000 under a sustained late-21st-century climate, J. <lb/>Glaciol., 68, 618-624, https://doi.org/10.1017/jog.2022.9, 2022. <lb/>Grootes, P. M., Stuiver, M., White, J. W. C., Johnsen, S., and <lb/>Jouzel, J.: Comparison of oxygen isotope records from the <lb/>GISP2 and GRIP Greenland ice cores, Nature, 366, 552-554, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/366552a0, 1993. <lb/>Gulliksen, S., Heinemeier, J., Nydal, R., Rud, N., Skog, G., Thom-<lb/>sen, M. S., and Funder, S.: 14C dating of samples collected <lb/>during PONAM expeditions to east Greenland, in: The Last <lb/>Interglacial-Glacial Cycle: Preliminary Report of the PONAM <lb/>Fieldwork in Jameson Land and Scorseby Sund, East Greenland, <lb/>Lundqua Report 33, 177-181, 1991. <lb/>Håkansson, L., Briner, J., Alexanderson, H., Aldahan, A., and <lb/>Possnert, G.: 10 Be ages from central east Greenland con-<lb/>strain the extent of the Greenland ice sheet during the <lb/>Last Glacial Maximum, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 26, 2316-2321, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2007.08.001, 2007a. <lb/>Håkansson, L., Graf, A., Strasky, S., Ivy-Ochs, S., Kubik, P. W., <lb/>Hjort, C., and Schlüchter, C.: Cosmogenic 10 Be-ages from the <lb/>Store Koldewey island, NE Greenland, Geogr. Ann. Ser. A, <lb/>89, 195-202, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-0459.2007.00318.x, <lb/>2007b. <lb/>Håkansson, <lb/>S.: <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Lund <lb/>Radiocar-<lb/>bon <lb/>Dates <lb/>VII, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>16, <lb/>307-330, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200059634, 1974. <lb/>Håkansson, <lb/>S.: <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Lund <lb/>Radiocar-<lb/>bon <lb/>Dates <lb/>VIII, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>17, <lb/>174-195, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200002034, 1975. <lb/>Håkansson, <lb/>S.: <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Lund <lb/>Radiocar-<lb/>bon <lb/>Dates <lb/>IX, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>18, <lb/>290-320, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200003179, 1976. <lb/>Håkansson, <lb/>S.: <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Lund <lb/>Radiocar-<lb/>bon <lb/>Dates <lb/>XX, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>29, <lb/>353-379, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200043769, 1987. <lb/>Hansen, K. E., Lorenzen, J., Davies, J., Wacker, L., Pearce, <lb/>C., and Seidenkrantz, M. S.: Deglacial to Mid Holocene en-<lb/>vironmental conditions on the northeastern Greenland shelf, <lb/>western Fram Strait, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 293, 107704, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2022.107704, 2022. <lb/>Hansen, L.: Landscape and coast development of a lowland <lb/>fjord margin following deglaciation, East Greenland, Ge-<lb/>ogr. Ann. Ser. A, 83, 131-144, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0435-<lb/>3676.2001.00149.x, 2001. <lb/>He, C., Liu, Z., Otto-Bliesner, B. L., Brady, E. C., Zhu, C., Tomas, <lb/>R., Buizert, C., and Severinghaus, J. P.: Abrupt Heinrich Stadial <lb/>1 cooling missing in Greenland oxygen isotopes, Sci. Adv., 7, <lb/>1007-1023, 2021. <lb/>Heaton, T. J., Köhler, P., Butzin, M., Bard, E., Reimer, R. W., <lb/>Austin, W. E. N., Bronk Ramsey, C., Grootes, P. M., Hughen, <lb/>K. A., Kromer, B., Reimer, P. J., Adkins, J., Burke, A., Cook, M. <lb/>S., Olsen, J., and Skinner, L. C.: Marine20 -The Marine Radio-<lb/>carbon Age Calibration Curve (0-55 000 cal BP), Radiocarbon, <lb/>62, 779-820, https://doi.org/10.1017/RDC.2020.68, 2020. <lb/>Heaton, T. J., Butzin, M., Bard, É., Bronk Ramsey, C., Köh-<lb/>ler, P., Hughen, K. A., and Reimer, P. J.: Marine ra-<lb/>diocarbon calibration in polar regions: A simple approxi-<lb/>mate approach using marine20, Radiocarbon, 65, 848-875, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/RDC.2023.42, 2023. <lb/>Hebbeln, D., Dokken, T., Andersen, E. S., Hald, M., and <lb/>Elverhøi, A.: Moisture supply for northern ice-sheet growth <lb/>during the Last Glacial Maximum, Nature, 370, 357-360, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/370357a0, 1994. <lb/>Hjort, C.: Glaciation in northern East Greenland during the <lb/>Late Weichselian and Early Flandrian, Boreas, 8, 281-296, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1979.tb00812.x, 1979. <lb/>Hjort, C.: A glacial chronology for northern East Green-<lb/>land, Boreas, 10, 259-274,https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-<lb/>3885.1981.tb00487.x, 1981. <lb/>Hjort, C.: Glaciation, climate history, changing marine levels and <lb/>the evolution of the Northeast Water polynya, J. Mar. Syst., 10, <lb/>23-33, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0924-7963(96)00068-1, 1997. <lb/>Hopkins, T. S.: The GIN Sea -A synthesis of its physical oceanog-<lb/>raphy and literature review 1972-1985, Earth-Sci. Rev., 30, 175-<lb/>318, https://doi.org/10.1016/0012-8252(91)90001-V, 1991. <lb/>Hughes, A. L. C., Rainsley, E., Murray, T., Fogwill, C. J., Schn-<lb/>abel, C., and Xu, S.: Rapid response of Helheim Glacier, south-<lb/>east Greenland, to early Holocene climate warming, Geology, 40, <lb/>427-430, https://doi.org/10.1130/G32730.1, 2012. <lb/>Hughes, A. L. C., Gyllencreutz, R., Lohne, Ø. S., Mangerud, J., and <lb/>Svendsen, J. I.: The last Eurasian ice sheets -a chronological <lb/>database and time-slice reconstruction, DATED-1, Boreas, 45, <lb/>1-45, https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12142, 2016. <lb/>Ingólfsson, Ó., Frich, P., Funder, S., and Humlum, O.: Pa-<lb/>leoclimatic implications of an early Holocene glacier ad-<lb/>vance on Disko Island, West Greenland, Boreas, 19, 297-311, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1990.tb00133.x, 1990. <lb/>Ingólfsson, Ó., Lysä, A., Funder, S., Möller, P., and Björk, <lb/>S.: Late Quaternary glacial history of the central west coast <lb/>of Jameson Land, East Greenland, Boreas, 23, 447-458, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1994.tb00612.x, 1994. <lb/>Ives, P. C., Levin, B., Robinson, R. D., and Rubin, M.: U. S. Ge-<lb/>ological Survey Radiocarbon Dates VII, Radiocarbon, 6, 37-76, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200010547, 1964. <lb/>Jamieson, S. S. R., Vieli, A., Livingstone, S. J., Cofaigh, C. Ó., <lb/>Stokes, C., Hillenbrand, C.-D., and Dowdeswell, J. A.: Ice-<lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>750 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>stream stability on a reverse bed slope, Nat. Geosci., 5, 799-802, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1600, 2012. <lb/>Jennings, A. E., Andrews, J. T., Knudsen, K. L., Hansen, C. V., <lb/>and Hald, M.: A mid-Holocene shift in Arctic sea-ice vari-<lb/>ability on the East Greenland Shelf, Holocene, 12, 49-58, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1191/0959683602hl519rp, 2002. <lb/>Jennings, A. E., Hald, M., Smith, M., and Andrews, J. T.: <lb/>Freshwater forcing from the Greenland Ice Sheet during <lb/>the Younger Dryas: Evidence from southeastern Green-<lb/>land shelf cores, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 25, 282-298, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2005.04.006, 2006. <lb/>Jennings, A. E., Sheldon, C., Cronin, T. M., Francus, P., Stoner, J., <lb/>and Andrews, J.: The holocene history of nares strait: transition <lb/>from Glacial Bay to Arctic-Atlantic Throughflow, Oceanogra-<lb/>phy, 24, 26-41, https://doi.org/10.5670/oceanog.2011.52, 2011. <lb/>Jennings, A. E., Walton, M. E., Ó Cofaigh, C., Kilfeather, <lb/>A., Andrews, J. T., Ortiz, J. D., De Vernal, A., and <lb/>Dowdeswell, J. A.: Paleoenvironments during Younger Dryas-<lb/>Early Holocene retreat of the Greenland Ice Sheet from outer <lb/>Disko Trough, central west Greenland, J. Quaternary Sci., 29, <lb/>27-40, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.2652, 2014. <lb/>Jennings, A. E., Andrews, J. T., Ó Cofaigh, C., Onge, G. S., Shel-<lb/>don, S. T., Cabedo-Sanz, P., and Hillaire-Marcel, C.: <lb/>Ocean forcing of Ice Sheet retreat in central west Greenland from <lb/>LGM to the early Holocene, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 472, 1-13, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2017.05.007, 2017. <lb/>Jones, R. S., Whitehouse, P. L., Bentley, M. J., Small, D., and Dal-<lb/>ton, A. S.: Impact of glacial isostatic adjustment on cosmogenic <lb/>surface-exposure dating, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 212, 206-212, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2019.03.012, 2019. <lb/>Joughin, I. A. N., Smith, B. E., and Howat, I. M.: A complete map of <lb/>Greenland ice velocity derived from satellite data collected over <lb/>20 years, J. Glaciol., 64, 1-11, 2018. <lb/>Kaufman, D. S. and Williams, K. M.: Radiocarbon date list VII: <lb/>Baffin Island, NWT, Canada, including marine dates from adja-<lb/>cent seas and East Greenland, Occas. Pap.-Inst. Arct. Alp. Res., <lb/>48, 1992. <lb/>Kaufman, D., McKay, N., Routson, C., Erb, M., Davis, B., Heiri, <lb/>O., Jaccard, S., Tierney, J., Dätwyler, C., Axford, Y., Brussel, <lb/>T., Cartapanis, O., Chase, B., Dawson, A., de Vernal, A., En-<lb/>gels, S., Jonkers, L., Marsicek, J., Moffa-Sánchez, P., Morrill, C., <lb/>Orsi, A., Rehfeld, K., Saunders, K., Sommer, P. S., Thomas, E., <lb/>Tonello, M., Tóth, M., Vachula, R., Andreev, A., Bertrand, S., <lb/>Biskaborn, B., Bringué, M., Brooks, S., Caniupán, M., Cheva-<lb/>lier, M., Cwynar, L., Emile-Geay, J., Fegyveresi, J., Feurdean, <lb/>A., Finsinger, W., Fortin, M. C., Foster, L., Fox, M., Gajew-<lb/>ski, K., Grosjean, M., Hausmann, S., Heinrichs, M., Holmes, N., <lb/>Ilyashuk, B., Ilyashuk, E., Juggins, S., Khider, D., Koinig, K., <lb/>Langdon, P., Larocque-Tobler, I., Li, J., Lotter, A., Luoto, T., <lb/>Mackay, A., Magyari, E., Malevich, S., Mark, B., Massaferro, <lb/>J., Montade, V., Nazarova, L., Novenko, E., Pařil, P., Pearson, <lb/>E., Peros, M., Pienitz, R., Płóciennik, M., Porinchu, D., Potito, <lb/>A., Rees, A., Reinemann, S., Roberts, S., Rolland, N., Salonen, <lb/>S., Self, A., Seppä, H., Shala, S., St-Jacques, J. M., Stenni, B., <lb/>Syrykh, L., Tarrats, P., Taylor, K., van den Bos, V., Velle, G., <lb/>Wahl, E., Walker, I., Wilmshurst, J., Zhang, E., and Zhilich, S.: A <lb/>global database of Holocene paleotemperature records, Sci. Data, <lb/>7, 1-34, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-0445-3, 2020. <lb/>Kelley, S. E., Briner, J. P., Young, N. E., Babonis, G. S., and Csatho, <lb/>B.: Maximum late Holocene extent of the western Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet during the late 20th century, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 56, 89-<lb/>98, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2012.09.016, 2012. <lb/>Kelley, S. E., Briner, J. P., and Young, N. E.: Rapid ice retreat in <lb/>Disko Bugt supported by 10 Be dating of the last recession of the <lb/>western Greenland Ice Sheet, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 82, 13-22, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2013.09.018, 2013. <lb/>Kelley, S. E., Briner, J. P., and Zimmerman, S. R. H.: The in-<lb/>fluence of ice marginal setting on early Holocene retreat rates <lb/>in central West Greenland, J. Quaternary Sci., 30, 271-280, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.2778, 2015. <lb/>Kelly, M.: Radiocarbon dated shell samples from Nordre Strøm-<lb/>fjord, West Greenland, with comments on models of glacio-<lb/>isostatic uplift, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 59, 1-20, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v59.7369, 1973. <lb/>Kelly, M.: Comments on the implications of new radio-<lb/>carbon dates from the Holsteinsborg region, central West <lb/>Greenland, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 95, 35-42, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v95.7642, 1979. <lb/>Kelly, M.: Preliminary investigations of the Quaternary <lb/>of Melville Bugt and Dundas, North-West Green-<lb/>land, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 100, 33-38, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v100.7691, 1980. <lb/>Kelly, M. and Bennike, O.: Quaternary geology of parts of <lb/>central and western North Greenland: a preliminary ac-<lb/>count, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 126, 111-116, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v126.7917, 1985. <lb/>Kelly, M. and Bennike, O.: Quaternary geology of western and cen-<lb/>tral North Greenland, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 153, <lb/>1-34, https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v153.8164, 1992. <lb/>Kelly, M. and Funder, S.: The pollen stratigraphy of <lb/>late Quaternary lake sediments of South-West Green-<lb/>land, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 64, 1-26, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v64.7374, 1974. <lb/>Kelly, M., Funder, S., Houmark-nielsen, M., Knudsen, K. L., <lb/>Kronborg, C., Landvik, J., and Sorby, L.: Quaternary glacial <lb/>and marine environmental history of northwest Greenland: a <lb/>review and reappraisal, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 18, 373-392, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0277-3791(98)00004-3, 1999. <lb/>Kjaer, K. H., Bjørk, A. A., Kjeldsen, K. K., Hansen, E. S., An-<lb/>dresen, C. S., Siggaard-Andersen, M.-L., Khan, S. A., Søn-<lb/>dergaard, A. S., Colgan, W., Schomacker, A., Woodroffe, <lb/>S., Funder, S., Rouillard, A., Jensen, J. F., and Larsen, <lb/>N. K.: Glacier response to the Little Ice Age during the <lb/>Neoglacial cooling in Greenland, Earth-Sci. Rev., 227, 103984, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2022.103984, 2022. <lb/>Kjeldsen, K. K., Korsgaard, N. J., Bjørk, A. A., Khan, S. A., <lb/>Box, J. E., Funder, S., Larsen, N. K., Bamber, J. L., Colgan, <lb/>W., Van Den Broeke, M., Siggaard-Andersen, M. L., Nuth, C., <lb/>Schomacker, A., Andresen, C. S., Willerslev, E., and Kjaer, K. <lb/>H.: Spatial and temporal distribution of mass loss from the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet since AD 1900, Nature, 528, 396-400, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nature16183, 2015. <lb/>Knutz, P. C., Sicre, M. A., Ebbesen, H., Christiansen, S., <lb/>and Kuijpers, A.: Multiple-stage deglacial retreat of the <lb/>southern Greenland Ice Sheet linked with Irminger Cur-<lb/>rent warm water transport, Paleoceanography, 26, PA3204, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2010PA002053, 2011. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>751 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Kuijpers, A., Troelstra, S. R., Prins, M. A., Linthout, K., <lb/>Akhmetzhanov, A., Bouryak, S., Bachmann, M. F., Lassen, <lb/>S., Rasmussen, S., and Jensen, J. B.: Late Quaternary sed-<lb/>imentary processes and ocean circulation changes at the <lb/>Southeast Greenland margin, Mar. Geol., 195, 109-129, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0025-3227(02)00684-9, 2003. <lb/>Laberg, J. S., Forwick, M., and Husum, K.: New geophysical evi-<lb/>dence for a revised maximum position of part of the NE sector of <lb/>the Greenland ice sheet during the last glacial maximum, Arktos, <lb/>3, 3, https://doi.org/10.1007/s41063-017-0029-4, 2017. <lb/>Landvik, J. Y., Weidick, A., and Hansen, A.: The glacial history <lb/>of the Hans Tausen Iskappe and the last glaciation of Peary <lb/>Land, North Greenland Reconstructions of the glacial dynamics <lb/>from spatial data mining View project Glacial history of Sval-<lb/>bard View project, Meddelelser om Grønland, Geosci., 39, 27-<lb/>44, 2001. <lb/>Lane, T. P., Roberts, D. H., Rea, B. R., Cofaigh, C., Vieli, <lb/>A., and Rodés, A.: Controls upon the Last Glacial Maxi-<lb/>mum deglaciation of the northern Uummannaq Ice Stream <lb/>System, West Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 92, 324-344, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2013.09.013, 2014. <lb/>Larsen, E., Fredin, O., Lyså, A., Amantov, A., Fjeldskaar, W., and <lb/>Ottesen, D.: Causes of time-transgressive glacial maxima posi-<lb/>tions of the last Scandinavian Ice Sheet, Nor. J. Geol., 96, 159-<lb/>170, https://doi.org/10.17850/njg96-2-06, 2016. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Funder, S., Kjaer, K. H., Kjeldsen, K. K., Knud-<lb/>sen, M. F., and Linge, H.: Rapid early Holocene ice re-<lb/>treat in West Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 92, 310-323, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2013.05.027, 2014. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Kjaer, K. H., Lecavalier, B., Bjørk, A. A., Colding, <lb/>S., Huybrechts, P., Jakobsen, K. E., Kjeldsen, K. K., Knudsen, K. <lb/>L., Odgaard, B. V., and Olsen, J.: The response of the southern <lb/>Greenland ice sheet to the Holocene thermal maximum, Geology, <lb/>43, 291-294, https://doi.org/10.1130/G36476.1, 2015. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Levy, L. B., Carlson, A. E., Buizert, C., Olsen, <lb/>J., Strunk, A., Bjørk, A. A., and Skov, D. S.: Instability of the <lb/>Northeast Greenland Ice Stream over the last 45,000 years, Nat. <lb/>Commun., 9, 1872, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-018-04312-<lb/>7, 2018. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Søndergaard, A. S., Levy, L. B., Olsen, J., Strunk, A., <lb/>Bjørk, A. A., and Skov, D.: Contrasting modes of deglaciation <lb/>between fjords and inter-fjord areas in eastern North Greenland, <lb/>Boreas, 49, 903-917, https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12475, 2020. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Søndergaard, A. S., Levy, L. B., Laursen, <lb/>C. H., Bjørk, A. A., Kjeldsen, K. K., Funder, S., <lb/>Strunk, A., Olsen, J., and Kjaer, K. H.: Cosmogenic nu-<lb/>clide inheritance in Little Ice Age moraines -A case <lb/>study from Greenland, Quat. Geochronol., 65, 101200, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quageo.2021.101200, 2021. <lb/>Larsen, N. K., Søndergaard, A. S., Levy, L. B., Strunk, A., <lb/>Skov, D. S., Bjørk, A., Khan, S. A., and Olsen, J.: Late <lb/>glacial and Holocene glaciation history of North and North-<lb/>east Greenland, Arctic, Antarct. Alp. Res., 54, 294-313, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/15230430.2022.2094607, 2022. <lb/>Lecavalier, B. S., Milne, G. A., Simpson, M. J. R., Wake, L., Huy-<lb/>brechts, P., Tarasov, L., Kjeldsen, K. K., Funder, S., Long, A. <lb/>J., Woodroffe, S., Dyke, A. S., and Larsen, N. K.: A model of <lb/>Greenland ice sheet deglaciation constrained by observations of <lb/>relative sea level and ice extent, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 102, 54-<lb/>84, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.07.018, 2014. <lb/>Leger, T. P. M., Hein, A. S., Bingham, R. G., Martini, <lb/>M. A., Soteres, R. L., Sagredo, E. A., and Martínez, O. <lb/>A.: The glacial geomorphology of the Río Corcovado, Río <lb/>Huemul and Lago Palena / General Vintter valleys, north-<lb/>eastern Patagonia (43°S, 71°W), J. Maps, 16, 651-668, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/17445647.2020.1794990, 2020. <lb/>Leger, T., Clark, C., Huynh, C., Jones, S., Ely, J., Bradley, S., <lb/>Diemont, C., and Hughes, A.: A Greenland-wide empirical re-<lb/>construction of paleo ice-sheet retreat informed by ice extent <lb/>markers: PaleoGrIS version 1.0, Mendeley Data V1 [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.17632/nh57cz4gys.1, 2024. <lb/>Lesnek, A. J. and Briner, J. P.: Response of a land-terminating <lb/>sector of the western Greenland Ice Sheet to early Holocene <lb/>climate change: Evidence from 10 Be dating in the Søn-<lb/>dre Isortoq region, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 180, 145-156, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2017.11.028, 2018. <lb/>Levy, L. B., Kelly, M. A., Howley, J. A., and Virginia, R. A.: Age <lb/>of the Ørkendalen moraines, Kangerlussuaq, Greenland: Con-<lb/>straints on the extent of the southwestern margin of the Green-<lb/>land Ice Sheet during the Holocene, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 52, <lb/>1-5, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2012.07.021, 2012. <lb/>Levy, L. B., Kelly, M. A., Lowell, T. V., Hall, B. L., Howley, J. A., <lb/>and Smith, C. A.: Coeval fluctuations of the Greenland ice sheet <lb/>and a local glacier, central East Greenland, during late glacial <lb/>and early Holocene time, Geophys. Res. Lett., 43, 1623-1631, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2015GL067108, 2016. <lb/>Levy, L. B., Larsen, N. K., Davidson, T. A., Strunk, A., Olsen, J., <lb/>and Jeppesen, E.: Contrasting evidence of Holocene ice margin <lb/>retreat, south-western Greenland, J. Quaternary Sci., 32, 604-<lb/>616, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.2957, 2017. <lb/>Levy, L. B., Kelly, M. A., Applegate, P. A., Howley, J. A., and Vir-<lb/>ginia, R. A.: Middle to late Holocene chronology of the western <lb/>margin of the Greenland Ice Sheet: A comparison with Holocene <lb/>temperature and precipitation records, Arct. Antarct. Alp. Res., <lb/>50, https://doi.org/10.1080/15230430.2017.1414477, 2018. <lb/>Levy, L. B., Larsen, N. K., Knudsen, M. F., Egholm, D. L., Bjørk, <lb/>A. A., Kjeldsen, K. K., Kelly, M. A., Howley, J. A., Olsen, J., <lb/>Tikhomirov, D., Zimmerman, S. R. H., and Kjaer, K. H.: Multi-<lb/>phased deglaciation of south and southeast Greenland controlled <lb/>by climate and topographic setting, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 242, <lb/>106454, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106454, 2020. <lb/>Lifton, N., Sato, T., and Dunai, T. J.: Scaling in situ cosmogenic nu-<lb/>clide production rates using analytical approximations to atmo-<lb/>spheric cosmic-ray fluxes, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 386, 149-160, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2013.10.052, 2014. <lb/>Lloyd, J. M., Park, L. A., Kuijpers, A., and Moros, M.: Early <lb/>Holocene palaeoceanography and deglacial chronology of Disko <lb/>Bugt, West Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 24, 1741-1755, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2004.07.024, 2005. <lb/>Lloyd, J. M., Ribeiro, S., Weckström, K., Callard, L., Ó Cofaigh, <lb/>C., Leng, M. J., Gulliver, P., and Roberts, D. H.: Ice-ocean <lb/>interactions at the Northeast Greenland Ice stream (NEGIS) <lb/>over the past 11,000 years, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 308, 108068, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2023.108068, 2023. <lb/>Long, A. J. and Roberts, D. H.: A revised chronology for the &quot;Fjord <lb/>Stade&quot; moraine in Disko Bugt, west Greenland, J. Quaternary <lb/>Sci., 17, 561-579, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.705, 2002. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>752 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Long, A. J. and Roberts, D. H.: Late Weichselian deglacial <lb/>history of Disko Bugt, West Greenland, and the dynamics <lb/>of the Jakobshavns Isbrae ice stream, Boreas, 32, 208-226, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.2003.tb01438.x, 2003. <lb/>Long, A. J., Roberts, D. H., and Wright, M. R.: Isolation <lb/>basin stratigraphy and Holocene relative sea-level change on <lb/>Arveprinsen Ejland, Disko Bugt, West Greenland, J. Qua-<lb/>ternary Sci., 14, 323-345, https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099-<lb/>1417(199907)14:4&lt;323::AID-JQS442&gt;3.0.CO;2-0, 1999. <lb/>Long, A. J., Roberts, D. H., and Rasch, M.: New observations <lb/>on the relative sea level and deglacial history of Greenland <lb/>from Innaarsuit, Disko Bugt, Quaternary Res., 60, 162-171, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0033-5894(03)00085-1, 2003. <lb/>Long, A. J., Roberts, D. H., and Dawson, S.: Early <lb/>Holocene history of the west Greenland Ice Sheet and <lb/>the GH-8.2 event, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 25, 904-922, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2005.07.002, 2006. <lb/>Long, A. J., Roberts, D. H., Simpson, M. J. R., Daw-<lb/>son, S., Milne, G. A., and Huybrechts, P.: Late Weich-<lb/>selian relative sea-level changes and ice sheet history in <lb/>southeast Greenland, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 272, 8-18, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2008.03.042, 2008. <lb/>Long, A. J., Woodroffe, S. A., Roberts, D. H., and Dawson, S.: <lb/>Isolation basins, sea-level changes and the Holocene history of <lb/>the Greenland Ice Sheet, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 30, 3748-3768, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2011.10.013, 2011. <lb/>Lowell, T. V., Kelly, M. A., Howley, J. A., Fisher, T. G., Barnett, P. <lb/>J., Schwartz, R., Zimmerman, S. R. H., Norris, N., and Malone, <lb/>A. G. O.: Near-constant retreat rate of a terrestrial margin of the <lb/>Laurentide Ice Sheet during the last deglaciation, Geology, 49, <lb/>1511-1515, https://doi.org/10.1130/G49081.1, 2021. <lb/>Manley, W. F. and Jennings, A. E.: Radiocarbon Date List VIII: <lb/>Eastern Canadian Arctic, East Greenland Shelf and Antarctica, <lb/>Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research. Occasional Paper, 50, <lb/>1996. <lb/>Marienfeld, P.: Faziesvariationen glazialmariner Sedimente im <lb/>Scoresby-Sund, Ost-Grönland, Zentralblatt für Geol. und Paläon-<lb/>tologie, 1, 1739-1749, 1990. <lb/>McCarthy, D. J.: Late Quaternary ice-ocean interactions in central <lb/>West Greenland, Durham University, Durham, 292 pp., https:// <lb/>etheses.dur.ac.uk/868/ (last access: 20 March 2024), 2011. <lb/>Mejdahl, V. and Funder, S.: Luminescence dating of Late Qua-<lb/>ternary sediments from East Greenland, Boreas, 23, 525-535, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.1994.tb00620.x, 1994. <lb/>Meredith, M., Sommerkorn, M., Cassotta, S., Derksen, C., Ekaykin, <lb/>A., Hollowed, A., Kofinas, G., Mackintosh, A., Melbourne-<lb/>Thomas, J., Muelbert, M. M. C., Ottersen, G., Pritchard, H., and <lb/>Schuur, E. A. G.: Polar regions, Chapt. 3, IPCC Special Report <lb/>on the Ocean and Cryosphere in a Changing Climate, 203-320, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Mienert, J., Andrews, J. T., and Milliman, J. D.: The East Greenland <lb/>continental margin (65°N) since the last degiaciation: Changes <lb/>in seafloor properties and ocean circulation, Mar. Geol., 106, <lb/>217-238, 1992. <lb/>Möller, P., Larsen, N. K., Kjaer, K. H., Funder, S., Schomacker, <lb/>A., Linge, H., and Fabel, D.: Early to middle Holocene valley <lb/>glaciations on northernmost Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., <lb/>29, 3379-3398, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2010.06.044, <lb/>2010. <lb/>Morlighem, M., Williams, C. N., Rignot, E., An, L., Arndt, J. E., <lb/>Bamber, J. L., Catania, G., Chauché, N., Dowdeswell, J. A., <lb/>Dorschel, B., Fenty, I., Hogan, K., Howat, I., Hubbard, A., Jakob-<lb/>sson, M., Jordan, T. M., Kjeldsen, K. K., Millan, R., Mayer, L., <lb/>Mouginot, J., Noël, B. P. Y., O&apos;Cofaigh, C., Palmer, S., Rys-<lb/>gaard, S., Seroussi, H., Siegert, M. J., Slabon, P., Straneo, F., van <lb/>den Broeke, M. R., Weinrebe, W., Wood, M., and Zinglersen, <lb/>K. B.: BedMachine v3: Complete Bed Topography and Ocean <lb/>Bathymetry Mapping of Greenland From Multibeam Echo <lb/>Sounding Combined With Mass Conservation, Geophys. Res. <lb/>Lett., 44, 11051-11061, https://doi.org/10.1002/2017GL074954, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Nelson, A. H., Bierman, P. R., Shakun, J. D., and Rood, D. H.: <lb/>Using in situ cosmogenic 10 Be to identify the source of sedi-<lb/>ment leaving Greenland, Earth Surf. Proc. Land., 39, 1087-1100, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.3565, 2014. <lb/>Newton, A. M. W., Knutz, P. C., Huuse, M., Gannon, P., <lb/>Brocklehurst, S. H., Clausen, O. R., and Gong, Y.: Ice <lb/>stream reorganization and glacial retreat on the north-<lb/>west Greenland shelf, Geophys. Res. Lett., 44, 7826-7835, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2017GL073690, 2017. <lb/>Nichols, R.: Geomorphology of Inglefield Land, North Greenland, <lb/>Meddelelser om Grønl., C. A. Reitzel, 1, 109, ISSN 0025-6676, <lb/>1969. <lb/>Niwano, M., Box, J. E., Wehrlé, A., Vandecrux, B., Colgan, W. T., <lb/>and Cappelen, J.: Rainfall on the Greenland Ice Sheet: Present-<lb/>Day Climatology From a High-Resolution Non-Hydrostatic <lb/>Polar Regional Climate Model, Geophys. Res. Lett., 48, <lb/>e2021GL092942, https://doi.org/10.1029/2021GL092942, 2021. <lb/>Nørgaard-Pedersen, N., Spielhagen, R. F., Erlenkeuser, H., Grootes, <lb/>P. M., Heinemeier, J., and Knies, J.: Arctic Ocean during the Last <lb/>Glacial Maximum: Atlantic and polar domains of surface wa-<lb/>ter mass distribution and ice cover, Paleoceanography, 18, 1-19, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2002PA000781, 2003. <lb/>Nørgaard-Pedersen, N., Mikkelsen, N., and Kristoffersen, Y.: Late <lb/>glacial and Holocene marine records from the Independence <lb/>Fjord and Wandel Sea regions, North Greenland, Polar Res., <lb/>27, 209-221, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1751-8369.2008.00065.x, <lb/>2008. <lb/>Norris, S. L., Tarasov, L., Monteath, A. J., Gosse, J. C., Hidy, A. <lb/>J., Margold, M., and Froese, D. G.: Rapid retreat of the south-<lb/>western Laurentide Ice Sheet during the Bølling-Allerød interval, <lb/>Geology, 50, 417-421, https://doi.org/10.1130/G49493.1, 2022. <lb/>Ó Cofaigh, C., Dowdeswell, J. A., Evans, J., Kenyon, N. H., <lb/>Taylor, J., Mienert, J., and Wilken, M.: Timing and signifi-<lb/>cance of glacially influenced mass-wasting in the submarine <lb/>channels of the Greenland Basin, Mar. Geol., 207, 39-54, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.margeo.2004.02.009, 2004. <lb/>Ó Cofaigh, C., Dowdeswell, J. A., Jennings, A. E., Hogan, K. <lb/>A., Kilfeather, A., Hiemstra, J. F., Noormets, R., Evans, J., <lb/>McCarthy, D. J., Andrews, J. T., Lloyd, J. M., and Moros, <lb/>M.: An extensive and dynamic ice sheet on the west green-<lb/>land shelf during the last glacial cycle, Geology, 41, 219-222, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1130/G33759.1, 2013. <lb/>Osman, M. B., Tierney, J. E., Zhu, J., Tardif, R., Hakim, G. J., <lb/>King, J., and Poulsen, C. J.: Globally resolved surface temper-<lb/>atures since the Last Glacial Maximum, Nature, 599, 239-244, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03984-4, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>753 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Otosaka, I. N., Shepherd, A., Ivins, E. R., Schlegel, N.-J., Amory, <lb/>C., van den Broeke, M. R., Horwath, M., Joughin, I., King, M. D., <lb/>Krinner, G., Nowicki, S., Payne, A. J., Rignot, E., Scambos, T., <lb/>Simon, K. M., Smith, B. E., Sørensen, L. S., Velicogna, I., White-<lb/>house, P. L., A, G., Agosta, C., Ahlstrøm, A. P., Blazquez, A., <lb/>Colgan, W., Engdahl, M. E., Fettweis, X., Forsberg, R., Gallée, <lb/>H., Gardner, A., Gilbert, L., Gourmelen, N., Groh, A., Gunter, B. <lb/>C., Harig, C., Helm, V., Khan, S. A., Kittel, C., Konrad, H., Lan-<lb/>gen, P. L., Lecavalier, B. S., Liang, C.-C., Loomis, B. D., McMil-<lb/>lan, M., Melini, D., Mernild, S. H., Mottram, R., Mouginot, J., <lb/>Nilsson, J., Noël, B., Pattle, M. E., Peltier, W. R., Pie, N., Roca, <lb/>M., Sasgen, I., Save, H. V., Seo, K.-W., Scheuchl, B., Schrama, <lb/>E. J. O., Schröder, L., Simonsen, S. B., Slater, T., Spada, G., Sut-<lb/>terley, T. C., Vishwakarma, B. D., van Wessem, J. M., Wiese, D., <lb/>van der Wal, W., and Wouters, B.: Mass balance of the Green-<lb/>land and Antarctic ice sheets from 1992 to 2020, Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. Data, 15, 1597-1616, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-1597-<lb/>2023, 2023. <lb/>Pados-Dibattista, T., Pearce, C., Detlef, H., Bendtsen, J., <lb/>and Seidenkrantz, M.-S.: Holocene palaeoceanography of <lb/>the Northeast Greenland shelf, Clim. Past, 18, 103-127, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Patton, H., Hubbard, A., Andreassen, K., Auriac, A., White-<lb/>house, P. L., Stroeven, A. P., Shackleton, C., Winsborrow, M., <lb/>Heyman, J., and Hall, A. M.: Deglaciation of the Eurasian <lb/>ice sheet complex, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 169, 148-172, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2017.05.019, 2017. <lb/>Pearce, C., Özdemir, K. S., Forchhammer Mathiasen, R., <lb/>Detlef, H., and Olsen, J.: The marine reservoir age of <lb/>Greenland coastal waters, Geochronology, 5, 451-465, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/gchron-5-451-2023, 2023. <lb/>Pearce, D. M., Mair, D. W. F., Rea, B. R., Lea, J. M., <lb/>Schofield, J. E., Kamenos, N., and Schoenrock, K.: The <lb/>glacial geomorphology of upper Godthåbsfjord (Nuup <lb/>Kangerlua) in southwest Greenland, J. Maps, 14, 45-55, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/17445647.2017.1422447, 2018. <lb/>Pedersen, M., Weng, W. L., Keulen, N., and Kokfelt, T. F.: <lb/>A new seamless digital 1:500 000 scale geological map of <lb/>Greenland, Geol. Surv. Denmark Greenl. Bull., 28, 65-68, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/geusb.v28.4727, 2013. <lb/>Perner, K., Moros, M., Snowball, I., Lloyd, J. M., Kuijpers, A., <lb/>and Richter, T.: Establishment of modern circulation pattern <lb/>at c. 6000 cal a BP in Disko Bugt, central West Greenland: <lb/>opening of the Vaigat Strait, J. Quaternary Sci., 28, 480-489, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.2638, 2013. <lb/>Philipps, W., Briner, J. P., Bennike, O., Schweinsberg, A., Beel, <lb/>C., and Lifton, N.: Earliest Holocene deglaciation of the central <lb/>Uummannaq Fjord system, West Greenland, Boreas, 47, 311-<lb/>325, https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12270, 2017. <lb/>Pittard, M. L., Whitehouse, P. L., Bentley, M. J., and Small, D.: <lb/>An ensemble of Antarctic deglacial simulations constrained by <lb/>geological observations, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 298, 107800, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2022.107800, 2022. <lb/>Porter, C., Morin, C., Howat, P., Noh, I., Bates, M.-J., Pe-<lb/>terman, B., Keesey, K., Schlenk, S., Gardiner, M., and <lb/>Tomko, J.: ArcticDEM, Harvard dataverse [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/C98DVS, 2018. <lb/>Puleo, P. J. K., Masterson, A. L., Medeiros, A. S., Schellinger, <lb/>G., Steigleder, R., Woodroffe, S., Osburn, M. R., and Axford, <lb/>Y.: Younger Dryas and early Holocene climate in south Green-<lb/>land inferred from oxygen isotopes of chironomids, aquatic <lb/>Moss, and Moss cellulose, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 296, 107810, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2022.107810, 2022. <lb/>Rasmussen, T. L., Pearce, C., Andresen, K. J., Nielsen, T., and <lb/>Seidenkrantz, M. S.: Northeast Greenland ice-free shelf edge at <lb/>79.4°N around the Last Glacial Maximum 25.5-17.5 ka, Boreas, <lb/>51, 759-775, https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12593, 2022. <lb/>Reimer, P. J. and Reimer, R. W.: A marine reservoir correc-<lb/>tion database and on-line interface, Radiocarbon, 43, 461-463, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200038339, 2001. <lb/>Reimer, P. J., Austin, W. E. N., Bard, E., Bayliss, A., Blackwell, <lb/>P. G., Bronk Ramsey, C., Butzin, M., Cheng, H., Edwards, R. <lb/>L., Friedrich, M., Grootes, P. M., Guilderson, T. P., Hajdas, I., <lb/>Heaton, T. J., Hogg, A. G., Hughen, K. A., Kromer, B., Manning, <lb/>S. W., Muscheler, R., Palmer, J. G., Pearson, C., Van Der Plicht, <lb/>J., Reimer, R. W., Richards, D. A., Scott, E. M., Southon, J. R., <lb/>Turney, C. S. M., Wacker, L., Adolphi, F., Büntgen, U., Capano, <lb/>M., Fahrni, S. M., Fogtmann-Schulz, A., Friedrich, R., Köhler, <lb/>P., Kudsk, S., Miyake, F., Olsen, J., Reinig, F., Sakamoto, M., <lb/>Sookdeo, A., and Talamo, S.: The IntCal20 Northern Hemisphere <lb/>Radiocarbon Age Calibration Curve (0-55 cal kBP), Radiocar-<lb/>bon, 62, 725-757, https://doi.org/10.1017/RDC.2020.41, 2020. <lb/>Reusche, M. M., Marcott, S. A., Ceperley, E. G., Barth, <lb/>A. M., Brook, E. J., Mix, A. C., and Caffee, M. W.: <lb/>Early to Late Holocene Surface Exposure Ages From <lb/>Two Marine-Terminating Outlet Glaciers in North-<lb/>west Greenland, Geophys. Res. Lett., 45, 7028-7039, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GL078266, 2018. <lb/>Rignot, E. and Mouginot, J.: Ice flow in Greenland for the Interna-<lb/>tional Polar Year 2008-2009, Geophys. Res. Lett., 39, L11501, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2012GL051634, 2012. <lb/>Rinterknecht, V., Gorokhovich, Y., Schaefer, J., and Caffee, M.: Pre-<lb/>liminary 10 Be chronology for the last deglaciation of the western <lb/>margin of the Greenland Ice Sheet, J. Quaternary Sci., 24, 270-<lb/>278, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.1226, 2009. <lb/>Rinterknecht, V., Jomelli, V., Brunstein, D., Favier, V., Masson-<lb/>Delmotte, V., Bourlès, D., Leanni, L., and Schläppy, R.: Unstable <lb/>ice stream in Greenland during the Younger Dryas cold event, <lb/>Geology, 42, 759-762, https://doi.org/10.1130/G35929.1, 2014. <lb/>Roberts, D. H., Long, A. J., Schnabel, C., Freeman, S., <lb/>and Simpson, M. J. R.: The deglacial history of south-<lb/>east sector of the Greenland Ice Sheet during the Last <lb/>Glacial Maximum, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 27, 1505-1516, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2008.04.008, 2008. <lb/>Roberts, D. H., Long, A. J., Schnabel, C., Davies, B. J., Xu, <lb/>S., Simpson, M. J. R., and Huybrechts, P.: Ice sheet extent <lb/>and early deglacial history of the southwestern sector of the <lb/>Greenland Ice Sheet, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 28, 2760-2773, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2009.07.002, 2009. <lb/>Roberts, D. H., Rea, B. R., Lane, T. P., Schnabel, C., and <lb/>Rodés, A.: New constraints on Greenland ice sheet dynam-<lb/>ics during the last glacial cycle: Evidence from the Uumman-<lb/>naq ice stream system, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 118, 519-541, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/jgrf.20032, 2013. <lb/>Rogozhina, I., Martinec, Z., Hagedoorn, J. M., Thomas, <lb/>M., and Fleming, K.: On the long-term memory of the <lb/>Greenland ice sheet, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 116, 1-16, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2010JF001787, 2011. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>754 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Rootes, C. M. and Clark, C. D.: Glacial trimlines to identify for-<lb/>mer ice margins and subglacial thermal boundaries: A review and <lb/>classification scheme for trimline expression, Earth-Sci. Rev., <lb/>210, 103355, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103355, <lb/>2020. <lb/>Sbarra, C. M., Briner, J. P., Graham, B. L., Poinar, K., Thomas, <lb/>E. K., and Young, N. E.: Evidence for a more exten-<lb/>sive Greenland Ice Sheet in southwestern Greenland dur-<lb/>ing the Last Glacial Maximum, Geosphere, 18, 1316-1329, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1130/GES02432.1, 2022. <lb/>Seidenkrantz, M.-S., Kuijpers, A., Olsen, J., Pearce, C., Lind-<lb/>blom, S., Ploug, J., Przybyło, P., and Snowball, I.: South-<lb/>west Greenland shelf glaciation during MIS 4 more extensive <lb/>than during the Last Glacial Maximum, Sci. Rep., 9, 15617, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-51983-3, 2019. <lb/>Shotton, F. W., Williams, R. E. G., and Johnson, A. S.: Birmingham <lb/>University Radiocarbon Dates VIII, Radiocarbon, 16, 285-303, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200059610, 1974. <lb/>Simonarson, L. A.: Upper Pleistocene and Holocene marine de-<lb/>posits and faunas on the north coast of Nûgssuaq, West <lb/>Greenland, GRØNLANDS Geol. UNDERSØGELSE, 140, 129, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/bullggu.v140.6682, 1981. <lb/>Simpson, M. J. R., Milne, G. A., Huybrechts, P., and Long, A. J.: <lb/>Calibrating a glaciological model of the Greenland ice sheet from <lb/>the Last Glacial Maximum to present-day using observa-<lb/>tions of relative sea level and ice extent, Quaternary Sci. Rev., <lb/>28, 1631-1657, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2009.03.004, <lb/>2009. <lb/>Sinclair, G., Carlson, A. E., Mix, A. C., Lecavalier, B. <lb/>S., Milne, G., Mathias, A., Buizert, C., and DeConto, <lb/>R.: Diachronous retreat of the Greenland ice sheet during <lb/>the last deglaciation, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 145, 243-258, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2016.05.040, 2016. <lb/>Skov, D. S., Andersen, J. L., Olsen, J., Jacobsen, B. H., Knudsen, M. <lb/>F., Jansen, J. D., Larsen, N. K., and Egholm, D. L.: Constraints <lb/>from cosmogenic nuclides on the glaciation and erosion history <lb/>of Dove Bugt, northeast Greenland, Bull. Geol. Soc. Am., 132, <lb/>2282-2294, https://doi.org/10.1130/b35410.1, 2020. <lb/>Small, D., Clark, C. D., Chiverrell, R. C., Smedley, R. K., Bateman, <lb/>M. D., Duller, G. A. T., Ely, J. C., Fabel, D., Medialdea, A., and <lb/>Moreton, S. G.: Devising quality assurance procedures for as-<lb/>sessment of legacy geochronological data relating to deglaciation <lb/>of the last British-Irish Ice Sheet, Earth-Sci. Rev., 164, 232-250, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2016.11.007, 1 January 2017. <lb/>Smith, L. M. and Licht, K. J.: Radiocarbon Date List IX: Antarctica, <lb/>Arctic Ocean and the Northern North Atlantic, INSTAAR Occas. <lb/>Pap., 54, 1-138, 2000. <lb/>Søndergaard, A. S., Larsen, N. K., Olsen, J., Strunk, A., and <lb/>Woodroffe, S.: Glacial history of the Greenland Ice Sheet and <lb/>a local ice cap in Qaanaaq, northwest Greenland, J. Quaternary <lb/>Sci., 34, 536-547, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.3139, 2019. <lb/>Søndergaard, A. S., Larsen, N. K., Steinemann, O., Olsen, J., <lb/>Funder, S., Egholm, D. L., and Kjaer, K. H.: Glacial history <lb/>of Inglefield Land, north Greenland from combined in situ <lb/>10Be and 14C exposure dating, Clim. Past, 16, 1999-2015, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-16-1999-2020, 2020. <lb/>Sparrenbom, C. J., Bennike, O., Björck, S., and Lambeck, <lb/>K.: Holocene relative sea-level changes in the Qaqor-<lb/>toq area, southern Greenland, Boreas, 35, 171-187, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.2006.tb01148.x, 2006. <lb/>Storms, J. E. A., de Winter, I. L., Overeem, I., Drijkonin-<lb/>gen, G. G., and Lykke-Andersen, H.: The Holocene <lb/>sedimentary history of the Kangerlussuaq Fjord-valley <lb/>fill, West Greenland, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 35, 29-50, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2011.12.014, 2012. <lb/>Stroeven, A. P., Hättestrand, C., Kleman, J., Heyman, J., Fa-<lb/>bel, D., Fredin, O., Goodfellow, B. W., Harbor, J. M., Jansen, <lb/>J. D., Olsen, L., Caffee, M. W., Fink, D., Lundqvist, J., <lb/>Rosqvist, G. C., Strömberg, B., and Jansson, K. N.: Deglacia-<lb/>tion of Fennoscandia, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 147, 91-121, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2015.09.016, 2016. <lb/>Sugden, D.: Deglaciation and Isostasy in the Sukkertoppen <lb/>Ice Cap Area, West Greenland, Arct. Alp. Res., 4, 97, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2307/1550394, 1972. <lb/>van Tatenhove, F. G. M., van der Meer, J. J. M., and Koster, E. A.: <lb/>Implications for Deglaciation Chronology from New AMS Age <lb/>Determinations in Central West Greenland, Quaternary Res., 45, <lb/>245-253, https://doi.org/10.1006/qres.1996.0025, 1996. <lb/>Tauber, H.: Copenhagen Radiocarbon Dates VII, Radiocarbon, 8, <lb/>213-234, https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200000126, 1966. <lb/>Tauber, H.: Copenhagen Radiocarbon Dates IX, Radiocarbon, 10, <lb/>295-327, https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033822200010912, 1968. <lb/>Ten Brink, N. W. and Weidick, A.: Greenland ice sheet his-<lb/>tory since the last glaciation, Quaternary Res., 4, 429-440, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0033-5894(74)90038-6, 1974. <lb/>The IMBIE Team: Mass balance of the Greenland Ice <lb/>Sheet from 1992 to 2018, Nature, 579, 233-239, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1855-2, 2019. <lb/>Trautman, <lb/>M. <lb/>A.: <lb/>Isotopes, <lb/>Inc. <lb/>Radiocarbon <lb/>Measurements <lb/>III, <lb/>Radiocarbon, <lb/>5, <lb/>62-79, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200036791, 1963. <lb/>Trautman, M. A. and Willis, E. H.: Isotopes, Inc. Ra-<lb/>diocarbon Measurements V, Radiocarbon, 8, 161-203, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033822200000102, 1966. <lb/>Wagner, B. and Melles, M.: Holocene environmental history of <lb/>western Ymer Ø, East Greenland, inferred from lake sediments, <lb/>Quatern. Int., 89, 165-176, https://doi.org/10.1016/S1040-<lb/>6182(01)00087-8, 2002. <lb/>Wagner, B., Melles, M., Hahne, J., Niessen, F., and Hub-<lb/>berten, H.-W.: Holocene climate history of Geographical Soci-<lb/>ety Ø, East Greenland -evidence from lake sediments, Palaeo-<lb/>geogr. Palaeocl., 160, 45-68, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-<lb/>0182(00)00046-8, 2000. <lb/>Washburn, A. L. and Stuiver, M.: Radiocarbon-Dated Postglacial <lb/>Delevelling in Northeast Greenland and Its Implications, Arctic, <lb/>15, 66-73, https://doi.org/10.14430/arctic3558, 1962. <lb/>Weidick, A.: Observations on some Holocene glacier fluctuations <lb/>in West Greenland, Bull. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 73, 1-<lb/>202, https://doi.org/10.34194/bullggu.v73.6611, 1968. <lb/>Weidick, A.: Short explanation to the Quaternary Map of <lb/>Greenland, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 36, 1-15, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v36.7269, 1971. <lb/>Weidick, A.: Holocene shore-lines and glacial stages in Greenland -<lb/>an attempt at correlation, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, <lb/>41, 1-39, https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v41.7281, 1972. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">T. P. M. Leger et al.: PaleoGrIS version 1.0 <lb/></note>

	<page>755 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Weidick, A.: A Review of Quaternary Investigations in Greenland, <lb/>Institute of Polar Studies, the Ohio State University, 68-71, http: <lb/>//hdl.handle.net/1811/48043, 1975. <lb/>Weidick, A.: C14 dating of survey material carried out in <lb/>1975, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 80, 136-144, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v90.7609, 1976. <lb/>Weidick, A.: C14 dating of Survey material carried out in <lb/>1976, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 85, 127-129, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v85.7545, 1977. <lb/>Weidick, A.: C14 dating of survey material carried out in <lb/>1977, Rapp. Grønlands Geol. Undersøgelse, 90, 119-124, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34194/rapggu.v90.7609, 1978. <lb/>Weidick, A. and Bennike, O.: Quaternary glaciation history and <lb/>glaciology of Jakobshavn Isbrae and the Disko Bugt region, West <lb/>Greenland: a review, Geol. Surv. Denmark Greenl. Bull., 14, 1-<lb/>78, https://doi.org/10.34194/geusb.v14.4985, 2007. <lb/>Weidick, A., Oerter, H., Reeh, N., Thomsen, H. H., and Thorn-<lb/>ing, L.: The recession of the Inland Ice margin during <lb/>the Holocene climatic optimum in the Jakobshavn Isfjord <lb/>area of West Greenland, Palaeogeogr. Palaeocl., 82, 389-399, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-0182(12)80010-1, 1990. <lb/>Weidick, A., Andreasen, C., Oerter, H., and Reeh, N.: Neoglacial <lb/>glacier changes around Storstrommen, North-East Greenland, <lb/>Polarforschung, 64, 95-108, 1996. <lb/>Weidick, A., Kelly, M., and Bennike, O.: Late Quaternary devel-<lb/>opment of the southern sector of the Greenland Ice Sheet, with <lb/>particular reference to the Qassimiut lobe, Boreas, 33, 284-299, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1502-3885.2004.tb01242.x, 2004. <lb/>Weiser, J., Titschack, J., and Hebbeln, D.: The deglaciation of <lb/>Upernavik trough, West Greenland, and its Holocene sedi-<lb/>ment infill: processes and provenance, Boreas, 52, 314-340, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/bor.12626, 2023. <lb/>Willemse, N.: Arctic Natural Archives, Ned. Geogr. Stud., 272, 181 <lb/>pp., 2000. <lb/>Williams, K. M.: Ice Sheet and Ocean Interactions, <lb/>Margin of the East Greenland Ice Sheet (14 Ka to <lb/>Present): Diatom Evidence, Paleoceanography, 8, 69-83, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/92PA02591, 1993. <lb/>Williams, K. M., Andrews, J. T., Weiner, N. J., and Mudie, P. J.: <lb/>Late Quaternary Paleoceanography of the Mid-to Outer Con-<lb/>tinental Shelf, East Greenland, Arct. Alp. Res., 27, 352-363, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2307/1552028, 1995. <lb/>Winkelmann, R., Martin, M. A., Haseloff, M., Albrecht, T., Bueler, <lb/>E., Khroulev, C., and Levermann, A.: The Potsdam Parallel <lb/>Ice Sheet Model (PISM-PIK) -Part 1: Model description, The <lb/>Cryosphere, 5, 715-726, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-5-715-2011, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Winsor, K., Carlson, A. E., and Rood, D. H.: 10 Be dating <lb/>of the Narsarsuaq moraine in southernmost Greenland: Ev-<lb/>idence for a late-Holocene ice advance exceeding the Lit-<lb/>tle Ice Age maximum, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 98, 135-143, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2014.04.026, 2014. <lb/>Winsor, K., Carlson, A. E., Caffee, M. W., and Rood, D. H.: Rapid <lb/>last-deglacial thinning and retreat of the marine-terminating <lb/>southwestern Greenland ice sheet, Earth Planet. Sc. Lett., 426, <lb/>1-12, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2015.05.040, 2015. <lb/>Yang, H., Krebs-Kanzow, U., Kleiner, T., Sidorenko, D., Rode-<lb/>hacke, C. B., Shi, X., Gierz, P., Niu, L., Gowan, E. J., Hinck, S., <lb/>Liu, X., Stap, L. B., and Lohmann, G.: Impact of paleoclimate on <lb/>present and future evolution of the Greenland Ice Sheet, PLoS <lb/>One, 17, 1-21, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0259816, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Yang, Q., Dixon, T. H., Myers, P. G., Bonin, J., Cham-<lb/>bers, D., and Van Den Broeke, M. R.: Recent increases in <lb/>Arctic freshwater flux affects Labrador Sea convection and <lb/>Atlantic overturning circulation, Nat. Commun., 7, 10525, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms10525, 2016. <lb/>Young, N. E., Briner, J. P., Axford, Y., Csatho, B., Babo-<lb/>nis, G. S., Rood, D. H., and Finkel, R. C.: Response of a <lb/>marine-terminating Greenland outlet glacier to abrupt cool-<lb/>ing 8200 and 9300 years ago, Geophys. Res. Lett., 38, 1-4, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2011GL049639, 2011a. <lb/>Young, N. E., Briner, J. P., Stewart, H. A. M., Axford, Y., Csatho, B., <lb/>Rood, D. H., and Finkel, R. C.: Response of Jakobshavn Isbrae, <lb/>Greenland, to Holocene climate change, Geology, 39, 131-134, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1130/G31399.1, 2011b. <lb/>Young, N. E., Schaefer, J. M., Briner, J. P., and Goehring, B. M.: <lb/>A 10 Be production-rate calibration for the Arctic, J. Quaternary <lb/>Sci., 28, 515-526, https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.2642, 2013a. <lb/>Young, N. E., Briner, J. P., Rood, D. H., Finkel, R. C., Corbett, <lb/>L. B., and Bierman, P. R.: Age of the Fjord Stade moraines <lb/>in the Disko Bugt region, western Greenland, and the 9.3 <lb/>and 8.2 ka cooling events, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 60, 76-90, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2012.09.028, 2013b. <lb/>Young, N. E., Briner, J. P., Miller, G. H., Lesnek, A. J., Crump, S. <lb/>E., Thomas, E. K., Pendleton, S. L., Cuzzone, J., Lamp, J., Zim-<lb/>merman, S., Caffee, M., and Schaefer, J. M.: Deglaciation of the <lb/>Greenland and Laurentide ice sheets interrupted by glacier ad-<lb/>vance during abrupt coolings, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 229, 106091, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2019.106091, 2020. <lb/>Young, N. E., Lesnek, A. J., Cuzzone, J. K., Briner, J. P., Badgeley, <lb/>J. A., Balter-Kennedy, A., Graham, B. L., Cluett, A., Lamp, J. L., <lb/>Schwartz, R., Tuna, T., Bard, E., Caffee, M. W., Zimmerman, S. <lb/>R. H., and Schaefer, J. M.: In situ cosmogenic 10 Be-14 C-26 Al <lb/>measurements from recently deglaciated bedrock as a new tool <lb/>to decipher changes in Greenland Ice Sheet size, Clim. Past, 17, <lb/>419-450, https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-17-419-2021, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-20-701-2024 <lb/>Clim. Past, 20, 701-755, 2024 </note>


  </text>

</TEI>