<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T14:44:25.400Z">11/21/2025 2:44:25 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T14:44:12.984378Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T14:44:12.984378Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Detection and long-term quantification of methane emissions from <lb/>an active landfill <lb/>Pramod Kumar 1 , Christopher Caldow 1,2 , Grégoire Broquet 1 , Adil Shah 1 , Olivier Laurent 1 , Camille Yver-Kwok 1 , <lb/>Sebastien Ars 3 , Sara Defratyka 1,a,b , Susan Warao Gichuki 1 , Luc Lienhardt 1 , Mathis Lozano 1 , Jean-Daniel Paris 1 , <lb/>Felix Vogel 3 , Caroline Bouchet 4 , Elisa Allegrini 4 , Robert Kelly 4 , Catherine Juery 5 , and Philippe Ciais 1 <lb/>1 Laboratoire des Sciences du Climat et de l&apos;Environnement (LSCE/IPSL), CEA-CNRS-UVSQ, Université Paris-Saclay, <lb/>91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France <lb/>2 Climate Science Centre, CSIRO Oceans and Atmosphere, Aspendale, VIC, 3195, Australia <lb/>3 Climate Research Division, Environment and Climate Change Canada, Toronto M3H 5T4, Ontario, Canada <lb/>4 SUEZ-Smart &amp; Environmental Solutions, Tour CB21/16 place de l&apos;Iris, 92040, La Défense, France <lb/>5 TotalEnergies Laboratoire Qualité de l&apos;Air (LQA), 69360 Solaize CEDEX, France <lb/>a now at: The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, EH89YL, United Kingdom <lb/>b now at: National Physical Laboratories, Teddington, TW110LW, United Kingdom <lb/>Correspondence: Pramod Kumar (pramod.kumar@lsce.ipsl.fr) <lb/>Received: 13 June 2023 -Discussion started: 10 August 2023 <lb/>Revised: 12 December 2023 -Accepted: 26 December 2023 -Published: 22 February 2024 <lb/></front>

		<body>Abstract. Landfills are a significant source of fugitive <lb/>methane (CH 4 ) emissions, which should be precisely and <lb/>regularly monitored to reduce and mitigate net greenhouse <lb/>gas emissions. In this study, we present long-term, in situ, <lb/>near-surface, mobile atmospheric CH 4 mole fraction mea-<lb/>surements (complemented by meteorological measurements <lb/>from a fixed station) from 21 campaigns that cover approx-<lb/>imately 4 years from September 2016 to December 2020. <lb/>These campaigns were utilized to regularly quantify the to-<lb/>tal CH 4 emissions from an active landfill in France. We use <lb/>a simple atmospheric inversion approach based on a Gaus-<lb/>sian plume dispersion model to derive CH 4 emissions. To-<lb/>gether with the measurements near the soil surface, mainly <lb/>dedicated to the identification of sources within the land-<lb/>fill, measurements of CH 4 made on the landfill perimeter <lb/>(near-field) helped us to identify the main emission areas <lb/>and to provide some qualitative insights about the rank of <lb/>their contributions to total emissions from the landfill. The <lb/>two main area sources correspond, respectively, to a covered <lb/>waste sector with infrastructure with sporadic leakages (such <lb/>as wells, tanks, pipes, etc.) and to the last active sector receiv-<lb/>ing waste during most of the measurement campaigns. How-<lb/>ever, we hardly managed to extract a signal representative <lb/>of the overall landfill emissions from the near-field measure-<lb/>ments, which limited our ability to derive robust estimates <lb/>of the emissions when assimilating them in the atmospheric <lb/>inversions. The analysis shows that the inversions based on <lb/>the measurements from a remote road further away from the <lb/>landfill (far-field) yielded reliable estimates of the total emis-<lb/>sions but provided less information on the spatial variabil-<lb/>ity of emissions within the landfill. This demonstrates the <lb/>complementarity between the near-and far-field measure-<lb/>ments. According to these inversions, the total CH 4 emis-<lb/>sions have a large temporal variability and range from ∼ 0.4 <lb/>to ∼ 7 t CH 4 d -1 , with an average value of ∼ 2.1 t CH 4 d -1 . <lb/>We find a weak negative correlation between these estimates <lb/>of the CH 4 emissions and atmospheric pressure for the active <lb/>landfill. However, this weak emission-pressure relationship <lb/>is based on a relatively small sample of reliable emission es-<lb/>timates with large sampling gaps. More frequent robust es-<lb/>timations are required to better understand this relationship <lb/>for an active landfill. <lb/>1 Introduction <lb/>Methane (CH 4 ) is Earth&apos;s second most important anthro-<lb/>pogenic greenhouse gas after carbon dioxide (Hartmann et <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></body>

		<page>1230 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>al., 2013; Kirschke et al., 2013) and has a much larger <lb/>global warming potential (Etminan et al., 2016). CH 4 emis-<lb/>sions are increasing (Jackson et al., 2020), resulting in a <lb/>high growth rate of global annual average CH 4 mole frac-<lb/>tions in the atmosphere, reaching up to 1911.88 ± 0.59 parts <lb/>per billion (ppb) for 2022, more than 2.5 times preindus-<lb/>trial levels (Lan et al., 2022; Nisbet et al., 2020), despite <lb/>a temporary pause between 1998 and 2007 (Bousquet et <lb/>al., 2006; Rigby et al., 2008; Turner et al., 2019). Accord-<lb/>ing to the values reported by NOAA, the annual increases <lb/>in 2020 (15.20 ± 0.41 ppb) and 2021 (17.75 ± 0.47 ppb) are <lb/>the greatest observed since the systematic record began in <lb/>1983 (Lan et al., 2022). CH 4 is a short-lived radiative forcer, <lb/>and reducing its emissions will deliver an immediate reduc-<lb/>tion of net global warming. Fossil fuel extraction, agricul-<lb/>ture, and waste management are responsible for over half <lb/>of all CH 4 emissions (Saunois et al., 2016). Reducing these <lb/>anthropogenic emissions, as pledged in Glasgow by more <lb/>than 100 countries (https://www.globalmethanepledge.org/, <lb/>last access: 10 May 2022), is viewed as an effective wedge to <lb/>meet the short-term objectives of the Paris Agreement, even <lb/>though achieving long-term neutrality goals will require re-<lb/>ducing carbon dioxide emissions as well. <lb/>Reducing fugitive emissions from landfills can make a <lb/>valuable contribution to the Glasgow methane pledge (Shin-<lb/>dell et al., 2012; Nisbet et al., 2020; Dreyfus et al., 2022), and <lb/>the European Union (EU) is planning on targets and regula-<lb/>tions for this sector (European Union Methane Action Plan, <lb/>2022). Methane is produced in landfills during the anaer-<lb/>obic microbial decomposition of organic waste (Bingemer <lb/>and Crutzen, 1987). Total waste emissions have increased <lb/>in past decades (Jackson et al., 2020), roughly doubling be-<lb/>tween 1970 and 2010 (Fischedick et al., 2014). Landfills <lb/>and waste constituted ∼ 18 % of total anthropogenic CH 4 <lb/>emissions in the year 2017 (Saunois et al., 2020; Jackson et <lb/>al., 2020). Society&apos;s reliance on landfills to store waste is set <lb/>to increase with population growth and development (Hein et <lb/>al., 1997; Hong et al., 2017; Lando et al., 2017). In the EU, <lb/>anaerobic decomposition in the waste sector is the second <lb/>largest methane source, accounting for ∼ 18 % of total emis-<lb/>sions in the year 2018 (European Environment Agency, 2020, <lb/>p. 73). Waste management is nevertheless regulated in the EU <lb/>(Scheutz et al., 2009; Bourn et al., 2019; Fjelsted et al., 2019; <lb/>Daugėla et al., 2020), and net land waste disposal emissions <lb/>decreased by 46 % between 1990 and 2018 (European En-<lb/>vironment Agency, 2020, p. 794), primarily through divert-<lb/>ing organic waste away from storage in landfills (European <lb/>Commission, 2020). Landfill emission mitigation is gaining <lb/>traction (Mønster et al., 2019; Bogner et al., 2008) by cur-<lb/>tailing organic waste reaching landfills (Shams et al., 2017) <lb/>and by recuperating the methane produced on site as biogas <lb/>(Scheutz et al., 2009; Duan et al., 2021). Although landfill <lb/>biogas can be flared (Tratt et al., 2014), biogas collection and <lb/>use for heat and electricity production is being implemented <lb/>more and more (Bogner et al., 1995; Riddick et al., 2018; <lb/>Themelis and Ulloa, 2007). <lb/>CH 4 flux estimates at the scale of individual sites have <lb/>proven to be indispensable in the establishment of effective <lb/>landfill emission regulation (Bogner and Matthews, 2003; <lb/>Scheutz et al., 2009; Tratt et al., 2014). Bottom-up inven-<lb/>tories of methane emissions can be derived from waste <lb/>quantity, waste composition, and emission factors (Jha et <lb/>al., 2008; Shams et al., 2017). But those inventory estimates <lb/>can be far from accurate as they rely on default emission fac-<lb/>tors that may not be representative of the real conditions on <lb/>site (Krautwurst et al., 2017; Nisbet et al., 2019). Therefore, <lb/>independent measurement-based flux estimates are vital to <lb/>derive relevant values for individual sites and for the develop-<lb/>ment of inventories which could reflect the high diversity of <lb/>site-level management practices, technologies, and environ-<lb/>mental conditions (Cambaliza et al., 2015; Bourn et al., 2019; <lb/>Nisbet et al., 2020). <lb/>Estimating the CH 4 emissions of a landfill site based on <lb/>on-site measurements can be challenging. Landfills are spa-<lb/>tially complex, with heterogeneous sources including point-<lb/>scale and area-scale emission sources that can vary substan-<lb/>tially over time (Rachor et al., 2013; Lando et al., 2017; <lb/>Fjelsted et al., 2019). Depending on the flux quantifica-<lb/>tion strategy, knowledge of the spatial distribution of the <lb/>sources within a site has been shown to be critical for ef-<lb/>fective emission quantification (Zazzeri et al., 2015; Riddick <lb/>et al., 2018; Daugėla et al., 2020). Landfill emissions occur <lb/>from both active (uncovered) and covered cells (Sonderfeld <lb/>et al., 2017), as well as from infrastructure including pipes, <lb/>wells, leachate ponds, and gas recuperation and/or process-<lb/>ing facilities (Bogner et al., 1995; Emran et al., 2017; Allen <lb/>et al., 2019). This surface heterogeneity means that emission <lb/>quantification methods must be adapted to the configuration <lb/>of each site (Bourn et al., 2019; Mønster et al., 2019). For <lb/>example, flux chambers deliver precise surface fluxes of very <lb/>local emissions at the scale of about 1 m 2 (Jha et al., 2008; <lb/>Lando et al., 2017; Fjelsted et al., 2019) but require a suf-<lb/>ficient spatial sampling density for adequate site characteri-<lb/>zation. Manual chamber installation and maintenance can be <lb/>arduous. <lb/>Alternatively, atmospheric inversion techniques can be <lb/>employed to quantify fluxes. The computation of emissions <lb/>from landfills with such techniques often relies on measure-<lb/>ments of the methane mole fractions downwind of the sites <lb/>(Lohila et al., 2007; Allen et al., 2019; Mønster et al., 2019; <lb/>Ars et al., 2017). These measurements can be utilized in mass <lb/>balance modeling, tracer release methods, or inverse atmo-<lb/>spheric dispersion models to quantify landfill methane fluxes <lb/>(Foster-Wittig et al., 2015; Yacovitch et al., 2018; Riddick <lb/>et al., 2018; Sonderfeld et al., 2017; Krautwurst et al., 2017; <lb/>Duan et al., 2022; Ars et al., 2017). This approach can cap-<lb/>ture emissions from a large area of the landfill, from multiple <lb/>areas and/or point sources, or from the entire site (Bourn et <lb/>al., 2019). <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1231 <lb/></page>

		<body>Several platforms can be used to sample the atmospheric <lb/>methane mole fractions within and around a landfill, each <lb/>with advantages and disadvantages. Examples include sta-<lb/>tionary towers (Riddick et al., 2018), satellites (Tu et <lb/>al., 2022; Maasakkers et al., 2022), manned aircraft (Cam-<lb/>baliza et al., 2015; Tratt et al., 2014; Krautwurst et al., 2017; <lb/>Gasbarra et al., 2019), unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) <lb/>(Allen et al., 2019; Bel Hadj Ali et al., 2020), and a mobile <lb/>ground-based laboratory (MGL) performing mobile plume <lb/>transects at ground level (Foster-Wittig et al., 2015; Son-<lb/>derfeld et al., 2017; Ars et al., 2017). Satellites can provide <lb/>broad spatiotemporal coverage and resolutions to monitor in-<lb/>dividual landfill methane emissions; however, they are only <lb/>applicable to strongly emitting landfills with total emissions <lb/>on the order of 1 t CH 4 h -1 due to their detection limit us-<lb/>ing the currently available measurement technology (Tu et <lb/>al., 2022; Maasakkers et al., 2022). Aerial aircraft or UAV <lb/>CH 4 mole fraction measurements, with wind measurements, <lb/>have great potential in monitoring landfill emissions (Gas-<lb/>barra et al., 2019; Allen et al., 2019). However, UAVs and <lb/>aircraft cannot sample for prolonged periods, providing only <lb/>a snapshot of emission fluxes (Mønster et al., 2019). Contin-<lb/>uous atmospheric measurements from stationary, in situ, and <lb/>precise sensors located within or close to a site can provide <lb/>long-term monitoring of emissions with a much lower detec-<lb/>tion limit (Riddick et al., 2018; Kumar et al., 2022). How-<lb/>ever, the deployment of a dense network of sensors is lim-<lb/>ited by cost -more specifically, by the lack of precise and <lb/>reliable low-cost CH 4 sensors (Fox et al., 2019; Mønster et <lb/>al., 2019). The mobile ground-based laboratory (MGL) mea-<lb/>surements can be used for routine sampling of the total emis-<lb/>sions from a landfill throughout its life-cycle. MGLs are typ-<lb/>ically equipped with a satellite positioning module, gas an-<lb/>alyzers, and wind sensors. MGLs can provide transects of <lb/>the plumes from landfills with both high spatial resolution <lb/>and coverage, e.g., by driving on a nearby downwind sam-<lb/>pling road (Scheutz et al., 2011; Zazzeri et al., 2015; Kumar <lb/>et al., 2021, 2022). They can also provide some insight into <lb/>the location of potential emission sources when sampling <lb/>near the source and combining sampled mole fractions with <lb/>wind measurements (Ars et al., 2020). If focusing on a sin-<lb/>gle site and planning campaigns under favorable wind con-<lb/>ditions, they can support routine analysis of a site&apos;s methane <lb/>emissions. However, MGL operation can be labor intensive, <lb/>and sampling can be limited to road infrastructure and favor-<lb/>able winds for adequate downwind positioning. In addition <lb/>to MGL sampling of downwind landfill methane plumes, a <lb/>tracer gas may be released at a known rate near to a tar-<lb/>geted source to estimate methane fluxes by exploiting mole <lb/>fraction ratios between methane and the tracer gas (Czepiel <lb/>et al., 1996; Scheutz et al., 2011; Yver Kwok et al., 2015). <lb/>In this study, we conducted MGL measurements to analyze <lb/>methane emissions from an active landfill. <lb/>This study was aimed at participating in the general ef-<lb/>fort (a) to develop novel, standardized approaches to monitor <lb/>CH 4 emissions from landfills using atmospheric techniques; <lb/>(b) to improve emission factors for landfill CH 4 emission <lb/>inventories; and (c) ultimately, to support a large decrease <lb/>in the methane emissions from the waste sector. This gen-<lb/>eral effort will keep on requiring long series of studies due <lb/>to the large differences between the landfills in terms of to-<lb/>pography, environment, wastes, management practices, etc. <lb/>Some studies tried to cover several landfills with one to a few <lb/>measurement campaigns (e.g., Mønster et al., 2015), demon-<lb/>strating the high variability of the emission factors across the <lb/>sites. However, the emissions from an individual landfill are <lb/>highly variable in time due to the sporadic nature of the fugi-<lb/>tive leaks, due to variations in meteorological drivers, and <lb/>due to the evolution of the landfill in time. A complementary <lb/>assessment of the landfill emissions should thus focus on this <lb/>variability. <lb/>The main objective of this study is thus to analyze methane <lb/>emissions from an active landfill site near Paris, France, <lb/>over a prolonged period of approximately 4 years, be-<lb/>tween September 2016 and December 2020, during which <lb/>it evolved significantly. The studied landfill is an ∼ 0.18 km 2 <lb/>managed landfill site, operated by SUEZ, and it has been in <lb/>operation since 2005. The site is composed of several cells, <lb/>some being covered by membranes, where biogas is recu-<lb/>perated from a network of wells connected to pipes, and <lb/>some being openly exposed to air while being filled with <lb/>waste. In this study, we use a simple inverse atmospheric <lb/>dispersion modeling approach to quantify CH 4 emissions us-<lb/>ing downwind near-surface mobile CH 4 mole fraction mea-<lb/>surements complemented by meteorological measurements <lb/>from a fixed station for 21 MGL campaigns. These MGL <lb/>campaigns were undertaken within the framework of vari-<lb/>ous projects (mainly TRACE but also, initially, wastemiti <lb/>and bridGES) in collaboration with SUEZ (Vogel, 2016; Ars, <lb/>2017; Ars et al., 2017) and were conducted mainly in three <lb/>phases: September to December 2016, August to October <lb/>2017, and July 2018 to December 2020. We regularly quan-<lb/>tify the net methane emissions of the site and their evolu-<lb/>tion over time. We also provide some information on specific <lb/>sources within the site using near-site transects combined <lb/>with complementary on-foot targeted leak detection (hence-<lb/>forth referred to as sniffing) measurements and on emission <lb/>spatial distributions through inversions using near-site tran-<lb/>sects. <lb/>Our analysis of the data for the methane emissions is based <lb/>on a simple Gaussian plume model which is driven by on-<lb/>site meteorological measurements and has been utilized and <lb/>evaluated previously for the inversions of methane emissions <lb/>from controlled-release experiments (Kumar et al., 2022, <lb/>2021). In Sect. 2, we describe the site and our data collec-<lb/>tion. Section 3 presents a first attempt at deriving informa-<lb/>tion on the distribution of the emissions within the landfill <lb/>based on the measurement from the foot sniffing and from <lb/>the MGL transects close to the site. We describe our inver-<lb/>sion approach in Sect. 4, followed by the results and discus-<lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1232 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>sions, respectively, in Sects. 5 and 6 and our conclusions in <lb/>Sect. 7. <lb/>2 Materials and methods <lb/>2.1 Site description <lb/>The studied landfill is located about 35 km southeast of <lb/>Paris (latitude: 48 • 38.434 N, longitude: 2 • 44.381 E; area: <lb/>∼ 0.18 km 2 ; altitude above the sea level: ∼ 100 to 120 m; <lb/>Fig. 1). It is close (about 200-300 m east) to an older closed <lb/>landfill (1974-2004), which has been completely covered <lb/>since 2005. The studied landfill began receiving waste in <lb/>2005, with its last waste having been received in 2022. It has <lb/>an overall waste capacity of ∼ 3.05 Mt. By the end of 2020, it <lb/>had received approximately 97 % of this capacity. The land-<lb/>fill has been divided up into approximately six cells, each <lb/>being progressively filled and compacted before being cov-<lb/>ered with a non-permeable membrane overladen with 0.8 m <lb/>of soil. The site is equipped with a leachate and biogas col-<lb/>lection network to collect and treat biogas and leachate to be <lb/>used on site. Two gas engines are installed on site to generate <lb/>electricity with the landfill gas. The cells of the landfill have <lb/>been filled in a counterclockwise fashion, starting with the <lb/>NE corner and progressing around to the SE corner, where <lb/>waste reception was ongoing during this study (see Fig. S1.1 <lb/>in the Supplement 1). Waste is deposited and compacted dur-<lb/>ing operational hours, which are 07:00 to 15:00 (local time) <lb/>during weekdays. At the end of each day, the active area <lb/>of the landfill is covered with clay or soil in order to mini-<lb/>mize odor and biogas emissions, as well as animal activity <lb/>overnight. <lb/>The topography of the landfill is complex. It may be gener-<lb/>ally described as a hill that rises towards the center and slopes <lb/>away towards the edge. The highest point of the landfill is a <lb/>few tens of meters above the outer edges, with variations in <lb/>time due to the evolution of the landfill. The area surrounding <lb/>the landfill is generally flat as it has been used as cropland. <lb/>The closed landfill exhibits similar topography to the stud-<lb/>ied one with a similar height and a slightly greater extent <lb/>(area ∼ 0.25 km 2 ; Fig. 1). Based on measurement surveys <lb/>conducted previously (Vogel, 2016) and during this study, we <lb/>see that there is no significant CH 4 signal from this closed <lb/>landfill in our measurements targeting the active landfill. <lb/>2.2 Scientific instrumentation <lb/>2.2.1 Mobile ground laboratory and sniffing <lb/>measurement framework <lb/>Atmospheric sampling was performed within and around the <lb/>studied landfill using an MGL. A vehicle was equipped with <lb/>one to three gas analyzers that continuously measured the <lb/>in situ CH 4 mole fraction, the mole fraction of additional <lb/>trace gases (CO 2 , CO, C 2 H 2 , H 2 O), and isotope mole frac-<lb/>tions (δ 13 C in CH 4 and δ 13 C in CO 2 ) depending on the type <lb/>of analyzer (Fig. 2). We utilized a variety of high-precision <lb/>cavity-enhanced absorption spectroscopy gas analyzers: the <lb/>Picarro G2203 (CH 4 , C 2 H 2 , H 2 O), G2401 (CH 4 , CO 2 , CO, <lb/>H 2 O), and G2201-i (CH 4 , CO 2 , δ 13 C in CH 4 , and δ 13 C in <lb/>CO 2 ), which use cavity ring down spectrometry; the ABB <lb/>Ultra-portable Greenhouse Gas Analyzer (ABB-UGGA) and <lb/>Micro-portable Greenhouse Gas Analyzer (ABB-MGGA), <lb/>which use off-axis integrated cavity output spectroscopy; <lb/>and a LI-COR LI-7810 prototype gas analyzer, which uses <lb/>optical-feedback cavity-enhanced absorption spectroscopy <lb/>(see Table 1). The accuracy of all gas analyzers was veri-<lb/>fied in the laboratory using low (1.98 ± 0.11 (1σ ) ppm) and <lb/>high (6.14 ± 0.23 (1σ ) ppm) CH 4 mole fraction calibration <lb/>standards that are traceable to World Meteorological Or-<lb/>ganization (WMO) greenhouse gas scales (WMOX2004A; <lb/>Crotwell et al., 2019). <lb/>The gas analyzers were connected to an air inlet located to-<lb/>wards the front of the MGL roof using 1/4 in. Synflex 1300 <lb/>tubing. Power was supplied by gel lead-acid batteries (12 V, <lb/>150 Ah) with either one battery connected directly to a power <lb/>inverter (12 V/230 V, DC/AC) or two batteries connected in <lb/>series (24 V/230 V, DC/AC). A Global Positioning Satellite <lb/>(GPS) module inside the MGL recorded the sampling posi-<lb/>tion at 1 Hz during the campaigns. All measurements were <lb/>synchronized to UTC. Moreover, the net gas analyzer time <lb/>response (including the delay induced by the sampling line) <lb/>was initially determined on site by providing a short burst <lb/>of breath into the air inlet and then timing the response for <lb/>post-correction of the campaign data set. <lb/>2.2.2 Meteorological measurements <lb/>Reliable meteorological and micrometeorological measure-<lb/>ments are required to support the analysis of the gas <lb/>mole fraction measurements and, in particular, to charac-<lb/>terize atmospheric conditions in the Gaussian plume dis-<lb/>persion model used for the inversion modeling to estimate <lb/>CH 4 emissions from the landfill. For the MGL measure-<lb/>ment campaigns during 2016-2017, a two-dimensional (2-<lb/>D) anemometer meteorological station, measuring 1 min av-<lb/>eraged wind speed and direction, was permanently installed <lb/>at ∼ 10 m height above ground level (a.g.l.) near the bio-<lb/>gas valorization plant (Fig. 1). For the majority of cam-<lb/>paigns between 2018 and 2020, a three-dimensional (3-<lb/>D) sonic anemometer (Gill Instruments WindMaster 3-Axis <lb/>Anemometer) was installed near the center and the high-<lb/>est point of the landfill where nearby obstacles were lim-<lb/>ited. The anemometer was installed on a mast at a height <lb/>of between about 2 to 7 m a.g.l. Data from the 3-D sonic <lb/>anemometer were recorded at 20 Hz using a Raspberry Pi <lb/>3B+ logging computer. For 4 of the 21 campaigns docu-<lb/>mented in this study, wind measurements were not made <lb/>on site, and, therefore, computations relied on wind obser-<lb/>vation data from the nearby Melun meteorological station <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1233 <lb/></page>

		<body>Table 1. <lb/>Summary of all 21 MGL measurement campaigns and corresponding atmospheric conditions, averaged values of the meteorological and turbulence parameters over the <lb/>campaign period (mean horizontal wind speed (U ) and direction (θ ), the Obukhov length (L), surface friction velocity (u <lb/> * ), and standard deviation of wind velocity fluctuations (σ <lb/>u , <lb/>σ <lb/>v , σ <lb/>w ) and Pasquill-Gifford-Turner (PGT) stability classes when the high-frequency measurements from the 3-D sonic were unavailable). <lb/>No. Date <lb/>Primary <lb/>Met <lb/>Number <lb/>U <lb/>θ <lb/>L <lb/>u <lb/> * <lb/>σ <lb/>u <lb/>σ <lb/>v <lb/>σ <lb/>w <lb/>PGT Comments <lb/>(sniffing) <lb/>data <lb/>of <lb/>(m s -1 <lb/>) <lb/>( • <lb/>) <lb/>(m) (m s -1 <lb/>) (m s -1 <lb/>) (m s -1 <lb/>) (m s -1 <lb/>) <lb/>gas analyzer <lb/>source <lb/>transects <lb/>ABCD EF <lb/>1 <lb/>13 September 2016 Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>6 <lb/>-<lb/>5.52 145 <lb/>D <lb/>2 <lb/>17 November 2016 Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>7 <lb/>-<lb/>6.61 246 <lb/>D <lb/>3 <lb/>5 December 2016 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>-<lb/>14 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>96 <lb/>C <lb/>Westside EF roads <lb/>4 <lb/>11 August 2017 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>3.50 345 <lb/>B <lb/>5 <lb/>28 September 2017 Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>10 <lb/>-<lb/>2.17 179 <lb/>B <lb/>6 <lb/>6 October 2017 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>2-D met <lb/>5 <lb/>22 <lb/>5.00 355 <lb/>C <lb/>7 <lb/>26 July 2018 <lb/>ABB-UGGA <lb/>Melun <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>10 <lb/>A <lb/>8 <lb/>27 November 2018 Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>1.85 335 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 January 2019 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>22 <lb/>12 <lb/>3.53 <lb/>2 -1500 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 February 2019 <lb/>ABB-MGGA <lb/>Melun <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>5 <lb/>A <lb/>11 <lb/>10 July 2019 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.65 <lb/>25 <lb/>-9 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>12 <lb/>2 August 2019 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>2.00 338 <lb/>-3 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>13 <lb/>29 August 2019 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 (ABB-MGGA) 3-D sonic <lb/>5 <lb/>-<lb/>2.59 303 <lb/>-17 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.12 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>Includes sniffing data <lb/>14 <lb/>13 September 2019 Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>5 <lb/>11 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>15 <lb/>-7 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>0.89 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>15 <lb/>9 December 2019 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>Melun <lb/>8 <lb/>-<lb/>9.00 345 <lb/>D <lb/>16 <lb/>5 February 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>13 <lb/>20 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>32 <lb/>-94 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>17 <lb/>4 March 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 (ABB-MGGA) 3-D sonic <lb/>18 <lb/>-<lb/>4.96 <lb/>1 <lb/>-205 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>1.11 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>Includes sniffing data <lb/>18 <lb/>4 September 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2401 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>15 <lb/>-<lb/>4.37 <lb/>48 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>1.53 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>19 <lb/>15 October 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2401 <lb/>Melun <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>4.00 <lb/>2 <lb/>C <lb/>20 <lb/>1 December 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2401 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>7 <lb/>12 <lb/>7.40 338 -1297 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>1.46 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>21 <lb/>8 December 2020 <lb/>Picarro-G2203 <lb/>3-D sonic <lb/>6 <lb/>12 <lb/>2.99 351 <lb/>-49 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.32 <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1234 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>Figure 1. Satellite image (source: © Google Earth) of the studied landfill (orange rectangle on the right side of the figure), an older closed <lb/>landfill (white rectangle on the left), and its surrounding area. The red quadrangle, blue rectangles, and blue circle designate the locations <lb/>of the active landfill cell during the period 2018-2020, the leachate ponds, and the biogas valorization plant, respectively. The letters A to F <lb/>designate the ends of the segments of the roads along which the mobile measurements were taken during the field measurements. Most of <lb/>the measurements were taken along the road segments A to B and B to C close to the landfill or along the E to F remote roads, which are <lb/>henceforth referred to as EF (E and F refer to the end-points of any distant sampling road; however, the measurements only from EF remote <lb/>roads south of the landfill were used for inversions). During most of the campaigns, a 3-D sonic anemometer was installed at an elevated <lb/>location near the center of the landfill. <lb/>Figure 2. Example of the mobile instrument configuration as set up <lb/>in a vehicle. Different combinations of instruments were used for <lb/>the different campaigns, as detailed in Table 1. The LICOR™ 7810 <lb/>in the picture was on loan to LSCE and was used in one campaign <lb/>only. <lb/>(48 • 36 37 N, 2 • 40 46 E) operated by Meteo France, which <lb/>is located ∼ 5.5 km SW of the studied landfill. For all cam-<lb/>paigns, we used atmospheric pressure, air temperature, and <lb/>humidity measurements from the Melun station. <lb/>2.3 Measurement strategy <lb/>The monitoring of the CH 4 emissions from the landfill site <lb/>posed two major challenges related to spatiotemporal vari-<lb/>ability: (a) that of the identification of the different methane <lb/>sources on the site, which can either be very localized <lb/>(hotspots) or more diffuse sources, and (b) that of the es-<lb/>timation of their emissions, which can vary over time due <lb/>to changing operational or external parameters, e.g., atmo-<lb/>spheric conditions. In order to tackle these challenges, the <lb/>main strategy for our measurement campaigns was (a) to <lb/>continuously measure CH 4 mole fractions across the atmo-<lb/>spheric plumes downwind of the landfill (obtaining plume <lb/>cross-sections) during MGL surveys of at least 1 h along <lb/>roads close to and distant from the site and (b) to conduct <lb/>some on-foot sniffing within the landfill to identify local <lb/>methane hotspots and to characterize the potential emissions <lb/>sources. The longer-term (seasonal and interannual) tempo-<lb/>ral variability was also addressed by conducting campaigns <lb/>over several years. MGL campaigns were performed on the <lb/>road along the perimeter of the site between points A, B, C, <lb/>and D in Fig. 1 and/or along the EF remote roads, where <lb/>E and F refer to the end-points of any distant sampling <lb/>road. Due to accessibility limitations of suitable EF remote <lb/>roads, the campaigns generally targeted days when winds <lb/>were from the northwest to the northeast to ensure that the <lb/>mobile transects on the EF remote roads south to the land-<lb/>fill lay downwind of the site and would intersect the land-<lb/>fill CH 4 emission plume. The measurements conducted on <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1235 <lb/></page>

		<body>these southern EF remote roads (subsequently referred to as <lb/>EF roads) are primarily used for inversions. When planning <lb/>the campaigns, such suitable meteorological conditions were <lb/>chosen from weather forecasts at least a day in advance. All <lb/>campaigns were carried out between mid-morning and early <lb/>afternoon on weekdays when the site could be accessed. <lb/>2.4 General information on the campaigns <lb/>We conducted a total of 27 MGL campaigns between <lb/>September 2016 and December 2020, with an average period <lb/>of revisit of ∼ 42 d, ranging between 7 and 149 d. However, <lb/>the measurements made during six MGL campaigns are ex-<lb/>cluded from the study because, during these campaigns, the <lb/>GPS MGL position was not recorded, which prevented us <lb/>from conducting robust analysis. Therefore, we conducted <lb/>our analysis for the 21 campaigns listed in Table 1. During <lb/>two of these MGL campaigns (29 August 2019 and 4 March <lb/>2020), we simultaneously conducted additional foot-based <lb/>sniffing measurements at the ground level within and around <lb/>the site for locating specific point or area sources within <lb/>the landfill site. In both sniffing campaigns, a portable ABB <lb/>MGGA was used to measure CH 4 mole fractions, with a <lb/>GPS positioning module, whilst walking around suspected <lb/>hotspots within the landfill. We obtained an average of about <lb/>10 plume cross-sections per campaign. For 11 of these 21 <lb/>MGL campaigns, we have plume cross-sections on EF roads <lb/>which were used in the inverse modeling framework (Sect. 4) <lb/>for the estimation of the total methane emissions from the <lb/>landfill. Sampling was performed along the ABCD road (see <lb/>Fig. 1) in all but one of the 21 MGL campaigns under a vari-<lb/>ety of different wind conditions. This sampling aimed to pro-<lb/>vide insight into the spatial distribution of emissions within <lb/>the landfill, but we also expected that plume cross-sections <lb/>along these roads could support the inversion of the total <lb/>emission from the landfills or from some of its main areas <lb/>of emissions, in particular from its different cells. <lb/>Table 1 summarizes information on the gas analyzers used, <lb/>the number of ABCD and/or EF plume cross-sections con-<lb/>ducted, and the meteorological and/or turbulence parame-<lb/>ters for all the selected 21 campaigns. For each selected <lb/>campaign, Figs. S1.2 to S1.22 show the CH 4 mole frac-<lb/>tion time series, plume cross-sections, and the corresponding <lb/>wind conditions according to on-site meteorological mea-<lb/>surements or local wind conditions in four campaigns from <lb/>the Melun weather station. The wind speed (U ) and wind <lb/>direction (θ ) for each campaign are averaged over each cam-<lb/>paign period. The averaged wind speeds in all of the selected <lb/>campaigns varied from ∼ 1 to ∼ 7 m s -1 (Table 1). During <lb/>two of the 21 campaigns, averaged wind speeds were equal <lb/>or below 1.5 m s -1 . The use of a Gaussian plume model for <lb/>such low wind speed conditions leads to higher uncertainty <lb/>in CH 4 emission estimates (Kumar et al., 2021, 2022). How-<lb/>ever, during these campaigns, we had CH 4 measurements <lb/>along the EF road that appeared to be suitable, and we still <lb/>attempted inversions to estimate the CH 4 emissions from <lb/>the site with these measurements. During several campaigns, <lb/>CH 4 mole fraction measurements were made even when un-<lb/>favorable winds were coming from the east to the southwest <lb/>directions (Table 1). The mobile transects in these campaigns <lb/>were mostly conducted along the ABCD road and/or along a <lb/>westside EF remote road, very near to the landfill. In other <lb/>campaigns, the wind directions ranged between the north-<lb/>west and northeast directions, which enabled us to use MGL <lb/>sampling on both the ABCD and EF roads (Table 1). <lb/>Whenever the high-frequency data from the 3-D sonic <lb/>anemometer were available, the essential turbulence param-<lb/>eters, the Obukhov length (L), surface friction velocity (u * ), <lb/>and standard deviation of wind velocity fluctuations (σ u , σ v , <lb/>σ w ) were computed over each campaign period. All of the <lb/>campaigns were conducted during daytime, and, thus, for the <lb/>campaigns with 3-D sonic data, the negative sign and mag-<lb/>nitude of the Monin-Obukhov stability parameter (1/L) in-<lb/>dicate that the atmospheric stability varied from near-neutral <lb/>to unstable and very unstable conditions. For the remaining <lb/>campaigns, the Pasquill-Gifford-Turner (PGT) atmospheric <lb/>stability classes, characterized based on the wind measure-<lb/>ments (Turner, 1970), varied from neutral (PGT class D) to <lb/>very unstable (PGT class A) conditions. <lb/>The background CH 4 mole fraction outside the plume <lb/>cross-sections conducted along ABCD and EF roads in each <lb/>campaign was taken as the first percentile of the CH 4 mea-<lb/>surements so that the enhancements in CH 4 due to landfill <lb/>emissions could be determined from this background. Mea-<lb/>surements obtained upwind of the landfill, usually between <lb/>points C and D (Fig. 1), confirmed that using the first per-<lb/>centile was appropriate to characterize the background CH 4 <lb/>field, on top of which lies the plumes from the landfill. This <lb/>approach of deriving a background from field measurements <lb/>eliminates any potential offset issues in the gas analyzers, <lb/>thereby reducing instrumental uncertainty. <lb/>Across all the 21 selected campaigns, the maximum CH 4 <lb/>enhancement above the background reached up to ∼ 70 and <lb/>∼ 3.5 ppm for the ABCD and EF roads, respectively. We <lb/>computed averages of the CH 4 mole fraction enhancements <lb/>for segments of these roads from the different mobile tran-<lb/>sects along them. To compute these averages, a road was di-<lb/>vided into equidistant segments with an averaged distance <lb/>interval between the measurement locations. Then, the CH 4 <lb/>mole fractions at each segment point were averaged by us-<lb/>ing the nearest-point CH 4 mole fraction values from differ-<lb/>ent mobile transects. These averaged CH 4 mole fractions are <lb/>shown in Fig. 3 for the EF roads and in Figs. S1.2-S1.22 for <lb/>all the roads. During most of the campaigns when the wind <lb/>was blowing from the direction of northwest to northeast, <lb/>the high CH 4 mole fraction enhancements represented ei-<lb/>ther individual plume cross-sections or averaged CH 4 plumes <lb/>and were observed along the road segments A-B or B-C <lb/>(Figs. S1.2 to S1.22). The averaged CH 4 plumes from differ-<lb/>ent campaigns along the ABCD road systematically showed <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1236 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>multiple CH 4 peaks at nearly the same downwind locations <lb/>during the series of MGL cross-sections. These different CH 4 <lb/>peaks indicate the heterogeneous distribution of CH 4 emis-<lb/>sions within the landfill. The different plume cross-sections <lb/>and corresponding averaged CH 4 plume along the EF road <lb/>show a more unimodal plume distribution in most of the <lb/>campaigns (Fig. 3). Measurements at this distance allow the <lb/>whole landfill to be considered as a single CH 4 emission <lb/>source. <lb/>3 Concentration mapping and leak detection: potential <lb/>point and area sources within the landfill <lb/>A rough knowledge a priori of (or assumptions on) the po-<lb/>sition and extent of the major CH 4 sources within the land-<lb/>fill are needed to set up the inversion configurations or to <lb/>strengthen the results from the inversions: whether the emis-<lb/>sions correspond to a set of point sources or relatively large <lb/>area sources and whether some areas tend to emit more than <lb/>the others as a function of the period when the campaigns are <lb/>conducted. Point and/or area sources within the landfill orig-<lb/>inate from biogas pipes, well heads, damaged membranes, <lb/>the biogas power plant, active and/or covered cells, leachate <lb/>ponds, etc. However, a priori knowledge of the spatial dis-<lb/>tribution of methane emissions within the studied landfill <lb/>was very limited before the sniffing campaigns. In a previous <lb/>study to quantify emissions from the same landfill using mo-<lb/>bile measurements from two campaigns (17 November and <lb/>5 December 2016), Albergel et al. (2017) divided the site into <lb/>five potential emission areas. This definition of potential area <lb/>sources was based on rough information from the landfill op-<lb/>erators and did not account for potential emissions from the <lb/>biogas valorization plant, leachate ponds, or the pipe or well <lb/>network. In this study, we conducted two sniffing campaigns <lb/>by foot and relied on these to identify the principal methane <lb/>hotspots (Sect. 3.1). Furthermore, we performed a detailed <lb/>analysis of the measurements conducted at the borders of the <lb/>landfill along the ABC road from different mobile campaigns <lb/>combined with corresponding wind speeds and directions to <lb/>explore if these could provide some insights about the po-<lb/>tential CH 4 emission sources within the landfill or on their <lb/>spatial representativity. <lb/>3.1 Identification of CH 4 hotspots from the sniffing <lb/>campaigns <lb/>We analyzed measurements from the foot-based sniffing <lb/>campaigns on 29 August 2019 and 4 March 2020 to identify <lb/>the potential methane hotspots and their source origin. It is <lb/>important to recognize that, during these sniffing campaigns, <lb/>CH 4 mole fraction measurements were often obtained very <lb/>close to the source, and, therefore, high mole fraction obser-<lb/>vations do not necessarily correspond to equally large fluxes. <lb/>Figure 4a shows the spatial distribution of CH 4 mole frac-<lb/>tions along the measurement path from the sniffing campaign <lb/>on 29 August 2019. Six locations with high CH 4 peaks, at <lb/>least ∼ 30 m apart from each other, were identified (Fig. 4b). <lb/>These locations were examined with a detailed map of the <lb/>biogas collection pipes, wells, leachate ponds, gas process-<lb/>ing facilities, etc. to identify their source origin. Based on <lb/>this analysis, we found that the two hotspots S1 and S2 are <lb/>near biogas network purges, S4 is located near a biogas net-<lb/>work well, S5 is at the location of a bioreactor tank, and S6 <lb/>is near a leachate bioreactor or biogas purge where landfill <lb/>gas is removed from the landfill cells and also close to a <lb/>major junction of biogas pipes. The hotspot S3 is near to a <lb/>leachate well and also downwind of a biogas network and a <lb/>well. The methane peaks in different mobile plume transects <lb/>on the ABC road during this campaign (Fig. S1.14c) are con-<lb/>sistent with these six hotspots within the landfill. <lb/>The results of the sniffing campaign on 4 March 2020 <lb/>confirmed CH 4 hotspots at similar locations (S1 to S6) to <lb/>those observed on 29 August 2019. Additional measure-<lb/>ments obtained near biogas network wells; a biogas network <lb/>purge (S9) and two along a drainage gutter behind the bio-<lb/>gas power plant (S7 and S8) (Fig. 4c) indicated three more <lb/>hotspots with measured methane mole fractions in the range <lb/>of 60 to 800 ppm. Therefore, we identified a total of nine <lb/>hotspots (S1 to S9) from the analysis of the two sniffing <lb/>campaigns (Fig. 4c). These nine potential methane emission <lb/>point sources were used in the inversion tests to estimate their <lb/>emissions. It is important to note that the rapid ability to iden-<lb/>tify leaks from these sniffing campaigns provides an opportu-<lb/>nity for site operators to easily diagnose methane emissions <lb/>and take actions to reduce them whilst also increasing the <lb/>yield of CH 4 that is captured and available for sale or use on <lb/>site. <lb/>3.2 Directional information on potential CH 4 emission <lb/>sources from the plume cross-sections along the <lb/>ABC road <lb/>Other than the two sniffing campaigns, which offered a snap-<lb/>shot insight into localized emission sources, little informa-<lb/>tion is available about the presence and characteristics of <lb/>emissions within the landfill. To gain more insights, we ana-<lb/>lyzed the plumes collected along the ABC road under various <lb/>wind conditions from different campaigns. A first analysis <lb/>of the ABC measurements from different mobile campaigns <lb/>indicates a similarity of the plume cross-sections along this <lb/>road despite changes in wind direction from one campaign to <lb/>the next (Figs. S1.1-S1.21). It indicates that these measure-<lb/>ments are more representative of both the localized leakages <lb/>from pipes and wells near to these roads than of the emis-<lb/>sions from the greater landfill. Furthermore, we constructed <lb/>bivariate polar plots from all the plume cross-sections along <lb/>the ABC road from the 11 campaigns between July 2018 and <lb/>December 2020, where on-site wind data from the 3-D sonic <lb/>anemometer were available (Table 1; Fig. 5). These bivari-<lb/>ate polar plots can provide useful directional information on <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1237 <lb/></page>

		<body>Figure 3. Enhancement of CH 4 mole fractions above the background in different plume cross-sections along the EF roads during different <lb/>measurement campaigns. The solid black line shows the averaged CH 4 mole fractions computed from the different plume cross-sections in <lb/>each campaign. <lb/>the potential emission sources and may help to identify the <lb/>presence and characteristics of these sources (Carslaw and <lb/>Beevers, 2013). <lb/>The bivariate polar plots from the ABC plume cross-<lb/>sections are constructed in the following way. The ABC road <lb/>is divided into seven segments (Seg-1 to Seg-7), and for each <lb/>segment, CH 4 mole fraction enhancements above the back-<lb/>ground are averaged over the duration of each transect in that <lb/>segment. Wind speed and direction measurements are aver-<lb/>aged over durations starting from 1 min prior to a transect <lb/>in a segment until the end of the transect in that segment. <lb/>The averaged wind speeds, wind directions, and mole frac-<lb/>tion data are partitioned into wind speed and direction bins, <lb/>and the mean CH 4 mole fractions are calculated for each bin. <lb/>The mean CH 4 mole fractions in each wind-speed-direction <lb/>bin are plotted using polar coordinates. We used wind direc-<lb/>tion intervals at 22.5 • and wind speed intervals at 1 m s -1 <lb/>for binning the data in each bivariate polar plot. The mean <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1238 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>Figure 4. (a) Observed CH 4 mole fractions from sniffing on 29 August 2019 within the studied landfill using an ABB MGGA along with a <lb/>GPS module and (b) high CH 4 mole fraction peaks from the sniffing data are assumed to correspond to the main emission hotspots: six of <lb/>them are identified during this campaign (S1 to S6). Panel (c) shows the locations of a total of nine emission hotspots (S1 to S9) identified <lb/>from both the sniffing campaigns on 29 August 2019 and 4 March 2020. The underlying aerial photograph background images are taken <lb/>from Google Earth (© Google Earth). <lb/>CH 4 mole fractions, calculated in wind-speed-direction bins <lb/>with limited data points, such that those with one,two, and <lb/>three points are down-weighted with the weights 0.25, 0.50, <lb/>and 0.75, respectively (Carslaw and Beevers, 2013). <lb/>Figure 5 shows the seven bivariate polar plots in each <lb/>segment (Seg-1 to Seg-7) along the ABC road. These bi-<lb/>variate plots provide different directional information on the <lb/>likely methane emission sources contributing to the methane <lb/>mole fractions in different segments. The polar plot in Seg-<lb/>1 suggests that at least two small sources were present just <lb/>north of this segment (near the biogas power plant), as in-<lb/>dicated by the elevated mean CH 4 mole fractions in the <lb/>bins with northerly winds when wind speeds were moder-<lb/>ate (∼ 4-6 m s -1 ). One of the sniffing campaigns on 4 March <lb/>2020 also identified two hotspots (S7 and S8) in this area <lb/>along a drainage gutter behind the plant (Fig. 4c, Sect. 3.1). <lb/>The polar plots in Seg-2 to Seg-6 indicate multiple emis-<lb/>sion sources within the whole landfill with potentially high <lb/>emitting sources corresponding to Seg-2 and Seg-3 and small <lb/>sources corresponding to Seg-4 to Seg-6. The high CH 4 mole <lb/>fractions in the northerly wind direction bins in Seg-2, 3, <lb/>and 4 are strongly influenced and most probably caused by <lb/>the last, uncovered, active cell of the landfill in the south-<lb/>east corner. The plots in Seg-2 to Seg-6 also indicate some <lb/>local emission sources near the roads, from the high mean <lb/>CH 4 mole fractions in the bins of low wind speeds. High <lb/>CH 4 mole fractions in the northerly wind direction bins in the <lb/>polar plot in Seg-5 indicate potential CH 4 emission sources <lb/>that could correspond to hotspots S4 and S6, identified by the <lb/>sniffing campaigns. The polar plot in Seg-7 has a small num-<lb/>ber of data points and does not indicate any major source <lb/>upwind of the segment. The polar plots in Seg-4 to Seg-6 <lb/>also show some unexpected elevated mean CH 4 mole frac-<lb/>tions in the bins with northeast wind directions and moderate <lb/>wind speeds, which indicates potential emitting sources in <lb/>the northeast, outside the landfill. However, there are only <lb/>agriculture farms in the northeast of these segments of the <lb/>landfill, where we do not expect any major methane sources, <lb/>except only minor methane emissions from using fertilizers <lb/>or manure, which are unlikely to explain such enhanced CH 4 <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1239 <lb/></page>

		<body>Figure 5. Bivariate polar plots of the mean CH 4 mole fraction en-<lb/>hancement above background in seven equidistant segments (Seg-1 <lb/>to Seg-7) obtained from mobile transects during 11 campaigns be-<lb/>tween July 2018 and December 2020 along the ABC road. Each <lb/>polar plot in a segment uses the values of CH 4 mole fractions av-<lb/>eraged over the duration of the part of each mobile transect in that <lb/>segment. Nine red stars (S1 to S9) indicate the key CH 4 hotspots <lb/>identified from two sniffing campaigns. <lb/>mole fractions. The ABC road follows the border of the land-<lb/>fill with localized leakages from pipes and wells near to these <lb/>roads, and half of the road segments (A-B and B-C) are adja-<lb/>cent to a steep ridge in the southeast. Therefore, recirculation <lb/>of the wind flow due to these ridges and the complex landfill <lb/>topography may explain these observations. The transport of <lb/>a plume in a complex flow field along the B-C road, espe-<lb/>cially when the wind is blowing from the direction of north-<lb/>east to southeast, does not follow the observed mean wind <lb/>directions. As the air from northeasterly or easterly wind di-<lb/>rections is deflected against the ridges of the landfill, it is pos-<lb/>sible that high CH 4 mole fractions may be measured along <lb/>the B-C road, even though the air would appear to originate <lb/>from outside the landfill. <lb/>This analysis of the polar bivariate plots substantiates <lb/>the evidence of methane hotspots identified from the sniff-<lb/>ing campaigns (Sect. 3.1). Furthermore, these results ques-<lb/>tion the ability of the ABC measurements, which might be <lb/>strongly impacted by sources located along the roads, to <lb/>spatially represent the emissions from the greater landfill. <lb/>This would hamper the use of these data for inverting land-<lb/>fill emissions. The complex atmospheric transport along the <lb/>ridge also raises large uncertainties in inversions using this <lb/>data with a simple Gaussian model (Sect. 5.1). <lb/>3.3 Definition of potential emission sources within the <lb/>landfill for inversion tests <lb/>The detection of hotspots during the two sniffing campaigns <lb/>within the landfill (Sect. 3.1) and the analysis of the mobile <lb/>Figure 6. The six potential area sources (boxes, A-i, i = 1, . . ., 6) in <lb/>the configuration of the inversion, defined as the biogas valorization <lb/>plant (A-1) and the five cells (A-2 to A-6). Nine red stars (S1 to S9) <lb/>indicate the CH 4 hotspots identified from two sniffing campaigns. <lb/>measurements along the ABC road in different wind condi-<lb/>tions from different campaigns (Sect. 3.2) indicate that land-<lb/>fill methane emissions come from a combination of area and <lb/>point sources. Consequently, we develop several inversion <lb/>configurations, one of which defines the potential sources <lb/>as the nine hotspots identified from the sniffing (Sect. 3.1, <lb/>Fig. 4c), while others correspond to the area sources (Fig. 6). <lb/>The analysis of the CH 4 enhancements measured along the <lb/>ABC road provided only qualitative directional information <lb/>on the area and/or point sources within the landfill (Sect. 3.2). <lb/>However, due to the complex nature of the landfill and <lb/>the spatiotemporal variability of emissions, it is uncertain <lb/>whether we have detected all the hotspots through sniffing, <lb/>and identifying the area sources of emissions with more dis-<lb/>persed emissions is exceedingly challenging. As a conse-<lb/>quence, we have chosen to define a set of large area sources <lb/>with uniformly distributed methane emissions for inversions. <lb/>Thus, we defined six potential emission source regions, i.e., <lb/>six area sources that include the biogas power plant (A-1) <lb/>and the five cells (A-2 to A-6) within the landfill (Fig. 6). <lb/>4 Atmospheric inversion of landfill methane emissions <lb/>We used a simple atmospheric inversion framework to quan-<lb/>tify CH 4 emissions from multiple potential sources within <lb/>the landfill using the MGL measurements. The inversion ex-<lb/>ploits some of the basic theoretical and practical components <lb/>of the approaches described in Kumar et al. (2022, 2021) and <lb/>Ars et al. (2017) and uses the assumption about the character-<lb/>ization of potential CH 4 emissions sources from Sect. 3. We <lb/>used a Gaussian plume dispersion model designed for single <lb/>point sources from Kumar et al. (2021, 2022) for estimat-<lb/>ing emissions from the nine CH 4 hotspots as point sources <lb/>(Sect. 3.2) and adapted the same Gaussian model to simulate <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1240 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>the dispersion from area sources when estimating emissions <lb/>from the six area sources (Sect. 3.3). Details on the Gaus-<lb/>sian plume model equations for a point source dispersion and <lb/>their adaptation to an area source dispersion are provided in <lb/>the Supplement 2 (Sect. S2.1). We describe two different ap-<lb/>proaches to formulate the Gaussian model for an area source <lb/>dispersion: method 1 is a very simple approach that modifies <lb/>the lateral plume spread in relation to the total plume width <lb/>as a sum of the plume spread due to atmospheric turbulence <lb/>and of the additional initial spread due to the source size <lb/>(Sect. S2.1.1a), and method 2 decomposes an area source <lb/>into multiple point sources and superimposes the modeled <lb/>Gaussian plumes from all of these point sources to compute <lb/>the average plume from that area (Sect. S2.1.1b). <lb/>When on-site measurements from a meteorological station <lb/>(3-D sonic anemometer or 2-D) were available, the Gaussian <lb/>model was driven by the averaged wind direction given by <lb/>the meteorological data. When relying on the data from the <lb/>Melun station, the mean wind direction was approximately <lb/>taken as a direction from the center of the landfill to the lo-<lb/>cation of the maximum averaged CH 4 mole fraction (Kumar <lb/>et al., 2021). This wind direction approximation was deemed <lb/>to be more representative of the landfill rather than of the <lb/>Melun wind direction, and we evaluated the effect of this ap-<lb/>proximation on the estimates in Sect. 5.2. In all cases, the <lb/>model is driven by the effective mean wind speed from the <lb/>meteorological data (Sect. S2.1). The dispersion parameters <lb/>in the Gaussian model are defined by the standard deviations <lb/>of the velocity fluctuations (σ v , σ w ) when we have the high-<lb/>frequency 3-D sonic data available, and in other cases (four <lb/>campaigns), they are based on the Briggs dispersion formu-<lb/>las for flat terrain (Briggs, 1973) corresponding to the de-<lb/>fined PGT stability classes. We used the Gaussian model to <lb/>simulate the plume (called the response function) of each po-<lb/>tential CH 4 source separately at the measurement locations, <lb/>with atmospheric conditions observed during the averaging <lb/>periods of ABC and/or EF plume transects and using a uni-<lb/>tary emission rate (1 kg s -1 ). A response function defines a <lb/>linear relationship between the emission rate of a potential <lb/>source and the concentration at a measurement location. <lb/>We used a non-negative least-squares minimization ap-<lb/>proach to formulate the inverse problem for the quantifica-<lb/>tion of unknown emissions of multiple potential emission <lb/>sources. The details of this inversion procedure are pro-<lb/>vided in the Supplement (Sect. S2.2). The principle of the <lb/>inversion process is to minimize the root sum squared mis-<lb/>fits between the averaged observed and modeled mole frac-<lb/>tion enhancements in the plumes from the multiple potential <lb/>sources. These inversions rely on a priori information about <lb/>the potential emission sources (e.g., number, type, location, <lb/>size, and/or shape), the response functions simulated with the <lb/>Gaussian model for each potential emission source, and the <lb/>observation vectors of the measured and modeled plumes. <lb/>We employed two options to define the observation vectors <lb/>in the inversion. The first observation vector (µ pt ) is defined <lb/>as the averaged CH 4 mole fractions at the measurement lo-<lb/>cations along the roads. Since we have to estimate multiple <lb/>sources of methane emissions within the landfill site, follow-<lb/>ing Ars et al. (2017), we discretize the roads into multiple <lb/>segments of equal length, and for each segment, the inte-<lb/>grated areas under the averaged CH 4 mole fractions are used <lb/>to define a different observation vector (µ SI ). This approach <lb/>reduces the tendency of the inversion to over-fit turbulent pat-<lb/>terns within the plume. We divide the plumes into a differ-<lb/>ent number of segments on the ABC and EF roads with 50 <lb/>and 100 m distance intervals, respectively. More information <lb/>about these observation vectors is given in the Supplement <lb/>(Sect. S2.2). <lb/>For both ABC and EF roads, we conducted six inversion <lb/>tests using two types of observation vectors (µ pt and µ SI ) <lb/>for three source configurations. The source configurations in-<lb/>volve nine point sources (hotspots identified from the sniff-<lb/>ing campaigns, as discussed in Sect. 3) and six area sources <lb/>(Sect. 3) modeled by two different area source adaptations of <lb/>the Gaussian model (method 1 and method 2). <lb/>5 Results <lb/>We conducted inversion tests for all of the selected cam-<lb/>paigns when the wind conditions allowed us to obtain plume <lb/>cross-sections on ABC (near-field) and/or EF roads (far-<lb/>field). However, it is challenging to model the plume cross-<lb/>sections along the ABC road using a simple Gaussian plume <lb/>dispersion model and, therefore, to invert the site emissions <lb/>based on the data measured on this road. The dispersion of <lb/>CH 4 from the potential sources to the ABC road is highly <lb/>sensitive to the complex topography of the landfill, which is <lb/>not taken into account in the Gaussian modeling. The vicin-<lb/>ity between this road and the potential sources in the landfill <lb/>makes these measurements also highly sensitive to factors <lb/>such as the a priori information on the location and extent <lb/>of the potential emission sources, while Sect. 3 shows that <lb/>we can hardly provide a precise distribution of the sources <lb/>within the landfill. Finally, Sect. 3.2 highlighted our lack of <lb/>understanding of the spatial representativity of the measure-<lb/>ments along the ABC road. The inversions using data from <lb/>the ABC road are thus likely hampered by large uncertainties <lb/>and need to be analyzed cautiously, but they may provide in-<lb/>sights into the spatial distribution of the emissions. On the <lb/>contrary, the shape of the observed averaged plume along the <lb/>EF roads is almost unimodal in most of the campaigns, and <lb/>the Gaussian model should be more suitable for the model-<lb/>ing of the transport over the distance between the potential <lb/>sources within the landfill and the EF road. Therefore, we <lb/>do not expect the inversions based on the data from the EF <lb/>road to provide better insights into the spatial distribution of <lb/>the emissions compared to the ABC road; however, we ex-<lb/>pect them to provide much more robust estimates of the total <lb/>emissions from the landfill than those based on the data from <lb/>the ABC road. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1241 <lb/></page>

		<body>The campaign of 10 January 2019 is taken as an example <lb/>to illustrate the analysis of the data and the inversions. The <lb/>Gaussian model for this campaign is driven by the measured <lb/>meteorological and turbulence parameters from the on-site 3-<lb/>D sonic anemometer data. Wind directions during this cam-<lb/>paign were mainly from the north which allowed us to get 22 <lb/>and 12 CH 4 plume cross-sections on the ABC and EF roads, <lb/>respectively (Table 1, Fig. S1.10). Furthermore, the abso-<lb/>lute magnitude of the Obukhov length (L) computed from <lb/>the 3-D sonic data is greater than 1000 m (Table 1), which <lb/>suggests neutral atmospheric stability conditions during this <lb/>campaign. The averaged CH 4 mole fraction plume along the <lb/>ABC road shows multiple peaks (Fig. S1.10), whereas the <lb/>averaged plume along the EF road is unimodal (Fig. 3a4). <lb/>Observed enhancements of the averaged CH 4 plumes above <lb/>the background reached up to ∼ 25 and ∼ 1.5 ppm along the <lb/>ABC and EF roads, respectively. <lb/>The division of the observed and modeled plumes over <lb/>sub-segments of ABC and EF roads (to build µ SI ) from the <lb/>10 January 2019 campaign is illustrated in Figs. 7a1 and b1 <lb/>and 8a1 and b1, respectively. Figures 7b1 and 8b1 illustrate <lb/>a comparison of the modeled plumes with method 1 and <lb/>method 2 from each potential area source at the measure-<lb/>ment roads ABC and EF, respectively. For the ABC road, the <lb/>shapes of modeled plumes from two different methods for <lb/>the area sources A-1 to A-3 (which are a little farther from <lb/>the ABC road) are approximately similar. However, notice-<lb/>able differences in the shapes and magnitudes (i.e., horizontal <lb/>spread) can be seen in the modeled plumes from the sources <lb/>A-4 to A-6, which are closer to the measurement road ABC. <lb/>The method-2 plumes are slightly narrower and have a larger <lb/>maximum than those from method 1. Figure 8b1 for the EF <lb/>measurements shows that the behavior of modeled plumes <lb/>from both methods is approximately similar and unimodal. <lb/>Some differences can be noticed in terms of magnitude and <lb/>width, with method-2 plumes being slightly narrower and <lb/>having a larger maximum than method 1 (Fig. 8b1). <lb/>5.1 Emission estimates using ABC road measurements <lb/>Figure 7 illustrates the inverted emissions using measure-<lb/>ments from the ABC road for the campaign of 10 Jan-<lb/>uary 2019. The total estimated CH 4 emissions using µ pt and <lb/>µ SI in the inversion tests with nine hotspots are 22.94 and <lb/>22.82 t CH 4 d -1 , respectively. The total emissions using µ pt <lb/>(and µ SI ) and using six area sources with method 1 and <lb/>method 2 are 12.98 (13.09) and 13.83 (13.56) t CH 4 d -1 , re-<lb/>spectively. Figure 7a2 and b2 show that the fit between the <lb/>observed and modeled µ pt from the Gaussian model using <lb/>the corresponding emission estimates with six areas sources <lb/>are slightly better than those from the nine hotspots. The in-<lb/>version using nine hotspots assigns the estimated emissions <lb/>to the three point sources that lie in two source areas, A-6 <lb/>and A-3, only (Fig. 7a3), whereas the estimated emissions <lb/>from the inversion using six area sources are approximately <lb/>equally distributed to three area sources A-4, A-5, and A-6 <lb/>(Fig. 7b3). It is noticed that the total estimates are weakly <lb/>sensitive to the observation vector µ pt or µ SI . However, the <lb/>discrepancy between the estimated emissions obtained with <lb/>different definitions of the potential emission sources and <lb/>also from different implementations of area sources (method <lb/>1 and method 2) in the inversion tests is noticeable. The abso-<lb/>lute differences between the estimated emissions using nine <lb/>point sources and six area sources in the inversions are ∼ 10 <lb/>and ∼ 9 t CH 4 d -1 for method 1 and method 2, respectively. <lb/>For most of the selected campaigns using data from the <lb/>ABC road, we observed a similar behavior by the estimated <lb/>CH 4 emissions from different inversion tests as from the re-<lb/>sults from the 10 January 2019 campaign. The estimated <lb/>emissions using ABC data from different campaigns vary be-<lb/>tween ∼ 2 to ∼ 36 t CH 4 d -1 using six area sources and ∼ 4 <lb/>to ∼ 23 t CH 4 d -1 using nine point sources in different in-<lb/>version tests (Fig. S2.1). The estimates show large biases in <lb/>the orders of magnitude between total methane emission es-<lb/>timates from different tests. The large differences in the in-<lb/>verted total CH 4 emissions using different definitions of the <lb/>potential sources in the inversion tests show a high sensitiv-<lb/>ity of the estimates to a priori information about potential <lb/>sources. <lb/>We analyzed the spatial distribution of methane emission <lb/>estimated from the inversions using ABC measurements. <lb/>Figure S2.16 shows the spatial distributions of the estimated <lb/>CH 4 emissions attributed to the individual source regions <lb/>from the inversions using six area sources and µ pt from the <lb/>ABC measurements from all the selected campaigns. This <lb/>shows that the two source areas A-1 and A-2 have negligible <lb/>contributions to the total estimated methane emissions. Emis-<lb/>sions from sources A-3 to A-6 are more regularly inferred <lb/>from most of the campaigns. Emissions from A-3 are vari-<lb/>able and may indicate a highly variable source, while emis-<lb/>sions from A-4 are more consistent, which may be expected <lb/>as this area of the landfill was active during this time. High <lb/>methane emissions attributed to the A-6 source region dur-<lb/>ing some of the campaigns may be emitted from the methane <lb/>hotspots identified from the foot sniffing campaigns near the <lb/>biogas network purges, biogas network well, and bioreactor <lb/>tank (Sect. 3.1). <lb/>5.2 Emission estimates using EF road measurements <lb/>For the campaign of 10 January 2019, the total estimated <lb/>CH 4 emissions using µ pt and µ SI from EF road measure-<lb/>ments in the inversions with nine hotspots are 4.50 and <lb/>3.98 t CH 4 d -1 , respectively. The total estimated CH 4 emis-<lb/>sions using µ pt (and µ SI ) and six area sources with method 1 <lb/>and method 2 are 4.44 (4.41) and 4.16 (4.18) t CH 4 d -1 , re-<lb/>spectively. Figure 8a2 and b2, respectively, for nine hotspots <lb/>and six area sources with µ pt in the inversions show a good <lb/>agreement between the observed and modeled CH 4 mole <lb/>fractions from the dispersion model using the corresponding <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1242 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>Figure 7. An example of modeling the individual plumes and emission rates from the inversion tests using (a) nine main hotspots and (b) six <lb/>area sources with µ pt from the measurements obtained along the ABC road on 10 January 2019. From left to right in each row, the first <lb/>to third columns plots respectively show (1) the average CH 4 mole fraction enhancements above the background (dashed black line, right <lb/>y axis) and modeled response functions (solid colored lines for method 1 and the same colored dotted lines for method 2, left y axis) for each <lb/>potential source, (2) the fit between the observed (dashed black lines) and modeled (solid blue lines) CH 4 mole fraction enhancements, and <lb/>(3) estimates of the CH 4 emissions (t CH 4 d -1 ) for each of the potential sources. Vertical dotted blue lines in the first column figures show <lb/>the point of division of the roads into sub-segments over which the averaged mole fractions are integrated to define µ SI . <lb/>inverted emissions. The estimated CH 4 emissions from the <lb/>inversions with method 1 and method 2 for an area source <lb/>implementation in the Gaussian model have a small percent-<lb/>age difference of ∼ 6 % using either µ pt or µ SI . The inver-<lb/>sion results using EF measurements are weakly sensitive to <lb/>the defined observation vectors µ pt and µ SI with ∼ 12 % <lb/>and less than ∼ 1 % percentage differences in flux estimates <lb/>from nine hotspots and six area sources, respectively. The <lb/>total estimated methane emissions using nine hotspots and <lb/>six area sources with µ pt had small percentage differences of <lb/>∼ 1 % and ∼ 8 % for method 1 and method 2, respectively. <lb/>Figure 8a3 shows that, in the inversion using nine hotspots, <lb/>the estimated emissions are distributed only to three point <lb/>sources in two source areas, A-6 and A-4. In contrast, the <lb/>inversion using six area sources assigns the estimated emis-<lb/>sions primarily to A-6, with small contributions from A-5 <lb/>and A-4, as shown in Fig. 8b3. <lb/>We conducted another sensitivity analysis of the inver-<lb/>sion results with respect to a different definition of the five <lb/>rectangular potential area sources defined within the five <lb/>cells (Fig. S2.2), as proposed by Albergel et al. (2017). <lb/>Using these five area sources and with µ pt obtained from <lb/>the EF measurements from 10 January 2019, the total es-<lb/>timated emissions (4.24 and 4.19 t CH 4 d -1 with method 1 <lb/>and method 2, respectively) (Fig. S2.3) have small percent-<lb/>age differences (∼ 4 % and ∼ 1 %) compared to the total es-<lb/>timated emissions (4.44 and 4.16 t CH 4 d -1 for method 1 and <lb/>method 2, respectively) obtained using six area sources in in-<lb/>versions. In order to analyze the effect of the approximated <lb/>wind direction (Sect. 4) on inversion results when relying on <lb/>the meteorological data from Melun met station in the Gaus-<lb/>sian model, we tested this assumption for the campaign on <lb/>10 January 2019, where, instead of using actual observed <lb/>wind direction, we forced the model to use the wind di-<lb/>rection approximation. With µ pt , total estimated emissions <lb/>of 4.03 and 3.80 t CH 4 d -1 using nine hotspots and six area <lb/>sources, respectively, have ∼ 11 % and ∼ 15 % differences <lb/>compared to those obtained using the actual observed mean <lb/>wind direction from the local 3-D sonic anemometer (4.50 <lb/>and 4.44 t CH 4 d -1 , respectively). Overall, different sensitiv-<lb/>ity tests using EF measurements from 10 January 2019 in-<lb/>dicate that the percentage differences between the total esti-<lb/>mated emissions range from less than 1 % to ∼ 15 %. This <lb/>suggests that the total estimated emissions exhibit weak sen-<lb/>sitivity to different input parameters in the inversion tests. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1243 <lb/></page>

		<body>Figure 8. An example of modeling the individual plumes and emission rates from the inversion tests using (a) nine main hotspots and (b) six <lb/>area sources with µ pt from the measurements obtained along the EF road on 10 January 2019. From left to right in each row, first to third <lb/>columns plots, respectively, show (1) the average CH 4 mole fraction enhancements above the background (dashed black line, right y axis) <lb/>and modeled response functions (solid colored lines for method 1 and the same colored dotted lines for method 2, left y axis) for each <lb/>potential source, (2) the fit between the observed (dashed black lines) and modeled (solid blue lines) CH 4 mole fraction enhancements, and <lb/>(3) estimates of the CH 4 emissions (t CH 4 d -1 ) for each of the potential sources. Vertical dotted blue lines in the first column figures show <lb/>the point of division of the roads into sub-segments over which the averaged mole fractions are integrated to define µ SI . <lb/>Figure 9 shows the estimated total methane emissions <lb/>from the studied landfill using µ pt obtained from the EF <lb/>measurements from the 11 campaigns where sampling was <lb/>conducted on the southern EF road. These estimations are <lb/>based on using nine hotspots as prior point sources and six <lb/>potential area sources, with two different methods (method <lb/>1 and method 2) for area source implementation in the <lb/>Gaussian model. Figures S2.3-S2.14 present more details <lb/>about these inversion results. The total CH 4 emissions using <lb/>nine hotspots from the inversions vary from 0.44 t CH 4 d -1 <lb/>(5 February 2020) to a maximum of 6.90 t CH 4 d -1 (1 De-<lb/>cember 2020), with an average emission of 2.24 t CH 4 d -1 . <lb/>These estimates are similar to the estimated emissions ob-<lb/>tained using six area sources with method 1 (and method 2) <lb/>which vary from 0.34 (0.34) to 7.04 (6.30) t CH 4 d -1 , with <lb/>an average value of 2.07 (2.00) t CH 4 d -1 . <lb/>Similarly to the inversion results using EF measurements <lb/>from the 10 January 2019 campaign, the results from differ-<lb/>ent inversion tests using three different definitions of the po-<lb/>tential emissions sources, two observation vectors, and two <lb/>different implementations of the area sources in the Gaus-<lb/>sian plume model show that the percentage differences be-<lb/>Figure 9. Summary of the total estimated CH 4 emissions using the <lb/>observation vector µ pt obtained from EF road data and using nine <lb/>hotspots from sniffing as point sources and six area sources with <lb/>two different methods (method 1 and method 2) for area source im-<lb/>plementation in the Gaussian model. <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1244 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>tween the total estimated emissions from different combina-<lb/>tions of these tests averaged over the 11 campaigns ranged <lb/>from ∼ 1 % to ∼ 15 %. This analysis shows that the emission <lb/>estimates using EF measurements are weakly sensitive to the <lb/>different definitions of potential emission sources, observa-<lb/>tion vectors, and other parameters considered in the inversion <lb/>tests. Thus, based on this analysis, we consider it to be that <lb/>the total estimated methane emissions using the EF measure-<lb/>ments are robust. The estimates obtained through ABC mea-<lb/>surements in inversions are much higher compared to the es-<lb/>timates from the EF road. These ABC estimates are highly <lb/>sensitive to different characterizations of potential sources <lb/>(Sect. 5.1) due to various factors such as the complex land-<lb/>fill topography, the inability to account for it in the Gaussian <lb/>model, our limited understanding of the spatial representa-<lb/>tivity of potential sources, the short distances between mea-<lb/>surements and potential sources, etc. This weakens our con-<lb/>fidence in the estimates derived from the data collected along <lb/>the ABC road. Therefore, we rely on the estimates obtained <lb/>using measurements from the EF road for the estimation of <lb/>landfill methane emissions. <lb/>We also analyzed the spatial distribution of the estimated <lb/>emissions from the EF road measurements. Figure S2.17 <lb/>shows that the inversions using EF measurements assign a <lb/>significant proportion of net methane emissions to the A-6 <lb/>area source (Fig. 6), along with some contributions from A-<lb/>4 and A-5. EF measurements additionally attributed a small <lb/>part of total methane emissions to the A-1 source area, which <lb/>includes the biogas plant and was not detected by the inver-<lb/>sions using ABC measurements. <lb/>6 Discussion <lb/>The averages of total CH 4 emissions using data from EF <lb/>measurements from all 11 campaigns (where suitable MGL <lb/>sampling was conducted) vary from ∼ 2.0 to ∼ 2.2 t CH 4 d -1 <lb/>in different inversion sensitivity tests. This indicates that the <lb/>use of remote mobile plume cross-section measurements is <lb/>suitable for quantification of the total methane emissions <lb/>from the site, which are weakly sensitive to the characteri-<lb/>zation of the potential emission sources and other influenc-<lb/>ing parameters like the observation vectors, wind directions, <lb/>etc. Thus, these results highlight the necessity of conduct-<lb/>ing measurements at a sufficient distance from the landfill to <lb/>obtain a reliable estimate of total methane emissions, min-<lb/>imizing the influence of landfill topography. However, this <lb/>increased distance makes it challenging to discern the spa-<lb/>tial distribution of emissions within the landfill. On the other <lb/>hand, the inversion tests performed with sampling from the <lb/>landfill perimeter (ABC) show a high sensitivity of the es-<lb/>timates to the spatial distribution of the potential emission <lb/>sources and other parameters in the inversions. It highlights <lb/>the difficulties in exploiting ABC measurements to estimate <lb/>CH 4 emissions using a simple Gaussian plume model due to <lb/>the model&apos;s inability to consider complex landfill topogra-<lb/>phy and lack of precise information about potential emission <lb/>sources. Thus, estimates using the ABC road were deemed <lb/>to be poorly representative of actual landfill methane emis-<lb/>sions. However, the ABC measurements taken in proximity <lb/>to the landfill are shown to be useful to identify and rank <lb/>the main emission areas, i.e., to get insights into the spatial <lb/>distribution of the emissions within the landfill. This demon-<lb/>strates the complementarity between the near-and far-field <lb/>measurements. <lb/>The total CH 4 emissions using data from the EF road <lb/>show a large temporal variability (∼ 0.4 to ∼ 7 t CH 4 d -1 ) <lb/>in landfill methane emissions (Fig. 9). The emission sources <lb/>and thus the methane emissions from an active landfill can <lb/>vary greatly even over a small period of a few days. For <lb/>example, total methane emissions on 8 December 2020 <lb/>(∼ 1.25 t CH 4 d -1 ) were far smaller than on 1 December <lb/>2020 (∼ 7 t CH 4 d -1 ) despite a 1-week interval between <lb/>these two sampling campaigns and despite the fact that mea-<lb/>surements were conducted during daytime hours of between <lb/>11:30 to 12:30 UTC in both campaigns. We anticipate that <lb/>the high temporal variability in the emissions is primarily <lb/>attributable to landfill activity, such as the fixing of a large <lb/>methane leak, which can lead to a substantial drop in emis-<lb/>sions within a short timeframe. However, the limited avail-<lb/>ability of day-to-day activity data for this landfill makes it <lb/>challenging to attribute the variability in our emission es-<lb/>timates based on the EF measurements to particular land-<lb/>fill activities. Thus, more mobile campaigns on the EF road <lb/>are required to more accurately monitor and to better un-<lb/>derstand temporal variabilities of landfill methane emissions. <lb/>Note that the estimates from each of the selected campaigns <lb/>are based on the measurements spanning an order of 1 to <lb/>2 daytime hours. However, different atmospheric conditions <lb/>and landfill activities during nighttime and other daytime <lb/>hours may contribute to a diurnal pattern in landfill emissions <lb/>(Sonderfeld et al., 2017). To better understand the diurnal <lb/>variability of landfill methane emissions, we need to mon-<lb/>itor the emissions at a higher temporal resolution. For this, <lb/>continuous automated measurements at a certain distance of <lb/>the site over long periods are required, which is impracti-<lb/>cal using a labor-intensive MGL unless the MGL were to be <lb/>permanently installed in a vehicle that travels along the EF <lb/>transect frequently. Continuous CH 4 mole fraction measure-<lb/>ments from a network of fixed sensors around a site along-<lb/>side meteorological measurements can provide an alternative <lb/>to develop an automated monitoring system to monitor long-<lb/>term landfill methane emissions at a higher temporal resolu-<lb/>tion. However, the deployment of a dense network of high-<lb/>precision sensors is still limited by cost. Recently, Riddick et <lb/>al. (2018) utilized a single-point continuous CH 4 measure-<lb/>ment that was sampled ∼ 700 m downwind from a landfill, <lb/>and they combined this with a Lagrangian particle model <lb/>to estimate the methane emissions at a high temporal reso-<lb/>lution. A similar approach can be applied to monitor land-<lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1245 <lb/></page>

		<body>fill methane emissions for short-and long-term temporal-<lb/>variability studies. Such an approach could be complemented <lb/>by other techniques, such as MGLs, which may provide com-<lb/>plementary information on the spatial variability of sources <lb/>within the landfill and which may be more suited to leak de-<lb/>tection and mitigation. <lb/>A limitation of our inversion approach is that it does not di-<lb/>agnose explicit estimates of the uncertainties in the estimated <lb/>CH 4 emissions. Extrapolating the results obtained with a <lb/>similar approach applied to controlled-CH 4 -release exper-<lb/>iments during the TADI-2018 and TADI-2019 campaigns <lb/>(Kumar et al., 2022, 2021), we assume that our emission esti-<lb/>mates from the EF road have a level of uncertainty of ∼ 30 %. <lb/>The errors diagnosed during TADI&apos;s controlled-release ex-<lb/>periments were mainly applicable for flat terrain conditions. <lb/>Here, much of the plume dispersion from the landfill to the <lb/>measurements transects occurs over flat terrain. However, the <lb/>landfill itself corresponds to a complex topography. We cur-<lb/>rently lack information on the errors from Gaussian plume <lb/>dispersion models when applied to such a terrain, making it <lb/>difficult to provide a more robust diagnostic of uncertainties <lb/>in our estimates. <lb/>Several studies have shown that the temporal variability <lb/>of landfill methane emissions is driven by absolute or tem-<lb/>poral gradients of some meteorological parameters, espe-<lb/>cially atmospheric pressure (Czepiel et al., 2003; Poulsen <lb/>et al., 2003; Xu et al., 2014; Aghdam et al., 2019; Kissas <lb/>et al., 2022). A limited number of studies, like Riddick <lb/>et al. (2018), have demonstrated a very weak negative or <lb/>no clear relationship between landfill CH 4 emissions and <lb/>changes in atmospheric pressure. We also analyzed these <lb/>emission-pressure or emission-temperature relationships us-<lb/>ing the estimated CH 4 emissions from the EF road measure-<lb/>ments and the atmospheric pressure and temperature mea-<lb/>sured at Melun station (Fig. S2.15). We observed a weak <lb/>negative correlation of landfill methane emissions with at-<lb/>mospheric pressure (R = -0.10) and a slightly stronger neg-<lb/>ative correlation with atmospheric temperature (R = -0.30) <lb/>(Fig. S2.15). Riddick et al. (2018) discussed several possible <lb/>contributing factors to this weak emission-pressure relation-<lb/>ship, such as ongoing landfill operations on an active land-<lb/>fill during a measurement campaign and emission data gaps. <lb/>These are reasonable contributory factors in our case of the <lb/>studied active landfill as the sample size of our landfill emis-<lb/>sion estimates is very small, with large data gaps between <lb/>emission estimates. <lb/>For near-landfill measurements on the ABCD road, <lb/>methane plumes coming from the sources within the land-<lb/>fill are generally not well mixed, either horizontally or verti-<lb/>cally, as they are too close to the emission sources. The dis-<lb/>crete landfill emission sources at higher elevations may not <lb/>be detected within these measurements, with the sampling <lb/>air intake at ∼ 2 m above the ground surface. Recirculation <lb/>of the wind flow due to complex landfill topography affects <lb/>the transport and dispersion of mixing methane plumes at the <lb/>measurement positions, which is difficult to simulate with <lb/>a simple Gaussian plume model that considers spatially ho-<lb/>mogeneous flow. Thus, the estimation of methane emissions <lb/>using these measurements requires a more complex model <lb/>that can resolve the flow field and turbulence induced by the <lb/>complex topography of the landfill. Computational fluid dy-<lb/>namics (CFD) models are more suitable for such applications <lb/>and have been used to simulate high-resolution flow fields <lb/>and turbulence in complex terrains. These CFD models could <lb/>provide opportunities to account for variations in the flow <lb/>field in space and time. However, the computational cost of <lb/>such a model for emission inversions will be high compared <lb/>to a simple Gaussian approach. <lb/>As discussed above, despite the large uncertainties in net <lb/>emissions estimated using ABC measurements, these esti-<lb/>mates together with the sniffing campaigns provide some in-<lb/>formation on the spatial distribution of emissions within a <lb/>landfill and thus insights into the relative contribution of the <lb/>different areas and types of activities occurring within the <lb/>landfill to the total landfill emissions. The spatial distribu-<lb/>tions of CH 4 emissions from individual source regions re-<lb/>vealed two main source areas (A-4 and A-6) and two other <lb/>areas (A-5 and A-3) with lesser emissions that contributed to <lb/>the total estimated methane emissions for most of the cam-<lb/>paigns. The inversions using EF measurements strengthened <lb/>the assumption that the A-6 source area is one of the main <lb/>contributors to net methane emissions, with additional con-<lb/>tributions from A-3, A-4, and A-5 and a small proportion of <lb/>total methane emissions from the A-1 source area. A-5, A-6, <lb/>and A-3 were covered with clay and membrane during most <lb/>of the campaigns, but there were junctures of biogas network <lb/>wells, bioreactor tanks, etc. within these source areas. As dis-<lb/>cussed in Sect. 3.1 with the analysis of near-surface sniff-<lb/>ing measurements, many of the identified hotspots were near <lb/>to these components, which contributed to a majority of the <lb/>methane emissions from these source areas. We observed sig-<lb/>nificant temporal variability in the emissions from this source <lb/>area (Fig. S2.16), and this variation underscores the fact that <lb/>the elevated emissions primarily coincide with instances of <lb/>sporadic leakages in potential emitting infrastructures in the <lb/>landfill. However, the source area A-4 was the last sector <lb/>where waste reception was ongoing during this study, par-<lb/>ticularly in the last phase of the campaigns when we had <lb/>reliable on-site meteorological measurements to support the <lb/>analysis of the emission spatial distribution within the land-<lb/>fill using the ABC measurements. During active waste recep-<lb/>tion, the corresponding reception areas, here A-4, are open <lb/>and uncovered, and A-4 was thus restricted from any sniff-<lb/>ing measurements due to safety considerations. However, the <lb/>analyses with the ABC measurements and with the inver-<lb/>sions identified A-4 as one of the continuous emitters and <lb/>as the largest source area on average, which is consistent <lb/>with the fact that the waste in this area is already produc-<lb/>ing biogas which is not collected (or only partially) because <lb/>of limited biogas network systems in this area and because <lb/></body>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1246 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<body>of the lack of final cover. As the areas on the southwestern <lb/>side of the landfill have been the first areas to be filled, the <lb/>methane emissions are significantly lower in this part. The <lb/>covering is designed to improve biogas capture for electric-<lb/>ity production on site. However, the methane production in <lb/>the newest areas and the leaks in the landfill infrastructure <lb/>may explain the higher emissions on the northern and eastern <lb/>sides (A-3, A-4, A-5, and A-6) of the landfill. Measurements <lb/>with a terrain-resolving flow and dispersion model may pro-<lb/>vide better information about the spatial distribution of emis-<lb/>sion sources within the landfill as these would better replicate <lb/>sniffing campaigns similar to those described in this study. <lb/>The information about the distribution of the emission <lb/>sources from the inversions and the hotspots identified from <lb/>the sniffing campaigns helps site operators to prioritize mit-<lb/>igation actions (cover improvement, improvement of land-<lb/>fill gas network collection, etc.). Typically, at landfill sites, <lb/>emission sources are highly variable in space and time, with <lb/>individual sources within the landfill ranging from sporadic <lb/>to continuous and from spatially heterogenous hotspots to <lb/>large diffusive areas. The analysis of measurements and in-<lb/>versions from the different MGLs help to provide some qual-<lb/>itative information about the potential emission sources, but <lb/>their ability to precisely locate the exact spatial distribution <lb/>of these sources is limited by the distance between the ve-<lb/>hicle (road) and the sources. Regular sniffing campaigns by <lb/>foot or by drone using a portable analyzer and GPS module <lb/>help, to some extent, to locate certain suspected hotspots. <lb/>Our long-term monitoring of landfill methane emissions <lb/>required significant resources and effort. It would have been <lb/>challenging to conduct a similar effort for other landfills. Ad-<lb/>ditional studies, like this one, will be essential for establish-<lb/>ing robust standard atmospheric monitoring techniques ap-<lb/>plicable to diverse landfills. Further research is needed to re-<lb/>fine the generic emission factors for landfill methane emis-<lb/>sions in methane emission inventories. However, we man-<lb/>aged to link the main part of the emissions to the waste-<lb/>tipping area which remains uncovered over a long period of <lb/>time with limited biogas collection systems. This type of re-<lb/>sult should provide useful information to site managers with <lb/>regard to effective mitigation actions and improved landfill <lb/>operation management. Our measurement strategy and in-<lb/>version approaches are generalizable for the monitoring of <lb/>emissions from other landfills, providing a basis for future <lb/>applications and development. <lb/>7 Conclusions <lb/>In this study, we present long-term, near-surface mobile mea-<lb/>surements from 21 campaigns for reliable quantification of <lb/>total methane emissions from an active landfill using atmo-<lb/>spheric inversion modeling. We applied a simple inversion <lb/>approach to quantify methane emissions from the landfill us-<lb/>ing a Gaussian plume model. Measurements from a remote <lb/>EF road, further away from the landfill, were preferable for <lb/>inverse modeling as the estimates based on these measure-<lb/>ments were proven to be only weakly sensitive to the defined <lb/>potential emission sources and other influencing parameters <lb/>in the inversions. The total CH 4 emissions estimated us-<lb/>ing different definitions of potential sources and using data <lb/>where sampling was conducted on the distant EF road (11 <lb/>campaigns) varied from ∼ 0.4 to ∼ 7 t CH 4 d -1 , with an av-<lb/>erage flux value of ∼ 2.1 t CH 4 d -1 . These estimated landfill <lb/>methane emissions showed large temporal variability. Emis-<lb/>sion estimates based on the measurements conducted along <lb/>the perimeter of the landfill (ABC) were very sensitive to the <lb/>characterization of potential emission sources and were lim-<lb/>ited in their ability to provide representative landfill emission <lb/>estimates. However, the analysis of these measurements, as <lb/>well as those from the sniffing campaigns within the landfill <lb/>site, helped to identify the main landfill emission areas. This <lb/>information remained insufficient to define the detailed spa-<lb/>tial distribution of the emission sources within the site. How-<lb/>ever, it showed that the two main area sources correspond re-<lb/>spectively to a covered waste sector with infrastructure with <lb/>sporadic leakages (such as wells, tanks, pipes, etc.) and to the <lb/>last active sector receiving waste during most of the measure-<lb/>ment campaigns. This demonstrates the complementarity be-<lb/>tween the near-and far-field measurements. Based on our es-<lb/>timated landfill emissions using EF road measurements, we <lb/>found a weak negative correlation between emissions and <lb/>atmospheric pressure and a slightly stronger inverse rela-<lb/>tionship between emissions and atmospheric temperature. To <lb/>better characterize such relationships and also for more accu-<lb/>rate monitoring of landfill emissions, we suggest that emis-<lb/>sion estimates should be maintained on longer-term measure-<lb/>ments, ideally measurements that are made continuously. In <lb/>order to better utilize these measurements for landfill emis-<lb/>sion quantification, especially when sampling close to the <lb/>landfill, we suggest using a more complex model, such as <lb/>a CFD model, that can resolve the flow field and turbulence <lb/>induced by the complex landfill topography. <lb/></body>

		<div type="availability">Code and data availability. The data and code are accessible upon <lb/>reasonable request. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available on-<lb/>line at: https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

		<div type="contribution">Author contributions. PK conducted the data analysis and imple-<lb/>mented the inverse modeling system and performed the model sim-<lb/>ulations and inversions. GB and PK designed the inverse modeling <lb/>system, and the LSCE members participated in the design of the <lb/>observation strategy. CC and AS organized the main series of the <lb/>measurement campaigns. CC, CYK, SWG, AS, OL, SA, SD, LL, <lb/>ML, JDP, and FV conducted the campaigns and processed the data <lb/>together with PK. PK, GB, and CC prepared and reviewed the paper <lb/></div>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1247 <lb/></page>

		<div type="contribution">with critical contributions from AS, PC, OL, and all the other co-<lb/>authors. All the co-authors participated in the discussions regarding <lb/>the results. <lb/></div>

		<div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none of <lb/>the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

		<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. We would like to thank the SUEZ site staff for <lb/>their assistance in the measurement campaigns. We also acknowl-<lb/>edge IFP Energies nouvelles-Géoscience, France, for participating <lb/>in some of the campaigns. <lb/></div>

		<div type="funding">Financial support. This research has been supported by Chaire In-<lb/>dustrielle TRACE (grant no. ANR-17-CHIN-0004-01), which is co-<lb/>funded by the French National Research Agency (ANR), TOTAL <lb/>Raffinage Chimie, SUEZ, and Thales Alenia Space (TAS). <lb/></div>

		<div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Abhishek Chatterjee <lb/>and reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

		<listBibl>References <lb/>Aghdam, E. F., Scheutz, C., and Kjeldsen, P.: Impact <lb/>of meteorological parameters on extracted landfill gas <lb/>composition and flow, Waste Manage., 87, 905-914, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.01.045, 2019. <lb/>Albergel, A., Morin, D., Buty, D., Nibart, M., Makke, L., Goix, <lb/>R., Kelly, R., Bouchet, C., and Vogel, F.: Inverse dispersion <lb/>modelling for a quick scan service to assess fugitive emissions <lb/>from landfills, in: 18th International Conference on Harmonisa-<lb/>tion within Atmospheric Dispersion Modelling for Regulatory <lb/>Purposes, Bologna, Italy, http://www.harmo18.eu/ (last access: <lb/>13 February 2024), 2017. <lb/>Allen, G., Hollingsworth, P., Kabbabe, K., Pitt, J. R., Mead, M. I., <lb/>Illingworth, S., Roberts, G., Bourn, M., Shallcross, D. E., and <lb/>Percival, C. J.: The development and trial of an unmanned aerial <lb/>system for the measurement of methane flux from landfill and <lb/>greenhouse gas emission hotspots, Waste Manage., 87, 883-892, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.WASMAN.2017.12.024, 2019. <lb/>Ars, S.: Caractérisation des émissions de méthane à l&apos;échelle locale <lb/>à l&apos;aide d&apos;une méthode d&apos;inversion statistique basée sur un mod-<lb/>èle gaussien paramétré avec les données d&apos;un gaz traceur, Univer-<lb/>sité Paris Saclay (COmUE), France, https://theses.hal.science/ <lb/>tel-01624241 (last access: 17 March 2023), 2017. <lb/>Ars, S., Broquet, G., Yver Kwok, C., Roustan, Y., Wu, L., Ar-<lb/>zoumanian, E., and Bousquet, P.: Statistical atmospheric inver-<lb/>sion of local gas emissions by coupling the tracer release tech-<lb/>nique and local-scale transport modelling: a test case with con-<lb/>trolled methane emissions, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 10, 5017-5037, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-10-5017-2017, 2017. <lb/>Ars, S., Vogel, F., Arrowsmith, C., Heerah, S., Knuckey, E., <lb/>Lavoie, J., Lee, C., Pak, N. M., Phillips, J. L., and Wunch, <lb/>D.: Investigation of the Spatial Distribution of Methane <lb/>Sources in the Greater Toronto Area Using Mobile Gas Mon-<lb/>itoring Systems, Environ. Sci. Technol., 54, 15671-15679, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c05386, 2020. <lb/>Bel Hadj Ali, N., Abichou, T., and Green, R.: Comparing estimates <lb/>of fugitive landfill methane emissions using inverse plume mod-<lb/>eling obtained with Surface Emission Monitoring (SEM), Drone <lb/>Emission Monitoring (DEM), and Downwind Plume Emission <lb/>Monitoring (DWPEM), J. Air Waste Manage., 70, 410-424, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/10962247.2020.1728423, 2020. <lb/>Bingemer, H. G. and Crutzen, P. J.: The production of methane <lb/>from solid wastes, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 92, 2181-2187, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/JD092iD02p02181, 1987. <lb/>Bogner, J. and Matthews, E.: Global methane emissions <lb/>from landfills: New methodology and annual esti-<lb/>mates 1980-1996, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 17, 1065, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2002gb001913, 2003. <lb/>Bogner, J., Spokas, K., Burton, E., Sweeney, R., and Corona, <lb/>V.: Landfills as atmospheric methane sources and sinks, <lb/>Chemosphere, 31, 4119-4130, https://doi.org/10.1016/0045-<lb/>6535(95)80012-A, 1995. <lb/>Bogner, J., Pipatti, R., Hashimoto, S., Diaz, C., Mareckova, K., <lb/>Diaz, L., Kjeldsen, P., Monni, S., Faaij, A., Qingxian, G., <lb/>Tianzhu, Z., Mohammed, A. A., Sutamihardja, R. T. M., and <lb/>Gregory, R.: Mitigation of global greenhouse gas emissions from <lb/>waste: Conclusions and strategies from the Intergovernmental <lb/>Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Fourth Assessment Report. <lb/>Working Group III (Mitigation), Waste Manage. Res., 26, 11-32, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/0734242X07088433, 2008. <lb/>Bourn, M., Robinson, R., Innocenti, F., and Scheutz, C.: <lb/>Regulating landfills using measured methane emissions: <lb/>An English perspective, Waste Manage., 87, 860-869, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.06.032, 2019. <lb/>Bousquet, P., Ciais, P., Miller, J. B., Dlugokencky, E. J., Hauglus-<lb/>taine, D. A., Prigent, C., van der Werf, G. R., Peylin, P., <lb/>Brunke, E. G., Carouge, C., Langenfelds, R. L., Lathière, J., <lb/>Papa, F., Ramonet, M., Schmidt, M., Steele, L. P., Tyler, S. <lb/>C., and White, J.: Contribution of anthropogenic and natural <lb/>sources to atmospheric methane variability, Nature, 443, 439-<lb/>443, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05132, 2006. <lb/>Briggs, G. A.: Diffusion estimation for small emissions, <lb/>ATDL contribution file no. 79, National Oceanic and <lb/>Atmospheric Administration, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2172/5118833, 1973. <lb/>Cambaliza, M. O. L., Shepson, P. B., Bogner, J., Caulton, D. R., <lb/>Stirm, B., Sweeney, C., Montzka, S. A., Gurney, K. R., Spokas, <lb/>K., Salmon, O. E., Lavoie, T. N., Hendricks, A., Mays, K., <lb/>Turnbull, J., Miller, B. R., Lauvaux, T., Davis, K., Karion, A., <lb/>Moser, B., Miller, C., Obermeyer, C., Whetstone, J., Prasad, K., <lb/>Miles, N., and Richardson, S.: Quantification and source ap-<lb/>portionment of the methane emission flux from the city of In-<lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1248 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>dianapolis, Elementa: Science of the Anthropocene, 3, 000037, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.12952/journal.elementa.000037, 2015. <lb/>Carslaw, D. C. and Beevers, S. D.: Characterising and un-<lb/>derstanding emission sources using bivariate polar plots and <lb/>k-means clustering, Environ. Modell. Softw., 40, 325-329, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsoft.2012.09.005, 2013. <lb/>Crotwell, A., Lee, H., and Steinbacher, M. (Eds.): 20th WMO/IAEA <lb/>meeting on carbon dioxide, other greenhouse gases and related <lb/>measurement techniques (GGMT-2019), GAW report No. 255, <lb/>World Meteorological Organization, Geneva, Switzerland, 2019. <lb/>Czepiel, P. M., Mosher, B., Harriss, R. C., Shorter, J. H., Mc-<lb/>Manus, J. B., Kolb, C. E., Allwine, E., and Lamb, B. K.: Land-<lb/>fill methane emissions measured by enclosure and atmospheric <lb/>tracer methods, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 101, 16711-16719, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/96JD00864, 1996. <lb/>Czepiel, P. M., Shorter, J. H., Mosher, B., Allwine, E., McManus, <lb/>J. B., Harriss, R. C., Kolb, C. E., and Lamb, B. K.: The in-<lb/>fluence of atmospheric pressure on landfill methane emissions, <lb/>Waste Manage., 23, 593-598, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0956-<lb/>053X(03)00103-X, 2003. <lb/>Daugėla, I., Suziedelyte Visockiene, J., and Kumpiene, J.: de-<lb/>tection and analysis of methane emissions from a land-<lb/>fill using unmanned aerial drone systems and semiconductor <lb/>sensors, Detritus, 10, 127-138, https://doi.org/10.31025/2611-<lb/>4135/2020.13942, 2020. <lb/>Dreyfus, G. B., Xu, Y., Shindell, D. T., Zaelke, D., and Ra-<lb/>manathan, V.: Mitigating climate disruption in time: A self-<lb/>consistent approach for avoiding both near-term and long-term <lb/>global warming, P. Natl. Acad Sci. USA, 119, e2123536119, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2123536119, 2022. <lb/>Duan, Z., Hansen, P. O. C. R., Scheutz, C., and Kjeld-<lb/>sen, P.: Mitigation of methane and trace gas emis-<lb/>sions through a large-scale active biofilter system at <lb/>Glatved landfill, Denmark, Waste Manage., 126, 367-376, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2021.03.023, 2021. <lb/>Duan, Z., Scheutz, C., and Kjeldsen, P.: Mitigation of <lb/>methane emissions from three Danish landfills using dif-<lb/>ferent biocover systems, Waste Manage., 149, 156-167, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.WASMAN.2022.05.022, 2022. <lb/>Emran, B. J., Tannant, D. D., and Najjaran, H.: Low-altitude aerial <lb/>methane concentration mapping, Remote Sens.-Basel, 9, 823, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/rs9080823, 2017. <lb/>Etminan, M., Myhre, G., Highwood, E. J., and Shine, K. P.: Radia-<lb/>tive forcing of carbon dioxide, methane, and nitrous oxide: A sig-<lb/>nificant revision of the methane radiative forcing, Geophys. Res. <lb/>Lett., 43, 12614-12623, https://doi.org/10.1002/2016GL071930, <lb/>2016. <lb/>European Commission: COMMUNICATION FROM THE COM-<lb/>MISSION TO THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT, THE COUN-<lb/>CIL, THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL COM-<lb/>MITTEE AND THE COMMITTEE OF THE REGIONS on an <lb/>EU strategy to reduce methane emissions, Brussels, COM(2020) <lb/>663 final, https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/ <lb/>?uri=CELEX:52020DC0663 (last access: 17 March 2023), 2020. <lb/>European <lb/>Environment <lb/>Agency: <lb/>Annual <lb/>European <lb/>Union <lb/>greenhouse <lb/>gas <lb/>inventory <lb/>1990-2018 <lb/>and <lb/>inventory <lb/>report <lb/>2020, <lb/>UNFCCC <lb/>Secretariat, <lb/>EEA/PUBL/2022/023, https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/ <lb/>annual-european-union-greenhouse-gas-1 <lb/>(last <lb/>access: <lb/>17 March 2023), 2020. <lb/>European Union Methane Action Plan: European Union Methane <lb/>Action Plan -Policies -IEA, https://www.iea.org/policies/ <lb/>17024-european-union-methane-action-plan <lb/>(last <lb/>access: <lb/>17 March 2023), 2022. <lb/>Fischedick, M., Roy, J., Acquaye, A., Allwood, J., Ceron, J.-P., <lb/>Geng, Y., Kheshgi, H., Lanza, A., Perczyk, D., Price, L., Santalla, <lb/>E., Sheinbaum, C., and Tanaka, K.: Industry, in: Climate Change <lb/>2014: Mitigation of Climate Change. Contribution of Working <lb/>Group III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmen-<lb/>tal Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Edenhofer, O., Pichs-<lb/>Madruga, R., Sokona, Y., Farahani, E., Kadner, S., Seyboth, K., <lb/>Adler, A., Baum, I., Brunner, S., Eickemeier, P., Kriemann, B., <lb/>Savolainen, J., Schlömer, S., von Stechow, C., Zwickel, T., and <lb/>Minx, J. C., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United <lb/>Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, 739-810, 2014. <lb/>Fjelsted, L., Christensen, A. G., Larsen, J. E., Kjeldsen, P., and <lb/>Scheutz, C.: Assessment of a landfill methane emission screen-<lb/>ing method using an unmanned aerial vehicle mounted thermal <lb/>infrared camera -A field study, Waste Manage., 87, 893-904, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.05.031, 2019. <lb/>Foster-Wittig, T. A., Thoma, E. D., Green, R. B., Hater, G. R., <lb/>Swan, N. D., and Chanton, J. P.: Development of a mobile tracer <lb/>correlation method for assessment of air emissions from land-<lb/>fills and other area sources, Atmos. Environ., 102, 323-330, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2014.12.008, 2015. <lb/>Fox, T. A., Barchyn, T. E., Risk, D., Ravikumar, A. P., and <lb/>Hugenholtz, C. H.: A review of close-range and screen-<lb/>ing technologies for mitigating fugitive methane emissions <lb/>in upstream oil and gas, Environ. Res. Lett., 14, 53002, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab0cc3, 2019. <lb/>Gasbarra, D., Toscano, P., Famulari, D., Finardi, S., di Tom-<lb/>masi, P., Zaldei, A., Carlucci, P., Magliulo, E., and Gi-<lb/>oli, B.: Locating and quantifying multiple landfills methane <lb/>emissions using aircraft data, Environ. Pollut., 254, 112987, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.112987, 2019. <lb/>Hartmann, D. L., Tank, A. M. G. K., Rusticucci, M., Alexander, <lb/>L. v, Brönnimann, S., Charabi, Y. A. R., Dentener, F. J., Dlugo-<lb/>kencky, E. J., Easterling, D. R., Kaplan, A., Soden, B. J., Thorne, <lb/>P. W., Wild, M., and Zhai, P. M.: Observations: Atmosphere and <lb/>Surface, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. <lb/>Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report <lb/>of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: <lb/>Stocker, T. F., Qin, D., Plattner, G.-K., Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., <lb/>Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia, Y., Bex, V., and Midgley, P. M., <lb/>Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and <lb/>New York, NY, USA, 159-254, 2013. <lb/>Hein, R., Crutzen, P. J., and Heimann, M.: An inverse mod-<lb/>eling approach to investigate the global atmospheric <lb/>methane cycle, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 11, 43-76, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/96GB03043, 1997. <lb/>Hong, J., Chen, Y., Wang, M., Ye, L., Qi, C., Yuan, H., <lb/>Zheng, T., and Li, X.: Intensification of municipal solid waste <lb/>disposal in China, Renew. Sust. Energ. Rev., 69, 168-176, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rser.2016.11.185, 2017. <lb/>Jackson, R. B., Saunois, M., Bousquet, P., Canadell, J. G., Poul-<lb/>ter, B., Stavert, A. R., Bergamaschi, P., Niwa, Y., Segers, <lb/>A., and Tsuruta, A.: Increasing anthropogenic methane emis-<lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<page>1249 <lb/></page>

		<listBibl>sions arise equally from agricultural and fossil fuel sources, <lb/>Environ. Res. Lett., 15, 071002, https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-<lb/>9326/ab9ed2, 2020. <lb/>Jha, A. K., Sharma, C., Singh, N., Ramesh, R., Purvaja, R., <lb/>and Gupta, P. K.: Greenhouse gas emissions from munici-<lb/>pal solid waste management in Indian mega-cities: A case <lb/>study of Chennai landfill sites, Chemosphere, 71, 750-758, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.10.024, 2008. <lb/>Kirschke, S., Bousquet, P., Ciais, P., Saunois, M., Canadell, J. G., <lb/>Dlugokencky, E. J., Bergamaschi, P., Bergmann, D., Blake, D. <lb/>R., Bruhwiler, L., Cameron-Smith, P., Castaldi, S., Chevallier, <lb/>F., Feng, L., Fraser, A., Heimann, M., Hodson, E. L., Houwel-<lb/>ing, S., Josse, B., Fraser, P. J., Krummel, P. B., Lamarque, J.-<lb/>F., Langenfelds, R. L., Le Quéré, C., Naik, V., O&apos;Doherty, S., <lb/>Palmer, P. I., Pison, I., Plummer, D., Poulter, B., Prinn, R. G., <lb/>Rigby, M., Ringeval, B., Santini, M., Schmidt, M., Shindell, D. <lb/>T., Simpson, I. J., Spahni, R., Steele, L. P., Strode, S. A., Sudo, <lb/>K., Szopa, S., van der Werf, G. R., Voulgarakis, A., van Weele, <lb/>M., Weiss, R. F., Williams, J. E., and Zeng, G.: Three decades <lb/>of global methane sources and sinks, Nat. Geosci., 6, 813-823, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1955, 2013. <lb/>Kissas, K., Ibrom, A., Kjeldsen, P., and Scheutz, C.: Annual upscal-<lb/>ing of methane emission field measurements from two Danish <lb/>landfills, using empirical emission models, Waste Manage., 150, <lb/>191-201, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2022.07.005, 2022. <lb/>Krautwurst, S., Gerilowski, K., Jonsson, H. H., Thompson, D. R., <lb/>Kolyer, R. W., Iraci, L. T., Thorpe, A. K., Horstjann, M., East-<lb/>wood, M., Leifer, I., Vigil, S. A., Krings, T., Borchardt, J., Buch-<lb/>witz, M., Fladeland, M. M., Burrows, J. P., and Bovensmann, <lb/>H.: Methane emissions from a Californian landfill, determined <lb/>from airborne remote sensing and in situ measurements, At-<lb/>mos. Meas. Tech., 10, 3429-3452, https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-<lb/>10-3429-2017, 2017. <lb/>Kumar, P., Broquet, G., Yver-Kwok, C., Laurent, O., Gichuki, S., <lb/>Caldow, C., Cropley, F., Lauvaux, T., Ramonet, M., Berthe, G., <lb/>Martin, F., Duclaux, O., Juery, C., Bouchet, C., and Ciais, P.: <lb/>Mobile atmospheric measurements and local-scale inverse es-<lb/>timation of the location and rates of brief CH 4 and CO 2 re-<lb/>leases from point sources, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 14, 5987-6003, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-14-5987-2021, 2021. <lb/>Kumar, P., Broquet, G., Caldow, C., Laurent, O., Gichuki, S., Crop-<lb/>ley, F., Yver-Kwok, C., Fontanier, B., Lauvaux, T., Ramonet, M., <lb/>Shah, A., Berthe, G., Martin, F., Duclaux, O., Juery, C., Bouchet, <lb/>C., Pitt, J., and Ciais, P.: Near-field atmospheric inversions for the <lb/>localization and quantification of controlled methane releases us-<lb/>ing stationary and mobile measurements, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., <lb/>148, 1886-1912, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.4283, 2022. <lb/>Lando, A. T., Nakayama, H., and Shimaoka, T.: Ap-<lb/>plication of portable gas detector in point and scan-<lb/>ning method to estimate spatial distribution of methane <lb/>emission in landfill, Waste Manage., 59, 255-266, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2016.10.033, 2017. <lb/>Lan, X., Thoning, K. W., and Dlugokencky, E. J.: Trends in <lb/>globally-averaged CH 4 , N 2 O, and SF 6 , Version 2024-01, NOAA <lb/>Global Monitoring Laboratory, https://doi.org/10.15138/P8XG-<lb/>AA10, 2022. <lb/>Lohila, A., Laurila, T., Tuovinen, J. P., Aurela, M., Hatakka, J., <lb/>Thum, T., Pihlatie, M., Rinne, J., and Vesala, T.: Micrometeo-<lb/>rological measurements of methane and carbon dioxide fluxes <lb/>at a municipal landfill, Environ. Sci. Technol., 41, 2717-2722, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/es061631h, 2007. <lb/>Maasakkers, J. D., Varon, D. J., Elfarsdóttir, A., McKeever, J., <lb/>Jervis, D., Mahapatra, G., Pandey, S., Lorente, A., Borsdorff, <lb/>T., Foorthuis, L. R., Schuit, B. J., Tol, P., van Kempen, T. <lb/>A., van Hees, R., and Aben, I.: Using satellites to uncover <lb/>large methane emissions from landfills, Sci. Adv., 8, eabn9683, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abn9683, 2022. <lb/>Mønster, J., Samuelsson, J., Kjeldsen, P., and Scheutz, C.: Quantifi-<lb/>cation of methane emissions from 15 Danish landfills using the <lb/>mobile tracer dispersion method, Waste Manage., 35, 177-186, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.WASMAN.2014.09.006, 2015. <lb/>Mønster, J., Kjeldsen, P., and Scheutz, C.: Methodolo-<lb/>gies for measuring fugitive methane emissions from <lb/>landfills -A review, Waste Manage., 87, 835-859, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.12.047, 2019. <lb/>Nisbet, E. G., Manning, M. R., Dlugokencky, E. J., Fisher, R. <lb/>E., Lowry, D., Michel, S. E., Myhre, C. L., Platt, S. M., <lb/>Allen, G., Bousquet, P., Brownlow, R., Cain, M., France, J. <lb/>L., Hermansen, O., Hossaini, R., Jones, A. E., Levin, I., Man-<lb/>ning, A. C., Myhre, G., Pyle, J. A., Vaughn, B. H., War-<lb/>wick, N. J., and White, J. W. C.: Very Strong Atmospheric <lb/>Methane Growth in the 4 Years 2014-2017: Implications for <lb/>the Paris Agreement, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 33, 318-342, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GB006009, 2019. <lb/>Nisbet, E. G., Fisher, R. E., Lowry, D., France, J. L., Allen, G., <lb/>Bakkaloglu, S., Broderick, T. J., Cain, M., Coleman, M., Fernan-<lb/>dez, J., Forster, G., Griffiths, P. T., Iverach, C. P., Kelly, B. F. J., <lb/>Manning, M. R., Nisbet-Jones, P. B. R., Pyle, J. A., Townsend-<lb/>Small, A., al-Shalaan, A., Warwick, N., and Zazzeri, G.: Methane <lb/>Mitigation: Methods to Reduce Emissions, on the Path to <lb/>the Paris Agreement, Rev. Geophys., 58, e2019RG000675, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2019RG000675, 2020. <lb/>Poulsen, T. G., Christophersen, M., Moldrup, P., and Kjeldsen, P.: <lb/>Relating landfill gas emissions to atmospheric pressure using nu-<lb/>merical modelling and state-space analysis, Waste Manage. Res., <lb/>21, 356-366, https://doi.org/10.1177/0734242x0302100408, <lb/>2003. <lb/>Rachor, I. M., Gebert, J., Gröngröft, A., and Pfeiffer, E. <lb/>M.: Variability of methane emissions from an old land-<lb/>fill over different time-scales, Eur. J. Soil Sci., 64, 16-26, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/ejss.12004, 2013. <lb/>Riddick, S. N., Hancock, B. R., Robinson, A. D., Connors, S., <lb/>Davies, S., Allen, G., Pitt, J., and Harris, N. R. P.: Development <lb/>of a low-maintenance measurement approach to continuously es-<lb/>timate methane emissions: A case study, Waste Manage., 73, <lb/>210-219, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2016.12.006, 2018. <lb/>Rigby, M., Prinn, R. G., Fraser, P. J., Simmonds, P. G., Lan-<lb/>genfelds, R. L., Huang, J., Cunnold, D. M., Steele, L. P., <lb/>Krummel, P. B., Weiss, R. F., O&apos;Doherty, S., Salameh, P. K., <lb/>Wang, H. J., Harth, C. M., Mühle, J., and Porter, L. W.: Re-<lb/>newed growth of atmospheric methane, Geophys. Res. Lett., 35, <lb/>L22805, https://doi.org/10.1029/2008GL036037, 2008. <lb/>Saunois, M., Bousquet, P., Poulter, B., Peregon, A., Ciais, P., <lb/>Canadell, J. G., Dlugokencky, E. J., Etiope, G., Bastviken, D., <lb/>Houweling, S., Janssens-Maenhout, G., Tubiello, F. N., Castaldi, <lb/>S., Jackson, R. B., Alexe, M., Arora, V. K., Beerling, D. J., Berga-<lb/>maschi, P., Blake, D. R., Brailsford, G., Brovkin, V., Bruhwiler, <lb/>L., Crevoisier, C., Crill, P., Covey, K., Curry, C., Frankenberg, C., <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/></note>

		<page>1250 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">P. Kumar et al.: Long-term quantification of landfill CH 4 emissions <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>Gedney, N., Höglund-Isaksson, L., Ishizawa, M., Ito, A., Joos, F., <lb/>Kim, H.-S., Kleinen, T., Krummel, P., Lamarque, J.-F., Langen-<lb/>felds, R., Locatelli, R., Machida, T., Maksyutov, S., McDonald, <lb/>K. C., Marshall, J., Melton, J. R., Morino, I., Naik, V., O&apos;Doherty, <lb/>S., Parmentier, F.-J. W., Patra, P. K., Peng, C., Peng, S., Peters, <lb/>G. P., Pison, I., Prigent, C., Prinn, R., Ramonet, M., Riley, W. <lb/>J., Saito, M., Santini, M., Schroeder, R., Simpson, I. J., Spahni, <lb/>R., Steele, P., Takizawa, A., Thornton, B. F., Tian, H., Tohjima, <lb/>Y., Viovy, N., Voulgarakis, A., van Weele, M., van der Werf, G. <lb/>R., Weiss, R., Wiedinmyer, C., Wilton, D. J., Wiltshire, A., Wor-<lb/>thy, D., Wunch, D., Xu, X., Yoshida, Y., Zhang, B., Zhang, Z., <lb/>and Zhu, Q.: The global methane budget 2000-2012, Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. Data, 8, 697-751, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-8-697-2016, <lb/>2016. <lb/>Saunois, M., Stavert, A. R., Poulter, B., Bousquet, P., Canadell, J. <lb/>G., Jackson, R. B., Raymond, P. A., Dlugokencky, E. J., Houwel-<lb/>ing, S., Patra, P. K., Ciais, P., Arora, V. K., Bastviken, D., Berga-<lb/>maschi, P., Blake, D. R., Brailsford, G., Bruhwiler, L., Carl-<lb/>son, K. M., Carrol, M., Castaldi, S., Chandra, N., Crevoisier, C., <lb/>Crill, P. M., Covey, K., Curry, C. L., Etiope, G., Frankenberg, <lb/>C., Gedney, N., Hegglin, M. I., Höglund-Isaksson, L., Hugelius, <lb/>G., Ishizawa, M., Ito, A., Janssens-Maenhout, G., Jensen, K. <lb/>M., Joos, F., Kleinen, T., Krummel, P. B., Langenfelds, R. L., <lb/>Laruelle, G. G., Liu, L., Machida, T., Maksyutov, S., McDon-<lb/>ald, K. C., McNorton, J., Miller, P. A., Melton, J. R., Morino, <lb/>I., Müller, J., Murguia-Flores, F., Naik, V., Niwa, Y., Noce, S., <lb/>O&apos;Doherty, S., Parker, R. J., Peng, C., Peng, S., Peters, G. P., <lb/>Prigent, C., Prinn, R., Ramonet, M., Regnier, P., Riley, W. J., <lb/>Rosentreter, J. A., Segers, A., Simpson, I. J., Shi, H., Smith, S. <lb/>J., Steele, L. P., Thornton, B. F., Tian, H., Tohjima, Y., Tubiello, <lb/>F. N., Tsuruta, A., Viovy, N., Voulgarakis, A., Weber, T. S., <lb/>van Weele, M., van der Werf, G. R., Weiss, R. F., Worthy, D., <lb/>Wunch, D., Yin, Y., Yoshida, Y., Zhang, W., Zhang, Z., Zhao, <lb/>Y., Zheng, B., Zhu, Q., Zhu, Q., and Zhuang, Q.: The Global <lb/>Methane Budget 2000-2017, Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 12, 1561-<lb/>1623, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-12-1561-2020, 2020. <lb/>Scheutz, C., Kjeldsen, P., Bogner, J. E., de Visscher, A., Gebert, <lb/>J., Hilger, H. A., Huber-Humer, M., and Spokas, K.: Micro-<lb/>bial methane oxidation processes and technologies for mitiga-<lb/>tion of landfill gas emissions, Waste Manage. Res., 27, 409-455, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/0734242X09339325, 2009. <lb/>Scheutz, C., Samuelsson, J., Fredenslund, A. M., and Kjeldsen, P.: <lb/>Quantification of multiple methane emission sources at landfills <lb/>using a double tracer technique, Waste Manage., 31, 1009-1017, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2011.01.015, 2011. <lb/>Shams, S., Sahu, J. N., Rahman, S. M. S., and Ahsan, A.: <lb/>Sustainable waste management policy in Bangladesh for re-<lb/>duction of greenhouse gases, Sustain. Cities Soc., 33, 18-26, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scs.2017.05.008, 2017. <lb/>Shindell, D., Kuylenstierna, J. C. I., Vignati, E., van Dingenen, <lb/>R., Amann, M., Klimont, Z., Anenberg, S. C., Muller, N., <lb/>Janssens-Maenhout, G., Raes, F., Schwartz, J., Faluvegi, G., <lb/>Pozzoli, L., Kupiainen, K., Höglund-Isaksson, L., Emberson, <lb/>L., Streets, D., Ramanathan, V., Hicks, K., Oanh, N. T. K., <lb/>Milly, G., Williams, M., Demkine, V., and Fowler, D.: Si-<lb/>multaneously mitigating near-term climate change and improv-<lb/>ing human health and food security, Science, 335, 183-189, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1210026, 2012. <lb/>Sonderfeld, H., Bösch, H., Jeanjean, A. P. R., Riddick, S. N., Allen, <lb/>G., Ars, S., Davies, S., Harris, N., Humpage, N., Leigh, R., <lb/>and Pitt, J.: CH 4 emission estimates from an active landfill site <lb/>inferred from a combined approach of CFD modelling and in <lb/>situ FTIR measurements, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 10, 3931-3946, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-10-3931-2017, 2017. <lb/>Themelis, N. J. and Ulloa, P. A.: Methane genera-<lb/>tion in landfills, Renew. Energ., 32, 1243-1257, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.renene.2006.04.020, 2007. <lb/>Tratt, D. M., Buckland, K. N., Hall, J. L., Johnson, P. D., <lb/>Keim, E. R., Leifer, I., Westberg, K., and Young, S. J.: <lb/>Airborne visualization and quantification of discrete methane <lb/>sources in the environment, Remote Sens. Environ., 154, 74-88, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2014.08.011, 2014. <lb/>Tu, Q., Hase, F., Schneider, M., García, O., Blumenstock, T., Bors-<lb/>dorff, T., Frey, M., Khosrawi, F., Lorente, A., Alberti, C., Bus-<lb/>tos, J. J., Butz, A., Carreño, V., Cuevas, E., Curcoll, R., Diek-<lb/>mann, C. J., Dubravica, D., Ertl, B., Estruch, C., León-Luis, S. <lb/>F., Marrero, C., Morgui, J.-A., Ramos, R., Scharun, C., Schnei-<lb/>der, C., Sepúlveda, E., Toledano, C., and Torres, C.: Quantifica-<lb/>tion of CH4 emissions from waste disposal sites near the city <lb/>of Madrid using ground-and space-based observations of COC-<lb/>CON, TROPOMI and IASI, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 22, 295-317, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-22-295-2022, 2022. <lb/>Turner, A. J., Frankenberg, C., and Kort, E. A.: Interpreting contem-<lb/>porary trends in atmospheric methane, P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, <lb/>116, 2805-2813, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1814297116, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Turner, D. B.: Workbook of atmospheric dispersion estimates, Of-<lb/>fice of Air Program Pub. No. AP-26, Environmental Protection <lb/>Agency, USA, 1970. <lb/>Vogel, F.: Waste Miti 2 -WP3 Quick-Scan Service -Assessment of <lb/>Fugitive Emissions from Landfill Operations in France, LSCE -<lb/>Université de Versailles Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines, 2016. <lb/>Xu, L., Lin, X., Amen, J., Welding, K., and McDermitt, <lb/>D.: Impact of changes in barometric pressure on landfill <lb/>methane emission, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 28, 679-695, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2013GB004571, 2014. <lb/>Yacovitch, T. I., Neininger, B., Herndon, S. C., van der Gon, <lb/>H. D., Jonkers, S., Hulskotte, J., Roscioli, J. R., and Zavala-<lb/>Araiza, D.: Methane emissions in the Netherlands: The Gronin-<lb/>gen field, Elementa: Science of the Anthropocene, 6, 57, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1525/elementa.308, 2018. <lb/>Yver Kwok, C., Laurent, O., Guemri, A., Philippon, C., Wastine, <lb/>B., Rella, C. W., Vuillemin, C., Truong, F., Delmotte, M., <lb/>Kazan, V., Darding, M., Lebègue, B., Kaiser, C., Xueref-<lb/>Rémy, I., and Ramonet, M.: Comprehensive laboratory and field <lb/>testing of cavity ring-down spectroscopy analyzers measuring <lb/>H 2 O, CO 2 , CH 4 and CO, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 8, 3867-3892, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-8-3867-2015, 2015. <lb/>Zazzeri, G., Lowry, D., Fisher, R. E., France, J. L., Lanoisellé, M., <lb/>and Nisbet, E. G.: Plume mapping and isotopic characterisation <lb/>of anthropogenic methane sources, Atmos. Environ., 110, 151-<lb/>162, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2015.03.029, 2015. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">Atmos. Meas. Tech., 17, 1229-1250, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-17-1229-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>