<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-21T14:38:51.514Z">11/21/2025 2:38:51 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.5194_bg-21-4533-2024</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication"/>
      <idno type="DOI"/>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-21T14:38:40.615977Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-21T14:38:40.615977Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<front>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Research article <lb/>Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a <lb/>large loss of tundra due to climate warming <lb/>Fredrik Lagergren 1 , Robert G. Björk 2,3 , Camilla Andersson 4 , Danijel Belušić 4,5 , Mats P. Björkman 2,3,a , <lb/>Erik Kjellström 4 , Petter Lind 4 , David Lindstedt 4 , Tinja Olenius 4 , Håkan Pleijel 6 , Gunhild Rosqvist 7 , and <lb/>Paul A. Miller 1 <lb/>1 Department of Physical Geography and Ecosystem Science, Lund University, Lund, 223 62, Sweden <lb/>2 Department of Earth Sciences, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden <lb/>3 Gothenburg Global Biodiversity Centre, Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden <lb/>4 Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute, Norrköping, 601 76, Sweden <lb/>5 Department of Geophysics, Faculty of Science, University of Zagreb, Zagreb, 10 000, Croatia <lb/>6 Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden <lb/>7 Department of Physical Geography, Stockholm University, Stockholm, 106 91, Sweden <lb/>a now at: Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, 405 30, Sweden <lb/>Correspondence: Fredrik Lagergren (fredrik.lagergren@nateko.lu.se) <lb/>Received: 30 August 2023 -Discussion started: 12 September 2023 <lb/>Revised: 11 January 2024 -Accepted: 19 January 2024 -Published: 5 March 2024 <lb/>Abstract. The Fennoscandian boreal and mountain regions <lb/>harbour a wide range of vegetation types, from boreal forest <lb/>to high alpine tundra and barren soils. The area is facing a <lb/>rise in air temperature above the global average and changes <lb/>in temperature and precipitation patterns. This is expected to <lb/>alter the Fennoscandian vegetation composition and change <lb/>the conditions for areal land use such as forestry, tourism <lb/>and reindeer husbandry. In this study we used a unique high-<lb/>resolution (3 km) climate scenario with considerable warm-<lb/>ing resulting from strongly increasing carbon dioxide emis-<lb/>sions to investigate how climate change can alter the veg-<lb/>etation composition, biodiversity and availability of suitable <lb/>reindeer forage. Using a dynamical vegetation model, includ-<lb/>ing a new implementation of potential reindeer grazing, re-<lb/>sulted in simulated vegetation maps of unprecedented high <lb/>resolution for such a long time period and spatial extent. <lb/>The results were evaluated at the local scale using vegeta-<lb/>tion inventories and for the whole area against satellite-based <lb/>vegetation maps. A deeper analysis of vegetation shifts re-<lb/>lated to statistics of threatened species was performed in <lb/>six &quot;hotspot&quot; areas containing records of rare and threat-<lb/>ened species. In this high-emission scenario, the simulations <lb/>show dramatic shifts in the vegetation composition, acceler-<lb/>ating at the end of the century. Alarmingly, the results sug-<lb/>gest the southern mountain alpine region in Sweden will be <lb/>completely covered by forests at the end of the 21st century, <lb/>making preservation of many rare and threatened species <lb/>impossible. In the northern alpine regions, most vegetation <lb/>types will persist but shift to higher elevations with reduced <lb/>areal extent, endangering vulnerable species. Simulated po-<lb/>tential for reindeer grazing indicates latitudinal differences, <lb/>with higher potential in the south in the current climate. In <lb/>the future these differences will diminish, as the potentials <lb/>will increase in the north, especially for the summer grazing <lb/>grounds. These combined results suggest significant shifts in <lb/>vegetation composition over the present century for this sce-<lb/>nario, with large implications for nature conservation, rein-<lb/>deer husbandry and forestry. <lb/></front>

	<body>1 Introduction <lb/>High-latitude regions harbour vast areas of relatively intact <lb/>ecosystems, harbouring species of great ecological and so-<lb/>cietal significance (Dobrowski et al., 2021). These north-<lb/>ern ecosystems are predicted to be more vulnerable to cli-<lb/>mate change than most other terrestrial biomes (Hickler et <lb/>al., 2012; IPCC, 2014). For each degree of global average <lb/></body>

	<front>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></front>

	<page>1094 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>temperature increase, the observed increase in Fennoscan-<lb/>dia has been estimated to be 2-3°(Rantanen et al., 2022), <lb/>and this relationship persists in future predictions (Ono et al., <lb/>2022). This temperature increase has strongly affected north-<lb/>ern ecosystems, resulting in changing vegetation patterns in <lb/>the Arctic (Elmendorf et al., 2012; Pearson et al., 2013), an <lb/>overall taller plant community (Bjorkman et al., 2018) and <lb/>increases in biomass (Hudson and Henry, 2009). The occur-<lb/>rence and distribution of shrubs have also been observed to <lb/>increase, both in high-latitude and high-altitude regions, as a <lb/>result of the warmer climate (Elmendorf et al., 2012; Myers-<lb/>Smith et al., 2011; Sturm et al., 2001). The distance species <lb/>have to migrate to keep up with climate change is, however, <lb/>shorter in alpine and oroarctic regions than in flat boreal and <lb/>arctic landscapes (Feeley et al., 2011). As the boreal forest <lb/>covers a wide area, its species composition and ability to <lb/>provide ecosystem services could undergo large shifts, e.g. <lb/>as a response to different disturbance patterns and hydrology <lb/>changes (Venäläinen et al., 2020), even if its geographical <lb/>extent is not changed. Consequences of future shifts in areal <lb/>extent of vegetation zones, which may not be proportional <lb/>to their current distributions, include reduced space of many <lb/>habitats (Pauli and Halloy, 2019) and increased pressure on <lb/>many species (Kuuluvainen and Gauthier, 2018). <lb/>In Fennoscandia, the herding of semi-domesticated rein-<lb/>deer is important for shaping this landscape, a practice which <lb/>utilizes the land from the coastal areas and the boreal forest in <lb/>winter up to the tundra in summer (Käyhkö and Horstkotte, <lb/>2017). Reindeer grazing directly affects the vegetation com-<lb/>position and diversity, both in the mountains (Olofsson et <lb/>al., 2001; Sundqvist et al., 2019; Vowles et al., 2017) and <lb/>forested regions (Kumpula et al., 2014). In summer, reindeer <lb/>have a mixed diet of shrub leaves, forbs, herbs, sedges, grass <lb/>and fungal fruit bodies, and reindeer forage has been shown <lb/>to reduce deciduous shrub expansion (e.g. Olofsson et al., <lb/>2001, 2009; Sundqvist et al., 2019; Vowles et al., 2017). In <lb/>winter, reindeer mainly eat ground and tree lichens, which <lb/>decreases ground lichen cover (Kumpula et al., 2014). How-<lb/>ever, reindeer husbandry is currently experiencing increased <lb/>pressure from human activities, such as forestry practices and <lb/>tourism (Fohringer et al., 2021; Kumpula et al., 2014; Sand-<lb/>ström et al., 2016), affecting 85 % of the herding area (Stoes-<lb/>sel et al., 2022). In addition, there are implications resulting <lb/>from climate change, such as difficult snow conditions mak-<lb/>ing winter forage hard (Rasmus et al., 2022; Rosqvist et al., <lb/>2021) and hot dry summers increasing heat stress (Käyhkö <lb/>and Horstkotte, 2017). Climate change is increasing the pres-<lb/>sure on both ecosystems and societies in these areas, a pres-<lb/>sure that will increase in coming decades (Constable et al., <lb/>2022). Reindeer grazing and browsing can to some degree <lb/>hold back the rate of treeline advancement and tundra shrubi-<lb/>fication (Stark et al., 2023) but will not completely stop it. A <lb/>future less open landscape will have a large impact on how <lb/>reindeer graze and dwell in the landscape and on the Sami <lb/>culture (Stark et al., 2023), but how that might affect the size <lb/>of a sustainable reindeer population is hard to predict. <lb/>Projections of future impacts of climate change in high-<lb/>latitude ecosystems can be made upon the implementation of <lb/>understanding arising from empirical studies (e.g. Bjorkman <lb/>et al., 2020; Myers-Smith et al., 2011) and remote sensing <lb/>(e.g. Callaghan et al., 2022) into models such as dynami-<lb/>cal vegetation models (DVMs) using climate model data as <lb/>input. The typical cell size of a regional climate model (of <lb/>the order of 10-50 km) often contains land surface types <lb/>ranging from forest to bare rock or glaciers in mountain-<lb/>ous areas. This information does not capture all local vari-<lb/>ation, especially in areas of complex terrain where altitudi-<lb/>nal differences can be strongly underestimated (Lind et al., <lb/>2020). Also, while representing most meteorological pro-<lb/>cesses, some are only crudely implemented at such relatively <lb/>coarse resolution in modelling studies (Lind et al., 2020). <lb/>In recent years, one of these DVMs, LPJ-GUESS, has been <lb/>adapted to the boreal and arctic regions (Miller and Smith, <lb/>2012; Wolf et al., 2008; Yu et al., 2017) and used with very <lb/>highly resolved climate data (e.g. 50 × 50 m) at a local scale <lb/>in sub-arctic Scandinavia (Gustafson et al., 2021; Tang et al., <lb/>2015). So far, however, no high-resolution (&lt; 10 km) study <lb/>of environmental change and its impact on vegetation cover-<lb/>ing the entire Fennoscandian boreal and oroarctic region has <lb/>been conducted. <lb/>Recently the first ever climate model projections at 3 km <lb/>grid spacing were completed for the entire Fennoscandian re-<lb/>gion (Lind et al., 2020, 2023). Results from such kilometre-<lb/>scale simulations (1-4 km compared to previous coarser res-<lb/>olution &gt; 10 km) offer an unprecedented insight into weather <lb/>and climate processes at high resolution, which is particu-<lb/>larly important in complex terrain. In addition, it is impor-<lb/>tant to understand how this improved weather and climate in-<lb/>sights might affect vegetation dynamics and for that a DVM <lb/>is needed. Thus, we here use these unique kilometre-scale <lb/>climate model projections for the high-emission RCP8.5 sce-<lb/>nario (Lind et al., 2023) and the state-of-the-art DVM, LPJ-<lb/>GUESS (Lindeskog et al., 2021; Smith et al., 2001, 2014), <lb/>including a new module of reindeer grazing, to investigate <lb/>the vegetation response to climate and environmental change <lb/>in the Fennoscandian boreal and mountain regions used for <lb/>reindeer herding. The results are validated against satellite <lb/>products and field data gathered in the study region. Fur-<lb/>thermore, we use consistent, high-resolution climate and ni-<lb/>trogen deposition scenarios to evaluate potential future veg-<lb/>etation changes in the region, with a special emphasis on <lb/>reindeer food supply and vegetation trends in &quot;hotspot&quot; ar-<lb/>eas with high biodiversity and conservation values. Since the <lb/>only available climate projection at this resolution is a high-<lb/>emission scenario, the simulated state at the end of the cen-<lb/>tury will provide a message to society of what to expect and <lb/>plan for if emissions continue to increase. We hypothesize <lb/>that this state will show extensive changes that will present <lb/>challenges for forestry, reindeer herding, tourism and nature <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1095 <lb/></page>

	<body>conservation, as the temperature increase is high in such a <lb/>scenario. <lb/>2 Material and methods <lb/>2.1 Study area <lb/>The study was restricted to the Fennoscandian mountain <lb/>range and the adjacent boreal areas used for reindeer herding <lb/>(Fig. 1), with a focus on ecosystems in Sweden. This region <lb/>is located between 58 and 71°N, spanning altitudes from sea <lb/>level to 2469 m a.s.l. (Galdhøpiggen, Norway), and is charac-<lb/>terized by continental to sub-oceanic climate (Oksanen and <lb/>Virtanen, 1995). Boreal forest dominates from the coast to-<lb/>wards the mountains up to latitude 68-69°N. Above the bo-<lb/>real forest there is a zone of mountain birch forest which <lb/>normally has a vertical distribution of ca. 200 m. The tree-<lb/>line, formed by mountain birch, is in Sweden at an altitude of <lb/>more than 1100 m in the south and decreases with latitude to <lb/>600 m in the north (Kullman, 2016). Above the treeline fol-<lb/>lows tundra with decreasing levels of vegetation height and <lb/>coverage (from shrub to barren tundra) and finally bare rocks <lb/>and snowfields. For a more detailed assessment of simulated <lb/>changes, six hotspot areas (90 × 90 km) in the larger domain <lb/>were selected to represent different vegetation zones with a <lb/>high species richness and large conservation values, from the <lb/>boreal forest to the high alpine tundra, and covering the en-<lb/>tire Swedish mountain range (Table 1, Fig. 1, Fig. S1 in the <lb/>Supplement). <lb/>2.2 Dynamical vegetation and ecosystem model <lb/>The dynamical vegetation and ecosystem model LPJ-GUESS <lb/>(v4.1, Nord et al., 2021) was used to simulate vegetation <lb/>change in the region. Detailed descriptions of the develop-<lb/>ment stages involve the first version (Smith et al., 2001), <lb/>arctic development (Miller and Smith, 2012; Wolf et al., <lb/>2008), N cycle (Smith et al., 2014), land cover (Lindeskog <lb/>et al., 2021) and further arctic implementations (Gustafson et <lb/>al., 2021). The model simulates the development of cohorts, <lb/>belonging to different plant functional types (PFTs), when <lb/>competing for light, nitrogen and water in replicate patches <lb/>(here set to 15 patches per simulated climate grid cell). Each <lb/>patch represents an area of ca. 1000 m 2 . The model includes <lb/>detailed process descriptions related to the cycling of wa-<lb/>ter (e.g. transpiration, evaporation, and snow and soil wa-<lb/>ter dynamics), carbon (e.g. photosynthesis, respiration, fire <lb/>and allocation of biomass) and nitrogen (e.g. nitrification and <lb/>restriction of photosynthesis) and is driven by temperature, <lb/>radiation, relative humidity, wind speed, CO 2 concentration <lb/>and nitrogen deposition data. The processes are calculated <lb/>at the cohort level except for those that take place in the soil. <lb/>The PFTs are described by parameters related to growth form <lb/>(tree, shrub or herbaceous), allocation, allometry, phenology, <lb/>life history, shade tolerance, and response to environmen-<lb/>tal and bioclimatic conditions. Patch-destroying disturbances <lb/>representing e.g. devastating pests or wind storms occur ran-<lb/>domly in each patch (the default v4.1 return time of 150 years <lb/>was used in the presented simulations). Separately, fire dis-<lb/>turbance simulated with the BLAZE module (Molinari et al., <lb/>2021) was applied. A simulation starts after a spin-up period <lb/>(set to 600 years) over which a detrended dataset compris-<lb/>ing the first 30 years of historical climate data is repeated to <lb/>attain a balance between the vegetation and the climate. <lb/>2.2.1 Plant functional types <lb/>In the present study, an expanded set of PFTs were used, <lb/>which includes high-latitude PFTs such as shrubs, with sep-<lb/>arate sets for mineral and wetland soils (Table 2). In each <lb/>grid cell, the simulations on mineral and wetland soils are <lb/>independent of each other. For fractions of land classified <lb/>as peatland, we use a version of the model with peatland <lb/>integration (Wania et al., 2009a, b), which includes a wet-<lb/>land hydrology module and wetland PFTs (Miller and Smith, <lb/>2012; Wolf et al., 2008; Zhang et al., 2013). The fractions <lb/>of mineral soil and wetland were prescribed and constant <lb/>over the simulation period based on the PEATMAP prod-<lb/>uct at a 0.125°(14 km in S-N direction and 5-7 km in W-<lb/>E direction depending on latitude within the assessed area) <lb/>resolution (Xu et al., 2018). Weighted averages of model re-<lb/>sults were calculated based on these fractions. For the shade-<lb/>intolerant broadleaf summergreen tree (IBS) PFT, some pa-<lb/>rameters were changed according to Gustafson et al. (2021) <lb/>in an application for Abisko, Sweden. Their revision was <lb/>made to reflect the fact that this global PFT in Fennoscan-<lb/>dia mainly represents mountain birch (Betula pubescens ssp. <lb/>tortuosa). Details of the IBS parameterization can be found <lb/>in Sect. S2 in the Supplement. <lb/>2.2.2 Reindeer grazing, browsing and trampling <lb/>To simulate the effect of reindeer grazing, browsing and <lb/>trampling, a new module was added to the model. Graz-<lb/>ing/browsing was simulated by removing a fraction of leaf <lb/>biomass. The model only includes stem and leaf as above-<lb/>ground compartments. We note however that browsing rein-<lb/>deer also consume tops, twigs and branch biomass, which <lb/>means that we may underestimate the effect on vegetation, <lb/>but to keep the model uncomplicated this simplification was <lb/>applied. Trampling was simulated by killing a fraction of the <lb/>individuals in a cohort or, in the case of herbaceous PFTs, <lb/>a fraction of total biomass. The grazing/browsing and tram-<lb/>pling levels were based on a constant intensity of herbivory. <lb/>For a specific PFT, the grazing/browsing was determined by a <lb/>preference value obtained from extensive observations of the <lb/>feeding preferences of semi-domesticated reindeer in Canada <lb/>(Denryter et al., 2017) and if the cohort&apos;s canopy height was <lb/>within reach of reindeer. The sensitivity to trampling was <lb/>based on the vegetation response in an artificial trampling <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1096 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 1. (a) The study area (shown as altitude), the six focus hotspot areas (squares and black text; see Fig. S1 for detailed maps) and the <lb/>four grazing exclosure sites (purple dots and text). (b) Map of grazing areas used for the semi-domesticated reindeer during different seasons <lb/>in Norway, Sweden and Finland (from Käyhkö and Horstkotte, 2017, used with permission). <lb/>Table 1. Description of the six hotspots. Maps of the areas are shown in Fig. S1. <lb/>Name <lb/>Coordinates Type <lb/>Protected area <lb/>Description <lb/>Abisko <lb/>68°01 N, <lb/>18°46 E <lb/>Mountain <lb/>Abisko National Park, <lb/>established 1909 <lb/>Including the highest mountains (2097 m) <lb/>in Sweden <lb/>Vindeln <lb/>65°49 N, <lb/>16°29 E <lb/>Mountain <lb/>Vindelfjällen Nature <lb/>Reserve, established 1974 <lb/>Including mountains reaching 1768 m <lb/>Helags <lb/>62°58 N, <lb/>13°06 E <lb/>Mountain <lb/>Vålådalen Nature Reserve, <lb/>established 1988 <lb/>Including the Helags mountain (1797 m) <lb/>Fulu <lb/>61°47 N, <lb/>13°17 E <lb/>Mountain <lb/>Fulufjället National Park, <lb/>established 1973 <lb/>At the southernmost part of the Scandes moun-<lb/>tains (1196 m, Sömlinghågna) in Sweden <lb/>Muddus <lb/>66°43 N, <lb/>20°17 E <lb/>Forest <lb/>Muddus National Park, <lb/>established 1942 <lb/>Mostly boreal forest with extensive wetlands <lb/>Björnlandet 64°07 N, <lb/>18°01 E <lb/>Forest <lb/>Björnlandet National Park, <lb/>established 1991 <lb/>Boreal forest with some wetlands <lb/>experiment (Egelkraut et al., 2020). All the consumed car-<lb/>bon in the leaves was treated as harvested but only a frac-<lb/>tion of the leaf nitrogen was. The other fraction of the con-<lb/>sumed N was added to the cohort&apos;s leaf N pool, which re-<lb/>flects the assumption that N leaving the herbivore as urine is <lb/>rapidly taken up by the plants (Barthelemy et al., 2018). A <lb/>detailed description of the module and its parameter values <lb/>is given in Sect. S3. From this module, the resulting output <lb/>of consumed C biomass was used as an indicator of potential <lb/>reindeer food consumption. In the presented simulations, the <lb/>simulated grazing, browsing and trampling in a patch were <lb/>set to have a return time of 3 years (see Sect. S3 for a moti-<lb/>vation), a grazing intensity of 0.1 (fraction per year), a max <lb/>height of 2.5 m and 35 % of browsed nitrogen (Ferraro et al., <lb/>2022; McEwan and Whitehead, 1970) removed from the har-<lb/>vest pool. <lb/>2.3 Model input data: climate <lb/>The regional climate modelling system HCLIM38 (Belušiae <lb/>et al., 2020) was used for downscaling the RCP8.5 sce-<lb/>nario simulation from the global climate model EC-Earth <lb/>(Hazeleger et al., 2010, 2012). The climate scenario was first <lb/>downscaled to 12 km with HCLIM38-ALADIN (Belušiae <lb/>et al., 2020) for the 1985-2100 period and then further to <lb/>3 km with HCLIM38-AROME (Belušiae et al., 2020) for the <lb/>1985-2005, 2040-2060 and 2080-2100 periods (Lind et al., <lb/>2020, 2023). For computational reasons we wanted to restrict <lb/>the size of the complete 1985-2100 NetCDF climate files <lb/>to less than 32 GB per climate variable. Therefore, we made <lb/>adjustments to the original data, reducing it at the southern, <lb/>northern and western limits of mainland Norway as well as <lb/>at an eastern border through the north of Finland (Fig. 1a). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1097 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 2. Plant functional types in the LPJ-GUESS simulations. The last six PFTs were used for the wetland simulation and the rest for <lb/>mineral soils. <lb/>PFT <lb/>Long name <lb/>Typically represented species <lb/>BNE <lb/>Boreal needleleaf evergreen tree, shade tolerant <lb/>Picea abies <lb/>BINE <lb/>Boreal needleleaf evergreen tree, shade intolerant <lb/>Pinus sylvestris <lb/>IBS <lb/>Shade-intolerant broadleaf summergreen tree <lb/>Betula pubescens ssp. tortuosa <lb/>TeBS <lb/>Shade-tolerant temperate broadleaf summergreen tree <lb/>Fagus, Quercus, Fraxinus spp. <lb/>C3G <lb/>Cool (C 3 ) grass <lb/>Poaceae <lb/>HSE <lb/>Tall shrub (up to 2 m), evergreen <lb/>Juniperus communis <lb/>HSS <lb/>Tall shrub (up to 2 m), summergreen <lb/>Alnus incana, Salix spp. e.g. S. phylifolia and <lb/>S. myrsinifolia, Betula nana <lb/>LSE <lb/>Low shrub (up to 0.5 m), evergreen <lb/>Vaccinium vitis-idaea, Empetrum spp. <lb/>LSS <lb/>Low shrub (up to 0.5 m), summergreen <lb/>Vaccinium myrtillus, small Salix spp. e.g. S. arbuscula <lb/>GRT <lb/>Graminoid and forb tundra <lb/>Grass, sedge and forb tundra species <lb/>EPDS <lb/>Evergreen prostrate (up to 0.2 m) dwarf shrubs <lb/>Vaccinium oxycoccos, Cassiope spp., Dryas octopetala, <lb/>Saxifraga spp. <lb/>SPDS <lb/>Summergreen prostrate (up to 0.2 m) dwarf shrubs <lb/>Dwarf Salix spp. e.g. S. herbacea, Arctostaphylos alpinus <lb/>CLM <lb/>Cushion forb, lichen and moss tundra <lb/>Saxifragaceae, Caryophyllaceae, Draba spp., lichens, mosses <lb/>pLSE <lb/>Peatland low shrub, evergreen <lb/>Vaccinium vitis-idaea, Cassiope spp. <lb/>pLSS <lb/>Peatland low shrub, summergreen <lb/>Vaccinium myrtillus, V. uliginosum, Salix hastata, <lb/>S. glauca <lb/>pCLM <lb/>Peatland cushion forb, lichen and moss tundra <lb/>Saxifragaceae, Caryophyllaceae, Papaver spp., Draba spp., <lb/>lichens, mosses <lb/>WetGRS <lb/>Cool, flood-tolerant (C 3 ) grass <lb/>Carex spp., Eriophorum spp., Juncus spp., Typha spp. <lb/>pmoss <lb/>Peatland moss <lb/>Spagnum e.g. S. fuscum <lb/>C3G_wet Peatland cool (C 3 ) grass <lb/>Poaceae <lb/>The year 1985 in the ALADIN 12 km data and the years <lb/>1985, 2040 and 2080 in the AROME 3 km data were spin-up <lb/>years. To test the robustness of the results, all climate vari-<lb/>ables used by the vegetation model were also compiled with-<lb/>out using the HCLIM spin-up years and tested on a subset <lb/>of 200 random grid cells. As there were no significant differ-<lb/>ences in the results, we present results based on climate data, <lb/>including the HCLIM spin-up years. <lb/>To fill the periods when only ALADIN data were avail-<lb/>able, we first produced datasets such that the four AROME <lb/>grid cells coinciding with a certain ALADIN grid cell <lb/>were filled with data from that ALADIN grid cell (termed <lb/>ALAatARO, 1985-2100). The periods with missing 3 km <lb/>AROME data were filled with the ALAatARO data using two <lb/>methods. <lb/>For precipitation, global radiation, relative humidity and <lb/>wind speed, linear regressions through the origin for the over-<lb/>lapping periods between AROME and ALAatARO data were <lb/>used. The relations were fitted separately by month, and, <lb/>specifically, data from 1985-2005 and 2040-2060 were used <lb/>to establish the relationships for the 2006-2039 period and <lb/>2040-2060 and 2080-2100 for the 2061-2079 period. The <lb/>relationships were then used to obtain 3 km data for the miss-<lb/>ing periods from ALAatARO data. <lb/>For daily, minimum and maximum temperatures a non-<lb/>parametric empirical quantile mapping (QUANT) bias <lb/>correction method (e.g. Osuch et al., 2017) was ap-<lb/>plied by month using daily temperature data for 21-<lb/>year periods. Two reference periods were used with <lb/>observed 1 × 1 km data from the Nordic Gridded Cli-<lb/>mate Dataset (NGCD; https://surfobs.climate.copernicus.eu/ <lb/>dataaccess/access_ngcd.php, last access: 26 February 2024) <lb/>that were aggregated to the AROME grid, 1985-2005 (used <lb/>for AROME grid data) and 1998-2018 (used for ALAatARO <lb/>grid data). In the quantile mapping, intervals of 1 % were ap-<lb/>plied and a smoothing was done using a running mean over <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1098 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>five intervals. Modelled and matching observed values were <lb/>linearly interpolated between the intervals. For consistency, <lb/>all calculations of quantiles were done for 21-year periods, <lb/>resulting in an overlapping period (1998-2005) for which <lb/>the AROME data were used. For the future, the difference <lb/>between the observed and scenario quantiles during the refer-<lb/>ence period was added to the matching quantile of future 21-<lb/>year periods. The future periods were 2040-2060 and 2080-<lb/>2100 for the AROME data and 2019-2039 and 2060-2080 <lb/>(2060 and 2080 were not used) for the ALAatARO data. <lb/>The RCP8.5 scenario used was the first dataset produced <lb/>at this high resolution for the entire region. It is a scenario <lb/>with strongly increasing emissions of greenhouse gases, but <lb/>the projection up to the mid-century is similar to lower-<lb/>emission scenarios (Meinshausen et al., 2011). In the resul-<lb/>tant daily air temperature data, the climate-change signal was <lb/>a 1.0-2.3 K increase in mean annual temperature from the <lb/>1991-2020 to the 2031-2060 periods of 30 years and a 2.5-<lb/>5.2 K increase from 1991-2020 to 2071-2100 (Fig. S4a-b). <lb/>For annual precipitation the relative change was -2.3 % to <lb/>23.1 % for 2031-2060 and -0.9 % to 50.1 % for 2071-2100 <lb/>(Fig. S4c-d). <lb/>2.4 Model input data: soil texture, atmospheric <lb/>nitrogen deposition and CO 2 <lb/>Soil texture data (clay and sand fraction) at 3 km resolution <lb/>were taken from SURFEX (Masson et al., 2013), the land <lb/>surface model of AROME, ensuring consistency with LPJ-<lb/>GUESS. These data originate from FAO soil texture data at <lb/>0.0833°(9 km in the S-N direction and 3-5 km in W-E) res-<lb/>olution (https://data.apps.fao.org/map/catalog/static/search? <lb/>keyword=DSMW, last access: 26 February 2024). <lb/>Nitrogen deposition at monthly temporal resolution was <lb/>used as input to LPJ-GUESS. The input was based on <lb/>two model simulations (MATCH-BIODIV and MATCH-<lb/>ECLAIRE) with the Multi-scale Atmospheric Transport and <lb/>Chemistry (MATCH; Andersson et al., 2015, 2007; Robert-<lb/>son et al., 1999) model. MATCH-BIODIV (Andersson et al., <lb/>2024; Eichler et al., 2023) was forced by the climate simula-<lb/>tion ALADIN at 12 km and anthropogenic air pollution emis-<lb/>sions from ECLIPSE V6b (Höglund-Isaksson et al., 2020). <lb/>This dataset (https://previous.iiasa.ac.at/web/home/research/ <lb/>researchPrograms/air/ECLIPSEv6b.html, last access: Febru-<lb/>ary 2020) has a resolution of 12 km and covers the 1987-<lb/>2051 period. MATCH-ECLAIRE (Engardt et al., 2017) was <lb/>constructed at 50 km resolution for 1900-2050, based on cur-<lb/>rent climate and varying anthropogenic air pollutant emis-<lb/>sions (ECLIPSE V4a, Lamarque et al., 2010). <lb/>MATCH-ECLAIRE was used to obtain 12 km resolution <lb/>nitrogen deposition fields for the 1900-1986 time period. <lb/>This was done by establishing a linear relationship through <lb/>zero for the overlapping period for each MATCH-BIODIV <lb/>and MATCH-ECLAIRE grid cell and subsequently applying <lb/>it to downscale the 50 km data for the 1900-1986 period. Af-<lb/>ter 2051, the 0.5°(56 km in S-N and 18-29 km in W-E) res-<lb/>olution Lamarque et al. (2011) dataset was used, which is <lb/>standard for LPJ-GUESS. A sensitivity test for a selection <lb/>of grid cells showed very minor differences when comparing <lb/>modelling results for simulations using the different resolu-<lb/>tion of N deposition data (results not shown), from which we <lb/>concluded that this simplification was justified. <lb/>The future trend in nitrogen deposition is similar for <lb/>MATCH-BIODIV and MATCH-ECLAIRE, i.e. declining <lb/>until mid-century. The modelled total deposition in the Scan-<lb/>dinavian mountain area is dominated by oxidized nitrogen, <lb/>which exhibits a clear decline, while reduced nitrogen de-<lb/>position levels off at around 2020 and after that even in-<lb/>creases slightly for MATCH-BIODIV. These datasets have <lb/>been evaluated against reanalysis data consisting of fused ob-<lb/>servations and modelled estimates (Andersson et al., 2024) <lb/>for years where all datasets were overlapping (1987-2013) <lb/>for high-altitude areas of the Scandinavian mountains. The <lb/>comparison shows a positive bias in the quantitative mod-<lb/>elled total nitrogen deposition of 18 % and 23 % for the <lb/>1987-2013 period, with a stronger positive bias in oxidized <lb/>nitrogen deposition and a partly balancing negative bias in <lb/>reduced nitrogen. The trend is similar between the modelled <lb/>and the reanalysed datasets over the period. <lb/>Historical and RCP8.5 CO 2 concentration data were the <lb/>same as those used by EC-Earth and HCLIM38, reaching at-<lb/>mospheric concentrations of 540.5 and 935.9 ppm in 2050 <lb/>and 2100, respectively (IPCC, 2013). <lb/>2.5 Model output validation and analysis <lb/>The output data from LPJ-GUESS are given as yearly states <lb/>or sums of fluxes averaged over the 15 simulated patches. <lb/>The data were further averaged over 10-year periods to re-<lb/>duce fluctuations arising from interannual weather variability <lb/>and random disturbances. <lb/>2.5.1 Validation <lb/>The simulated total leaf-area index (LAI) was compared to <lb/>the yearly maximum of the monthly SURFEX LAI prod-<lb/>uct (Masson et al., 2013), taken from ECOCLIMAP2.2 <lb/>based on MODIS at 1 km resolution in 2000 (Faroux <lb/>et al., 2013). Further, modelled LAIs for the specific <lb/>PFTs within a grid cell were used to determine vege-<lb/>tation class for comparison to two remote-sensing-based <lb/>vegetation products: the land cover of northern Eurasia <lb/>(GLCE) based on SPOT 4 at 1 km resolution (Bartalev et <lb/>al., 2003) and the CLC2018 land cover dataset (Corine) <lb/>based on Sentinel 2 at 100 m resolution (https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.2909/960998c1-1870-4e82-8051-6485205ebbac, Coper-<lb/>nicus, 2019). The conversions (described in detail in <lb/>Sect. S5) were based on Bartalev et al. (2003) and Kosztra et <lb/>al. (2019) for GLCE and Corine, respectively. The satellite-<lb/>based products were aggregated to the 3 km AROME grid <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1099 <lb/></page>

	<body>cells, based on the dominant class, to enable a statistical anal-<lb/>ysis of the agreement by means of confusion matrixes (e.g. <lb/>Congalton, 1991), with the satellite products used as ground <lb/>truth. Three measures of accuracy were calculated. Producer <lb/>accuracy (PA; the probability that a value in a given class <lb/>was classified correctly, i.e. correctly predicted grid cells of <lb/>a class / total number of ground truth grid cells in that class) <lb/>and user accuracy (UA; the probability that a value predicted <lb/>to be in a certain class really is in that class, i.e. correctly <lb/>predicted grid cells of a class / total number of grid cells pre-<lb/>dicted to be in the class) were calculated for each vegeta-<lb/>tion class, as well as the overall accuracy (sum of all cor-<lb/>rectly classified grid cells for all classes / total number of grid <lb/>cells). <lb/>The model output was also evaluated against ground-based <lb/>data for biomass (trees and shrubs) and vegetation cover-<lb/>age (field layer) using data collected in 2011-2012 from <lb/>four long-term exclosure experiments in Pulsuvuoma, Rit-<lb/>sem, Långfjället and Fulufjället (for Ritsem only field-layer <lb/>coverage), all established in 1995 (Fig. 1a) (Eriksson et al., <lb/>2007; Vowles et al., 2017). At each site and for each veg-<lb/>etation type (birch forest or shrub heath) there were three <lb/>fenced exclosure plots and three ambient plots of a 25 × 25 m <lb/>dimension. For the grid cells corresponding to these exper-<lb/>iments, the model was run both with (a) continuous graz-<lb/>ing and (b) grazing stopped after 1995. To convert model-<lb/>simulated total biomass C to dry mass, a factor of 2.0 was <lb/>used (Thomas and Martin, 2012), and to convert modelled to-<lb/>tal biomass to above-ground biomass, we assumed a factor of <lb/>0.85 based on earlier estimates for Swedish birch forest (be-<lb/>tween 0.79 and 0.92, Johansson, 2007). For seedlings, Hut-<lb/>tunen et al. (2013) reported values of about 0.6 increasing to <lb/>0.7 with fertilization and elevated temperature, but seedlings <lb/>in general have a lower above-ground fraction (Qi et al., <lb/>2019). The vegetation cover data of the shrub and field layer, <lb/>visually estimated at species level, were aggregated to the <lb/>LPJ-GUESS PFTs and compared to simulated LAI for two <lb/>to three close grid cells with similar altitude. Although the <lb/>comparison of fractional plant cover and LAI is not strictly <lb/>direct, the two measures are closely related (George et al., <lb/>2021). <lb/>2.5.2 Analysis <lb/>Due to the more detailed adapted vegetation zones for boreal <lb/>and arctic conditions in the GLCE classification, compared to <lb/>Corine, the future trends presented in the results below focus <lb/>only on the GLCE data. <lb/>To assess the simulated vegetation diversity, the Shan-<lb/>non (1948) diversity index (D) was calculated for each of <lb/>the six hotspots (Fig. 1), letting the number of grid cells of <lb/>different vegetation classes represent diversity: <lb/>D = -<lb/>(p i × ln (p i )) , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where p is the fraction of the total number of classified grid <lb/>cells in the hotspot (excluding prescribed water and wetland <lb/>cells) belonging to class i. Only one vegetation class present <lb/>would give a D of 0, and 10 classes with the same p would <lb/>give a value of 2.3. <lb/>The simulated potential reindeer consumption of leaf car-<lb/>bon was aggregated to reindeer-herding communities in Swe-<lb/>den for traditional seasonal grazing grounds (Fig. 1b), with <lb/>the help of GIS data obtained from the Swedish Sami Par-<lb/>liament (http://www.sametinget.se, last access: 26 Febru-<lb/>ary 2024). <lb/>2.6 Biodiversity data <lb/>To investigate the sensitivity of the hotspot sites to change, <lb/>species observations of all available species groups, together <lb/>with threatened and red-listed species, were extracted for <lb/>each hotspot area using a GeoJSON file in the Artdatabanken <lb/>Species Observation System (https://artportalen.se/, data re-<lb/>trieved: 29 October 2021). Further, to identify species being <lb/>classified as alpine, the database artfakta (https://artfakta.se/ <lb/>artinformation/lists, last access: 26 February 2024) was used <lb/>with the selection criterion &quot;landscape type&quot; set to &quot;moun-<lb/>tainous&quot;. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Validation <lb/>3.1.1 Validation of simulated vegetation against <lb/>satellite-based products <lb/>Simulated LAI was substantially lower than in the satellite-<lb/>based SURFEX product but had a reasonable agreement <lb/>(Fig. 2a-b, LAI Simulated = 0.78 × LAI SURFEX -1.99, r 2 <lb/>= <lb/>0.59). A reason for the low simulated values compared to <lb/>the reference could be that the yearly maximum of the SUR-<lb/>FEX data was used, which can cause an overestimation if <lb/>there are errors in the monthly data. Another aspect is that <lb/>LAI is defined as one sided for SURFEX and projected in <lb/>LPJ-GUESS, which corresponds to a factor of about 1.35 for <lb/>needleleaf canopies (Flower-Ellis and Olsson, 1993). <lb/>The simulations capture most of the broad patterns seen in <lb/>the vegetation distribution from forest to non-vegetated areas <lb/>when compared to the satellite-based products in 2000 and <lb/>2018 (Fig. 2c-f). For the detailed classes of the GLCE map, <lb/>the overall accuracy is however only 32 % of the grid cells <lb/>(Table S6a) and for the somewhat wider classes of Corine <lb/>37 % (Table S6b). Classifying in broader classes, the extent <lb/>of forest agreed for 84 % of grid cells simulated to be for-<lb/>est for both GLCE and Corine (user accuracy, UA) and for <lb/>90 % and 94 % of the satellite-based forest grid cells (pro-<lb/>ducer accuracy, PA) for GLCE and Corine, respectively. The <lb/>most common class of the boreal forest, the needleleaf ev-<lb/>ergreen forest class, is mixed more with broadleaf trees in <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1100 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 2. Satellite-based products of LAI (a), GLCE vegetation classes (c) and Corine vegetation classes (e) compared to simulated total <lb/>LAI (b) and vegetation classes based on LAI averaged over 10-year periods for different PFTs according to the GLC northern Eurasia <lb/>classification (d) and Corine (f) (see Fig. S5a-b). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1101 <lb/></page>

	<body>the simulation, and the distribution west of the mountains is <lb/>overestimated compared to the satellite-based products. With <lb/>the new parametrization of the IBS PFT (Table S2), the de-<lb/>ciduous broadleaf forest expands too much in the north on <lb/>the east side of the mountain ranges. Many (30 %) of the <lb/>grid cells that have shrub tundra according to the satellite <lb/>data were classified as shrub vegetation, resulting in poor UA <lb/>for broadleaf deciduous shrubs (0.5 %) and needleleaf ever-<lb/>green shrubs (0.0 %) and poor PA for shrub tundra (0.2 %), in <lb/>the GLCE comparison. The classes are distinguished based <lb/>on if the LAI of trees and tall shrubs is more than 20 % of <lb/>the total LAI (Fig. S5b). Similarly, for Corine the simulated <lb/>transitional woodland-shrub class mainly coincides with grid <lb/>cells classified as broadleaf forest, moors and heathland and <lb/>sparsely vegetated by the satellite product (Fig. S5a). <lb/>Aggregating the tundra classes for GLCE gave a UA of <lb/>83 % and PA of 36 %, where the low PA is the result of many <lb/>grid cells classified as shrub tundra by the satellite data be-<lb/>ing simulated to be forest or shrub vegetation. The moors <lb/>and heathland class is the third largest in the Corine satellite <lb/>data and was often classified as forest, natural grassland or <lb/>transitional woodland-shrub by the simulation (UA 18 %, PA <lb/>4 %). The LAI limits for the definition of the bare rock and <lb/>glacier classes from the simulation were the same for GLCE <lb/>and Corine classification, and both classes were reduced in <lb/>abundance from 1995-2004 to 2013-2022. The UA and PA <lb/>for these classes were in the range of 11 %-57 %. <lb/>3.1.2 Validation of the effect of the new reindeer <lb/>module against vegetation inventories and <lb/>reindeer exclosures <lb/>Comparing model data and the in-situ-estimated biomass for <lb/>the northernmost Pulsuvuoma site showed that simulated tree <lb/>and shrub biomass was underestimated by ca. 35 % but was <lb/>within the inventoried uncertainty range of the exclosure site <lb/>(Fig. 3). For the southern sites, biomass was overestimated <lb/>by ca. 50 % in Långfjället and by 200 % in Fulufjället. A rea-<lb/>son for the substantial overestimation for Fulufjället is that <lb/>it was dominated by needleleaf trees in the simulation. This <lb/>was confirmed by test simulations; excluding pine and spruce <lb/>PFTs (BINE and BNE) reduced biomass with 14 %, and also <lb/>excluding the birch PFT (IBS) reduced biomass with 78 %. <lb/>The in-situ-observed coverage of the shrub and field lay-<lb/>ers from the four exclosure sites was dominated by low ev-<lb/>ergreen shrubs, mainly Calluna vulgaris, Empetrum nigrum <lb/>and Vaccinium vitis-idaea, except for the Ritsem shrub heath, <lb/>which was dominated by graminoids and herbs (Fig. S6). The <lb/>total simulated LAI of the shrub and field layers was low for <lb/>the two northern sites (0.08 to 0.26 compared to inventoried <lb/>coverage of 59 %-75 %) and was dominated by graminoids <lb/>and herbs in the Ritsem shrub heath and high summergreen <lb/>shrubs below the Pulsuvuoma birch forest. There was a trend <lb/>that exclosure from reindeer grazing decreased the abun-<lb/>dance of graminoids and herbs in both observations and sim-<lb/>Figure 3. Simulated (sim.; mean over the years 2009-2013, striped <lb/>bars) above-ground tree and shrub biomass compared to inventoried <lb/>data (inv.; 2011 or 2012, solid bars, no biomass data were available <lb/>for the Ritsem exclosure site) from experiments with ambient plots <lb/>and simulations with reindeer presence (amb.; dark bars) and plots <lb/>with exclosure from 1995 and simulations without reindeer (excl.; <lb/>bright bars). Average and standard deviation over three inventoried <lb/>plots or the two to three closest simulated grid cells. <lb/>ulations. For the two southern sites, the inventoried coverage <lb/>and simulated LAI were similar except for Fulufjället, which <lb/>had a simulated overstorey of denser evergreen conifers in-<lb/>stead of birch. The trends after exclosure are less clear for <lb/>the southern sites, and the short shrub classes that dominate <lb/>in the inventories are almost totally absent in the simula-<lb/>tions, which are dominated by high shrubs (up to 2 m tall), <lb/>graminoids and herbs. It should be noted that Fulufjället is <lb/>located outside the area used for reindeer herding, though it <lb/>is occasionally visited by reindeers from Norway and moose, <lb/>and the modelling case is hypothetical. <lb/>3.2 Simulations and analysis of trends in vegetation <lb/>(2000-2100) <lb/>3.2.1 Trends in simulated vegetation classes over the <lb/>whole simulated area <lb/>In the RCP8.5 scenario a dramatic shift in simulated vegeta-<lb/>tion composition was found, especially after 2050 (Fig. 4). <lb/>By 2041-2050 the shrub vegetation classes are already seen <lb/>to expand to higher elevations in the mountains, and the <lb/>broadleaf forests in the north start to be mixed with conifers. <lb/>At the end of the century, the simulated area coverage of <lb/>open-vegetation classes and the bare soil and rock classes <lb/>was found to be negligible. For instance, the Fennoscandian <lb/>low arctic tundra, which stretches like a wedge from the Kola <lb/>Peninsula to the northernmost Swedish Lapland, in the lee <lb/>of the mountain chain, would be completely lost by 2100 <lb/>(Fig. 4c). Along the southern part of the Norwegian coast and <lb/>the south-eastern part of the Swedish boreal forest, temper-<lb/>ate broadleaf trees (TeBS PFTs) start to become dominant <lb/>in the 2091-2100 period, shown by increasing areas of the <lb/>deciduous broadleaf class. <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1102 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 4. Simulated vegetation classes according to the GLC northern Eurasia classification based on average LAI for different PFTs over <lb/>10 years, for three periods (a-c) in the RCP8.5 scenario. <lb/>In the western part of the mountains at latitude 68°N, de-<lb/>ciduous and mixed forests advance from a simulated current <lb/>maximum altitude of ca. 500 m a.s.l. to more than 1200 m <lb/>in 2090-2100 (Fig. 5a-c). On the east side there is no al-<lb/>titudinal advancement of the forest but a shift from decid-<lb/>uous broadleaf trees to conifers. Shrub vegetation classes, <lb/>especially needleleaf shrubs, become dominant at middle to <lb/>high altitudes, for 66°N (Fig. 5d-f) and 68°N at about 700 <lb/>to 1200 m and for 61.5°N less distinctly at 1000 to 1700 m <lb/>(Fig. 5g-i). At latitude 61.5°N, the lower mountains east of <lb/>the mountain range become almost completely covered by <lb/>evergreen needleleaf forest. The changes seen in the 2041-<lb/>2050 period are less distinct, but the increase in needleleaf <lb/>shrubs has started by then, and in the highest elevations a <lb/>shift in grid cell classification from permanent snow/ice to <lb/>bare rock can be seen, indicating continued melt of glaciers <lb/>and snowfields. As the classification is based on LAI, see <lb/>Sect. S5, it indicates that plants have the potential to grow <lb/>there. <lb/>3.2.2 Analysis of vegetation composition in hotspots <lb/>with the help of statistics of threatened species <lb/>According to the GLCE satellite-based product, the shrub <lb/>tundra class forms a large fraction of the vegetation next to <lb/>the boreal needleleaf forest (Fig. 6, Table S7a-d). The offi-<lb/>cial maps from Sweden show forest for parts of this area, e.g. <lb/>in the valleys of the Abisko area. For the Vindeln and Helags <lb/>hotspots, the simulated distribution of forest is close to the <lb/>satellite-based reference, but for the Fulu hotspot there are <lb/>just a few grid cells simulated as vegetation other than boreal <lb/>forest. For Björnlandet the mixture of broadleaf trees in the <lb/>forest is of a similar magnitude but with a different pattern. <lb/>The extent of sedge tundra was larger in the simulations than <lb/>for the GLCE reference for the three northern mountain sites. <lb/>By 2041-2050 a significant shrubification occurs in <lb/>Abisko, Vindeln and Helags (Fig. 6), and forests start to es-<lb/>tablish at the edges of the current shrub and tundra vegeta-<lb/>tion, an advancement that accelerates until the 2091-2100 <lb/>period. In Abisko the needleleaf shrub class reached a cov-<lb/>erage of approx. 45 % of the land area at the end of the cen-<lb/>tury, expanding mainly over former broadleaf shrub, tundra <lb/>and bare soil classes (Table S7a). In Vindeln and Helags the <lb/>evergreen needleleaf forest reaches approx. 80 % coverage <lb/>of the assessed area in 2091-2100 (Table S7b-c). In the bo-<lb/>real forest below the Fulu mountain and in the Muddus and <lb/>Björnlandet areas, we see that the needleleaf forest becomes <lb/>more mixed with broadleaf trees (Fig. 6, Table S7d-f), which <lb/>is also shown by the higher Shannon diversity index (D; Ta-<lb/>ble 3). It should be noted that the bog class, which is well <lb/>represented in Muddus, is excluded from the calculation of <lb/>D as it is prescribed and not dynamic. Including this class <lb/>would increase D, but we would not be able to correctly as-<lb/>sess the change over time. <lb/>For the northernmost hotspot studied, Abisko, the bare soil <lb/>and rock class will almost disappear in the RCP8.5 scenario, <lb/>but most other classes will remain in similar proportions of <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1103 <lb/></page>

	<body>Table 3. The Shannon diversity index (D) calculated from the fractional cover of GLCE vegetation classes (see Sect. S7) of the hotspots. <lb/>Classes with non-dynamical vegetation like water and bogs were not included in the calculation. <lb/>Abisko Vindeln Helags Fulu Muddus Björnlandet <lb/>Satellite-based class 2000 <lb/>1.44 <lb/>1.38 <lb/>1.42 0.50 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>LPJ-GUESS simulation 1995-2004 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>1.72 <lb/>1.25 0.32 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>LPJ-GUESS simulation 2091-2100 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.52 0.83 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>the grid cells, though with a shift within the hotspot area <lb/>(Table S7a). This is reflected in a minor increase in D (Ta-<lb/>ble 3) from 1.69 to 1.75 for this hotspot. Vindeln and Helags <lb/>will see a clear decrease in diversity as needleleaf forest and <lb/>shrubs will come to dominate (Table 3). For Fulu and the for-<lb/>est hotspots an increase in diversity is projected as the forests <lb/>will be more mixed. <lb/>Vindeln was the area with the lowest number of reported <lb/>species, whereas Helags was the most diverse area with over <lb/>70 % more species reported than for Vindeln (Table 4). The <lb/>four other sites all had fairly equal numbers of reported <lb/>species, in the range of 5155-5647 species. However, all <lb/>hotspots had a similar share of red-listed species and threat-<lb/>ened species, approximately 8 %-10 % and 3 %-4 %, respec-<lb/>tively (Table 4). Of all threatened species in Sweden (2764 <lb/>species), only 5.2 % (144 species) are classified as alpine, <lb/>and almost 2/3 of these threatened alpine species are found <lb/>in Abisko, comprising more than half of all the threatened <lb/>species in Abisko. For Vindeln and Helags, the number of <lb/>threatened alpine species is just below 20 %, whereas the <lb/>southernmost mountain hotspot Fulu and the forest hotspots <lb/>Muddus and Björnlandet have less than 10 % of their threat-<lb/>ened species classified as alpine. With respect to the species <lb/>groups to which most of the threatened species belong, it can <lb/>be noted that mosses contribute the largest number of species <lb/>in Abisko (Table 4). Except Vindeln, where birds consist of <lb/>the group with the most threatened species, fungi represent <lb/>the largest number of threatened species for the other four <lb/>hotspot areas. <lb/>3.3 Simulations of reindeer presence <lb/>3.3.1 Simulated effect on vegetation at reindeer <lb/>exclosure sites (1985-2100) <lb/>Three grid cells within the exclosure experiments with a wide <lb/>range of conditions were selected to exemplify the simu-<lb/>lated development of the vegetation composition until 2100 <lb/>(Fig. 7). Simulated LAI for the Ritsem shrub heath indicates <lb/>a steep increase in the year 2003, corresponding to an es-<lb/>tablishment of C 3 grass, after which this PFT has a rather <lb/>constant LAI over the simulation period (Fig. 7a-b). Shrub <lb/>vegetation (PFT LSS, LSE (both low shrubs), HSS and HSE <lb/>(tall shrubs)) increases gradually in Ritsem. At all sites, de-<lb/>ciduous shrubs would have a higher fraction without sim-<lb/>ulated reindeer grazing and trampling, but the difference is <lb/>minor. The mountain birch PFT (IBS) dominates simulations <lb/>for the Pulsuvuoma birch forest over the simulation period <lb/>(Fig. 7c-d), but for the heath grid cells there is no period <lb/>with a high fraction of mountain birch forests (Fig. 7a-b, <lb/>e-f). Instead PFTs that represent the needleleaf coniferous <lb/>forest (BNE and BINE) start to establish at the Ritsem and <lb/>Pulsuvuoma grid cells around 2035, and these PFTs are al-<lb/>ready present in the simulations for Långfjället, and at the <lb/>end of the simulation they are dominant at both shrub heath <lb/>sites. The summergreen prostrate dwarf shrub PFT (SPDS) <lb/>has a maximum fraction of ca. 50 % of LAI in Ritsem, though <lb/>with a very sparse coverage, before C 3 grass takes over, but <lb/>apart from that, short shrubs (LSS and LSE), prostrate dwarf <lb/>shrubs (SPDS and EPDS), and the graminoid and forb tundra <lb/>(GRT) PFTs only have a minor presence in the simulations. <lb/>3.3.2 Trends in simulated potential reindeer leaf <lb/>consumption (2000-2100) <lb/>With a constant grazing pressure, simulated reindeer leaf <lb/>consumption of a PFT depends on available leaf mass, ac-<lb/>cessibility of the leaves (height less than 2.5 m) and how ap-<lb/>petizing it is (preference value -see Table S3). In the cur-<lb/>rent climate the highest consumption was found east of the <lb/>mountain range with an increasing gradient from north to <lb/>south (Fig. 8a). In the boreal forest zone, the grazing level <lb/>is quite evenly distributed, although there is a tendency for <lb/>lower values in areas with a higher fraction of needleleaf <lb/>PFTs (Fig. 4). By the 2041-2050 period, the change is small, <lb/>although some increased potential in the least vegetated ar-<lb/>eas can be seen (Fig. 8b). By the end of the century there is <lb/>a substantial increase in potential consumption in the higher-<lb/>altitude areas as well as in the inland boreal forest (Fig. 8c). <lb/>In the south and towards the east there is a trend towards re-<lb/>duced potential reindeer consumption in the forested cells. <lb/>The traditional spring and autumn grazing grounds of the <lb/>Swedish reindeer-herding communities overlap to a high de-<lb/>gree (Fig. 1b), and both have a latitudinal dependency on po-<lb/>tential reindeer consumption that is gradually reduced and <lb/>eventually disappears by the end of the century (Fig. 9a, c). <lb/>For the summer grazing grounds there is a clear latitudi-<lb/>nal dependency that is shifted in parallel (i.e. potential con-<lb/>sumption increases uniformly) until the 2041-2050 period, <lb/>but by the end of the century the latitudinal trend is gone <lb/>or becomes negative, with higher potential consumption in <lb/>the northern part of the study region (Fig. 9b). For the win-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1104 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 5. Profiles of simulated vegetation class according to GLCE for the 2013-2022 and RCP8.5 2041-2050 and 2091-2100 time periods, <lb/>shown at the grid cells&apos; longitude and altitude for three latitude bands at 68.0°N (a-c), 66.0°N (d-f) and 61.5°N. The width of the bands <lb/>(13.6-19.7 km) was set so that the area of each band was 9000 km 2 and contained about 1000 grid cells. <lb/>Table 4. Threatened species (VU -vulnerable, EN -endangered, CR -critically endangered) reported across species groups as well as total <lb/>number of species and red-listed species reported for the six biodiversity hotspot areas. <lb/>Abisko <lb/>Vindeln <lb/>Helags <lb/>Fulu <lb/>Muddus <lb/>Björnlandet <lb/>Species group <lb/>VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR VU <lb/>EN <lb/>CR <lb/>Birds <lb/>20 <lb/>11 <lb/>3 <lb/>24 <lb/>14 <lb/>3 <lb/>28 <lb/>13 <lb/>3 <lb/>23 <lb/>14 <lb/>3 <lb/>25 <lb/>14 <lb/>4 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>Fungi <lb/>12 <lb/>2 <lb/>27 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>57 <lb/>7 <lb/>1 <lb/>52 <lb/>9 <lb/>4 <lb/>63 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>39 <lb/>5 <lb/>Insects <lb/>19 <lb/>5 <lb/>22 <lb/>1 <lb/>21 <lb/>6 <lb/>19 <lb/>3 <lb/>37 <lb/>10 <lb/>23 <lb/>11 <lb/>Lichens <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>4 <lb/>29 <lb/>16 <lb/>7 <lb/>24 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>14 <lb/>5 <lb/>14 <lb/>4 <lb/>Mosses <lb/>40 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>33 <lb/>9 <lb/>16 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>Vascular plants <lb/>18 <lb/>7 <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>17 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>26 <lb/>12 <lb/>3 <lb/>8 <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Other groups <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Threatened species <lb/>159 3.1 % <lb/>137 3.4 % <lb/>262 3.7 % <lb/>229 4.4 % <lb/>210 3.7 % <lb/>149 2.8 % <lb/>(% of total) <lb/>Threatened species of <lb/>91 <lb/>57 % <lb/>25 <lb/>18 % <lb/>51 <lb/>19 % <lb/>20 <lb/>9 % <lb/>19 <lb/>9 % <lb/>9 <lb/>6 % <lb/>which are alpine species <lb/>Red-listed species <lb/>423 8.2 % <lb/>369 9.1 % <lb/>651 9.3 % <lb/>528 <lb/>10 % <lb/>547 9.7 % <lb/>411 7.8 % <lb/>(% of total) <lb/>Total reported species <lb/>5155 <lb/>4058 <lb/>7034 <lb/>5205 <lb/>5647 <lb/>5250 <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1105 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 6. Satellite-based (GLCE, second column) and simulated (columns 3-5) vegetation composition in hotspots within four mountain <lb/>areas (rows 1-4) and two forest areas (rows 5-6) (see Fig. 1a for location), for 1995-2004 and for two future periods following RCP8.5. <lb/>Each area is 90 × 90 km (30 × 30 grid cells). The first column shows the official vector-based map from Lantmäteriet (the overview map, <lb/>open data Creative Commons license (CC0), https://www.lantmateriet.se/en/, last access: 9 September 2021). <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1106 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>Figure 7. Simulated development of the vegetation composition (based on LAI for different PFTs; see Table 2 for description) at selected <lb/>grid cells in the exclosure experiments from 1985-2100, for RCP8.5. <lb/>ter grazing grounds, the latitudinal dependencies are weak, <lb/>and the southern communities have a trend of reduced po-<lb/>tential grazing over time (Fig. 9d). A more detailed compila-<lb/>tion of the changes in the individual communities is given in <lb/>Sect. S8. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>The simulated changes in vegetation composition at the end <lb/>of the century are extensive in our high-emission RCP8.5 <lb/>scenario. For instance, we see a successive change in for-<lb/>est composition, from a cover of almost purely evergreen <lb/>trees to a cover containing a larger fraction of broadleaf and <lb/>mixed forest by the end of the century at the alpine Fulu and <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1107 <lb/></page>

	<body>Figure 8. Simulated potential reindeer consumption (g C m -2 yr -1 ) from 2013-2022 (a) and the change in 2041-2050 (b) and 2091-2100 (c) <lb/>in RCP8.5. <lb/>Figure 9. Simulated average potential reindeer consumption of leaf biomass in the 51 reindeer-herding communities in Sweden for the <lb/>different seasonal grazing grounds (a-d) and four time periods (colour) in RCP8.5. <lb/>low-elevation Muddus and Björnlandet hotspots. In Sweden, <lb/>conifers are highly favoured by forestry for traditional and <lb/>economic reasons, although pine forest regenerations are al-<lb/>ready encountering large problems (e.g. from moose graz-<lb/>ing and diseases), which can further contribute to an increase <lb/>in broadleaf forests in the future (Ara et al., 2022). Our re-<lb/>sults show that a profound vegetation change will occur at <lb/>the southern alpine hotspots Vindeln, Helags and Fulu, with <lb/>the most dramatic changes projected for Helags and Vindeln. <lb/>Here, rapid tree growth and expansion are observed in this <lb/>scenario, with only a few tundra-denoted grids remaining by <lb/>2091-2100. This change is also associated with a strong re-<lb/>duction in landscape diversity, as indicated by a decrease <lb/>in the vegetation-class-based Shannon diversity index. To-<lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1108 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>day, the largest continuous Fennoscandian low arctic tundra <lb/>areas are found between the Swedish high mountains and <lb/>the border between Finland and Sweden at latitudes around <lb/>68.5°N and in the northern and western parts of the Finn-<lb/>marksvidda plateau in the north of Norway. In a changed <lb/>climate, the edges of the tundra area have probably become <lb/>&quot;Scandinavianized&quot; (Vuorinen et al., 2017); i.e. the coverage <lb/>of dwarf birches and lichens has decreased, while the Eri-<lb/>caceae species have increased. In the simulations, the tun-<lb/>dra remaining in Helags and Vindeln will be dominated by <lb/>needleleaf evergreen shrubs with just a few scattered sedge <lb/>tundra areas (e.g. wet tundra areas). These results are simi-<lb/>lar to the results from long-term warming experiments and <lb/>monitoring plots in the northern Scandes, where most com-<lb/>munities showed a &quot;heathification&quot; with time, both in the ex-<lb/>perimental warming and under ambient conditions subjected <lb/>to the ongoing temperature increase (Scharn et al., 2021). <lb/>In Fulu, the relatively extensive alpine tundra areas are sit-<lb/>uated just above the treeline today, and here the tundra will <lb/>be completely lost following RCP8.5. Thus, with a continued <lb/>warming of up to 5 K to the end of the century in our model <lb/>domain, which is not totally unlikely as the world is currently <lb/>on track to reach a global warming of 2.9 K (United Nations <lb/>Environment Programme, 2023) and given the Arctic warm-<lb/>ing amplification (Rantanen et al., 2022), the Fennoscandian <lb/>vegetation is likely to undergo rapid shifts. <lb/>The simulated change in the extent of vegetation zones is <lb/>driven by establishment of PFTs, but the richness of newly <lb/>established vegetation depends on the migration of all as-<lb/>sociated types of organisms. The distance species need to <lb/>spread to keep up with the shifts in climate is much shorter in <lb/>mountainous regions than in flat regions, and since the abil-<lb/>ity to spread and inhabit new regions varies among species, <lb/>a loss in species richness only occurs if new immigrants <lb/>are stronger competitors than the intrinsic species (Pauli and <lb/>Halloy, 2019). Although total reported species richness is the <lb/>largest in the Helags biodiversity hotspot area and the low-<lb/>est in Vindeln, both have equal fractions of alpine species. <lb/>Despite the fact that the analysis portal is the best available <lb/>database, it should be kept in mind that the data obtained <lb/>from the analysis portal rely on what has been reported by <lb/>a large community of public and professional naturalists, <lb/>which means that biases can exist, e.g. depending on the <lb/>specific biological interests of rapporteurs visiting the differ-<lb/>ent areas. As they share the same trajectories, it seems likely <lb/>that the homogenization of the vegetation composition in the <lb/>Helags and Vindeln areas will lead to profound shifts in the <lb/>conditions for many species, especially for the alpine species <lb/>occurring here. In contrast to the southern alpine hotspots, <lb/>our modelling results indicate that the northernmost hotspot <lb/>area Abisko likely will retain large areas of alpine vegetation <lb/>at higher elevations, and its landscape diversity could even <lb/>increase slightly. A substantial transformation of the vegeta-<lb/>tion cover is however also expected for Abisko. This includes <lb/>shrubification, a process that has already been observed in <lb/>this region (Hedenås et al., 2011; Rundqvist et al., 2011; <lb/>Scharn et al., 2022, 2021), and the broadleaf forest moving <lb/>up well above 1000 m a.s.l. from the current level of about <lb/>600-800 m (Callaghan et al., 2013), a treeline advance that <lb/>has also been noted in local high-resolution simulations of <lb/>Abisko (Gustafson et al., 2021). Abisko is the hotspot with <lb/>the largest fraction of threatened alpine species in our study, <lb/>and, given the large elevation span in the region, there are <lb/>possibilities that some species may survive in microrefugia <lb/>(Mee and Moore, 2014). Our results imply that a revision of <lb/>the red-list and threatened species categories is urgent. This <lb/>is because many of the alpine species in the hotspot areas that <lb/>are not listed today will be threatened as warming continues <lb/>(Schwager and Berg, 2019). <lb/>The simulated potential reindeer consumption shows <lb/>a striking increase in the summer grazing ground north <lb/>of ca. 65.5°N. Although the simulated potential rein-<lb/>deer consumption is high, it is in the range of what <lb/>can be estimated from the current reindeer population in <lb/>Sweden. Today, reindeer husbandry is practised in about <lb/>50 % of the Swedish land area (i.e. 225 000 km 2 , https:// <lb/>www.sametinget.se/rennaring_sverige, last access: 26 Febru-<lb/>ary 2024), and the population is 225 000-280 000 animals <lb/>in winter (https://www.sametinget.se/rennaring_sverige, last <lb/>access: 26 February 2024). With a consumption of 3-5 kg <lb/>biomass per reindeer per day (Yu et al., 2017), this equals <lb/>to an average total consumption over the area of about <lb/>0.8 g C m -2 yr -1 , a number likely underestimated as the live-<lb/>stock is larger in summer before autumn slaughter. However, <lb/>in our simulations of potential reindeer winter consumption, <lb/>the trends were weak both in latitude and in time. Using a <lb/>constant herbivory intensity in the simulations means that <lb/>the potential reindeer consumption shown represents a hy-<lb/>pothetical case in which we investigate how much would be <lb/>consumed of the amount that is actually present if the same <lb/>number of reindeers and the same amount of food of the same <lb/>quality are present in all grid cells. This means that we have <lb/>not considered mitigation and adaptation factors that may be <lb/>of great importance, such as climate feedbacks on the popu-<lb/>lation size and changes in what land areas the reindeer feed <lb/>(Bråthen et al., 2017; Speed et al., 2019). Reindeer grazing, <lb/>browsing and trampling may also cause indirect feedback to <lb/>the climate by affecting the vegetation and ground proper-<lb/>ties, which in turn affects snow cover, albedo, carbon cycling <lb/>and biogenic volatile organic compound emissions (Brach-<lb/>mann et al., 2023; Holmgren et al., 2023). The representa-<lb/>tion of available reindeer food in the forested winter graz-<lb/>ing grounds is challenging. In our simulations, the potential <lb/>reindeer consumption mainly consists of grasses that occur <lb/>for a period after the random disturbances (with an average <lb/>150-year interval), but grasses are not the preferred reindeer <lb/>food during winter. Instead, reindeer eat lichens in winter, <lb/>which naturally can form dense layers under forests in the <lb/>region. Current forest management, creating a dense and uni-<lb/>form tree cover, disturbs the growth of lichens (Kumpula et <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1109 <lb/></page>

	<body>al., 2014). Furthermore, our weak trends during winter also <lb/>depend on a delicate balance between a general increased <lb/>productivity and higher density of the tree canopies. This <lb/>balance is also important for the implementation of ground <lb/>lichen PFTs, since there is a negative relationship between <lb/>forest density and lichen abundance (Sandström et al., 2016). <lb/>Thus, future improvements to simulations considering rein-<lb/>deer grazing would need the following: a better representa-<lb/>tion of winter forage by developing a new lichen PFT (e.g. <lb/>Porada et al., 2016), an improved light-interception scheme, <lb/>forest management functionality and scenarios (e.g. Lin-<lb/>deskog et al., 2021), and a representation of restricted access <lb/>to the field and bottom-layer vegetation during periods of <lb/>difficult snow conditions. Although the simulated potential <lb/>reindeer consumption does not show dramatic shifts over the <lb/>simulated period, reindeer herding will nevertheless experi-<lb/>ence climate-and weather-related challenges in the future <lb/>with e.g. concerns about hot and dry summers, more frequent <lb/>freeze-thaw cycles and rain-on-snow events during winters, <lb/>and expanding and denser forests (Käyhkö and Horstkotte, <lb/>2017; Rosqvist et al., 2021). Thus, to be able to tackle and un-<lb/>derstand future challenges for reindeer herding this not only <lb/>suggests a need to include trophic interactions in models, but <lb/>it also suggests that it is crucial to evaluate the impact of ex-<lb/>treme events on other important aspects of the environment <lb/>for reindeer herding other than vegetation state alone. <lb/>We show the benefit of using high-resolution climate data <lb/>to drive our DVM, enabling the simulation of a diverse land-<lb/>scape, exemplified by our hotspot analysis (which would <lb/>have less than four grid cells at a typical RCM resolution <lb/>of 50 × 50 km). Climate representation has also improved. In <lb/>particular, the simulated precipitation patterns in coastal and <lb/>mountain areas as well as the ratio between snow and rain-<lb/>fall at high altitude show significantly better agreement with <lb/>observations at higher resolutions (Lind et al., 2020). Thus, <lb/>highly resolved climate data in combination with a state-<lb/>of-the-art dynamical vegetation model clearly contribute to <lb/>a better understanding of climate-vegetation interactions in <lb/>mountainous regions. <lb/>Using the detailed classification from GLCE, the accu-<lb/>racy scores for the simulated vegetation classes compared <lb/>to the satellite product are low. For such a large area and <lb/>high resolution as in the present study, an evaluation against <lb/>satellite products is the only alternative with a complete cov-<lb/>erage, but the satellite classes cannot be considered a real <lb/>&quot;ground truth&quot;. An example of possible misclassification of <lb/>the GLCE data is clear from the fact that the mountain birch <lb/>forest in some of the valleys is classified as shrub vegeta-<lb/>tion, most clearly seen for Abisko and Vindeln when com-<lb/>pared to the official vector-based maps. The shrub and tundra <lb/>ecosystems have many subclasses, and the model has some <lb/>difficulty in reproducing the satellite-based pattern for these. <lb/>Furthermore, the parameterization of the PFTs representing <lb/>these systems is based on global or regional implementations <lb/>driven by monthly climate data at coarse spatial scale (Wolf <lb/>et al., 2008; Zhang et al., 2013), and it is not surprising that <lb/>the results call for some model adjustment. The comparisons <lb/>of results from the simulations with and without reindeer <lb/>presence against exclosure site data do not show conclusive <lb/>results. By only removing leaf biomass, we may have under-<lb/>estimated the effect of browsing, which particularly affects <lb/>the height development of deciduous shrubs (Vowles et al., <lb/>2017). To study the effect of reindeer exclosures in situ also <lb/>has some experimental constraints and uncertainty (Stark et <lb/>al., 2023), e.g. as other grazers like the hare or the lemming <lb/>can also have a significant impact on the vegetation (Olof-<lb/>sson et al., 2012; Vowles et al., 2016). A further limitation <lb/>of the vegetation simulations is that a soil layer is always <lb/>present. The strong expansion of shrubs on former bare soil <lb/>and rock and permanent snow/ice classes, e.g. as predicted <lb/>for the Abisko area, is, therefore, probably overestimated, <lb/>and instead parts of this area would become some type of tun-<lb/>dra associated with shallow soils. Dispersal capacity and fire <lb/>disturbance are also factors that may restrict vegetation ex-<lb/>pansion, as integration of these processes into an extrapola-<lb/>tion of current trends in Alaska and western Canada reduced <lb/>the predicted shrub expansion on non-shrub tundra from <lb/>39 % to 25 % by 2100 (Liu et al., 2022). In LPJ-GUESS, <lb/>new PFTs can establish when climatic conditions are met, as <lb/>we assume seeds are always present. Taking seed dispersal <lb/>into account will in general slow down migration rates (Ep-<lb/>stein et al., 2007; Zani et al., 2022). In mountainous terrain <lb/>the distances will, however, be shorter and less dependent on <lb/>dispersal capacity, e.g. reflected in abounded observations of <lb/>tree seedlings more than 100 m above the treeline in Scan-<lb/>dinavian mountains (Hofgaard et al., 2009). The disturbance <lb/>return interval is an important and uncertain parameter that <lb/>varies in time and space, which affects carbon stocks, the <lb/>balance between shade-tolerant and shade-intolerant species, <lb/>and plant establishment (Pugh et al., 2019). Recent studies <lb/>have suggested longer intervals (Pugh et al., 2019), but there <lb/>are also studies that show fire return intervals of 50-90 years <lb/>in boreal forest in Sweden (Dubber et al., 2017). There are <lb/>also a lot of other activities that may prevent the establish-<lb/>ment of new plants, like soil processes, seed predation, plant <lb/>browsing and mortality caused by smaller animals like ro-<lb/>dents and hares, pests, pathogens, snow damage, moose, et <lb/>cetera, which could be of potential importance. There is also <lb/>a positive bias in the nitrogen deposition scenario (Andersson <lb/>et al., 2024) that could have further enhanced the simulated <lb/>rate at which higher vegetation types expand (Gustafson et <lb/>al., 2021). In the boreal forest region, the simulations have a <lb/>higher fraction of broadleaf trees than the reference. A rea-<lb/>son for this is that more than 90 % of these forests are man-<lb/>aged, and needleleaf trees are favoured in planting and thin-<lb/>ning (Hannerz and Ekström, 2021), whereas the simulations <lb/>represent natural, unmanaged vegetation where broadleaf <lb/>trees are common during the regeneration phase after distur-<lb/>bances in boreal forest (Angelstam and Kuuluvainen, 2004). <lb/>However, notwithstanding these limitations, our simulations <lb/></body>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1110 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<body>clearly show that for Fennoscandia, the RCP8.5 pathway re-<lb/>sults in more prominent temperate features in the boreal for-<lb/>est and that these will expand northwards and to higher alti-<lb/>tudes, resulting in a significant loss in tundra. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>Our application of highly resolved climate data greatly im-<lb/>proved both the representation of climate conditions and the <lb/>variation in simulated vegetation in mountainous landscapes. <lb/>Climate and environmental change consistent with the high-<lb/>emission RCP8.5 scenario could cause dramatic shifts in <lb/>the vegetation composition of the Fennoscandian boreal and <lb/>mountain regions, with consequences for reindeer herding, <lb/>forestry and tourism sectors, how we should practise con-<lb/>servation, and how we should manage our northern ecosys-<lb/>tems. Indeed, these changes have already started and been <lb/>observed, but they will accelerate during the 21st century. <lb/>Following a climate trajectory in line with RCP8.5, the south-<lb/>ern and lower-elevation parts of the Fennoscandian moun-<lb/>tain range that today have tundra vegetation will be cov-<lb/>ered by forests in the coming century, while high-elevation <lb/>regions will undergo intense shrubification. In the northern <lb/>tundra regions, most vegetation types will still be present <lb/>at the end of the century but will shift in altitude and be <lb/>compressed to smaller regions. This will threaten already-<lb/>vulnerable species, especially those with slow dispersal rates <lb/>and low competitive ability. In the southern part of the study <lb/>area a massive loss of alpine habitats and species is ex-<lb/>pected. The question is rather what new vegetation types <lb/>and species could occupy this area under continued climate <lb/>change. There is, however, uncertainty at many levels in this <lb/>type of study: what emission scenario will the future hold, <lb/>and is it adequately interpreted by the global and regional cli-<lb/>mate models? Is the vegetation&apos;s direct response to climate, <lb/>CO 2 concentration and nitrogen deposition adequately de-<lb/>scribed in the DVM? How will secondary effects of climate <lb/>change alter disturbance patterns and land use? Due to com-<lb/>putational limitations in this high-resolution application, it <lb/>has not been possible to quantify these uncertainties (e.g. we <lb/>only have one climate scenario), but it is clear from our re-<lb/>sults and those from previous studies that all these aspects <lb/>are important. The direction in which the results point is, <lb/>however, clear in most aspects. The rate of actual vegetation <lb/>changes will also depend on factors such as forest manage-<lb/>ment, reindeer husbandry, other disturbances (such as fire) <lb/>and the dispersal rate of different species. Our results indicate <lb/>trends towards increasing amounts of suitable reindeer for-<lb/>age, at least in northern Sweden, but other changes resulting <lb/>from climate change, such as the extent of open landscapes, <lb/>heat stress and altered snow conditions, are likely to impact <lb/>reindeer-herding practises more than forage availability. The <lb/>expected and potentially additive pressures of environmen-<lb/>tal changes call for scenario-based research where the main <lb/>drivers of the development, including climate change, air pol-<lb/>lution, land use and ecological processes, are considered in a <lb/>consistent framework. <lb/></body>

	<div type="availability">Code availability. The LPJ-GUESS code used and developed in <lb/>this study is archived in the LPJ-GUESS community repository <lb/>on Zenodo: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8262590 (Lagergren et <lb/>al., 2023). More information about the model can be found at <lb/>https://web.nateko.lu.se/lpj-guess (last access: 26 February 2024). <lb/>Data availability. A selection of the MATCH-BIODIV <lb/>dataset and the MATCH-ECLAIRE (Engardt et al., <lb/>2017) datasets is archived in Zenodo (MATCH-BIODIV: <lb/>https://zenodo.org/record/7573171, Andersson et al., 2023, and <lb/>MATCH-ECLAIRE: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4501636, <lb/>Engardt and Simpson, 2021). The ALADIN and AROME <lb/>HCLIM climate datasets (Lind et al., 2023) and the complete <lb/>MATCH-BIODIV nitrogen deposition dataset (Andersson et <lb/>al., 2024) were generously shared with the authors but are not <lb/>publicly accessible; the data can be accessed upon inquiry to <lb/>the authors. The ECLIPSE V6b nitrogen deposition data are <lb/>available from IIASA (https://previous.iiasa.ac.at/web/home/ <lb/>research/researchPrograms/air/ECLIPSEv6b.html, Klimont and <lb/>Heyes, 2024), and the NGCD data used for bias correction of <lb/>temperature can be accessed from the MET Norway Thredds Ser-<lb/>vice <lb/>(https://thredds.met.no/thredds/catalog/ngcd/catalog.html, <lb/>Norwegian Meteorological Institute, 2024). The FAO <lb/>soil texture data are available on the SURFEX site <lb/>(https://www.umr-cnrm.fr/surfex/spip.php?article135, <lb/>SURFEX, 2024). The Corine land cover data (https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.2909/960998c1-1870-4e82-8051-6485205ebbac, <lb/>Copernicus, 2019) and the GLCE product for northern Eurasia <lb/>(https://forobs.jrc.ec.europa.eu/glc2000/data, Bartalev, 2024) are <lb/>freely available. The GIS data of reindeer-herding communities <lb/>were obtained after personal contact with Peter Benson from the <lb/>Swedish Sami Parliament (https://www.sametinget.se, last access: <lb/>26 February 2024) but are not freely available. Vegetation cover <lb/>data (Vowles et al., 2017) can be accessed through Environment Cli-<lb/>mate Data Sweden (https://doi.org/10.5879/ECDS/2017-01-29.1/0, <lb/>Vowles, 2018). The biomass data from the exclosure sites are not <lb/>available to the public but can be accessed by personal contact with <lb/>the authors (Robert G. Björk). Species observations for the hotspots <lb/>are available on the Artdatabanken Species Observation System <lb/>(https://artportalen.se/, Artdatabanken, 2021). Model simulation <lb/>results with LPJ-GUESS for this paper are stored on DataGURU: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.18161/j395-1j66 (Lagergren and Miller, 2023). <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available on-<lb/>line at: https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

	<div type="contribution">Author contributions. FL and PAM designed the study with contri-<lb/>butions from RGB, CA, MPB, EK, HP and GR. FL carried out the <lb/>vegetation model development, setup, runs and data analysis with <lb/>support from PAM. RGB extracted and analysed the biodiversity <lb/>data with help from MPB and HP. DB, PL and DL provided the cli-<lb/></div>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1111 <lb/></page>

	<div type="contribution">mate scenario and associated soil and vegetation attributes. CA and <lb/>TO provided high-resolution nitrogen deposition data. FL carried <lb/>out bias correction and filling of continuous climate and nitrogen <lb/>deposition data with advice from DB, EK and CA. RGB, MPB and <lb/>GR contributed with expertise in reindeer husbandry and its inter-<lb/>action with the vegetation. FL prepared the paper with input from <lb/>all co-authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none of <lb/>the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. The work is a contribution to the strategic re-<lb/>search areas MERGE and BECC, and the nature-based future solu-<lb/>tions profile area hosted by Lund University. We thank Peter Benson <lb/>at Sametinget for providing data of the reindeer husbandry districts <lb/>in Sweden and Mora Aronsson, Debora Arlt and Johan Nilsson for <lb/>advice regarding the extraction of data from the Analysis Portal for <lb/>Biodiversity Data. We also thank Leanne van der Kuijl for a valu-<lb/>able review as part of a graduate course at Wageningen University <lb/>&amp; Research. <lb/></div>

	<div type="funding">Financial support. This work was supported by the BioDiv-<lb/>Support project funded through the 2017-2018 Belmont Forum and <lb/>BiodivERsA joint call for research proposals, under the BiodivScen <lb/>ERA-Net COFUND programme, the Svenska Forskningsrådet For-<lb/>mas (grant nos. 2018-02434, 2018-02436, 2018-02437 and 2018-<lb/>02438), the Academy of Finland (grant no. 326328), the Agence <lb/>Nationale de la Recherche (grant no. ANR-18-EBI4-0007), the <lb/>Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung (KFZ, grant no. <lb/>01LC1810A), and the Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación (APCIN, <lb/>grant no. PCI2018-093149). <lb/></div>

	<div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Bertrand Guenet and <lb/>reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

	<listBibl>References <lb/>Andersson, C., Langner, J., and Bergström, R.: Interannual vari-<lb/>ation and trends in air pollution over Europe due to cli-<lb/>mate variability during 1958-2001 simulated with a regional <lb/>CTM coupled to the ERA40 reanalysis, Tellus B, 59, 77-98, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0889.2006.00231.x, 2007. <lb/>Andersson, C., Bergström, R., Bennet, C., Robertson, L., Thomas, <lb/>M., Korhonen, H., Lehtinen, K. E. J., and Kokkola, H.: MATCH-<lb/>SALSA -Multi-scale Atmospheric Transport and CHemistry <lb/>model coupled to the SALSA aerosol microphysics model -<lb/>Part 1: Model description and evaluation, Geosci. Model Dev., <lb/>8, 171-189, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-8-171-2015, 2015. <lb/>Andersson, C., Belusic, D., Kjellström, E., Lagergren, F., <lb/>Lind, P., Lindstedt, D., Miller, P., and Olenius, T.: BioDiv-<lb/>Support: Webtool dataset v1.0 (v1.0), Zenodo [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7573171, 2023. <lb/>Andersson, C., Olenius, T., Alpfjord Wylde, H., Almroth Rosell, <lb/>E., Björk, R. G., Björkman, M. P., Moldan, F., and Engardt, M.: <lb/>Long-term reanalysis, future scenarios and impacts of nitrogen <lb/>deposition on northern European ecosystems including the Baltic <lb/>Sea and the Scandinavian Mountains, in preparation, 2024. <lb/>Angelstam, P. and Kuuluvainen, T.: Boreal forest disturbance <lb/>regimes, successional dynamics and landscape structures -a Eu-<lb/>ropean perspective, Ecol. Bull., 51, 117-136, https://www.jstor. <lb/>org/stable/20113303 (last access: 26 February 2024), 2004. <lb/>Ara, M., Barbeito, I., Kalén, C., and Nilsson, U.: Regenera-<lb/>tion failure of Scots pine changes the species composition <lb/>of young forests, Scandinavian J. Forest Res., 37, 14-22, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/02827581.2021.2005133, 2022. <lb/>Artdatabanken (Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences): <lb/>Species Observation System, Artdatabanken [data set], https: <lb/>//artportalen.se/, data retrieved: 29 October 2021. <lb/>Bartalev, S.: Global Land Cover 2000 -Download, Northern Eura-<lb/>sia v4.0, European Commission [data set], https://forobs.jrc.ec. <lb/>europa.eu/glc2000/data, last access: 26 February 2024. <lb/>Bartalev, S. A., Belward, A. S., Erchov, D. V., and Isaev, A. <lb/>S.: A new SPOT4-VEGETATION derived land cover map <lb/>of Northern Eurasia, Int. J. Remote Sens., 24, 1977-1982, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/0143116031000066297, 2003. <lb/>Barthelemy, H., Stark, S., Michelsen, A., and Olofsson, J.: Urine <lb/>is an important nitrogen source for plants irrespective of veg-<lb/>etation composition in an Arctic tundra: Insights from a N-<lb/>15-enriched urea tracer experiment, J. Ecol., 106, 367-378, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12820, 2018. <lb/>Belušić, D., de Vries, H., Dobler, A., Landgren, O., Lind, <lb/>P., Lindstedt, D., Pedersen, R. A., Sánchez-Perrino, J. C., <lb/>Toivonen, E., van Ulft, B., Wang, F., Andrae, U., Ba-<lb/>trak, Y., Kjellström, E., Lenderink, G., Nikulin, G., Pietikäi-<lb/>nen, J.-P., Rodríguez-Camino, E., Samuelsson, P., van Meij-<lb/>gaard, E., and Wu, M.: HCLIM38: a flexible regional climate <lb/>model applicable for different climate zones from coarse to <lb/>convection-permitting scales, Geosci. Model Dev., 13, 1311-<lb/>1333, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1311-2020, 2020. <lb/>Bjorkman, A. D., Myers-Smith, I. H., Elmendorf, S. C., Normand, <lb/>S., Rueger, N., Beck, P. S. A., Blach-Overgaard, A., Blok, D., <lb/>Cornelissen, J. H. C., Forbes, B. C., Georges, D., Goetz, S. J., <lb/>Guay, K. C., Henry, G. H. R., HilleRisLambers, J., Hollister, R. <lb/>D., Karger, D. N., Kattge, J., Manning, P., Prevey, J. S., Rixen, <lb/>C., Schaepman-Strub, G., Thomas, H. J. D., Vellend, M., Wilmk-<lb/>ing, M., Wipf, S., Carbognani, M., Hermanutz, L., Levesque, E., <lb/>Molau, U., Petraglia, A., Soudzilovskaia, N. A., Spasojevic, M. <lb/>J., Tomaselli, M., Vowles, T., Alatalo, J. M., Alexander, H. D., <lb/>Anadon-Rosell, A., Angers-Blondin, S., te Beest, M., Berner, L., <lb/>Bjork, R. G., Buchwal, A., Buras, A., Christie, K., Cooper, E. <lb/>J., Dullinger, S., Elberling, B., Eskelinen, A., Frei, E. R., Grau, <lb/>O., Grogan, P., Hallinger, M., Harper, K. A., Heijmans, M. M. <lb/>P. D., Hudson, J., Huelber, K., Iturrate-Garcia, M., Iversen, C. <lb/>M., Jaroszynska, F., Johnstone, J. F., Jorgensen, R. H., Kaarle-<lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1112 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>jarvi, E., Klady, R., Kuleza, S., Kulonen, A., Lamarque, L. J., <lb/>Lantz, T., Little, C. J., Speed, J. D. M., Michelsen, A., Milbau, <lb/>A., Nabe-Nielsen, J., Nielsen, S. S., Ninot, J. M., Oberbauer, S. <lb/>F., Olofsson, J., Onipchenko, V. G., Rumpf, S. B., Semenchuk, P., <lb/>Shetti, R., Collier, L. S., Street, L. E., Suding, K. N., Tape, K. D., <lb/>Trant, A., Treier, U. A., Tremblay, J.-P., Tremblay, M., Venn, S., <lb/>Weijers, S., Zamin, T., Boulanger-Lapointe, N., Gould, W. A., <lb/>Hik, D. S., Hofgaard, A., Jonsdottir, I. S., Jorgenson, J., Klein, <lb/>J., Magnusson, B., Tweedie, C., Wookey, P. A., Bahn, M., Blon-<lb/>der, B., van Bodegom, P. M., Bond-Lamberty, B., Campetella, G., <lb/>Cerabolini, B. E. L., Chapin III, F. S., Cornwell, W. K., Craine, <lb/>J., Dainese, M., de Vries, F. T., Diaz, S., Enquist, B. J., Green, <lb/>W., Milla, R., Niinemets, U., Onoda, Y., Ordonez, J. C., Ozinga, <lb/>W. A., Penuelas, J., Poorter, H., Poschlod, P., Reich, P. B., Sande, <lb/>B., Schamp, B., Sheremetev, S., and Weiher, E.: Plant functional <lb/>trait change across a warming tundra biome, Nature, 562, 57-62, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-018-0563-7, 2018. <lb/>Bjorkman, A. D., García, C. M., Myers-Smith, I. H., Ravolainen, <lb/>V., Svala Jónsdóttir, I., Westergaard, K. B., J. P., Aron-<lb/>sson, M., Bennett, B., Gardfjell, H., Heiðmarsson, S., Stewart, <lb/>L., and Normand, S.: Status and trends in Arctic vegetation: <lb/>Evidence from experimental warming and long-term monitor-<lb/>ing, Ambio, 49, 678-692, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-019-<lb/>01161-6, 2020. <lb/>Brachmann, C. G., Vowles, T., Rinnan, R., Björkman, M. P., Ek-<lb/>berg, A., and Björk, R. G.: Herbivore-shrub interactions influ-<lb/>ence ecosystem respiration and biogenic volatile organic com-<lb/>pound composition in the subarctic, Biogeosciences, 20, 4069-<lb/>4086, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-20-4069-2023, 2023. <lb/>Bråthen, K. A., Ravolainen, V. T., Stien, A., Tveraa, T., <lb/>and Ims, R. A.: Rangifer management controls a climate-<lb/>sensitive tundra state transition, Ecol. Appl., 27, 2416-2427, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.1618, 2017. <lb/>Callaghan, T. V., Jonasson, C., Thierfelder, T., Yang, Z., Hedenås, <lb/>H., Johansson, M., Molau, U., Van Bogaert, R., Michelsen, <lb/>A., Olofsson, J., Gwynn-Jones, D., Bokhorst, S., Phoenix, G., <lb/>Bjerke, J. W., Tømmervik, H., Christensen, T. R., Hanna, E., <lb/>Koller, E. K., and Sloan, V. L.: Ecosystem change and stability <lb/>over multiple decades in the Swedish subarctic: complex pro-<lb/>cesses and multiple drivers, Philos. T. R. Soc. B, 368, 20120488, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2012.0488, 2013. <lb/>Callaghan, T. V., Gatti, R. C., and Phoenix, G.: The need to un-<lb/>derstand the stability of arctic vegetation during rapid climate <lb/>change: An assessment of imbalance in the literature, Ambio, 51, <lb/>1034-1044, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-021-01607-w, 2022. <lb/>Congalton, R. G.: A review of assessing the accuracy of classifica-<lb/>tions of remotely sensed data, Remote Sens. Environ., 37, 35-46, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0034-4257(91)90048-b, 1991. <lb/>Constable, A. J., Harper, S., Dawson, J., Holsman, K., Mustonen, <lb/>T., Piepenburg, D., and Rost, B.: Cross-Chapter Paper 6: Polar <lb/>Regions, in: Climate Change 2022: Impacts, Adaptation and Vul-<lb/>nerability. Contribution of Working Group II to the Sixth Assess-<lb/>ment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, <lb/>edited by: Pörtner, H.-O., Roberts, D. C., Tignor, M., Poloczan-<lb/>ska, E. S., Mintenbeck, K., Alegría, A., Craig, M., Langsdorf, S., <lb/>Löschke, S., Möller, V., Okem, A., and Rama, B., Cambridge <lb/>University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York, NY, USA, <lb/>2319-2368, https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009325844.023, 2022. <lb/>Copernicus: CORINE Land Cover 2018 (raster 100 m), Europe, 6-<lb/>yearly, Copernicus [data set], https://doi.org/10.2909/960998c1-<lb/>1870-4e82-8051-6485205ebbac, 2019. <lb/>Denryter, K. A., Cook, R. C., Cook, J. G., and Parker, K. L.: Straight <lb/>from the caribou&apos;s (Rangifer tarandus) mouth: detailed observa-<lb/>tions of tame caribou reveal new insights into summer-autumn <lb/>diets, Can. J. Zool., 95, 81-94, https://doi.org/10.1139/cjz-2016-<lb/>0114, 2017. <lb/>Dobrowski, S. Z., Littlefield, C. E., Lyons, D. S., Hollenberg, C., <lb/>Carroll, C., Parks, S. A., Abatzoglou, J. T., Hegewisch, K., and <lb/>Gage, J.: Protected-area targets could be undermined by climate <lb/>change-driven shifts in ecoregions and biomes, Commun. Earth <lb/>Environ., 2, 198, https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00270-z, <lb/>2021. <lb/>Dubber, W., Eklundh, L., and Lagergren, F.: Comparing field inven-<lb/>tory with mechanistic modelling and light-use efficiency mod-<lb/>elling based approaches for estimating forest net primary pro-<lb/>ductivity at a regional level, Boreal Environ. Res., 22, 337-352, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Egelkraut, D., Barthelemy, H., and Olofsson, J.: Reindeer tram-<lb/>pling promotes vegetation changes in tundra heathlands: Re-<lb/>sults from a simulation experiment, J. Veg. Sci., 31, 476-486, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/jvs.12871, 2020. <lb/>Eichler, A., Legrand, M., Jenk, T. M., Preunkert, S., Andersson, <lb/>C., Eckhardt, S., Engardt, M., Plach, A., and Schwikowski, M.: <lb/>Consistent histories of anthropogenic western European air pol-<lb/>lution preserved in different Alpine ice cores, The Cryosphere, <lb/>17, 2119-2137, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-17-2119-2023, 2023. <lb/>Elmendorf, S. C., Henry, G. H. R., Hollister, R. D., Björk, R. G., <lb/>Boulanger-Lapointe, N., Cooper, E. J., Cornelissen, J. H. C., Day, <lb/>T. A., Dorrepaal, E., Elumeeva, T. G., Gill, M., Gould, W. A., <lb/>Harte, J., Hik, D. S., Hofgaard, A., Johnson, D. R., Johnstone, <lb/>J. F., Jonsdottir, I. S., Jorgenson, J. C., Klanderud, K., Klein, <lb/>J. A., Koh, S., Kudo, G., Lara, M., Levesque, E., Magnusson, <lb/>B., May, J. L., Mercado-Diaz, J. A., Michelsen, A., Molau, U., <lb/>Myers-Smith, I. H., Oberbauer, S. F., Onipchenko, V. G., Rixen, <lb/>C., Schmidt, N. M., Shaver, G. R., Spasojevic, M. J., Porhalls-<lb/>dottir, P. E., Tolvanen, A., Troxler, T., Tweedie, C. E., Villareal, <lb/>S., Wahren, C.-H., Walker, X., Webber, P. J., Welker, J. M., and <lb/>Wipf, S.: Plot-scale evidence of tundra vegetation change and <lb/>links to recent summer warming, Nat. Clim. Change, 2, 453-457, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1465, 2012. <lb/>Engardt, M. and Simpson, D.: Deposition of sulphur and <lb/>nitrogen in Europe 1900-2050. Model calculations <lb/>with EMEP and MATCH models, Zenodo [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4501636, 2021. <lb/>Engardt, M., Simpson, D., Schwikowski, M., and Granat, L.: De-<lb/>position of sulphur and nitrogen in Europe 1900-2050. Model <lb/>calculations and comparison to historical observations, Tellus B, <lb/>69, 1328945, https://doi.org/10.1080/16000889.2017.1328945, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Epstein, H. E., Yu, Q., Kaplan, J. O., and Lischke, H.: Simulating <lb/>future changes in Arctic and subarctic vegetation, Comput. Sci. <lb/>Eng., 9, 12-23, https://doi.org/10.1109/mcse.2007.84, 2007. <lb/>Eriksson, O., Niva, M., and Caruso, A.: Use and abuse of reindeer <lb/>range, Acta Phytogeographica Suecica, 87, 1-110, 2007. <lb/>Faroux, S., Kaptué Tchuenté, A. T., Roujean, J.-L., Masson, V., <lb/>Martin, E., and Le Moigne, P.: ECOCLIMAP-II/Europe: a <lb/>twofold database of ecosystems and surface parameters at 1 km <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1113 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>resolution based on satellite information for use in land surface, <lb/>meteorological and climate models, Geosci. Model Dev., 6, 563-<lb/>582, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-6-563-2013, 2013. <lb/>Feeley, K. J., Silman, M. R., Bush, M. B., Farfan, W., Cabrera, K. <lb/>G., Malhi, Y., Meir, P., Revilla, N. S., Quisiyupanqui, M. N. R., <lb/>and Saatchi, S.: Upslope migration of Andean trees, J. Biogeogr., <lb/>38, 783-791, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2699.2010.02444.x, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Ferraro, K. M., Schmitz, O. J., and McCary, M. A.: Effects <lb/>of ungulate density and sociality on landscape heterogeneity: <lb/>a mechanistic modeling approach, Ecography, 2022, e06039, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/ecog.06039, 2022. <lb/>Flower-Ellis, J. G. K. and Olsson, L.: Estimation of volume, total <lb/>and projected area of Scots pine needles from their regression on <lb/>length, Studia Forestalia Suecica, 190, 1-19, 1993. <lb/>Fohringer, C., Rosqvist, G., Inga, N., and Singh, N. J.: Reindeer hus-<lb/>bandry in peril?-How extractive industries exert multiple pres-<lb/>sures on an Arctic pastoral ecosystem, People and Nature, 3, <lb/>872-886, https://doi.org/10.1002/pan3.10234, 2021. <lb/>George, J.-P., Yang, W., Kobayashi, H., Biermann, T., Car-<lb/>rara, A., Cremonese, E., Cuntz, M., Fares, S., Gerosa, G., <lb/>Grünwald, T., Hase, N., Heliasz, M., Ibrom, A., Knohl, A., <lb/>Kruijt, B., Lange, H., Limousin, J.-M., Loustau, D., Lukeš, <lb/>P., Marzuoli, R., Mölder, M., Montagnani, L., Neirynck, J., <lb/>Peichl, M., Rebmann, C., Schmidt, M., Serrano, F. R. L., <lb/>Soudani, K., Vincke, C., and Pisek, J.: Method compari-<lb/>son of indirect assessments of understory leaf area index <lb/>(LAI(u)): A case study across the extended network of ICOS <lb/>forest ecosystem sites in Europe, Ecol. Indic., 128, 107841, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2021.107841, 2021. <lb/>Gustafson, A., Miller, P. A., Björk, R. G., Olin, S., and Smith, <lb/>B.: Nitrogen restricts future sub-arctic treeline advance in an <lb/>individual-based dynamic vegetation model, Biogeosciences, 18, <lb/>6329-6347, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-6329-2021, 2021. <lb/>Hannerz, M. and Ekström, H.: Nordic Forest Statistics 2020 <lb/>-Resources, Industry, Trade, Conservation, and Climate, <lb/>Nordic Forest Research, 32 pp., https://nordicforestresearch.org/ <lb/>wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Nordisk-skogsstatistik-3.pdf (last <lb/>access: 26 February 2024), 2021. <lb/>Hazeleger, W., Severijns, C., Semmler, T., Þtefanescu, S., Yang, <lb/>S., Wang, X., Wyser, K., Dutra, E., Baldasano, J. M., Bin-<lb/>tanja, R., Bougeault, P., Caballero, R., Ekman, A. M. L., Chris-<lb/>tensen, J. H., van den Hurk, B., Jimenez, P., Jones, C., Kåll-<lb/>berg, P., Koenigk, T., McGrath, R., Miranda, P., Van Noije, T., <lb/>Palmer, T., Parodi, J. A., Schmith, T., Selten, F., Storelvmo, <lb/>T., Sterl, A., Tapamo, H., Vancoppenolle, M., Viterbo, P., and <lb/>Willén, U.: EC-Earth A Seamless Earth-System Prediction Ap-<lb/>proach in Action, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 91, 1357-1363, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/2010bams2877.1, 2010. <lb/>Hazeleger, W., Wang, X., Severijns, C., Þtefanescu, S., Bintanja, <lb/>R., Sterl, A., Wyser, K., Semmler, T., Yang, S., van den Hurk, <lb/>B., van Noije, T., van der Linden, E., and van der Wiel, K.: <lb/>EC-Earth V2.2: description and validation of a new seamless <lb/>earth system prediction model, Clim. Dynam., 39, 2611-2629, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-011-1228-5, 2012. <lb/>Hedenås, H., Olsson, H., Jonasson, C., Bergstedt, J., Dahlberg, U., <lb/>and Callaghan, T. V.: Changes in Tree Growth, Biomass and Veg-<lb/>etation Over a 13-Year Period in the Swedish Sub-Arctic, Ambio, <lb/>40, 672-682, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-011-0173-1, 2011. <lb/>Hickler, T., Vohland, K., Feehan, J., Miller, P. A., Smith, B., <lb/>Costa, L., Giesecke, T., Fronzek, S., Carter, T. R., Cramer, W., <lb/>Kühn, I., and Sykes, M. T.: Projecting the future distribution <lb/>of European potential natural vegetation zones with a gener-<lb/>alized, tree species-based dynamic vegetation model, Global <lb/>Ecol. Biogeogr., 21, 50-63, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1466-<lb/>8238.2010.00613.x, 2012. <lb/>Hofgaard, A., Dalen, L., and Hytteborn, H.: Tree recruitment above <lb/>the treeline and potential for climate-driven treeline change, <lb/>J. Veg. Sci., 20, 1133-1144, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-<lb/>1103.2009.01114.x, 2009. <lb/>Höglund-Isaksson, L., Gómez-Sanabria, A., Klimont, Z., Rafaj, <lb/>P., and Schöpp, W.: Technical potentials and costs for reducing <lb/>global anthropogenic methane emissions in the 2050 timeframe <lb/>-results from the GAINS model, Environmental Research <lb/>Communications, 2, 025004, https://doi.org/10.1088/2515-<lb/>7620/ab7457, 2020. <lb/>Holmgren, M., Groten, F., Carracedo, M. R., Vink, S., and Limpens, <lb/>J.: Rewilding Risks for Peatland Permafrost, Ecosystems, 26, <lb/>1806-1818, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10021-023-00865-x, 2023. <lb/>Hudson, J. M. G. and Henry, G. H. R.: Increased plant biomass in <lb/>a High Arctic heath community from 1981 to 2008, Ecology, 90, <lb/>2657-2663, https://doi.org/10.1890/09-0102.1, 2009. <lb/>Huttunen, L., Ayres, M. P., Niemelä, P., Heiska, S., Tegel-<lb/>berg, R., Rousi, M., and Kellomäki, S.: Interactive ef-<lb/>fects of defoliation and climate change on compensatory <lb/>growth of silver birch seedlings, Silva Fennica, 47, 964, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.14214/sf.964, 2013. <lb/>IPCC: Annex II: Climate System Scenario Tables, in: Cli-<lb/>mate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribu-<lb/>tion of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of <lb/>the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: <lb/>Prather, M., Flato, G., Friedlingstein, P., Jones, C., Lamar-<lb/>que, J.-F., Liao, H., and Rasch, P., Cambridge University <lb/>Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107415324, 2013. <lb/>IPCC: Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of <lb/>Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of <lb/>the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Core <lb/>Writing Team, Pachauri, R. K., and Meyer, L. A., IPCC, Gen-<lb/>eve, 151 pp., http://hdl.handle.net/10013/epic.45156.d001 (last <lb/>access: 26 February 2024), 2014. <lb/>Johansson, T.: Biomass production and allometric above-and <lb/>below-ground relations for young birch stands planted at <lb/>four spacings on abandoned farmland, Forestry, 80, 41-52, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/forestry/cpl049, 2007. <lb/>Käyhkö, J. and Horstkotte, T.: Reindeer husbandry un-<lb/>der global change in the tundra region of Northern <lb/>Fennoscandia, Publications from the Department of Ge-<lb/>ography and Geology, University of Turku, 72 pp., <lb/>https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.22151.39841, 2017. <lb/>Klimont, Z. and Heyes, C.: ECLIPSE V6b global emission fields, <lb/>IIASA [data set], https://previous.iiasa.ac.at/web/home/research/ <lb/>researchPrograms/air/ECLIPSEv6b.html, last access: 26 Febru-<lb/>ary 2024. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1114 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Kosztra, B., Büttner, G., Hazeu, G., and Arnold, S.: Up-<lb/>dated CLC illustrated nomenclature guidelines, European <lb/>Topic Centre on Urban, land and soil systems, Environ-<lb/>ment Agency Austria, 126 pp., https://land.copernicus.eu/ <lb/>content/corine-land-cover-nomenclature-guidelines/docs/pdf/ <lb/>CLC2018_Nomenclature_illustrated_guide_20190510.pdf (last <lb/>access: 26 February 2024), 2019. <lb/>Kullman, L.: Ecological overview of past and recent history of the <lb/>alpine tree line ecotone and plant cover in the Swedish Scan-<lb/>des, Svensk Botanisk Tidsskrift, 110, 132-272, 2016 (in Swedish <lb/>with English summary). <lb/>Kumpula, J., Kurkilahti, M., Helle, T., and Colpaert, A.: Both rein-<lb/>deer management and several other land use factors explain the <lb/>reduction in ground lichens (Cladonia spp.) in pastures grazed by <lb/>semi-domesticated reindeer in Finland, Reg. Environ. Change, <lb/>14, 541-559, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-013-0508-5, 2014. <lb/>Kuuluvainen, T. and Gauthier, S.: Young and old forest in <lb/>the boreal: critical stages of ecosystem dynamics and man-<lb/>agement under global change, Forest Ecosystems, 5, 26, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s40663-018-0142-2, 2018. <lb/>Lagergren, F. and Miller, P. A.: LPJ-GUESS model results with <lb/>arctic plant functional types (PFTs) for Fennoscandia from <lb/>the BioDiv-Support project at RCP 8.5, DataGURU [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.18161/j395-1j66, 2023. <lb/>Lagergren, F., Olin, S., and Miller, P. A.: Incorporat-<lb/>ing reindeer grazing and damage by ozone in LPJ-<lb/>GUESS for the BioDiv-Support project, Zenodo [code], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8262590, 2023. <lb/>Lamarque, J.-F., Bond, T. C., Eyring, V., Granier, C., Heil, A., <lb/>Klimont, Z., Lee, D., Liousse, C., Mieville, A., Owen, B., <lb/>Schultz, M. G., Shindell, D., Smith, S. J., Stehfest, E., Van <lb/>Aardenne, J., Cooper, O. R., Kainuma, M., Mahowald, N., <lb/>McConnell, J. R., Naik, V., Riahi, K., and van Vuuren, D. <lb/>P.: Historical (1850-2000) gridded anthropogenic and biomass <lb/>burning emissions of reactive gases and aerosols: methodol-<lb/>ogy and application, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 10, 7017-7039, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-10-7017-2010, 2010. <lb/>Lamarque, J. F., Kyle, G. P., Meinshausen, M., Riahi, K., Smith, <lb/>S. J., van Vuuren, D. P., Conley, A. J., and Vitt, F.: Global <lb/>and regional evolution of short-lived radiatively-active gases <lb/>and aerosols in the Representative Concentration Pathways, Cli-<lb/>matic Change, 109, 191-212, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-<lb/>011-0155-0, 2011. <lb/>Lind, P., Belušiae, D., Christensen, O. B., Dobler, A., Kjellström, E., <lb/>Landgren, O., Lindstedt, D., Matte, D., Pedersen, R. A., Toivo-<lb/>nen, E., and Wang, F. X.: Benefits and added value of convection-<lb/>permitting climate modeling over Fenno-Scandinavia, Clim. <lb/>Dynam., 55, 1893-1912, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-020-<lb/>05359-3, 2020. <lb/>Lind, P., Pedersen, R. A., Kjellström, E., Landgren, O., Matte, <lb/>D., Dobler, A., Belušiae, D., Médus, E., Wang, F., Chris-<lb/>tensen, O. B., Christensen, J. H., and Verpe Dyrdal, A.: Cli-<lb/>mate change information over Fenno-Scandinavia produced with <lb/>a convection-permitting climate model, Clim. Dynam., 61, 519-<lb/>541, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-022-06589-3, 2023. <lb/>Lindeskog, M., Smith, B., Lagergren, F., Sycheva, E., Ficko, A., <lb/>Pretzsch, H., and Rammig, A.: Accounting for forest man-<lb/>agement in the estimation of forest carbon balance using the <lb/>dynamic vegetation model LPJ-GUESS (v4.0, r9710): imple-<lb/>mentation and evaluation of simulations for Europe, Geosci. <lb/>Model Dev., 14, 6071-6112, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-14-<lb/>6071-2021, 2021. <lb/>Liu, Y., Riley, W. J., Keenan, T. F., Mekonnen, Z. A., <lb/>Holm, J. A., Zhu, Q., and Torn, M. S.: Dispersal and <lb/>fire limit Arctic shrub expansion, Nat. Commun., 13, 3843, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-31597-6, 2022. <lb/>Masson, V., Le Moigne, P., Martin, E., Faroux, S., Alias, A., <lb/>Alkama, R., Belamari, S., Barbu, A., Boone, A., Bouyssel, F., <lb/>Brousseau, P., Brun, E., Calvet, J.-C., Carrer, D., Decharme, B., <lb/>Delire, C., Donier, S., Essaouini, K., Gibelin, A.-L., Giordani, H., <lb/>Habets, F., Jidane, M., Kerdraon, G., Kourzeneva, E., Lafaysse, <lb/>M., Lafont, S., Lebeaupin Brossier, C., Lemonsu, A., Mahfouf, <lb/>J.-F., Marguinaud, P., Mokhtari, M., Morin, S., Pigeon, G., Sal-<lb/>gado, R., Seity, Y., Taillefer, F., Tanguy, G., Tulet, P., Vincendon, <lb/>B., Vionnet, V., and Voldoire, A.: The SURFEXv7.2 land and <lb/>ocean surface platform for coupled or offline simulation of earth <lb/>surface variables and fluxes, Geosci. Model Dev., 6, 929-960, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-6-929-2013, 2013. <lb/>McEwan, E. H. and Whitehead, P. E.: Seasonal changes in the en-<lb/>ergy and nitrogen intake in reindeer and caribou, Can. J. Zool., <lb/>48, 905-913, https://doi.org/10.1139/z70-164, 1970. <lb/>Mee, J. A. and Moore, J.-S.: The ecological and evolution-<lb/>ary implications of microrefugia, J. Biogeogr., 41, 837-841, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/jbi.12254, 2014. <lb/>Meinshausen, M., Smith, S. J., Calvin, K., Daniel, J. S., Kainuma, <lb/>M. L. T., Lamarque, J. F., Matsumoto, K., Montzka, S. A., Raper, <lb/>S. C. B., Riahi, K., Thomson, A., Velders, G. J. M., and van Vu-<lb/>uren, D. P. P.: The RCP greenhouse gas concentrations and their <lb/>extensions from 1765 to 2300, Climatic Change, 109, 213-241, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-011-0156-z, 2011. <lb/>Miller, P. A. and Smith, B.: Modelling Tundra Vegetation Re-<lb/>sponse to Recent Arctic Warming, Ambio, 41, 281-291, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-012-0306-1, 2012. <lb/>Molinari, C., Hantson, S., and Nieradzik, L. P.: Fire Dy-<lb/>namics in Boreal Forests Over the 20th Century: A <lb/>Data-Model Comparison, Fron. Ecol. Evol., 9, 728958, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fevo.2021.728958, 2021. <lb/>Myers-Smith, I. H., Forbes, B. C., Wilmking, M., Hallinger, M., <lb/>Lantz, T., Blok, D., Tape, K. D., Macias-Fauria, M., Sass-<lb/>Klaassen, U., Lévesque, E., Boudreau, S., Ropars, P., Hermanutz, <lb/>L., Trant, A., Siegwart Collier, L., Weijers, S., Rozema, J., Ray-<lb/>back, S. A., Schmidt, N. M., Schaepman-Strub, G., Wipf, S., <lb/>Rixen, C., Ménard, C. B., Venn, S., Goetz, S., Andreu-Hayles, <lb/>L., Elmendorf, S., Ravolainen, V., Welker, J., Grogan, P., Epstein, <lb/>H. E., and Hik, D. S.: Shrub expansion in tundra ecosystems: dy-<lb/>namics, impacts and research priorities, Environ. Res. Lett., 6, <lb/>045509, https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/6/4/045509, 2011. <lb/>Nord, J., Anthoni, P., Gregor, K., Gustafson, A., Hantson, S., <lb/>Lindeskog, M., Meyer, B., Miller, P., Nieradzik, L., Olin, <lb/>S., Papastefanou, P., Smith, B., Tang, J., and Wårlind, D.: <lb/>LPJ-GUESS Release v4.1.1 model code, Zenodo [code], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8065737, 2021. <lb/>Norwegian Meteorological Institute: NGCD -Nordic Grid-<lb/>ded Climate Dataset, Norwegian Meteorological Institute <lb/>[data set], https://thredds.met.no/thredds/catalog/ngcd/catalog. <lb/>html, last access: 26 February 2024. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/></note>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<page>1115 <lb/></page>

	<listBibl>Oksanen, L. and Virtanen, R.: Topographic, altitudinal and regional <lb/>patterns in continental and suboceanic heath vegetation of north-<lb/>ern Fennoscandia, Acta Botanica Fennica, 153, 1-80, 1995. <lb/>Olofsson, J., Kitti, H., Rautiainen, P., Stark, S., and Oksanen, L.: <lb/>Effects of summer grazing by reindeer on composition of vege-<lb/>tation, productivity and nitrogen cycling, Ecography, 24, 13-24, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1034/j.1600-0587.2001.240103.x, 2001. <lb/>Olofsson, J., Oksanen, L., Callaghan, T., Hulme, P. E., Oksanen, <lb/>T., and Suominen, O.: Herbivores inhibit climate-driven shrub <lb/>expansion on the tundra, Glob. Change Biol., 15, 2681-2693, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2009.01935.x, 2009. <lb/>Olofsson, J., Tømmervik, H., and Callaghan, T. V.: Vole and lem-<lb/>ming activity observed from space, Nat. Clim. Change, 2, 880-<lb/>883, https://doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1537, 2012. <lb/>Ono, J., Watanabe, M., Komuro, Y., Tatebe, H., and Abe, <lb/>M.: Enhanced Arctic warming amplification revealed in <lb/>a low-emission scenario, Commun. Earth Environ., 3, 27, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-022-00354-4, 2022. <lb/>Osuch, M., Lawrence, D., Meresa, H. K., Napiorkowski, J. J., and <lb/>Romanowicz, R. J.: Projected changes in flood indices in selected <lb/>catchments in Poland in the 21st century, Stoch. Env. Res. Risk <lb/>A., 31, 2435-2457, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00477-016-1296-5, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Pauli, H. and Halloy, S. R. P.: High Mountain Ecosys-<lb/>tems Under Climate Change, in: Oxford Research En-<lb/>cyclopedia of Climate Science, edited by: Pauli, H. <lb/>and Halloy, S. R. P., Oxford University Press, 1-56, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228620.013.764, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Pearson, R. G., Phillips, S. J., Loranty, M. M., Beck, P. <lb/>S. A., Damoulas, T., Knight, S. J., and Goetz, S. J.: <lb/>Shifts in Arctic vegetation and associated feedbacks un-<lb/>der climate change, Nat. Clim. Change, 3, 673-677, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1858, 2013. <lb/>Porada, P., Ekici, A., and Beer, C.: Effects of bryophyte and <lb/>lichen cover on permafrost soil temperature at large scale, The <lb/>Cryosphere, 10, 2291-2315, https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-10-2291-<lb/>2016, 2016. <lb/>Pugh, T. A. M., Arneth, A., Kautz, M., Poulter, B., and <lb/>Smith, B.: Important role of forest disturbances in the global <lb/>biomass turnover and carbon sinks, Nat. Geosci., 12, 730-735, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-019-0427-2, 2019. <lb/>Qi, Y. L., Wei, W., Chen, C. G., and Chen, L. D.: Plant <lb/>root-shoot biomass allocation over diverse biomes: A global <lb/>synthesis, Global Ecology and Conservation, 18, e00606, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2019.e00606, 2019. <lb/>Rantanen, M., Karpechko, A. Y., Lipponen, A., Nordling, K., <lb/>Hyvärinen, O., Ruosteenoja, K., Vihma, T., and Laaksonen, <lb/>A.: The Arctic has warmed nearly four times faster than <lb/>the globe since 1979, Commun. Earth Environ., 3, 168, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-022-00498-3, 2022. <lb/>Rasmus, S., Horstkotte, T., Turunen, M., Landauer, M., Löf, A., <lb/>Lehtonen, I., Rosqvist, G., and Holand, Ø.: Reindeer hus-<lb/>bandry and climate change -Challenges for adaptation, in: <lb/>Reindeer Husbandry and Global Environmental Change -Pas-<lb/>toralism in Fennoscandia, edited by: Horstkotte, T., Holand, <lb/>Ø., Kumpula, J., and Moen, J., Routledge, London, 99-117, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4324/9781003118565-8, 2022. <lb/>Robertson, L., Langner, J., and Engardt, M.: An Eule-<lb/>rian limited-area atmospheric transport model, J. Appl. <lb/>Meteorol., <lb/>38, <lb/>190-210, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0450(1999)038&lt;0190:Aelaat&gt;2.0.Co;2, 1999. <lb/>Rosqvist, G. C., Inga, N., and Eriksson, P.: Impacts of cli-<lb/>mate warming on reindeer herding require new land-use strate-<lb/>gies, Ambio, 51, 1247-1262, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-<lb/>021-01655-2, 2021. <lb/>Rundqvist, S., Hedenås, H., Sandström, A., Emanuelsson, U., Eriks-<lb/>son, H., Jonasson, C., and Callaghan, T. V.: Tree and Shrub Ex-<lb/>pansion Over the Past 34 Years at the Tree-Line Near Abisko, <lb/>Sweden, Ambio, 40, 683-692, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-<lb/>011-0174-0, 2011. <lb/>Sandström, P., Cory, N., Svensson, J., Hedenås, H., Jougda, L., <lb/>and Borchert, N.: On the decline of ground lichen forests in <lb/>the Swedish boreal landscape: Implications for reindeer hus-<lb/>bandry and sustainable forest management, Ambio, 45, 415-429, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-015-0759-0, 2016. <lb/>Scharn, R., Little, C. J., Bacon, C. D., Alatalo, J. M., Antonelli, <lb/>A., Björkman, M. P., Molau, U., Nilsson, R. H., and Björk, <lb/>R. G.: Decreased soil moisture due to warming drives phy-<lb/>logenetic diversity and community transitions in the tundra, <lb/>Environ. Res. Lett., 16, 064031, https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-<lb/>9326/abfe8a, 2021. <lb/>Scharn, R., Brachmann, C. G., Patchett, A., Reese, H., Bjorkman, A. <lb/>D., Alatalo, J. M., Björk, R. G., Jägerbrand, A. K., Molau, U., and <lb/>Björkman, M. P.: Vegetation responses to 26 years of warming at <lb/>Latnjajaure Field Station, northern Sweden, Arctic Science, 8, <lb/>858-877, https://doi.org/10.1139/as-2020-0042, 2022. <lb/>Schwager, P. and Berg, C.: Global warming threatens con-<lb/>servation status of alpine EU habitat types in the Euro-<lb/>pean Eastern Alps, Reg. Environ. Change, 19, 2411-2421, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-019-01554-z, 2019. <lb/>Shannon, C. E.: A mathematical theory of communication, Bell <lb/>Syst. Tech. J., 27, 379-423, 1948. <lb/>Smith, B., Prentice, I. C., and Sykes, M. T.: Representation of <lb/>vegetation dynamics in the modelling of terrestrial ecosys-<lb/>tems: comparing two contrasting approaches within Euro-<lb/>pean climate space, Global Ecol. Biogeogr., 10, 621-637, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1466-822X.2001.t01-1-00256.x, 2001. <lb/>Smith, B., Wårlind, D., Arneth, A., Hickler, T., Leadley, P., Silt-<lb/>berg, J., and Zaehle, S.: Implications of incorporating N cy-<lb/>cling and N limitations on primary production in an individual-<lb/>based dynamic vegetation model, Biogeosciences, 11, 2027-<lb/>2054, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-11-2027-2014, 2014. <lb/>Speed, J. D. M., Austrheim, G., Kolstad, A. L., and Solberg, E. J.: <lb/>Long-term changes in northern large-herbivore communities re-<lb/>veal differential rewilding rates in space and time, Plos One, 14, <lb/>e0217166, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0217166, 2019. <lb/>Stark, S., Horstkotte, T., Kumpula, J., Olofsson, J., Tøm-<lb/>mervik, H., and Turunen, M.: The ecosystem effects of <lb/>reindeer (Rangifer tarandus) in northern Fennoscandia: Past, <lb/>present and future, Perspect. Plant Ecol., 58, 125716, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ppees.2022.125716, 2023. <lb/>Stoessel, M., Moen, J., and Lindborg, R.: Mapping cumulative pres-<lb/>sures on the grazing lands of northern Fennoscandia, Sci. Rep., <lb/>12, 16044, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-20095-w, 2022. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/></note>

	<page>1116 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">F. Lagergren et al.: Kilometre-scale simulations over Fennoscandia reveal a large loss of tundra <lb/></note>

	<listBibl>Sturm, M., Racine, C., and Tape, K.: Climate change -Increas-<lb/>ing shrub abundance in the Arctic, Nature, 411, 546-547, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/35079180, 2001. <lb/>Sundqvist, M. K., Moen, J., Björk, R. G., Vowles, T., Kytöviita, M.-<lb/>M., Parsons, M. A., and Olofsson, J.: Experimental evidence of <lb/>the long-term effects of reindeer on Arctic vegetation greenness <lb/>and species richness at a larger landscape scale, J. Ecol., 107, <lb/>2724-2736, https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.13201, 2019. <lb/>SURFEX: Soil texture -FAO at 10 km (global), SURFEX <lb/>[data set], https://www.umr-cnrm.fr/surfex/spip.php?article135, <lb/>last access: 26 February 2024. <lb/>Tang, J., Miller, P. A., Persson, A., Olefeldt, D., Pilesjö, P., <lb/>Heliasz, M., Jackowicz-Korczynski, M., Yang, Z., Smith, B., <lb/>Callaghan, T. V., and Christensen, T. R.: Carbon budget esti-<lb/>mation of a subarctic catchment using a dynamic ecosystem <lb/>model at high spatial resolution, Biogeosciences, 12, 2791-2808, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-2791-2015, 2015. <lb/>Thomas, S. C. and Martin, A. R.: Carbon Content <lb/>of Tree Tissues: A Synthesis, Forests, 3, 332-352, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/f3020332, 2012. <lb/>United-Nations-Environment-Programme: Emissions Gap Report <lb/>2023: Broken Record -Temperatures hit new highs, yet world <lb/>fails to cut emissions (again), Nairobi, United Nations Environ-<lb/>ment Programme, https://doi.org/10.59117/20.500.11822/43922, <lb/>2023. <lb/>Venäläinen, A., Lehtonen, I., Laapas, M., Ruosteenoja, K., Tikka-<lb/>nen, O.-P., Viiri, H., Ikonen, V.-P., and Peltola, H.: Climate <lb/>change induces multiple risks to boreal forests and forestry in <lb/>Finland: A literature review, Glob. Change Biol., 26, 4178-4196, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.15183, 2020. <lb/>Vowles, T.: Vegetation inventories from the study: Expansion of <lb/>deciduous shrubs but not evergreen dwarf shrubs inhibited by <lb/>reindeer in Scandes mountain range (1.0), Göteborgs universitet <lb/>[data set], https://doi.org/10.5879/ecds/2017-01-29.1/0, 2018. <lb/>Vowles, T., Molau, U., Lindstein, L., Molau, M., and Björk, R. <lb/>G.: The impact of shrub browsing by mountain hare and rein-<lb/>deer in subarctic Sweden, Plant Ecol. Divers., 9, 421-428, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/17550874.2016.1264017, 2016. <lb/>Vowles, T., Gunnarsson, B., Molau, U., Hickler, T., Klemedts-<lb/>son, L., and Björk, R. G.: Expansion of deciduous tall <lb/>shrubs but not evergreen dwarf shrubs inhibited by rein-<lb/>deer in Scandes mountain range, J. Ecol., 105, 1547-1561, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12753, 2017. <lb/>Vuorinen, K. E. M., Oksanen, L., Oksanen, T., Pyykönen, <lb/>A., Olofsson, J., and Virtanen, R.: Open tundra persist, but <lb/>arctic features decline-Vegetation changes in the warming <lb/>Fennoscandian tundra, Glob. Change Biol., 23, 3794-3807, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.13710, 2017. <lb/>Wania, R., Ross, I., and Prentice, I. C.: Integrating peat-<lb/>lands and permafrost into a dynamic global vegetation <lb/>model: 2. Evaluation and sensitivity of vegetation and car-<lb/>bon cycle processes, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 23, GB3015, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2008gb003413, 2009a. <lb/>Wania, R., Ross, I., and Prentice, I. C.: Integrating peat-<lb/>lands and permafrost into a dynamic global vegetation <lb/>model: 1. Evaluation and sensitivity of physical land sur-<lb/>face processes, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 23, GB3014, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2008gb003412, 2009b. <lb/>Wolf, A., Callaghan, T. V., and Larson, K.: Future changes in veg-<lb/>etation and ecosystem function of the Barents Region, Climatic <lb/>Change, 87, 51-73, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-007-9342-4, <lb/>2008. <lb/>Xu, J., Morris, P. J., Liu, J., and Holden, J.: PEATMAP: <lb/>Refining estimates of global peatland distribution <lb/>based on a meta-analysis, Catena, 160, 134-140, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2017.09.010, 2018. <lb/>Yu, Q., Epstein, H., Engstrom, R., and Walker, D.: Circumpolar <lb/>arctic tundra biomass and productivity dynamics in response to <lb/>projected climate change and herbivory, Glob. Change Biol., 23, <lb/>3895-3907, https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.13632, 2017. <lb/>Zani, D., Lehsten, V., and Lischke, H.: Tree migration in <lb/>the dynamic, global vegetation model LPJ-GM 1.1: effi-<lb/>cient uncertainty assessment and improved dispersal ker-<lb/>nels of European trees, Geosci. Model Dev., 15, 4913-4940, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-4913-2022, 2022. <lb/>Zhang, W. X., Miller, P. A., Smith, B., Wania, R., Koenigk, T., <lb/>and Döscher, R.: Tundra shrubification and tree-line advance <lb/>amplify arctic climate warming: results from an individual-<lb/>based dynamic vegetation model, Environ. Res. Lett., 8, 034023, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/8/3/034023, 2013. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 1093-1116, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-1093-2024 </note>


  </text>


  </TEI>